<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc38" title="Join Freemasonry" shortTile="join-freemasonry" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-11-23" dateModified="2019-10-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Join_Freemasonry" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Join Freemasonry</head><p>Freemasonry is the largest and oldest secular fraternal order in the world, crossing all religious boundaries to bring men together of all countries, sects, and opinion in peace and harmony. Its members have included major religious figures, kings, and presidents. To join the brotherhood, you must demonstrate the values that have been shared by millions of Masons for hundreds of years. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Basic Requirements</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be a man at least 21 years of age. This is the most basic requirement under most Grand Lodge (the center of authority for Freemason groups) jurisdictions. Some jurisdictions accept men who are 18 and over, and in other cases exceptions are made for the sons of members, or for university students. <figure rend="Join Freemasonry Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Believe in a supreme being. There are a few jurisdictions that don't require members to believe in a deity, but this is a requirement for most Freemasons. You must believe in a single god or deity above all others. People from all religious backgrounds are welcome as long as this holds true.  <figure rend="Join Freemasonry Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have high morals. This may be the most important quality to have as a potential Freemason. The fraternity's motto is "better men make a better world," and honor, personal integrity, and responsibility are held in high esteem. You must be able to demonstrate that you are a man with good character in the following ways: <figure rend="Join Freemasonry Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Have a good reputation such that those who know you would vouch for your character.</item>
<item>Be a good family member, with the means to support your family.</item></list></item>
<item>Have an educated understanding of Freemasonry. Many people seek to enter the fraternity because they heard about it in movies, books, and mainstream media. Freemasonry is often portrayed as a secret society that is trying to take over the world, with clues to this effect hidden all over Paris and DC. The truth is that Freemasonry is comprised of regular men striving to support each other in fellowship, friendship, and good citizenship. Becoming a member gives you access to the following: <figure rend="Join Freemasonry Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Entrance to the monthly gatherings at Freemason lodges, where you commune with fellow Masons.</item>
<item>Initiation into the teachings on the history of Freemasonry.</item>
<item>Participation in the ancient rites of Freemasonry, such as the handshake, rituals of initiation, and free use of the Masonic square and compass symbol.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Petitioning</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>To be one, ask one. The traditional way of joining Freemasonry is to ask someone who is already a member. If you know someone who's a member, let him know that you're interested in joining, and tell him you'd like to petition for membership. He should direct you to the appropriate venue to issue your petition; you'll have to answer some questions about why you want to become a member. If you don't know someone who's member, there are a few things you can try:  <figure rend="Join Freemasonry Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Look for a "2B1Ask1" sign. You'll see this on bumper stickers, shirts, hats, and other items displayed by Freemasons who want to welcome new members.</item>
<item>Look for the Masonic square and compass symbol. This is a bit harder to spot, but you may see someone wearing it on a t-shirt or another item.</item>
<item>Look up your local Freemason lodge in the phone book. Call the lodge and ask them how to pursue membership in that jurisdiction.</item></list></item>
<item>Interview with the Freemasons. After you've submitted your petition to a particular lodge, the Freemasons there will review it and decide whether to invite you in for an interview with an investigative committee. If they wish to call you in, a date and time will be arranged. During the interview, you can expect the following: <figure rend="Join Freemasonry Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You'll be asked questions about why you want to become a Freemason, and you'll be asked to describe your life story and your own character.</item>
<item>You'll get the opportunity to ask them questions about how things work at the Lodge.</item></list></item>
<item>Wait to hear their decision. After the interview, the Freemasons will conduct an investigation into your life, which will include calls to people close to you who can verify that you have a high moral character. They may also conduct a background check to determine whether you've had issues with crime, drugs or alcohol. <figure rend="Join Freemasonry Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Accept an invitation to join. Once the investigative committee has made their decision, you'll receive a call and an official invitation to join the fraternity. You'll receive further instructions about meetings. <figure rend="Join Freemasonry Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Joining the Fraternity</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start as an Entered Apprentice. This is the first stage of initiation, and you'll learn the basic principles of Freemasonry After you gain enough knowledge and put in some time, you'll work your way up through two more symbolic degrees. <figure rend="Join Freemasonry Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Throughout the apprenticeship period, you must continue to demonstrate good character.</item>
<item>Before you can advance to the next degree, you must demonstrate proficiency in understanding the degree work you experienced.</item></list></item>
<item>Advance to the Fellow Craft degree. You'll delve deeper into the teachings of Freemasonry, especially as they pertain to the arts and sciences. To complete this degree, you'll be tested on your knowledge about everything you've learned so far. <figure rend="Join Freemasonry Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get a Master Mason degree. This is the highest level you can achieve, and it usually takes several months to get there. To get the degree, you must demonstrate proficiency in the values of Freemasonry. Your completion of the degree will be celebrated with a ceremony. <figure rend="Join Freemasonry Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You don't have to be rich to join. While initiation fees vary, annual dues usually range from about $40 to $300/year.</item>
<item>Whilst Freemasonry is an all male fraternity, there are some Orders which allow the admission of females: Order of the Eastern Star, Jobs Daughters and the irregular Co-Masonry.</item>
<item>Depending on where you live, there could be one or more Freemasonic groups.  In Freemasonry, there tend to be two types of philosophy.  The first is that of the "regular" Grand Lodges and the other is that of the "irregular" Grand Lodges (often called Grand Orients).  Do your research on the groups in your locale and determine what is right for you in this regard before joining.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are many myths regarding Freemasons and Freemasonry. Some of these myths go back one hundred years or more but are still espoused today by its detractors. Again, do your research, but know when to separate the fact from fiction.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
