<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc54" title="See Things As They Are" shortTile="see-things" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-01-28" dateModified="2018-08-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/See_Things_As_They_Are" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>See Things As They Are</head><p>Trying to see things as they are sounds simple to most people. What is is, what isn't, isn't. That being said, there's a massive difference between seeing and perceiving, and indeed seeing and comprehending. Long-held prejudices are just some of the things that make seeing things as they are difficult. Sometimes your mind does not accept somethings as it is, you make assumptions and judgements. This can be because you've already built up a mental image and then you find it difficult change your preconceived notions. Seeing things as they are takes time and patience and it's important to keep in mind the clichéd but none-the-less true phrase, beauty is in the eye of the beholder. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Try to be non-judgmental. Do not let your prejudices affect how you see things, this include how people act as well as physical objects. Try not to judge anything or anyone regarding its components. Keep a kind neutrality in most situations. <figure rend="See Things As They Are Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn to be accepting to see things as they are. Do not treat people as though they are inferior to you. Accept everything that is given to you, count your blessings if you belive in blessings. If your friend has given something to your other friend but not to you, don't get heated up about your supposed inferiority and your friend's supposed superiority. Just accept whatever you have with a gracious and willing nod. <figure rend="See Things As They Are Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Live in the present moment. Let go of what has happened in the past. Forget the moments you were heated, abashed or embarrassment. Go for a fresh start whenever you need to see things as they are. Realize that others have made mistakes too. Feel every breath you take, every bit of happiness you experience and every word you speak. <figure rend="See Things As They Are Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn the virtue of patience. Everyone makes mistakes in life, but being patient enough to recover is a skill. Try to learn that skill. <figure rend="See Things As They Are Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn from past mistakes. Learn so that you do not repeat the same mistakes and improve your outlook. <figure rend="See Things As They Are Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be forgiving. Everyone makes mistakes. People will not always live up to our expectations; holding on to past wrongs will only act as a barrier and hold you back from seeing things as they are. Forgiveness makes you free to move forward. <figure rend="See Things As They Are Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Let go of the past. You cannot meet future goals if you are caught up in the past. Learn from the past but do not let it dictate your future. <figure rend="See Things As They Are Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Understand you cannot control life but you can control your inner self. What happens in life may not always be the way you hope, but how you deal with the situation determines if you are successful or have failed. <figure rend="See Things As They Are Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Accept that there is only today. Tomorrow is not promised, but today you have the chance to make better choices than yesterday. Sometimes you will get a second chance. Live in  the present moment. <figure rend="See Things As They Are Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Believe time is important for seeing things as they are. Use time well; cherish it. It is the little moments in time which creates life's big picture. Make the little moments count! <figure rend="See Things As They Are Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Pray the Serenity prayer: "God, grant me the serenity to accept the things I cannot change; Courage to change the things  I can; And the wisdom to know the difference. Amen."</item>
<item>Don't expect people to be like you. We all come from different backgrounds, see things differently and have our own opinions. Be open to seeing things from other perspectives.</item>
<item>Another prayer which comes from the Native American tradition is the following: "Oh Great Spirit, grant that I may judge no man until I have walked two moons in his moccasins. Amen."</item>
<item>Consider learning how to practice vipassana meditation as a way of clearing your mind of distracting thoughts that will allow you to become more present with what is happening.</item></list>
</text>
