<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc152" title="Fire an Employee from Your Cleaning Business" shortTile="fire-employee-cleaning" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-09-24" dateModified="2019-07-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Fire_an_Employee_from_Your_Cleaning_Business" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fire an Employee from Your Cleaning Business</head><p>For many small cleaning businesses, the buck stops with the owner. Hiring and firing decisions are made exclusively by the owner. Terminating an employee can generate some extreme emotions. Further, terminating without cause in some states can land you in hot water. Luckily, there's a guide to help you through this tricky situation if you don't have an HR department to deliver the news.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Document Fireable Offenses in an Employee Handbook</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prevent the need to terminate an employee with clearly defined rules. Make sure to provide all employees with this documentation. You can protect yourself further by requiring employees to sign the handbook acknowledging that they read and understand your expectations of them.</item>
<item>Include clearly defined steps that will occur leading up to termination while creating your employee handbook. For example, you can use a progressive disciplinary system for smaller offenses that when combined with an employee performance management plan can help some employees redirect to more appropriate behavior. However, make sure to document any disciplinary actions for an employee to support your reasoning for terminating the employee.</item>
<item>Establish which offenses result in specific disciplinary actions and how many times an employee can receive an infraction in a set period of time that will result in termination. If there are offenses that can result in immediate termination, make sure these are well-known among your staff.</item></list>
<head>Documenting Infractions</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Document each time a disciplinary action is necessary. Keep track of employees who are demonstrating the qualities you want to keep in addition to the negatives so you will be able to provide a fair, holistic assessment of each employee during reviews, redirection, or termination.</item>
<item>Address the employee in question quickly when an infraction occurs - within 24 hours of the infraction. If it is an offense that would result in immediate termination, make sure you have evidence of the infraction to support your reasoning. Even if you are in a state that does not require a reason to terminate an employee, you can expect that employee to seek unemployment as a result of their termination. This documentation will demonstrate that they were fired at-cause and will protect your business from wrongful termination lawsuits.
<list type="unordered"><item>Some examples of infractions that you may decide should result in immediate termination: Theft, repeated breaches of company policy, harassment, assault, and threats. As a business owner, you are ultimately responsible for making sure all of your employees feel comfortable in their work environment so there should be policies in place that are zero tolerance.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Time For Termination</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Expect some tension in the meeting, even if the employee knows ahead of time that they will be let go. However, the first thing you should try to make sure to do is to talk to the employee one-on-one. Dismissing someone from a position shouldn't be done with an audience when it can be avoided. The only time when you might want to include more than yourself and the employee when you terminate an employee is when you feel threatened and unsafe firing the employee alone.</item>
<item>Remain professional. Regardless of how the employee acts, your reaction or lack of reaction can help determine how the meeting goes.</item>
<item>Be firm, clear, and considerate without making it personal. You are terminating the employee for a reason, so stick to this reason and your documentation that supports it. You are trying to get through an extremely emotional meeting, so it is important that the employee understands that you are not firing them because you do not like them, but because they violated company policy.</item>
<item>Be prepared to answer questions about the dismissal process. The terminated employee will want to know when their last day will be, when they will receive their final paycheck, COBRA and other important benefits they may be entitled to.</item></list>
<head>Dealing with the Aftermath</head>
<p>If you thought that firing one employee wouldn't have ramifications across your employee base, you will probably be surprised to learn that firing someone creates a ripple effect through your workforce that can leave some people feeling uneasy about their status with your business. It is up to you to reassure them.</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Meet with your remaining employees in a casual setting. Explain that X person was released from their employment and how their tasks will be redistributed among the remaining staff.</item>
<item>Reaffirm your company policies with the staff without stating explicitly why the person was let go. In most cases, the only people who need to know are the ones directly involved--you and the terminated employee. Letting everyone know the gritty details makes you look unprofessional, so it is recommended to avoid this unless there is a safety concern.</item></list>
</text>
