<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc131" title="Date a White Girl if You're Black Guy" shortTile="date-white-girl-re" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-10-18" dateModified="2016-01-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Date_a_White_Girl_if_You%27re_Black_Guy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Date a White Girl if You're Black Guy</head><p>Dating a white girl can feel a little out of your comfort zone, especially if you grew up in very different subcultures. However, with patience and tenacity, you can overcome the cultural gap and maintain a strong relationship.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Accept the culture that she grew up in. Depending on your backgrounds, the two of you may have had very different upbringings. If you respect each other, you can broaden each other's horizons. In general, white girls tend to grow up in a culture that...
<list type="unordered"><item>Emphasizes safety. She may have been overprotected by her parents.</item>
<item>Shelters them from many of the world's problems. Middle-class white girls tend to have all their needs and some of their desires provided for. They might not realize the scale on which problems such as racism exist (or even that they exist at all).</item>
<item>Pushes them to value beauty and material goods. White girls (like other girls) undergo a lot of pressure to conform to a narrow vision of beauty. She may feel insecure about her looks, and feel that she needs to put a lot of work into her clothes and makeup.</item></list></item>
<item>Don't subject yourself to a racist girlfriend. While most white people will slip up from time to time and do or say something unintentionally racist, a good white girl will listen to you and learn from her mistake. If she constantly says racist things, or doesn't listen to you when you call her out, you're better off without her.</item>
<item>Don't be afraid to approach the subject of race with her at some point or another. If your relationship becomes serious, race will come up: you will continue to experience racism, and she may witness it or have people treat her rudely because of your race.
<list type="unordered"><item>Unless she's extremely well-educated, there will be things she doesn't know about racism. You can teach her yourself, or encourage her to look it up on the internet, depending on the subject and your energy levels.</item>
<item>Remember: as much as you have to teach her about race, she has to teach you about gender. In some ways, you'll be able to sympathize.</item></list></item>
<item>Meet her family, and introduce her to yours. Depending on how conservative the parents are, this might be a difficult conversation. However, most parents are unlikely to be openly racist, especially when there is a real, respectable person of color standing in front of them. It will probably go well.</item>
<item>Remember to take time for yourself. Sometimes, being a black guy in a world full of white people is exhausting. Hang out with your family, work on your hobbies, and spend plenty of time recharging.</item>
<item>Appreciate your girlfriend for who she is. That's what matters most.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you find yourself dating mostly white girls, despite the presence of women of color, consider it a red flag. Do you view women of color as less attractive? Could you be dealing with some internalized racism, or misogynistic? Reflect on your racial attitudes.</item></list>
</text>
