<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc167" title="Deal with Looking 18 when You Are 13" shortTile="deal-looking--" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-07-24" dateModified="2018-11-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Deal_with_Looking_18_when_You_Are_13" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Deal with Looking 18 when You Are 13</head><p>It can be awkward being really young but looking twice your age. Times have changed and teens are physically maturing much more rapidly. So, here's some advice that should help you deal with such a situation.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand that you are wonderfully and perfectly made. There is nothing weird about you, or wrong. You are alive and present to add something positive and beautiful to the world, otherwise you wouldn't exist.</item>
<item>Think about how you dress. For example, if you're a 13 year old girl but dress like 18, chances are you'll attract attention from 18 year old boys. Tell it like it is. Don't be afraid to say you're 13 and not interested. If a guy persists, then move away from the situation. No self-respecting 18 year old guy or girl should be hunting after a 13 year old. Dress plays an important role in the messages you give out about yourself. If you know you get certain kinds of attention when you wear mini skirts and crop tops, change up your style. There are loads of age appropriate fashion ideas online and in stores you can mix, match and be creative with!</item>
<item>Be aware that makeup tends to make you look older. If you use it often, tone it down to just lip gloss and acne cream (if you need that). While there may be a lot of pressure from friends and media to wear the stuff, the truth is you probably don't need it as much as you think you do and it can mess with your skin at such a young age. There are many different applications of makeup, but it all boils down to the same thing––appearing more attractive. You're a teenager, older people wish they could have skin like yours again! If you're just dong it to be attractive, ask yourself, what am I trying to attract? And why? Bottom line, you're beautiful. A little make up may be okay, but after all, you're still a teenager, not a young adult.</item>
<item>Behave appropriate to your age. Don't pretend to be something you're not. If you're 13, act like you're 13. You're brand spanking new to the "teen" club but you're still very much liable to your parents, it's okay to still enjoy Disney movies and Cartoon Network can still be your favourite Channel. You'll undoubtedly get more attention from older crowds because you look older but don't be in a rush to join them before your time. Have fun being crazy and goofy!</item>
<item>Be sensible, not tempted. The thing about looking older than you really are is that you'll be tempted to get away with things your peers wouldn't be able to. Like maybe walk into an off-license and buy alcohol/cigarettes or sneak into clubs etc. Don't do it. The temptation may arise at some point. Be honest with yourself and the people around you. Do what's right because it's right. Peer pressure, bullying, rejection are all very real and damaging. But, when you know who you are and you're happy with yourself, eventually the right people and opportunities will find you. Be strong and dare to be different.</item></list>
</text>
