<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc159" title="Improve Work Relationships" shortTile="improve-work-relationships" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-09-02" dateModified="2019-02-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Improve_Work_Relationships" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Improve Work Relationships</head><p>It's important to get along with everyone you work with to make sure that your work doesn't suffer. If you're reading this article, it might be because you have a good working relationship with your colleagues that you want to improve, or you have an issue with some coworkers that you're looking to resolve. Either way, this guide should help you improve your work relationships.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Reflect on your work style. There are several things you should look for in the way that you work: Identifying your strengths and weaknesses might help you understand why your work relationship with your colleagues is suffering. <figure rend="Have Fun at Work Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>What are your strengths (for example, are you a hard worker who doesn't stop until the job is done)?</item>
<item>What are your weaknesses (for example, do you usually leave things until the last minute)?</item></list></item>
<item>Identify who (if anyone) has an issue with your work style. This might not be very obvious, since most people will choose not to tell you what it is that bothers them about your working style. This will help narrow the list of people you need to improve your relationship with. <figure rend="Behave at Work Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Talk to the individual(s). This might be a hard step to take if you had a conflict with this person, but you should not hesitate to address the issue directly with the person. As long as you approach them in a friendly, non-threatening way, you might be able to resolve the problem without conflict. If you are simply looking to improve your relationship with your colleagues, most people will welcome your conversation because they will see it as an effort to improve your interpersonal skills. They will likely offer constructive feedback on what you are doing well, and how you can improve. <figure rend="Have Fun at Work Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do something nice for the individual(s) in your workplace. This doesn't need to be something major - it can be as simple as bringing them a coffee or small snack, or helping them out when they need it. If your coworkers see that you are willing to go out of your way to do something nice for them, they will likely be more trusting and supportive of you, and will want to repay the favour in the future. <figure rend="Have Fun at Work Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not spread rumors or gossip around the office about anyone. This can destroy any progress you've made in improving the work relationship.</item>
<item>Always try to improve your relationships before they become difficult and filled with anger or resentment.</item>
<item>Get to know your coworkers a little bit (for example, if they are married, have kids, pets, etc). This will give you nice conversation topics to talk about, and will allow the person to view you as a friend.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are having troubles with one of your coworkers, it might be a better idea to approach your boss first and see what they think you should do.</item>
<item>Do not approach your coworkers to discuss this during a busy time. If they are not available, they might not be willing to hear you and could make them resent you more.</item></list>
</text>
