<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc83" title="Stop Being a Side Chick" shortTile="stop-being-side-chick" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-02-26" dateModified="2018-10-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Stop_Being_a_Side_Chick" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Stop Being a Side Chick</head><p>Having romantic relationships with no strings can lead to feeling used and confused. The "side chick" comes in various forms but the common trait is no commitment. While this may work for some, it's an uncomfortable place to be for those who have fallen into it without thinking through the consequences. If this is the case for you, here are some suggestions to help you stop being the side chick and start expecting a whole lot more from your closest and most intimate relationships. If you're "asking for a friend", you've come to the right place.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know your worth. You are a diamond! You are neither common nor easily duplicated. Identify the qualities that make you unique and accentuate them. Recognize that you are more valuable than being a side chick.
<list type="unordered"><item>His main girl has worth too. How do you think she feels about you being with him?</item></list></item>
<item>Know what you want. If you're looking for loyalty and commitment, you're with the wing guy. What are you getting out of the relationship? Perhaps it is material items, but is it worth it? Sure he says he likes or maybe even loves you, but how can you trust him? It is vital that you realise you are capable of being independent and are aware of unhealthy codependent relationships; your relationship may be one!</item>
<item>Teach others how to treat you by having high standards. Let your partner know that you have a standard by explaining what you consider to be acceptable conduct. Demonstrate behavior that is satisfactory and reward him when he communicates the proper understanding.</item>
<item>Express your expectations. Be very transparent about your assumptions of the relationship and get clarity on his as well. You have to be realistic on the roles and boundaries that you each will adhere to. Clarify and gaps in your beliefs and communicate your principles. If he reveals expectations that don't gel with yours, then it's unfortunate but you're not a good match.</item>
<item>Confront the culprit. When there are issues of inconsistency, challenge them against your expectations. Do not allow him to contradict what you deem as satisfactory behavior. Do not compromise for the sake of argument. Use wisdom when you plan your conversation.</item>
<item>Be willing to let go. If/when discrepancies persist, give a consequence and follow through. Never threaten to leave when you aren’t mentally or physically ready. Plan your exit and execute it at the set time.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>It is very important to know yourself before you start getting to know someone else. Self-esteem leads to self-respect! Self respect has to be present before you can demand it from anyone else.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your partner is used to having side chicks, old habits are hard to break. But, if he really cares for you, he will eventually appreciate you!</item></list>
</text>
