<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc165" title="Prepare for a Perfect Day (Girls)" shortTile="prepare-perfect-day" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-03-07" dateModified="2019-08-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Prepare_for_a_Perfect_Day_%28Girls%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prepare for a Perfect Day (Girls)</head><p>Every girl gets jittery thinking about the day that lies ahead late at night, how subconscious these thoughts may be. But it doesn't have to be that way! Below, there are many tips and tricks listed designed to make your life a bit easier. Remember, you can make your own list of preparations for what you want to do, but this is just to get you started!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go through your day and all the things that you have planned to do the night before. From the broadest most important topics to the littlest things; like finally taking a picture of your kitty licking her nose. <figure rend="Prepare for a Perfect Day (Girls) Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're thinking about preserving your face, remember that those five minutes it takes to organize your thoughts and pack your bags; clean up the last bits of your room will be charged onto your account by the morning of stress.</item>
<item>Pick up those books that you know you will need. You will be pleasantly surprised by what a difference it makes in your morning commute.</item></list></item>
<item>Take care of your face the night before. Pluck your eyebrows if necessary, for if you do it in the morning, the redness may not recede in time and you might just patch on the make up a bit too much. If you have severe acne, use your regular prescription. If you are just on the brink, make sure to use a mild yet effective face cleanser to make sure to prevent those frustrating spots in your face. After, make sure to dab your face dry and spread a lotion of your choice evenly onto your cheeks and T-zone (between eyebrows and all around your nose) so that you don't wake up to nasty blistering. Once again, this process may seem tedious, but wouldn't you much rather wake up to a beautiful, shining, acne clam face rather than one that reflects your distress? <figure rend="Prepare for a Perfect Day (Girls) Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Brush your hair! This will spare you of tangles. <figure rend="Prepare for a Perfect Day (Girls) Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to sleep. It really helps to organize your thoughts by jotting down a few key points in your journal, no matter how "important" they seem. If they keep you up at night, they are important to you and that's what's important. Sometimes writing them down helps insomnia more than repetitively venting. Listen to some calming music that doesn't allow you to fall asleep to (so that you remember to turn it off before you sleep!), such as Norah Jones or Beyonce's "Halo" <figure rend="Prepare for a Perfect Day (Girls) Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try to think of something positive that you are looking forward to right when you wake up. If possible, you should have written this in your journal the night before. This will bring you a higher energy level and a stronger desire to wake up and get yourself out of bed and start your day. Smile! It'll make you feel good. The prettiest face is the one that glows from the inside. <figure rend="Prepare for a Perfect Day (Girls) Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Shower! Have a consistent routine of how you wash yourself but don't zone out. This will waste time and water and you will lower your energy level. A shower that's too quick can tend to stress you and you may not wash properly. <figure rend="Prepare for a Perfect Day (Girls) Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Brush your hair immediately after the shower. Unless that does not coincide with your regular hairstyle. This is so no tangles may begin to infest themselves. Use a hair detangler or volumizer to make it easier to comb through, from the bottom up. Then, put lotion on your face. <figure rend="Prepare for a Perfect Day (Girls) Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your day doesn't turn out the way you wanted it to, don't be discouraged. It probably still turned out great.</item>
<item>Remember to be optimistic!</item></list>
</text>
