<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc89" title="Make Your Enemy Jealous of You (Girls)" shortTile="make-enemy-jealous" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-07-15" dateModified="2018-01-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_Your_Enemy_Jealous_of_You_%28Girls%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Your Enemy Jealous of You (Girls)</head><p>This article will make your enemies very jealous of you and help you feel like you are so much better than they are. If this is your intention, rather than having a more mature, live and let live attitude, please follow each step carefully.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be confident. Be strong and stand up for yourself. When your enemies shout, scream or accuse you, stand up for yourself and say that if they accuse you then you will accuse them. Don't be too rude, just state that you will make accusations in a friendly way and don't let them be the boss of you or think that you are a weakling. Be brave but don't be too strong to a point that you come across as bossy.</item>
<item>Dress better. Sometimes show off. Don't always hide your beauty. Let it out and show you are better dressed than your perceived enemies. Maybe wear a dress one day, or a skirt, or tight jeans, maybe you can even highlight your hair. Show the world you are beautiful. If your enemies copy your style, by wearing dresses one day, or a skirt, or tight jeans, walk up to them and say, "Am I your role model? because your dressing after me!". Hopefully your enemies will understand you. If you want to be sure they will know what you mean, try saying, "Am I your role model? Because you are dressing in a very similar way as I dress". Don't scream your words, just give say it, laugh and do not explain yourself too much and then walk off and pretend your problem is solved.</item>
<item>Ignore your enemies then. Just walk away when they say something mean. Show them you don't want be around them, walk away when they are heading towards you. Reply to them when they say something nice and if they say something rude just pretend you didn't hear anything or make a good comeback. If they try to make you jealous about something they think they have but you don't, shake your head, walk away, and if they talk to you, ignore them.</item>
<item>Make better friends. If your enemies think you have better friends, they will think your friends will stand up for you, or that you will now be able to forget about them because you are busy with your new, better friends.</item>
<item>Do not show your enemies if you are lonely or sad, because they will take advantage of it. You should have a distraction ready if you want to easily ignore them. A phone, a good book, maybe a drawing book, it depends on your interests.</item>
<item>Have fun. Don't let them destroy your entire life, forget about them and just have fun. If they bother you just say 'Please leave me alone, I've had enough.' or 'I'm not in the mood to fight, so leave me alone.' and walk off.</item>
<item>If they make you sad, get away from them. Go to a place you feel safe and don't think about it. They will most likely take advantage of your sadness and use it to hurt you more.</item>
<item>Accept if they apologize. They probably realized what they did was mean, and they are actually sorry. Tell them that they did hurt you, but that you forgive them. Don't tell them that you won't forgive them, because they finally gave up being mean to you, and you could really hurt them if you rejected their apology (They could even everything up again!).</item></list>
</text>
