<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc39" title="Explain 'the Law of Attraction' to Others" shortTile="explain--law-attraction" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-08-26" dateModified="2018-06-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Explain_%27the_Law_of_Attraction%27_to_Others" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Explain 'the Law of Attraction' to Others</head><p>Have you discovered the law of attraction and want to share this idea with your loved ones and others? It can be difficult to convey a concept such as the law of attraction, especially if you are introducing the idea to someone for the first time. Here are a few easy steps by which you can share your knowledge of the law attraction with others.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand the law of attraction. For this you can watch movies based on the law of attraction, try reading books written on the topic, you can also search about law of attraction on your search engine. There are many free resources available that contain detailed information about the law of attraction. <figure rend="Explain 'the Law of Attraction' to Others Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>The easiest way to share the law of attraction with someone is to show them a movie, video, book or audio with them which resonates with you the most. If it is not possible for you to actually share a copy of the book, audio or video with them, you can simply recommend the resource so that they can get the same on their own. <figure rend="Explain 'the Law of Attraction' to Others Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>The second way is to explain the law of attraction to them verbally. The way to do this will depend on the kind of person you are planning on sharing the concept with. You have to be careful that you do leave an impact on their mind otherwise the explanation will be of no use. It is important to be serious while explaining law of attraction. Try to back your theory with a lot of data and real examples. Relating actual facts that they can look up and mentioning real successful people who believe in the law of attraction will help you prove your point. Also relate any true instances of the law of attraction working in your own life, if any. Not everyone will accept the idea of the law of attraction. It is important to understand that your task is only to convey the concept to the other person. Making them believe in the law of attraction, trying to make them practice it or even making them accept the ideology is not your task. Everyone is free to choose what they believe in and practice and so you must respect other's choices and beliefs. <figure rend="Explain 'the Law of Attraction' to Others Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>It is easier to start by sharing what you yourself have received rather than using your own words. If you want then you can use sentences like ,"Thoughts become things" or "We are like magnets and attract stuff to ourselves through our thoughts". Such sentences simplify the explanation and will help them understand the concept easily. It is better to keep the explanation simple for beginners and get into details once they understand the basics. But this is purely optional and you can use your own words if you think that is what you are most comfortable with. <figure rend="Explain 'the Law of Attraction' to Others Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Another way to share the law of attraction is to explain the law step by step. First, the idea of the law of attraction itself, then how to use it and finally the changes you can bring to your life by using it. Sometimes the way through which you have understood the law of attraction may not be as effective for another person as it has been for you. It is okay if this happens, let the other person understand the law of attraction on their own accord and at their own pace. <figure rend="Explain 'the Law of Attraction' to Others Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>There are several books available for children that explains the law of attraction too. Even if you decide to explain the law of attraction to a child yourself, do not dumb down the concept and do not answer or impose your opinions on the questions that you do not know the answer to. Children absorb beliefs fast and the beliefs which they internalize stay with them for a long time. A faulty belief will hinder their use of the law of attraction.  <figure rend="Teach Children (Age 3 to 9) Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Finally use the law of attraction yourself ! Believe that they will successfully understand the law and will apply it in their lives to improve. Visualize them in their wiser state where they create intentionally and are in vibrational harmony. Do not try to force someone into believing something that they are not ready for or which they do not agree with. Also do not be bothered or get affected if the other person does not accept the idea of the law of attraction. Just believe, let go and have fun. <figure rend="Explain 'the Law of Attraction' to Others Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be honest about what you do and do not know about the law of attraction. Search the internet or or other materials about a particular part if you are not clear about it.</item>
<item>Name the source from which you are explaining the law of attraction.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not force a belief on anyone. Everyone has the right to choose their own beliefs and you should not try to change their's, just because the belief resonates with you.</item>
<item>The concept of the law of attraction itself is understood, perceived and practiced by people in different ways. Others might not choose to look at the law of attraction in the same way that you do. You should not be affected by this. Respect other's opinions as this concept is open to different interpretations.</item></list>
</text>
