<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc105" title="Understand Relationships: a Girls Perspective" shortTile="understand-relationships" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-05-10" dateModified="2016-11-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Understand_Relationships%3A_a_Girls_Perspective" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Understand Relationships: a Girls Perspective</head><p>Everyone has or has had or wants a boyfriend but the thing is that they break your hearts or they just aren't interested in relationships so this is my guild about understanding boyfriends.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Knowing your guy</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>In a relationship you should know each other because if your dating someone and you know nothing about them, you won't understand each other and connect. One of the reasons your probably dating them is their good looks, they could be rude, a cheater, a liar, a bully. Do you really want to date that person? I didn't think so. Relationships aren't about being the cutest couple or liking someone because of their looks, you understanding me? Good so get to know that person.</item></list>
<head>What you are to him</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>When you have boyfriend, you can sometimes space out from your friends, listen I’m not saying break-up with him but you have to know that not everything is about you and him. As the girlfriend you can sometimes feel jealous of potential threats, so you ask yourself what you are to him: are you a very special person, just a girlfriend, an acquaintance, a friend, nothing. You need to calm down and just relax, you can just ask him what you are to him or what you mean to him, and it’s ok.</item></list>
<head>What he is to you</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>When in a relationship, you feel different emotions and so does he e.g. love, jealousy, anger, sadness, loneliness, happiness and way more. As well as wondering what you mean to him, you have to ask what he means to you. He could be thinking that right now too, you need to ask yourself if he feels so much to you or he doesn't feel right but don't go breaking his heart ok. Before you decide to break-up with him if he doesn't match to you), make sure it's not too hard on him. He might get angry and plant revenge that could actually end up hurting you both so think hard on that one.</item></list>
<head>Is it love?</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>As i have said above you feel all emotions in a relationships and one of the most important emotions is the L word also known as love. You might be the first one to say it or he might be the first to say it but most of the time it's the guy and it's more natural for them. Listen I'm not an expert in the subject but I have been in a relationship and we have said that we love each other and we have hated each other while we were dating, experienced jealousy, I even got in fights with my friends but we patched things up and we're now fine</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't get really worried about losing him because if you have talked about your feelings and you mean so much to each other you both know that no-one's a potential threat</item>
<item>Don't pester him about your feelings and don't keep asking him what he feels</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>don't say "I love you" too fast or you will drive him away</item></list>
</text>
