<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc132" title="Find Your Better Half" shortTile="find-better-half" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-10-15" dateModified="2016-01-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find_Your_Better_Half" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find Your Better Half</head><p>Are you having trouble finding the one? Well, you’re not the first and you certainly won’t be the last in being anguished by this thing we humans call “the matters of the heart.” Finding love has always been difficult. But with these guidelines at your disposal, unearthing Cupid’s arrow might not be as problematic.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Learn to love yourself before attempting to love another. You know how you change your wardrobes daily to whatever you feel would suit a certain event or a crowd? Yes, well with your personality, the same can’t be done. It’s something you were born with, so whether you like it or not, it’s a “till death do us apart” kind of relationship you have with it. But if you persist and try to change your characters, you surely will end up with the grim results of either facing an identity crisis or a dwindling confidence. And those two are your love life’s arch-nemesis. So accept who you are, embrace your every element, and disregard those who unduly criticize. <figure rend="Find Your Better Half Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know what sort of person will light your fire. You can’t go out into the woods at night with a torch light not knowing what to look for, right? So who is the one you label as your knight in shining armor or your princess? Is he/she the kind to mutter a word and have you in stitches? Is that soul mate of yours one with not a bead of humor in his/her temperament? Is that life-long companion you’ve always dreamt of emotional, independent, confident, wise, responsible, or carefree? You have to know what you want first, before you set out for the search. <figure rend="Find Your Better Half Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Let your friends take control of the wheel. No one can possibly know your likes and dislikes more than your closest friends. Ever seen the show Disaster Dates on MTV? See how they victimize one another by virtue of their exclusive insight? Your friends won’t do the same to you, but they just might be able to serve you that anxiously awaited soul-mate on a silver platter. So, having put in mind that there is no failure in trying, let your friends take control of the wheel and set you up with someone. <figure rend="Find Your Better Half Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try out dating sites. Make wise choices in your pursuit; select the right places to scour for Cupid’s arrow. Dating sites vary considerably in appeal and it's worth finding the one that aligns with your philosophy and needs, so that the same people you are interested in are actually looking in the same place. <figure rend="Find Your Better Half Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember that you’re available, <hi rend="italic">not</hi> desperate. Being desperate or arrogant usually curtails your chance at getting a second date. First impressions really do matter, so: <figure rend="Find Your Better Half Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don’t forget that you’re available, and that you’re on the quest of finding the one. But appearing to be too available runs the risk of making you look too desperate, which can have your date run out of the restaurant for his or her dear life. So calm down.</item>
<item>It doesn’t hurt to have some spice in you. Act as though dating comes to you as a second nature. But be sure to keep that flare within reason, as it can lose its composure and turn everything to dust.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never give up on love.</item>
<item>Engage yourself in recreational activities.</item>
<item>Don’t be afraid to put yourself out there.</item></list>
</text>
