<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc126" title="Tell if Someone You Like Hates You" shortTile="tell-someone-hates" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-12-31" dateModified="2015-05-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Tell_if_Someone_You_Like_Hates_You" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tell if Someone You Like Hates You</head><p>If you are wondering if someone whose company you enjoy, or someone you like to talk to, actually hates you, there must be something that has already alerted you to the possibility. Obviously you've already done a step, namely noticing a glitch in the matrix (a.k.a you feel like they hate you.) Confirming it requires some tact and courage.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Asking the Person in Question</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be alert. If you see hints of things that you do to make this person annoyed, you're in the hotspot, you're getting closer into knowing that this person is better off without you, whether a significant other, or just a friend. You've most likely annoyed them or have done things to tip them off, thus creating a barrier between you and them.</item>
<item>Ask. If you feel straightforward, just ask if anything is wrong. If they instinctively say "no", then you're getting closer. If they hesitate and then say "no", you can chill for a bit, because they probably don't hate you. In other words, approach and ask if everything is okay––if answered quickly, "no", then keep reading; if not, relax.</item></list>
<head>Ask A Mutual Friend</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask someone both of you trust and to whom you can tell anything. This is where you'll get the gold. Ask this person if they too, have noticed any change in behavior with the person in question. If they say "no", ask them if they've talked about you to them before, if they say "no" once more, leave them because they are being fake mutual friends. Approach someone else you have said 'yes' to either one of the questions, keep talking. Here are some questions you should ask:Do not, I repeat, do not ask them all of these questions in one day, they will soon know what is going on, which is exactly what you don't want. Do not tell the mutual friend(s) that you hate him/her YET. They will jump to conclusions which will lead to the asking him/her the fatal question.
<list type="unordered"><item>"Have they mentioned anything mean about me"</item>
<item>"Do you think something has happened to him/her?"</item>
<item>"Have they gotten mad with someone lately?"</item>
<item>"Have they mentioned me at all?"</item>
<item>"Don't you notice anything strange about him/her? Or is it just me?"</item>
<item>And lastly, when everything seems going to plan ask: "Do you think they hate me?"</item></list></item></list>
<head>Become 'Friends'</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>You could keep asking and stalking their Facebook, Twitter, and Instagram pondering if they truly hate you, but what good will that do? If they are genuine people, they won't be posting all about you. But if they are the people I think they are they will. So that's why this one part will be of the one true skill we've done: stalk.Here are ways to find the scoop:What if the mutual friend finds all these screenshots and likes? Exactly, they'll jump to conclusions. So these are some things you can do to avoid that:Slowly join all the pictures to capture evidence of true hatred. When you're positive they hate you move on to the next part.
<list type="unordered"><item>Become 'friends' with them on every social media. Careful, do not add them all at once, or they will become suspicious.</item>
<item>Like some of their stuff, but don't be obsessive with them, occasionally like their posts.</item>
<item>Start looking through their previous posts, or past pictures, screenshot anything that looks like it was about you, or feel like something you did.</item>
<item>Do not make a seperate album or library for those screenshots, c'mon, we are secret spies!</item>
<item>Mix in the screenshots with selfie, group pics, pictures of your cat, just blend them in with the rest.</item>
<item>If you're going to do a marathon of stalking, then upload those screenshots to your computer and delete them from your phone.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Approach The Hater</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Simple as that. Come forward and ask: "Do you hate me?" and if replied with 'no', wait until the end. If answered anything but 'no', simply walk away with content.Everyday, come up to them, or go somewhere near them and repeat one of their post you thought was about you, like this:That why they know that you've seen that post, or they will agree with you. If so, then they (most) likely don't hate you.If in the previous paragraphs, they said 'no,' notify if they said it in a certain tone, or a tone that they usually talk in. Remember that sometimes people will just say no to get you out of their face. That's fine, you get out of their face, give them space. But keep liking and reading their posts. Come back to them a few days later and confess that you feel like they hate you.
<list type="unordered"><item>"Ugh, I hate it when people are fake #basic"</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't be annoying with the questions.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The mutual friend could be in a plan with him/her, if so, question them too.</item></list>
</text>
