<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc177" title="Be a Normal High School Girl Without Dating" shortTile="normal-high-school" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-12-27" dateModified="2019-04-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Normal_High_School_Girl_Without_Dating" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Normal High School Girl Without Dating</head>Those who frown upon abstinence from dating claim that romance is the highlight of a person's youth. However, for most people they could not be more wrong - when surrounded by opportunities for education, friendships, and ways to discover who you truly are, it's hard to say that dating is everybody's activity of choice. If you're not interested in a relationship at the moment, there are still plenty of ways to make your high school experience unforgettably fun.
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider your reasons for choosing not to participate in dating. Do you feel as though you are too young? Are you gay or bisexual but closeted to any potential dating options? Do you want to focus on your grades and extracurriculars? Are you scared of being rejected, cheated on, or otherwise getting your heart broken? Are you aromantic or asexual? Figuring out exactly <hi rend="italic">why</hi> you want to abstain from romance can strengthen your stance, plus it makes explaining things to curious friends a whole lot easier.  <figure rend="Seem Weird Without Faking It Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Whatever reason you have should be respected. Don't let anybody belittle you for your choices.</item></list></item>
<item>Don't distance yourself from the gender(s) you're attracted to. If you're a straight girl, it's alright to be friends with boys without flirting with or dating them. This doesn't mean that you have to launch into a friendship with every classmate of the male gender -- all it means is that you should be careful before limiting the people you hang out with.  <figure rend="Be a Rebel in Middle School (for Girls) Step 5Bullet1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some people are unable to accept the fact that two people with compatible sexualities are just friends. If somebody accused you of dating your friend, laugh and tell them otherwise.</item></list></item>
<item>Don't let your stance on relationships determine how you dress. Some people believe that girls who wear revealing clothes are automatically asking for romantic or sexual attention. This isn't always the case, though - there are a multitude of reasons as to why one would choose a skimpier style of dress.  <figure rend="Be a Rebel in Middle School (for Girls) Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You don't need to explain your clothing choices to anybody.</item></list></item>
<item>Encourage your friends to change the subject when it comes to dating. This only applies if you're uncomfortable with talk of relationships and crushes. It's important not to come across as judgemental or condescending - whether your friends chose to participate in dating or not, it doesn't make them any better or worse than you are.  <figure rend="Be a Rebel in Middle School (for Girls) Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be polite. "LaTosha, it's really cool that you've found a cute girlfriend, but could we please talk about something else right now?" is infinitely better than "Shut up about girls!"</item></list></item>
<item>Talk to somebody if you feel that dating culture is bothering you. It's not always easy choosing to abstain from romance as a teenager. If you feel pressured or targeted due to your lack of a partner, talking to a parent, teacher or counsellor can help minimise bullying or make you feel more confident about your choices.  <figure rend="Seem Weird Without Faking It Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't be cruel or judgemental towards those who choose to engage in dating. Not being in a relationship doesn't make you better - or worse - than anybody else. Before spewing out judgements, remember that dating in high school is an individual choice, and that you don't know anybody's reasoning for choosing to partake. Be kind towards others, regardless of how different they are from you.  <figure rend="Be Different from Rest of the Girls Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This applies to other people, too - if they judge you for not dating, they're cruel and you probably shouldn't interact with them.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always remember that you have friends to help you during any situation...</item>
<item>Tell everything that happens to a parent, who can offer helpful suggestions.</item>
<item>It is never too late to back out of a bad situation.  If someone does not understand, remember that they are immature themselves and nothing is wrong with you.</item>
<item>Try to avoid a history of going out with a boy at all.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If anything becomes abusive, get help from a trusted person immediately.</item></list>
</text>
