<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc53" title="Witness to an Evangelical" shortTile="witness-evangelical" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-07-22" dateModified="2019-03-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Witness_to_an_Evangelical" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Witness to an Evangelical</head><p>When it comes to expressing your beliefs you may encounter one major pitfall. That pitfall is being labeled as a moralist who is out to impose your morals on others. There has got to be a better way to express your beliefs while respecting others. We all express our beliefs. Some people make it a vocation to express their beliefs to others. They are called evangelists. To an atheist the term is a kind of swear word because atheists do not like being evangelized. Atheists often complain that evangelists place themselves as morally superior by telling other how to live their lives. Atheists also don't care much for what they consider to be mythology to be expressed as fact. It is fair to say that simply talking about one's religion and its morals will not cut the mustard when it comes to reaching out to atheists. Now here are some steps to best express your beliefs.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Work on living up to your beliefs. Benjamin Franklin once said that the wisest teacher in the world is an ant and that ant says nothing. If your beliefs state that you should be selfless then be selfless. Otherwise your religion is nothing more than a tool to make yourself feel better than everyone else. That won't do anyone any good. Study the basic tenets of your religion. All the major world religions hinge on the golden rule. Do unto others as you would have them do unto you. Everything beyond that is purely commentary. Make a few simple rules that are based both on your religion and your own abilities. Then make sure to follow your own rules. No one will take advice from people who can't follow your own rules. If you cannot fully follow the rules that you profess then at least admit imperfection.</item>
<item>Find a way to clearly communicate. This should be a no-brainer, but even the best intentions come across faulty if you don't think things through. This means considering how others will interpret your words. Read a book or two about communication skills and learn to target your messages based on who the audience is. Someone who does not believe in God will not take any kind of story to be a solid base for fact. You would need to find a reason to back your moral claims. You could also study real life cases that support your moral belief.</item>
<item>Accept it when someone does not believe you. No one is going to hell for “failing to convert the unbeliever.” God is loving and merciful after all. As long as you work primarily on setting a strong example you can make a difference. Even if you do not convince someone of God's existence, you can still prove the importance of loving compassion. If you take anything from this lesson then you should take this: setting an example is greater than speaking. This is true even if you do not say a single word.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be well versed in your own faith system</item>
<item>Study basic communication skills and maybe some more advance skills</item>
<item>Learn logic and reason in order to structure your claims. A valid argument is still useful even if no one thinks that it is fully sound. (Look up the difference between valid and sound.)</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Not always going to be easy.</item>
<item>Not everyone will be convinced at first.</item>
<item>The most difficult part is living up to your own ideals.</item></list>
</text>
