<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc51" title="Be the Perfect Catholic Angel" shortTile="perfect-catholic" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-12-14" dateModified="2015-05-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_the_Perfect_Catholic_Angel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be the Perfect Catholic Angel</head><p>Being a good Catholic can be quite simple. Yet being the perfect Catholic angel is a harder task. Yet with strength and God by your side you will make it through and come out a changed person.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Praying can be a very easy task when it comes to the basic nightly prayer or grace before eating. Yet to become the perfect Catholic you must be constantly praying. You want to have your heart so open to the Lord that whatever your thoughts are, the Lord may hear them too. You will have great communication with God which is an essential trick for becoming a Catholic Angel. Here are some tips for getting into a better habit of praying:
<list type="unordered"><item>Always thank God for what you have, remeber everything you own has been provided by him.</item>
<item>Whenever you overcome a problem, remember it was God who got you through it and you should thank him</item>
<item>Say a prayer at least every hour, every thirty minutes is best though.</item></list></item>
<item>Cultivating the Catholic Way of Life. The Catholic lifestyle can be considered a very ideal lifestyle to many. Just like the the step above you should be sure to pray constantly. Next be sure to go to church at least weekly. If you ever miss Sunday mass because of a serious bed ridden injury or illness (anything else is inexcusable) then there is always Monday and Tuesday mass to make up for it. In your home there should be at least one cross located in any room. You can buy these in your local gift shop, or Good Will. And of course have a Bible and Rosary available in every room, but any old Catholic should know that.</item>
<item>Make Sure You Complete All the Sacraments. Through the Catholic religion there are many opportunities to become closer to your faith. You should already began as a young child going through Baptism, your First Communion, and Confession. Hopefully you are either going through or already have been Confirmed into the Catholic Church. Confirmation can be considered such an incredible event through your Catholic journey. Next is Matrimony or Holy Orders, either one can be a very Holy choice, especially if you marry another Catholic or choose to be a religious figure. Either way you will become closer to your faith. And as life slows down or if you have become to sick to go to Church, then the anointing of the sick may become necessary.</item>
<item>Spread the Catholic Faith.If you are strengthening your faith, why not strengthen others? Find others who share your religions and strengthen their fire for God. Whenever you have friends over, read a couple passages of the Bible, prayer for a few hours, do the Rosary a couple times, and go to Church together. Why not spread the news even more?  Here are some tricks to spread your faith
<list type="unordered"><item>Make pamphlets of the good news of the Lord</item>
<item>Hand out Bibles to people sitting near you in restaurants</item>
<item>Give out Rosaries and prayer books!</item></list></item>
<item>Continue with your faith. Don't let it stop now it has only began! The journey to becoming the Perfect Catholic Angel doesn't just happen over night, it takes an entire lifetime of strong faith. So just continue these steps and you will succeed. See you in Heaven!</item></list>
<head>Rosary Prayer</head>
<p><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Doc:Rosary_in_English,Rosary_in_Latin">Doc:Rosary in English,Rosary in Latin</ref></p>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep your religious flame strong</item>
<item>Be strong against those who judge you</item>
<item>Tell them you have forgiven them</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't force people to convert</item>
<item>Religion will come natural don't stress out over it</item></list>
</text>
