<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc124" title="Help a Friend with Family Problems" shortTile="help-friend-family" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-02-01" dateModified="2017-02-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Help_a_Friend_with_Family_Problems" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Help a Friend with Family Problems</head><p>Our lives can be stressful and hard in some places, but most of us can go home and find a loving family that makes us feel welcome, safe and secure. Some people however, don't have a nice home to go to at the end of the day. Although you may not know it, some of your friends could have problems at home that make them feel uncomfortable, sad or alone. Start with Step 1 to learn how to help them.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Let your friend know that they are not alone. Even though they may think so. Knowing that there are people out there that care about you can be comforting. (Especially if you are not usually taken very good care of).</item>
<item>Listen to them. They may not want to share all the details, and that is fine (don't push them for answers) but they may also want to pour out everything that has happened to them since their troubles began. This is where you just need to let them get it out of their system; they have probably been carrying this burden with them for a long time. This will also give you an idea of what really is the problem and can give you a bigger picture on why they are feeling the way they are.
<list type="unordered"><item>What you can say: If it is a one off thing (for example) they have had a falling out or argument with a parent or sibling, it is nothing to get too worried about as, chances are, they will make up within a week. But for that week, you can reassure them by saying things along the lines of "Put things into perspective, how long have you been without arguing?" or "Think of all the good times you have had together." But if it is a long term thing like they are being mistreated at home or they somehow feel uncomfortable living in the way they are then, gently advise them to seek help from a specialist (maybe someone at school that is a child welfare department). You must be aware that they will probably reject the idea as they do not want people to know about their problems but you must try to convince them that it is the right thing to do. In the mean time, here are a few things you can do to help them through their time of need.</item></list></item>
<item>Help them take their mind off of what they are going through. If they are not so comfortable at their own house, then perhaps offer if you want to spend time with them after school, in a coffee shop or a park just to talk (but not about any of their, or your, problems). Spending some quality time with them just as friends can be the best thing you can do if they are feeling down.</item>
<item>Don't give up on them. This may be a long term thing and chances are that they will need you. So be patient with them. although, you can't let their problems overtake your life, you are just support. Don't think that you are any less important than you are.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be a good listener</item>
<item>Give them supportive advice (gently)</item>
<item>Seek help from a professional</item>
<item>Spend time with them</item>
<item>Be a loyal friend</item>
<item>Don't let it take over your life</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some people may react differently to different methods of comfort; this is only a general guide.</item></list>
</text>
