<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc224" title="Be a Teen Guidette" shortTile="teen-guidette" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-07-21" dateModified="2017-05-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Teen_Guidette" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Teen Guidette</head><p>Do you want to be like the guidettes who made it famous on Jersey Shore, but still want to be classy? You're only a teenager so some things that they show on Jersey Shore, are not suitable for your age group. Keep reading for tips on how to be the most gorgeous teen guidette ever!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Don't be trashy! No matter how old you are, being trashy is never okay! A lot of guidettes can be trashy or inappropriate, but some guidettes are very responsible &amp; classy. <figure rend="Be a Teen Guidette Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember, it will be hard to pull off the Guidette look if you are not Italian! It is best to be at least 3/4 Italian. If not, people may look at you as a poser! However, Snooki pulls off the Guidette look pretty well, &amp; she is Chilean! <figure rend="Be a Teen Guidette Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have gorgeous, long, shiny hair. Most Guidettes either have dark brown hair or black hair. You can't be a blonde or a red head. It just won't work! Again, you have to be Italian...&amp; most Italians have dark hair. Also, I suggest straightening your hair for an everyday look. If you don't have long hair, try out extensions! Make sure that they don't look fake though. I recommend trying out Luxy Hair Extensions or Hello Gorgeous extensions. <figure rend="Be a Teen Guidette Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear flattering makeup! For school, use foundation, bronzer, eyeliner, mascara, and a light pink lipstick/lip balm.(Snooki uses MAC lipstick.) Also, false lashes are optional, as long as they are natural looking. Nothing too bold!! Don't wear anything too dark or heavy. <figure rend="Be a Teen Guidette Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Always be tanned. In the summer, tan outside almost every day! If you can handle it, then use SPF 4 or SPF 8. (That will help you get a deeper tan.) Also, use a self-tanner. Just make sure that you do not look orange! Try to look brown. <figure rend="Be a Teen Guidette Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear cute, designer clothes. You do not have to buy anything really expensive though. Wear Victoria's Secret PINK sweats, Ed Hardy, bebe, Armani Exchange, Guess, Juicy Couture tracksuits, etc. Wear skinny jeans, yoga pants, lounge outfits, bodycon dresses/mini skirts, etc. <figure rend="Be a Teen Guidette Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have fashionable accessories! (BIG Hoop earrings, cross necklaces, Louis Vuitton purses, Dolce &amp; Gabbana, Gucci hats &amp; purses, Prada, Chanel earrings, so on.) In the winter, wear Uggs almost everyday! Have at least 3 of them. Try to buy some Snooki Slippers as well for lounging around the house. <figure rend="Be a Teen Guidette Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be fit &amp; healthy, but still enjoy some real Italian food. &amp; if you are a REAL Italian...remember, it ain't sauce... it's called gravy! <figure rend="Be a Teen Guidette Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Always have blinged out nails, gel nails, or French tips. <figure rend="Be a Teen Guidette Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Slang. Use words like grenade, yo, yous, hon/honey, etc. Do NOT sound fake though. <figure rend="Be a Teen Guidette Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Confidence. You can't be a real guidette without confidence! So Do NOT be shy! You can be sweet, but not shy. For example, Sammi from Jersey Shore is sweet &amp; a nice person, but she's not too quiet. <figure rend="Be a Teen Guidette Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Jersey is NOT pronounced "Joysey." It's pronounced "Jerzey."</item>
<item>Have a nice group of friends to hang out with.</item>
<item>If you don't have a New York/Jersey/Philly accent, then do NOT fake one! If you do have a REAL one, then great!</item>
<item>Don't be someone you're not!</item>
<item>It helps if you live/were born in a North Eastern place to be a Guidette. Ex. New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania(especially Philadelphia), etc. You may seem like a wanna-be if you are not from the Northeast or Mid Atlantic area.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use heat protectant when you use any heat appliances to your hair!</item>
<item>Remember, you are still a kid. Don't do something that you may get in trouble for.</item>
<item>Don't do bad in school just because it may seem cool. It's not cool.</item>
<item>Don't do drugs, smoke, or drink!</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Designer purses</item>
<item>Some makeup. (Brands like MAC, Clinique, NARS, Too Faced, etc.</item>
<item>Tracksuits &amp; sweats</item>
<item>Dark, shiny, &amp; long hair.</item></list>
</text>
