<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc114" title="Make a Girl Fall in Love with You as a Fat Person" shortTile="make-girl-fall-love" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-06-29" dateModified="2016-04-20" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_a_Girl_Fall_in_Love_with_You_as_a_Fat_Person" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make a Girl Fall in Love with You as a Fat Person</head><p>Hello there! Here, I will not only go over how to get the girl, but how to feel confident!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Feel confident about yourself. You should feel confident in who you are! Girls love confidence in any type of guy. If you truly feel your weight is an issue, then signing up for a local gym and controlling the foods you eat on a daily basis is bound to make you feel much better in your own body!</item>
<item>Let the girl know that you have feelings! It's good to ease upon the subject every here and there, but you don't want to ease on so slow that she thinks you're not interested! Don't go full stalker, but finding out what makes her laugh or things she likes is a good boost into letting her know you care about her opinion and consider her enough to take some time to learn about her.</item>
<item>Keep communicating! Try not to distance yourself to the point where she doesn't know you exist, but don't be breathing down her neck every passing moment. If she's comfortable and you've talked verbally enough to where she wouldn't mind, ask her politely for her number! Try to avoid texting her every day, but space it out slightly so she doesn't feel like she's being stalked, but knows you're interested. Try to set up times where you two can talk personally as well, because all-text chats get boring and unfulfilling after a while.</item>
<item>When hanging out, make sure to let her know you care about what she has to say by letting her talk as well. You can obviously talk if you want, but try to allow her some time to say what's on her mind! See if you can ease on in conversations (not all at once!) how you feel, or compliment her! Let her know that you really appreciate the time she spent to get ready that day to hang out with you.</item>
<item>Make sure you're there for her when times are dark for her! It's understandable if you can't be there for a serious reason, but if you have the ability to be there, be there! Try to limit being there when she wants every now and then, but try to be when she needs as much as you can! She'll realize she really enjoys talking to you, and she'll want to talk more.</item>
<item>Eventually, you should be at the point (Note: This can take a while! Be patient!) where you can ask if she'd like to go out with you (or whatever situation you attempted!)</item>
<item>If she's taken, don't try to convince her out of her relationship, especially if she's happy in it. If she has a crush on someone else, try not to force her away from that either, but you can still try to be there for her more! And if she's not interested, no means no! You can still try to be friends, but if she doesn't want to date, let her keep her choice! It could be her own loss if you truly were a great guy to her and she was being stuck-up in the end.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be kind!</item>
<item>A little mystery keeps a girl interested, so avoid big, detailed responses!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You may end up in the friend-zone if steps appear too friendly to her.</item>
<item>Not every girl is alike, so don't follow this as a script! Try to be yourself!</item></list>
</text>
