<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc174" title="Be an Elegant Teen" shortTile="elegant-teen" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-07-23" dateModified="2018-10-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_an_Elegant_Teen" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be an Elegant Teen</head><p>Teenage is the age when a lot of changes takes place within us. Among those changes, one such change is loss of elegance due hormonal imbalance and change of attitude towards life. This article will guide you to enjoy your teenage without compromising with elegance.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Have good manners: If you want to become more socially elegant, you are going to have to know appropriate manners.
<list type="unordered"><item>Say "please" and "thank you"</item>
<item>Offer to help out around your house and when you are invited to other peoples houses.</item>
<item>Do not swear. Swearing can make you appear rude and uneducated.</item>
<item>Use appropriate grammar and pronunciation. It is important because it will help you communicate yourself more effectively to others.</item></list></item>
<item>Pay attention to how you dress. There are different dress codes for different occasions. The dress code is a good thing to keep in mind when attending any event. If you have to go into a meeting for work you wouldn't go in a boy-band shirt or a hoodie, so think things through and choose appropriately. This will show that you are elegant, mature and you will probably appear more respectful.</item>
<item>Maintain your table manners. If you want to appear elegant you shouldn't talk with your mouth full. Always chew with your mouth closed and clean up after yourself. Sloppiness isn't very attractive when it comes to the dinner table.</item>
<item>Gain confidence. Setting goals and following through to accomplishing them can help you boost your confidence. Confidence can really boost your elegance.
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure that you stand and sit straight, teenage is often accompanies with a sudden height growth to which our spine is not very well adapted. Due to this, many teens tend to lean down while standing or sitting. So make sure that you keep yourself straight as much as possible.</item>
<item>Don't be too hard on yourself. If someone is picking on you, ignore them. Generally, if someone is picking on you they just want a reaction out of you and if you give them that they will see that you're interested in a conflict.</item>
<item>Speak clearly and speak your mind, politely. This can be helpful because people will see that you are not shy, you are willing to put yourself on the spot and it will draw attention to you. If you are open and be yourself people will be more likely to engage in conversation with you. Never say nasty or hateful things of any nature because it may hurt someones feelings and if you have nothing nice to say do not say anything at all. In most cases if you say mean things about people it only reflects upon you.</item></list></item>
<item>Compliment others. If you compliment people they will feel appreciated, respected and important. It means a lot to people if you notice their accomplishments and tell them that they have done well.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be kind to all people and animals.</item>
<item>Don't be crude; this will make you appear immature.</item>
<item>Do not look at life from only your perspective.  Attempt to see life through other people's perspectives. If you can do this it will help you develop more compassion.</item>
<item>Respect everyones perspective of every situation.</item>
<item>Try not to react to people out of anger.</item>
<item>If there is a conflict between your friends or family, be creative and think of new ways to help everyone problem solve.</item>
<item>If you see other kids being made fun of at school, stick up for them.</item>
<item>Help out with chores around your house.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not think you are better than everyone else.</item>
<item>Make sure you don't become a totally different person over night because people will think something is wrong.</item>
<item>Your friends are important and can be a good support system so do not abandon your friends when you decide to present yourself in a more elegant or sophisticated way.</item>
<item>Do not pretend that you are something you are not. It is important to be true to who you are while establishing your new elegant manners.</item></list>
</text>
