<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc175" title="Be a Sunny, Amazing Girl (Ages 11 to 14)" shortTile="sunny-amazing-girl" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-12-06" dateModified="2018-10-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Sunny%2C_Amazing_Girl_%28Ages_11_to_14%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Sunny, Amazing Girl (Ages 11 to 14)</head><head>Steps</head>
<head>Keeping Great Habits</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Eat healthily. You need to eat healthily to keep that beautiful, glowing appearance. Try fresh fruits and berries, and maybe a newly picked carrot. Who doesn't love a sweet watermelon? Try going on a 1-week full-on, only fruit-and-veg diet. You'll feel so refreshed your habits will improve immediately. You can even form the fruits and vegetables into a smoothie.</item>
<item>Have a morning routine. Have an hour-early alarm clock, but don't wake up an hour early. Instead, take that one hour to snooze and relax, and you will feel so much more confident. Or wake up just to chill with your computer, or to send a text message or selfie. Then, it will feel as if school starts in the middle of the day!</item>
<item>Be organized. Organization doesn't have to mean boredom! Keep fun, coloured notebooks, and have one for each class! Try to keep notes tidy and neat, as you need to be very organized to be an amazing girl. Not for others, but to make your life easier. You will find it a whole lot easier to keep track of whatever with organization!</item>
<item>Compliment. When you meet somebody, saying "Hi!" and waving can give you a friend. Then, say something you like about their appearance, or "You're in a great mood today!" can give them the impression you want. Make sure to smile, and if you get something in return, say "Thanks!" and give them a beam. Then, walk away, feeling refreshed.</item>
<item>When you come home from school, help around the house. Babysit your younger siblings, or volunteer to cook! Also, you can bake muffins or treats for your parents and siblings. You know, being nice can actually give you stuff. If people like you, they will also treat you nicely, and they will know you a whole lot better.</item>
<item>React properly when insulted. Don't just shout at them. Instead, smile and say, "Kay! Thanks for sharing that! I'll see you later!" Another way is to ask them for advice. Saying, "I know I'm on the chubby side! Do you have any advice? I try to stay to fruits, you know!" Give a laugh and walk away leaving the bully behind you.</item></list>
<head>Having The Top-Class Social Life</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be A Social Butterfly. Mingle with lots of different people, unless they can hurt you. Try to know a girl before you shut them down. Don't be a backstabber, try to be a kind, cheerful, stylish friend, and they will see that you are a to-go-hands-down friend super star!</item>
<item>Try to look good. Make-up is quite simple: just some lipstick and mascara, and possibly eyeshadow. Try to wear colourful, classy, outfits. Here's a tip: only have a primary and secondary colour! That way, you will look stylish with a few colours only!</item></list>
</text>
