<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc85" title="Know when a Man Is Overthinking" shortTile="know-man-overthinking" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-08-06" dateModified="2018-09-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Know_when_a_Man_Is_Overthinking" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Know when a Man Is Overthinking</head><p>A relationship is a beautiful treasure to have, especially since it signifies that you have a bond with another person. However, it also requires work and lots of love. Although a good relationship reaps benefits and happiness, there will also be obstacles and bumps that it has to endure. You and your partner may not always be certain about your love for each other. You both may suffer from insecurity or fear of the future. However, this article will teach you to show your love to your partner when he is overthinking your relationship. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Notice if your partner is quiet. Silence often signifies that there is a problem that is not being stated. Your partner may not talk to you as often, and his answers might be short. Even if he may be a man of few words, there is a difference between a natural silence and a forced one. Since communication is an important key between partners, silence can be detrimental to a relationship.</item>
<item>Read his body language. If your partner seems overly defensive or rude, his behavior may be caused by several factors. He may not want to talk to you, he feels smothered and wants his space, or he could be feeling pressured into participating in activities. Also, consider his reaction if you bring up topics about your future with him. Realize that his reaction may be a result of fear. He could also be feeling as if you are forcing him to settle down with you.</item>
<item>Watch out when your partner begins to find faults in your relationship. Rather than becoming defensive, you should remind him that you love him before giving him space. Let him know that you are ready to talk when he wants to. By reacting in a calm manner, you will show your partner that you value his feelings and boundaries. If he truly loves you, he will contact you as soon as his emotions settle down. However, avoid pushing him and making him feel pressured; otherwise, it may lead to anger and a breakup.</item>
<item>Ask your partner how he is feeling. If his behavior seems strange or he appears troubled, ask him, "Is something wrong?" Ignoring the problem will only cause it to worsen, leaving your partner feeling abandoned and unloved. By kindly addressing the situation and showing your support, you will prove to your partner that you care for him. Despite the fact that he may not want to share his feelings, he will feel better in knowing that you support him.</item>
<item>Be respectful of your partner's space. Although you can show him that you love him, you must also be aware of his personal bubble and boundaries. Keep a safe distance when interacting with your partner, especially if he is emotional.</item></list>
</text>
