<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc208" title="Ask Your Parents to Let You Wear Makeup" shortTile="ask-parents-wear" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-08-22" dateModified="2017-01-20" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Ask_Your_Parents_to_Let_You_Wear_Makeup" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ask Your Parents to Let You Wear Makeup</head><p>Do you want to wear makeup, but your parents won't let you? This article can help you talk to your parents about the issue. If you approach it carefully, they may give you permission to start wearing it. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Talking to Your Parents</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose a time to talk to your parents. Ideally, find a time when they are not busy or stressed out with something else.</item>
<item>Broach the subject. Start by saying something like, "Mom, Dad, I know you said I can't wear makeup until I'm 15 (or whatever age they previously said you can start), but I was wondering if I could start wearing some now, even just a little bit?" Don't whine or complain. Use a calm voice when talking.</item>
<item>Promise to start or continue taking good care of your general cleanliness and appearance. Let them know you'll continue showering daily, washing your face, brushing your hair and teeth, wearing appropriate clothing, etc. This can help show your parents that you'll be responsible enough to handle wearing makeup.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're currently not taking good care of yourself, and you promise your parents you will start taking better care of yourself in order to earn makeup privileges, they may make you do a trial run of proving to them you can start showering daily, taking care of your hair and teeth, etc. If this happens and you earn makeup privileges, don't fall back into your old ways of being unhygienic, as your parents may revoke your makeup privileges, and taking good care of your health is just a good habit in general.</item></list></item>
<item>Make it a bonding experience if possible. If they do end up giving permission, ask your mom if you two could go shopping together and pick some makeup out. You can also ask your mom to give you hints on how to properly apply makeup.</item>
<item>Be subtle with your makeup. Never apply makeup heavily; always apply it lightly.</item>
<item>Take care of your skin. It's also important that you always wash your face at the end of the day. By forgetting to do this, you run the risk of your face breaking out and aggravating existing acne or other skin conditions.</item></list>
<head>Reacting If You Still Don't Get Permission</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do not get angry or throw a fit. This will make you seem immature and possibly validate their beliefs that you're still too young. Calmly ask them why they won't allow you to wear makeup till a certain age. Listen to them carefully, and when they're finished, accept their answer, even though it's hard.</item>
<item>Look for compromises. Ask them if you could compromise with them by wearing something else, like flavored lip balms, or nail polish.</item>
<item>Consider alternatives. If you still end up not being able to wear makeup for a few more years, look for other ways to change your appearance. Go through your dresser and come up with some new outfit combinations. Look online for new hairstyles and try them out.</item>
<item>Embrace your own beauty and personality. Most importantly, don't stress out about not being able to wear makeup yet. Many people look nice even without wearing cosmetics. It's a cliche, but your personality is truly what matters in the long run. A nice, friendly smile is worth more than the pink lip gloss on top of it.</item></list>
</text>
