<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc21" title="Deter Coyotes" shortTile="deter-coyotes" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-10-21" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Deter_Coyotes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Deter Coyotes</head><p>Coyotes are one of the top ten most fearsome predators in North America. These animals aren’t usually a threat to humans, but can make a mess on your land and become aggressive at close range. Simply preventing access to food sources (like garbage) will help keep them away. You can also build a fence or use other deterrents to keep them out. Hazing the coyotes with noise, blasts of water, and other means will make them want to find somewhere else to go.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Making Your Land Unappealing to Coyotes</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Keep food sources out of reach. Coyotes are attracted to easy food sources that might be found outdoors, including garbage and pet food. If you want to keep coyotes away, make sure you don’t give the access to these easy targets. For instance: <figure rend="Deter Coyotes Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep garbage outside in containers with locking lids.</item>
<item>If you feed pets outdoors, clean up any leftover food as soon as they are done.</item>
<item>Do not let containers of water sit out, since coyotes may try to drink from them.</item>
<item>Keep birdfeeders clean and securely closed.</item>
<item>If you have fruit trees, pick up fallen fruit instead of leaving it on the ground.</item></list></item>
<item>Trim bushes and trees to remove coyote cover. If there are trees with low limbs, shrubs, or thick brush on your land, clear it to several feet off of the ground. That way, coyotes won’t have thick cover to hide behind. <figure rend="Deter Coyotes Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Use clippers, hedge trimmers, or a similar tool to remove any branches, limbs or growth from the lower portion of vegetation.</item></list></item>
<item>Get a guard animal. Coyotes are relatively small animals, and normally only prey on small animals like mice and rabbits. Large or aggressive animals will frighten them. Get a guard animal that you can leave outside. <figure rend="Deter Coyotes Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Dogs, donkeys, and llamas all make good guard animals.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Putting Up a Border on your Land</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use scent deterrents. Take clean rags, wrap them around a stick, and soak them in ammonia. You can also spray the rag with cologne. Stick them in the ground, on the borders of your land. Strong smells that seem unnatural to coyotes will scare them away. <figure rend="Deter Coyotes Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Replace the rags after each rainfall.</item></list></item>
<item>Build a deterrent fence. Coyotes are skilled jumpers, but a fence that is  to  high can deter them. To keep them from digging under the fence, make sure that it goes at least  down into the soil. <figure rend="Deter Coyotes Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>An electric fence can also work to keep coyotes away.</item></list></item>
<item>Use motion-activated sprinklers. Set them up on the edges of your land. If coyotes creep in, the sensors will be activated and the animals will be struck with a blast of water. Coyotes hate being disturbed, so this will drive them away. <figure rend="Deter Coyotes Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can find these sprinklers at most hardware and home supply stores.</item></list></item>
<item>Install outdoor lights. Usually, coyotes like to lay low and are actually very skittish. Bright lights make the area seem too visible for their liking, so they will stay away. Set bright outdoor lights up outside your home, in your yard, or wherever you suspect coyotes lurk. <figure rend="Deter Coyotes Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Strobe lights will be especially annoying to coyotes, so go for those if you can find them.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Hazing Coyotes</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make loud noise. If you actually see coyotes on your land, immediately start making noise. Shouting, screaming, and clapping will all frighten a coyote. You can also create a shaker by filling a can or bottle with coins, beans, and other loud objects. <figure rend="Deter Coyotes Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Spray the coyotes. Attach high-powered, far-shooting nozzles on your garden hoses. If you see coyotes in the distance, turn the hose on and blast them with water. It won’t hurt the animals, but it will make the look for somewhere else to hang out. <figure rend="Deter Coyotes Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use lethal deterrents, if necessary. In some cases, you may be able to shoot or otherwise kill coyotes. However, the use of lethal deterrents may or may not be legally permitted in your area. Check with your local game management office or county extension agency for details. <figure rend="Deter Coyotes Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can use paintball guns as an alternative to lethal weapons.</item>
<item>High-powered water guns filled with vinegar can also be used to deter coyotes.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Handling a Coyote Encounter</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do not run. If you encounter a coyote at close range, the most important thing to do is to stand your ground. Running away may cause the coyote to see you as prey. <figure rend="Deter Coyotes Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to make yourself appear taller. Stand up, and try to get on top of something like a stump, rock, or chair.</item>
<item>If there are small children nearby, pick them up for safekeeping.</item></list></item>
<item>Do not approach the animal. Coyotes mostly prefer to keep to themselves. If you keep your distance from the animal, they will probably slink away all by themselves. If you go up to the animal, however, they might feel frightened and become aggressive to protect themselves. <figure rend="Deter Coyotes Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make noise. Shouting, clapping, and yelling also work to deter coyotes at close range. As soon as you see one, make some noise. <figure rend="Deter Coyotes Step 13.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Teach young children to shout “Go away, coyote!” if they see one. That way, if you’re not with them, but hear “coyote,” you’ll know what is happening and can come help them.</item></list></item>
<item>Act aggressively. Keep your distance, but show the coyote you are something they don’t want to mess with. Wave your arms around and stamp your feet. Throw things like rocks or sticks. Hold something like a broom, walking stick, or shovel. <figure rend="Deter Coyotes Step 14.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If coyotes are common in your area, you might also want to carry pepper spray as a deterrent.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
