<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc170" title="Be Outgoing Outside of School" shortTile="outgoing-outside" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-12-25" dateModified="2018-12-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_Outgoing_Outside_of_School" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Outgoing Outside of School</head><p>For some people, it's easy to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Outgoing">be outgoing</ref> within the context of school, but it gets more difficult when it comes to social events <hi rend="italic">outside</hi> of school. This article focuses on how you can ease that transition.</p>
<p>Have you ever been to a birthday party and you were bored with no one to talk to but everyone else was having a grand time? Have you ever been with friends at a sleepover and couldn't wait until the next morning to leave? Do you feel yourself <hi rend="bold">closing up</hi> and out of the loop when you're hanging with your friends? Hopefully this wikiHow will help you to become more <hi rend="bold">social and outgoing</hi> and less shy!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>A lot of times [not all the time though] people are shy because they aren't <hi rend="bold">confident</hi> in themselves. So what you should do is practice. Practice talking (read out loud, talk into a voice recorder, etc). Getting used to talking in general will make it easy for you to talk to people that you don't necessarily know (like people you may meet at a party). And a lot of times, when you're out with your friends you do <hi rend="bold">crazy stuff</hi>, like singing, dancing, taking pictures, etc. And if you're not comfortable with yourself, doing these things in public can cause you to just sit out and watch. So while you're alone in your room, practicing some of your dance moves so you don't end up looking like a fool! Sing into your mirror or in the car! And take pictures of course with different "faces" and poses. Do these things on your own, so in front of your friends you're more confident in yourself! <figure rend="Be Comfortable and Confident With Yourself Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get to know people! It helps if you get to know someone one on one first. So when you make new friends email them or call them, and get to know them [not just as classmates]! If you get to know people, then when you plan something you'll know what type of activities to plan so everyone will have fun and it won't be awkward. <figure rend="Report an Emergency Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you feel like you're still not fully with it, then try to get used to some things. If you don't like rap music, don't complain about it at a party! Learn to tolerate things. If you don't like shopping at a certain store, don't whine when your friends want to go in there, just tolerate it. And give things a chance, don't just hate a trend, type, etc. "just because." <hi rend="bold">Don't</hi> be fake and compromise who you are, but give things a chance! <figure rend="Stop Being Emotional Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Smiling always draws people in!</item>
<item>Don't care what people think, yes you have heard this a million times but it's true. Most of the time people tend to not be out there because they are afraid of being judged well news flash your going to get judged anyway so just get out there!</item>
<item>Don't worry about looking goofy, everyone else is looking just as ridiculous, so there's no reason to worry about what others think if they're doing it too!</item>
<item>Don't be afraid to get out and do something! Just do it and have fun with it.</item>
<item>Try to spend time with your friends, not just hanging out ONCE. The more time you spend with them, the more comfortable you'll both be!</item>
<item>Talk to people!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You may feel uncomfortable talking to certain people. <hi rend="bold">Talk to them anyway</hi>, unless you have had a bad history with them and it puts your physical well-being at risk. But, you should always <hi rend="bold">forgive and forget,</hi> no matter who it is.</item>
<item>Don't be stuck up towards people!</item>
<item>This may not always work.</item></list>
</text>
