<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc67" title="Enhance Your Understanding of Different Religions" shortTile="enhance-understanding" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-08-13" dateModified="2019-05-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Enhance_Your_Understanding_of_Different_Religions" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Enhance Your Understanding of Different Religions</head><p>Understanding and connecting with people of different religions can be a fun and interesting way to learn about history and the world around you. Having a basic understanding of what other people believe in will help you have better and more fulfilling conversations with them. You never know when you might learn something new!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Reading about Religions</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Search online for each faith that you are interested in learning about. Websites such as the BBC, the United Religions Initiative, and other organizations will have the general background information about a religion, including its founding story, core beliefs, recent events, holidays, and geographical concentration. <figure rend="Enhance Your Understanding of Different Religions Step 1 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, you might be interested in learning about Buddhism, Judaism, and Islam. A quick search about the history of these religions will yield plenty of results.</item>
<item>It might be helpful to break this research into sections such as history, prominent figures, or core beliefs. Alternatively, choose just one of the websites mentioned above to do all of the reading you can. This will keep your research focused.</item></list></item>
<item>Search for and carefully read religious publications sponsored by each religion. Many religious organizations have online publications directly from their leaders that discuss current events in the church and refer back to their main core beliefs. Many religious leaders are active online, especially on social media websites, so check out social media accounts for links to meaningful articles and upcoming events or holidays. <figure rend="Enhance Your Understanding of Different Religions Step 2 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Websites such as the Catholic <ref target="https://www.vaticannews.va">https://www.vaticannews.va</ref> will have information about current events and teachings.</item>
<item>If you want to learn more about Judaism, check out <ref target="https://jps.org/">https://jps.org/</ref>, which has a large resource library with Jewish publications.</item></list></item>
<item>Read the Holy Book of a religion that interests you. Most religions have a text or set of texts that has all of the teachings and stories of the religion. Normally these books are pretty lengthy and complex. If you are truly interested in a religion, read their Holy Book (or some parts of it that interest you). This will give you a good idea of how the religion is set up. <figure rend="Enhance Your Understanding of Different Religions Step 3 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Getting Involved</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Attend a religious service. If there is a religion that you are particularly interested in learning about, find a nearby place of worship and attend one of their services. Here, you will be able to see the beliefs in practice and participate in an act of worship. It’s also a great place to make connections and meet new people. <figure rend="Enhance Your Understanding of Different Religions Step 4 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Start-a-Conversation-with-a-Stranger">Have a conversation</ref> with someone of a different faith. To deepen your understanding of a religion, sit down and have a conversation with someone of a different religion. Ask them questions about their faith and how they practice their religion. Answer any questions that they might have about yours. <figure rend="Enhance Your Understanding of Different Religions Step 5 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example, you can ask questions such as “How many times per week do you worship?” or “What is your favorite religious holiday and why?” or “What does your faith mean to you?”</item>
<item>They will likely have questions about your faith as well, and you should answer them to the best of your ability.</item></list></item>
<item>Meet with a religious leader. If you have more complex questions about the foundation or history of a religion, or if you are confused by its practices, set up an appointment to meet with a leader of that religion. They are well educated and should have the answers to most of your questions. <figure rend="Enhance Your Understanding of Different Religions Step 6 Version 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>They might refer you to some additional reading or research to help answer your questions. Be prepared to leave with a little bit of homework.</item></list></item>
<item>Listen to music from the religion. Cultural aspects of a religion are very important, and many religions have specific music that they incorporate into worship. Listening can give you an idea of the mood of the religion when it comes to worship, and the words (if there are any) can communicate stories from the religion. <figure rend="Enhance Your Understanding of Different Religions Step 7 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Sign up for an online course about religion. Taking an online course will provide you with a more structured means of learning about religion. Many colleges offer classes online that will work with your schedule and that can be completed in your free time. You can also find options on websites like Coursera. <figure rend="Enhance Your Understanding of Different Religions Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Attend a community lecture. Some communities, especially those with a diverse population, will sponsor lectures by different religious leaders. These bring together people of different beliefs to have a conversation about religion and society. Check your local church and community calendars to see if there are any upcoming that you could attend. <figure rend="Enhance Your Understanding of Different Religions Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always start with studying the history of the religion.</item>
<item>Remember that there's a serious basis to religions that are only used as punchlines in the West - there's much more to Rastafarianism than weed, for example.</item>
<item>Talk to scholars both from and outside of the religion you are studying. It is important to have multiple perspectives.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always show respect and be polite when discussing religion. This is a very personal topic and should be handled with care.</item></list>
</text>
