<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc6" title="Be a Beauty Guru" shortTile="beauty-guru" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-02-24" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Beauty_Guru" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Beauty Guru</head><p>makeup?  check   crazy cool style? check    gorgeous hair? check, these are some things that can help you become a BEAUTY GURU!!!!!!!!!!!!!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>makeup</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>knowing how to put on makeup, is very important to becoming a beauty guru.begin by identifying what colors suite you. when it comes to figuring out which eyeshadows and what concealer is your type, its pretty simple to figure out. one way would be to go to a local beauty place and ask them about which makeup products would work best for you. If you don't really like going to beauty stores to ask for advice, then play around with makeup. see what works best for you and what does not. also try not to go to heavy on the makeup because it sometimes look really bad and it can make you look in some ways old, which we both know your gorgeous and not old.</item></list>
<head>clothing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>clothing is very similare to makeup, you really have to know what suites you. first figure out what colors you looks best in, do you looks better in bright colors or darker colors?then figure out what type of styles fit you. for example: does something tight and high waisted look good or maybe something loose and retro looking? it is all up to what looks good on you.now if you think you don't exactly have the best eye for seeying what looks good or not, you can always go to a designer or an expertise clothing shop and ask them what would look good on you.</item></list>
<head>hair</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>hair is super imporatant and it can also show off your mood. try to always do updos or styles that are cute and classy or instyle. mostly do updos when you feel great or when maybe its boiling out. when it comes to letting your hair down, try to style it with a hat or a beanie maybe. you would mostly wear your hair down if its cold outside or your just are lazy. usually you wear your hair down during seasons like fall or winter, because its just the trend. also hair can really help to complete your style, so even if it is winter see how the updo would complete the style.</item></list>
<head>social media</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>going on social media is a big part. social media can really help you with finding out what the trends are right now or it can hel p you with diy crafts or room decor. it can also inspire you in lots of things. also if you want start your own YouTube channel or if your friends have a YouTube channel try to be in those channels a lot, that is usually how you get known.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>also ask your friends for tipsfriends can usually tell you what trends are in. they can also help you know what looks good on you and what suites your style</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>when on social media please do not give any personal info away, that can be SUPER DANGEROUS!if you have some trouble with makeup ask someone for help or keep practicing until you get itthe makeup will not harm you if you have trouble with it but it can be a little dangerous, in case you don't know were things go. for example: if you put eyeliner on your lips instead of lipstick</item></list>
</text>
