<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc107" title="Get a Guy to Like You if You Are an Introvert" shortTile="guy-introvert" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-02-16" dateModified="2019-03-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_a_Guy_to_Like_You_if_You_Are_an_Introvert" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get a Guy to Like You if You Are an Introvert</head> So you're trying to get a guy to like you, but you're not the most extroverted person you know? Don't worry! Getting him to like you is easier than you think. Take good care of yourself, capitalize on your introverted strengths, and pay attention to him.
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look for a guy who is compatible with you. A good guy to date is someone you feel comfortable around, or an extrovert; they could convince you to open up. Some guys who seem extroverted are covering up their shyness.
<list type="unordered"><item>Try new things and always have a nice smile on your face.</item></list></item>
<item>Take good care of yourself. If you look your best, you'll look and feel more attractive. Wash your hair, face, and body regularly. Choose a nice-smelling body wash, shampoo, or subtle perfume. Brush your teeth and use mouthwash. Some guys just like to chill and if you care too much about your appearance he will not pay attention to you because he will be a little uncomfortable.</item>
<item>Own your introversion. As an introvert, you have unique skills and strengths. You can highlight these to better attract a potential partner. You have...
<list type="unordered"><item>A thoughtful, reflective personality. Sometimes just to have differences is a good thing.</item>
<item>Listening skills</item>
<item>Lots of knowledge</item>
<item>Hidden depths</item>
<item>A well-developed viewpoint</item></list></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Listen">Be interested</ref> (not just interesting). If you feel more comfortable listening than talking, go for it! People love to be heard, and you have an advantage here. Ask him questions about...
<list type="unordered"><item>His interests and passions</item>
<item>His family</item>
<item>His pets</item>
<item>His favorite places</item>
<item>His plans and dreams</item></list></item>
<item>Share the things that you find interesting. As you speak, watch his body language, to see if he is interested in the subject. If he is, you two can enjoy a long and thoughtful discussion. If not, switch gears and ask him a question about his life.
<list type="unordered"><item>Someone who is interested will generally look at you, nod and make remarks at times, fidget minimally, and turn their face and body towards you. (This may vary due to cultural differences or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Interpret_Autistic_Body_Language">disabilities</ref>.)</item></list></item>
<item>Be your best self, not someone else. There's a difference between being your best, and trying to be someone you think will please him. There's no need to pretend to love something that bores you, try to impress him, or underplay your talents. If you get him to like you by being dishonest about yourself, then he isn't here for the real you.
<list type="unordered"><item>If he doesn't like you as you are, then he's a bad match for you. Move on, you'll find a better guy who likes you as you are.</item></list></item>
<item>Be honest about your feelings. If you are nervous, say so. He is probably nervous too. It may be your first moment of mutual empathy.
<list type="unordered"><item>Notice something you both love or care about, things that would make you think, that he's somehow similar to you, and connect it to fun and excitement when you are together.</item>
<item>Always be truthful! Hiding behind a fake personality is never the way to go.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
