<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc24" title="Care for a House of Pets" shortTile="care-house-pets" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-01-04" dateModified="2017-03-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Care_for_a_House_of_Pets" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Care for a House of Pets</head><p>If you have several  pets such as dog ,bird ,cat, mouse and turtle ..... they can be hard to care for all at once . Your dog may hate the sqeaukey nosie of bird chirping.while  the dog barking may give the bird a heart attack.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>When rasing more than one animal they may not like each other</item>
<item>If introducing your dog to a new bird, or small animal let the dog in calm and let it sniff a lot Dogs, like cats, are predators in the wild, and most will naturally view a bird as prey who should be pursued and conquered. Even if your dog is timid with a less active  prey drive than others, the instinct to hunt a bird will always certainly be there somewhere. Start very slowly when introducing your dog to your bird in order to help them get used to each other. Bring them into contact with each other over the course of a couple of weeks so that they can really become comfortable together Rushing things could possibly lead to mistakes and accidents, which can be life threatening for your pets in you aren't careful. . If small animal seems scared spearate the two be prepared to stop any fights . DO NOT LEAVE IN ROOM UNSUPERVISED .It’s best to let dogs become familiar with each other on neutral territory or outdoors. Each dog should be walked separately on a leash, and each walker should have a bag of tasty  treats or food broken into small pieces. At first, walk the dogs at a distance where they can see each other but are not too provoked by each other’s presence</item></list>
<p>If you’re thinking of getting a cat for your dog or a dog for your cat, it’s important to consider both animals’ personalities. It may be helpful to look for a companion that has already been exposed to the other species in the past.
If a dog attempts to aggressively chase, pick up or any cat, it is best to not even consider getting a cat — or at least to proceed with caution. Additionally, a dog who growls, lunges at or obsessively barks at a cat would probably do best in a cat-free environment. Likewise, a cat who growls, swats at, runs from or hides from dogs would probably prefer to not live with a dog.
If a dog loves chasing things, then a fearful, shy cat who runs away probably wouldn’t be the best choice, as it could trigger the dog to chase. Similarly, an energetic cat who runs and pounces would fall into this same category. A better match here would be a calm, confident cat who will not run (in fear or play).
If a dog plays roughly, it is best to avoid kittens or elderly cats who can easily be hurt. Instead, stick to playful adults who are interested in play, but are also confident enough to take care of themselves. If a cat is rambunctious or playful, a dog that is playful, but gentle, could be a great option.With cats bring in both calm in a room with food so that they are comfortable. if hyper they may be almared an attack</p>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If they do not do well together give it  time .</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Becareful</item></list>
</text>
