<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc204" title="Live a Better Teenage Life" shortTile="live-better-teenage" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-08-21" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Live_a_Better_Teenage_Life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Live a Better Teenage Life</head><p>During some part of our life, we will regret things we did in the past, or what we're doing now. But it's never too late to start over! You can be more positive, you can be more organized, be deep into conversations. You can be a new you. It's you story. You may need a little whiteout and that's okay, we all make mistakes. So write a new chapter, and explore a new you. Run free, exactly how you want too. You are in control. You can start over.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Who Are You?  Think to yourself, who am I? How do I act to fellow friends or family? Do I have bad grades? Am I disorganized? Are my thoughts negative? Think of everything about yourself, the good parts the bad parts. Get to know the true you. Is this who you want to be? We all feel like we need to change sometime in our life. It's ok to change. It's ok to start new. So take the journey and find out who you truly are.</item>
<item>Find Your Flaws.   We all have flaws, that's ok its normal. Look around you, are you disorganized? Have you been mean or negative? Find what you want to change and write it down in a notebook. Ponder on these thoughts and figure out how you can be better. Don't hide from your weaknesses, it won't help. Facing your biggest fears and challenges may be very hard, but in the end it will let you lighten up. You won't have heavy grudges on your shoulders of the past. The main part of this course is to let go of the negative burdens of the past and focus on the present.</item>
<item>Forgiveness.     Was there anyone who hurt you? Have you ever forgave them? Don't hold a grudge, it can be the worst weight on your shoulder. Forgive the person that hurt you. We all make mistakes. We learn from the mistakes we make but we need someone to be on their side to do so. Forgive them, it will help you and them. If you have hurt anyone or said something insulting or negative. Ask for forgiveness. So you start new with this acquaintance relationship. If they don't forgive you, then move on. This person doesn't care for you if they don't forgive when you ask. Don't have a relationship with this person, it will make other relationships much more complicated. Move on. Forgiveness is the main subject of a good connected relationship. If you have a good relationship with others, you will have a good relationship with yourself.</item>
<item>Organization.       Having a cluttered living place will overwhelm your life and make you more stressed. Look at everything you have, what do you use daily, what makes you happy? The things that have no meaning to you or you don't truly need or use then it has done its purpose and needs to move on. Being organized can help with school or work. It will be much easier to find supplies. Organization will make you feel free and comfortable with you room or living area. Being Organized and clean has helped me so much and already made me a better person.</item>
<item>Listen to Music.  Listening to your favorite music, whether it's classical or rock can really help you calm down or feel energized. You feel happy (unless it's gloomy music). If you are about to do a huge presentation or speech, listen to music before you go up in front of your peers. This will help you feel energized and pumped to talk to everyone. So make sure to pull out some headphones and an mp3 player when you feel like the whole world is closing on you.</item>
<item>Be an Optimistic Person.    Find the positive side to every problem. Trust me, everyone wants to be around someone who is positive, outgoing and happy. This will cause less problems and fights. So next time you feel like bursting out something negative, hold it back.</item>
<item>Let Go.     Let go, let go of burdens, let go of grudges, let go of hate, let go of clutter. Let go of everything that doesn't make you happy. Start over, start new. Become the new you. Enjoy life that will keep you moving forward. Become who you want to be, become the true you.                                                                   August 20, 2015</item></list>
</text>
