<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc106" title="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy" shortTile="partner-involved" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-10-03" dateModified="2019-07-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_Your_Partner_Involved_in_Your_Pregnancy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy</head><p>Pregnancy is normally an exciting time for expecting mothers. Sometimes, however, it can be challenging to get your partner involved in your pregnancy. Inviting your partner to participate in doctor’s visits, preparing your home for the baby, and celebrating your pregnancy can help you get your partner more involved.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Involving Your Partner in the Daily Aspects of Your Pregnancy</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Invite your partner to each doctor’s appointment. While every prenatal appointment isn’t going to be extremely exciting, it’s important that your partner is invited to all of them. Encourage them to accompany you to as many as they can. This is an easy way for them to feel connected to you, your pregnancy, and the health of your baby. <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Give your partner a copy of your appointment schedule. If they use a digital calendar, try adding the appointments to their schedule.</item></list></item>
<item>Let your partner touch your belly regularly. A great way to involve your partner in your pregnancy is to foster physical bonding among you, your partner, and the baby. Encourage your partner to sing or talk to the baby on a regular basis. <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try making a regular ritual of it by asking your partner to sing or talk to the baby before bed each night.</item></list></item>
<item>Give your partner daily updates on how you’re feeling. Chances are your partner has never been pregnant before and might have difficulty relating to what you’re going through. One way to involve them in the daily experience of pregnancy is to update them on how you’re feeling emotionally and physically. This can foster empathy, understanding, and deeper bonding between the two of you. <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you ask your partner how they are feeling as well, and take time to really listen to what they’re saying. This is a new and exciting time for both of you!</item></list></item>
<item>Have a talk about sex during pregnancy. Chances are you and your partner will have questions about having sex while you are pregnant. Explore the topic together by reading about it, doing online research, and talking to your doctor. This will help you both feel more comfortable about having sex while you are expecting. <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask your partner for help with everyday tasks. Being pregnant means you might not be able to do daily activities with ease. Instead of struggling to vacuum or put the groceries away, ask your partner for help with these tasks. This will contribute to a feeling of involvement for your partner and ease the burden on you and your body. <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Preparing for the Baby’s Arrival with Your Partner</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Involve your partner in the birth plan. Coming up with a birth plan is an important part of any pregnancy and a great way to get your partner involved. Whether you choose a natural non-medicated home birth or a plan that includes having a C-section, make sure your partner is involved in all aspects of the process. <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try reading a book on birthing plans together. This can give your partner an idea of the different options and provide an opportunity for the two of you to come up with a plan as a couple.</item></list></item>
<item>Register for a childbirth class together. Involving your partner in the education process is key to getting and keeping them involved in your pregnancy. A childbirth class is a great way to bond and to learn about what to expect during childbirth. <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Aim for a class that fits into their schedule, as well as yours.</item></list></item>
<item>Choose a baby name together. One way to get your partner more involved with your pregnancy and preparing for the arrival of your bundle if joy is through the naming process. Rather than choosing a name on your own, make it a group decision. Explore names in books and online until you settle on one (or several) that you are both excited about. <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create the baby registry together. Chances are your friends, co-workers, or family are planning a baby shower for you and have asked you to create a registry for items you will need. These will include things like a crib and playpen to make your home baby-ready. Involve your partner in picking out items for the registry. <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Set a nursery budget as a couple. Preparing your home for the arrival of an infant can be a time consuming and costly endeavor. Working together as a couple to set a budget and stick to it will involve your partner in the pregnancy as well as help you avoid unexpected arguments over how much to spend on a crib or a changing table. <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Design the nursery together. An important part of the nesting process will be setting up the nursery. Rather than making all the decorating decisions yourself, involve them in the process. You might be pleasantly surprised with the results! <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Let your partner assemble the nursery furniture if possible.</item></list></item>
<item>Put your partner in charge of hospital preparations. As your due date approaches, there will be lots to do. This includes packing a hospital bag, planning the route to the hospital, and installing the infant car seat. Put your partner in charge of these important tasks! Accomplishing them will help your partner feel more intimately involved in the childbirth process. <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Celebrating Your Pregnancy with Your Partner</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Include your partner in the pregnancy announcement. Make sure that the announcements about your pregnancy include your partner. Don’t decide how to do it by yourself. Instead make sure they are involved in the decision and actual announcing. Tag them on Facebook, include them when you break the news to family on Skype, or send out a printed announcement with a photo of both of you. <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Request their presence at the baby shower. A baby shower doesn’t have to be all about the woman who is pregnant with the child. Your partner can be involved in the planning of the baby shower and can attend as well. This can help them feel involved in your pregnancy and the anticipation of the baby’s arrival. <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 14 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask his friends to throw him a Dadchelor party. If your partner is a woman, ask her friends to throw her a Momchelor party. Your friends are planning a baby shower for you, and your partner also deserves a celebration before the baby arrives. <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 15 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Give your partner an active role in the delivery room. Celebrating the baby's arrival begins in the delivery room. Give them roles they feel comfortable with. This can mean helping you with breathing and delivery or even cutting the umbilical cord. <figure rend="Get Your Partner Involved in Your Pregnancy Step 16 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
