<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc11" title="Buy a Coatimundi Pet" shortTile="buy-coatimundi-pet" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2019-01-25" dateModified="2019-08-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Buy_a_Coatimundi_Pet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Buy a Coatimundi Pet</head><p>Are you interested in buying a Coatimundi? This article will teach you how to buy a Coatimundi. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Research</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find out about Coatimundis, their upkeep and running costs.
<list type="unordered"><item>Find out if you are allowed to keep them. Separate states and countries have differing laws about exotic pets such as these.</item></list></item>
<item>Determine whether you are capable of caring for them. While coatis are extremely cute when young, they often become aggressive and dangerous as they get older. They have destructive behavior and you will always need to wear thick gloves when handling them, as they have sharp teeth and will easily bite you.
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember, these are wild animals and can only be partially trained.</item>
<item>They are not a sensible pet to have with young children.</item>
<item>Unless you are very confident about looking after this animal, it is not wise to continue.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Buying and extra fees</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a coati for sale.
<list type="unordered"><item>They are often within a price range of between 600 to 1000 dollars (450 to 750 pounds). Always look for a hand-raised coati as they are often much less aggressive.</item>
<item>You may have to apply for a permit or license to keep one.</item>
<item>You may also have to have it shipped to where you live.</item></list></item>
<item>Buy a large enough cage/enclosure.
<list type="unordered"><item>Your enclosure must be very big so as to give them enough room to move around. They will also need one outside, and many people recommend one with measurements like 10 x 10 x 10 feet. They cannot be left to roam around the house as they will destroy your furniture.</item></list></item>
<item>Understand what coatis can eat. Coatis can survive on a diet of grain-free dog food. You will also need to feed them some vegetables, but be sure to research what they can and can't eat (keep avocados, chocolate and anything with caffeine in away from them).</item>
<item>Get plenty of toys and games for your coati. This is important as they need lots of mental stimulation and are naturally very curious and clever animals.</item></list>
<head>Caring for you coati</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Play with it. You will want to keep it occupied, as it may become aggressive and destructive if you leave it alone.</item>
<item>Train it.
<list type="unordered"><item>You can litter train a coati (although this would take extra work)</item>
<item>You can also train it to go for walks on a harness and leash.</item></list></item>
<item>Closely supervise if any children want to play with it. <hi rend="bold">Never</hi> leave children alone with your coati; the result can be destructive.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are buying a male over six months old, make sure he is already neutered.</item>
<item>Coatis need a strict diet: 60 percent high grade, grain free dog food, 10 percent fresh fruit, 20 percent poultry, beef, or eggs, 10 percent vegetables (and more as necessary)</item>
<item>A good option for an outdoor cage is a walk-in aviary.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Coatis are not ideal pets and you should not attempt to acquire one if you have not got exactly the right environment for them</item>
<item>Coatis will destroy things so keep anything valuable out of reach</item>
<item>Coatis prefer warmer environments so do not keep them if you live somewhere cold all year round.</item></list>
</text>
