<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc36" title="Trap Your Pet" shortTile="trap-pet" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2005-11-27" dateModified="2017-04-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Trap_Your_Pet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Trap Your Pet</head><p>You may have to trap a very nervous or unhandled animal to carry out necessary tasks like a visit to the vet.  It is necessary that the animal is comfortable as possible and does not get injured.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>One (Indoors or Outside)</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prop the box/basket up upside down with the stick. <figure rend="Trap Your Pet Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Attach the leash/rope to the stick. (Alternatively, you can hook a clothes hanger to the stick, and then attach the leash/rope to the clothes hanger). <figure rend="Trap Your Pet Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Put the food or treat in the box/basket. For best results, put the food as far back as you can. <figure rend="Trap Your Pet Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hide a bit away but close enough so that you can pull the leash or rope. <figure rend="Trap Your Pet Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pull the rope once animal is under the box/basket. <figure rend="Trap Your Pet Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Two (Indoors only)</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Leave your pet alone so it will calm down.  Make sure someone is watching it so it does not get injured in the process of chewing wires, getting caught behind furniture, etc.   <figure rend="Trap Your Pet Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try to lure it with food.  Pick the animal's favorite treats.  Break them up into smaller pieces so that the animal does not consume too much sugar, etc.  Pick a food that is safe for the animal, and if you are unsure, it's best to look it up. <figure rend="Trap Your Pet Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If all else fails, try to move your animal into a corner.  Then pet it to calm him/her down, and eventually, pick it up in a way that will not hurt the animal.   <figure rend="Trap Your Pet Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you do not let the pet know you are there.</item>
<item>This works best with cats or dogs.</item>
<item>If your pet is not a cat or dog, you can try different, original 'traps' in which food is the basic bait.</item>
<item>If you use the clothes hanger, the hook should be hooked to the bottom.</item>
<item>If your pet is strong enough and will come to a hard, strong bait (Ex: a dog bone), you can tie the string to the bait and have the bait in the middle of the basket so you do not have to stay and watch.</item>
<item>For turtles, you could fill a little bowl (bigger than the turtle) with water and sprinkle in food. Make a ramp that isn't very steep for the turtle to climb in to. Then WAIT... this, unlike the other trap may NOT work.</item>
<item>If the pet is a cat, you can have a short stick propping it up from the side and tied to the opposite side of the basket to act as a tripwire with the bait behind it.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Trapping an animal can damage your relationship with it. Only do it if you must catch the animal for worming, de-fleaing etc</item>
<item>Don't pull the rope/leash too fast or it takes a second longer for the trap to fall.</item>
<item>Remember, trapping your pet is different than <hi rend="italic">entrapping</hi> your pet. Not only is this illegal, but it is a very good way to alienate your pet. Although the conviction may not stand up in court, do you really want to be the guy who seduced his dog?</item>
<item>Pull the rope once the animal is under it a lot. If you pull it too soon and the animal isn't in far enough, then it can run.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Laundry basket or box</item>
<item>Stick</item>
<item>Leash or rope</item>
<item>Food or treat</item>
<item>Clothes hanger ((optional but recommended)</item>
<item>Towel</item></list>
</text>
