<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc58" title="Awaken Your Spirit" shortTile="awaken-spirit" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-08-26" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Awaken_Your_Spirit" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Awaken Your Spirit</head><p>There is an energy inside all of us that is unique to the individual. The user can bring this energy forth and apply it to any goal they wish to achieve and receive positive progress in return. By following the steps provided you can bring harmony and happiness to your life.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take a minute, sit down, and take a few deep breaths. Close your eyes and turn off distractions. The objective is to think clearly. Imagine the happiness you wish to achieve. <figure rend="Awaken Your Spirit Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait until after you have relaxed to begin. <figure rend="Awaken Your Spirit Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create two lists on paper. Writing them out will help you visualize the process of success. Starting with the “do not” list, write out all the negativity you do not wish to have, keeping your main goal in mind. Then using that list as inspiration, write out the positive things you want to incorporate in your life. <figure rend="Awaken Your Spirit Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For example: You don't want to be lazy and inactive. You want to wake up early, eat right and exercise. All in order to achieve the goal of being physically fit, for this will bring you happiness.  The lists will help you manifest your goals.</item></list></item>
<item>Take a few moments to create within your body the feeling that you would have as if you accomplished your goals or desires. And try to do something that will bring up these feelings of happiness and accomplishment as often as possible. IF your goal is to be more physically fit, start taking walks everyday, experiencing the feelings of accomplishment will release positivity which then brings like vibrations back to you. <figure rend="Awaken Your Spirit Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Think about your idols. The people who have what you want. What do they have in common that they do habitually. Bloggers, for instance, research daily on what interests them, maybe you shouldn’t watch much TV and Google something. Rich men like to play golf. So if that is who you want to become, pick up the hobby. <figure rend="Awaken Your Spirit Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Step back and realize when your life is going very good, when it’s slowing down, and when it’s starting to progress. If you know how to see this you can make choices that will make that recession period less difficult on your life plans .This feeling of recession could be anywhere in your life such as finances, relationships or it can be emotional. which brings you to your final step. <figure rend="Awaken Your Spirit Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pay attention. If you see something dwindling, give extra attention to that particular aspect.  You must Push past the negative to turn the situation around to where you are again happy with the circumstances. The goal is to have big ups and little downs. <figure rend="Awaken Your Spirit Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Understand that everything comes down to two options. You can do everything you can to fight for what you desire, or you can sit back and wait for a better opportunity. Since balance is important in our lives, I would choose from my heart to decide which direction to take. Knowing that there is no right or wrong choice. <figure rend="Awaken Your Spirit Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember that everything in nature is alive, if you take the time to build a connection with it the balance in life may become easier. <figure rend="Awaken Your Spirit Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
