<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc130" title="Deal with a Depressed Boyfriend/Girlfriend" shortTile="deal-depressed-boyfriendgirlfriend" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-11-04" dateModified="2016-01-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Deal_with_a_Depressed_Boyfriend%2FGirlfriend" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Deal with a Depressed Boyfriend/Girlfriend</head><p>Depression feels terrible, and it can be hard to relate to a partner who is struggling with it. These tips will help you guide your partner through this difficult time.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take aside your partner to talk. Explain that they've seemed sad lately, and ask if there's anything you can do to help. Offer to listen if they'd like to talk about it.  <figure rend="Woman Helps Sad Man.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't push your partner to share what's wrong. Pressuring them will make them feel like you don't fully respect their feelings. Instead, give them as much space as they'd like, and trust that they'll come to you if they feel that it will help them.</item></list></item>
<item>If they want to talk, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Actively_Listen">listen closely and respectfully</ref>. Give them your undivided, nonjudgmental attention. They may have a concrete reason for being sad, or its only cause may be the chemicals in their brain—which leads them to think that they're sad for no reason.  <figure rend="Man Listening to Woman.png"></figure></item>
<item>Reassure your partner. Let them know that you're there for them, that you love them, and that you care about them. Little words of comfort help a lot more than you might think.  <figure rend="Two Girls Talking about Neurodiversity.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Many depressed people feel guilt about their depression. Assure your partner that they aren't being a burden or wet blanket. Tell them you know that their lack of energy is not their fault.</item></list></item>
<item>Find ways to keep your partner supported so they won't feel alone. Depression is a draining and isolating illness that can remove people from their family and friends. By maintaining a continuous presence in your partner's life, you can help them fight it.  <figure rend="Man and Woman Cuddle.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Spend as much time with them as you can and make them feel needed. It helps a lot when they know that they aren't alone and aren't worthless. Even just a hug helps.</item>
<item>Set up activities with them that include going outdoors. Have a picnic, go out for a walk, go to the park, the beach, even just walk your dog with him/her. Going outdoors can help, since it's a change in environment from what they are usually in when they have depressing thoughts.</item>
<item>Go on a vacation with them for a while if possible. Go to a place they've always wanted to visit, or even just an attraction in town.</item>
<item>You don't have to entertain them singlehandedly! Get a support network of friends, siblings, and parents of your loved one. Together you can check in on your partner frequently, and make sure that they never feel too alone or abandoned.</item></list></item>
<item>Be patient. You may have to repeatedly reassure your partner that they are still a good person, or that you really won't leave them. This is because depression can distort negative thoughts in their minds, making them come back again and again when ordinary people could dismiss them with logic. Continuously supporting your partner in many little ways—hugs, compliments, visits to their house, little gifts, active listening, sweet notes or drawings—can provide a steady stream of positive evidence to help keep the bad thoughts at bay.  <figure rend="Sweet Note.png"></figure></item>
<item>Take good care of yourself. You cannot heal your partner all by yourself, nor can you be much help if you're neglecting your own needs. Remember: You can't save a drowning person if you're too tired to swim.  <figure rend="Young Woman Relaxes with Laptop.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Look after your health. Get plenty of sleep, eat fruits and vegetables, and exercise. This will help you stay alert and centered.</item>
<item>Don't forget your life outside of your partner. Meet up with your friends, take quiet time for your hobbies, spend time on work or school, and do non-romantic things that you enjoy.</item></list></item>
<item>Figure out a plan to proceed where your partner can be fully supported and receive the help they need. <figure rend="Holding Hands.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If they are having suicidal thoughts, they need outside help right away. Offer to help them call a suicide hotline (U.S 1-800-273-8255), use a text-based hotline (e.g. <ref target="http://www.crisischat.org/">CrisisChat</ref>) or tell one of their parents. If they think it would be too hard, offer to do the talking while they sit in the room with you. If they ask you to keep it secret, tell someone anyway—it may save your partner's life.</item>
<item>Offer to help them find a doctor and/or therapist who can help them feel better. Many people find that pills and therapy help them combat depression.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Understand that this is not your fault. Every person has problems in their lives, but you are not this person's problem. Their brain chemicals are not your fault.</item>
<item>Compliment them a lot! Words have a big impact on people. Make sure they know that you love them, care about them, and that they're very important and mean a lot to you.</item>
<item>Make sure they know that you aren't going to leave them or abandon them because of their depression.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't try to minimize their pain by telling them how other people have it worse or that they should be over it by now. This will only increase feelings of guilt and sadness.</item>
<item>Call an emergency number if you believe that something bad is about to happen.</item>
<item>Make sure they don't believe that their depression is their own fault.</item></list>
</text>
