<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc197" title="Have a Good Day As a Teen" shortTile="good-day-teen" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-10-24" dateModified="2019-10-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have_a_Good_Day_As_a_Teen" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have a Good Day As a Teen</head><p>A great day can sharpen your mind, keep you healthy, and even improve the quality of your whole week. There are many things you can do as a kid that'll make you feel good that day.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get up early, and stretch yourself out. Around eight AM should do it.This will help your muscles get used to moving after sleep. If you didn't get your eight to eleven hours of sleep last night, save the great day for tomorrow. You will need energy. <figure rend="Have a Good Day As a Teen Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat a healthy, nutritious, and energy boosting breakfast. Stay away from sugary cereals and caffeine, (no Fruit Loops or Mountain Dew) as they will give you a boost and then make you feel groggy later. Eat oatmeal with fruit, or bacon strips and pancakes. <figure rend="Have a Good Day As a Teen Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do something fun until late morning/before midday. Read a book, play a board game, or just practice your violin until around ten o'clock AM. Do something that you enjoy, and it will get you in a good mood for the rest of the day. <figure rend="Have a Good Day As a Teen Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Bake cookies, lemon bars, or make pudding. You will need it later in the day. Be sure to follow the recipe instructions or you could end up with one tough cookie, or worse. But have fun with it. <figure rend="Have a Good Day As a Teen Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Invite a friend, cousin, or sibling to go to the park with you. Bring a picnic basket full of yummy food, and whatever you made earlier. Play on the swings, slide down the slides, and play some tag or hide 'n seek. <figure rend="Have a Good Day As a Teen Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have a picnic in the park with your friend, cousin, or whoever you brought to the park with you. Lay a soft blanket on the grass and enjoy the experience. Great snacks include sandwiches, apples, pears, cookies, and baked potato/corn chips. Be sure to bring juice boxes and water bottles. <figure rend="Have a Good Day As a Teen Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Play again in the park with your friend. Have fun, play tag, and swing on the swings. You should have lots of energy from the healthy lunch you ate earlier. Be careful though, you don't want to get hurt on the playground. If you get tired, just sit on a park bench and watch the pretty ducks, squirrels, etc. <figure rend="Have a Good Day As a Teen Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Change into your swimming suit and take a dip in the neighborhood pool with your friends and siblings. Make it a party. Swim to your hearts desire, you can even race your friends. Jump into the deep end if you can swim, and have a contest to see who can make the best splash. <figure rend="Have a Good Day As a Teen Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Head home and do something quiet and very fun, like study for school, tidy up your room, organize your dresser, and even practice your musical instrument. If this isn't your style, make something with clay, or just dance around to your favorite music. Sing like nobody is listening, dance like nobody is watching. Just have fun. <figure rend="Have a Good Day As a Teen Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat a tasty dinner with your parents, siblings, and pets. Ask your mom if you can invite a few friends over for dinner. <figure rend="Have a Good Day As a Teen Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Turn in early. Go to bed around seven thirty, eight, or at the latest, nine o' clock. Listen to some relaxing music and move on to dreamland. Maybe next weekend you can have another great day. <figure rend="Have a Good Day As a Teen Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not get up too late, or you will be too groggy and you will not have time for all the wonderful things you would have done that day. Set your alarm clock to turn on the radio in the morning to wake you up.</item>
<item>It's best to do this on the weekend, since you have school during the weekdays.</item>
<item>Apply sunscreen and wear a hat at the pool. A sunburn will really turn your great day sour.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure to do your homework or chores before you go and have fun. Not only will it make you worry about it when having fun, but not doing your homework/chores could lower your grades/anger your parents. Be responsible!</item>
<item>Bites hurt. Always wear bug spray when engaging in outdoor activities for prolonged periods of time.</item></list>
</text>
