<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc144" title="Travel More and Work Less" shortTile="travel-more-work" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-02-23" dateModified="2018-10-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Travel_More_and_Work_Less" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Travel More and Work Less</head><p>Most people would love to travel more and work less. However, to pay for longer trips, you will have to, at first, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_a_Hard_Worker">work hard</ref>, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Save_Money">save</ref> and try not to have too many other obligations in life. When you have done this, you will be able to enjoy the fruits of your labour. There may also be opportunities to work overseas in an area of your interest. By working in a field that you are passionate about, it will not be perceived as work.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_a_Job">Find a well paying job</ref> and save. Initially you will have to work more - not less. This will help build your savings in order for you to travel for long periods of time without working. <figure rend="Travel More and Work Less Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Avoid having children and/or pets. It is harder to save when you have little ones and animals that you have to provide for. You will spend your working life supporting your kids and pets instead of travelling. In addition, you, generally, do not have the freedom to travel for great lengths of time when you have these responsibilities. <figure rend="Travel More and Work Less Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose economical destinations. There are cheaper places in the world to visit for months (and even years) at a time, such as India and South America. However, you will, depending on how long you want to stay, need to make your dollar go further. This means staying at accommodations with basic and perhaps shared facilities, buying groceries instead of eating out, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Use_Public_Transit_when_Traveling">using public transport</ref>, and developing your <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Bargain">bargaining</ref> skills and shopping around for the best deals at all times. <figure rend="Travel More and Work Less Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Obtain a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_a_Work_Visa">work visa</ref> and get a job overseas that is related to an interest of yours. You may, for example, be interested in skiing and apply for work at ski fields outside your country. If you are working in the industry, it is likely you will receive free use of facilities, discounts and other perks. It does not feel like work when you have a job that is related to your hobbies. <figure rend="Travel More and Work Less Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Build_a_Positive_Attitude">positive attitude</ref> towards work. It is all about perspective. Work, like travel, allows you to meet different types of people, grow as a person and develop cultural tolerance. By earning income, you will also reach your travel goals faster. <figure rend="Travel More and Work Less Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember there is some work involved in travelling. Researching, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Plan_a_Trip">planning</ref>, organising and finding the best bargains for your visit overseas takes work in order for your trip to run smoothly. <figure rend="Travel More and Work Less Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>When you intend to travel for long periods of time, look after your health prior to and during your trip. Sleep well, get plenty of exercise and have a balanced diet which includes fruits and vegetables.</item>
<item>It is vital that you purchase travel insurance before taking an extended trip. Please note that it may be cheaper to buy annual travel insurance than insurance for a shorter length of time spent overseas. Compare prices.</item>
<item>Consult your travel doctor and ensure you receive the required vaccinations prior to your trip.</item>
<item>Purchase a travel first aid kit.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Safe_in_a_Foreign_Country">Be a safe traveller</ref>. Always be aware of your surroundings. Research common scams and crimes committed on tourists at your destination or destinations and take the necessary precautions.</item>
<item>Ensure that you do not get sick while overseas. To avoid getting sick, check the quality of water and food you are eating. If you are unable to drink the local water, carry bottled water and do not eat salads or have ice in your drinks. You should also brush your teeth with bottled water. With regards to food, stick to fruits that are peeled and make sure your meals are cooked properly.</item></list>
</text>
