<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc19" title="Hand Feed Baby Birds" shortTile="hand-feed-baby-birds" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-01-29" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Hand_Feed_Baby_Birds" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hand Feed Baby Birds</head><p>This wikiHow explains how to hand-feed a baby bird if one finds its way into the care of humans. This could be due to a bird being orphaned, parent's not giving it accurate care, raising baby birds for selling, or any baby birds found out of their nest outside. Although, if a wild baby bird is found out of it's nest, inexperienced people should no intervene and for the safety of all involved should call a licensed specialist to care for the bird.Use this guide as a starting point to do more research.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Preparing to Feed</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Gather needed supplies. Depending on the size of bird that you are hand-feeding, the supplies you will need may vary. The list typically consists of:
<list type="unordered"><item>Paper towels (both wet and dry)</item>
<item>The food you are feeding the baby bird</item>
<item>Gloves</item>
<item>A bright, safe, warm space</item>
<item>Whatever size feeding apparatus you deem appropriate
<list type="unordered"><item>Large birds like macaws will require a larger feeding apparatus. Smaller birds like parrotlets and hummingbirds will require small pipettes or eye droppers.</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Ensure to have a proper habitat for the baby bird. Create a safe, secure, and warm workplace for the baby bird to be resting as you are trying to feed it, as well as make sure the other baby birds are in a safe location. Most breeders use a plastic tub with towels, to hold the baby birds they are not currently feeding.</item></list>
<head>Providing Proper Nutrition</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Research appropriate food. Learn what type of nutrients are required by the species of bird you are feeding.</item>
<item>Purchase prepackaged powder. Many pet stores carry powders with the correct ratio of nutrients. In that case, all you have to do is add enough water to make it easy for the baby bird to swallow.
<list type="unordered"><item>If ready-made powder is not available, you can make your own food by pureeing all the required ingredients into a fine mash and then add water. If the bird is slightly older, it can also be fed softened dog food, eggs, or dog kibble.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Feeding the Baby Bird</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Commence the feeding process. When you are ready to feed, take one bird out at a time and bring it to your work space.</item>
<item>Make sure to support your baby birds head and body as you are trying to feed.</item>
<item>Coax your bird to eat. Baby birds feeding response typically causes them to readily accept food. This feeding response causes baby birds to open their mouth to easily accept the food their parents bring them. If this is not the case you can carefully open their beaks by pressing on the edges of their mouth and force feed them until they start to readily accept food.</item>
<item>Feed your baby bird until they stop readily accepting food. Alternatively, watch until their crop (the pouch on the front of the neck) seems full, then stop feeding.</item></list>
<head>Finishing the Feeding</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Clean up the baby. Once your baby bird is full, make sure to wipe your birds beak gently with a wet cloth, to get rid of any spilled food. Also, make sure to check that no other parts of their body have food that could dry and cause them discomfort.</item>
<item>Place your baby bird back in their safe holding area. Clean up your work space.
<list type="unordered"><item>It is very important to clean your feeding tool after each feeding and before feeding a different bird (if applicable) to lessen the chance of spreading diseases.</item></list></item>
<item>Feed again in two hours. Once everything has been cleaned up, you can put your baby bird(s) away and wait for two hours, when you get to do it all over again.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure to be <hi rend="italic">extremely gentle</hi> with baby birds. Their bodies are not fully developed and their bones are brittle and can be easily broken.</item>
<item>Baby birds are hard work, but can be very rewarding. If you are not up to the task, find a trained professional that can give your baby bird the best chance of survival.</item></list>
</text>
