<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc173" title="Be an Indian Youth" shortTile="indian-youth" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-03-06" dateModified="2018-10-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_an_Indian_Youth" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be an Indian Youth</head><p>This article mainly focuses on how to explore the actual  "you". How to show the world what Indian youth can do even in stressful conditions means to have guts to solve major problems of India without being a civil servant, or daughter or son of a millionaire. You can take little financial support (if needed) from relatives, friends, communities, trust funds helping children to study, or can give an advertisement in daily newspaper for city students to contribute their leisure time and used books of old junior classes. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find people like you, find retired school teachers and ask them to contribute to teaching such students in their free time. Ask bankers, lawyers and doctors to visit the teaching site at least twice a week if possible, and contribute for students welfare in any way; through money, teaching or guiding related to career for further studies, making students confident and reassure that they too can pursue their dreams.</item>
<item>Visit the places where they live with their family at least once a month to have a conversation with their parents and tell them the importance of education. Tell them to cooperate and make them aware of how and where you teach the students.</item>
<item>Have faith that whatever you do for the welfare of Indians will be fine even without a lot of external support.</item>
<item>Start with short responsibilities like teaching village children under 5 yrs of age。 A tree can be good only if the seed was good。 Children are like wet mud，it is up to you to see how to mould them into strong beautiful pots to grasp a plant.
<list type="unordered"><item>Any undergraduate from any stream can teach students of 5th to 10th standard, at least try，nothing is wrong in trying。Make efforts to explore more and more poor, needy, beggars，sons and daughters in 1 km or 5km area [ if possible] to be the priority for teaching.
<list type="unordered"><item>For teaching，only 2 things are important: - teacher and students。 Infrastructure doesn't matter。You can teach even under the canopy of a big tree, free gardens, rooms at a low rent.</item></list></item>
<item>Tell students that the only thing which can remove poverty from someone's life is knowledge. Education is the only worth which is immortal and can be carried on even after death.</item></list></item>
<item>Teach 20 to 30 students for a one-hour session daily; try to have two or three sessions a day; your time is better spent helping the needy than browsing Facebook or wandering around.</item>
<item>Teach them how to read in English and Hindi, as both of these languages are building blocks of initial education. Tell them to review what is taught for the day twice at home.</item>
<item>Tell them to help each other, as each child is unique in this world; some may be able to grasp a concept faster than others. Tell them to help the average students. As a youth, your advice will be received more readily than that of aged people.</item>
<item>Make them all friendly and helpful to each other.</item>
<item>Remember you won't be able to teach all the subjects, but nonetheless you will be greatly helping them. Something is better than nothing.</item>
<item>Focus mainly on poor, needy kids. Help as much as you can and teach them to pursue their dreams. Teach them good habits along with studies.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't exploit the poor or needy students at the cost of teaching for free.</item>
<item>Make them feel like they can dream of a great future。</item>
<item>Make them believe that if they work hard and be at the top in studies，the government will help them to pursue their dreams.</item>
<item>Every student can't be the best； Don't let the average students feel low， encourage them because while talent is great, hard work is essential.</item>
<item>Tell them to always be positive about life and accept what it gives and what it takes.</item>
<item>If you find yourself alone as a teacher, don't stop helping those students because you are alone. You are already preparing more people like you by teaching those students.</item>
<item>Encourage them to help more kids after they become someone with the resources to do so. That way, poverty and illiteracy will decrease with each generation.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If the students you taught won't help other needy children the way you helped them, don't push them。We all have different paths。</item>
<item>Don't neglect teaching them virtues along with educating them. Otherwise, they might cheat you.</item>
<item>Don't expect anything in return for your good deeds. Be satisfied in knowing that you've helped someone who really needed it.</item></list>
</text>
