<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc164" title="Decorate an Executive Office" shortTile="decorate-executive" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-12-01" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Decorate_an_Executive_Office" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Decorate an Executive Office</head><p>Your office is a place to represent your hard work and achievements. It becomes a second home, and there are many ways to decorate. Choose decorations like art, lights, plants, and elegant furniture. Arrange your office with your guests in mind while showing off your status in the company. Whether you’ve moved into a new office or are looking to revamp your setup, there are many ways to decorate your office. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Choosing Your Decorations</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Purchase elegant, luxurious furniture. Select classic yet luxurious furniture to make your office look professional and stylish. Choose leather upholstery and wood framed pieces. Your office will look refined and regal. <figure rend="Decorate an Executive Office Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Look for traditional details like bun feet, parquet panels, and picture frame drawer fronts, all different finishing touches to furniture. </item></list></item>
<item>Add lamps to cut back on harsh fluorescent lights. Try including indirect lighting, like task lights or lamps, to cut back on fluorescent lighting and give a soft, warm glow to your office. <figure rend="Decorate an Executive Office Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Also try to take advantage of any natural light by selecting opaque curtains or purchasing elegant curtain tie backs.</item></list></item>
<item>Select a warm and welcoming color scheme. Your office should look traditional and elegant, and you can achieve this by using warm and welcoming colors, especially shades of brown. Look for mahogany, walnut, and cherry shades of furniture and decorations. Include neutral colors, like tan, beige, and cream. <figure rend="Decorate an Executive Office Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This scheme is especially relevant for conservative lines of work, like law or banking.</item>
<item>Also use warm accent colors like burgundy, red, or orange.</item></list></item>
<item>Buy art and hang paintings on your walls. Select art that fits your color scheme to brighten up any room. You can purchase art from galleries, art dealers, or websites like Artsy.net. Consider displaying art from local artists to add some style and help your community. <figure rend="Decorate an Executive Office Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Choose art that fits your style, like modern or classic. Go for something colorful or black and white.</item>
<item>You can pick a few different paintings in various sizes. Try for one large painting and a few smaller ones.</item>
<item>Place your art on the wall where it will have a foot or two of space around it, so your art becomes a focal piece.</item></list></item>
<item>Display awards and diplomas. Your executive office is the place to show off your hard work and great abilities. Hang your diplomas or awards on the wall so your guests can see them. <figure rend="Decorate an Executive Office Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use plants, alive or fake. Plants will add a bit of life and color to your space. Go with a potted plant or desk-size bonsai.  If you don’t have time for daily waterings, try adding items like driftwood or fake plants to still add warmth but not interfere with your work day.  <figure rend="Decorate an Executive Office Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Arranging Your Space</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Rearrange the room if it does not make a good first impression. Does your office look professional and neat? Does it reflect your executive status?  First impressions can make all the difference, and you want your office to reflect who you are as an executive. Change up the look of your office by rearranging or buying new decorations if it does not offer a warm and professional first impression. <figure rend="Decorate an Executive Office Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Store extra papers on shelves or in filing cabinets to maintain a neat space. Avoid clutter by establishing proper homes for your work files, like in shelves or cabinets. Try to not stack piles of paper or boxes of documents. You don’t want to decorate your office with clutter. <figure rend="Decorate an Executive Office Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Tidy up your workspace before you leave for the day.</item>
<item>You want your office to look clean and professional at all times.</item></list></item>
<item>Arrange your desk so you can immediately see the door. This is a professional way to arrange your furniture because you look attentive and are responsive. This will give you the ability to easily greet visitors and talk to coworkers. Put your desk in a central position, so it becomes the central focal point in the room. You look professional if you are the focal point <figure rend="Decorate an Executive Office Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Arrange your office so every task has a home. Your office is not professional if it is messy, so designate a particular spot for specific office tasks.  Create a grid system to organize your office. Dedicate certain spots for particular tasks. This will make your room look organized and professional, while helping you keep organized.  <figure rend="Decorate an Executive Office Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Put your printer and copier in one area.</item>
<item>Place your filing cabinet and folders in another spot.</item>
<item>Put your extra pens near your computer.</item>
<item>Place all books and reference materials on a shelf.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider a space for your visitors. Designate a space for guests to sit in your office. You can establish this space at the foot of your desk or right inside the doorway. Find some elegant chairs for seating, and include an end table or coffee table. <figure rend="Decorate an Executive Office Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
