<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc129" title="Handle Your Boyfriend Sleeping with One of Your Family Members" shortTile="handle-boyfriend" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-11-05" dateModified="2019-01-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Handle_Your_Boyfriend_Sleeping_with_One_of_Your_Family_Members" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Handle Your Boyfriend Sleeping with One of Your Family Members</head><p>What could be worse than a boyfriend cheating on you? Him doing it with your family member. This situation is hopefully rare, but if it happens to you, it'll no doubt feel like a betrayal on both sides. How do you move on?</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Stay calm. Okay, being cheated on is never okay, so you don't have to stay totally calm. But try to keep cool and collected to help you decide how to move forward; you'll make better decisions for your future if you manage to keep a somewhat cool head. <figure rend="Handle Your Boyfriend Sleeping with One of Your Family Members Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take some time to think. The heat of the moment isn't the best time to decide if you can move forward as a couple or have to call it quits. Take some time by yourself to think and reflect, before you decide what to do. <figure rend="Handle Your Boyfriend Sleeping with One of Your Family Members Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hear him out. You may feel he doesn't deserve to be heard - and indeed, maybe he doesn't. But you'll know you made a fully informed decision if you take the opportunity to hear his side of the events and his reasons, before you act. <figure rend="Handle Your Boyfriend Sleeping with One of Your Family Members Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide what path to take forwards. The following steps will be different depending on what you decide to do: <figure rend="Handle Your Boyfriend Sleeping with One of Your Family Members Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you decide to stay: Sometimes people make mistakes, and they ask for forgiveness. If the relationship is worth while then you should consider talking to your boyfriend and ask him what is it that drove him to cheat on you with a family member. Promise each other that this will never happen again.</item>
<item>If you choose to break up with your boyfriend: You should let him know that the reason why you are breaking up is because he did something that crossed the line with you. Make sure to give him closure.
<list type="unordered"><item>Cut your boyfriend off. If you choose for the relationship to be over, then you should really not have any contact with your boyfriend. The more contact you have with him the more painful the experience will be and the longer it will take to get over him.</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Confront your family member. Ask your family member the whole story in a calm way. They are more likely to tell you the truth when they don't feel threatened by you. <figure rend="Handle Your Boyfriend Sleeping with One of Your Family Members Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try to forgive. You can never get rid of your family, but you can get rid of hateful feelings towards someone who hurt you. <figure rend="Handle Your Boyfriend Sleeping with One of Your Family Members Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Decide whether you want to speak to your family member any time soon, or if you ever want to speak to them again. This does not mean that you have not forgiven them. Maybe you are not prepared to talk or see them for a while until you are no longer hurt by the situation.</item></list></item>
<item>Move forwards. Whether you decide to stay with your boyfriend or not, you'll want to find a way to move past the event. If you've broken up with him, start fresh and focus on yourself and the relationships with people who respect you. If you've decide to stick with him, move forwards together as a couple; do something to signify that you're "starting fresh" and putting the past behind you. Perhaps go for a vacation away together, or "reset" your anniversary date to now. <figure rend="Handle Your Boyfriend Sleeping with One of Your Family Members Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you do decide to stay together, don't hold it over him forever. The healthy way to move in is to put the past behind you and start over, rather than hold a grudge and bring it up with every fight you have. It's easier said than done, but moving on should be your goal.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't do anything crazy to harm people. Control your emotions, and anger towards people.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure that you get the whole story in order to be fair to everyone</item></list>
</text>
