<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc20" title="Train a Pet (Land Animal)" shortTile="train-pet-land-animal" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-12-28" dateModified="2017-12-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Train_a_Pet_%28Land_Animal%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Train a Pet (Land Animal)</head><p>Training a pet can be difficult, but if you do it right, it will be easy. Training a land animal is quick but can also require some patience. However, it will pay off!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Gather all needed materials, this will vary for all different types of pets.
<list type="unordered"><item>Food or reward of some kind</item>
<item>Leash and/or collar</item>
<item>Gloves (if the animal is viscous)</item>
<item>Patience!</item></list></item>
<item>Choose a name for your pet, as this will come in handy. You will need to call your pet in a lot of different ways. Make sure that your animal knows you, otherwise it will act skittish around you. If you got your animal from a shelter, it may have been previously mistreated by something or someone, so treat your pet kindly.</item>
<item>The basic commands are come, stay, sit, down, no, okay or yes. These commands are simple to master, start with "no"and <hi rend="italic">okay" first. Reward your pet when it accomplishes a command. Also, if you live in a more than one story house, also teach your pet to climb Stairs.</hi></item>
<item>Practice with your pet. When you feel your pet has mastered these, you can move on to trickier commands (spin, roll over, beg, bark).</item>
<item>Go for a walk with your pet! If you live nearby a park, go there with your pet on a leash. This will allow you, as a new owner, to see how your pet reacts to others. Make sure to not make your pet do anything it doesn't want to.</item>
<item>Establish rules with your pet. This is very important!! Teach your pet to deposit waste outside, not eat certain foods, do not bite, etc. don't give in to your pet, otherwise you will show weakness. Then the pet might try to exploit you. Always be in control!!</item>
<item>Is your pet registration complete? Is your pet checked at the vet? You need to do this regularly, so you could have the vet office call you when it is time for an appointment. If your dog feels sick, CALL THE VET!!</item>
<item>Make sure to feed your pet regularly, and allow him or her time to play. Once your pet is potty trained, when you go to work you could let them roam free. Your pet is a living thing and deserves to be treated with care! Make time for them every day and it will make being a pet owner worth it! (Sometimes cats can be left alone but sometimes they will want to play! Don't feel disappointed if your cat does not play, cats can be very solitary creatures.)</item>
<item>As you probably know, some animals don't mix together. Cats vs. dogs, cats vs. birds, etc. Be sure that these enemy animals are either kept apart, or do not fight. Your pet might not like some other animal and that is fine. Remember that your pet can be traumatized by something and that will effect them permanently.</item>
<item>Enjoy your pet and welcome it into your family! Now you are done with this article, How to Train Your Pet.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>For the "food or reward" part, you should find out the kind of thing your animal likes. Make sure they are not allergic to anything, or this could cause problems.</item></list>
</text>
