<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc43" title="Start an Evil Cult" shortTile="start-evil-cult" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-12-07" dateModified="2017-01-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Start_an_Evil_Cult" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Start an Evil Cult</head><p>So you were sitting in your cubicle or desk today when you thought, "Wouldn't it be cool to start my own evil cult?" We've all been there, nothing to be ashamed of, but would you do this? You've searched it up on your favorite search engine, internet explorer, but you can't seem to find much on the subject. Well don't worry my friend, this is what you have been looking for.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a reason for starting your cult. You are sure you want to do this, but why exactly? Do some soul searching to figure out why you want to dedicate the rest of your life to this cult. Maybe it's because you're just bored, want to overthrow the government, or because you want to watch all of your enemies burn in the fiery pits of hell.</item>
<item>Pick something or someone to worship. Cults like to obsess over things, find something for yours to. It could be someone like satan or jeb bush, or an object such as a holy chalice (which you secretly bought at goodwill for 50 cents) or that vintage star trek action figure you got from ebay.</item>
<item>ROBES, ROBES, ROBES... What's a cult without long black robes? You need plenty of robes for your cult members. If you are rich, you could even have your cult name embroidered on them!</item>
<item>Speaking of cult names. You need a cult name! How else is the government supposed to track you down? Several things to take into consideration when coming up with a name are: your values, who/ what you worship, your leader's name, and edgy words that will sound cool in a name. Some good examples of cults are: Scientology, Heaven's Gate, and The Manson Family.</item>
<item>Buy the supplies you need for meetings. What are you going to do when you meet? What do you need when you meet? Buy those things, if you can't think of anything, candles, sage, and syringes.</item>
<item>Create an altar. This is an optional step, but is highly practiced. Altars usually have a picture of whatever/ whomever you are worshiping, candles surrounding it, flowers, sage or lavendar sprinkled around it, incense burning, and money layed before it. Other options are blood, bones, and fingernails. Once you have your altar set up, you should come up with a chant, oath, ward, or prayer to say to it every day.</item>
<item>Make a set of rules before allowing people to join. Get a piece of paper and list all of the rules required for somone in your cult. Some examples are: Never wash your body on fridays, set up an altar in your house and bring a (no longer living) sacrifice to it every night, you must go to the cult's own school of satanism, or before eating something with gluten in it, you must hop on your left foot three times.</item>
<item>Get people to be in your cult. Advertise your cult by telling people on your reddit forums about it, posting an advertisement at your work and/ or school, and making your own website on the deep web.</item>
<item>Enjoy your brand new cult!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>-Your actions are not excused simply because you are in a cult. That means if you kill someone, you have to pay the price.</item>
<item>-Starting an evil cult is a dangerous thing, before you commit yourself to this, be aware of the risks involved.</item></list>
</text>
