<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc178" title="Be a Good 12 Year Old" shortTile="good--year-old" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-01-10" dateModified="2019-08-17" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Good_12_Year_Old" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Good 12 Year Old</head><p>As a 12 year old, you probably want to please others around you and be the best you can be, and this article can probably help you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Keeping a Good Relationship with Your Parents</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Follow household rules. Go to bed when you are told, and do chores if you are required to do so. If you are unhappy with a particular rule, speak with your parents (and other household members) about changing it. <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be polite and respectful to your parents, siblings and other household members. Treat others as you would like to be treated. Say please and thank you, and have good table manners. <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Give your parents cards and presents on their birthday, Christmas, Mothers/Fathers day, etc. Make an effort to get them something nice that they will like. <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Assure them that you love them. They love you, and it will make them happy to know you love them. <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Spend quality time with family. Although you are almost a teenager, it is important to spend time with family! <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Succeeding in School</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do homework to the best of your ability and hand it in on time. This will help you in learning new and important things. <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Revise before assessments, especially in subject your are not so good at. In order to get good grades, you will have to pass exams, and it can really help to revise a few days before the test. Ask family members and friends to quiz you on things. <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take notes in class and ask questions if you are stuck. Contributing to the class is also great, as you can teach others new things! <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear correct uniform. If your school doesn't have one, wear suitable clothes (such as jeans, t-shirt and sneakers) and if you are a girl, natural looking makeup. <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Follow school rules. They are there for a reason. <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Dressing Appropriately</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Have a variety of clothes. <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For girls, a good selection would be casual dresses, formal dresses, jackets, leggings, t-shirts, tights, jeans, flats, heels, boots and trainers.</item>
<item>For boys, Jeans, t-shirts, shirts, trousers, jackets and shoes.</item></list></item>
<item>Choose footwear wisely. Girls may want to wear heels at this age, and that is fine as long as they are not worn daily and are not too high (2-3 inches is ideal). Smart shoes should be kept for school and special occasions, and for daily activities casual shoes should be worn. <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Dress according to the weather. In winter you will need a coat, and in summer you will probably want to wear light, loose clothing. <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't dress in skimpy clothes. It's fine to shop in the adults department at this age, but choose modest clothes, as boys/men might take it the wrong way. <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 14.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Behaving Age Appropriately</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Travel to school alone or with friends (if possible). This age is when you should start going out alone and travelling to school is a good start. <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't go on dates. You are too young to date, and you should wait a couple more years. <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have friends and hang out with them a lot. <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn to cook. Even though your parents will still cook meals for you, it's a good skill to learn! <figure rend="Be a Good 12 Year Old Step 18.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
