<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc27" title="Make Your Animal Feel Loved" shortTile="make-animal-feel" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-12-05" dateModified="2016-01-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_Your_Animal_Feel_Loved" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Your Animal Feel Loved</head><p>Your furry, feathered, and scaly friends all require a certain amount of love and attention in order to be happy. Without the human interaction, many pets become depressed. Therefore, it is very important to make your animal feel loved and cherished.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Figure out how much attention your specific type of animal requires
<list type="unordered"><item>For instance, a dog will likely want to be included and interacted with a lot more frequently than a turtle. Cats tend to have varying attitudes but many of them only want attention when they seek it out themselves, not necessarily when you want to play with them.</item></list></item>
<item>Give attention daily
<list type="unordered"><item>An animal is a daily investment. You have to spend time with the animal every day often several times throughout the day. Unlike wild animals, domestic animals crave the attention that people give them and they need it to be happy and healthy.</item>
<item>In this way, an animal is a lot like a baby; you have to nurture it.</item></list></item>
<item>Play with the animal to keep them engaged
<list type="unordered"><item>At zoos, animals participate in what is known as "enrichment." This is done to stimulate the senses of the animal. Pets require this as well.</item>
<item>You can play tug-o-war with a dog, throw a ball, give a cat a catnip toy, provide a cuttlebone for a bird, build a tube system for a hampster, etc.</item></list></item>
<item>Allow time for snuggling
<list type="unordered"><item>At the end of a long day when your pet is tired (and you are too!), some animals may enjoy snuggling. By simply allowing them to share a blanket with you, sit on your lap, or petting them you can make your animals life much better.</item></list></item>
<item>If your animal has a crate, put it somewhere near people
<list type="unordered"><item>It may make sense to put a whining puppy somewhere far away from the people in the house because they are annoying. However, as your dog gets used to its crate, it is important that you place them somewhere that is populated so that they do not get bored or lonely. For instance, you could put the crate in the kitchen or the living room. This is also true for bird cages.</item></list></item>
<item>Feed animals appropriately and give treats
<list type="unordered"><item>One of the best things you can do to show your animal that you care is to buy them treats. A varied diet can help keep the dog kibble or bunny pellets from looking so mundane.</item>
<item>You can use treats as motivation for training your animals which not only keeps them engaged but also is helpful for teaching them manners and to respond to your voice.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider getting them a "friend"
<list type="unordered"><item>If you do not have hours to devote to your pet every day but still wish to have one, it may be a good idea to get a companion animal for them. Generally, this would be one of the same species. The other animal would give them someone to communicate with and play with when you are not around.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not overfeed your pets! Treats are great but make sure to check the labels of the pet food bags to see just how much to feed (based on weight and sometimes age) so that your pet stays healthy.</item>
<item>When introducing a new pet, always take it slow at first because it can seem threatening to your original pet. Make sure to give the original pet lots of love to show that you are not replacing them.</item></list>
</text>
