<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc110" title="Get a Shy Girl to Like You" shortTile="shy-girl" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-01-31" dateModified="2018-11-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_a_Shy_Girl_to_Like_You" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get a Shy Girl to Like You</head><p>Do you like a girl but she's too shy to open up? Here's a few words of advice to help you to get her talking.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Talk to her. She might seem like she doesn't want anyone to talk to her but shy people actually like it when other people talk to them. Be talkative and ask for her opinion once in a while but don't over do it. There's a difference between shy and asocial.</item>
<item>Be persistent. Keep talking to her until she feels comfortable around you. She will most likely begin to accept you and start to open up. She might be shy but she's still a person.</item>
<item>Look good. People who take care of their appearance tend to be perceived as more likable and approachable. Don't become annoying or force yourself though! She will avoid you if you become to forward. Typically they are shy for certain reasons.
<list type="unordered"><item>Be clean. Take care of yourself. Keep your clothes clean and maintain good hygiene. But don't over do it, like combing your hair every five minutes or checking yourself on your camera. It will make you seem conceited and girls don't find that very attractive.</item>
<item>Fix your hair. Put on gel, comb it to the side, or just keep it clean and neat.</item>
<item>Wear properly fitting clothes. Sagging pants and oversized t-shirts can look unflattering because they are not suited to your body type.</item>
<item>Dress to impress. This doesn't mean you should wear a tuxedo or anything like that; just make sure your outfit matches.</item></list></item>
<item>Notice things about her. But don't be creepy about it. Just take things in consideration like maybe she doesn't like big crowds so you could hang out with her somewhere where it's more calm with less people. Or maybe she likes a certain band or artist. You could look into it and relate. Just don't be fake. Share your own interests as well.</item>
<item>Ask her out. Since she's shy it might be a little harder to get her to go somewhere alone with you so maybe you could plan something with a group of friends and invite her. That way you will be able to go out with her and she won't be as hesitant to go out with you. Besides she would get to meet your friends so it would help her open up a bit more. You'd kill two birds with one stone.</item>
<item>Be yourself. Don't try to be someone you are not just to get a girl. That will get you nowhere. You have more chances of getting the girl to like you as yourself than anything else. Be open to her and make her feel comfortable around you. Show her you can be trusted.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Compliment_Girls">Give her a compliment or two</ref>. Now this is vital. Shy girls love the compliment, especially from someone they find attractive, even though words may fail them just because they are too shy to make a move. Be the perfect admirer in all ramifications.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never change who you are, you'll only regret it later.</item>
<item>Talk to her whenever you see her. Don't just walk by without even at least saying hi.</item>
<item>Make it obvious that you like her. It's the only way she'll accept you in that way.</item>
<item>Be confident and show your style.</item></list>
<head>Warning</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The fact that she is shy doesn't mean she won't notice when you get creepy and finally turns into a stalker. Be wise and respect her boundaries.</item></list>
</text>
