<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc203" title="Improve Your Quality Of Life As A Teenage Girl" shortTile="improve-quality-life" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-09-22" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Improve_Your_Quality_Of_Life_As_A_Teenage_Girl" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Improve Your Quality Of Life As A Teenage Girl</head><p>Teenage girls have major conflicts in life, such as school, and relationships. It gets very difficult as you mature. Reading this article will improve your teenage life. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Perfect From The Inside Out</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Diet-in-Your-Teen-Years">Construct a healthy diet</ref>. To be perfect from the inside out, you have to make sure that the majority of things you put into your body are going to help you to be your best and healthiest self. Whether you are vegan, vegetarian or a meat eater, your diet should mainly consist of fruits and vegetables! Fruits and vegetables are the best way to keep you feeling and looking your best. Other things to include in your diet are whole grains, legumes and other high protein foods such as tofu, chicken, beef and etc. Things to avoid are highly processed foods (for example, white bread, chocolate, soda, ice cream, etc.). However, that isn't to say that you should <hi rend="bold">never</hi> eat these things but just try to keep them to a minimum.</item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Drink plenty of water. This is an absolute <hi rend="bold">essential</hi> when it comes to looking and feeling your best. Use a hydration calculator so that you can enter your details and see how much water you should be drinking per day. Also, make sure you drink more water if you are exercising. Drinking things like green tea, peppermint tea, lemon water and apple cider vinegar are also good alternatives to just drinking plain water. In fact, it is recommended drinking all of those things daily if possible.</item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take medications and vitamins. If you have any medications prescribed by your doctor or any vitamins/supplements that you take, make sure to try and keep a good routine and take them around the same time daily. Being consistent with these things will make them work their best.</item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be yourself and stay true to yourself. Stick to the morals and values you believe in and don't let other people change you. You know what's right and wrong for you and if you stick to that then you'll always come out on top. Be kind and considerate towards people but don't be a pushover. Let your voice and opinions be heard loud and clear. Do the things that make <hi rend="bold">you</hi> happy and don't worry about what other people say or think. Love yourself and others will too.</item></list>
<head>Hygiene and Beauty</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make sure to shower every day. Sometimes showering in the morning makes you feel refreshed and ready for the day. Some people have late night showers so that they sleep comfortably. Use a body cleanser/exfoliater every time you shower. Wash your hair every second day if your hair is oily or once to twice a week if your hair is dry - figure out the right routine for you. Shave/wax/epilate your legs, underarms, eyebrows, moustache and bikini area regularly (this is optional, if you prefer to leave your body hair as it is then that's cool too). Cleanse your face 1-2 times a day and exfoliate 1-2 times a week. Once a week, give yourself a good pampering with a face mask, foot bath, manicure, and pedicure etc.</item>
<item>Brush, floss, and use mouthwash twice a day <hi rend="bold">everyday</hi>. Keeping your teeth and mouth clean and healthy is important. Unless you want all your teeth to be disgusting and falling out by the time you're 30, brushing your teeth will make it look hundreds time as nice. If you want to go further, you can also use gels, trays and whitening kits and etc.</item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look after your skin! Try to moisturize your body regularly and put sunblock on <hi rend="bold">everyday</hi>. Find any toners, serums or moisturizers that work well with the skin on your face and use them daily. Make sure to find a daily moisturizer for your face that has SPF in it!</item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Wear makeup. When it comes to makeup, it's completely optional. Some people like to wear makeup and some people prefer to stay natural. Whatever your preference, it really doesn't matter. Do what makes you happy and comfortable.</item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use deodorant. Make sure that you always have some deodorant on hand. Apply it every morning, after every bath/shower, after swimming and regularly through the day. Another option is to wear a body spray/perfume.</item></list>
<head>Exercise</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Exercise daily. Exercise is a really important part of being healthy. Not only does it make you physically fit and healthy but it also helps to keep your mind clear, focused and happy. Try to make sure that you incorporate <hi rend="bold">at least</hi> 30 minutes of exercise/working out 5-6 days a week. Try to balance your routine with different types of exercises. Running, walking, cycling, Pilates, yoga, lifting weights, push ups, crunches, planks etc. These are all really good exercises but to have a really good exercise regime you need to include all these types of exercise and more. Mix it up and find out what your favorite exercises are.</item>
<item>Make sure you take rest days. If you're working out every day, seven days a week then eventually you will crash and burn. Rest days are really important for your body to repair and recover.</item></list>
</text>
