<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc13" title="Photograph Your Own Pet Calendar" shortTile="photograph-pet-calendar" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-12-06" dateModified="2019-06-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Photograph_Your_Own_Pet_Calendar" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Photograph Your Own Pet Calendar</head><p>With today's technology and resources, creating your gifts for the family is pretty easy. There are many sites, like <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Use_Shutterfly">Shutterfly</ref>, that make creating and mailing printed gifts a breeze. This wikiHow will show you what you need to do to create your pet calendar.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Planning it Out</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider the holidays you might highlight in your images. There are twelve months to a year, and you will want to plan accordingly.  The events you want to depict will change from person to person, or even family to family. It's up to you. For example, you could put together photos that highlight:
<list type="unordered"><item>January - New Years' Day or Martin Luther King, Jr. Day</item>
<item>February - President's Day or Valentine's Day</item>
<item>March -  St. Patrick's Day or Read Across America Day</item>
<item>April - Easter Sunday or National Tartan Day (or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Celebrate_April_Fool's_Day">April Fool's Day</ref>)</item>
<item>May - Kentucky Derby Day or Cinco de Mayo</item>
<item>June - June Solstice or Kamehameha Day</item>
<item>July - Independence or Bastille Day</item>
<item>Aug - Purple Heart Day or National Aviation Day</item>
<item>Sep - Labor Day or National Cleanup Day</item>
<item>Oct - <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Decorate_for_Halloween">Halloween</ref> or White Cane Safety Day</item>
<item>Nov - <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Observe_Veterans_Day">Veterans' Day</ref> or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Thanksgiving_Centerpiece">Thanksgiving</ref></item>
<item>Dec - <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Celebrate_the_12_Days_of_Christmas">Christmas Day</ref> or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Celebrate_Hanukkah">Hanukkah</ref></item></list></item>
<item>Prepare a '<ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Create_a_Storyboard">storyboard</ref>' or similar plan for each month and shot. That way, you are completely prepared for each <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Category:Photo_Shoots">photo shoot</ref>. This will help ensure that you have everything that you need when you need it.</item>
<item>Be prepared with supplies. Use your storyboard to make sure that you have whatever you need ahead of time — costumes, props, backdrop, backgrounds, etc. If everything is ready beforehand, you won't have to juggle setting your pet up and gathering props at the same time.</item>
<item>Spread shooting out over a few days. There aren't too many pets that are going to patiently pose for costumes and photos for very long; do multiple shorter sessions to get all the shots you need.</item></list>
<head>Choosing the Backgrounds, Costumes, and Props</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prepare some background images. If you haven't photographed any images that you want to use, then browse the <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Category:Image_Hosting_and_Sharing_Websites">Royalty-Free sites</ref> for photographs that will work. Things that you want to pay close attention to are:
<list type="unordered"><item>Direction of the sun(light)</item>
<item>Type of light (Harsh, Direct, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_an_Emergency_Flash_Diffuser">Diffused</ref>, etc.)</item></list></item>
<item>Select <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Choose_a_Halloween_Costume_for_Your_Dog">costumes</ref> that are comfortable and easy to put on and take off.</item>
<item>Make sure the costumes work well with your pets' coloring. Black clothes on a black cat, even with a white background, won't work.</item>
<item>Choose <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Category:Stage_and_Movie_Props">props</ref> that will be easy to use (or wear). What you choose depends a lot on what your pet looks like and will tolerate.</item>
<item>Have a backdrop (different than a background) that will allow you to cut your pet out of the image to put into the backgrounds that you have.</item>
<item>Check the website/calendar service that you will be using, if applicable. There are probably many stores that you can find locally that do this as well. You will want to know how much of the image processing you need/want to do. Do you need to do it all in Photoshop (which will give you more control) or will the website allow you to put them together with their templates (easier but often more restricted)?</item></list>
<head>Getting Cooperation From Your Pets</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know what makes your pet tick. Are they food motivated, or do they like affection? Maybe you already have them <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Clicker_Train_a_Cat">clicker-trained</ref>? You will need to know how to get an expression or angle or position.</item>
<item>Experiment ahead of time on what are good angles for your dog or cat. Just like us, they have a good side, too. Take some casual practice shots to get an idea of how best to photograph your pal.</item>
<item>Make sure that wherever your pet is '<ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Pet_Photography_Studio_Using_Your_Bed">posed</ref>', is very secure. You are not going to get any good shots if your animal is worried about falling off the table.</item>
<item>Take a lot of photographs. You never know when you are going to get just the right look or angle. It's called 'spray and pray' and it works, especially with animals.</item>
<item>Move around and keep your pet involved and interest. Your photos will be boring if your pet is bored.
<list type="unordered"><item>As you go, keep the focus on your pet. Remember, you are photographing your pet. You are not photographing your pet in your room.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Editing Your Photos</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Import your images into your software. There are many free ones, on and off-line, as well as a lot of commercial software for you. Krita or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Transparent_Image_Using_Gimp">Gimp</ref> are a couple of great free programs that you can use.</item>
<item>Find out what size that you need your images to be. If you're using an online service/site to print your calendar, their purchasing pages will tell you the required size. You want to know how wide and how tall that they need to be.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Crop_Your_Images">Crop your images</ref> so that they will fit properly in the calendar.</item>
<item>Make sure that your images look good. Whether you are using a phone or camera, you want to make sure that your pets are well lit. If any of them come out poorly and you can't fix it with editing, consider a reshoot.</item></list>
<head>Getting It Printed</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose the format that you want to use. There are many types of calendars to choose from. Wall, desk, and easel calendars are just a few of your choices.</item>
<item>Follow the ordering process from your chosen site. The setup, placement, and ordering steps will differ depending on what platform you use, but most offer clear instructions. If they provide you with a proof of the product you're ordering, be sure to check it out closely before confirming your purchase; once you've ordered, you may not be able to return it.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The calendar (or whatever you create) does not have to be about pets. It could be about any interests that you have, or share, with your family.</item>
<item>This may seem like a lot of work but you will be glad that you did it, when you are putting it all together.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Props for each photograph</item>
<item>White backdrop (for photographing your pet against)
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have a lighter pet, you will want a darker backdrop.</item></list></item>
<item>Software for <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Photograph_for_Compositing">compositing</ref> your pet into the backgrounds</item>
<item>Treats for your pet(s)</item>
<item>If using a DSLR (or SLR), use a fast lens. This will make it easier to take the photos.</item></list>
</text>
