<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc176" title="Be a Normal Teen (Girls)" shortTile="normal-teen-girls" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-05-26" dateModified="2019-10-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Normal_Teen_%28Girls%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Normal Teen (Girls)</head><p>Are you tired of being criticized for not being a normal teen? Do you want to know how to be a normal teen? This article will show you how to be a normal teen.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know that there is no specific "attitude." Just go with the flow and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Yourself">be yourself</ref>. There is no such thing as normal; normal in this context (wikiHow) means to fit in well with society. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teen (Girls) Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear clothes that express you. You don't have to look like that model in "Seventeen." Develop your own style as you go along.  If you wear unusual clothing with confidence, you can still be "normal." <figure rend="Be a Normal Teen (Girls) Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be mindful of those around you if you choose to swear.  It is important to respect that others might find vulgar language distasteful, including many adults.  (Some teens choose to abstain completely from swearing, and that's fine, too!) <figure rend="Be a Normal Teen (Girls) Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Choose your friends wisely. Yes, you're going to meet people who do mean things. But you don't have to be one of those people. You can be whatever and hang with whoever.  If your friends don't treat you the way you deserve, or if they pressure you to do things you're not comfortable with, you can choose new friends! <figure rend="Be a Normal Teen (Girls) Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be active. Don't just lay around the house. Get out and go to the pool with your friends, go talk to boys, play a sport, do whatever you find fun. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teen (Girls) Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have a healthy social life. Lots of girls these days have Instagram, Snapchat, Twitter, Pinterest, etc. You do not have to have these to have a social life. Socialize face-to-face with people. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teen (Girls) Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Confident">Be confident</ref>. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teen (Girls) Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Refrain from obsessing about money, or talking about how much your parents make. You can be cool and normal no matter what your family's economic status. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teen (Girls) Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep your hygiene up. Take a shower or bathe every day and use antiperspirant. Brush your hair and teeth, floss, use mouthwash, daily stuff. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teen (Girls) Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make the grade. Try your best in school. Getting straight A's is excellent; it's not nerdy at all. Make high goals for your academic life, and try your best to achieve them. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teen (Girls) Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have a life. "Normal" girls have best friends and hang out with guys. They occasionally get into trouble with things such as ding-dong-ditch, but nothing too life changing . <figure rend="Be a Normal Teen (Girls) Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember that normal doesn't exist. Be yourself; no one likes a poser. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teen (Girls) Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find a friend who you can tell everything to, someone you can trust 100%. Don't bottle everything up! <figure rend="Be a Normal Teen (Girls) Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't let other people run your life.</item>
<item>Find your hobby. With it, you can find friends with similar interests.</item>
<item>Have fun! Be yourself, don't let <hi rend="italic">anyone</hi> ruin your fun. Life is a party.</item>
<item>Don't limit your social life to the internet. Go hang out with friends at the mall.</item>
<item>Play with pets, siblings, friends, etc.</item>
<item>Try after-school activities to make new friends and fill your time.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't try to be someone you're not. Making friendships with people who aren't like you may seem like a good idea at first, but just be yourself and find people like you. It will most likely turn out great in the long run!</item>
<item>Don't over-commit yourself--spend some time relaxing as a teen!</item>
<item>Don't develop self-esteem issues or eating disorders just to look like the photo-shopped model on the front of a magazine.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Trustworthy friends</item>
<item>Clothes you like</item>
<item>Self-esteem</item>
<item>Confidence</item></list>
</text>
