<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc216" title="Bribe Your Parents" shortTile="bribe-parents" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-10-18" dateModified="2017-05-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Bribe_Your_Parents" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bribe Your Parents</head><p>From Old French briber (“go begging”) we have the enticing word <hi rend="italic">bribe</hi>. Are you tired of your parents always saying <hi rend="italic">no</hi> or even <hi rend="italic">maybe</hi>, only to later say <hi rend="italic">no</hi> again? Bribery is often associated with being dishonest or even doing something illegal, but when it comes to your parents, chances are you're just looking to persuade them to do something for you. In that case, this article will help you. It's possible you could bribe your those hapless souls who gave you your life, to do anything. After all, what have they done for you <hi rend="italic">lately</hi>?</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be indubitably good for an entire day. This means do the dishes. Take out the trash. Be quiet in the house for gosh sakes. Be nice to that creep of a sister of yours. Do your homework. Check your homework. Put your homework in your backpack so your mom won't have to drive it to you at school tomorrow when you have carelessly left it on your desk.  Read a book. Call your grandmother, not to ask for money. Just to talk.</item>
<item>Make sure you have good grades. To be on the safe side, keep up your grades at all times, you never know when you are going to need to lean on your parents to give you another video game. So read, read, read, and do well in school.</item>
<item>Get a job to do your part. Work in the neighborhood so that you can make some money and pay some of those bills. Shovel sidewalks, cut lawns, walk dogs. Whatever it takes to do your part.</item>
<item>Pick the right time. Don't try to dragoon your mom into buying you yet another cute pair of Uggs, if she is paying the bills tonight. That moment when your mom is sitting at the kitchen table, tearing her hair out, trying to decide between paying the electric bill and paying for your dance lessons is not a good time to ask for more material possessions you can't live without.</item>
<item>Offer something in return. Bribery, as mentioned in Wiktionary, is <hi rend="italic">Something (usually money) given in exchange for influence or as an inducement to dishonesty.</hi> With your parents, chances are money isn't going to be your exchange of choice. But think about it like this: can you offer to do something, in exchange for them agreeing to what you want?</item>
<item>Butter them up. It helps if you remind them (tactfully, don't go overboard) about all the great things you've done in the past for them.</item>
<item>Guilt them. All you need is to remind them of the terrible, terrible things they've done in the past to you. Like promising to sign you up for ballet lessons the moment you quit piano lessons, but six years later, you're still ballet-deprived. Then give them about a minute to be affected by guilt. Swoop in and mention how much you would absolutely love the newest iPhone.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you aren't having an attitude to your siblings; or parents, and help clean up a bit to prove you are really responsible.</item>
<item>Your parents might of just came home from work and want to relax for a bit and watch some TV, or they are busy paying bills or getting ready to go somewhere, make sure they are sitting down doing nothing important, or I guarantee you they will probably say no.</item>
<item>Getting good grades is really important for your education, but you can also use it to bribe a parent that you are responsible.</item>
<item>Maybe your parents have an old phone that still works, or it still doesn't work (whatever at least it's a phone), have a trial for a couple days and see how you do with a phone.</item>
<item>You know your parents don't have the money to be paying YOUR phone bill every now and then, because they have to pay for their phone, so why don't you pitch in and pay some money to, or better yet do some chores.</item>
<item>Your parents may have some things you shouldn't do on your phone, so tell them to over what you can and can't do on your phone.</item>
<item>Maybe there was an emergency and your parents weren't home, you could tell them that you could call them or maybe you use their phone too much, tell them that you wouldn't use their phone anymore.</item>
<item>Give your parents the best day ever. End with a massage or bowl of ice-cream. Mention your request casually.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Oh also here are some examples of things parents do when they are not busy; on their phone, laying on the couch, cooking (well sometimes), or doing a house chore. Also, make sure your siblings or anyone is in the room, make sure it is nice and quiet.</item>
<item>Make sure you are doing chores when you are having a phone or they will take your phone and tell you your trial is over.</item>
<item>Be careful, you may be one of the people who get angry easily.</item>
<item>Good grades are; A's and B's</item></list>
</text>
