<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc98" title="Have a Relationship" shortTile="have-a-relationship" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-03-03" dateModified="2016-12-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have_a_Relationship" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have a Relationship</head><p>There are many different ways that human beings interact with one another, and these interactions are called 'relationships.' Having a relationship with another human can be both frustrating and rewarding, but at the end of the day, a relationship is your best option for interacting with the outside world and sharpening your social skills.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Locate another human being. The most important part of any relationship is that there are two separate entities that interact in some way. Determine which human with whom you would like to have a relationship. It is best to choose a human that is close to you geographically, or someone that is easy for you to contact. Be creative! You can choose a human for a relationship almost anywhere that there are humans. Common areas for choosing humans to participate in relationships are:
<list type="unordered"><item>A store.</item>
<item>Your home.</item>
<item>A restaurant.</item>
<item>Your place of work.</item>
<item>The street.</item>
<item>A park.</item></list></item>
<item>Approach the human. Before you being a relationship with a human, you must establish contact with the human. Try saying hello, or comment on the weather or politics. Do not try to have a relationship with a human before establishing contact.</item>
<item>Determine whether or not the human is open to having a relationship with you. A relationship needs two parties to be engaged in the process. You can determine this by having what is called a conversation. In a conversation, two humans will say things to one another, often with the goal of learning something about one another, or the world around them. If you find yourself engaged in a conversation with your chosen human, there is a good chance you are on your way to having a relationship!</item>
<item>Determine what type of relationship you want with the human. There are many types of relationships that humans can have with one another, and sometimes those relationships can change. Although at times it can be tough to keep track of all the different types of relationships you have with other humans, you can use context clues or mnemonic devices to remind yourself of the specific type of relationship you have with another human. For example, if you often find yourself exchanging money or goods with the other human when you interact, there is a good chance that your relationship is of a professional or economic nature. Here are some of the most common relationships that most humans begin with:
<list type="unordered"><item>Acquaintances</item>
<item>Family</item>
<item>Buyer/Seller</item>
<item>Boss/Employee</item>
<item>Teacher/Student</item>
<item>Police/Pedestrian</item>
<item>Producer/Consumer</item></list></item>
<item>Once you have determined what type of relationship you will have with the human, it is up to both of you to maintain that relationship. If you see this person on a regular basis, maintaining the relationship can be as simple as repeating your first conversation over and over again. However, most humans choose a more complex method of maintaining their relationship, which often involves learning and remembering facts about each other and sometimes consuming food together.</item></list>
</text>
