<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc207" title="Keep Your Friends from Being Boycrazy" shortTile="keep-friends-being" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-03-21" dateModified="2016-01-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Keep_Your_Friends_from_Being_Boycrazy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Keep Your Friends from Being Boycrazy</head>
<p>You may only think of boys as friends, but your friends are obsessed with boys. If this annoys you, this article will teach you how to keep your friends from going insane over the opposite sex.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pull your friend aside for a private conversation. Let her know how you feel about her sudden obsession with boys. Gently inform her about how she has been changing. It's best to tell your friend about your feelings rather than hide them from her. If she is aware of how you feel, it will probably help her to change her ways and see your point of view.   <figure rend="Keep Your Friends from Being Boycrazy Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure to use "I feel that you have been [insert action]" rather than sounding accusatory.</item>
<item>Realize your friend may be unaware of her actions. Avoid sounding harsh, and be gentle with her to avoid an argument. You wouldn't want to lose a friend because of how you treated her when confronting her about her problem.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider making your friend feel guilty, such as saying, "Who do you want? Boys or me?" This may cause her to snap out of her obsessive state and realize she has been pushing you away. Understand she has the right to date, but know when to step in if she gets a little too focused on males. <figure rend="Keep Your Friends from Being Boycrazy Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you don't make her feel guilty. Often when people feel guilty about something, they tend to get mad at whoever blamed them or called them out for something.</item></list></item>
<item>Encourage her to do other activities to get her mind off boys. Get her to participate in sports, such as soccer or softball. Have her hang around you while you're talking to boys as friends. That will influence her. <figure rend="Keep Your Friends from Being Boycrazy Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Introduce your friend to other nice females. Form a group purely consisting of girls, and avoid spending time with males during your friend's obsessive state. <figure rend="Keep Your Friends from Being Boycrazy Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know when to take a step back. Some females become so obsessed with boys that they forget to properly think. They may not realize how their actions affect others. Sometimes, time is your best friend. Wait for your friend to eventually realize what she has been doing, and allow her to gain control of her situation.</item>
<item>Remember to keep your cool. If you are always upset at her if she talks to a boy, most likely she will get upset with you for trying to "control her life".</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't hang around boys too long when you're trying to influence her. She'll turn boy crazy again.</item>
<item>Above all, remember that you aren't her parents and you can't take over and make her choices for her. If she chooses to be boy-crazy, don't expect her to change as soon as she finds out that you think it's annoying. It is her life, and she can make her own choices.</item></list>
</text>
