<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc189" title="Be Tougher (for Girls)" shortTile="tougher--girls" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-04-09" dateModified="2018-10-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_Tougher_%28for_Girls%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Tougher (for Girls)</head><p>Have you ever felt that you are weak or wimpy? Do you feel like you need encouragement? Maybe you just feel like you're too emotional. Well, not anymore!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>You are what you think. If you want to be tough, you need to have confidence and believe. Maybe something has happened to you that makes you feel weak. Yet everyone has a time where they succeeded. Think about it to feel confident and tough!</item>
<item>Have a role model. Knowing someone who is tough can help you get tougher too. Pretend to be like that person and make her/him your role model. Now, if you don't know anyone like that, you can try cartoon characters. Try going for characters in TV shows for kids, now not things like Super Why, but try something for tweens. They have characters who can be very tough, yet not rude or mean. Okay, I know it sounds silly to have a role model who is a character in a movie, but hey, they're just as good! Here are some tough movie characters you might try: Jewel from Rio, Eva from Rio, Chirp from PEEP and the Big Wide World, (that probably sounds baby-ish, I know) Atlanta from Class of the Titans, or Jasmine from Aladdin.</item>
<item>Know a lot about your role model. You need to know what makes your tough role model tough, so you know what to do to be a version of them. Here are some character traits of the characters before. Jewel would be a great choice. Jewel can be a very tough macaw, and is as independent and rebellious as she can be. Yet, be careful if she is your role model; she can sometimes get rude, so only get the tough part done. Eva is a perfect choice. (Eva is my role model!) She is sometimes loud and strict. In fact, she is underestimated, because people don't know her too well. She only gets loud if Rafael, her kids, or anyone else start bugging her. Most of the time she is an adventurous, tough, clever, competitive, sassy, and nice toucan who is truly the real Eva. Chirp is an awesome choice. Chirp is a red robin who is cunning, adventurous, curious, and not afraid of a little competition. Quack always tries to steamroll Chirp with his criticism, yet never succeeds. Chirp knows how to keep her cool in tough times, and is a very tough red robin. Atlanta, on the other hand, is very strong. She is a strong, adventurous, energetic, tough, sassy, and ready-to-go kind of teenager. She knows how and when to use her skills, and knows how to use them in the strongest way. Strong and ready, Atlanta is one tough girl, who would make a great role model for you. Jasmine is free-spirited, and in many ways resembles the "rebellious princess" archetype. She is very pretty and expresses her feelings if she wishes to. Jasmine also never brings down anyone else and she never lets anyone bring her down from doing what she wants. Nice, rebellious and independent, Jasmine is very tough for a princess.  <figure rend="Miscellaneous 34 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't dress up too much. Keep it simple. Don't wear a Halloween costume while in the grocery store trying to look tough. Use your clothes to express your feelings, just don't go overboard.</item>
<item>Remember what doesn't kill you makes you stronger. Don't be afraid to try your best, as your failures will only make you better. Be nice, be strong, and be the tough girl you know you are!</item></list>
</text>
