<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc57" title="Overcome Family Pressure to Be in a Religion" shortTile="overcome-family-pressure" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-09-19" dateModified="2019-07-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Overcome_Family_Pressure_to_Be_in_a_Religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Overcome Family Pressure to Be in a Religion</head><p>Religion and values are often instilled as a result of family or community norms. There are geographical areas where sects or groups of very similar religions and beliefs have settled. The prevalence in certain areas to follow similar belief systems and norms can prove daunting for anyone who comes to believe differently. If you have come to the realization that the religious beliefs and values of your family or community are not in sync with your own, you may have a very hard time with being accepted and respected for who you are. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand the reasoning for this article. It is written to help you understand what to do to in this situation. Often, historically, families have rejected dissimilar beliefs of family or community members. This caused social distancing and even sometimes forced a geographic relocation. This does not have to happen. There are ways of resolving these often unspoken conflicts and coming to a better communal existence. It takes persistence, patience and understanding on both sides of healthy relationships in order to accomplish a comfortable existence.</item>
<item>Find others who do believe similarly to yourself. Perhaps you live in an area where there are few people who think exactly like you do. Somehow, make a connection with another who feels or thinks very similarly and is very accepting to you as a person. This will bolster your confidence in speaking up about your need to be accepted and respected by others. Once you realize that you have a friend or family member with similar beliefs, you should feel the strength to discuss openly your need for further social acceptance. Finding that friend or family member might be achieved through seeking a social group or social network outside of your own neighborhood or family group. <figure rend="Overcome Family Pressure to Be in a Religion Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Accept that you may unconsciously feel the situation is worse than it is. Often the problem of feeling left out or unaccepted can be a construct of your own mind. If possible, openly ask the family and friends if they are willing to accept you, even if your beliefs and values differ. If you can reach out to others, you are already on the road to coming to terms with what it means to believe differently and still be able to successfully seek social acceptance. Sometimes once you establish your stance on certain beliefs or norms, others are more accepting than you might have anticipated. At the very least, you will have established your viewpoint. <figure rend="Overcome Family Pressure to Be in a Religion Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Understand yourself and your own needs. Whenever you recognize resistance or if you experience open hostility for your beliefs, you may want to re-evaluate your position. Recognize, establish and accept your need for maintaining social connections, despite the differences in belief systems. This will help you decide how much you are willing to do to maintain the relationship. <figure rend="Overcome Family Pressure to Be in a Religion Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do not try to take on a discussion with a whole group of family or friends at once. Usually, sorting out your relationships is easier to do one on one. <figure rend="Overcome Family Pressure to Be in a Religion Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try not to use a holiday get-together as your opportunity to discuss these differences with someone for the first time. Take an understanding friend with you to any gathering where there is going to be heavy symbolism or rituals that are specific to other belief systems. Try to keep an open mind in how you outwardly react to these demonstrations of faith or values. Use the same respect that you would give if you were attending the rituals of a tribe or group in a foreign country. <figure rend="Overcome Family Pressure to Be in a Religion Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Avoid situations where the planned activities are going to disrupt you emotionally, due to strong conflict with your beliefs. You must respect your need to sanctify your beliefs, as a first step in having others understand and respect you. Discreetly avoiding specific situations will not always be a viable alternative, but it is a tool that you can use to prevent open conflict in family or group gatherings. <figure rend="Overcome Family Pressure to Be in a Religion Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Discuss your position constructively. When you open up a conversation regarding dissimilar beliefs, try to discuss your position with as little emotion as possible. Also, give the other person a chance to establish some of their views. Do not attempt to control or dominate the conversation. <figure rend="Overcome Family Pressure to Be in a Religion Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be prepared for your discussion. Once you have come to an agreement on a good time to talk with a friend or family member, you should prepare yourself. Review how having your own beliefs has affected your existence in the family, group or community. Be ready to openly discuss how you feel, without allowing emotions to interfere with expressing your stance clearly. This is a difficult step. Allowing yourself to become demonstrably emotional while asking for understanding, can foster a weakening of your position. It can make your decision to stay rooted in your own beliefs seem less firm. <figure rend="Overcome Family Pressure to Be in a Religion Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Listen with an open mind. Once you meet with another, try to give them equal time to share their feelings and position. Let them express openly how your beliefs and your stance make them feel. It is healthy to give them compassionate understanding, as that is exactly what you are wanting to obtain from them in return. <figure rend="Overcome Family Pressure to Be in a Religion Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remind others how important their approval is to you. You are endeavoring to speak up about no your right to freedom of belief. You also are speaking up about your need for family and community relationships to be warmly experienced. <figure rend="Overcome Family Pressure to Be in a Religion Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember that with any difference, there are typically many similarities. This is the way to build a relationship with another on a firm foundation. You must find, embrace and remind them of how very similar you are to each other. <figure rend="Overcome Family Pressure to Be in a Religion Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Reap the rewards of your efforts. If you try to follow some these steps, in effort to improve your relationships with family or community members, then you are a fantastic human being. You recognize the importance of familial and communal belonging! Social acceptance is one of our most basic needs! <figure rend="Overcome Family Pressure to Be in a Religion Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
