<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc16" title="Care for an Anteater" shortTile="care-anteater" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-05-26" dateModified="2019-07-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Care_for_an_Anteater" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Care for an Anteater</head><p>Caring for any exotic species of animal should never be untaken lightly. Raising an abandoned baby anteater found in its natural environment would be virtually impossible for anyone without training in caring for mammals. Zoos and wildlife parks have specialised staff who know how to provide for these  relatives of sloths. In the highly unlikely event you find yourself atemping to care for a Giant anteater (Myrmecophaga tridactyla), a Silky anteater (Cyclopes didactylus) or a
Northern (Tamandua mexicana) or Southern tamandua (Tamandua tetradactyla), these steps provide some general advice and guidance, geared toward displaying the animal.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Designing an Enclosure</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Provide an appropriate habitats. Anteater habitats occupied by wild anteaters include dry tropical forests, rainforests, grasslands and savannas. Grassland with plants, rocks, dirt, and water may work.</item>
<item>Consider how many an anteaters you want. Anteaters are solitary mostly. These animals are prepared to defend their 1.0- to 1.5-miles squared, (2.6- to 2.9-kilometres squared) territories; They can take up a lot of space, so the more anteaters you have, the bigger enclosure you should have. Anteaters don't normally enter the territory of another anteater of the same sex so you may want to have one habitat for each animal to prevent fighting or unintentional breeding.</item>
<item>Consider mixing animals if you care for more than one type of exotic animal. Giant anteaters may do well as a single-species exhibit, but it isn't bad to consider a mixed species exhibit, like capybaras and tapirs. Don't add 'too' many animals, though.</item>
<item>Consider giving them indoor access also. Coming from humid climates, giant anteaters do better in a warmer environment than a cold one. Consider giving them a heated house if you are caring for them in a location that does not replicate the climatic conditions of their natural environment. A captive bred animal from a zoo may be hardier than a anteater born in the wild.</item>
<item>Determine if you can create a climate suitable for anteaters. An anteater's body temperature fluctuates between 33 and 36 °C (91 and 97 °F). In common with other xenarthrans, anteaters have among the lowest body temperatures of any mammal. These means they can tolerate fluctuations in body temperature greater than those of most mammals. If they appear to not do well in the cold, you make them a house, they are more likely to stay in it for longer periods at a time in cold weather.</item></list>
<head>Preparing Food for Anteaters</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look up what captive anteaters eat. Provide a suitable milk if you are caring for a baby anteater. You may wish to provide a substitue for the anteaters natural diet as it is hard to supply several thousand ants 24/7. Be aware you may stunt the animal's growth, weaken it's immune system or cause failure-to-thrive if you don't meet it's nutritional requirements.</item>
<item>Scatter foliage around your enclosure to encourage ants. However, only make the ants side meals or snacks.</item>
<item>Consider making anthill enrichment. Anteaters usually eat out of these in the wild, so it may be more preferable than just in a bowl.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ensure you have the appropriate permits for keeping an exotic animal.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Anteaters do not make good pets.</item></list>
</text>
