<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc223" title="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls)" shortTile="give-life-makeover" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-03-06" dateModified="2019-09-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Give_Your_Life_a_Makeover_%28Teen_Girls%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls)</head><p>Being a teen is hard! Sometimes you just need a fresh start. This will help you get to that calm, organized, and healthy state.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Making Over Your Personal Space</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Clean out your closet. Since your closet is one of the main things in your room, you need to make sure it is always kept clean. <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Get several big garbage bags and put the clothes in piles: throw away, give away, sell, laundry and clean.
<list type="unordered"><item>Put the dirty clothes into the washing machine/hamper, while the clean clothes back in your closet after folding them and sorting them the way you want. This could be by color, style or usage rate.</item>
<item>Hang up any shirts, T-shirts, dresses, sweaters and cardigans etc., and fold up pants, jeans, leggings etc.</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Clean your desk or working space. <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sort the things on your desk into 3 piles: keep, throw away and give away. Do the same as what you did with your clothes.</item>
<item>If your desk has drawers sort them out like you did the surface of your desk.</item>
<item>Put back what you want to keep but make sure to organize it and not put it back where it doesn’t belong!</item></list></item>
<item>Re-make your bed. <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Strip your sheets off the bed and throw them in to the laundry.</item>
<item>Get new sheets that you like and are comfortable to sleep on, and put them on the bed. It's good to have a comfortable bed that also looks good.</item>
<item>Arrange the pillows however you want it.</item></list></item>
<item>If you have shelves or a nightstand, organise them the way you did with your closet: throw away, give away, sell and keep. Remember, whatever you put back make sure you put it back neatly! <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wipe any surfaces you have, they might be dusty! <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Making Over Your School Space</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>During recess or any free time, stay behind and organize your locker. Throw away anything you don't need (ex. scrap paper). <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take away all the things that don't belong in a locker, like candy wrappers or banana peels!</item>
<item>Decorate! If you are allowed, stick wallpaper cuttings or wrapping paper on the walls of your locker, put stickers and photographs on the door.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Keeping Up With Your Health and Wellbeing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Sit down and think, are you healthy? Most people will tell themselves that they are, when they know that some changes could be made to make them healthier. <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a food chart! It's a chart that says what you eat every day and at what time. This will organize your eating habits. Make sure that you follow what you written down and in between meals to snack on something healthy like an apple. <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Exercising is extremely important to lead a healthy life. Find a sport you like such as swimming or softball, or go to the gym. You can even go to a nature sanctuary and hike, it's all considered exercise and will also lower stress level. <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure your skin is healthy too, and go to a dermatologist if acne is a problem and use any medical cream that they give you. Wash your face every morning or night to feel refreshed and have clear and healthy skin. <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Improving Your Personal Style and Hygiene</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take the time to organize your cosmetics. <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take the time to make sure your hair is nice, straighten it the night before or sleep with curling ribbons, wake up a little bit earlier to do that cool braid you have wanted to try. <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do your makeup. Cover any blemishes with a concealer a shade lighter than your natural skin tone and if you have dark circles under your eyes, apply some there too.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have an uneven skin tone (redness, light or dark patches etc.) use either tinted moisturizer, light foundation or a BB cream. For young skin, a BB cream works best because it moisturizes, protects and covers blemishes without looking thick and cakey.</item>
<item>If you don't have naturally rosy cheeks, apply a small amount of blush (not a shimmery blush).</item>
<item>For your eyes, use a primer (or concealer) on your lids to make your eye makeup last longer. If you would like, use a natural colored eyeshadow and/or eyeliner. Curl your lashes and apply a black or brown mascara, but make sure you don't put too much on.</item>
<item>Don’t forget a little bit of clear or tinted lip gloss.  <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Set out clothes the night before, try them on to make sure it looks good. This saves you time in the morning or you can choose several clothing items or outfits and choose which one you want to wear the next day and the second outfit you can wear the next day. <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 14 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Shower at least once or twice every day, especially during hot weather and after sports. <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 15 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to the salon! This is optional, but you should have your hair trimmed every six weeks to prevent split ends and to help promote hair growth. If you have a picture of a hairstyle you like, take it to the salon and they will be able to do your hair similarly. <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 16 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do your nails! Paint them a nice colour, or do a French manicure. Paint your nails with clear base coat polish or a French pink, and paint white tips on the top of your nails. YouTube has many tutorials on nail art and manicures that are simple and easy to do. <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 17 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wax or shave, if you need to. Just remember, body hair removal is optional. Waxing can be a better option for you than shaving, although it takes more time and hurts a bit more and you may break out if you are allergic. Not only does your hair vanish, it takes off any dead skin on the surface leaving your legs feeling gorgeous! Remember to wax at least once every 3 months or it'll hurt more the next time and your hair will grow back. <figure rend="Give Your Life a Makeover (Teen Girls) Step 18 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take time to be with your friends or they'll feel left out and ignored.</item>
<item>Don't forget to study. School is very important!</item>
<item>Remember to just be yourself! This is the best makeover any girl can have. Being kind and compassionate to others is more important then anything else.</item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
