<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc22" title="Know What to Expect if Your Pet is Seriously Ill" shortTile="know-expect-pet-seriously" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-04-19" dateModified="2017-04-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Know_What_to_Expect_if_Your_Pet_is_Seriously_Ill" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Know What to Expect if Your Pet is Seriously Ill</head><p>If your vet and he/she mentions surgery to you, be informed and ask the right questions.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Determine how serious the surgery is. Some dogs may need surgery immediately while others can benefit from a wait and see or “monitor it for a while approach.” Like with people considering surgery, you should consider the benefits, risks, recovery and expensive of surgery.</item>
<item>Do not assume your cat or dog needs emergency surgery. Many active dogs can get pains and strains just from jumping wrong, landing on a paw incorrectly, or may have a simple upset stomach. Most vets are open twelve or more hours per day, and can treat your best friend with x-rays and advanced equipment in the office. A pet without an appetite can be temporarily ill so monitoring them is important. If you work, leave them in a cage or confined area in case of vomiting or diarrhea. Be sure they have water and check on them for their breathing, pain level, and alertness. If everything seems off then call the vet Be able to explain exactly what is happening and ask if the pet should be seen? In one example: the dog's owner knew her puppy ate her prescription medication, so the vet said to bring the dog in now because the dog could go into convulsions.</item>
<item>Understanding the cost of veterinary care is important. The cost of re-doing stitches which didn't work the first time, in my town cost between- $400.00 and $600.00. This cost included the cost of veterinary care, anesthesia, wound cleaning, a drainage tube to remove blood and fluid build-up and drugs to bring the pet back out of anesthesia. I was given a prescription to get antibiotics that I had to pick up at a regular pharmacy. There is pet insurance you can apply for and some charity organization who work with low-income pet owners that can be really helpful. Veterinarians donate their time for this at about half of the regular expense. Calling another veterinarian for a second opinion to determine their fees may be helpful, however, they can not diagnose over the phone, so be prepared to determine the urgency of the pet's condition.</item>
<item>When traveling with your sick or injured pet, it may be necessary to call a friend or family member to assist you. Your pet could be too weak to jump into the car, or could have diarrhea or be vomiting. You will need to focus on your driving to get the the office or surgery center safely. A sick pet could really distract you. Bring their leash, but they may just want to relax on the back seat. Also bring blankets and paper towels or rags in case they become sick.</item>
<item>Plan to wait a good while for the veterinarian to determine what is wrong with your pet. This could take an hour or several hours depending on what is wrong. A pet could be bleeding internally, being observed for seizures, being x-rayed or dozens of other situations. A good vet will watch the pet carefully, and not rush to come out to meet with you until they are fairly certain of the problem, so be patient. These places operate on a triage system, meaning they focus on the pets with life threatening problems first. Expect some uncomfortable chairs, a coffee machine and a vending machine, but little more. The place should look extremely clean with signs posted to stay out of the medical part of the clinic unless invited. This only makes sense. There are conference rooms for the doctor and you to discuss the problem and the potential expense, since payment is due at the end of the surgery per a written agreement in most situations.</item>
<item>Facing surgery, pet owners tend to be extremely emotional. They may be wringing their hands, crying, or be nervous not knowing what is going on. Eventually, someone will break the ice, and the pet owners will share their story. Most strangers are kind in this setting. One pet owner with a very sick pet will likely hold the door, or make similar gestures, when your pet is released. Everyone likes a happy ending.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be prepared to wait.</item></list>
</text>
