<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc101" title="Text 101 for Guys" shortTile="text--guys" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-09-21" dateModified="2016-11-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Text_101_for_Guys" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Text 101 for Guys</head><p>TEXTING 101 For GUYS</p>
<p>What is the purpose for text messaging? I am sure most of you already know what the answer is to that... Now, unless you live in a cave then you are probably not familiar with text messages. Ok, let me help you out... text messages are short, "email like" brief messages you can send to your friends and family with your cell phone. And the interesting part is that most women love texting... So sending a powerful, well crafted text can help move things along... but you must know the difference between good/bad text messages. But of course! Texting should never replace a phone call, but sending a few can be an excellent way to get a woman to THINK ABOUT YOU throughout her day.Texting shouldn't end after your first date either...So let's cover the basics of text messaging. Over the last three months, I have taught over 50 guys how they can use simple text messages to STAND OUT from the other guys who might be interested in the same girl or to simply improve a shaky relationship.  Here are a few "text" examples to get you started if you are new to texting and please avoid using slag... Let's go over the texts MISTAKES men make first... please put them on your NEVER send list:</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>TEXT MISTAKES</item>
<item>1.  Shirtless pictures... Ok, we all know you go to the gym 5 times a week, and think she would appreciate a ripped photo of you with your shirt off. Think again!! It just shows that you are a low value man because a high value man would never dish out revealing photos of his body just like that. If you really want to send her photos that will put a smile on her face, send pictures of your pet or yourself fully dressed.r one step here and then click "Add Step"</item>
<item>2. Texting too much 4.30am: Morning (Ok 4:30 AM is too early for a morning text)8.15am: Just got to the office. 15 minutes late. Hope my boss didn’t notice12:00 noon: It's lunch break honey! 17:00 hrs: Finished work now, going for a drink with a friend. Wish you were here, dear:)23:00 hrs:  I’m back home dear, did you have a good day? ( btw, 23:00 hrs is too late to text a woman) Over texting, never ever goes down well, especially the ones that rudely wake her at 4am. If you are worried you might lose control and start texting a girl you like, give your phone to a friend or switch it off...nter one step here and then click "Add Step"</item>
<item>3 Texting while DrunkHey babezzz, how you are? Sinking about you...Not gona to lie, I liekking you# 4 Psycho behavior TextingMaking a woman feel guilty over texts = psycho behaviour"Why didn't you answer my call?""Do I really deserve this?""Hello, anybody there?"You are online, I can see you tying...answer me now!"I know you are clearly trying to avoid me?"ter one step here and then click "Add Step"</item>
<item>HOT TEXT Examples...</item>
<item>How long should you wait before you initiate the first call/text? 4-5 hours </item>
<item>) "Hi, I was thinking about you. So I thought I should say hi!" </item>
<item>) "Just a quick note to say... I can’t stop talking to my friends about you" I can't wait to introduce you to my friends! </item>
<item>) (After the date text) That was fun. My favorite part was when you looked at me with your cute smile.That  made me feel so great. I wonder what will happen next time we see each other? I am already looking forward to it. * Don't copy my text word by word,:-)you need to alter this to fit your situation, but you get the idea... </item>
<item>) You: “Next time I see you I want us to take you to. . . Restaurant”   Her: “Which one?”  You: “Oh, you will find out . . . </item>
<item>) "I’m missing you. Do you Miss me yet?" </item>
<item>)  Swamped with work. But I just wanted you to know I am thinking about you... I hope to see you  soon...</item>
<item> 7) (After date, text) "I enjoyed your company... Had such a great time! You really made me feel like a king..." I can't wait to see you again... </item>
<item>) I love your hair style...so simple but beautiful! </item>
<item>) I have always appreciated how caring you and the ways you make me feel special </item>
<item>) When I think of you, I can't help it but smile. You are so sweet! r one step here and then click "Add Step"</item></list>
</text>
