<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc181" title="Be Yourself in School (Girls)" shortTile="yourself-school-girls" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-07-20" dateModified="2019-01-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_Yourself_in_School_%28Girls%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Yourself in School (Girls)</head><p>In schools across the world, girls can feel social pressures to be someone who in fact they are not. It is important that as an individual, you can express yourself and not feel the need to live up to someone elses expectations. This short article will guide you on how to be yourself in school.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>It`s completely normal for a girl to feel the need to be accepted. Even so, some tend to go too far, observing what the well-liked girls seem to be wearing, maybe changing their style for the approval of a crush, or the "in" crowd. Lets say you were clay, don`t smooth yourself out to appease society`s norms, but mold yourself to fit your own liking, who YOU decide to be. <figure rend="Be Yourself in School (Girls) Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Express your own individual style, whether your the starving artist, eccentric goth, tom girl, cocky  sweetheart, there are so many aspects to your personality! You can depict your inner workings from the timid bud to the most delicate bloom of who you are, soon your hair, speech, clothes, and hobbies will all be a beautiful reflection of you!  <figure rend="Be Yourself in School (Girls) Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>As expected, there will be others who won`t appreciate the true person you really are, but though they may see you through scornful eyes, you are magnificent, and the inferior hypocrites will drown. Why? As long as your assured of yourself, their opinion is as substantial as the scum behind your toilet. People will love you, if you love yourself.:) <figure rend="Be Yourself in School (Girls) Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Music- whether you are into Lady Gaga to The Agonists to Mozart, be open about the music you love, you should NEVER be ashamed of what you love. For many music is a big part of life so if you want to express yourself, feel free to share the music you love. <figure rend="Be Yourself in School (Girls) Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stand up for what you believe in! If someone dismisses your opinion, that's their mistake! From protesting animal cruelty, to trying to make a difference in your school, always speak out. And even if your not into things of that sort, remember to always express yourself with words, and your words should be heard. Don`t let the sea of modern day stereotypes pull you into the undertow! <figure rend="Be Yourself in School (Girls) Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Lastly, do your best in all that you do. Extremely clichéd, I know, but I had to use it. Make your work rich and advanced, see that you excel and devote a part of you into your work. For even through every day classwork or projects assigned to you, you can express yourself through those, too! Whether your writing an essay, speech, or performing in any other way, put a little bit of you in it. And before you know  it, you`ll be at the top of the world! <figure rend="Be Yourself in School (Girls) Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You will meet nasty people who WILL disagree. Don`t let them get to you.</item></list>
</text>
