<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc84" title="Relax with Your Partner" shortTile="relax-partner" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-04-04" dateModified="2018-10-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Relax_with_Your_Partner" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Relax with Your Partner</head><p>If this is your first time, don't be nervous. This article is broken down into three parts: The initiation, the cuddle, and the ending.  Tips are down below! Have fun!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>The initiation</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>You first need to be aware that your partner may not be willing to relax and cuddle, so ask him/her if he/she wants to cuddle and relax.</item>
<item>Once you obtain permission, find a place to do so.  It could be a bench at a park, a shady area under a tree, or your own home.  Find what works for you</item>
<item>Once you found your cuddle spot, start by simply sitting down and talking.  Chances are the flirting will turn your partner on and will make him/her want to do more than just sit.</item>
<item>Once you begin to talk, move your shoulders from straight to facing him/her, and see how your partner responds to that.</item></list>
<head>The actual cuddle</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Once you have your place, time, and body positioned, you are ready to start the cuddle.  Place your hand on your partner's middle leg and lean your head on his/her shoulder.</item>
<item>Play with each other's hair.  It feels good and will turn you on.  Intertwine your fingers throughout the scalp, twirl curls, finger comb whispies, and bounce curls</item>
<item>For girls: Rest your head on your partner's shoulder and intertwine your legs in your partner's.  For guys: Be the shoulder, but if you are dating another guy, ask whose shoulders will be the shoulder. If you are shorter than he is, you may not want to be the shoulder, just because the distace might hurt your significant other's neck</item></list>
<head>The Ending</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>This is the awkward part.  But do not fear.  Begin by taking your head off the shoulder you are leaning on.  Breathe a sigh of contentedness and begin to sit up straight.  Your partner should get the clues and begin to sit up straight as well.</item>
<item>After you are in an upright position, begin to talk again, if you haven't done so, and begin to talk about lunch or dinner.</item>
<item>Be cordial.  Kiss your partner's cheek or corner of mouth, and say you had a great time.</item>
<item>Walk slowly.  Brisk walking sends the signal that you are trying to escape. Hold hands and go to a meal</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not be to jumpy with this idea, chances are that your partner will not take to the idea very well</item>
<item>If your partner wants to, then go to step #2</item>
<item>Guys, be careful about resting your head on a girl's shoulder, she might think you rather immature</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you did not enjoy it or if your partner didn't, apologize and talk about what else you can do besides this.</item></list>
</text>
