<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc26" title="Create a Bond with an Animal By Petting Them" shortTile="create-bond-animal" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-03-20" dateModified="2018-12-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Create_a_Bond_with_an_Animal_By_Petting_Them" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Create a Bond with an Animal By Petting Them</head><p>This page will be about how to create bonds with animals and how to pet/stroke them.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Stroking/petting</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>First, make sure you can be gentle with the animal you want to stroke/pet. You don't want to hurt it, scare it or be too rough and put it out of its comfort zone.</item>
<item>Make sure you know a lot about the animal you want to stroke/pet. If it gets scared or angry easily, you want to make sure that you can keep safe and give best methods of petting it.</item>
<item>Be sure to start off with the easier methods of petting and the gentler methods, use the harder method when the same animal knows you a bit better.</item>
<item>When you know the animal knows you a bit better, or if it is still timid, then coax it with some food. Everytime you see the same animal and keep feeding it little bits or food, it will know that it can trust you a lot more as you want to feed it more than harm it.</item>
<item>After the animal trusts you a lot more, you can finally go on to creating a bond with the same animal, just make sure you keep it gentle.</item></list>
<head>Creating a bond</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If you haven't read the first part about petting/ stroking. Then please check that out before reading this part.</item>
<item>Start off with the petting and the coaxing methods with the animal. It will trust you a lot more in the bond.</item>
<item>Make sure you can spare a lot of time to spend with the animal, so that the bond can go a bit further. So that everytime you see it, it may or may not recognize you.</item>
<item>Even if you have made a bond with your animal, it is important to stay gentle and passive to the animal, if you don't the trust for you in the animal might decrease.</item>
<item>Take other things to animal, for example, if the animal is a stray cat, take some coloured feathers or a toy mouse. This can also help the bond and stroking the animal a lot easier.</item>
<item>Remember, bonds with anything can take years to form, so don't try to speed it up. It is exactly the same as with humans in relationships.</item>
<item>Follow this tutorial again and again, so you can be able to stroke and create a bond and it will make creating a bond easier.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take latex gloves if the animal is liable to bite. If you are allergic to latex, try other options</item>
<item>Be sure to not grab the animal or try to immediately pick it up, it may or may not get scared.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be careful if it is a dangerous animal, you don't want to get injured in the process.</item></list>
</text>
