<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc117" title="Survive a Breakup After 18 Years of Marriage and 2 Small Children" shortTile="survive-breakup-" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-04-02" dateModified="2017-05-21" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Survive_a_Breakup_After_18_Years_of_Marriage_and_2_Small_Children" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Survive a Breakup After 18 Years of Marriage and 2 Small Children</head><p>You wake up one morning, only to find that life as you once knew it will never ever be the same again. Your husband of 18 years have bought airline tickets and luxurious hotel accommodations for himself and a prostitute to go on vacation to sunny Palm Beach, leaving you and the kids at home.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Step 1.  Now what?  Your whole world is shattered. First you breathe, just breathe, so you don't explode.  You will be shaking, filled with rage, anger, emotions that cannot be put into words.  Stay calm, there is light at the end of the tunnel.</item>
<item>Step 2.  You wait for him to leave for his glorious vacation.  You take the kids to school, you do your normal things throughout the day, so you keep busy.  Now you go deep, start the introspection.  Strategize, plan, and do not take this lightly, you have to put the time and effort into planning, instead of being angry.  Channel that energy into your plan for your future and that of your children.</item>
<item>Step 3. Now its time to see an Attorney, go through the effort of booking the appointment and keeping it, because you are going to need one.  Discuss your plan of action and find out how beneficial this will be for you and your children.</item>
<item>Step 4.  I know by now you are fit to be tied, take all his belongings out of the house, rain or sun put them in neat little boxes and trash bags at the end of the driveway for trash day.</item>
<item>,Step 5. Now get a locksmith, change the locks, all the alarm codes, sell his car if you can while he is away.  (And if its not trash day, donate all his clothes to the thrift store)  If you are having problems selling his car, donate it to the salvation army, they will even come and get it.</item>
<item>Step 6. Now wait for him to return, and get a restraining order against him while he is away, when he shows up call the police.  They will certainly escort him off the property for you.</item>
<item>Step 7. Now present him with the demands and resolutions from your attorney visit, or you will drag him through the mud, both him and his prostitute.  More than likely, if he has any ounce of dignity left, he will spare his children the embarrassment and humiliation of his deplorable behavior and blatant disregard for his family.</item>
<item>Step 8. Dont forget to wave goodbye.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>NEVER MOVE OUT.  NEVER EVER</item>
<item>No matter how much he begs, pleads, and apologize, don't even think of conceding.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be aware of your feelings of uncertainty and being scared.  This is completely normal and will pass in time.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A good support system.  This can be either close friends or family members who have your best interest at heart.</item></list>
</text>
