<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc56" title="Teach and Avoid the Dangers of Fake Faith Healers" shortTile="teach-avoid-dangers" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-10-12" dateModified="2019-06-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Teach_and_Avoid_the_Dangers_of_Fake_Faith_Healers" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Teach and Avoid the Dangers of Fake Faith Healers</head><p>Here is how to teach and also avoid the dangers of fake faith healers.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>How to teach the dangers of fake faith healers</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look up on one or more of the various search engines. <figure rend="Teach and Avoid the Dangers of Fake Faith Healers Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know and teach scriptures. Like, “If you lend money to one of my people among you who is needy, do not be like a moneylender; charge him no interest” (Exodus 22:25; see also Psalm 15:5) and also Deuteronomy 23:19-20 ESV /, “You shall not charge interest on loans to your brother, interest on money, interest on food, interest on anything that is lent for interest. You may charge a foreigner interest, but you may not charge your brother interest, that the Lord your God may bless you in all that you undertake in the land that you are entering to take possession of it and also Leviticus 25:35-37 ESV ; “If your brother becomes poor and cannot maintain himself with you, you shall support him as though he were a stranger and a sojourner, and he shall live with you. Take no interest from him or profit, but fear your God, that your brother may live beside you. You shall not lend him your money at interest, nor give him your food for profit and many other scriptures such as Matthew 7:15-18 and also 1st Timothy 6: 10. <figure rend="Teach and Avoid the Dangers of Fake Faith Healers Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Teach people the warnings signs and also how to react like <hi rend="italic">Warning sign #1</hi> <hi rend="italic">: If he says to give up medication because God's going to heal you, DO NOT under any circumstances follow what he is telling you because this is a BIG AND DEFINITE tip off that this ^healer^ is fake.Just like for example if MegaI Love Music from YouTube is offered a ride by ^Dish Network workers^ who look friendly but He (MegaILoveMuzic from YouTube) calls Dish Network and says like ^Hi, my name is (name) and I am at (where MegaILoveMuzic is at) and this is a Dish Network vehicle's license plate number (license plate number is told) are these workers really Dish Network workers?^and the Dish Network customer service says ^no in fact there is no scheduled Dish Network service for (address)^for example, this is A BIG AND DEFINITE tip off that these ^Dish Network workers^  are evil doers who have intentions on first tricking him then getting him to a secluded location then harming and hurting and quite possible murdering him so he should not ever go in these ^Dish Network workers^ ^Dish Network^ vehicle.Same thing if a televangelist says like ^give up medication^ for example, this is highly illegal and dangerous to follow and you should NOT follow his ^holy^ advice.</hi> for example. <figure rend="Teach and Avoid the Dangers of Fake Faith Healers Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get and make post cards, YouTube videos, etc. warning people of the dangers of fake faith healers. <figure rend="Teach and Avoid the Dangers of Fake Faith Healers Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>How to avoid the dangers of fake faith healers</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask yourself important questions like <hi rend="italic">What is he saying</hi> <hi rend="italic">? Is he telling me what I must actually do for example if I am being bullied at a dishwashing job that I should report the offender to police for example?</hi>  for example. <figure rend="Teach and Avoid the Dangers of Fake Faith Healers Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Answer the important questions (in your mind of course) like <hi rend="italic">He is saying and insisting that God will protect me from this mean dishwasher I have at my dishwashing job</hi> <hi rend="italic">. But wait even the devils believe in God and tremble James 2: 19,this guy is not telling me stuff like report the mean dishwasher to the police, instead this ^healer^ is telling me to just trust in God.So I better not follow what this ^healer^ says.</hi>  for example. <figure rend="Teach and Avoid the Dangers of Fake Faith Healers Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Act on the answers to your important questions like going to the police to report a mean dishwasher assaulting you at your dishwashing job for example and tell yourself either in your mind or verbally or both like   ^good and holy advice^ that I should just trust in God, because even the demons believe in God and tremble James 2: 19, so I must never just trust God, I must do actions as well to get what I need done get done.  <hi rend="italic">for example.</hi> <figure rend="Teach and Avoid the Dangers of Fake Faith Healers Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take heed of websites, others etc. warning about fake faith healers. <figure rend="Teach and Avoid the Dangers of Fake Faith Healers Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Please make websites, blogs, others, videos, mixes, mix, video, other, blog, website etc. warning people to never follow dangerous advice/dangerous advices/etc. given by fake faith healers.</item>
<item>Please report fake faith healers.</item>
<item>Fake faith healers get information by wearing a non visible earpiece and also microphone, which the microphone transmits the voices being told  for example and also the earpiece is so that he can hear what is being told to him from someone (probably his wife) telling him whatever.</item></list>
</text>
