<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc134" title="Meet a Boyfriend Through Friends" shortTile="meet-boyfriend-through" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-08-09" dateModified="2018-04-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Meet_a_Boyfriend_Through_Friends" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Meet a Boyfriend Through Friends</head><p>Meeting men can be hard, but if you have mutual friendships then that's already half the battle right there! Here are some ways you can meet boys/men through friends.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Simply ask your friend</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Whether your friend is a girl or boy, simply asking them if they have a single, cute friend that would be interested in you could be the most simplest way to get a boyfriend.  This would take the edge off going on a blind date, because you and your friend could go together with the target boyfriend and it would be less awkward. If the two of you are vibing on each other, then go for it!</item></list>
<head>Get your friend to be your wingman</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If you already know target boyfriend and you like him, then tell your friend and most likely they will help you!  Since they are friends with both you and the target boy, it is easy for them to be the middle man to set you guys up. They can tell the boy good things about you, invite him over when your there too, have parties together, and so forth.  There are a million different scenarios where you both could be at the same place same time.  Just be careful to be not too pushy or over-familiar.  If he's not showing signs that he's interested, then back off and just be friends. Maybe in time he will grow to have feelings.</item>
<item>Planting the seed in his mind about you is also half the battle.  If you are being yourself and natural, plus your friend's wingman-ment, then there is a strong chance that he will be thinking about it (about you).  The most important thing is to be yourself, out-going (fake it even if you're shy) and be comfortable around him.  Guys are surprisingly good at picking up vibes, and if your not comfortable or being fake, then he'll slowly withdraw from you.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your friend and the boy are going to the movies, ask if you can come along for example.  Flirting is always a good way to show that you like them.  (Research how good flirting is done)Soon enough, if you are connecting well with the guy, you guys will be in a couple and your friend will be the third wheel.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not over do it.  Guys can get scared off easily if flirting is not done properly, and if you are always there like a stalker, then it is not good.  Be approachable, poised, and friendly.If your friend tells you he doesn't like you back, then accept it.  Don't obsess. It can get messy.</item></list>
</text>
