<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc1" title="Deal with Being a Tween" shortTile="deal-being-tween" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2019-07-12" dateModified="2019-07-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Deal_with_Being_a_Tween" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Deal with Being a Tween</head><head>Steps</head>
<head>Health</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Most people should wash their hair around 3-4 times a week, but it depends on your hair type. If you have oily hair, you might even wash your hair every day (but be careful, because washing your hair everyday can strip away its natural oils),  while those with dry hair should only wash their hair once a week.
<list type="unordered"><item>Wash with a shampoo and conditioner right for your hair.</item>
<item>Optionally, use hair masks and other treatments.</item></list></item>
<item>Brush your teeth twice every day, no more, no less. Brushing your teeth less than twice away can result in a buildup of plaque, and brushing your teeth more than twice a day wears away your enamel, weakening your teeth.
<list type="unordered"><item>Floss as well to remove plaque stuck in between your teeth.</item>
<item>Clean the roof of your mouth and tongue, because bacteria is found in there too.</item></list></item>
<item>Don’t paint your nails more than twice a month. Trim and shape them at least once a month.
<list type="unordered"><item>Toenails should always be cut straight to avoid ingrowns.</item></list></item>
<item>Wash your face twice every day with a cleanser appropriate for your skin. If you want, moisturise and tone as well.</item>
<item>Always wash your hands before eating or cooking, and after you use the bathroom. Avoid picking your nose, touching your eyes, or biting your fingernails.
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you get vaccinated. Vaccination rarely causes harm, and the diseases you can get are much worse than the pain of an injection.</item></list></item>
<item>It’s recommended by doctors that tweens and teens exercise for at least an hour everyday, but if you aren’t used to exercise, start with 15 minutes a day and work from there.
<list type="unordered"><item>Cardio exercise helps prevent heart disease, builds your immunity, and improves your endurance and stamina, while strength exercise makes you stronger and prevents injury.</item></list></item>
<item>Eat a balanced diet, including carbohydrates, vegetables, fruit, dairy, and meat/fish/other sources of protein.
<list type="unordered"><item>Don’t go on a diet for a short period of time. You will just gain the weight back, and unless you have been told by a medical professional to lose weight, you probably don’t need to. Just eat healthily, and you will notice plenty of positive changes in your body.</item></list></item>
<item>Shower every day, and use deodorant/antiperspirant to expel any odours, use perfume as well if you want. Change outfits everyday.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you still seem to smell after regularly following these steps, visit a doctor to check for an underlying health problem.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Time Mangement</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do your homework as soon as possible. If you have the time, finish all of your homework as soon as you get home from school. Use a planner and record your assignments for each class throughout the day,</item>
<item>Live a balanced life. Make time for everything in your life every week.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are struggling, try leaving some of your commitments. Prioritise what matters most to you.</item></list></item>
<item>Keep your personal space clean. Regularly tidy your room. If you have a cluttered home, you will have a cluttered mind.</item>
<item>Look after your mental health. Take some time off every day for self-care. Do whatever makes you feel calm and happy for this time.</item></list>
<head>Social Life</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make friends with lots of people. If you have a fight with your closest friends, you have others to rely on.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are introverted and struggle with making friends, sign up to more extra-curricular. The more people you meet, the more you will connect with.</item></list></item>
<item>Report bullying. Whether you are being bullied, or you witness someone else being bullied, immediately report it to a trusted adult. If you don't know what to do, there are plenty of helplines out there.</item></list>
</text>
