<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc118" title="Find a Foreign Wife from Europe or America" shortTile="find-foreign-wife" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-03-25" dateModified="2017-05-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find_a_Foreign_Wife_from_Europe_or_America" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find a Foreign Wife from Europe or America</head><p>if you are a guy who wants to improve his living and move to other countries and find your soulmate then here are some tips that will help you</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>collect money for going to the country you want</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>find a job and start collecting money for going to the country that you want to live in.THis is the toughest thing that you might have to do if you are not rich because going to European countries requires a lot of money.</item></list>
<head>getting a girl</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>this step is not much difficult if you have a smart phone and internet and you know how to use your phone.You must also be able to speak english in order to communicate to women of other countries.</item>
<item>choose the most popular dating sites of the country in which you want to go.You can find the dating websites of specific countries by simply searching google.You can also download dating apps from play store which are worldwide popular.</item>
<item>create your profile on the dating apps or websites that you find most working.Upload best of your photos on those websites.DO NOT upload the photos in which you look ugly.</item>
<item>pretend that you live in America or Europe and don't tell the people on that website that which country you are from.</item>
<item>contact the chicks that you like the most on that website.try to contact chicks who are new on those dating websites.chat with them for a few hours and get to know them.Don't ask them any personal questions just ask them a few simple questions and just be normal.</item>
<item>after getting to know them ask them for their kik messenger id because kik messenger is one of the most popular in America and Europe.if they don't use kik then ask them for skype or any other social messenger they use.don't ask them for facebook or Twitter because if you'll give them your facebook or Twitter then they will get to know where are you from.also don't exchange your phone numbers at the moment.just ask them for the messengers in which their is only your username shown and nothing else is shown.</item>
<item>chat with them and get them to like you.If you are handsome then it will be very easy for you because there is deficiency of handsome men in Europe(wink).Try to be a romantic person and never tell them where you live currently.</item></list>
<head>going to the country you want to live in the future</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>by that time you will have collected enough to go to Europe  or America.just go there and find a job and ask the one you've been chatting with to meet you.:)</item></list>
<head>getting her to like you</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>real world is very different from the chatting world so you will have to do the same things again in real life to get her to like you and when you think it is the right time,just propose her and she will say YES!have a lovely life with her.</item></list>
<head>never tell her about what you did</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>if you will tell her that you have been lying to her then she will get pissed off and she will leave you within days.just love her by heart and be her MAN.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>chat with as many people on dating sites as you can this will give you an idea of European culture.</item>
<item>don't use your real name on dating websites.</item>
<item>never talk about religion with her.</item>
<item>don't rush.</item>
<item>don't give her your phone number.</item>
<item>build good english speaking skills.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>don't do anything against the laws or you might get punished.</item></list>
</text>
