<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc133" title="Improve Relationships with Your Beloved" shortTile="improve-relationships" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-09-15" dateModified="2015-05-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Improve_Relationships_with_Your_Beloved" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Improve Relationships with Your Beloved</head><p>Your perspective towards your relationship can only lead to the stage you want. The keyword for a perfect relation with your mate is love and dedication. But what matters most is the implementation of love or better said how you show or exhibit your love in the relationship.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>The first and foremost thing that can help you fetch your love back into your partners mind is your smile, happiness and confidence in you that shows you are good enough for him or her. Moreover if you feel neglected or you find that your partner is not noticing this change in you, remember its only you who can make him notice. But of course don't overdo anything, never let your partner feel that you are doing anything to get him or her closer to you. All methods that I recommend here can only help you. If you can perform these in a confidential manner, as humans tend to be alert if they notice anything special and since a relationship is based on how a heart feels not on how a mind calculates, so its your part to play it safe on him or her.</item>
<item>Second most important point is to show your contentment. Contentment here means your satisfaction.You have to show that you are very satisfied with your partner and this will definitely work on him. Like it is said-"The love you give out multiplies and comes back to you".So,once you can show that you are satisfied with him or her, things will get to sort out automatically and you will be amazed to see the instant effects. By the implementation of this you will make your partner comfortable. A relationship lasts long only when both person feel comfortable. Its you who will have to start making your mate comfortable by being satisfied with the relation you have. This will incorporate the sense of security in your mate's mind. This feeling in turn will poke him to accept you the way you are. In short you are inducing the attitude of acceptance in your partner's mind by accepting him.</item>
<item>Strong will power is something that attracts your partner towards you. Of course you might feel that will power is an abstract feeling but then you must realise that you are also after an abstract thing that is love and relationship. So the fact is you can use one abstract thing to attract another thing of similar behaviour. Strong will power can only show you results if you start thinking of the person you love when he or she is not really present before you. When you are alone you have the chance to put your thoughts in your mates mind just by thinking of him or her. What happens is when we think of something too much then we usually get it by the Law of attraction of the universe. So you can use this abstract method to get your love revived and relive your love story.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Only happiness can fetch you happiness and only love can fetch you love. So firstly be happy and then implement the three steps written above. You will definitely get the benefits.</item></list>
</text>
