<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc186" title="Grow Facial Hair Fast As a Teenager" shortTile="grow-facial-hair" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-10-06" dateModified="2018-10-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Grow_Facial_Hair_Fast_As_a_Teenager" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Grow Facial Hair Fast As a Teenager</head><p>If you're worried about the poor growth of your facial hair at the age of 18, and do not have the patience to leave it to the future days when you can see your beard has grown naturally. Here are some tips that can help you grow your beard faster.There are two ways by which you can pursue the growth of your facial hair,</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Using Natural Methods to Increase Facial Hair Growth</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get enough sleep. Good sleep is a must if you want to achieve a faster growth of facial hair. Get a good sleep as much as possible within a comfortable environment (sleeping in absolute darkness is recommended). <figure rend="Theisakhadem.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Reduce stress. Although it may be hard to do this, meditation and music can be of great help. <figure rend="37806223344_5fd6f57377_k.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stop shaving or trimming. Let your facial hair grow naturally for two to three weeks without shaving or trimming. It can be quite irritating, but you can achieve your purpose by just holding on to your patience.</item>
<item>Eat healthy food. Eating healthy food is the best way by which you can supplement the growth of your beard naturally. Include any food products that are rich in biotin, folic acid, vitamin A and vitamin B3 in your daily diet in order to encourage the faster growth of your facial hair.</item>
<item>Exercise. Regular exercise can help to enhance the production of testosterone, which is necessary for boosting the hair growth in a natural process. Weight lifting and squats are some recommended exercises.</item>
<item>Avoid junk food. Avoid taking junk food, as it may affect the body in many ways that can hamper the growth of the hair.</item>
<item>Use a mild cleanser. Wash your face at least twice a day with a mild cleanser mixed in warm water. This will help to clean the hair follicles and promote the hair growth. Also use a moisturizing cream containing Eucalyptus that can help remove the dry patches of the skin and help in a faster hair growth.</item>
<item>Massage your face. Use an exfoliating cream that can help remove the dead skin cells and clean the pores of the hair.</item>
<item>Drink plenty of water.</item></list>
<head>Taking Supplements to Promote Facial Hair Growth</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take creatine. Include salmon, tuna, beef and pork in your diet. They contain creatine, which helps to boost the production of testosterone, which is essential for hair growth.</item>
<item>Apply Rogaine. Although the drug is not approved by the FDA, you can try applying a paste made of Rogaine and warm water on your face to promote hair growth.</item>
<item>Apply a mixture of various supplements. Prepare a mixture of 1 tablespoon each of Castor Oil, Grapeseed Oil, Evening Primrose Oil, Sheanut Oil, Almond Oil, Coconut Oil and Extra Virgin Olive Oil with a moisturizing lotion and apply on the face twice a day. This will help to keep the skin exfoliated and to remove any dead cells inside the hair follicles.</item>
<item>Try medication. You can try one tablet each of Arginine and Biotine for helping the growth of your facial hair.</item>
<item>Use plant oils. Prepare a mixture of the following plant oils with warm water, adding arginine, MSM and biotin supplements. Cedarwood essential oil, clary sage essential oil, carrot seed essential oil, tea tree essential oil, vetiver essential oil, rosemary essential oil, eucalyptus essential oil, cypress essential oil, ylang essential oil, chamomile essential oil and lavender essential oil are the plant oils that you can use. Apply the mixture on your face, head, eyebrows, and eyelashes at bedtime to get the best effect.</item>
<item>Look into topical remedies. There are some topical remedies that you can try at home. Prepare a mixture of mustard leaves and Amla Oil and blend it well to form a paste. Apply the paste on your face and leave for 20 minutes before washing. You can also try the same procedure using lime juice and ground cinnamon.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sleeping in a 'dark' room helps to grow facial hair faster.</item>
<item>Limit blue light exposure from mobile and computer screens, etc.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Stay away from smoking.</item></list>
</text>
