<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc196" title="Be More Successful at Life Starting at a Young Age" shortTile="more-successful-life" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-12-23" dateModified="2019-01-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_More_Successful_at_Life_Starting_at_a_Young_Age" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be More Successful at Life Starting at a Young Age</head><p>Do you want to be more successful in life? Are you young and not sure how to do that? If you are smart and around middle school age, the reliable, solid advice in this article is perfect for you. Get started at step number one below.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Pay_Attention_in_Class">Pay attention in school.</ref> <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Take_Notes">Take proper notes</ref> and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Sit">sit upright</ref> so you <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_More_Alert">stay alert</ref>. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Healthy_Breakfast_Meals">Eat a good breakfast</ref> in the morning, and have a bottle of cold water with you to drink. You should feel comfortable in class, but not so comfortable that you <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Stay_Awake_During_School">fall asleep</ref>. <figure rend="Be More Successful at Life Starting at a Young Age Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Ask_a_Question_Intelligently">Ask questions.</ref> Many people don't ask questions because they are afraid it will make them sound dumb, but smart people question everything. If you don't understand something, don't and wait until after class to ask your teacher, be brave <hi rend="italic">raise your hand</hi>. <figure rend="Be More Successful at Life Starting at a Young Age Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Use_a_Public_Library">Go to the library</ref>.  Check out books on science, math, music, poetry etc. These are all subjects frequently studied by successful people.  The library is a goldmine of knowledge.  Ask your librarian what books they would recommend.  Librarians can answer almost any question you have, or direct you to the answer, so go for it! <figure rend="Be More Successful at Life Starting at a Young Age Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Learn_a_Language">Learn a language</ref>. There are some very good computer software programs that can assist you in learning a new language. You can ask your teachers or the library if they know any good computer programs for learning new languages. <figure rend="Be More Successful at Life Starting at a Young Age Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Respectful">Be respectful</ref>. People will take you a lot more seriously if you are respectful. Teachers may be shocked if you say thank you, please, yes sir, no sir. Even if you are smart, but you act arrogant, they will not respect you.  You'll get a lot farther showing respect. <figure rend="Be More Successful at Life Starting at a Young Age Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Dress_Well">Dress nicely</ref>, and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Hygienic">practice good hygiene</ref>. This means pull up your shirt, buy clothes that fit. Do nice makeup, if you are male or female, do your hair pretty and neat, and wear clean clothes. Take a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Take_a_Daily_Shower">shower daily,</ref> <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Brush_Your_Teeth">brush your teeth</ref>, and wear deodorant. <figure rend="Be More Successful at Life Starting at a Young Age Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Cut out any unproductive activities that waste valuable time (ex. Smoking cigarettes, playing video games.) You should still have some time to relax, just don't play Super Mario Bros. for six hours a night.</item>
<item>Don't hang around with the wrong people.</item>
<item>Be organized.</item>
<item>Listen to classical pieces (Mozart, Beethoven, Bach).</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some friends will blow you off if you study and don't hang out with them 24/7. Ignore them. In the long run, having a good education is more important than spending a few hours at an arcade.</item>
<item>Keep a cool head. Take a break from time to time, and blow off steam. To be successful, you need a clear goal and a cool head.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A library card</item></list>
</text>
