<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc199" title="Live It up Before You're Twelve" shortTile="live-up-before-re" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-04-07" dateModified="2019-06-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Live_It_up_Before_You%27re_Twelve" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Live It up Before You're Twelve</head><p>Although growing up is exciting, it also means you'll be less able to do things that you loved to do as a kid. This article will teach you how to enjoy your last years before you become a teenager.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Blanket_Fort">Build a fort</ref>. Use blankets, pillows, chairs, tables, and anything else you can find to make an elaborate fort to watch movies or spend the night in. When it's finished, invite your siblings, parents, friends, or pets in it with you. Watch movies, tell scary stories, and share secrets in the fort. <figure rend="Live It up Before You're Twelve Step 01.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Climb_a_Tree">Climb a tree.</ref> Take advantage of the fact that you're still light enough to sit on the smaller branches towards the top. Have a contest to see who can climb the fastest or the highest. Don't be afraid to get dirty! <figure rend="Live It up Before You're Twelve Step 02.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Pamper_Yourself">Pamper yourself</ref>. Not everything you do has to be kid like. Ages 10 and 11 are great ages because you get to act like a teenager when you want, but can still go back to acting like a child without anyone getting mad at you. If you want to spend some time acting more like a teenager, get some magazines or a good book and take a bubble bath. Spend an hour or two of me time in the tub before you come out. <figure rend="Live It up Before You're Twelve Step 03.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Go_to_the_Movies">Go to the movies</ref>. Ask your parents if you can take a friend to the movies. If your parents aren't comfortable with you going alone, sit a few seats away from them with your friend so that the two of you can talk without your parents overhearing. <figure rend="Live It up Before You're Twelve Step 04.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get lost in your imagination. Get all your chores and homework done early in the morning. Spend the rest of the day pretending you're a paleontologist out on a dig or the leader of a distant planet. Think of your parents as your assistants or your loyal subjects so that you can continue your play during meals. <figure rend="Live It up Before You're Twelve Step 05.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat your favorite foods. Ask your parents to make you a dinner with all your favorite foods from when you were a kid, including your favorite dessert! Don't worry about being polite for one night—just enjoy the foods as if you were a little kid again! <figure rend="Live It up Before You're Twelve Step 06.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Creative">Do something creative</ref>. Invite some friends over for a crafts day. Paint, draw, write, sculpt...do whatever sort of creative activity makes you want. At the end, trade finished products and all agree to keep them in your rooms. You could also try to sell them to your parents if you want. <figure rend="Live It up Before You're Twelve Step 07.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Not_Care_What_People_Think">Be free</ref>. Many teens suffer from worrying about other people. Just let go and be free. Wear what YOU like. Act like yourself. Be true to yourself.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you really want to live it up, try to have a family vacation out of the country if you can afford it.</item></list>
</text>
