<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc31" title="Get Your Pet Blessed" shortTile="pet-blessed" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-06-21" dateModified="2017-06-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_Your_Pet_Blessed" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Your Pet Blessed</head><p>We give affection, care, and attention to our adorable creatures. We feel angry or depressed when our pet dies. We play with them all the time. Here is another nice thing you can do for the pet you love.</p>
<p>Every year, on October 4th, many Catholic and Anglican churches celebrate the feast of St. Frances, a holy man, who loved God, wore robes, begged for his food, and who especially loved and cared for animals. St. Frances lived in Italy between the years 1184 and 1226.  He was born into a very wealthy family and lived a wild life seeking fun and happiness. It was a vision that told him to turn to a holy life and live in Assisi. He is now called St. Frances of Assisi. Since he loved animals, a celebration called The Feast of St. Francis is celebrated every year. Pets get blessed by the Priest to help us remember that God made animals and that they are loveable and worthy of respect, as St. Frances knew. Even in today's world, you can have your animals blessed, any kind of animal, by attending a service called The Blessing of the Animals.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Planning</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to Church before October fourth. Go to your local Anglican or Catholic church or to any church where you know that this event is going to be celebrated. <figure rend="Get Your Pet Blessed Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask for the time and place of celebration. Ask the church secretary or the Priest what time the service will be held and where. Some churches hold two services. Services will alway be on October fourth and will almost always be done outside.</item></list>
<head>Preparation</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Put a collar around your pet's neck and attach a leash. Or make sure your pet is securely placed in a carrying kennel. It's best if the kennel has openings so that the holy water that is going to be sprinkled onto your pet is able to reach and touch your pet. <figure rend="Get Your Pet Blessed Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Control your pet throughout the ceremony. It is very important, and that is why leashes or kennels or whatever you use to control your pet are recommended.</item>
<item>Feed your pet before the service. So that it is more likely to behave and be quiet.</item>
<item>Prevent any harms. If you are planning to bring an animal that could harm other animals or people, take preventive steps.
<list type="unordered"><item>Muzzle a dog, and if people come up to pet the dog, tell them quickly not to do so, as the dog might try to bite.</item>
<item>Similarly, keep a horse on the outskirts of the crowd and make sure no child walks behind the horse, as the horse may kick.</item></list></item>
<item>Stay aware. Be cautious, as it is unusual for many different kinds of animals to be brought together like this, and you don't want anyone or any animal harmed.</item></list>
<head>Celebration</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to the church with your pet and walk to the location of the service. If you aren't feeling sure about what to do, ask a nearby person. If that person is a member of the church, they've probably done this before and will be happy to help you.</item>
<item>Listen to readings. Usually, everyone stands around with their pets, and the Priest or Deacon will explain the meaning of the service and how it will go, step by step.</item>
<item>Pray. Then the leader will say some prayers asking God to bless all these animals, hoping the animals have a happier, healthier life. A Priest may even pray to St. Frances whom the Priest believes is in heaven, watching down over all animals.</item>
<item>Reassure your pet. Finally, the Priest or Deacon will ask God to bless your pet with a happy future and will lightly sprinkle your pet with holy water. Only a very few drops of water will get on your pet, as the water is shaken out of a small, silver tube that has small holes. <figure rend="Get Your Pet Blessed Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If this might frighten your pet, even thought the Priest usually doesn't get too close to the animal, be sure you have good control over your pet for its sprinkling.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Calm your pet down before the ceremony so it doesn't cause trouble.</item>
<item>Know what your pet is sensitive to, and stay away from these obstacles.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>It's your responsibility to look after your pet!</item>
<item>It is very important to know that this is "'not"' a baptism of your pet. It is just a blessing which is exactly like a wish for good things. Baptisms require whole church services and are done only for humans. It would be very disrespectful of the meaning of baptism if baptism were applied to animals.</item></list>
</text>
