<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc65" title="Understand Agnosticism" shortTile="understand-agnosticism" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-02-25" dateModified="2018-08-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Understand_Agnosticism" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Understand Agnosticism</head><p>You may have come across someone who identifies him/herself as an agnostic. Or you may feel that you are agnostic and want to be sure. In this article, you can understand the idea of agnosticism and learn what it means to be an agnostic.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Read the tips in this wikiHow article. As our goal is to understand agnosticism, we have to gather information about this worldview.</item>
<item>Read the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agnosticism">Wikipedia article</ref> about agnosticism. Wikipedia is a great place to start when researching about a general topic.</item>
<item>Search Facebook or other social media websites for groups of agnostics and join them. This will help you connect with other agnostics and have personal discussions with them to understand more about the topic. You will also make new like-minded friends.</item>
<item>If you live in a progressive community, seek out agnostic groups that gather in your local community. You may be able to find them through the local listings or by searching online at event sites like Meetup.</item>
<item>Keep an open mind when learning about agnosticism. This is a worldview often held by people who have thought about and evaluated the existence of a deity.</item>
<item>Talk about the different views and have varied discussions with your fellow agnostics. This will help you open your mind to new worldviews and interesting knowledge.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Agnosticism is the belief that at present time humanity does not have the knowledge, nor the capabilities to prove or disprove the existence of any deity or supernatural elements.</item>
<item>Weak agnostics consider the possibility that we may obtain the knowledge or capabilities to do so in the future. Strong agnostics believe it is impossible to ever do so.</item>
<item>The term <hi rend="italic">agnosticism</hi> was coined by Huxley in the nineteenth century.</item>
<item>Agnosticism is not the same as atheism. Atheism is the lack of a belief in the existence of a deity.</item>
<item>People who hold this opinion are often unsure about the existence of a higher being, but don't feel certain enough that the existence of a higher being has been disproved. Therefore they hold the opinion that one could possibly exist.</item>
<item>Agnosticism and atheism can co-exist. A person may identify himself as an agnostic atheist, which means he agrees about the lack of knowledge and capabilities to disprove the existence of any deity, and at the same time does not believe that such a deity actually exists (although it may be possible).</item>
<item>Agnostics may have some interesting points to consider. You could even make friends, but remember that you should always become friends with someone because of their personality, not their beliefs.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't make grave assumptions about why they question the existence of a deity or higher power.</item>
<item>Don't keep a closed mind. You do not have to alter your own beliefs, but accept that it is normal for others to have beliefs different than yours.</item>
<item>If you assume that the only reason this belief is held is because someone is ignorant or stupid, you may get into a fight or argument.</item>
<item>Don't try to proselytize or attempt to convert agnostics to believers, as they want you to respect their position as much as they respect yours.</item></list>
</text>
