<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc128" title="Get Her to Choose You" shortTile="get-her-to-choose" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-11-30" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_Her_to_Choose_You" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Her to Choose You</head><p>When it comes to dating, many men wonder why a woman would choose him over all of the other guys out there. Do women always seem to choose your friends instead of you? Do you feel like you are only one in your group who does not get noticed when out on the town? If so, its easy to start doubting yourself and to think negative thoughts. The truth is that you do have a lot to offer. What may be stopping you from meeting beautiful women is the fact that you are too busy thinking about what you don’t have. The great thing about women is that they all want different things. That means that there are ways for you to stand out from the crowd and get her to choose you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be comfortable with yourself. One of the biggest turn-ons for women is a man who is comfortable with himself. When a woman is around a man who is comfortable in his own skin, she will be able to sense this and instantly relax. Why? Well, it signals to her that you are genuine, relaxed, and will most likely accept her for who she is. Women want a man who is easy to talk to and be around. If you show her this side of yourself, she will choose to be around you. <figure rend="Get Her to Choose You Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be humble. Avoid being the loudmouth guy who brags about his possessions at all costs. It will not impress most women and can actually be a turn-off. Instead, be the guy who catches her eye and smiles at her, who genuinely seems to want to get to know her, who comes across as friendly, down to earth, and confident. This will make you the man women want to spend the rest of the night talking to. Guess what? She just chose you! <figure rend="Get Her to Choose You Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pay attention to her. If you want to stand out in a woman’s eyes, start by giving her your full and undivided attention. To women, there is nothing more flattering than having a man fully focused on her. The best way to see if she wants your attention in the first place is to make eye contact and smile. If she holds your gaze or looks back and smiles, then you can rest assured that she is interested. Once you have used your eyes to meet her, you can use your ears to keep it going by paying close attention to what she is saying. It’s always good to nod and to ask questions to show that you are listening. <figure rend="Get Her to Choose You Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be true to your word. Women want a man who can be trusted and relied on during the good times and the bad. One of the biggest gripes you will hear from women is how men don’t do what they say they will. You want to be the man who she can trust, rely on, and who can make her feel secure. <figure rend="Get Her to Choose You Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be trustworthy. This can be as simple as being true to your word and keeping your promises. In order to be trustworthy, you must be honest. Remember, women can be really good at picking up on b.s. and lies. All you have to do is answer her questions as honestly as possible. Also, remember to be real. You don’t want to come across as something that you aren't. If you can be true to your word, she will choose you. <figure rend="Get Her to Choose You Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Show her your funny side. If you can make a woman laugh, you are already closer to having her choose you than the other guy in the room. If you are thinking, “Great, there goes my shot, I’m not a funny guy”, I’m going to let you in on a little secret. You don’t need to be a funny to make her laugh! Just let your natural sense of humor shine through. If she’s funny, don’t be afraid to laugh at her jokes and to tease her a little. Remember, when someone makes us laugh, we naturally feel happy and alive. These good feelings can help create affection and can help you both to feel comfortable with each other. This will get her to choose you. <figure rend="Get Her to Choose You Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>It may take time to do these things naturally, but you can create a lasting impression that will get the woman you want to choose you if you take the time to learn them.</item></list>
</text>
