<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc220" title="Have Fun when Parents Are Out of the House" shortTile="fun-parents-out-house" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-12-13" dateModified="2017-06-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have_Fun_when_Parents_Are_Out_of_the_House" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have Fun when Parents Are Out of the House</head><p>Do you ever experience the frustration when your parents are at home but you want to do something they will not allow? Same goes to when your parents are out, you can't think of what to do?</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start by creating a list. Write down the things that you want to do when your parents are not at home. This can be added to over time. <figure rend="Have Fun when Parents Are Out of the House Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask unsuspicious questions. Ask questions that don't let your parents suspect that you are planning something. You want to know when your parents are going out so you can plan beforehand. Also, try to find out where they are going. This information can be helpful at unexpected times. <figure rend="Have Fun when Parents Are Out of the House Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Schedule. Schedule the night with activities according to how long your parents are going to be away for. Also schedule when you are going to be tidying up. <figure rend="Have Fun when Parents Are Out of the House Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Create escape plans. In case your parents get home earlier than expected, plan whether to run to your bedroom and do what you are supposed to be doing, run to the bathroom and sit on the toilet, go to the kitchen and get a glass of water, or lie on the couch pretending to be asleep. <figure rend="Have Fun when Parents Are Out of the House Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Think up excuses. If you accidentally spill something or break something, think up reasonable and acceptable excuses of why you spilt/broke something. <figure rend="Have Fun when Parents Are Out of the House Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take notes. Note down any tasks your parents wish for you to complete whilst they are out of the house. Do them as soon as possible in case you forget later on. <figure rend="Have Fun when Parents Are Out of the House Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When your parents' car leaves the house, look through a vantage point where you can see the driveway. This is in case your parents leave something behind, return to the house, and catch you doing activities you shouldn't be doing. <figure rend="Have Fun when Parents Are Out of the House Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep the volume down. Your parents might decide to call you. If you are playing music very loud, you cannot hear the phone ringing. If you do not pick up, your parents will be worried and may even contact the police. Also, nosy neighbours may report to your parents that they heard loud music. <figure rend="Have Fun when Parents Are Out of the House Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep out of sight. If anyone, especially neighbours can see you through windows, move to another place where you will not be seen. Also, keep the house normal. Do not stupidly put up streamers and balloons or close all lights. This makes you way less suspicious. <figure rend="Have Fun when Parents Are Out of the House Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Dispose of your things. If you have been doing something your parents never let you do such as drink soft drink, do not throw the can in a bin in plain sight. Either hide the can under a pile of rubbish in the bin, dispose of it in your garbage bin, or throw it in a neighbour's bin. Either way, do not litter. <figure rend="Have Fun when Parents Are Out of the House Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Choose activities which do not require a lot of tidying up.</item>
<item>After your parents go out, lock the door if they already haven't. In this way, if you forget to keep a lookout, you always know your parents are home when you hear the jingling of keys in the lock.</item>
<item>Sit near your vantage point so that if your parents arrive home unexpectedly, you know when to flee.</item>
<item>If you would like to go on the computer and your parents check the history, make sure that you delete the history.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not wait until your parents get to the door, to run to your bedroom. They can hear your footsteps and wonder what you have been doing.</item>
<item>Do not do things that have a long term effect, such as drinking alcohol, as when your parents get home, they know by your flushed cheeks and your behaviour what you have been doing.</item>
<item>Do something quiet as your parents may decide to visit the neighbour the next day. The neighbour may tell your parents that they heard loud music last night, and you will get busted.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Earphones (if you listen to music)</item>
<item>Notebook</item></list>
</text>
