<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc71" title="Become an Aesthetic" shortTile="become-aesthetic" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-06-15" dateModified="2016-06-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Become_an_Aesthetic" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Become an Aesthetic</head><p>Aesthetics is a philosophical field of study which traditionally focuses on questions of beauty, value and usefulness of art. We all appreciate "beauty", but what do we mean by that? An aesthetic philosopher tries to unfold this concept and find its (many) meanings.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>An aesthetic philosopher is one who's concerned mainly with our sensitivities and how we judge such sensory information. It is an interesting field for those who like to ask what 'moves' us, and why we appreciate certain things and despise others.  <figure rend="Become an Aesthetic Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Writing is a good practice for thinking. Writing helps thinking by forcing you to recognize your abilities or inabilities to conceptualize your abstract ideas. It also helps you proceed logically from one assertion to another. Is it beautiful? If so, why it is beautiful to me? How is my judgment of daily things different from someone else's? <figure rend="Become an Aesthetic Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to art galleries, museums, see monuments and ask why do people call these great, magnificent, works of art. Each work of art has a historical significance, which is often avoided. Is beauty somewhat constant or suffers dramatic changes and meaning throughout history? The meaning of art must be studied historically otherwise we miss the implicit meaning it has acquired today, and then we can start asking questions like "should art makes us think?" or "is art by its nature political?" <figure rend="Become an Aesthetic Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember to not stop questioning your assertions. We often draw our conclusions too quickly over things we enjoy or because of an idea's simplicity. Part of being an aesthetic philosopher is to question what conditions your (and others) motives, beliefs and desires in order to understand feelings better rather than always letting oneself become taken by feelings. <figure rend="Become an Aesthetic Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Another aspect of Aesthetics is looking at how we perceive things. Each person has a different background and formation, although we, humans, are similar, to each every image has a personal or cultural significance that is out of reach of our feelings, but perhaps not out of reach of our understanding.  <figure rend="Become an Aesthetic Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Read work by aesthetic philosophers to get a grounding. Various authors have approached the questions of aesthetics giving it an expanding image to work with, the beauty of philosophizing is not an self-centered activity of sages and/or isolated minds. Know your limits of thinking and learn novel ways in which we can interpret aesthetics by reading others' take on the subject. Also share your opinions on the matter with others to see if you can construct, replace and defend your conceptions. <figure rend="Become an Aesthetic Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>The best place to start is questioning, but not any kind of questioning. Philosophy questions, but it also questions itself. An aesthetic, as a philosopher constantly studies and applies the knowledge first to himself, his own beliefs and prejudices. Understand that beauty, sensations and uses of art will always vary, use these differences we have between each other to change the way you think about the world. The field does not directly concern how one should behave, but concern our conceptions of certain values and how you will see and consequently act upon this world. <figure rend="Become an Aesthetic Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Seek out different areas of philosophy. Aesthetic is just a branch of philosophy and its delimitation is mainly for scholarly accessibility and not because it's a pure field of inquiry. Its applications expand when we start asking how everyday images affect our ideas, or how the media or advertising shapes our views about beauty. <figure rend="Become an Aesthetic Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
