<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc219" title="Be Organized (Kids)" shortTile="organized-kids" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-04-16" dateModified="2019-05-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_Organized_%28Kids%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Organized (Kids)</head>
<p>Are you having trouble staying organized? This tutorial will teach you to stay organized at home and at school. It will save you lots of time and stress, and may even impress your parents!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Organize Your Room</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make your bed. If you haven't washed your sheets in a while, be sure to do that as well. After they are clean, you can make your bed.</item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item>Clean the floor. Remove large and sharp objects that are on the floor. If you have access to one, use your vacuum cleaner.</item>
<item>Throw away any trash you find. Any trash or scraps that are in your room can be sent to the trashcan.</item>
<item>Put away anything that already has a place. This means putting away clean clothes in your closet or dresser, picking up loose toys, and other things.
<list type="unordered"><item>Set aside everything else. You'll find a home for it after you straighten the rest of your room.</item></list></item>
<item>Clear off other surfaces. Bookshelves, dresser tops, and desks are prime culprits here.
<list type="unordered"><item>Return items with a purpose to your surfaces. Items that you don't use often can go in bins, or in the trash. (Or sent to children without toys!)</item></list></item>
<item>Purge your closet and drawers. Go through your clothes and get rid of unfitting clothes, or clothes you don't like. Try it all on to make sure you don't get rid of something valuable!</item>
<item>totally trashed belong in the trash.</item>
<item>Straighten your closet and drawers. Fold clothes neatly and sort them by category. Socks and underthings go in one drawer, shirts in another, etc. Hang dresses and jackets neatly in your closet.</item></list>
<head>Get Organized for School</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Purchase a quality backpack. It should have plenty of space to store and tote your supplies. Make sure it is the right size for you. It's okay to splurge on this item to get a long-lasting backpack.
<list type="unordered"><item>A roller backpack is fine if your school permits it. <figure rend="Be Organized (Kids) Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Buy all the school supplies you need. Get or make a list of all the things you will need. If you were given a list, stick to it. If you're making your own, include the following:
<list type="unordered"><item>Pencils. If you use traditional pencils, have a personal pencil sharpener. If you use mechanical pencils, have spare leads. Colored pencils are also useful.</item>
<item>Highlighters. Have a couple of colors.</item>
<item>Pens. Black and blue are the standard colors, but feel free to get more if you so desire.</item>
<item>Notebooks. College ruled, one-subject notebooks are the norm.</item>
<item>Loose-leaf paper. You might not need a whole notebook for a class, so a stash of paper would be useful.</item>
<item>Scissors, a glue stick, and a ruler. You probably won't use these as often as you do the other supplies, but they will come in handy. You won't have to share with anyone if there aren't quite enough supplies to go around. <figure rend="Be Organized (Kids) Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Store unused items. If you don't need an item you bought, you can store it for use at a later time.
<list type="unordered"><item>You can keep a basket in a closet to hold these supplies.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Stay Organized at School</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Keep your supplies in one place. This can be your backpack, your desk, or your locker. Store writing utensils and other small items in your pencil case.</item>
<item>Also, don't let too many people borrow your stuff because chances are, you won't get it back.   <figure rend="Be Organized (Kids) Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep your desk clean. At school, people will not like it if your things are all over the floor, or spread out on your desk. Once you are done with a book, put it away. Only have the bare necessities on your desk.</item>
<item>Buy things that will help you to be more organized. Like binders, planners, a calendar, etc. These will help you be more organized wherever you are!</item>
<item>Use a planner. Planners are useful in many ways. Ask your parents about activities, and put them in your planner along with its time and date. Make sure you have the travel time included as well. If something starts at noon and it takes thirty minutes to get there, leave at 11:25 so you have some leeway.</item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If it helps, re-arrange your room to give you more space.</item>
<item>Have a specified area for doing homework/school tasks that is clear of distractions.</item>
<item>Do not consider your calendar/planner in a negative way. Some people think that the planner dictates your life. Consider it positively; as a means to keep you organized.</item>
<item>Ask your parents for help if you're not sure if you need something.</item>
<item>It's very important to put things away immediately after using them. This will drastically decrease the amount of disorder and cleaning you have to do.</item>
<item>Also ask your parents if you can't organize your bedroom by yourself.</item></list>
</text>
