<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc30" title="Play With a Pet" shortTile="play-pet" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-10-01" dateModified="2019-10-20" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Play_With_a_Pet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Play With a Pet</head>It's a very important deal to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Nice_to_Your_Pets">give your pets attention</ref> and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Keep_Your_Pets_Happy">love</ref>. And pets love to play! They will feel loved and satisfied after playing with you, and this is good for both of you, because the pet will also be tired enough to sleep for some hours. Before waking up and wanting to play again, of course!
<head>Steps</head>
<head><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Category:Dog_Toys_and_Play">Play with Dogs</ref></head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Hide the <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Healthy_Dog_Treats">treats</ref>. If you have a well-trained and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Category:Dog_Training">obedient dog</ref>, you could try to make him/her <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Teach_Your_Dog_to_Sit">sit</ref> and then hide some treats around in the room where you are. Then when you say "Go"! The dog will run around, trying to find all the treats! Remember to hide the treat a place your dog can reach. <figure rend="Play With a Pet Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hide 'n Seek. Remember the game you used to play when you was a kid? Maybe your kids play it, but it's not just for humans! Like the previous step, this requires an obedient and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Train_a_Dog">well-trained dog</ref>. Make the dog wait sitting down somewhere, facing a wall or better yet, a corner. Then you <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Category:Hiding_Games">hide</ref>! Be careful, sometimes the dog peeks! And <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Quiet">don't make too much noise</ref> hiding. Then <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Train_a_Dog_to_Come">call the dogs</ref> name and wait for the dog to find you! Note that this play works the best if you are alone with your dog at home, because other people can distract the dog. <figure rend="Play With a Pet Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Chase the sheet! This requires a garden and an old sheet. Find an old sheet that you don't use, and go out to your garden with your dog. Now, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Run">run around</ref> with the sheet behind you and watch your dog go crazy, trying to catch it! <figure rend="Play With a Pet Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>The moving red dot game. This requires a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Play_With_a_Laser_Pointer">laser pointer</ref>. Use the laser pointer to make your dog (or cat) go mad! Point it around on the floor, and at the walls and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Look_After_Your_Pet">watch your pet</ref> trying to get a hold of it! Don't point the laser at your pet's eye though, it can harm the dog. <figure rend="Play With a Pet Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Play_With_Cats">Play with Cats</ref></head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Cats love strings! Cut a piece of yarn or something similar and drag it around the floor or bed, and watch your cat go crazy after it! This is almost guaranteed a success, since all cats love strings! <figure rend="Play With a Pet Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Cats love boxes! Ever heard of <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2XID_W4neJo">Maru?</ref> Cats are in love with boxes and will most likely jump in them, because they seem so fun! Specially if there's a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Yogurt_and_Cheese_Cat_Treats">treat</ref> waiting in the box...  <figure rend="Play With a Pet Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>The hand under the blanket. This might leave some scratches! Have your hand under a blanket, and wiggle your fingers to make the blanket move. Your cat won't know it's you, and he/she will be acting mad, trying to catch the little "mouse" under the blanket! <figure rend="Play With a Pet Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Play_With_Your_Parakeet">Play with Birds</ref></head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Birds really appreciate paper. They like to shred it, and can spend hours with a piece of paper, making it into a thousand small pieces! Just remember to use plain white paper with no dyes, since this could be harmful for your pet. Also, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Help_a_Nesting_Bird">help the bird</ref> by having already cut the pieces of paper smaller, so that the bird can handle it. <figure rend="Play With a Pet Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Birds like feathers. It's a funny thing actually. You can save your birds shed feathers (Do not pluck them off yourself, that's mean!) and when you have a reasonable amount, tie them to the end of a cotton twine or similar, and then you can tie it to the roof of your <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Clean_a_Birdcage">birds cage</ref>, and watch your pet have fun with the new "friend"!  <figure rend="Play With a Pet Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Take_Care_of_Mice">Play with Rats and Mice</ref></head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Let your pet crawl into your pockets! Don't close the pocket though. Let the pocket be open and only do this if your clothes isn't tight at all. This is why this works best with sweatshirt pockets. The pet will crawl in and out the pocket, and crawl around you! <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_a_Gentle_Person">Be careful</ref> so that the rat/mouse doesn't fall off you! <figure rend="Play With a Pet Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Build_an_Obstacle_Course"> Make an obstacle course</ref>. You can use treats to navigate the <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Tame_a_Mouse">mouse</ref>/<ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Care_for_a_Pet_Rat">rat</ref> through your homemade obstacle course! Place the treats with about  of distance. <figure rend="Play With a Pet Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Under the cover! Place your pet under a piece of cloth or something similar, and watch him/her trying to find out! Do not use a heavy cover, though, and if you see your pet doesn't like it, or is taking too long to find out, then stop the play, before the pet gets mad or ill. <figure rend="Play With a Pet Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Play_With_Your_Rabbit">Play with Rabbits</ref></head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Place <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Category:Tricks_with_Objects">random objects</ref> on the floor! This includes small tunnels that your <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Category:Rabbits">rabbit</ref> can go through, some <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Homemade_Rabbit_Toys">newspaper for your rabbit</ref> to shred, some balls to play with and some treats. Of course, your rabbit will be most interested in the <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Rabbit_Treat">treats</ref>, but afterwards you will figure out what your <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Fun_Rabbit_Toy">rabbit enjoys playing with</ref>! <figure rend="Play With a Pet Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Peek a Boo. Take a piece of cloth and hold it over your rabbit. Then take off the cloth and<ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Water_Drop_Sound_With_Your_Mouth"> make a noise</ref> ("Boo!" Or "Whee!") and see if your rabbit enjoys it. Some rabbits get mad, and some just find it weird! <figure rend="Play With a Pet Step 14.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make homemade, improvised toys for your pets. Usually they like these more than the expensive, store-bought ones.</item>
<item>Encourage your pet to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Jazz_Up_Your_Everyday_Life">play everyday</ref> to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Keep_Your_Pets_Happy">keep them healthy and happy</ref>.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Sew_a_Catnip_Mouse">Catnip</ref> makes cats go crazy!</item>
<item>Some of the plays you can play with your rabbit/mouse, also goes with your rabbit and vice versa.</item>
<item>Some of the plays you can <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Have_Fun_with_Your_Dog_Outdoors">play with your dog</ref>, also goes with <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Category:Cats">your cat</ref> and vice versa.</item>
<item>Remember, if your pet seems tired or sick, try not to overdo it on the playing.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be careful so that you don't get bitten or scratched. If you do, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Treat_a_Wound">cleanse the wound</ref> with <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Your_Own_Soap">water and soap</ref>.</item>
<item>Be careful with <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Take_Care_of_Your_Pet">giving food to your pet</ref> right after playing. Some pets have sensitive stomachs and will <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Clean_Pet_Vomit_from_Carpet">throw up</ref>.</item>
<item>Provide <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Purify_Water">water for the animal</ref> after the play session, so that he/she stays hydrated.</item>
<item>Don't play with a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Care_for_a_Sick_Pet">sick pet</ref>, or with a pet that has just eaten or given birth recently.</item>
<item>Never use plastic bags to hide treats in.</item>
<item>It's dangerous to play wild games with small animals, like birds or mice. They have small hearts that can't take too much of the excitement.</item></list>
</text>
