<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc81" title="Get Alone Time Between You and Your Crush" shortTile="alone-time-between" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-12-01" dateModified="2018-12-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_Alone_Time_Between_You_and_Your_Crush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Alone Time Between You and Your Crush</head><p>If you want to start building a relationship with the boy/girl you are attracted to, spending time together without the company of other people is important. This article will show you how in 9 day steps.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Getting To Know Your Crush</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start with small talk. It's important to get to know your crush before you try to get them alone and start a relationship. If you see your crush in the halls or end up crossing paths one way or another, try to make small talk to show that you're interested in them, and that you care. Introduce yourself and ask how they are. Try making comments on the things around you, or your opinion on a class, assignment, or teacher. This opens up the conversation to your crush to express his or her own opinion, and start a discussion. If he/she doesn't get the message, you can simply ask them a question, or ask for an opinion.</item>
<item>Show you're interested in a friendship. Most good relationships started as friendships, so it's important to try to develop this with your crush. For example, if you are allowed to choose your own lab partner for biology, and this boy or girl happens to be in your class, then ask them to be partners. Stuff like this can be difficult at first, especially if you are shy or have a fear of being rejected, so it's good to prepare before you make your move. You can try requesting to sit at their lunch table, or ask if they would like to sit with you. If your crush accepts your offers, then refer to Step One to try to start a discussion. If you end up getting rejected, don't feel bad. Rejection doesn't simply mean the person doesn't like you, it could be for many reasons.</item>
<item>Invite them out with a group of friends. So you've been talking for a while, and getting to know them. Now, you can invite them to go out with you and a small group of friends. You can go to the mall, to a resturant, a party, or anywhere your group wants. If your crush accepts, this is a big step in your relationship. Your crush wants to get to know you more, and you can officially consider yourselves friends. Make sure you accomadate him or her as much as possible, keep them included, talk to them, and introduce them to your friends. In short, make sure that they both you and them have a good time!</item></list>
<head>Developing A Relationship</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Maintain your friendship. Continue to regularly invite them to hang out with you and your friends. You can ask for their number so you talk with them from home. Keep talking to them and including them. Help them out and show that you care.</item>
<item>Start to develop a relationship. Keep going out with them in a group, but single them out more. Drift away from the rest of your friends a bit. Ask them about more personal things than just their opinion on the weather. Ask them how their day is. Try to talk minimally about yourself. That only pushes people away. Be a good listener.</item>
<item>Start to get them alone. Go to a movie or resturant, and ask your crush if they would like to sit alone with you. This will most likely reveal whether they considers you a friend--or something more. If they say yes, that's great! Chances are, your crush probably likes you back. However, if their response is "no", that doesn't mean that they DON'T like you. Maybe they're just happier being friends, or they want to take things more slow.</item></list>
<head>Getting Them Alone</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Invite them somewhere without your friends. If they've been accepting your offers to sit alone together, apart from your friends, then they might just be ready for time totally alone with you. Not nessacarily a date, but some private time alone. Ask your crush where they would like to go, and take them there. You've successfully obtained alone time with your crush.</item>
<item>Make the most of your time together. Talk, joke, have fun! Be casual and sweet. Offer to pay for the bowling, movie, food, etc. Be a lady/gentleman. That means being polite, kind, and understanding, and acting appropriately. It dosn't mean you should act 'proper', per se, just like a nice, fun-loving person.</item>
<item>Revealing your feelings for them. You don't have to do this, but if you want to start a relationship with this person, there's no better time to do it then when you're officially alone with them! Pick a time when things are relatively quiet and calm. That means you shouldn't do it during the climax of an action movie. A great time would be when you two are eating or waiting for food at a resturant. Say this: "[insert crush name here], I really love hanging out with you. You're a great guy/girl. I think you're smart, funny, and handsome/pretty. If you would like to as well, I would love to be your girl/boyfriend/date." Give them some time to answer. If they reject, then say: "Well, in that case, I am so happy that we are friends." If they accept, then you are a very lucky person, and you now have a boy/girlfriend.</item></list>
</text>
