<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc33" title="Train Your Pet" shortTile="train-pet" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-02-12" dateModified="2016-11-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Train_Your_Pet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Train Your Pet</head><p>Can't train your pet? Are your pets going crazy? Keep on reading to learn to train your pet properly.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get your pet to trust you. He will only obey you if he trusts that you are doing the right thing. Treat him like any other person. Don't hypnotize him or sneak gross-tasting vitamins into his food. Keep working with him. <figure rend="Train Your Pet Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Train your pet to use the bathroom. Litter boxes, for example, work on cats. If you have something like a bunny, though, it can just go in its own habitat. Train your dog to go outside, not in the house. Find how your pet goes to the bathroom and train him. <figure rend="Train Your Pet Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Teach your pet tricks. Sit, stand, stay, sing, all the s words; they're all Simple. Find what tricks can be taught on each pet. "Sing" can't be taught to a rabbit as well as it can to a dog, and "Sleep" can't exactly be taught to a dog as well as it can to a cat. What tricks are appropriate?  Find them and then research to learn to teach it. <figure rend="Train Your Pet Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Show your pet how to act around strangers. Bring in strangers frequently, and teach your dog not to bark, your cat not to puke, or your frog not to jump out of its cage and kill itself. See? Reacting positively upon strangers is a hard trick to master, but don't give up! <figure rend="Train Your Pet Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Bring in a professional trainer to help train your pet. There are millions of trainers out there with pockets filled with treats. They know how to really teach your pet the right way, so if you feel like you can't do it, try the real pro. <figure rend="Train Your Pet Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Teach your pet to love by loving your pet. Show how much you care for them and they will soon care for you. It may take some time to achieve it, depending on the animal and it's background. <figure rend="Train Your Pet Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tell him orders and if he obeys them give him treats and if he does not, do not shout at him and do it again. <figure rend="Train Your Pet Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>No dog of any age understands all of the words in the English or any language that is spoken in your home, you have to teach them. But puppies, especially, have not learned to pick up on little cues from your voice or manners, so don't get frustrated or upset if your puppy is not responding as you would like them too. <figure rend="Train Your Pet Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>To train a puppy you have to be firm. Not to mean but firm and calm. Puppies are like us adults and children. What happens if you scream at a child, they get scared? And try to hide the evidence, if it happens again. Same with animals, patience is the key. <figure rend="Train Your Pet Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When you are house training your puppy, for example, and your puppy has an accident inside your house while you are not looking, grabbing your little dog and shoving its nose in the poop will not teach it not to poop indoors. Chances are your dog has already forgotten that it pooped, and all you are doing is making it afraid of the smell. Puppies that are improperly punished can grow up poorly trained and terrified of people and you. <figure rend="Train Your Pet Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>To train your dog when you see him or her make a mistake, quickly take him to the spot where it happened and have him next to you put a pad on it and tell him before you put the pad on the spot no that this is not good. Lay the pad on the floor and tell him yes this is good also have a treat ready for your pup, put it on the floor on the pad. So that next time he can picture it in his mind that he will get a treat next time if he pees on the pad. <figure rend="Train Your Pet Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Little by little as you get to know your puppy when he is about to use the restroom. As he is sniffing where to find a spot pick him or her up and take him out side. He or she has no choice but to use the restroom outside when your puppy has did its Businesses, quickly go to him or her kneel down and hold the treat in your hand and as your pup is coming to you oh don’t forget to call his or her name, let your pup sniff your hand and also reward your baby. That is some of a little way to train your pet the right way. <figure rend="Train Your Pet Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Buy your pet's favorite treats and fill your cabinets with them.</item>
<item>Try not to give up! Once your pet is trained you'll be happy that you didn't.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't let your pet bite or act inappropriate to you under any circumstances.  Even if they look cute, don't take so much pity on them.</item></list>
</text>
