<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc60" title="Ignore the Talk About the End of the World" shortTile="ignore-talk-end-world" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-01-03" dateModified="2016-05-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Ignore_the_Talk_About_the_End_of_the_World" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ignore the Talk About the End of the World</head>
<p>Think back to 2012. Remember all the talk about the impending End of the World, the Mayan calendar, Planet X, and all that? Conversations like that pop up every now and then, and you may not feel comfortable around them. Here are some suggestions for ignoring -- or at least calmly accommodating -- that kind of thinking. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Ignore_Someone">Ignore</ref> the Doomsday talk. Periodically it becomes popular to think about the end of the world. Conversations will occasionally break out in that direction. Probably your best course of action is either to try redirecting the talk to another topic or simply excusing yourself and escaping! Try to avoid people who like discussing that kind of thing. Do not read or watch Doomsday features in the media.  <figure rend="Avoid the Talk About the End of the World Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember history. False "prophets" emerge from time to time, people such as the late televangelist Harold Camping who publicly predicted that the Second Coming and the Apocalypse would begin on May 21, 2011 and be followed in due course by Judgment Day and the Rapture. That was only one of the more recent examples of such predictions. Your job, then, is simply to remember these past false alarms and greet future prophecies with some healthy skepticism.  <figure rend="Avoid the Talk About the End of the World Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stay calm when you hear such talk. Use your head while analyzing the rationale behind such predictions. Various online sources like to make a name for themselves by predicting Doomsday. So far none of them has ever proved even remotely accurate. Keep that in mind when the "scare talk" starts circulating next time. Paranoia feeds such sites.  <figure rend="Avoid the Talk About the End of the World Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Seek comfort from friends and family. Talk to people you trust to be level-headed in moments of public panic. Facing so-called Doomsday alone can be scary when lots of people are losing their heads. Offer emotional support to one another, and remind each other about past Doomsday predictions.  <figure rend="Avoid the Talk About the End of the World Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Read scientific journals and other knowledgeable sources. People who make a living studying astronomy, geology and history are good sources of trustworthy information regarding claims of impending apocalyptic disaster.  <figure rend="Be Spiritual Without Being Religious Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't pass along rumors and prophecies about looming apocalyptic events. Let them stop with you. Others may find such reports irritating and irrational if not strange or silly.</item>
<item>If someone passes along information to you about Planet Nibiru or Planet X (the alleged "extra" planet threatening our well-being), respond by doing some level-headed research. Start simply by reading Wikipedia's article on "planets beyond Neptune." Then read articles from NASA and Science and Scientific American magazines. Read these before you let the many apocalyptic websites scare you.</item>
<item>Use your head. You were born with common sense. Use that, too. Don't succumb to fear mongering. Wait until every intelligent person you know is scared to death about an impending Doomsday before becoming scared yourself. Be the last in that line.</item></list>
<head>Warning</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>False Prophets may have a financial goal in mind. Be very skeptical.</item>
<item>Don't pass along apocalyptic warnings. You'll end up looking silly and untrustworthy.</item>
<item>Beware of survival kits. Someone is just out to capitalize on your fears or paranoia.</item></list>
</text>
