<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc180" title="Be the Perfect Teenage Guy" shortTile="perfect-teenage-guy" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-05-25" dateModified="2019-03-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_the_Perfect_Teenage_Guy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be the Perfect Teenage Guy</head><p>There was obviously a reason why you ended up on this page. Do you just sit at home and watch TV while petting your 7 cats? Or are you overweight, and maybe a little lazy? Well, I'm glad that you came, because this is the page to get you off your butt and start to mold and shape yourself to be the person that you've always wanted to be. I know you want to be that stereotypical teen guy, with a body that turn heads, especially girls'. So go on; read up. There's nothing stopping you except yourself.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Getting in Shape</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start eating right. Just think about it: every time you pick up a McDonald's burger, you are putting chemicals in your mouth. Yes, they are most for preservation, but chemicals nonetheless. That can't be good for you body in any way, and you will need to cut that out of your diet if you are willing to follow this advice. <figure rend="Be the Perfect Teenage Guy Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Start eating whole grains. Be careful with how much white bread you eat. That's just as bad as eating Burger King's burger buns every time you make a sandwich.</item>
<item>Eat more fruits and veggies. Literally. There are too many people that don't even touch the stuff; no wonder our nation is obese. Having at least one fruit with every meal, and try to have a couple at breakfast. Same with veggies.</item>
<item>Try to become a vegetarian. Not for very long, and you don't even have to be that strict about it. Just try it for a week and see what happens. You might be surprised.</item></list></item>
<item>Start working out. You don't even have to go to a gym for this one. You can do work out exercises at home. Having a weight bench is a plus, though. Invest in some dumbbells, too.Your workout routine could include: <figure rend="Be the Perfect Teenage Guy Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>In the mornings:</item>
<item>80 jumping jacks</item>
<item>20 push ups</item>
<item>50 crunches</item>
<item>10 lunges (each leg)</item>
<item>20 squats</item>
<item>:45 second wall sit</item>
<item>Run 10 minutes.</item>
<item>At night:</item>
<item>50 crunches</item>
<item>10 dumbbell curls (each arm)</item>
<item>20 dumbbell raises</item></list></item>
<item>Run everyday. Not only does it help you in the long haul, girls will love it, too. Try to do it enough that a  run is just a "warmup". Also, drink water, water, WATER! To be properly hydrated, it is said you must drink 3 gatorade  bottles plus a cup of water per day. Try to drink more than that. <figure rend="Be the Perfect Teenage Guy Step 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Having the Clothes</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get some staples of a teen boy's wardrobe: <figure rend="Be the Perfect Teenage Guy Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Beanies</item>
<item>Skinny jeans</item>
<item>Chinos</item>
<item>Flannel</item>
<item>Plaid shirts</item>
<item>Tank tops</item>
<item>Van/Converse</item>
<item>Nike</item>
<item>Ray-bans</item></list></item>
<item>Show off your look. Once you have a nice body, you are allowed to show it off a little bit. There is nothing stopping you from wearing cool tank tops and a beanie. <figure rend="Be the Perfect Teenage Guy Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
