<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc155" title="Get On With Work" shortTile="get-on-with-work" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-03-06" dateModified="2018-08-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_On_With_Work" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get On With Work</head><p>Work is a very important thing - whether its for your career, school, university, or perhaps just general 'work'. But the important thing is that it needs to get done. It needs to be finished.
This may be a hard task to achieve - things can go wrong, you can lose your concentration, you can easily get bored, and easily become distracted. </p>
<p>This article shows you how to get on with work so you can complete it without being distracted or rushing it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know your time limit. How long do you have to finish it? It may be between an hour or a week. Depending on the time you have - you may want to consider timing yourself and aiming for a certain time to finish. <figure rend="Get On With Work Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Plan. Plan when you start and when you finish. Also, plan a break. Halfway through, make sure you have time to relax and remove yourself from the hard-work for a few minutes. Having a quick break will also refresh your memory and keep you from getting bored. <figure rend="Get On With Work Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Set up your working area. Find a suitable working area where you will not become distracted and nobody can interfere. Make sure you have plenty of working space and everything you need. Here is a rough guide of what you might need; depending on what you are studying, you may want to adjust the list to suit your needs. <figure rend="Get On With Work Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>A computer or laptop</item>
<item>A dictionary</item>
<item>A calculator</item>
<item>A pen</item>
<item>Sheet(s) of paper</item>
<item>A pencil</item>
<item>A ruler</item>
<item>A compass</item>
<item>A rubber</item></list></item>
<item>Make yourself comfortable. Sit down in a comfortable chair and make sure the temperature and atmosphere of the room is right for you. Open a window if you need fresh air, turn up the heating if you are cold, etc. This will make it much easier for you to settle into the atmosphere of working and you will probably find it less boring. <figure rend="Get On With Work Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have a glass of water with you, and a few light snacks. Place a glass of water far from your work (particularly computers) just in case you spill it, and a small plate of snacks. You may want to include the following: <figure rend="Get On With Work Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Fruit (grapes, a banana, etc.)</item>
<item>Biscuits</item>
<item>Chocolate (in small portions)</item></list></item>
<item>Don't focus too much on the snacks and try to focus most of your attention on the work you are doing. Try not to eat it all in one go - take a few bites and then leave the rest for later. <figure rend="Get On With Work Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take a quick break. Make sure you have enough time to refresh your brain and relax slightly, but not so much that you completely forget about the work and/or get carried away and not be bothered to start working again. About 15 - 20 minutes should be enough time. During your break, consider a mini snack and drink, and try not to over-work your brain. Just relax and watch T.V or perhaps have a little sleep. But remember to set the alarm! <figure rend="Get On With Work Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Listen to some music to settle yourself. The work will be much more enjoyable if you have some music in the background to keep you going. <figure rend="Get On With Work Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Bring your mobile to keep yourself alert. If texting a few friends every now and then will keep you happy - then do it. But don't engage in a non-stop texting session. Keep it short and don't text too much. It will take your mind off studying every now and then so you don't feel so bored. <figure rend="Get On With Work Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you are using a computer, have emails ready and a few other tabs open. Perhaps visit your favorite site? Every now and again, quickly check your emails or quickly read something from your favorite site - but don't spend ages and don't do it continuously. <figure rend="Get On With Work Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make it fun by organizing your work and making it neat. Complete it in different sections - not all in one go. After each section, take some time to take a look at it to check for any mistakes, and then go onto the next section. With an organised space, water and snacks, a few friendly text messages from friends, and music in the background, you'll probably handle it quite well. <figure rend="Get On With Work Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be proud of your work! Once you have finished, check it, and go to relax. If you have any other work to complete - have a quick break before going onto the next thing. You don't want to wear yourself out! <figure rend="Get On With Work Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Focus most of your attention on the work. Even though checking emails now and again, listening to soft music, and eating a few snacks every now and then may make your work easier to get on with, it is important to remember that you are there to do your work.</item>
<item>When you have finished, tidy up your work space. This will keep it organised and tidy for the next time you have to do work.</item>
<item>When texting and emailing friends, if you know you are going to get a fast reply, explain you are doing work. This will let the person who are emailing know not to send long, complicated messages and have long texting/emailing conversations.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't rush your work. Remember, you have plenty of time. Rushing your work will only make it look scruffy and untidy. Even if you aren't very good at making your work look presentable - try your best.</item>
<item>Don't over-work. Of course, try your hardest and get as much as possible completed, but when you come to stage where you really need a break - then take one.</item></list>
</text>
