<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc3" title="Have Swag As a Kid" shortTile="swag-kid" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-11-25" dateModified="2019-07-12" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have_Swag_As_a_Kid" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have Swag As a Kid</head><p>Are you a kid who wants to have swag? It is a simple process, luckily, as long as you believe that the only way to have swag is that described in this article. Read on from step one to have swag as kid according to the contributors to this article.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Wear colors that compliment each other, and you as well. Wear black and white, wear navy and cream, try any swag-ish colors together. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Play some sports. Football, rugby and basketball are swag sports. If you play sports, you might even meet some new friends! <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear a snap-back or beanie when you feel you'll have swag doing so. Wear a beanie when swimming or a snap-back in bed if you think that gives you swag. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Pick clothes with a pattern: plaid, striped or graphic shirts. Wear green/blue/grey camo pants and a shirt at any appropriate time. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get a matching snap-back every time you get new clothes. Make sure it has a sticker and don't take the sticker off but do take the price tag off. Get the snap-backs however you think gives you most swag. Buy them, steal them, borrow them or plead with your parents to get them to buy them for you. How you get them doesn't matter, just get a matching snap-back every you buy any new clothes, from a suit to a new pair of underpants. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Dress_Like_a_Hipster">Dress hipster</ref>. Wear brightly colored skinny jeans, but avoid yellow and pink skinny jeans. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear sneaker brands like Jordan, Adidas, Nike, and Reebok. If you can't afford those brands of shoes, get Above the Rim, Protégé, And1, South Pole, and Rocawear. You can't have swag without these brands, apparently. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hang out with friends constantly. Hang out with friends instead of studying, at bedtime, when out with your parents or visiting your gran, if you think it gives you swag. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't worry if you have no girlfriend. You do not have to have a girlfriend, but if you want one, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Yourself">be yourself</ref>! <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Play video games you like, ones such as NBA 2k/Madden or Call of Duty so you could have something to talk about with your friends. Playing video games gives you swag, as long as you don't play video games you do not like. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Practice good hygiene. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Brush_Your_Teeth">Brush your teeth</ref> everyday, and shower every night and/or morning. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Maintain good grades even if you want to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Cool">be cool</ref>. You won't have a good job if you don't have good grades, possibly. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Don't bully.</hi> It's not cool at all! Stand up for someone who is getting bullied, but <hi rend="italic">don't fight</hi>-- use a quiet, persuasive tone instead. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Workout a couple of days a week. Remember to give the exercising a rest at least three days each week. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get some cologne, but don't spray too much. Use it on you body, or spray it on anything else that you think spraying with cologne will give you swag. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Crack some <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Tell_a_Joke">jokes</ref> with your friends. Don't talk about other people, though, because it might come back and haunt you. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't sag. Just show the elastic band, though, if you want to sag. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get an edge up with your haircut. Add a Nike sign on the side of your head for style if you want. <figure rend="Have Swag As a Kid Step 18.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
