<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc102" title="Live in the Friendzone" shortTile="live-friendzone" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-09-19" dateModified="2016-11-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Live_in_the_Friendzone" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Live in the Friendzone</head><p>So you've decided that you just can't live without the person who won't return your romantic advances, but still wants to be friends with you nonetheless.  Here's how to maintain the friendship, while also maintaining your sanity.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>The Perry Method</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>First, take your ego and cremate it.  You won't be needing it where you're going.  The ashes of your cremated ego will form the bed of an emotional garden, from which grows your new normal.</item>
<item>Don't wait for the person you desire to change their mind about you.  Normally, giving up all hope is a bad thing.  But in this case it is the single most helpful thing you can do.  Accept the fact that people are intitled to their own feelings and that these feelings are legitimate.</item>
<item>Create emotional (and perhaps even physical) distance from this person.  Have a discussion with your friend and explain that you need some time to compose yourself emotionally.  Slowly re-introduce this person back into your life as the feelings of longing subside.</item>
<item>No more physical contact.  Sorry, but this one is a must.  Short hugs, handshakes, fist bumps, and high fives are all acceptable.  But if you two used to cuddle, snuggle, or anything of that sort it has to stop.  This kind of physical contact creates an emotional bond and can set you spirling into a relapse.</item>
<item>When you decide to start re-introducing this person back into your life, avoid hanging out in a one-on-one setting.  You are less likely to get emotional in front of several people.</item>
<item>Spend time with other friends.  They can be a source of relief and can help distract you from "you know who."</item>
<item>When you're alone, ease you mind by engaging in healthy activities such as physical exercise/sports, light reading, writing poetry, or singing.</item>
<item>Finally, now that you've deconstructed your feelings and rebuilt them to suit your needs, you can begin your new life as the "friend" without feeling like someone is doing the Mexican Hat Dance on your heart.</item></list>
<head>The Hard Way</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a significant other of your own.  Of course, this is easier said than done, but it is an extremely effective way of redirecting your romantic energies.  Since your romantic needs are being met, only feelings of friendship remain.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not compromise your own feelings just to please someone else.  If you find that you cannot change the way you feel for a person, end contact and move on.  Although this is not ideal, the pain of leaving is far less severe than the perpetual agony of being around a person who you will always have unrequited romantic feelings for.</item>
<item>While it is important to let go of the hope of the other person changing the way they feel about you, this does not apply if the other persons feelings actually do happen to change.  If the person you have romantic feelings for starts to develop romantic feelings in return, don't be stupid.  That is a call you will have to make based on the circumstances. There is a difference between holding out false hope, and accepting that feelings can change.  If it happens it happens, but don't drive yourself insane waiting for something that may never come to pass.</item>
<item>If using the "Hard Way" method, do not treat your new significant other as a replacement or "stand-in."  Love them for who they are in their own right. Also, if romantic feelings do begin to redevelop for the original love interest, cut off all contact with that person or end the relationship you are in.  You owe it to your significant other to be honest.  Anything less is "emotional cheating" and can be even more damaging than cheating in a physical way.</item></list>
</text>
