<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc138" title="Get to Lord Howe Island" shortTile="lord-howe-island" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-12-18" dateModified="2019-07-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_to_Lord_Howe_Island" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get to Lord Howe Island</head><p>Lord Howe Island is a popular year-round tourist destination and stopover spot for yachts sailing the Tasman Sea. Fly to the beautiful UNESCO World Heritage island on small propeller planes from the Australian mainland, or sail in on your own private yacht or sailboat. Keep in mind that there are only a limited number of tourists allowed on the island at any given time, so make sure to make all your travel and accommodation reservations well in advance!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Flying to Lord Howe Island</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Book a flight from Sydney, Brisbane, or Port Macquarie, Australia. Flights depart from Sydney daily, Brisbane on weekends, and Port Macquarie seasonally from February to June and September to December. Qantas is the only airline that currently flies to Lord Howe Island, so you will have to fly on this airline. <figure rend="Get to Lord Howe Island Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The flights to Lord Howe Island from the Australian mainland are less than 2 hours. They average about 1 hour and 50 minutes.</item>
<item>The cost of a round-trip flight from Sydney to Lord Howe Island ranges from about $650 USD to $1150 USD depending on how far you book it in advance.</item>
<item>There are connecting flights with Qantas from many major Australian cities.</item>
<item>If you are booking a flight internationally, it is best to book a flight with Qantas as part of your international flight reservations.</item>
<item>Book your flight to the island directly through Qantas, with a travel agent, or through a trustworthy online booking service.</item></list></item>
<item>Arrange for your accommodations before or at the same time you book your flight. There is a tourist bed limit on Lord Howe Island of 400. It’s important to book your accommodations at the same time as your flight to make sure you have a place to stay. <figure rend="Get to Lord Howe Island Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are 18 lodges, guest houses, and rental apartments that make up the 400 tourist beds available on Lord Howe Island.</item></list></item>
<item>Arrive for your flight on time with your boarding pass and identification. Follow your airline confirmation’s instructions to check in and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_Your_Boarding_Pass_at_the_Airport">get your boarding pass</ref>. Bring your passport if you are traveling internationally. Australian citizens do not need to bring a passport. <figure rend="Get to Lord Howe Island Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you can choose your seat, try to sit on the right side of the plane for the best panoramic views of the island as you arrive.</item></list></item>
<item>Bring up to  of checked bags and  of carry-on items. The flights to Lord Howe Island have strict baggage weight limits, so make sure that your baggage does not exceed these. This also applies to passengers connecting from overseas flights. <figure rend="Get to Lord Howe Island Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your baggage exceeds the weight limits, Qantas will try to put your excess baggage on another flight, but there are no guarantees that it will arrive the same day.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Arriving by Boat</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Contact the Lord Howe Island Board to book a public mooring spot. Visit the Lord Howe Island Board’s website at <ref target="https://www.lhib.nsw.gov.au/">https://www.lhib.nsw.gov.au/</ref> and fill out a mooring application. The LHIB will send you an approval by email or fax to present to the Port Operations Manager when you arrive at the island. <figure rend="Get to Lord Howe Island Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The LHIB will assign you 1 of 2 types of public mooring systems based on your vessel type. There are 16 total public moorings in the Lord Howe Island lagoon.</item>
<item>You can pay all fees by credit card at the time of booking. The fees are set by the LHIB and may vary from time to time. The fee for mooring is about $46 USD per night.</item></list></item>
<item>Take a private yacht or sailboat to the island. There are currently no commercial passenger boats that go to Lord Howe Island. The only way to arrive is on your own private boat. <figure rend="Get to Lord Howe Island Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you don’t have a private boat to take to the island, your only other option is to fly.</item></list></item>
<item>Sail into the lagoon to your mooring spot and take a dinghy to shore. Attach your boat to the assigned public mooring and use a dinghy to get the rest of the way to shore. Pull your dinghy up on the beach or up the boat ramp. <figure rend="Get to Lord Howe Island Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Public moorings are located approximately  from shore.</item>
<item>No dinghies or outboard motor boats are available for hire, so you will need your own dinghy to get to shore.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Making the Most of Your Trip</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Choose whether to visit during high or low season. The most popular time to visit the island is from September to June. July and August are the wettest months on Lord Howe Island. <figure rend="Get to Lord Howe Island Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Even during the drier times of the year, it can rain at any time on the island. Pack accordingly to prepare for sudden changes in weather.</item>
<item>There are still plenty of sunny days and activities during the low season. You will likely have more options for accommodation if you book during this time.</item></list></item>
<item>Rent a bike or walk around the island. There are very view cars on the island and it is easy to get everywhere on foot or by bicycle. There is no need to rent a car as you will be able to bike the entire length of the island in about 20 minutes. <figure rend="Get to Lord Howe Island Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The few cars on the island have to obey a speed limit of  per hour.</item></list></item>
<item>Visit Lord Howe Marine Park to go snorkeling or scuba diving. The coral reefs that surround the island are home to a large variety of fish, plants, and animals, some of which you won’t find anywhere else in the world! Book a snorkel or scuba tour with an agency in town that will take you to locations where you are guaranteed to swim with colorful fish. <figure rend="Get to Lord Howe Island Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If snorkeling and scuba diving don't interest you, you can also take a tour out into the waters surrounding the island on a glass-bottomed boat to see the fish.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
