<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc25" title="Get Your Pet to Like You" shortTile="get-your-pet-to-like" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-10-15" dateModified="2017-11-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_Your_Pet_to_Like_You" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get Your Pet to Like You</head><p>We all love our pets, but the question is: "Do they like you?"
Getting them to like you takes some work, but in the end, it'll all be worth it</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Play with them. If it's a cat, use yarn or string, just make sure they don't eat it. You can also use store bought toys. If it's a dog, the best way to play with them is taking them outside to play ball every 30-45 minutes for about 5 or more minutes. If your pet doesn't like to play, just leave toys around for them to play with when they feel like it.</item>
<item>Make sure the area you let them in (if it's not your whole house) is comfortable for your pet. This lets them be in a nice environment that they can easily enjoy without being bothered or disrupted. If you have kids, don't let them crawl or smother your pet. You want them to be comfortable in your home, rather than afraid of what's out of their comfortable area.</item>
<item>Always make sure they get their alone time. Especially for cats, all pets want to be alone sometimes. Make sure you're not smothering them and trapping them under blankets or in your bed, couch, chair, etc. If they wanted to be with you, they would either come or when you go towards them, they most likely won't run away, depending on the way you approach them.</item>
<item>Love your pet! Most people think that cats will scratch you if you start petting them, but most times it's because they might be startled or because they didn't like the way you approached them. If you have a cat, you know it trusts you if it either shows you it's belly or makes full eye contact with you. If you guys are making eye contact and the cat blinks very slowly, this is a sign that it loves you. If a dog goes crazy when you get home or makes eye contact with you, those are also signs that it trusts or respects you.</item>
<item>Train them appropriately. It takes time for a dog to be trained, so don't get mad and pass judgment too quickly. Start training them tricks when they're young, so they will know it for longer. Make sure though that you feed it treats or praise your dog when they do something good, or say "No!" when they're being bad. If you want to train a cat, a way to do that is by using something called a clicker, but it's a lot more difficult to train a cat.</item>
<item>Pay attention to your pet's body language. This is very important because you'll know if your pet is enjoying what's happening or if it's annoying. If your cat is hissing, growling, or meowing uncontrollably, it's telling you to back off. A tail of a cat that is flickering back and forth very quickly means it could be irritated, or if its ears are all the way back, it's irritated. If your dog is being punished for nothing, it will become annoyed by not doing that thing you punished it for. Make sure to watch out for your pet's body language at all times.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Feed your pet regularly. If you feel you're overfeeding your pet, don't always give it food, maybe once in the morning and at night</item>
<item>If your pet wants to be alone, LEAVE IT ALONE. Clearly, it doesn't feel like being a pet, so leave it alone and if it wants to be with you, it will come to you</item>
<item>If you accidentally hurt or step on your pet (it happens), and it bites you back or something, don't get mad at it. It's only using its self-defense, so maybe a small "No!" or nothing would be best.</item>
<item>Don't spend every minute with your pet. If you do, both you and your pet will get bored of each other, and when your pets want to play with you sometimes, you might not want to.</item>
<item>Be aware of what your pet is doing. If you're watching TV, your pet could be doing anything. It's a good idea to check on your pets ever 30 minutes or so.</item>
<item>Be aware of the litter box or taking your dog out to go to the bathroom. Make sure to clean litter boxes every day if you have more than 1 cat or every other day, and take your dog out 10 minutes after they eat and every 30 minutes otherwise.</item></list>
</text>
