<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc63" title="Not Be Affected by Your Friends Insulting Your Views on Religion" shortTile="affected-friends" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-09-12" dateModified="2016-01-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Not_Be_Affected_by_Your_Friends_Insulting_Your_Views_on_Religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Not Be Affected by Your Friends Insulting Your Views on Religion</head><p>If your so called friends tease you over your beliefs you have a few choices. You can ignore them, get new friends or just not let it affect you. Other people who are not your friends may also 'have a pop at' or begin 'dissing' your views on religion. You can, with the aid of this article, not be affected by this ignorant and bigoted behaviour. Read on from step one below for how.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Remember, different strokes for different folks. Not everyone has the same views on everything. You may look at your religion as pure and loving, but to others it may have some faults. Be more tolerant than those that are insulting your views. <figure rend="Not Be Affected by Your Friends Insulting Your Views on Religion Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't let their taunts affect you. Deep down, it's what you believe that matters, not how they see your beliefs. Stand by your beliefs in your own mind. You have your reasons for believing what you believe. They probably don't have a good reason for insulting your religious beliefs. They are probably doing it through ignorance or fear. You can be unaffected by the insults because you are completely devoted to your beliefs and your faith is unshakable. They may insult your beliefs because they have no strong faith of their own to hold onto. You should pity those that taunt you.br&gt; <figure rend="Not Be Affected by Your Friends Insulting Your Views on Religion Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Debate, but do it rationally. You can defend your views, but do it without resorting to emotional attacks or defensiveness. You will get nowhere by shouting or being melodramatic. Explain that your religion gives you hope and is part of your way of life, and ask that they respect your position. Everyone is entitled to belief what they wish in enlightened society. They should respect your beliefs as they expect their beliefs to be respected. <figure rend="Not Be Affected by Your Friends Insulting Your Views on Religion Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stick up for yourself. Don't take a "holier than thou" attitude or be condescending, but realize you have a right to believe as you will. Don't apologize for your faith. On the flip side, they are entitled to think as they will, and you should not retaliate by attacking them. <figure rend="Not Be Affected by Your Friends Insulting Your Views on Religion Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Strengthen your faith. Read religious texts, pray, or talk to local religious leaders. Remember why you believe what you do, and the feelings and help it gives you in life. A stronger tree of belief stands up better against the winds of insult. <figure rend="Not Be Affected by Your Friends Insulting Your Views on Religion Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get involved with your religious community. From participating in events with like-minded individuals, you can build your faith and find others who share your beliefs. <figure rend="Not Be Affected by Your Friends Insulting Your Views on Religion Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stand strong. In the end, don't bow yourself to the insults. Persevere. If you struggle standing alone, find a parent, friend, or religious leader to help you, or ask your God for strength. <figure rend="Not Be Affected by Your Friends Insulting Your Views on Religion Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep an open mind, opinions are different with each thinking mind.</item></list>
</text>
