<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc192" title="Be the Coolest Girl in Your Class" shortTile="coolest-girl-class" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-05-17" dateModified="2019-03-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_the_Coolest_Girl_in_Your_Class" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be the Coolest Girl in Your Class</head><p>You may have looked around in your class, and you may have noticed the other girls chatting away, having a blast. You may have noticed that they wear really nice clothes, take extreme amounts of caution when doing their hair, and just really friendly to everyone around them. You may have asked yourself, "<hi rend="italic">How do I become the coolest girl in my class?"</hi></p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Embrace your confidence. Some girls assume that it's "cool" or "trendy" to be insecure, and spend entire conversations moaning about their perceived flaws. Those people, however, tend to be considered attention seekers and are shunned from popular social circles. If you have a good self-esteem, it will naturally draw people to you and cause them to think highly of you as well.  <figure rend="Be a Success in Middle School Step 29.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>There's a difference between confident and conceited. "I'm proud of how well I did on the test" is modest enough, but "I'm the smartest girl in the whole grade" will be interpreted as arrogant and weird.</item></list></item>
<item>Be outgoing -- start conversations, don't wait for others to make the first move. Cool and popular girls embody a sassy, friendly and talkative personality that makes them adored by the rest of the student body. It would be rather awkward if they sat around and waited for a possible friend to approach them. Instead try to be bold: who knows, the person next to you might be delighted that you made the choice to talk to them.  <figure rend="Be a Success in Middle School Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't participate in mindless gossip or bullying. It's virtually a friend-repellent, even though high school movies preach otherwise: if somebody constantly gossiped about those around them, wouldn't you assume they talk about you the exact same way? There are very few people who'd eagerly accept a cruel, disloyal person into their clique.  <figure rend="Be a Success in Middle School Step 21.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This doesn't mean you have to be a passive good-girl who's devoid of of any semblance of personality. Staying a good person doesn't mean - and will never mean - being boring.</item></list></item>
<item>Compliment your friends. If somebody's self-esteem goes through the roof during a conversation with you, they're going to be eager for another one soon. An overwhelming amount of girls (and boys) around this age are painfully insecure - if you encourage their confidence while showing them yours, it's going to be a refreshing break from what they're exposed to on the daily.  <figure rend="Be a Success in Middle School Step 18.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't pass on a compliment that isn't one hundred percent genuine -- if they can tell, you will come across as awkward and fake.</item></list></item>
<item>Discover your sense of humour. If she wants her potential friends to stay engaged, it's important for a cool girl to develop a unique way to make them laugh. Whether you're naturally sarcastic or more of a slapstick gal, figure out what amuses you and work on a couple of jokes in order to broadcast it to others.  <figure rend="Be a Success in Middle School Step 20.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Chances are, you're probably funny. The trick is in making people see it.</item></list></item>
<item>Research fashion styles that you like. Once you've found one, stick to it. If you're leaning towards the traditional "popular girl" image, draw heavily from preppy and girly-girl subcultures. However, if you're not too fond of pastels and frilly skirts, don't be discouraged - whether she's a tomboy or a rebel or sort of punk, a cool girl can dress however she pleases as long as she has the right attitude.  <figure rend="Be a Success in Middle School Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be careful when it comes to romance. Rushing into a relationship merely for it's own sake is unhealthy and will probably make you look desperate. If you're content in all other areas of your life - school, friends, family, hobbies - and you're excited towards the prospect of having a partner, go ahead and ask somebody out. Even if they seem <hi rend="italic">way</hi> out of your league, remember that it's better to shoot and miss than to never bother playing at all.  <figure rend="Be a Success in Middle School Step 19.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The person you're dating doesn't have to be a guy. Cool girls can be gay or bisexual, too.</item></list></item>
<item>Don't compromise who you are. This is, above all, the essence of a cool girl - being unapologetic about the eclectic, unique individual you are and standing out from the crowd. If you sacrifice your true personality in pursuit of social status and a couple of friends, you'll be another forgettable face in the eyes of those who are "cool" regardless. Figure out who you are and don't let that person go.  <figure rend="Be a Success in Middle School Step 4 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't change yourself because of peer pressure.</item>
<item>Don't be a teacher's pet, but do try to be in the top set in school.</item>
<item>Learn hard and try your best in every lesson</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you do not change <hi rend="italic">everything</hi> about yourself, or your friends might think you are weird.</item>
<item>Do not wear too much makeup. Some people turn orange!</item></list>
</text>
