<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc37" title="Use Law of Attraction and the Secret Movie Teachings" shortTile="use-law-attraction" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-17" dateModified="2019-09-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Use_Law_of_Attraction_and_the_Secret_Movie_Teachings" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Use Law of Attraction and the Secret Movie Teachings</head><p>Ever since the launching of <hi rend="italic">The Secret</hi> movie and DVD back in March 2006, the movie and the book of that name by Rhonda Byrne have taken the world by storm. There are many misconceptions about the Law of Attraction and this wiki is an attempt to clear up the confusion. The biggest misunderstanding is that most people think it's just being positive and that being anything other than positive negatively affects your chances at creating what you want in your life. However, the Law of Attraction is based on vibrations and even though how we think affects are vibrations, there is quite a bit more to it. It's very similar to how a tuning fork works, in that when one fork is struck, it will cause others with that same frequency nearby to vibrate; we, as humans, also have magnetic frequencies that attract whatever we are vibrating.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pay attention to how you feel. If you are not feeling good, ponder what it is you are thinking that is causing you to feel bad. Work that Subject over in your mind until you have a new thought that raises your vibration. Your feelings are a built-in barometer for how you are vibrating. <figure rend="Use Law of Attraction and the Secret Movie Teachings Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Challenge your ingrained beliefs. If you have a pattern of thinking the same way about a particular subject matter—money, health, relationships—you will find that you have ingrained beliefs that are coming up whenever that subject matter comes to mind. Those beliefs can be empowering or they can be dis-empowering ones. Taking a look at your existing circumstances gives you a glimpse as to your overall vibration because whatever you are living - is a reflection of that. That is a good place to start in re-thinking your beliefs. <figure rend="Use Law of Attraction and the Secret Movie Teachings Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Let everyone off the hook. Counting on others to behave a certain way in order for you to be happy is a trap. Just like you cannot jump through all the various hoops required in order to make the people close to you happy—the same thing applies to you being able to accommodate all those demands. Take charge of your life and understand that you can be happy no matter what others are doing. It just takes a different perspective. Happier people attract more circumstances to be happy about. <figure rend="Use Law of Attraction and the Secret Movie Teachings Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Let yourself off the hook. Stop fretting over all the perceived mistakes you have made. The other people involved in those situations are most likely not even still thinking about what happened. And if they are, it is because they have not been willing to give up that incident in favor of being happy now. Whatever happened, happened. Get over it. Today is a new day with lots of opportunities to do things differently based on what you learned about your preferences. <figure rend="Use Law of Attraction and the Secret Movie Teachings Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Love. If you can feel absolute love for everything and everyone around you, you will be in complete and utter harmony with the Universe. Every good thing will come to you! <figure rend="Use Law of Attraction and the Secret Movie Teachings Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Believe you deserve a piece of the money cycle. One of the things that people seem to really want the most is money. Money is fantastic, and there is plenty of it. All you have to do is believe that you have all the money you want/need. Write tremendous, million-dollar checks or use Monopoly money to pretend you have all of this money. When you can feel good and secure about money, that's when the magic of wealth begins. Oh, and always feel grateful for any amount of money. Gratitude attracts support. <figure rend="Use Law of Attraction and the Secret Movie Teachings Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Now is the time to change. Your existing circumstances show who you were, not who you are. The frequency you are on now affects the person you will be, so make sure you feel good!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The more you focus on negative emotions, the worse you will feel and the more negative circumstances you will attract. Focus on someone/something you truly care about or love, and then you'll automatically feel good if you think about it for a minute.</item>
<item>This is like building a new muscle. And just like exercising a muscle on your body—it is cumulative. You didn't get to where you are in one day and you won't change things around in one day.</item></list>
</text>
