<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc55" title="Develop a Well Formed Conscience (Christianity)" shortTile="develop-well-formed" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-10-23" dateModified="2016-08-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Develop_a_Well_Formed_Conscience_%28Christianity%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Develop a Well Formed Conscience (Christianity)</head><p>A conscience is not simply an inner voice, unlike the idea of an angel and a devil perched on our shoulders. A conscience is something that we must work on over time by forming, informing, and following it. A popular method to form a conscience utilizes the 'SEER' method, which stands for "Study, Elect, Execute and Review." This article will describe the steps of the SEER method, as well as a real-world example of how it can be used in daily life.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Study the conscience. The Bible and the Catechism of the Catholic Church (CCC) are both excellent resources to gather information about the moral content of an action that may be executed. These resources can remind one of the principles of morality. Consider the best ways to apply moral rules. If one is unsure about the moral quality of an action, it is recommended to ask someone of great moral wisdom, such as a wise family member, or even a member of the Clergy, for guidance. <figure rend="Develop a Well Formed Conscience (Christianity) Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember that God made us great. Think about the action that is about to be done. Is it in line with how we, gifted by God, ought to act? This step is when the actual decision (to act or not to act) comes in to play. If the action is of a lesser good or greater evil, one should not perform it. Prayer can play a big role in whether or not we should act. <figure rend="Develop a Well Formed Conscience (Christianity) Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Execute: If our conscience tells us that our action is right, after the first two steps, then we should act. Remember that according to Pope John Paul II, "[Moral acts] express and determine the goodness or evil of the individual who performs them." This means we are responsible for our actions! <figure rend="Develop a Well Formed Conscience (Christianity) Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Evaluate the action that was performed. Was it the best action? Will this decision prosper me? Is this something God would consider right?  <figure rend="Develop a Well Formed Conscience (Christianity) Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Repeat: We have an ongoing obligation to form, inform, and follow our conscience. The SEER method can assist us in this. Thus, the SEER method is cyclic, starting with our first moral action, and terminating when we pass away. <figure rend="Develop a Well Formed Conscience (Christianity) Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Real World Example</head>
<p>Imagine a thirteen year old boy asks his seventeen year old relative for advice. The thirteen year old asks his relative about underage drinking. </p>
<list type="unordered"><item>"Hey, I figured out where the key is hidden to my dad's liquor cabinet! I am really interested in drinking some of his Tequila, but I am not sure. Every time I am about to open it, I get this weird feeling. I am just not sure if it is right," says the young boy.</item>
<item>Mike, his older relative responds to him, "Well, let's <hi rend="italic">study</hi> the action. Do you think it is sinful?" The boy has a puzzled look on his face.</item></list>
<p>Mike elaborates,"Are there any of the Ten Commandments that would prohibit you doing that?"</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>The young boy responds, "Well, I guess it is sorta stealing."</item>
<item>"Anything Else?" Mike asks.</item>
<item>"I guess I wouldn't be honoring my mother and father."</item>
<item>"And if your dad notices that his Tequila is gone..."</item>
<item>"I guess then I would have to lie to him. That is three Commandments I would break!"</item>
<item>Mike, proud of his younger relative, responds, "God made you amazing. Do you think that God would want you stealing liquor, or do you think that is less than what He expects?"</item>
<item>"How do I figure that out?"</item></list>
<p>Mike suggests that they pray together.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>After the prayer, the boy remarks, "I don't think God wants me to do that, so I am not going to."</item>
<item>Mike says to the boy, "I am proud of you for your decision. I think you are doing the right thing by not stealing any. Do you think you are doing the right thing?"</item></list>
<p>The boy shakes his head in agreement.</p>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember to consult the Bible, the CCC, or a wise friend if you need advice.</item>
<item>Prayer is a good way to get help from God in making your choice.</item>
<item>Remember your ongoing obligation!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember that a majority opinion doesn't make something right!</item>
<item>A conscience is not an inner voice, or a feeling.</item></list>
</text>
