<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc125" title="Understanding Relationships Better (S.M.B)" shortTile="understanding-relationships" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-01-21" dateModified="2017-01-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Understanding_Relationships_Better_%28S.M.B%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Understanding Relationships Better (S.M.B)</head><p>Understand the opposite sex</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Know what source you are.There are two source of  influence in life: Spirit and Mind.They are known as Male and Female</item>
<item><figure rend="Mi 1.png"></figure>Know the functions of your source of influence.This is not to say men are spirit and female are mind, it's a direct identical description of the two taken from their human nature.If you are a Female meaning your source of influence comes from the source Mind, to understand yourself better look at how your own mind functions, whats needed for the mind to do something. your question would be how do I convince myself to do something.The mind is the most powerful organ ever on earth that controls and able to multitask but lacks domination meaning it only knows and understand what gets expose too it just like women, the amount of effort that takes place for the mind to do something is the same amount of effort it takes for you women to fall for something.If you are a Male your source of influence is Spirit. Meaning you grow from what you get in this case there are only two influences which are namely good and bad there is no ying yang the one you get fed the most you become that and when one is fully grown it becomes very difficult to change it's behavior unlike the mind that stores info to understand and convince itself, no time to understand and store info for the spirit.The spirit strength and weakness is temptation. No convincing needed there for example. Beautiful long legs killer body babe walks past. you know what happens after that.</item>
<item><figure rend="Ro.jpeg"></figure>Know your role for every healthy relationship the effort is shared according to ones role. If you are in a relationship and you want to imitate the other role meaning playing from the source you are not there will always be conflicts. You cannot be a male but  want to act like the female in your relationship for example, you what your partner to convince you all the time to do something like wise the female you cannot take your partners place by wanting to be the one who dominates.</item>
<item>How to keep a healthy relationship. Love your role and be good at it, never try to over power your partner will your strength but work together because if you are a female remember with the spirit what you feed it, it will grow from it and become it, it is not like you that stores and reminds.</item>
<item>Do not commit yourself in a relationship before you know who you are. Know what type of a person you are; for example, flashy or down to earth, then search for your soul mate.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Learn who you are first</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't ever try and change what is</item></list>
</text>
