<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc35" title="Keep a Pet" shortTile="keep-pet" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-02-17" dateModified="2019-01-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Keep_a_Pet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Keep a Pet</head><p>All humans have the need to nurture. And it is to curb this desire that we keep pets. This article will tell you about how you can give your pet and yourself a friendly relation and that though a deep one.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Remember that they are living creatures. You must always keep in mind that your pet has feelings. Just like humans, they want freedom, good food, entertainment and may have acute feelings like sorrow, happiness etc. A pet may not be a human but its feelings and needs are very similar. They may not be able to express their feelings to us but they feel just like us and they enjoy and suffer, just like humans. <figure rend="Keep a Pet Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>For small animals: Don't make them live in a small cage; choose a big cage or make them one! <figure rend="Keep a Pet Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Treat them like your family. It is every pet owner's duty and responsibility to see that they don't feel as if they are different or that they suffer from loneliness or sorrow. You must take and treat them as a family member, loving and caring for them as if it was your own family member. <figure rend="Keep a Pet Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Understand them. Read and learn about your pet. This way you will be able to understand his or her needs. Try to understand his or her body language. Spending more time with him or her will strengthen your relationship and allow you to understand your pet better. A pet who is comfortable in new surroundings will not be active and may be defensive/aggressive. These pets are ideal for families or the elderly. On the other hand, curious and active personalities are not submissive and are ideal for families without children below 10 years old. <figure rend="Keep a Pet Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take responsibility of your pet and its stuff, rather than hiring a person to look after them. Unless your pet will be alone for a long period of time, examples would be for an entire day or a few days at length. <figure rend="Keep a Pet Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Give them freedom. Allow your pet to enjoy his or her freedom. Don't disturb his or her sleep and try not to leave them in a closed atmosphere (except fish) <figure rend="Keep a Pet Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Let them do what they want. Allow your pet to come in contact that is harmful, try not to disturb  him or her as they might have a reason but are unable to express it. <figure rend="Keep a Pet Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never neglect your pet or leave it alone for an extended period of time.</item>
<item>It's preferable not to leave your pet alone for more than 6 hours at a stretch.</item>
<item>If you have fish try to provide them with a big aquarium. Provide it the company of other fish (that are suitable to be together), but don't overcrowd the tank.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't anger your pet.</item>
<item>Don't disturb it when its depressed or wants its own space.</item></list>
</text>
