<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc109" title="Know if She Really Loves You" shortTile="know-really-loves" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-04-17" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Know_if_She_Really_Loves_You" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Know if She Really Loves You</head><p>Love is always there. We men tend to be more committed as often and get hurt when things don't turn out to be what we assume them to be. It is about a sure feeling in your partner. It is always not about them cheating on you, but rather its about their messed up, entangled, jumbled feelings that don't fit in a particular frame. So here are some tips to know if SHE really loves you and is not confused:</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Jealousy, Interest and Caring</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Talk about other girls, intentionally. Look if she gets angry at you talking about them. She's got to be posessive of you, dude! And if she is, it means her interest is maintained in you. And yeah, dumb as it may seem, look if she does have some genuine interest in one of your friends or somebody, and if she despises that interest immidiately, that's a good sign. Remember my friend, feelings are fluids. They can't be locked. Yeah, control is something we can. That's the time you actually gotta hold her tight.</item>
<item>A relationship is all about caring for each other. You're a moron if only and only sex matters to you; or her. See if she frequently asks you about your health, or like  whether you had your meals, if you're good in your hread, if you are being treated well at home, what's making you sad. She should your another 'YOURSELF'.</item></list>
<head>Continuity</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Remember, continuity is the key to keeping on a good relationship. If a girl is not that into you, she won't mind keeping you off for a while. You know it from your texts, calls, seeing her often.</item></list>
<head>Does she miss you?</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Kudos if she's annoying you with calls, texts, dates (crazy as it might be). It is because she can't keep away from you. If this is the case, learn to respect her.  She really loves you.</item></list>
<head>How much she gives herself to you?</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Life is not easy. If she weeps before you, know that it is because she feels comfortable being herself around you, weak or dirty or strong or whatever. If your rudeness makes her cry, apologize stupid! She really does love you!</item></list>
<head>How far will she go for you?</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ofttimes tell her that you need this something or that (pretend). Does she say she will or try or cannot? That may level up your understanding of her depth into you. Don't make her do that for you. Remember, you are a man and as man you gotta support her. Not she. If you keep asing for things, she's definitely gonna think you're a moron.</item></list>
</text>
