<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc123" title="Wait Until Marriage to Have Sex" shortTile="wait-until-marriage" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-02-07" dateModified="2015-12-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Wait_Until_Marriage_to_Have_Sex" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wait Until Marriage to Have Sex</head>
<p>There's nothing wrong with waiting until marriage to have sex. Even in the 21st century, there are people who still wish to wait until marriage before having sex. It's a personal choice and it can be based on any number of reasons, from faith to personal preference.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Reach your own decision. Decide why it matters to you to wait until marriage before you have sex. There are more reasons that faith-based ones, so there is no need to feel that that is the only suitable reason. Here are some of the reasons you might wish to wait:
<list type="unordered"><item>You want to be absolutely sure that this person is the right person for you. If the engagement follows through completely to marriage, you'll be content to know that both of you could wait out of respect for one another.</item>
<item>You faith is key to why you wish to stay abstinent.</item>
<item>Although you're keen to have sex with your fiance or fiancee, you also really want to make the wedding night a special occasion and to wait to explore that side of each other during the honeymoon, like the icing on the cake.</item>
<item>You feel that sex would prevent you from really getting to know each other properly as people, as the lust might obscure you from seeing the real character of your beloved.</item>
<item>Other reasons that you come up with, as needed.</item></list></item>
<item>Talk to your fiance or fiancee about this decision. Tell your partner why you wish to abstain from sex before marriage and find out how he or she feels about the situation.
<list type="unordered"><item>Realize that your fiance or fiancee may not be as keen as you to wait until marriage. In this case, it will be a matter of whether or not they respect your choice enough to wait it out regardless. This won't be easy and could cause tensions between you. Also realize that they might have the exact opposite reason from yours, arguing that compatibility sexually is part of knowing the whole package before signing up together for life.</item>
<item>If your partner doesn't share the same faith-based beliefs as you, it's important to talk this through clearly and carefully so that they understand just why this is so important to you. Offer to take them to your place of worship to talk someone there about it, if they agree.</item></list></item>
<item>Talk to your parents. Not all parents wait until marriage to have sex, but if yours did, they'll be able to assist you with advice on what it's like and how to cope with the tension leading up to the marriage. Their respect for your decision will help to bolster your decision to wait.</item>
<item>Talk to your faith-based adviser, if this is relevant. For example, talk to your priest, minister, rabbi, or other faith-based counselor. He or she can help you find different faith-based sources that can give you the inner strength and resolve to keep waiting and staying abstinent until marriage. These can be useful resources to tell others too.</item>
<item>Talk to trusted friends. True friends accept and respect your decisions, whether they agree with you or not.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you want to marry a virgin like yourself, there's nothing wrong with that - they still exist!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Stay away from anyone who doesn't respect your decision.</item></list>
</text>
