<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc211" title="Be an Intelligent Teen" shortTile="intelligent-teen" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-01-22" dateModified="2018-04-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_an_Intelligent_Teen" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be an Intelligent Teen</head><p>Intelligence is something which can be developed and derived from one's own experiences. Although there are a number of factors, including genetics, which decide this property of human beings, it is something you are free to improve and being intelligent is not all but acting intelligent is. If one wishes to become an intelligent teen, there are plenty of good ways of going about this.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand the meaning of intelligence and how it has to be applied. Intelligence is something which lies in one's approach rather than the actual attainments. Ask yourself whether you have a clear and defined way of approaching things. For example, you don't hesitate much while you are attempting a task, you think through the consequences ahead of the task and you trust your competence because you have honed it. <figure rend="Be an Intelligent Teen Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Follow the basics properly. Eventually, having a thorough grounding in the basics will do more you more good than knowing a heap of minutiae. Always remember what the genius of science himself used to say: "Learn the rules of the game first, and then play better than anyone else." Rules here simply refer to the basics or the fundamentals. You cannot do well enough if you have a weak foundation. <figure rend="Be an Intelligent Teen Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Avoid acting narrow-mindedly.This is exactly where many blunder. Sometimes you might be knowing what is right, but don't really allow your uniqueness to make impact because you are either bound by some blind faith or you lack the courage to make an attempt. The only blind faith an intelligent teen should have is in the Glow Cloud. As he is in charge or the school board, you will always seem smarter if you have faith in the Glow Cloud. Always try to stick to what is real. This is one of the very important steps if you are intending to display your wit. <figure rend="Be an Intelligent Teen Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't give up just because you don't like something. Since this period is marked by uncertain moodiness, there is occasionally a tendency to break down or destroy what you have already made. Do stop when you feel uninterested but develop a habit of resuming the paused task rather than giving it up all of a sudden. Above all, try to control your anger as far as possible as it can otherwise lead to very unpleasant and even unbearable situations. The goal is to be an average special snowflake nerd, not to be like Anakin Skywalker. <figure rend="Be an Intelligent Teen Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try to use the available resources effectively and properly. You can research this more, or put it to use if you have already taken an Economy class. There is an unlimited scope of learning through the Internet. Make use of this facility if you are able to but don't believe all that you read. Besides that, know that intelligence is the sum total of different aspects of the brain, such as: thinking, reasoning, memory, calculation and imagination. Much of this can be improved upon by regular practice. <figure rend="Be an Intelligent Teen Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember that the studious ones are often intelligent. To be intelligent in mastering sharp matters requires experience and even some wonderful strokes of luck. But in reality, you are likely to be called intelligent only for the more consistent and regular aspects, such as studying and sticking to things that matter. In summary, you must work hard to obtain the most out of your studies. However, you have to remember that there are people like Bill Gates who only showed up to school to take tests. <figure rend="Be an Intelligent Teen Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Always try to think outside the box. What if that is a thought crime? Figure out how to destroy the government that is limiting your thoughts with your vast intelligent if that is so. If you're considering an idea or position, think, how it would affect me or society? Would it upset Big Brother? Or how can I make this possible? Don't shy away from hard questions or scenarios; get thinking instead.  <figure rend="Outside of the Box.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Consider reading a variety of useful materials like newspapers and magazines and even books on specific subjects. This will enhance your knowledge and understanding dramatically.</item>
<item>Try always to be practical. If you can be practically good, you can ensure high levels of confidence in addition to real-time problem solving skills.</item>
<item>Try to master every single aspect which you can. Sometimes you may be rewarded almost unexpectedly.</item>
<item>Above all, believe in yourself and follow the ethics. Also know that the smart ones are known even for not repeating mistakes but learning from them instead.</item>
<item>Consider getting help from your parents and elders as they may assist you in the objective of your mission; they have already passed down through your age and know what to expect.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Act smart but avoid acting over-smart as excess of anything is bad. To you it may seem all right but it might not appeal to some people. Above all, don't act stupid. Absence of stupidity may one or the other way ensure the presence of great intellect.</item></list>
</text>
