<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc184" title="Have Old Fashioned Morals As a Teen" shortTile="old-fashioned-morals" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-08-12" dateModified="2019-04-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have_Old_Fashioned_Morals_As_a_Teen" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have Old Fashioned Morals As a Teen</head><p>Though gender non-conformity, progressive thinking and sexual liberation aren't necessarily bad things, there's no shame in leading an old-fashioned lifestyle, either. If you're finding yourself drawn to the values of your parents' generation than the one you were born in, you might find that your morals are better described as "old fashioned" than relatively recent.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider which "old-fashioned" morals you're eager to follow. Think for yourself when it comes to this: is everything society believes to be "bad" really so wrong? Perhaps you're a fan of chivalry and look forward to starting a traditional family, but you feel as though you're the most liberated when you're sexually active. Or maybe you'd only be willing to participate in sexual acts with a husband or a wife, but you've never particularly cared about religion. Don't let the views of other "old fashioned" people sway you into changing who you want to be.  <figure rend="Cheerful Girl Says Yes.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Though this article will advice you how to follow the most common interpretation of old-fashioned morals, you can pick-and-choose which parts to integrate into your life.</item></list></item>
<item>Reach out to your place of worship. Teenagers with traditional values are often getting involved with religious causes that they are passionate about. If you don't know where to start, you can try your hand at volunteering for a Bible Study (or a discussion of another religious book) or a religion-related summer camp for younger children. Be open about your faith and willing to have conversations with people who are curious about it.  <figure rend="Cute Muslim Girl Thinking.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>While there's no shame in being openly religious, forcing your beliefs onto others is generally perceived as disrespectful and obnoxious . Don't judge others for not following the same religion that you do.</item></list></item>
<item>Strive to be <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Honest">honest</ref>, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Generous">generous</ref> and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_a_Good_Person">an all-around good person</ref>. These are essentially the fundamental aspects of old-fashioned morals, regardless of which variant of them you are pursuing. Don't be stingy with your good deeds, either: look for any excuse to spread love to those around you, whether it's by giving a compliment or pitching in to help a friend.  <figure rend="Woman Speaks Nicely to Man.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Treat your school janitor or the homeless woman who sleeps in your neighbourhood the same way you'd treat a well-known CEO .</item></list></item>
<item>Show love and respect towards your parents or parental figures. Though many teenagers go through a phase in which they rebel against their parents to assert their independence, old-fashioned youth set themselves apart by admiring benevolent authority figures and being unafraid to ask for their support. The family relationship is more often than not for life.  <figure rend="Man Hugs Teen Girl.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your parents are manipulative, abusive or negatively affect your mental or physical health, you are not obligated to remain on good terms with them. Contact the police if you feel as though you are in serious danger.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider changing your ordinary clothing style. Though people with old-fashioned morals don't necessarily have a distinct appearance, light colours and modest pieces generally signify conservatism and traditional values. If you're still relatively new to this way of life, don't throw out all your clothes and go all-in: shopping for a proper shirt or a pair of dress shoes could go a long way if you've spent the last couple of years in skimpy skirts.  <figure rend="Smiling Asexual Girl with Cornrows.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can express your dedication towards your morals through your clothes, though you'll have to involve a little creativity. If you're striving to help LGBT+ rights, a shirt with a pride flag signals your support. A Black teenager wearing a "Black Lives Matter" shirt shows a dedication to fight for their community.</item></list></item>
<item>Understand your views on romance and sexuality. Many people consider abstinence an integral part of their morals, although others believe in complete sexual freedom as long as informed consent is given. If you're in high school or college, the culture surrounding pairing up might make avoiding dating slightly more difficult, although few people will actively push your boundaries if you've explicitly told them your morals on the topic.  <figure rend="Lovers Kissing Sitting Down.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If somebody repeatedly makes sexual advances after you've asked them to stop, it stops being flirting and becomes harassment.</item></list></item>
<item>Don't be afraid to adjust your worldview. People change. If you feel as though you're starting to lean towards progressive ideals , explore these beliefs and research other perspectives in order to become more informed about this potential lifestyle change. If you're eager to start becoming "more" traditional, respect and accept this, too.  <figure rend="Smiling Young Woman and Man.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>As long as it's not unhealthy or immoral, do what puts a smile on your face.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
