<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc23" title="Transform a Non Animal Lover to a Crazy Pet Lover" shortTile="transform-non-animal" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-02-09" dateModified="2016-12-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Transform_a_Non_Animal_Lover_to_a_Crazy_Pet_Lover" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Transform a Non Animal Lover to a Crazy Pet Lover</head><p>How to Transform a Non Animal Lover to a Crazy Pet Lover</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Its not necessary everyone will love pets as much as you do.If you are staying with someone who is unlike you.Here are few tricks (also depending how well you know the person).It is not difficult but at the same time,make sure you do not enforce.Loving should come naturally.</item>
<item>When you get a pet home,ensure that you are ready to take complete responsibility of the pet.This should not be expected out of anyone else.</item>
<item>If you are friend is  not very comfortable in getting a pet home,this is where we bridge a gap.</item>
<item>Try playing and petting the Pet in front of your friend,and you may also ask/him or her if they would like to pet them too.Do not force.</item>
<item>If the pet is naughty and is still teething,it might chew on everything it finds,make sure it does not harm your friend.If the pet at all bites/scratches,maybe you can scold the pet slightely by pointing your finger at the place he has bitten.</item>
<item>Do not beat the pet,this might scare him and might eventually run away.A slight amount of discipline is always welcome,exactly the way we treat kids but this time being more sensitive.</item>
<item>Keep the house clean as much as possible,it should never stink.A clean house is hygienic and always welcoming in-spite of having a pet.</item>
<item>Try to leave the pet with our friend,it is most likely they will not be very comfortable,but if you know your friend well,they'll eventually end up liking and loving the pet.</item>
<item>Now,it would be nice to push a lil responsibility towards your non-animal love friend,when it comes to feeding him.Try to tell him/her to prepare its lunch as you would be late.And gradually the pet would also understand that it is being loved by this stranger who is no longer one.And eventually your pet and your friend will start understanding one another.</item>
<item>Tag your friend along for all medical aids for the pet.If they show interest,you can explain them about the ailments.</item>
<item>Over the weekend,pull in your friend and try playing with your pet.</item>
<item>If your pet is a CAT,and prefers to roam around the house for nature call,ask your friend to call him home.</item>
<item>Encourage your friend to mingle and play with the pet.</item>
<item>And Eureka! After few days/weeks you'll see a difference between them,this is home tried and tested and it absolutely works.Lets transform this world into an animal loving and caring nation!</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are slight chances that they will never get along well,until both are untamed.But in any case if this is not working and if this leads to ignorance and annoyance please return the pet to a family who'll take care and nurse the pet.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>As we all know when cats.dogs are teething they tend to bite,scratch and chew,make sure you are letting your companion know that this is harmless and  they have been vaccinated with all ailments.</item>
<item>Also having lint(fur) on their clothes,as the animal might shed fur,get a lint sprayer.</item></list>
</text>
