<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc103" title="Follow the Steps of Courtship" shortTile="follow-steps-courtship" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-07-08" dateModified="2017-01-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Follow_the_Steps_of_Courtship" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Follow the Steps of Courtship</head><p>When you hear the word "Courtship", you might think of 18th century English aristocrats "wooing" a fair lady or a Medieval knight courting a young princess. But in fact, courtship, defined as the period before engagement or marriage, or before the establishment of an agreed relationship, is a tradition of all times and all cultures, and is still a very good way of winning the heart of someone you love. There are, however, some universal rules that need to be observed in order to "court" someone, at least in the old-fashioned, literal sense. Now, keeping in mind that the tradition has usually been a man wooing a woman ( read: asking for her hand in marriage ), in the 21th century anyone can be the pursuer or the pursued, and although we're writing for a male audience, the same rules apply for other genders. Have fun courting and who knows, this age-old tradition might just help you to get the person you want !</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find out if they're interested. Believe it or not, but while men like to let their inner wolf instincts loose and go "hunt" the object of their desire, courtship is normally triggered and controlled by women. Sending out (usually) non-verbal cues, like a brief glance in your direction, coupled with a smile and maybe a seductive flashing of the eyelashes or even a wink if you're lucky, should give you a definite idea that she's interested and available. The rest is now up to you. However, when a woman does not give out these cues, she may not be interested and/or available, in which case it's best to either just remain friends or look for love somewhere else.</item>
<item>Show your interest. Now that you know you have a chance, it's time to give her the best you've got. You have to not only show her your affection and adoration for her ( by giving her presents for example, taking her out to a movie she likes to see, writing her letters if you're feeling especially poetic), but you also have to show her why she would want to "pick" you. It's animal mating calls at their finest. She wants to know that you'll be more than just a brief fling: a dependable and devoted husband, and (optionally) a great parent for her children. Listen more than you talk, and answer her questions as honest as you can, while always leaving room for the mystery-aspect: letting her figure you out and get to know you while still keeping her own guard up will let her feel more comfortable to the idea of "something more' growing out of your relationship.</item>
<item>Committing. After you've pursued her for some time ( this can vary from three weeks or less up to two years ), it's now up to you both to take the next step. Again, when she lets you know ( verbally or non-verbally) she's ready to commit and you feel ready to commit as well, you can end the hunting game and go in for the "kill", so to speak: marriage. This is the ultimate goal of traditional courtship, but a very important step should be taken before either of you can even think of getting married:</item>
<item>Meeting the parents. Yes, traditional courtship was all too familiar with this seemingly modern torture. Though it doesn't have to be. Be on your best behaviour when talking to your love's mom and dad, letting them know that you really love their precious child and will take good care of her. In a way you'll have to court them just the same; bond with them and ask them for permission to marry their daughter as well: they will likely appreciate your good manners and will be won over by your charm. And with that out of the way, courtship has reached it's ending point:</item>
<item>Marriage. Or living together, getting engaged, a civil union, anything that works for your relationship. Every relationship has that point where the people involved decide they're willing to dive into the deep together: in the past, this has usually meant getting married. Looking back, you may laugh at how you were both so young and in love, and went through all that trouble pursuing each other, hunting and wooing until finally admitting your love for one another. But perhaps you wouldn't have gotten to this point had you not first spent some time chasing each other around, getting each other aroused and hungry for more in the process that, throughout history, has proved its merit by providing us some of the most enduring marriages of all time: Courtship.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>-Respect for each others personal boundaries and consent is very important. It may be a sort of hunt to you, but it's only fun if both parties enjoy it.</item>
<item>Just because someone is trying to court you, doesn't mean you can take a back seat: enjoy the attention and reciprocate it if you feel the same: Just because someone is hitting on you, doesn't mean you can't show them your active side: if anything, it makes the hunt more interesting!</item>
<item>Like i said before, although the ritual of Courtship stems from a very strict gender-conforming society in which males were expected to take the active role and women the passive role, doesn't mean that if you're a girl interested in someone you can't go ahead and court them like you really mean it! Anyone loves to be admired or seduced, in fact flattery will get you pretty much anywhere! As for guys: if someone is trying to pursue you and win your affections, go ahead and enjoy the attention! It can be nice to be on the receiving end as well!</item>
<item>While in the past there was a big emphasis on parental agreement on a marriage, going so far that the fathers often had more say in the commitment than their daughters who were actually doing the marrying (!), nowadays many people get married sometimes without their parents even knowing about it! If you want to court someone the traditional way however, it is important that you win the approval of your future in-laws: after all, they did raise your partner to become the person you love so much today!</item></list>
</text>
