<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc210" title="Live Life As a Kid" shortTile="live-life-kid" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-06-09" dateModified="2018-10-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Live_Life_As_a_Kid" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Live Life As a Kid</head><p>No matter what adults say, being a kid can be tough. You only have a few years of experience, and yet you need to navigate in a huge world full of incredible and scary things. This article will offer you some guidance so that you have a better shot at having a full, happy, healthy childhood.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Learn as much as you possibly can while you're still young. You probably have all sorts of questions coming to mind every day-- try your best to get them answered! Your questions might annoy adults, but you're at an age when your brain is flexible enough to learn things easily. When you get older, it'll be tougher. So go ahead! Ask about leaves, cows, books, dinosaurs, buildings, anything!  <figure rend="Live Life As a Kid Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>To learn new things, have new experiences. Try playing a sport, hanging out with the new kid, or trying a new food.</item></list></item>
<item>Stay away from unfriendly cliques at school. It's natural for people to feel more comfortable around people similar to them. However, this can sometimes lead to distrust and suspicion of "outsiders." Stay away from groups that exclude people! You have so many potential friends out there. Why hang out with a group that will chase them away?  <figure rend="Live Life As a Kid Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Always <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be-Yourself">be you</ref>! You'll hear this a lot in life, but it's a good rule to follow. The world wouldn't be interesting if everyone acted, dressed, and looked the same-- and people would be miserable in keeping up the act. Let your true self shine and you'll be much happier for it. <figure rend="Live Life As a Kid Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Do_Well_in_School">Do well in school</ref>. No excuses! Sometimes school seems like a chore, yes, but it's helping you grow and preparing you for your future. Now's the time to create good study habits-- things will get <hi rend="italic">really</hi> tough in a few years! Do your best and never sell yourself short for any reason. <figure rend="Live Life As a Kid Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Listen to the thoughts of others. Everyone has a different point of view on a lot of things, but there's no need to fight about it. Listen carefully to others and you may learn a lot about them-- and maybe yourself, too! <figure rend="Live Life As a Kid Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Talk to people! Talking is the first step to new relationships, whether they're friendships or romantic. It's also a great way to learn from people-- try talking to a foreign exchange student or an elder. You never know what you might learn! <figure rend="Live Life As a Kid Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make friends. Having friends is healthy. Try to grow at least one close friendship, where you can tell each other secrets and have serious conversations.  <figure rend="Live Life As a Kid Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>As demonstrated by the many wikiHow "Popularity" articles, lots of people desire a large group of friends, and that might be true of you. Keep in mind, though, that you only have so much time that you can dedicate to friends; in spreading out this time between friends, you might not have enough time to really bond. If you have a small friend group, there's plenty of time to bond with each.</item>
<item>Choose your friends carefully. The most important things to look for in a friend are trust, respect, loyalty, cooperation, and accountability.
<list type="unordered"><item>Examples of each: Feeling safe in telling your friend secrets is trust. Knowing your friend treats you well and equally is respect. Knowing your friend will stand up for you is loyalty. Getting along well is cooperation. Knowing they will make good on any promises is accountability.</item></list></item></list></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Never</hi> discriminate against people. Discrimination means avoiding or mistreating someone just because they're from a certain group. You might run into discrimination against women, racial minorities, non-straight people, disabled people, poor people, the elderly, and heavy people. <hi rend="italic">None of these are okay.</hi> Surely you're annoyed when someone ignores or makes fun of you for being a kid. How would you feel if you had to deal with that your whole life? Well, that's similar to how people feel when they face discrimination. Keep that feeling in mind.  <figure rend="Live Life As a Kid Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Avoid making bad choices. You never know how a situation could get out of hand, so it's best to play it safe. Avoid drugs, alcohol, and gangs. These are all things you will always regret in the end.  <figure rend="Live Life As a Kid Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are faced with the "chicken" taunt, explain that you're not scared; you're just smart enough to avoid asking for trouble.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't be afraid to take good risks-- for instance, trying out for a school play is a risk because the outcome is uncertain. It's a good risk because if you get the part, the outcome is good. If you don't, the outcome is still okay-- no great loss. Remember: you miss 100% of the shots you don't take.</item>
<item>Be the bigger person in disputes. Try to be diplomatic (talk things out) or walk away. Fighting isn't good, and it has serious consequences.</item>
<item>Stay updated on <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Stay_Informed_About_Current_Events">current events</ref>. That way, you'll be thinking more about the whole world instead of your personal world.</item>
<item>Always <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Good_First_Impression">make a good first impression</ref> when meeting new people.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Nice">Be nice</ref>, or at least respectful if you can't help it. This shows good character and it makes everything more pleasant for everyone.</item>
<item>Learn to balance work and play; having fun is important since adults get way less free time than you do!</item>
<item>Make sure to get enough exercise. Exercise is vital for your physical health! Try walking, speed walking, riding your bike or going for a jog or run.</item>
<item>Have a good sense in style and wear appropriate brands, you may observe people (don't stare or creep them out) to notice any popular brands. But only check people your age, you can also make a graph for popular brands.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Learn the difference between getting help and tattling. Getting help is when there is a problem that you and/or others cannot solve alone. Tattling is trying to get someone in trouble.</item></list>
</text>
