<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc169" title="Be the Best Possible (Girls)" shortTile="best-possible-girls" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-03-30" dateModified="2019-08-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_the_Best_Possible_%28Girls%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be the Best Possible (Girls)</head><p>Have you ever wondered if you could be your best all the time? Well now you can with this step by step guide.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get plenty of sleep. You need plenty of sleep to have a lot of energy in the morning. Also, if you get a lot of sleep you won't feel crabby in the morning. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have good hygiene. Wash your hair every other day. To shower, First apply shampoo and wash thoroughly. Then add conditioner to your hair ends. Shave your legs and underarms. Wash your body and after that wash the conditioner of your hair ends. Don't forget to wash your teeth three times a day. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Apply sunscreen before going outside for a long periods of time. You should do this so your skin isn't red. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear a lot of lotion. It moisturizes your skin and keeps it happy and healthy. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't go over the top! This means wearing only three bracelets per arm and two necklaces max. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear cute earrings. Try to do something different everyday. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be selfless. Now this doesn't mean no more you time, it means helping others more often. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you are going to do something with your hair,  Try piggy tails, pony tails and half up half down. Do not go over the top! <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stay true to yourself. Don't change for anyone. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't swear or curse. This means no bad language or profanity. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't be loud. Make your voice isn't too loud or too soft. Try to speak in a gentle tone. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If someone says something rude just ignore them. People are going to make fun of you in life and you need to learn to deal with it. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Obtain as much education as possible, starting from writing notes in school and doing your homework properly. Also, get good grades to get accepted into a good college. Do your best in school. Don't give up right away when you don't know any answers to the math worksheet, try harder. Ask a teacher or friend for help. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep a journal or diary! Write in it 4-5 times a week. It is worth the time. If you think it's nerdy or uncool, don't worry. It can be private and no one needs to know you keep it. Just label it "SCIENCE JOURNAL" and problem solved. No one will think its your diary. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 14 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Exercise! Exercise about each day for 30 minutes and make it make you sweat - yes sweat. Take a dance class, go jogging, biking, join a hiking club, play tennis, racket ball, soccer, basketball. Do aerobics. Do something. It will improve your fitness, but more importantly it will improve your outlook on life and the world. Exercise is a secret potion to happiness and well being and being happy always makes you more attractive. Being fit is always more attractive than not being fit. And don't think you have to be like a skinny model to be fit. Fit means you can run and enjoy it. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 15 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Leave your hair natural. Don't dye it or bleach it. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 16 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear light makeup. Wear lip gloss and a light pink blush. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 17 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Always say hello to everyone you meet, yes even strangers. It will make their day. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 18 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be a good listener. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 19 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be corteges. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 20 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be positive and optimistic. Instead of dreading going to school/work, you can put on a smile and say "I am going to have a great day!" <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 21 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't gossip about others. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 22 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Always tell the truth. If not who would think you are perfect. Be sure to be honest. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 23 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stay organized. <figure rend="Be the Best Possible (Girls) Step 24 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
