<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc168" title="Be a Normal Teenage Girl" shortTile="normal-teenage-girl" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-11-10" dateModified="2018-10-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Normal_Teenage_Girl" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Normal Teenage Girl</head><p>Help on just how to look and act to achieve the coveted status of 'normal'.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Change hairstyles if your hair is long enough. It is always good to experiment with your own styles. Pluck your eyebrows if you wish. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep your make-up modest and matching. Wearing red whilst having pink and blue make-up on, and too much of it, will <hi rend="italic">not</hi> give people the right impression on you. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you have enough clothing. Look at what clothes you need and buy that. Do not buy loads of jeans when you really need a new coat. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do the same for shoes and accessories. Have different shoes, clothes and accessories for every different occasion. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have good manners and confidence. Being rude, disrespectful and shy is not going to make people like you. Instead, try to be a polite, kind, confident person. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Watch your language. Do not swear too much and be mindful who you swear around. Also, having a wide range of vocabulary can be very useful. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be humorous, not offensive. Many people enjoy being around somebody who'll make them laugh, but don't offend people. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Talk often, but not too much. Don't be shy to say your opinion but don't butt in and interrupt everything. Let everyone speak. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be cool, calm and collected. Getting annoyed or angry at everything won't help anybody. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have good self esteem and believe in yourself. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do not copy others. Copying others work or style does not help you in any way later in life. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Respect others, but do as you would be done by. So give people respect, but if for example they ignore you, ignore them. They may need to know what it feels like. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have lots of friends. Trust them and spend time with them. Express your annoyance towards them if you have any, so you don't end up bursting into a full fire rage at them. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Love your family, and show it. Hug, kiss and compliment your family to make them feel appreciated, loved and respected. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Whatever happens, don't hold grudges forever. People are always making mistakes, and friendships and family is a million times more important than one silly mistake. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Behave well at school. Do your homework, have all necessary equipment and have a fun day. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 16.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Join clubs. Don't be afraid to join the football team, or learn Italian in lunchtimes etc.! <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Respect your bedroom. Keep it clean, nice and well decorated. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look after and care for your possessions. Don't get a new phone and ask for a different one a month later. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 19.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat well. Drink lots of water and keep a balanced diet. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 20.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Clean yourself thoroughly, daily. Wash your hair as often as needed and brush your teeth at least twice a day. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 21.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get enough sleep. Websites will inform you how much sleep you need for your age. <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 22.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Enjoy life. Play games, watch TV, and have fun! <figure rend="Be a Normal Teenage Girl Step 23.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
