<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc136" title="Attend a Travel Show" shortTile="attend-travel-show" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-03-20" dateModified="2019-10-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Attend_a_Travel_Show" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Attend a Travel Show</head><p>Many people love to travel, but not as many are aware of the fun that can be had by journeying to a travel industry trade show — that is, a travel show.  Travel shows tend to pop up in the convention centers of major cities during the winter months, and offer a wide array of vendors, exhibits, entertainment, and deals.  Find a travel show you'd like to visit, plan ahead to sniff out the best bargains, and maximize your fun quotient while you attend for a day or two.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Finding a Travel Show to Attend</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Search for travel shows in major cities.  In the United States, for instance, cities like New York, Chicago, Los Angeles, Washington, and San Francisco have large annual travel shows.  So too do cities like Denver, Cincinnati, and many others.  Basically, if you live near a major city with a convention center, there is a good chance that you'll find a travel show. <figure rend="Attend a Travel Show Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do a web search for “travel show” and your city of interest and see what comes up.  If you're looking for the biggest travel shows in the U.S., check out the ones in New York or Los Angeles.</item></list></item>
<item>Plan to attend during the winter.  Attending a travel show can help warm up the winter months by providing a wide array of information and deals for exotic getaways.  Most U.S. travel shows are held between January and early April — basically, opposite the prime vacation season. <figure rend="Attend a Travel Show Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look over the show's website.  Once you've identified a travel show you'd like to attend, take some time to browse its website.  All substantial travel shows, and the biggest ones in particular, will have official websites with detailed information on vendors, exhibits, activities, special guests, deals and prizes, and so on. <figure rend="Attend a Travel Show Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Take note of items that pique your interest and use this list to help plan your day or two of attendance at the show.  The major shows are far too big for you to be able to experience everything, so you'll need to be choosy.</item></list></item>
<item>Buy your tickets ahead of time.  U.S. travel shows tend to charge an entry fee of around $10-$20 per day, but discounts can often be had if you buy your tickets ahead of time instead of at the door.  Check out the show's website for your ticket buying options. <figure rend="Attend a Travel Show Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If the show runs for multiple days, you might also be able to get a discount for buying a two-day pass, for instance.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Getting Discounts and Deals</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do your homework before the show.  Practically every vendor at a travel show will offer some combination of special travel deals, discounts, prizes, giveaways, and raffles to draw in visitors.  You won't have time to visit every booth, so use the website to identify discounts and deals that interest you.  That way, you can map out and target your visit so you have a chance at the most appealing discounts and freebies. <figure rend="Attend a Travel Show Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The website and/or your ticket packet should also include a floor map of the show; use it to mark your route so that you can hit all the booths you want to visit.</item></list></item>
<item>Take advantage of freebies.  Although your main focus should be on tracking down awesome travel deals and entering drawings for great cash or travel prizes, that doesn't mean you need to ignore the more run-of-the-mill free stuff.  As with other types of trade shows, you can fill up on an assortment of logo-emblazoned pens, mouse pads, keychains, frisbees, and the like. <figure rend="Attend a Travel Show Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't weigh yourself down too much with freebies, or waste time better spent elsewhere.  But if you could use another “can cozy” to keep your favorite canned beverage cold, why not grab one?</item></list></item>
<item>Talk to vendor representatives at booths that interest you.  Some travel show visitors avoid talking to the vendor reps because they assume they'll just get a never-ending sales pitch for the “vacation deal of a lifetime.”  You may run into some of this, but you will also find reps who are knowledgeable and enthusiastic.  Talking to them can really help you decide between vacation destinations, or choose where to stay or what to do at your dream destination. <figure rend="Attend a Travel Show Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Enjoying the Travel Show</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Check out the performances.  Entertainment performances, and particularly dance routines, are a common feature of travel shows.  Different dance groups will wear costumes and present dances that represent nations and cultures from around the world.  These types of performances are also a nice way to take a break from hustling from booth to booth on the exhibit floor. <figure rend="Attend a Travel Show Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Look for performance schedules on the travel show's website or your ticket packet.</item></list></item>
<item>Go to lectures and demonstrations.  Larger shows often bring in travel industry celebrities as headliners to help draw in visitors.  You might find hosts of popular cable or public television travel shows giving lectures or offering travel tips.  Cooking demos, often showcasing cuisine from popular destinations, are also a common occurrence. <figure rend="Attend a Travel Show Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The more well-known the individual — Rick Steves, Andrew Zimmern, or Samantha Brown, to name a few — the more prominently they will be advertised, and the larger the crowd is likely to be.</item>
<item>Even if a lecture or demo isn't a must-see event for you, it does provide another excuse to take a bit of a breather from the hustle and bustle of the convention.</item></list></item>
<item>Try hands-on activities.  Many travel shows are also now advertised as “adventure shows,” for those interested in more action-packed vacations.  Don't be surprised to find a climbing wall in the convention hall, or a zip line carrying squealing visitors overhead. <figure rend="Attend a Travel Show Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Since you'll be doing a lot of standing and walking, it's a good idea to wear comfortable clothes and sensible shoes in any case — but especially if you're interested in adventure activities.</item></list></item>
<item>Bring the kids along.  Most vacation destinations are advertised as family-friendly, so travel shows in turn usually have activities and content geared toward kids and families.  Examine the website for information on kid-centric performances, games, exhibits, and activities.  Also, many travel shows let kids in free with a paying adult. <figure rend="Attend a Travel Show Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
