<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc214" title="Be the Unique, Friendly and Smart Girl" shortTile="unique-friendly-smart" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-11-15" dateModified="2015-11-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_the_Unique%2C_Friendly_and_Smart_Girl" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be the Unique, Friendly and Smart Girl</head><p>Do you ever feel like all you've got in life is a lot of problems and then there's this girl who is popular, smart, and happy- all at once?  Do you wish your life would be exactly like hers? Then keep reading! This article will teach you how to be like this socially liked girl! (Ages 9-18).</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Morning Routine</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Wake up early each morning on school days. Try not to be late, that's no good because you're missing out a lot and it affects your education more than you think! And it might damage your reputation if you miss out too much.
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember, getting a good nights sleep will help you get more focused and socially active. </item>
<item>Bedtime by age groups (Note that these are just recommendations and that it's very individual, if you feel like going to bed earlier/later- do it. Only you can decide):</item>
<item>9:            8:30</item>
<item>10:          9:00</item>
<item>11:        10:00</item>
<item>12:        10: 15</item>
<item>13:        10: 21</item>
<item>14-15:  10: 30</item>
<item>16-17:  10:45</item>
<item>18:        11: 00</item></list></item>
<item>When you have woken up take a shower. Rinse your body, then shampoo your hair. Rinse  and put shower gel where needed. Rinse again and you're done.</item>
<item>When you have showered, get your hairstyle ready. Try experimenting with different hairstyles! (Tip: make sure that you know how to do the hairstyle one day in advance so that you're sure it doesn't take too much time or that it's not too difficult): <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Do_Simple_and_Cute_Hairstyles">Do Simple and Cute Hairstyles</ref></item>
<item>When you are done, brush your teeth for some minutes. Use mouthwash if needed.</item>
<item>If you've got bad breath, try using a tongue scraper or use these tips: <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Prevent_Bad_Breath">Prevent Bad Breath</ref></item>
<item>Apply makeup if you want but make sure that you don't overdo it, natural beauty is always the best!</item>
<item>Then get to school. Taking the bus is preferred since it's public transport and better for the environment. If taking the car, pick up your friends if possible so that the amount of cars is reduced.</item></list>
<head>Looks</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get your own unique style
<list type="unordered"><item>Experiment and find out what you're comfortable with and pick clothes according to that. You can tell when someone is comfortable with what they're wearing, they seem more confident so choose what you like!</item></list></item>
<item>Clothing
<list type="unordered"><item>You don't have to wear the latest fashion to be fashionable, pick something you think looks nice! But if you want to follow the latest trends, look it up online or in magazines.</item>
<item>Remember that some clothes may not be appropriate in certain situations.</item>
<item>Do not copy someone else's style, take inspiration instead and use it in your own style!</item></list></item>
<item>Wear accessories that matches your clothes.
<list type="unordered"><item>Wear a necklace, a hand bag, or a bracelet. Even consider nail-polish!</item></list></item>
<item>Wear comfy shoes.
<list type="unordered"><item>Some examples are sneakers, sandals, boots, ballet flats etc.</item></list></item>
<item>Wear make up
<list type="unordered"><item>This is not necessary, don't feel like you must use makeup. It's optional.</item>
<item>If you have pimples/acne, treat them with some of these tips: <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_Rid_of_Acne_Naturally">Get Rid of Acne Naturally</ref></item></list></item></list>
<head>Eat healthy</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>A healthy lifestyle is good for your skin and the rest of your body, and it will give you a confidence boost as well. You should not feel forced to eat anything you don't want to eat just because it's healthy, but a balanced diet is good.  Drink plenty of water!</item></list></item>
<item>Food tips
<list type="unordered"><item>Fruit, yogurt, and granola.Greens like spinach, kale, or celery. Try mixing them up into a smoothie. Eggs and a lean ham or turkey. They will give you protein that will give you lots of energy. Oatmeal, whole grain bread, or healthy cereal. Avoid sugary cereals because they will give you a spike of energy that will make you crash later. Avoid foods that are soaked in grease, butter, or maple syrup. These foods can be great for the weekend or special occasions, when you're trying indulge and relax a little more and aren't so focused on being alert.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Be good at School/college</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Have a good posture
<list type="unordered"><item>If slouching you may not get the respect you should get, people tend to be taken less seriously when having a bad posture so try to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Improve_Your_Posture">Improve Your Posture</ref>!</item></list></item>
<item>In school
<list type="unordered"><item>Listen carefully during a presentation and when given instructions. Then you can start right away with the assignment and you will have the information you need.</item>
<item>Don't fool around in class, that's what breaks are for. Don't annoy other people who actually wants to learn something.</item>
<item>Try to be friends with a lot of people, or at least be nice to them. Then you'll probably like school a little bit more!</item>
<item>School isn't boring when you have goals, friends and the motivation to learn. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Stay_Motivated_in_School">Stay Motivated in School</ref></item></list></item>
<item>When you get home, study!
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember to take breaks, eat something and stay hydrated.</item>
<item>Try to make studying fun by inviting a couple of friends who you can study with.</item>
<item>Organizing is the key to success, it makes it hard for you to forget assignments and tests.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Social life</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to parties
<list type="unordered"><item>Parties are a great way to maximize your social circle and they're also great for training on your social skills!</item>
<item>If you're going to drink, drink carefully and don't get too wasted. You might do something you'll regret in the morning.</item></list></item>
<item>Be a good friend
<list type="unordered"><item>Be fun and outgoing, do stuff with your friends and try to be a great friend.</item>
<item>Remember to be kind towards everyone you meet, then you'll be well-liked!</item></list></item></list>
<head>Other stuff</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><list type="unordered"><item>While waiting for something, tell jokes or stories to keep your friends entertained.This is a time to let your creativity blossom!</item>
<item>Don't make too much noise while watching movies, you will ruin the movie for everyone.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
