<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc146" title="Make Travel Easy and Stress Free" shortTile="make-travel-easy" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-02-05" dateModified="2015-09-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_Travel_Easy_and_Stress_Free" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Travel Easy and Stress Free</head><p>Travelling can be a positive and life changing experience. While it is possible for travelling to overwhelm you with experiences, it will turn you into a storyteller and if done right from the beginning, travelling can be a great combination of fun, adventure and relaxation. If you’re planning a vacation abroad, these simple and easy steps can make your trip a truly rejuvenating and refreshing experience and you will return home with a fresh mind, ready  to kick start your routine with a wide smile!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask yourself the reason for travel. First things first, it is important to know why you want to travel. Is it for some adventure, relaxation or to experience new things? Once you understand the reason for your travel, you will get your direction or the next step, namely, choosing where you want to go. <figure rend="Make Travel Easy and Stress Free Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Budget for the trip, including making savings. When you’ve decided where you want to go, the next most important thing is to check your budget.  Do you think you’ve got enough bills in your pocket that you can travel to your chosen place? If not, it’s time to start saving now with a positive attitude. This can also help you decide when you want to start your trip – because you will only be able to make arrangements once you’ve saved enough. <figure rend="Make Travel Easy and Stress Free Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Decide the destination. Once you know why you want to travel and have the budget in hand, you can have a better idea about the type of destination you want to visit. Are you interested in historic sites? Beaches? Night life? Mountains? Depending on your interests, you can choose a destination. Choosing a destination, whether within the country or international, can help you move forward towards the next phase of easy travel. <figure rend="Make Travel Easy and Stress Free Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Look for cheap travel deals. Even if know you’ve saved enough, you still want to travel as cheaply as possible and save some more, especially if you’re travelling in a group, whether with family or friends. So look for cheap travel deals across the internet and you’ll surely find a deal and experience that suits your budget. Some deals even include hotel accommodation, transport, city tours, etc. One good trick is to book flights as early as possible for discounts and special offers. <figure rend="Make Travel Easy and Stress Free Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to get breakfast included as much as possible when booking accommodation. That way, you can fill up in the morning for free, getting lots of energy to start the day with.</item></list></item>
<item>Collect all the essentials and get ready. Once you’ve bought tickets, it’s time to get ready and collect all of your essentials. Make sure you’re covered by sufficient insurance, have enough accessible cash on you (always keep extra for an emergency), have the visas if you need any (also make sure you have a visa for destinations where you will be stopping over for a transit). Get all your documents together so that you’re good to go! <figure rend="Make Travel Easy and Stress Free Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Travel with an open mind. Expect anything unexpected. You may see delays, traffic, a different culture, lifestyle, food, people, even a shortage of cash sometimes and other mishaps – this is all what travel is about – experiencing things with a new perspective. Once you expect to experience new things, and are okay with having to handle delays, you’ll be a happy traveler and free from stress. Just remember that you’re on a trip to enjoy. So make the most of it. <figure rend="Make Travel Easy and Stress Free Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make and save your memories. Travelling is all about experiencing new things, getting away from routine, enjoying your trip and living in the moment. Make sure you take lots of photographs and make cheerful memories whether travelling alone or with a group. This will make your trip worthwhile. Smile more and go places and forget about the everyday routine back home. <figure rend="Make Travel Easy and Stress Free Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
