<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc66" title="Be Single Minded" shortTile="single-minded" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-01-15" dateModified="2019-08-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_Single_Minded" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Single Minded</head><p>Being "single-minded" has to do with the power of focus.  Your ability to focus is ultimately your biggest ally in accomplishing tasks and projects.  With practice this is an ability one can develop.  Your level of achievement and success depends upon it.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Define "single-minded":  It is an adjective meaning: 1) Determined 2) Having one overriding purpose or goal. 3) Steadfast; resolute.  Now let's define "focus". 1) The concentration of attention or energy on something.  The opposite of this would be "absent-minded", "scattered", or perhaps just "distracted." <figure rend="Single minded Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know that there are good forms of "single-mindedness" and bad forms.  Here's the difference. <figure rend="Single minded Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The bad single minded: When one becomes so preoccupied with a task that they lose all grip with their daily responsibilities and accountability to others, this is obviously a form of self delusion.  We often label these personality types as "self-centered" or "self obsessed", carrying a negative connotation.  Often people that are mentally ill or mentally challenged will be seen doing the same movements over and over.  This is hardly the "single-mindedness" we are after.</item>
<item>The good form of "single-minded" is the ability to block out distractions and erroneous thoughts in order to concentrate better. Your desire to become more single-minded will enable you to finish projects with more efficiency in less time.</item></list></item>
<item>Practice the common methods and some not so common methods to develop your power of focus: <figure rend="Single minded Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Creating the environment is step 1.  If it's a task where you are seated at a desk then you will need to clean the desk area and become more organized.  At that time a new project starts with a "clean slate." Let's suppose you are trying to quit smoking.  Create the environment to allow this to be possible.  In other words on your quit date the house and car you occupy need to be "smokeless" in every way. No ashtrays, lighters, etc.</item>
<item>The power of "intention".  This is a slightly different perspective than mere goal setting.  Intention means on the deepest level figure out exactly what is you intend on creating, then affirming this to yourself and visualizing an approximate end result, i.e. being a non-smoker, finishing a work assignment, writing a college thesis, etc.</item>
<item>Set and setting.  In other words "where" are you most likely be able to focus or accomplish your goal?  With what external conditions around you are tolerable to your concentration abilities? For example if your intention is to be a non-smoker then you are more likely to succeed hanging out in a local gym, vs. the local bar.  If you are trying to finish studying for college exams, you may want to create privacy vs. the kids running around and playing in your study space.</item>
<item>Set small steps and short term goals.  Do this in writing in outline form.  Breaking down the steps can help the mind from not getting overwhelmed.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>There is another truth. "If you keep doing what you have always done, you will continue to get what you've always got!"</item>
<item>Sleep alone is probably the most overlooked activity you can change. Get quality sleep!</item>
<item>Remember, single steps can lead to single-mindedness!  Simple steps can lead to a more creative and functional outlook.  Work on the above steps and your life will change for the better.</item>
<item>Nothing changes till it changes.  You need to apply creative ways of applying the above steps.  You will get out of this what you put into it.</item>
<item>Uncommon methods, yet highly effective in producing "focus", would be things like doing Tai Chi, yoga, and most definitely all forms of meditation.  Hypnosis has been known to work as well as Neuro Linguistic Programming.  Vitamin/mineral therapy is certainly helpful, as well as plenty of rest.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't rely on externals such as caffeine or the assorted "energy" drinks, as they may temporarily create some focused energy, they all have a "crash," meaning even less concentration!</item>
<item>Don't fall into the trap of making "single-mindedness" turn to obsession.  The key to long term success is finding your own perfect balance.</item></list>
</text>
