<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc7" title="Avoid Beauty Mistakes" shortTile="avoid-beauty-mistakes" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-08-19" dateModified="2017-08-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Avoid_Beauty_Mistakes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Avoid Beauty Mistakes</head><p>Due to our ignorance there are many things we do which may lead to problems and issues related to our beauty. This article would share with you few tips which if you use start implementing from teenage, you can avoid a lot of beauty issues</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Take Care Of Your Smile</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Brush twice daily.</item>
<item>Get braces if required. Consult an Orthodontist to check whether your jaws and teeth align properly or not. Few years of braces will result into a more beautiful and confident smile.</item>
<item>Remember your teeth are very important part of your body so take care of them and visit dentist regularly.</item></list>
<head>Take Care Off Your Physique</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Play a sport or do an Outdoor activity. Avoid sitting continuously for long time. Stay Active</item>
<item>Eat healthy and Nutritious Food. What we eat has a great effect on our body. Avoid Junk Food, Sugar and Refined Food.</item>
<item>Take care of your body. It will help you to be in shape.</item></list>
<head>Take Care Of Your Eyesight</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Avoid watching Television and working on Laptop s/Computers continuously for long time
<list type="unordered"><item>Continuously using smartphones  may also strain your eyes.</item></list></item>
<item>Consult ophthalmologist regularly and get your eyesight checked. This would help to avoid spectacles.</item>
<item>Eat food rich in beta-carotene such as carrots, spinach etc.</item></list>
<head>Take Care Of Your Skin</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Wash your face twice daily. If your skin in oily then you may wash your face thrice a day but try not to wash more than this.</item>
<item>Exfoliate using a mild scrub twice weekly. Those who have pimples may avoid exfoliating till the pimples are cured. Exfoliation will help to avoid blackheads and whiteheads</item>
<item>Moisturize your skin after you wash or exfoliate. Use sunscreen based moisturizers during day time. Oily skin people may use Gel based sunscreens.</item>
<item>Avoid oily food.</item>
<item>Consult dermatologist if facing pimples outburst.</item>
<item>Never ever break or touch pimples. This may lead to permanent marks or spots on your face.</item>
<item>Use  mixture of gram-flour powder, yogurt and turmeric powder It's the best face pack for all types of skin.</item>
<item>Keep yourself  hydrated. Avoid excessive coffee or tea.</item>
<item>Avoid smoking. Smoking is extremely harmful for skin and can make you look older.</item>
<item>Avoid heavy makeup daily and keep light or no makeup.</item>
<item>Don't wash your skin with soap.</item></list>
<head>Take Care of Your Hair</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Massage your scalp with oil before shampoo preferably with coconut oil or castor oil.</item>
<item>Shampoo your hair as per your hair type, however avoid washing your hair daily.</item>
<item>Don't comb wet hair as wet hair tends to break easily.</item>
<item>Avoid regular use of hair dryer and let your hair air dry. Using hair drier can lead to frizzy hair and split ends</item>
<item>Avoid coloring or using too much hair products like hair sprays, creams etc.</item>
<item>Once a week go for deep conditioning of your hair.</item>
<item>If suffering from severe hair fall or graying  consult Dermatologist.</item>
<item>Avoid excessive curling or hair straightening as they may also lead to hair damage and hair fall</item></list>
<head>Body and Face Hair Removal</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Avoid using depilatory creams especially for your underarms and other sensitive areas, as this may lead to permanent darkening of your skin.</item>
<item>Have a warm water shower and exfoliate before shaving / waxing or epilating</item>
<item>Avoid ingrown hair by exfoliating regularly. Shaving should first be done in the direction of hair growth and then against the direction of hair growth. This would avoid shaving bumps and in grown hair</item>
<item>Opt for threading or plucking for your face rather than waxing or shaving. Never use depilatory creams not specifically meant for face on your face. Waxing should be done by professional only.</item>
<item>Use scrubs and pumice stone from early age, this may reduce your hair growth</item></list>
<head>Stay Confident</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Stay confident, Never let anybody make you feel inferior. Try to look your best possible, however don't go overboard. Its ok to have few flaws, but at the same time treat your body the way it is deserved to be treated.</item>
<item>Smile often. Smile is the best accessory</item>
<item>Be knowledgeable, read books . Have opinions but don't make judgement</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Consult specialist for any beauty concern, don't treat yourself on your own.</item>
<item>Start taking care of yourself and avoiding beauty mistakes from early age.</item>
<item>Avoid too many medications and try to be more natural</item>
<item>Use branded and good quality products</item></list>
</text>
