<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc62" title="Explore the Difference Between Knowledge and Understanding" shortTile="explore-difference" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-11-22" dateModified="2016-08-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Explore_the_Difference_Between_Knowledge_and_Understanding" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Explore the Difference Between Knowledge and Understanding</head><p>Perhaps the "secret ingredient" of all wisdom is <hi rend="italic">understanding</hi>, that near magical insight where not only the concept but its practical application make perfect sense.
The complication however, is that understanding and knowledge aren't always the same thing. So, while a person may diligently study a philosophy, it might never create much benefit on a deep level, or ever make sense so the lesson remains deep, abstract and inaccessible. This common problem afflicts many and is a major obstacle towards being able to develop skills in life.</p>
<p>This tutorial explores the differences between the two and how to ensure you get maximum benefit from various religious and philosophical teachings and to reach a greater depth of understanding in your field of study.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start at the beginning and look at what knowledge is. Knowledge, in effect, is  the accumulation of facts, myths, trivia and beliefs. Its an all  encompassing field of data that we use to live by from methods to  complete a task, data to be able to plan as well as the ability to  reflect on what was learnt. <figure rend="Break-a-Habit-Step-4-Version-3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Reflect on how you accumulated this great store of data. Data can be  accumulated from schools and other people and the mind stores this if it  has interest in it, be it trivial interest or functional relevance.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider how much of your knowledge you actually understand on a deep  level. By and large, the amount of knowledge we have is far greater than  the amount of it we really understand. For example, we may all know that  placing a raw egg into boiling water will cook the egg, but we don't  necessarily understand the process that affects the proteins in the egg,  however a specialist who studies the process will not only learn how,  but understand why. In the same way, we may know many pieces of wisdom  but much of it we simply store as learnt, but not as understood as we  seldom observe it or apply it in a mindful manner. <figure rend="Do-Mindful-Meditation-Step-11-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Explore the relationship with knowledge and the present moment.  Knowledge when closely observed, reveals itself to be entirely linked to  the past, but not the present moment. All our knowledge and information  has been accumulated over a long period of time, the present moment  simply is - there is just awareness and being. <figure rend="Achieve-Short-Term-Goals-Step-6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>It is important to consider this aspect. There is very little data-  knowledge we didn't come across through education, experiences and from  personal study, but this retention of data is simply the retention of  data that is not obtained "now", but was obtained "then" and is now  stored for our personal use in our minds.</item></list></item>
<item>Test what happens when you release the past. You may try this as a  thought experiment, or during a meditation exercise. If you do let go  sufficiently to be fully aware of the present moment, its likely only to  be for a few minutes as the process of the mind depends on knowledge so  it quickly reverts to the process it is familiar with using. <figure rend="Meditate for Beginners Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider now the relationship you have with your philosophy or  religion. How much of it is knowledge learned as opposed to knowledge  understood? It is a very surprising point to understand, that many of  the methods to live well and be happy have already been discovered by  the multitude of philosophers, saints and religious leaders over time.  So why is it that we may hear the answer, but it still not make any  difference, yet for some it does? <figure rend="Do-Mindful-Meditation-Step-13-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start to explore individual facets of the philosophy. By contemplating  its intention as well as its method of application as well as its  alternatives and its non application, you can get a deeper insight. Its  still not sufficient at this stage, but this is the foundation to  building understanding. The greater deal of understanding happens when  the knowledge learned is applied directly in the moment. <figure rend="Develop-Telepathy-Step-12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The fascinating part of the mind is that it can see the same thing  and still learn something new. Just like when you look at a photograph  or a painting many times, eventually more and more of it becomes  apparent to you. You see more subtle effects of light and shadow, the  brush-strokes and paint textures and colours and more subtle parts of  the background which can give new meaning and interest. With this in  mind, you can explore the philosophy or teaching, or more generally life  and the mind itself to be able to comprehend it and find deeper  applications and benefits.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider the benefits and possibilities of improving your understanding. In essence, understanding is a very  deep process with great benefits, whereas simple book knowledge, rote learning or mnemonic style  information occupies a very shallow level of the mind and so gives  minimal benefits. It is only when a person has learned it well enough to apply  it in the moment, can understanding then grow from knowledge.  Finish the process by reflecting again on the difference between  knowledge and understanding. Knowledge ultimately being the collection  of past events and second hand knowledge obtained elsewhere. In the  present moment, there is simply understanding and the opening towards  serenity and happiness. <figure rend="Develop-Emotional-Intelligence-Step-7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
