<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc185" title="Be a Happy, Healthy Tween Girl" shortTile="happy-healthy-tween" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-07-30" dateModified="2018-10-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Happy%2C_Healthy_Tween_Girl" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Happy, Healthy Tween Girl</head><p>Lots of girls wonder: How can they be their very best while balancing school, hobbies, social life, and athletics? It can be challenging! This article can show you how to do all that and more!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Staying Healthy</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Keep yourself <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Stay_Hydrated">hydrated</ref>. One of the most important parts of feeling and looking good is very simple; stay hydrated! Make sure to drink plenty of water, especially while outside or exercising. Make sure to drink at <hi rend="italic">least</hi> eight full glasses a day. It not only keeps you looking bright and happy, but it makes you feel good, too! <figure rend="Be a Happy, Healthy Tween Girl step 2 version 1.png"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Exercise">Exercise</ref>. Exercise is vital to keeping a growing girl feeling refreshed. Whether it is <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Ride_a_Bicycle">riding a bike</ref>, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Use_a_Treadmill">running on a treadmill</ref>, doing <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Do_a_Push_Up">push ups</ref>, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Walk_a_Dog">walking the dog</ref> or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Dance">dancing</ref> with a younger sibling, all forms help you to staying fit! If you are active and get at least 30 minutes of exercise a day, this is a great start. You may require even more, however. Some girls work out because they want to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Lose_Weight_As_a_Preteen">lose weight</ref>. That is okay, as long as you do not over- exert yourself. <figure rend="Be a Happy, Healthy Tween Girl step 2 version2.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Talk to a parent first before trying to lose weight.</item></list></item>
<item>Eat right. Another important part to staying healthy is eating right! You should consume between five and thirteen serving of fruits and vegetables a day, that is equivalent to two and a half to six and a half cups daily. <figure rend="Be a Happy, Healthy Tween Girl step 3 version 1.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Substitute beef for chicken and turkey and a bag of chips for an apple or some carrots. <figure rend="Be a Happy, Healthy Tween Girl step4verxion2.png"></figure></item>
<item>If you eat dessert often, try to restrict consumption of high calorie sweets once a week.</item>
<item>Be careful not to over-eat or under-eat as this can be dangerous if done regularly. Make sure to have three meals every day.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Looking Your Best</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Keep your makeup natural. You are beautiful just the way you are. Do not forget that. Make sure to always make your makeup look natural and light, if you do decide to wear any at all. A little blush, concealer, lip gloss, and a light eye shadow is fine, but do not go to extremes with mascara, eyeliner, dark eye shadow, and lipstick. <figure rend="Be a Happy, Healthy Tween Girl step 6 version 1.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure the makeup you are wearing follow the rules approved by your parents, so as not to get in trouble.</item>
<item>Make sure to check your school's policy on makeup if you want to wear some to school. Some schools don't allow it.</item></list></item>
<item>Wear clothes that compliment your complexion. For example, if you are a blonde, try wearing colours that compliment you like red and purple. Brunettes will look stunning in red. If you have red or orange hair, wear forest green colors, as it will bring out your hair. <figure rend="165348.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Having Good Hygiene</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Remember that good hygiene can help you look and feel nicer. Make sure to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Take_a_Shower">shower</ref> or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Take_a_Bath">bathe</ref> every day if you can. Use a mild soap to wash off the day's dirt from your skin. Carefully wash and dry your face, hands, feet, armpits and bottom. Take a shower after you exercise or get sweaty to keep clean. <figure rend="Take a Shower Step 4 Version 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Smell good. Use body sprays that you like. Use deodorants if you like. <figure rend="Spray Yourself With Deodorant Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can use perfume sometimes but it's usually best to keep it subtle don't overdo it.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Learning Good Behaviour</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Learn to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Forgive">forgive</ref>. Gracefully distance yourself from those who back bite or bad mouth you. <figure rend="Help Teenagers Deal With Bullies Step 18.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have healthy interactions. Get on social media so you can connect with your friends. <figure rend="Reconnect With Old Friends Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Shower every day. Try to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Wash_Your_Hair">wash your hair</ref> three times a week. Washing your hair every day has been proven to make hair thinner.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't judge people if they seem inferior. Remember that you aren't perfect either.</item>
<item>Never miss out on meals frequently, over-exercise or make yourself throw up. These are all dangerous habits and are signs of having an <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Know_if_You_Have_an_Eating_Disorder">eating disorder</ref> such as <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Prevent_Anorexia">anorexia</ref> or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Prevent_Bulimia">bulimia</ref>. If you think you may have problems <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_Help_for_Your_Eating_Disorder">get help</ref> immediately.</item>
<item>It's fine to keep in touch with friends on social media but be aware of the dangers online and be <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Safe_on_the_Internet">safe</ref>.</item></list>
</text>
