<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc161" title="Deal with Difficult Co Workers in the Work Place" shortTile="deal-difficult-co" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-07-21" dateModified="2018-06-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Deal_with_Difficult_Co_Workers_in_the_Work_Place" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Deal with Difficult Co Workers in the Work Place</head>
<p>Many people have to deal with difficult people in the work place. This will help teach you to deal with those people in a way that will make your day less stressful.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>When you are getting ready for work, think to yourself, "Today will be a good day". It is always good to think positively instead of negatively. Listen to music that gets you going and motivated while you are getting ready. <figure rend="Deal with Difficult Co Workers in the Work Place Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Kill people with kindness. If you are nice to everyone, even to those who are rude to you, it will make it harder for them to be mean to someone who treats them nicely. Smile and say hello like you would to a friend or a family member. <figure rend="Deal with Difficult Co Workers in the Work Place Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you can predict it, you can plan for it. If you can think of all the ways possible that could happen to make your day go sour, think of different solutions to fix it. <figure rend="Deal with Difficult Co Workers in the Work Place Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get the last word. If one of your co workers is saying things are totally out of line to you, be sure that you are the last one to say something. Then smile and walk away and continue on with your business. Sometimes it is hard to let things go. Trust me, I know. <figure rend="Deal with Difficult Co Workers in the Work Place Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>The greater the hate you have for someone, the greater the burden is for you to carry the weight. Don't hate on anyone. Just get in there and do your job like you are supposed to. Always be the bigger person in these situations. <figure rend="Deal with Difficult Co Workers in the Work Place Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't get dragged down. The old saying is "misery loves company".</item>
<item>Listen. It's normal to want to just tune people out but, this doesn't stop them. They will think that nobody cares about them and talk and argue more forcefully. Use normal listening techniques.</item>
<item>Don't agree. A person might complain about the boss or something and it's normal to add a nod while talking to them, but just be careful because if the boss finds out you agreed with the rude employee, it could add fuel to the fire.</item>
<item>Cut them off. After all your efforts, you see this people to be hopelessly negative, you need to cut them off. Make sure they aren’t just venting for a few minutes, make sure you weren’t previously encouraging them, make sure they can’t switch to problem solving, and then politely shut them down.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you say rude comments back to the person, you will only cause more trouble. You don't want to be like them, you want to go to work and get the job done then leave.After all, you are there to work, not to make besties.</item></list>
</text>
