<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc28" title="Get the Most Money for a Pet You're Selling" shortTile="money-pet-re-selling" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-05-24" dateModified="2015-05-26" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_the_Most_Money_for_a_Pet_You%27re_Selling" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get the Most Money for a Pet You're Selling</head><p>When you're selling a pet, you'd naturally like to get the most money possible for it. Follow these steps to learn how to get the best deal when selling your pet.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Cleaning Up!</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>You'll have better luck if your pet has a nice personality.  Make sure your pet doesn't bite or show  aggression toward anyone, including other animals. If it does, include that information in your listing to let people know.</item>
<item>Clean your pet. Make sure he/she smells good and has a nice clean coat so the next owner won't have to clean it right away.  You won't get a good price for your pet if it's not clean.
<list type="unordered"><item>get some nice smelling shampoo</item>
<item>fill a bucket with warm water</item>
<item>rub water into the fur/hair</item>
<item>massage your pet slowly with the shampoo</item>
<item>rinse all of the shampoo out with water. If your pet was really dirty, you may need to wash it a second time</item>
<item>dry your pet</item>
<item>Brush the fur of your pet. Let birds groom themselves</item></list></item>
<item>Now, clip your pet's toenails, so when he/she gets to their new house they won't scratch furniture, floors, hands, etc.</item>
<item>If your pet has teeth, try your best to brush them.This is important because the more fully you groom your pet, the more likely you'll be to get a good price </item>
<item>Make sure that your pet is extremely well groomed and and looks perfect before moving on.</item></list>
<head>Make an ad</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take a picture of your pet. Make sure it looks wonderful!</item>
<item>POSTER: Make a poster that explains your pet. Describe how they act around strangers, people walking by, friends, children, any pets, etc. Mention your pet's personality and what activities he likes. Include a picture of your pet in the poster, and list your contact information. Place posters around town.</item>
<item>ONLINE AD:
<list type="unordered"><item>Post an ad on craigslist</item>
<item>You could even create a website for your animal if you or a relative or friend have the skills and knowledge to accomplish that. You could incorporate several nice photos of your pet, and include all of the information mentioned above.</item></list></item></list>
<head>SELLING</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Have a price in mind (which you can advertise if you like), but be ready to negotiate with a serious buyer</item>
<item>Once you've settled on a price, be prepared to send your pet off with his new owner, along with any pet supplies you care to include in the deal</item>
<item>If you had an ad on craigslist, take it down. Remove any posters you put up, and if you started a website, either close it down or change it to another use.</item>
<item>If you find you're feeling lonely without your pet, it may be time to start thinking about getting another pet.</item></list>
</text>
