<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc195" title="Be a Child at Heart As a Teen" shortTile="child-heart-teen" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-12-27" dateModified="2018-09-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Child_at_Heart_As_a_Teen" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Child at Heart As a Teen</head><p>Teens are the busiest people ever. Think about it; after school activities, maintaining decent grades, relationships, spending time with friends, chores, parents, and siblings, it can be too much to handle sometimes! Now, the average child doesn't deal with pretty much any of those things, which is why many teens nowadays want to revert back to those kiddie days, or at least have a child-like heart once more to lighten up life in general.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ditch the "cool person" personality. Little kids hardly care about seeming cool to their friends. Little kids do what they feel most content doing; that's why they're so happy and giggly all the time. They simply don't care what people are thinking about them, unless they're trying to impress that certain someone. <figure rend="Compromise with Your Parents Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make your romantic relationships special. Act as if your current girlfriend/boyfriend is your very first mate. Remember the days when Valentine's Day would roll around and you went all-out for that special someone? Do that for your significant other today. Buy the cheesiest, most child-like romantic card there is in the store for her. Buy him that Nerf gun he always wanted as a kid. Don't make the center of your relationship hooking up or impressing each other. Just be happy with each other, and never go to sleep angry with one another. <figure rend="Deal With Being the Oldest Kid Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Appreciate your family. Little boys and girls love nothing more than their mommies and daddies, so show your mom and dad that you absolutely love them. Make them handmade cards and go spend quality time with them. Even if your relationship with your parents isn't exactly what you would like it to be, you still have the power to change that. <figure rend="Act More Intelligent Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Your friends need your child-like love too. Have play dates with your friends! You don't need to watch Dora together or anything, but have silly, pure fun. Set up a tea party or have a water balloon fight. Share your deepest secrets with them. Run around in your underwear with them! Friends are the absolute perfect people to be child-like with. <figure rend="Avoid Talking in Class Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't be embarrassed about getting goofy or silly. A big part of having a child-like heart is simply not caring what others think.</item>
<item>Spend time with a child. Babysit and actually engage yourself with what the child is doing. Sit down and enjoy a jigsaw puzzle or watch a kiddie program.</item>
<item>Take advantage of summertime; it's the peak time to act like a little kid again.</item>
<item>Dig up old stuff of yours that you owned when you were a little kid.</item>
<item>Don't take life too seriously. Have fun while you can. A good motto to live by is "Young, wild, and free."</item>
<item>Realise that it's completely fine to act/dress quirky.</item>
<item>Spend less time worrying about what you wear and about your hair. Spend more having fun!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't throw temper tantrums like a little kid would.</item>
<item>Don't lighten up too much to the point when you don't take important things, such as college applications, seriously.</item></list>
</text>
