<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc0" title="Do Hairdos for Prom" shortTile="hairdos-prom" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2019-10-21" dateModified="2019-10-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Do_Hairdos_for_Prom" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Do Hairdos for Prom</head>Prom is a milestone event that many people look forward to for years and years. With this big night coming up right around the corner, a lot of effort and planning involved in the process of prom preparation are already beginning! One major component for prom preparation is your hairstyle, and how you get it done. Many people struggle with how they will do their prom hair due to budget restrictions, so resorting to a do-it-yourself hairstyle is often the way to go for many, and is even possible for even those who have minimal experience with hairstyling.
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Deciding Which Hairstyle</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider the prom dress before beginning to look at hairstyles.
<list type="unordered"><item>Consulting fashion and style websites to help guide what hair will best suit the dress is the first major step. Click here  to view an example of a website one may consult to learn more about what hairstyles are compatible with different kinds of dresses.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider the length and volume of hair you have to work with.
<list type="unordered"><item>Not all styles will work with short hair as they may with longer hair, and vice versa. Same goes for thickness of hair, different thicknesses will restrict you to certain styles.</item></list></item>
<item>Ask yourself about the jewelry you may or may not have already thought about.
<list type="unordered"><item>Is your jewelry bold, such as large earrings that need to show? Questions like this will also help you narrow down your hairstyle options to potentially an up-do or something that will show your ears.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Prep Your Hair</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>(Optional) Purchase or create your own hair mask and apply to the hair thoroughly the night before the event.
<list type="unordered"><item>This step is optional but can make a dramatic difference in the appearance of some people's hair if it is damaged or has a lack of moisture .</item></list></item>
<item>Wash your hair.
<list type="unordered"><item>Regardless of whether or not you used the hair mask, washing your hair properly gives you a clean slate for when you style it, without any potential grease or sweat that can make your hair unappealing.</item>
<item>Shampooing the hair thoroughly and lightly conditioning at the ends of the hair will give you the ideal conditions for styling your hair the next day.</item></list></item>
<item>Dry your hair completely before going to sleep.
<list type="unordered"><item>Blowdrying your hair is the recommended option since it not only dries your hair but will also give it some added volume without even having to tease the hair. If you cannot blow dry your hair, air drying will also do.</item>
<item>Make sure the hair is completely dry before sleeping so it does not ruin the preparation for styling.</item></list></item>
<item>Apply the necessary products to hair.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you know your hair gets frizzy or anything along those lines quickly, apply the necessary products before or after drying.</item>
<item>Consult hair care websites such as the one listed here  if you are unsure but interested in any products you may need.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Braided Low-Hanging Bun</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Part your hair to either the left or right side. You should have one side that is more heavy in hair.</item>
<item>Tease your hair.
<list type="unordered"><item>Lift up your hair in small sections at a time and use a small comb to gently tease the side that will fall flat on your head. Refer to this video  for further detail on teasing.</item>
<item>Repeat this step throughout your hair in smaller sections to ensure your hair is going to look uniform in volume.</item></list></item>
<item>Create a loose braid using the hair from the parted side that has the greater amount of hair, excluding some strands for a face frame.
<list type="unordered"><item>Braid along the side of your head until you have reached the back of your head, and secure the braid with a clear hair elastic, so that it does not show up.</item>
<item>Look at your hair, you should now have a small section that is braided and ends in a ponytail, and a section of hair that is untouched and left out.</item></list></item>
<item>Combine the ponytail from the braid and all of the remaining hair into one low ponytail that can be centered, to the left, or right and secure with a hair tie.
<list type="unordered"><item>Using this ponytail you can create a low-hanging bun of your choice. The bun does not have to be a perfect donut bun, but if you prefer to have the perfect donut bun, refer to a separate tutorial of how to create one.</item>
<item>Secure the bun with a hair tie and decorative clips for added support and style, and the look is complete!</item></list></item></list>
<head>The Teased Half-Up</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Section the hair off into two levels.
<list type="unordered"><item>The top section will be from the ears up.</item>
<item>The bottom section of hair will be all of the hair left below the ears.</item></list></item>
<item>Tease the top section of hair thoroughly.
<list type="unordered"><item>As mentioned in the hair style before, tease the hair in smaller sections to ensure that you are getting a better overall voluminous appearance.</item>
<item>Brush your bangs into the half up or leave them out to frame your face.</item>
<item>Secure the top section of your hair with a hair tie or a decorative clip of your choice that can coordinate with your dress.</item></list></item>
<item>Curl the bottom section of your hair.
<list type="unordered"><item>Use a 1" curling wand so the curls aren't too tight but also not too loose. This is also a personal choice. so if you prefer to use a curling wand to give you more loose/ tight curls, you can go ahead and do so.</item></list></item>
<item>Finish the look off with some hair spray to give your hair some added texture and hold, and voila! </item></list>
<p>References</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>[1] <ref target="https://makeuptutorials.com/match-hair-and-dresses-how-to-get-them-right/">https://makeuptutorials.com/match-hair-and-dresses-how-to-get-them-right/</ref></item>
<item>[2] <ref target="https://ilesformula.com/how-to-properly-apply-a-hair-mask-for-best-results/">https://ilesformula.com/how-to-properly-apply-a-hair-mask-for-best-results/</ref></item>
<item>[3] <ref target="https://www.allure.com/gallery/best-products-for-your-hair-type">https://www.allure.com/gallery/best-products-for-your-hair-type</ref></item>
<item>[4] <ref target="https://www.seventeen.com/prom/g2060/prom-hairstyle-inspiration/">https://www.seventeen.com/prom/g2060/prom-hairstyle-inspiration/</ref></item></list>
</text>
