<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc202" title="Have Fun As a Nine‐Year‐Old" shortTile="fun-nineyearold" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-04-23" dateModified="2018-01-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have_Fun_As_a_Nine%E2%80%90Year%E2%80%90Old" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have Fun As a Nine‐Year‐Old</head><p>This article will show you how to have fun at a young age even if you are a boy or a girl.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Having Fun Alone</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Grab a book! The reason books are made is for you to read alone in peace and quiet. If you read a book in noise it won't be that much fun so why not do it now? You can read books that you can finish in one day or books you can finish in one week or books you can finish in one month.</item>
<item>Draw! One of the most alone time activities is to draw. All you need is something to draw with (Pencil, Crayons etc.) and you need something to draw on (Paper, Drawing notebook etc.). Then draw whatever hits your head!</item>
<item>Play video games! Most video games don't need more than one player so all you need is a laptop or a TV and a video game you can go right ahead and play!</item>
<item>Watch TV! One of the most relaxing activities to do while you're alone is to turn your favorite channel or a program like Netflix and have a movie marathon!</item></list>
<head>Having Fun With Friends</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Play truth or dare! If you are a girl truth or dare might be your favorite game but if you are a boy you can still play it. All you need is a brain and minimum two players or you can use the app truth or dare on your phone!</item>
<item>Play Would you rather! This is the best game to play with friends, to play all you need is a brain and minimum two players or you can use the app would you rather on your phone!</item>
<item>Play hide and seek! One of the most common games to play with friends is hiding and seek altho after 2015 this game was not played a lot but it is still a fun game so play it!</item>
<item>Go to the park! Ah going to the park most kids adore playing in the park and feeling the fresh air so if you have a park close to your house go ask your mom and go have fun!</item></list>
<head>Having Fun With Family</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Watch family movies! When you sit down and watch TV with family it helps you bond with your family so go grab blanket warm yourselves up and watch TV!</item>
<item>Play board games! One of the most popular board games is monopoly so go to the mall buy it and start playing!</item>
<item>Play card games! Playing card games make the family happy and make you grow up faster!</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>While playing truth or dare ask truth first if the player doesn't answer your truth tell a dare.</item>
<item>Don't watch movies too long because when your young your brain needs to take a break so make your max TV time of the day 3 - 5 hours.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't go to the park without adult supervision so if you get hurt a grown up will help you.</item>
<item>While playing truth or dare never ask about a really personal truth or your will be suspicious!</item></list>
</text>
