<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc137" title="Go to Nami Island from Seoul" shortTile="go-nami-island-seoul" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2019-01-19" dateModified="2019-05-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Go_to_Nami_Island_from_Seoul" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Go to Nami Island from Seoul</head><p>Nami Island, also known as Namiseom or Namiseom Island, is a tourist spot northeast of Seoul, the capital of South Korea. The small half-moon shaped island is located in the North Han River, and is only  in diameter. Despite its tiny size, Nami Island has become a popular spot for visitors thanks to its picturesque trees, gardens, and European-influenced architecture. Once you travel to Gapyeong Station in the first part of your trip, you can take a bus, ride a taxi, or walk to Nami Island. Or, you can travel directly to Nami Island from Seoul using other travel methods.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Getting to Gapyeong Station</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take the Gyeongchun subway from Yongsan for an inexpensive option. If you’re taking the subway (also called the metro) to Nami Island, you’ll need to get to Gapyeong station first. The Gyeongchun Line takes 90 to 120 minutes to get to Gapyeong Station and costs 2,350 Korean won ($2.08 USD). <figure rend="Go to Nami Island from Seoul Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you’re flying into Incheon International Airport or Gimpo International Airport, you can take the subway from the airport to Yongsan Station.</item>
<item>Rechargeable smart cards, called T-money, are often used to pay for transportation in and around Seoul. These cards can be bought and loaded with credit at the airport, subway stations, and convenience stores for 4,000 won ($3.53).</item></list></item>
<item>Ride the ITX train from Yongsan Station if you’re in a hurry. A train ride to Gapyeong Stations takes about 1 hour. It typically costs around 5,200 won ($4.60) for reserved seating tickets and 4,900 ($4.33) for standing/non-assigned tickets. <figure rend="Go to Nami Island from Seoul Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Check departure times from Yongsan Station to Gapyeong Station on the Korail website. Type “Yongsan” into the Departure field and “Gapyeong” into the Arrive field. You’ll see a list of travel times for the ITX-Cheongchun train.</item>
<item>You can use a Korail pass, which includes free seat reservations, or buy Korail tickets on the KTX website: <ref target="http://www.letskorail.com/ebizbf/EbizBfTicketSearch.do">http://www.letskorail.com/ebizbf/EbizBfTicketSearch.do</ref>.</item></list></item>
<item>Drive to Gapyeong Station in your own vehicle for more freedom. From Seoul, the drive to Gapyeong Station is about . Depending on the route you take and the volume of traffic, your commute might take 1 to 2 hours. <figure rend="Go to Nami Island from Seoul Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Google Maps does not provide driving directions from Seoul to Gapyeong or Nami Island. If you’re staying in Seoul and are unfamiliar with which route to take, it might be helpful to ask a hotel employee, or your host if you’re staying in someone’s home. </item></list></item>
<item>Hire a taxi for shorter travel time to Nami Island. Taxis are usually parked near the information center at Gapyeong Station. Taxi rides range from 4000 won ($3.53) to 5000 won ($4.42) and take 2 to 3 minutes. Taxis are a great option if you want to get to Nami Island more quickly. <figure rend="Go to Nami Island from Seoul Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take the city bus to Nami Island for a less expensive option. A city bus travels from Gapyeong Station to Nami Island about every half hour. You can take the 33-5 or 33-36 city bus. A bus ride costs 1250 Korean won ($1.10) and takes 5 to 10 minutes to arrive in Nami Island. <figure rend="Go to Nami Island from Seoul Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can purchase bus tickets at Gapyeong Station using won or a rechargeable T-money card.</item></list></item>
<item>Walk from Gapyeong Station to Nami Island on foot instead. The walk from Gapyeong to Nami Island takes about 20 to 25 minutes. The distance is slightly less than . You might prefer to take a taxi or bus if the weather is bad, or if you’re traveling in a group with children or older tourists. <figure rend="Go to Nami Island from Seoul Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Traveling Directly from Seoul</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take the Nami Island Direct Shuttle Bus from Seoul for a convenient option. Nami Island operates a shuttle bus service that travels from 3 different pickup points in Seoul: Insadong, Namdaemun, and Myeongdong. A round-trip ticket for an adult costs 15,000 won ($13.25) and 7,500 won ($6.62) for a one-way ticket. <figure rend="Go to Nami Island from Seoul Step 7.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can find information on reserving a shuttle bus on the Nami Island website here: <ref target="https://namisum.com/en/location/">https://namisum.com/en/location/</ref>.</item></list></item>
<item>Hire a driving service for you or your travel group if you want more privacy. If you prefer a private car service instead of public transport, you can hire a car or van to take you to Nami Island from Seoul. A small car can be a comfortable option for groups of 4 or fewer people. A van can provide plenty of room for groups larger than 4 people. <figure rend="Go to Nami Island from Seoul Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>The cost for a driving service will vary based on how many people are in your group and what types of cars are available. A 7-seater van through a company like Indiway, for example, might cost about 120,000 won ($137.90).</item></list></item>
<item>Buy a tour package to plan your transport and itinerary in advance. Some tour companies offer packages to Nami Island that include shuttle bus transport and sightseeing. Tour package prices vary based on which activities you pick, but they might range from 40,000 won ($35.33) to 50,000 won ($44.16). <figure rend="Go to Nami Island from Seoul Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Klook is a popular travel booking service used for touring Nami Island. You can look at an example of one of their tour packages here: <ref target="https://www.klook.com/activity/789-chuncheon-rail-bike-seoul/">https://www.klook.com/activity/789-chuncheon-rail-bike-seoul/</ref>.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Enjoying Nami Island</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Visit the Garden of Morning Calm for picturesque foliage. The Garden of Morning Calm arboretum is one of the most popular tourist spots on Nami Island. There are different festivals held in every season, and the plants and flowers look beautiful no matter what time of the year you visit. <figure rend="Go to Nami Island from Seoul Step 10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Regular adult tickets cost 9,500 won ($8.39). Youth tickets for middle school to high school-aged teens cost 7,000 won ($6.18). Kids of elementary school-age and under cost 6,000 won ($5.30).</item>
<item>The Garden of Morning Calm website doesn’t specify age ranges for their youth or kids tickets, so you might ask for clarification when buying tickets.</item></list></item>
<item>Experience European culture in Petite France. Petite France has flea markets, puppet shows, photo opportunities, and more. Many Korean soap operas, or “K-dramas,” were filmed here. Adult tickets cost 10,000 won ($8.83), teen tickets cost 8,000 won ($7.07), and child tickets cost 6,000 won ($5.30). <figure rend="Go to Nami Island from Seoul Step 11.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Petite France offers some discounts for certain groups like Gapyeong citizens and senior citizens.</item>
<item>Like the Garden of Morning Calm, Petite France separates teens from children based on their educational level, not age. Ask for more information when buying your tickets if you need to.</item></list></item>
<item>Enjoy spicy Korean food like tteok-bokki and dakgalbi. Tteok-bokki is a spicy rice cake and a common Korean street food. You can find tteok-bokki at Yeongajiga Lunch Box. Another popular dish on Nami Island is dakgalbi, a spicy chicken and vegetable stir fry. It’s available at Seomhyanggi. <figure rend="Go to Nami Island from Seoul Step 12.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Nami Island has plenty of other food and drink options, like pizza, sandwiches, and coffee.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
