<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc190" title="Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers)" shortTile="live-amazing-lovely" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-08-25" dateModified="2018-09-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Live_an_Amazing%2C_Lovely_Life_%28Teenagers%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers)</head><p>If you are a teenager and, unfortunately, your life is falling a little short of amazing and lovely, don't worry! Just carefully follow the steps in this article, and, with a little time and effort, your life will be amazing and lovely. Get started at step one below.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Avoid staying alone all the time. Stay alone at times, but not for the whole day, sit with your parents, brother or sister, a friend or a neighbor. If you keep your solidarity, you would start loving it and there comes a time when you'll stop enjoying with people and find happiness in loneliness. Maybe you'll start fearing of meeting them too. It's also important to maintain a balance! Sometimes you need some alone time. <figure rend="Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers) Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't always try to satisfy others. If you didn't do anything wrong but someone is just not friendly enough, don't always try to satisfy them and if they did not get satisfied, don't get upset. Enjoy yourself with your friends so that your life is lovely and amazing. Find friends who can appreciate you for who you are and what you are like now, instead of wanting you to change. <figure rend="Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers) Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Optimistic">optimistic</ref> and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Positive">positive</ref>. Try to comment about good stuff and not complain about bad things. <figure rend="Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers) Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Never let sadness control you. If you are sad, don't just give up to sadness and keep on crying, dance or talk to others or even read something that may help you to be positive again. <figure rend="Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers) Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go out. Go out with your friends for lunch or to the club that will make you feel more excited and happy and get you that amazing, lovely life.</item>
<item>Be yourself. If you have a role model in terms of appearance or even personality, don't be a salve to it. Be yourself too. Don't always be trying to stop being yourself and act like your Role model. Be yourself even if you have a role model. Keep her/his actions in mind, not their exact appearance or personality. <figure rend="Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers) Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Share your knowledge. <figure rend="Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers) Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Fill your day with joyful stuff, like watching tv or chatting, enjoying music and dancing. <figure rend="Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers) Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Change. If you don't like something about yourself, change it and if you can't, just accept yourself (no one is perfect anyway).</item>
<item>Forgive yourself and others. if you made a decision not to be so hyper today or not to talk a lot and you couldn't do it, don't get mad, just forgive yourself. Forgiveness is key to an awesome, lovely life. <figure rend="Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers) Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Organized">Organize</ref>: If you stay in an organized room with your books and clothes organized, this will help you <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Positive">stay positive</ref>. <figure rend="Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers) Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Appreciate little things. For example, your mother doing some pancakes. Feel happy and appreciate it . <figure rend="Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers) Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Always try to look good. Keep your hair clean with your favorite hair style and dress up in a nice way even at home. Get your pretty girly pajamas on. <figure rend="Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers) Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be good in school. Get good grades and study well and if you hate studying just sit at the desk with your snacks an favourite pen, and, maybe, some classic music . Try to let your sister or mother stay with you. Its good to have company while studying. <figure rend="Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers) Step 14.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take risks. if they are fun but not dangerous ones like you may die or get a serious injury. <figure rend="Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers) Step 15.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Never criticize yourself. <figure rend="Live an Amazing, Lovely Life (Teenagers) Step 16.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be yourself, cause everybody is already taken.</item>
<item>Be generous and help others.</item>
<item>Be nice to people even if you don't like them.</item>
<item>Get on with everybody. try to be sociable and friendly.</item>
<item>Try to improve yourself more and more by reading books or articles or even asking for help.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never be negative. Negativity attracts more negativity and so on.</item>
<item>Don't stay a lot with negative people</item>
<item>Avoid being cruel and stop gossiping about other people. stay good and you will feel good.</item>
<item>Don't criticize others. neither face to face nor behind their backs</item></list>
</text>
