<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc179" title="Be a Classy Preteen Girl" shortTile="classy-preteen-girl" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-02-27" dateModified="2019-08-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Classy_Preteen_Girl" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Classy Preteen Girl</head><p>As a preteen, you are no longer a cute little child but you are also not quite old enough to be a glamorous woman, you're stuck in between, so what to be? To be a classy preteen, you need style and sophistication. This article should give you a few pointers into the right direction.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be yourself: If you are like everyone else, you are lacking individuality. Do not let others tell you who to be, do as you wish and follow your instincts. Perhaps find a classy role model to guide your way, be open to opinions and advice, but always remain true to who you are. <figure rend="Look Like a Super Model in Elementary or Middle School Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Think about your style. Do you want to have a classical wardrobe with dresses, frills, and Mary Janes? Or do you want to have a modern elegance to how you dress? It's up to you. <figure rend="Look Like a Super Model in Elementary or Middle School Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Slowly, but surely begin to evolve your wardrobe. Begin with baby doll tops, flats, and other cute things while wearing jeans. Begin to add more skirts if you don't have a lot already or leggings. <figure rend="Look Like a Super Model in Elementary or Middle School Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Own a few good pieces of jewelry, even if you want to borrow your mother's. Wear a charm bracelet or that one special necklace all the time. Avoid wearing cheap, plastic jewelry. <figure rend="Clean Rhinestone Jewelry Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Always keep your room clean. Gradually begin to add décor and ask to change your sheets to something else if you don't like how they look now. You can also add a very light air freshener plug-in to make your room smell nice, if you want. <figure rend="Get Your Little Sister to Be Nice to You Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Slowly become smarter and more mature with your speech. Ease away from slang and say 'please' and 'thank you' whenever necessary <figure rend="Apologize to Your Older Sister Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be nice to everyone you meet. If you look down upon people who can't be as absolutely  perfect as yourself you'll probably be labeled as a snob. Respect your parents and adult peers as well. <figure rend="Look Like a Super Model in Elementary or Middle School Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep up your personal hygiene. Brush your teeth as many times as you need to and suck on breath mints. If you need to, wear deodorant. You can also spritz fragrance on your wrists. <figure rend="Apply Cologne Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Carry a purse. You don't need to take it everywhere. Carry it shopping, to movies, to dinner, etc. You don't need to carry it to school if you're not in middle school yet. <figure rend="Spot a Fake Prada Purse Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you want to wear makeup, then ask your mom, older sister, etc. to help you make it look natural. Clean your face with warm soapy water when you want to take off your makeup.</item>
<item>Stores like TJ Maxx and ROSS have very nice decorations if you're planning to decorate your room to match your personality. They also carry discounted department store fragrances.</item>
<item>Wear light touches of make up. Cream eye shadow , tinted lip balm , blush , mascara and ( if you are allowed ) face powder.</item>
<item>If you can't afford to buy $500+ of new jewelry or a designer purse, then I suggest Borrowing your mothers. Ask first, though. Purses can be found at thrift stores, too, but make sure they aren't damaged.</item>
<item>Don't wear makeup. Just wash your face and wear a little bit of lip gloss. You are beautiful the way you are.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't jump right into this. People may think you are trying to pretend to be rich. It may take several weeks or a few months to change.</item>
<item>Your parents may be concerned you're growing up too fast, so be careful about how you act and how old you are. Ensure them that you're still their little girl.</item>
<item>Don't be something you're not, and don't refer to this guide just to follow the crowd.</item></list>
</text>
