<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc116" title="Make Your Guy Feel Appreciated" shortTile="make-guy-feel-appreciated" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-04-03" dateModified="2017-03-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_Your_Guy_Feel_Appreciated" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Your Guy Feel Appreciated</head><p>Many girls don't know how to make her boyfriend feel appreciated or feel loved. It isn't that hard to make your guy to feel appreciated. Here are some steps to guide you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Buy him something not just on his birthday.
<list type="unordered"><item>The easiest thing to do is buy something for your guy. Buying gift for his birthday is a common thing to do. Try buying him something special and it will make him know that you remember him and I am sure he will feel appreciated.</item>
<item>Don't know what to buy for your guy? Guys love food. So why don't you try buy him snacks that he like? This also will show that you really care about his likes and dislikes.</item>
<item>Besides, you can buy him something that he always want all the time. It doesn't matter if the thing that you want to give is cheap or expensive, as long as he know that you care for him.</item></list></item>
<item>Send him sweet texts when he is busy.
<list type="unordered"><item>Another way is to send him texts or messages that will make him smile from ear to ear. For example, "take care baby, I will always love you" or "have a nice day my dear bae". When he check his phone, he will feel loved because someone care for him even it is just a simple text.</item></list></item>
<item>Sing for him.
<list type="unordered"><item>Singing for him especially the song that you both like can probably made his day. He will feel lucky to have a caring girlfriend like you. Singing doesn't need a good voice. So don't be afraid to sing for him and at the same time, you will be confident with your voice.</item></list></item>
<item>Always compliment him.
<list type="unordered"><item>A guy love it when someone compliment him even it is just a small thing. When he won the third place in a competition, praise him a lot like he is the champion. This also will not make him sad for not getting the first place.</item>
<item>Call him as 'my hero' or 'my man' also will make him feel appreciated and even love you more.</item>
<item>Sending images or quotes about love will make him know that you really love him and care about him.</item>
<item>Don't forget to tell him what you like about himself. If he got a pair of beautiful eyes or a cute nose then go tell him. He will feel like he is the most handsome guy in the world and will feel happy because someone think that he is handsome.</item></list></item>
<item>Never make him feel insecure.
<list type="unordered"><item>Insecurity is good in a new relationship to make him desire you badly. But as the weeks turn to months, avoid making him feel insecure by dating other guys or flirting with someone else when he is around. The more you make him feel insecure, the more he may love you, but deep inside, he would hate the way you make him feel so weak and pained all the time.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make your own sentence instead of taking any song lyrics.</item>
<item>Always look him in the eyes because man love it.</item>
<item>Soccer and game are two things that a guy can't live without. So don't be angry if he needs these two things more than he need you.</item>
<item>Always be yourself even if you are a bit silly or something you think weird to act in front of him.</item>
<item>Treat him like a little baby when he is sick.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never tell him that you miss another guy even the guy you miss is your friend.</item>
<item>Don't praise his bestfriend too much as this might cause jealousy.</item>
<item>Give him time to hang around with his friends and don't be too clingy with him.</item>
<item>Depend on your own. Don't always ask him to treat or buy you something even if you can't afford it.</item></list>
</text>
