<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc95" title="Get a Guy to Hate You" shortTile="guy-hate" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-04-05" dateModified="2019-01-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Get_a_Guy_to_Hate_You" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Get a Guy to Hate You</head><p>Do you hate a guy and want him to hate you? If you're trying to change a guy's mind about you, a mixture of being up front, creating distance, and being a little bit harsh when needed can help make all the difference.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be clear and upfront. Tell him you're not interested in him and walk off. Don't listen to his pleading or anything he says. Tell him you are just not the one for him and that you just don't mesh with his personality. <figure rend="Get a Guy to Hate You Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ignore him, as needed. He will eventually catch on and he should move on.  It may seem harsh but he will keep coming back for more if you don't! <figure rend="Get a Guy to Hate You Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Avoid contact. If you're at school, avoid sitting next to him or becoming his partner in projects. If you're at work, keep interactions short, work-focused and professional. <figure rend="Get a Guy to Hate You Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are assigned to be his partner at school, go up to the teacher and ask nicely for a different one. If your teacher asks why, explain politely that he won't stop bothering you and it annoys you. Don't be pushy or sound stuck-up. That will lower your chances of getting a new partner.</item>
<item>If the teacher refuses, have as little contact with the guy as possible. Speak in short, clipped sentences and don't look at him. If you are a naturally flirty person make sure you don't flirt with him at all.</item></list></item>
<item>Cut off communication. If he has your phone number or any contact with you over the Internet, block him and ignore all phone calls from him. Delete any friend requests he sends you or messages. Totally shut him off. <figure rend="Get a Guy to Hate You Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Tell him you have a boyfriend. If he asks who you are dating, just tell him it doesn't matter. Tell him that you're not interested in him, and he should respect your relationship and your boundaries. <figure rend="Get a Guy to Hate You Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get support from others as needed. If he continues to bother you, ask your parents for advice; they will be a good judge of what steps are necessary to create clear boundaries.  <figure rend="Get a Guy to Hate You Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you're an adult seeking to create distance from someone who isn't respecting your boundaries despite your clear attempts to change his opinion, consider reporting it to the authorities or filing for a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_a_Restraining_Order">restraining order</ref>. Keep in mind these are extreme moves, though, so only pursue them if you feel you are in some kind of danger.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't have a friend go over and tell him you're not interested! Doing that yourself is much better. Tell him calmly you're not interested and you would prefer to be friends. Try to sound relaxed because if you sound tense, he will most likely continue to chase you.</item>
<item>Just block him out.</item>
<item>If he makes a joke and the whole class is laughing, act as if you didn't hear it or don't laugh and instead of that, look at your nails and roll your eyes. If that doesn't work, then start flirting with other boys in front of him and if he joins, walk away.</item>
<item>Get a friend to kiss him, if you can; he may fall in love with her and then he will stop following you around.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You may have to hurt him a teeny bit if he just won't stop. Just don't over hurt him!</item>
<item>Be careful! The guy may be sensitive so don't hurt him.</item>
<item>Try not to make an enemy of him.</item></list>
</text>
