<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc213" title="Be a Good Preteen or Teen Girl" shortTile="good-preteen-teen" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-01-07" dateModified="2017-02-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Good_Preteen_or_Teen_Girl" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Good Preteen or Teen Girl</head><p>If you've decided you want to become a well-liked, helpful person just know that it's not hard to get there! It takes some dedication, but if it's worth it to you, then read on!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Take care of yourself. Stay clean and fresh. If you do, people will get a good impression of you. <figure rend="246_365 When I ruled the world (Explored!).jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Brush your teeth twice a day, using a soft-bristle brush and mint-flavored toothpaste. Not only is it good for your teeth, but it will also keep you from getting a bad breath, and it'll make your smile bright.</item>
<item>Floss. To get a total cleaning of the mouth, you need to floss. Unlike brushing your teeth, you only need to floss once a day.</item>
<item>Use mouthwash. This is optional, but it will make your mouth even cleaner if you do.</item>
<item>Use deodorant.  Body spray can also help. This is especially important to use in the summer because warm weather can induce that smelly sweat!</item>
<item>Using lotion will keep your skin looking smooth, and it will keep it moisturized. If you have acne, use an acne lotion instead. It'll make the acne go away faster.</item>
<item>Wash your face in the morning and before bed with a facial cleanser. This gets rid of the dirt and germs that cause acne.</item></list></item>
<item>Be organized. Organization prevents the stress of looking for misplaced items and not knowing what you need to do in school. <figure rend="White clean bedroom style.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Regularly clean your room. Vacuum/sweep, collect dirty clothes, and pick up random trash. This will make the environment more pleasant for you, and your company.</item>
<item>Make your bed in the morning. This makes a big difference.</item>
<item>Have a place for everything so you'll know where to find it when you need it. Make sure to put it back in its place when it's done!</item>
<item>Throw out useless stuff. Or give it away, recycle it—whatever. It's one less thing cluttering your mind, regardless, and it the process makes organization easier.</item></list></item>
<item>Be a model citizen.
<list type="unordered"><item>Respect everyone, no matter their of race, gender, sexuality, or religion.</item>
<item>When you have been entrusted with a task, be sure to follow through. You made the promise, and people are counting on you to keep it.</item>
<item>Be mature. Your not a little kid anymore. You need to act your age. Try to act older if you can.</item>
<item>When you mess up or do something wrong, admit it.</item>
<item>Look out for situations you can help out with. If you want to get a reputation for being helpful, offer to help as much as possible. Make sure, though, that you aren't patronizing when asking—just a simple "do you need help?" is the best way to ask.</item></list></item>
<item>Get a good education
<list type="unordered"><item>Try your best. Aim to reach your full potential. It may be hard sometimes, but you can do it. If you truly feel you are pushing yourself to hard, then try for something easier, but not to easy.</item>
<item>Tell your parents about your day. When they ask you how your day went, don't just say "Good." Tell them how it really was and why.</item>
<item>Ask your parents and teachers for help WHEN YOU NEED IT! Just don't let them give you all the answers.</item>
<item>Do your homework as soon as you get home, that way, you can have the rest of the day to yourself.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
