<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc88" title="Know if Your Boyfriend Is Gay" shortTile="know-boyfriend-gay" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-02-16" dateModified="2018-04-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Know_if_Your_Boyfriend_Is_Gay" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Know if Your Boyfriend Is Gay</head><p>Have you ever questioned your sexuality? It's normal if you have but what's not normal is when you are still in a relationship with someone when your attracted to the opposite sex. Don't worry these tips will get you noticing</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Don't think just because he doesn't want sex he's gay.
<list type="unordered"><item>Sometimes people tend to think that when men don't want sex there gay. This may not be the case, the man may just want some time.</item></list></item>
<item>How does he look at you compared to others?
<list type="unordered"><item>Lets face it, we all love cheesy relationships where we stare at each other and go all soft but if you feel a man doesn't look at you cute or pay attention to you he may not be into you, although if he looks at boys how he's meant to look at you this may be a warning sign. Maybe its even dodgy if he looks at you the same way as he looks at guys</item></list></item>
<item>Jealousy. Normal and not.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you tend to get jealous then that's normal in life, everyone gets jealous once in a while, but if you feel like your getting jealous over your guy and another guy, then this may be the case your guys gay.</item></list></item>
<item>You're the only female apart for your guy's relatives in his life.
<list type="unordered"><item>This might not always be because your guy's gay, it might just be because he doesn't really socialize with girls.</item>
<item>However, it might be worth considering your guys' sexuality status if he doesn't even want to be around girls all of the time because even if a guy is in a relationship, he would still want to be around girls normally.</item></list></item>
<item>Bum and breasts.
<list type="unordered"><item>All guys love breasts and bums, it's science but if you're around your guy and a really fit, hot girl walks in with massive breasts and a huge bum, fitting a perfect figure but your man doesn't even flinch (he ignores it completely) this isn't because he's gay.</item>
<item>It is scientifically proven that men never show appreciation of other girls figure when there around their girls because the normal issue is that if they did their girl would get pissed and mad at them. </item></list></item>
<item>HE MIGHT JUST BE BISEXUAL!
<list type="unordered"><item>Not even that but he might just be a good friend to men a well as girls.</item>
<item>If your guy thinks he's impressing you he might try to do it to boys as well, stupidly but he could.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't forget it is normal for a guy to change their sex status so don't blame yourself or get to upset! There are over 550,000,000 people on this planet, you'll find someone else for sure</item>
<item>If you are really worried take into consideration that the most likely thing your guy would do if he did change is tell you so you to can break up.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You shouldn't break up with him straight away, even if one of the things I mention that he does if he's gay is n the list because that doesn't mean it's 100% certain it is true.</item>
<item>The normal a guy would do if he did change was tell you so if you are ready for the next steps to talk to him and explain your situation instead of just ending the relationship at once leaving the guy in wonder and in shock and pain</item>
<item>If you do talk to him and he admits he's gay just nicely end the relationship perhaps adding "But of course we could still be friends," This is because there's nothing worse then making a guy feel bad all because he normally turned gay or bisexual. POOR HIM</item></list>
</text>
