<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc209" title="Be Smart in School (Girls)" shortTile="smart-school-girls" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-05-02" dateModified="2019-09-20" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_Smart_in_School_%28Girls%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Smart in School (Girls)</head>Have you always been the one with a low score on every subject? Well, if you have or if you want to improve your grades and test scores then read on from step one below to be smarter in school.
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do your homework. Most people don't like getting homework, but it has an important purpose. Homework helps you review a lesson while the information is still fresh in your mind. It also lets your teacher know if you understand the concepts or need more help.  <figure rend="Be Smart in School (Girls) Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take notes in every class. Note-taking is a lot of work, but in the long run, it pays off. Writing stuff down in and of itself helps you remember it better. And when the test rolls around, you'll have plenty of material to study from. <figure rend="Take Better Notes Step 04.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Focus on vocabulary when taking notes. Knowing the definitions of different terms in Science or Language Arts is always helpful. Sometimes teachers might give you extra credit, merits or points.</item></list></item>
<item>Read every night. Reading is helpful for people of all ages: it helps you learn vocabulary, spelling, and grammar while expanding your mind to new ideas. Challenge yourself to read a variety of materials such as classics, non-fiction, autobiographies and things outside typical school reading lists. If your school has a library, you should take some time at lunch or break to go there and just read some books to exercise your mind before class. <figure rend="Be Smart in School (Girls) Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Study your textbook and notes. This is especially important for any subject you have a difficult time with. Bring your textbook home at night and go over previous lessons for the test (and maybe the next lesson, as well). If you study every night, you'll be fully ready for any test you face.  <figure rend="Be Smart in School (Girls) Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use flash cards. Flash cards are useful for geography, spelling, vocabulary, math, etc. Have someone quiz you or use them to quiz yourself. That way, you can build up your knowledge so it will stay with you. <figure rend="Be Smart in School (Girls) Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Bring your reading book home to study. If you need to write a book report or essay on it later on, it will be much easier if you write down notes while reading. Post-it notes are helpful for marking important pages for later reference.  <figure rend="Be Smart in School (Girls) Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do further research. After you get home from school and finish your normal homework, why not look into what you learned during the day? Look for newspaper or online articles, essays, and informational books. Look for worksheets or quizzes as well. Taking some notes is a good idea. <figure rend="Collect Old Rare Books Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to learn something new every day. For instance, you could research a different math term every day, or a new vocabulary word. Try subscribing to a "word per day" website (one that suits your age group). That way you will receive a new word on Twitter or through email every day.</item>
<item>Try to research something for each class; for instance, you could research dichotomous keys for science and composers for music. For Literature, you could study poets, and for History, you could research different historical periods.</item></list></item>
<item>Keep yourself informed on current events. Read the newspaper and watch the news. This will be helpful in any Politics or Social Studies classes, and it will also help you gain a deeper understanding of the world we live in.  <figure rend="Be Smart in School (Girls) Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Join extracurricular clubs. Studious clubs such as debate, journalism, chess, and math will put you in an academic mindset. They are also a great way to meet and befriend like-minded individuals who can teach you lots of new things.  <figure rend="Start a Youth Drama Team Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Playing an instrument might not have socializing involved, but it will also help expand your mind.</item></list></item>
<item>Keep a planner. Write down your assignments, due dates, test dates, and so on. That way you can stay organized and won't have to worry about forgetting anything. <figure rend="Be Smart in School (Girls) Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be on good terms with your teacher. Teachers are there to help you. Be nice and respectful to your teacher. Show them that you're serious about your education: pay attention in class, raise your hand, ask questions when you're confused, and so on. Ask them if there's anything you should work on. And if you need help, ask them for it. <figure rend="Be Smart in School (Girls) Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Write stories or keep a diary in your spare time. This will help you practice grammar, syntax, and creative writing in general. If you dedicate time to writing, your teachers <hi rend="italic">will</hi> notice.  <figure rend="Write a Novel As a Kid Step 08.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Do some science experiments at home and show your teacher. Examples include a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_a_Volcano">paper-mache volcano</ref>, a sundial, or salt crystals. This will impress them (and maybe earn you some extra credit).  <figure rend="Build a DNA Model Step 17.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep it balanced! You need a social life and some fun to be healthy and happy. Everyone needs a break once in a while. Hang out with your friends and spend quality time with your family. Being smart doesn't mean you can't have fun. <figure rend="Be Smart in School (Girls) Step 18.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't worry about getting into a romantic relationship. You'll have plenty of time for that in college and beyond; at a younger age, romance tends to distract and cause drama. Give yourself time to grow and mature. Also, you can get in to break-ups and that can sometimes lower your grades.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Healthy">Be healthy</ref>, as it can really improve your grades. Eat nutritiously and have three meals a day.</item>
<item>Try to get 8-10 hours of sleep every night. The adequate rest will help you stay focused and energized during the day.</item>
<item>Don't try and force this. Forcing will only make you crumble and fall apart. You will grow thinking that you have to be perfect which is unhealthy for your brain's growth.</item>
<item>If you want to remember some information, say it several times before you sleep. It's very helpful to do that.</item>
<item>Do not stop reading books, even if reading isn't really your thing. Reading develops the mind, and it helps your language skills.</item>
<item>If you have to work hard at something, don't be discouraged! Some subjects come easier to one person, while another has to work harder at it. Staying calm and focused is the key.</item>
<item>Do some extracurricular activities that will help you to increase your knowledge.</item>
<item>Try and go to tutoring. Your teacher can help you if you're struggling.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are being bullied, you should tell your parents or your teachers.</item>
<item>If you struggle, don't worry. Just ask an adult to help you.</item>
<item>If your teacher is mean, just pay attention in class and do your work. You could also read <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Deal_With_a_Mean_Teacher">How to Deal With a Mean Teacher</ref></item></list>
</text>
