<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc93" title="April Fool Your Girlfriend" shortTile="april-fool-girlfriend" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-07-30" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/April_Fool_Your_Girlfriend" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>April Fool Your Girlfriend</head><p>April Fools is the day for pranking those near and dear to you, including your girlfriend. A good April Fools prank will be surprising, playful, and a little silly. It should make the person laugh and give them a mild scare. You can April Fool your girlfriend by doing a prank in her home. You can also make prank items to give to her like a fake parking ticket, a fake dessert, or even a fake proposal.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Pulling a Prank in Your Girlfriend’s Home</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Fill her room with balloons. An easy, fun prank is to blow up a bunch of balloons and fill her room with them. Do this when she is out at work or over at a friend’s house. Make sure the balloons fill the room completely. Shut the door after you have filled the room so she is in for a fun surprise when she opens her bedroom door. <figure rend="Create-a-Paris-Chic-Teen-Bedroom-Step-5-Version-2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Go for balloons in your girlfriend’s favorite color to add something a little special to the prank.</item></list></item>
<item>Cover her room in Post-It notes. Another good way to prank her space is to cover her room in bright post it notes from top to bottom. Layer the Post-It notes all over her furniture, the walls, and the windows in her room. Put Post-Its on her computer and other items. <figure rend="Study Well Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do this when she is away for the night or out of town. That way, when she comes home, she’ll be in for a fun surprise.</item></list></item>
<item>Wrap her belongings in tin foil. Tin foil is a cheap, easy way to pull a prank on your girlfriend. Wrap all the items in her bedroom in tin foil. Put tin foil all over the items in her bathroom or her living room. Choose a room she uses often and make it harder for her to access by using tin foil. <figure rend="Make a Prison Lighter Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you have the time and energy, wrap her belongings in several layers of tin foil. This will make it harder for her to unwrap each item.</item></list></item>
<item>Place toast in her shower. Make her shower nice and “toasty” by placing slices of toast in her shower. Position freshly toasted slices of bread in her bathtub. Then, wait for her reaction when she goes to take a shower or a bath. <figure rend="Clean-a-Bathtub-Step-7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Giving Her Prank Items</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Give her a fake parking ticket. Use a real parking ticket as a template and change it to her name. Make the ticket very expensive. Include a note on what the ticket is for and make it seem plausible, such as when she ran a red light a few days ago. <figure rend="Figure-Out-Whether-or-Not-It's-a-Date-Step-16.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can then mail the ticket to her. Or you can pretend to find the ticket in the mail and give it to her that way.</item>
<item>Make sure you tell your girlfriend that the ticket is a prank and not real, especially if she seems very worried. Say to her, "April Fools!" and rip up the fake ticket.</item></list></item>
<item>Put mayonnaise in her toothpaste. Squeeze out her toothpaste and replace it with mayonnaise. Do this when she is sleeping or away for the day. Then, watch as she tries to brush her teeth with mayonnaise instead of toothpaste in the morning. <figure rend="Get-Rid-of-a-Pimple-Using-Toothpaste-Step-4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make fake Oreos. Scrape off the cream in Oreos and replace it with toothpaste. Then, give your girlfriend a box of the fake Oreos and watch her eat one. <figure rend="Eat-Fast-Step-19.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be careful that she does not eat a lot of the fake Oreo, as eating a lot of toothpaste can make her sick.</item></list></item>
<item>Send her a prank text message. When she sends you a text, respond with a message that says, “This number has been disconnected. Please contact your provider.” You can also respond with a message like, “Who dis?” or “I don’t have this number in my contacts, sorry!” <figure rend="Discuss-Your-Lesbian-or-Bisexual-Interest-in-a-Friend-Step-4-Version-3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your girlfriend seems very confused by the message, you can send her a text that says "April Fools!" so she knows you are joking.</item></list></item>
<item>Give her a glitter bomb. Glitter bombs can be made by filling an envelope with glitter. Then, give her the envelope so she is showered in glitter. <figure rend="Make a Glitter Bomb Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not throw the glitter bomb at her, as this can result in injury.</item></list></item>
<item>Create a fake proposal. Put a ring pop in a ring box and wrap it with a bow. Then, give it to your girlfriend as a gift. Watch her reaction as she pulls out the ring pop, rather than an actual engagement ring. <figure rend="Buy-a-Promise-Ring-Step-20.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This prank can be intense and should only be done if your girlfriend has a very good sense of humor. She may get upset at you for this type of prank, so do it at your own risk.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
