<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc217" title="Enjoy Being 11" shortTile="enjoy-being-" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-09-27" dateModified="2018-05-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Enjoy_Being_11" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Enjoy Being 11</head><p>So you're 11. Being 11 is a great thing, and you only get to be 11 for one year.  A lot will change in a year. Most 11 year olds have no idea how special being 11 is. It can be very fun, challenging, and scary. Scroll down for the tips!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Don't do anything stupid. You're 11, and it's not safe to do anything that you're not supposed to be doing. Don't skip school, don't bully others, and try not to get into too much trouble. If you do something stupid, you will regret it later. <figure rend="Enjoy Being 11 Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Know that some days are good and some are bad. Accept that there are going to be those days where you get super embarrassed, days where you'll get yelled at by a mean teacher, and days that you'll forget something really important. This is okay, it happens to everyone. Just because you weren't awesome today, doesn't mean that you can't be awesome tomorrow. <figure rend="Enjoy Being 11 Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Smile. Smiling will automatically make you and everyone around you 10x happier. Smiling is a great way to cheer someone up. You never know what could be on someone's mind or what they've gone through, so smile as much as possible and mean it. <figure rend="Enjoy Being 11 Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make friends. Friends are really important, because they are there to cheer you up, support you, laugh with you, play with you, and help you enjoy every second of being 11 years old. Don't be afraid to talk to people and socialize! A simple hello will start a conversation. <figure rend="Enjoy Being 11 Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try hard at school. School is very important, since it's your future and education. Your education is very important, because it can affect your whole future, and it is just an absolute need in life. Pay attention in class and always do your homework. Try! Study hard for tests, and be organized. Make school come first no matter what. <figure rend="Enjoy Being 11 Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Strive for your goals. If you have a chance that's not going to be there forever and you sort of want to strive for but are not too sure, then strive for it. Goals are meant to be achieved, and once you've achieved them, you'll be much, much happier. <figure rend="Enjoy Being 11 Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Live life to the fullest! Just have fun and enjoy life. Once you hit 11, you will start to grow up super fast, and you'll start to lose track of time. Just take the chance when you can, be brave, make your friends, and don't worry! <figure rend="Enjoy Being 11 Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Experiment with your hair and clothes with your parents' permission.</item>
<item>Try to always get a good night's rest.</item>
<item>Stand up for yourself and be tough.</item>
<item>Don't try to imitate bad influences.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't try to grow up too fast, because life will get more complicated quite soon.</item></list>
</text>
