<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc17" title="Prepare for a Pet" shortTile="prepare-pet" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-04-25" dateModified="2018-04-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Prepare_for_a_Pet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prepare for a Pet</head><p>Your'e so excited! A new addition is coming to your family!!!! A new pet!!! It can be hard to decide whats best for your pet, and how to prepare for the new member. This article will help you with preparing. Lets get started!!!!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>First, you need to make sure you have the budget!!! Money is very important for taking care of something. You'll also need to do some research. For example, if you are getting a puppy then you want to make sure that you are up for the challenge of raising a puppy. When you do your research be sure to make a list of the neceseties that the animal will need. The things you will need are listed down below in the following:*What food and water types, and setup*How big the living space needs to be for the pet*How much attention the animal needs*The responsibilities such as poop, pee, cleaning, medication for your pet, etc.</item>
<item>Second, you need to be sure that the people around you are comfortable with you having this sort of pet. Some people around you may have allergies or fears that are essential to know if you are going to have an animal. If you are still living with your parents/guardian(s) then be sure to ask them before taking this big step. Here is a list of people you should probably talk to about the pet: Landlords, Room mates, Parents/guardian(s), etc. You basically just want to ask anyone who owns your living space, or somehow contributes to your soon to be pet.</item>
<item>Third, buy the necessary things for the pet. Go to your local Petsmart © or Pet-co © and sure enough what you'll need will be there. If for some reason it's not,go to target or any nearby supermarket and grab it. Be sure to get ALL of the items your pet needs. While your at it, you might want to get the cleaning supplies for the type of animal your'e getting. If you need any help or have any questions, ask a nearby manager.</item>
<item>The fourth step is the best step of all!!! You get to go get your new pet!!!! If you are buying your pet from somebody online, make sure that the pictures and description look legit. Also double check the adress on the post/website before you drive/walk there. If you are buying your pet from a pet store, then all you need to do is walk in the store with your money on you. One pet ay give you a bad vibe, while an other may make you smile. Always go with your first instinct. Last of all, have fun with your new furry (or in some cases not so furry) Friend(s)!!!!:)</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You might want to add 50 dollars or so onto your original budget. You never know if the food and cage could cost an extra $50.</item>
<item>NEVER abandon your pet. Give it to someone who you know will love and take care of your pet</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>NEVER abandon your pet. Give it to someone who you know will love and take care of your pet</item></list>
</text>
