<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc99" title="Be the Bad Boy and Still Get the Girl" shortTile="bad-boy-still-girl" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-01-01" dateModified="2017-06-17" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_the_Bad_Boy_and_Still_Get_the_Girl" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be the Bad Boy and Still Get the Girl</head>
<p>Is your crush into "bad boys", and you are a "nice guy"? It's 2016, which means there will be a new you. Just follow these steps and you will win over the girl. These steps can also get you out of the friend zone or can help you <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Win_a_Girl's_Heart">win her</ref> when she already rejected you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Bad Boy Looks</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Sort your hair out. Start with the thing that your crush will look at the most, your hair, apparently. Bad boys don't get that rock band hairstyles crap. Just get something simple such as a buzz cut, taper, or a mohawk. If you have a shaved head, stick to it.
<list type="unordered"><item>Ask the girl herself how you should wear your hair. That's very bad boy.... because it shows that you care about what she think and lack your indenty and can't make even simple decisions. A girl values her opinions, remember that, if you think it is important.</item>
<item>Get a haircut that fits you. You shouldn't just go into a barber shop and get a haircut that you will regret getting in the end. Both bad boys and nice guys be themselves.</item></list></item>
<item>Stay healthy. Girls look for guys who can protect them emotionally, but also physically. Exercising and eating salads will make you just the guy she needs. But, girls don't want an extremely strong boyfriend. Girls want to feel special, and a guy who cares more about their muscles than her, that's a turn-off. Exercise at least three-four times a day, but never too much.</item>
<item>Look like a winner. Nice Guys believe that they can wear sweaters and jeans to impress girls. That's BS. Bad boys wear skinny jeans and black jackets and matching colors. Matching colors include red and white, red and black, green and white, black and yellow, etc. Red and blue may be a good match, but not a "Bad Boy" match. Also wear Lebron shoes, Nikes, and Jordans. They show that you have a taste. Caps also work too. But, if you are in school and you have to wear your uniform, make an effort to add something in your uniform without breaking the rules.</item></list>
<head>Speaking Like a Bad Boy</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Use bad boy language. Nice Guys use great words to describe a girl such as "pretty" and "radiant", and a Bad Boy can use those words too. But girls who are into Bad Boys are used to words such as "on fleek/point" or "lit". But if you're looking for humor, you could probably say a joke followed up by "bout a week ago". This came from Bobby Shmurda's hit rap, which is still popular.  So try you're best to use these words as much as possible, and she'll be impressed.</item></list>
<head>Bad Boy Flirting</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>If you just started to become a bad boy, you would have to break the touch barrier by doing simple things such as stroking your crush's hair or helping her put on her coat. But the hair would be better to start off with. After you play or stroke her hair, you could compliment her on it. But don't mess it up, just a fast stroke and then done. But don't bounce (leave) after you touch her, that's just creepy.</item>
<item>Compliment her correctly. Bad boys compliment girls as well, but never too much. Just say "you look nice" or "hey beautiful". But the problem is, avoid the awkwardness. If she doesn't appreciate the compliment, that doesn't mean she doesn't appreciate you. Girls will never get tired of compliments. But the thing is, never over-compliment. You're making her bring back out the Nice Guy in you. One or two compliments and then you're done.</item>
<item>Avoid being needy or too available. You want to be with her, but Bad Boys try their best to make sure that the girl pursues them as much as they pursue them. Also, don't push things quickly into a relationship. Like Nice Guys, you would also have to start out in a friendship, but don't act too much of a friend. Don't always agree with her or help her out. As hard as a may sound, you can't always be there for her, even when she knows you like her. She would probably see that and take advantage of you.</item>
<item>Do not be too desperate. Hang out with your friends and let her hang out with her friends. But, there comes times where you'd have to go out of your own way for her. If you see someone annoying her, just look at them or tell them to "shut up". If you're lucky, you two might say the same thing at the same time. For example, if you two both tell them to shut up at the same time, which could be kinda funny. But after that, you two could socialize.</item>
<item>Know your boundaries. Girls could tell when a guy still likes them, and you don't want to show that off too much. Know when you've talked about something with her too much, know when you've <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Flirt">flirted</ref> too much, and most importantly, know when to talk to her or not. Girls don't feel like talking when they are sad or angry, so make them feel calm. Also, never talk to a girl when she is talking to her friends. She will either pretend she can't see or hear you or tell you to shut up.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Girls do like tough guys. Tough doesn't mean fighting people when they don't deserve it, it means persistence. As desperate as it sounds trying to ask her out again, she will be impressed by your persistence.</item>
<item>Bad Boys put their opinions first. Your crush also has to be interested in you if you want to get into a relationship. Remain a bit of mystery and have your own needs. Both Nice Guys and Bad Boys try to make girls feel accepted in the world, but Nice Guys try to do that every time.</item>
<item>Bad Boys have to be social and popular. Girls would not be interested in you if your name isn't "known".</item>
<item>Talk to her once a day. Avoiding or ignoring a girl says that you are not interested in her anymore.</item></list>
</text>
