<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc157" title="Coordinate an Office Potluck" shortTile="coordinate-office" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-04-24" dateModified="2017-07-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Coordinate_an_Office_Potluck" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Coordinate an Office Potluck</head><p>Office potlucks are a great way to get to know your coworkers and help with office morale.  It also gives everyone a chance to share a favorite dish or just a meal with their coworkers without having to spend a ton of money to go to dinner or to a bar for drinks.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide whether you want your potluck to have a theme. Examples include: Breakfast potluck, Mexican potluck, baked potato bar, etc.</item>
<item>Make sure to check if there are any coworkers with allergies or dietary restrictions. Examples:  peanut/tree nut allergy, lactose intolerant, gluten free, vegetarian, etc.</item>
<item>Create a sign up sheet. List the potluck theme at the top and leave space for your coworkers to sign up!  Also, don't forget to list the dietary restrictions if there are any. 
<list type="unordered"><item>Some people may be picky about who knows about any allergies so you can do a general statement such as "We do have a peanut allergy please make sure all dishes are Peanut free!" instead of listing the person who has the allergy!</item></list></item>
<item>Issue reminders for what people agreed to bring, especially if the sign up sheet was put up a month or two in advance.  It would be a good idea to send out a reminder at least a week before the potluck so everyone will have time to purchase their ingredients and get everything made.</item>
<item>Have someone in the kitchen to set up the potluck on the day.  (This can be a category on the sign up sheet in case there is someone who is not able to make a dish who wants to participate.) Have them go in about an hour or so before the potluck is due to start (or an hour or so before lunch time) and heat up anything that needs it and set everything out on the table or counter.</item>
<item>Designate to someone to clean up.  (This can also be a category on the sign up sheet.) They will be in charge of putting away any left overs, doing the dishes, and wiping down the kitchen.</item>
<item>Enjoy and have fun!  At this point see if anyone would like to make the potluck a regular event.  Many companies have monthly potlucks.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>List categories on the sign up sheet as suggestions as well as blank spaces for people to list their own dish.</item>
<item>Make a limited amount of spaces for each category.  For example list desserts with 3 or 4 bullet points or lines under it for people to sign up on.  You don't want to end up with 25 desserts and 1 main dish!  (Unless it is a dessert themed potluck!)</item>
<item>Make sure to add paper plates, cups, drinks, and ice to the list.  In my experience these are the most forgotten items.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>It's important to take note of any allergies or diet restrictions.  You are trying to bring your office together, you do not want to make someone feel left out because they cannot eat anything that was brought in!</item>
<item>If there is someone who forgot and added an ingredient that cannot be consumed by someone or one or two dishes (in the case of a vegetarian or vegan) have a product in it that someone cannot or will not eat please mark it clearly.</item>
<item>Bring both caffeinated and decaffeinated beverages.</item></list>
</text>
