<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc141" title="Meet Locals While Traveling" shortTile="meet-locals-traveling" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-01-08" dateModified="2019-10-07" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Meet_Locals_While_Traveling" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Meet Locals While Traveling</head><p>When traveling abroad or even domestically, numerous opportunities abound for meeting the local residents of your destination. Getting to know these people can afford a unique and personal experience that can become the highlight of your trip. This article offers steps on how to meet locals while traveling.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Chat with locals online. Dozens of instant messaging websites and traveler forums allow you to connect with people who live where you will be visiting. Don't be hesitant to ask them for suggestions and recommendations on what to visit, where to travel, and where any locally popular attractions are located. This will let you get a sense of how the people in the area really live. <figure rend="Meet Locals While Traveling Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Talk to people on your way. On the plane, train, cruise, or bus ride to your destination, try <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Talk_to_Someone_You've_Never_Met">starting a conversation</ref> with someone. Chances are you may find a person native to the area or who knows someone that lives there. <figure rend="Meet Locals While Traveling Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Ask_a_Question_Intelligently">Ask questions</ref>. Upon arriving at your destination, ask the staff or concierge at your hotel, resort, or lodge where the locals hang out. You may receive a much more personalized answer than a traditional guidebook can provide. <figure rend="Meet Locals While Traveling Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Visit smaller towns. While most tourists spend much of their trip exploring big cities, schedule a day or two to stop in smaller towns or suburbs outside the city where more locals are usually found. Strike up a conversation with a friendly looking stranger at a restaurant or store. <figure rend="Meet Locals While Traveling Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Polite">Be polite</ref>. Kindness goes a long way, especially from tourists visiting a foreign destination. Make sure to research the customs, traditions, and cultures of the people you'll be interacting with, and always greet people in a friendly manner or you risk insulting them. <figure rend="Meet Locals While Traveling Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use community-marketplace platforms. Various travel communities allow you to use services that locals provide, including accommodation, dining experiences and transport. These allow you to immerse yourself into the local culture, and see their lifestyles from a first-hand perspective. <figure rend="Meet Locals While Traveling Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Repay locals' efforts with gratitude. Be a friend to them and let them ask about you. <figure rend="Meet Locals While Traveling Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some tour companies offer "off-the-beaten-path" excursions that take tourists to sites and attractions most people may not visit, such as local festivals and outskirt towns. This is an excellent way to get to interact with locals in an environment much less fast paced than a sprawling urban metropolis.</item>
<item>If being hosted by a local family for a traditional meal or another visit, always show gratitude for their hospitality and thank them before leaving. It may be wise to bring a small gift or something that can contribute to a meal as a nice gesture.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid offending the locals. Many Western behaviors that are acceptable to a foreigner may be viewed much differently in another country, and occasionally will not go ignored. If you're invited to attend a meal at a local's home and you don't like what is being served, simply pass when the dish is offered and do not voice your opinion.</item></list>
</text>
