<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc70" title="Explore Theories and Live Beyond Them" shortTile="explore-theories" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-07-17" dateModified="2016-06-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Explore_Theories_and_Live_Beyond_Them" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Explore Theories and Live Beyond Them</head><p>Exploring different theories of belief and existence is something everyone does at some point. The problem is that there are so many - how do you make the right belief choices, live them out, and go beyond them? Spend time exploring these theories on a regular basis will help you to clarify your own beliefs and how you should behave as a result.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider what your own point of views are and what you believe. Write these down and look at how they influence your way of thinking and acting. These might be theories on anything, such as why we are here, how we are here, what is right and what is wrong and so on. <figure rend="Explore Theories and Live Beyond Them Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider how you got them. Did you get them from your education, from your relatives, friends or mentors. Did you get them from mainstream society or are they your own theories? <figure rend="Explore Theories and Live Beyond Them Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Examine alternative points of view to your own. If you have ever had someone else disagree, or offer an alternative idea to one of your own, examine that one and why you select your own above another persons. <figure rend="Explore Theories and Live Beyond Them Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to see if the other persons ideas are valid, sometimes one person is right and one is wrong, but sometimes both can have different but valid points of view and sometimes theories are right in some conditions, and wrong in others.</item></list></item>
<item>Go back to your ideas first and compare the two. Try not to have any bias or prejudice to another persons ideas or your own, but just see how ideas give you and another person advantages and disadvantages. <figure rend="Explore Theories and Live Beyond Them Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Explore if any theories are bullet proof. Many theories or views often are relevant in some cases, but not relevant in others and that an opposite idea might have merit. Look for any points of view that are applicable in every case, how rare are they? <figure rend="Explore Theories and Live Beyond Them Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you can find some, explore why they are 100% consistent and if they have an opposite. If you can find none, Try to find out why that it is by looking a little deeper and asking more questions.</item></list></item>
<item>Explore the current relevancy to points of view. Ask other people their ideas and examine wisdom and culture generally. Is there some ideas that become redundant in changes of technology? <figure rend="Explore Theories and Live Beyond Them Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Some examples of old ideas might be that the world is flat, or that diseases are caused by magic. By sailing around the world it was shown the idea of a flat world was incorrect and today is no longer relevant. In the same way, it wasn't until the microscope was invented to see viruses and bacteria that cause many illnesses that we know that its not spells and curses.</item></list></item>
<item>Try to apply different ideas to your own, they might seem bizarre and totally foreign, but see if they work and have any value. <figure rend="Explore Theories and Live Beyond Them Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Consider that views and ideas are just part of the thing we call an identity and culture. As well as how we perceive and remember events and the strength of how we feel and react to events and impulses. <figure rend="Explore Theories and Live Beyond Them Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Consider this analogy. A persons mind is like the room we live in, ideas and beliefs are like the wallpaper or paint we put up to personalize our room. Is it possible that with so much wallpaper we have papered or painted over the windows and doorways so we cannot see beyond our own mindset?</item></list></item>
<item>Examine if there are in the world many people who go through life without seeing beyond their own ideas and if that limits them or harms them and others. Are you or other people prisoners in a gilded cage of ideas and beliefs? <figure rend="Explore Theories and Live Beyond Them Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>De-clutter your own mind. If you feel that you are a prisoner, start to let go of some ideas and see if you can live without them. You don't have to abandon them all, although try to see if it is possible to live without them entirely and if that does in fact set you free. <figure rend="Explore Theories and Live Beyond Them Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If that gives you benefit or well-being, tear down some of that wallpaper and let the light in.</item>
<item>If that makes you feel nervous, Try to see why. Is there a loyalty to that theory, or something you identify with? Or are you fond of a particular idea above what is really happening?</item></list></item>
<item>Consider the relevance of this analogy: A person can know some things as real and true, but if they explore what they don't know and cannot find answers, they should not be ashamed to say they don't know. <figure rend="Explore Theories and Live Beyond Them Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>There is a true honesty in admitting you don't know the things you don't rather than making up something in order to be certain. If things change and it is possible for the truth to be known, then a truly honest person would not be ashamed to examine it and accept it.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider finally that there are not many truths, but one. That things are true or that they aren't. What is true does not belong to anyone, any society or any idea, but is relevant to everyone, anywhere. Try to find the truth that applies to everyone beyond ideas, theories and cultures and how that can help yourself and other people. <figure rend="Explore Theories and Live Beyond Them Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be wary of trying to change other people, or doing this as an excuse to change people, no one can truly change another, we can only change ourselves.</item></list>
</text>
