<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc201" title="Do the Right Thing when Nobody Else Is (Teens)" shortTile="right-thing-nobody" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-05-25" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Do_the_Right_Thing_when_Nobody_Else_Is_%28Teens%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Do the Right Thing when Nobody Else Is (Teens)</head><p>When you feel like everybody is doing the wrong thing, you might feel the temptation to join in. This is a normal feeling especially for those trying to fit in. However, you can get into a world of trouble by going along with the crowd, so everyone once in a while, you need to make waves and do the right thing.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>When you say no, be confident. Many people can detect if your voice is lacking confidence and will then give you push back, using peer pressure for bad. However, if you sound confident, the other person will most likely not push the issue any further. You can look confident by standing up straight and using a firm voice.</item>
<item>When people are bullying someone or gossiping about them, say something about it. Wouldn't you like them to say something if they were hearing gossip about you? You can start by telling the victim and telling the perpetrators to cut it out. If the bullies decide to continue bullying, don't give up! Get a trusted adult involved in the situation. You will be happy that you did!</item>
<item>If you are dared to do something that you know to be wrong, don't let your peers bully you into doing it by telling you that you have to. You do not have to and if it is something that will physically or emotionally harm you or somebody else, do not do it. If you are in the courtroom and you tell the judge that you only did the crime because you were dared to, he will laugh at you then sentence you the same way he would had you not been dared.</item>
<item>Don't expect an award for doing what is right. It simply will not happen, so don't get your hopes up. Your award will be the satisfaction that you feel in knowing that you did the right thing.</item>
<item>Listen to your parents. If there is a party and your parents say that you are not allowed to go, leave it at that. They are preventing you from being put into a compromising situation. Whatever you do, do not sneak out. There are many reasons why it is dangerous, but one of the many is that no one knows where you are and that could result in injury or kidnapping if not worse.</item>
<item>If you become the new focus of the bullying, talk to a parent or another trusted adult. Bullying is never okay, no matter who is doing the bullying. Even if you become the bully(s) new focus, don't stop what you are doing. This just means that you are making a difference in the world, even if it is only a little difference.</item>
<item>Cyberbullying is not okay even though it is not in person! If someone is cyberbullying you or someone else, tell a moderator or report them. Most social media sites have a report button for just this sort of thing and it is always anonymous so don't be afraid of repercussions. Never partake in cyberbullying! Just watching cyberbullying without doing anything makes you an active participant in the bullying!</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Stand up for the underdog when nobody else is. Who knows when they might stand up for you!</item>
<item>Don't let teasing bother you if you are doing the right thing, they are just trying to get you to go along with the crowd.</item>
<item>Exuding confidence is very helpful in these situations.</item>
<item>Don't tease someone to fit in!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Staying away from truth or dare may help you in the long run!</item></list>
</text>
