<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc82" title="Be Straight Forward With Guys" shortTile="straight-forward" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-07-02" dateModified="2018-10-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_Straight_Forward_With_Guys" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Straight Forward With Guys</head><p>Ladies, you may have come to realize that men can be completely oblivious at times. Has it ever occurred to you that you are allowed to be the straight forward one in this case? Are you head over heels for someone and they just have no clue? You've come to the right place.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>First, you should probably have an intense discussion with yourself before you go through with this. Men tend to have a lot of pride and at times are incredibly stubborn. So if the guy you're interested in is oblivious as well as has a "it's a man's world" attitude, maybe they're not the one for you if you're considering being very 'modern century' with them. <figure rend="Be Straight Forward Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Once you've decided that this guy is really worth it, then consider this: has this guy noticed any of your small hints whatsoever? If he hasn't then i recommend being extremely blunt with him. From experience, if you just go up to a guy and straight out say "i know this may seem random to you, but i like you and i would like to try to be more than friends", may work in some cases. If you've known him for a long time and it's one of those relationships where you've been friends forever and now you want to be a little bit more than friends. Consider straight out kissing him.it's worked in the past. <figure rend="Be Straight Forward Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If this guy has never taken any of your hints, ever. Then invite him out "with friends", and when you arrive they have all amazingly canceled on you both. Now i guess it's just going to be you and him;) <figure rend="Be Straight Forward Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get to know him even better if you don't already. Make it interesting, perhaps play a game with him. For example, the truth game. Ask any question and they must answer honestly. Take turns embarrassing and getting to know each other, it takes the edge off of the night. <figure rend="Be Straight Forward Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Towards the end of the night, i encourage you to get cozy with your date. Stick a little bit closer to them gradually throughout the night. Go for a walk, link you're arm through theirs. If he looks confused, outright tell him, "well i didn't think you'd ever make a move so i figured i would." Make sure to smile while you say this** If this doesn't get his attention, again, just kiss him, cheek or lips. whatever you're more comfortable with, and emphasize you had a great night, that you'd want to do this again. If it goes a little further, then he got the hint;) <figure rend="Be Straight Forward Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Last but not least, if you want this relationship to be long term, make sure you explain to him why you did what you did. He may be a little confused as to why you were so "spur of the moment" but really ladies, we know better than that. <figure rend="Be Straight Forward Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>I hope this helps you get the man of your dreams <figure rend="Be Straight Forward Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Guys sometimes need the obvious placed right in front of their faces to understand, that's okay. You just need to get up the courage to put it there.</item>
<item>If you're having trouble getting up the courage to be straight forward think of all the time you'll save by doing so, and that if you don't, you'll have regrets. It's best not to have regrets in a relationship.</item></list>
</text>
