<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc50" title="Understand Angels and Demons per the Bible" shortTile="understand-angels" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-01-31" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Understand_Angels_and_Demons_per_the_Bible" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Understand Angels and Demons per the Bible</head><p>There is a great fascination in our modern culture with the spiritual world. There have been many movies that deal with the theme of angels and demons. People seem to be curious now about these spiritual beings that we usually cannot see. Here are some things to help you understand how they function, etc.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Realize that the spiritual realm is all around us, according to the Bible.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you could put on spiritual glasses, so to speak, you could expect to see angels and demons walking, possibly, anywhere in your city; down the street, sometimes next to people, according to accounts detailed in the Bible.</item>
<item>Before the destruction of the cities of <hi rend="italic">Sodom and Gomorrah,</hi> it is reported that visible angels visited Lot, Abraham's son-in-law, to warn of this, and hurried Lot and his family out of there. But first they shined a great light so that lustful barbarians could not see to raid Lot's house.</item>
<item>We cannot normally see them, but that does not mean they are not there.</item></list></item>
<item>Know that both angels and demons have a ranking system in the Bible.
<list type="unordered"><item>Just like armies have ranks, so do angels and demons. Demons are strategically placed over the world by regions.</item>
<item>The Bible refers to the "Prince of Persia" that kept the angel from getting to Daniel to answer his prayer. That was the prince of demons over the physical area of Persia. In each region there is evidently a commanding officer and demons under him.
<list type="unordered"><item>Then the angel said to Daniel,<hi rend="italic"> "...I shall now return to fight against the prince of Persia [a demon]; so I am going forth, and behold, the prince of Greece [a demon] is about to come. However, I will tell you what is inscribed in the writing of Truth. As yet, here is no one who stands firmly with me against these forces except the [Archangel] Michael your prince [of Israel]." </hi>(Daniel 10:20-21)</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>Understand that some demons/angels can have an appearance like human beings, some like animals and some like monsters, according to the Bible.
<list type="unordered"><item>The angel or demon over any nation would always be fallible; his knowledge of the Divine plan is limited. His tool, a nation (committed to his charge) is also imperfect. An imperfect being with work to do, still has significant power and impact granted to him.</item></list></item>
<item>Apparently in certain cases, demons can overpower angels, depending on the rank of each.</item>
<item>Remember that demons are fallen angels.
<list type="unordered"><item>One third of the angels fell from heaven with Satan before the earth was made. So, two-third of an "innumerable company of angels" (Hebrews 12:22) does outnumber the demons with one-third of the innumerable host, a lot of demons.</item></list></item>
<item>Realize that some angels also can look like normal human beings.
<list type="unordered"><item>Some are covered in wings, the seraphim, but others look like us, according to visits by angels, who appeared to be men as reported by various prophets.</item>
<item>That is why there is the verse: "Do not forget to entertain strangers, for by so doing some have unwittingly entertained angels." (Hebrews 13:2)</item></list></item>
<item>Know that Christians cannot be possessed by demons but they can be oppressed.
<list type="unordered"><item>Oppression looks something like depression. It can also be when someone struggles with anger more than the average person. One might be oppressed by a demon of anger. Or if someone has fear more than a normal person would, one might be oppressed by a demon of fear.</item></list></item>
<item>Realize that if you are Christian, you do have authority over demons.
<list type="unordered"><item>You can tell them to go away. It is as simple as saying, "In the name of Jesus, demon of ___, I command you to leave. You are not welcome here."; give thanks and praise God.</item>
<item>Oftentimes angels will gather around us human beings in agreeing in prayer and worship. There are many accounts of people seeing into the spiritual realm and seeing angels singing with us human beings, praising God. Pretty amazing.</item></list></item>
<item>Know that angels really do appear from time to time to help people.
<list type="unordered"><item>There are many stories, and even live videos, of angels lifting trucks off of people, etc. The Bible says that "He (God) will order his angels to protect you wherever you go." (Psalm 91:11) Protection can be true for both Christians and non-Christians.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>In being interested in angels, we need to be careful to not worship angels. They are created beings as we are. The Bible talks about the worship of angels as being a sin. To think about them some is useful, but to become obsessed with them is not.</item>
<item>One needs to be watchful in any case, realizing that Satan, the prince of this world is to blame for many mishaps, knowing we may blame God. Don't, since unexpected things may happen. Avoid being at the wrong place at the wrong time. You are strongly urged to be a "fan" of God, so praise God—and be in His blessing, as <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Blessed_(Christianity)">explained by Jesus</ref>, in His beatitudes, living right, paid and "prayed up".</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sometimes demons can appear to be angels. The Bible says that Satan appears as "an angel of light." Just because you or someone you know sees an angel, that does not mean it is a good angel. It may very well be a demon appearing as an angel to trick you or them. Don't assume that every supernatural thing you may see is good. Keep your guard up.</item></list>
</text>
