<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc127" title="Find a Girlfriend and Make Her Like You" shortTile="find-girlfriend-make" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-12-28" dateModified="2017-01-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find_a_Girlfriend_and_Make_Her_Like_You" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find a Girlfriend and Make Her Like You</head><p>You are someone who wants to find a girl and make her like you. This article will help you at least a bit.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Find a girlfriend and make the relationship last for as long as possible. The first thing you have to do is find the right girl. In order to do that you need someone who has similar point of views on things you talk about. Yes, you need to spend time with her to make her feel more comfortable around you. Not only the point of views, but also interests. Not all of your interests have to be the same, you just have to have the same type of interests. For instance, both having activities that are either sporty or more indoors.</item>
<item>Create a deeper relationship. The more time you spend, the better, obviously. If you trust her a lot, then it could be good if you tell her something about yourself that few people know about, and make her feel that you trust her so that she also can feel that she can trust you. The most important thing of all is to be yourself. Remember, the right girl will like you for who you are, not for who you want to be or who you're trying to be.</item>
<item>Some things might happen that you find quite noticeable, like her being irritated or something might have happened that makes her feel upset. Ask her what is wrong and whatever she says, accept it! Doesn't matter if she tells you or not, sometimes they just want to be alone, but other times they want to be comforted by someone. If she doesn't want to talk about it, just make sure you don't push her to tell you, just say 'ok' or ' if you want to talk about it, I'll be here to listen anytime.' Now in the case that she is avoiding the subject or tells you that she's just irritated and that you should leave it, then it is probably just that time of the month again.</item>
<item>Hopefully by now you are good friends, at least, and time for your relationship to take the next step. Ask her on a date already! There should be wikiHows that will tell you how to do that. </item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try not to be persistent, a lot of girls don't like that, for most things</item>
<item>Do not try to rush the relationship and remember your boundaries. Some girls might like that, but if you're not at that point in the relationship, best avoid that.</item>
<item>When she needs you, be there for her!</item>
<item>Adding to the previous warning, try not to over think everything, that could make you too nervous and could cause you to fail at doing something you really want to.</item></list>
</text>
