<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc97" title="Know if You Should Date Your Crush" shortTile="know-date-crush" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-03-22" dateModified="2017-01-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Know_if_You_Should_Date_Your_Crush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Know if You Should Date Your Crush</head><p>You have a special guy you have got your eyes on. All of a sudden, he asks you to go out with him. What now? Do you want to date him? Are you even ready to date? Well, here are some simple tips to help you know if you are ready to really date.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get to know him! This point is super crucial. If you and your crush don't even have anything in common, how can you possibly date each other. Your relationship will become a disaster. Here are some important tips for you to know if you two are really meant for each other.
<list type="unordered"><item>See if the two of you have anything in common. From small things like having two younger siblings, to bigger things like having the same hobby, as long as the two of you can connect, you may be on the right path to date.</item>
<item>Ask his friends about him. Let them tell you what his real personality is like. Is he funny and sweet? Or is he really a jerk? Make sure you know what you are really dealing with before you even consider dating him.</item>
<item>Become friendly with him. By doing this, you two can get closer, letting you get to know him more. From there, take it one step further by flirting and getting a little romantic. Don't be afraid to let him know your true feelings.</item></list></item>
<item>Talk to your parents!
<list type="unordered"><item>Your parent's main job is to keep you safe. Ask them what age they think is appropriate to allow you to date. If they say you are to young, respect their opinion. Whatever you do, don't try and push it by arguing. They will think you are unresponsible and won't be able to trust you to date.</item>
<item>Say your parents say you aren't ready but you think that you are. Again, don't argue about it. Talk to them calmly about why you think you are ready and how they will know they can trust you.</item>
<item>If they are still not budging, start mentioning a crush of yours randomly. For example, if you and your crush are going to the same school, bring up school with your mom or dad and mention good things about this one guy/girl that you go there with. Say how friendly he/she is or how smart they are. This will let your parents know that you are thinking about dating and this one boy/girl is a great person to date.</item>
<item>If your mom and dad say "NO, and that's final," don't worry! Your time will come and when you and your parents are ready, discuss it with them. Its not the end of the world if you have to wait. Make sure you are patient and act responsible about the whole situation</item></list></item>
<item>Make sure your crush is also ready! Maybe you are totally ready to date but your crush is just not sure. Or vice versa. Whatever you do, DO NOT push them to do it. It is them and their family's decision and by forcing him to do it, you are ruining your relationship.
<list type="unordered"><item>Wait things out and be patient. You have a long life to live and you don't have to rush things all at once. Make sure you are both comfortable and let him know how you feel about your relationship.</item>
<item>Say it is you that isn't ready and they are trying to make you go out with him. Stand up for yourself! If they are doing this to you, your relationship is not one that you will want to continue any further. Tell them that you aren't ready and if they keeps forcing you on it, leave him. Don't hurt yourself on a small relationship.</item>
<item>This is a scenario that many of you are probably worrying about. Say you are both finally ready, you have been patient, and now, you are ready to date. BUT YOU DON"T LIKE EACH OTHER ANYMORE. Don't stress out. Crushes come and go. You can always try to pick your relationship up again but it's ok to move on as well. If you really do like them still but they are no longer interested, then it might be time to move on. If they like you still but now you are no longer interested, its ok to let them know that so they can move on from your relationship instead of holding on.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Good luck with your relationship! Here are some extra tips:*Flirt with them to let him know you are ready</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't be afraid to tell them you like/love them</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be yourself around them</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>If they aren't interested, don't feel bad! There will always be plenty of guys/girls who are interested in you ;-)</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you aren't ready but are being forced into a relationship, don't be afraid to tell an adult or close friend about what is happening</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be honest with each other. If you really aren't comfortable dating, let them know!</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be patient with your feelings</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not lie to your parents or date behind their back! This will only end badly when they do find out. And trust me, they will find out. Just keep an honest relationship and talk to your parents about your feelings</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not force a relationship on another person, that will make them uncomfortable and could also affect your possible relationship with their family</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do not argue with your parents about whether or not you are allowed to date. They are there to protect you, not make your life miserable.</item></list>
</text>
