<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc215" title="Avoid Distractions (Teenagers)" shortTile="avoid-distractions" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-10-23" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Avoid_Distractions_%28Teenagers%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Avoid Distractions (Teenagers)</head><p>Do you know that hot guy/girl you're totally checking out? He/she may be just the heartthrob but you have work to do so cut it out!
Lets admit it at one point or another we have all let our eyes wander shamelessly all around sometimes landing on a hottie, some class clown setting up a prank, or just started doodling in our notebooks. Now no-one by any means is a super human with their eyes bulging out of their sockets, registering every move or breath by concentrating that hard. We do lose concentration due to many reasons sometimes out of our control but sometimes we just get distracted. This article will break down main distractions and give you a few helpful tips.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Lets be honest with ourselves: no matter where you are, whatever the situation, you spot one gorgeous being and all sense of concentration is out of the window. It's replaced by your subconscious self coming up with different scenarios involving you and that person
<list type="unordered"><item>If they are in a radius of even a meter near you then their cuteness has probably left you dazed as to how to react, unless of course you're a confident human who has your actions handled, then you're doing great. While you're busy working out scenarios and ways to behave around them, you've completely been thrown off what you were actually doing.</item>
<item>Whether that was a listening to your maths teacher explain how they met. This is what you do when that certain someone is near you and distracting you senseless:</item>
<item>After spotting them near you, catch their eyes and keep it short and sweet with a simple smile and "Hi" to 'The eye candy' and go back to what you're doing.</item>
<item>Any time there's a break or opportunity to be able to stop paying attention to the task at hand. Approach them, strike a conversation and just ask them to hang out when you're both free.</item>
<item>Stealing a few glances is more than fine. Just don't openly stare at them when you're checking them out, it may freak them out  <figure rend="Nokia_Lumia_1520_(11433201303).jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Turn off all the gadgets. Cell phones, iPads, laptops, televisions and many other things are just awesome. From providing every means of entertainment from under the sun to looking super sleek and trendy. Gadgets are everywhere.
<list type="unordered"><item>They can be great means of research and sources but they also play a huge role in distraction. At one point we have all sat their too occupied with our laptop than to be productive and get something done itching to be done.</item>
<item>Then we have argued and convinced our brain "What's the worst that could come of it?" or "I totally have time to get it done later." Therefore, we procrastinate and in the end probably forget about it of put it off altogether. This is what you do if you find yourself in similar situations:</item>
<item>Try and get an authority figure someone like your mom, a responsible friend or a sibling to help you out with the work or at least stay nearby to keep an eye and make sure you are strictly on task.</item>
<item>Get your gadgets and switch them off or make sure the battery's completely dead so you won't be tempted.</item>
<item>Do your work in a public area like a library, an after school study group or even a homework club. Some schools run homework clubs where they give you great help if you have any questions while still keeping you on task.</item>
<item>Playing some music while working is great. However, if it becomes a distraction with having to change a tune constantly. You could just create a playlist of songs for studying or just don't have them in and leave them as a little reward if you get your work done.</item></list></item>
<item>Turn off all social networks/media/texting. In this day and age the social media game is going strong.
<list type="unordered"><item>They're all great fun and a great way of socializing with anyone from around the world. As fascinating as it is, it's a huge distraction for many. Over time we do get attached and the temptations of the Internet are ones that are hard to break.</item>
<item>Opt out of receiving notification so you aren't disturbed every time.</item>
<item>Put your phone on silent so no matter how many texts or tweets you receive it won't make a noise once,helps you concentrate so much better.</item>
<item>Put every device connected to the internet somewhere well away from you if your not going to use them appropriately, if so use books instead.</item>
<item>Put your status as busy on social networks or just let a friend know you can't text them  due to work you have to do and you can always text later on.</item>
<item>Remember they may even try and just have an easygoing conversation meaning no harm or have any bad intentions towards you. However it could be at the wrong place at the wrong time. For example, it could be when your teacher is about to explain something you don't understand and want too know more about.</item>
<item>If you didn't reply to them and ignored them it would be rude and they may get the wrong idea but if you did and your teacher heard there going to get mad.</item></list></item>
<item>Consider these steps to resolve the situation:
<list type="unordered"><item>Ignore them and pretend you didn't hear them they may just give up as awkward as it would be for them. But if they call you repeatedly then don't do that it gives the vibe that your avoiding.</item>
<item>Say a quick Hi and look away back to where the teacher is. If they ask a question to keep the conversation going just give quick response like a yes or no and they'll probably just give up. After all a one sided conversation is pretty dull.</item>
<item>Give a short response and ask if they wanna hang out and you'll text them the details later they'll probably just say something like cool and you can both go back to paying attention.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
