<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc115" title="Maintain a Healthy and Successful Relationship After Being Damaged from All the Bad Ones" shortTile="maintain-healthy" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-06-28" dateModified="2015-08-04" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Maintain_a_Healthy_and_Successful_Relationship_After_Being_Damaged_from_All_the_Bad_Ones" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Maintain a Healthy and Successful Relationship After Being Damaged from All the Bad Ones</head><p>We all had a fair share of kissing frogs that don't turn into Princes, but do we all know how to maintain a healthy and successful relationship when we finally found our Prince? This article will aid you to become a Princess for the Prince you finally found.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Don't quickly start dating after you end a relationship. You need time to heal, time to relax and time to reflect.
<list type="unordered"><item>Have fun being single, spend time alone, spend time with friends and family.</item>
<item>Fall back in love with yourself.</item>
<item>Reflect on things that you could've done differently, things he could've done differently. You must understand why it didn't work and accept it, so you can move on from it.</item>
<item>Realize the things you don't want or accept in your next relationship and the reasons why.</item></list></item>
<item>Start off slow in your next relationship.
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't feel pressure to try so hard to make the next relationship work.</item>
<item>Get to know your Prince at a comfortable pace because he might not turn out to be your Prince after all.</item>
<item>Go on casual dates to feel more comfortable around each other. (Dinner, dancing, picnic, movies, bowling, etc)</item></list></item>
<item>Get to the point where the connection is there. Remember don't rush it.
<list type="unordered"><item>The timing is right. Everything is going smoothly.</item>
<item>You still feel those darn butterflies when you see him or he calls you.</item>
<item>A little disagreements here and there, that don't grow into big agreements.</item>
<item>Your going on dates that are pre-planned or spontaneous.</item>
<item>Some simple gift exchanges.</item></list></item>
<item>The honeymoon stage is slowly coming to an end. Now entering the Newlywed stage. Everything is perfect. Those butterflies haven't left yet but there getting comfortable.
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't start getting insecure</item>
<item>Don't start comparing all those frogs you kissed to your Prince</item>
<item>Don't bring up the pass to compare but for allowing him to learn and understand more about you</item>
<item>Your not a victim of bad relationships</item>
<item>Show him how much you've learned about yourself</item></list></item>
<item>Your in a new relationship. It took some time but you finally have your Prince. The newlywed stage is over. Butterflies are still there.
<list type="unordered"><item>Talk about everything everyday at least once a day. Keep the lines of communication open</item>
<item>Make time for each other. Don't crowd him. The real world is slowly crushing through your once lived fairytale</item>
<item>Life happens. (work, school, hobbies, friends, day to day activities and etc.)</item>
<item>Remember you bout went from solo to duo.</item></list></item>
<item>Incorporating two lives into one. You'll have your own life and he will have his but now your apart of his and he is apart of yours.
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't force it. It should come natural. It's all about balance</item>
<item>Once again Princesses do not become INSECURE</item>
<item>Relax, enjoy your alone time when you get it,</item>
<item>Enjoy hanging out with friends and family</item></list></item>
<item>Quality time is essential to a healthy and successful relationship.
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't waste time complaining about not spending enough time with each other. Trust me, he knows already. You can ask what can we do to acquire more time with each other? Make it a short conversation.</item>
<item>Talk about the stuff going on in each other lives.</item>
<item>Plan date nights, weekend getaways, stop by his job with lunch or coffee.</item>
<item>If you miss him and he has been really busy, write him a letter. It's thoughtful and he will feel special.</item>
<item>Quality time is best spent just enjoying each other company. Try not to argue.</item>
<item>Once in awhile send him a cute text message (thinking of you, missing you, loving you ....oops are you there yet)</item></list></item>
<item>Trust. Trust is built starting from the first initial encounter and then throughout your entire relationship. It never stops growing because it can easily be broken.
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't lie about anything. White lies are unacceptable. People believe if you can easily lie about the little stuff then you probably lie about everything.</item>
<item>Be honest about everything. Example: He asks "Do you want to go to my mother's house?" You answer truthfully "No not really, but if it's important to you then I'll go." You probably will still have to go but at least you were honest.</item>
<item>An honest relationship aids in building a trusting relationship which is a healthy relationship.</item></list></item>
<item>Your Prince should be your best friend.
<list type="unordered"><item>Honest, loyal, fateful, trusting, non- judgemental, understanding, supportive, and aiding in the growth of your life.</item>
<item>With time and patience, if he is truly your Prince you will not only have falling in love with the best parts of him but as well as his flaws.</item>
<item>He will also have falling in love with all of you.</item>
<item>Love is forever two souls intertwined and falling forever in a succesful healthy bliss</item>
<item>Stay true to yourself and the people you love.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Love yourself</item>
<item>Except yourself</item>
<item>Respect yourself</item>
<item>Build Trust</item>
<item>Communicate</item>
<item>Quality Time</item>
<item>Be honest</item>
<item>Take your time</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>In order to fall you have to realize you might hit the end.</item>
<item>In order to build you have to realize it might still crash down.</item>
<item>Remember you might have to kiss some frogs before you find your Prince</item>
<item>Analogies of the frogs to Princes. Butterflies in stomach.</item></list>
</text>
