<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc12" title="Make an Imaginary Pet Shelter in Your Home" shortTile="make-imaginary-pet" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-05-01" dateModified="2019-01-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_an_Imaginary_Pet_Shelter_in_Your_Home" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make an Imaginary Pet Shelter in Your Home</head><p>This is all about making an Imaginary Pet Shelter/Adoption Center! Have fun with it and be creative!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Making Pets</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make adoption sheets. Adoption sheets should include a box for drawing the pet, a spot for the name of the pet, a spot for its price, a spot for its personality, a spot for its gender, a spot for its species, a spot for its breed/type, a spot for its age, a spot for its markings+colorings, a spot for its mother and its father, and a spot for its current owner. You can also include a spot for its birthday.</item>
<item>Pick its species and breed/type. For example, if you were making a dog you would pick its breed, such as Siberian Husky or German Shepherd. You can also make your own species and/or breeds/types!</item>
<item>Now, fill out the rest of the spots on your Adoption Sheet! For the owner spot, either put your name OR the name of your Imaginary Pet Shelter.</item>
<item>Draw your pet! Go wherever your imagination takes you!</item></list>
<head>Pricing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Create a currency for your friends and family to use at your imaginary stores. Also, make a way for your friends and family to earn more of that currency.</item>
<item>Depending on how much of your currency your family can earn at once, pick a price for each pet based on its rarity. For common pets, maybe do 3 times the average amount of currency that people are able to earn at once. For the rarest pets, maybe do more like 10 or even 20 times the average amount of currency that people can earn in one go!</item></list>
<head>Setting Up</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pick where your Imaginary Pet Shelter will be. I would suggest your bedroom or some other place that your family doesn’t mind you using.</item>
<item>Decide how you will display the pets. You could use Sticky tack and stick the Adoption Sheets to the walls, or you could set them out on tables. There are many ways to display your pets! Be creative!</item></list>
<head>Advertising</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Tell your friends and family about your Imaginary Pet Shelter! Have them come check it out! If you are allowed to, put posters around town that have contact information, the name of your shelter, a description of your shelter, and your name!</item></list>
<head>Selling</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make Adoption Certificates. Adoption Certificates should have a spot to write a pet’s name, a spot to write the date of adoption, and a spot for the new owner to sign!</item>
<item>Have the people who buy pets subtract the amount of currency that they spent from the currency that they have.</item>
<item>Give the new owner the Adoption Sheet of the pet they bought!</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make games for people to play with their pet!</item>
<item>Make a way for people to care for their pet!</item>
<item>Make a pet store for people to buy accessories, food, etc. for their pet!</item></list>
</text>
