<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc91" title="Improve Your Relationship with Your Child As a Working Mother" shortTile="improve-relationship" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-10-02" dateModified="2019-09-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Improve_Your_Relationship_with_Your_Child_As_a_Working_Mother" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Improve Your Relationship with Your Child As a Working Mother</head><p>There are a lot of moms out there who struggle to develop their relationship with their children as they have no time or much energy left at the end of the day. Of course, it is very tough to maintain a good relationship with your children especially if you are working for long hours. However here are some ways to use the very little time you get to develop an intimate bond with your child/children.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Develop an Organised System of Management of Chores at Home</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Teach your child what is expected. Your child should be taught to do his personal little chores by himself. Tasks, such as packing a bag, cleaning his room, picking up his laundry, are all things that can be done by a small child. When your child completes any of this tasks encourage him by giving a little surprise gift once in a while. This will help encourage your child to be independent and self - reliant.</item>
<item>Make a relaxed timetable for all of your child's activities. Include activities like studying, playing and cleaning. This will greatly help in  time management of your child. This will ensure that a lot of tasks will be completed even in your absence.</item></list>
<head>Spend Time with Your Children</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Set time aside for your child/children. Even if you have a busy schedule its important to fit in time for your children. Find a time that works for you both and put it into the time table, give your child your full attention during that time.</item>
<item>Spend time with your child(ren). You may be rushed but this is a necessary commitment for their well being. You can indulge in activities such as playing games, doing chores, or running errands with your children. This will help in developing a closer bond with your child.
<list type="unordered"><item>Talk to your child while getting him/her ready for school or other outdoor places. You can ask your child about the things that happened in his/her school and what he/she learnt that day.</item>
<item>Try to spend at least half an hour with your child/children every day.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Make Sure That Your Child Knows His/Her Own Information</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Let your child know what to do in emergencies. If you have a busy work schedule your child is going to be spending a lot of time home alone. If a dangerous situation arises they will need to know what to do without you there. Your child should know your phone number, their other parents phone number and their neighbours phone number. This way they will be able to contact someone in an emergency.
<list type="unordered"><item>if your child or someone who is with your child (for example a friend) is in immediate danger (for example a fire or medical emergency) tell them to call 911.</item></list></item>
<item>During holidays talk to your child about himself. Let your child know about his family, his positive behaviours, old memories together. If your child has made a mistake have a calm conversation to him about it.</item></list>
</text>
