<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc205" title="Shine As a Teen Girl" shortTile="shine-teen-girl" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-26" dateModified="2019-06-01" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Shine_As_a_Teen_Girl" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Shine As a Teen Girl</head><p>Do you want to feel like a star? Is there a special boy (or girl) that you want to impress, but are you too shy or insecure? Then read on and fall into the new you! Whether you're just becoming a teen at 13 or getting ready to become an official adult at 18, the teen years are a roller coaster ride.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look in the mirror. What DO you love about your appearance? Is it your eyes, lips, hair? What don't you like? <figure rend="Shine As a Teen Girl Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Then think about your personality, what annoys people about you? What are your best characteristics? <figure rend="Shine As a Teen Girl Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a list of those like and dislikes, but don't put more than five in the dislike list. Also, do not put impossible things in the dislike column. Example: I am too tall. That's something you can't change, so embrace it! <figure rend="Shine As a Teen Girl Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Act confident. With pimples and changes in your body it's easy to begin to feel insecure at times, but no matter what, keep your head high and let it be known you love who you are. Don't be arrogant because no one likes a snob, but if people make fun of you, use your humor to turn the joke back on them. If you're sure of who you are and what you believe, the other girls will want to be like you. <figure rend="Shine As a Teen Girl Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Now go out and fix what you don't like about yourself (that you can)! If you don't like your hair, try a new style. If you wish you could be more patient, start practicing! <figure rend="Shine As a Teen Girl Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask your mom, or other loved one to teach you to apply make up. But keep it natural. Ashley Tisdale says, "I always think natural makeup is prettiest. It just looks prettier." And it's no lie! Mascara, eyeliner, powder, and lip gloss are all you need. If you don't want to wear makeup, that's fine, too. <figure rend="Shine As a Teen Girl Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Dress fashionably, but modestly. For a cute style read How to Be a Preppy Girl. <figure rend="Shine As a Teen Girl Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Study in school, and do the best you can. Set goals for yourself! <figure rend="Shine As a Teen Girl Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get involved in sports or school activities. Sports are a great way to meet people and make new friends. They also help you stay in shape and learn new skills. Discipline is something else you learn in sport, which makes you a good leader and liked by other teen girls. <figure rend="Shine As a Teen Girl Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be yourself. It's tempting to try to dress or act like someone else as a teen girl to get attention, but whenever you try to imitate someone else you always end up second. No one can do you better than you. Besides, people can tell when you're being fake. <figure rend="Shine As a Teen Girl Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Have fun!</item>
<item>Be nice to people. That's a great quality.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Never</hi> do anything stupid just to lose weight, impress a boy (or girl), etc.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Never</hi> try be anyone you're not,</item></list>
</text>
