<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc47" title="Love the Universe" shortTile="love-universe" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-04-04" dateModified="2019-03-14" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Love_the_Universe" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Love the Universe</head><p>Having a love affair with the cosmos is what dreams are made of. It's time to ditch your anxiety for complete assurance that the Universe has got your back.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Start every day with gratitude by completing these ten simple steps... <figure rend="1949229 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Thank the Universe (God, Life) for the fact you woke up</item>
<item>Give thanks for the bed that kept you comfortable all night, and/or for other things many of us take for granted: family, food, clothing, a job, a place to live, friends, and so on.</item></list></item>
<item>Meditate; that is, prepare your mind for miracles  The Universe’s wish is that we be happy now. The Universe is not interested in what plans we have to postpone our happiness on the chance we will attain it in the future. Furthermore, it is not concerned regarding any subconscious desire we might have to retain our psychic obstacles to love no matter our reasons for so doing, and regardless of the origins of those love-blocking strategies. By meditating, we cooperate with the Universe’s wish for us to be happy and clear our mind of any thought that tries to convince us otherwise. Start meditation with a simple request to your mind  <hi rend="italic" style="">  Dear Mind,<hi rend="italic"> <hi rend="italic" style="">I am about to enter into meditation. I thank you for being concerned about my well-being and how you look for various solutions to my problems. However, I am now giving you some time off as I take over responsibility for our well-being from a deeper part of Self. I assure you that I will come back to you after a short while and ask that you support this process by not attempting anxiously to reassert your control either by interrupting the meditation, by distracting me or by creating some mini-drama. I want you to know that this process is safe, and that 'you' and 'I' will become stronger, more capable and more resilient as a result.</hi> <hi rend="italic" style="">Thank You for your trust and patience. </hi></hi></hi></item><hi rend="italic" style=""><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="italic" style="">
<item>Send love to people....just because you can. When you send love to another person, it will automatically come back to you. Even if you cannot act in a loving way you can always send people love with your thoughts. <figure rend="1949229 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be gentle with yourself (this is known as 'self-compassion') and remember how far you've already come. When you begin to lose faith in a cosmic force, (e.g., God, the universe) it is always useful to take note of how far you've come over the past 1 year, 5 years, 10 years, and so on. You will be surprised at how much you've grown. <figure rend="1949229 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Surrender your plans and let Life take over. Life has a plan that works, we don't. Surrender your own plans to the Universe and take inspired steps based on what life brings to you. You will save yourself a lot of time and a lot of heartache.  This can start with a simple prayer "Dear Universe, I do not know what is best for me today, so I leave the blessings in your hands." <figure rend="1949229 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ditch, (or, if you prefer, discipline) the Ego. The Ego's agenda, based as it is on faulty interpretations of reality bent to socially and culturally dictated criteria regarding 'fitting in' and 'belonging', can be a troublemaker. It's like a 'sincere friend' who is constantly pressuring you to act in ways that it perceives are in your (really, its) best interests. The ego's agenda is not necessarily healthy or good for you. You can ditch (or, again, discipline) your ego by doing what feels right from a deeper perspective and not according to what you think you 'should' do. You can ditch (train) your ego by loving (accepting, caring about, appreciating) yourself more just the way you are and by no longer judging other people as much. <figure rend="1949229 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Spend time outside and with Nature.  No, this step is not asking you to go and hug a tree. This step is about going outside and receiving the gifts of the Universe for yourself. See the beauty in the flowers and the sky, listen to birds singing, take time to smell the grass and feel the wind. You may notice that, whilst you're doing any of these things, it's impossible to be unhappy. <figure rend="1949229 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep an open mind; practice perceiving through all of your senses. Life is already speaking to you in many ways. Be open and receptive to the messages Life has to offer. <figure rend="1949229 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Breathe deeply &amp; listen to your heartbeat. If you really want to feel the presence of the Universe (following the principle, 'what is without reflects what is within') then take some time to listen to your heartbeat and feel your breath--sense your own presence. You can do this by dancing to your favorite song, for example. <figure rend="1949229 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Love is a choice and not a reaction. You are free to make the decision to LOVE. As you learn to love yourself more and as you practice loving others until you become good at it, you will begin to feel love for the whole universe welling up within you. Once you're there, you'll know you've arrived. <figure rend="1949229 10.jpg"></figure></item></hi></hi></hi></list><hi rend="italic" style=""><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="italic" style="">
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't worry if you feel down some days. Whoever said feeling down was wrong? In fact, it is well known that one of the most powerful ways to manage bad feelings is to feel them clearly, rather than run from them. What you'll learn from this approach is the truth: those are your feelings, so you are in charge of how they affect you, and you can set the stage for changing them by feeling them authentically, then releasing them once they've done their job. Also helpful: know that Life has got your back, that 'this too shall pass' and that, in time, you'll 'feel better soon'.</item>
<item>The Universe is just one word for 'creation'. You can substitute 'Life' or the name of your personally accepted deity if you'd like!</item></list></hi></hi></hi>
</text>
