<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc104" title="Keep Your Relationship with Your Boyfriend Strong" shortTile="keep-relationship" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-05-26" dateModified="2017-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Keep_Your_Relationship_with_Your_Boyfriend_Strong" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Keep Your Relationship with Your Boyfriend Strong</head><p>In the honey moon stage of a relationship couples are always the strongest but when that end most relationships get lost in what they should do. This will hopefully help you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Don't be clingy. By this I mean just remember that he has his own life, as do you. If he'd rather hang out with his friends this weekend rather than go see a movie with you let him do so. Know that he will spend the next free time he has with you. Although know when he is acting strangely. Yes he should get free time to hang out with friends but don't let him break plans with you just to hang out with someone else.</item>
<item>Don't be jealous. If you're a girl who tends to get jealous over other girls in your mans life just realize that he cares more for you than any other girl out there. If he's going to hang out with a female friend it might feel better if you talk to him while they are hanging out, or maybe you can ask to go along. Don't throw in his face that he hangs out with too many girls or tell him that he can't hang out with someone. He will most likely go behind your back to do so. Also try not to get jealous over him spending time with friends. If he's hung out with guy friends 4 times this week and you miss him let him know that you miss him and would like to hang out the next time he is free. Try not to say things like "you can hang out with them, but not with me?"</item>
<item>Remind him you love him. There might not always be the long paragraphs, staying up on skype till 3am, or calling each other for hours on end, but that doesn't mean that he doesn't still love you the same. Send him little messages here and there to remind him that you love him and that you're always there. You can message him things like "I love you" or "I was just thinking about you and thought I'd send you a message." It will brighten up his day, trust me.</item>
<item>Stay calm. After the honey moon stage is when couples typically start noticing annoying habits of one another that were never apparent before. If he starts telling you things you do that annoy him make sure to stay calm. Try saying that you'll try and fix it rather than turning it back on him. If you think it would help ask if the next time you are together you two can sit down and tell each other what bothers you and agree to try and fix them one thing at a time. During any other arguments try and stay calm, if he is yelling then speak calmly. If he doesn't seem to calm down within ten minutes of the conversation suggest that he take some time to calm down and come back when he's less frustrated so the two of you can talk.</item>
<item>Do things for him. Most guys enjoy a girl who would make them something to eat while they watch the movie that they've been dying to see or to put his dishes in the sink while you're on the way to the kitchen. If you're heading to the kitchen ask him if he'd like something to eat or drink, watch a movie that he'd like to watch, etc. He'll feel very appreciated and loved.</item>
<item>Give him gifts. I'm not saying go out and spend your money on things he likes, but every once in a while it doesn't hurt to buy or make him a "just because" card saying that you love him and care for him. They don't even have to be often or really big. Bake him a cake if you know that he's coming over, make his favorite meal, pick some flowers from outside, give him a picture frame with you in it. Easy things that are very inexpensive to make him feel loved and appreciated.</item>
<item>Talk about issues. This ties in with staying calm, if you are having an issue with something don't be afraid to talk about it. Don't say it accusingly. Instead of saying "You always do this and it pisses me off" say, "I feel aggravated because this happens sometimes and I don't know why, I'd like to talk about it." Changing the way you say things will lessen his anger and yours.</item>
<item>Be spontaneous. I know since the honey moon stage is over its a little more difficult to plan surprise dates or to just show up to say hi, but try your best. If you miss him show up at his house or leave a letter on his front porch. He'll feel like you went out of your way to do something nice for him which will feel wonderful.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you get aggravated easily you may also want to sit and think about happy things during arguments instead of how much he aggravates you.</item>
<item>Don't change yourself. If you aren't clingy like most girls let him know that you want some time to yourself.</item>
<item>Be happy. When the going gets tough just remember that you're glad to have him in your life.</item>
<item>If you feel suspicious about something, ask. He may get mad, but if you never ask you'll never know.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If he starts yelling and gets out of control, you should leave. Don't be scared to just walk out.</item>
<item>Trying to get your relationship back on track after the honeymoon phase doesn't always work, some relationships just weren't meant to last that long. If you get too many problems and you're constantly stressed out and feel like ripping your hair out whenever you talk to him. It's probably a better idea to end the relationship than to suffer like that.</item></list>
</text>
