<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc193" title="Have Great Day (Teenage Girls)" shortTile="great-day-teenage" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-07-24" dateModified="2018-09-25" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have_Great_Day_%28Teenage_Girls%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have Great Day (Teenage Girls)</head><p>Hi! welcome to my first article. Here you will find some help to have a great and fun day. Also as I mentioned before this is my first article so I would appreciate it if you could write a comment or suggestion about it, only if you want. Hope this is useful for you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>The night before. Try to go to bed at a resonable time. Like 10:30 p.m., but first make sure that:
<list type="unordered"><item>You have done everyting that you had to do that day.</item>
<item>Put your cellphone and laptop charging if you think that you will use them. If not, try not to use them a lot the next day.</item>
<item>Wash your teeth and face.</item></list></item>
<item>Waking up. Also try to wake up at resonable time. Make sure that you've had at least 8 hours of sleep. Then get out of your bed and wash your face with cold water so you can wake up a little more. Get a shower if you want to, to feel relaxed.</item>
<item>Breakfast. Breakfast is one of the most important meals of the day. Make sure you have a high protein breakfast so you can start with lots of energy your day.</item>
<item>Do some excersise. A little bit of excercise would help.Try 30 minutes. Maybe you could go running outside or walk. Also there are some apps which could help you do some excercise to help you if you don´t feel like going out. Don´t be lazy and put your sport clothes and move a bit.</item>
<item>After excercise. Go to your studying desk and do homework or study for a test. If you would like, listen to music. Find the type of music that helps you study. If you don´t think it is necesary don´t listen to it or if it disturbes you. Take some breaks. Don´t use your cellphone, it could distract you and you will be using it a lot, not knowing that maybe 15 minutes of your break already past. Have on you´re study desk:
<list type="unordered"><item>Pencil case.</item>
<item>Computer.</item>
<item>Notebooks.</item>
<item>School books.</item>
<item>More things that you consider necessary.</item></list></item>
<item>When you finish doing all your important stuff, why don´t you do something with your friends? Or if you don´t feel like it, do something that you like.</item>
<item>Take a nap. Maybe you will feel a little tierd after doing all these things. So take a 30min. nap.</item>
<item>Organize your next day. Sit on your couch or desk and get your agenda. Plan activites and write important  things you have to do tomorrow. Plan things that you honestly know you will do.</item>
<item>Eat dinner. Eat something that you like and healthy.</item>
<item>Finally. Change into your pajama and brush your teeth or before changing get a shower. Make sure that you did everything that it said in step 1 and go to sleep.</item></list>
</text>
