<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc166" title="Act 13 when You Are" shortTile="act-" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-12-29" dateModified="2019-05-18" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Act_13_when_You_Are" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Act 13 when You Are</head><p>Do people often doubt that you're actually 13? Do your parents tell you to "act your age"? Do you think you're not quite mature enough, and wish you could act older? Read on!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Assess why you want to act older or more mature. Don't try to "grow up" just because you want to imitate someone, and don't stop <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Yourself">being yourself.</ref> <figure rend="Act 13 when You Are Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Is it because your parents are telling you to become more mature?</item>
<item>Are you in trouble at school frequently for "acting up", or do your teachers complain that you're not focused enough for your age?</item>
<item>Do you hope that if you show you're more responsible, your parents might trust you with more responsibilities and freedom?</item></list></item>
<item>Recognize that becoming more mature does <hi rend="italic">not</hi> mean that you have to sacrifice what makes you essentially you. It usually doesn't mean giving up things that interest you, either. <figure rend="Act 13 when You Are Step 2Bullet1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Consider how you could become more mature in the interests that you do have. For example, instead of staying in kiddie swimming class, consider joining a swim squad. If you like reading, but you've only read kids' books before, start looking at the Teen section of the library or bookstore, or ask your friends and teachers for recommendations.</item>
<item>Be skeptical of people who say that certain interests aren't "mature" enough. Although, as mentioned, you can consider becoming more mature in certain areas, it's unlikely that an entire general interest, such as caring for your pet hamster, is in itself immature. Immaturity is more about how you approach these interests, and how you behave in general.</item></list></item>
<item>Find out what behaviors are causing people to think that you're younger than you are. Generally, actions considered immature include squealing, or running and jumping around. This especially applies around adults -- people your own age might get excited together at recess, but when you're with adults and/or in a formal setting, you're old enough to know that that behavior is not appropriate. <figure rend="Act 13 when You Are Step 3Bullet1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This does not apply to reactions to extremely traumatic events. If someone has died or something else genuinely bad is happening, it's natural and OK to cry and express your emotions. Adults do this too in these situations.</item></list></item>
<item>Take responsibility for your personal space. <figure rend="Act 13 when You Are Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Clean_Your_Room">Tidy your room</ref> once a week, or more often. Yes, this includes keeping your desk neat!</item>
<item>Decorate your room in a more teenage theme -- consider asking your parents if you can repaint and/or replace your bedspread. Bedspreads with movie characters printed on them are usually considered childish.</item>
<item>If you share a room with a sibling, try to get your sibling on board with keeping it relatively tidy. If they're younger than you, but old enough to learn to put away their toys, you could teach (or help) them to do this - without nagging! If they're too young, you could be mature by tidying up a bit for them. If the sibling you share with is the same age as you or older, they should be tidying up too!</item>
<item>If your sibling absolutely refuses to clean their side/area of the room, just clean your own side.</item></list></item>
<item>Take responsibility for your schoolwork. Yes, it might be annoying, but the workload is probably starting to increase, and starting good schoolwork habits now will help you in later years. <figure rend="Act 13 when You Are Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you get a bad grade, don't ignore it; consider how you could improve in future. Ask your teacher for help or to explain things you didn't understand.</item></list></item>
<item>Behave normally with pets. If you have pets, don't go over the top with them; let them come to you. Chasing them around is considered immature, and you might scare your pet away from you by doing it! <figure rend="Act 13 when You Are Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Treat siblings well. If you have a little sibling, don't fight! Never hit or punch; that is what a two-year-old would do. Instead, sort it out by talking your issues through or walking away from the situation.  <figure rend="Act 13 when You Are Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hang out with your friends. When you go shopping, invite some friends to come if they are available; try going to Hollister, Forever 21, Aeropostale, American Eagle, Hot Topic, and so forth. <figure rend="Act 13 when You Are Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you do not already babysit, you could try getting a babysitting gig or be a mother's helper. Other job opportunity could be raking leaves for a neighbor, mowing lawns, walking dogs, or grooming dogs. A job will not only make you more mature; it will also earn money that you can save for college or your future.</item>
<item>Wear mature makeup or none at all. Instead of wearing bubblegum lip gloss, save up for some more mature lipstick that is not too dark. Instead of wearing bright pink, blue, or purple eye shadow, skip it and wear smokey eye shadow or light brown. Don't over do your makeup either; you do not want to look over done. It will make you look inexperienced. <figure rend="Act 13 when You Are Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't gossip; you might lose friends because of it.</item>
<item>If you have a cell phone, you should use it, but if you over use it, you will seem even more immature and impolite to adults.</item>
<item>Have Facebook, Instagram, or Twitter, you're allowed when you're 13.</item>
<item>Don't annoy people on purpose just to be funny. It is impolite, and that is the type of thing an eight year old might do.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Never</hi> make <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Stop_Your_Brother_or_Sister_from_Making_Silly_Noises_to_Get_Your_Attention">silly noises</ref>. Don't giggle over farting noises, silly noises, swearing; just ignore them.</item></list>
</text>
