<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc120" title="Tell a Guy That He Isn't Good in Bed" shortTile="tell-guy-isnt-good" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-02-20" dateModified="2016-05-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Tell_a_Guy_That_He_Isn%27t_Good_in_Bed" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tell a Guy That He Isn't Good in Bed</head><p>It's a challenge to finally decide to sleep with your partner, friend with benefit or anything in between and find that the whole thing fails to live up to your expectations. However, don't feel as though it should not be something to be done again, because in a few steps, your sex life should hopefully see an improvement, before you decide whether to tell him straight!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Make allowances if this is his first time. If this is his first time having sex, don't be disheartened if he doesn't have many moves yet. You can now act as a teacher to him, helping him to learn what feels good for both of you. Having a knack for sex comes with experience; you are only bad if you haven't practised, and with practise comes excellence. So, don't tell him he is terrible right away, but see whether you can help him get better.</item>
<item>Tell him you are disappointed that you couldn't quite come to the edge. That will result in him feeling as though he didn't do a good job, and next time see him putting in a good effort to try harder to make you feel better! Just don't tell him straight that it wasn't good, or else he may not want to try to improve at all.</item>
<item>Do not say the words "you are bad" directly. Subtle hints work just as well, because not only does it save embarrassment, but it lets the other person know you respect him enough to be honest, but are not rude enough to be just straight up rude! It isn't lying, as you are telling him exactly what you want, all whilst saving his ego the embarrassment of knowing he is bad in bed!</item>
<item>Be willing to build his confidence in bed. Try something new! Most of what causes bad sex is being timid towards trying new things, so don't let that happen. Let him know you are completely confident in yourself and ready to try new things, and your confidence will rub off on him too, making his performance better.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you enjoy something they do, let them know. One reason why sexual activity becomes monotonous or bad is because someone doesn't know what the other partner wants. Tell him what you like, and you will see an improvement quickly.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If this guy is your boyfriend, don't result to cheating on him just so you get sexually satisfied. Trust that with time his performance will get better and that you will be happy you didn't make such a heat of the moment mood!</item>
<item>Never let him find out how you feel through other people. This will only cause for him to be embarrassed and you will end up feeling much worse than he will!</item></list>
</text>
