<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc112" title="Find Out Whether Your Older Sister Has a Crush" shortTile="find-out-whether" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-08-01" dateModified="2018-10-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Find_Out_Whether_Your_Older_Sister_Has_a_Crush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Find Out Whether Your Older Sister Has a Crush</head><p>Do you think your older sister has a crush on a potential significant other? Are you curious but want to be careful about how you ask her? When it comes down to it, your sister's crush is none of your business, but if you just can't let it go, you can try finding out more about her feelings with a little probing.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Consider the people in her life. Is there anyone your older sister watches a lot online or constantly leaves the house to be with? Is there anyone she talks about a lot, or, perhaps more significantly, talks about with her friends but never mentions around you?</item>
<item>Try snooping, with caution. If you're good with computers, then look at her internet history. Wait until she leaves her computer still running to maybe do a chore, or go to for a snack. Then open her internet history, scroll through, and see whether she's visited the same Facebook or Twitter profile over and over again. Be careful when doing this, as she might get upset and feel that you're invading her privacy.
<list type="unordered"><item>Reading her messages or other private communication is a huge invasion of privacy; avoid this unless you're really looking for her to get mad at you.</item></list></item>
<item>Use a direct approach. Once you know, or strongly suspect she has a crush, try saying to her something like this, "Hey sis, do you have a crush on so-and-so?" Watch very carefully for her facial expression. If she blushes, seems embarrassed, or immediately replies too emphatically with a "no," she just might actually have a crush on the person in question. Leave her alone for a while, as she's made it obvious she doesn't want to take the conversation further. If she's honest, look at her body language and decide if you can further talk about it. <figure rend="Get Along with Your Sister Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep probing about her crush, without pushing her too far. If she gets mad or grumpy, then she might have a crush on them. Try not to annoy her too much. Remember, it's none of your business really. Consider what you have to gain by finding out who your sister has a crush on. You may just be being nosy and intrusive. Perhaps you just can't stand it she has something you don't or think you have a right to know everything that is going on.</item>
<item>Follow her around. Try to meet this person if possible. Listen in to her conversations with them on her cell phone. Pretend to want to talk to her about something. When she refuses to talk to you in order to finish the conversation, walk around her room and listen in to her conversation. When she asks you whether you were <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Eavesdrop">eavesdropping</ref>, say, "Well, I needed to ask you a question!" Make the question relevant so she doesn't know. Make sure you don't do this too often as she might get suspicious. <figure rend="Follow Someone Without Getting Caught Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be careful if you want to do something like talk to her parents. If you're concerned for her safety and believe her parents wouldn't approve, confront her about it herself and try to express your concern. If it's innocent, many would recommend just keeping it to yourself. She most likely be angry if you tell. <figure rend="Talk to a Parent About a Bad Grade on Your Report Card Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure you don't get caught!</item>
<item>Don't try to probe her about her crush too much as she might lash out back at you.</item></list>
</text>
