<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc194" title="Feel Like a Teen when You're Not Yet Old Enough" shortTile="feel-teen-re-old" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-01-26" dateModified="2019-06-02" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Feel_Like_a_Teen_when_You%27re_Not_Yet_Old_Enough" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Feel Like a Teen when You're Not Yet Old Enough</head><p>Do you feel like the world is going too slowly for you? As a tween, it can feel like it's taking forever to "grow up" into teen-hood. Although it's not really long in the greater scheme of things, if you feel older already, it can be frustrating. In this article, you'll find some ways to feel like a teen even though you're not yet old enough.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Online</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Join social media. This doesn't mean to lie about your age to join Facebook or YouTube, but try to find fun sites without any age requirements. Sites like Twitter don't require users to be 13 or older, but they don't allow people under 13 to provide them with personal info (like full name or phone number) without parental consent. So be sure to ask your parents first! <figure rend="Feel Like a Teen when You're Not Yet Old Enough Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>For sites that require 13 and over, ask your parents for permission. If they feel that you're old enough to handle the site, then you'll be able to use it.</item></list></item>
<item>Get Snapchat. While Snapchat may be restricted for 13s and over, their version Snapkidz (which is accessed by signing up with an under 13 Date of Birth) allows you to take pictures and edit them. <figure rend="Feel Like a Teen when You're Not Yet Old Enough Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Play games. If you like video games, try playing games that aren't restrictive on age. This can include sports games like FIFA or Madden. If sports aren't your kind of game, try The Sims or Forza/Driveclub. <figure rend="Feel Like a Teen when You're Not Yet Old Enough Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't lie about your age. Lying about your age could cause your account on sites to be taken down, become bullied or be exposed to adult nature. Even if your friends are signing up for restricted websites, don't give in to peer pressure. <figure rend="Feel Like a Teen when You're Not Yet Old Enough Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn about internet safety. This is important, no matter your age but especially so while you're young. <figure rend="Feel Like a Teen when You're Not Yet Old Enough Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never arrange to meet up with someone you don't already know.</item>
<item>Be sure to identify scammers or pedophiles.</item>
<item>Get a good antivirus and try to identify a virus before you install it.</item>
<item>Never give your password or any personal info over the internet to someone you don't know no matter what.</item></list></item></list>
<head>In Real Life</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look into fashion. See what's popular. When people are teens they tend to care more about what they wear. While adapting fashion may make you feel more like a teen, don't feel forced to be sensitive about what clothing you wear. <figure rend="Feel Like a Teen when You're Not Yet Old Enough Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you are taller, this step should be easier for you, as you may be able to fit into teen size clothing or even adult sizes.</item>
<item>If you are smaller, don't worry. Try to adapt clothing in the kid's section to suit your style.</item></list></item>
<item>Find a hobby. Find one that's more directed at teens than kids if you can.This can include drawing, computers, musical instruments, sports etc. In your school, there may also be clubs for your hobby, making you more enthusiastic about the activities involved. <figure rend="Feel Like a Teen when You're Not Yet Old Enough Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Call your friends to chat. Ask them for their numbers and ring them up. <figure rend="Feel Like a Teen when You're Not Yet Old Enough Step 8.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If you haven't got your own phone, try landline or your parent's phones.</item>
<item>If you're parents don't let you do this, don't worry. Not all teens do this, and using phones can become an addiction if used too much.</item></list></item>
<item>Go out more. Ask your friends if they want to hang out. <figure rend="Feel Like a Teen when You're Not Yet Old Enough Step 9.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always ask parents beforehand, and be home the time they tell you. Be sure to follow any rules they give you.</item>
<item>Be sure to learn road safety, especially in the dark.</item>
<item>Bring a phone with you. If you don't have one ask to use your parent's.</item>
<item>Be wary of stranger danger. Don't trust someone you don't know.</item></list></item>
<item>Don't try to be too old. Plenty of teenagers actually want to be kids, so don't be afraid to be like a kid! <figure rend="Feel Like a Teen when You're Not Yet Old Enough Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Your parents may not want you to try to be older. If they don't want you to, respect their wishes.</item>
<item>Using the Internet doesn't make you fully anonymous, so be very careful about what info you put online.</item>
<item>Don't be mean to people over the Internet, as it could really upset them.</item>
<item>If anyone tries to meet with you, tell your parents right away.</item></list>
</text>
