<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc198" title="Have Fun Outside when None of Your Friends Are Home" shortTile="fun-outside-none" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-05-15" dateModified="2019-08-08" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Have_Fun_Outside_when_None_of_Your_Friends_Are_Home" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Have Fun Outside when None of Your Friends Are Home</head><p>You wake up the sun is shining and the birds are singing! You can't wait to go outside! You get dressed and you call all your friends, but none of them can come outside. You don't want to waste this beautiful day inside, so you don't know what to do. Here is what you can do!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Quiet activities</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Think of your own things to do! Make a list when you have a spare moment or two. <figure rend="Have Fun Outside when None of Your Friends Are Home Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Grab a good book or magazine and sit outside and read. If you can, sit under a large, shady tree to keep heat away. <figure rend="Have Fun Outside when None of Your Friends Are Home Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Bring out a notebook to write. You may be inspired by the pretty day. <figure rend="Have Fun Outside when None of Your Friends Are Home Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Backyard activities</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Still have a swing set from when you were younger (or for your younger siblings or for you depending on how old you are)? Swing. Slide down the slide maybe even up the slide. Get your siblings (if you have any) maybe even your parents to join in on the fun! <figure rend="Have Fun Outside when None of Your Friends Are Home Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Grab some neighbors, your family, or maybe some aunts, uncles and cousins (if they live close by) and play a game! Soccer, football, baseball, basketball, even a wiffle ball game. <figure rend="Have Fun Outside when None of Your Friends Are Home Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you have a pool and it's open and warm enough, go swimming! <figure rend="Have Fun Outside when None of Your Friends Are Home Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you have a strong and sturdy tree in your backyard, learn how to climb it! You never know when you might have to use that skill. <figure rend="Have Fun Outside when None of Your Friends Are Home Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Buy a box of sidewalk chalk and go draw pictures on the pavement. Be careful where you draw, though--your neighbors may not like your artwork in front of their houses. <figure rend="Have Fun Outside when None of Your Friends Are Home Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Play with a pet. If you or someone you know has a pet, play with it. <figure rend="Have Fun Outside when None of Your Friends Are Home Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Out and about</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Go to a nearby park and take a walk! Take a trail or hike. <figure rend="Have Fun Outside when None of Your Friends Are Home Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go mini golfing with yourself, it'll give you a good chance to get some practice and you can't lose! <figure rend="Have Fun Outside when None of Your Friends Are Home Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you live near a beach, go to it. <figure rend="Have Fun Outside when None of Your Friends Are Home Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Is there a water park or recreation center near you? You could go swimming, skateboarding, or play basketball or tennis there. <figure rend="Have Fun Outside when None of Your Friends Are Home Step 13.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Have fun. Play with pets, ride bikes, or play board games.</item>
<item>If you're home alone, make sure your parents say it's okay to go outside.</item>
<item>Just use your imagination.</item>
<item>Don't take climbing a tree to the next level by hurting yourself.</item>
<item>If you're going to play sports, make sure you have the right equipment.</item>
<item>Don't have a climbing tree in your yard? Ask a neighbor or friend/family to climb theirs! It's great to see the world from that high.</item>
<item>When it starts to get late, or the weather gets bad (rain, wind, cold temperatures, etc.), go inside and find some other fun stuff to do - there are tons of possibilities.</item>
<item>If your parents don't let you walk around the neighborhood by yourself, then ask a neighbor to go with you!!</item>
<item>Make sure to have an adult with you when you go swimming.</item>
<item>Don't have a pool? Use a kiddie pool! It's fun and although you think you might be a little old, just go for it anyway. You can't be too old for some fun.</item>
<item>If you are a girl, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Paint_Your_Nails">paint your nails</ref>.</item>
<item>Try something new. You'd be surprised at the things you might enjoy so step out of your comfort zone a bit.</item>
<item>Make sure it is warm enough if you're going swimming. If it is winter, make sure that you have access to a heated indoor pool.</item>
<item>Try planning late night parties. That way it will be cool enough for outdoor games.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Learn_Gymnastics_at_Home">Do gymnastics</ref> on a mat/yoga mat.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Have the right equipment if you are going to play a sport so that you don't get injured.</item>
<item>If you are younger, always have someone around  if you are going swimming; most swimming centers have age limits for swimmers requiring guardians.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sports equipment (e.g.: Football,Tennis set, etc.) Exercise is good for you and still can be fun!</item>
<item>A blanket to sit on (if outdoors)</item>
<item>A book or magazine. (Reading can be fun and can improve your imagination.)</item>
<item>A Diary/Laptop/Notebook/Writing pad etc. (Write a diary or a story to keep you occupied.)</item>
<item>A Snack (You might be sick of getting up and down, so take a snack out with you.)</item></list>
</text>
