<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc111" title="Read a Man's Mind from a Woman's Point of View" shortTile="read-mans-mind-womans" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-09-02" dateModified="2018-07-10" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Read_a_Man%27s_Mind_from_a_Woman%27s_Point_of_View" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Read a Man's Mind from a Woman's Point of View</head><p>Is that guy two doors down an absolute mystery to you? Or do you just have difficulties understanding why your boyfriend does certain things? A father, brother, uncle, a teacher or your nation's prime minister, a man has many facets to his personality. Although seemingly difficult, men are easy to be understood. All you need to do is observe. Read on to find some tips on how to read a man's mind.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get to know him better. Talking to him, finding out his interests, beliefs, opinions, etc can really help when it comes to reading a guy's mind. Most men don't try hard to make their thoughts clear. They prefer to give hints with short terms like, 'I care about you', 'It doesn't matter to me', 'My childhood days were like...', 'I can't do it because...', 'I don't think you have what it takes' etc. Men, when asked, speak the truth. Like it or not.
<list type="unordered"><item>Do they ever lie saying, 'I love shopping for and with you', 'Go, conquer the world, fly high,...'? Not all, however most men prefer speaking the truth about things.</item>
<item>They lie about obvious acts they do which can make them look bad like cheating and humiliations.</item></list></item>
<item>Watch him. Guys tell a lot about themselves and what they're thinking through their body language.</item>
<item>Rationalize. If you can reason and be empathetic, he will be more likely and comfortable to share what you have to know. If you judge or humiliate him, he may not consider you friendly enough to open up with you.
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't let a third person know what you know. If he finds out, he may take it too seriously and never trust you with secrets.</item></list></item>
<item>Be honest. Try not to speak too supportive to be true or too encouraging that you may seem like you are faking it. He knows the truth. A word of encouragement can go a long way with men provided you are doing it keeping the truth in mind. If you go overboard or do it every other day, they may take it for granted.</item>
<item>Express you need for space. Don't cram or curb your needs that you feel suffocated. Men try to understand women's needs if they are vocal about and hold on to it. The more you allow them to take over, the more they may overpower you.</item>
<item>Let go of their persistent habits. The more you nag or whine about their bad habits at home, the more they may be consistent at it. Take a deep breath and let go for a long duration. If they care, they may do 'something' about it seeing that you can let go.
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't place your hopes too high though. It may not work or work for some time and come back as you change back to your own nagging again.</item></list></item>
<item>Keep at it. Even if you NEVER seem to be able to guess what he's thinking, don't give up! It gets easier with practice.</item>
<item>Point out their mistakes. Speak up if they are misunderstanding something and/ or are about to make a wrong decision. Even if they don't listen, after you are proven right, they will remember your word and be watchful of what you think in future decisions.</item>
<item>Don't be fooled. They may say all sorts of lies to win you if you like flattery. If you don't, they may try to act per your liking to make you agree to what they want. Observe their acts and make committed observations. Men are majorly fixed in their dealings. Truth is, if you must read a man's mind, you must be a committed observer. Keep a close eye on his dynamics on a daily routine and stay focus when there is a slight change in their behavioral chemistry. Sometimes, you need not engage a man to know what his next line of action will be. If your observation is perfect, chances are that you can predict his every move. Just like a game of chess, stay skillful.</item>
<item>Discern between good men and bad men. Chances are, men who do all sorts of repulsive things will hint at their filthy intents with their kind of suggestions, remarks, glance, gestures, etc. The good ones may not do anything at all to appear inactive in raising their opinions at all. A woman can tell between good and bad men by the way they touch, smile, glare or choose to do certain things. An intuition may be right in understanding hidden intentions. You can be careful and also appalled at knowing their truth. You have accept the truth though instead of running from any unacceptable truth. Because if you start running away from truth, you may run into problems and forget about yourself.</item>
<item>Know at your own stake. Whether or not to know a man is an individual choice. The more interest you take in him, the more interested he may get in you for better or for worse. Follow your heart, know when to stop, keep up with your life and give them space and time to know what they must know.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep in mind that all men are different and think differently so the way your ex-boyfriend thought isn't necessarily the way your new boyfriend is going to think.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Smile but not too often that they may think that you are extra interested in them.</item></list>
</text>
