<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc163" title="Work for Friends" shortTile="work-friends" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-06-03" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Work_for_Friends" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Work for Friends</head><p>Working for a friend can be both an advantage and a disadvantage. In order for you to make such a relationship work, you need to follow some accommodating steps. Review the following list of suggestions if you want to know how to work for a friend.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Decide if you really want to work for a friend. Recognize that under the worst circumstances, working for a friend may result in a severed friendship. Weigh the pros and the cons, and determine whether the job is worth the risk. <figure rend="Work for Friends Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make a list of all your concerns regarding working for friends. For example, ask yourself if you are willing to have a friend overseeing your projects, delegating work to you, setting deadlines and having certain expectations. Consider how you would respond if your friend had a problem with your performance or had to give you a written warning. <figure rend="Work for Friends Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Meet with your boss at work and be honest about your concerns. Discuss each of your expectations and agree that at work you will both maintain a business relationship. Ask that your work relationship not influence your friendship. Define clear roles, duties, and objectives so as to avoid future confrontations. <figure rend="Work for Friends Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Understand that your friend has to be your boss at work. Expect that it is just as difficult for your boss to maintain a professional relationship with you at work even though you are friends. Help your boss deal with the business relationship by assuming the position of employee. Know your place so that your friend is not put into a position of having to remind you. <figure rend="Work for Friends Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't expect special treatment because your boss is a friend. This is not a professional attitude--nor is it fair to you, your coworkers or your boss. <figure rend="Work for Friends Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Separate your work relationship from your personal friendship. When at work, remain professional and when at home or socializing with your friend, refrain from talking about work. You should also avoid office gossip or the temptation to reveal workplace secrets about other coworkers. <figure rend="Work for Friends Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remain professional at work, especially in front of other employees. Don't try to embarrass or undermine your boss. If you feel your boss is dealing with a situation the wrong way, then arrange a private meeting to discuss your concerns. Should your boss feel that the decision was correct, then accept it and move on. <figure rend="Work for Friends Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't discuss your boss with your coworkers or reveal private information. You may be friends with your coworkers, but don't try to gain credibility with them by revealing personal information about your boss. Don't try to use your friendship to help your coworkers. You are on equal ground with your coworkers, so don't elevate your status because your friend's the boss. Not only will this create resentment from your coworkers, but it will eventually result in friction between you and your boss. <figure rend="Work for Friends Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
