<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc187" title="Start over As a Teenager" shortTile="start-over-teenager" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-05-10" dateModified="2018-10-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Start_over_As_a_Teenager" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Start over As a Teenager</head><p>So all of us teens have this moment were you just feel like you need to start over. If it's because of a really bad breakup or you don't want to be 'that shy kid' anymore. Here is how you should start over your life and strive to become the best version of you.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Move on and forgive your past. If you are starting over, forget all the 'bad' things you've done and start thinking of all the good things you will do in the future. Try getting rid of anything that reminds you of whatever is bothering you, so it will be easier to forget. <figure rend="Start over As a Teenager Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start writing in a journal. If your goal is to eat healthier or to be more confident, try writing down what exactly you are going to do. You can write down healthy recipes to try to it's also a great friend to talk to because you can tell them anything. For example, if you want to gain confidence, write down what is holding you back from showing the world who you are. You shouldn't care what people think of you. All you have to know is that you try. Even if you don't succeed, you at least know that you tried. <figure rend="Start over As a Teenager Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Work on becoming healthy and fit. Having a balanced diet can make you feel refreshed. Make sure you eat the right foods and stay away from the evil ones like white sugar, white bread and fast food that is so processed, some types (like McDonalds) doesn't even rot. Having a balanced diet is good and all but exercise is also important. When you exercise, your body produces these hormones called endorphins. Also know as the Happy Hormones. These hormones will naturally make you feel great. Your body needs at least one day to rest. If you really don't know what to do, then do this. Go running for 30 minutes 3 times a week and the other 3 times go for a 30 minute walk. The other day will be your rest day. <figure rend="Start over As a Teenager Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make your room more "YOU". This is the final step. Since your bedroom is where you should feel most at home, it's hard to feel that way when it has nothing to do with you. Try to throw away or give away any unnecessary things like old toys, books or even clothes if you want. If you do that, just think of a theme for your room that will suit you. It might be neon colours, animals, plants, gaming, etc. If you have to share a room with someone, make a line down the middle of your room and tell them that they can't go on your side and you can't go on their side. <figure rend="Start over As a Teenager Step 4.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
