<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc44" title="Attain Ataraxia" shortTile="attain-ataraxia" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2016-06-01" dateModified="2019-03-28" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Attain_Ataraxia" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Attain Ataraxia</head><p>Ancient Greek philosopher Epicurus identified "Ataraxia," (ἀταραξία) a Greek word meaning "without trouble," as a mental state of peace, tranquility, balance and the root of happiness in life. Ataraxia is similar to the Buddhist concept of Nirvana but with less of the spirituality and mysticism attached to it. Unlike the concept of Nirvana, Ataraxia is not eternal. It does not defeat death. Epicurus never challenged the concept of human mortality with ideas of an afterlife or of reincarnation. His materialist philosophy recognized the mortality of humanity and the suffering that comes from that mortality but he argued that the suffering came from wanting too much from life and letting oneself be disappointed by not getting or having all that one wants. In order to defeat the suffering of life and achieve or attain a state of Ataraxia, or happiness, one must begin by eliminating all desires for wealth, luxury, power, prestige and romantic love.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Recognize that suffering comes from wanting too much from life, such as romantic love, luxuries (big houses, expensive clothes, fast cars), power, prestige, position and wealth. Recognize that all these</item>
<item>Recognize that all your suffering in life comes from wanting too much from the world, such as romantic love, luxuries (big houses, expensive clothes, fast cars), power, prestige, position and wealth. Recognize that all these things are fleeting and that you will not take them with you when you die. Recognize that the nature of wanting things is inherently painful. Wanting and not having something or striving for something and not getting it is painful. Living your life in obsession of the obtaining of these worldly things will only make you feel miserable about yourself. Even if you become the wealthiest person on earth you will still be miserable because nothing will ever be enough.</item>
<item>Free yourself from your desires. Stop wanting these things. Stop looking for power and prestige; its vanity. Stop looking for romantic love; it brings only jealousy, doubt, confusion and more suffering. Stop chasing money.</item>
<item>Learn to enjoy simple pleasures in life. Cherish the relationships you have with people that you love and people who love you. Work to enrich yourself with education and art. Learn new skills. We gain more satisfaction from what we do and what we learn to make than from the things we buy or own. Develop hobbies. Make friends and speak candidly and compassionately with them.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try eating simple foods.</item>
<item>Try wearing simple clothes.</item>
<item>Try driving an inexpensive car or not owning a car at all and riding a bicycle or public transportation instead.</item>
<item>Try not to obsess over how much money you or anyone else is making.</item>
<item>Try not to obsess over how you look.</item>
<item>Try to love yourself more.</item>
<item>Try to avoid feeling like you need anyone else's love in your life.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Epicureanism is an essentially hedonistic philosophy but it does not encourage some of the behaviors often associated with hedonism such as extravagance, gluttony, or excessive overindulgence in any behavior such as eating, sleeping, drinking (particularly alcohol), drug use, or sex. At the same time, Epicureanism does not condemn the moderate enjoyment of any of these activities, so long as they do not become the central focus of your life. If you allow any of these passions to consume you, you will become a miserable slave to passion and will lose your Ataraxia.</item>
<item>Epicurus encouraged simplicity but not necessarily poverty. His philosophy and his life may make him sound like a monk, but he did not live exactly like a monk as we know monks from the Buddhist or Christian traditions. He was a man and he enjoyed the natural joys of life. He did not condemn the enjoyment of the natural human behaviors but he warned that overindulgence easily leads to obsession and eventually suffering. The best way to break the cycle of suffering and attain Ataraxia is to let go of desire but not to deny yourself any and all pleasure in life.</item></list>
</text>
