<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc87" title="Calculate the Effect of Your Next Move with Your Girlfriend/Boyfriend" shortTile="calculate-effect" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-08-23" dateModified="2018-03-21" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Calculate_the_Effect_of_Your_Next_Move_with_Your_Girlfriend%2FBoyfriend" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Calculate the Effect of Your Next Move with Your Girlfriend/Boyfriend</head><p>Ever been in that disastrous situation when people dangerously mistook you? If your answer is yes, then this topic is all for you. Read on to learn more.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>If You Can Do It On Your Own</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Don't do the first thing that comes to your mind. It can probably ruin the conversation, or it can give the other person an impression of blabbermouth.</item>
<item>Get imaginative! You must have heard the saying "Think before you speak". If you never figured out how to do it, try thinking about the future events that would occur if you trigger them by your next action.
<list type="unordered"><item>e.g. If a girl asks you if you have a crush and you want to tell her that you have a crush on her, stop. If you say so, she might get embarrassed,or she might feel insecure around you if she didn't expect that answer from you.</item>
<item>If you still don't understand just think "What might happen if [whatever you would say]."</item></list></item>
<item>Don't just think - think fast or risk it. It is not always necessary that you can think fast.Just go for the best appropriate expression. If you can't think fast,people are definitely going to think that you are indecisive or ignoring them.
<list type="unordered"><item>e.g. There is a girl in your class who is jaw-dropping beautiful, but you can't think of how to approach or how your approach will effect her.Do not stall over her while you think.You can get in serious trouble.Instead,just walk over to her,bring out your hand for a handshake and say "Hello, I am [Your name], and you are?". This would give you enough time to think of your next action.</item></list></item></list>
<head>When You Can't Do It On Your Own</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>You come to a conclusion: you are really slow. Don't worry.Just ask the person what you should say in an interesting manner.
<list type="unordered"><item>e.g If your crush asks you whether you have a crush on someone, ask him/her "How would you react if I said I have a crush on you?" It does not end here.If they say they would be happy, then continue your conversation. However, if they say they would feel sad or hurt, say "I was just checking,don't worry."</item></list></item>
<item>Make them feel you are avoiding a certain topic for now. Tell them you will talk about it later. You can then go home and workout the future events for the next day effectively.</item>
<item>Keep your confidence up and keep saying "Sorry if you got me wrong." Nothing else can outperform this trick.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep innovating the future in your mind.After all the future is what you want it to be.</item></list>
</text>
