<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc183" title="Do Everything when You're a Girl" shortTile="everything-re-girl" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-09-23" dateModified="2019-09-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Do_Everything_when_You%27re_a_Girl" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Do Everything when You're a Girl</head><p>All you need to know as you grow up as a girl. This article explains how to do everything, get good grades in school, be happy, make your parents proud, get prepared for the career you want, keep healthy, get along well with others, feel great about yourself and everything! Read on from step one below, this is the only wikiHow a girl needs!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Know_How_Much_Sleep_You_Need">Get enough sleep</ref>. You need at least <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Have_a_Good_Night's_Sleep">eight hours of sleep</ref> each night. To make this easier, wear comfortable clothing to bed such as flannel shorts, an oversized t-shirt, or nothing if you prefer it. Once you've gotten into bed immediately turn out the light and get into your average position. If anything is uncomfortable fix it immediately until you're completely comfortable. Reading a book before bed helps to relax you.'The Sleep Book' by Doctor Seuss is a good one. <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Have_Good_Hygiene_(Girls)">Have good personal hygiene</ref>. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Wash_Your_Hands">Wash your hands</ref> after you use the bathroom and before you eat or prepare food. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Take_a_Shower">Take a shower</ref> at least every day. These are general health things you should keep in mind. <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Take_a_Water_Efficient_Shower">Shower efficiently</ref>. Wet your hair and scrub a quarter sized amount of shampoo into your scalp. Rinse out the shampoo thoroughly, squeezing the water out of your hair. Rub conditioner in the ends of your hair. Wash your body whilst the conditioner is still in your hair. Shave your legs and underarms if you like. Then rinse out the conditioner. <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have clean teeth. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Brush_Your_Teeth">Brush your teeth</ref> two or three times a day. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Floss">Floss</ref> one or two times a day. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Use_Mouthwash">Use mouthwash</ref> if you like. Be sure to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Go_to_the_Dentist">visit your dentist</ref> every six months to maintain good dental health. <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_Clear,_Smooth_Skin">Have clear skin</ref>. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Establish_an_Effective_Skincare_Routine">Find a face cleansing routine</ref> that works for you. A suggestion is to use a cleanser twice a day, a toner once a day, a moisturizer twice a day and a scrub or mask once a week. Use body moisturizer every so often to maintain soft, sweet smelling skin. <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Smell_Nice">Smell nice</ref>. Use deodorant if you think you'll sweat (if it's a hot day, if you have sport etc). If you like wear a little bit of perfume (make sure not to over-do it), or wear a pleasant body mist. <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Dress_Nice_Every_Day_(for_Girls)">Dress nice</ref>. Make sure you have the essentials. These include two pairs of good fit jeans (one blue and one black), one pair of good fit slacks, two sweater sets, two blouses, t-shirts in many colors, one above the knee skirt, one below the knee skirt, socks, tights or leggings, under garments, one pair of slip on shoes (little or no heel), one pair of tennis shoes, one pair of slip on shoes (higher heel), one pair of knee high boots, one pair of converse (plain black), two or three hoodies, one ski jacket, a few summer scarves and some belts and hats. Have some dresses if you like wearing them. Avoid jeans all together if you prefer. There are no rules about what you where when you have a free choice, no item of clothing is essential. <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have nice hair. Style your hair however you like. Your hairdresser can suggest some nice styles that suit you. Some things you might like to have to maintain nice hair are gel, hairspray, shampoo, conditioner, leave in conditioner, de-tangling spray, and temporary dye. <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you prefer to, wear make-up. Make-up essentials include blush, powder, concealer, chapstick, lipgloss, lipstick, eyeshadow, eyeliner, mascara, blush brush, eyeshadow brush, crease brush, eyebrow and lash brush and a lip brush. Don't over-do the make-up, as it looks tacky if you do. <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep well-kept nails. To do this you will need clippers and/or a nail file, cuticle cream and nail cleaner (optional). It's handy to have a cuticle pusher, a cuticle nipper, buffer and some nice nail polish. <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 10 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go well in school. Keep your grades up. If you're having trouble in a particular subject, ask your teacher, an older sibling or parent for help, or get a tutor. <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Maintain_a_Healthy_Weight">Maintain a healthy weight</ref>. Exercise regularly and eat healthily. Don't be afraid to eat chocolate or other food you enjoy once in a while and don't starve yourself. Some girls these days are unfortunately becoming anorexic or bulimic. Try not to become a victim of these conditions. If you have a friend who is interested in this, discourage them. If you know someone who is truly anorexic or bulimic, get them help by telling the school counselor or parents. <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have friendship in your life. Friends are important. Don't dump your old friends for new ones, and be friends with the right people. If they talk a lot and do not so well in school it will probably affect your grades. If someone is annoying you by constantly following you around, no matter how hard it is, just ask them if they could give you some alone time. <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Build_a_Positive_Attitude">positive attitude</ref>. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Happy">Be happy</ref>! Listen to adults such as parents and teachers, as they are, hopefully, wise and full of experience. You don't have to listen to everyone, only people that you trust and respect. If a peer tells you that you're not smart just tell them, "It's none of your business whether I'm doing well in school so don't tell me if I'm smart or not." <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 14 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Organized">Be organized</ref>. Keep your room, backpack, desk, and locker neat and tidy. If you're just a slob in general, try really hard to be organized as it helps with nearly all aspects of your life. <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 15 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get involved in hobbies and/or extra-curricular activities. Try playing an instrument, drawing, acting in a school play, taking up a sport etc. These activities help to keep you fulfilled and happy, and also builds new skills. <figure rend="Do Everything when You're a Girl Step 16 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
