<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc79" title="Recognize a Toxic Person" shortTile="recognize-toxic-person" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-10-19" dateModified="2019-06-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Recognize_a_Toxic_Person" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Recognize a Toxic Person</head>Toxic people are found in everyday life. Whether it be manipulating someone, judging, or more, they carry a lot of personality traits that are easy to catch. Once, you learn to recognize the traits, it will help you understand how to let go of toxic people.
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Understand manipulation. Mental manipulation, to be more precise, is a common trait found in toxic people. They will do anything they can to achieve manipulating someone, in the most emotionally damaging way, to get whatever they need. Whether it be an emotional, or a physical need, they will do whatever they can to get what they want. <figure rend="Screen Shot 2018 10 19 at 3.48.48 PM.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>This can lead to a person feeling that no matter what they do, they will never be good enough for someone.</item>
<item>There’s also a sense of they will not ever obtain happiness unless they are with this person or they will never amount to anything.</item></list></item>
<item>Recognize inconsistencies. Inconsistency is a well-known trait that toxic people possess. One day, they’ll be your best friend; the next, they treat you like you do not matter.
<list type="unordered"><item>You may find that you are not allowed to branch out and meet other people, but they are. They can do whatever they want but the second you try and do what they are doing, it is not deemed to be okay.</item></list></item>
<item>Notice narcissism. Toxic people can be very narcissistic. It is and will always be <hi rend="italic">all about them</hi>. If you received the highest grade in your class, you are on the honor role, and have a full ride to college, instead of congratulating you, they will somehow turn it into some success that they have.
<list type="unordered"><item>Alternatively, they will twist it into how much better they are than you and how your accomplishments and you as a person do not matter.</item></list></item>
<item>Note that they seek satisfaction. A toxic person usually seeks satisfaction in their relationships. They need to have all their needs meet as quickly as possible. <figure rend="SatisfyingTheirNeeds.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can’t do anything that will benefit or satisfy your own needs, everything has to be on their own time.</item></list></item>
<item>Understand that they are not typically supportive. If you receive a job promotion, they will not be as enthusiastic as you. If your best friend is getting married, they will not be happy for you.
<list type="unordered"><item>The only time they do care about anything that has to do with you, is if or when there is a positive impact on them.</item></list></item>
<item>Accept that they are rarely apologetic. They will be the last people to ever apologize to you. No matter how in the wrong they are, it is very difficult to get them to utter the words “I’m sorry”.
<list type="unordered"><item>This is tied to their ability to manipulate people. Somehow, their wrong will turn into something you did which will be significantly worse than what they “allegedly” did not do.</item></list></item>
<item>Realize that they judge you. Toxic people will judge you on everything that you do. If you talk to someone, drink your coffee without a straw, etc, they will judge you. If you don’t talk to someone, don’t drink coffee, and more, they will judge you. <figure rend="Screen Shot 2018 10 19 at 3.31.12 PM.png"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Anything that can benefit them, they will find a way to criticize you.</item></list></item>
<item>Watch for acts of "Divide and Conquer". People who are toxic, want you to decide between two things. Usually, that decision involves two people; them and another person. Very strategically, they will find a way to gain the attention and satisfaction they are seeking, even if it means you must cut an important relationship with someone else.
<list type="unordered"><item>As long as the toxic person is at the center of attention and satisfied, that is all that matters to them. <hi rend="bold">You</hi> must meet their satisfaction, always, so they monopolize your time, making sure it is <hi rend="italic">all about them</hi>.</item></list></item>
<item>Accept that "life" revolves around them. They tend to lack any interest in anything that is going on in your life. Toxic people cannot give you the care you need when it comes to stuff that may be going on.
<list type="unordered"><item>Relationships are already difficult as is, you need someone who shows a genuine interest in your life.</item>
<item>These are just the many traits that a toxic person possesses. Once you understand them, it will be easier to drift away from them, or, to identify their personality early on so you can prevent a toxic relationship. Here are some steps to help.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
