<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc188" title="Be a Successful Teen" shortTile="successful-teen" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-04-19" dateModified="2019-06-29" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Successful_Teen" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Successful Teen</head><p>When in high school you are introduced to brand new things like drugs, sex, alcohol, and peer pressure. It's very hard to stay away from these things, but there are things you can do to help. Always think twice, every decision you make has consequences.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be confident and learn more about yourself than you already know. Once you know who you are, you will be able to make smarter decisions on whether or not you will do drugs or have sex. <figure rend="Develop Poise Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Love and feel comfortable about yourself. It can be hard at times, but by constantly reminding yourself that you are amazing, it can save you from harder paths down the road. <figure rend="Develop Poise Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember that your family is there for you. If you're having a bad day, it wouldn't hurt to try to talk to your family. <figure rend="Be Who You Want to Be Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Remember that once you lose your virginity, it's gone for good. You can become baptized and be a "born-again" virgin, but that won't change the fact that you had sex at some point in your life.</item>
<item>Remember that drugs come with harsh consequences. While drugs may be fun, they are also a very serious and dangerous thing to have in your life. Being caught with drugs can prevent you from getting into the college you might have wanted. <figure rend="Stop Being Emotional Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Focus on studying and getting good grades. Ignore peers trying to get you to slack off with them. A good college will make you a lot happier than that pizza you grabbed with your friends on finals week. <figure rend="Deal With Migraines Step 1Bullet7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Ask yourself what kind of life you want to lead. Maybe talk to your school's counselor about this. Once you know the direction you want to have in life, it'll be easier to visualize and then achieve those goals. <figure rend="Deal With a Hard Life Step 1.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Stay connected! Having a support group of friends and family will help you stay happy and strong on your bad days.</item>
<item>Go talk to someone you trust if you're really starting to feel stressed, and remember, stress just happens sometimes.</item>
<item>Try to break relationships and friendships with anyone who is pressuring you or hurting you. They're not worth the energy to maintain a relationship with if they are trying to get you to do something you do not want to do.</item>
<item>Try keeping a journal to channel anger or stress into text.</item>
<item>Remember that the right decision for you might not be the right decision for those around you.</item>
<item>Always ignore peer pressure and listen to what you want to do, even though it'll be really hard sometimes.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Remember, "Stuff happens". The biggest part of being a good teen is staying happy, so if you're ever feeling down, just make yourself smile and laugh like an idiot. You'll feel stupid at first, but soon you'll be laughing from your own stupidity.</item>
<item>Being caught with drugs, even if you were just holding them for a friend, will get you in more trouble than it's worth. Even though you might feel like a jerk, just say no to holding drugs.</item>
<item>If you know that this is the "one" that you want in your life forever, and have thought about it for a while and know that you won't regret sleeping with this person, by all means, go ahead and have sex. But only if it's right for you.</item>
<item>A lot of people will tell you that sex and drugs are bad and need to be avoided at all costs. That is the right decision for them. While drugs are never a good escape, don't sink into a depression if you slip up and smoke once.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sleep</item>
<item>Strong-will</item>
<item>Judgement</item>
<item>Ability to say no</item></list>
</text>
