<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc74" title="Understand Stoicism" shortTile="understand-stoicism" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-05-18" dateModified="2019-03-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Understand_Stoicism" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Understand Stoicism</head><p>Ever heard of stoicism and wanted to know more, better still to understand and maybe become one.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Read about the origin of Stoicism.  Stoicism is a philosophy from the Graeco-Roman period of classical history. Founded by Zeno of Citium, whose works have now been lost. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take to heart the teachings of Zeno that all suffering comes from certain destructive emotions, known as the stoic passions. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>To achieve true happiness you must control your passions. The primary passions are distress, fear, lust and delight. These are described as follows by Zeno:
<list type="unordered"><item>Distress is an irrational contraction, or a fresh opinion that something bad is present, at which people think it right to be depressed. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 3Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Fear is an irrational aversion, or avoidance of an expected danger <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 3Bullet2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Lust is an irrational desire, or pursuit of an expected good. <figure rend="890870 3b3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Delight is an irrational swelling, or a fresh opinion that something good is present, at which people think it right to be elated. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 3Bullet4.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>All these are then sub-divided with different destructive emotions for each primary passion. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Read and understand Stoic writings based on the time period that they were written in.  Most Stoic works have been lost, to learn more about stoic thought read these: <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Marcus Aurelius' Meditations' and "Thoughts to Myself",Seneca's 'Letters from a stoic' and his 'On the shortness of life'. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 5Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>John Sellars' 'Stoicism' gives a good history of stoicism, that is easy to read, while comprehensive. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 5Bullet2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Bertrand Russell's 'A history of western philosophy' also discusses Stoicism, both of these will give you outside opinion of Stoicism. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 5Bullet3.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Control your emotions at all time through the right assent of external and internal impressions- this is the Stoic's famous principle.  Stoic calm has come into the English language from stoicism.  Stoic calm is a famously advocated principle by Stoics. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Lead a plain and simple life, disdain anything added by the way of decoration. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have a few Laconic tendencies, like Laconic brevity in speech and eating sparingly. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear simple but comfortable clothes. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>You should always be familiar with poverty, just in case you became poor. Stoicism doesn't mean you can't be rich, Seneca was a senator and Marcus Aurelius was an emperor, they merely advocated non-materialism. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Like the Buddhist idea of the universe, believe everything is constantly changing and humans were unimportant; just tiny parts of nature, it is therefore necessary for you to accept fate without fuss. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be happy in all circumstances. Stoic's advocated the idea that no matter what happens to you, you are still happy; a stoic saying goes something like this; Full of belly and happy, hungry and happy, well rested and happy, tired and happy, etc. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Prepare and be familiar with death for your life is short, however you must not be fearful, as fear is unbecoming to the stoic. <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Courage of the soul as well as humility and honesty is at the heart of the stoic philosophy, also compassion and solidarity between men <figure rend="Understand Stoicism Step 14.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always be ready and never take things for granted as they can be snatched from you at any moment.</item>
<item>Try meditation, many stoics advocated a Buddhist like meditation.
<list type="unordered"><item>Read and research stoicism to find out more.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Quick Summary</head>
</text>
