<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc80" title="Distance Yourself from a Negative Friend" shortTile="distance-yourself" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2019-03-30" dateModified="2019-05-27" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Distance_Yourself_from_a_Negative_Friend" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Distance Yourself from a Negative Friend</head><p>Friends can be a great part of your life. However, some friends begin to take advantage of your situations, deliberately be rude to your face, or drag you down with their problems. They can eat off your happiness, and even bring negative habits into your life. Those are obvious signs you should break it off... But how?</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Try avoiding a raging argument with this person. Often these people can be emotionally attached to you, and it can be hard to tell them that you don't think this will work. Try finding a private place to speak with them, and casually bringing it up during the end or beginning of a conversation.</item>
<item>Before you talk to them, remember the reasons you don't think this will work out. You can rehearse the event in your head. This way you will be mentally prepared for the situation, and not scramble for quick answers. Also, remember they have a side of the story and acknowledge it while speaking with them.</item>
<item>Keep your cool. The last thing you need is yelling or screaming with this person. Speak calmly and reasonably, and state your case. They might not agree with you, and if things get too heated, you can restate your case and try to exit the situation. They might not fully agree with you or understand, and trying, again and again, won't always work.</item>
<item>After you have talked to them, try to add some distance. Avoid getting pulled back into the negative relationship. Often the message might not fully reach them, and they might try to go back to the same friendship. Be wary of this, and avoid getting caught in the loop again.
<list type="unordered"><item>They might try to make some excuses for their behavior, so you must use your best reasoning here. Every situation varies. They might truly be hurt and telling the truth, or they might be using an excuse to draw you back into.</item>
<item>Example: Alena and Jordan have been friends forever; however, Jordan doesn't want to be Alena's friend. She feels like she can never be herself around Alena, and that Alena uses her as a crutch because she has no friends. Jordan tells Alena this, and Alena begins crying and complaining about her family life and how she has so lonely. Alena feels horrible and tries to support her friend again. A few months later, Jordan feels like Alena is taking control of her again.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try not to do this over texts. Emotions aren't fully explained, and it’s very flat and 2d. If you truly care for this person, try to meet with them. Texts can also sound like you don't care, and really hurt your friend.</item>
<item>Situations vary! Not all are the same, and a small conflict doesn't equal a terrible friendship. However, if your friend is abusing you mentally, physically, or emotionally. Ask an adult for help immediately.</item></list>
</text>
