<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc145" title="Take a Trip Without Feeling Guilty for Leaving the Kids Behind" shortTile="take-trip-without" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-02-22" dateModified="2019-01-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Take_a_Trip_Without_Feeling_Guilty_for_Leaving_the_Kids_Behind" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Take a Trip Without Feeling Guilty for Leaving the Kids Behind</head><p>Your kids are your responsibility, but sometimes you just need to take a break from parenting without guilt standing in the way. At the end of the day, you deserve a break - maybe even several days of break. Keep on reading for how to get rid of your guilt!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><figure rend="Prepare for a Trip Step 11.jpg"></figure> <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Prepare_for_a_Trip">Prepare for the trip</ref>. Make sure everything's perfect, like the time you'll be leaving and the time you'll be coming back, just so you know when you'll be back with your beloved children!</item>
<item><figure rend="Prepare for a Trip Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure> Tell the kids about it. They deserve to know where their parent is - you're supposed to be their role model, after all, so don't hold this back from them.  It might be rough if your kids always need you by their sides, but try to tell them your reasons and soon enough, they'll be convinced.</item>
<item><figure rend="Babysit Step 6 Version 3.jpg"></figure> Make sure your kids are in good hands. Leaving them alone is not a very good choice, especially if your kids are young and they won't be able to manage their lives or the house on their own. A trustworthy family member or a close friend should do the job for you - a babysitter might be too expensive for such a long trip.  Just make sure the kids like this person, or both your kids and their company's lives could be unpleasant while you're away.</item>
<item><figure rend="Raise a Child Step 16.jpg"></figure> Ensure that your kids won't need anything while you're away. Before you take off, make sure there's everything your kids might need in the house, and let them know how to use the washing machine and how to prepare a good meal for themselves, because take-outs aren't the best choice out there.  If you need to work out a ride to school, decide whether a short walk or use of the bus will be the best option, based on your location.</item>
<item><figure rend="Distract Yourself Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure> <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Distract_Yourself">Distract yourself</ref>.  If, despite your preparations, you still find yourself worrying about the kids, look at possible activities to fill your day and switch your mind to a different topic.  Spending the entire vacation in anxiety over your children won't make the trip worth it.</item>
<item><figure rend="Talk to a Girl over the Phone Step 6 Version 3.jpg"></figure> Stay in contact.  There's no need to ignore your family's existence.  Try scheduling a time each day to make a call, email, write letters, or otherwise contact the children.  You can even text throughout the day if you'd like.</item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Call home a lot. It'll be nice for the kids knowing you didn't forget about them.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>If your kids will have real problems without you there, maybe postpone that trip a little. There's nothing more important than your kid's safety!</item></list>
</text>
