<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc160" title="Work in an All Boy Environment" shortTile="work-boy-environment" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2014-07-31" dateModified="2017-05-05" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Work_in_an_All_Boy_Environment" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Work in an All Boy Environment</head><p>Are you working only with boys? It's important to have self control around them or you could end up in serious trouble. </p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Look for options between friends or just acquaintances. Observe for now; just see who's who. Follow your gut. For example, if a boy invites you to a party and you've only know him for one day, don't go. It may be tempting, but it's not worth the risk. Try going to future parties once you know him better. If one comes to work/class hammed, that's a no-no. But if there's a decent guy (friendly, has a good personality, honest, and reasonable), then continue with this person. <figure rend="Work in an All Boy Environment Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't see a guy and go, "He's mine" if you are a female.  As hard as it is, you need to calm down and think about the possibilities. If you work with this guy, it might cause problems at work. You could get fired, break his heart, and probably get a bad reputation from others. <figure rend="Work in an All Boy Environment Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't give it up completely; in very rare circumstances, it can work. But if you're an apprentice and you like the tradesman who is teaching you, then forget it. If you don't work together, it's not so much of a problem.</item></list></item>
<item>Think of him as a good guy friend. If you have a friend already, that's great! We don't want to be loners in our working careers. Treat him as you would treat any other person regardless of race, gender, looks and anything else, and hopefully he will treat you well back. If you like him, just ease into it. <figure rend="Work in an All Boy Environment Step 3.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't do something stupid, such as making out in the toilets, because he's hot. If you don't really know him, it could create something worse. Remember there are still boys, who most likely just want you to take your top off.
<list type="unordered"><item>It is not likely that they would cover you up if that happened. That's a bit biased, and not all are boys are like that, but sadly a majority of them are. Some are really lovely, though.</item></list></item></list></item>
<item>If you're still curious about any others at work/class, continue and observe. We can't be quick to judge, and if you're feeling a tad sneaky, you can listen in. See what they think of you, or something like that. That can be useful. <figure rend="Work in an All Boy Environment Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If most of them are your friends or acquaintances to you, simply sit near them/ wait for them to invite you over to sit with them, or try asking "May I please borrow some deodorant?" or "I have no lunch. Would you please lend me some food?"</item>
<item>Alternatively, just join there conversations on music, food, work, and so on. It does work and it takes some self confidence, courage and a leap of faith. Some are absolute gentlemen. This can be rare, but yes, they do exist. Just make sure he's not trying to win you over, and chat you up so he can get in your pants. Distinguish between being nice and being flirty.</item></list></item>
<item>If it's not really working, be shy and think before you speak. If you go to toilet and the toilet seat is up, don't go "You guys should put the seat down because I'm here." Just be casual and aloof. <figure rend="Work in an All Boy Environment Step 5.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If they burp loudly, ignore it. Don't convert the class/workplace into a girls' environment. This area of work is mostly there territory. For example, you wouldn't like if they turned your beauty salon into a guys' place to work. So, don't do it to theirs. Boys will be boys, but if you can brush it off and leave it, that's good.</item>
<item>Sometimes, if they talk about girls in an inappropriate way, leave the room. But if it's going too far or offends you in some way, tell your superior. It might cause problems and you can brush it off, but you still don't deserve to hear something that insults you or makes you feel uncomfortable.</item></list></item>
<item>Make sure you can handle this stuff. It's important to be safe with in any work space. If you can take any of these problems or curiosities (or anything like that), this will be a fun and fulfilling career for you. <figure rend="Work in an All Boy Environment Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If it's your passion, embrace it! Do it for yourself, because that's what you want to do. Don't let someone you're not happy with ruin it for you, and change your whole perspective, but they can make it a good experience for you, to live it up, and to follow your ambitions. Remember that this is for you.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't get too carried away.  There will be downfalls, but you should get up, keep trying, and avoid making the same mistake twice.</item></list>
</text>
