<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc92" title="Tell a Loved One You Have a Psychotic Disorder" shortTile="tell-loved-one-psychotic" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-08-09" dateModified="2017-10-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Tell_a_Loved_One_You_Have_a_Psychotic_Disorder" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tell a Loved One You Have a Psychotic Disorder</head><p>Psychosis is wildly misunderstood and stigmatized to the point where telling someone you love that you suffer from it can be a very anxiety-inducing event. Hopefully, one of these methods can help you open up to family, friends, or your partner and help you gain support.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Writing a Report</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prepare a report on psychosis with information and sub-categories so that you can make sure your loved one will have all the information and won't be confused. The sub categories should be:
<list type="unordered"><item>What is psychosis?</item>
<item>What are the symptoms of psychosis</item>
<item>Which symptoms affect me the most and how could you help?</item>
<item>Facts &amp; Myths about psychosis</item></list></item>
<item>You will have to do research on psychosis. Even though you have a psychotic disorder, you aren't told  everything about it. Although a lot of psychotic people can be aware of their psychosis, because the lack of grip on reality you might not be entirely aware of all the symptoms and ways it affects you. Especially if you had the psychotic disorder since you were a kid, you may have grew up thinking that some of the symptoms were things that everyone faced.
<list type="unordered"><item>A lot of your research should be from other people who face psychosis</item>
<item>Avoid any website that says psychotic people (or any mentally ill people) are inherently dangerous or abusive</item>
<item>When getting information from articles or blog posts, check the comment section to see if anyone's debunked the information or added anything extra</item></list></item>
<item>Proof-read your paper and then ask a friend to circle any mistakes with a red pen. If you aren't out about your psychotic disorder to any of your friends, privately message any article writers or bloggers who have psychosis and ask if they'd like to proof read your paper.</item>
<item>Choose a way to present this to your loved one! You can:
<list type="unordered"><item>Leave it on their bed / mail box / door step and ask them at the end of the letter to talk to you about it later</item>
<item>Sit them down beside you and ask if you can talk to them about something a little serious (respect their response if they say "could we later, I'm a bit busy right now") and then read it to them</item>
<item>Present your report like a classroom presentation, if you like you can even turn your report into a PowerPoint presentation</item>
<item>Make a video of yourself reading off the report and then show it to your loved one when you're ready</item></list></item></list>
<head>Have a Serious Conversation</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Instead of giving your loved one a bunch of information at once, tell them information piece by piece.
<list type="unordered"><item>say "I have a disorder that gives me psychosis. Psychosis isn't a disorder in itself, but it's something that you get sometimes when you're mentally ill. It messes up my sense of reality, meaning that I'll get hallucinations and delusions sometimes."</item>
<item>wait for your loved one to ask you any questions</item>
<item>try to answer with your best knowledge</item></list></item>
<item>Try not to force your loved one to stay and help if they are unable to do so.Your loved one might not understand, they might not be mentally healthy enough to help you, or they just might not be physically capable of helping you. If they have to go then let them go.</item>
<item>You also can not force your loved one to do anything for you because you need help coping.
<list type="unordered"><item>You can't make your loved one do something they're uncomfortable with</item>
<item>You can't  hurt your loved one (on purpose or on accident) and then use psychosis as an excuse. You still need to apologize when you hurt someone.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ask your loved one to do research of their own, but be around when they do it Incase they come across any uninformed websites</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be prepared for your loved one to leave or get upset</item>
<item>If your loved one is abusive towards you after you come out, try hour best to keep them out of your life</item></list>
</text>
