<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc139" title="Pack for a Trip to the Universal Orlando Resort" shortTile="pack-trip-universal" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2018-10-11" dateModified="2019-07-06" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Pack_for_a_Trip_to_the_Universal_Orlando_Resort" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pack for a Trip to the Universal Orlando Resort</head><p>The Universal Orlando Resort is a popular vacation destination, fun for people of all ages. However, figuring out how to pack can be daunting, especially if you’ve never been there before. This article will provide you with some valuable information on packing for your Universal Orlando Resort trip.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Before Starting to Pack</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Check the weather. This should be done about a week before your trip. Go online, and search “Weather in Orlando, Florida”, and you should get a forecast. This will help you with knowing what clothes you’ll need to pack.</item>
<item>Research airline luggage regulations if you’re flying. Find out how many bags you’re allowed to take, and the maximum weight they’re allowed to be. Make note of this information and keep it with you when you’re packing.
<list type="unordered"><item>If your bag exceeds the maximum weight, that’s okay. You just need to be prepared to pay the extra fee you’ll be charged, which varies from airline to airline.</item></list></item>
<item>Download the park app on your phone. The free Universal Orlando app provides you with ride wait times, the ability to purchase theme park tickets (and redeem them), and even more. It’s an essential for a great trip. </item>
<item>Know what size luggage you’ll need. If you’re only going for around three days or less, a smaller piece of luggage will most likely work fine. If you’re staying longer than that, then consider purchasing a larger piece of luggage.
<list type="unordered"><item>Knowing the needs of you and your group can help, because some may need to pack more than others, for different reasons such as something medical.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Packing Clothing and Accesories</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Pack your summer clothing. Especially if you are traveling during the summer months, the Universal Orlando Resort will likely be hot.Therefore, it’s essential that you pack things like sundresses, sunglasses, shorts and tank tops.</item>
<item>Include a bathing suit. This way, you’ll be able to take advantage of the water park, Volcano Bay, as well as your hotel pool, which can be especially beneficial in heat or after a long day at the parks.</item>
<item>Pack some warmer clothes. Especially if you’re traveling in the winter months, you may encounter a cooler day during your trip. Therefore, having some warmer clothes on hand will help prevent your group from being cold.
<list type="unordered"><item>You can avoid packing things like gloves and hats. You’ll likely only need a springtime jacket, some warm pants and a sweatshirt.</item></list></item>
<item>Add in some fancier clothing. Although most restaurants on the property are casual,  you may end up going off property to a restaurant that requires you to be dressed fancier.</item>
<item>Include some comfortable shoes. Like at any theme park, you’re going to be walking, <hi rend="italic">a lot</hi>. That is why having some comfortable shoes for you and all of the members of your party is going to be beneficial for everyone.</item>
<item>Consider taking a Harry Potter costume with you if you’re a Potterhead. This isn’t a must have, but it can be something unique to walk around the park in, especially if you’re a huge fan of Harry Potter.</item>
<item>Be sure to take ponchos along with you for every member of your group. Yes, it may be warm during your trip, but there’s a good chance it could also rain. Having ponchos is beneficial so that you don’t get caught in one of these showers.</item></list>
<head>Packing Other Essentials</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Include some sunscreen. This will be of the utmost importance, especially if you’re traveling during the summer months, as it will prevent you and your group members from getting sunburned.
<list type="unordered"><item>When you bring it, put it on even if it looks cloudy outside.</item>
<item>Do not take no for an answer, and make sure every member of your group puts on sunscreen.</item></list></item>
<item>Take a water bottle. Walking around can get pretty tiring, so having some nice, ice cold water with you will be very beneficial. Yes, you can buy water from the park, but a bottle will cost you 3 dollars, and even if you get free ice water from them, it comes in a tiny little cup with no lid on it. </item>
<item>Throw in a backpack. This way, you can easily store all your park essentials in one convenient place.
<list type="unordered"><item>Keep in mind however that on most of the thrill rides, you will be asked to store your backpack in a locker located near the ride. </item></list></item>
<item>Include basic medical things for your group. This could be things like Tylenol, band aids, a package of tissues, and hand sanitizer. This way, if a member of your group has a minor medical issue while in the park, you’ll save yourself a trip to first aid.</item>
<item>Add in a few snack items. This will be helpful for a long day in the park, if you’re stuck in a line and a member of your group is getting hungry. It will also be able to save you some cash in the long run.
<list type="unordered"><item>If you’re staying in a room with a mini fridge or other spaces for food storage, consider taking along items for breakfast and things like sandwiches. This way, you’ll be able to save money by not needing to go buy breakfast, and you can take a midday break in your room to eat lunch.</item></list></item>
<item>Take entertainment items for your kids. This will be helpful if you encounter a rainy day, and need to go back to the hotel. Your kids will likely not be bored, because they’ll still have fun things they can do.
<list type="unordered"><item>Some things you can take are their favorite dolls, a favorite book (or even a new one), and even some portable electronics.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be aware that while you can bring food items and store them in your room (and you can bring small snacks into the park), you are not allowed to bring any picnic lunches into the park. This is why it is recommended that you take a midday break and eat lunch in your hotel room. </item>
<item>You are also not allowed to bring any clothing that contains obscene/offensive messages or gestures. </item>
<item>Do your homework. Be sure to research the amenities that your resort offers, so you’ll know if you’re allowed to store food in your room. This will help to avoid potential upset or confusion.</item></list>
</text>
