<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc142" title="Fit Travel Into Your Life" shortTile="fit-travel-life" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2017-06-05" dateModified="2017-08-16" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Fit_Travel_Into_Your_Life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fit Travel Into Your Life</head><p>Most people think that they are too busy to travel, or have too many responsibilities. But what they don't realize is that traveling can help them clear their mind, give them a new learning experience, and help them get out of their comfort zone. Having these steps can help them fit traveling into their lives.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Deciding where you want to go. The first step in fitting traveling into your life is to think about where to go.  Make a list of all the locations you hope to visit someday and prioritize them. This can help you narrow down on where to go first. If still can't decide, start by choosing the first one that comes to your head</item>
<item>Think about why you want to travel. If you need a break from your hectic schedule, consider planning a relaxing beach vacation. If you are going crazy with boredom, look into an adventure vacation white-water rafting, zip lining, or rock climbing. Become one with nature by visiting a national park, or gain a new perspective by visiting a country halfway across the globe.</item>
<item>Choosing a date. Look at how many vacation days you have for work or look at your breaks you have from school and prioritize by that. Plan to save your vacation days instead of just wasting them just because you don't feel like going to work today. Once you know your date of travel, it is important to notify your boss or people significant to you so they know in advance you won't be available during your time of absence.</item>
<item>Setting a Budget. Do your best to estimate how much your entire trip will cost. Factor in travel expenses (plane or train tickets, gasoline if you're driving), hotels or hostels, travel insurance, passport or visa fees, transportation at your destination (taxis, buses, car rental), the average cost of a meal (or set the total amount you are allowed to spend on food each day). Be sure you leave yourself some cash to splurge on something special and something extra for emergencies. After you have this figured out, plan out your daily expenses by saving up a certain amount before your departure for your trip.</item>
<item>Annual physical check up. If you are heading outside of the country, check to see if you are up-to-date with your vaccinations. Initial consultation at a travel medicine clinic should occur at least four to six weeks before your departure to give yourself time to get your immunizations any assessments that might take some time.</item>
<item>Plan how to get there. Is your destination you want to reach close enough to drive or will you have to take a bus, plane, or train? There are dozens of websites you can use to search for reasonable flights all over the world. Take the time to check multiple booking search engines, as they don't always feature the same deals. Try the airlines' direct websites, too. If you're not flying, you can book train and bus travel online, too. If you planning to take a rental car, make sure you have a booking in advance just to make sure they have cars available the day of your departure.</item>
<item>Plan where to stay. There are tons of options when it is coming to where to stay. Make sure you look at the prices for each and what fits you the best. You can look into Airbnb's, hotels, hostels, or even apartments for rent. All are good options so just make sure you look at what can accommodate you the best for your trip.</item>
<item>Familiarize yourself with the destination you plan on visiting. If you are planning to visit somewhere where the language is different than your native language, learn a few key words such as-- "hello" or "thank you". If language is not an issue, still be familiar with what will be close by to where you will be.</item>
<item>Make an itinerary.  If you plan to visit multiple cities on your trip, try to determine how many days you will spend at each location. Decide which attractions are priorities and find out if you need tickets in advance. Make sure you are not too strict with the time, just because if you are running behind schedule it may disappoint you and spoil your trip.</item>
<item>Find someone to look over your home and pets.  If you will be gone for a significant period of time, you should probably find someone to take care of your house if you have houseplants and/or pets. Having somebody look after your house is also good for security purposes in case anything goes wrong while you are away. Also, coming back to a clean house gives you a good feeling after being away from it for a while.</item>
<item>Pack. Check the average weather at your destination for the time of year you are traveling. It can help with what to pack. If you are taking a flight, make sure to look at restrictions carry on items have on liquids and such. Don't forget to pack any medications you would need.</item>
<item>Get going! Double-check to make sure you have not left any loose ends before you leave on your trip. If you are flying print your boarding pass ahead of time. Check-in over the computer within 24 hours of your flight!</item></list>
</text>
