<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc171" title="Be Awesome (for Girls)" shortTile="awesome--girls" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-11-01" dateModified="2019-07-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_Awesome_%28for_Girls%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Awesome (for Girls)</head><p>Are you a girl? Do you want to become awesome anywhere circumstances may put you? Here's how.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Make_Friends">Make friends</ref> with people around you. Practice <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Start_a_Good_Conversation">starting good conversation</ref>. Humour makes people comfortable, and will help you form bonds with others. To <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Bond_With_Loved_Ones">form closer bonds,</ref> you can <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Host_a_Sleepover">hold a sleepover</ref> or <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Have_a_Party">have a party</ref> with people you'd like to get to know better. Parental consent comes first, though. <figure rend="Be Awesome for Girls Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Not_Care_What_People_Think">Don't worry about what others think of you</ref>. Everyone's different and everyone is <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Unique">unique</ref>. Also, don't change in order to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Fit_In">fit in</ref>. If the popular girls are wearing something amazing, that does not mean you have to have the exact same thing to be awesome. <figure rend="Be Awesome for Girls Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Active">Be active</ref>. Don't just sit there and be lazy, stand around with a racket occasionally. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Have_Fun">Have fun</ref> while you're being active or playing sports. Getting active will help <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Healthy">keep you healthy</ref>. <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Exercise">Regular exercise</ref> can improve your mood and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Relieve_Stress">relieve stress</ref>, ultimately making you a <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_a_Happier_Person">happier person</ref>. <figure rend="Be Awesome for Girls Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Do_Well_in_School">do well in school.</ref> Ask for help if you need it. It's okay to get a bad grade once in a while, as long as you tried your best. It is awesome to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_Good_Grades">get good grades</ref>, so <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Pay_Attention_in_Class">pay attention in class</ref> and put in the effort, especially math! Math and science aren't just subjects for boys. <figure rend="Be Awesome for Girls Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Develop your skills and talents. Skills take time to develop and effort to master. Different skills and talents are good conversation starters. People will soon be asking you to teach them new skills and vice versa. This can be in any field: gymnastics or sports in general, art, music, trivia, computer programming—you name it. Make sure to choose something you enjoy doing, not something everyone else wants to see you do. You can show off your skills once in a while, but don't be a big show-off otherwise people won't like you anymore. <figure rend="Be Awesome for Girls Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't be pushy and don't hang all over guys to get their attention. Just be their friend, enjoy their company and they'll appreciate you for it. And remember not to gossip or whinge to them; it makes them feel awkward and they'll ignore you. <figure rend="Be Awesome for Girls Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Dress_Cute">Wear cute clothes</ref>. You don't have to wear super expensive designer clothes all the time, but <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Cute">be cute</ref>. That doesn't mean that you go out of your way to look sleazy; comfortable and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Stylish">stylish</ref> is the goal. <figure rend="Be Awesome for Girls Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have your own unique, personal style. A good way to do that is to mix styles. For example, you can <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Get_a_Sporty_Cute_Look_(for_Girls)">be sporty and girly</ref> at the same time, or sophisticated or casual at the same time; run with it. Don't be too wild! <figure rend="Be Awesome for Girls Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't blend in: <hi rend="bold">Stand Out</hi> Dress in your own personal style (go back a step for more info). Make sure your style matches your personality: don't wear clothes or dress in fashions you don't feel comfortable in. Have your own "signature" look that no one else has. <figure rend="Be Awesome for Girls Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Just <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Love_Yourself">love yourself</ref> and everyone else will see your awesomeness. <figure rend="Be Awesome for Girls Step 10.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Becoming awesome doesn't mean you become snobbish.</item>
<item><ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Nice">Be nice</ref>. That is super important when it comes to being awesome.</item>
<item>Don't try to do/say things people have already done/said because then people will think you are a copycat.</item>
<item>Believe in yourself and be confident in who you are, what you do and what you look like!</item>
<item>Don't be nasty. Being nice is key to being awesome.</item></list>
</text>
