<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc206" title="Be a Good Kid at the Age of 12" shortTile="good-kid-age-" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2015-05-10" dateModified="2018-08-22" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Good_Kid_at_the_Age_of_12" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Good Kid at the Age of 12</head><p>Being a good kid has its ups and downs. You can no longer pull pranks, argue with your siblings and you lose some chances of having fun. But the good thing is that you'll be respected, gain trust and probably get some neat rewards from your parents!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Restrain yourself from telling lies. Though lying is a great way to get out of trouble, gain some sweet treats and get something we want, we don't actually need to lie. Even if it's little fibs, try not to lie, especially to your parents.
<list type="unordered"><item>One way to do so is to not have a reason to lie in the first place. For example, if you sneak out late at night and your parent finds you, you are naturally inclined to lie to get out of trouble. However, if you hadn't snuck out in the first place, you wouldn't have had to lie.</item></list></item>
<item>Obey your parents. When they tell you to take out the trash, do it! You'll probably get rewarded and thank your parents later in life.
<list type="unordered"><item>Your parents, by asking you to do certain things, are preparing you for your later life.</item>
<item>When you are independent, no one will be there to remind you to take out the trash. However, if your parents drilled it into you to do so when you were younger, you will remember.</item></list></item>
<item>Do all your chores without being asked to. This includes cleaning your bedroom, washing the dishes and putting away your games. This brings on responsibility and your parents will surely notice it, this way, when you ask to take up something like caring for a dog, they'll know you're responsible enough to do it. Don't act rude.</item>
<item>Don't use bad language. It is not necessary for you to curse or say rude remarks. If swearing is a habit, replace the swear with another word such as sugar or fudge.</item>
<item>Don't get in trouble at school. This includes being rude to teachers/classmates, disturbing the class or being late. This can have repercussions later in life, and if you want to have the reputation of being a good kid, getting in trouble is not the way to do so.
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't hang around with bad influences. If your friends tend to do bad things, you know they're bad to be with.</item>
<item>Even if you think you will be seen as cool to do bad things, don't do them. You know your own limits, and peer pressure is not the way to go.</item></list></item>
<item>Complete homework, tasks or assignments at school. Getting good grades is another step into becoming a good kid (and getting a better life).</item>
<item>Act mature. You don't need to be a grown up to be mature. Don't have tantrums on not getting what you want, Don't say things like <hi rend="italic">you're stupid</hi> or <hi rend="italic">you stink</hi>. Be polite and most importantly, be responsible.</item>
<item>Be respectful. This is one of the most important values in anyone, no matter what age. Respect should be shown to everyone and everything that shows respect to you.
<list type="unordered"><item>Your parents should especially have a lot of respect from you. This will show them that you are a good kid and that they can count on you. In return, they will respect you and give you more rights and freedoms but also more independence.</item>
<item>Friends deserve your respect as well. Friendship is important thing, especially at age 12, and respect is one way to solidify your childhood friendships. At this age there is a lot of drama, and respect can avoid that. Your friends will also respect you, which will give you a sense of security.</item>
<item>Many other people and even things deserve your respect too. Teachers, adults in general, and possessions are all in need of respect in order for you to be a happy, respected twelve-year old.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't hold grudges, forgive and forget instead. It is easier to be kind to somebody if you are not holding anything against them.</item>
<item>If you feel like you are pressured into acting up, just try to ignore the pressure to do so.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Telling a lie, hurting someone's feelings, can easily ruin your reputation as a good kid.</item></list>
</text>
