<text id="autogum_secondRound_doc172" title="Be an Intimidating Girl" shortTile="intimidating-girl" type="secondRound" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-11-22" dateModified="2019-07-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_an_Intimidating_Girl" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be an Intimidating Girl</head><p>Being a strong, independent, and confident girl in today's world can be "intimidating" to others. Successful people can be all these things without being hateful. Here's how to present yourself powerfully so others will know who's the boss.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Work on your Attitude: You have to have the "I don't care attitude" mostly when someone you feel is not worth your time talks to you. Look at them with one eyebrow raised, and your arms crossed, legs hips apart. Body language is key.  Also, practice a glare.  A glare is key, but make sure it says "You don't matter, but don't you dare show me attitude" . <figure rend="Be an Intimidating Girl Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Grow some humor. The way you talk plays a large role. Talk with dry humor, insult, and wit. Don't be afraid to insult someone to their face.Than throw in a signature stare, which is combined of  model eyes, and a slight smirk. <figure rend="Be an Intimidating Girl Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure you make it clear you are better than someone else. No matter how you do it. It's important to make your friends feel like they are on a lower level.You can laugh loudly with your friend to make everyone turn their heads when you make fun of people. <figure rend="Be an Intimidating Girl Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Appearance: Dress however you want, look however you want but not very 'feminine' or trendy, walk with a slight swagger(hand  slightly in your back or side pocket) as if you own the scene,because you know you do!Don't walk too fast, walk slower than normally and just think <hi rend="bold">smooth</hi>. <figure rend="Be an Intimidating Girl Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be smart. You have to be intimidating to everyone. Study hard in your spare time, read if you must. <figure rend="Be an Intimidating Girl Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Talk at every opportunity possible. Act like you know their deepest secrets and desires. Just stare right into their eyes, to make then uncomfortable, and when they get flushed and look away, smirk with your mouth closed.Never Back Down! <figure rend="Be an Intimidating Girl Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You can still smile, joke, laugh, and other things you usually do.</item>
<item>Don't try to change yourself for other people.</item>
<item>Being intimidating does not mean you have permission to be a cold-hearted person, or emotionless.</item>
<item>Don't try too hard, people will notice.</item>
<item>Don't over do your makeup or hair.</item>
<item>Be built, as a girl maybe you can lift weights and do push ups. Anything to grow you muscles, no one will mess with you!</item>
<item>Know that the boys and men might not be intimidated yet, but do everything above to get them intimidated.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't do this if you are the new kid. People will quickly shove you out and you will end up being a loner forever.</item>
<item>You might get shot down a lot.</item></list>
</text>
