<text id="autogum_fiction_doc130" title="Moran of the Lady Letty" shortTile="moranladyletty" author="Norris, Frank" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/3/2/321/321-0.txt">
<head>V. A Girl Captain</head>

<p>When Wilbur came on deck the morning after the sinking of the bark he was surprised to find the schooner under way again. Wilbur and Charlie had berthed forward during that night--Charlie with the hands, Wilbur in the Captain's hammock. The reason for this change of quarters had been found in a peremptory order from Moran during the dog-watch the preceding evening.</p>

<p>She had looked squarely at Wilbur from under her scowl, and had said briefly and in a fine contralto voice, that he had for the first time noted: “I berth aft, in the cabin; you and the Chinaman forward. Understand?”</p>

<p>Moran had only forestalled Wilbur's intention; while after her almost miraculous piece of seamanship in the rescue of the schooner, Charlie and the Chinese crew accorded her a respect that was almost superstitious.</p>

<p>Wilbur met her again at breakfast. She was still wearing men's clothing--part of Kitchell's outfit--and was booted to the knee; but now she wore no hat, and her enormous mane of rye-colored hair was braided into long strands near to the thickness of a man's arm. The redness of her face gave a startling effect to her pale blue eyes and sandy, heavy eyebrows, that easily lowered to a frown. She ate with her knife, and after pushing away her plate Wilbur observed that she drank half a tumbler of whiskey and water.</p>

<p>The conversation between the two was tame enough. There was no common ground upon which they could meet. To her father's death--no doubt an old matter even before her rescue--she made no allusion. Her attitude toward Wilbur was one of defiance and suspicion. Only once did she relax:</p>

<p>“How did you come to be aboard here with these rat-eaters--you're no sailor?” she said abruptly.</p>

<p>“Huh!” laughed Wilbur, mirthlessly; “huh! I was shanghaied.”</p>

<p>Moran smote the table with a red fist, and shouted with sonorous, bell-toned laughter.</p>

<p>“Shanghaied?--you? Now, that is really good. And what are you going to do now?”</p>

<p>“What are you going to do?”</p>

<p>“Signal the first home-bound vessel and be taken into Frisco. I've my insurance to collect (Wilbur had given her the 'Letty's' papers) and the disaster to report.”</p>

<p>“Well, I'm not keen on shark-hunting myself,” said Wilbur. But Moran showed no interest in his plans.</p>

<p>However, they soon found that they were not to be permitted to signal. At noon the same day the schooner sighted a steamship's smoke on the horizon, and began to raise her rapidly. Moran immediately bound on the ensign, union down, and broke it out at the peak.</p>

<p>Charlie, who was at the wheel, spoke a sentence in Chinese, and one of the hands drew his knife across the halyards and brought the distress signal to the deck. Moran turned upon Charlie with an oath, her brows knitted.</p>

<p>“No! No!” sang Charlie, closing his eyes and wagging his head. “No! Too muchee los' time; no can stop. You come downside cabin; you an' one-piece boss number two (this was Wilbur) have um chin-chin.”</p>

<p>The odd conclave assembled about Kitchell's table--the club-man, the half-masculine girl in men's clothes, and the Chinaman. The conference was an angry one, Wilbur and Moran insisting that they be put aboard the steamship, Charlie refusing with calm obstinacy.</p>

<p>“I have um chin-chin with China boys las' nigh'. China boy heap flaid, no can stop um steamship. Heap flaid too much talkee-talkee. No stop; go fish now; go fish chop-chop. Los' heap time; go fish. I no savvy sail um boat, China boy no savvy sail um boat. I tink um you savvy (and he pointed to Moran). I tink um you savvy plenty heap much disa bay. Boss number two, him no savvy sail um boat, but him savvy plenty many all same.'</p>

<p>“And we're to stop on board your dough-dish and navigate her for you?” shouted Moran, her face blazing.</p>

<p>Charlie nodded blandly: “I tink um yass.”</p>

<p>“And when we get back to port,” exclaimed Wilbur, “you think, perhaps I--we won't make it interesting for you?”</p>

<p>Charlie smiled.</p>

<p>“I tink um Six Company heap rich.”</p>

<p>“Well, get along,” ordered Moran, as though the schooner was her property, “and we'll talk it over.”</p>

<p>“China boy like you heap pretty big,” said Charlie to Moran, as he went out. “You savvy sail um boat all light; wanta you fo' captain. But,” he added, suddenly dropping his bland passivity as though he wore a mask, and for an instant allowing the wicked malevolent Cantonese to come to the surface, “China boy no likee funnee business, savvy?” Then with a smile of a Talleyrand he disappeared.</p>

<p>Moran and Wilbur were helpless for the present. They were but two against seven Chinamen. They must stay on board, if the coolies wished it; and if they were to stay it was a matter of their own personal safety that the “Bertha Millner” should be properly navigated.</p>

<p>“I'll captain her,” concluded Moran, sullenly, at the end of their talk. “You must act as mate, Mr. Wilbur. And don't get any mistaken idea into your head that, because I'm a young girl and alone, you are going to run things your way. I don't like funny business any better than Charlie.”</p>

<p>“Look here,” said Wilbur, complaining, “don't think I'm altogether a villain. I think you're a ripping fine girl. You're different from any kind of girl I ever met, of course, but you, by jingo, you're--you're splendid. There in the squall last evening, when you stood at the wheel, with your hair--”</p>
</text>
