<text id="autogum_fiction_doc244" title="The Go Ahead Boys and the Racing Motor-Boat" shortTile="goaheadboysracingmotorboat" author="Kay, Ross" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/5/6/562/562.txt">
<head>THE LOST FISH</head>

<p>"You come with me, Freddie," said Mr. Button. Fred's face flushed at the term applied to him by his grandfather and still deeper color appeared in his cheeks when he saw a mischievous expression appear in the eyes of the girls. To be called by the name be which he was called when he was a little fellow, or at least very much smaller than he was at the present time, was the last thing that could be applied him in the way of teasing. Mr. Button, however, had no thought of annoying his grandson and used the term simply because it had been familiar to him from the time when Fred was born.</p>

<p>"Good-by, Freddie, good-by," called the three Go Ahead boys together, as their comrade obediently followed the call and at once joined his grandfather and the man who had demanded the bond and turned into the street.</p>

<p>"That fellow was waiting for us," exclaimed George in surprise. "I believe that Mr. Button knew all the time that he was to be here."</p>

<p>"Well, what do you make of it?" inquired Grant.</p>

<p>"I don't know what to make of it. That man and a lot of his friends from the canal-boats force their way on board the Black Growler and leave only when they are scared by the coming of the Caledonia. Then the first thing we know he shows up here at Cape Vincent and orders us to give up a bond which he says we have."</p>

<p>"And the worst of it is that we have it," said George ruefully.</p>

<p>"HAD it, you mean," suggested Grant soberly.</p>

<p>"That's right," joined in John. "We gave it up and had it recorded in Fred's name. Now I suspect that those two men somehow have put up a job on Fred and that we'll lose our bond."</p>

<p>"'Our' bond is good," scoffed George.</p>

<p>"Well, whose is it?" demanded John.</p>

<p>"That's what we don't know, but that doesn't mean that everything we see, which may be the property of somebody we don't know, belongs to us."</p>

<p>"Well, if this Mr. Somebody owns that bond why doesn't he come and claim it?" retorted John.</p>

<p>"It's my opinion that Mr. Somebody has come," said Grant dryly.</p>

<p>"What do you mean?" inquired George.</p>

<p>"I don't know that I mean anything. I'm thinking though that the man who owns that bond, if it is good for anything, isn't going to rest easily until he finds out where it is."</p>

<p>"Do you think that boatman owns it?" asked John.</p>

<p>"It's plain that he knows something about it," answered Grant.</p>

<p>Meanwhile the two girls in the party were becoming somewhat impatient.</p>

<p>"My, nobody knows how thirsty I am!" said Miss Susie, who had been an interested listener and for some strange reason had not joined in the conversation.</p>

<p>"Plenty of water around here," suggested John.</p>

<p>"I don't mean that," said the girl quickly. "I mean something cold."</p>

<p>"And frozen?" asked John.</p>

<p>"My, how quick witted you are!" laughed the girl. "That's exactly what we want."</p>

<p>"I suppose we might as well give in first as last," said George in mock despair. "If anybody knows where we can get any ice cream we'll start."</p>

<p>"We'll start anyway," spoke up Miss Susie. "If we start we shall find it."</p>

<p>Evidently success attended the efforts to locate the ice cream parlors for long before the return of the boys and girls to the Black Growler, Fred and his grandfather had come back, the latter becoming more impatient with the failure of the young people to appear.</p>

<p>Sam Hodge meanwhile had been busily engaged in his inspection of the machinery of the Black Growler. When his task was completed he did not make any remarks, but his face apparently beamed with satisfaction.</p>

<p>"Sam," said Fred, "what do you think our chances are against that Varmint II?"</p>

<p>"'Gainst the which?" demanded Sam.</p>

<p>"That motor-boat that we were racing."</p>

<p>"I think it will depend somewhat on how fast we go," said Sam.</p>

<p>"What a wise man you are," laughed Fred. "I might have thought of that myself if I had tried hard. Do you think we can beat that boat? That's what I want to know."</p>

<p>"I think we can if we go faster than she does," replied Sam.</p>

<p>"Well, can we make her go faster?"</p>

<p>"You can if the speed is in her."</p>

<p>"Well, do you think the speed is in her?"</p>

<p>"I can't say just yet," said Sam, who was not to be moved from his cautious position. "Here come your friends," he added as the boys and girls were seen approaching the dock.</p>

<p>Mr. Button grumbled over the delay which had been caused by the failure of the young people to return, but as no one except Fred understood just what he was saying slight attention was paid him.</p>

<p>Meanwhile at Sam's command the engine was started, and the Black Growler, free from the dock once more, soon was noisily and speedily making her way down the mighty river.</p>

<p>"Why didn't you beat that other boat?" demanded Miss Susie of Fred.</p>

<p>"That wasn't what we were trying to do."</p>

<p>"Well, what were you trying to do?" demanded the girl.</p>

<p>"Testing our boat and at the same time trying to find out what time they could make in the Varmint II."</p>
</text>
