<text id="autogum_fiction_doc248" title="A Collection of Beatrix Potter Stories" shortTile="collectionbeatrixpotter" author="Potter, Beatrix" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/5/8/582/582.txt">
<head>THE PIE AND THE PATTY-PAN</head>

<p>Pussy-cat sits by the fire--how should she be fair? In walks the little dog--says "Pussy are you there? How do you do mistress Pussy? Mistress Pussy, how do you do?" "I thank you kindly, little dog, I fare as well as you!" Old Rhyme.</p>

<p>ONCE upon a time there was a Pussy-cat called Ribby, who invited a little dog called Duchess to tea.</p>

<p>"Come in good time, my dear Duchess," said Ribby's letter, "and we will have something so very nice. I am baking it in a pie-dish--a pie-dish with a pink rim. You never tasted anything so good! And YOU shall eat it all! <hi rend="italic">I</hi> will eat muffins, my dear Duchess!" wrote Ribby.</p>

<p>Duchess read the letter and wrote an answer:--"I will come with much pleasure at a quarter past four. But it is very strange. <hi rend="italic">I</hi> was just going to invite you to come here, to supper, my dear Ribby, to eat something MOST DELICIOUS."</p>

<p>"I will come very punctually, my dear Ribby," wrote Duchess; and then at the end she added--"I hope it isn't mouse?"</p>

<p>And then she thought that did not look quite polite; so she scratched out "isn't mouse" and changed it to "I hope it will be fine," and she gave her letter to the postman.</p>

<p>But she thought a great deal about Ribby's pie, and she read Ribby's letter over and over again.</p>

<p>"I am dreadfully afraid it WILL be mouse!" said Duchess to herself--"I really couldn't, COULDN'T eat mouse pie. And I shall have to eat it, because it is a party. And MY pie was going to be veal and ham. A pink and white pie-dish! and so is mine; just like Ribby's dishes; they were both bought at Tabitha Twitchit's."</p>

<p>Duchess went into her larder and took the pie off a shelf and looked at it.</p>

<p>"It is all ready to put into the oven. Such lovely pie-crust; and I put in a little tin patty-pan to hold up the crust; and I made a hole in the middle with a fork to let out the steam--Oh I do wish I could eat my own pie, instead of a pie made of mouse!"</p>

<p>Duchess considered and considered and read Ribby' s letter again--</p>

<p>"A pink and white pie-dish-and YOU shall eat it all. 'You' means me--then Ribby is not going to even taste the pie herself? A pink and white pie-dish! Ribby is sure to go out to buy the muffins..... Oh what a good idea! Why shouldn't I rush along and put my pie into Ribby's oven when Ribby isn't there?"</p>

<p>Duchess was quite delighted with her own cleverness!</p>

<p>Ribby in the meantime had received Duchess's answer, and as soon as she was sure that the little dog would come--she popped HER pie into the oven. There were two ovens, one above the other; some other knobs and handles were only ornamental and not intended to open. Ribby put the pie into the lower oven; the door was very stiff.</p>

<p>"The top oven bakes too quickly," said Ribby to herself. "It is a pie of the most delicate and tender mouse minced up with bacon. And I have taken out all the bones; because Duchess did nearly choke herself with a fish-bone last time I gave a party. She eats a little fast--rather big mouthfuls. But a most genteel and elegant little dog infinitely superior company to Cousin Tabitha Twitchit."</p>

<p>Ribby put on some coal and swept up the hearth. Then she went out with a can to the well, for water to fill up the kettle.</p>

<p>Then she began to set the room in order, for it was the sitting-room as well as the kitchen. She shook the mats out at the front-door and put them straight; the hearth-rug was a rabbit-skin. She dusted the clock and the ornaments on the mantelpiece, and she polished and rubbed the tables and chairs.</p>

<p>Then she spread a very clean white table-cloth, and set out her best china tea-set, which she took out of a wall-cupboard near the fireplace. The tea-cups were white with a pattern of pink roses; and the dinner-plates were white and blue.</p>

<p>When Ribby had laid the table she took a jug and a blue and white dish, and went out down the field to the farm, to fetch milk and butter.</p>

<p>When she came back, she peeped into the bottom oven; the pie looked very comfortable.</p>

<p>Ribby put on her shawl and bonnet and went out again with a basket, to the village shop to buy a packet of tea, a pound of lump sugar, and a pot of marmalade.</p>

<p>And just at the same time, Duchess came out of HER house, at the other end of the village.</p>

<p>Ribby met Duchess half-way own the street, also carrying a basket, covered with a cloth. They only bowed to one another; they did not speak, because they were going to have a party.</p>

<p>As soon as Duchess had got round the corner out of sight--she simply ran! Straight away to Ribby's house!</p>

<p>Ribby went into the shop and bought what she required, and came out, after a pleasant gossip with Cousin Tabitha Twitchit.</p>

<p>Cousin Tabitha was disdainful afterwards in conversation--</p>
</text>
