<text id="autogum_fiction_doc361" title="Master and Man" shortTile="masterman" author="Tolstoy, Leo, graf" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/9/8/986/986-0.txt">
<head>III</head>

<p>At the entrance to the street the wind still raged and the road was thickly covered with snow, but well within the village it was calm, warm, and cheerful. At one house a dog was barking, at another a woman, covering her head with her coat, came running from somewhere and entered the door of a hut, stopping on the threshold to have a look at the passing sledge. In the middle of the village girls could be heard singing.</p>

<p>Here in the village there seemed to be less wind and snow, and the frost was less keen.</p>

<p>‘Why, this is Grishkino,’ said Vasili Andreevich.</p>

<p>‘So it is,’ responded Nikita.</p>

<p>It really was Grishkino, which meant that they had gone too far to the left and had travelled some six miles, not quite in the direction they aimed at, but towards their destination for all that.</p>

<p>From Grishkino to Goryachkin was about another four miles.</p>

<p>In the middle of the village they almost ran into a tall man walking down the middle of the street.</p>

<p>‘Who are you?’ shouted the man, stopping the horse, and recognizing Vasili Anereevich he immediately took hold of the shaft, went along it hand over hand till he reached the sledge, and placed himself on the driver’s seat.</p>

<p>He was Isay, a peasant of Vasili Andreevich’s acquaintance, and well known as the principal horse-thief in the district.</p>

<p>‘Ah, Vasili Andreevich! Where are you off to?’ said Isay, enveloping Nikita in the odour of the vodka he had drunk.</p>

<p>‘We were going to Goryachkin.’</p>

<p>‘And look where you’ve got to! You should have gone through Molchanovka.’</p>

<p>‘Should have, but didn’t manage it,’ said Vasili Andreevich, holding in the horse.</p>

<p>‘That’s a good horse,’ said Isay, with a shrewd glance at Mukhorty, and with a practised hand he tightened the loosened knot high in the horse’s bushy tail.</p>

<p>‘Are you going to stay the night?’</p>

<p>‘No, friend. I must get on.’</p>

<p>‘Your business must be pressing. And who is this? Ah, Nikita Stepanych!’</p>

<p>‘Who else?’ replied Nikita. ‘But I say, good friend, how are we to avoid going astray again?’</p>

<p>‘Where can you go astray here? Turn back straight down the street and then when you come out keep straight on. Don’t take to the left. You will come out onto the high road, and then turn to the right.’</p>

<p>‘And where do we turn off the high road? As in summer, or the winter way?’ asked Nikita.</p>

<p>‘The winter way. As soon as you turn off you’ll see some bushes, and opposite them there is a way-mark--a large oak, one with branches--and that’s the way.’</p>

<p>Vasili Andreevich turned the horse back and drove through the outskirts of the village.</p>

<p>‘Why not stay the night?’ Isay shouted after them.</p>

<p>But Vasili Andreevich did not answer and touched up the horse. Four miles of good road, two of which lay through the forest, seemed easy to manage, especially as the wind was apparently quieter and the snow had stopped.</p>

<p>Having driven along the trodden village street, darkened here and there by fresh manure, past the yard where the clothes hung out and where the white shirt had broken loose and was now attached only by one frozen sleeve, they again came within sound of the weird moan of the willows, and again emerged on the open fields. The storm, far from ceasing, seemed to have grown yet stronger. The road was completely covered with drifting snow, and only the stakes showed that they had not lost their way. But even the stakes ahead of them were not easy to see, since the wind blew in their faces.</p>

<p>Vasili Andreevich screwed up his eyes, bent down his head, and looked out for the way-marks, but trusted mainly to the horse’s sagacity, letting it take its own way. And the horse really did not lose the road but followed its windings, turning now to the right and now to the left and sensing it under his feet, so that though the snow fell thicker and the wind strengthened they still continued to see way-marks now to the left and now to the right of them.</p>

<p>So they travelled on for about ten minutes, when suddenly, through the slanting screen of wind-driven snow, something black showed up which moved in front of the horse.</p>

<p>This was another sledge with fellow-travellers. Mukhorty overtook them, and struck his hoofs against the back of the sledge in front of them.</p>

<p>‘Pass on... hey there... get in front!’ cried voices from the sledge.</p>

<p>Vasili Andreevich swerved aside to pass the other sledge.</p>

<p>In it sat three men and a woman, evidently visitors returning from a feast. One peasant was whacking the snow-covered croup of their little horse with a long switch, and the other two sitting in front waved their arms and shouted something. The woman, completely wrapped up and covered with snow, sat drowsing and bumping at the back.</p>

<p>‘Who are you?’ shouted Vasili Andreevich.</p>

<p>‘From A-a-a...’ was all that could be heard.</p>

<p>‘I say, where are you from?’</p>

<p>‘From A-a-a-a!’ one of the peasants shouted with all his might, but still it was impossible to make out who they were.</p>

<p>‘Get along! Keep up!’ shouted another, ceaselessly beating his horse with the switch.</p>

<p>‘So you’re from a feast, it seems?’</p>

<p>‘Go on, go on! Faster, Simon! Get in front! Faster!’</p>
</text>
