<text id="autogum_fiction_doc289" title="The Round-Up: A Romance of Arizona; Novelized from Edmund Day's Melodrama" shortTile="roundupromancearizona" author="Miller, Marion Mills" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/7/6/763/763.txt">
<head>Josephine Opens the Sluices</head>

<p>Entering the living-room, Bud found Echo surrounded by several girls from Florence and the neighboring ranches, who were driving her almost distracted with their admiring attentions, for she was greatly disturbed about her lover's inexplicable absence. Had she been free from the duties of hospitality, she would have leaped on her horse and gone in search of him.</p>

<p>Echo's wedding-attire would seem as incongruous as Jack's to the eyes of an Easterner, yet it was entirely suited to the circumstances, for the couple intended, as soon as they were married, to ride to a little hunting-cabin of Jack's in the Tortilla Mountains, where they would spend their honeymoon.</p>

<p>She was dressed in an olive-green riding-habit, which she had brought from the East. The skirt was divided, and reached just below the knee; her blouse, of lighter material, and brown in color, was loose, allowing free play for her arms and shoulders. High riding-boots were laced to the knee. A sombrero and riding-gloves lay on the table ready to complete her costume.</p>

<p>Bud coldly acknowledged Echo's affectionate and happy greeting, and curtly informed her that Jack had arrived.</p>

<p>She rushed out of doors with a cry of joy.</p>

<p>Running across the courtyard toward her lover, who awaited her with outstretched arms, she began:</p>

<p>"Well, this is a nice time, you outrageous--" when Polly stopped her with a mock-serious look. "Wait a minute--wait a minute" (the girl drawled as if reining in a too eager horse) "don't commence calling love-names before you get the hitch--time enough after. He has been actin' up something scandalous with me."</p>

<p>Jack threw up his hands in protest, hastily denying any probable charge that the tease might make. "Why, I haven't been saying a word!" he cried.</p>

<p>Polly laughed as she ran to the door.</p>

<p>"No, you haven't," she answered mockingly, as one agrees with a child whose feelings have been hurt. "He's only been tellin' me he loved--" Pausing an instant, she pointed at Echo, ending her sentence with a shouted "you."</p>

<p>With her hand on Jack's shoulder, Echo said: "Polly, you are a flirt. You've too many strings to your bow."</p>

<p>"You mean I've too many beaux to my string!" laughingly answered the girl.</p>

<p>"You'll have Slim Hoover and Bud Lane shooting each other up all on your account," chided Echo.</p>

<p>"Nothing of the kind," pouted Polly. "Can't a girl have friends? But I know what you two are waiting for?"</p>

<p>"What?" asked Jack.</p>

<p>"You want me to vamose. I'm hep. I'll vam."</p>

<p>And Polly ran into the kitchen to tell the men that the bridegroom had arrived, but couldn't be seen until the bride was through with an important interview with him. So she hustled them all into the living-room, where the girls were.</p>

<p>This room was a long and low apartment, roughly plastered. The heavy ceiling-beams, hewn with axes, were uncovered, giving an old English effect, although this was not striven for, but made under the stress of necessity. The broad windows were trellised with vines, through which filtered the sunshine. A cooling evening breeze stirred the leaves lazily. The chairs were broad and comfortable--the workmanship of the monks of the neighboring mission. In the corners stood squat, earthen water-jars of Mexican molding. On the adobe walls were hung trophies of the hunt; war-bonnets and the crudely made adornments of the Apaches.</p>

<p>Navajo blankets covered the window-seats, and were used as screens for sets of shelves built into the spaces between the windows.</p>

<p>Polly carried in on a tray a large bowl of punch surrounded by glasses and gourds. This was received with riotous demonstrations. She placed it in the center of a table made of planks laid on trestles, and assisted by the other girls, served the men liberally from the bowl.</p>

<p>The guests showed the effects of outdoor life and training. Their gestures were full and free. The tones of their voices were high-pitched, but they spoke more slowly than their Eastern cousins, as if feeling the necessity, even when confined, of making every word carry. No one lolled in his seat, but sat upright, as if still having the feel of the saddle under him.</p>

<p>Toward women in all social gatherings, the cowboys act with exaggerated chivalry, but, as Sage-brush would describe it, they "herd by their lonesome." There is none of the commingling of sexes seen in the East. At a dance the girls sit at one end of the room, the men group themselves about the doorway until the music strikes up. Then each will seize his partner after the boldest has made the first move. When the dance-measure ends the cowboy will rarely escort partner to her seat, but will leave her to find her way back to her chum, while he moves sheepishly back to the doorway, to be received by his fellows with slaps on the back and loud jests. At table cowboys carry on little conversation with the girls. They talk amongst themselves, but at the women. The presence of the girls leads them to play many pranks on one another. The ice is long in breaking, for their habitual reserve is not easily worn off. Later in the evening this shyness is less marked.</p>

<p>As Jack and Echo entered the doorway, Parenthesis had arisen from his seat at the head of table and was beginning: "Fellow citizens--"</p>
</text>
