<text id="autogum_fiction_doc3" title="Three Sunsets and Other Poems" author="Lewis Carroll">
<head>BEATRICE.</head>

<p>In her eyes is the living light Of a wanderer to earth From a far celestial height: Summers five are all the span-- Summers five since Time began To veil in mists of human night A shining angel-birth.</p>

<p>Does an angel look from her eyes? Will she suddenly spring away, And soar to her home in the skies? Beatrice! Blessing and blessed to be! Beatrice! Still, as I gaze on thee, Visions of two sweet maids arise, Whose life was of yesterday:</p>

<p>Of a Beatrice pale and stern, With the lips of a dumb despair, With the innocent eyes that yearn-- Yearn for the young sweet hours of life, Far from sorrow and far from strife, For the happy summers, that never return, When the world seemed good and fair:</p>

<p>Of a Beatrice glorious, bright-- Of a sainted, ethereal maid, Whose blue eyes are deep fountains of light, Cheering the poet that broodeth apart, Filling with gladness his desolate heart, Like the moon when she shines thro' a cloudless night On a world of silence and shade.</p>

<p>And the visions waver and faint, And the visions vanish away That my fancy delighted to paint-- She is here at my side, a living child, With the glowing cheek and the tresses wild, Nor death-pale martyr, nor radiant saint, Yet stainless and bright as they.</p>

<p>For I think, if a grim wild beast Were to come from his charnel-cave, From his jungle-home in the East-- Stealthily creeping with bated breath, Stealthily creeping with eyes of death-- He would all forget his dream of the feast, And crouch at her feet a slave.</p>

<p>She would twine her hand in his mane: She would prattle in silvery tone, Like the tinkle of summer-rain-- Questioning him with her laughing eyes, Questioning him with a glad surprise, Till she caught from those fierce eyes again The love that lit her own.</p>

<p>And be sure, if a savage heart, In a mask of human guise, Were to come on her here apart-- Bound for a dark and a deadly deed, Hurrying past with pitiless speed-- He would suddenly falter and guiltily start At the glance of her pure blue eyes.</p>

<p>Nay, be sure, if an angel fair, A bright seraph undefiled, Were to stoop from the trackless air, Fain would she linger in glad amaze-- Lovingly linger to ponder and gaze, With a sister's love and a sister's care, On the happy, innocent child.</p>

<head><hi rend="italic">Dec. 4, 1862.</hi></head>

<p><figure/></p>

<head>STOLEN WATERS.</head>

<p>The light was faint, and soft the air That breathed around the place; And she was lithe, and tall, and fair, And with a wayward grace Her queenly head she bare.</p>

<p>With glowing cheek, with gleaming eye, She met me on the way: My spirit owned the witchery Within her smile that lay: I followed her, I knew not why.</p>

<p>The trees were thick with many a fruit, The grass with many a flower: My soul was dead, my tongue was mute, In that accursëd hour.</p>

<p>And, in my dream, with silvery voice, She said, or seemed to say, "Youth is the season to rejoice--" I could not choose but stay: I could not say her nay.</p>

<p>She plucked a branch above her head, With rarest fruitage laden: "Drink of the juice, Sir Knight," she said: "'Tis good for knight and maiden."</p>

<p>Oh, blind mine eye that would not trace-- Oh, deaf mine ear that would not heed-- The mocking smile upon her face, The mocking voice of greed!</p>

<p>I drank the juice; and straightway felt A fire within my brain: My soul within me seemed to melt In sweet delirious pain.</p>

<p>"Sweet is the stolen draught," she said: "Hath sweetness stint or measure? Pleasant the secret hoard of bread: What bars us from our pleasure?"</p>

<p>"Yea, take we pleasure while we may," I heard myself replying. In the red sunset, far away, My happier life was dying: My heart was sad, my voice was gay.</p>

<p>And unawares, I knew not how, I kissed her dainty finger-tips, I kissed her on the lily brow, I kissed her on the false, false lips-- That burning kiss, I feel it now!</p>

<p>"True love gives true love of the best: Then take," I cried, "my heart to thee!" The very heart from out my breast I plucked, I gave it willingly: Her very heart she gave to me-- Then died the glory from the west.</p>

<p>In the gray light I saw her face, And it was withered, old, and gray; The flowers were fading in their place, Were fading with the fading day.</p>

<p>Forth from her, like a hunted deer, Through all that ghastly night I fled, And still behind me seemed to hear Her fierce unflagging tread; And scarce drew breath for fear.</p>

<p>Yet marked I well how strangely seemed The heart within my breast to sleep: Silent it lay, or so I dreamed, With never a throb or leap.</p>

<p>For hers was now my heart, she said, The heart that once had been mine own: And in my breast I bore instead A cold, cold heart of stone. So grew the morning overhead.</p>

<p>The sun shot downward through the trees His old familiar flame: All ancient sounds upon the breeze From copse and meadow came-- But I was not the same.</p>

<p>They call me mad: I smile, I weep, Uncaring how or why: Yea, when one's heart is laid asleep, What better than to die? So that the grave be dark and deep.</p>

<p>To die! To die? And yet, methinks, I drink of life, to-day, Deep as the thirsty traveler drinks Of fountain by the way: My voice is sad, my heart is gay.</p>

<p>When yestereve was on the wane, I heard a clear voice singing So sweetly that, like summer-rain, My happy tears came springing: My human heart returned again.</p>

<p>_"A rosy child, Sitting and singing, in a garden fair, The joy of hearing, seeing, The simple joy of being-- Or twining rosebuds in the golden hair That ripples free and wild.</p>

<p>"A sweet pale child-- Wearily looking to the purple West-- Waiting the great For-ever That suddenly shall sever The cruel chains that hold her from her rest-- By earth-joys unbeguiled.</p>
</text>
