<text id="autogum_fiction_doc120" title="The Early Short Fiction of Edith Wharton — Part 1" shortTile="earlyshortfictionedith" author="Wharton, Edith" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/2/9/295/295-0.txt">
<head>II</head>

<p>As Wyant emerged from the house he paused once more to glance up at its scarred brick facade. The marble hand drooped tragically above the entrance: in the waning light it seemed to have relaxed into the passiveness of despair, and Wyant stood musing on its hidden meaning. But the Dead Hand was not the only mysterious thing about Doctor Lombard’s house. What were the relations between Miss Lombard and her father? Above all, between Miss Lombard and her picture? She did not look like a person capable of a disinterested passion for the arts; and there had been moments when it struck Wyant that she hated the picture.</p>

<p>The sky at the end of the street was flooded with turbulent yellow light, and the young man turned his steps toward the church of San Domenico, in the hope of catching the lingering brightness on Sodoma’s St. Catherine.</p>

<p>The great bare aisles were almost dark when he entered, and he had to grope his way to the chapel steps. Under the momentary evocation of the sunset, the saint’s figure emerged pale and swooning from the dusk, and the warm light gave a sensual tinge to her ecstasy. The flesh seemed to glow and heave, the eyelids to tremble; Wyant stood fascinated by the accidental collaboration of light and color.</p>

<p>Suddenly he noticed that something white had fluttered to the ground at his feet. He stooped and picked up a small thin sheet of note-paper, folded and sealed like an old-fashioned letter, and bearing the superscription:--</p>

<p>To the Count Ottaviano Celsi.</p>

<p>Wyant stared at this mysterious document. Where had it come from? He was distinctly conscious of having seen it fall through the air, close to his feet. He glanced up at the dark ceiling of the chapel; then he turned and looked about the church. There was only one figure in it, that of a man who knelt near the high altar.</p>

<p>Suddenly Wyant recalled the question of Doctor Lombard’s maid-servant. Was this the letter she had asked for? Had he been unconsciously carrying it about with him all the afternoon? Who was Count Ottaviano Celsi, and how came Wyant to have been chosen to act as that nobleman’s ambulant letter-box?</p>

<p>Wyant laid his hat and stick on the chapel steps and began to explore his pockets, in the irrational hope of finding there some clue to the mystery; but they held nothing which he had not himself put there, and he was reduced to wondering how the letter, supposing some unknown hand to have bestowed it on him, had happened to fall out while he stood motionless before the picture.</p>

<p>At this point he was disturbed by a step on the floor of the aisle, and turning, he saw his lustrous-eyed neighbor of the table d’hote.</p>

<p>The young man bowed and waved an apologetic hand.</p>

<p>“I do not intrude?” he inquired suavely.</p>

<p>Without waiting for a reply, he mounted the steps of the chapel, glancing about him with the affable air of an afternoon caller.</p>

<p>“I see,” he remarked with a smile, “that you know the hour at which our saint should be visited.”</p>

<p>Wyant agreed that the hour was indeed felicitous.</p>

<p>The stranger stood beamingly before the picture.</p>

<p>“What grace! What poetry!” he murmured, apostrophizing the St. Catherine, but letting his glance slip rapidly about the chapel as he spoke.</p>

<p>Wyant, detecting the manoeuvre, murmured a brief assent.</p>

<p>“But it is cold here--mortally cold; you do not find it so?” The intruder put on his hat. “It is permitted at this hour--when the church is empty. And you, my dear sir--do you not feel the dampness? You are an artist, are you not? And to artists it is permitted to cover the head when they are engaged in the study of the paintings.”</p>

<p>He darted suddenly toward the steps and bent over Wyant’s hat.</p>

<p>“Permit me--cover yourself!” he said a moment later, holding out the hat with an ingratiating gesture.</p>

<p>A light flashed on Wyant.</p>

<p>“Perhaps,” he said, looking straight at the young man, “you will tell me your name. My own is Wyant.”</p>

<p>The stranger, surprised, but not disconcerted, drew forth a coroneted card, which he offered with a low bow. On the card was engraved:--</p>

<p>Il Conte Ottaviano Celsi.</p>

<p>“I am much obliged to you,” said Wyant; “and I may as well tell you that the letter which you apparently expected to find in the lining of my hat is not there, but in my pocket.”</p>

<p>He drew it out and handed it to its owner, who had grown very pale.</p>

<p>“And now,” Wyant continued, “you will perhaps be good enough to tell me what all this means.”</p>

<p>There was no mistaking the effect produced on Count Ottaviano by this request. His lips moved, but he achieved only an ineffectual smile.</p>

<p>“I suppose you know,” Wyant went on, his anger rising at the sight of the other’s discomfiture, “that you have taken an unwarrantable liberty. I don’t yet understand what part I have been made to play, but it’s evident that you have made use of me to serve some purpose of your own, and I propose to know the reason why.”</p>

<p>Count Ottaviano advanced with an imploring gesture.</p>

<p>“Sir,” he pleaded, “you permit me to speak?”</p>

<p>“I expect you to,” cried Wyant. “But not here,” he added, hearing the clank of the verger’s keys. “It is growing dark, and we shall be turned out in a few minutes.”</p>
</text>
