<text id="autogum_fiction_doc234" title="The Underdogs: A Novel of the Mexican Revolution" shortTile="underdogsnovelmexican" author="Azuela, Mariano" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/5/4/549/549.txt">
<head>IX</head>

<p>A whirlwind of dust, scorching down the road, suddenly broke into violent diffuse masses; and Demetrio's army emerged, a chaos of horses, broad chests, tangled manes, dilated nostrils, oval, wide eyes, hoofs flying in the air, legs stiffened from endless galloping; and of men with bronze faces, ivory teeth, and flashing eyes, their rifles in their hands or slung across the saddles.</p>

<p>Demetrio and Camilla brought up the rear. She was still nervous, white-lipped and parched; he was angry at their futile maneuver. For there had been battles, no followers of Orozco's to be seen. A handful of Federals, routed. A poor devil of a priest left dangling from a mesquite; a few dead, scattered over the field, who had once been united under the archaic slogan, RIGHTS AND RELIGION, with, on their breasts, the red cloth insignia: Halt! The Sacred Heart of Jesus is with me!</p>

<p>"One good thing about it is that I've collected all my back pay," Quail said, exhibiting some gold watches and rings stolen from the priest's house.</p>

<p>"It's fun fighting this way," Manteca cried, spicing every other word with an oath. "You know why the hell you're risking your hide."</p>

<p>In the same hand with which he held the reins, he clutched a shining ornament that he had torn from one of the holy statues.</p>

<p>After Quail, an expert in such matters, had examined Manteca's treasure covetously, he uttered a solemn guffaw.</p>

<p>"Hell, Your ornament is nothing but tin!"</p>

<p>"Why in hell are you hanging on to that poison?" Pancracio asked Blondie who appeared dragging a prisoner.</p>

<p>"Do you want to know why? Because it's a long time since I've had a good look at a man's face when a rope tightens around his neck!"</p>

<p>The fat prisoner breathed with difficulty as he followed Blondie on foot; his face was sunburnt, his eyes red; his forehead beaded with sweat, his wrists tightly bound together.</p>

<p>"Here, Anastasio, lend me your lasso. Mine's not strong enough; this bird will bust it. No, by God, I've changed my mind, friend Federal: think I'll kill you on the spot, because you are pulling too hard. Look, all the mesquites are still a long way off and there are no telegraph poles to hang you to!"</p>

<p>Blondie pulled his gun out, pressed the muzzle against the prisoner's chest and brought his finger against the trigger slowly ... slowly.... The prisoner turned pale as a corpse; his face lengthened; his eyelids were fixed in a glassy stare. He breathed in agony, his whole body shook as with ague. Blondie kept his gun in the same position for a moment long as all eternity. His eyes shone queerly. An expression of supreme pleasure lit up his fat puffy face.</p>

<p>"No, friend Federal," he drawled, putting back his gun into the holster; "I'm not going to kill you just yet.... I'll make you my orderly. You'll see that I'm not so hardhearted!"</p>

<p>Slyly he winked at his companions. The prisoner had turned into an animal; he gulped, panting, dry-mouthed. Camilla, who had witnessed the scene, spurred her horse and caught up with Demetrio.</p>

<p>"What a brute that Blondie is: you ought to see what he did to a wretched prisoner," she said. Then she told Demetrio what had occurred. The latter wrinkled his brow but made no answer.</p>

<p>War Paint called Camilla aside.</p>

<p>"Hey you ... what are you gobbling about? Blondie's my man, understand? From now on, you know how things are: whatever you've got against him you've got against me too! I'm warning you."</p>

<p>Camilla, frightened, hurried back to Demetrio's side.</p>

<head>X</head>

<p>The men camped in a meadow, near three small lone houses standing in a row, their white walls cutting the purple fringe of the horizon. Demetrio and Camilla rode toward them. Inside the corral a man, clad in shirt and trousers of cheap white cloth, sat greedily puffing at a cornhusk cigarette. Another man sitting beside him on a flat cut stone was shelling corn. Kicking the air with one dry, withered leg, the extremity of which was like a goat's hoof, he frightened the chickens away.</p>

<p>"Hurry up, 'Pifanio," said the man who was smoking, "the sun has gone down already and you haven't taken the animals to water."</p>

<p>A horse neighed outside the corral; both men glanced up in amazement. Demetrio and Camilla were looking over the corral wall at them.</p>

<p>"I just want a place to sleep for my woman and me," Demetrio said reassuringly.</p>

<p>As he explained that he was the chief of a small army which was to camp nearby that night, the man smoking, who owned the place, bid them enter with great deference. He ran to fetch a broom and a pail of water to dust and wash the best corner of the hut as decent lodging for his distinguished guests.</p>

<p>"Here, 'Pifanio, go out there and unsaddle the horses."</p>

<p>The man who was shelling corn stood up with an effort. He was clad in a tattered shirt and vest. His torn trousers, split at the seam, looked like the wings of a cold, stricken bird; two strings of cloth dangled from his waist. As he walked, he described grotesque circles.</p>

<p>"Surely you're not fit to do any work!" Demetrio said, refusing to allow him to touch the saddles.</p>
</text>
