<text id="autogum_fiction_doc438" title="Anthem" shortTile="anthem" author="Rand, Ayn" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/1/2/4/1249/1249.txt">
<head>{+Chapter Seven+}</head>

<p>It is dark here in the forest. The leaves rustle over our head, black against the last gold of the sky. The moss is soft and warm. We shall sleep on this moss for many nights, till the beasts of the forest come to tear our body. We have no bed now, save the moss, and no future, save the beasts.</p>

<p>We are old now, yet we were young this morning, when we carried our glass box through the streets of the City to the Home of the Scholars. No men stopped us, for there were none about [-from-] the Palace of Corrective Detention, and the others knew nothing. No men stopped us at the gate. We walked through {+the+} empty passages and into the great hall where the World Council of Scholars sat in solemn meeting.</p>

<p>We saw nothing as we entered, save the sky in the great windows, blue and glowing. Then we saw the Scholars who sat around a long table; they were as shapeless clouds huddled at the rise of [-the-] {+a+} great sky. There were {+the+} men whose famous names we knew, and others from distant lands whose names we had not heard. We saw a great painting on the wall over their heads, of the twenty illustrious men who had invented the candle.</p>

<p>All the heads of the Council turned to us as we entered. These great and wise of the earth did not know what to think of us, and they looked upon us with wonder and curiosity, as if we were a miracle. It is true that our tunic was torn and stained with brown stains which had been blood. We raised our right arm and we said:</p>

<p>"Our greeting to you, our honored brothers of the World Council of Scholars!"</p>

<p>Then Collective 0-0009, the oldest and wisest of the Council, spoke and asked:</p>

<p>"Who are you, our brother? For you do not look like a Scholar."</p>

<p>"Our name is [-Equality-] {+Equity+} 7-2521," we answered, "and we are a Street Sweeper of this City."</p>

<p>Then [-is-] {+it+} was [-as-] if a great wind had stricken the hall, for all the Scholars spoke at once, and they were angry and frightened.</p>

<p>"A Street Sweeper! A Street Sweeper walking in upon the World Council of Scholars! It is not to be believed! It is against all the rules and all the laws!"</p>

<p>But we knew how to stop them.</p>

<p>"Our brothers!" we said. "We matter not, nor our transgression. It is only our brother men who matter. Give no thought to us, for we are nothing, but listen to our words, for we bring you a gift such as [-had-] {+has+} never been brought to men. Listen to us, for we hold the future of mankind in our hands."</p>

<p>Then they listened.</p>

<p>We placed our glass box [-upon-] {+on+} the table before them. We spoke of it, and of our long quest, and of our tunnel, and of our escape from the Palace of Corrective Detention. Not a hand moved in that hall, as we spoke, nor an eye. Then we put the wires to the box, and they all bent forward and sat still, watching. And we stood still, our eyes upon the wire. And slowly, slowly as a flush of blood, a red flame trembled in the wire. Then the wire glowed.</p>

<p>But terror struck the men of the Council. They leapt to their feet, they ran from the table, and they stood pressed against the wall, huddled together, seeking the warmth of one another's bodies to give them courage.</p>

<p>We looked upon them and we laughed and said:</p>

<p>"Fear nothing, our brothers. There is a great power in these wires, but this power is tamed. It is yours. We give it to you."</p>

<p>Still they would not move.</p>

<p>"We give you the power of the sky!" we cried. "We give you the key to the earth! Take it, and let us be one of you, the humblest among you. Let us [-all-] work together, and harness this power, and make it ease the toil of men. Let us throw away our candles and our torches. Let us flood our cities with light. Let us bring a new light to men!"</p>

<p>But they looked upon us, and suddenly we were afraid. For their eyes were still, and small, and evil.</p>

<p>"Our brothers!" we cried. "Have you nothing to say to us?"</p>

<p>Then Collective 0-0009 moved forward. They moved to the table and the others followed.</p>

<p>"Yes," spoke Collective 0-0009, "we have much to say to you."</p>

<p>The sound of their [-voices-] {+voice+} brought silence to the hall and to [-be-] {+the+} beat of our heart.</p>

<p>"Yes," said Collective 0-0009, "we have much to say to a wretch who have broken all the laws and who boast of their infamy! How dared you think that your mind held greater wisdom [-that-] {+than+} the minds of your brothers? And if the [-Councils-] {+Council+} had decreed that you [-should-] be a Street Sweeper, how dared you think that you could be of greater use to men than in sweeping the streets?"</p>

<p>"How dared you, gutter cleaner," spoke Fraternity 9-3452, "to hold yourself as one alone and with the thoughts of [-the-] one and not of [-the-] many?"</p>
</text>
