<text id="autogum_fiction_doc373" title="Joe Wilson and His Mates" shortTile="joewilsonmates" author="Lawson, Henry" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/1/0/3/1036/1036-0.txt">
<head>JOE WILSON AND HIS MATES</head>

<p>Author of “While the Billy Boils”, “On the Track and Over the Sliprails”, “When the World was Wide, and other verses”, “Verses, Popular and Humorous”, “Children of the Bush”, “When I was King, and other verses”, etc.</p>

<p>The Author’s Farewell to the Bushmen.</p>

<p>Some carry their swags in the Great North-West Where the bravest battle and die, And a few have gone to their last long rest, And a few have said “Good-bye!” The coast grows dim, and it may be long Ere the Gums again I see; So I put my soul in a farewell song To the chaps who barracked for me.</p>

<p>Their days are hard at the best of times, And their dreams are dreams of care-- God bless them all for their big soft hearts, And the brave, brave grins they wear! God keep me straight as a man can go, And true as a man may be! For the sake of the hearts that were always so, Of the men who had faith in me!</p>

<p>And a ship-side word I would say, you chaps Of the blood of the Don’t-give-in! The world will call it a boast, perhaps-- But I’ll win, if a man can win! And not for gold nor the world’s applause-- Though ways to the end they be-- I’ll win, if a man might win, because Of the men who believed in me.</p>

<p>Contents.</p>

<p>Prefatory Verses--</p>

<p>The Author’s Farewell to the Bushmen.</p>

<p>Part I.</p>

<p>Joe Wilson’s Courtship. Brighten’s Sister-In-Law. ‘Water Them Geraniums’. I. A Lonely Track. II. ‘Past Carin’’. A Double Buggy at Lahey’s Creek. I. Spuds, and a Woman’s Obstinacy. II. Joe Wilson’s Luck. III. The Ghost of Mary’s Sacrifice. IV. The Buggy Comes Home.</p>

<p>Part II.</p>

<p>The Golden Graveyard. The Chinaman’s Ghost. The Loaded Dog. Poisonous Jimmy Gets Left. I. Dave Regan’s Yarn. II. Told by One of the Other Drovers. The Ghostly Door. A Wild Irishman. The Babies in the Bush. A Bush Dance. The Buck-Jumper. Jimmy Grimshaw’s Wooing. At Dead Dingo. Telling Mrs Baker. A Hero in Dingo-Scrubs. The Little World Left Behind.</p>

<p>Concluding Verses-- The Never-Never Country.</p>

<p>Part I.</p>

<p>Joe Wilson’s Courtship.</p>

<p>There are many times in this world when a healthy boy is happy. When he is put into knickerbockers, for instance, and ‘comes a man to-day,’ as my little Jim used to say. When they’re cooking something at home that he likes. When the ‘sandy-blight’ or measles breaks out amongst the children, or the teacher or his wife falls dangerously ill--or dies, it doesn’t matter which--‘and there ain’t no school.’ When a boy is naked and in his natural state for a warm climate like Australia, with three or four of his schoolmates, under the shade of the creek-oaks in the bend where there’s a good clear pool with a sandy bottom. When his father buys him a gun, and he starts out after kangaroos or ‘possums. When he gets a horse, saddle, and bridle, of his own. When he has his arm in splints or a stitch in his head--he’s proud then, the proudest boy in the district.</p>

<p>I wasn’t a healthy-minded, average boy: I reckon I was born for a poet by mistake, and grew up to be a Bushman, and didn’t know what was the matter with me--or the world--but that’s got nothing to do with it.</p>

<p>There are times when a man is happy. When he finds out that the girl loves him. When he’s just married. When he’s a lawful father for the first time, and everything is going on all right: some men make fools of themselves then--I know I did. I’m happy to-night because I’m out of debt and can see clear ahead, and because I haven’t been easy for a long time.</p>

<p>But I think that the happiest time in a man’s life is when he’s courting a girl and finds out for sure that she loves him and hasn’t a thought for any one else. Make the most of your courting days, you young chaps, and keep them clean, for they’re about the only days when there’s a chance of poetry and beauty coming into this life. Make the best of them and you’ll never regret it the longest day you live. They’re the days that the wife will look back to, anyway, in the brightest of times as well as in the blackest, and there shouldn’t be anything in those days that might hurt her when she looks back. Make the most of your courting days, you young chaps, for they will never come again.</p>

<p>A married man knows all about it--after a while: he sees the woman world through the eyes of his wife; he knows what an extra moment’s pressure of the hand means, and, if he has had a hard life, and is inclined to be cynical, the knowledge does him no good. It leads him into awful messes sometimes, for a married man, if he’s inclined that way, has three times the chance with a woman that a single man has--because the married man knows. He is privileged; he can guess pretty closely what a woman means when she says something else; he knows just how far he can go; he can go farther in five minutes towards coming to the point with a woman than an innocent young man dares go in three weeks. Above all, the married man is more decided with women; he takes them and things for granted. In short he is--well, he is a married man. And, when he knows all this, how much better or happier is he for it? Mark Twain says that he lost all the beauty of the river when he saw it with a pilot’s eye,--and there you have it.</p>
</text>
