<text id="autogum_fiction_doc232" title="Under the Andes" shortTile="underandes" author="Stout, Rex" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/5/4/546/546.txt">
<head>Chapter</head>

<p>I. THE SWEETHEART OF A KING. II. BEGINNING THE DANCE. III. A MODERN MARANA. IV. ALLONS! V. THE CAVE OF THE DEVIL. VI. CAPTURED. VII. THE FIGHT IN THE DARK. VIII. THE DANCE OF THE SUN. IX. BEFORE THE COURT. X. THE VERDICT. XI. A ROYAL VISITOR. XII. AT THE DOOR. XIII. INTO THE WHIRLPOOL. XIV. A FISHING PARTY. XV. THE RESCUE. XVI. THE ESCAPE. XVII. THE EYES IN THE DARK. XVIII. A VICTORY AND A CONVERSATION. XIX. AFLOAT. XX. AN INCA SPEAR. XXI. THE MIDST OF THE ENEMY. XXII. THE BEGINNING OF THE END. XXIII. WE ARE TWO. XXIV. CONCLUSION.</p>

<p>Chapter I.</p>

<p>THE SWEETHEART OF A KING.</p>

<p>The scene was not exactly new to me. Moved by the spirit of adventure, or by an access of ennui which overtakes me at times, I had several times visited the gaudy establishment of Mercer, on the fashionable side of Fifth Avenue in the Fifties. In either case I had found disappointment; where the stake is a matter of indifference there can be no excitement; and besides, I had been always in luck.</p>

<p>But on this occasion I had a real purpose before me, though not an important one, and I surrendered my hat and coat to the servant at the door with a feeling of satisfaction.</p>

<p>At the entrance to the main room I met Bob Garforth, leaving. There was a scowl on his face and his hand trembled as he held it forth to take mine.</p>

<p>"Harry is inside. What a rotten hole," said he, and passed on. I smiled at his remark--it was being whispered about that Garforth had lost a quarter of a million at Mercer's within the month--and passed inside.</p>

<p>Gaudy, I have said it was, and it needs no other word. Not in its elements, but in their arrangement.</p>

<p>The rugs and pictures and hangings testified to the taste of the man who had selected them; but they were abominably disposed, and there were too many of them.</p>

<p>The room, which was unusually large, held two or three leather divans, an English buffet, and many easy chairs. A smoking-table, covered, stood in one corner.</p>

<p>Groups of men were gathered about each of the three roulette wheels ranged along the farther side. Through a door to the left could be seen the poker tables, surrounded by grave or jocular faces. Above the low buzz of conversation there sounded the continual droning voices of the croupiers as they called the winning numbers, and an occasional exclamation from a "customer."</p>

<p>I made my way to the center wheel and stood at the rear of the crowd surrounding it.</p>

<p>The ball rolled; there was a straining of necks amid an intense silence; then, as the little pellet wavered and finally came to a rest in the hole number twenty-four a fervent oath of disappointment came from some one in front of me.</p>

<p>The next moment, rising on tiptoe to look over the intervening shoulders, I found myself looking into the white face of my younger brother Harry.</p>

<p>"Paul!" he exclaimed, turning quickly away.</p>

<p>I pushed my way through and stood at his side. There was no sound from the group of onlookers; it is not to be wondered at if they hesitated to offend Paul Lamar.</p>

<p>"My dear boy," said I, "I missed you at dinner. And though this may occupy your mind, it can scarcely fill your stomach. Haven't you had enough?"</p>

<p>Harry looked at me. His face was horribly pale and his eyes bloodshot; they could not meet mine.</p>

<p>"For Heaven's sake, Paul, let me alone," he said, hardly above a whisper. "I have lost ninety thousand."</p>

<p>In spite of myself I started. No wonder he was pale! And yet--</p>

<p>"That's nothing," I whispered back. "But you are making a show of yourself. Just now you were swearing like a sailor. See how your hand trembles! You were not made for this, Harry; it makes you forget that you're a gentleman. They are laughing at you. Come."</p>

<p>"But I say I have lost ninety thousand dollars," said the boy, and there was wildness in his eye. "Let me alone, Paul."</p>

<p>"I will repay you."</p>

<p>"No. Let me alone!"</p>

<p>"Harry!"</p>

<p>"I say no!"</p>

<p>His mouth was drawn tight and his eyes glared sullenly as those of a stubborn child. Clearly it was impossible to get him away without making a scene, which was unthinkable. For a moment I was at a complete loss; then the croupier's voice sounded suddenly in my ear:</p>

<p>"You are interrupting us, sir."</p>

<p>I silenced him with a glance and turned to my brother, having decided in an instant on the only possible course.</p>

<p>"Here, let me have your chair. I will get it back for you. Come!"</p>

<p>He looked at me for a moment in hesitation, then rose without a word and I took his place.</p>

<p>The thing was tiresome enough, but how could I have avoided it? The blood that rushes to the head of the gambler is certainly not food for the intellect; and, besides, I was forced by circumstances into an heroic attitude--and nothing is more distasteful to a man of sense. But I had a task before me; if a man lays bricks he should lay them well; and I do not deny that there was a stirring of my pulse as I sat down.</p>
</text>
