<text id="autogum_fiction_doc0" title="Alice's Adventures in Wonderland" shortTile="alicesadventureswonderland" author="Carroll, Lewis" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/1/11/11-0.txt">
<head>CHAPTER XII. Alice’s Evidence</head>

<p>‘Here!’ cried Alice, quite forgetting in the flurry of the moment how large she had grown in the last few minutes, and she jumped up in such a hurry that she tipped over the jury-box with the edge of her skirt, upsetting all the jurymen on to the heads of the crowd below, and there they lay sprawling about, reminding her very much of a globe of goldfish she had accidentally upset the week before.</p>

<p>‘Oh, I BEG your pardon!’ she exclaimed in a tone of great dismay, and began picking them up again as quickly as she could, for the accident of the goldfish kept running in her head, and she had a vague sort of idea that they must be collected at once and put back into the jury-box, or they would die.</p>

<p>‘The trial cannot proceed,’ said the King in a very grave voice, ‘until all the jurymen are back in their proper places--ALL,’ he repeated with great emphasis, looking hard at Alice as he said do.</p>

<p>Alice looked at the jury-box, and saw that, in her haste, she had put the Lizard in head downwards, and the poor little thing was waving its tail about in a melancholy way, being quite unable to move. She soon got it out again, and put it right; ‘not that it signifies much,’ she said to herself; ‘I should think it would be QUITE as much use in the trial one way up as the other.’</p>

<p>As soon as the jury had a little recovered from the shock of being upset, and their slates and pencils had been found and handed back to them, they set to work very diligently to write out a history of the accident, all except the Lizard, who seemed too much overcome to do anything but sit with its mouth open, gazing up into the roof of the court.</p>

<p>‘What do you know about this business?’ the King said to Alice.</p>

<p>‘Nothing,’ said Alice.</p>

<p>‘Nothing WHATEVER?’ persisted the King.</p>

<p>‘Nothing whatever,’ said Alice.</p>

<p>‘That’s very important,’ the King said, turning to the jury. They were just beginning to write this down on their slates, when the White Rabbit interrupted: ‘UNimportant, your Majesty means, of course,’ he said in a very respectful tone, but frowning and making faces at him as he spoke.</p>

<p>‘UNimportant, of course, I meant,’ the King hastily said, and went on to himself in an undertone,</p>

<p>‘important--unimportant--unimportant--important--’ as if he were trying which word sounded best.</p>

<p>Some of the jury wrote it down ‘important,’ and some ‘unimportant.’ Alice could see this, as she was near enough to look over their slates; ‘but it doesn’t matter a bit,’ she thought to herself.</p>

<p>At this moment the King, who had been for some time busily writing in his note-book, cackled out ‘Silence!’ and read out from his book, ‘Rule Forty-two. ALL PERSONS MORE THAN A MILE HIGH TO LEAVE THE COURT.’</p>

<p>Everybody looked at Alice.</p>

<p>‘I’M not a mile high,’ said Alice.</p>

<p>‘You are,’ said the King.</p>

<p>‘Nearly two miles high,’ added the Queen.</p>

<p>‘Well, I shan’t go, at any rate,’ said Alice: ‘besides, that’s not a regular rule: you invented it just now.’</p>

<p>‘It’s the oldest rule in the book,’ said the King.</p>

<p>‘Then it ought to be Number One,’ said Alice.</p>

<p>The King turned pale, and shut his note-book hastily. ‘Consider your verdict,’ he said to the jury, in a low, trembling voice.</p>

<p>‘There’s more evidence to come yet, please your Majesty,’ said the White Rabbit, jumping up in a great hurry; ‘this paper has just been picked up.’</p>

<p>‘What’s in it?’ said the Queen.</p>

<p>‘I haven’t opened it yet,’ said the White Rabbit, ‘but it seems to be a letter, written by the prisoner to--to somebody.’</p>

<p>‘It must have been that,’ said the King, ‘unless it was written to nobody, which isn’t usual, you know.’</p>

<p>‘Who is it directed to?’ said one of the jurymen.</p>

<p>‘It isn’t directed at all,’ said the White Rabbit; ‘in fact, there’s nothing written on the OUTSIDE.’ He unfolded the paper as he spoke, and added ‘It isn’t a letter, after all: it’s a set of verses.’</p>

<p>‘Are they in the prisoner’s handwriting?’ asked another of the jurymen.</p>

<p>‘No, they’re not,’ said the White Rabbit, ‘and that’s the queerest thing about it.’ (The jury all looked puzzled.)</p>

<p>‘He must have imitated somebody else’s hand,’ said the King. (The jury all brightened up again.)</p>

<p>‘Please your Majesty,’ said the Knave, ‘I didn’t write it, and they can’t prove I did: there’s no name signed at the end.’</p>

<p>‘If you didn’t sign it,’ said the King, ‘that only makes the matter worse. You MUST have meant some mischief, or else you’d have signed your name like an honest man.’</p>

<p>There was a general clapping of hands at this: it was the first really clever thing the King had said that day.</p>

<p>‘That PROVES his guilt,’ said the Queen.</p>

<p>‘It proves nothing of the sort!’ said Alice. ‘Why, you don’t even know what they’re about!’</p>

<p>‘Read them,’ said the King.</p>

<p>The White Rabbit put on his spectacles. ‘Where shall I begin, please your Majesty?’ he asked.</p>

<p>‘Begin at the beginning,’ the King said gravely, ‘and go on till you come to the end: then stop.’</p>

<p>These were the verses the White Rabbit read:--</p>

<p>‘They told me you had been to her, And mentioned me to him: She gave me a good character, But said I could not swim.</p>
</text>
