<text id="autogum_fiction_doc224" title="Ann Veronica: A Modern Love Story" shortTile="annveronicamodernlove" author="Wells, H. G. (Herbert George)" type="fiction" dateCollected="2019-10-22" sourceURL="http://gutenberg.readingroo.ms/5/2/524/524-0.txt">
<head>Part 7</head>

<p>It was rather less than a week after that walk that Capes came and sat down beside Ann Veronica for their customary talk in the lunch hour. He took a handful of almonds and raisins that she held out to him--for both these young people had given up the practice of going out for luncheon--and kept her hand for a moment to kiss her finger-tips. He did not speak for a moment.</p>

<p>“Well?” she said.</p>

<p>“I say!” he said, without any movement. “Let’s go.”</p>

<p>“Go!” She did not understand him at first, and then her heart began to beat very rapidly.</p>

<p>“Stop this--this humbugging,” he explained. “It’s like the Picture and the Bust. I can’t stand it. Let’s go. Go off and live together--until we can marry. Dare you?”</p>

<p>“Do you mean NOW?”</p>

<p>“At the end of the session. It’s the only clean way for us. Are you prepared to do it?”</p>

<p>Her hands clenched. “Yes,” she said, very faintly. And then: “Of course! Always. It is what I have wanted, what I have meant all along.”</p>

<p>She stared before her, trying to keep back a rush of tears.</p>

<p>Capes kept obstinately stiff, and spoke between his teeth.</p>

<p>“There’s endless reasons, no doubt, why we shouldn’t,” he said. “Endless. It’s wrong in the eyes of most people. For many of them it will smirch us forever.... You DO understand?”</p>

<p>“Who cares for most people?” she said, not looking at him.</p>

<p>“I do. It means social isolation--struggle.”</p>

<p>“If you dare--I dare,” said Ann Veronica. “I was never so clear in all my life as I have been in this business.” She lifted steadfast eyes to him. “Dare!” she said. The tears were welling over now, but her voice was steady. “You’re not a man for me--not one of a sex, I mean. You’re just a particular being with nothing else in the world to class with you. You are just necessary to life for me. I’ve never met any one like you. To have you is all important. Nothing else weighs against it. Morals only begin when that is settled. I sha’n’t care a rap if we can never marry. I’m not a bit afraid of anything--scandal, difficulty, struggle.... I rather want them. I do want them.”</p>

<p>“You’ll get them,” he said. “This means a plunge.”</p>

<p>“Are you afraid?”</p>

<p>“Only for you! Most of my income will vanish. Even unbelieving biological demonstrators must respect decorum; and besides, you see--you were a student. We shall have--hardly any money.”</p>

<p>“I don’t care.”</p>

<p>“Hardship and danger.”</p>

<p>“With you!”</p>

<p>“And as for your people?”</p>

<p>“They don’t count. That is the dreadful truth. This--all this swamps them. They don’t count, and I don’t care.”</p>

<p>Capes suddenly abandoned his attitude of meditative restraint. “By Jove!” he broke out, “one tries to take a serious, sober view. I don’t quite know why. But this is a great lark, Ann Veronica! This turns life into a glorious adventure!”</p>

<p>“Ah!” she cried in triumph.</p>

<p>“I shall have to give up biology, anyhow. I’ve always had a sneaking desire for the writing-trade. That is what I must do. I can.”</p>

<p>“Of course you can.”</p>

<p>“And biology was beginning to bore me a bit. One research is very like another.... Latterly I’ve been doing things.... Creative work appeals to me wonderfully. Things seem to come rather easily.... But that, and that sort of thing, is just a day-dream. For a time I must do journalism and work hard.... What isn’t a day-dream is this: that you and I are going to put an end to flummery--and go!”</p>

<p>“Go!” said Ann Veronica, clenching her hands.</p>

<p>“For better or worse.”</p>

<p>“For richer or poorer.”</p>

<p>She could not go on, for she was laughing and crying at the same time. “We were bound to do this when you kissed me,” she sobbed through her tears. “We have been all this time--Only your queer code of honor--Honor! Once you begin with love you have to see it through.”</p>

<head>CHAPTER THE FIFTEENTH</head>

<head>THE LAST DAYS AT HOME</head>

<head>Part 1</head>

<p>They decided to go to Switzerland at the session’s end. “We’ll clean up everything tidy,” said Capes....</p>

<p>For her pride’s sake, and to save herself from long day-dreams and an unappeasable longing for her lover, Ann Veronica worked hard at her biology during those closing weeks. She was, as Capes had said, a hard young woman. She was keenly resolved to do well in the school examination, and not to be drowned in the seas of emotion that threatened to submerge her intellectual being.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, she could not prevent a rising excitement as the dawn of the new life drew near to her--a thrilling of the nerves, a secret and delicious exaltation above the common circumstances of existence. Sometimes her straying mind would become astonishingly active--embroidering bright and decorative things that she could say to Capes; sometimes it passed into a state of passive acquiescence, into a radiant, formless, golden joy. She was aware of people--her aunt, her father, her fellow-students, friends, and neighbors--moving about outside this glowing secret, very much as an actor is aware of the dim audience beyond the barrier of the footlights. They might applaud, or object, or interfere, but the drama was her very own. She was going through with that, anyhow.</p>

<p>The feeling of last days grew stronger with her as their number diminished. She went about the familiar home with a clearer and clearer sense of inevitable conclusions. She became exceptionally considerate and affectionate with her father and aunt, and more and more concerned about the coming catastrophe that she was about to precipitate upon them. Her aunt had a once exasperating habit of interrupting her work with demands for small household services, but now Ann Veronica rendered them with a queer readiness of anticipatory propitiation. She was greatly exercised by the problem of confiding in the Widgetts; they were dears, and she talked away two evenings with Constance without broaching the topic; she made some vague intimations in letters to Miss Miniver that Miss Miniver failed to mark. But she did not bother her head very much about her relations with these sympathizers.</p>
</text>
