<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc113" title="Be and Feel Beautiful All the Time" shortTile="feel-beautiful-time" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2011-01-30" dateModified="2019-09-23" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_and_Feel_Beautiful_All_the_Time" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be and Feel Beautiful All the Time</head><p>The first step to looking beautiful is feeling beautiful. This article can help you do both by allowing you to embrace your flaws while enhancing your best features.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Build confidence. This will help with you understanding your natural beauty, in and out. Stand straight. Smile at yourself. Notice the positive things. It is all important. Embrace your flaws, but enhance your good features. Below are tips in order to help you. <figure rend="Be and Feel Beautiful All the Time Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Take care of your skin and body. Keep up with your personal hygiene. Shower every day or every second day to leave you smelling fresh and feeling renewed. Wash your body with good smelling body wash, and wash your hair appropriately. If you wash your hair too often, you may find it starts producing more oil to try and replenish the oil it lost. Clean your hair by massaging your scalp with shampoo using your fingertips. Then wash with conditioner for shine and to prevent tangling. Massage into your hair for 20 seconds and leave it in for 2 minutes. Ensure you apply deodorant soon after your shower, as that makes it most effective and allows it to absorb into the skin before you start to sweat. <figure rend="Be and Feel Beautiful All the Time Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wash your face regularly. This will unclog your pores and help get rid of acne. Use an appropriate cleanser for your skin type, and moisturise after. Moisturising will both replenish dry skin, and also calm oily skin by preventing it from producing excess oil. Don't forget to moisturise your elbows and knees and anywhere else that gets dry or flaky. Try a variety of products to find the ones that work best with your skin.</item></list></item>
<item>Fix your hair. One of the things we spend the most time on in the morning is our hair. Brush it regularly to prevent tangles and make it shine, but if you have curly hair, a wide tooth comb is best as it will prevent frizz. If possible, use a brush with natural bristles, such as boar bristles. This helps redistribute oils from your scalp down to the ends and makes your hair look shinier and smoother. Don't forget to gently massage or brush your scalp! This both improves bloodflow to allow hair growth, and prevents dandruff by exfoliating your scalp and removing dead skin. Get haircuts often to remove split ends, and try to find a hairstyle that works with your face and body shape. <figure rend="Be and Feel Beautiful All the Time Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Minimise your use of hot tools. These can damage your hair by drying it out and ultimately cause split ends. If you curl your hair, try alternative heatless methods such as rollers, curlformers, or pincurls. If you straighten your hair, try wrapping it smooth against your head with pins while you sleep. If you still want to use hot tools, make sure you apply a good heat protectant first.</item></list></item>
<item>Apply tasteful makeup. Utilise different colours and styles to make you look your best. Be sure you don't apply so much that it becomes noticeable or cakey. Use dark colors to push backwards, and use light colors to pull forwards. Mask any features you don't like and accentuate the ones you do. <figure rend="Be and Feel Beautiful All the Time Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Exercise. Exercising not only tones your muscles and reduces body fat, but it also gets your blood flowing which improves your skin. Studies have also shown that people who exercise regularly are less likely to develop cardiovascular disease or diabetes. <figure rend="Be and Feel Beautiful All the Time Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Eat healthily. Eating fruits and vegetables give you the energy you need and make you look great. It improves your complexion too. Follow the suggested serving portions of the food pyramid and make sure you get the nutrients you need. If you're having trouble eating healthy, throw out most tempting foods and only have one night a week when you can eat some junk food. Remember to wash your hands before eating. In addition never forget to drink right amount of water. Staying hydrated can reduce bad breath, dry or flaky skin, chapped lips, and a variety of other issues. <figure rend="Be and Feel Beautiful All the Time Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be yourself. Being a unique individual will make you more attractive. <figure rend="Be and Feel Beautiful All the Time Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Get plenty of rest to help improve your skin and face.</item>
<item>Smile. It gives you a boost of confidence and makes you look more inviting.</item>
<item>You are you, and that is who you are meant to be. Don't try to be someone else.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Losing weight does not mean having to starve yourself. Starvation can actually slow down your metabolism! Just remember to eat healthier foods.</item>
<item>Don't go overboard on the exercising; you can really hurt yourself.</item></list>
</text>
