<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc115" title="Look Lovely" shortTile="look-lovely" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2008-08-10" dateModified="2019-05-03" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Look_Lovely" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Look Lovely</head><p>Absolutely anyone can look beautiful, no matter what your features. Here's a simple guide on how you can look lovely.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Experiment with different hairstyles and clothing styles. How else will you find out what looks good on you? Don't worry about having a few fashion disasters, because what you will be left with a style that suits you, and also your personality. <figure rend="Look Lovely Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Exercise every day to make sure your body is in tip-top shape. It doesn't matter if you have a flat chest, or short legs. As long as you keep your body fit and at a healthy weight, you'll look great. <figure rend="Look Lovely Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Moisturizing isn't just important for your face. Put lotion all over your body to keep it silky smooth. You may also want to try exfoliating, too, otherwise you will just be moisturizing dead skin. Your hands, elbows and knees are especially important to moisturize, as they are prone to dryness. <figure rend="Look Lovely Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wash your face every day, preferably twice. Always use cleanser and moisturizer, and perhaps toner. Ask your dermatologist what will be best for your skin. For instance, if you are prone to spots, you may want to try using  a top-selling brand of skin care and acne medication . It is also a good idea to exfoliate your face, and use face-masks, but not too much, as this will strip your face of essential oils. <figure rend="Look Lovely Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep your eyebrows trim by plucking them often. If you do so every day, you will only have a few hairs to pluck each time, meaning you won't have to go through much pain. If you aren't sure what shape you should be plucking them into, go to a salon and get a professional wax. After this, it will be easier to keep them neat and tidy. Use some petroleum jelly based product to slick them down, and if need be, use some eyebrow pencil to darken them. <figure rend="Look Lovely Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item><hi rend="bold">When applying your makeup</hi> it is always very important to have good lighting. You may look nice in a dimly lit room, but when you go out in the sunlight discover you have made many errors in your makeup application. If you can, buy a lighted makeup mirror and use this. Now for the application of the makeup... <figure rend="Look Lovely Step 6.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Apply a foundation, preferably liquid and matching your skin tone. Then, for the perfect skin, apply a dusting of powder. This will also seal the foundation in place. Finally, top it off with a bit of rouge to define your cheekbones. <figure rend="Look Lovely Step 6Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When it comes to eyeshadow, where which ever colour you have discovered suits you (see step 1.) You will also know how you like to wear your eyeliner, if any. However, I do recommend you <hi rend="italic">always</hi> wear mascara, even if it simply clear. Beforehand, use eyelash curlers. <figure rend="Look Lovely Step 6Bullet2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Using lip liner gives your lips a much more polished look. NEVER wear lip liner a darker or lighter shade than your lipstick. Apply the liner to all of your lips, not just the outside, and then apply the lipstick over. <figure rend="Look Lovely Step 6Bullet3.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Always wear the same perfume, as this way people will recognize it as your scent. Apply to your wrists, neck, hands, forearms, temples, and the backs of your knees. Do not wear too much, though, as this will overpower people. <figure rend="Look Lovely Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>To keep your nails nice and strong, cut and file them often, and consider other factors such as your diet. Soaking your hands in a moisturising scented oil will leave them smelling and looking lovely. Match your nail varnish with your clothing, and stay away from the black polish. If you want a dark colour, go for a deep purple, or crimson. <figure rend="Look Lovely Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Buy an eyelash comb, so you can brush through your lashes and get rid of any clumps.</item>
<item>If you apply foundation to your eyelids and lips, your eye makeup and lipstick will last for longer.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Using the wrong kind of foundation could <hi rend="bold">permanently</hi> damage your skin and clog up your pores, causing spots.</item>
<item>If you apply perfume to your clothes, not only will it not last very long, but it will damage the clothing, too.</item></list>
</text>
