<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc121" title="Be a Fabulous Man (Straight or Gay)" shortTile="fabulous-man-straight" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2014-10-28" dateModified="2018-11-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Fabulous_Man_%28Straight_or_Gay%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Fabulous Man (Straight or Gay)</head><p>Have you ever thought to yourself, "I need to be more fabulous." This is something that many of us think but too scared to try. You might not want people to think that you are gay or that you are not manly. Look no further. Your manly #FAB has arrived.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Clothing</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Don't be scared to try small fashion statements. Pick small things such as hats, necklaces, earrings or bracelets. These are small so they are good to experiment with. Start off trying things that are new but not necessarily aiming to be fabulous. Just go far enough to get out of your comfort zone. Maybe just try a new pattern on a shirt or wear a beanie. Experiment!</item>
<item>Try to add larger accessories and new types of clothes to your wardrobe. If you keep your clothes in draws, don't! Fabulous people always care for things like this. Try things like man-bags. Experiment with articles of clothing as well. Scarves are often good fashion statements. Different shoes are also a good idea. Try classier dress-like shoes made with more experimental materials such as leather. If you wear Vans then maybe try Converse. If you wear boots a lot then try dress shoes.</item>
<item>Throw your usual sense of style out the window! What? You like your style? Well go be not-so-fabulous then. Start with color changes. Have dull colors for large items such as shirts and pants. Black, white or gray are perfect. Then add things like shoes, scarves and other things that pop with amazing colors. Try green, blue, pink and red.</item></list>
<head>Lifestyle Changes</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Eat healthy. Do you see fabulous people stuffing their faces at a fast food? No! It gives you a sense of class to eat healthy. This also goes for exercise. Just generally be healthy.</item>
<item>Be clean. You cannot be fabulous and dirty. Shower every day and don't wear clothes twice. Also remember to wear deodorant. Use non-scented roll-on deodorant over smelly spray deodorant and make yourself smell nice with cologne instead.</item>
<item>Fix your skin. Don't be caught growing a beard. Either be seen wit a cleanly-shaved face, a bit of stubble or a reasonable sized beard. Also, don't shave/wax your legs. Chest is acceptable.</item>
<item>Have a refined hobby. Try things with class such as golf, horse riding, wine or coffee tasting or even drawing or photography.</item>
<item>Get sleep. It is hard to be fabulous if you only had an hour of sleep the previous night.</item></list>
<head>Attitude</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Don't fiddle. If you are doing something then concentrate on it. Focus.</item>
<item>Be that happy-go-lucky guy. Be positive and optimistic. This will add to your fabulous aura..</item>
<item>Be right. If you don't know something then don't engage in conversation about it. If you know about something then go away and have fun proving people wrong. If you, by chance, are wrong. Don't defend yourself too much. This is highly not fabulous...</item></list>
</text>
