<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc117" title="Be Classically Beautiful" shortTile="classically-beautiful" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2006-07-27" dateModified="2019-01-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_Classically_Beautiful" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Classically Beautiful</head><p>Audrey Hepburn, Vivien Leigh, Grace Kelly, Ingrid Bergman, Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, all these women are classic beauties. They all understood that the key to classic beauty is to keep it simple.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Wear classic pieces.</hi> Classic women never wear trendy clothes. They wear classic pieces such as a simple black dress with a striking accessory, aviator glasses, a colorful scarf or a pretty set of pearls. Think of Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis's famous over-sized sunglasses and timeless suits. You don't have to go back to the nineteen-fifties, but expand your wardrobe when possible, and learn to have your own sophisticated style. (Some people are very classic and still keep up a colorful, fun appearance) <figure rend="Dress-Professionally-Step-11-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep make-up to a minimum. A little foundation, lip gloss and mascara can go a very long way. Learn how to make your best features stand out. <figure rend="Get-Pale-Skin-Step-15-Version-4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Respect your hair's natural texture. Always aim for a shiny and healthy style. Consult a hairdresser to figure out what style will suit your face and the easiest way to maintain your hair. You don't want to spend hours in front of the mirror. <figure rend="Style-Shoulder-Length-Hair-Step-4-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have good personal hygiene. Keep nails and toenails looking prim and proper, a simple French manicure is always elegant. <figure rend="Overcome-Sadness-Step-5-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be positive and happy. A positive outlook is always beautiful. <figure rend="Enjoy-Being-Alone-Step-2-Version-2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>If something is really bothering you, it's okay to show it. But a Classic Beauty is known for being reserved, calm and always in control.</item></list></item>
<item>Know what you're talking about. Intelligence is key. Brush up on as many subjects as possible. <figure rend="Become-Sociable-Step-6-Version-3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Black is something classic beauties always wear, but try to accentuate the simplicity of it with accessories of a single other color such as red, white, or green. <figure rend="Dress-Professionally-Step-3-Version-2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Find the classic colors that work best with your complexion and eye color. For example: <figure rend="Make-Someone-Feel-Better-Step-10.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Blue eyes: Orange (complementary), Dark Blue, Dark Purple, Light Green, Grey, white, Black, Turquoise (analogous), Blue-Purple (analogous),Dark Red. Colors to avoid are: bright red, lime green, hot pink, brown, baby blue, any tints (colors visibly mixed with white)</item>
<item>Brown eyes: Any Pink, Charcoal, any very dark color, Yellow (it brings out undertones in the eyes, despite it's undignified reputation) Green (also, undertones). Colors to avoid: none, brown is neutral, and so goes with everything.</item>
<item>Green eyes: Purple (it really does bring out the color of your eyes), Dark red (green's complimentary color), dark blue, black, Brown, off-white. Colors to avoid: Grey, since it weighs down the natural tones in your iris, muting the color. However, if your eyes are bright green or blue green, gray brings it out quite nicely. Yellow, bright red (compliments can be jarring when both of the colors are vivid), bright white, orange, and green (which drowns out your eye color).</item>
<item>Black eyes: any color.</item>
<item>Ruddy (blue-toned/pink after exertion/freckled) skin: Cool colors (blue, purple, green, and all the analogous colors between them including Red-purple) Black, Grey. Colors to avoid: Yellow, and the corresponding analogous colors, any red (sorry) and White. Wear dark orange or red-orange at your discretion.</item>
<item>Sallow (yellow toned/ tanning rather than freckling) any warm or neutral colors. Avoid yellow, but golds can look nice</item>
<item>If you are African-American or have a darker complexion, you can wear almost any color. Golds are especially beautiful, though.</item>
<item>If you have red hair,  you can wear: Golds, beiges, corals, purples, very dark or light greens (just avoid the "Christmas green" color) dark blues.</item></list></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Being true to yourself and having confidence is key.</item>
<item>Having "inner beauty" is just as important as being outwardly beautiful. Being beautiful on the inside will show that you are a very special girl not worth losing.</item>
<item>Always have appreciation; that is the key to a happy life.</item>
<item>Tattoos and Body Piercings. Appearances convey a strong message to others; you can be judged by an individual or right before an event that will play a prominent role in your future (Ex. a prospective employer, acquiring a higher position in a reputable company, etc.). Therefore, take careful consideration when deciding if it is a good idea for you to get visible tattoos or body piercings. Even though a person’s outward appearance does not automatically show his or her true inner qualities, appearances can reflect how a person is willing to be perceived by the world. Also keep in mind that although tattoos and piercings are individual expressions, they can be permanent or difficult (and often costly) to remove if you change your mind in the future. If you are in doubt about how tattoos and piercings may impact you in the future, forget about getting them and find other ways to show self expression, such as creating works of art, poetry, hobbies, etc.</item>
<item>Study classic beauties like Audrey Hepburn, Dorothy Dandridge, Grace Kelly, etc. and try to imitate them. It's fun and it will help.</item>
<item>Don't go for all the trends. Buy classic timeless pieces. When you buy something, think to yourself, if I look at a photo of myself ten years from now, will I laugh and say, "I cannot believe I actually wore that!".</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't try to be someone you're not; be your own classic beauty.</item></list>
</text>
