<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc119" title="Be Beautiful in a Wheelchair" shortTile="beautiful-wheelchair" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2008-09-30" dateModified="2019-03-15" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_Beautiful_in_a_Wheelchair" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be Beautiful in a Wheelchair</head><p>You maybe can't turn around the fact that you are in a wheelchair, but whether it is temporary or permanent always remember that you are you and nothing will ever change that. So what if you are in a wheelchair? You are beautiful and unique and you. And anyone can feel beautiful despite their differences.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be positive! If you're not positive of yourself, people will see it, and it will show. Smile or laugh. Don't complain or whine. Instead, tell someone about your problem nicely, and be polite to the others around you. <figure rend="Be Beautiful in a Wheelchair Step 01.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Start a sport, do wheelchair basketball, racing and other sports that can involve a wheelchair. This will make you feel better, because you have other people that face the same problems as you, AND you get to share the same hobby! You feel like they can relate to you! Go online try to find some wheelchair fan sites, or find people with wheelchairs. <figure rend="Be Beautiful in a Wheelchair Step 02.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you feel like you want to wear makeup, you can! But don't expect it to make you feel 100% fine. <figure rend="Be Beautiful in a Wheelchair Step 03.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Clothing can be made with altered patterns to provide a better fit for a person who is always sitting down.  Pants and skirts can have the lap fullness removed.  A coat, jacket or blazer can have some of the back shortened (since you will be in a wheelchair with a back).  Dresses will need to have the hems evened.  Any alteration will help your clothes to fit you better. Maybe you or a friend can learn to sew. <figure rend="Be Beautiful in a Wheelchair Step 04.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't let a wheelchair stop you from being creative. Maybe there is some sort of holiday or special occasion. Decorate your wheelchair with fun funky things to show people your unique creativity. <figure rend="Be Beautiful in a Wheelchair Step 05.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>No matter what, you will always stumble upon those less mature people who will enjoy having fun at your expense. If this happens, be calm and tell them to stop. Don't be a snitch and tell on them. What does that do? It makes them pick on you MORE. You have to stand up for yourself. But if the same group of people keep picking on you, it's time to tell an adult. This is not tattle telling! <figure rend="Be Beautiful in a Wheelchair Step 06.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Video</head>
<p><ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ySPekGsfFGM">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ySPekGsfFGM</ref></p>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Wear some sweet accessories (necklace, bracelets, rings, anklets)or makeup, if you feel it'll make you feel better.</item>
<item>Be a social butterfly! Because when you're having a conversation with someone, they'll have their mind on only the conversation, and forget the fact that you're in a wheelchair!</item>
<item>Get an electric wheelchair so you can operate it on your own  rather than having to rely on friends and family. You will have more freedom using an electric one and won't feel as closed up and isolated. But if you can't afford it, you can still use a normal wheelchair, and push it by yourself. But after a long day of pushing yourself around, you're darned to be exhausted! Treat yourself!</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't trust anyone to push you in a wheelchair, unless it's you, a teacher, parent/guardian, or trusted friend.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A wheelchair</item>
<item>Great personality</item></list>
</text>
