<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc109" title="Look and Feel Fabulous" shortTile="look-feel-fabulous" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2008-07-05" dateModified="2018-11-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Look_and_Feel_Fabulous" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Look and Feel Fabulous</head><p>Are you bored with your life. If you are lacking friends, fun, and beauty read on!</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Beauty</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Wash and condition your hair and let it dry <hi rend="italic">naturally</hi>. For a fab new hair look, start to twist your hair. It will start to coil keep going 'till it becomes a bun. Tie it up in a bun and spray hairspray on it for texture. For a girlie twist, use a scarf to tie it even more tightly. If that look isn't for you, then let put some product through your hair to suit your hair type and let it dry naturally. A lot of the time, natural looks better. <figure rend="Look and Feel Fabulous Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use a pale hypoallergenic nail polish. <figure rend="Look and Feel Fabulous Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use baby moisturizer to keep your skin silky smooth. Remember to concentrate on the elbows, knees and anywhere that you get dry skin. <figure rend="Look and Feel Fabulous Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use a foundation that matches your skin tone. Don't listen to what the girl at the beauty counter is saying! She may say get a darker foundation to make you look 'sun kissed', but that's all wrong. Get a foundation that suits you! The key to amazing foundation is that it has to look like you haven't got any on. And to do that, you need it to look like your natural skin colour. <figure rend="Look and Feel Fabulous Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Apply eye-shadow and mascara. Search up tutorials on how to do eye make-up that best suits your eye type. It's important that you don't try and mask or change your features, just enhance them, because you're beautiful. <figure rend="Look and Feel Fabulous Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Slick on a bit of lippy or lip balm. <figure rend="Look and Feel Fabulous Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Friends and Fun</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Talk to people you don't know - Introduce yourself and talk about movies and websites. People are drawn to others with confidence, so make sure that you ooze confidence. <figure rend="Look and Feel Fabulous Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Exercise at a club (such as netball, basketball and football). You will have fun and make friends! <figure rend="Look and Feel Fabulous Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Writing can be fun, so write to your friends if you are bored and haven't seen them in a while. (You won't run up a huge phone bill if you do it often.) <figure rend="Look and Feel Fabulous Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Instead of going straight home after school go for a quick jog somewhere close to your home. You won't feel as tired at home. (Ask parents first!) <figure rend="Look and Feel Fabulous Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Just dance! You'll instantly smile. <figure rend="Look and Feel Fabulous Step 11.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear a little bit of body spray to smell lovely and feel great too. <figure rend="Look and Feel Fabulous Step 12.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be yourself no matter what anyone says.</item>
<item>Try to have a positive mind no matter what.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Have fun, but don't endanger yourself or others!</item>
<item>Writing letters requires stamps in order to mail the letters, and stamps can be expensive.</item>
<item>Don't get obsessed about your weight, you're beautiful and fabulous no matter what anyone says.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Shampoo</item>
<item>Conditioner</item>
<item>Bobble</item>
<item>A scarf</item>
<item>Pale hypoallergenic nail polish</item>
<item>Baby moisturizer</item>
<item>Foundation</item>
<item>Eye-shadow</item>
<item>Mascara</item></list>
</text>
