<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc120" title="Be a Noticeable Beauty" shortTile="noticeable-beauty" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2009-09-27" dateModified="2018-11-19" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Be_a_Noticeable_Beauty" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Be a Noticeable Beauty</head><p>What's a Noticeable Beauty? Is that one young lady who always looks perfect, and walks perfectly, and is very sociable too. And as the title says, she is noticeable, and wherever she goes, people all notice her beauty and wonder who is she.
Wanna be like that? Read on.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be clean. You must take a shower at least  every other day. But you should probably take one every day. But wash your hair with shampoo and conditioner only two or three times a week depending on your hair type. So, in the other days that you don't wash you hair, make sure to take your showers wearing a bath cap, so you don't get your hair wet. <figure rend="Be a Noticeable Beauty Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have beautiful hair. Try to often, or at least once a week, go to a beauty salon and do your hair, and care for it. Make sure you keep it always well hydrated and taken care of. And never forget to comb and brush your hair at least every time it's needed. <figure rend="Be a Noticeable Beauty Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have girly style. Heels, dresses, skirts. Buy some fashion magazines or get into some fashion websites, and make researches about what's on fashion right now. And go for it. You don't have to buy expensive stuff, but make sure you buy clothes that look like what is fashionable now. <figure rend="Be a Noticeable Beauty Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear make up. Be tasteful about it. Pluck your eyebrows well too. Well, wear concealer, face powder, light eye shadow, thin eyeliner, mascara and a little bit of blush, and finish it with a lip gloss or lipstick. <figure rend="Be a Noticeable Beauty Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Have the noticeable beauty attitude. Have you seen how those glamorous girls walk? They walk confident and that matches greatly with the stunning looks. So don't ruin a beautiful look by walking non-confident, make sure you walk confident, so your new beauty will be noticed by even more people everywhere and all the time. <figure rend="Be a Noticeable Beauty Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be communicative and sociable. Don't act all desperate to be friends with people, that never looks cool and doesn't match a beautiful and confident lady. What you gotta do is to get used to greeting "good morning/afternoon/evening/night" to people, as that are basic good manners that always works to make people like you and think of you as classy. To make introductions with someone, simply approach and say "Good [morning/afternoon/evening], I'm [<hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">insert your name here</hi></hi>]. What's your name?" <figure rend="Be a Noticeable Beauty Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be present. You can't make a new friend then forget about them, so no contact will last. Make sure you call them sometimes to ask how things are going, and talk to them as often as you can, at least to ask how are their life going and tell about yours. <figure rend="Be a Noticeable Beauty Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be seen. After learning it all, if you wanna be known as a beauty, you gotta make sure people see you. Go walk at crowded places, where most people go, and walk around there and make your beauty noticed. With these steps correctly followed, people sure will can't help but will look at you, and they will wonder "who is that beauty?" <figure rend="Be a Noticeable Beauty Step 8.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't be shy, but don't be hyper. Just be simply sociable and pretty.</item>
<item>Confidence is key. People are drawn to people that like themselves.</item></list>
</text>
