<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc114" title="Make Yourself Look Natural, Have a Subtle Appearance but Beautiful" shortTile="make-yourself-look" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2011-04-29" dateModified="2018-11-20" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Make_Yourself_Look_Natural%2C_Have_a_Subtle_Appearance_but_Beautiful" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Make Yourself Look Natural, Have a Subtle Appearance but Beautiful</head><p>In this article, you'll learn the basics of taking care of your skin, making yourself look noticed but in a way that you don't really POP OUT, and tips on how to wear your clothes.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Try sticking to colors like white, black, grey, light or really dark red, light yellow, light blue, light pink, or a middle-color green. These colors make you look mature and pretty. These colors don't make you pop out like neons do or bright, bright red or yellow, but makes you stand out enough for you to be noticed. <figure rend="Make Yourself Look Natural, Have a Subtle Appearance but Beautiful Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="ordered"><item>Try sticking to jeans and sweatpants. Usually, Jeans would go well with one of your looser tops and sweatpants would go with one of your tighter tops. It's always opposite; something baggy, something has to be tight. Something loose, something has to be baggy. Otherwise, if you go for two tight things you wear, you'll look easy or trashy and and show-off-type-body person.. <figure rend="Make Yourself Look Natural, Have a Subtle Appearance but Beautiful Step 1Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you want to wear leggings, be sure to wear a subtle color short over them that are high or make sure you have a longer type shirt to cover your whole bottom or close to it. Nobody likes seeing underwear creases or outlines. <figure rend="Make Yourself Look Natural, Have a Subtle Appearance but Beautiful Step 1Bullet2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>If you think make up is really necessary, be sure to wear it very lightly. If you're wearing mascara, be sure to make your eyelashes spread out and not make it clumpy looking. <figure rend="Make Yourself Look Natural, Have a Subtle Appearance but Beautiful Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="ordered"><item>Also, don't wear that barbie type lipstick that's bright bright pink or a reddish pink. <figure rend="Make Yourself Look Natural, Have a Subtle Appearance but Beautiful Step 2Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try sticking to colors like a dark dark red, a brown maybe, or a shiny very light pink that's barely noticeable. If you'd like eyeshadow, try to go for a subtle look. No really dark colors or colors that stand out very well. <figure rend="Make Yourself Look Natural, Have a Subtle Appearance but Beautiful Step 2Bullet2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Try going on a diet. Like eating healthy foods like veggies and fruit. Be sure to drink lots of water, juice, and milk. Try no pop for awhile. Even though there's not scientific evidence yet that pop brings up pimples to your skin, try to stay away from that. <figure rend="Make Yourself Look Natural, Have a Subtle Appearance but Beautiful Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try to wear your hair up in a really high ponytail with a subtle color from above. Make sure though, if you're wearing a ponytail that there's not many clips shown or bobby pins. Second, Keep your hair down. This is another option. Keeping your hair down is a very nice look, when it's brushed. If you're still in school, during bells try to secretly brush your hair. Once you're done with that, you will get guaranteed comments! Also, if you want to do something different, try doing piggy tails that are loose if you have really long hair. Try not to do this all the time since you want to be known for all different types of hair styles you try, not just one. Try not to do other things like a braid on one side and a ponytail on the other or two braids in the front and a couple in the back. <figure rend="Make Yourself Look Natural, Have a Subtle Appearance but Beautiful Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear deodorant! You're getting to an age where you need to wear it so you don't stink. Also, try wearing a light scented perfume. Again, not very noticeable but when someone walks up to you, they should be able to smell it. Try choosing scents that smell like flowers or natural things. <figure rend="Make Yourself Look Natural, Have a Subtle Appearance but Beautiful Step 5.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>DON'T cover up pimple or zits! Although it may look better all covered up in make up, once you take that make up off, it will probably be bigger than before and get redder. Then you'll just have to keep on covering it.</item></list>
</text>
