<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc122" title="Look Bangin" shortTile="look-bangin" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2008-05-20" dateModified="2018-11-17" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Look_Bangin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Look Bangin</head><p>This is a way of how to look "banging" so if you like it, do it. If you're not into it, don't read it. This is just some straight up advice if you're trying to attract somebody or some people. By the way it works.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Get your hair healthy: Start using a good conditioner so that when you style your hair it will remain healthy and in good condition. <figure rend="Look Bangin Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get cute  clothes that show your shape. Get tight jeans with a cute top that doesn't make you look completely flat. If you've got a booty and are flat buy a push-up or Wonder Bra to make you feel more feminine and confident. When you buy your jeans make sure that they make you look like you have a booty. If you don't have a booty there are many alternatives to fix it. You can work out and make a booty or you can wear padded underwear that gives you an extra boost. Don't worry, I know plenty of people who can get away with it. But to be honest, the best way to look "banging" is to be yourself so you can attract the right guy, girl , or crowd. When you buy shoes get some Nike's or Reebok's or even Fila's. They are all great brands of shoes and look cute with jeans. Keep in mind that when you are buying your clothes that they make you look like you are in shape. You don't have to be in perfect shape to be "banging" you just have to know how to dress yourself. <figure rend="Look Bangin Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear makeup: Start off with mascara that makes your eyelashes super thick and long.  As you are waiting for your mascara to dry, you will need powder foundation that matches your skin tone perfectly. The reason for this is to protect your face and soak up any extra oils so your skin doesn't look greasy. Now, you will need bronzer and just put some on your cheeks. You can't really go wrong with bronzer unless you put too much. Next apply some eyeliner gently to the bottom lid going thicker as you reach the outer corners. Also put some on the top inside your eye to make your eyes look really cute. Get some shimmery eyeshadow and put a little bit in the inner corners of your eye. All you have to do next is very carefully and gently line your lips with a lip pencil and blend very well. Top it off with a light pink or clear lip gloss. <figure rend="Look Bangin Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get a cute hairstyle: A really good one is uneven side bangs and the rest of your hair long and straight. Scrunching is great! Its also very easy to do and you can read one of my other articles to learn how to do it. <figure rend="Look Bangin Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Learn how to flirt and become more open towards people. Communication and your attitude is the true key to look "banging". Have a sweet yet sexy attitude and communicate well with others. Don't come across as stupid or a know it all and you'll be good to go! <figure rend="Look Bangin Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Show off your own personal style, add a few accessories hold your head up high and be confident. Smile, you absolutely must smile! A smile puts the finishing touches on a great look! <figure rend="Look Bangin Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Finished. <figure rend="Look Bangin Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Always smile!</item>
<item>Just be yourself and have fun.</item>
<item>Love a lot.</item>
<item>Talk a lot.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't dress like you are ready to give someone a lap dance. You don't want people to get the wrong impression of you. Keep your personal style cool, cute, and casual, while still looking sexy.</item>
<item>Don't overdo your makeup.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A little bit of cash to find some cute clothes.</item>
<item>Hair appliances and products, as well as some makeup.</item>
<item>A nice pair of your favorite kicks.</item></list>
</text>
