<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc123" title="Look and Feel Your Best Every Day" shortTile="look-feel-best-day" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2006-08-01" dateModified="2019-05-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Look_and_Feel_Your_Best_Every_Day" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Look and Feel Your Best Every Day</head><p>Do you ever feel like you're just not looking good? If you feel that way, it will often lead to a spiral in which you just feel down and aren't your usual unique self. You can learn to look and feel your best every day so that those problems won't happen any longer.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>First, take a shower. You sweat while you sleep and that makes you stink. Use a good smelling soap and be sure to shave your underarms and legs if it's necessary. Use shampoo and conditioner, but not too much conditioner. <figure rend="Look and Feel Your Best Every Day Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Once you get out, check to see if your eyebrows need any plucking. It's less painful to pluck after a nice hot shower. Next, dry your hair to about 95% dry so it doesn't completely dry out. Then, wash your face if you didn't in the shower. <figure rend="Look and Feel Your Best Every Day Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Don't forget to rub in a good lotion or cream on your neck, shoulders, and arms. Make yourself smell good, but remember not to overdo it or mix scents. <figure rend="Look and Feel Your Best Every Day Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Of course, brush your teeth, floss and use mouthwash. <figure rend="Look and Feel Your Best Every Day Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>If you straighten or do anything else to your hair, do so. (Tip: never straighten your hair if it's wet. Sure, it saves time, but it makes your hair dry, which damages your hair, and gives it a straw-like appearance) <figure rend="Look and Feel Your Best Every Day Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wearing too much foundation doesn't look natural. If you have serious acne, go to the dermatologist or use an acne solution. It'll be the best thing you ever do for yourself. In the mean time, pat on some concealer with a light powder and go easy with the foundation. <figure rend="Look and Feel Your Best Every Day Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Although natural beauty is the best kind, if you're going to use makeup don't use too much. Choose to play up the lips or the eyes, never both. If you want to do your eyes, use an eyeshadow, and maybe some mascara or eyeliner and a natural color lip with a little clear gloss. If you want to go for the lips, use your favorite lipstick and only use a little mascara on your eyes. (No tarantula legs.) <figure rend="Look and Feel Your Best Every Day Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Make sure your nails are clean. Keep them short, and use a moisturizing lotion of your hands. People often judge you on the way your hands and nails are kept. Don't wear polish until it chips away, and don't over grow your nails. If you're going for fakes, go for the classic short French manicure look. Bold fake nails are outdated. Avoid buying the plastic kind and doing them yourself. Go to a salon. If you can't afford that, just keep your nails short and clean. <figure rend="Look and Feel Your Best Every Day Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get dressed, and before you go shopping know what looks best on you. Consider the color of your eyes, your skin tone, your body shape and your personal style when shopping. <figure rend="Look and Feel Your Best Every Day Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Beauty is mostly internal. Have confidence in yourself &amp; you're beautiful! Be nice to everyone, and treat people how you want to be treated. Don't forget what all those cheesy Nick Jr. shows taught us!</item>
<item>Beauty is not all outside. If you are a happy, bubbly person, your skin will appear radiant and beautiful.</item>
<item>Remember, beauty does not equal immodest clothing; wearing clothes that are not too tight and revealing actually boosts your confidence level. Taking a good picture of yourself can also make yourself feel better.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't use too much makeup for every day looks. Save it for parties and special occasions.</item>
<item>Dress appropriately for your age and body type. You wouldn't want complete strangers making rude comments about you because your shirt is too short on your belly, and your stomach is drooping out of your pants, or because you're 30 or older and wearing neon-green eyeshadow and hot pink lipstick. When shopping for clothes, make sure they fit properly. If you find an item that you really like, but it's not in your size, don't buy it.</item>
<item>Don't lay anything on too thickly. Less is really more, plus, it's easier to build upon, than to have to wash off and start all over because you put too much on in the first place</item>
<item>Get advice from a good hair stylist if you want to to do something different to your hair, Going for the scissors yourself is almost never a good idea.</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>A good shampoo and conditioner</item>
<item>Great smelling soaps or body wash</item>
<item>Lotions and body sprays</item>
<item>Hygiene essentials.</item>
<item>Soap, exfoliating scrub, and foaming cleanser for your face</item></list>
</text>
