<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc108" title="Look Good for a Boy" shortTile="look-good-boy" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2007-06-03" dateModified="2019-08-24" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Look_Good_for_a_Boy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Look Good for a Boy</head><p>This is for girls who want to both look good and feel good about themselves when flirting with a boy.  If you follow these tips on how to take care of yourself, you will both look and feel good, and he will notice.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Groom Yourself</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Be fresh.  Take a shower and don't forget to shave (Some men prefer hair on women) .  Use fragrant bath gels and shampoos. <figure rend="Look Good for a Boy Step 1 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Moisturize.  Keep your skin soft by rubbing body lotion or body butter all over right after getting out of the shower. <figure rend="Look Good for a Boy Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Smell good.  Use a light body spray or oil on your wrists, behind your ears, on your chest, and behind your knees. <figure rend="Look Good for a Boy Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Get Ready</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Put on just a little make-up. Whatever you feel highlights your best features, be it a little mascara, some lipgloss, or a bit of blush.  Don't overdo it - you want him to see you, not what you're wearing. Or rock the natural look. <figure rend="Look Good for a Boy Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Fix your hair.  You want your hair to be soft and flowing, not stiff and full of hair product.  It doesn't have to be fancy, just make sure to brush it so you (or he) can get your fingers through it and it's not in your face. <figure rend="Look Good for a Boy Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get dressed.  Choose an outfit that is sexy but not too revealing. You want to be comfortable and not concerned about your skirt riding up or your shirt falling down. <figure rend="Look Good for a Boy Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Accessorize.  Put on a pair of earrings or paint your nails if this makes you feel good.  Don't do anything that you wouldn't normally be comfortable with, and avoid jewelry that is too large or heavy or extreme polish colors. <figure rend="Look Good for a Boy Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Double check.  Is there food in your teeth?  Do you feel well?  You don't want to be distracted or cranky if your mind is on something else or you're tired, so make sure you're in the mood. <figure rend="Look Good for a Boy Step 8 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Have your <hi rend="italic">own</hi> style.</item>
<item>Healthy habits such as getting regular exercise, being well rested, and maintaining a balanced diet do wonders for making you both look and feel good.</item>
<item>Dress for the occasion.</item>
<item>Always take care of yourself, whether there's a guy around or not!  The trick to getting a guy to like you is to like yourself.</item>
<item>Mix creams to moisturize your skin.</item>
<item>Also some guys don't like makeup. Some guys don't like when girls shave. Just be yourself.</item>
<item>Guys don't like bad breath.</item>
<item>Remember, you don't want to change your entire style for a guy, even if you're convinced you're in love with him. If you're on a date or any fancy occasion, I'd recommend taking some tic-tacs, some money, your phone. Anything else such as pads or a hairbrush are optional.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't overdo anything. You don't want to overdress or wear too much makeup or perfume.</item></list>
</text>
