<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc110" title="Look Great with What You've Got (for Girls)" shortTile="look-great-ve--girls" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2007-03-20" dateModified="2018-11-30" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Look_Great_with_What_You%27ve_Got_%28for_Girls%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Look Great with What You've Got (for Girls)</head><p>You want to look great without being stereotyped. You're on a budget and want a look you can create with what you've got. This article can help get you there.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Feel great about yourself; that always helps you look and feel better. Try reminding yourself that there is nobody else in the world just like you and that you can be whoever you want to be, but above all, you want to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Yourself">Be Yourself</ref>. <figure rend="Look Great with What You've Got (for Girls) Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Develop a simple but efficient beauty routine (optional). Try cleaning up your look by plucking your eyebrows a bit. If you aren't sure how to do this and are a bit doubtful, have your mom, an older sister, or a friend help you. <figure rend="Look Great with What You've Got (for Girls) Step 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Make sure that you wash your face with a facial soap or detergent daily. If you're on a really strict budget, just use a bar of soap that is not so strong in fragrance. Try Neutrogena Oil-Free acne Wash if you are allowed to purchase something. <figure rend="Look Great with What You've Got (for Girls) Step 2Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Moisturize your face daily with any lotion that does not have too strong a fragrance. If you have very sensitive skin, do a skin test. Dab a bit of the lotion into the inside of your elbow and wait six hours to see if you have a reaction. If so, do not use that product. <figure rend="Look Great with What You've Got (for Girls) Step 2Bullet2.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Start applying makeup (again optional). Use a light-weight SPF based foundation that matches your skin tone. If you have dry lips use lip-balm instead of lip gloss. The key is to be you and not to wear a mask of makeup on your face. If you really like to play up your eyes definitely use mascara. But if you like a lot use glitter on your eyes or a sparkly cream shadow on your lids (don't use eyeshadow without applying mascara too). <figure rend="Look Great with What You've Got (for Girls) Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Keep your hair looking great. <figure rend="Look Great with What You've Got (for Girls) Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try to keep your natural hair color. <figure rend="Look Great with What You've Got (for Girls) Step 4Bullet1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get a trim every 4-6 weeks. <figure rend="Look Great with What You've Got (for Girls) Step 4Bullet2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Try not to use heat styling products. But if you absolutely have to do it only once every 1-2 weeks. Wash your hair every other day. Use a deep conditioner if you have one. If you can not afford one then just use what you have. <figure rend="Look Great with What You've Got (for Girls) Step 4Bullet3.jpg"></figure></item></list></item>
<item>Try on different styles when you go into stores.  Take a bunch of stuff into the dressing room, try it on, and <hi rend="italic">look in the mirror</hi>.  See what you actually like, and not what you <hi rend="italic">thought</hi> you might like.  Then you can modify your look.  And if you put the clothes back on the hangars when you're done, the clerks won't hate you the next time you come in to try stuff on. <figure rend="Look Great with What You've Got (for Girls) Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>When you put on something at home and don't like it, it doesn't fit you right any more, or you can't quite make it work with other things you own, put it in the "donate" pile or give it to a friend.  The trick is to keep only the clothing and accessories that make you look and feel good, so that when you're throwing an outfit together at the last minute when you're still half asleep, you still feel good about your look later in the day. <figure rend="Look Great with What You've Got (for Girls) Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wear comfortable clothes that suit your mood. You don't need the most expensive, flashy, baggy, tight, or nicest clothes to look great. Remember, looking great is not just about your appearance, but also your attitude and how you carry yourself. <figure rend="Look Great with What You've Got (for Girls) Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Be a real person, then you'll know that your friends like you for yourself, and you like them for who they are as well.</item>
<item>Work hard in school and ask teachers for help if you need it.</item>
<item>Respect your parents.</item>
<item>Don't judge others.</item>
<item>Do not fall victim to peer pressure!</item>
<item>Treat others with kindness and make friends with everybody. Sometimes the best friendships are with the people you thought were mean or weird.</item>
<item>Don't act stupid for boys.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>People are always going to be talking, laughing, looking, and gossiping about you. Don't worry, because it happens to everyone. That's just life and things usually improve when you have determination and confidence.</item>
<item>Don't wear cleavage showing clothes if you have it. Even though you have cleavage, it doesn't mean it is the best idea to show it off all the time.</item></list>
</text>
