<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc106" title="Look Beautiful, Healthy and Fit Naturally" shortTile="look-beautiful-healthy" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2011-08-25" dateModified="2019-10-11" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Look_Beautiful%2C_Healthy_and_Fit_Naturally" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Look Beautiful, Healthy and Fit Naturally</head><p>Everyone wants to <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Look_and_Feel_Healthy">look healthy</ref>, <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Keep_Fit">fit</ref>, and <ref target="https://www.wikihow.com/wiki/Be_Beautiful">beautiful</ref>. People want to maintain their figure but don’t know how to maintain it. Luckily with just a few minor tweaks you can feel amazing in no time.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Looking After Your Health</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Do not starve yourself. Starving your body can actually give you the opposite of what you want by making your body go into survival mode which means it will hold on to fat easier. Lose weight the healthier way  by eating fresh fruits and vegetables, going to the gym, and by drinking more water. <figure rend="Look Beautiful, Healthy and Fit Naturally Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Hydrate your body first thing in the morning. Start your day having aloe-vera pulp, coconut water or normal water. Leave a cup on your nightstand to remind yourself to drink every morning. <figure rend="Look Beautiful, Healthy and Fit Naturally Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Replace coffee with tea. Instead of drinking coffee all the time, have two cups of green tea every day. You can drink coffee but not frequently. Green tea is filled with antioxidants and can help you have better skin and shed off those extra pounds. <figure rend="Look Beautiful, Healthy and Fit Naturally Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Exercise as much as possible. Get a membership at your local gym and try your hardest to go there at least once a week then twice a week etc. Workout at home if you're not comfortable doing it in public areas. <figure rend="Look Beautiful, Healthy and Fit Naturally Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Swap out processed sugar. Swap processed sugar with a healthy option such as coconut sugar or agave. Treat yourself to a sugary snack once in a while such as a cupcake or cake pops. <figure rend="Look Beautiful, Healthy and Fit Naturally Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Incorporate healthy fats. Remember not all fats are bad however, fats from donuts, cakes, and pies are. Add healthy fats to your food like extra virgin olive oil, flaxseed, walnuts, almonds, avocado etc by adding it to salads, smoothies, soups, and more. <figure rend="Look Beautiful, Healthy and Fit Naturally Step 6.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Look After Your Hair</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Give yourself a scalp massage. Massage your scalp with warm coconut or castor oil twice a week. Leave it overnight and shampoo the following morning with a natural sulfate free shampoo. Massaging the scalp stimulates growth which can lead to potential hair growth. <figure rend="Look Beautiful, Healthy and Fit Naturally Step 9.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Wait until your hair is dry to comb it. Brushing wet hair is a big no no when it comes to hair. Never use a brush on wet hair as it will only tear it out. Instead use wide toothed comb, make sure to comb your hair from bottom to top not top to bottom. <figure rend="Look Beautiful, Healthy and Fit Naturally Step 10.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get rid of head or pubic lice. Purchase products from a local drugstore to help with your lice. Visit a doctor you trust if the problem gets worse. Use home remedies such as applying the juice of basil leaves to your hair, leave overnight, and then wash off. <figure rend="Look Beautiful, Healthy and Fit Naturally Step 11.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Look After your Skin</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Apply vinegar on your back for 10-30 minutes with cotton pads, results amazing in 3-4 weeks (for acne problems). <figure rend="Look Beautiful, Healthy and Fit Naturally Step 12.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Cleanse your face with unboiled milk. Pour some milk into a large bowl, any milk will do. Dip a washcloth into the milk and squeeze out the excess. Gently exfoliate your skin by rubbing the washcloth in circular motions around your face. Rinse off with cold water and continue with your normal skincare routine. <figure rend="Look Beautiful, Healthy and Fit Naturally Step 13.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get rid of pimples. There are many popular home remedies for blemishes such as: <figure rend="Look Beautiful, Healthy and Fit Naturally Step 14.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Apply mint juice on pimples. Allow it to dry before washing.</item>
<item>Dilute apple cider vinegar with water, use as a toner.</item>
<item>Mash an avocado, leave it on for 20 minutes before washing.</item>
<item>Make a paste with oatmeal and water, leave it on for 10 minutes before washing.</item>
<item>Drinking lots of water can also improve your skin tremendously.</item></list></item>
<item>Tone uneven areas. To tone uneven areas on your body rub lemon on your skin, use for 3-4 months. Apply sun screen after using lemon and take caution, as lemon can actually make your skin photosensitive meaning it can actually do the reverse of what your going for. <figure rend="Look Beautiful, Healthy and Fit Naturally Step 15.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Apply olive oil (or coconut oil with water mixed in to make a liquid) , pour the oil into a bowl, dip a cloth in it and rub it gently onto your face.</item></list>
</text>
