<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc104" title="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out" shortTile="feel-beautiful-inside" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2009-11-24" dateModified="2018-12-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Feel_Beautiful_Inside_and_Out" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Feel Beautiful Inside and Out</head><p>Beauty is a word with endless meaning. Despite this, it does tend to describe a positive energy coming from within, not a state achieved by make-up and varnish. If you want others to feel that you are beautiful, you need to feel the same about yourself, both inside and out.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<head>Attending to outer beauty</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Have high standards of hygiene. Shower daily, use deodorant and wear clean clothes. These simple things have the power to leave you feeling good and looking your best. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 1 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Care for your teeth. Have good oral hygiene-brush and floss your teeth, and use mouthwash if you need to. Teeth that are well cared for will last you a lifetime. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 2 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Care for your hair. Your hair is one of the first things people notice about you. Keep it looking clean, neat, and shiny. Wash it every other day, or every 3 days if it's not particularly oily. Use shampoo and conditioner that work for your hair type. Brush it every day, even if you don't style it. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 3 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Try out new hairstyles. Find the one that suits you best at each stage of your life.</item></list></item>
<item>Look after your skin. Use a shower puff to exfoliate your body every other day in the shower. Rinse your body in cool water. Moisturize your skin after washing it, every day. Wash and moisturize your face twice a day. Use a toner if you need it, and exfoliate every other day. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 4 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Deeply moisturize your feet regularly.</item></list></item>
<item>Wear clothes that you feel good in. Choose the clothes that feel comfortable and that you know accentuate your best features. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 5 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Attending to both inner and outer beauty</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Realize that a healthy body presents a healthy glow. This is beautiful to behold. It also frees you up to spend more time addressing your intellectual and spiritual growth. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 6 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Exercise regularly. This helps you to keep fit, restores energy and releases those precious endorphins that lift your mood and improve your spirit. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 7 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Go to bed early. Begin giving yourself more quality sleep, during which both body and mind are restored, allowing you to wake up feeling refreshed. It will also enhance your creativity and help you to process your emotions and feelings. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 8 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Stretch yourself and wake up and sit on your bed with a very beautiful and confident smile. Be grateful for such a beautiful life and such a beautiful morning. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 9 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do a few yoga stretches (Surya Namaskar) to improve your blood circulation.</item></list></item>
<item>Say no to junk food today. Eat healthy and drink water instead of sodas or sugary drinks. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 10 Version 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Treat yourself. After working or studying hard, you deserve a treat. Have a massage, take a walk in the woods, visit a friend you haven't seen for ages, or simply hang out at home doing absolutely nothing. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 11 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Attending to inner beauty</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Relax. Take time everyday to have you time. Meditate, have a hot bath, read a good book just take it easy. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 12 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Write. If you are in a negative state of mind about yourself, write a list of good things about yourself and things that you can improve on. Also write how you can improve them and what you can then do to maintain it. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 13 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Love yourself. You shouldn't want to be anyone else and if you do think why. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 14 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Face the world with a smile. Greet your neighbours, friends, newspaper boy and everyone whom you know. Smile with a gratitude to this universe for whatever you are. Say 'Thank You' with a heartfelt smile to all those who acknowledge your beauty. Help the people around you. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 15 Version 2.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Spread positivity. If you do it, hopefully everyone else will too.</item></list></item>
<item>Empathise. Other people appreciate this. Try to understand what it would be like to be this person. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 16 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Listen. However much you want to talk about your problem, a conversation is a two-way thing. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 17 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Be kind. This is best way to interact with others in life. Deliver it in huge amounts, and especially to the grumpiest and the saddest. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 18 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Come home with a smile. If you've had a hard day, indulge in a relaxing bubble bath for 10 to 20 minutes. A little relaxation will put you in a good state of mind for the rest of the evening. <figure rend="Feel Beautiful Inside and Out Step 19 Version 2.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Avoid coffee and carbonated drinks completely.</item>
<item>Avoid watching movies (horror or violence) before bedtime.</item>
<item>Keep your house clutter free.</item>
<item>Think positive and positive things may happen.</item>
<item>Minimize your frustration.</item>
<item>Be happy with yourself and surround yourself with the beloved optimist ones.</item>
<item>Have goals.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Stay away from smoking; it ages you and is extremely unhealthy.</item>
<item>Minimize alcohol.</item></list>
</text>
