<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc116" title="Look Fabulous" shortTile="look-fabulous" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2008-02-22" dateModified="2019-08-13" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Look_Fabulous" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Look Fabulous</head><p>Looking fabulous is about having great style, letting a wonderful personality shine through, presenting yourself well, keeping fit, and knowing how to flaunt your assets to their best advantage. It is not the same as being simply pretty, beautiful, or well-dressed–alone these are nice enough features but to be <hi rend="italic">fabulous</hi> requires a balanced and refined combination of it all. See if this is something you'd like to achieve by reading these suggestions.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Have a beauty and fashion clean out. Go through your wardrobe and bathroom cabinet. Keep only the things that fit, are not torn, stained or damaged in any way. For makeup, don't keep anything that is really old, unused or looks bad or cheap. For clothes don't keep anything that you don't like or haven't worn. Go through shoes, accessories, everything. Depending on your current level of fabulousness, this may or may not leave you with many clothes or much makeup. <figure rend="Look Fabulous Step 1.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Buy quality underwear. And wear it! Discard the ratty faithfuls and buy some that maximize your assets and become the new, good quality faithfuls instead. It doesn't matter who doesn't see them; <hi rend="italic">you</hi> know they're on and you'll feel better for it, as well as being shaped better. <figure rend="Look Fabulous Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get decent "basics". The definition can vary depending on your personal style, but generally this consists of tees, socks, gym wear, etc in neutral, muted colours. Go on a shopping trip to a reliable store. This should not be expensive. Get everything that you need. <figure rend="Look Fabulous Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Purchase the "classics". These are the time-tested essentials that you can't go wrong with (as opposed to faddy fashions). When shopping, think classy. Classics aren't impulse buys, make a list before you get out of the house. Google search "Tim Gunn's 10 Essential Elements" to get an example, though this may not be to everybody's taste. This section of your wardrobe should be of high quality, both the style and the piece should last season after season. <figure rend="Look Fabulous Step 4.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Reshape your wardrobe to evolve it into <hi rend="italic">you</hi>. Look through fashion magazines (or even just their websites) to see what the current trends are. Skinny jeans or flares? Hats or headbands? What appeals to you in the current trends? Only choose the ones that you like and that suit you. Don't go overboard on this one - this bit's for cheap, seasonal clothes. Get a few items every season. <figure rend="Look Fabulous Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Kick in a good beauty regime. Make sure you have a daily cleanse-tone-moisturise facial care regime. In the summer months, put on a light sunscreen every day. Shower daily. Shave or wax regularly. Keep nails clean and tidy. Use odour-free deodorant. Pick a signature scent that you always wear, put it on right after you get out of the shower, it can smell funny on fabrics. <figure rend="Look Fabulous Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Use a stick foundation (in the correct colour for your skin tone) to even out skin, try SPF. Use mascara to play up eyes. To add colour, use blush for paler complexions and lipstick (in natural colour) for darker ones. <figure rend="Look Fabulous Step 7.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get a great hairstyle. Wash and condition hair five times a week. Blow-dry every time you wash, make sure you use some heat-protection product. Get your hair cut regularly to dispel split-ends. <figure rend="Look Fabulous Step 8.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Exercise weekly (at least). If you find exercise boring, do sports that are more enjoyable. If you're really into exercise, do an anaerobic-aerobic-yoga routine. <figure rend="Look Fabulous Step 9.jpg"></figure></item></list>
<head>Tips</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Have a good attitude. Be confident. It's 50% of the look</item>
<item>Always drink lots of water.</item>
<item>A great addition to looking fabulous is sounding fabulous. Read newspapers and books so you always have lots to talk about.</item>
<item>Always be yourself. Never go over your comfort zone.</item>
<item>Wear something that brings out something about yourself.</item></list>
<p>(Some examples are eyes,hair,hips,ect).</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don't wear cheap sunglasses, it's bad for your eyes.</item>
<item>When shopping, use all the help you can get. Ask the shop assistants for advice. Check if the store provides free makeovers or free personal shoppers.</item>
<item>It may help to have style icons who inspire you -  think Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, Marilyn Monroe or Audrey Hepburn.</item></list>
<head>Warnings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Never buy the most expensive outfits there are at a store, unless it's really worth it. Look at the sale rack.</item>
<item>Don't put on too much makeup, EVER!</item>
<item>Looks don't necessarily improve what others think of you. If you're changing yourself to get more friends or for some guy to like you, then don't do it. Do it for yourself!</item></list>
<head>Things You'll Need</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Bin bag</item>
<item>Money</item>
<item>Pen and pad</item>
<item>Computer</item>
<item>Fashion magazines</item>
<item>Face wash</item>
<item>Facial toner</item>
<item>Moisturizer</item>
<item>Deodorant</item>
<item>Hair dryer</item>
<item>Heat protection product</item>
<item>Sun lotion</item>
<item>Wax or razor</item>
<item>Stick foundation</item>
<item>Mascara</item>
<item>Blush or lipstick</item>
<item>Perfume</item></list>
</text>
