<text id="autogum_thirdRound_doc107" title="Look Good and Feel Great" shortTile="look-good-feel-great" type="thirdRound" dateCollected="2019-11-04" dateCreated="2011-04-26" dateModified="2018-12-09" sourceURL="https://www.wikihow.com/Look_Good_and_Feel_Great" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Look Good and Feel Great</head><p>A lot of us struggle with occasional or even chronic low self-esteem. We feel like we're not good enough, we're either too fat or too skinny, have breasts that are too large or too small, we're too tall or too short etc. It's time we teach ourselves how to look good and feel great.</p>
<head>Steps</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Ask yourself "What is the problem?" You've got to get to the root of it. First ask yourself what you don't like about yourself. Then go deeper; <figure rend="Look Good and Feel Great Step 1.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">why</hi> don't you like this aspect of yourself;</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">when</hi> did it start to occur;</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">how</hi> did you come to this conclusion?</item>
<item>When you ask yourselves these questions, you get to the root of it and you will be able to tackle it from there.EG: I think I'm too fat; because I can't fit into my clothes and guys  don't like me; it started when I told a guy I liked him but he turned me  down; He likes athletic girls so he must not like me because I am fat.</item></list></item>
<item>Address the problem. Now you know what the problem is, address it. For the above example, ask yourself: Who is he for him to affect me so much? The key here is for you to know that nothing else matters but yourself. The key to addressing the problem is to understand that the base of the problem might not be so important after all. <figure rend="Look Good and Feel Great Step 2.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Change for <hi rend="italic">yourself</hi>. What has been said so far is for you to understand yourself and pick up your confidence again. Now you want to look good and feel great? It all boils down to the individual. The first step has been conquered: Confidence. <figure rend="Look Good and Feel Great Step 3.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Develop a healthy lifestyle. It is clichéd, but there is nothing that beats a healthy lifestyle. Beauty comes from the inside. Now you've got the confidence in you, time to be healthy. <figure rend="Look Good and Feel Great Step 4.jpg"></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item>Eat right. Eating disorders work from the outside in; this is <hi rend="bold">not</hi> how beauty works and at the end of the day, you become a "disorder" yourself. And eating the right foods will put a glow in your skin; something a ton of BB Cream cannot do for you.</item>
<item>Exercise. This induces "feel good" hormones so when you do exercise you feel  better about yourself. Don't you think you'll feel more confident if you  can run faster than that beauty queen who does her daily jogs around the estate to show off her boobs?</item></list></item>
<item>Dress <hi rend="bold">right</hi>. Dress to impress does not mean showing skin or going about in the latest article of clothing from the runway of D&amp;G and other brands. It means to dress to accentuate your assets and minimize your flaws. If you have a curvy figure, don't go about in clothes that stick thin models flaunt. You don't see a plus sized model wearing a size 0. There are clothes for different body types so understand what your body type is and wear what you look good in, not what the latest trend dictates. <figure rend="Look Good and Feel Great Step 5.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Love yourself. No, you're not crazy if you wake up in the morning and look at yourself in the mirror and say "Hey beautiful. You're looking gorgeous today!" If you want to be loved, there's no one else you can rely on for that other than yourself. And love will make you feel great. <figure rend="Look Good and Feel Great Step 6.jpg"></figure></item>
<item>Get away from negativity. If you are in a group with people who keep putting you down, get out of there! They are doing nothing to make you feel good so why bother? Remember, the only person who is important is you. You wanna feel good, get away from people who make you feel bad about yourself. <figure rend="Look Good and Feel Great Step 7.jpg"></figure></item></list>
</text>
