<text id="autogum_bio_doc509" title="Alexander Campbell of Carco" shortTile="alexander-campbell" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-06" dateModified="2018-06-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Campbell_of_Carco" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Alexander Campbell of Carco</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alasdair Caimbeul</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Alexander Campbell of Carco</hi> (died February 1608) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Scotland">Scottish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nobility">noble</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prelate">prelate</ref>. Coming from a branch of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clan_Campbell">Clan Campbell</ref> in the allegiance of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Argyll">Earl of Argyll</ref>, his career began in the 1560s still only a minor, serving the Earl of Argyll's interest. He was made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Brechin">Bishop of Brechin</ref>, and almost immediately alienated the majority of the bishopric's historical resources into the hands of the earl.</p>
<p>After some traveling to receive a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestant">Protestant</ref> education at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geneva">Geneva</ref>, he returned to Scotland in the mid-1570s as an adult and resumed his career as minister and (now) titular Bishop of Brechin. He held this position until 1607, a year before his death.</p>
<head>Accession and alienation</head>
<p>A native of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atholl">Atholl</ref> and the son of Eóin Caimbeul (Sir John Campbell), laird of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ardkinglas">Ardkinglas</ref>, he was born in the mid-16th century.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MacDonald-1">[1]</ref> During the minority of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_VI_of_Scotland">James VI of Scotland</ref>, Alexander's brother Seamus Caimbeul (James Campbell of Ardkinglass), became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comptroller">comptroller</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MacDonald-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Still a minor, on 6 May 1566, at the instigation of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archibald_Campbell,_5th_Earl_of_Argyll">Gilleasbaig Caimbeul</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestant">Protestant</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Argyll">Earl of Argyll</ref>, Alasdair Caimbeul was put to the vacant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Brechin">bishopric of Brechin</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> Crown nomination to the papacy was sent on 21 July 1566, and although Caimbeul was acting with a bishop's authority almost immediately, there is no proof that he had received consecration until he is clearly represented as consecrated-bishop in a document dating to 23 July 1569.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>The earl's purpose in pushing his young kinsman into the bishopric was made clear by the new bishop's following actions. Bishop Alasdair proceeded to alienate most of the bishopric's lands and revenues, giving the lion's share to the earl. According to the historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Keith_(historian)">Robert Keith</ref>, Bishop Alasdair "retained for his successors scarce so much as would be a moderate competency for a minister in Brechin".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Travels</head>
<p>In May 1567, Alasdair Caimbeul received royal licence to leave Scotland, though he was still in the country in July 1569, when he voted against the proposal to annul the divorce between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary,_Queen_of_Scots">Mary, Queen of Scots</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Hepburn,_4th_Earl_of_Bothwell">Earl of Bothwell</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MacDonald-1">[1]</ref> Although his activities are difficult to trace, Caimbeul was attending school in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geneva">Geneva</ref> in January 1574, but travelled back to Scotland later in the year with his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tutor">tutor</ref> Andrew Polwart and the latter's friend <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Melville">Andrew Melville</ref>, who were in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref> by July of the same year.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MacDonald-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Later episcopate</head>
<p>After returning to his native country, he resumed his charge as minister and titular Bishop of Brechin, attending <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Assembly_of_the_Church_of_Scotland">general assemblies</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_Scotland">Scottish Church</ref> in his capacity as bishop.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MacDonald-1">[1]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Paton_(bishop)">James Paton</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Dunkeld">Bishop of Dunkeld</ref>, another Argyll acolyte, accused Caimbeul of giving out pensions on the revenues of his bishopric.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MacDonald-1">[1]</ref> This came before the Edinburgh assembly of March 1575, which ordered that John Erskine of Dun, Superintendent for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angus,_Scotland">Angus</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Mearns">the Mearns</ref> instruct Caimbeul on the duties befitting a bishop.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MacDonald-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Five years later, Bishop Alasdair was once again in trouble with the church. He failed to attend a summons issued to him by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dundee">Dundee</ref> assembly of July 1580, and in 1582 another assembly ordered the Presbytery of the Mearns to bring charges against him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MacDonald-1">[1]</ref> The outcome of these charges is, however, not known, as the records do not survive.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MacDonald-1">[1]</ref> In the following two decades, though, Caimbeul can be seen to take an active part in establishment politics, attending many assemblies, parliaments and meetings of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privy_Council_of_Scotland">privy council</ref>, often acting as a supporter of Argyll.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MacDonald-1">[1]</ref> Notably, the privy council which met at Brechin in April 1602 denounced him as a traitor, even though Caimbeul himself was sitting on it.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MacDonald-1">[1]</ref> That was the last time that Caimbeul sat on the privy council.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MacDonald-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Death and family</head>
<p>Caimbeul resigned the bishopric of Brechin on or before 22 April 1607.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MacDonald-1">[1]</ref> He retired to his estates at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carco">Carco</ref>, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kinclaven">Kinclaven</ref> in Atholl. He died the following year, in February 1608.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>As marriage became acceptable in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish_Reformation">post-Reformation Scotland</ref>, Caimbeul was married twice, firstly to the daughter of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laird">laird</ref> of Circlet, Margaret Bethune, and secondly to Helen Clephane.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MacDonald-1">[1]</ref> Clephane, who bore him two daughters and one son survived her husband's death as a widow.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MacDonald-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
