<text id="autogum_bio_doc262" title="Gregory IV of Athens" shortTile="gregory-iv-athens" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-05-05" dateModified="2018-10-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gregory_IV_of_Athens" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gregory IV of Athens</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Gregory IV</hi>, (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_language">Greek</ref>: Γρηγόριος Αργυροκαστρίτης, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albanian_language">Albanian</ref>: <hi lang="sq" rend="italic">Grigor Gjirokastriti</hi>;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Pelushi-1">[1]</ref> died 1828) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greeks">Greek</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-2">[2]</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albanians">Albanian</ref> scholar and cleric who became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan_of_Athens">Metropolitan of Athens</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Pelushi-1">[1]</ref> in 1827–1828.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Pelushi-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-mann-4">[4]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>Title page of the New Testament in Greek and Albanian</caption></figure>
<p>Gregory was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gjirokastër">Gjirokastër</ref> (Aryrokastro) in the mid to late-18th century. In ca.1784 he was a teacher in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Academy_(Moscopole)">New Academy</ref>, a famous educational institution in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscopole">Moscopole</ref>, a leading center of Greek culture at the time.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> In 1799 he was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Paramythia">Bishop of Paramythia</ref> but remained in this position for only a few months. In 1799, while Patriarch of Constantinople was Gregory V, he was appointed Archbishop of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euboea">Euboea</ref>, also called  "Bishop of Evripos". In the summer of 1821, when the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_War_of_Independence">Greek War of Independence</ref> spread to Euboea, the Turks put him under detention until January 1823.</p>
<p>When freed, he immediately put himself at the disposition of the Greek Revolutionary Government. In his letter to the High Parliament he thanks God for saving him from the hands of the "<hi rend="italic">tyrants of the Nation</hi>", expresses his will to "<hi rend="italic">do his best effort for everything for the benefit of Greece and especially for the people of this island (Euboea)</hi>" and requests the Parliament to use him "<hi rend="italic">for everything that may be beneficial to the Homeland</hi>".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> It seems though, that before his detention Gregory had already been involved in the Revolution, because a good number of Epirots, and indeed many from Argyrokastro, had been fighting in Euboea. It is assumed by the historians that this is the reason that the Turks had arrested him.</p>
<p>Gregory kept on informing the central government on the situation in Euboea, but the government did not use him for the Revolution. By July 1823 the failure of Revolution in Euboea as well as the usurpation of his position by Bishop Neophytos of North Euboea, forced Gregory, among many others, to flee to Corfu retaining his title. In Corfu he translated the New Testament from ancient Greek to Albanian along with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vangjel_Meksi">Vangjel Meksi</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-mann-4">[4]</ref> This work was partially published in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corfu">Corfu</ref> in 1824 and fully in 1827.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> It contains both the Greek and the Albanian text, the latter printed in Greek letters, too.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> Gregory divided the originally one volume edition of 839 pages into two volumes, considering it a more suitable solution because "Albanians kept the holy scriptures close to their chest".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Clayer2007-10">[10]</ref> it For this work one of his biographers Kourilas considers Gregory as "<hi rend="italic">the founder of the Albanian philology</hi>" adding that <hi rend="italic">"...albanologists use this translation as basic text but they only mention his (Gregory's) name ... but nothing about his home country and life</hi>" (Kourilas, p.349).</p>
<p>In 1827 he returned to Euboea and on 16 September he was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan_of_Athens">Metropolitan of Athens</ref> and remained so until his death, in March 1828. He was buried in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chalkis">Chalkis</ref>, Euboea, in accordance to his will.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
</text>
