<text id="autogum_bio_doc590" title="Caspar Schwenckfeld" shortTile="caspar-schwenckfeld" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2002-02-25" dateModified="2019-01-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caspar_Schwenckfeld" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Caspar Schwenckfeld</head>
<figure><caption>Kaspar Schwenkfeld</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caspar</hi> (or <hi rend="bold">Kaspar</hi>) <hi rend="bold">Schwen(c)kfeld von Ossig</hi> (<ref resource="./Media:GT_Caspar_Schwenkfeld_von_Ossig.ogg" target="//upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/cf/GT_Caspar_Schwenkfeld_von_Ossig.ogg">listen</ref>(<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Media_help">help</ref>·<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:GT_Caspar_Schwenkfeld_von_Ossig.ogg">info</ref>)) (1489 or 1490 – 10 December 1561) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Germans">German</ref> theologian, writer, and preacher who became a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestant_Reformer">Protestant Reformer</ref> and spiritualist. He was one of the earliest promoters of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestant_Reformation">Protestant Reformation</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silesia">Silesia</ref>.</p>
<p>Schwenckfeld came to Reformation principles through <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Müntzer">Thomas Müntzer</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andreas_Karlstadt">Andreas Karlstadt</ref>. However, he developed his own principles and fell out with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Luther">Martin Luther</ref> over the eucharistic controversy (1524). He had his own views on the sacraments - the Heavenly Flesh doctrine - developed in close association with his humanist colleague, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valentin_Krautwald">Valentin Crautwald</ref> (1465–1545). His followers became a new sect (<hi rend="italic">see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schwenckfelders">Schwenckfelders</ref></hi>), which was outlawed in Germany, but his ideas influenced <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anabaptist">Anabaptism</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pietism">Pietism</ref> on mainland Europe, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puritan">Puritanism</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/England">England</ref>.</p>
<p>Many of his followers were persecuted in Europe and thus forced to either convert or flee. Because of this, there are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schwenkfelder_Church">Schwenkfelder Church</ref> congregations in countries such as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> (which was then a part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref>).</p>
<head>Life</head>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Schwenckfeld was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ossig">Ossig</ref> near Liegnitz, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silesia">Silesia</ref> now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Osiek,_Lubin_County">Osiek</ref>, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Legnica">Legnica</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poland">Poland</ref>, to noble parents in 1489.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> From 1505 to 1507 he was a student in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cologne">Cologne</ref>, and in 1507 enrolled at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viadrina_European_University">University of Frankfurt on the Oder</ref>. Between 1511 and 1523, Schwenckfeld served the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Liegnitz">Duchy of Liegnitz</ref> as an adviser to Duke Charles I (1511–1515), Duke George I (1515–1518), and Duke Frederick II (1518–1523).</p>
<head>From Catholic to Magisterial Reformer to Radical Reformer</head>
<p>In 1518 or 1519, Schwenckfeld experienced an awakening that he called a "visitation of God." Luther's writings had a deep influence on Schwenckfeld, and he embraced the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lutheranism">Lutheran</ref>" Reformation and became a student of the Scriptures. In 1521, Schwenckfeld began to preach the gospel, and in 1522 won Duke Friedrich II over to Protestantism. He organized a <hi rend="italic">Brotherhood</hi> of his converts for the purpose of study and prayer in 1523. In 1525, he rejected Luther's idea of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Real_Presence">Real Presence</ref> and came to a spiritual interpretation of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eucharist">Lord's Supper</ref>, which was subsequently rejected by Luther. Schwenckfeld began to teach that the true believer ate the spiritual body of Christ. He pushed for reformation wherever he went, but also criticized reformers that he thought went to extremes. He emphasized that for one to be a true Christian, one must not change only outwardly but inwardly. Because of the communion and other controversies, Schwenckfeld broke with Luther and followed what some describe as a "middle way". Because of his break from Luther and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magisterial_Reformation">Magisterial Reformation</ref>, scholars typically categorize Schwenckfeld as a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radical_Reformation">Radical Reformation</ref>. He voluntarily exiled himself from Silesia in 1529 in order to relieve pressure on and embarrassment of his duke. He lived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strasbourg">Strassburg</ref> from 1529–1534 and then in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swabia">Swabia</ref>.</p>
<head>Teachings</head>
<p>Some of the teachings of Schwenckfeld included opposition to war, secret societies, and oath-taking, that the government had no right to command one's conscience, that regeneration is by grace through inner work of the Spirit, that believers feed on Christ spiritually, and that believers must give evidence of regeneration. He rejected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infant_baptism">infant baptism</ref>, outward church forms, and "denominations". His views on the Eucharist prompted Luther to publish several sermons on the subject in his 1526 <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Sacrament_of_the_Body_and_Blood_of_Christ—Against_the_Fanatics">The Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Christ—Against the Fanatics</ref></hi>.</p>
<head>Publications</head>
<p>In 1540 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Luther">Martin Luther</ref> expelled Caspar Schwenckfeld from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silesia">Silesia</ref>. In 1541, Schwenckfeld published the <hi rend="italic">Great Confession on the Glory of Christ</hi>. Many considered the writing to be heretical. He taught that Christ had two natures, divine and human, but that he became progressively more divine.  He also published a number of works about interpreting the Scriptures during the 1550s, often responding to the rebuttals of the Lutheran Reformer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthias_Flacius">Matthias Flacius Illyricus</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>In 1561, Schwenckfeld became sick with dysentery, and gradually grew weaker until he died in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulm">Ulm</ref> on the morning of December 10, 1561. Because of his enemies, the fact of his death and the place of his burial were kept secret.</p>
<head>Schwenkfelder Church</head>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">Schwenkfelder Church</hi> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palm,_Pennsylvania">Palm, Pennsylvania</ref></caption></figure>
<p>Schwenckfeld did not organize a separate church during his lifetime, but followers seemed to gather around his writings and sermons. In 1700 there were about 1,500 of them in Lower Silesia. Many fled Silesia under persecution of the Austrian emperor, and some found refuge on the lands of Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolaus_Ludwig_Zinzendorf">Nicolaus Ludwig Zinzendorf</ref> and his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herrnhuter_Brüdergemeinde">Herrnhuter Brüdergemeinde</ref>. These followers became known as Schwenkfelders. A group arrived in Philadelphia in 1731, followed by five more migrations up to 1737. In 1782, the Society of Schwenkfelders was formed, and in 1909 the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schwenkfelder_Church">Schwenkfelder Church</ref> was organized.</p>
<p>The Schwenkfelder Church has remained small, and currently there are five<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> churches with about 3,000 members in southeastern Pennsylvania. All of these bodies are within a fifty-mile radius of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philadelphia">Philadelphia</ref>.</p>
<head>Schwenkfelder Library &amp; Heritage Center</head>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schwenkfelder_Library_&amp;_Heritage_Center">Schwenkfelder Library &amp; Heritage Center</ref> is a small museum, library and archives in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pennsburg,_Pennsylvania">Pennsburg, Pennsylvania</ref>. It is the only institution dedicated to the preservation and interpretation of the Schwenkfelder story, including Caspar Schwenckfeld, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radical_Reformation">Radical Reformation</ref>, religious toleration, the Schwenkfelders in Europe and America, and the Schwenkfelder Church. The Schwenkfelder Library &amp; Heritage Center has exhibits and programs throughout the year.</p>
</text>
