<text id="autogum_bio_doc391" title="Drekale" shortTile="drekale" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-11-06" dateModified="2018-12-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drekale" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Drekale</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Drekale</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_Cyrillic_alphabet">Serbian Cyrillic</ref>: Дрекале) was according to tradition the chieftain (<hi rend="italic">vojvoda</hi>, "duke") of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuči">Kuči</ref> tribe and founder of the Drekalović brotherhood which produced the chieftains of Kuči for three centuries.</p>
<head>Name</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Drekale</hi> is derived from the archaic Slavic Verb <hi rend="italic">dreka</hi> (as in <hi rend="italic">derati se</hi>) "to scream, shout, outcry".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Šimundić1988-1">[1]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drekavac">Drekavac</ref>, literally "the screamer",<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Levi-2">[2]</ref> was the name for a mythological creature in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_folklore">Serbian folklore</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bogeyman">bogeyman</ref> (registered in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbia">Serbia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bosnia_and_Herzegovina">Bosnia and Herzegovina</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montenegro">Montenegro</ref>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-SMR-3">[3]</ref> According to Rovinski, Drekale is the Albanian-language corruption of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrej">Andrej</ref></hi>;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Ровинский2013-4">[4]</ref> that being his actual name.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>History</head>
<p>Drekale was elected the position of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vojvoda">vojvoda</ref></hi> ("duke") of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuči">Kuči</ref> tribe probably in the second half of the 16th century, based on the proposal of Dreca Dedin.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Petrović1981-6">[6]</ref> According to a story, <hi rend="italic">vojvoda</hi> Žijo Peralov of Kosor married his daughter Mara to Drekale.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> Their descendants were to be known as <hi rend="italic">Drekalović</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>There are several stories on his origin.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>One story has Drekale as the "son of a Mrnjavčić and the daughter of Klimenti vojvoda Martin". This would mean that he was a descendant of the Old Kuči.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Radovanović2004-9">[9]</ref></item>
<item>Local legends tell that Drekale was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skanderbeg">Skanderbeg</ref>'s grandson, baptized as a Serbian Orthodox Christian. There are three different versions of this connection. Two of them say that Drekale (Andreja) was the son of Skanderbeg's daughter Mara and a father from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Klimenti_(tribe)">Klimenti</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bratonožići">Bratonožići</ref> tribe. In reality Skanderbeg never had a daughter. According to the third version, Drekale was a son of Skanderbeg's son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_II_Kastrioti">Ivan</ref> (Gjon).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Ровинский2013-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref>  The connection of Drekale with Skanderbeg, as well as assertions that he was of Albanian origin is widely disputed, since it was impossible for Skanderbeg's great-grandson to be alive in the second half of the 16th century.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></item>
<item>According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edith_Durham">Edith Durham</ref> Drekale descent from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berisha_(tribe)">Berisha</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></item></list>
<p>Legends about the progenitor of the Kastrati say that it was Drekale's brother who had come from Kuči, while Đ. Slijepčević stressed that it was more likely that the progenitor came from Kuči but descended from some other family as Drekale in fact had no brothers.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Slijepčević1983-13">[13]</ref></p>
<p>Dreca Dedin in fact passed his own title of Vojvoda to him, impressed by his successful peace negotiations with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanjak_of_Scutari">Vizier of Skhoder</ref>. Marko Miljanov points out that he was the first elected Vojvoda, as well as the first Vojvoda of the overall tribe, since at the time the Ottoman authorities appointed one in every village. Drekale had two sons, Nikola and Lale. According to tradition, Drekale, along with his older son Nikola, was killed in a skirmish by the members of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kelmendi">Kelmendi</ref> tribe while they were shepherding in the Žijevo mountains. His son Lale survived thanks to the fact that, being still young, he switched his clothes in child's play with a certain Muslim boy from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Podgorica">Podgorica</ref> by the name of Lisičić. Unfortunate boy, who was occasionally shepherding with them, was killed instead. Some historians place this event around 1550.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> Lale later avenged the death of his father and brother, with the help of Muslims from Podgorica. The vengeance is described in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_epic_poetry">epic folk song</ref> <hi rend="italic">Priest Milutin and the Drekalovići</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>Drekale is commemorated in literature and oral traditional poetry, such as <hi rend="italic">Vojvoda Drekale and Vuk of the Klimente</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marko_Miljanov">Marko Miljanov</ref> wrote about Drekale and his descendants in his works.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MiljanovČađenović1996-17">[17]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simo_Matavulj">Simo Matavulj</ref> extensively discussed about Drekale in one of his novels.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref></p>
</text>
