<text id="autogum_bio_doc721" title="Alexander Vaus" shortTile="alexander-vaus" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-10" dateModified="2018-06-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Vaus" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Alexander Vaus</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alexander Vaus</hi> [<hi rend="bold">Vause</hi>, <hi rend="bold">de Vaus</hi>] (d. after 1450) was a late 14th century and 15th century <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Scotland">Scottish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prelate">prelate</ref>. Said to have been the younger son of one Patrick Vaus (died 1392), he apparently held "church livings" in Galloway as early as 1421.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p><p>
He is found in possession of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Precentor">precentorship</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dornoch_Cathedral">Dornoch Cathedral</ref>, seat (<hi rend="italic">cathedra</hi>) of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Caithness">diocese of Caithness</ref>, when a papal mandate from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avignon_Pope_Benedict_XIII">Avignon Pope Benedict XIII</ref>, 25 July 1398, authorised his appointment as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeacon_of_Caithness">Archdeacon of Caithness</ref>: </p><p>To William de Gerland and Thomas de Edname, canons of Caithness, and the official of Caithness. Mandate to collate Alexander Vause, of noble birth, precentor of Caithness, to the archdeaconry of Caithness, a non-elective, non-major dignity with cure, value not exceeding 30 merks sterling, vacant because John de Innes had held it for more than a year without being raised to the priesthood, and without dispensation, and still unlawfully detains it at present; notwithstanding that Alexander is known to hold the said precentorship, which, however, on his peaceful assecution to the archdeaconry he is to demit.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p><p> He may have held this <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeaconry">archdeaconry</ref> for as many as nine years,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> until he was provided as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Orkney">Bishop of Orkney</ref> by Pope Benedict XIII sometime between the date of the above letter and 7 November 1408, probably close to the latter date.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>It is not clear if he ever obtained possession of the bishopric of Orkney, being opposed by the nominee of the Roman pope, probably John Pak of Colchester, and by the King of Norway with Orkney's metropolitan, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_Trondheim">Archbishop of Trondheim</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-252-5">[5]</ref> A letter from the Avignon pope, dated 12 February 1408, granted faculty to Alexander to be consecrated as Bishop of Orkney by three other bishops, "without prejudice to the archbishop of Nidaros to whom Orkney is accustomed to be subject".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> Alexander does not appear to have been consecrated by the time he was provided, on 4 May 1414, to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Caithness">bishopric of Caithness</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Alexander received from the Pope an indult for local consecration, dated 22 January 1415,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> and although the act of consecration itself is unrecorded, he was certainly consecrated by 16 January 1419, when he appeared for the first time as full bishop in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melrose_Abbey">Melrose Abbey</ref> document.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> He was Bishop of Caithness for around eight years, before being translated again, on 4 December 1422, to become <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Galloway">Bishop of Galloway</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> His translation occurred while Alexander was present at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papal_see">papal see</ref>,  following the death of Bishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_de_Buittle">Thomas de Buittle</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Dowden-368-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>Alexander was told by the papacy to take the oath of fealty to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Martin_V">Pope Martin V</ref> in the presence of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Glasgow">Bishop of Glasgow</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Dunkeld">Bishop of Dunkeld</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> He held the bishopric of Galloway for nearly twenty-eight years. Little of Vaus' activities as Bishop of Galloway, like any of the sees that he held are particularly well documented. He witnessed a charter of Margaret, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_of_Touraine">Duchess of Touraine</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Douglas">Countess of Douglas</ref>, at "Treyff", on 26 November 1426, and on 22 September 1429.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Dowden-368-11">[11]</ref> He attended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perth,_Scotland">Perth</ref> parliament of 10 March 1430.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Dowden-368-11">[11]</ref> He is found again in the <hi rend="italic">Register of the Great Seal</hi> on 24 July and again on 6 September 1444.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Dowden-368-11">[11]</ref> He resigned the see to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Spens">Thomas Spens</ref> on 8 January 1450.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> The later historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hector_Boece">Hector Boece</ref> related that Bishop Vaus had gone to a great deal of effort to enable Spens to succeed him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Dowden-368-11">[11]</ref> Vaus seems to have lived for some time after his voluntary resignation of the see of Galloway, as it was said by Boece that Spens refrained from being styled as lord or bishop in the presence of the elderly Vaus.
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Dowden-368-11">[11]</ref></p>
</text>
