<text id="autogum_bio_doc424" title="William Barksted" shortTile="william-barksted" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-06-22" dateModified="2018-11-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Barksted" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>William Barksted</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">William Barksted</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fl.">fl.</ref> 1611) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_people">English</ref> actor and poet.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>William Barksted in 1609 performed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ben_Jonson">Ben Jonson</ref>'s <hi rend="italic">Epicene</hi>, and in 1613 in Beaumont and Fletcher's <hi rend="italic">Coxcomb</hi>. When he performed in <hi rend="italic">Epicene</hi> he was of the company "provided and kept" by Kirkham, Hawkins, Kendall, and Payne, and in Jonson's folio of 1616 he is associated with "Nat. Field, Gil. Carie, Hugh Attawel, Joh. Smith, Will Pen, Ric. Allen, and Joh. Blaney." This company of actors, in the reign of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I_of_England">Elizabeth</ref> the "children of the chapel", under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_I_of_England">James I</ref> was the "children of the queen's revels"; but on the title-page of <hi rend="italic">Hiren</hi> it is "his Maiesties", not the "queen's" revels, so that the designation may have varied. Certain documents (a bond and articles of agreement in connection with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Henslowe">Philip Henslowe</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Alleyn">Edward Alleyn</ref>) introduce Barksted's name in 1611 and 1615–16, as belonging to this company of actors referred.</p>
<p>Nothing later concerning him has been discovered, except an anecdote worked into the <hi rend="italic">Wit and Mirth</hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Taylor,_the_Water_Poet">John Taylor, the Water Poet</ref>, in 1629. In some copies also of the <hi rend="italic">Insatiate Countess</hi>, dated 1631, the name of John Marston is displaced by that of William Barksted. It was possibly as actor that he became acquainted with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_de_Vere,_18th_Earl_of_Oxford">Henry</ref>, earl of Oxford, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_de_Vere,_Countess_of_Derby">Elizabeth, countess of Derby</ref>. The former he calls, in the verse-dedication of <hi rend="italic">Hiren</hi>, "the Heroicke Heroes". The Countess of Derby is addressed as "Your honor's from youth oblig'd".’</p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>Barksted was the author of the poems <hi rend="italic">Mirrha, the Mother of Adonis; or Lustes Prodegies</hi> (1607); and <hi rend="italic">Hiren, or the Faire Greeke</hi> (1611). On the title-page of the latter, he describes himself as "one of the servants of his Maiesties Revels". There is a "Prologue to a playe to the cuntry people" in Ashmole MS. 38 (art. 198), which <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Carew_Hazlitt">William Carew Hazlitt</ref> attributed to Barksted, that is signed "William Buckstead, Comedian". Such unhappily is the little personal fact that research has yielded.</p>
<p>Barksted has been identified by some with W. B., the author of a rough verse-translation of a "Satire of Juvenal", entitled <hi rend="italic">That which seems Best is Worst, exprest in a paraphrastical transcript of Iuvenal's tenth Satyre. Together with the Tragicall Narration of Virginius's Death interserted</hi>, London, 1617. This is a paraphrase resembling in method Barksted's <hi rend="italic">Mirrha</hi>, which is paraphrased from the tenth book of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ovidius">Ovid</ref>'s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metamorphoses">Metamorphoses</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>Both <hi rend="italic">Mirrha</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Hiren</hi> owe much to "Venus and Adonis", and their author pays the following tribute to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shakespeare">Shakespeare</ref> at the close of <hi rend="italic">Mirrha</hi>:—</p>
But stay my Muse in thine owne confines keepe,
And wage not warre with so deere lou'd a neighbor,
But hauing sung thy day song, rest and sleepe,
Preserue thy small fame and his greater fauor:
His song was worthie merrit (Shakspeare hee)
Sung the faire blossome, thou the withered tree:
Lawrell is due to him, his art and wit
Hath purchas'd it, Cypres thy brow will fit.
</text>
