<text id="autogum_bio_doc534" title="Thomé Lopes" shortTile="thome-lopes" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-11-20" dateModified="2018-12-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thom%C3%A9_Lopes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Thomé Lopes</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thomé Lopes</hi> (sometimes modernized as <hi rend="bold">Tomé Lopes</hi>) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portuguese_people">Portuguese</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Captain's_clerk">scrivener</ref>, writer of an eyewitness account of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/4th_Portuguese_India_Armada_(Gama,_1502)">second journey</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vasco_da_Gama">Vasco da Gama</ref> to India (1502–1503).</p>
<p>Thomé Lopes's background is obscure.  All that is known is that he was a native of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porto">Porto</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portugal">Portugal</ref>.</p>
<p>In early 1502, Thomé Lopes was hired as a <hi rend="italic">escrivão</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Captain's_clerk">captain's clerk</ref>) aboard an unnamed ship owned and outfitted by Ruy Mendes de Brito <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> (a gentleman of the royal chamber of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manuel_I_of_Portugal">Manuel I of Portugal</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref>) and captained by an Italian, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Buonagratia">Giovanni Buonagratia</ref> (João de Buonagracia) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florence">Florence</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>  This ship was part of a Portuguese squadron of five ships, under the overall command of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Estêvão_da_Gama_(c._1470)">Estêvão da Gama</ref> (cousin of Vasco da Gama).  This squadron set out from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisbon">Lisbon</ref> on 1 April 1502, intending to catch up and join the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/4th_Portuguese_India_Armada_(Gama,_1502)">4th Portuguese India Armada</ref> of admiral <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vasco_da_Gama">Vasco da Gama</ref>, which had left a few months earlier (February 1502).  According to Lopes, their squadron caught up with the main armada on 21 August 1502 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anjediva">Anjediva</ref> Island, off the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malabar_Coast">Malabar Coast</ref> of India.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Among the most memorable passages in Lopes's account, is a detailed description of the notorious <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/4th_Portuguese_India_Armada_(Gama,_1502)#Massacre_of_the_Pilgrim_Ship">massacre of the Muslim pilgrim ships</ref> (3 October 1502 a day "that I remember every day of my life"<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref>) on the orders of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vasco_da_Gama">Vasco da Gama</ref>. Later Portuguese chroniclers have dealt uneasily with this act of cruelty, but Lopes's vivid and often heart-breaking narrative leaves little unmentioned.</p>
<p>Another famous episode reported by Lopes is the execution by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impaling">impaling</ref> of three Muslims in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cochin">Cochin</ref>, on the orders of the Trimumpara Raja, the Hindu <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Cochin">prince of Cochin</ref>, for the sacrilege of selling a cow for beef to the crew of a Portuguese ship in harbor. It is notable that it was admiral <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vasco_da_Gama">Vasco da Gama</ref> himself (not usually known for his cultural sensitivity) who arrested the three men and handed them over to the Cochinese authorities for justice, and forbade any further purchases of cows by Portuguese sailors.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>Lopes and the armada left India in February 1503, beginning its return journey back to Portugal.  Lopes reports how his ship was nearly sunk in a collision with another off <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozambique_Island">Mozambique Island</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> Somewhere around the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape_of_Good_Hope">Cape of Good Hope</ref> in July, Lopes reports an encounter with two of the ships of the outgoing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/5th_Portuguese_India_Armada_(Albuquerque,_1503)">5th Armada</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afonso_de_Albuquerque">Afonso de Albuquerque</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>On 30 July 1503 Thomé Lopes's ship, accompanied by two others, came across and landed on the South Atlantic island of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Helena">Saint Helena</ref>. Lopes refers to it as an unknown island,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> and gives its position relative to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ascension_Island">Ascension Island</ref> (which he refers to by that name<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref>). It is commonly accepted that Ascension island was first discovered in May 1501 on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/3rd_Portuguese_India_Armada_(Nova,_1501)">outward journey</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/João_da_Nova">João da Nova</ref>, and some writers<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> have questioned how  Lopes could have known about that island as he left Lisbon before Nova's fleet returned.  A clue is given in Lopes's own account, where he describes how, in August 1502, they picked up letters in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malindi">Malindi</ref> left by the returning João da Nova.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref>  These letters might have described Nova's discovery of Ascension island on the outward journey (although not, of course, Nova's own discovery of Saint Helena on his return in May 1502).  The only quibble remains with Lopes's use of the name "Ascension" island, as it is commonly thought Nova originally named it <hi rend="italic">Conceição</hi> (Conception island), and it was only renamed "Ascension" later (May 1503) by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afonso_de_Albuquerque">Afonso de Albuquerque</ref>.  One possible explanation is that Lopes's account might not have been written immediately in 1502, but a little later after his arrival in Portugal, after the name of Ascension island had already been settled upon.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref>  But the most probable explanation is simply that the name (and maybe even the locational information) was reported to Thomé Lopes precisely by the two 5th Armada ships that, as already mentioned, Lopes just encountered near the Cape of Good Hope (the two would have been coming precisely from Albuquerque's (re-)discovery of Ascension island).</p>
<p>The original Portuguese version of Thomé Lopes's account has been lost, but an Italian translation was published in 1550 in Venice, in a collection of travelogues collected by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Battista_Ramusio">Giovanni Battista Ramusio</ref>.  A translation back to Portuguese was commissioned and published in 1812.</p>
<p>Thomé Lopes's account is one of several eyewitness account of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/4th_Portuguese_India_Armada_(Gama,_1502)">4th Portuguese India Armada</ref> of 1502-03. It is widely regarded as reliable, and frequently resorted to by historians to correct the accounts by later 16th-century chroniclers (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/João_de_Barros">João de Barros</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaspar_Correia">Gaspar Correia</ref>, etc.)</p>
</text>
