<text id="autogum_bio_doc562" title="Stefano Porcari" shortTile="stefano-porcari" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-09-30" dateModified="2019-05-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefano_Porcari" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Stefano Porcari</head><p><hi rend="bold">Stefano Porcari</hi> (early 15th century - 9 January 1453) was an Italian politician and humanist from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rome">Rome</ref>, known as the leader of a rebellion against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Nicholas_V">Pope Nicholas V</ref> and the Papal secular authority in Rome.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<figure><caption>Palazzo della Signoria (Palazzo Vecchio), Florence</caption></figure>
<p>Porcari was born into a wealthy family of Rome. He received a humanist education and became an admirer of the ancient <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Republic">Roman Republic</ref>. Porcari trained as a lawyer, and in 1427 and 1428 was elected <hi rend="italic">capitano del popolo</hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_Florence">Florence</ref> under the protection of Pope <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_V">Martin V</ref>. There he met the humanist scholar <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonardo_Bruni">Leonardo Bruni</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camaldolese">Camaldolese</ref> monk <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ambrose_Traversari">Ambrose Traversari</ref>. While in Florence, it was Porcari's habit, during public celebrations, to give speeches from a balcony on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palazzo_Vecchio">Palazzo della Signoria</ref>, exhorting the people to honor justice, as the foundation of the <hi rend="italic">commune</hi>. He then traveled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France">France</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Greg-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>After his return to Italy in 1430, he held several positions in Italian communes such as the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Podestà">podestà</ref></hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bologna">Bologna</ref> (1432), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siena">Siena</ref> (1434), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orvieto">Orvieto</ref> (1435) and was also governor of the fortress of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trani">Trani</ref>. He came back to Rome under the rule of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Eugenius_IV">Pope Eugenius IV</ref>. When the latter died and before the new pope was elected, he repeatedly addressed the populace to overthrow the papal rule, and to replace them by one based on the ancient Roman republic.</p>
<p>The new pope, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_V">Nicholas V</ref>, pardoned him, but kept him away from Rome with several assignments. </p>
<p>However, his participation in other plots (including one connected with the crowning of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_III,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Frederick III</ref> in Rome), and an inflammatory speech in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piazza_Navona">Piazza Navona</ref> against the government, led the pope to exile him to Bologna. Roberto Cessi suggests that if this was taken as anything more than a criticism of the local city administrators, he would have been dealt with more harshly.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In late December 1452 Porcari was able to escape and return to Rome. Here he organized an insurrection whose result would be the proclamation of the Republic and, for Porcari, the title of tribune, the same held by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cola_di_Rienzo">Cola di Rienzo</ref> in the 14th century. The action was set for the Feast of the Epiphany, 6 January 1453, and would be backed by some three hundred mercenaries.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Greg-1">[1]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_of_Trebizond">George of Trebizond</ref> claimed to have become aware of the conspiracy, through a disaffected priest, nearly a year before and attempted to warn Pope Nicholas.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Monfasani-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Nicholas V, warned by Cardinal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basilios_Bessarion">Basilios Bessarion</ref> that Porcari had disappeared, ordered investigations. Porcari had planned to arrest Nicholas at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_St._Peter's_Basilica">Old St. Peter's Basilica</ref> and kill members of the <hi rend="italic">curia</hi>. Among the co-conspirators were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefano_Infessura">Stefano Infessura</ref> and members of the Orsini. The conspirators were captured, including Porcari, who had tried to take shelter in the house of prince <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latino_Orsini">Latino Orsini</ref>. He was subsequently tried and hanged at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castel_Sant'Angelo">Castel Sant'Angelo</ref> on  9 January 1453.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Of Porcari's literary works, sixteen <hi rend="italic">concioni</hi> (discourses) have survived. The description of his revolt was provided by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leon_Battista_Alberti">Leon Battista Alberti</ref> in the epistle <hi rend="italic">De porcario coniuratione</hi>.</p>
</text>
