<text id="autogum_bio_doc222" title="David Hughson" shortTile="david-hughson" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-11-12" dateModified="2019-10-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Hughson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>David Hughson</head>Not to be confused with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Pugh_(artist)">Edward Pugh (artist)</ref>.
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">Emblematical Representation of Commerce and Plenty Presenting the City of London with the Riches of the Four Quarters of the World</hi>, from Volume I of Hughson's description of London.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Hughson</hi> (c. 1760s – 1820s), which may have been a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pen_name">pen name</ref> of <hi rend="bold">Edward Pugh</hi>, was a writer on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Topography">topography</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_London">history of London</ref>. He produced a description of the city based on "an actual <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/perambulation">perambulation</ref>" (walk) that was published in six volumes between 1805 and 1809 and contains 150 copper plate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Engraving">engravings</ref> principally based on illustrations by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Blemmell_Schnebbelie">Robert Blemmell Schnebbelie</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Gyfford">Edward Gyfford</ref>. He also produced works on topical matters such as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_India_Company">East India Company</ref>, religious subjects, and works of household management targeted at people of the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_class_in_the_United_Kingdom">middling and genteel ranks of life</ref>".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-hend-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Little is known of Hughson's life other than that David Hughson was probably a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pseudonym">pseudonym</ref> and that his real name may have been David Pugh,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-adams-2">[2]</ref> or Daniel Pugh,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> or Edward Pugh,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> or R. Pugh.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-halk-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>In his book <hi rend="italic">The East-India Question Fairly Elucidated</hi> (1813) he described himself as a "native" of London and as having resided in the city for over 50 years, indicating that he may have been born in the early 1760s.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> The last original work published in his name was his 1829 revision of William Augustus Henderson's <hi rend="italic">Modern Domestic Cookery</hi> (best known as the author of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Housekeeper's_Instructor">The Housekeeper's Instructor</ref></hi>). In his works he is described as having the degree of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LLD">LLD</ref> (doctor of laws) and, in one, of MD.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-hend-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fish_Street_Hill">Fish Street Hill</ref></hi>, drawn by Edward Gyfford and engraved by John Roffe for Hughson's description of London. Published by J. Stratford, Holborn, October 1807.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></caption></figure>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Purfleet">Purfleet</ref></hi>, drawn by Edward Gyfford and engraved by Sparrow, for Hughson's description of London. Published by J. Stratford, Holborn, December 1807.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></caption></figure>
<head>Perambulation of London</head>
<p>Hughson is best known for his <hi rend="italic">London; Being an Accurate History and Description of the British Metropolis and its Neighbourhood, to Thirty Miles Extent</hi> which he prepared from "an actual perambulation" (a real walk) of the city. The work was first published between 1805 and 1809 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Stratford_(printer)">James Stratford</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holborn,_London,_England">Holborn</ref> in 149 parts of about 24 pages each for binding into six volumes. After Stratford, it was also published by Joseph Robins of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tooley_Street">Tooley Street</ref> and parts by J. Robins of Ivy Lane, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paternoster_Row">Paternoster Row</ref>. It includes 150 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copper_plate_engraving">copper plate engravings</ref> but also many engraved titles and small <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woodcut">woodcut</ref> illustrations. The engravings are mostly by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ambrose_Warren_(engraver)">Ambrose Warren</ref> from works by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Blemmell_Schnebbelie">Robert Blemmell Schnebbelie</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Gyfford">Edward Gyfford</ref>. Other engravers who contributed were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Woolnoth">William Woolnoth</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Roffe">John Roffe</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J._S._Storer">J. S. Storer</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-adams-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In 1817, he published <hi rend="italic">Walks Through London</hi> (2 vols.) which contained 96 copper engravings and 24 on wood. The principal engravers and artists were J. Greig, T. Higham and W. Wallis. J. C. Varrall, E.J. Roberts, W. Morland and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C._J._M._Whichelo">C. J. M. Whichelo</ref> also contributed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-adams2-9">[9]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halkett_and_Laing">Halkett and Laing</ref>, in their dictionary of anonymous and pseudonymous literature, give the author of this work as "Dr. R. Pugh" but say it has also been ascribed to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Hamilton_Reid">William Hamilton Reid</ref> and Mrs Reid.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-halk-5">[5]</ref> Reid's obituary in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Gentleman's_Magazine">The Gentleman's Magazine</ref></hi> (1826), however, states that although Reid prepared topographical notes on London, his research was unpublished at the time of his death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Domestic economy</head>
<p>In 1817, he published <hi rend="italic">The New Family Receipt-Book: Or Universal Repository of Domestic Economy</hi>. The book collected recipes, medical information, advice on household management, and other material. Among the contents are articles on an "Easy Method of Curing the Sea-Scurvy" and a method "To Increase the Force of Gun-Powder".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Lokmanbooks-11">[11]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arnold_Oxford">Arnold Oxford</ref> suggests it is an abbreviated version of the anonymous 1810 book, <hi rend="italic">The Family Receipt-Book</hi>, the title page of which is almost identical.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></p>
<p>In 1829, <hi rend="italic">Modern Domestic Cookery, and Useful Receipt Book, Adapted for Families in the Middling and Genteel Ranks of Life</hi> was published in New York, stated to be written by W. A. Henderson (author of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Housekeeper's_Instructor">The Housekeeper's Instructor</ref></hi>) and "enlarged and improved by D. Hughson M.D."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-hend-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Other works</head>
<p>In 1814, he published <hi rend="italic">A Copious Account of the French and English Prophets, Who Infested London During 1707</hi> which dealt with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camisard">Camisard</ref> Huguenot preachers, the first of whom arrived in London in 1706, and their fate. In the same year he published the Quaker biography, <hi rend="italic">The Life of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Nayler">James Nayler</ref>, A Fanatical Enthusiast, Who Profanely and Blasphemously Personated Jesus Christ</hi>. Both were reprinted in M. Aikin's <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Religious Impostors</hi> in 1821.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref></p>
<head>Selected publications</head>
<head>London</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">London; Being an Accurate History and Description of the British Metropolis and its Neighbourhood, to Thirty Miles Extent, from an Actual Perambulation</hi>. J. Stratford, London. <ref target="https://archive.org/details/londonbeinganac05hughgoog/page/n10">Vol. I</ref>, 1805. <ref target="https://archive.org/details/londontothirtym00hughgoog/page/n8">Vol. II</ref>, 1805. <ref target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015023994513">Vol. III</ref>, 1806. <ref target="https://archive.org/details/londonbeinganac03hughgoog/page/n8">Vol. IV</ref>, 1807. <ref target="https://archive.org/details/londonbeinganac02hughgoog/page/n8">Vol. V</ref>, 1808. <ref target="https://archive.org/details/londonbeinganac01hughgoog/page/n7">Vol. VI</ref>, 1809.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=i85AAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=RA1-PA55">A Copious Account of the French and English Prophets, Who Infested London During 1707, etc</ref></hi>. S.A. Oddy, London, 1814.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=-YiaknI9Iu4C&amp;pg=PP3">A Respectful Appeal to the Consideration and Justice of the Mayor, and Commonality, and Citizens of London &amp;c.</ref></hi> Sherwood, London, 1816.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://archive.org/details/anepitomeprivil00pughgoog/page/n8">An Epitome of the Privileges of London, Including Southwark, as Granted by Royal Charters &amp;c.</ref></hi> Sherwood, Neely, and Jones, London, 1816.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Walks Through London, Including Westminster and the Borough of Southwark, With the Surrounding Suburbs; &amp;c.</hi> Sherwood, Neely, and Jones, London, 1817. <ref target="https://archive.org/details/walksthroughlond01pugh/page/n7">Vol. I</ref>, <ref target="https://archive.org/details/walksthroughlond02pugh/page/n7">Vol. II</ref>.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Multum in Parvo. The Privileges of Southwark, Comprised in the Charters Granted to the City of London by Edward III., Edward IV., Edward VI. &amp;c.</hi> Southwark, c. 1818.</item></list>
<head>Other</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://app.digitale-sammlungen.de/bookshelf/bsb10281641/view?view=ImageView&amp;manifest=https%3A%2F%2Fapi.digitale-sammlungen.de%2Fiiif%2Fpresentation%2Fv2%2Fbsb10281641%2Fmanifest&amp;canvas=https%3A%2F%2Fapi.digitale-sammlungen.de%2Fiiif%2Fpresentation%2Fv2%2Fbsb10281641%2Fcanvas%2F1"><hi rend="italic">The East-India Question Fairly Elucidated &amp;c.</hi></ref> C. Chapple, London, 1813.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://archive.org/details/memoirsofreligio00aiki/page/n141">The Life of James Nayler, A Fanatical Enthusiast, Who Profanely and Blasphemously Personated Jesus Christ &amp;c.</ref></hi>. S.A. Oddy, London, 1814.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://archive.org/details/b22007325/page/n5">The New Family Receipt-Book: Or Universal Repository of Domestic Economy &amp;c.</ref></hi> W. Pritchard &amp; J. Bysh, London, 1817.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=osu.32435071164867;view=1up;seq=25">Modern Domestic Cookery, and Useful Receipt Book, Adapted for Families in the Middling and Genteel Ranks of Life &amp;c.</ref></hi> Thomas Kinnersley, New York, 1829. (Written by W. A. Henderson, revised by D. Hughson)</item></list>
</text>
