<text id="autogum_bio_doc762" title="Guy de Bourgogne" shortTile="guy-de-bourgogne" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-02-02" dateModified="2019-08-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guy_de_Bourgogne" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Guy de Bourgogne</head><hi rend="italic">This article is about Cardinal Guy de Bourgogne (d. 1272), not Archbishop Guy de Bourgogne, who became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Calixtus_II">Pope Calixtus II</ref> (d. 1124).</hi>
<p><hi rend="bold">Guy de Bourgogne</hi>, O.Cist. (born in Burgundy,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> date unknown; died in Rome, 20 May 1272), was a French monk, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbot">Abbot</ref>, and Cardinal of the Roman Catholic Church.</p>
<p>Guy was Abbot of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cîteaux_Abbey">Cîteaux</ref> from 1257 or 1258 until 1262.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref>  There was evidently some considerable tension in the Abbey during his administration, including a body of dissident monks.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Alexander_IV">Pope Alexander IV</ref> was forced to intervene.  In a letter of 13 June 1260, for the sake of peace in the monastery and so that monastic unity not be destroyed, the Pope said, he forbade members of the Order to make appeals outside of their Order whenever faced with some difficulty or other which might compromise the rigor of the observance.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>  Considering the papal letter, the appeals must have been to the Pope himself.  One of the irritants was the work of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_of_Lexington">Etienne de Lexington</ref>, Abbot of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clairvaux_Abbey">Clairvaux</ref> (1243-ca. 1255), who, following the lead of his predecessor, had established a college in Paris, the <hi rend="italic">Couvent des Bernardins</hi> or <hi rend="italic">du Chardonnet</hi>, for the education of Cistercian monks.  This educational ambition was a departure from the original rigor of the Cistercian rule.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref>  It is said that Abbot Guy de Bourgogne had Abbot Etienne deposed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Guy de Bourgogne was created a Cardinal by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Urban_IV">Pope Urban IV</ref> in a Consistory held on 20 May 1262, and named Cardinal Priest of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Lorenzo_in_Lucina">San Lorenzo in Lucina</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>Cardinal Guy was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papal_legate">Apostolic Legate</ref> in Denmark, Sweden, Bremen, Magdeburg, Gniezno, and Salzburg on 8 June 1265.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref>  In 1266 he held a synod at Bremen with Archbishop Hildebold.  proceed to a synod in Magdeburg.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref>  He then arrived in Denmark, still in 1266, where his task was to compose the differences between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric_V_of_Denmark">King Erik V</ref>, the Queen Mother Margaret Sambiria, Archbishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jakob_Erlandsen">Jakob Erlandsen</ref> of Lund who had been exiled to Germany, and the nobility, instigated by Duke Valdemar of Jutland.  Pope Urban IV had sided with the bishops against the King.  Cardinal Guy summoned the king to a meeting, but, justifiably pleading the lack of security, the King refused to attend, and appealed directly to the Pope.  Cardinal Guy then travelled to Lübeck, where he met with the Archbishop and several other exiled bishops.  Obtaining no satisfaction from the Legate,  Archbishop Erlandsen travelled to Viterbo to deal directly with the new Pope, Clement IV;  he never returned to Denmark.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> Cardinal Guy then visited Sweden, where he granted an indulgence to the Cistercian abbey church of Nydala.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> He celebrated a synod at Vienna on 10 May 1267, attended by six bishops and many other prelates, in which, among other things, he attempted once again to demand clerical celibacy and the separation of clerics from their wives and concubines.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref>  He visited Kraków beginning on 28 June 1267.  He celebrated another synod at Bratislava in Hungary, attended by eight bishops, in the same year.  He preached the Holy Land Crusade.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref>   He was recalled by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Clement_IV">Pope Clement IV</ref> in a letter of 8 May 1267.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> and again in late October, 1267.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref>  Pope Clement wrote to him on October 26/27, 1267, that he was sending a legate to replace him, though travel was being blocked by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conradin">Conradin</ref>; as soon as the legate arrives, he is to return to Viterbo.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> <ref target="http://www2.fiu.edu/~mirandas/bios1262.htm#Bourgogne">Salvador Miranda</ref> states that "he celebrated a synod in Breslau on February 2, 1268."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref>  A subscription of Cardinal Guy, however, indicates that he was back in Viterbo on 28 February 1268.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref>  The correct date for the synod is probably in 1267, not 1268, especially considering Pope Clement's repeated letters of May and October, 1267.</p>
<p>Cardinal Gui took part in the very long Election of 1268—1271 at Viterbo, following the death of Clement IV, which came to be known as the first conclave.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref>   He signed the letter of protest, as did all of the Cardinals, on 20 August 1270, which required the Podestà and the people of Viterbo to swear not to molest the Cardinals or the members of their entourages.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref> In the last stage of the negotiations, he was one of the six cardinals elected to the Commission of Compromise,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-20">[20]</ref> who finally, on 1 September 1271, chose Teobaldo Visconti, Archdeacon of Liège and Papal Legate in the Holy Land.  He subscribed the Electoral Manifesto.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-21">[21]</ref>  Teobaldo arrived in Italy in January, 1272, and was ordained to the priesthood in Rome on 19 March, and consecrated and crowned on 27 March 1272.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-22">[22]</ref></p>
<p>Cardinal Guy de Bourgogne died less than two months later, on 20 May 1272.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-23">[23]</ref></p>
</text>
