<text id="autogum_bio_doc778" title="Henry Bodrugan" shortTile="henry-bodrugan" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-08-22" dateModified="2018-01-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Bodrugan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Henry Bodrugan</head>
<figure><caption>Arms of Bodrugan, <hi rend="italic">Argent, three bendlets gules</hi></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sir Henry de Bodrugan</hi> (c.1263-1308) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cornish_people">Cornish</ref> landowner, knight and politician.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Bodrugan was the son and heir of Sir Roger de Bodrugan (d. 1277) by Isolda (d.1311), later wife of Sir Henry de Pomeroy (d. 1281) and Sir Walter de Aylesbury, daughter of Symon de Pyn. Isolda's great uncle was the Seneschal and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_Sheriff_of_Cornwall">High Sheriff of Cornwall</ref>, Sir Stephen Haym, one of the founding <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_(priest)">canons</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glasney_College">Glasney College</ref>.</p>
<p>When his father died Henry was still under aged and his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wardship">wardship</ref> went to Sir William de Alneto. On 19 May 1277 Henry's wardship was purchased by his uncle, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Bodrugan_(priest)">William Bodrugan</ref>, later Provost of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glasney_College">Glasney</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeacon_of_Cornwall">Archdeacon of Cornwall</ref>. Henry became the heir of both his uncle, William, and his great uncle, Reginald.</p>
<p>In 1287 he married Sybil de Mandeville (29 September 1264-c.1307) daughter of an unknown Mandeville and his wife Alice Giffard. Sybil's grandparents were Hugh Giffard and Sibyl, daughter and co-heiress of Walter de Cormeilles. From 1239 until his death in 1246 Hugh was responsible for raising the young prince, later King, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_I_of_England">Edward I</ref>. Sybil's maternal uncles were the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chancellor">Lord Chancellors</ref> of England, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Giffard">Walter Giffard</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_York">Archbishop of York</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Godfrey_Giffard">Godfrey Giffard</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Worcester">Bishop of Worcester</ref>. Her aunt Mabel was the Abbess of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shaftesbury_Abbey">Shaftesbury Abbey</ref>. Sybil was the widow of Peter le Poer (d. 4 April 1283), likely related to Eustace le Poer who, together with Thomas de Mandeville, brought an army from Ireland to Scotland to fight for Edward I of England. Sybil was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_of_the_Bedchamber">lady of the Queen’s chamber</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleanor_of_Castile">Eleanor of Castile</ref> and her children were still with the Queen's children in 1289-90. She was buried in Glasney College and her son Sir Otto paid for the Bodrugan Chantry to be built there in his parents' honour.</p>
<p>Henry and Sybil had two children:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto_Bodrugan_(died_1331)">Otto</ref>, married Margaret Champernowne (d. 1360).</item>
<item>Joan (b. 1285), married Sir Henry Champernowne.</item></list>
<p>These children and their spouses feature heavily in the novel <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_House_on_the_Strand">The House on the Strand</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daphne_du_Maurier">Daphne du Maurier</ref>.</p>
<head>Landowner</head>
<p>His principal residence appears to have been at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodrugan_Barton">Bodrugan</ref>, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Goran">Goran</ref>, with others at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Looe">Pendrym</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tregrehan_House">Tregrehan</ref>. At his death he owned the manors of Bodrugan, Pendrym, Trethem, Tretheak, Treworrick, Tremodret, Trevellion, Tregrehan, Trethew and Lantyan Parva. The large manor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Restronguet_(manor)">Restronguet</ref> was held by his mother who did not die until 1311. Henry had already given away the manor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barcelona,_Cornwall">Trelawne</ref> to his daughter on her marriage. The manor of Markwell, which belonged to his uncle William, was given to William's illegitimate daughter, but eventually returned to Henry's son Otto. In addition to these manors he held other lands and tenements across Cornwall.</p>
<p>He held some property in Ireland through his wife who was named heir to her brother Walter in 1288. The Mandevilles were important sub-tenants of the earldom of Ulster and, between 1300 and 1304, Edward I issued numerous letters of nomination for Henry's attorneys in Ireland (his brothers John and Peter, and John le Fugheler). In 1305 John le Poer, baron of Doneyl in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterford,_Ireland">Waterford</ref>, and Sibyl's son by her first marriage, was found owing Henry £200. The sheriff of Waterford was commanded by the king to levy £50 of the lands and chattels of John le Poer of the £200. Through her brother he also came to hold 1/6 of the manor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luton">Luton</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bedfordshire">Bedfordshire</ref> which Walter had exchanged for portions of the manors of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eltham">Eltham</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woolwich">Woolwich</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mottingham">Mottingham</ref>. When Sybil died these Mandeville estates passed to her son by her first marriage.</p>
<head>Political career</head>
<p>He was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member_of_Parliament">Member</ref> (MP) of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_England">Parliament of England</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cornwall_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Cornwall</ref> in 1307. In 1284 he was one of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justices_of_Assize">Justices of Assize</ref> for Cornwall, and in 1302 he was a juror at the assizes. In 1309, months after his death, he was summoned to parliament as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hereditary_peer">baron</ref>. As he could not sit in that parliament his descendants were unable to claim the title of baron.</p>
<head>Military career</head>
<p>In 1286 Henry joined <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_I_of_England">Edward I</ref> on an expedition to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gascony">Gascony</ref>. In April he was given permission to go "beyond the seas" for one year with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Burnell">Robert Burnell</ref>, Bishop of Bath and Wells, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edmund_Crouchback">Edmund Crouchback</ref> and others. After sailing to northern France in mid-May they reached Gascony by August. Henry was knighted by 1289, perhaps as a result of his participation in the expedition. As there is no record of him serving in Wales, he was probably part of the 1294 expedition to Gascony with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Brittany,_Earl_of_Richmond">John of Brittany</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Latimer,_1st_Baron_Latimer">William Latymer</ref>. From 1300 Henry became involved in Edward's Scottish wars, his coat of arms is features as No. 227 in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_rolls_of_arms#14th_century_rolls">Galloway Roll</ref>. In September 1302 the king issued a pardon to Henry's retinue, his younger brothers Peter and John, Adam de Markwell (married to Henry's uncle's illegitimate daughter), Serlo Wyse and John le Fugheler for crimes they had committed "in consideration of their service in Gascony and Scotland". The crimes were the retaliatory measures the men had taken after Henry was attacked by Thomas Lercedekne and Ralph de Bloyou at the house of William Bloyou at Glasney.</p>
</text>
