<text id="autogum_bio_doc746" title="Raimondo de&apos; Cabanni" shortTile="raimondo-de-cabanni" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-12-16" dateModified="2019-03-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raimondo_de%27_Cabanni" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Raimondo de' Cabanni</head><figure><caption>Wedding of Raimondo and Philippa, from a manuscript of a French translation of Boccaccio, illustrated by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Fouquet">Jean Fouquet</ref> (1458). The wedding is in the centre, while Philippa as a wetnurse is seen at left and at right, in the background, the torture of Philippa and her son.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Raimondo de' Cabanni</hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[lower-alpha 1]</ref> also called <hi rend="bold">Raymond of Campania</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[lower-alpha 2]</ref> (died October 1334), was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Naples">Neapolitan</ref> knight and courtier of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_African">black African</ref> origin. Through a combination of his own abilities and an advantageous marriage to one of the queen's inner circle, he rose through the ranks to hold the highest office in the royal household by the time of his death.</p>
<head>Origins and early life</head>
<p>The only information on Raimondo's origins and early life are found in the last chapter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Boccaccio">Giovanni Boccaccio</ref>'s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De_Casibus_Virorum_Illustrium">The Fates of Illustrious Men</ref></hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[lower-alpha 3]</ref> written around 1360. Boccaccio claims to have heard the details from two elderly Neapolitan officials, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marino_Bulgaro">Marino Bulgaro</ref> and Costantino della Rocca,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[lower-alpha 4]</ref> during the time he frequented the Neapolitan court as a young man between 1327 and 1341.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEWalter1972-8">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Boccaccio's account is consistent, where it can be checked, with what is known from contemporary documents. That Raimondo was a black African is likely, since a treaty of 1275 greatly limited the legal trade in slaves between Naples and its nearest African neighbour, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hafsid_Caliphate">Hafsid Caliphate</ref>, by forbidding the capture or importation of Hafsid subjects as slaves, thus shifting demand to non-Hafsid (i.e. black) African slaves.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHouben201617–20-9">[5]</ref> Boccaccio claims that Raimondo was "an Ethiopian<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[lower-alpha 5]</ref> man who had in all respects such figure and color as have the Ethiopians who are otherwise called Moors."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEDevisseMollat1979144-2">[1]</ref> He was originally a slave sold by pirates to Raimondo de' Cabanni, provost of the royal kitchens. This Raimondo, recognising the boy's abilities, freed him, had him baptized, gave him his name and named him his heir in both his property and his office.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEWalter1972-8">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Rise at court</head>
<p>The earliest document to mention Raimondo is dated 6 February 1305. It records that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert,_King_of_Naples">Robert, Duke of Calabria</ref>, son of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_II_of_Naples">Charles II</ref>, granted an annual pension of 20 <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oncie">oncie</ref></hi> to Raimondo on the occasion of his marriage to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philippa_of_Catania">Philippa of Catania</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[lower-alpha 6]</ref> wet nurse of Robert's second son, Louis.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEWalter1972-8">[4]</ref> (By comparison, the annual salary of a professor at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Naples">University of Naples</ref> was between 10 and 20 <hi rend="italic">oncie</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHouben201617–20-9">[5]</ref>) The document states that the marriage took place in that year. Since the Neapolitan chancery began the year on 1 September, Raimondo's marriage must have taken place between 1 September 1304 and 6 February 1305.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEWalter1972-8">[4]</ref> The marriage took place in the church of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Maria_La_Nova">Santa Maria La Nova</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESmurra201110–11-12">[6]</ref></p>
<p>His rapid rise in the Angevin court cannot be completely retraced in the documents. Probably he owed his rise partially to his wife's influence as the governess of Robert's children. According to Boccaccio, Raimondo, being an "extremely audacious man" (<hi rend="italic">vir extrema audacia</hi>), asked for and received <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ennoblement">ennoblement</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knighthood">knighthood</ref> on the occasion of his wedding. There is no record of this in contemporary documents.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEWalter1972-8">[4]</ref></p>
<p>On 25 February 1311, Robert, now king, re-confirmed the pension he had granted six years earlier and at that time Raimondo was a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Familiaris">familiaris</ref></hi> of the court. The earliest document that calls Raimondo a "knight" (<hi rend="italic">miles</hi>) is a charter from 1325 or 1326. At that time, he was a <hi rend="italic">familiaris</hi> at the court of Robert's eldest son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles,_Duke_of_Calabria">Charles, Duke of Calabria</ref>, whom he served as chamberlain and as the master marshal in charge of his stables. By the time of his death, Raimondo had been promoted to the office of seneschal of the royal hospice, the highest office in the royal household.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEWalter1972-8">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Through royal favour and connections, he acquired a palace in Naples by the Porta della Fontana in the neighbourhood of the royal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castel_Nuovo">Castel Nuovo</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEWalter1972-8">[4]</ref> He also acquired numerous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fief">fiefs</ref> of the crown, such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minervino_di_Lecce">Minervino</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mottola">Mottola</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foggia">Pantano di Foggia</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[lower-alpha 7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESmurra201113–14-14">[7]</ref> as well as other fiefs from Charles of Calabria in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terra_d'Otranto">Terra d'Otranto</ref>. A document of 1324 shows him and his wife as co-owners with another couple<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[lower-alpha 8]</ref> of the castles of  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cercepiccola">Cercepiccola</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sassinoro">Sassinoro</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Pietro_Avellana">San Pietro Avellana</ref>, Rocca del Vescovo, San Giuliano and Pacile. Other properties are known from the division made by his widow and children after his death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEWalter1972-8">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESmurra201113–14-14">[7]</ref></p>
<p>On 14 June 1333, Raimondo and his sons Carlo and Perrotto were compensated with 10 <hi rend="italic">oncie</hi> and 24 <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarì">tarì</ref></hi> for the loss of several of their horses which had died while in the king's service.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESmurra201113–14-14">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Death and succession</head>
<figure><caption>Detail of the tomb effigy of Raimondo.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESmurra201136-16">[8]</ref></caption></figure>
<p>Raimondo died in October 1334. He received a lavish funeral and was buried in the complex of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Chiara,_Naples">Santa Chiara</ref>, the resting place of the Angevin kings.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEWalter1972-8">[4]</ref> His monumental sepulchre is topped by his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tomb_effigy">effigy</ref> in the figure of a recumbent knight in prayer.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHouben201617–20-9">[5]</ref> He left behind three children by Philippa:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Carlo (dead by 1340). He served as vice-seneschal of the hospice and as royal chamberlain. He married a woman of the high nobility, Margherita da Ceccano, and they had four children: Raimondello, named after his father; Antonello; Sancia; and Giovannella.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEWalter1972-8">[4]</ref> At his birth in 1328, Raimondello received a "woollen cloak decorated with parrots"<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[lower-alpha 9]</ref> as a gift from the king.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESmurra201111–12-18">[9]</ref> He was still a minor on 15 July 1345.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESmurra201111–12-18">[9]</ref></item>
<item>Perrotto (died 1336). He also served as a chamberlain.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEWalter1972-8">[4]</ref> His wife was named Francesca.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESmurra201113–14-14">[7]</ref> He was buried beside his father in the same chapel in Santa Chiara, where is sarcophagus and effigy can still be viewed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESmurra201127–34-19">[10]</ref></item>
<item>Roberto (died 1345). He abandoned an ecclesiastical career to become count of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eboli">Eboli</ref> and ultimately grand seneschal of the realm.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEWalter1972-8">[4]</ref> He married Sichelgaita Filomarino and had a daughter, Caterina.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHouben201617–20-9">[5]</ref></item></list>
<p>Following Raimondo's death, his widow, sons and daughter-in-law Francesca came to an agreement over several <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casalia">casalia</ref></hi> he had owned, namely <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lizzano,_Apulia">Lizzano</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Marzano_sul_Sarno">San Marzano</ref>, Roccelle and a part of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castrignano_del_Capo">Castrignano</ref>, Giuliano and the unidentified <hi rend="italic">casalia</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Pau et Piscarie</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tricase</hi> in the Terra d'Otranto.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESmurra201113–14-14">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Carlo and Roberto's daughters Sancia and Caterina were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ladies_in_waiting">ladies in waiting</ref> to Queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sancha_of_Majorca">Sancha</ref> in 1336. Sancia later became the countess of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morcone">Morcone</ref>. In 1345, she was accused along with her mother and her surviving uncle of the assassination of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew,_Duke_of_Calabria">Andrew, Duke of Calabria</ref>, the husband of Queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joanna_I_of_Naples">Joanna I</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-20">[lower-alpha 10]</ref> All three were arrested, tortured and imprisoned. Philippa died in prison and Roberto was executed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHouben201617–20-9">[5]</ref> On 16 May 1346, a declaration (<hi rend="italic">provvedimento</hi>) was issued declaring Raimondello innocent in the assassination.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESmurra201111–12-18">[9]</ref> This rapid collapse of the fortunes of the Cabanni family following Raimondo's death was the theme of Boccaccio's account.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHouben201617–20-9">[5]</ref></p>
</text>
