<text id="autogum_bio_doc465" title="Henry Nevill, 6th Baron Bergavenny" shortTile="henry-nevill-th-baron" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-09-24" dateModified="2017-07-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Nevill%2C_6th_Baron_Bergavenny" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Henry Nevill, 6th Baron Bergavenny</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Henry Nevill, 6th and <hi rend="italic">de jure</hi> 4th Baron Abergavenny</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Order_of_the_Bath">KB</ref> (between 1527 and 1535–10 February 1587) was an English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peerage_of_England">peer</ref>. He was the son of Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Nevill,_5th_Baron_Bergavenny">George Nevill, 5th Baron Bergavenny</ref>, and Mary Stafford (daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Stafford,_3rd_Duke_of_Buckingham">Edward Stafford, 3rd Duke of Buckingham</ref>). He succeeded to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_Abergavenny">barony</ref> upon the death of his father, George Nevill, 5th Baron Bergavenny.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Henry, sixth (sometimes <hi rend="bold">fourth</hi>) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Abergavenny">Lord Abergavenny</ref>, had summons to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_England">parliament</ref> on 23 January 1552, to 15 October 1586. He was one of the peers that sat in judgment on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary,_Queen_of_Scots">Mary, Queen of Scots</ref>, at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fotheringhay_Castle">Fotheringay</ref>. He died at his seat called Comfort, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birling,_Kent">Birling, Kent</ref>, on 10 February 1587.</p>
<p>He married first, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frances_Neville">Frances</ref>, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Manners,_1st_Earl_of_Rutland">Thomas Manners, 1st Earl of Rutland</ref>; he married secondly, Elizabeth, daughter of Stephen Darell, of Spelmonden, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kent">Kent</ref> (she remarried to Sir William Sedley, of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southfleet">Southfleet</ref>, Kent, Knt. and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sedley_Baronets">Bart.</ref>); by his first wife, he had an only daughter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Neville,_Baroness_le_Despencer">Mary Neville</ref> who married Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Fane_(d_1589)">Thomas Fane</ref>.</p>
<head>Wyatt's rebellion</head>
<p>During the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wyatt's_rebellion">Wyatt's rebellion</ref> of January–February 1554 Henry and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Southwell_(sheriff)">Robert Southwell</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_Sheriff_of_Kent">High Sheriff of Kent</ref> married to Henry's niece Margaret, led the loyalist forces against the rebels. According to D. M. Loades, "Sir Robert Southwell and Lord Abergavenny were almost the only significant gentlemen in the country whose loyalty was never in doubt";<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-L84-1">[1]</ref> "Southwell, Abergavenny and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Cheney">Cheney</ref> were the most active royalist leaders."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-L78A-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Henry and Southwell began recruitment of loyalist forces on 24 January, one day before the outbreak of the rebellion, although at this stage they had little success.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-L78B-3">[3]</ref> On 26 January Wyatt declared Henry and Southwell "traitors to God, the Crown and the Commonwealth" for "stirring up the Queen's most loyal subjects of the realm."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> By 27 January the loyalists's position improved, and their combined forces in Kent matched the numbers of Wyatt's force in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rochester,_Kent">Rochester</ref>, at around two thousand men on each side.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-L58-5">[5]</ref> Henry and Southwell with six hundred men blocked the road from Tonbridge to Rochester to prevent consolidation of the rebels.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-L58-5">[5]</ref> On 28 January Southwell defeated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Isley">Henry Isley</ref>'s company of rebels at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wrotham">Wrotham</ref>, taking around sixty prisoners.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-L59-6">[6]</ref> However, on the same day the army of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Howard,_3rd_Duke_of_Norfolk">Duke of Norfolk</ref> deserted to Wyatt;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-L61-7">[7]</ref> Henry and Southwell fled to London.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> Wyatt marched to London himself with around three thousand men,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Z220-9">[9]</ref> but lost the initiative; Southwell and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Cheney">Thomas Cheney</ref> managed to raise another loyalist company in his rear.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-F119-10">[10]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-L63-11">[11]</ref> On 4 February Henry and Southwell marched to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greenwich">Greenwich</ref>. Wyatt was cut off from his base in Kent, and could not count on reinforcements while the loyalists' forces gained strength every day.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-L63-11">[11]</ref> By 7 February Wyatt's army disintegrated. Amongst Wyatt's supporters who were later sentenced to death was Thomas Fane, later Henry Nevill's son in law. Fane was pardoned due to his youth and he went on to become a loyal supporter of the crown, member of parliament and son in law to Neville.</p>
<head>Issue</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Neville,_Baroness_le_Despencer">Mary Neville, Baroness le Despencer</ref>, died 28 June 1626, aged 72, buried at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mereworth">Mereworth</ref>, Kent, having married at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birling,_Kent">Birling</ref>, 12 December 1574, as second wife, to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Fane_(d_1589)">Thomas Fane</ref>, of Badsell, Kent<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> (whose son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Fane,_1st_Earl_of_Westmorland">Francis</ref>, was created <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Westmorland">Earl of Westmorland</ref>), knighted at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dover_Castle">Dover Castle</ref>, 26 August 1573, died 13 March 1589, w.d. 12 March 1589, pd. 10 February 1590. Lady Fane claimed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_Abergavenny">barony of Abergavenny</ref> against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Nevill,_7th_Baron_Bergavenny">Edward Nevill</ref>, the heir male upon whom the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abergavenny_Castle">castle of Bergavenny</ref> was settled as aforesaid, and as a compromise, she was by letters patent, 25 May 1604, confirmed in the name, style, and dignity of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_le_Despencer">Baroness le Despencer</ref>, to the heirs of her body, with the ancient seat, place, and precedence of her ancestors.</p>
<head>Ancestry</head>
</text>
