<text id="autogum_bio_doc793" title="Henry IV, Count of Waldeck" shortTile="henry-iv-count-waldeck" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-07-08" dateModified="2019-02-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_IV%2C_Count_of_Waldeck" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Henry IV, Count of Waldeck</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Henry IV, Count of Waldeck</hi> (c.1282/1290 – 1 May 1348) was the ruling Count of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waldeck_(state)">Waldeck</ref> from 1305 to 1344.  He was the second ruling count named "Henry", which is why some authors call him "Henry II".  However, two earlier non-ruling members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Waldeck">House of Waldeck</ref> are usually called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_II_of_Waldeck">Henry II</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_III_of_Waldeck">Henry III</ref>, and the subject of this article is commonly called Henry IV.</p>
<p>He was the eldest son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto_I,_Count_of_Waldeck">Otto I</ref> and his wife Sophie, the daughter of Landgrave <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_I,_Landgrave_of_Hesse">Henry I</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landgraviate_of_Hesse">Hesse</ref>.</p>
<head>Reign</head>
<p>Like is father, Henry served the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishopric_of_Mainz">Archbishopric of Mainz</ref> as <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amtmann">Amtmann</ref></hi> in northern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hesse">Hesse</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eichsfeld">Eichsfeld</ref>.</p>
<p>Immediately after the start of his reign in 1306, Henry began the construction of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wetterburg_Castle">Wetterburg Castle</ref>.  This gave rise to a dispute with Archbishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_II_of_Virneburg">Henry II</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishopric_of_Cologne">Cologne</ref>, who argued that the castle was located in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Westphalia">Westphalia</ref>, which he held.  Henry II demanded that the castle be demolished.  Henry IV argued that his family had held a castle on that site for a long time, and he was just rebuilding it.  A lengthy legal battle ensued.  In 1310, Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric_I,_Duke_of_Saxe-Lauenburg">Eric I, Duke of Saxe-Lauenburg</ref> of Saxe-Lauenburg ruled in favour of Mainz.  However, Henry IV appealed.  Arbitration by a neighbouring nobleman was not possible, as they were all biased.  Cologne then occupied <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marsberg">Marsberg</ref> and also claimed Medebach and Canstein.  Henry IV strenuously objected.  Bishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_II_of_Münster">Louis II</ref> of Münster, who was a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Hesse">House of Hesse</ref> and thus a distant relative of Henry IV, nevertheless ruled that the occupation of Marsberg was justified and that Cologne was entitled to demolish Wetterburg Castle.  In 1325, a compromise was reached, in which Waldeck and Cologne would share ownership of Wetterburg Castle<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>For unknown reasons, Henry IV was taken prisoner by Archbishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_of_Aspelt">Peter</ref> of Mainz in 1307.  A deed sealed by King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_I_of_Germany">Albert I of Germany</ref> from March 1308 mentions that Peter and Henry IV have reconciled their differences.  Henry was then released from prison.</p>
<p>In 1312, he promised Landgrave <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto_I,_Landgrave_of_Hesse">Otto I</ref> to support him in his dispute with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Brunswick-Lüneburg">Duchy of Brunswick-Lüneburg</ref>.  The Dukes of Brunswick-Lüneburg were also fighting a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feud">feud</ref> against the Archbishopric of Mainz, whose Amtmann Henry IV had been since 1305.  Close to Brunswick's Schonenberge Castle, Henry IV built a castle of his own, in order to neutralize Schoeneberge.  In 1313, he made an alliance with Archbishop Peter of Mainz against Brunswick-Lüneburg.  In 1315, Henry IV and Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William,_Count_of_Arnsberg">William</ref> of Arnsberg divided the County of Rüdenberg, which until then they had administered jointly, between themselves.</p>
<p>As a reward for loyal his service, Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_IV,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Louis IV</ref> made Henry IV parton of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_imperial_city">Imperial City</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dortmund">Dortmund</ref> and supervisor of the Jews in the city.  In 1337, he was also made supervisor of the Jews in the bishoprics of Münster and Osnabrück.  He was tasked to collect imperial taxes from the Jews.  In 1332, the Lords of Grafschaft sold him a 50% share in Nordenau Castle.  He later purchased another share.</p>
<p>In 1344, Henry wanted to retire from government for health reasons.  With the consent of his sons an inheritance contract was completed, which provided that in future the county would not be divided and there could only be a single of Count of Waldeck at any one time.  This agreement, however, did not last long, and Waldeck was divided several times after Henry's death.</p>
<p>Henry died in 1348 and was buried in the "Waldeck Chapel" in the Marienthal Abbey in Netze (now part of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waldeck,_Hesse">Waldeck</ref>).  His grave stone can still be found there.</p>
<head>Marriage and issue</head>
<p>In 1304, he married Adelaide of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Cleves">Cleves</ref> (d. after 26 July 1327), daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dietrich_VII,_Count_of_Cleves">Dietrich VII, Count of Cleves</ref>. He had several children with her:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto_II,_Count_of_Waldeck">Otto II</ref> was the eldest and succeeded as Count of Waldeck</item>
<item>Dietrich was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_(priest)">canon</ref> in Cologne, Münster and Mainz</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_V_of_Waldeck">Henry V</ref> was also canon and held <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prebendaries">prebendaries</ref> in Cologne and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Minden">Minden</ref>, where he was a  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean_(Christianity)">Dean</ref></item>
<item>Elisabeth (d. before 22 June 1385), married Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John,_Count_of_Nassau-Hadamar">John</ref> of Nassau-Hadamar (d. 20 January 1365), the son of Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emicho_I,_Count_of_Nassau-Hadamar">Emicho I</ref></item>
<item>Armgard, married a Count of Diepholz</item>
<item>Matilda</item></list>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
