<text id="autogum_bio_doc664" title="Henry VII, Count of Waldeck" shortTile="henry-vii-count-waldeck" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-11-22" dateModified="2019-03-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VII%2C_Count_of_Waldeck" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Henry VII, Count of Waldeck</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Henry VII of Waldeck</hi> (died after 1442<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>) was Count of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waldeck_(state)">Waldeck</ref> from 1397 until his death, after which he acted several times as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bailiff">bailiff</ref> for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electorate_of_Mainz">Electorate of Mainz</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upper_Hesse">Upper</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lower_Hesse">Lower Hesse</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was the second son of the Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VI,_Count_of_Waldeck">Henry VI</ref> of Waldeck and Elizabeth of Berg and was considered a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belligerent">belligerent</ref> man.</p>
<p>Even before his father, he attacked the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Paderborn">Bishopric of Paderborn</ref>.  He was accused of having destroyed the castle and town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blankenrode">Blankenrode</ref>.  In 1395, he was made to swear that he would never again invade Paderborn, and Waldeck had to transfer its share in the castle and town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liebenau,_Hesse">Liebenau</ref> to Paderborn.</p>
<p>After his father's death, the county of Waldeck was divided between Henry and his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adolph_III,_Count_of_Waldeck">Adolph III</ref>.  Thus, Adolph III founded the older line of Waldeck-Landau and Henry founded the Waldeck-Waldeck line.  He resided at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waldeck_Castle_(Waldeck)">Waldeck Castle</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1399, he was appointed bailiff of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amt_(country_subdivision)">districts</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fritzlar">Fritzlar</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hofgeismar">Hofgeismar</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battenberg_(Eder)">Battenberg</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rosenthal,_Hesse">Rosenthal</ref>, Elenhog and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wetter,_Hesse">Wetter</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electorate_of_Mainz">Electorate of Mainz</ref>.  Henry reckoned that this office provided him with enough power that he could afford to break his alliance with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landgraviate_of_Hesse">Landgraviate of Hesse</ref>.  At Whitsuntide 1400, he marched his troops to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kassel">Kassel</ref>.  He could not take the city.  He did, however, set fire to several neighbouring villages.  He lost his office in 1404, but was re-appointed temporarily in 1406.  In 1410, he was again appointed bailiff in Upper and Lower Hesse.  He then attacked Hesse and destroyed the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kirchhain">Kirchhain</ref>, whereupon Landgrave <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hermann_II,_Landgrave_of_Hesse">Hermann II</ref> persuaded Archbishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_II_of_Nassau">John II</ref> of Mainz to relieve henry of his duties.  Peace was restored in 1420 and Henry made an alliance with Landgrave <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_I,_Landgrave_of_Hesse">Louis I</ref> that would last until his death.</p>
<p>On 5 June 1400, Henry and his men, who included <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friedrich_von_Hertingshausen">Friedrich von Hertingshausen</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konrad_von_Falkenberg">Konrad von Falkenberg</ref>, attacked Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_I,_Duke_of_Brunswick-Lüneburg">Frederick I</ref> of Brunswick-Wolffenbüttel at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kleinenglis">Kleinenglis</ref>, south of Fritzlar.  A fierce battle followed and the Duke was killed.  Duke Frederick had been on his way home from a congress of princes in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frankfurt">Frankfurt</ref>, where King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslaus,_King_of_the_Romans">Wenceslaus</ref> had been deposed.  Frederick thought that he had a good chance to succeed Wenceslaw, but Archbishop John II of Mainz favoured the election of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rupert_of_Germany">Rupert</ref>, the Elector Palatine.  The newly elected King Rupert investigated the attack on Duke Frederick and Henry was sentenced to the foundation of an altar with perpetual requiem mass at the St. Peter's Church in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fritzlar">Fritzlar</ref>.</p>
<p>Henry also had disputes with his brother Adolph, some of them violent.  In 1421, they settled their disputes and confirmed the division of the county.  They also agreed the neither of them would be allowed to pledge or sell off parts of the county without knowledge and consent of the other.  Deeds relating to either half of the county were to be archived in a common archive at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waldeck_Castle_(Waldeck)">Waldeck Castle</ref>.  Completed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fief">fiefs</ref> would revert to joint ownership.  Future disputes were to be investigated and settled by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burgmann">burgmannen</ref> and councils.  In later years, this treaty was renewed and refined.</p>
<p>Henry led numerous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feud">feuds</ref> with neighboring nobles, including the Lords of Padberg and the Bengler League. The Padberg Feud, also known as Korbach Feud, lasted from 1413 to 1418. Every year on the day of Saint Regina's feast on June 20th a mass and a procession are held in the Hanseatic City of Korbach in remembrance of this feud.</p>
<p>In 1424, Henry and his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolrad_I,_Count_of_Waldeck">Wolrad</ref> pledged half of their territory for life to Landgrave <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_I,_Landgrave_of_Hesse">Louis I</ref> for 22000guilders.  Louis paid up and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burgmann">burgmannen</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vassals">vassals</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/burgher">burghers</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peasants">peasants</ref> of the affected area paid him <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homage_(feudal)">homage</ref>.  However, Archbishops <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conrad_III_of_Dhaun">Conrad</ref> of Mainz and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dietrich_II_of_Moers">Dietrich</ref> of Cologne, in his capacity as administrator of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdiocese_of_Paderborn">Archdiocese of Paderborn</ref> objected and Henry and Wolrad recanted, claiming they had promised the land to Mainz in an earlier treaty, and in 1426, they pledged the land to Mainz for 18000guilders instead, opening their castles to the Archbishops of Mainz and Cologne.  This was one of the causes of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mainz-Hessian_War">Mainz-Hessian War</ref> of 1427.  Conrad offered Louis to refund him his 22000guilders, but Louis turned the offer down.  He declared war on the archbishop on 21 July 1427.  Henry and Wolrad fought on the Mainz side in this war.  Hesse won the war and Henry had to refund the 22000guilders.  In 1438, Henry saw himself forced to acknowledge Landgrave Louis as his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liege_lord">liege lord</ref>.</p>
<head>Marriage and issue</head>
<p>In 1398, Henry married Margaret of Nassau-Wiesbaden-Idstein.  They had three children:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolrad_I,_Count_of_Waldeck">Wolrad</ref>, who would succeed him as Count of Waldeck</item>
<item>Elizabeth</item>
<item>Margaret</item></list>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
