<text id="autogum_bio_doc397" title="Willem van den Blocke" shortTile="willem-van-den-blocke" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-01-27" dateModified="2019-07-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Willem_van_den_Blocke" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Willem van den Blocke</head>
<figure><caption>The High Gate in Danzig – Status before the removal of the walls (drawing by Julius Greth, 1855)</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Willem van den Blocke</hi> (alternative names: Willem van den Block, Willem van den Bloocke, Wilhelm von dem Block, Wilhelm von dem Blocke, Wilhem van Block) (c. 1550 – 1628) was a sculptor and architect of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southern_Netherlands">Flemish</ref> descent who was active in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baltics">Baltics</ref> and worked in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mannerism">mannerist</ref> style.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>He was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mechelen">Mechelen</ref>, the son of Franciscus van den Blocke who was a sculptor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-RKD-1">[1]</ref> Willem received his first training in the art of stone carving and sculpting in his father's workshop in Mechelen.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-blo-2">[2]</ref> He then likely moved for further training to the workshop of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cornelis_Floris_de_Vriendt">Cornelis Floris de Vriendt</ref> in Antwerp.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-WVDB-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In 1569 he went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Königsberg_(Prussia)">Königsberg</ref> (Kaliningrad).  He was part of a group of pupils and assistants of Cornelis Floris, which included <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gert_van_Egen">Gert van Egen</ref>, Robert Coppens and Philips Brandin, who moved to the Baltic region to take advantage of Floris’ network and the international popularity of the Floris style.  The Baltic region was at the time politically relatively stable when compared to Willem's native home, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_Netherlands">Spanish Netherlands</ref>, which were rife with religious persecution.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-os-4">[4]</ref> The van Block family were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mennonite">Mennonites</ref> and were particularly vulnerable to such persecution in their home country.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-blo-2">[2]</ref> In the Baltics there was also less competition from other artists.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-os-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>In Konigsberg van den Blocke worked on the monumental tomb of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert,_Duke_in_Prussia">Albert, Duke in Prussia</ref>, designed by Floris, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Königsberg_Cathedral">local cathedral</ref>. In 1581 he designed and executed the tomb of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elisabeth_of_Brandenburg-Küstrin">princess Elizabeth</ref>, the first wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Frederick,_Margrave_of_Brandenburg-Ansbach">George Frederick, Margrave of Brandenburg-Ansbach</ref>, also in the Königsberg Cathedral.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ox-5">[5]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>Uppsala Cathedral, tomb of King John III of Sweden.</caption></figure>
<p>After 14 years of service to the Margrave, he received a recommendation letter and then went to work in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poland">Poland</ref>. He received many commissions such as the design and execution of the tomb of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Báthory">Christopher Báthory</ref>, brother of the King of Poland <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Báthory">Stephen Báthory</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ox-5">[5]</ref> He completed this commission from 1581 to 1583 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barczewo">Wartenburg</ref> (Barczewo).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-RKD-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In early 1584 he went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alba_Iulia">Gyulafehérvár</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transylvania">Transylvania</ref> to install in the local church a tomb he had created.</p>
<p>Willem van den Blocke moved on 18 June 1584 to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danzig">Danzig</ref> (Gdańsk), the center of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vistula_delta_Mennonites">Vistula delta Mennonites</ref>, carrying with him a recommendation by Stephen Báthory, the king of Poland. As he was in royal employ, he did not have to join the local guild.  He ran a workshop in Danzig until his death<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ox-5">[5]</ref> His most important work in Danzig was the design of one of the gates in the city walls, called the High Gate (completed in 1588). He also created numerous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epitaph">epitaphs</ref> and tombs. He also designed the facades of town houses in Danzig, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toruń">Toruń</ref> (Thorn) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elbing">Elbing</ref> (Elbląg).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-RKD-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>His son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abraham_van_den_Blocke">Abraham van den Blocke</ref> was also an architect and sculptor,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> whereas his sons <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacob_van_den_Blocke">Jacob van den Blocke</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isaak_van_den_Blocke">Isaak van den Blocke</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_van_den_Blocke">David van den Blocke</ref> were painters.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-RKD-1">[1]</ref> Van den Blocke died in Danzig in the same year as his sons Abraham and Isaac, likely from an infectious disease.</p>
<head>Work</head>
<p>Willem van den Brocke is regarded as the main representative in the Baltics of Italianizing Flemish mannerism as developed first by Cornelis Floris.  Although he designed many building ornaments, he is best known for his monuments.  His monuments are characterized by their clarity and rich ornamentation.  The deceased are presented realistically.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ox-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Epitaph of Edward Blemke in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Mary's_Church,_Gdańsk">St. Mary's Church</ref>, 1591</item>
<item>Tomb of the King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_III_of_Sweden">John III of Sweden</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uppsala_Cathedral">Uppsala Cathedral</ref> (1593–1596), was until 1782 installed in the Great Armoury in Danzig, and re-assembled at the current location in 1817–1818</item>
<item>Tomb of Ture Nilsson <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bjelke_(noble_family)">Bjelke</ref> and his wife Margaret Svantesdotter Sture in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linköping_Cathedral">Linköping Cathedral</ref>, c. 1615</item></list>
<head>Attributed Works (selection)</head>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mannerism">Mannerist</ref> crown most probably created for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Báthory">Stephen Báthory</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gdańsk">Gdańsk</ref> after Willem van den Blocke]'s design in about 1584<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-artinpl-7">[7]</ref></caption></figure>
<head>Epitaphs</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Brandes family in the St. Mary's Church, Danzig, 1588</item>
<item>Christoph von Dohna in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Canute's_Cathedral">St. Canute's Cathedral</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Odense">Odense</ref> in Denmark, 1586</item>
<item>Valentin Bodecker in the St. Nicholas Church in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elbing">Elbing</ref>, 1587</item>
<item>Family Stroband in the Church of the Assumption of the Blessed Virgin Mary in Toruń, 1590</item></list>
<head>Tombs</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Kos family in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oliwa_Cathedral">Oliwa Cathedral</ref>, 1600 or 1620</item>
<item>Martin de Berzewice in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisnowo">Lisnowo</ref> near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brodnica">Brodnica</ref>, 1592 (destroyed 1939)</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Báthory">Andreas</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balthasar_Báthory">Balthasar Báthory</ref> in the St. Andrew's Church in Wartenburg, 1598</item>
<item>Peter Tarnowski in the cathedral of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Łowicz">Łowicz</ref>, after 1604</item>
<item>Stanislaus Radziwill in the former Bernardine church in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vilnius">Vilnius</ref>, 1618–1623</item></list>
<head>Facades of houses</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Home of the Danzig St. George Archers (late 16th century)</item>
<item>Esken house in Torun (1590)</item></list>
</text>
