<text id="autogum_bio_doc148" title="Jonny Gould" shortTile="jonny-gould" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-10-14" dateModified="2019-10-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonny_Gould" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Jonny Gould</head>For the sports presenter, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonathan_Gould_(presenter)">Jonathan Gould (presenter)</ref>. For the professional footballer, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonathan_Gould">Jonathan Gould</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Jonny Gould</hi> is a British radio and TV presenter who broadcasts on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sky_News">Sky News</ref> on Sunrise and previously as a sports presenter at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smooth_Radio">Smooth Radio</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC_Radio_2">BBC Radio 2</ref>.</p>
<head>Smooth Radio and BBC Radio 2</head>
<p>Gould presented breakfast show sport for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smooth_Radio">Smooth Radio</ref> between 2012 and 2014.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>After the Olympics, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smooth_Radio">Smooth Radio</ref> then retained Gould to be reunited with breakfast presenter Simon Bates to present the morning sports news, more than 15 years after they first broadcast together on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talksport">Talksport</ref>.</p>
<p>Gould joined BBC Radio 2, deputising for Vassos Alexander as sports presenter on the Breakfast Show.</p>
<head>talkSPORT and talkRADIO</head>
<p>In addition to the weekday shows on Smooth Radio, Gould presented the weekend sports show Extra Time on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talksport">Talksport</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> He also presented the Sports Bar and Kickoff alongside Stan Collymore, Bobby Gould and Tony Cascarino.</p>
<p>Gould returned to working for the Wireless Group presenting the evening show on the newly launched DAB station <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talkradio">talkRADIO</ref>. He moved to late afternoon on Sundays from November 2016.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> He left the station in July 2017.</p>
<head>Sky News and ESPN</head>
<p>Since 2008 Gould has been a regular newspaper and sports pundit on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sky_News">Sky News</ref> providing comment and analysis. From February 2014, he became a regular contributor on Sunrise with Eamonn Holmes. He also appeared on Between The Lines on ESPN with Ray Stubbs.</p>
<head>Al Jazeera</head>
<p>In 2010 Gould started to appear regularly on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al_Jazeera_English">Al Jazeera English</ref> as a football expert to discuss a wide variety of football-related stories including the FIFA World Cup host country announcements for 2018 and 2022 and the many political controversies involving FIFA's Sepp Blatter.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>ITV Sport</head>
<p>From 2000 to 2002, Gould presented <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ITV_Sport">ITV Sport</ref>'s Football First, a live four-hour football scores and reports show, and Euro Fever, a live studio show with an audience and guests. He also presented ITV's Goal Rush and was Premiership Plus first ever touchline reporter, covering the channel's first eleven games.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Channel 5</head>
<p>From 1997 to 2000, Gould was the sports presenter on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Channel_5_(UK)">Channel 5 (UK)</ref>'s morning news show  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/5_News">5 News</ref> with Katie Ledger.</p>
<head>IRN and LBC</head>
<p>Between 1992 and 1995 Gould provided sports news for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent_Radio_News">Independent Radio News</ref> as Sports Editor and went on to become Associate Sports Editor in 1994. He also co-presented the Thursday Night Sports Phone-In with Robbie Vincent between 1990 and 1994.</p>
<head>BBC World Service</head>
<p>From 1990 to 1993, Gould presented <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC_World_Service">BBC World Service</ref> "Sports Roundup" and "Sports World", the BBC's flagship Saturday afternoon programme.</p>
<head>Sportsmedia</head>
<p>Gould is CEO of Sportsmedia, which provided over 150 national and local radio stations and social media with daily sports content. The company was started in 1992 and client stations included Global Radio and Jazz FM. The bulletin service closed after 24 years of service, although the business continues to produce video content and activate sponsorships via radio features, podcasts and online. Corporate clients included Sky Sports, Capital One and Northern Rail <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Other</head>
<p>Gould is also an ambassador for Action Duchenne <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> a national charity supporting people living with Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy and Striker Boy, a mental health awareness campaign with the charity, MIND.</p>
</text>
