<text id="autogum_bio_doc770" title="Elizabeth the Cuman" shortTile="elizabeth-cuman" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-12" dateModified="2019-01-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_the_Cuman" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Elizabeth the Cuman</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Elizabeth the Cuman</hi> (1244-1290) was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_consort">Queen consort</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_V_of_Hungary">Stephen V of Hungary</ref>. She was regent of Hungary during the minority of her son in 1272-1277.</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cumans">Cumans</ref> were the western tribes of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cumania">Cuman-Kipchak confederation</ref>. Her people followed a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shamanism">shamanist religion</ref> and were considered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paganism">pagans</ref> by contemporary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christians">Christians</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Europe">Europe</ref>.</p>
<head>Questions of parentage and family</head>
<p>In 1238, Khan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Köten">Köten</ref>, her father according to historians, led the Cumans and a number of other clans in invading the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Hungary_in_the_Middle_Ages">Kingdom of Hungary</ref> while fleeing from the advancing hordes of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mongol_Empire">Mongol Empire</ref>. In time, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Béla_IV_of_Hungary">Béla IV of Hungary</ref> negotiated an alliance with Köten and his people, granting them asylum in exchange for their conversion to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholicism">Roman Catholicism</ref> and loyalty to the King. The agreement was sealed with the betrothal of Elizabeth to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_V_of_Hungary">Stephen</ref>, eldest son of Béla IV. The agreement seems to have occurred while Stephen was an infant. Elizabeth was unlikely to have been older than her future husband. In 1241, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mongol_invasion_of_Europe">Mongol invasion of Europe</ref> under the leadership of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Batu_Khan">Batu Khan</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subutai">Subutai</ref> began, with Hungary among its primary targets. Köten was assassinated by Hungarian nobles fearing he would lead a defection to the other side.</p>
<p>Other historians point out that a charter of her father-in-law, Béla IV, refers to a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cumans">Cuman</ref> chieftain Seyhan as his "kinsman," which can be interpreted to mean that Seyhan was in fact Elizabeth's father.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>She also had an unidentified sister, who married Hungarian noble <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gregory_III_Monoszló">Gregory Monoszló</ref>.</p>
<head>Queen</head>
<p>Béla IV returned from Austria following the Mongol evacuation. Upon his return to power, Béla began rebuilding his country, including a massive construction campaign which produced the system of castles as a defense against the threat of a Mongol return. Köten was deceased but the betrothal was still in effect. Elizabeth was converted to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholicism">Roman Catholicism</ref> in preparation for her marriage. The marriage of Stephen and Elizabeth occurred in 1253. The groom was twelve years old and the bride close in age to him. She became queen of Hungary upon her father-in-law's death on 3 May 1270.</p>
<head>Regent</head>
<p>Stephen died on 6 August 1272. Elizabeth became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent">regent</ref> for their ten-year-old son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ladislaus_IV_of_Hungary">Ladislaus IV</ref>. Her regency lasted until 1277 and saw palace revolutions and civil wars. Her upbringing of her son would cause further problems for his reign. Ladislaus favored the society of the "semi-pagan" Cumans, from whom he was descended through his mother. He wore Cuman dress as his court wear, surrounded himself with Cuman concubines and thus alienated the Hungarian nobility. His later attempts to regain Hungarian loyalty instead alienated parts of the Cumans. He was murdered in his tent by Cumans while camped in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bihar_(county)">Bihar county</ref> on 10 July 1290. By that time Elizabeth herself seems to have also been deceased. There is no mention of her in the reign of his successor, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_III_of_Hungary">Andrew III</ref>. There is a tradition that she died in the year 1290.</p>
<head>Children</head>
<p>Elizabeth and Stephen V of Hungary were parents to six known children:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_of_Hungary,_Queen_of_Serbia">Elizabeth</ref> (c. 1255 - 1313), married firstly to Zavis Vítkovci, Lord of Rosenberg, Skalitz and Falkenstein, and secondly to King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefan_Uroš_II_Milutin_of_Serbia">Stefan Uroš II Milutin of Serbia</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_of_Hungary,_Queen_of_Serbia">Catherine</ref> (c. 1257 - after 1314), married to King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefan_Dragutin_of_Serbia">Stefan Dragutin of Serbia</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_of_Hungary_(Árpád_dynasty)">Maria</ref> (c. 1258 - 25 March 1323), married to King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_II_of_Naples">Charles II of Naples</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna_of_Hungary">Anna</ref> (c. 1260 - 1281), married to the Byzantine emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andronikos_II_Palaiologos">Andronikos II Palaiologos</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ladislaus_IV_of_Hungary">Ladislaus IV</ref> (August, 1262 - 10 July 1290), married to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elisabeth_of_Sicily,_Queen_of_Hungary">Elizabeth of Sicily</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew,_Duke_of_Slavonia">Andrew</ref> (1268 – 1278), Duke of Slavonia</item></list>
</text>
