<text id="autogum_bio_doc700" title="Karl Thopia" shortTile="karl-thopia" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-05-04" dateModified="2019-10-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_Thopia" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Karl Thopia</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Karl Thopia</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albanian_language">Albanian</ref>: <hi lang="sq" rend="italic">Karl Topia</hi>) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albanians">Albanian</ref> feudal prince and warlord who  ruled <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albania">Albania</ref> from the middle of the 14th century until the first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_wars_in_Europe">Ottoman conquest</ref> of Albania.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> Thopia usually maintained good relations with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Curia">Roman Curia</ref>.</p>
<head>Family</head>
Main article: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thopia_family">Thopia family</ref>
<p>The first mention of the Thopia is from 1329,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hahn1867-2">[2]</ref> when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tanusio_Thopia">Tanusio Thopia</ref> was mentioned as one of the counts of Albania.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Léonard1932-3">[3]</ref> In 1338, Tanusio was mentioned as Count of Matia (conte di Matia).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_Hopf">Karl Hopf</ref>, Tanusio's son or brother Andrea, as told by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gjon_Muzaka">Gjon Muzaka</ref> (fl. 1510), had fallen in love with the daughter of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_of_Naples">Robert of Naples</ref> when her ship, en route to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principality_of_the_Morea">Principality of the Morea</ref> to be wed with the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bailli">bailli</ref></hi>, had stopped at Durazzo where they met. Andrea abducted and married her, and they had two sons, Karl and George. King Robert, enraged, under the pretext of reconciliation had the couple invited to Naples where he had them executed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hopf1960-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Control of Durrës and the Princedom of Albania</head>
<p>The long protracted turmoil of dynastic wars had made germinate in their real victims, the Albanians, the seeds of national sentiment which contained great promise, so that, when after Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefan_Dušan">Stefan Dušan</ref>'s death, a descendant of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefan_Uroš_I">Stefan Uroš I</ref>, returned to the province, the inhabitants rose en masse and, under the leadership of Karl Thopia, cut down the pretender and his entire force in the battle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acheloos_(municipality)">Acheloos</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Houtsma-456-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>In 1358, Karl rose against the rule of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anjou">Anjou</ref> and managed to drive them out of Durrës from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epirus">Epirus</ref> and Albania.  He ruled most of modern central Albania from 1358 to 1388 and claimed the title of <hi rend="italic">princeps Albaniae</hi>.</p>
<p>Since 1362, Karl sought himself to set <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Durrës">Durrës</ref>, which was in the possession of the Duchess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joanna_of_Anjou">Joanna of Anjou</ref>. The first, certainly still unsuccessful siege lasted from April 1362 until May 1363. Then, Thopia had to withdraw his troops, who were weakened by an epidemic disease.  Only in 1367 could Karl conquer Durrës, who had attained in the meantime the tacit agreement of the Venetians for his project and turn this important port into his residence.</p>
<p>Karl gained control of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Durrës">Durrës</ref> in 1368, which was where the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anjou">Angevins</ref> held out due to their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Albania_(medieval)">Kingdom</ref> becoming smaller in size.</p>
<p>Thopia ruled over the regions of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Durrës">Durrës</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kruja">Kruja</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peqin">Peqin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elbasan">Elbasan</ref>, Mokra and Gora, that is, along both sides of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Via_Egnatia">Via Egnatia</ref> as far east as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lake_Ohrid">Lake Ohrid</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jacques-169-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Rivalry with the Balšići</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balša_II">Balša II</ref> made a fourth attempt to conquer Durrës, an important commercial and strategic center, which was ruled by his rival, Karl Thopia. In 1385, Balša II started an offensive, capturing Durrës from Karl Thopia the following year, and proclaimed himself <hi rend="italic">Duke of Durazzo</hi> (Durrës).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jacques-169-7">[7]</ref> Thopia called on the Turks for assistance. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murad_I">Murad I</ref> gladly sent an army of 40,000 men from Macedonia. In the plain of Savra between Elbasan and Lushnja, Balša II <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Savra">fought the Turks and was defeated</ref> and killed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jacques-169-7">[7]</ref> Thopia again gained control over Durazzo, probably under Ottoman suzerainty.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFine1994390-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Venetian alliance</head>
<p>In the last decade of his rule, Karl closely followed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_of_Venice">Republic of Venice</ref>, particularly with regard to foreign policy. On 17 August 1386, Karl Thopia allied himself with Venice and committed himself to participate in all wars of the Republic or pay auxiliary funds and supply grain. In addition, he promised the Venetian buyers protection in his lands. In return, Venice supplied a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galley">galley</ref>, permitted recruitment of Thopia's mercenaries in Venetian areas and instructed the captain of their Adriatic fleet to protect Karl's coasts from the Ottomans. The Ottomans undertook several heavy attacks on Durrës, which also still persisted as Karl died in January 1388. His son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gjergj,_Lord_of_Durrës">Gjergj</ref>, became Karl's successor.</p>
<head>St. Gjon Vladimir's Church</head>
<p>In 1381, Karl built the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Gjon_Vladimir's_Church">St. Gjon Vladimir's Church</ref> in the proximity of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elbasan">Elbasan</ref>, where <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jovan_Vladimir">Jovan Vladimir</ref>'s remains were held until 1995.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref>
He is depicted in the icon of St. Vladimir, painted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Onufri">Onufri</ref>, wearing a crown and standing by the Church of the Saint.</p>
<p>Inscriptions:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>A calligraphic inscription in Greek says: "<hi rend="italic">ΚΑΡΛΑ ΘΕΩΠΙΑϹ ΚΑΙ ΚΤΗΤΩΡ ΤΗϹ ΑΓΙΑϹ ΜΟΝΗϹ ΤΟΥ ΑΓΙΟΥ</hi>" (Karla Theopias, builder of the Holy Monastery of the Saint).</item>
<item>Another Greek inscription in the building refers to him as: "... ο πανυψηλώτατος πρώτος Κάρλας Θεωπίας ανεψιός δε και αίματος ρύγας της Φραγγίας... οικοδόμησεν τον πάνσεπτον ναόν τούτον του αγίου Ιωάννου του Βλαδιμήρου ..." (<hi rend="italic">the highest and prime Karlas Theopias, nephew and by blood king of Francia ... built this holy church of St. John Vladimir ...</hi> ) dated 1382. This inscription is currently located in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Historical_Museum_(Albania)">Albanian Historical Museum</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tirana">Tirana</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></item>
<item>"<hi rend="italic">These signs of a great lord ... Carla Thopea</hi>" (ετούτα τα σιμάδηα αυθέντου μέγα ... Κάρλα Θοπήα).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></item></list>
<head>Issue</head>
<p>Karl married Serbian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balšić_noble_family">Voislava Balšić</ref>, in c. 1370. The pair had four children:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Thopia">George Thopia</ref> (fl. 1388–d. 1392), Lord of Durrës (Durazzo). Married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teodora_Branković">Teodora Branković</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helena_Thopia">Helena Thopia</ref> (fl. 1388–1403), married Venetian count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco_Barbarigo_di_Croia">Marco Barbadigo</ref> (first marriage) and Serbian lord <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konstantin_Balšić">Konstantin Balšić</ref> (second marriage)</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vojsava_Thopia">Vojsava Thopia</ref>, married N. Cursachio (first marriage) and in 1394, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progon_Dukagjini">Progon Dukagjini</ref>, Lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lezhë">Lezhë</ref> and uncle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pal_Dukagjini">Pal Dukagjini</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> (second marriage)</item></list>
<p>Karl had two more children but the parentage is unknown:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Maria, married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Filippo_di_Maramonte">Filippo di Maramonte</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niketa_Thopia">Niketa Thopia</ref>, married a daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Komnen_Arianiti">Komnen Arianiti</ref>.
<list type="unordered"><item>Mara, married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balša_III">Balša III</ref> in 1407 (divorced by 1412).</item></list></item></list>
<head>Ancestry</head>
</text>
