<text id="autogum_bio_doc723" title="John Thornton (glass painter)" shortTile="john-thornton-glass" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-30" dateModified="2019-08-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Thornton_%28glass_painter%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Thornton (glass painter)</head>
<figure><caption>Thornton's depiction of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_John_the_Baptist">St John the Baptist</ref>, from the Great East Window of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York_Minster">York Minster</ref>, showing his characteristic treatment of faces</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">John Thornton</hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coventry">Coventry</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floruit">fl</ref>. 1405-1433) was a master <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glazier">glazier</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stained_glass">stained glass</ref> artist active in England during the 15th century. The output of his workshop includes some of the finest English medieval glass.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>The first certain record of Thornton, apart from a possible 1371 reference in Coventry, is his 1405 contract with the Dean of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York_Minster">York Minster</ref> to glaze the quire east window.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sge180-1">[1]</ref> The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_York">Archbishop of York</ref> at the time was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Scrope_(cleric)">Richard le Scrope</ref>, a former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Lichfield_and_Coventry">Bishop of Lichfield and Coventry</ref>, and the window was funded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Skirlaw">Walter Skirlaw</ref>, also previously Bishop of Coventry, so it seems possible both men would have recommended Thornton based on their knowledge of his work in his home town.</p>
<p>Thornton was made a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom_of_the_City">freeman</ref> of York in 1410, but was known to be back living in the St John's Bridges area of Coventry (now known as Burges<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref>) by 1413. He appears again in 1433, when he received further payment from the dean and chapter of York, and was recorded as holding property there.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sge180-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>It has been suggested, though without any strong evidence, that Thornton was the son of a "John Coventre", a glazier in the royal glass-painting workshops at Westminster in 1351 and 1352, who later assisted in setting up windows at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windsor_Castle">Windsor Castle</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_III_of_England">Edward III of England</ref>. Thornton could have worked as an assistant to his father before rising to the position of designer and draughtsman.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nq-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>Thornton was instrumental in disseminating the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Gothic">International Gothic</ref> style in the north and Midlands of England. The products of his workshop can be recognised by their favouring of white glass and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silver_nitrate">yellow stain</ref> set against blue and ruby "seaweed"-patterned backgrounds, and by the very distinctive modelling of faces.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sge183-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Thornton's masterpiece is the Great East Window of York Minster, the largest in the building and containing about 1,680 square feet (156m2) of glass. According to the contract, much of the work was to be executed by his own hand, though specifically only to "pourtray [...] the histories, images, and other things to be painted on the [window]"; evidently some of the glazing would be carried out by apprentices or workmen.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-blair280-5">[5]</ref> Thornton is likely to have recruited glaziers locally in York: he seems to have been an enthusiastic teacher, and his style quickly became dominant in the area.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-marks182-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>Work thought to be by Thornton can also be found in several smaller churches, as well as in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Mary's_Guildhall">St Mary's Hall</ref> in Coventry. His surviving windows for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coventry_Cathedral">Coventry Cathedral</ref> were removed before it was destroyed in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coventry_Blitz">Coventry Blitz</ref> and have been preserved.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bbc-7">[7]</ref> He is also thought to have produced the windows from the chapel at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hampton_Court,_Herefordshire">Hampton Court, Herefordshire</ref>, which are now dispersed in various collections, and seven panels in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_St._Mary_Magdalene,_Newark-on-Trent">Church of St. Mary Magdalene, Newark-on-Trent</ref>.</p>
<p>The Thornton 'tradition' continued in York even after the middle of the 15th century, though many of the works produced show a coarsening or loss of quality compared with Thornton's authentic creations.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sge185186-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Examples of his work from the East Window in York Minster</head>
<list type="unordered">
<item>The Lamb on Mount Zion and the Redeemed</item>
<item>Bishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Skirlaw">Walter Skirlaw</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucius_of_Britain">King Lucius</ref> and two other Kings</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_the_Conqueror">King William I</ref>, King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_the_Confessor">Edward the Confessor</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_III_of_England">King Edward III</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Celestine_III">Pope Celestine III</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_of_York">St William</ref> and an unidentified Prelate</item>
<item>St John glimpses God in Majesty</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seven_churches_of_Asia">Seven churches of Asia</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Eleuterus">St Eleutherius</ref>, St Pirrannus and an unidentified Archbishop-Saint</item>
</list>
</text>
