<text id="autogum_bio_doc370" title="Gabriel de Espinosa" shortTile="gabriel-de-espinosa" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-12-04" dateModified="2019-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabriel_de_Espinosa" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gabriel de Espinosa</head>
<figure><caption>Portrait of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sebastian_of_Portugal">Sebastian of Portugal</ref>, impersonated by Gabriel de Espinosa.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Gabriel de Espinosa</hi> (death in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madrigal_de_las_Altas_Torres">Madrigal de las Altas Torres</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Province_of_Ávila">Ávila</ref>, August 1, 1595), was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spain">Spanish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor">impostor</ref>. He was the protagonist of the incident known as the "baker of Madrigal", which consisted of the impersonation of the late King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sebastian_of_Portugal">Sebastian of Portugal</ref>, for which he was executed.</p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>After the disappearance of king Sebastian at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Alcácer_Quibir">Alcácer Quibir</ref> (1578), many efforts were made to ransom imprisoned Portuguese soldiers. Several soldiers returned to Portugal, which led many Portuguese to believe Sebastian had survived the battle and would return to claim his throne. This led to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sebastianism">Sebastianism</ref>: the belief that Sebastian could return at any moment. Sebastian did not have descendants and thus eventually the throne went to his uncle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_II_of_Spain">Philip II of Spain</ref>, losing Portugal its independence.</p>
<head>People involved</head>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Austria">John of Austria</ref>, father of María Ana de Austria.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>María Ana de Austria.</caption></figure>
<p>Very little is known of Espinosa's early years. Some scholars believe that he was probably born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toledo,_Spain">Toledo</ref> as this town had he oldest document known about him, his title of baker, but in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madrigal_de_las_Altas_Torres">Madrigal</ref> is believed thar he was born there. What is known is that in 1594 he arrived at Madrigal alongside his two-year-old daughter, Clara, and his wife, Isabel Cid. People noticed that the new baker spoke several languages (at least, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_language">French</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_language">German</ref>),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> knew how to ride a horse and, in general, appeared to be more than a humble officer. Although it is not impossible that he had learned these skills working for the militia of Captain Pedro Bermúdez, where he served.</p>
<p>In the same town lived <hi rend="bold">Friar Miguel de los Santos</hi>, the possible thinker of the scam, who had been a confessor in the court of King Sebastian, and had supported the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/António,_Prior_of_Crato">Prior of Crato</ref> in his intention to succeed said king. For that reason he had been exiled from Portugal and sent to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Castile">Castile</ref> by Philip II.</p>
<p>The third person involved is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/María_Ana_de_Austria_(1568-1629)">María Ana de Austria</ref>, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Austria">John of Austria</ref>. She entered the convent of Agustinas de Madrigal at the age of six, sent by his uncle Philip II. It seems that she had no religious vocation whatsoever, and that she preferred adventure stories, especially if they referred to her father or her cousin Sebastian, whom, like many others at the time, she believed alive.</p>
<head>The plot</head>
<p>Probably Friar Miguel de los Santos noticed the physical resemblance between Espinosa and Sebastian (among other things, they were both redheads, something unusual in Portugal) and convinced Espinosa to impersonate the late king. De los Santos also introduced him to Ana de Austria. Either because she believed him to actually be her cousin or just because she wanted to escape the convent she agreed to promise in marriage with him until she could obtain permission from the Pope.</p>
<p>Sebastian was arrested in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valladolid">Valladolid</ref> for talking disrespectfully of the king and the jailers found on him 4 letters (two by Miguel de los Santos and two by Ana de Austria) talking about the plot. The matter was then referred to the royal court and both Miguel and Ana were also arrested.</p>
<head>Process, conviction and death</head>
<p>Accused of crimes of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lese_majesty">lese majesty</ref>, both Espinosa and Miguel de los santos were repeatedly interrogated, sometimes under torture. Espinosa made contradictory declarations during the process and he was sentenced to death by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanging">hanging</ref> on August 1, 1595. He remained calm and proud during the execution. After the hanging, Gabriel was decapitated and dismembered and his remains were exposed to the town in each one of the four gates of the wall. His head was exposed at the facade of the Town hall.</p>
<p>Miguel de los Santos was also hanged in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plaza_Mayor,_Madrid">Plaza Mayor, Madrid</ref>. He maintained that he believed Espinosa to be the king.</p>
<p>Philip II didn't take a lot of pity on his niece either. She was locked in strict closure in the convent of Our Lady of Grace, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ávila,_Spain">Ávila</ref>. After the death of Philip II (1598) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_III_of_Spain">Philip III</ref> forgave her and allowed her to return to the convent of Madrigal of which she eventually became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prior">prior</ref>.</p>
<head>In literature</head>
<p>The theme was used in some literary works of the 19th century, such as the play  <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traidor,_inconfeso_y_mártir">Traidor, inconfeso y mártir</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/José_Zorrilla">José Zorrilla</ref> (1849) or the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serial_(literature)">serial</ref> <hi rend="italic">El cocinero de Su Majestad o El pastelero de Madrigal</hi> (1862) by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manuel_Fernández_y_González">Manuel Fernández y González</ref>.</p>
</text>
