<text id="autogum_bio_doc292" title="James Anderson (Freemason)" shortTile="james-anderson-freemason" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-02-15" dateModified="2019-10-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Anderson_%28Freemason%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>James Anderson (Freemason)</head>For other people with the same name, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Anderson_(disambiguation)">James Anderson</ref>.
<p>Dr. <hi rend="bold">James Anderson</hi> (c. 1679/1680 – 1739) was a Scottish writer and minister born and educated in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberdeen">Aberdeen</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scotland">Scotland</ref>. He was ordained a minister in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_Scotland">Church of Scotland</ref> in 1707 and moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, where he ministered to the Glass House Street congregation until 1710, to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Presbyterian">Presbyterian</ref> church in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swallow_Street">Swallow Street</ref> until 1734, and at Lisle Street Chapel until his death. He is reported to have lost a large sum of money in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Sea_Company">South Sea Company</ref> crash of 1720. Anderson is best known, however, for his association with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freemasonry">Freemasonry</ref>.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>He was the brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adam_Anderson_(economist)">Adam Anderson</ref>, (1692–1765); James was born about 1680, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberdeen">Aberdeen</ref>, where he was educated, and probably took the degrees of M.A. and D.D. In 1710 he was appointed minister of the Presbyterian church in Swallow Street, London, whence he was transferred, in 1734, to a similar charge in Lisle Street, Leicester Fields. According to the <hi rend="italic">Gentleman's Magazine,</hi> he is said to have been "well known among the people of that persuasion resident in London as Bishop Anderson", and he is described as "a learned but imprudent man, who lost a considerable part of his property in the fatal year 1720".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> Several of his sermons were printed. One of them, <hi rend="italic">No King-Killers</hi>, preached in 1715, on the anniversary of the execution of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_I,_King_of_England">Charles I</ref>, was a zealous defence of the conduct of the Presbyterians during the civil wars, and reached a second edition. Anderson was a freemason, and when, in 1721, on the revival of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freemasonry">freemasonry</ref> in England, the grand lodge determined to produce an authoritative digest of the <hi rend="italic">Constitutions</hi> of the fraternity, the task was assigned to him (Entick's edition (1747) of the <hi rend="italic">Constitutions,</hi> p.194 et seq.). It was as a grand warden of the lodge that he presented to it, on completing his task, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitutions_of_the_Free-Masons">The Constitutions of the Free-Masons; containing the History, Charges, Regulations, &amp;c. of that Most Ancient and Right Worshipful Fraternity. For the Use of the Lodges. London. In the year of Masonry 5723, Anno Domini 1723.</ref></hi> This work, which passed through several editions, was long recognised by the English freemasons to be the standard code on its subject, and was translated into German. An American facsimile of the first edition of 1723 was issued at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_City">New York City</ref> in 1855, and there are reprints of the same edition in Cox's <hi rend="italic">Old Constitutions belonging to the Freemasons of England and Ireland</hi> (1871) and in the first volume of Kenning's <hi rend="italic">Masonic Archæological Library</hi> (1878). Anderson also contributed to masonic literature <hi rend="italic">A Defence of Masonry, occasioned by a pamphlet called “Masonry Dissected”</hi> (1738?), which was translated into German, and is reprinted in <hi rend="italic">Golden Remains of the Early Masonic Writers</hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Oliver_(freemason)">George Oliver</ref> (1847).</p>
<head>Freemasonry</head>
<p>Anderson was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freemason">Freemason</ref>, the Master of a Masonic lodge, and a Grand Warden of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Premier_Grand_Lodge_of_England">Grand Lodge of London</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westminster">Westminster</ref>.  He was commissioned in September 1721 by the Grand Lodge to write a history of the Free-Masons, and it was published in 1723 as <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitutions_of_the_Free-Masons">The Constitutions of the Free-Masons</ref>.</hi> Anderson's name does not appear on the title page, but his authorship is declared in an appendix.</p>
<p>Anderson's work, although of the first importance to the history of freemasonry, is unfortunately marred by a number of extravagant claims which are simply incredible. Indeed, it was shown at the tercentenary conference of the respected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quatuor_Coronati_Lodge">Quatuor Coronati</ref> research Lodge at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen's_College,_Cambridge">Queen's College, Cambridge</ref>, that Anderson's history of the founding of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Lodge_of_London_and_Westminster">Grand Lodge</ref> is doubtful, since the public houses mentioned could probably not have accommodated the meetings that he claims were held in 1717. Anderson's account must be broadly accurate, having been widely published within six years of the events described, but it may have been backdated by two or three years, perhaps to aggrandise some brethren as Past Grand Officers.</p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>In 1732 appeared the work by which Anderson is chiefly remembered, <hi rend="italic">Royal Genealogies; or, the Genealogical Tables of Emperors, Kings, and Princes, from Adam to these times.</hi> Professedly based on <hi rend="italic">Genealogische Tabellen</hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Hübner">Johann Hübner</ref>, it was largely supplemented by Anderson's industry. While the earlier sections of the work are of little historical value, the later are often of use in relation to the genealogies of continental dynasties and houses. The volume closes with a synopsis of the English peerage, and in the preface the author intimated his readiness, if adequately encouraged, "to delineate and dispose at full length the genealogies of all the peers and great gentry of the Britannic isles". Anderson's last work, which he was commissioned to undertake by the first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Egmont">Earl of Egmont</ref> and his son from materials furnished by them, bore the title, <hi rend="italic">A Genealogical History of the House of Yvery, in its different branches of Yvery, Lovel, Perceval, and Gournay</hi>; but the first volume alone was completed when Anderson died on 25 May 1739, and a second volume, subsequently published, was due to another pen (see "To the Reader" in vol. ii). The work was soon withdrawn from circulation on account of some disparaging remarks in it on the condition of the English peerage and on the character of the Irish people. It was re-issued, however, without the offensive passages, in 1742 (see <hi rend="italic">Notes and Queries,</hi> 1st series, iv.158, and <hi rend="italic">Letters of Horace Walpole</hi> (1857), i.107 n., and ii.145). Much of the genealogical matter in the book has been pronounced to be mythical (Drummond's <hi rend="italic">Histories of Noble British Families</hi> (1846), art. ‘Percival’). Another work of Anderson's, <hi rend="italic">News from Elysium, or Dialogues of the Dead, between Leopold, Roman Emperor, and Louis XIV, King of France,</hi> was published shortly after his death in 1739.</p>
<p>The <hi rend="italic">Constitutions</hi> was edited and reprinted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benjamin_Franklin">Benjamin Franklin</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philadelphia">Philadelphia</ref> in 1734, becoming the first Masonic book printed in America. An electronic edition of that work is online.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> A second London edition, much expanded, appeared in 1738. The work was translated into many languages, including Dutch (1736), German (1741), and French (1745).</p>
<p>His other published works include:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=yrqeY839bMwC">Royal Genealogies, Or the Genealogical Tables of Emperors, Kings and Princes</ref></hi> (1732)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">A Defence of Masonry</hi> (1738?)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">News from Elysium</hi> (1739)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">A Genealogical History of the House of Yvery</hi> (1742)</item></list>
</text>
