<text id="autogum_bio_doc103" title="William Jeffery" shortTile="william-jeffery" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-04-16" dateModified="2019-07-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Jeffery" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>William Jeffery</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">William R. Jeffery</hi> is an American professor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolutionary_developmental_biology">evolutionary developmental biology</ref> whose studies focus on the evolution of development, especially blind cavefish and tunicates. He is a fellow of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Association_for_the_Advancement_of_Science">American Association for the Advancement of Science</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linnean_Society_of_London">Linnean Society of London</ref>.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicago">Chicago</ref>, Jeffery obtained his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bachelor_of_science">bachelor of science</ref> degree from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Illinois">University of Illinois</ref> in 1968 and his Ph.D. from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Iowa">University of Iowa</ref> three years later. In 1971, for a year, he worked as a teacher at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Children's_School_of_Science,_Woods_Hole,_MA">Children's School of Science, Woods Hole, MA</ref>. From 1971 to 1972 he was a postdoctoral fellow at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Wisconsin–Madison">University of Wisconsin–Madison</ref> and the same years worked as postdoc at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McArdle_Laboratory">McArdle Laboratory</ref> of University of Wisconsin–Madison. He continued his postdoctoral fellowship from 1972 to 1974 at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tufts_University_School_of_Medicine">Tufts University School of Medicine</ref> for those two years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-umd-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>After becoming a faculty member in zoology in the University of Texas at Austin, Jeffery published a study in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Developmental_Biology_(journal)">Developmental Biology</ref></hi> which suggested that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poly(A)-binding_protein">Poly(A)-binding protein</ref> is present in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oocyte">oocyte</ref> and is responsible for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oogenesis">oogenesis</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African_clawed_frog">African clawed frog</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> In 1983 he along with Craig R. Tomlinson and Richard D. Brodeur studied <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Styela_plicata">Styela plicata</ref>'</hi>s eggs and suggested that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cytoplasmic_region">cytoplasmic regions</ref> also carry <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Messenger_RNA">messenger RNA</ref> codes for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Actin">actin</ref> isoform.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> In 1995 he and Noriyuki Satoh studied tailless <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tadpole">tadpole</ref> larvae of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ascidiacea">Ascidiacea</ref> species and discovered that the Manx gene may be responsible for tail control and development.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>In 1990, Jeffery moved from the University of Texas to the University of California, Davis and was a researcher at the Bodega Marine Laboratory. Here he continued to work on evolutionary changes in development between tailess and tailed ascidian species and began research to develop the cave fish Astyanax mexicanus as a model system to study the evolutionary basis of eye and pigment degeneration in cave animals. In 1995-96 Jeffery was President of the Society for Developmental Biology. From 1996 to 1999 Jeffery was the head of the Department of Biology at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pennsylvania_State_University">Pennsylvania State University</ref> and then from that year to 2004 was chairman of the same field at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Maryland">University of Maryland</ref>. For a year after that he was a visiting scientist at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centre_national_de_la_recherche_scientifique">CNRS</ref> and then held the same position at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruđer_Bošković_Institute">Ruđer Bošković Institute</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zagreb">Zagreb</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Croatia">Croatia</ref> from 2011 to 2012.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-umd-1">[1]</ref>  Currently, Jeffery holds a joint appointment at the University of Maryland and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marine_Biological_Laboratory">Marine Biological Laboratory</ref> <ref target="http://research.mblwhoilibrary.org/groups/55-MBL_Bell_Center_for_Regenerative_Biology_and_Tissue_Engineering">Bell Center for Regenerative Biology and Tissue Engineering</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woods_Hole,_Massachusetts">Woods Hole, Massachusetts</ref>.</p>
<head>Honors and awards</head>
<p>In 1992 Jeffery was elected as a fellow of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Association_for_the_Advancement_of_Science">American Association for the Advancement of Science</ref> and then in 2008 became a fellow of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linnean_Society_of_London">Linnean Society of London</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-umd-1">[1]</ref> Most recently, in 2012 Jeffery was awarded the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A.O._Kovalevsky_Medal">Alexander Kowalevsky Medal</ref> by the St. Petersburg Society of Naturalists for extraordinary achievements in evolutionary developmental biology and comparative zoology.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
</text>
