<text id="autogum_bio_doc738" title="John Bullock (bishop)" shortTile="john-bullock-bishop" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-10" dateModified="2018-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Bullock_%28bishop%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Bullock (bishop)</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">John Bullock</hi> O.S.A. (d. 1439 × 1440) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augustinian">Augustinian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_(priest)">canon</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prelate">prelate</ref> active in the 15th century <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Scotland">Kingdom of Scotland</ref>. While earning a university degree between 1409 and 1417, Bullock gained several benefices in Scotland, and claimed the headship of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Andrews_Cathedral_Priory">St Andrews Cathedral Priory</ref> before becoming <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Ross_(Scotland)">Bishop of Ross</ref> in 1418. He held the latter position until his death, which occurred in either 1439 or 1440.</p>
<head>Early career</head>
<p>Though his career has not been elaborated by modern historians, Bullock is known to have been a university graduate, having a B. Dec., i.e. a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bachelorate">Bachelorate</ref> in Decrees (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_law">canon law</ref>); he did not hold that degree in 1409, but did by 1417.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Bullock was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_regular">canon regular</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_St._Andrews">diocese of St. Andrews</ref>, and on 23 March 1409, is recorded as holding the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vicarage">vicarage</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dull,_Perth_and_Kinross">Dull</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Dunkeld">diocese of Dunkeld</ref> when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avignon_Pope_Benedict_XIII">Avignon Pope Benedict XIII</ref> granted his petition to hold the vicarage of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tranent">Tranent</ref> in the diocese of St Andrews.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>A letter of Benedict XIII, dated 5 June 1417, reveals that John Bullock was one of three clergymen claiming the title <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prior_of_St_Andrews">Prior of St Andrews</ref>, a claim which he seems to have given up in the following year when he had the chance to become <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Ross_(Scotland)">Bishop of Ross</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Bishop of Ross</head>
<p>A papal mandate dated 9 March 1418, provided John, "elect of Ross", to "the bishopric of Ross, vacant by the death outside the curia of Alexander, late bishop under whom the bishopric was reserved to papal provision."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>On 11 March, an indult was issued to John allowing him to be consecrated by any bishop of his choice, assisted by two other bishops.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Another papal letter, issued on 15 March, granted one John Begiert, OSA, B. Dec., canon of St Andrews, the vicarage of Dull, "vacant by the promotion of John Bullock, former vicar, to the bishopric of Ross".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>The pope has reserved the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Ross_(Scotland)">bishopric of Ross</ref> for his own appointment and, on 16 March, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Lyell">Thomas Lyell</ref>, who had been elected by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cathedral_chapter">cathedral chapter</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fortrose">Fortrose</ref> "in ignorance of the reservation", was granted 40 crowns in compensation for his expenses, and two days later, he was granted a canonry in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Aberdeen">diocese of Aberdeen</ref> allowed to be held alongside his other benefices.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Bullock was in possession of the temporalities of the bishopric by 1 August 1419.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-268-8">[8]</ref> He was consecrated between 16 July, when as "elect and confirmed" he sent a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proctor">proctor</ref> to the Provincial Synod, and 16 August 1420, when he as "through the grace of Gode Byschop of Rosse", sealed a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charter">charter</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>As a sign of reconciliation and the ending of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_Schism">Western Schism</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Martin_V">Pope Martin V</ref> confirmed Benedict XIII's provision and retrospectively confirmed Bullock's acts as bishop on 1 February 1423, after the translation of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gruffydd_Young">Gruffydd Young</ref> to the titular bishopric of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hippo_Regius">Hippo</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>Most of the details of Bullock's episcopate are obscure. On 4 September 1439, Bishop Bullock appended his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seal_(device)">seal</ref> to the contract between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_Beaufort,_Queen_of_Scotland">Joan Beaufort</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_Dowager">Queen Dowager</ref>, and Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Livingston_of_Callendar">Alexander Livingston of Callendar</ref>, a contract that made Livingstone guardian of the boy king, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_II_of_Scotland">James II of Scotland</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>He is dead by 26 September 1440, when a papal mandate rejected the postulation of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Munro_(bishop)">Andrew Munro</ref> and provided <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Tulloch_(Bishop_of_Ross)">Thomas de Tulloch</ref> to the bishopric, explicitly vacant because of Bullock's death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-268-8">[8]</ref></p>
</text>
