<text id="autogum_bio_doc051" title="Katya Komisaruk" shortTile="katya-komisaruk" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-08-21" dateModified="2019-06-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katya_Komisaruk" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Katya Komisaruk</head><p><hi rend="bold">Katya Komisaruk</hi> is an American <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil_rights">civil rights</ref> lawyer and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_justice">social justice</ref> activist.  She attended <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvard_Law_School">Harvard Law School</ref>, helped form the Midnight Special Law Collective and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Causa_Justa_::_Just_Cause">Just Cause Law Collective</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-mc-history-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Early years</head>
<p>As a child in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Detroit">Detroit</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michigan">Michigan</ref>, Komisaruk was inspired by reading about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_Rose">White Rose</ref> group who resisted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nazism">Nazism</ref> in Germany.  "It was important to me to know that not everybody was wrong, that there were some people who did the right thing even when everybody else was failing to stop the train", she says about this early influence.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Komisaruk attended <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reed_College">Reed College</ref> and began an MBA program at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_California,_Berkeley">University of California, Berkeley</ref>.</p><p>
On June 2, 1987 Komisaruk broke into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vandenberg_Air_Force_Base">Vandenberg Air Force Base</ref> and destroyed a mainframe computer that she believed to be part of a U.S. first-strike nuclear launch system, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_Positioning_System">NAVSTAR</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref>  From an <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los_Angeles_Times">Los Angeles Times</ref></hi> article that year:</p><p>She broke into the building and for two hours trashed a million-dollar mainframe <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_303X#IBM_3031">IBM 3031</ref> computer, hacking away at it with crowbar, bolt cutters, hammer and cordless drill. She danced on the computer chips she had pried loose, spray-painted the casing walls with slogans such as "International Law," "Nuremberg" and "Defense of Necessity," and climbed to the roof to take similar action against a satellite dish.</p><p>She left behind a bouquet of flowers, a box of Mrs. Fields cookies, and a poem: "I have no gun / You must have lots. / Let's not be hasty / No cheap shots. Please have a cookie and a nice day." Komisaruk walked off the base, hitched a ride to the Bay Area, got some legal advice and gave herself up after holding a news conference at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/50_United_Nations_Plaza_Federal_Office_Building_(San_Francisco)">Federal Building in San Francisco</ref>.</p><p>In her defense, she attempted to cite the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg_principles#Principle_VI">Nuremberg Principle</ref> against starting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_of_aggression">wars of aggression</ref>, although the court was not allowed to hear that argument.  In fact, the judge forbade her or her attorney from using any of the terms "nuclear missile", "first strike", "Nuremberg principles", or "international law".</p>
<p>An extensive interview with her about the incident was published in 1988.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>While serving a 5-year sentence, Komisaruk studied for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_School_Admission_Test">Law School Admission Test</ref> (LSAT) and in 1990 gained acceptance to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvard_Law_School">Harvard Law School</ref> the same week she was paroled.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Komisaruk helped represent 600 defendants arrested in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1999_Seattle_WTO_protests">1999 Seattle WTO protests</ref>, mostly accused of "failure to disperse".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref>  As a volunteer for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Direct_Action_Network">Direct Action Network</ref>, she suggested a solidarity tactic in which the alleged protestors clog the courts by insisting on a jury trial, unless the City Attorney <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Sidran">Mark Sidran</ref> agree to a blanket deal in which all defendants are given the same treatment.  92% of the cases were dropped, and the prosecution only brought six cases to trial.  Five of the tried defendants were acquitted, and the one conviction resulted in community service and a small fine.</p>
<p>In the follow-on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington_A16,_2000">2000 Washington, D.C. protests</ref> against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_Bank">World Bank</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Monetary_Fund">International Monetary Fund</ref> (IMF), Komisaruk used a similar approach to get approximately 1,300 activists released with a $5 fine.  In Los Angeles, activists were arrested over three days during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2000_Democratic_National_Convention_protest_activity">2000 Democratic National Convention protests</ref>.  Komisaruk documents that 50 people used solidarity tactics, refused to give their names, and went on a hunger strike until a universal plea bargain was worked out.  The activists were released with suspended sentences in consideration of time served, and the prosecutor went on to publicly commend the protestors' integrity and commitment.</p>
<p>Leaving the Midnight Special Law Collective in 2000, Komisaruk formed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Causa_Justa_::_Just_Cause">Just Cause Law Collective</ref>, specializing in activist support and defense.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-mc-history-2">[2]</ref>  The organization later became "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Causa_Justa_::_Just_Cause">Causa Justa :: Just Cause</ref>", which has changed laws in favor of renters, and fights evictions in Oakland, California.</p>
<p>Komisaruk's defense of a client accused of prostitution, who was caught in an undercover sting operation in Oakland, California in 2003, helped catalyze <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robyn_Few">Robyn Few</ref>'s bid to legalize prostitution in California.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref>  Few went on to form <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sex_Workers_Outreach_Project_USA">Sex Workers Outreach Project USA</ref>, and the Just Cause Law Collective's "<ref target="http://www.midnightspecial.net/materials/kyr.html">Know Your Rights</ref>" materials are used to educate sex workers about their legal rights.</p>
</text>
