<text id="autogum_bio_doc495" title="Patriarch Hermogenes of Moscow" shortTile="patriarch-hermogenes" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-07-25" dateModified="2019-10-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarch_Hermogenes_of_Moscow" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Patriarch Hermogenes of Moscow</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Hermogenes</hi>, or <hi rend="bold">Germogen</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian_language">Russian</ref>: Гермоге́н) (secular name <hi rend="bold">Yermolay</hi>) (before 1530 – 17 February 1612) was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarch_of_Moscow_and_all_Russia">Patriarch of Moscow and all Russia</ref> from 1606. It was he who inspired the popular uprising that put an end to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_of_Troubles">Time of Troubles</ref>. Hermogenes was glorified by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian_Orthodox_Church">Russian Orthodox Church</ref> in 1913. </p><figure><caption><hi rend="italic">Patriarch Hermogenes refusing to bless the Poles</hi> painting by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pavel_Chistyakov">Pavel Chistyakov</ref> (1860).</caption></figure>
<p>At the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Synod">Holy Synod</ref> of 1589, which established the patriarchy in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow">Moscow</ref>, Hermogenes was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan_bishop">Metropolitan</ref> of the newly conquered city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kazan">Kazan</ref>. During the following two decades, he gained renown for a number of Muslim <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Volga_Tatars">Volga Tatars</ref> converted to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_Orthodoxy">Eastern Orthodoxy</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1606, Hermogenes was summoned by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/False_Dmitry_I">False Dmitry I</ref> to take part in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governing_Senate">Senate</ref> recently instituted in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow">Moscow</ref>. There he learnt about the tsar's design to marry a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic">Roman Catholic</ref> woman, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marina_Mniszech">Marina Mniszech</ref>, and firmly declared against such an alliance. At that he was exiled from the capital, only to return with great honours several months later, when the false tsar had been deposed, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ignatius_of_Moscow">Patriarch Ignatius</ref> followed suit.</p>
<figure><caption>Hermogenes at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Millennium_of_Russia">Millennium Monument</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Novgorod">Novgorod</ref></caption></figure>
<head>Patriarch of Moscow</head>
<p>The new tsar, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vasily_IV">Vasily IV</ref>, helped Hermogenes to become <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarch_of_Moscow_and_all_the_Rus'">Patriarch of Moscow and all the Rus'</ref>: Metropolitan Hermogenes was elected to the primatial See, and on 3 July 1606 he was installed as Patriarch by the assembly of the holy hierarchs at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dormition_Cathedral,_Moscow">Moscow's Dormition cathedral</ref>. Metropolitan Isidore handed the Patriarch the staff of the holy hierarch Peter, and the Tsar gave as a gift to the new Patriarch a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panagia">panagia</ref>, embellished with precious stones, a white klobuk and staff. In the ancient manner, Patriarch Hermogenes made his entrance riding upon a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donkey">donkey</ref>. During Vasily's reign, Hermogenes generally supported the tsar's efforts to pacify the country and anathemized <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Bolotnikov">Ivan Bolotnikov</ref> and his army. </p>
<head>Time of Troubles</head>
Further information: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_of_Troubles">Time of Troubles</ref>
<p>When Vasily was dethroned and the Poles took hold of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow_Kremlin">Moscow Kremlin</ref>, Hermogenes staunchly opposed their plans to put <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wladyslaw_IV">Wladyslaw IV</ref> on the Russian throne, unless he converted to Orthodoxy. Despite knife threats from some of the boyars, he refused to sign any petitions to the Polish king, thus preventing Wladyslaw from coronation.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In December 1610 Hermogenes distributed letters to various Russian towns, urging the populace to rise against the Poles. When the volunteer army under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prokopy_Lyapunov">Prokopy Lyapunov</ref> finally approached Moscow, he defied the Polish exhortations to anathemize the army. Despite being threatened with death penalty, he cursed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholics">Roman Catholics</ref> and showed support for Lyapunov. After that, he was arrested and thrown into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chudov_Monastery">Chudov Monastery</ref>. There he heard about the new volunteer army, mustered by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuzma_Minin">Kuzma Minin</ref> and commanded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince_Pozharsky">Prince Pozharsky</ref>, and blessed them both. Thereupon the patriarch was beaten and starved to death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Death and legacy</head>
<p>The body of Hermogenes was buried in the Chudov monastery, but in 1654 was transferred to the Moscow Dormition cathedral. The purported relics of Patriarch Germogen were accidentally found in one of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crypt">crypts</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chudov_Monastery">Chudov Monastery</ref> during the 1913 repair works. In connection with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romanov">Romanov</ref> Dynasty Tercentenary, celebrated that same year, he was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian_Orthodox_Church#Canonization">canonized</ref> as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hieromartyr">hieromartyr</ref> and transferred to the nearby <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dormition_Cathedral,_Moscow">Dormition Cathedral</ref>.</p>
<p>The Russian Orthodox Church commemorates him on 17 February, the day of his death, and 12 May, the day of his recognized glorification.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
</text>
