<text id="autogum_bio_doc549" title="Juan de Cartagena" shortTile="juan-de-cartagena" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-11-03" dateModified="2019-10-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_de_Cartagena" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Juan de Cartagena</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Juan de Cartagena</hi> (died c. 1520) was a Spanish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accountant">accountant</ref> and captain of one of the five ships led by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinand_Magellan">Ferdinand Magellan</ref> in his expedition of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_circumnavigation">first circumnavigation</ref> of the earth. Cartagena frequently argued with Magellan during the voyage and questioned his authority. Following a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Easter_mutiny">failed mutiny attempt</ref> of which Cartagena was the principal organizer, Magellan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marooning">marooned</ref> Cartagena on a remote island in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patagonia">Patagonia</ref> in 1520, before continuing on to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strait_of_Magellan">Strait of Magellan</ref>.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Cartagena was a native of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burgos">Burgos</ref>, the historic capital of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Castile">Old Castile</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEJoyner1992274-1">[1]</ref> Cartagena was a confidante and "nephew" of archbishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_Rodríguez_de_Fonseca">Juan Rodríguez de Fonseca</ref>, the influential head of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casa_de_Contratación">Casa de Contratación</ref> which regulated trade with Spain’s American colonies. Historians have interpreted "nephew" as a euphemism indicating that Cartagena was Fonseca's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illegitimate">illegitimate</ref> son.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBergreen200355-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTECameron197467-3">[3]</ref> His age at the time of Magellan's expedition is unknown, but he was married and had a daughter, Doña Catalina.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEJoyner1992274-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Magellan's voyage</head>
<p>Trained as an accountant, Cartagena had no experience as a seaman.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBergreen200355-2">[2]</ref> Despite this, he used his influence with Fonseca to secure appointment as Inspector General (<hi rend="italic">Veedor General</hi>) of Magellan's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armada_de_Molucca">Armada de Molucca</ref></hi> with authority to supervise the expedition's financial and trading operations.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_V,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">King Charles V</ref> of Spain also directed Cartagena to report on the expedition directly, rather than through Magellan as captain-general. This split responsibility would be a source of difficulty during the subsequent voyage.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBergreen200355-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In recognition of Cartagena's influence, and in order to please his supporters, Magellan named him captain of the largest ship of the expedition, the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Antonio_(spanish_ship)">San Antonio</ref></hi>, subject only to Magellan's own authority as captain-general of the fleet.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ten-6">[6]</ref> Cartagena earned a salary of 110,000 <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maravedí">maravedí</ref></hi>, the highest of anyone in the fleet, including Magellan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBergreen200347-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Tensions surfaced between Cartagena and Magellan as soon as the fleet departed Spain. In councils between captains, Cartagena routinely opposed Magellan's navigation decisions and refused to salute his superior when required by custom to do so. A storm delayed the fleet south of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenerife">Tenerife</ref>, and food had to be rationed; Cartagena took this opportunity to publicly criticise Magellan and suggest he was not competent to command. Magellan promptly had him arrested, relieved of his command and confined aboard the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victoria_(ship)">Victoria</ref></hi> for the remainder of the voyage to South America.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Mutiny</head>
<p>Cartagena remained a captive until the fleet reached <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patagonia">Patagonia</ref>. On 1 April 1520 he secretly left the <hi rend="italic">Victoria</hi> and reboarded the <hi rend="italic">San Antonio,</hi> where he rallied supporters among the Spanish crew and officers in opposition to the Portuguese Magellan. In company with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concepción_(ship)">Concepción</ref></hi>'s captain Gaspar de Quesada, pilot <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_Sebastián_Elcano">Juan Sebastián Elcano</ref> and thirty Spanish crew members, Cartagena seized control of <hi rend="italic">San Antonio</hi> and declared the vessel independent of Magellan's command. The officers of both <hi rend="italic">Concepción</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Victoria</hi> joined in the mutiny, and on 2 April 1520 a letter was sent to Magellan's flagship, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trinidad_(ship)"><hi rend="italic">Trinidad</hi></ref> demanding that the captain-general acknowledge that the fleet was no longer under his command.</p>
<p>Magellan brought the <hi rend="italic">Trinidad,</hi> alongside <hi rend="italic">Victoria</hi> and lowered a boat to carry back his reply. When the boat crew reached <hi rend="italic">Victoria</hi>'s deck they made a pretense of handing over a letter; when <hi rend="italic">Victoria</hi>'s captain sought to take it the boat crew stabbed him to death. Simultaneously, fifteen men from Magellan's ship climbed aboard and attacked the mutineers. <hi rend="italic">Victoria</hi>'s crew joined their cause and the ship was seized.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>Cartagena had relocated to <hi rend="italic">Concepción</hi> prior to the battle, and so remained temporarily free. However, only that vessel and <hi rend="italic">San Antonio</hi> remained in the mutineer's hands. Magellan ranged his three ships across the mouth of the bay in which the fleet had anchored, and cleared the decks for engagement with Cartagena's two vessels. In strong winds overnight on April 2, <hi rend="italic">San Antonio</hi> dragged its anchor and drifted helplessly toward <hi rend="italic">Trinidad.</hi> Magellan ordered a broadside fired, at which the crew of <hi rend="italic">San Antonio</hi> surrendered and allowed the vessel to be retaken. Realising the mutiny had failed, on April 3 Cartagena followed suit and surrendered <hi rend="italic">Concepción</hi> without resistance.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JCB26-10">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>After the mutiny, Magellan held a trial of the conspirators. Cartagena's ally <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaspar_de_Quesada">Gaspar de Quesada</ref> (captain of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concepción_(carrack)">Concepción</ref></hi>) was sentenced to death by beheading. However, Magellan was reluctant to execute a close relative of Fonseca,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBergreen2003153-11">[11]</ref> so Cartagena was sentenced to be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marooning">marooned</ref> along with another conspirator, the priest Pedro Sánchez de la Reina. The sentence was carried out on August 11, 1520, four months after the mutiny, shortly before the fleet departed their winter quarters at St. Julian.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBergreen2003170-12">[12]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEJoyner1992150-13">[13]</ref> Cartagena and the priest were given a small supply of ship's biscuits and drinking water and left on a small island off the Patagonian coast. Neither was seen or heard from again.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JCB26-10">[10]</ref></p>
</text>
