<text id="autogum_bio_doc647" title="Robert Skerne" shortTile="robert-skerne" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-07-12" dateModified="2019-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Skerne" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Robert Skerne</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Skerne</hi> (died 1437) was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member_of_Parliament_(UK)">MP</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surrey_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Surrey</ref> in 1420 and again in 1422.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HOP-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>There is difficulty in determining if the MP and a Robert Skerne of Yorkshire who served as royal clerk to both <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_II_of_England">Richard II</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_IV_of_England">Henry IV</ref> were the same individual. A Robert Skerne stood surety in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Court_of_Chancery">Chancery</ref> for his friends during the two reigns. There are grounds to assume that the records relate to the same person.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HOP-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>The earliest record of Skerne's career come from 1389 when he was rewarded by the crown with the keepership of St. Ellen’s hospital (<hi rend="italic">Bracefordspittle</hi>) in Yorkshire and the farm of the manor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Willoughton">Willoughton</ref> in Lincolnshire which he was still paying rent for in November 1420. Skerne was appointed commissioner to audit the accounts of persons collecting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pavage">pavage</ref> in London in October 1406. He was appointed Commissioner of Sewers in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surrey">Surrey</ref> in December 1417. Skerne was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justice_of_the_Peace">J.P.</ref> in Surrey from 28 October 1417, a post he held for fourteen years. He was made commissioner to raise a royal loan in November 1419 and was tax collector for Surrey in January 1420. That same year he became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member_of_Parliament_(UK)">MP</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surrey_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Surrey</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Parliaments_of_England#Parliaments_of_Henry_V">9th parliament of Henry V</ref>. His judicial career continued, being appointed commissioner of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oyer_and_terminer">oyer and terminer</ref> in July 1421. Skerne was MP for Surrey again in 1422 in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Parliaments_of_England#Parliaments_of_Henry_VI">first Parliament</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VI_of_England">Henry VI</ref>. In April 1431 he was commissioner to assess a royal loan and, in December that year, he retired as JP.
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HOP-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Marriage and property</head>
<p>Skerne is noted for having married Joan, youngest daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alice_Perrers">Alice Perrers</ref>, mistress of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_III_of_England">Edward III</ref>, which implies that Skerne had connections at court. Joan profited little from her mother's estate following Perrers' death in 1400/1401 but acquired the manor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compton_Murdak">Compton Murdak</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warwickshire">Warwickshire</ref>. Joan fought a series of sometimes protracted legal battles to support her claim to more of the estate. Skerne took <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seisin">seisin</ref> of Joan's mother’s Berkshire manor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_Hanney">East Hanney</ref>, and in 1406 Joan settled on a compromise with her sister, Jane, over property in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upminster">Upminster</ref>, Essex, paying Joan an annuity of 4 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_(money)#England_and_Scotland">marks</ref> for life. Joan and Skerne also eventually managed to reassert her title to some of the holdings purchased by Alice Perrers in Oxford.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HOP-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Skerne, however, was not dependent on his wife's estate. He held <hi rend="italic">Downhall</hi> in Guildford from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merton_College,_Oxford">Merton College</ref>, lands and rents in Kingston upon Thames and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thames_Ditton">Thames Ditton</ref>, the manor of Freemantles, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windlesham">Windlesham</ref> and land in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hampshire">Hampshire</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HOP-1">[1]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Bray_(antiquary)">Bray</ref> says, in his <hi rend="italic">History of the County of Surrey</hi>  that Robert lived at <hi rend="italic">Downhall</hi> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canbury">Canbury</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingston_upon_Thames">Kingston upon Thames</ref>, styled a '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Messuage">capital messuage</ref>' or 'manor', held of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merton_Priory">Merton Priory</ref> situated to the south of the present day <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingston_Railway_Bridge">railway bridge</ref>. Others have been unable to corroborate that this Robert Skerne lived there.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-VCHSurrey-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>After Joan’s death, some time before January 1431, Skerne gifted one of the messuages to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Osney_Abbey">Osney Abbey</ref> in return for admission into the fraternity, and arrangements for prayers to be said in memory of his late wife. He retired from the bench at this time but was signatory to further legal documents dating up to 1435.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HOP-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Death and legacy</head>
<p>Robert Skerne died 9 April 1437. He was buried alongside his wife in a tomb in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All_Saints_Church,_Kingston_upon_Thames">All Saints Church, Kingston upon Thames</ref>, marked by a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monumental_brass">monumental brass</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>The brass bears the Latin inscription:</p>
<p>Following his uncle's death, his nephew, William, founded a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chantry">chantry</ref> in his honour. William's son, also named Robert, inherited Downhall, Kingston, it subsequently passing to his son, Swithin, in 1485-6.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-VCHSurrey-2">[2]</ref></p>
</text>
