<text id="autogum_bio_doc734" title="John Dongan" shortTile="john-dongan" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-13" dateModified="2019-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Dongan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Dongan</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">John Dongan</hi> [<hi rend="bold">Donegan</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Donnegan</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Donkan</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Duncan</hi>] (died <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1413_in_Ireland">1413</ref> x) was a medieval <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manx_people">Manx</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prelate">prelate</ref>. After holding the position of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeacon">Archdeacon</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic_Diocese_of_Down_and_Connor">Down</ref>, he held three successive bishoprics, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_the_Bishops_of_the_Diocese_of_Sodor_and_Man">Mann</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_the_Isles">the Isles</ref> (Sodor), then the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Episcopal_see">see</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Derry">Derry</ref> and then, lastly, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Down">Down</ref>.</p>
<p>He resigned his last bishopric in 1413, and died afterwards at an unrecorded date. He was the last bishop of the united diocese of Sodor, which split into the "Scottish" and "Irish" (Manx) parts because of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_Schism">Western Schism</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Bishop of Mann and the Isles</head>
<p>According to the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manx_Chronicle">Manx Chronicle</ref></hi>, he was a native Manxman.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> Despite this, the earliest major ecclesiastical position he is recorded to have obtained was Irish: in 1368 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Urban_V">Pope Urban V</ref>  appointed him <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeacon">Archdeacon</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic_Diocese_of_Down_and_Connor">Down</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Christian-ODNB-3">[3]</ref> (Dongan was originally <hi rend="italic">Donnagáin</hi> and found in the south <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulster">Ulster</ref>/north <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leinster">Leinster</ref> area . In the following years Dongan worked as a papal tax-collector and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuncio">nuncio</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ireland">Ireland</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Christian-ODNB-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>This service in Ireland was further rewarded in 1374 when he was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_the_Bishops_of_the_Diocese_of_Sodor_and_Man">Bishop of Mann</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_the_Isles">the Isles</ref> (Sodor), receiving <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consecration">consecration</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_Langham">Simon Langham</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardinal-Bishop_of_Palestrina">Cardinal-Bishop of Palestrina</ref> on either 25 or 26 November 1374.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> He did not immediately make it back to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British_Isles">British Isles</ref>, because while returning from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avignon">Avignon</ref> he was kidnapped.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Christian-ODNB-3">[3]</ref> After being imprisoned at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boulogne-sur-Mer">Boulogne-sur-Mer</ref>, he was ransomed for 500 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_(money)">marks</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>He is not known to have returned to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isle_of_Man">Isle of Man</ref> until 25 January 1377, when he is said to have celebrated his first mass at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peel_Cathedral">St Germanus' Cathedral</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peel,_Isle_of_Man">Peel</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Christian-Dowden-6">[6]</ref> Charter evidence confirming two Manx churches to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whithorn_Priory">Whithorn Priory</ref>, reveals that on 5 February he held a "general chapter", which may have involved a general investigation of church landholdings in the diocese in his role as papal nuncio and tax-collector for the diocese, two roles he had received in addition to the bishopric of Sodor in 1374.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Christian-Dowden-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Bishop of Mann only</head>
<p>In 1380, allegations were lodged against Dongan that revenues he had been collecting — in an official capacity as collector in Ireland for Pope Urban — were illegally retained.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Christian-ODNB-3">[3]</ref> These allegations did not turn out to be of great consequence, and he sided with English-backed Urban against the Scottish-backed anti-pope <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avignon_Pope_Clement_VII">Clement VII</ref>. The latter deprived him of bishopric on 15 July 1387, appointing Michael, previously <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_Cashel">Archbishop of Cashel</ref>, to replace him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Although Dongan retained <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> episcopal authority in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isle_of_Man">Isle of Man</ref>, this marked, in the words of one historian, the "final rift between the Hebrides and the Isle of Man within the diocese".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Christian-ODNB-3">[3]</ref> The northern, Scottish-controlled portion of his diocese was lost to the new bishop, and in fact Dongan was to be the last bishop to preside over both the Scottish and English-controlled islands that had until then formed the diocese of Sodor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>These developments meant that Dongan's already poor diocese was minuscule, too small really to necessitate a full-time bishop, and so Dongan's episcopal status was put to use elsewhere by busier prelates.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> In the early 1390s he is found in England acting as a kind of deputy to various English bishops. On 14 January 1390, for instance, he is found working on the commission of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Salisbury">Bishop of Salisbury</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Christian-Dowden-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>In 1391 and 1392 he was performing ordinations in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_London">diocese of London</ref> on behalf of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_London">Bishop of London</ref>, though he was no longer at that stage Bishop of Sodor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Christian-Dowden-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Irish bishoprics</head>
<p>By this point the non-Avignon papacy, under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Boniface_IX">Pope Boniface IX</ref> (Urban's successor), decided to move Dongan into an Irish see. Ireland was (as a territory of the King of England) in their allegiance and thus candidates they appointed to Irish bishoprics could actually expect to take physical possession. On 11 July 1391 he was provided to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Derry">bishopric of Derry</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Province_of_Armagh_(Roman_Catholic)">province of Armagh</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> He held this position for only three years, as on 16 September 1394 he was translated to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Down">bishopric of Down</ref>, also in the province of Armagh.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>As the bishop of Down, his most notable role was his diplomatic interactions on behalf of the English crown with the native Gaelic leaders of Ireland and Scotland. In 1405 he was given this role and appointed "keeper of the liberty of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulster">Ulster</ref>".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Christian-ODNB-3">[3]</ref> In September 1407 he and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janico_Dartas">Janico Dartas</ref>, "Admiral of Ireland", were authorised to arrange a peace with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domhnall_of_Islay,_Lord_of_the_Isles">Domhnall of Islay</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_of_the_Isles">Lord of the Isles</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Christian-ODNB-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Such negotiations were still taking place in 1408, and though records for the process vanish afterwards, the two marriages recorded in 1410 between Dartas' children and the family of this Scottish magnate suggests a peaceful accord was reached.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Christian-ODNB-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Bishop Dongan resigned his see in 1413.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref>  This is the last notice of him, so it is unclear when exactly he died, though it is presumed to be soon afterwards.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Christian-ODNB-3">[3]</ref></p>
</text>
