<text id="autogum_bio_doc216" title="Lynching of Joe Coe" shortTile="lynching-joe-coe" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-07" dateModified="2019-08-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynching_of_Joe_Coe" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Lynching of Joe Coe</head>For the early Latter Day Saint leader, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_Coe">Joseph Coe</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Joe Coe</hi>, also known as <hi rend="bold">George Smith</hi>, was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African-American">African-American</ref> laborer who was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynching">lynched</ref> on October 10, 1891, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Omaha,_Nebraska">Omaha, Nebraska</ref>. Overwhelmed by a mob of one thousand at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_County_Courthouse_(Omaha)#Second_courthouse">Douglas County Courthouse</ref>, the twelve city police officers stood by without intervening. Afterward, the mayor called the lynching "the most deplorable thing that has ever happened in the history of the country."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Biography and death</head>
<p>Coe was a married man with two children who lived on North 12th Street north of downtown Omaha. On October 7, 1891, Lizzie Yates, a five-year-old white child who also lived in North Omaha, accused Coe of assaulting her. Before the verdict was passed rumors swept through Omaha about Coe getting away with the crime, about the girl dying, and about Coe receiving a small punishment.</p>
<p>A crowd of men was already gathered at the old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_County,_Nebraska">Douglas County</ref> Courthouse the day when Coe was brought in, to witness an unrelated, scheduled <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanging">hanging</ref>, an official execution. Rumors flew around Omaha that the girl had died, the guilty party was in jail, and was only going to be punished with  20 years' incarceration.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>The next day, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ochlocracy">mob</ref> of several hundred to 1,000 men formed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Downtown_Omaha">downtown Omaha</ref> early on October 10 and overwhelmed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Omaha_Police_Department">police</ref> at the courthouse.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Councilman Moriarty drove his cane through a window and led the men against the courthouse.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Ginzburg,_R._1988_p_128-4">[4]</ref> Leaders drove Coe to the assumed victim's house in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Near_North_Side_(Omaha,_Nebraska)">Near North Side</ref> neighborhood to be identified by the parents. The mother immediately said she had seen Coe roaming around the house, although she would not swear that it was him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Ginzburg,_R._1988_p_128-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>When the mob brought Coe back to the courthouse to be lynched, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_E._Boyd_(politician)">James E. Boyd</ref>, the governor of Nebraska, and the county sheriff both appealed to the men to disperse. Instead, by midnight a crowd of 1,000 to 10,000 people had gathered at the courthouse.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> The mob beat Coe and dragged him through city streets. He was probably already dead when he was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanging">hung</ref> from a streetcar wire at 17th and Harney Streets.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_mayors_of_Omaha,_Nebraska">Omaha mayor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_C._Cushing_(Omaha)">Richard C. Cushing</ref> quickly condemned the lynching as "the most deplorable thing that has ever happened in the history of the country."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Aftermath</head>
<p>Seven men were arrested for the crime, including the chief of police and the manager of a large dry goods store. A mob gathered outside the jail and threatened to destroy it unless the suspects were freed on bail but the County Attorney was determined to refuse them.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>The following day when Coe's body was set for public viewing at a downtown <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mortuary">mortuary</ref>, six thousand spectators filed by. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huckster">Hucksters</ref> sold pieces of the lynching rope as souvenirs.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>Ten days after the lynching, the Douglas County Assistant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coroner">Coroner</ref> testified in court that Smith died of "fright", rather than of the wounds inflicted on him by the mob. Those wounds included sixteen wounds to his body and three <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vertebrae">vertebrae</ref> broken in his spine. Despite this, the coroner testified, "[T]he heart was so contracted and the blood was in such a condition that the doctor was satisfied that the man was literally scared to death." County Attorney Mahoney said he would have to modify the charges against the lynchers.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> The grand jury decided not to prosecute.</p>
</text>
