<text id="autogum_bio_doc751" title="Niccolò and Maffeo Polo" shortTile="niccolo-maffeo-polo" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-07-07" dateModified="2019-09-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niccol%C3%B2_and_Maffeo_Polo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Niccolò and Maffeo Polo</head><p><hi rend="bold">Niccolò Polo</hi> (Italian:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Italian">[nikkoˌlɔ pˈpɔːlo]</ref>, Venetian:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Venetian">[nikoˌɰɔ ˈpolo]</ref>; c.1230 – c.1294)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[nb 1]</ref> and <hi rend="bold">Maffeo Polo</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Italian">[mafˈfɛːo ˈpɔːlo]</ref>, Venetian:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Venetian">[maˈfɛo ˈpolo]</ref>; or Matteo <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Italian">[matˈtɛːo]</ref>, Venetian:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Venetian">[maˈtɛo]</ref>; c.1230 – c.1309)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[nb 2]</ref> were Italian traveling merchants best known as the father and uncle, respectively, of the explorer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco_Polo">Marco Polo</ref>. The brothers went into business before Marco's birth, established trading posts in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sudak">Sudak</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crimea">Crimea</ref>, and in a western part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mongol_Empire">Mongol Empire</ref> in Asia. As a duo, they reached modern-day China before temporarily returning to Europe to deliver a message to the Pope. Taking Niccolò's son Marco with them, the Polos then made another journey through Asia, which became the subject of Marco's account <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Travels_of_Marco_Polo">The Travels of Marco Polo</ref></hi>.</p>
<head>First voyage</head>
<p>Leaving Niccolò's infant son Marco behind, Niccolò and Maffeo left <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_of_Venice">Venice</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref>, where they resided for several years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[nb 3]</ref>  The two brothers lived in the Venetian quarter of Constantinople, where they enjoyed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extraterritoriality">diplomatic immunity, political chances and tax relief</ref> because of their country's role in establishing the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin_Empire">Latin Empire</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth_Crusade">Fourth Crusade</ref> of 1204. However, the family judged the political situation of the city precarious, so they decided to transfer their business northeast to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sudak">Soldaia</ref>, a city in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crimea">Crimea</ref>, and left Constantinople in 1259 or 1260. Their decision proved wise. Constantinople was recaptured in 1261 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_VIII_Palaeologus">Michael Palaeologus</ref>, the ruler of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Empire_of_Nicaea">Empire of Nicaea</ref>, who promptly burned and razed the Venetian quarter and reestablished the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_Empire">Byzantine Empire</ref>. Captured Venetian citizens were blinded,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-zorzi-5">[2]</ref> while many of those who managed to escape died aboard overloaded refugee ships fleeing to other Venetian colonies in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aegean_Sea">Aegean Sea</ref>.</p>
<p>As their new home on the north rim of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_Sea">Black Sea</ref>, Soldaia had been frequented by Venetian traders since the 12th century. When the Polos reached it, it was  part of the newly formed Mongol state known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Horde">Golden Horde</ref>. Searching for better profits, the Polos continued their journey to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarai_(city)">Sarai</ref>, where the court of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berke">Berke Khan</ref>, the ruler of the Golden Horde, was located. At that time, the city of Sarai was no more than a huge encampment, and the Polos stayed for about a year. The Polo brothers became merchant partners, <hi rend="italic">ortoq</hi>, of Berke to sell wares entrusted to them.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[3]</ref> Finally, they decided to avoid Crimea, because of a civil war between Berke and his cousin <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hulagu_Khan">Hulagu</ref> or perhaps because of the bad relationship between Berke Khan and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_Empire">Byzantine Empire</ref>. Instead, they moved further east to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bukhara">Bukhara</ref>, in modern-day <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uzbekistan">Uzbekistan</ref>, where the family lived and traded for three years.</p>
<p>In 1264, Niccolò and Maffeo joined up with an embassy sent by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ilkhanate">Ilkhanate</ref> ruler Hulagu to his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kublai_Khan">Kublai Khan</ref>, both grandsons of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genghis_Khan">Genghis Khan</ref>. In 1266, they reached the seat of Kublai Khan, the leader of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mongol_Yuan_dynasty">Mongol Yuan dynasty</ref>, at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khanbaliq">Dadu</ref>, present day Beijing, China. In his book, <hi rend="italic">The Travels of Marco Polo</hi>, Marco explains how Kublai Khan officially received the Polos and sent them back  with a Mongol named Koeketei as an ambassador to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope">pope</ref>. They brought with them a letter from the Khan requesting 100 educated people to come and teach <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christianity">Christianity</ref> and Western customs to his people and oil from the lamp of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Sepulcher">Holy Sepulcher</ref>. The letter also contained the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paiza">paiza</ref>, a golden tablet a foot long and 3 inches (7.6cm) wide, allowing  the holder to acquire and obtain lodging, horses and food throughout the Kublai Khan's dominion. Koeketei left in the middle of the journey, leaving the Polos to travel alone to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayas_(city)">Ayas</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenian_Kingdom_of_Cilicia">Armenian Kingdom of Cilicia</ref>. From that port city, they sailed to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City_of_Acre">Saint Jean d'Acre</ref>, capital of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Jerusalem">Kingdom of Jerusalem</ref>.</p>
<p>The long <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sede_vacante">sede vacante</ref></hi> between the death of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Clement_IV">Pope Clement IV</ref>, in 1268, and the election of the new pope in 1271  delayed the Polos' attempts to fulfil Kublai's request. As suggested by Theobald Visconti, then papal legate for the realm of Egypt, in Acre for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ninth_Crusade">Ninth Crusade</ref>, the two brothers returned to Venice in 1269 or 1270, waiting for the nomination of the new pope. Here Niccolò met up once again with his son Marco, now fifteen or sixteen, who had been living with his aunt and another uncle in Venice since the death of his mother at a young age.</p>
<head>Second voyage</head>
See also: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco_Polo">Marco Polo</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Europeans_in_Medieval_China">Europeans in Medieval China</ref>
<figure><caption>Niccolò and Maffeo Polo remitting a letter from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kublai_Khan">Kublai Khan</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Gregory_X">Pope Gregory X</ref> in 1271.</caption></figure>
<p>As soon as he was elected in 1271, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Gregory_X">Pope Gregory X</ref> (the former Theobald Visconti) received the letter from Kublai Khan, remitted by Niccolò and Maffeo. Kublai Khan was asking for the dispatch of a hundred missionaries, and some oil from the lamp of Jerusalem. The two Polos (this time accompanied by the 17-year-old Marco Polo) returned to Mongolia, accompanied by two Dominican friars, Niccolò de <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vicenza">Vicence</ref> and Guillaume de <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tripoli,_Lebanon">Tripoli</ref>. The two friars did not finish the voyage due to fear, but the Polos reached Kanbaliq and remitted the presents from the Pope to Kublai in 1274.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[4]</ref> It is usually said that the Polos used the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northern_Silk_Road">Northern Silk Road</ref> although the possibility of a southern route has been advanced.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[5]</ref>
The Polos spent the next 17 years in China. Kublai Khan took a liking to Marco, who was an engaging storyteller. He was sent on many diplomatic missions throughout his empire. Marco carried out diplomatic assignments but also entertained the Khan with interesting stories and observations about the lands he traveled. According to Marco's travel account, the Polos asked several times for permission to return to Europe but the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Khan">Great Khan</ref> appreciated the visitors so much that he would not agree to their departure.</p>
<p>Only in 1291 did Kublai entrust Marco with his last duty, to escort the Mongol princess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Koekecin">Koekecin</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Cocacin</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Il Milione</hi>) to her betrothed, the Ilkhan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arghun">Arghun</ref>. The party traveled by sea, departing from the southern port city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quanzhou">Quanzhou</ref> and sailing to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sumatra">Sumatra</ref>, and then to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persia">Persia</ref>, via <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sri_Lanka">Sri Lanka</ref> and India (where his visits included <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mylapore">Mylapore</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madurai">Madurai</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alleppey">Alleppey</ref>, which he nicknamed Venice of the East). In 1293 or 1294 the Polos reached the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ilkhanate">Ilkhanate</ref>, ruled by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaykhatu">Gaykhatu</ref> after the death of Arghun, and left Koekecin with the new Ilkhan. Then they moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trabzon">Trebizond</ref> and from that city sailed to Venice.</p>
<head>Popular culture</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Niccolò and Maffeo Polo are featured in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Assassin's_Creed_(series)"><hi rend="italic">Assassin's Creed</hi> series</ref>, having become key figures in the history of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hashashin">Assassin Order</ref>.</item>
<item>The brothers are also featured in Netflix's historical fiction series, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco_Polo_(TV_series)">Marco Polo</ref></hi>.</item>
<item>Niccoló and Maffeo are also characters in the 1982 miniseries <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco_Polo_(miniseries)">Marco Polo</ref>, played by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denholm_Elliott">Denholm Elliott</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Vogel">Tony Vogel</ref>, respectively.</item></list>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
