<text id="autogum_bio_doc268" title="Gregory V of Constantinople" shortTile="gregory-v-constantinople" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-12-26" dateModified="2019-07-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gregory_V_of_Constantinople" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gregory V of Constantinople</head><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Patriarch Gregory V</hi> redirects here. It can also refer to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarch_Gregory_V_of_Alexandria">Patriarch Gregory V of Alexandria</ref>.</hi>
<p><hi rend="bold">Gregory V</hi> (Greek: Γρηγόριος Ε΄, born Γεώργιος Αγγελόπουλος, <hi rend="italic">Georgios Angelopoulos</hi>), (1746 – 22 April 1821) was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecumenical_Patriarch_of_Constantinople">Ecumenical Patriarch of Constantinople</ref> from 1797 to 1798, from 1806 to 1808 and from 1818 to 1821. He was responsible for much restoration work to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_St_George,_Istanbul">Patriarchal Cathedral of St George</ref>, which had been badly damaged by fire in 1738. </p>
<p>At the onset of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_War_of_Independence">Greek War of Independence</ref>, as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethnarch">Ethnarch</ref> of the Orthodox <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Millet_(Ottoman_Empire)">Millet</ref>, or court of law, Gregory V was blamed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Dynasty">Ottoman Sultan</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahmud_II">Mahmud II</ref> for his inability to suppress the Greek uprising. This was in spite of the fact that Gregory had condemned the Greek revolutionary activities in order to protect the Greeks of Constantinople from such reprisals by the Ottoman Turks. After the Greek rebels scored several successes against the Ottoman forces in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peloponnese">Peloponnese</ref>, these reprisals came. </p>
<p>During Holy Week in April of 1821, Gregory was taken out of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_St_George,_Istanbul">Patriarchal Cathedral</ref> on 22 April 1821 (10 April <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Style">Old Style</ref>), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Easter">Easter Sunday</ref>, directly after celebrating the solemn Easter Liturgy, Gregory was accosted by the Ottomans. He was taken out of the cathedral, still in full Patriarchal vestments, and hanged, being left for two days on the main gate of the Patriarchate compound, all by order of the Sultan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fortescue341-1">[1]</ref> This was followed by a massacre of the Greek population of Constantinople.</p>
<p>The Patriarch's body was eventually interred in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan_Cathedral_of_Athens">Metropolitan Cathedral of Athens</ref>. He is commemorated by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_Orthodox_Church">Greek Orthodox Church</ref> as an <hi rend="italic">Ethnomartyr</hi> (Greek: <hi rend="italic">Εθνομάρτυρας</hi>). In his memory, the Saint Peter Gate, once the main gate of the Patriarchate compound, was welded shut in 1821 and has remained shut ever since.</p>
<head>Influence</head>
<p>The brutal execution of Gregory V, especially on the day of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Easter">Easter Sunday</ref>, shocked and infuriated the Greeks, and Orthodox <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian_Empire">Russia</ref>. It also caused protests in the rest of Europe and reinforced the movement of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philhellenism">Philhellenism</ref>. There are references that during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_War_of_Independence">Greek War of Independence</ref>, many revolutionaries engraved on their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sword">swords</ref> the name of Gregory, seeking revenge.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dionysios_Solomos">Dionysios Solomos</ref>, in his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hymn_to_Liberty">Hymn to Liberty</ref>, which became later the Greek national anthem, also mentions the hanging of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarch">Patriarch</ref> in some <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanza">stanzas</ref>.</p>
<head>Greek-Jewish animosity</head>
Further information: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_the_Jews_in_the_Ottoman_Empire">History of the Jews in the Ottoman Empire</ref>
<p>According to several accounts,  after Gregory's death his body, along with those of other executed prelates, was turned over to the city's Jews, who dragged it through the streets and threw it into the sea.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fortescue341-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fleming-2">[2]</ref> This lead to several bloody reprisal attacks in southern Greece by the Greek rebels (the accounts differ on whether the Greeks who did this were forced or volunteered, but the tale spread widely), who regarded the Jews as collaborators of the Turks. This in turn led to the Jews joining the Turks in attacks on Christians in some locations in northern Greece, which fuelled a new wave of anti-Jewish attacks in the south.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fleming-2">[2]</ref> During the night, the patriarch's corpse was recovered by Greek sailors, who brought it to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Odessa">Odessa</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fortescue341-1">[1]</ref> After the funeral, some Greek sailors attacked Jewish shops which had remained open during the ceremony.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Orbach1980-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In Russia, in Odessa local Greek committed the first Russian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Odessa_pogroms#1821_pogrom">Pogrom</ref> killing 14 Jews.</p>
<head>Gallery</head>
<list type="unordered">
<item>The Saint Peter's Gate at the Patriarchate. Gregory V was hanged here. Since then the Gate was never opened again.</item>
<item>Painting by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_von_Hess">Peter von Hess</ref> depicting the casting of the corpse of Patriarch Gregory V of Constantinople into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bosphorus">Bosphorus</ref>.</item>
<item>Statue of Grigorios (University of Athens) by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgios_Fytalis">Georgios Fytalis</ref></item>
<item>The shrine of Patriarch Grigorios (Metropolitan Cathedral of Athens)</item>
</list>
</text>
