<text id="autogum_bio_doc710" title="Kujava Radinović" shortTile="kujava-radinovic" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-05-27" dateModified="2019-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kujava_Radinovi%C4%87" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kujava Radinović</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kujava Radinović</hi> was the second wife of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Ostoja_of_Bosnia">Stephen Ostoja of Bosnia</ref> and as such she was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Bosnian_consorts">Queen of Bosnia</ref> from 1399 to 1404 and again from 1409 to 1415. She was the daughter of the nobleman Radin Jablanić.</p>
<head>Queenship</head>
<p>Kujava married King Stefan Ostoj Kotromanić in 1399, shortly after he repudiated his first wife, Queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vitača">Vitača</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFine2007-1">[1]</ref> Ostoj gained support of the noble family of Radenović by marrying Kujava, as they were closely related to the new <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_consort">queen consort</ref>. Kujava was sister (i.e. cousin) of prince Pavle Radenović.  Kujava is first mentioned as queen in a charter dating from 5 February 1399.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Acta-2">[2]</ref> Queen Kujava resided in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobovac">Bobovac</ref> along with her husband and son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefan_Ostojić">Stefan Ostojić</ref>. When her husband was deposed by the powerful Bosnian nobility in 1404, he left Bobovać and fled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Hungary">Hungary</ref>, but Kujava and Stefan remained in Bosnia. The crown was given to Kujava's nephew, King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tvrtko_II">Tvrtko II</ref>. Tvrtko II himself was deposed in 1409 when Kujava's husband returned from exile and reassumed the throne.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Anđelić-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Queen Kujava's marriage started falling apart in 1415. Prince Pavle Radenović, Kujava's brother (i.e. cousin),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFine1994-4">[4]</ref> was killed in a plot set by Kujava's husband. The authorities of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_of_Ragusa">Republic of Ragusa</ref> were informed that the Queen of Bosnia was concerned for her future due to her relation to Pavle.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFine1975282-5">[5]</ref> Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hrvoje_Vukčić_Hrvatinić">Hrvoje Vukčić Hrvatinić</ref> died soon after, leaving behind a wealthy widow, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jelena_Nelipčić">Jelena Nelipčić</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFine1994-4">[4]</ref> Seizeing the opportunity, Ostoj repudiated Kujava and married the widowed duchess.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFine1994-4">[4]</ref> His complicity in the plot and murder of Pavle Radenović outraged the magnates, who sharply denounced him at a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanak">stanak</ref></hi>. The 16th century Ragusan historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mavro_Orbini">Mavro Orbini</ref> wrote that even his son sided against him, resenting the treatment of his mother and the union with Jelena.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEŽivković198175-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>In 1418, Kujava's former husband died and their son was elected king. Kujava was now recognized as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_mother">queen mother</ref> and suddenly became very influential and powerful, <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> ruling along with her son. Her son's short reign was marked by Queen Kujava's conflicts with Queen Jelena. Their conflicts stopped in the summer of 1419, when Stephen imprisoned his stepmother. Jelena died under suspicious circumstances in 1422.</p>
<head>Intrigues</head>
<p>Kujava's son was dethroned in favour of Tvrtko II in 1420. He died before April 1422, when Kujava asked the Ragusan authorities to intervene with Tvrtko on her behalf.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEŽivković198181-7">[7]</ref> Nevertheless, she set about seeking revenge for her son's deposition. She received support from the Republic of Ragusa during its hostility towards Tvrtko, and conspired with certain magnates to dethrone him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEŽivković1981103-8">[8]</ref> She failed in her endeavour to enthrone <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vuk_Banić">Vuk Banić</ref>, a purported relative of the royal family, and Vuk had to flee to Ragusa along with some other conspirators. In March 1423 Tvrtko reprimanded Ragusa for allowing Vuk to exchange letters with his aunt, while Vuk himself maintained that he had never contacted her. The former queen then attempted to make use of the souring relations between Tvrtko and some of his vassals. With this in mind, she turned to Ragusa, but it is not clear what exactly she wanted. Ragusan authorities tried to reconcile her with Tvrtko, and also intervened on her behalf with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandalj_Hranić_Kosača">Sandalj Hranić Kosača</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zlatonosović_family">Zlatonosović family</ref>. They also assisted her with her financial difficulties.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEŽivković1981104-9">[9]</ref> Kujava was still intriguing in 1426, secretly corresponding with Vuk. Her influence in the kingdom and abroad had waned considerably, however. Ragusan authorities, having settled their differences with Tvrtko, refused her appeal for financial aid.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEŽivković1981117-10">[10]</ref> In 1434, they again sent her gifts, this time through an envoy of another pretender, her husband's illegitimate son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radivoj_Ostojić">Radivoj Ostojić</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEŽivković1981174-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>Three sets of remains were discovered in a small tomb in the Bobovac chapel during archaeological excavations in the 1960s, apparently reinterred there during the reign of Tvrtko II. They are believed to belong to Kujava, her former husband and her son.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAnđelić197392-12">[12]</ref></p>
</text>
