<text id="autogum_bio_doc716" title="Walter Leslie" shortTile="walter-leslie" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-07-23" dateModified="2018-04-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Leslie" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Walter Leslie</head>This article is about the crusader. For the Holy Roman Empire Field Marshal, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Leslie_(1607–1667)">Walter Leslie (1607–1667)</ref>. For the Indian Army officer, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Leslie_(Indian_Army_officer)">Walter Leslie (Indian Army officer)</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Sir Walter Leslie</hi> (died 1382) was a 14th-century <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scotland">Scottish</ref> nobleman and crusader, one of the foremost knights of his time. </p>
<p>Leslie was a younger son, probably the third son, of Sir Andrew Leslie of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leslie_Castle">Leslie Castle</ref> sixth in line from Bartholomew, founder of the name Leslie<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberdeenshire_(historic)">Aberdeenshire</ref>, by his wife Mary Abernethy, daughter and coheiress of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_de_Abernethy">Sir Alexander Abernethy</ref>. Along with his elder brother Norman, he obtained safe conduct through England on his way to Prussia to participate in a crusade against the pagans of that region. He had returned by 1356. He is then said to have gone to France, to aid the French in their wars with the English. He must have gone there more than once, for he was present at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Pontvallain">Battle of Pontvallain</ref> in 1370, where he proved instrumental in the English defeat, and was rewarded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_V_of_France">King Charles</ref> with a yearly pension of two hundred gold francs.</p>
<p>He was present in Scotland in 1363, when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_II_of_Scotland">King David</ref> granted him a pension of forty pounds sterling. Later that year, David obtained from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_III_of_England">Edward III of England</ref> a safe passage for Walter and Norman to travel to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Land">Holy Land</ref>. They traveled via <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italy">Italy</ref>; they appear as witnesses to a deal signed by the authorities of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florence">Florence</ref> with the notorious "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_Company">White Band</ref>", a group of English mercenaries who had fought in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hundred_Years'_War">Hundred Years' War</ref> and were then plying their trade in Italy. Walter and Norman eventually joined the crusade of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_I_of_Cyprus">Peter King of Cyprus</ref>, as the latter attacked the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egypt">Egyptian</ref> city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexandria">Alexandria</ref>. The city was captured, but King Peter was unable to hold it, and abandoned the city after looting it.</p>
<p>Walter returned to Scotland in 1366, and was warmly welcomed by King David. The king was fascinated by the cult of the crusader, and Walter's previous exploits had already made him one of the royal favorites. As a reward for his latest exploits, David gave him permission to marry <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euphemia_I,_Countess_of_Ross">Euphemia</ref>, the daughter and heiress of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William,_5th_Earl_of_Ross">Earl of Ross</ref>, whom David coerced into allowing the marriage. The marriage took place on 13 September of the same year. After this, he appears to have remained in Scotland for a time, taking a prominent part in public affairs and frequently witnessing royal charters. </p>
<p>When King David died in 1371, Walter may have been worried that the new king, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_II_of_Scotland">Robert Stewart</ref>, who was an ally of the Earl of Ross, may have rescinded the patronage. However, the new king did not, and when Ross died in 1372, Euphemia inherited the title, and Walter became <hi rend="italic">jure uxoris</hi> earl or lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ross,_Scotland">Ross</ref>.</p>
<p>Walter died at Perth on 27 February 1382. He left two children, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Leslie,_Earl_of_Ross">Alexander</ref> (the future Earl of Ross) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mariota,_Countess_of_Ross">Mariota</ref>, who would marry <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domhnall,_Lord_of_the_Isles">Donald Lord of the Isles</ref>. Although Alexander did eventually inherit the earldom, <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> control of Ross passed into the hands of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Stewart,_Earl_of_Buchan">Earl of Buchan</ref>, aka the "Wolf of Badenoch", who was Countess Euphemia's second husband before she divorced him in 1392.</p>
</text>
