<text id="autogum_bio_doc351" title="John Hill (courtier)" shortTile="john-hill-courtier" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-02" dateModified="2019-06-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Hill_%28courtier%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Hill (courtier)</head><p>
Major-General <hi rend="bold">John "Jack" Hill</hi> (died 22 June 1735) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Great_Britain">British</ref> army officer and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Courtier">courtier</ref> during the reign of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne,_Queen_of_Great_Britain">Queen Anne</ref>. While of no particular military ability, his family connections brought him promotion and office until the end of Anne's reign.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Jack, as he was known, was the youngest son of the merchant Francis Hill and his wife Elizabeth Jenyns, and hence the brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abigail_Masham,_Baroness_Masham">Abigail Hill</ref>, later Baroness Masham. The failure of his father's business left the family dependent upon the largesse of their cousin <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarah_Churchill,_Duchess_of_Marlborough">Sarah Churchill</ref>, later Duchess of Marlborough. Sarah paid for Hill's education at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Albans_School_(Hertfordshire)">St Albans Grammar School</ref> from 1690–1691, and obtained for him an appointment as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Page_(occupation)">page</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince_George_of_Denmark">Prince George of Denmark</ref> in 1692 and then in 1698 as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Groom_of_the_Bedchamber">Groom of the Bedchamber</ref> to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince_William,_Duke_of_Gloucester">Duke of Gloucester</ref>. After Gloucester's death, he briefly returned to Prince George's household in 1700.</p>
<head>Military career</head>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Churchill,_1st_Duke_of_Marlborough">Duke of Marlborough</ref> obtained for Hill a captaincy in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grenadier_Guards">Grenadier Guards</ref> in November 1702, and he was made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adjutant_general">adjutant general</ref> to the forces sent into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portugal">Portugal</ref> in 1703. In May 1705, he was made colonel of the former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Devonshire_Regiment">Lord Stanhope's Regiment of Foot</ref>. This rapid rise owed little to military talent; while partly brought about through the patronage of Marlborough, it was increasingly due to the ascent of his sister Abigail, who was now displacing her cousin the Duchess in Anne's favour.</p>
<p>In 1706, he and his regiment took part in the expedition under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Savage,_4th_Earl_Rivers">Earl Rivers</ref>, originally directed against the coast of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France">France</ref> but subsequently diverted to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisbon">Lisbon</ref>. In 1707, Hill and the regiment were shipped to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valencia,_Spain">Valencia</ref>, to take part in the campaign which ended with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Almansa">Battle of Almansa</ref>. Hill commanded a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brigade">brigade</ref> during the battle, comprising his own regiment with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9th_(East_Norfolk)_Regiment_of_Foot">William Steuart's</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/36th_(Herefordshire)_Regiment_of_Foot">Thomas Alnutt's</ref> regiments. Hill's brigade attacked the French during the latter stages of the battle and allowed the remaining British forces to retreat in good order, but he and his regiment were captured by the French.</p>
<p>Hill was paroled and returned to England to reform his regiment, which was sent to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref> in summer 1708 and took part in the siege of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mons">Mons</ref> in 1709. On 26 September 1709, Hill's regiment was sent to advance the siege lines against the town and had to fight off a sally in which it suffered 150 casualties, including Hill, who was wounded.</p>
<head>Rise under the Tories</head>
<p>By 1710, Hill's sister, Lady Masham, had supplanted her cousin in the Queen's affections and now joined <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Harley,_1st_Earl_of_Oxford_and_Earl_Mortimer">Robert Harley</ref> to weaken Marlborough and advance her brother. The Queen, prompted by Harley, solicited for Hill the colonelcy of the late <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/4th_Queen's_Own_Hussars">Earl of Essex's Regiment of Dragoons</ref>. Marlborough refused to promote Hill over officers more experienced and deserving, placing additional strain on his relationship with the Queen. In April, he was forced to accede to the Queen's demand that Hill be promoted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brigadier_general">brigadier general</ref>. In May, Hill also received a pension of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pound_sterling">£</ref>1000 p.a. during the lifetime of the Queen. Marlborough and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whig_(British_political_party)">Whigs</ref> in Parliament attempted to have Lady Masham removed from Court, an unsuccessful move which ultimately precipitated Marlborough's own political demise.</p>
<p>Hill, in the meantime, was returned as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member_of_Parliament">Member of Parliament</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lostwithiel_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Lostwithiel</ref> in 1710. He showed little activity in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British_House_of_Commons">House of Commons</ref>, although, as his one-time patroness, the Duchess of Marlborough sourly noted, he did trouble himself to vote once, when ill, to support Harley's attacks on Marlborough.</p>
<head>Expedition against Quebec</head>
Main article: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quebec_Expedition">Quebec Expedition</ref>
<p>Well-connected with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harley_Ministry">Harley Ministry</ref>, Hill's star continued to rise. When <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_St_John,_1st_Viscount_Bolingbroke">Henry St John</ref> in 1711 revived a plan for the capture of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quebec_City">Quebec</ref>, Hill was proposed as commander-in-chief to gain the Queen's favor. 5000 troops under Hill's command,
in thirty transports escorted by ten <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ship_of_the_line">ships of the line</ref> under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hovenden_Walker">Sir Hovenden Walker</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quebec_Expedition">embarked for Quebec</ref>, but eight transports with 800 men were wrecked in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Lawrence_River">Saint Lawrence River</ref> on 11 August 1711 owing to fogs and gales. Hill and Walker, after a Council of War, abandoned the enterprise without firing a shot and returned to England. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonathan_Swift">Jonathan Swift</ref>, a confidant of Hill, noted that Hill's friends privately blamed him for his irresolution and lack of leadership. Hill's Tory connections, however, allowed him to escape any check in his career arising from this disaster.</p>
<head>Further promotion</head>
<p>In June 1712, Hill became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lieutenant-General_of_the_Ordnance">Lieutenant-General of the Ordnance</ref>, the Whig <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Erle">Thomas Erle</ref> having been turned out, and received the office of Governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunkirk">Dunkirk</ref> after the signing of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Utrecht">Treaty of Utrecht</ref>. In July he was promoted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Major_general">major general</ref>, and sworn of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privy_Council_of_Great_Britain">Privy Council</ref> in November. Perhaps impelled by hopes of a never-offered peerage, he did not stand for election in 1713. In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, Hill was elected to the society of wits headed by Swift and St John, and was known for his great conviviality. He returned to Dunkirk in February 1714 as a commissioner to inspect the fortifications, but came back to England in August for the accession of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_I_of_Great_Britain">George I</ref>.</p>
<head>Later life</head>
<p>With the death of Anne and the accession of George I, Hill lost his offices, but retained his commission as major-general. He sold his colonelcy to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Montagu_(died_1738)">Edward Montagu</ref> in July 1715 and retired. Both he and Lady Masham retained Tory sympathies in their later years, which Hill spent at his seat in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egham">Egham</ref> and his London house in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jermyn_Street">Jermyn Street</ref>, where he died. He left his estate to his nephew <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Masham,_2nd_Baron_Masham">Samuel Masham, 2nd Baron Masham</ref>.</p>
</text>
