<text id="autogum_bio_doc692" title="Demetrios Laskaris Leontares" shortTile="demetrios-laskaris" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-05-03" dateModified="2019-09-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demetrios_Laskaris_Leontares" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Demetrios Laskaris Leontares</head><p><hi rend="bold">Demetrios Laskaris Leontares</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Leontarios</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_language">Greek</ref>: Δημήτριος Λάσκαρις Λεοντάρης, died 6 September 1431) was an important <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_Empire">Byzantine</ref> statesman and military leader of the early 15th century, serving under the emperors <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manuel_II_Palaiologos">Manuel II Palaiologos</ref> (r. 1391–1425) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_VIII_Palaiologos">John VIII Palaiologos</ref> (r. 1425–1448).</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Nothing is known of Leontares's early life, except a statement by the historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doukas_(historian)">Doukas</ref> that Leontares had served with distinction as an officer in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morea">Morea</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thessaly">Thessaly</ref> in the 1390s.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PLP-1">[1]</ref> Leontares first appears in the historical sources in 1403. As a close friend and trusted agent of Manuel II, he escorted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_VII_Palaiologos">John VII Palaiologos</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thessalonica">Thessalonica</ref>, the Byzantine Empire's second city, which John VII had been granted as a semi-independent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Appanage">appanage</ref> by Manuel. Leontares remained in the city and served as John VII's advisor and liaison to Manuel II until the former's death in 1408.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> At this point, Manuel placed him as tutor and regent over his young son, the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despotes">despotes</ref></hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andronikos_Palaiologos,_Lord_of_Thessalonica">Andronikos Palaiologos</ref>, who succeeded John VII as governor of Thessalonica.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Leontares remained in Thessalonica as its effective governor until 1415/16,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> when the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_dynasty">Ottoman prince</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Düzmece_Mustafa">Düzmece Mustafa</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Junayd_of_Aydın">Junayd of Aydın</ref> fled to the city after a failed attempt to seize the Ottomans' European domains from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mehmed_I">Mehmed I</ref> (r. 1413–1421). Mehmed demanded the surrender of the rebel, but Leontares referred him to Manuel II in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref>. Eventually, a deal was reached whereby Mustafa would be kept in exile in the Byzantine island of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lemnos">Lemnos</ref> and Junayd in Constantinople, in exchange for an annual subsidy of 300,000 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Akçe">aspers</ref>. Leontares himself escorted Mustafa on the ship to Constantinople.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PLP-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>In late 1420/early 1421 and again in May 1421, Leontares was dispatched by Manuel II to Mehmed I in missions of good will, as reports of preparations for an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Constantinople_(1422)">Ottoman attack on Constantinople</ref> increased. The first meeting occurred during a crossing of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bosphorus">Bosphorus</ref> by Mehmed. Leontares, at the head of a group of Byzantine aristocrats and officials and supplied with gifts, met Mehmed at the Constantinopolitan suburb of Koutoulos (probably modern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurtuluş">Kurtuluş</ref>) and escorted him to Diplokionion (modern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beşiktaş">Beşiktaş</ref>), where the Emperor and his sons awaited in their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galley">galley</ref>. The second meeting was a full embassy to the Sultan's residence in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrianople">Adrianople</ref> in May 1421, perhaps connected with a purported amendment in Mehmed's will that would have made Manuel guardian of his two younger sons. Leontares was cordially received, but negotiations were prevented by Mehmed's death on 21 May. To prevent another struggle for succession, his death was kept secret for a while, and Leontares found himself under virtual house arrest. Only with difficulty did he manage to find out news of the Sultan's death and report them to Constantinople.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PLP-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>Following the death of Mehmed, the hawkish party in the Byzantine court, headed by Manuel II's son and co-emperor John VIII, became ascendant, and Manuel II resigned effective control of the state to him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> Leontares released Mustafa and Junayd from their exile, and the Ottoman prince was promised imperial support against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murad_II">Murad II</ref> if he would surrender the strategically important fortress of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gelibolu">Gallipoli</ref>. With Byzantine support, Mustafa besieged and took Gallipoli, and managed to quickly establish his authority over the Ottomans' European domains. However, when Leontares was dispatched to demand Gallipoli from Mustafa, he was rebuffed. In the event, Mustafa was defeated by Murad in spring 1422, abandoned by his supporters, caught and executed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PLP-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>Leontares appears again in 1427, when he headed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_fleet">Byzantine fleet</ref> in its last naval victory, over the forces of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlo_I_Tocco">Carlo I Tocco</ref> (r. 1411–1429) at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_the_Echinades_(1427)">Battle of the Echinades</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PLP-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> He later retired to a monastery, under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monastic_name">monastic name</ref> <hi rend="bold">Daniel</hi>, and died probably on 6 September 1431. He was buried at the Petra Monastery in Constantinople.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PLP-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markos_Eugenikos">Markos Eugenikos</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gennadios_Scholarios">Gennadios Scholarios</ref> wrote funeral eulogies in his honour.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PLP-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref></p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Little is known about his family, except that he had brothers and was married, having one known son, John Laskaris Leontares.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PLP-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
