<text id="autogum_bio_doc773" title="Władysław of Bytom" shortTile="wladyslaw-bytom" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-05-14" dateModified="2018-02-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/W%C5%82adys%C5%82aw_of_Bytom" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Władysław of Bytom</head><p><hi rend="bold">Władysław of Bytom</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polish_language">Polish</ref>: <hi lang="pl" rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Władysław bytomski</hi></hi>; 1277/83 – around 8 September 1352), was a Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Koźle">Koźle</ref> during 1303-1334, Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bytom">Bytom</ref> from 1316, Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toszek">Toszek</ref> since 1329 and Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siewierz">Siewierz</ref> during 1328–1337.</p>
<p>He was the second son of Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casimir_of_Bytom">Casimir of Bytom</ref> by his wife Helena.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Władysław's first official appearance was in 1289 on occasion of the homage of his father to King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslaus_II_of_Bohemia">Wenceslaus II of Bohemia</ref>. In 1303 Władysław received from his father the town of Koźle.</p>
<figure><caption>Władysław of Bytom agrees not to support anyone against the Polish king, Casimir the Great, and in particular the Czech king. Parchment from February 1346</caption></figure>
<p>For unknown reasons, after his father's death in 1312 Władysław retained only Koźle, and the capital of the Duchy, Bytom was given to his younger brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siemowit_of_Bytom">Siemowit</ref>. Also, the two of Casimir I's sons who followed the church career also received further lands: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolesław_of_Toszek">Bolesław</ref> obtained <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toszek">Toszek</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mieszko_of_Bytom">Mieszko</ref> received <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siewierz">Siewierz</ref> (another brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_of_Bytom">George</ref> was the co-ruler of Władysław, and in fact exercised the whole government).</p>
<p>In 1316 Władysław assumed the government over <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bytom">Bytom</ref>. The circumstances around the removal of Siemowit are unknown, and the next notices about him are found only on 19 February 1327, where Władysław, Siemowit and George paid homage to the Bohemian King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Luxembourg">John of Luxembourg</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opawa">Opawa</ref>. One year before (1315) his brothers Bolesław and Mieszko chosen to live in Hungary and put their lands under the regency of Władysław.</p>
<p>In 1328, Mieszko formally resigned his domain over Siewierz on Władysław's behalf and one year later (1329), the death of Bolesław allowed the Duke of Koźle to reunited the whole paternal lands under his rule. However, this unity didn't remain for too long. The continuous financial problems forced Władysław to sold part of his inheritance. First, on 21 February 1334 he pledged the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Koźle">Koźle</ref> to his cousin Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leszek_of_Racibórz">Leszek of Racibórz</ref> by the amount of 4,000 pieces of silver with the compromise that, in the event of his death without issue, Koźle return to the Duchy of Bytom. Leszek died two years later, in 1336, and according to the terms of the pledge Koźle would return to Władysław, but soon after he was forced to give this lands to his eldest son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casimir_of_Koźle">Casimir</ref>, and after his death in 1347, the town was given to his younger brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolesław_of_Bytom">Bolesław</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1337 Władysław suffered further territorial losses. Firstly, on 8 May he sold Siewierz to Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casimir_I,_Duke_of_Cieszyn">Casimir I of Cieszyn</ref> and at the end of that year, he gave to his cousin Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolko_II_of_Opole">Bolko II of Opole</ref> the town of Toszek by the amount of 100 fines. Finally, around 1340 Władysław decided to give <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gliwice">Gliwice</ref> to his brother Siemowit as a separate Duchy.</p>
<p>Władysław's extremely cautious politics radically changed: in the course of Polish-Bohemian War during the years 1345-1348 he stood at the side of the Polish Kingdom, especially after the unexpected victories in the Battles of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pogoń">Pogoń</ref> (now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sosnowiec">Sosnowiec</ref>) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lelów">Lelów</ref>. In 1345 Władysław could repelled the attack of the Bohemian troops and on 15 February 1346  he signed a treaty with King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casimir_III_of_Poland">Casimir III of Poland</ref> under which the latter agreed to provide military help against Bohemia. Unfortunately, Poland wasn't able to use this great possibility of extending his influence on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upper_Silesia">Upper Silesia</ref>, and after 1348 Władysław was found again as an ally of Bohemia.</p>
<p>Władysław died before 8 September 1352 and it's unknown where he was buried. His lands were inherited by his only surviving son, Bolesław. Soon before his death, Władysław concluded an agreement with the Bohemian King allowing the succession of women in his Duchy, which happened in 1355 and caused the division of Bytom between the Dukes of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oleśnica">Oleśnica</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cieszyn">Cieszyn</ref>.</p>
<head>Marriages and Issue</head>
<p>By 21 September 1308, Władysław married firstly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beatrice_of_Brandenburg">Beatrix</ref> (b. ca. 1270 – d. bef. 26 April 1316), daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto_V,_Margrave_of_Brandenburg-Salzwedel">Otto V the Long</ref>, Margrave of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brandenburg">Brandenburg</ref>-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salzwedel">Salzwedel</ref> and widow of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolko_I_the_Strict">Bolko I the Strict</ref>, Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Świdnica">Świdnica</ref>. They had two children:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casimir_of_Koźle">Casimir</ref> (b. ca. 1312 – by 2 March 1347).</item>
<item>Euphemia (b. ca. 1313? – d. 3 January 1378), married by 2 March 1333 to Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konrad_I_of_Oleśnica">Konrad I of Oleśnica</ref>.</item></list>
<p>By 6 April 1328, Władysław married secondly Ludgarda (b. ca. 1310 - d. by 3 June 1362), daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_II,_Lord_of_Mecklenburg">Henry II the Lion</ref>, Prince of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mecklenburg">Mecklenburg</ref> and Lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burg_Stargard">Stargard</ref>. They had six children:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Agnes (b. ca. 1328 – d. 7 April 1362), Abbess of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trzebnica">Trzebnica</ref> (1348).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></item>
<item>Katharina (b. 1329/30 – d. aft. 29 May 1377), Abbess of Trzebnica (1362).</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolesław_of_Bytom">Bolesław</ref> (b. 1330 – d. by 4 October 1355).</item>
<item>Beatrix (b. ca. 1335 – 20 February 1364), married on 15 May 1357 to Count Berthold of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hardegg">Hardegg</ref>.</item>
<item>Elencza (d. 9 July 1339), a nun in Racibórz.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></item>
<item>A son (bef. 8 May 1337 – d. bef. 1355).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></item></list>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
