<text id="autogum_bio_doc035" title="Beranton Whisenant" shortTile="beranton-whisenant" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-06-05" dateModified="2018-12-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beranton_Whisenant" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Beranton Whisenant</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Beranton Whisenant Jr.</hi> (c. 1979 - May 24, 2017) was an American federal prosecutor.</p>
<head>Early life and career</head>
<p>Whisenant graduated from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fredric_G._Levin_College_of_Law">University of Florida Law School</ref> in 2004. He also studied shortly at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Cape_Town">University of Cape Town</ref>. He was  admitted to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florida_Bar">Florida Bar</ref> in 2004 and remained an active member. </p>
<p>For nine years he worked at a private law firm, Foley &amp; Mansfield Partner, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miami">Miami</ref>. At Foley &amp; Mansfield Partner he worked on cases of civil litigation, product liability, contracts, personal injury, wrongful death, and medical malpractice defense. His next job was as Assistant State Attorney in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacksonville,_Florida">Jacksonville, Florida</ref>, his hometown. He joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Attorney">United States Attorney</ref>'s Office in Miami in January 2017. </p>
<p>He lived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miramar,_Florida">Miramar, Florida</ref> a suburb of Miami. He was an active member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleventh_Judicial_Circuit_Court_of_Florida">Eleventh Judicial Circuit</ref> Professionalism Panel and Chair of The Florida Bar’s Eleventh Judicial Circuit Grievance Committee in Division ‘L. He was a member of the William Reece Smith Jr. Leadership Academy as well as a member of The Florida Bar’s Judicial Nominations Procedure committee and of the Florida Supreme Court’s Commission on Professionalism. He was a guest teacher at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Miami">University of Miami</ref> Paralegal Program and the University of Miami School of Law and Florida Coastal School of Law. Whisenant volunteered at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Habitat_for_Humanity">Habitat for Humanity</ref> and volunteered as a lawyer, for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pro_bono">pro bono</ref> legal work.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>U.S. Attorney</head>
<p>Beranton Whisenant worked in the U.S. Attorney's Office in Miami in its major crimes unit. The office prosecutes criminal and civil cases from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Pierce">Fort Pierce</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Key_West">Key West</ref>. He was reportedly working on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Travel_visa">visa</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Passport">passport</ref> fraud cases prior to his death.</p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>The body of Beranton Whisenant was found on a Florida beach with possible head trauma or possible head gunshot wound on May 25, 2017. Miranda Grossman, a Hollywood police spokeswoman, reported that his body was found at 6:30 am, by a passerby on the city's beach. He was wearing a dress shirt and black pants. Hollywood police detectives working to determine if the death was a homicide, suicide or something else. All of Whisenant personal effects were on his body, so robbery is not a motive. </p>
<p>Whisenant was 37 years old. He had been a U.S. Attorney for only five months. His memorial service was held on June 1, 2017 at Antioch Missionary Baptist Church in Miami.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Whisenant was survived by his three children, his wife, Ebony, a doctor who teaches at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florida_International_University">Florida International University</ref>’s medical school, and his parents, both Jacksonville physicians.</p>
<p>The U.S. attorney’s office and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal_Bureau_of_Investigation">Federal Bureau of Investigation</ref> (FBI) determined that his death had no connection to his employment as a prosecutor or his federal criminal cases, leaving the death investigation to the Hollywood Police Department. Hollywood police and the Broward medical examiner’s office declined numerous public records requests on Whisenant’s death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>The lack of information from authorities about his death opened the door for hypotheses.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
</text>
