<text id="autogum_bio_doc291" title="Black Caesar (pirate)" shortTile="black-caesar-pirate" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-05-23" dateModified="2019-10-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_Caesar_%28pirate%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Black Caesar (pirate)</head>For the 19th century Haitian pirate, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henri_Caesar">Henri Caesar</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Black Caesar</hi> (died 1718) was a legendary 18th-century African pirate. The lengends say that for nearly a decade, he raided shipping from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florida_Keys">Florida Keys</ref> and later served as one of Captain <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackbeard">Blackbeard</ref>'s, a.k.a. Edward Teach's, crewmen aboard the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_Anne's_Revenge">Queen Anne's Revenge</ref>.</hi> He was one of the surviving members of Blackbeard's crew following his death at the hands of Lieutenant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Maynard">Robert Maynard</ref> in 1718. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caesar's_Rock">Caesar's Rock</ref>, one of three islands located north of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Key_Largo">Key Largo</ref>, is named in his honor,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> and is the present-day site of his original headquarters. However, there is no historical evidence to support Caesar's existence. </p>
<head>Biography according to legend</head>
<p>Black Caesar, according to traditional accounts, was a prominent African tribal war chieftain. Widely known for his <hi rend="italic">"huge size, immense strength and keen intelligence,"</hi> he evaded capture from many different slave traders. Caesar was finally captured when he and twenty of his warriors were lured onto a ship by a slave trader. Showing him a watch, the trader promised to show him and his warriors more objects, which were <hi rend="italic">"too heavy and too numerous to bring on shore"</hi> if they came aboard his ship. He enticed them to stay with food, musical instruments, silk scarves and jewels, however he had his men raise anchor and slowly sail away. When Caesar discovered what was happening, he and his men attempted to charge their captors but were driven back by the well-armed sailors using swords and pistols. Although it took a considerable length of time for him and his warriors to accept their captivity, he was eventually befriended by a sailor who was the only man Black Caesar would accept food and water from.</p>
<p>As they neared the coast of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florida">Florida</ref>, the sudden appearance of a hurricane threatened to destroy the ship on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florida_Reef">Florida Reefs</ref>. Recognizing the ship's imminent destruction, the sailor snuck below decks and freed Caesar. The two then forced the captain and crew into a corner, most likely at gunpoint, and boarded one of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Longboat">longboats</ref> with ammunition and other supplies. The wind and waves pushed them to shore where they waited out the storm, apparently the only survivors of the doomed ship.</p>
<p>They soon began using the lifeboat to lure passing ships which stopped to give assistance. While posing as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shipwreck">shipwrecked</ref> sailors, they would sail out to the vessel offering to take them aboard. Once they were close to the vessel, they brought out their guns and demanded supplies and ammunition, threatening to sink the ship if they were refused. He and the sailor continued this ploy for a number of years and amassed a sizable amount of treasure which was buried on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elliott_Key">Elliott Key</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> However, he and the sailor had a falling out over a young woman the mate had brought back from one of the ships they had looted. Fighting over her, Caesar killed his longtime friend in a duel and took the woman for his own.</p>
<p>He began taking on more pirates over time and soon was able to attack ships on the open sea. He and his crew were often able to avoid capture by running into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caesar_Creek_(Florida)">Caesar Creek</ref> and other inlets between Elliot and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Rhodes_Key">Old Rhodes Key</ref> and onto the mangrove islands. Using a metal ring embedded in a rock, they ran a strong rope through the ring, heel the boat over, and hide their boat in the water until the patrol ship or some other danger went away. They might also lower the mast and sink the ship in shallow water, later cutting the rope or pumping out the water to raise the boat and continue raiding. It is thought that he and his men buried 26 bars of silver on the island, although no treasure has ever been recovered from the island.</p>
<p>He apparently had a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harem">harem</ref> on his island, having at least 100 women seized from passing ships, as well as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internment">prison camp</ref> which he kept prisoners in stone huts hoping to ransom them. When leaving the island to go on raids, he left no provisions for these prisoners and many eventually starved to death. A few children reportedly escaped captivity, subsisting on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berries">berries</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shellfish">shellfish</ref>, and formed their own language and customs. This society of lost children gave rise to native superstition that the island is haunted.</p>
<p>During the early 18th century, Caesar left <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Biscayne_Bay">Biscayne Bay</ref> to join <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackbeard">Blackbeard</ref> in raiding American shipping in the Mid-Atlantic serving as a lieutenant on his flagship <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_Anne's_Revenge">Queen Anne's Revenge</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-D._Moore._1997_pp._31-3">[3]</ref>  In 1718, after Blackbeard's death battling with Lieutenant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Maynard">Robert Maynard</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ocracoke_Island">Ocracoke Island</ref>, he attempted to set off the powder magazine as per Blackbeard's instructions. However, Caesar was stopped by one of the captives who tackled him as he prepared to light a trail of gunpowder leading to the magazine. He struggled with the man below decks until several of Maynard's sailors were able to restrain him. Taken prisoner by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colony_of_Virginia">Virginian colonial</ref> authorities, he was convicted of piracy and hanged in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Williamsburg,_Virginia">Williamsburg, Virginia</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>In popular culture</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>The descendants of Caesar and his crew are depicted in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_Payson_Terhune">Albert Payson Terhune</ref>'s 1922 novel <hi rend="italic">Black Caesar's Clan</hi> which describes people living near Caesar's Creek who chase off treasure hunters looking for Caesar's lost fortune.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jimmy_Akingbola">Jimmy Akingbola</ref> played Black Caesar in the 2005 mini series <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackbeard_(2005_film)">Blackbeard: Terror at Sea</ref></hi>.</item>
<item>In the 2006 film <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackbeard_(2006_film)">Blackbeard</ref></hi>, Black Caesar is depicted by Christopher Clyde-Green as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boatswain">Boatswain</ref> on Blackbeard's ship.</item></list>
<head>See also</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maroon_(people)">Maroon (people)</ref></item></list>
<head>References</head>
<head>Further reading</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Love, Dean. "Pirates and Legends". <hi rend="italic">Florida Keys Magazine</hi>. (1st quarter, 1981): 10-14.</item>
<item>True, David O. "Pirates and Treasure Trove of South Florida". <hi rend="italic">Tequesta: The Journal of the Historical Association of Southern Florida</hi> (1947): 3-13.</item>
<item>Woodman, Jim. <hi rend="italic">The Book of Key Biscayne</hi>. Miami: Miami Post, 1961.</item></list>
</text>
