<text id="autogum_bio_doc744" title="Roger Lestrange" shortTile="roger-lestrange" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-05-15" dateModified="2019-11-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Lestrange" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Roger Lestrange</head>For the 17th-century pamphleteer, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_L'Estrange">Roger L'Estrange</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Roger Lestrange</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Roger Strange</hi> (died 31 July 1311) was an English knight, commander and royal advisor.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<head>Role in Wales</head>
<p>The second son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Lestrange_(died_1269)">John Lestrange</ref> and his wife Lucy, daughter of Robert of Tregoz, he was given land taken by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_III_of_England">Henry III of England</ref> from rebels in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Barons'_War">Second Barons' War</ref>. From May 1270 to October 1274 he was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheriff_of_Yorkshire">Sheriff of Yorkshire</ref>, but the focus of his activities was in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheshire">Cheshire</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shropshire">Shropshire</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Staffordshire">Staffordshire</ref>. Due to his local knowledge of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Welsh_Marches">Welsh Marches</ref> he was an important advisor to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_I_of_England">Edward I of England</ref> during his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conquest_of_Wales_by_Edward_I">conquest of Wales</ref>. During Edward's first campaign in 1277 he was put in charge of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oswestry_Castle">Oswestry Castle</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dinas_Bran">Dinas Bran</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Builth_Castle">Builth</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montgomery_Castle">Montgomery Castle</ref> - the Welsh inhabitants living near these castles regarded him as a tyrant.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Roger played a major part in the 1282-83 campaign and on 30 October 1282 succeeded <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Mortimer,_1st_Baron_Mortimer">Roger Mortimer, 1st Baron Mortimer</ref> as the English commander in mid-Wales. On 11 December he fought at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Orewin_Bridge">battle of Orewin Bridge</ref>, in which <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llywelyn_ap_Gruffudd">Llywelyn ap Gruffydd</ref> was killed - Lestrange wrote the letter informing Edward of his death. From 1283 he took part in the siege and capture of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castell_y_Bere">Castell y Bere</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref>  In 1284 he took part in Edward's castle-building campaign in north Wales<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> In 1287 he took part in the suppression of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhys_ap_Maredudd">Rhys ap Maredudd</ref>'s revolt and the siege of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dryslwyn_Castle">Dryslwyn Castle</ref>, as well as the suppression of the 1294 Welsh uprising under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madog_ap_Llywelyn">Madog ap Llywelyn</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anglo-French_War_(1294–1303)">1295 Gascogny and 1297 Flanders campaigns</ref>. On 21 October 1283 he was transferred to the role of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justiciar#England">justiciar</ref> of the "Forest south of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/River_Trent">Trent</ref>", which he held until 12 February 1297.</p>
<head>Marriages</head>
<p>Roger's first marriage was to Maud, widow of Roger II de Mowbray, 6th Baron Mowbray (died 1266), younger brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_de_Mowbray">William de Mowbray</ref>. After her death, he was allowed to hold her lands and property until her children came of age in 1278. On the death of his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamo_le_Strange">Hamo le Strange</ref> without issue in 1272 or 1273 Roger inherited <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ellesmere,_Shropshire">Ellesmere, Shropshire</ref> and other lands. His second wife Eleanor died in 1280 and in 1307 he married his third wife, another Maud.</p>
<head>Later life</head>
<p>In 1291 he was sent as an envoy to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Nicolas_IV">pope Nicolas IV</ref>, only returning in 1292. He was summoned to several meetings of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Parliament">parliament</ref> and the royal counsel and in 1295 he was given the title <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_Strange">Baron Strange</ref>. Despite his contribution to the conquest of Wales, he did not have a fiefdom or lordship there, although he had hoped to rule <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maelor_Saesneg">Maelor Saesneg</ref> in north Wales.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> He served in the royal household as a knight for many years but he was already recorded as being sick in 1298 - Edward decreed in 1306 that he was so indebted to him for his service that he would attend his funeral. He undertook several further smaller missions for the king and was one of the signatories of the barons' letter to the pope in 1301. He died without surviving issue in 1311 after a long illness.</p>
</text>
