<text id="autogum_bio_doc565" title="John Gunthorpe" shortTile="john-gunthorpe" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-07-16" dateModified="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Gunthorpe" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Gunthorpe</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">John Gunthorpe</hi> (died 1498) was an English administrator, Keeper of the Privy Seal and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean_of_Wells">Dean of Wells</ref>.</p>
<head>Education and career</head>
<p>Gunthorpe was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Student">student</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cambridge_University">Cambridge University</ref> and had already entered into clergyship and received holy orders. By private appointment he served as a secretary to Queen Elizabeth.  By 1452 he was Master of Arts at Cambridge University and served as a junior proctor in 1454-5.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> Gunthorpe traveled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italy">Italy</ref> and was in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferrara">Ferrara</ref> in August 1460. He had been attending the lectures of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guarino_da_Verona">Guarino da Verona</ref> on rhetoric at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferrara">Ferrara</ref>.  His teacher Guarino died at the end of 1460 and this may be why Gunthorpe moved on.  In January 1462 Gunthorpe was formally taken into papal service.  Pope <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pius_II">Pius II</ref> examined Gunthorpe for fitness, and appointed him as a papal chaplain and minor penitentiary in St Peter's Basilica and in the Papal Curia.  From 1460-1465, Gunthorpe went through a period of post-graduate study in Italy, where he perfected his Latin rhetorical style.  He also learned <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greece">Greek</ref> and presumably Italian, and gained experience in the international arena of the papal court.</p>
<head>Service under the King</head>
<p>Gunthorpe returned to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/England">England</ref> in 1465 and became intimately integrated into the religious, diplomatic, financial, and political life of the court and government of Edward IV. Gunthorpe's involvement in Anglo-Castilian diplomacy concluded in 1470 when he was one of the ambassadors commissioned on 14 March by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_Edward_IV">King Edward IV</ref> to embark upon an ultimately fruitless effort to persuade Enrique IV against the repudiation of the treaty between their kingdoms.  Gunthorpe was in the royal household as a king's chaplain by the summer of 1466.</p>
<head>1468-1476</head>
<p>In 1468, he returned to Cambridge University and was granted a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bachelor's_degree">baccalaureate</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theology">theology</ref>. On 9 December 1468, Gunthorpe became the king's almoner, the person who had charge of the king's charities from gifts of money to the distribution of surplus food from the king's table; the office can be traced back at least to the twelfth century. John Gunthorpe was the first person on record to have been called ‘King's High Almoner’. He was also a warden.</p>
<p>In 1472, Gunthorpe became a monk at St. Stephen's chapel and remained a monk of St. Stephen's for the rest of his life. He was also a monk of many other chapels.  However, even though he was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monk">monk</ref> at all of these chapels, his place of residence was with the king.  In 1476 he became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean_of_the_Chapel_Royal">dean of the king's household chapel</ref>, with supervisory authority over every aspect of the chapel's function.</p>
<head>Later life</head>
<p>On 10 November 1481 a group of nine men, among whom Gunthorpe was named first, obtained a royal licence to found and endow a guild in the parish church of St Mary in North Somercotes, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lincolnshire">Lincolnshire</ref>. On 9 April 1483, Gunthorpe's patron and benefactor King Edward IV died at Westminster Palace. On 10 May Gunthorpe was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Privy_Seal">Keeper of the Privy Seal</ref> under the authority of Richard of Gloucester.  Richard had formally been named protector two days before and as King Richard III he reappointed Gunthorpe on 27 June The appointment was reiterated on 6 July, the day of Richard's magnificent coronation ceremony in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westminster_Abbey">Westminster Abbey</ref>. John was the only keeper of the Privy seal to serve Richard III.  He was not seen as a very smart choice of keeper since he was the former secretary of Queen Elizabeth, and Richard was fearful of a Woodville faction in 1483.</p>
<p>While serving as Keeper of the Privy Seal, Gunthorpe served his king in Anglo-Scottish diplomacy by truce-making in Scotland, and extension of a truce with Francis II, Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brittany">Brittany</ref>; he also helped work out a truce with the Tudor family in Brittany in October 1483, which was extended to 1492</p>
<head>Why picked?</head>
<p>Gunthorpe's geographical origins might have recommended him to Richard in 1483 and Gunthorpe was a learned man.  But it is the perennial enigma of Richard III that brings attention to Gunthorpe.  In 1485, Richard gave Gunthorpe a present - the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swan">swans</ref> in the waters of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Somerset">Somerset</ref>, the birds having a long association with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_family">royalty</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chivalry">chivalry</ref>.</p>
<head>Tudor Authority</head>
<p>Richard III died on 22 August 1485 and Gunthorpe went to service under Henry Tudor - <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VII_of_England">Henry VII</ref>. Also soon after Richard III died Gunthorpe became the resident <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean_of_Wells">Dean of Wells</ref>.  As the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean_of_Wells">Dean of Wells</ref>, Gunthorpe's interests extended into the judicial sphere though the court Christian within his authority.</p>
<p>He presided over many cases including the case of John Pope.</p>
<head>Last Years and Death</head>
<p>In the last year of his life, Gunthorpe found himself playing host to the king.  Gunthorpe was a man of learning, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhetorician">rhetorician</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linguist">linguist</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Priest">priest</ref> and theologian, and an experienced <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diplomat">diplomat</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secretary">secretary</ref>, but is not survived by substantial literary remains.
On 5 June 1498, John Gunthorpe died.  He is buried in St Katherine's Chapel, Wells Cathedral.</p>
<p>He answered the call of three kings to a wide variety of royal service, and moved smoothly in the highest circles of ecclesiastical and secular authority.
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
</text>
