<text id="autogum_bio_doc759" title="Raymond Martini" shortTile="raymond-martini" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-11-16" dateModified="2019-05-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raymond_Martini" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Raymond Martini</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Raymond Martini</hi>, or <hi rend="bold">Ramon Martí</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> was a 13th-century <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catalan_people">Catalan</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominican_Order">Dominican</ref> friar and theologian. He is remembered for his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polemic">polemic</ref> work <hi rend="italic">Pugio Fidei</hi> (c. 1270). In 1250 he was one of eight friars appointed to make a study of oriental languages with the purpose of carrying on a mission to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jews">Jews</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moors">Moors</ref>. He worked in Spain as a missionary, and also for a short time in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tunis">Tunis</ref>. A document bearing his signature and dated July 1284 shows that he was at that time still living.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>He was born in the first half of the 13th century at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subirats">Subirats</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catalonia">Catalonia</ref>; and died after 1284. It is speculated that he could have been of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jews">Jewish</ref> origin. In 1250 he was selected by the provincial chapter, sitting in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toledo,_Spain">Toledo</ref>, to study Oriental languages at a Dominican school which had been founded for the express purpose of preparing its pupils to engage in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polemics">polemics</ref> against Jews and Moors. Subsequently he lived for a long time in a monastery at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barcelona">Barcelona</ref>.</p>
<head>Censorship of the Talmud</head>
<p>In March 1264, he was commissioned, with the Bishop of Barcelona, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raymond_of_Penyafort">Raymond of Penyafort</ref>, and two other Dominicans, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arnau_de_Segarra">Arnau de Segarra</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pere_Gener">Pere Gener</ref>, to examine the Hebrew manuscripts and books which the Jews, by order of the king, were to submit to them, and to cancel passages deemed offensive to the Christian religion. This is the first instance of Dominican <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Censorship">censorship</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talmud">Talmud</ref> in Spain.</p>
<p>Their report was not severe, however, since Martí declared that many passages were confirmatory of the truth of Christianity, and that the Talmud should not be burned entirely (<hi rend="italic">Pugio Fidei</hi>, ii.14, §8).</p>
<head>Polemic literature</head>
<p>Martí was the author of two anti-Jewish books, one of which, the <hi rend="italic">Capistrum Judaeorum</hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> first published in 1990. His refutation of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Koran">Koran</ref> is lost.</p>
<p>There is at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bologna">Bologna</ref> a manuscript of his <hi rend="italic">Capistrum Judaeorum</hi>, aimed at the errors of the Jews; and at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tortosa">Tortosa</ref> a manuscript containing <hi rend="italic">Explanatio <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apostles'_Creed">simboli apostolorum</ref> ad institutionem fidelium</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>  which has a marginal note that it was edited "<hi rend="italic">a fratre Ro Martini de ordine predicatorum</hi>".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Martí's work was for a long time the chief source for Dominican polemics.</p>
<head>The <hi rend="italic">Pugio Fidei</hi></head>
<p>His chief work, the <hi rend="italic">Pugio Fidei</hi>, was lost for a long time, but was finally brought to light by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justus_Scaliger">Justus Scaliger</ref>, and edited by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_de_Voisin">Joseph de Voisin</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sorbonne">Sorbonne</ref> (d. 1685), with many notes, under the title <hi rend="italic">Pugio Fidei Raymundi Martini Ordinis Prædicatorum Adversus Mauros et Judæos</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> (Paris, 1651).</p>
<p>The work treats of God's omniscience, the Creation, immortality, and the resurrection of the dead, and attempts to show the falsity of the Jewish religion; the latter part of the work is valuable on account of its extracts from the Talmud, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Midrash">Midrash</ref>, and other sources.</p>
<p>This work was used by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porchetus_de_Salvaticis">Porchetus de Salvaticis</ref> at the beginning of the 14th century in his <hi rend="italic">Victoria Porcheti adversus impios Hebreos</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> (printed 1520), by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hieronymus_de_Sancta_Fide">Hieronymus de Sancta Fide</ref> in his <hi rend="italic">Hebraeomastix</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> and elsewhere, and was plagiarized by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Petrus_Galatinus">Petrus Galatinus</ref>.</p>
<p>About 1620 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/François_Bosquet">François Bosquet</ref> discovered in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collegium_Fuxense">Collegium Fuxense</ref> (the Collège de Foix in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toulouse">Toulouse</ref>) a manuscript of the <hi rend="italic">Pugio</hi>, and it was from this and three other manuscripts that de Voisin edited the work. Better known than this edition is its reprint by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J._B._Carpzov">J. B. Carpzov</ref> (Leipzig and Frankfurt, 1687), with the anti-Jewish preface <hi rend="italic">Introduction in Theologiam Judaicam</hi>.</p>
<head>Knowledge of Hebrew literature</head>
<p>Martí has been accused of forgery because of his quotations from <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genesis_Rabbah">Genesis Rabbah</ref>,</hi> which were not otherwise known; but <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leopold_Zunz">Leopold Zunz</ref> defends him against this charge (<hi rend="italic">Gottesdienstliche Vorträge der Juden</hi> p.300).</p>
<p>Martí was widely read in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hebrew_literature">Hebrew literature</ref>, quoting not only from Talmudic and Midrashic works, but from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rashi">Rashi</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abraham_ibn_Ezra">Abraham ibn Ezra</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maimonides">Maimonides</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ḳimḥi">Ḳimḥi</ref>. His fundamental views, which he attempts to substantiate by his citations, are that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus">Jesus</ref> is announced in rabbinical literature as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Messiah">Messiah</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Son_of_God">Son of God</ref>; that the Jewish laws, although revealed by God, are abrogated by the advent of the Messiah; and that the Talmudists corrupted the text of the Bible, as is indicated by the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiqqun_soferim">tikkune soferim</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>Another prominent aspect of his contribution was the enumeration and rejection of the "Tikkun <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sofer">Sopherim</ref>", alleged corrections made by Jewish scribes on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bible">Biblical</ref> text. Martí directly and publicly charged these emendations upon the Hebrew scribes as "willful corruptions and perversions introduced by them into the sacred text."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Jewish Encyclopedia bibliography</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antoine_Touron">Antoine Touron</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Histoire des Hommes Illustres de l'Ordre de St. Dominique,</hi> i.489-504, (Paris, 1743)</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacob_Quétif">Jacob Quétif</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J._Echard">J. Echard</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Scriptores Ordinis Prædicatorum,</hi> i.396-398, ib. (1719)</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Christoph_Wolf">Johann Christoph Wolf</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Hebræa,</hi> i.1016-1018, iii.989-991;</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Jakob_Herzog">Johann Jakob Herzog</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G.L._Plitt">G.L. Plitt</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Real-Encyklopädie für protestantische Theologie und Kirche</hi>;</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heinrich_Graetz">Heinrich Graetz</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte,</hi> vii.124, 150.</item></list>
<head>Further bibliography</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Philippe Bobichon, « Ramón Martí (XIIIe siècle): un ‘Maître orientaliste’ ?, dans: Portraits de Maîtres offerts à Olga Weijers, Porto 2012, p. 405-414.</item>
<item>Philippe Bobichon, « Quotations, Translations, and Uses of Jewish Texts in Ramon Martí, s <hi rend="italic">Pugio Fidei</hi> », dans <hi rend="italic">The Late Medieval Hebrew Book in the Western Mediterranean. Hebrew Manuscripts and Incunabula in Context</hi>, Brill, <hi rend="bold">2015</hi>, p.266-293.</item>
<item>Philippe Bobichon, « La ‘bibliothèque’ de Raymond Martin au couvent Sainte-Catherine de Barcelone: sources antiques et chrétiennes du <hi rend="italic">Pugio fidei</hi> (ca 1278) », in <hi rend="italic">Entre stabilité et itinérance. Livres et culture des ordres mendiants, XIIIe-XVe siècle</hi>, Turnhout <hi rend="bold">2014</hi>, p. 329-366.</item>
<item>Philippe Bobichon,« [Ramon Martí, Pugio fidei] Le manuscrit Latin 1405 de la Bibliothèque Sainte-Geneviève (Paris), autographe et œuvre d’un converti », dans Görge K. Hasselhoff et Alexander Fidora (éd), Ramon Martí’s Pugio Fidei. Studies and Texts, volume introductif à l’édition complète du Pugio fidei, Santa Coloma de Queralt: Obrador Edendum [Exemplaria Scholastica, 8], 2017, p. 39-101.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Harvey">Richard Harvey</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Raymundus Martini and the Pugio Fidei: The Life and Work of a Medieval Controversialist (London, 1991, available at lulu.com/content/1385305)</hi>;</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ambrose_of_Altramum">Ambrose of Altramum</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Dominicana,</hi> ed. Rocaberti, pp.58, 449-456, Rome, 1677</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J._G._Walch">J. G. Walch</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca theologica selecta,</hi> i.609, (Jena, 1757)</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solomon_Marcus_Schiller-Szinessy">Solomon Marcus Schiller-Szinessy</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Journal of Philology,</hi> xvi (1887), 131-152</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L._Zunz">L. Zunz</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Die Gottesdienstlichen Vorträge der Juden,</hi> pp.287–293, Berlin, 1832</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E._B._Pusey">E. B. Pusey</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Fifty-Third Chapter of Isaiah,</hi> vol. ii, Oxford, 1877</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adolf_Neubauer">Adolf Neubauer</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Book of Tobit,</hi> pp. vii-ix, xx-xxv, ib. 1878</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A._Epstein">A. Epstein</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Magazin für Wissenschaft des Judenthums,</hi> 1888, pp.65–99,</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I._Levi">I. Levi</ref>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revue_des_Études_Juives">Revue des Études Juives</ref>,</hi> xvii (1888), 313-317.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eusebi_Colomer_i_Pous">Eusebi Colomer i Pous</ref>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_pensament_als_Països_Catalans_durant_l’Edat_Mitjana_i_el_Renaixement">El pensament als Països Catalans durant l’Edat Mitjana i el Renaixement</ref>,</hi> (1997), p.194.</item></list>
</text>
