<text id="autogum_bio_doc558" title="Thomas Moyle" shortTile="thomas-moyle" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-08" dateModified="2019-11-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Moyle" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Thomas Moyle</head>
For the 14th century English parliamentarian, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lostwithiel_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Lostwithiel (UK Parliament constituency)</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Sir Thomas Moyle</hi> (born 1488, died 2 October 1560, probably at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastwell,_Kent">Eastwell, Kent</ref>) was a commissioner for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VIII_of_England">Henry VIII</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dissolution_of_the_monasteries">dissolution of the monasteries</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Speaker_of_the_British_House_of_Commons">speaker</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Commons_of_the_United_Kingdom">House of Commons</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_England">Parliament of England</ref> from  1542 to 1544.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was the fourth son of John Moyle (died 1495, born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cornwall">Cornwall</ref>, MP for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodmin_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Bodmin</ref> and Kentish, Cornish and Devon landowner) and Anne Darcy (his second wife, one of Sir Robert Darcy's daughters and heirs, by his wife Elizabeth Tyrrell).
By 1528, Thomas had followed his father's example and married an heiress, Katherine Jordeyne, one of the daughters of Edward Jordeyne (died 1514), a leading goldsmith at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheapside">Cheapside</ref> with a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manorialism">manor</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raynham,_Norfolk">Raynham</ref> and employed at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_mint">mint</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tower_of_London">Tower of London</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHyde2004-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>He entered politics in 1542 as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member_of_Parliament">Member of Parliament</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peterborough_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Peterborough</ref> and was elected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Speaker_of_the_House_of_Commons_(United_Kingdom)">Speaker of the House</ref>.
He subsequently represented <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rochester_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Rochester</ref> four times from 1545 to 1553 and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King's_Lynn_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">King's Lynn</ref> in November 1554.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In 1537, he returned to England from Ireland, and soon made himself conspicuous as a zealous servant of Henry, rather after the manner of Audley.
He enlarged his estates by securing monastic property, and soon became a rich and prominent official.
In 1539, he was with Layton and Pollard in the west, and signed with them the letters from Glastonbury showing that they were trying to find hidden property in the abbey, and to collect evidence against Whiting, the abbot.
The same year, he was one of those appointed to receive <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_of_Cleves">Anne of Cleves</ref> on her arrival. Moyle was returned member for the county of Kent in 1542, and chosen speaker of the House of Commons.
He addressed the king in an extraordinarily adulatory speech, but his tenure of office was made notable by the fact that he was said to be the first speaker who claimed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliamentary_privilege">privilege of freedom of speech</ref>.
The exact wording of his request is, however, uncertain.
During his term of office the subject became prominent owing to Ferrar's case, in which Henry conciliated the commons.
The king doubtless was glad to have a trusty servant in the chair, as during this session <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_Howard">Catherine Howard</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_Rochford">Lady Rochford</ref> were condemned.
He was returned for Rochester in 1544, and in 1545 he was a commissioner for visiting Eastridge Hospital, Wiltshire.
It is difficult to know the attitude he took up under Mary, but it seems probable that he supported her, and was, like many of Henry's followers, a Protestant only in a legal sense.
On 20 September 1553, and in March 1554, he was returned for Rochester, and on 20 Dec. 1554 was elected for both Chippenham and King's Lynn.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEArchbold1894-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Moyle employed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Plantagenet_(Richard_of_Eastwell)">Richard Plantagenet</ref> to build <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastwell_Place">Eastwell Place</ref> and (according to family tradition recorded around 1720 in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Desiderata_Curiosa">Desiderata Curiosa</ref></hi>) listened to his claims to be son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_III_of_England">Richard III</ref> and allowed him to live in the grounds until his death in 1550. Moyle was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_Sheriff_of_Kent">High Sheriff of Kent</ref> for 1556–57.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHyde2004-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>Moyle made his will on 1 August 1560, leaving his wife property at Clerkenwell and his grandchildren various houses in Newgate.  Also leaving some land and an endowment to Eastwell parish for an almshouse, he split the remainder of his estates (in Kent, Surrey, Middlesex, Devon, and Somerset) between his daughter Amy's widower Thomas Kempe and his daughter Katherine.  He also left £6 13s. 4d. to Clement Norton, a former vicar of Faversham who had, like Moyle, joined in the 1543 anti-evangelical <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prebendaries'_plot">prebendaries' plot</ref> to overthrow <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Cranmer">Thomas Cranmer</ref> as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_Canterbury">Archbishop of Canterbury</ref>.</p>
</text>
