<text id="autogum_bio_doc196" title="Boaz Mahune" shortTile="boaz-mahune" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-11-11" dateModified="2019-04-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boaz_Mahune" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Boaz Mahune</head>
<figure><caption>Lahainaluna Mission Seminary, c. 1840s.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Boaz Mahune</hi> (died 1847) was a 19th-century politician and civil servant of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Hawaii">Kingdom of Hawaii</ref>. He helped contribute to the writing of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1840_Constitution_of_the_Kingdom_of_Hawaii">1840 Constitution of the Kingdom of Hawaii</ref> and was the author of its preamble the <hi rend="italic">He Olelo Hoakaka</hi>, or the Declaration of Rights of 1839.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Born in the early 1800s, Mahune was a member of the lesser strata of Hawaiian nobility, subordinate to the high chiefs or <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aliʻi">aliʻi</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEOsorio200215-1">[1]</ref> He was a cousin of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Kanoa">Paul Kanoa</ref>, who served as Governor of Kauai from 1846 to 1877.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHawaiian_Historical_Society194367-68-2">[2]</ref> He adopted the name "Boaz" from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boaz">Biblical figure</ref> after his conversion to Christianity. It was often spelled as Boas.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEOsorio200215-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKamakau1992370-3">[3]</ref>
He was a member of the first class of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lahainaluna_Seminary">Lahainaluna Seminary</ref> under the school's first principal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lorrin_Andrews">Lorrin Andrews</ref>. His classmates included historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Malo">David Malo</ref>, royal advisor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonah_Kapena">Jonah Kapena</ref>, and royal diplomat <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haalilio">Timothy Haʻalilio</ref>. Graduating in 1835, he was considered one of the most brilliant scholars in the school and was one of the ten chosen to remain as monitors, teachers in the children's school and assistants in translating.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHawaiian_Historical_Society194367-68-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Along with a few of his fellow graduates from Lahainaluna, he assisted King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamehameha_III">Kamehameha III</ref> and his chiefs in the writing of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1840_Constitution_of_the_Kingdom_of_Hawaii">Hawaii's first constitution</ref>. Mahune became one of the secretaries and advisors to the King. He was responsible for writing the first draft of the Declaration of Rights of 1839, originally written in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawaiian_language">Hawaiian language</ref>. After several round of changes by the king and his councilors, it was published June 7, 1839. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHawaii18424-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHawaiian_Historical_Society194367-68-2">[2]</ref>
Considered Hawaii's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magna_Carta">Magna Carta</ref>, it laid down the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_and_legal_rights">inalienable rights</ref> of the people, the principles of equality of between the <hi rend="italic">makaʻāinana</hi> (commoner) and the <hi rend="italic">aliʻi</hi> (chiefs) and the role of the government and law in the kingdom.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKuykendall1965159-161-5">[5]</ref>
Along with the Declaration of Rights, many of the laws codes within the constitution were of Mahune's authorship. Mahune wrote most of the laws concerning taxation.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHawaii18424-4">[4]</ref> King Kamehameha III specifically directed him to conform them to the principles of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Political_economy">political economy</ref> that he learned in Lahainaluna.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHawaiian_Historical_Society194367-68-2">[2]</ref>
The bulk of Mahune's work and ideas were influenced by his missionary education at Lahainaluna and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Declaration_of_Independence">United States Declaration of Independence</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBenhamHeck199849-6">[6]</ref> although recently doubts have been cast upon the actual authorship of the Declaration and the majority of the Constitution. Hawaiian historian Jon Kamakawiwoʻole Osorio believe that it was American missionary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Richards_(Hawaii)">William Richards</ref>, who was mainly responsible and that Mahune and Jonah Kapena, were only assistants to the creation of the Declaration of Rights.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEOsorio200216-17,_24-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Mahune served as the manager for the King's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sugarcane">sugarcane</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sugar_plantations_in_Hawaii">plantation</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wailuku">Wailuku</ref> on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maui">Maui</ref>, which proved to be unsuccessful.  Serving as a judge in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lahaina">Lahaina</ref> for a period of time, he returned to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honolulu">Honolulu</ref> in 1846, where he went back to working for the government as a civil servant. In March 1847, Mahune died after a distressing and painful illness of several months. He died without writing a will; his landholdings had been quite extensive including properties in each of the main islands showing his rank and favor in the royal court.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHawaiian_Historical_Society194367-68-2">[2]</ref></p>
</text>
