<text id="autogum_bio_doc086" title="Kofi Boahene" shortTile="kofi-boahene" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-14" dateModified="2018-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kofi_Boahene" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kofi Boahene</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kofi Owusu Boahene</hi> is a Ghanaian-born American physician, writer, researcher, and academic.</p>
<p>He is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Professor">professor</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plastic_surgery">facial plastic</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reconstructive_surgery">reconstructive surgery</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johns_Hopkins_University_School_of_Medicine">Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</ref> and a facial plastic surgeon in Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johns_Hopkins_Hospital">Johns Hopkins Hospital</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baltimore">Baltimore</ref>, Maryland. As a facial plastic surgeon, Boahene specializes solely in plastic surgery of the face, head and neck.</p>
<head>Early years</head>
<p>Boahene, who is the first born of eight children grew up on Binton Street, a less-affluent neighborhood in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Kaneshie">North Kaneshie</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accra">Accra</ref>. His parents, Pastor and Mrs. James Owusu, operated a pharmacy store before becoming full-time missionaries in the early 1980s. He attended primary school at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bubuashie">Bubuashie</ref>, Datus Preparatory School and his secondary school education at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prempeh_College">Prempeh College</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kumasi">Kumasi</ref>.</p>
<head>Education</head>
<p>In 1991, after his A-Level exams and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Service">National Service</ref> with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghana_Meteorological_Agency">Ghana Meteorological Agency</ref>, he traveled to Russia to pursue training in veterinary medicine. He became fluent in the Russian language at a time where the former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soviet_Union">Soviet Union</ref> was opening its doors to the outside world. Due to political reasons in the Soviet Union, and other factors, Boahene moved to the United States.</p>
<p>Boahene received his medical degree from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meharry_Medical_College">Meharry Medical College</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nashville,_Tennessee">Nashville, Tennessee</ref>, graduating with the highest honors in his class. He completed his residency in Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mayo_Clinic">Mayo Clinic</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rochester,_Minnesota">Rochester, Minnesota</ref>, where he trained under leading facial plastic surgeons and rhinologists.</p>
<p>Boahene completed a highly specialized fellowship training in facial plastic and reconstructive surgery under the mentorship of one of facial plastic surgeon Dr. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Hilger">Peter Hilger</ref>. His training included cosmetic surgery of the face, use on minimally invasive techniques for facial rejuvenation, microvascular surgery, craniofacial surgery, and skull-base surgery in both children and adults. Because of his particular interest in craniofacial surgery, Boahene spent some time in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australia_Craniofacial_Center">Australia Craniofacial Center</ref>, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adelaide">Adelaide</ref>, directed by Professor David David.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Boahene is an assistant professor of facial plastic and reconstructive surgery at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johns_Hopkins_University_School_of_Medicine">Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</ref>, Department of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otolaryngology">Otolaryngology</ref>, Head, and Neck Surgery in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baltimore">Baltimore</ref>, Maryland. He trains both surgical residents and Fellows the art and craft of facial plastic and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reconstructive_surgery">reconstructive surgery</ref>. He is an oral board examiner for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Board_of_Facial_Plastic_Surgery">American Board of Facial Plastic Surgery</ref> that certifies surgeons who specialize in facial plastic surgery. He also writes questions for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Board_of_Otolaryngology_Head_and_Neck_Surgery">American Board of Otolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery</ref>.</p>
<p>For his expertise, Boahene has been an invited speaker at both national and international conferences in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panama">Panama</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peru">Peru</ref>, Germany, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghana">Ghana</ref>, United States, Canada and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caribbean_Islands">Caribbean Islands</ref>.</p>
<p>He has authored in several peer-reviewed journals, major text books in facial plastic surgery and is a regular reviewer for the archives of facial plastic surgery journal. He is an expert in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhinoplasty">rhinoplasty</ref>, and has particular interest in cosmetic and reconstructive nose surgery in various ethnic groups.</p>
<head>Honors and achievements</head>
<p>In 1993, he received the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alpha_Omega_Alpha_Medical_Honors_Award">Alpha Omega Alpha Medical Honors Award</ref>. In 1998 and 1999, he was selected as an ethnic scholar in cancer research by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Academy_of_Cancer_Researchers">American Academy of Cancer Researchers</ref> (AACR). At Mayo, he received a Best Teacher Recognition Award and the Distinguished Mayo Brothers Fellowship Award. The Distinguished Mayo Brother's Fellowship Award is an award given to only two surgeons in any given year throughout the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mayo_Foundation">Mayo Foundation</ref>. Recently, Boahene was awarded the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_R._Anderson_Prize_for_Scholastic_Excellence">Jack R. Anderson Prize for Scholastic Excellence</ref> for attaining the highest score in the nation on written and oral examinations administered by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Board_of_Facial_Plastic_and_Reconstructive_Surgery">American Board of Facial Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery</ref> (ABFPRS).</p>
<head>Advances in the field</head>
<p>Boahene is actively involved in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tissue_engineering">tissue-engineering</ref> research that is exploring ways to improve wound healing, enhance injectable tissue fillers, and generate new cartilage or bone for facial reconstruction.</p>
<p>In 2003, he received an international medicine travel grant and was able to participate in his first medical mission to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref>. Since then, Boahene has been on several medical mission trips to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peru">Peru</ref> and his native country, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghana">Ghana</ref>. "I enjoy medical missions. It is where you see physicians at their best... working with little, complaining the least, but accomplishing the most."</p>
</text>
