<text id="autogum_bio_doc175" title="Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku" shortTile="josaiah-ndubuisi" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-02-23" dateModified="2019-08-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josaiah_Ndubuisi_Wachuku" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku</head>
<hi rend="bold">Warning:</hi> Page using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_royalty">Template:Infobox royalty</ref> with unknown parameter "buried" (this message is shown only in preview).
<p><hi rend="bold">Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku</hi> was king, paramount warrant chief, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Servant_leadership">servant leader</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eze">Eze</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ngwa">Ngwa-land</ref> – in the then <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aba,_Nigeria">Aba</ref> Division of Eastern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nigeria">Nigeria</ref> – during British colonial times. King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku belonged to the Royal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynasty">House</ref> of Ebii; which, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Igbo_language">Igbo language</ref>, is specifically called: Ụmụ Ebii; meaning: Children of Ebii. In recent history, the Royal House of Ụmụ Ebii is headed by the eldest living son of King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku. Currently, Barrister: Sir Chikezie Ndubuisi Wachuku is Head of Ụmụ Ebii Royal House.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Royal ancestry</head>
<p>In royal lineage, King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku, whose brothers were: James Wachuku and Marcus Wachuku, was the son of Wachuku: Ọgbaregbe: Ebii: Mkpeyi: Chekwa: Megwa: Mgbawa, etc. King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku's apogean royal ancestor, Mgbawa, had moved from Umụlọlọ: Eziama Ntịgha: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abia_State">Abia State</ref>: Nigeria, in about the last quarter of the 17th century; to settle in their current Nbawsi native land.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Wives and queens</head>
<p>Crucially, royal wives and queens of King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku were: Rebecca Ngwanchiwa Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku, ..., Elizabeth Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku, Mercy Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku, Mary Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku, Dorcas Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku, Nwannediya Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Kingship epoch</head>
<p>While he served Ngwa people, Igboland, Commonwealth of Nations and humankind, King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku empowered women and less privileged persons in Ngwaland and beyond. Women were given vital voice and platform to state their needs and share their viable vision for sustainable development, family values, education, healthcare, energy, mechanization, technology, creativity, innovation, infrastructure, industrialization, democratic politics, servant leadership, trade, financial inclusion, environment, sustainability, agriculture, land ownership, legal representation, peace, human rights and fairness; including during Nsulu Women's protest; that started on Saturday 3 January 1948; concerning King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku's "palm oil plantations, machines for cracking kernels and PMOs: Pioneer Oil Mills;" which King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku's second son: Prince <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaja_Wachuku">Jaja Wachuku</ref>; "who had returned from Ireland in 1947; after graduating from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Dublin">University of Dublin</ref> as a lawyer;" helped resolve by serving to humanely support those protesting women, legally and financially.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Female children</head>
<p>Accordingly, King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku was the father of 10 daughters and 18 sons. Daughters of King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku are: Agnes Wachuku: Mrs. Agnes Francis Nwokedi, Ugbọakụ Wachuku, Awụsakụ Wachuku, Rose Wachuku: Mrs. Rose Akparanta, Nwaọlụchi Wachuku, Nwaozichi Wachuku: Mrs. Nwaozichi Okey, Chima Wachuku: Mrs. Chima Nnamji, Catherine Wachuku, Nwanyieze Wachuku: Mrs. Nwanyieze Onuorah, Ulọakụ Wachuku.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref></p>
<head>Male children</head>
<p>Eighteen sons of King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku are: Albert Wachuku, Jaja Wachuku, Benjamin Wachuku, Jonah Wachuku, Chikezie Wachuku, Ibe: Ibemaduabughịchi Wachuku, Alọzie Wachuku, Eguzoikpe Wachuku, Ogbonna Wachuku, Madu: Maduadighịbeyanma Wachuku, Victor Wachuku, ON: Ọnwụnyịriụwa Wachuku, Joseph Wachuku, Timothy Wachuku, Onweremadu Wachuku, Alibọr Wachuku, Chivọr Wachuku, Evo Wachuku; and notably, his second son: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaja_Wachuku">Jaja Wachuku</ref>, was first indigenous speaker of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Representatives_of_Nigeria">House of Representatives of Nigeria</ref>, first Nigerian ambassador and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Permanent_representative">permanent representative</ref> to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_Nations">United Nations</ref>; as well as first Nigerian minister for foreign affairs and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commonwealth_of_Nations">commonwealth</ref> relations.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-20">[20]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-21">[21]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-22">[22]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-23">[23]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-24">[24]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-25">[25]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-26">[26]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-27">[27]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-28">[28]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-29">[29]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-30">[30]</ref></p>
<head>Grandchildren and progenies</head>
<p>From his daughters and their husbands, King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku has these listed grandchildren: Afam Francis Nwokedi, Adaobi Anne Nwokedi, Late Victor Nwokedi, Uju Nwokedi; Nnamdi Nnamji; Aniweta Onuorah, Nneka Onuorah: Mrs. Nneka Okuntola, Ebele Onuorah: Mrs. Ebele Alegieuno, Ifeyinwa Onuorah: Mrs. Ifeyinwa Ogunbowale; and many others.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-31">[31]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-32">[32]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-33">[33]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-34">[34]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-35">[35]</ref></p>
<p>Through his sons and their wives, King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku was the grandfather of Banners Wachuku, Heọma Wachuku, Ụwaọma Wachuku, Obialọr Wachuku, Ezebugwu Wachuku, Uchechi Wachuku, Amụchọnu Wachuku, Amarihu Moore Wachuku, Akụnna Wachuku: Mrs. Akunna Nwafor, Onyedinma Wachuku, Okezie Wachuku, Obidike Wachuku, Ndidi Wachuku: Randy, Konyere Wachuku, Chukwudi Wachuku: Lager, Chuku Wachuku: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chuku_Wachuku">Chukumereamuonwana Wachuku</ref>, Obimndi Wachuku, Nne Wachuku: Mrs. Nne Stanley Onyemerekeya, Okey Wachuku, Anaba Wachuku, Chinedum Wachuku, Nwabueze Wachuku: Mrs. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nwabueze_Nwokolo">Nwabueze Nwokolo</ref>, Ndubuisi Wachuku, Emenụwa Wachuku, Idu Wachuku, Frances Nkem Wachuku, Chinyere Ananaba Wachuku, Vidal Wachuku, Charles Wachuku, Chukwumaobi [Chuks] Wachuku, Emeka Donald Wachuku, Joy Ngọzi Wachuku, Princess Chinwendu Wachuku, Onyinyechi Chiemela Wachuku, Chibueze Wachuku, Ijeọma Wachuku Ụkwa, Kelechi Wachuku, Chidiebere Wachuku, Okechuku Wachuku, Onyeọma Wachuku: Mrs. Onyeọma Oshodi, Obinna Wachuku, Ugonma Wachuku, Chukwuemeka Wachuku, Adanna Wachuku: Mrs. Adanna Ajoku, Nnenna Wachuku, Obinna Wachuku, Udochukwu Edward Wachuku, Ugonna Wachuku, Uchenna Wachuku: General CityMojo, Ikenna Wachuku, Chineme Alexis Wachuku: Mrs. Chineme Robson, Ngọzi Vanessa Wachuku, Onyekachi Marianne Wachuku, Ijeọma Isabel Wachuku; and so many other grandchildren and great-grandchildren in Nigeria and around the world.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-36">[36]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-37">[37]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-38">[38]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-39">[39]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-40">[40]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-41">[41]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-42">[42]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-43">[43]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-44">[44]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-45">[45]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-46">[46]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-47">[47]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-48">[48]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-49">[49]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-50">[50]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-51">[51]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-52">[52]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-53">[53]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-54">[54]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-55">[55]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-56">[56]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-57">[57]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-58">[58]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-59">[59]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-60">[60]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-61">[61]</ref></p>
<head>Wachuku pedigree</head>
<p>Royal Merchant Prince Wachuku Ọgbaregbe was King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku's father. Wachuku's children were: Josaiah, James, Marcus, Nmaji and Janet. Wachuku's second Son: James Nwanjoku Wachuku's sons are: Young Wachuku, Nnanna Wachuku, Adiele Wachuku, Eze Wachuku, Willie Wachuku, Goddy Wachuku; and James' daughters are: Ulọma, Margaret, Nwaobilo, Omeonu, Chinyere, Uzuka, Kaka, Dora, Dinah and others. Wachuku's third son: Marcus Nwogu Wachuku's sons are: Franklin Wachuku, Fanso Wachuku, Uche Nathan Wachuku, Chijioke Wachuku, Ike Wachuku; and Marcus' daughters are: Chiọma, Nwandiụto, Ugbọmma; including grandchildren and great-grandchildren from brothers and sisters of King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku; who comes from 19 generations of royal chiefs in "Igbo country of Eastern Nigeria."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-62">[62]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-63">[63]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-64">[64]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-65">[65]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-66">[66]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-67">[67]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-68">[68]</ref></p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>Going the way of all humankind, King Josaiah Ndubuisi Wachuku died on Monday 2 January 1950 at General Hospital <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aba,_Abia">Aba</ref> Ngwa; following a necessary operation. His death caused angry protests by Ngwa people; against doctors who performed operation on him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-69">[69]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-70">[70]</ref></p>
</text>
