<text id="autogum_bio_doc287" title="Beatriz de Padilla" shortTile="beatriz-de-padilla" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-01-27" dateModified="2019-08-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beatriz_de_Padilla" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Beatriz de Padilla</head><p><hi rend="bold">Beatriz de Padilla</hi> (b. 1620's) was a Mexican-born <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morisco">Morisco</ref> woman who rose from slavery to property ownership.  Her legal battles and persecution by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_Inquisition">Spanish Inquisition</ref> gained her notability during her lifetime.  </p>
<p>Born in Mexico after 1620, de Padilla was the daughter of Lorenzo de Padilla, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_people">Spaniard</ref> and Cecilia de Alvarado, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mulatto">mulatta</ref> slave and later servant in Lagos, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guadalajara,_Mexico">Guadalajara, Mexico</ref>. De Padilla was originally a slave owned by the priest Francisco Perez Rubin, but he emancipated her do to her exemplary service.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Caste system</head>
<p>During de Padilla's life, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Spain">New Spain</ref> followed a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caste">caste</ref> system that categorized people based on the amount of "pure blood" or Spanish blood.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> This system limited the already restricted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_mobility">social mobility</ref> of non-Spaniard races and those who possessed a lesser amount of Spanish blood were segregated from jobs, were banned from carrying arms, had to live with their masters and could not be in large groups.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> As one of de Padilla's parents was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mulatta">mulatta</ref> slave and possessed African blood, de Padilla was not considered a Spaniard and lived as a slave.</p>
<p>Despite being categorized as a non-Spaniard under the caste system, de Padilla would have been able to enjoy some of the flexibility that came with being considered a non-Spanish woman. Caste females did not have to adhere to the same social regulations as "pure blood" Spanish women. Spanish colonial society did not believe that caste females had any honor to keep or defend, whereas Spanish women were expected to adhere to purity standards - however this did not stop some from seeing caste females' behaviors as a threat to Christian order and morality.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> .<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Legal issues</head>
<p>According to sources, De Padilla took many lovers, some of whom were of high standing.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref>
As a consequence, she was frequently accused by authorities immoral behaviors and violating the expected gender roles of Spanish/Christian women. </p>
<p>De Padilla was also accused of mistreating her slaves and servants.  In one instance, one of de Padilla's servants, Catalina Ia Garay, accused her of burning her with hot grease and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Branding_as_punishment">branding</ref> her. These claims were unfounded, but De Padilla confessed to them.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>De Padilla was targeted by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_Inquisition">Spanish Inquisition</ref> for her relationship with Diego Ortiz Saavedra, a wealthy priest. Ortiz Saavedra had fathered an illlegitimate child with de Padilla.  Before he died, he announced that he was leaving his belongings to de Padilla and the child.  As a result, his family denounced her to the Inquisition.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>At the hearings, witnesses claimed that de Padilla had poisoned Ortiz Saavedra by placing her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Menstrual">menstrual</ref> blood in his bathwater.  They also claimed that she caused him to lose his sanity before his death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> The Inquisition brought in La Garay as a witness.  She repeated her earlier accusations and added more of them.  However, they were later disproved.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>In her defense, De Padilla stated that Ortiz Saavedra had loved her and that his family had falsified the claims to take her inheritance. The Inquisition exonerated and released de Padilla.  She returned to Lago and resumed a relationship with a former lover, the lord mayor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juchipila">Juchipila</ref>, Don Diego de las Marinas.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-4">[4]</ref></p>
</text>
