<text id="autogum_bio_doc434" title="George Paulet (1553–1608)" shortTile="george-paulet-" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-10-24" dateModified="2019-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Paulet_%281553%E2%80%931608%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>George Paulet (1553–1608)</head>For the admiral, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_George_Paulet">Lord George Paulet</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Sir George Paulet</hi> (1553–1608), also known as <hi rend="bold">Pawlet</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Powlet</hi>, was an English soldier, administrator, and governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Derry">Derry</ref> who was killed by the followers of Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cahir_O'Dogherty">Cahir O'Dogherty</ref> during <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/O'Doherty's_Rebellion">O'Doherty's Rebellion</ref>. After his death, Paulet's command at Derry was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burning_of_Derry">burned to the ground</ref> by the rebels.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBagwell1885-1">[1]</ref> Paulet was knighted in 1607.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEShaw_II1906142-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>He was a son of Sir George Paulet (died 1558) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crondall">Crondall</ref>, Hampshire, brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Paulet,_1st_Marquess_of_Winchester">William Paulet, 1st Marquess of Winchester</ref>, and his third wife, Elizabeth, daughter of William Windsor, 2nd <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_Windsor">Baron Windsor</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHunter2004-4">[4]</ref> Paulet was educated at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eton_College">Eton</ref>, 1564–72, and at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King's_College,_Cambridge">King's College, Cambridge</ref>, 1572-5.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEVenn_Part_I(III)1924321-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Early career</head>
<p>His contemporaries call George a gentleman of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hampshire">Hampshire</ref>. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_I_of_England">king's</ref> letters of 20 and 23 July 1606, directing his appointment to the governorship of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Derry">Derry</ref>, speak of his service in the wars.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBagwell1885-1">[1]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>One of the oldest depictions of fort Derry, Ireland.  Derry was sacked and burned by the O'Doherty &amp; McDavitt clans in 1608.</caption></figure>
<p>He began at Derry by buying land from the constable, Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Docwra">Henry Docwra</ref>, who had built a town there more than thirty years after the destruction of Randolph's settlement. Docwra incurred the hostility of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Blount,_8th_Baron_Mountjoy">Charles Blount, 8th Baron Mountjoy</ref> (who became Earl of Devonshire), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Deputy_of_Ireland">Lord Deputy of Ireland</ref>, by supporting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donnell_Ballagh_O'Cahan">Donnell Ballagh O'Cahan</ref>, Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cahir_O'Doherty">Cahir O'Doherty</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niall_Garve_O'Donnell">Niall Garve O'Donnell</ref>, who he thought had been  ill-treated. James I agreed with Devonshire on Irish policy, about the desirability of ruling <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulster">Ulster</ref> through <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_Ó_Neill,_2nd_Earl_of_Tyrone">Hugh Ó Neill, 2nd Earl of Tyrone</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rory_Ó_Donnell,_1st_Earl_of_Tyrconnell">Rory Ó Donnell, 1st Earl of Tyrconnell</ref>, without much regard for minor chiefs. Devonshire died 3 April 1606; but he had previously approved the sale of Docwra's property to Paulet, whom he knew well. Docwra accordingly sold him his house, land which he had bought, and his company of foot, at a low price. The vice-provostship of Derry was thrown in without extra charge.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBagwell1885-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>The new governor was established at Derry in the early winter of 1606, and on 20 February following <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Arthur_Chichester">Sir Arthur Chichester</ref>, the new Lord Deputy, told <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Cecil,_1st_Earl_of_Salisbury">Robert Cecil, 1st Earl of Salisbury</ref> that he was unfit for the place, and that there had been many dissensions since his arrival. He fell out with  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Montgomery_(bishop)">George Montgomery</ref>, the new <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Derry">bishop of Derry</ref>, over land claims. Tyrone and Tyrconnell fled from Ireland early in September 1607 (the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flight_of_the_Earls">Flight of the Earls</ref>); O'Cahan, who ruled the greater part of what is now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_Londonderry">County Londonderry</ref>, and of O'Doherty, the chief of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inishowen">Inishowen</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_Donegal">County Donegal</ref>, came under some suspicion. Docwra had tried to divide these chiefs from the Earls, but Paulet had his own ideas on handling them.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBagwell1885-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>O'Doherty put some armed men on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tory_Island">Tory Island</ref>, but this seems to have been done with the consent of the few inhabitants. Sir Richard Hansard, who commanded for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plantation_of_Ulster">Plantation of Ulster</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lifford">Lifford</ref> in Donegal, recounts that O'Dogherty left <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burt_Castle">Burt Castle</ref>, on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lough_Swilly">Lough Swilly</ref>, at the end of October to superintend the felling of timber for building; but that this gave rise to a report that he was in rebellion. He then began to arm about seventy followers, refusing all recruits from outside his own district. Paulet made an unsuccessful attempt to seize Burt in the chief's absence, and reported everything to Chichester. O'Doherty remonstrated with him in a temperate letter; Paulet then (falsely) denied strongly that he had ever intended to surprise Burt, and accused O'Doherty of treason. O'Doherty went to Dublin early in December and made his excuses to Chichester, who accepted them, but without much confidence. On 18 April the privy council ordered him to be fully restored to such of his ancestral lands as were still withheld, but this order did not reach the Irish government until he was actually in rebellion.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBagwell1885-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>O'Doherty's Rebellion</head>
Main article: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burning_of_Derry">Burning of Derry</ref>
<p>The <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Annals_of_the_Four_Masters">Annals of the Four Masters</ref></hi> state that Paulet struck O'Doherty; there is more support for the idea that Paulet provoked  O'Doherty  into rebellion by insults. Paulet's carelessness invited attack, though Chichester warned him repeatedly to keep good watch. On the night of Monday, 18 April 1608, O'Doherty, at the head of fewer than a hundred men, seized the outpost at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Culmore">Culmore</ref> by a trick, and surprised Derry itself an hour before daybreak. Paulet was killed by O'Doherty's foster-father <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phelim_Reagh_MacDavitt">Phelim Reagh MacDavitt</ref>, and the city was sacked and burned. Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josias_Bodley">Josias Bodley</ref>, not however an eye-witness, reported that Paulet fell fighting valiantly; but the English government spoke of his cowardice. Paulet had been warned by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Hansard">Richard Hansard</ref>, who held his own against the rebels at Lifford.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBagwell1885-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Despite the early success at Derry, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/O'Doherty's_Rebellion">O'Doherty's Rebellion</ref> was defeated by the swift response of the Dublin government. A force was sent out which recovered the ruins of Derry and killed O'Doherty at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Kilmacrennan">Battle of Kilmacrennan</ref>.</p>
<head>Marriage and issue</head>
<p>Paulet married Joan Kyme, daughter of Richard Kyme of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lewes">Lewes</ref>, Sussex and Margery Humphrey. They had a son and a daughter.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHasler1981-6">[6]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Histfam-7">[7]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Frances Paulet, married Richard Mascall of South Malling, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sussex">Sussex</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Histfam-7">[7]</ref></item></list>
<p>His wife was with him at Derry, and the contemporary tract <hi rend="italic">Newes from Ireland concerning the late treacherous Action</hi>; (London, 1608) says he had children there also. Lady Paulet had only a short imprisonment with the O'Doherties; but her husband's death left her in poverty, which was partly relieved out of the Tyrone forfeitures. She was alive in 1617.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBagwell1885-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTECoulson2009180-8">[8]</ref></p>
</text>
