<text id="autogum_bio_doc772" title="Nicholas Geregye" shortTile="nicholas-geregye" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-11-17" dateModified="2019-08-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Geregye" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Nicholas Geregye</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicholas from the kindred Geregye</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hungarian_language">Hungarian</ref>: <hi lang="hu" rend="italic">Geregye nembeli Miklós</hi>; died after 1279) was a Hungarian baron and landowner, member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geregye_(genus)"><hi rend="italic">gens</hi> Geregye</ref>, who held several positions.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>He was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judge_royal">judge royal</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Geregye">Paul</ref> (d. before 1271) and an unidentified mother from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Győr_(genus)">Győr clan</ref>, who was a granddaughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palatine_of_Hungary">palatine</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat_Győr">Pat Győr</ref>. He had three brothers – <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Geregye">Stephen</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geregye_II_Geregye">Geregye II</ref>, Eth II – and a sister, Agnes who married Turul Nagymihályi and after her husband's death, she joined to the monastery at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret_Island">Margaret Island</ref>. Nicholas' grandfather was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voivode_of_Transylvania">voivode</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eth_Geregye">Eth I</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMarkó2006280-1">[1]</ref> As Geregye and Eth appeared in contemporary records decades later at the turn of the 1270s and 1280s than their elder brothers, historian Attila Zsoldos considers they were children from a supposed second marriage of Paul Geregye.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEZsoldos2016112-2">[2]</ref> There is no information about Nicholas' any wives or descendants.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMarkó2006280-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Duke Stephen's partisan</head>
<p>Nicholas and his brother Stephen were first mentioned by a royal charter in 1256, when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Béla_IV_of_Hungary">Béla IV of Hungary</ref> obliged their father Paul to return certain acquired lands along the Sebes-Körös: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tileagd">Telegd</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Săcădat">Szabolcs</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Șuncuiuș">Sonkolyos</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vadu_Crișului">Bertény</ref> with its royal customs (today Tileagd, Săbolciu, Șuncuiuș and Birtin in Romania, respectively) to the original owners. In the previous year, the Geregye troops seized the landholdings of the neighboring <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Csanád_(genus)">Csanád</ref> clan; it is plausible that both Nicholas and Stephen had participated in the skirmhish.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEZsoldos2016109-3">[3]</ref> According to a 1278 charter, Paul and his sons unlawfully possessed the land of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Săcueni">Székelyhíd</ref> (today Săcueni, Romania) too.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEZsoldos2016109-3">[3]</ref> Following these lawless deeds, Paul became disgraced in the royal court and never held any dignities or positions anymore. In this context, Nicholas and Stephen belonged to the partisans of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_V_of_Hungary">Duke Stephen</ref>, whose relationship with his father Béla IV deteriorated by the early 1260s.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEZsoldos200711-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>It is possible Nicholas was identical with that namesake courtier, who served as count (head) of the ducal household in 1259.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEZsoldos201169-5">[5]</ref> Around the same time, his brother Stephen was <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ispán">ispán</ref></hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vas_County">Vas County</ref> in 1260.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEZsoldos2011224-6">[6]</ref> Following that Nicholas functioned as voivode of Transylvania between 1267 and 1268, during the end of the reign of Béla IV (it is presumable, he held the dignity uninterruptedly from 1264 to 1270). The voivodeship belonged to the realm of Duke Stephen, who even adopted the title junior king in the second half of the 1260s.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEZsoldos201138-7">[7]</ref> The Geregye brothers supported the duke in the civil war conflict between father and son, which evolved in 1264–65. It is possible that they fought in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Isaszeg_(1265)">Battle of Isaszeg</ref> in March 1265, as one of Nicholas' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castle_warrior">castle warriors</ref> from Vas County was granted the status of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_servant_(Kingdom_of_Hungary)">royal servants</ref> for his military merits in the battlefield by Stephen.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEZsoldos2016113-8">[8]</ref> Historian Attila Zsoldos considers their lands' geographical proximity to the ducal court in Transylvania, and their father'  Paul deteriorating relationship with Béla IV both contributed to their involvement in the rebellion against the royal power.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEZsoldos2016113-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Aspirations to oligarchy</head>
<p>The Geregye brothers' loyalty to Duke Stephen suddenly broke up in May 1270, when the latter ascended the throne and became King of Hungary as Stephen V. Nicholas, along with several magnates, fled the country and placed himself under the protection of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottokar_II_of_Bohemia">Ottokar II</ref>. The Bohemian king also received the Dobronya Castle at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Podzámčok">Dobróváralja</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upper_Hungary">Upper Hungary</ref> (today Podzámčok, Slovakia) by Nicholas. He participated in Ottokar's campaign against Hungary in 1271, when Nicholas besieged and occupied the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nitra_Castle">Nyitra Castle</ref> and came through on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hron">Garam River</ref>. After the peace treaty between Stephen V and Ottokar II (1271), he returned to Hungary, however he regained his former political influence only after the death of king Stephen V in 1272.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMarkó2006281-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>Between 1272 and 1274, during the reign of the minor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ladislaus_IV_of_Hungary">Ladislaus IV</ref>, Nicholas was voivode of Transylvania and thus <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ispán">ispán</ref> (<hi rend="italic">comes</hi>) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Szolnok_County">Szolnok County</ref> three times.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEZsoldos201138–39-10">[10]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEEngel2001382-11">[11]</ref> He was elected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judge_royal">judge royal</ref> and head of Bánya (Árkibánya) ispánate in 1275.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEZsoldos201133-12">[12]</ref></p>
<p>He actively participated in the struggle for power between the barons and supported the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kőszegi_family">Kőszegi family</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joachim_Gutkeled">Joachim</ref> from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gutkeled">Gutkeled clan</ref>. Nicholas and his brothers tried to establish a dominion independently of the king. Nicholas had started to expand his influence over the territories that surrounded his possessions and castles, Adorján, Almás, Sólyomkő and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valkó">Valkó</ref>. However king Ladislaus IV eliminated their rebellion with a military force in 1277. After that the Geregye clan lost its estates and political positions.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMarkó2006281-9">[9]</ref></p>
</text>
