<text id="autogum_bio_doc229" title="Dionysius I, Metropolitan of Malankara" shortTile="dionysius--metropolitan" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-02-10" dateModified="2019-08-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dionysius_I%2C_Metropolitan_of_Malankara" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Dionysius I, Metropolitan of Malankara</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mar Dionysius I</hi>, also known as <hi rend="bold">Mar Thoma VI</hi> (died 8 April 1808), was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malankara_Metropolitans">Metropolitan</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malankara_Church">Malankara Church</ref> from 1765 until his death. A member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pakalomattom_family">Pakalomattom family</ref>, he was a shrewd administrator who appealed to outside authorities to assert his position as the sole leader of the Malankara Church and to attempt to reunite all the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Thomas_Christians">Saint Thomas Christians</ref>.</p>
<p>Mar Thoma VI succeeded <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mar_Thoma_V">Mar Thoma V</ref> as Malankara Metropolitan in 1765, and unlike his predecessors, who were claimed by their opponents not to have been properly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ordination">ordained</ref> as bishop, he received orders from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syriac_Orthodox">Syriac Orthodox</ref> bishops in 1772, thus ending any controversy. Other events of his reign include the separation of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thozhiyoor">Thozhiyoor</ref> church (now the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malabar_Independent_Syrian_Church">Malabar Independent Syrian Church</ref>), the arrival of English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestant">Protestant</ref> missionaries, and the first translation of the Bible from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syriac_language">Syriac</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malayalam">Malayalam</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>The man who would be Mar Dionysius was the nephew of his predecessor as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malankara_Metropolitan">Malankara Metropolitan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mar_Thoma_V">Mar Thoma V</ref>, and a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pakalomattom">Pakalomattom</ref> family. In 1757, as part of a play to assert his authority and autonomy in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syriac_Orthodox_Church">Syriac Orthodox Church</ref>, Mar Thoma V consecrated his nephew as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coadjutor_bishop">coadjutor bishop</ref> and named him his successor, in contradiction to the wishes of the Syriac Orthodox hierarchy. Upon Mar Thoma V's death in 1765, the younger Pakalomattom was ordained as Metropolitan on 8 May, taking the name Mar Thoma VI.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>As with his predecessors as Metropolitan going back to the first, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mar_Thoma_I">Mar Thoma I</ref>, Mar Thoma VI's critics charged that his succession, and therefor his position, was invalid. To overcome this criticism, in 1772 Mar Thoma VI underwent a second ordination at the hands of the Syriac Orthodox bishop Mar Gregorios in the church in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niranam">Niranam</ref>. He received all the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Orders">Holy Orders</ref>, from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tonsure">tonsure</ref> to the episcopal consecration, and thereafter took the name Mar Dionysius.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Syriac Orthodox and other critics of Mar Thoma VI saw this as his only ordination, while his supporters saw it as a "re-ordination", but either way, it ended the controversy over the validity of his position.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>This done, Dionysius focused on his second primary aim of securing his place as the sole head of the Malankara Church, a measure opposed by some in the Syriac Orthodox hierarchy. To this end, Dionysius appealed to both the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholic_Church">Catholic Church</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Great_Britain">British</ref> colonial government in India. Several times he contacted the Catholic hierarchy, both locally and in Rome, seeking to have his church, with him as its designated head, brought into full communion. This would have the double aim of solidifying his authority, and re-uniting all the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Thomas_Christians">Saint Thomas Christians</ref>, who had been split into Catholic and independent (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malankara_Church">Malankara</ref>) factions since the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coonan_Cross_Oath">Coonan Cross Oath</ref> of 1653. His appeals were considered in Rome, where the Church was willing to grant him temporal but not spiritual authority over the Saint Thomas Christians. In the end, however, no satisfactory deal was ever made and the factions remained separate.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>In 1771, Mar Gregorios consecrated a second bishop, Kattumangatt, who took the name Mar Cyril (Koorilose). Dionysius saw Cyril as a threat to his authority, and appealed to the colonial authorities to suppress the rival bishop. Cyril left for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thozhiyur">Thozhiyur</ref>, outside of the colonial jurisdiction, and established what would become an independent church. This body is now known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malabar_Independent_Syrian_Church">Malabar Independent Syrian Church</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> Subsequently, however, Gregorios and the other Syrian bishops died and were not replaced, leaving no further internal challengers to Dionysius.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Invasion by Mysore</head>
<p>Mysore was a land locked kingdom. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyder_Ali">Hyder Ali</ref>, ruler of this kingdom decided to invade <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malabar_Coast">Malabar</ref> to get access to the Arabian Sea. He entered Malabar in 1781 and crushed the Nair soldiers. After his death <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tippu_Sultan">Tippu Sultan</ref> came to the throne. During that period Christians were persecuted.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balarama_Varma">Bala Rama Varma</ref> was the ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Travancore">Travancore</ref> at this time. He was one of the least popular sovereigns whose reign was marked by unrest and various internal and external problems to the state.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> He became King at the young age of sixteen and came under the influence of a corrupt nobleman known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jayanthan_Sankaran_Nampoothiri">Jayanthan Sankaran Nampoothiri</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kozhikode">Calicut</ref>. One of the first acts of atrocities during his reign was the murder of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raja_Kesavadas">Raja Kesavadas</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> the existing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dewan">Dewan</ref> of Travancore.  Sankaran Nampoothiri was then appointed as Dewan (Prime minister) with two other ministers.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> Using his influence, Mar Thoma VI was put in jail at Alleppy and was forced to conduct a service according to Catholic rites, but escaped during a rebellion in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Travancore">Travancore</ref> under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Velu_Thampi">Velu Thampi</ref> in 1799.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref></p>
<head>Relations with the Church of England</head>
<p>Toward the end of Dionysius' reign, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claudius_Buchanan">Claudius Buchanan</ref> (1766–1815) visited <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kerala">Kerala</ref> in 1806, and arranged for the translation of the Bible into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malayalam">Malayalam</ref>. Dionysius gave him the manuscript of the Bible written in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syriac_language">Syriac language</ref>. This manuscript was later deposited in the public library of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Cambridge">University of Cambridge</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref></p>
<p>During the visit Buchanan suggested the Malankara Church seek a close relationship with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_England">Church of England</ref>. Soon after his visit, Dionysius convened a meeting of church elders at Aarthattu, where he declared the Malankara Church would not accept Anglican doctrine, nor those of any other foreign church.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></p>
<head>Death and succession</head>
<p>Dionysius consecrated Pakalomattom Mathen Kathanar as his successor in 1796 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chengannur">Chengannur</ref> church. Dionysius died on 8 April 1808 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niranam">Niranam</ref>, and he was interred <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Mary's_Orthodox_Cathedral,_Puthencavu">St. Mary's Orthodox Cathedral, Puthencavu</ref>, with Mathen conducting the funeral service. Mathen subsequently received his orders, taking the name <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mar_Thoma_VII">Mar Thoma VII</ref>.</p>
</text>
