<text id="autogum_bio_doc530" title="Tisquesusa" shortTile="tisquesusa" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-04-18" dateModified="2019-03-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tisquesusa" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tisquesusa</head>
<figure><caption>Tisquesusa depicted in 1688</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tisquesusa</hi>, also spelled <hi rend="bold">Thisquesuza</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Thysquesuca</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Thisquesusha</hi> (died <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facatativá">Facatativá</ref>, 1537) was the fourth and last independent ruler (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zipa">zipa</ref></hi>) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bacatá">Bacatá</ref>, main settlement of the southern Muisca between 1514 and his death in 1537. The name brought about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colombia">Colombian</ref> capital Bogotá. Tisquesusa was the ruler of the southern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muisca_Confederation">Muisca Confederation</ref> at the time of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_conquest_of_the_Muisca">Spanish conquest of the Muisca</ref>, when the troops led by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gonzalo_Jiménez_de_Quesada">Gonzalo Jiménez de Quesada</ref> and his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hernán_Pérez_de_Quesada">brother</ref> entered the central Colombian highlands. His <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zaque">zaque</ref></hi> counterpart in the northern area of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muisca_people">Muisca</ref> was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quemuenchatocha">Quemuenchatocha</ref>.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Tisquesusa was <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cacique">cacique</ref></hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chía,_Cundinamarca">Chía</ref> and following the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Women_in_Muisca_society#Matrilineal_heritage_of_rule">Muisca heritage rules</ref>, he as nephew of the previous ruler <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nemequene">Nemequene</ref> succeeded his uncle in 1514. At the start of his reign, Tisquesusa fought against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panche_people">Panche</ref> in the west of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muisca_Confederation">Muisca Confederation</ref>. The brother of Tisquesusa and later -according to Muisca heritage rule illegal- successor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sagipa">Sagipa</ref> was the general in the southern Muisca army. Early on in his reign Tisquesusa went to war with the northern Muisca ruled by Quemuenchatocha. Forty thousands <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guecha_warrior">guecha warriors</ref> of the southern Muisca fought against fifty thousand northern Muisca. Earlier, support of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraca">iraca</ref></hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sugamuxi">Sugamuxi</ref> of the Iraca Valley helped the northern troops in their battles, but this time the third party helped settling a truce between both parties which lasted until the arrival of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_conquest_of_the_Americas">Spanish conquistadores</ref> in 1537.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>The Spanish conquest</head>
Main article: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_conquest_of_the_Muisca">Spanish conquest of the Muisca</ref>
<p>The arrival of the Spanish conquerors was revealed to Tisquesusa by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohan_(legendary)">mohan</ref> Popón, from the village of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ubaque">Ubaque</ref>. He told the Muisca ruler that foreigners were coming and Tisquesusa would die "bathing in his own blood".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> When Tisquesusa was informed of the advancing invasion of the Spanish soldiers, he sent a spy to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suesca">Suesca</ref> to find out more about their army strength, weapons and with how many warriors they could be beaten. The <hi rend="italic">zipa</hi> left the capital Bacatá and took shelter in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nemocón">Nemocón</ref> which directed the Spanish troops to there, during this march attacked by more than 600 Muisca warriors.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>When Tisquesusa retreated in his fortified place in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cajicá">Cajicá</ref> he allegedly told his men he would not be able to combat against the strong Spanish army in possession of weapons that produced "thunder and lightning". He chose to return to Bacatá and ordered the capital to be evacuated, resulting in an abandoned site when the Spanish arrived. In search for the Muisca ruler the conquistadores went north to find Tisquesusa in the surroundings of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facatativá">Facatativá</ref> where they attacked him at night.</p>
<p>Tisquesusa was thrusted by the sword of one of De Quesada's soldiers but without knowing he was the <hi rend="italic">zipa</hi> he let him go, after taking the expensive mantle of the ruler. Tisquesusa fled hurt into the mountains and died of his wounds there. His body was only discovered a year later because of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_vulture">black vultures</ref> circling over it.</p>
<p>At the death of Tisquesusa, his son Hama and daughter Machinza hid the sister of the <hi rend="italic">zipa</hi>, Usaca, in one of the settlements on the Bogotá savanna. When one of the conquistadors, Juan María Cortés, found out about this, he prepared a battle to gain control over the area. At that moment, Usaca appeared and resisted against the Spanish conqueror. Legend tells that he dropped his weapons and fell in love with her, eventually marrying the sister of Tisquesusa and they were baptised in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usaquén">Usaquén</ref>, meaning "Land of the Sun" in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chibcha_language">Muysccubun</ref>. This formed the start of the construction of a colonial village, today part of the capital and known for its colonial architecture and parks.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-TiempoUsaca-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Succession to the throne</head>
<p>Contrary to Muisca tradition, where the eldest son of the oldest sister of the previous ruler would become the next <hi rend="italic">zipa</hi>, the reign was taken over by Tisquesusa's brother; his army general <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sagipa">Sagipa</ref>. This would be the last ruler of the southern Muisca, defeated in 1538 and died of Spanish torture in early 1539.</p>
<head>Tisquesusa in Muisca history</head>
<head>Modern historical revisionism</head>
<p>In investigations in the 21st century about the existence of Tisquesusa, doubt has been cast on his name. The name Tisquesusa originates from the work <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elegías_de_varones_ilustres_de_Indias">Elegías de varones ilustres de Indias</ref></hi> written by poet <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_de_Castellanos">Juan de Castellanos</ref> decades after the events of the conquest. In his work he names Tisquesusa as the <hi rend="italic">zipa</hi>, while other researchers, such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jorge_Gamboa_Mendoza">Jorge Gamboa Mendoza</ref>, maintain the name was "Bogotá".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[note 1]</ref> Later <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Muisca_scholars">scholars</ref>, such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedro_Simón">Pedro Simón</ref> simply took the names from earlier sources without verifying them.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-EspectadorTisquesusa-6">[5]</ref></p>
</text>
