<text id="autogum_bio_doc648" title="Maurice Spata" shortTile="maurice-spata" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-21" dateModified="2018-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maurice_Spata" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Maurice Spata</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Muriki</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Maurice Spata</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albanian_language">Albanian</ref>: <hi lang="sq" rend="italic">Muriq Shpata</hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_language">Greek</ref>: Μουρίκης Σπάτας; fl.1399–1414) was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despotate_of_Arta">ruler of Arta</ref> from late 1399/early 1400 until his death in 1414 or 1415. Maurice's reign was dominated by his wars with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlo_I_Tocco">Carlo I Tocco</ref>. Maurice was able to defend his capital of Arta, but despite some victories failed to prevent the fall of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ioannina">Ioannina</ref> to Tocco. As a result, his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yaqub_Spata">Yaqub Spata</ref> who succeeded him was defeated in October 1416, ending the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despotate_of_Arta">Despotate of Arta</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Maurice was a scion of the Albanian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spata_family">Spata family</ref>. He was a grandson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gjin_Bua_Spata">Gjin Bua Spata</ref>, the first Albanian ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arta,_Greece">Arta</ref>. He had one brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yaqub_Spata">Yaqub Spata</ref>, and two half-siblings from his mother's second marriage, Charles Marchesano and Maddalena.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26524._Σπάτας_Μουρίκης-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP5969._Εἰρήνη-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010255-3">[3]</ref> Shortly before Gjin died on 29 October 1399, he appointed his brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sgouros_Spata">Sgouros Spata</ref>, ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naupactus">Naupactus</ref>, as his successor as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despotate_of_Arta">Lord of Arta</ref>. A few days after Sgouros took over <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arta,_Greece">Arta</ref>, however, the town was captured by the adventurer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vonko">Vonko</ref>. While Sgouros fled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angelokastro,_Aetolia-Acarnania">Angelokastron</ref>, a short time after, possibly as early as December 1399, Maurice managed to evict Vonko from Arta and took over the governance of the city himself.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26524._Σπάτας_Μουρίκης-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010164,_169-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFine1994355–356-5">[5]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>Map of the southern Balkans and western Anatolia in 1410. Ottoman and Turkish territories are marked in shades of brown, Byzantine territory in pink, Venetian and Venetian-influenced areas in green, and other Latin principalities in blue</caption></figure>
<p>In 1402–03, Maurice came to Sgouros' aid when the latter was besieged at Angelokastron by the forces of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlo_I_Tocco">Carlo I Tocco</ref>. The attack, under Carlo's general Galasso Peccatore, was repulsed, but Sgouros died soon after, leaving his possessions to his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Spata">Paul Spata</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010170-6">[6]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFine1994356-7">[7]</ref> In his campaigns against the Spatas, Tocco was supported by a rival Albanian clan to the Spatas, the Bua brothers Maurice and Dimo.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010169–170-8">[8]</ref> In 1406, Carlo and the Bua brothers joined forces to raid and devastate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acarnania">Acarnania</ref> and the vicinity of Arta, but the city itself, stoutly defended by Maurice Spata, held out. At Angelokastron, however, Paul Spata, who lacked his father's ability, felt threatened by the Tocco advance and in 1406 called in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> assistance. The Ottoman army, under Yusuf Beg, was defeated, however, and the Turks departed after coming to terms with the Tocchi. As Maurice refused to come to his cousin's aid, Paul ceded Angelokastron to the Ottomans (only for Carlo Tocco to capture it within less than a year) and retired to Naupactus, which he sold to Venice in 1407–08.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26524._Σπάτας_Μουρίκης-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFine1994356-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010171–172-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>In order to contain Tocco, Maurice turned to his northern neighbour, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despot_(court_title)">Despot</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ioannina">Ioannina</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esau_de'_Buondelmonti">Esau de' Buondelmonti</ref>. Relations between them were tense because Esau, who in 1396 had taken Maurice's mother Irene as his wife, had divorced her in 1402 to marry <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eudokia_Balšić">Eudokia Balšić</ref>. Nevertheless, the common threat brought the two together, and in ca. 1410, an alliance was concluded between them, sealed by the marriage of Maurice's daughter to Esau's son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giorgio_de'_Buondelmonti">Giorgio</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26524._Σπάτας_Μουρίκης-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010173–174-10">[10]</ref> The war between Maurice and Carlo Tocco was a war of raids and counter-raids, punctuated by battles that ended now in defeat and now in victory, with intermittent truces sealed by marriage alliances, such as when Charles Marchesano was wed to a natural daughter of Carlo Tocco.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26524._Σπάτας_Μουρίκης-1">[1]</ref> It was on the occasion of the latter, which was held at Rogoi, that Maurice and his guests were informed of Esau's death on 6 February 1411. This event triggered a contest between Tocco and the Albanian lords to secure possession of Ioannina, left in the hands of the infant Giorgio and his mother, for themselves. The major role in subsequent developments was played by the inhabitants of Ioannina themselves, who soon deposed Eudokia Balšić and Giorgio. Allied with the lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gjirokastër">Gjirokastër</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gjon_Zenebishi">Gjon Zenebishi</ref>, Maurice unsuccessfully besieged the Epirote capital twice and plundered its environs. The Ioannites, who utterly opposed the idea of having an Albanian or Serbian ruler over them, opted to surrender their city to Tocco instead, who entered the city in triumph on 1 April.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26524._Σπάτας_Μουρίκης-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010175–177-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>This event consolidated the pact between Maurice and Zenebishi, which was further confirmed by another marriage alliance between Maurice's daughter and Zenebishi's son Simon. The two Albanian lords were willing to negotiate with Tocco, but the latter, buoyed by his success, launched raids against both their territories. As a result, Maurice and Zenebishi sent appeals to their clansmen, and a large Albanian army met and almost annihilated the Tocco army at a battle fought at Kranea in the district of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mesopotamon">Mesopotamon</ref>, in spring or summer 1412. The victorious Albanians marched to the walls of Ioannina, but were again unable to take the city.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26524._Σπάτας_Μουρίκης-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010179–180-12">[12]</ref> In late 1412 or early 1413, Carlo Tocco was forced to turn to the Turks for support, arranging for the marriage of one of his natural daughters with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musa_Çelebi">Musa Çelebi</ref>, one of the Ottoman princes contending for the sultanate during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Interregnum">Ottoman Interregnum</ref>. The alliance eased Tocco's position, but Musa was defeated and killed later in the year by his brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mehmed_I">Mehmed I</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010181-13">[13]</ref> At the same time, Maurice concluded an alliance to Tocco's Italian rival in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morea">Morea</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince_of_Achaea">Prince of Achaea</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centurione_II_Zaccaria">Centurione II Zaccaria</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26524._Σπάτας_Μουρίκης-1">[1]</ref> Maurice's half-brother Charles, who had been appointed governor of Rhiniasa, tried to go over to Tocco, but was apprehended by the local magnates and handed over to Maurice.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26524._Σπάτας_Μουρίκης-1">[1]</ref> A scandal involving Zenebishi's son and a son-in-law of Maurice led to a quarrel between the two Albanian rulers and the collapse of their alliance. Tocco moved quickly to win over Zenebishi and conclude peace with him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26524._Σπάτας_Μουρίκης-1">[1]</ref> Maurice died in 1414 or 1415,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26524._Σπάτας_Μουρίκης-1">[1]</ref> and was succeeded by his full brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yaqub_Spata">Yaqub Spata</ref>, in Arta, while Charles Marchesano was given the governorship of Rogoi. Maurice's successors proved unable to withstand Tocco's assaults, however, and in October 1416, Yaqub was captured and killed in an ambush. Arta surrendered, ending the era of Albanian rule in the area.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010185–187-14">[14]</ref></p>
<head>Issue</head>
<p>From his marriage to Nerata, a Serbian woman, Maurice is known to have had a number of unnamed daughters, usually considered to have been three:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26524._Σπάτας_Μουρίκης-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010255-3">[3]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>a daughter who married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giorgio_de'_Buondelmonti">Giorgio de' Buondelmonti</ref></item>
<item>a daughter who married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_Zenevisi">Simon Zenevisi</ref>, lord of Strovilo</item>
<item>a daughter who married, after Maurice's death, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlo_II_Tocco">Carlo II Tocco</ref></item></list>
<p>The first daughter is believed by Karl Krumbacher to have married <hi rend="italic">Giorgio</hi>, a son of "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Balšić">George Balšić</ref> and Eudokia".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Krumbacher1988-15">[15]</ref></p>
</text>
