<text id="autogum_bio_doc581" title="Marco Marziale" shortTile="marco-marziale" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-04-26" dateModified="2019-02-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco_Marziale" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Marco Marziale</head>Left: Portrait of a man, by Marco Marziale. Right:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allegory">Allegory</ref> with unknown <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coat_of_arms">coat of arms</ref>. (Reverse of the portrait). <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louvre_Museum">Louvre Museum</ref>.
<figure><caption>Supper at Emmaus - <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gallerie_dell'Accademia">Gallerie dell'Accademia</ref></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Marco Marziale</hi> was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_of_Venice">Venetian</ref> painter from, known to have been active from 1492/1493 to 1507.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Penny,_103-1">[1]</ref> He was a pupil of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Bellini">Giovanni Bellini</ref>, as stated in some of his inscriptions signing works, and was also influenced by Giovanni's brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gentile_Bellini">Gentile</ref>, with possibly some elements of the style of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perugino">Perugino</ref> also.  From January 1493 (old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julian_calendar">Julian calendar</ref>), when he must have at least completed his training, he was employed by the Republic of Venice as an assistant to Giovanni Bellini on the Great Council Chamber in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doge's_Palace,_Venice">Doge's Palace</ref> at a fairly modest salary.  These paintings were all lost in the great fire of 1574.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref>  In 1493 he joined the confraternity of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scuole_Grandi_of_Venice">Scuola di San Marco</ref>.</p>
<p>In about 1500 he may have moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cremona">Cremona</ref>, which Venice had just taken over in 1499, and which it held until 1509, when the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Milan">Duchy of Milan</ref> recaptured the city.  Marziale would no doubt have been unwelcome after this, if he was in the city.  He is not documented there, but painted two altarpieces for Cremonese churches; it is possible these were sent from Venice, although the records of the scuola show him as absent from the city in 1505.  In 1507 he signed works now in London and Berlin, after which nothing further about him is known.</p>
<p>Several signed works are known, including the only two large <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Altarpiece">altarpieces</ref>, both from churches in Cremona and now in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Gallery,_London">National Gallery, London</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>  Two versions of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supper_at_Emmaus">Supper at Emmaus</ref></hi>, adapted from a lost work by Giovanni Bellini known from a print, are in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gemäldegalerie,_Berlin">Gemäldegalerie, Berlin</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gallerie_dell'Accademia">Gallerie dell'Accademia</ref> in Venice, where there is also a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circumcision_of_Jesus">Circumcision of Jesus</ref></hi> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Museo_Correr">Museo Correr</ref>, dated 1499.  Including unsigned attributed works, there is a probable surviving oeuvre of about a dozen paintings;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Penny,_103-1">[1]</ref> apart from the wall-paintings lost in 1574, much of his painting may be among the large number of pieces assigned to the workshop of Giovanni Bellini.  A small <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adoration_of_the_Magi">Adoration of the Magi</ref></hi>, formerly in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virginia_Museum_of_Fine_Arts">Virginia Museum of Fine Arts</ref>, and only just attributed as an early work of Marziale's, was sold at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christie's">Christie's</ref>, New York for $98,500 in January 2009.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>He was a rather conservative painter, whose works continued to follow compositional formats from the late 15th century, despite his possibly being only a few years older than <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giorgione">Giorgione</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Titian">Titian</ref>.  His main figures stand upright and still in the older Venetian style, already long superseded in Florentine art.  Although his figures are stiff, even "wooden",<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref>  he takes great interest in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Textile">textiles</ref> and decor in his works.  Both the London altarpieces are set in spaces in front of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apse">apses</ref> decorated with gold <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mosaic">mosaics</ref> in the manner of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Mark's_Basilica">San Marco, Venice</ref>, and also of altarpieces by Giovanni Bellini.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref>  The <hi rend="italic">Circumcision</hi> altarpiece features several <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donor_portrait">donor portraits</ref> of the family of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tommaso_Raimondi">Tommaso Raimondi</ref>, the lawyer and poet who commissioned the work; their lavish and fashionable clothes are carefully depicted.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> In 1872, the English critic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Ruskin">John Ruskin</ref> asked a friend in Venice to make a careful drawing of the embroidered table-cloth, probably from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egypt">Egypt</ref>, depicted in the Correr <hi rend="italic">Circumcision</hi>, which Ruskin adapted into a pattern for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wallpaper">wallpaper</ref> which he used in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Study_(room)">study</ref> of his house <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brantwood">Brantwood</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lake_District">Lake District</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>In Cremona he influenced, and may have trained, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Altobello_Melone">Altobello Melone</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Notes</head>
<head>References</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Penny">Penny, Nicholas</ref>,  National Gallery Catalogues (new series): <hi rend="italic">The Sixteenth Century Italian Paintings, Volume I</hi>, 2004, National Gallery Publications Ltd, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/1-85709-908-7">1-85709-908-7</ref></item></list>
</text>
