<text id="autogum_bio_doc307" title="Adam Cusack" shortTile="adam-cusack" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-06" dateModified="2018-12-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adam_Cusack" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Adam Cusack</head><p><hi rend="bold">Adam Cusack</hi> (c.1630–1681) was an Irish  landowner, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barrister">barrister</ref> and judge of the seventeenth century.</p>
<p>He was born at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rathgar">Rathgar</ref>  (then deep in the countryside, now a suburb of  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dublin">Dublin</ref>), the second son of Robert Cusack of Rathgar Castle  (which Adam inherited on the death of his elder brother) and his wife Alice, daughter of Sir George Sexton of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Limerick">Limerick</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>  His father sat in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irish_House_of_Commons">Irish House of Commons</ref> as MP for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kells_(Parliament_of_Ireland_constituency)">Kells</ref> in 1640-2. He was the grandson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Cusacke">John Cusacke</ref>  (died 1626),  a wealthy Dublin  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merchant">merchant</ref>  who was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Mayor_of_Dublin">Lord Mayor of Dublin</ref>  in 1608-9, and his wife Margaret Gough (née Allen).  The Cusacks originally came from Ballymolghan, County Meath.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>During the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Rathmines">Battle of Rathmines</ref> in August 1649 Rathgar Castle was surrounded by troops, but not attacked: Adam and his father were both in the Castle at the time.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> He was educated at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trinity_College,_Dublin">Trinity College, Dublin</ref> and became a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teaching_fellow">fellow</ref> of the college in 1654. He entered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lincoln's_Inn">Lincoln's Inn</ref> in 1655, was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Called_to_the_Bar">called to the Bar</ref> in 1660, and entered the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King's_Inn">King's Inn</ref> in 1661. His choice of the law as a profession may have been influenced by  the fact that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Barry,_1st_Baron_Barry_of_Santry">James Barry, 1st Baron Barry of Santry</ref>, a leading barrister who  became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chief_Justice_of_Ireland">Lord Chief Justice of Ireland</ref>  in 1660, was his cousin, his mother being  Adam's paternal aunt Anne Cusacke.
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Adam was appointed second justice of the provincial court of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Connacht">Connacht</ref> in 1661 and became the last <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief_Justice_of_Connacht">Chief Justice of Connacht</ref> in 1670.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> On the abolition of that office in 1672 he was appointed a justice of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Court_of_Common_Pleas_(Ireland)">Court of Common Pleas (Ireland)</ref>. In the
relaxed political atmosphere of the early 1670s his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anglo-Irish">Anglo-Irish</ref>  background and
tolerant attitude to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholics">Roman Catholics</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> were not  a professional  disadvantage. He had also  the advantage of having married Catherine Keating, sister of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Keating_(judge)">John Keating</ref>, later to be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief_Justice_of_the_Irish_Common_Pleas">Chief Justice of the Irish Common Pleas</ref> and niece of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maurice_Eustace_(Lord_Chancellor)">Maurice Eustace</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chancellor_of_Ireland">Lord Chancellor of Ireland</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>The only serious  objection to his appointment  to the  High Court Bench was his health: from early middle age onwards he suffered badly from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gout">gout</ref>, which became so severe that he  was  unable to perform his judicial duties for  at least two years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> He died, aged only about 50, in 1681, and was buried in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Audoen's_Church,_Dublin">St. Audoen's Church, Dublin</ref>. In his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Will_(law)">will</ref>, which, according to Elrington Ball, shows his  kindly and charitable nature, he left money to the poor of St. Audoen's  parish and of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rathfarnham">Rathfarnham</ref>, for the relief of poor prisoners, and bequests  to  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_King's_Hospital">the Bluecoat School</ref>
at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxmantown">Oxmantown</ref> and to the army <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hospital">hospital</ref> at Back Lane, Dublin.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> The bulk of his estate was left to his widow Catherine, who remarried his cousin Nicholas Cusack; she and Adam had no children.</p>
<p>Rathgar Castle fell into decay in the eighteenth century, and was a ruin by 1769, when the Dutch-born artist  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabriel_Beranger">Gabriel Beranger</ref>  did a watercolour which shows two men surveying   the remains. The Castle's precise location is something of a mystery, but it   probably stood on what is now  Highfield Road,   at the present site of  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Luke's_Hospital,_Rathgar">St. Luke's Hospital, Rathgar</ref>. It was built by the Segrave family  in the sixteenth century, on what had previously been <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monastic">monastic</ref> land,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> and  was bought by Adam's grandfather John in 1609.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
</text>
