<text id="autogum_bio_doc624" title="Thomas Bardolf, 5th Baron Bardolf" shortTile="thomas-bardolf-th" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-18" dateModified="2019-08-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Bardolf%2C_5th_Baron_Bardolf" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Thomas Bardolf, 5th Baron Bardolf</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Thomas Bardolf, 5th Baron Bardolf</hi> (born prior to 1390-died 19 February 1408) was a baron in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peerage_of_England">Peerage of England</ref>, Lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wormegay">Wormegay</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norfolk">Norfolk</ref>, of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shelford,_Nottinghamshire">Shelford</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoke_Bardolph">Stoke Bardolph</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nottinghamshire">Nottinghamshire</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hallaton">Hallaton</ref> (Hallughton), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leicestershire">Leicestershire</ref>, and others, and was "a person of especial eminence in his time".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>A supporter of the rebellion of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Percy,_1st_Earl_of_Northumberland">Henry Percy, 1st Earl of Northumberland</ref> against King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_IV_of_England">Henry IV of England</ref> after the death of Percy's son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Percy_(Hotspur)">Harry Hotspur</ref>, he died from wounds received at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Bramham_Moor">Battle of Bramham Moor</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>The eldest son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_4th_Lord_Bardolf">William 4th Lord Bardolf</ref>, Knight, of Wormegay, Thomas Bardolf de Wormegay, 5th <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_Bardolf">Baron Bardolf</ref>, was summoned to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_England">Parliament of England</ref> from 12 September 1390 to 25 August 1404.</p>
<p>He took part with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Percy,_1st_Earl_of_Northumberland">Henry Percy, 1st Earl of Northumberland</ref>, and others, in their insurrection against King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_IV_of_England">Henry IV</ref>, and being pursued by the Royal army in great force, was obliged to flee to France. But about three years after returning to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/England">England</ref>, he resumed his alliance with the Earl of Northumberland, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_de_Mowbray,_4th_Earl_of_Norfolk">Thomas Mowbray (Earl Marshall)</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Scrope_(cleric)">Richard le Scrope</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_York">Archbishop of York</ref>, only to be defeated again in Yorkshire by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Lancaster,_1st_Duke_of_Bedford">John of Lancaster</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ralph_Neville,_1st_Earl_of_Westmorland">the Earl of Westmorland</ref>. The king ordered the execution of Mowbray and Scrope, who were subsequently beheaded at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York">York</ref>.</p>
<p>Finally, in 1408, at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Bramham_Moor">Battle of Bramham Moor</ref>, the rebels suffered a total defeat. Northumberland was slain, and Lord Bardolf "so much hurt" that he died of his wounds soon after.</p>
<p>Bardolf had married Avicia, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ralph_de_Cromwell,_2nd_Baron_Cromwell">Ralph de Cromwell</ref>, 2nd <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_Cromwell">Baron Cromwell</ref>. He left two daughters, Anne and Joan, his co-heirs. However, his honours and lands had already been forfeited to the Crown by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Attainder">attainder</ref>.</p>
<head>Aftermath</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Dugdale">William Dugdale</ref> states that "Lord Bardolf's remains were quartered, and the quarters disposed of by being placed above the gates of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York">York</ref>, Lenne [possibly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King's_Lynn">King's Lynn</ref>?], and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shrewsbury">Shrewsbury</ref>, while the head was placed upon one of the gates of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lincoln,_Lincolnshire">Lincoln</ref>; his widow obtained permission, however, in a short time, to remove and bury them."</p>
<p>The estates were divided between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Beaufort,_1st_Duke_of_Exeter">Thomas Beaufort, 1st Duke of Exeter</ref> (the king's half-brother), Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_de_Dunbar,_10th_Earl_of_March">George de Dunbar</ref>, Knight, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_of_Navarre,_Queen_of_England">Joan of Navarre, Queen of England</ref>; but the latter's proportion, upon the petition of Sir William Clifford, knt.,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref>  and his wife, Anne, and Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Phelip,_6th_Lord_Bardolf">William Phelip</ref> and his wife, Joan, to the king, was granted in reversion, after the Queen's decease, to those husband's of the attainted nobleman.</p>
<p>Also, on "27 April 1407. The King to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_Sheriff">sheriff</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lincolnshire">Lincoln</ref>. Referring to the late plea in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Court_of_Chancery">Chancery</ref> between Amicia (sic) wife of Thomas, late lord of Bardolf, and George de Dunbarre regarding certain lands in Ruskynton forfeited by Thomas, which had been granted by the King to George, with the manor of Calthorpe, the half of Ancastre (and many others), wherein it was adjudged that Rusynton should be excepted from the grant and restored to her with the rents, etc., from 27 November 1405, drawn by George, - the King orders him to restore the same to Amicia. Westminster. [Close, 9 Henry IV. m.17.]".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Arms</head>
<p>Bardolf’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coat_of_arms">coat of arms</ref> was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blazon">blazoned</ref> <hi rend="italic">Azure, three cinquefoils, or</hi>, meaning three gold cinquefoil flowers on a blue shield. </p>
</text>
