<text id="autogum_bio_doc256" title="Citoyenne Henri" shortTile="citoyenne-henri" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-19" dateModified="2018-08-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citoyenne_Henri" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Citoyenne Henri</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Citoyenne Henri</hi> (often called <hi rend="bold">Citizen Henry</hi> in English) was a woman who accompanied <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/André-Jacques_Garnerin">André-Jacques Garnerin</ref> on a trip by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balloon_(aircraft)">balloon</ref> on 8 July 1798 from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parc_Monceau">Parc Monceau</ref> in Paris. </p>
<p>She was credited as the first woman "who ever had the courage to trust herself in the regions of air", although several women had already made ascents in a balloon: on 20 May 1784, the Marchioness and Countess of Montalembert, the Countess of Podenas and a Miss de Lagarde had taken a trip on a tethered balloon in Paris, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Élisabeth_Thible">Élisabeth Thible</ref> had made an ascent in an untethered balloon on 4 June 1784.</p>
<head>Announcement and legal challenge</head>
<p>The balloonist and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parachute">parachuting</ref> pioneer André-Jacques Garnerin announced in 1798 that on his next ascent he would be accompanied by a young woman. Although the public and press were in favour of Garnerin's idea, he was forced to appear in front of officials of the Central Bureau of Police to attempt to justify his project. Chief among their concerns was the effect that the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atmospheric_pressure">air pressure</ref> might have on the organs of the delicate female body, though it appears that they were also concerned about the moral implications of a man and woman being alone in a balloon together. When questioned as to the expected results of the atmospheric pressure and what would happen if the woman was to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fainting">lose consciousness</ref>, Garnerin replied that he did not expect anything untoward to occur and that he would be personally responsible for dealing with any mishaps. Unsatisfied with Garnerin's responses, the police issued an injunction against him, forbidding the ascent on the grounds that the young woman was committing herself to the venture without any idea of the possible outcome.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Handy-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Garnerin refused to accept the decision handed down by the Central Bureau and appealed to the administration of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Department_(country_subdivision)">department</ref>. Consultation with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interior_minister">Minister of the Interior</ref> and Minister of the Police followed and the injunction was eventually overturned on the grounds that "there was no more scandal in seeing two people of different sexes ascend in a balloon than it is to see them jump into a carriage." They also concluded that the decision of the woman to take the balloon trip showed proof of her confidence in the experiment and a degree of personal intrepidity.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Handy-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Citoyenne Henri had already been chosen by Garnerin to accompany him, and as result of the lifting of the ban he was immediately ready to proceed with his plan. He advertised the ascent in the <hi rend="italic">L'Ami des Lois</hi>:</p>
<p>The young citoyenne who will accompany me is delighted to see the day approach for the journey. I shall ascend with her from the Parc de Mousseaux,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[Note 1]</ref> some time during the next ten days.</p>
<head>The balloon flight</head>
<p>On 8 July 1798 a large number of spectators gathered in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parc_Monceau">Parc Monceau</ref> to witness the ascent. By all accounts Citoyenne Henri was young and beautiful, and she and Garnerin took several turns around the park to the applause of the crowd before she was assisted into the basket of the balloon by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astronomy">astronomer</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jérôme_Lalande">Jérôme Lalande</ref>. The balloon trip passed without incident and the journey ended at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goussainville,_Val-d'Oise">Goussainville</ref> about 30 kilometres (19mi) to the north of Paris.</p>
<p>There is no record of the relationship between Garnerin and Citoyenne Henri, where he recruited her for the trip or what her motives were in accepting. Garnerin gave her a present after the trip.</p>
<head>Aftermath</head>
<p>There was fervent press interest in the beautiful young girl for a few days, but her fame did not endure.
Shortly afterwards, on 10 November 1798, Garnerin's future wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeanne_Geneviève_Labrosse">Jeanne Geneviève Labrosse</ref> was also taken up in his balloon. Subsequently both his wife and his niece <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Élisa_Garnerin">Élisa Garnerin</ref> became well known for their parachuting feats and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sophie_Blanchard">Madame Blanchard</ref> was celebrated for her solo ballooning, relegating the less impressive exploits of Citoyenne Henri to a footnote in history.</p>
</text>
