<text id="autogum_bio_doc587" title="François Vatable" shortTile="francois-vatable" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-17" dateModified="2019-10-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fran%C3%A7ois_Vatable" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>François Vatable</head><figure><caption>"Hebrew latin Sacred Bible", ten editions published between 1584 and 1729</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">François Vatable</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> (late 15th century – 16 March 1547) was a French humanist scholar, a Hellenist and Hebraist.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamaches">Gamaches</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Picardy">Picardy</ref>, he was for a time rector of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bramet">Bramet</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Valois">Valois</ref>. In 1530 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_I_of_France">Francis I of France</ref> appointed him as one of his Royal Lecturers in what afterwards became known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collège_de_France">Collège de France</ref>. Vatable got the chair of Hebrew. At a later date a royal grant conferred upon Vatable the title of Abbot of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bellozane">Bellozane</ref>, with the benefices attached thereto. Vatable is regarded as the restorer of Hebrew scholarship in France, and his lectures in Paris attracted a large audience including Jews. He was known by  his immense erudition, his gift of communication,  his talent as a teacher and the support of his listeners. His work is not very extensive, but very admired.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Vatable died in Paris.</p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>Vatablus published no works of his own, but in his early years (1518 onwards as an assistant to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lefèvre_d'Etaples">Lefèvre d'Etaples</ref>) he procured new Latin translations and editions from the Greek works by <hi rend="italic">The Philosopher</hi>, as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aristotle">Aristotle</ref> was known. These works were inquiries in physics, human and animal nature, psychology, astronomy, and meteorology (<hi rend="italic">Physica, De caelo, De anima, De generatione et corruptione, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meteorologica">Meteorologica</ref></hi>, and the so-called <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parva_naturalia">Parva naturalia</ref></hi> (minor tracts on physical phenomena)). These became standard textbooks of Universities throughout Europe.</p>
<p>As a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_lecturer">Royal lecturer</ref> he actively participated in the edition of a better text of the different Books of the Bible. He procured Hebrew editions for scholarly use (published by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Estienne">Robert Estienne</ref>, or in English Robert Stephens). To the edition of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minor_Prophets">Minor Prophets</ref> he added the commentary of the famous Jewish Rabbi <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Kimhi">David Kimhi</ref>. From the lecture notes taken by Vatable's pupils, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Estienne">Robert Estienne</ref> also drew material for the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scholia">scholia</ref></hi> which he added to his edition of the Latin Bible in two columns, juxtaposing the new Latin translation of the Zurich Bible by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leo_Jud">Leo Jud</ref> to the standard Latin text of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vulgate">Vulgate</ref>. Afterwards the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sorbonne">Sorbonne</ref> doctors sharply inveighed against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lutheran">Lutheran</ref> tendencies of some of the notes in Estienne's Bible. By then Vatable had already died. The notes in Estienne's Bible are a model of clear, concise literary, and critical exegesis. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salamanca">Salamanca</ref> theologians, with the authorization of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_Inquisition">Spanish Inquisition</ref>, issued a new thoroughly-revised edition of them in their Latin Bible of 1584. From the edition of 1729 which <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Migne">Migne</ref> republished in his <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scripturae_sacrae_cursus_completus">Scripturae sacrae cursus completus</ref></hi> (1841), the scholia on the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Book_of_Esdras">Book of Esdras</ref></hi> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Book_of_Nehemiah">Book of Nehemiah</ref>.</hi> The notes on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psalms">Psalms</ref>, published separately in 1545 were re-edited - and augmented - in Estienne's <hi rend="italic">Liber Psalmorum Davidis</hi> (1557), published in Geneva. These were reprinted together with remarks of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugo_Grotius">Hugo Grotius</ref>, by Vogel, under the misleading title: <hi rend="italic">Francisci Vatabli annotationes in Psalmos</hi> (1767).</p>
</text>
