<text id="autogum_bio_doc468" title="Álvaro I of Kongo" shortTile="alvaro-kongo" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-08-16" dateModified="2016-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%81lvaro_I_of_Kongo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Álvaro I of Kongo</head>
<figure><caption>The coat of arms issued to King Álvaro I in 1578</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Álvaro I Nimi a Lukeni lua Mvemba</hi> was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manikongo">Manikongo</ref> (Mwene Kongo), or king of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Kongo">Kongo</ref>, from 1568 to 1587.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Álvaro's father was an unknown Kongo nobleman who died, leaving his mother to remarry to King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henrique_I_of_Kongo">Henrique I</ref>. When Henrique I died fighting on the eastern frontier, he had left Álvaro as his regent.  According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duarte_Lopes">Duarte Lopes</ref>, Kongo's ambassador to Rome in 1584-88, Álvaro had taken up the kingship by common consent. However, there do appear to have been others who wished to be king, and some scholars, notably <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francois_Bontinck">Francois Bontinck</ref>, think that Álvaro's rule was seen as an usurpation. The invasion of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jagas">Jagas</ref>, which took place shortly after Álvaro became king, is sometimes seen as a protest against this usurpation.  Other scholars, however doubt the connection between the Jaga invasion and a dynastic crisis.</p>
<p>The Jagas, however, did create a major problem for Álvaro, who had to abandon the capital of Mbanza Kongo, and flee to an island in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Congo_River">Congo River</ref>. From that place he sought help from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portugal">Portugal</ref> to restore him to the throne and expel the Jagas. Portugal responded by sending  an expedition of 600 soldiers, mostly from the colony of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/São_Tomé_and_Príncipe">São Tome</ref>, under the command of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francisco_de_Gouveia_Sottomaior">Francisco de Gouveia Sottomaior</ref>. Gouveia Sottomaior's instructions included obtaining some sort of vassalage from Álvaro and regaining control of the Portuguese community in Kongo by building a fort to "protect" them. However that might be, strong opposition by Portuguese in Kongo, led by Álvaro's confessor, Francisco Barbuda, prevented most of Gouveia Sottomaior's instructions from being carried out.</p>
<p>However, Álvaro apparently did permit the Portuguese to settle in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luanda">Luanda</ref> and the colony of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angola">Angola</ref> was born when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paulo_Dias_de_Novais">Paulo Dias de Novais</ref> arrived with his force in 1575. Álvaro sought to relieve the potential threat to his sovereignty by assisting Dias de Novais, sending troops to help him in 1577. However, he, or at the very least Francisco Barbuda, was instrumental in persuading the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Ndongo">king of Ndongo</ref>, where Dias de Novais had his principal forces, to drive the Portuguese out. Once this had happened, however, Álvaro sent an army to Angola to assist the Portuguese and to conquer Ndongo. The conquest failed, however, as the Kongo army was overextended and could not cross the Bengo River successfully.</p>
<p>Álvaro sought to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Culture_of_Europe">Europeanize</ref> Kongo more fully than had been the case before. He was the first king to refer to the capital city as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M'banza-Kongo">São Salvador</ref>. He also sought to obtain a bishop from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Rome">Rome</ref>, though it was not until the reign of his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Álvaro_II_of_Kongo">Álvaro II of Kongo</ref> that this was accomplished.</p>
<p>In 1587, he was succeeded by his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Álvaro_II_of_Kongo">Álvaro II</ref>.</p>
</text>
