<text id="autogum_bio_doc252" title="Ismail Pasha (Tripolitanian)" shortTile="ismail-pasha-tripolitanian" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-10-26" dateModified="2018-12-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ismail_Pasha_%28Tripolitanian%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ismail Pasha (Tripolitanian)</head>For other people named Ismail Pasha, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ismail_Pasha_(disambiguation)">Ismail Pasha (disambiguation)</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Ismail Pasha</hi> (fl. 1780–1792) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> statesman of Georgian origin, he grew up in Tunis during the reign of Ali Pasha (1759-1782)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sicilli-2">[2]</ref> Because of this, he became the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kethüda">kethüda</ref></hi> (assistant/deputy) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cezayirli_Gazi_Hasan_Pasha">Cezayirli Gazi Hasan Pasha</ref>, the famous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kapudan_Pasha">Kapudan Pasha</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sicilli-2">[2]</ref> He would go on to serve as the Ottoman governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egypt_Eyalet">Egypt Eyalet</ref> (1788–89, 1789–91) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morea_Eyalet">Morea Eyalet</ref> (1791–92).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sicilli-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JabartiPhilipp1994-2/315-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Governorship of Egypt</head>
<p>When Cezayirli Gazi Hasan Pasha was ordered by the sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abdülhamid_I">Abdülhamid I</ref> to take troops to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egypt_Eyalet">Egypt</ref> and drive out the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mamluk">Mamluk</ref> emirs led by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ibrahim_Bey_(Mamluk)">Ibrahim Bey (Mamluk)</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murad_Bey">Murad Bey</ref>, who had become <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> rulers of the province, Ismail Pasha went with him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sicilli-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JabartiPhilipp1994-2/181-4">[4]</ref> When Hasan Pasha completed the removal (at least temporarily) and departed, he left Ismail Pasha behind in Egypt.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sicilli-2">[2]</ref> Ismail Pasha then received the news that he was appointed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_governor_of_Egypt">Ottoman governor of Egypt</ref> on 2 December 1788.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sicilli-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JabartiPhilipp1994-2/286-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>When the Mamluk emirs, who had secured a negotiation with Ismail Pasha's predecessor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keki_Abdi_Pasha">Keki Abdi Pasha</ref> as to their power and holdings in Egypt, found that he had been replaced by Ismail Pasha, they refused to honor the deal.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JabartiPhilipp1994-2/286–287-6">[6]</ref> Abdi Pasha, angry over his dismissal and this turn of events, sent agents to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Istanbul">Istanbul</ref>, the capital, to persuade the sultan to reappoint him as governor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JabartiPhilipp1994-2/289-7">[7]</ref> This was successful, and within a month, on 3 January 1789, news arrived that Abdi Pasha had been reappointed the governor of Egypt and Ismail Pasha had been dismissed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JabartiPhilipp1994-2/289-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>However, less than a month later, on 30 January 1789, messengers from Istanbul appeared carrying an order for the re-dismissal of Abdi Pasha and the reappointment of Ismail Pasha, this being the result of the persuasions of Ismail Pasha's former employee and friend <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cezayirli_Gazi_Hasan_Pasha">Cezayirli Gazi Hasan Pasha</ref>, who had undone what Abdi Pasha's agents had done to have him dismissed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JabartiPhilipp1994-2/289-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>In the beginning of his second term, news arrived from Istanbul that the Ottoman Empire had had a brief victory in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russo-Turkish_War_(1787–92)">Russo-Turkish War (1787–92)</ref> when they overran the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banat">Banat</ref> region previously taken by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian_Empire">Russians</ref> (although the Ottomans would go on to lose the war), ordering a day of celebration in Cairo.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JabartiPhilipp1994-2/293-8">[8]</ref> Ismail Pasha then proceeded to whitewash and clean the walls of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Azhar_University">Al-Azhar University</ref>, among other things. News also arrived that sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abdülhamid_I">Abdülhamid I</ref> had died on April 7, being replaced by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Selim_III">Selim III</ref>, and that Ismail Pasha's former employee Cezayirli Gazi Hasan Pasha had been dismissed from the post of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kapudan_Pasha">Kapudan Pasha</ref> after holding the office for 20 years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JabartiPhilipp1994-2/293-8">[8]</ref> At one point, Ismail Pasha became very angry with a man named Abdul Wahhab Efendi the Bosnian, and hearing of his derisions of him, slapped him in the face and plucked his beard before his ministers pulled him away.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JabartiPhilipp1994-2/313-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>In early 1791, an extremely deadly plague ravaged Egypt, killing many of all ages including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ismail_Bey_al-Kabir">Ismail Bey al-Kabir</ref>, the favored <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mamluk">Mamluk</ref> emir at the time. After his death, other Mamluk emirs competed over who would take leadership of the emirs. Mass graves were dug for the dead.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JabartiPhilipp1994-2/314–315-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>In the first few days of May 1791, a message arrived from Istanbul, dismissing Ismail Pasha from the governorship and replacing him with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safranbolulu_Izzet_Mehmet_Pasha">Safranbolulu Izzet Mehmet Pasha</ref>. Ismail Pasha was told to report to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morea_Eyalet">Morea Eyalet</ref> (modern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peloponnese">Peloponnese</ref> peninsula, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greece">Greece</ref>), of which he was now appointed as governor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JabartiPhilipp1994-2/315-3">[3]</ref> The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mamluk">Mamluk</ref> emirs complained that Ismail Pasha, who was familiar to them, was being replaced by a stranger and asked him to send a petition to remain governor of Egypt. Ismail Pasha refused and hastily began packing his belongings for departure. The emirs grew suspicious that he was hurrying because of unpaid debts to the treasury and forced him to remain in Egypt until the new governor Safranbolulu Izzet Mehmet Pasha could arrive and audit him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JabartiPhilipp1994-2/315–316-11">[11]</ref> They put him under house arrest, and when the new governor arrived and Ismail Pasha paid what he owed, he finally left on a ship for Morea on 26 June 1791.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-JabartiPhilipp1994-2/317-12">[12]</ref></p>
<head>Governorship of Morea and death</head>
<p>After arriving in Morea sometime in late summer 1791, Ismail Pasha was dismissed from this post later that year or the next (1792), and his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vizier">viziership</ref> was revoked.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sicilli-2">[2]</ref> He shipped his possessions to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Tunis">Tunis</ref> and foreign lands and was placed under house arrest.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sicilli-2">[2]</ref> After being freed, he moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuscany">Tuscany</ref> in Italy.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sicilli-2">[2]</ref> Although the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Habsburg_Monarchy">Austrian government</ref> helped to have his viziership and status as a civil servant returned, Ismail Pasha remained in Tuscany and died there.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sicilli-2">[2]</ref></p>
</text>
