<text id="autogum_bio_doc680" title="Ulrich IV, Lord of Hanau" shortTile="ulrich-iv-lord-hanau" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-02-26" dateModified="2018-04-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulrich_IV%2C_Lord_of_Hanau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ulrich IV, Lord of Hanau</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ulrich IV, Lord of Hanau</hi> (1330/40–1380) was Lord of Hanau from 1369 or 1370 until his death. Based on the estimated year his parents married, he is assumed to have been born between 1330 and 1340. He was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulrich_III,_Lord_of_Hanau">Ulrich III</ref> of Hanau and Adelaide of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Nassau">Nassau</ref>.</p>
<head>Reign</head>
<p>Ulrich IV succeeded his father when he died in late 1369 or early 1370. The exact date of Ulrich III's death has not been recorded.</p>
<head>Imperial policies</head>
<p>On 20 March 1371, Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslas,_King_of_the_Romans">Wenceslas</ref> of Bohemia, acting as the representative of his father, Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_IV,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Charles IV</ref>, appointed Ulrich IV as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor">governor</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wetterau">Wetterau</ref>, a position his father had held before him. However, he must have been relieved of his duties later that year, as we find Archbishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Luxemburg-Ligny">John</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Mainz">Mainz</ref> on this post in the fall of 1371. Perhaps Charles IV never confirmed Ulrich IV's appointment.</p>
<p>During his reign, he was involved in various <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feud">feuds</ref> and regional wars. He was a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_League_(Hesse)">Star League</ref>, a group of territorial lords trying to counter the growing influence of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landgraviate_of_Hesse">Landgraviate of Hesse</ref>. Possibly in the context of the War of the Start League, Ulrich IV killed Frowin of Hutten, an ally of Hesse, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steinau_an_der_Straße">Steinau an der Straße</ref>. Details of how this happened, are unknown. Relatives of Frowin, led by his brother Conrad, pursued Ulrich and took him prisoner. Ulrich's uncle, Bishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adolph_I_of_Nassau">Adolph</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Speyer">Speyer</ref> mediated and Ulrich was released, in exchange for a ransom of 7500 guilder. Ulrich also had to donate a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanctuary_lamp">sanctuary lamp</ref> to the monastery at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schlüchtern">Schlüchtern</ref>, provide for a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Requiem">requiem</ref> and 50 guilders for the maintenance of the altar, and 100 guilders for a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conciliation_cross">conciliation cross</ref> at the house where the crime had been committed. Finally, he had to make some <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concession_(politics)">political concessions</ref>, designed to prevent him from continuing to fight on the side of the Star League.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Even during the War of the Star League, Ulrich IV continued his father's pacification policies.</p>
<head>Territorial acquisitions</head>
<p>By his marriage to Elizabeth of Wertheim, Ulrich IV acquired a quarter of Breuberg Castle and the associated Lordship. The Counts of Wertheim bought this share back in 1409.</p>
<p>In 1371, Ulrich purchased Steinheim, situated on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_(river)">Main</ref> opposite Hanau, from the Lords of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eppstein">Eppstein</ref>, as well as the remaining shares in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alzenau">Alzenau</ref>. However, in 1377, he sold half of Steinheim to his brother-in-law, Count William II of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katzenelnbogen">Katzenelnbogen</ref>. From 1378 to 1389, he and his successor held castle and city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Königstein_im_Taunus">Königstein</ref> and other rights and sources of income, as security for a loan he and the City of Frankfurt had extended to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Counts_of_Falkenstein_(Rhineland-Palatinate)">Lords of Falkenstein-Münzenberg</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1372, he sold <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Babenhausen,_Hesse">Babenhausen</ref> for 4000 guilders to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lands_of_the_Bohemian_Crown">Bohemian Crown</ref>. The King of Bohemia immediately gave it back to him as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fief">fief</ref>. The background of this transaction was that the King, as Elector wanted to secure a route from his residence to Frankfurt, because the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Bull_of_1356">Golden Bull of 1356</ref> stipulated that all future Imperial elections were to take place in Frankfurt. Babenhausen is about a day's travel east of Frankfurt, making a very suitable "stepping stone" on the route to the site of the election. In 1374, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fulda_monastery">Fulda monastery</ref> pledged <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otzberg_Fortress">Otzberg Fortress</ref>, the city of Hering and its share of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Groß-Umstadt">Umstadt</ref> to Ulrich IV. In 1390, the monastery sold these territories to Elector Palatine <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rupert_II,_Elector_Palatine">Rupert II</ref>, so that he became Hanau's debtor. In 1377, Ulrich acquired the second half of Schlüchtern, by swapping it with Bishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerard_of_Schwarzburg">Gerard</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Würzburg">Würzburg</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bütthard">Bütthard</ref> castle and the district of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Altenhaßlau">Altenhaßlau</ref> as a fief.</p>
<head>Domestic policies</head>
<p>In 1375 Ulrich IV confirmed and extended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primogeniture">primogeniture</ref> decree his grandfather <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulrich_II,_Lord_of_Hanau">Ulrich II</ref> had issued in 1339. He gave it its final form, that would be mostly, but not always, adhered to in the County of Hanau for the coming centuries.</p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>Ulrich IV died in September or October 1380. He was buried — like all his predecessors — in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arnsburg_Abbey">Arnsburg Abbey</ref>. He was the last of the Lords of Hanau to be buried there.</p>
<head>Marriage and issue</head>
<p>In 1366 or 1367 he married Elizabeth,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> the daughter of Eberhard of Wertheim. They were engaged on 11 February 1366; the wedding agreement was signed on 15 February 1366; on 12 March 1367 she is first mentioned as Ulirch IV's wife in a document. From this marriage four children are known:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulrich_V,_Lord_of_Hanau">Ulrich V</ref> ruled Hanau from 1380 to 1404</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reinhard_II,_Count_of_Hanau">Reinhard II</ref>, ruled from 1404 to 1451</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Hanau">John</ref>, co-ruler from 1404 to 1411</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conrad_of_Hanau_(Dean)">Conrad</ref> (before 1388 – after 1419), cleric</item></list>
<head>Ancestors</head>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
