<text id="autogum_bio_doc736" title="Duncan Campbell, 1st Lord Campbell" shortTile="duncan-campbell-st" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-23" dateModified="2019-03-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duncan_Campbell%2C_1st_Lord_Campbell" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Duncan Campbell, 1st Lord Campbell</head><figure><caption>A 16th or 17th century illustration from <hi rend="italic">The Black Book of Taymouth</hi> shows Duncan flanked by two of his descendants. On Duncan's right stands his grandson <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colin_Campbell,_1st_Earl_of_Argyll">Colin Campbell, 1st Earl of Argyll</ref> and on his left is his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colin_Campbell_of_Glenorchy">Colin of Glenorchy</ref>. (Description after Boardman, <hi rend="italic">The Campbells.</hi>)</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Duncan Campbell, 1st Lord Campbell</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classical_Gaelic">Classical Gaelic</ref> <hi rend="italic">Donnchadh mac Cailein</hi>, and also called <hi rend="bold">Donnchadh na-Adh</hi> (English: Duncan the fortunate) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loch_Awe">Loch Awe</ref>, (died  1453), was a Scottish nobleman and politician. He was an important figure in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scotland">Scottish</ref> affairs in the first half of the 15th century and Justiciar of Argyll. He was head of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clan_Campbell">Clan Campbell</ref> for 40 years.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Duncan's date of birth is in 1390 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loch_Awe">Lochow</ref>, Argyll.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> He was the son of Colin Campbell of Lochawe<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref>, and Mariota Campbell. Colin (called Colin Iongantach 'Wonderful', and 'Colin The Good Knight') was the eldest son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archibald_Campbell_of_Lochawe">Archibald Campbell of Lochawe</ref>, while Mariota was the daughter of John Campbell, and thus heiress to the lands of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ardscotnish">Ardscotnish</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glen_Orchy">Glen Orchy</ref>. Colin obtained a dispensation by 13 January 1366 permitting the marriage of Mariota to his son John. He evidently changed his plans and married Mariota himself as in 1372 he obtained a second dispensation, this allowing Colin and Mariota to remarry, after a separation, having already married although within the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prohibited_degree_of_kinship">prohibited degree of kinship</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Duncan may not have been their eldest son: a brother named John <hi rend="italic">Annam</hi>, John the Weak, is said to have been passed over. Duncan was seemingly the chosen heir by 6 February 1393 when he was granted the lands of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Menstrie">Menstrie</ref> by his father. On Colin's death, some time before 19 January 1414, Duncan became head of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clan_Campbell">Campbells</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loch_Awe">Loch Awe</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Family ties</head>
<p>Duncan was twice married, first to Marjorie (d. before August 1432), daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Stewart,_Duke_of_Albany">Robert Stewart</ref>, Duke of Albany, secondly to Margaret Stewart of Ardgowan (d. after August 1442).</p>
<p>Duncan's closeness to the Albany Stewarts led to King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_I_of_Scotland">James I of Scotland</ref> viewing him with some suspicion, and James sent Duncan south as a hostage in England. The documentary record calls him Campbell of Argyll, and gives his share of the liability for the king's ransom as 1500 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merk_(coin)">merks</ref>, more than any other hostage save one.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> In time Duncan and the king were somewhat reconciled and following James's assassination Duncan was among the supporters of Queen Dowager <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_Beaufort,_Queen_of_Scotland">Joan</ref>.</p>
<head>"The fortunate"</head>
<p>During the minority of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_II_of_Scotland">James II</ref>, Duncan professed support and loyalty to the regency, while constantly expanding his power in Argyll, often at the expense of the Crown. He was nevertheless knighted before March 1440 and created a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_of_Parliament">Lord of Parliament</ref> as <hi rend="bold">Lord Campbell</hi> of Lochawe by James II in 1445.</p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>He died between February 1453 and 21 May 1454, and was buried in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collegiate_church">collegiate church</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kilmun">Kilmun</ref>, which he and his wife Margaret Stewart had founded in 1442 (see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kilmun_Parish_Church_and_Argyll_Mausoleum">Kilmun Church</ref>). Their effigies can still be seen in a niche with a wide cusped arch.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>His first successor was Archibald, Master of Campbell; also known as Archibald Roy of Kilbride since he was born in Kilbride, two miles from Inverary. Archibald Roy of Kilbride was the 14th Campbell, the Sixth McCailen More, and 16th Knight of Lochow.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>His second son by his wife Margaret, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colin_Campbell_of_Glenorchy">Colin</ref>, was the founder of the Campbell of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breadalbane,_Scotland">Breadalbane</ref> line (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Breadalbane_and_Holland">Earl of Breadalbane and Holland</ref>). His other sons by his second marriage, Archibald, Duncan, and Neil, created the Campbell septs of Otter, Auchinbreck, and Ormidale, respectively.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>His grandson <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colin_Campbell,_1st_Earl_of_Argyll">Colin</ref>, son of Archibald 'Gillespic,' (d. 1440) his only child by his first wife, succeeded him as Chief of the Clan Campbell.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
</text>
