<text id="autogum_bio_doc662" title="Richard Talbot (archbishop of Dublin)" shortTile="richard-talbot-archbishop" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-07-10" dateModified="2019-08-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Talbot_%28archbishop_of_Dublin%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Richard Talbot (archbishop of Dublin)</head><p><hi rend="bold">Richard Talbot</hi> (c. 1390 – 15 August 1449) was an English-born statesman and cleric in fifteenth-century Ireland.   He was a younger brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Talbot,_1st_Earl_of_Shrewsbury">John Talbot, 1st Earl of Shrewsbury</ref>. He held the offices of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_Dublin_(Roman_Catholic)">Archbishop of Dublin</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chancellor_of_Ireland">Lord Chancellor of Ireland</ref>. He was one of the leading political figures in Ireland for more than thirty years, but his career was marked by controversy and frequent  conflicts with other statesmen. In particular his quarrel with the powerful Earl of Ormonde was  the main cause of the Butler–Talbot feud, which dominated Irish politics for decades, and seriously weakened the authority  of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Crown">English Crown</ref> in Ireland.</p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Talbot,_1st_Earl_of_Shrewsbury">John Talbot, 1st Earl of Shrewsbury</ref>, elder brother of <hi rend="bold">Richard Talbot</hi>, who was John's strongest   political ally.</caption></figure>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>He was the third son of Richard Talbot, 4th <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_Talbot">Baron Talbot</ref>, and his wife Ankaret le Strange. His elder brothers were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilbert_Talbot,_5th_Baron_Talbot">Gilbert Talbot, 5th Baron Talbot</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Talbot,_1st_Earl_of_Shrewsbury">John Talbot, 1st Earl of Shrewsbury</ref>. He seems to have entered the Church while he was still in his early teens. He became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prebendary">prebendary</ref>  of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hereford_Cathedral">Hereford Cathedral</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York_Cathedral">York Cathedral</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean_of_Chichester">Dean of Chichester</ref> in 1415. In 1416 he was elected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_Armagh">Archbishop of Armagh</ref> but failed to secure <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papal">Papal</ref>   confirmation  of his election. The following year he was consecrated Archbishop of Dublin.</p>
<head>Archbishop of Dublin</head>
<p>He was an active and reforming Archbishop, who established a new <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corporation">corporation</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Patrick's_Cathedral,_Dublin">St. Patrick's Cathedral</ref> and founded <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chantries">chantries</ref> in St. Michael's Church and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Audoen's_Church">St. Audoen's Church</ref>. His rule as Archbishop   was marked by  a long-running conflict with John Swayne, who had become Archbishop of Armagh in 1418,  two years after  Talbot failed to obtain confirmation of his election to that see. Talbot revived an old dispute about primacy between the sees of Dublin and Armagh,  and refused to accept the right of Swayne to call himself <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primate_of_Ireland">Primate of Ireland</ref>. Swayne was equally intransigent:  in 1429  he refused to attend a session of the Irish Parliament in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leinster">Leinster</ref> if his primacy was not acknowledged.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Political career</head>
<p>Richard's  elder brother John, the future 1st  Earl of Shrewsbury, was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Lieutenant_of_Ireland">Lord Lieutenant of Ireland</ref> between 1414 and 1420 and again
in 1425 and  in 1446-7. Richard acted as his brother's Lord  Deputy  of Ireland, and also as Justiciar of Ireland. In 1423 he was appointed Lord Chancellor of Ireland  and held  the latter office for most of the next twenty years.</p>
<p>The condition of English rule in Ireland at this time has been described as a chronic state of "imbecility, folly and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corruption">corruption</ref>". Talbot was at least prepared to act firmly: in 1419  he arrested <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Preston,_2nd_Baron_Gormanston">Christopher Preston, 2nd Baron Gormanston</ref> and other members of the  nobility on suspicion of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treason">treason</ref>, although nothing came of these charges. Inevitably he made enemies: in 1426 he was deprived of the  Lord Chancellorship but he was soon restored to office. A more serious crisis arose in 1429 when he was accused of fomenting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rebellion">rebellion</ref>, and summoned to London to account for his actions. Clearly the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privy_Council">Privy Council</ref> was satisfied with his defence since he was not deprived of office.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Butler–Talbot feud</head>
<p>The charges against Talbot may have been connected with the long-running feud between the Talbots and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Butler,_4th_Earl_of_Ormonde">James Butler, 4th Earl of Ormonde</ref>. Shrewsbury had been charged with "harsh treatment" of Ormonde, and his brother intensified the quarrel, to the point where <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anglo-Irish">Anglo-Irish</ref> politics became increasingly split between the Talbot and Butler factions. The Talbot faction was dominant in the 1430s, when there was a brief lull in the feud, but in 1442 the appointment of Ormonde as Lord Lieutenant of Ireland caused the feud to break out with fresh bitterness. Talbot was sent to London to ask for an English  Lord Lieutenant to replace Ormonde,  and produced an extraordinary document which he claimed was the petition of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_Ireland">Irish Parliament</ref> against Ormonde (it is unclear if in fact the Parliament had authorised it).</p>
<p>Talbot denounced Ormonde as an  old and feeble man  (in fact he was fifty, some years younger than Talbot himself), who  was  unfit to keep order in Ireland. He was accused of having lost most of his property through his own  negligence; there were vague references to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treason">treason</ref> and "crimes not fit for a bishop to speak of". The Council felt that it could not ignore the charges, and Ormonde was summoned to London to account for his actions. He defended himself with great vigour and was allowed to  keep  his office. He made numerous counter-charges against Talbot, including a charge of assaulting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Dyke">Robert Dyke</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_the_Rolls_in_Ireland">Master of the Rolls in Ireland</ref>, and other members of the Council. The Council in the end rebuked both sides in the dispute for weakening the Irish government by "creating divisions and rumours among the King's men".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Relations between the Talbots and the  Butlers did eventually improve, and to mark the two families'  reconciliation,  Ormonde's daughter Elizabeth married Shrewsbury's son and heir, the future <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Talbot,_2nd_Earl_of_Shrewsbury">2nd Earl</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> Talbot was removed from the office of Lord  Chancellor, though he acted as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justiciar_of_Ireland">Justiciar of Ireland</ref> and as  Lord Deputy during his brother's final term of office. He showed his usual spirit by refusing a second chance to become Archbishop of Armagh when Swayne at last  retired in 1439.</p>
<p>He died in Dublin on 15 August 1449, aged about sixty, and was buried in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Patrick's_Cathedral,_Dublin">St. Patrick's Cathedral, Dublin</ref>.  His brother John was killed at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Castillon">Battle of Castillon</ref> in 1453.</p>
<head>Character</head>
<p>Richard Talbot was undoubtedly  a man of great intelligence and strong character: O'Flanagan<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> thought him a man in every way as remarkable as his brother "the great Earl of Shrewsbury". On the other hand, he had serious character flaws, being high-handed, quarrelsome and undiplomatic. His feud with Archbishop Swayne weakened the  authority of the Church; and his quarrel with Ormonde, which seems to have been  personal, is generally agreed to have been a major factor in weakening English rule in Ireland. Even in  a turbulent age when cases of assault and even <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murder">murder</ref>  were common enough it was notable that Talbot, despite his clerical office, was prepared to use violence: in 1442 he was accused of  personally beating up two senior members of the Irish Council, Hugh Banent and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Dyke">Robert Dyke</ref>.</p>
</text>
