<text id="autogum_bio_doc611" title="Alice Chestre" shortTile="alice-chestre" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-05-15" dateModified="2019-06-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alice_Chestre" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Alice Chestre</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alice Chestre</hi> (sometimes written "Chester" or "Chestour") (died 1485) was a merchant and a benefactor of the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bristol,_England">Bristol, England</ref>.  She married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Chestre">Henry Chestre</ref> (or Chester), a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draper">draper</ref> who traded in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisbon">Lisbon</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bordeaux">Bordeaux</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brittany">Brittany</ref>, exporting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloth">cloth</ref> and importing other goods.  He was the third son of Robert Chester of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stow_St_Edward">Stow St Edward</ref>.</p>
<p>Henry died on 14 February 1471, while he was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_local_government_in_Bristol#Mayors">Mayor of Bristol</ref>. After a few <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benefaction">benefactions</ref>, he left all of his possessions to Alice in his short <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Will_(law)">will</ref>.  Alice took over her husband's business after his death.  As a businesswoman, she was a trader like her deceased husband, and imported iron and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wine">wine</ref> from Spain while exporting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Textiles">textiles</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ireland">Ireland</ref>, Lisbon, Spain, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flanders">Flanders</ref>, often in her own ships.  She amassed a very large fortune in this manner and donated freely to both her city and her local <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parish_church">parish church</ref>, that of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All_Saints,_Bristol">All Saints, Bristol</ref>.</p>
<p>Most of her donations were ecclesiastical.  She donated a house in Broad Street to All Saints, established a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chantry">chantry</ref> for her husband, commissioned a weekly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus">Jesus</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mass_(liturgy)">mass</ref> and two anniversary masses for her husband.  She also gave her church numerous embroideries (including a black and gold <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hearse">hearse</ref> cloth for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Funeral">funerals</ref>, bearing the words "Orate pro animabus Henrici Chester et Aliciae uxoris eius" ), ornate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Altar">altar</ref> fronts, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plate_(dishware)">plate</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silver">silver</ref> cross, and paid for a new <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rood">rood</ref> loft.  The church's record of benefactors refers to her, somewhat effusively, as "this blessed woman".  In religious terms, she was a pious woman who was dedicated to the emergent cultus of the holy name of Jesus.  As a widow, she was vigorously engaged in the world of business affairs and civic duties.  She gave the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Port_of_Bristol">Port of Bristol</ref> a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crane_(machine)">crane</ref> in 1475, at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Welsh_Back">Welsh Back</ref> which is the first evidence of a crane in the port. Record of the construction can be seen in the churchwardens' accounts for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All_Saints'_Church,_Bristol">All Saints' church</ref> (Ref. P/AS/Chw/1) (<ref target="http://archives.bristol.gov.uk/Record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=P.AS%2fChW%2f1&amp;pos=1">online catalogue</ref>), held by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bristol_Archives">Bristol Archives</ref>, which are currently on display at the  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M_Shed">M Shed</ref> museum.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In November 1472, she commissioned a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carpenter">carpenter</ref>, Stephen Morgan, to rebuild a house in the High Street, next to the Bull Inn (later the Angel Inn).  Extraordinarily, the building contract survives in the parish collection of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All_Saints'_Church,_Bristol">All Saints' church</ref> (Ref. P/AS/D/HS/C/9) (<ref target="http://archives.bristol.gov.uk/Record.aspx?src=CalmView.Catalog&amp;id=P.AS%2fD%2fHS%2fC%2f9&amp;pos=1">online catalogue</ref>), in the collections of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bristol_Archives">Bristol Archives</ref>, currently on display at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M_Shed">M Shed</ref> museum.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timber-framed">timber-framed</ref> house was completed in March the following year, with a shop on the ground floor, a hall above with an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oriel_window">oriel window</ref>, a chamber above the hall with another oriel window, and another chamber above the first.  The house is shown in drawings and photographs made before it collapsed in 1865.</p>
<p>One of her sons was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prior">Prior</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barlynch_Priory">Barlynch Priory</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Somerset">Somerset</ref>.  A second son inherited her house in High Street, and later donated it to All Saints.</p>
</text>
