<text id="autogum_bio_doc617" title="Sikandar Shah Miri" shortTile="sikandar-shah-miri" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-08-12" dateModified="2019-08-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sikandar_Shah_Miri" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sikandar Shah Miri</head>Not to be confused with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sikandar_Lodhi">Sikandar Lodhi</ref>, the Afghan Sultan of Delhi.
<p><hi rend="bold">Sikandar Shah Miri</hi> better known as <hi rend="bold">Sikandar Butshikan</hi> ("Sikandar the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iconoclast">Iconoclast</ref>"),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Kaw2004-1">[1]</ref> was the sixth <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sultan">sultan</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shah_Miri_dynasty">Shah Miri dynasty</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kashmir">Kashmir</ref>. He ruled the kingdom from 1389 to 1413 and is criticised for his strenuous efforts to convert the Hindus of Kashmir to Islam.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-google-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Rule</head>
<head>Persecution of Hindus</head>
<p>He is remembered by Hindus for perpetrating hardship upon his non-Muslim subjects in a bid to make them convert to Islam. It was under the influence of the Sufi saint, Mir Mohammad Hamadani, that he committed atrocities against non-Muslims in his lands. Large numbers of Hindus converted, fled, or were killed for refusal to convert during his reign.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-google-2">[2]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>A rare photo of the ruins of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surya">Surya</ref> Temple at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martand">Martand</ref>, which was destroyed due to the iconoclastic policies of Sikandar Butshikan, photo taken by John Burke in 1868.</caption></figure>
<p>Sikandar won the sobriquet of <hi rend="italic">but-shikan</hi> or idol-breaker, due to his actions related to the desecration and destruction of numerous temples, chaityas, viharas, shrines, hermitages, and other holy places of the Hindus and Buddhists. He banned dance, drama, music, iconography and such other religious, cultural or aesthetic activities of the Hindus and Buddhists, and classified them as heretical and un-Islamic. He forbade the Hindus to apply a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tilak">tilak mark</ref> on their foreheads. He did not permit them to pray and worship, blow a conch shell or even to toll a bell.So unspeakable was Sikandar's tyranny that he even stopped Hindus and Buddhists from cremating their dead and compelled them to bury the bodies using Muslim rituals. He imposed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jizya">Jizya</ref>, a poll-tax to be paid by non-Muslims living as subjects in a Muslim state, and the levy was a heavy one: each non-Muslim was required to pay an annual tax of four <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tola_(unit)">tolas</ref></hi> of silver. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-google-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Islamization of Kashmir</head>
<p>During the Shah Miri dynasty, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islam">Islam</ref> was firmly established in Kashmir and his rule has been considered controversial by some due to his rigid policies in Kashmir. In consonance with the customs in Delhi and elsewhere, Sikandar created the office of <hi rend="italic">Sheikh-ul-Islam</hi> and more important, decided that the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamic_law">Islamic law</ref> should be valid instead of the traditional law. But, as in other places, that may have been restricted mainly to the personal law.</p>
<p>It was during Sikander's reign that a wave of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sufi">Sufi</ref> saints headed by Mir Muhammad Hamadani (1372–1450) arrived in Kashmir in 1393. It is possibly under Hamadani's influence that Sultan Sikandar implemented an orthodox religious policy. The selling of wine, dancing of women, music and gambling were prohibited. The non-Mulsims had to pay <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jizya">jizya</ref></hi>, and were forbidden to display religious symbols like wearing <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tilak">tilak</ref></hi>. The Kashmiri chronicler <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonaraja">Jonaraja</ref> writes: </p>
<p>"The good fortune of the subjects left them and the king forgot his kingly duties and took delight, day and night, in breaking images.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>He [Sikander] prohibited all types of frugal games. Nobody dared commit acts which were prohibited by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sharia">Sharia</ref>. The Sultãn was constantly busy in annihilating Hindus and destroyed most of the temples.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>He strived to destroy the idols of the infidels. He demolished the famous temple of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shiva">Mahãdeva</ref> at Bahrãre. The temple was dug out from its foundations and the hole (that remained) reached the water level. Another temple at Jagdar was also demolished. Rãjã Alamãdat had got a big temple constructed at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sinpur">Sinpur</ref>. (...) The temple was destroyed [by Sikander].<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Sikander burnt all books the same wise as fire burns hay. All the scintillating works faced destruction in the same manner that lotus flowers face with the onset of frosty winter."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
</text>
