<text id="autogum_bio_doc547" title="Giovanni Antonio de Carbonariis" shortTile="giovanni-antonio" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-04-17" dateModified="2019-04-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Antonio_de_Carbonariis" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Giovanni Antonio de Carbonariis</head><p><hi rend="bold">Fr. (Brother) Giovanni Antonio de Carbonariis</hi> was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Order_of_Saint_Augustine">Augustinian Friar</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milan">Milan</ref> who served in London as envoy between the Duke of Milan and King Henry VII. He is known to have sailed with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Cabot">John Cabot</ref> (aka Giovanni Caboto) during his 1498 expedition to North America. He may have founded a mission settlement and North America's oldest, and only medieval, church at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carbonear,_Newfoundland_and_Labrador">Carbonear, Newfoundland and Labrador</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>History</head>
<p>Giovanni Antonio de Carbonariis accompanied Francesco Pagano’s diplomatic mission to London at the start of 1490, as did Christopher Carbonariis, who appears to have some family connection. Jones says that "de Carbonariis" appears to be a family name. Giovanni Carbonariis' association to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Cabot">John Cabot</ref> has been known since the 19th century, based on his letter of 20 June 1498 to the Duke of Milan. He said that ‘Messer Giovanni Antonio de Carbonariis’ had accompanied Cabot’s recently departed expedition. The Friar had left with five ships provided by King Henry VII of England.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> The Spanish envoy in London, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedro_de_Ayala">Pedro de Ayala</ref>, wrote to the Crown noting that one of the five ships in Cabot's expedition had been badly damaged in a storm and was forced to land in Ireland, leaving Cabot to sail on. The ambassador notes that on the damaged ship was ‘another Friar Buil.’ This was an allusion to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernardo_Buil">Bernardo Buil</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minim_(religious_order)">Minim</ref> missionary who had accompanied <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Columbus">Christopher Columbus</ref>'s 1493 expedition.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Based on limited information, historians thought that Carbonariis was a minor player in the expeditions, and may not have sailed further than Ireland. Historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Williamson_(historian)">James Williamson</ref> had ascertained that Carbonariis was 'a man of some importance', having served as an envoy between the Duke of Milan and Henry VII,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-friar-4">[4]</ref> but the friar had been overlooked by most historians since then interested in the English voyages of exploration from Bristol. </p>
<figure><caption>Augustinian</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alwyn_Ruddock">Alwyn Ruddock</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_London">University of London</ref> was one of the world's foremost experts on John Cabot's expedition and suggested in correspondence that Carbonariis had a more important role, but due to ill health was unable to publish her findings.  After her death in December 2005, all of her research notes and materials were destroyed, according to instructions in her will. Learning of her research, Dr Evan Jones of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Bristol">University of Bristol</ref> has re-investigated her claims, finding new documents and verifying some of her positions. This includes that Carbonariis was an Augustinian friar who had been educated in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pavia">Pavia</ref>. In the late 15th century, he was serving as the deputy papal tax collector in England. Since his principal, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adriano_Castellesi">Adriano Castellesi</ref>, had been in Rome since 1494, Carbonariis was in effective control of one of the most lucrative clerical appointments in England. In this period, the Church still owned about one third of the land in England, and the Pope took ten per cent of the income generated from that property.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-alwyn-5">[5]</ref> Based on his position, Carbonariis controlled institutional wealth and had access to King Henry. </p>
<p>Fr. Giovanni Antonio Carbonariis emerges as a key player in Ruddock's account of John Cabot's voyages. While she never published a full account, she claimed that he was the explorer's most important backer in England, having arranged for Cabot to get a loan from Italian bankers in London for an expedition after the Venetian arrived in London in 1495. Even more importantly, she suggests that it was Carbonariis who secured Cabot an audience with King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VII_of_England">Henry VII of England</ref>. In March 1496 Cabot and his three grown sons were granted royal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Letters_patent">Letters patent</ref> for westward exploration. Ruddock also claims that Carbonariis outfitted a ship, called the <hi rend="italic">Dominus Nobiscum</hi>, which accompanied the 1498 expedition. The ship carried other Italian friars who, with Carbonariis, are believed to have established a church and religious community in Newfoundland.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> In his account of this period, historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Hakluyt">Richard Hakluyt</ref> had mistakenly associated the friars and ship by that name with a 1527 voyage by Cabot's son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sebastian_Cabot_(explorer)">Sebastian Cabot</ref>; but, the latter's ships for that expedition were named <hi rend="italic">Samson</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mary of Guildford</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>While the religious community in Newfoundland is thought to have lasted at most only a few years, it would have been significant as North America's first Christian settlement. This church appears to have been named after the church of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Giovanni_a_Carbonara">San Giovanni a Carbonara</ref> in Naples, which was the mother church of a group of reformed Augustinian Friars called the 'Carbonara'. Dr Ruddock suggested that the community was located at what is now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carbonear,_Newfoundland_and_Labrador">Carbonear, Newfoundland and Labrador</ref>, the modern name being a relic survival of the 15th-century settlement.(Williamson had already noted a connection between the name of the papal deputy and Carbonear.)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-friar-4">[4]</ref> From 2010-14 archeological excavations were undertaken by Professor Peter Pope (d. 2017)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memorial_University_of_Newfoundland">Memorial University of Newfoundland</ref> in Carbonear to study its colonial history. Remains from the 17th into the 19th century were found.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-provarch-9">[9]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>Ruddock's book proposal and surviving letters to colleagues do not indicate the sources on which she based her claims about the North American settlement, but she had written of discovering more than 20 documents related to Cabot's voyages. Historian Evan Jones has investigated some of her claims and confirmed evidence for a 1499 voyage undertaken by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Weston_(explorer)">William Weston</ref>, a merchant of Bristol; he is now identified as the first Englishman to lead an expedition to North America.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> Evan Jones and co-researchers, including Margaret Condon (University of Bristol) and Dr Francesco Guidi Bruscoli (University of Florence), are carrying out further investigations of Dr Ruddock's claims as part of <ref target="http://www.bristol.ac.uk/history/research/cabot.html">The Cabot Project.</ref></p>
<head>External links and sources</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://archive.today/20111030104043/http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/119408885/abstract">'E. T. Jones, 'Alwyn Ruddock: "John Cabot and the Discovery of America "', <hi rend="italic">Historical Research</hi>, 81, (May, 2008), 235-6'</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://archive.today/20130105121003/http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/122579649/abstract">E. T. Jones, 'Henry VII and the Bristol expeditions to North America: the Condon documents'</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Historical Research</hi> (Early View, August 2009)'</item>
<item><ref target="https://archive.today/20121222211350/http://www.bris.ac.uk/history/contact/jones.html">'Dr Evan Jones'</ref>, staff page at University of Bristol</item>
<item><ref target="http://www.livescience.com/history/070416_cabot_church.html">'Mystery Surrounds Possible Oldest Church in North America'</ref>, Livescience, 16 April 2007</item>
<item><ref target="http://www.bris.ac.uk/news/2009/6515.html">'The lost voyage: First English-led expedition to North America'</ref>, 27 August 2009, Press release, University of Bristol</item>
<item><ref target="http://www.biographi.ca/en/bio/carbonariis_giovanni_antonio_de_1E.html">"Giovanni Antonio de Carbonariis"</ref>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dictionary_of_Canadian_Biography">Dictionary of Canadian Biography</ref> Online</hi></item></list>
</text>
