<text id="autogum_bio_doc643" title="Valentina Visconti, Duchess of Orléans" shortTile="valentina-visconti" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-03-20" dateModified="2019-03-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valentina_Visconti%2C_Duchess_of_Orl%C3%A9ans" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Valentina Visconti, Duchess of Orléans</head>Not to be confused with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valentina_Visconti,_Queen_of_Cyprus">Valentina Visconti, Queen of Cyprus</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Valentina Visconti</hi> (1371 – 4 December 1408) was a Sovereign Countess of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vertus">Vertus</ref>, and Duchess consort of Orléans as the wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_de_Valois,_Duke_of_Orléans">Louis de Valois, Duke of Orléans</ref>, the younger brother of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_VI_of_France">Charles VI of France</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Adams255-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Valentina was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milan">Milan</ref> as the second of the four children of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gian_Galeazzo_Visconti">Gian Galeazzo Visconti</ref>, the first Duke of Milan,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Azzolini120-3">[3]</ref> and his first wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabella,_Countess_of_Vertus">Isabelle</ref>, a daughter of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_II_of_France">John II the Good</ref> of France. She was probably named after her paternal great-grandmother Valentina Doria, wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefano_Visconti">Stefano Visconti</ref>.</p>
<p>After her mother's death in childbirth in 1373, Valentina and her siblings were raised by their paternal grandmother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bianca_of_Savoy">Bianca of Savoy</ref> and aunt <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Violante_Visconti">Violante Visconti</ref>. The deaths of her brothers Carlo (1374), Gian Galeazzo (1376) and Azzone (1381) left Valentina as the only surviving child of her parents' marriage and the sovereign Countess of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vertus">Vertus</ref>, a title she shared with her spouse.</p>
<p>In 1380, a marriage was negotiated with her cousin Carlo Visconti, Lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parma">Parma</ref> (fourth son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernabò_Visconti">Bernabò Visconti</ref>, Lord of Milan) and a papal dispensation was even granted; however, Bernabò later annulled the betrothal and, in 1382, married his son to a French noblewoman, Beatrice of Armagnac.</p>
<p>The death of Bernabò in 1385 left Gian Galeazzo as the sole ruler over the Visconti inheritance, and with this Valentina's status changed considerably. At this point, the new Lord of Milan opened negotiations with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslaus_IV_of_Bohemia">King Wenceslaus of Germany and Bohemia</ref> for a marriage between Valentina and his half-brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Görlitz">John of Görlitz</ref>; at the same time, he also negotiated a union with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_II_of_Naples">Louis II of Anjou, titular King of Naples</ref> (who was at that time was betrothed to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucia_Visconti">Lucia Visconti</ref>, one of Bernabò's daughters). However, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marie_of_Blois,_Duchess_of_Anjou">Marie of Blois, Dowager Duchess of Anjou</ref> finally cancelled the negotiations, and then Gian Galeazzo turned his attention to his nephew-by-marriage <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_I,_Duke_of_Orléans">Louis, Duke of Touraine</ref>, second son of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_V_of_France">Charles V of France</ref> and brother of the reigning <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_VI_of_France">Charles VI</ref>. King Wenceslaus became aware of the double game of Gian Galeazzo, and broke off the negotiations with a letter full of insults, leaving Louis the only suitor of Valentina, his first cousin.</p>
<p>Because of the close relationship between bride and groom, a papal dispensation was granted on 25 November 1386, and the marriage contract was signed on 27 January 1387 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris">Paris</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Azzolini120-3">[3]</ref> Valentina received as a dowry the County of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vertus">Vertus</ref> (which was the dowry of her own mother at the time of her marriage in 1348) and the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asti">Asti</ref>, with the sums of 450,000 florins in cash and 75,000 florins in jewelry. In the contract was also stipulated that in absence of male heirs, Valentina would inherit the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visconti_of_Milan">Visconti</ref> dominions. It was because of this, that her grandson <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_XII_of_France">Louis XII of France</ref> claimed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Milan">Duchy of Milan</ref> and embarked on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italian_Wars">Italian Wars</ref>. The marriage by proxy was celebrated three months later, on 8 April, in both the Milanese and French courts.</p>
<p>Valentina was only able to leave Milan for France on 23 June 1389, because of "reasons of security" given to her father: in fact, Gian Galeazzo wanted to amend the marriage contract after the pregnancy of his second wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caterina_Visconti">Caterina Visconti</ref> (another Bernabò's daughters) ended. Only after the birth of his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gian_Maria_Visconti">Gian Maria</ref> on 7 September 1388 did he feel secure enough to send his daughter to France.</p>
<p>Escorted by her paternal cousin <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amadeus_VII,_Count_of_Savoy">Amadeus VII, Count of Savoy</ref> and a retinue of 300 knights, Valentina was finally handed to Louis's envoys. The formal marriage took place in the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melun">Melun</ref>, on 17 August 1389.</p>
<p>The union produced eight children:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>A son (born and died in Paris, 25 March 1390), buried in Paris église Saint-Paul.</item>
<item>Louis (Paris, Hôtel de Saint-Pol, 26 May 1391 - September 1395), buried in Paris église des Célestins.</item>
<item>John (September 1393 - Château de Vincennes, bef. 31 October 1393), buried in Paris église des Célestins.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles,_Duke_of_Orléans">Charles, Duke of Orléans</ref> (Hôtel royal de Saint-Pol, Paris, 24 November 1394 - Château d'Amboise, Indre-et-Loire, 4 January 1465),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Adams255-1">[1]</ref> father of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_XII_of_France">Louis XII of France</ref>.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip,_Count_of_Vertus">Philip, Count of Vertus</ref> (Asnières-sur-Oise, Val d'Oise, 21/24 July 1396 - Beaugency, Loiret, 1 September 1420).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Adams255-1">[1]</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John,_Count_of_Angoulême">John, Count of Angoulême</ref> (24 June 1399 – Château de Cognac, Charente, 30 April 1467),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Adams255-1">[1]</ref> grandfather of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_I_of_France">Francis I of France</ref>.</item>
<item>Marie (Château de Coucy, Aisne, April 1401 - died shortly after birth).</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret,_Countess_of_Vertus">Margaret</ref> (4 December 1406 - Abbaye de Laguiche, near Blois, 24 April 1466), married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard,_Count_of_Étampes">Richard of Brittany, Count of Étampes</ref>. She received the County of Vertus as a dowry.</item></list>
<p>In 1392 her husband exchanged the Duchy of Touraine for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_of_Orléans">Duchy of Orléans</ref>; since then, Valentina was styled <hi rend="italic">Duchess of Orléans</hi>.</p>
<p>Because of intrigues at the court of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_VI_of_France">Charles VI of France</ref> and the enmity of the queen, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabeau_of_Bavaria-Ingolstadt">Isabeau of Bavaria-Ingolstadt</ref>, Valentina was exiled from the court and had to leave Paris. There were rumours that Isabeau was having an affair with Louis and that Valentina was very close to the King, who was in poor mental health.</p>
<p>A patroness of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eustache_Deschamps">Eustache Deschamps</ref>, who wrote poetry in her honour, she was also the mother of one of France's most famous poets, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles,_Duke_of_Orléans">Charles of Orléans</ref>.</p>
<p>Louis de Valois' murder was orchestrated by his cousin and political rival <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_the_Fearless">John the Fearless, Duke of Burgundy</ref> in 1407.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> Valentina outlived her husband by only a little over a year, dying at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blois">Blois</ref> at the age of 37.</p>
<head>Ancestors</head>
</text>
