<text id="autogum_bio_doc706" title="Maud de Ufford, Countess of Oxford" shortTile="maud-de-ufford-countess" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-11-05" dateModified="2019-10-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maud_de_Ufford%2C_Countess_of_Oxford" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Maud de Ufford, Countess of Oxford</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Maud de Ufford, Countess of Oxford</hi> (1345/1346 – 25 January 1413) was a wealthy English noblewoman and the wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_de_Vere,_8th_Earl_of_Oxford">Thomas de Vere, 8th Earl of Oxford</ref>. Her only child was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_de_Vere,_9th_Earl_of_Oxford">Robert de Vere, 9th Earl of Oxford</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Favourite">favourite</ref> of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_II_of_England">Richard II of England</ref>. In 1404 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Essex">Essex</ref>, she took part in a conspiracy against King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_IV_of_England">Henry IV of England</ref> and was sent to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tower_of_London">Tower of London</ref>; however, she was eventually pardoned through the efforts of Queen consort <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_of_Navarre,_Queen_of_England">Joanna of Navarre</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>She resided in the village of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Bentley">Great Bentley</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Essex">Essex</ref>.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Maud was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ireland">Ireland</ref> sometime in about 1345 or 1346. Her parents were Sir Ralph de Ufford, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justiciar_of_Ireland">Justiciar of Ireland</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maud_of_Lancaster">Maud of Lancaster</ref>, widow of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Donn_de_Burgh,_3rd_Earl_of_Ulster">William Donn de Burgh, 3rd Earl of Ulster</ref>. Maud was their only child and heiress, although she had a uterine half-sister, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_de_Burgh,_4th_Countess_of_Ulster">Elizabeth de Burgh</ref>, who was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suo_jure">suo jure</ref> Countess of Ulster. </p>
<p>On 9 April 1346, Maud's father died in Kilmainham. Sir Ralph had been an incompetent Justiciar, and was disliked by the Irish.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> Maud, who was a baby, and her mother fled to England. Sometime between 8 August 1347 and 25 April 1348, Maud's mother became a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canoness">canoness</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augustinian">Augustinian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Campsey_Priory">Priory of Campsey</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suffolk">Suffolk</ref>.</p>
<head>Marriage</head>
<p>Sometime before 10 June 1350, when she was still a child, she married Thomas de Vere, son and heir of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_de_Vere,_7th_Earl_of_Oxford">John de Vere, 7th Earl of Oxford</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maud_de_Badlesmere">Maud de Badlesmere</ref>. He would succeed to the title of 8th Earl in 1360; henceforth, Maud was styled as the Countess of Oxford. The marriage produced one son:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_de_Vere,_9th_Earl_of_Oxford">Robert de Vere, 9th Earl of Oxford</ref>, Marquess of Dublin, Duke of Ireland (16 January 1362- 1392), married firstly, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philippa_de_Coucy">Philippa de Coucy</ref>, and secondly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agnes_de_Launcekrona">Agnes de Launcekrona</ref>.</item></list>
<p>Maud's husband died in September 1371. Maud was provided-for in terms of dower and jointure; from 1371, she held nearly half the de Vere ancestral estates and she received an annual income of £662.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Her principal residence was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Bentley">Great Bentley</ref> in Essex. She was described as a profligate landowner,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> and later engaged in litigations with her brother-in-law, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aubrey_de_Vere,_10th_Earl_of_Oxford">Aubrey de Vere, 10th Earl of Oxford</ref> over de Vere property.</p>
<p>In 1387, when her son Robert repudiated his first wife, Philippa for Agnes de Launcekrona, a Czech lady-in-waiting of Queen consort <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_of_Bohemia">Anne of Bohemia</ref>, Maud took Philippa's side against her son. She admitted to holding Philippa "more dear than as if she had been her own daughter",<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> and did not hesitate to curse Robert for his actions. Philippa was afterwards taken into Maud's household. Despite her anger at her son's treatment of his wife, Maud nevertheless visited him in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Brabant">Brabant</ref> following his forced exile by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lords_Appellant">Lords Appellant</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_England">Parliament</ref> in 1388, where she brought him gifts. She received a pardon on 10 May 1391 for "having crossed the sea without licence to Brabant to confer with her son Robert de Vere, late earl of Oxford, and for relieving him with certain gifts".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> Maud remained in high favour with King Richard after her son's exile, having received on 16 November 1389 a grant of the farm of all the lands "lately her husband's" for twenty years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> This was cancelled upon her son's death in 1392, when his uncle Aubrey succeeded as Earl of Oxford.</p>
<head>Conspiracy</head>
<p>In 1404, Maud involved herself in a conspiracy along with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbot">abbots</ref> of Beeleigh, Colchester, and St. Osyth to depose King Henry IV by way of a French invasion, and replace him with King Richard who was allegedly still alive. It was also alleged that she had caused the white harts of Richard II's livery to be fashioned.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> She was arrested and sent to the Tower of London in May 1404; however, due to the intervention of Queen consort Joanna of Navarre, she was eventually pardoned by King Henry on 16 November 1404.</p>
<p>Maud died on 25 January 1413 at her residence in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Bentley">Great Bentley, Essex</ref> and was buried at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bruisyard_Abbey">Bruisyard Abbey</ref> in Suffolk instead of the monastery of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl's_Colne">Earl's Colne</ref> of which she had been the patron, and where her husband and son were buried.</p>
</text>
