<text id="autogum_bio_doc457" title="James Altham" shortTile="james-altham" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-12-17" dateModified="2018-10-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Altham" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>James Altham</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Sir James Altham</hi> (died 1617) was an English judge.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Altham was descended from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Altham">Christopher Altham</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Girlington">Girlington</ref>, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West_Riding_of_Yorkshire">West Riding of Yorkshire</ref>. He was the third son of James Altham of Mark Hall, Latton, in Essex, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheriff_of_London">Sheriff of London</ref> in 1557–58, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_Sheriff_of_Essex">sheriff of Essex</ref> in 1570, by Elizabeth Blancke, daughter of Thomas Blancke of London, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Worshipful_Company_of_Haberdashers">Haberdasher</ref>, and sister of Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Blanke">Thomas Blanke</ref>, who was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Mayor_of_London">Lord Mayor of London</ref> in 1583. Altham was educated at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trinity_College,_Cambridge">Trinity College, Cambridge</ref>, entered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gray's_Inn">Gray's Inn</ref> in 1575 and was called to the bar in 1581.</p>
<p>He is mentioned in Croke's reports for the first time as arguing a case in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen's_Bench">Queen's Bench</ref> in 1587. In 1589 he was elected M.P. for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bramber_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Bramber</ref> in Sussex. He was knighted in 1605.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Legal career</head>
<p>He was appointed reader at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gray's_Inn">Gray's Inn</ref> in 1600, and in 1603 double reader (duplex lector). In the same year he was made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serjeant-at-law">serjeant-at-law</ref>. In 1606 he was appointed one of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barons_of_the_exchequer">barons of the exchequer</ref>, in succession to Sir J. Savile, and knighted. In 1610, a question having arisen concerning the power of the crown to impose restrictions on trade and industry by proclamation, the two chief justices, the chief baron, and Baron Altham were appointed to consider the matter. The result of their consultation was that they unanimously resolved "that the king by his proclamation cannot create any offence which was not an offence before...  That the king hath no prerogative but that which the law of the land allows him... and lastly, that if an offence be not punishable in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Chamber">Star Chamber</ref>, the prohibition of it by proclamation cannot make it punishable there."’</p>
<p>Altham was one of the judges whose opinion was taken in 1611 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chancellor_Ellesmere">Lord Chancellor Ellesmere</ref> on the case of the heretics <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bartholomew_Legate">Bartholomew Legate</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Wightman">Edward Wightman</ref>, whom <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_Abbot">Archbishop Abbot</ref> wanted burned. Altham was reputed hostile to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Coke">Edward Coke</ref>, who was deliberately not consulted. The two men were burned, one at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smithfield,_London">Smithfield</ref>, the other at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burton-upon-Trent">Burton-upon-Trent</ref>.</p>
<p>Altham's signature, together with those of the other twelve judges, is appended to the letter to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_I_of_England">the king</ref> relative to his action in the <hi rend="italic">commendam</hi> case, in which the power of the crown to stay proceedings in the courts of justice in matters affecting its prerogative is denied. A serjeant-at-law, in arguing a case involving the right of the crown to grant commendams, i.e. licences to hold benefices that otherwise would be vacated, had in the performance of his duty disputed, first, the existence of any such prerogative except in cases of necessity; secondly, the possibility of any such case arising. The thereupon wrote by his attorney-general, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Bacon">Francis Bacon</ref>, a letter addressed to Lord Coke requiring that all proceedings in the cause should be stayed. This letter having been communicated to the judges, they assembled, and after consultation the letter already mentioned was sent to the king. The king replied by convening a council and summoning the judges to attend thereat. They attended, and, having been admonished by the king and the attorney-general, all, with the exception of Coke, fell upon their knees, acknowledged their error, and promised amendment.</p>
<p>Altham died on 21 February 1617, and the lord keeper, Sir Francis Bacon, in appointing his successor, characterised the late baron as "one of the gravest and most reverend of the judges of this kingdom." He was buried in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxhey_Chapel">Oxhey Chapel</ref>, built by himself on his estate at Oxhey in Hertfordshire, where a monument still preserves his memory and that of his third wife, who died on 21 April 1638.</p>
<head>Family life</head>
<p>By his first wife, Margaret, daughter of Oliver Skinner, Altham had issue one child only, a son James, afterwards Sir James Altham of Oxhey, knight. This Sir James Altham married Elizabeth, daughter of Sir Richard Sutton of London, and had issue a boy, who died in infancy, and two daughters, Elizabeth and Frances.</p>
<p>Elizabeth Altham married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Annesley,_1st_Earl_of_Anglesey">Arthur Annesley, 1st Earl of Anglesey</ref>, second <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viscount_Valentia">Viscount Valentia</ref> and first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Anglesey">Earl of Anglesey</ref>, whose second son, Altham Annesley, was created in 1680 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_Altham">Baron Altham</ref> of Altham, with limitation in default of male issue to his younger brothers. His only son dying in infancy, the title devolved upon the younger branch of the Annesley family, who subsequently succeeded to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earldom_of_Anglesey">earldom of Anglesey</ref>. The earldom lapsed in 1771, when the English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Lords">House of Lords</ref> decided against the legitimacy of the last claimant.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frances_Vaughan,_Countess_of_Carbery">Frances</ref>, the second daughter of Sir James Altham of Oxhey, married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Vaughan,_2nd_Earl_of_Carbery">Richard Vaughan, 2nd Earl of Carbery</ref>. The title lapsed in 1713.</p>
<p>By his second wife, Mary, daughter of Richard Stapers, Esq., Altham had three children, a son Richard, who died without issue; two daughters, Elizabeth and Mary. Elizabeth married first Sir Francis Astley of Hill Morton and Melton, knight, then <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Digby,_1st_Baron_Digby">Robert Digby, 1st Baron Digby</ref> (c. 1599–1642) (Irish peerage), and lastly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Robert_Bernard,_1st_Baronet">Sir Robert Bernard, 1st Baronet</ref>, serjeant-at-law. Mary married Sir Francis Stydolph (d. 1655) and was the mother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stydolph_baronets">Sir Richard Stydolph, Baronet</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>By his third wife, Helen Saunderson, Altham had no children.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Altham">Robert Altham</ref>, currently a circuit judge is one of his descendants.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-LG-3">[3]</ref></p>
</text>
