<text id="autogum_bio_doc701" title="Euthymius of Tarnovo" shortTile="euthymius-tarnovo" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-07-23" dateModified="2019-11-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euthymius_of_Tarnovo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Euthymius of Tarnovo</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saint Euthymius of Tarnovo</hi> (also <hi rend="italic">Evtimiy</hi>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarian_language">Bulgarian</ref>: Свети Евтимий Търновски, <hi rend="italic">Sveti Evtimiy Tarnovski</hi>) was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarch_of_Bulgaria">Patriarch of Bulgaria</ref> between 1375 and 1393. Regarded as one of the most important figures of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medieval">medieval</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgaria">Bulgaria</ref>, Euthymius was the last head of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarian_Orthodox_Church">Bulgarian Orthodox Church</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Bulgarian_Empire">Second Bulgarian Empire</ref>. Arguably the best esteemed of all Bulgarian patriarchs, Euthymius was a supporter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hesychasm">hesychasm</ref> and an authoritative figure in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_Orthodox">Eastern Orthodox</ref> world of the time.</p>
<head>Early years</head>
<p>Born around 1325 (between 1320–1330) and possibly an offspring of the eminent Tsamblak family of the capital <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarnovo">Tarnovo</ref>, Euthymius was educated at the monastery schools in and around the city and became a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monk">monk</ref>. He joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kilifarevo_Monastery">Kilifarevo Monastery</ref> around 1350, attracted by the fame of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodosius_of_Tarnovo">Theodosius of Tarnovo</ref>. Theodosius appointed him his first assistant in 1363 and the two went together to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tsarigrad">Tsarigrad</ref>, with Theodosius dying soon afterwards.</p>
<p>Euthymius then consecutively joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Studion">Studion</ref> monastery and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Lavra">Great Lavra</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Athanasius_the_Athonite">Athanasius the Athonite</ref> on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mount_Athos">Mount Athos</ref>. He was influenced by outstanding scholars and reformers of Southeastern Europe's spiritual life, such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gregory_the_Sinaite">Gregory the Sinaite</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gregory_Palamas">Gregory Palamas</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Callistus_Philotheus">Callistus Philotheus</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Kukuzelis">John Kukuzelis</ref>. He was sent into exile on the island of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lemnos">Lemnos</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_Emperor">Byzantine Emperor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_V_Palaiologos">John V Palaiologos</ref> and, upon his release, returned to the Bulgarian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zograf_Monastery">Zograf Monastery</ref> on Mount Athos. It was there that he first reflected on the spelling reforms and planned corrections to the translations of the clerical books.</p>
<head>Activity in Bulgaria</head>
<p>Around 1371 Euthymius returned to Bulgaria and founded the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Trinity_Patriarchal_Monastery">Holy Trinity Patriarchal Monastery</ref> near Tarnovo, where he grounded the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarnovo_Literary_School">Tarnovo Literary School</ref>. He established <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orthography">orthographic</ref> rules and corrected inaccurately translated religious books by comparing them to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medieval_Greek">Greek</ref> originals. These corrected texts became models for the Orthodox churches using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_Slavonic_language">Church Slavonic language</ref>: Bulgaria, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbia">Serbia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romania">Romania</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukraine</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gregory_Tsamblak">Gregory Tsamblak</ref>, his biographer, compared Euthymius' work to that of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moses">Moses</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ptolemaic_Kingdom">Egyptian</ref> king <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ptolemy_I_Soter">Ptolemy I</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1375, following the death of Patriarch Joanicius, Euthymius was elected to become his successor. A supporter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asceticism">asceticism</ref>, Euthymius aimed to persecute <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heresy">heresies</ref> and moral decay. Euthymius became a prominent figure in the Orthodox world and a number of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan_bishop">metropolitans</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hegumen">hegumens</ref> addressed him to interpret theological matters.</p>
<p>There are 15 known works by Euthymius, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liturgical_book">liturgical books</ref>, laudatory works, passionals and epistles. Among his literary disciples are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gregory_Tsamblak">Gregory Tsamblak</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan_of_Kiev">Metropolitan of Kiev</ref>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyprian,_Metropolitan_of_Moscow">Cyprian</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan_of_Moscow">Metropolitan of Moscow</ref>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joasaph_of_Bdin">Joasaph of Bdin</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantine_of_Kostenets">Constantine of Kostenets</ref>.</p>
<head>Establishment of Tarnovo Literary School and language reform</head>
<p>During the time of patriarch Theodosius of Tarnovo Euthymius founded and ran the Tarnovo literary school, which was to quickly become an important cultural center of the Slavic Christian world.
Euthymius initiated a language reform in  Old Bulgarian that was widely influential to the standardized literary languages of Serbia, Walachia, Moldova, and the Ukrainian principalities.</p>
<p>Partial list of works:</p>
<p>Hagiographies</p>
<p>“Hagiography of St. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_of_Rila">Ivan of Rila</ref>”</p>
<p>“Hagiography of St. Ilarion Maglenski”</p>
<p>“Hagiography of St. Philothea Temnishka”</p>
<p>“Hagiography of St. Petka of Tarnovo”</p>
<p>Praises</p>
<p>“Praise for Mikhail Warrior”</p>
<p>“Praise for Ioan Polivotski”</p>
<p>“Praise for St. Nedelya”</p>
<p>“Praise for St. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantine_I">Constantine</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helena_of_Constantinople">Helena</ref>”</p>
<p>Letters</p>
<p>“Letter to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyprian,_Metropolitan_of_Moscow">Cyprian</ref>"</p>
<p>“Letter to metropolitan Arsenius”</p>
<p>“Letter to Nikodim – monk of Tismana”</p>
<head>Fall of Tarnovo and its consequences</head>
<p>In the spring of 1393 the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Dynasty">Sultan</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayezid_I">Bayezid I</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suleyman_Çelebi">Suleyman Çelebi</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Tarnovo">laid siege</ref> to the Bulgarian capital Tarnovo with his sizable forces. With <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Bulgarian_monarchs">Tsar</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Shishman_of_Bulgaria">Ivan Shishman</ref> out of the city (leading the remnants of his troops to the fortress of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikopol,_Bulgaria">Nikopol</ref>), Euthymius was the one entrusted with the defense of Tarnovo. After a three-month siege on 17 July 1393, the Ottomans captured the capital despite its ferocious resistance; Gregory Tsamblak several years later suggested the conquest was due to treason from one of the non-Christian neighborhoods of Tarnovo.</p>
<p>Joasaph of Bdin, Metropolitan of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vidin">Vidin</ref>, a contemporary of the event, described it as follows: "A great Muslim invasion happened and total destruction was done with this city and its surroundings." According to Gregory Tsamblak, churches were turned into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mosque">mosques</ref>, priests were expelled and substituted with "teachers of shamelessness." 110 noted citizens of Tarnovo and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boyar">boyars</ref> were massacred, but Patriarch Euthymius was reprieved and sent into exile in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macedonia_(theme)">theme of Macedonia</ref> (contemporary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thrace">Thrace</ref>), possibly in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bachkovo_Monastery">Bachkovo Monastery</ref>. He is supposed to have died there in 1402–1404. The Tarnovo Patriarchate thereupon ceased to exist as the Bulgarian church lost its independence and became subordinate to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarchate_of_Constantinople">Patriarchate of Constantinople</ref> until 1870.</p>
<p>Patriarch Euthymius has been <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canonized">canonized</ref> and his memory is honored on the same day as that of his namesake <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euthymius_the_Great">Euthymius the Great</ref>, 20 January.</p>
<head>Commemoration</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Evtimiy_Crag">St. Evtimiy Crag</ref> on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Livingston_Island">Livingston Island</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Shetland_Islands">South Shetland Islands</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antarctica">Antarctica</ref> is named after Patriarch Euthymius of Bulgaria.</p>
</text>
