<text id="autogum_bio_doc037" title="Alexander A. Balandin" shortTile="alexander--balandin" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-23" dateModified="2019-09-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_A._Balandin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Alexander A. Balandin</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alexander A. Balandin</hi> is an electrical engineer and materials scientist known for his studies of phonons and excitons in nanostructures, experimental and theoretical investigation of thermal properties of graphene, electronic 1/f noise in novel materials and devices as well as for his works on practical applications of semiconductor nanostructures and graphene in electronics, optoelectronics and energy conversion.</p>
<head>Academic career</head>
<p>Alexander A. Balandin received his BS in 1989 and MS in 1991 degrees summa cum laude in Applied Physics and Mathematics from the Moscow Institute of Physics &amp; Technology (MIPT), Russia. He received his second MS in 1995 and PhD in 1996 degrees in Electrical Engineering from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Notre_Dame">University of Notre Dame</ref>, USA. From 1997 to 1999, he worked as Research Engineer in the Device Research Laboratory at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_California,_Los_Angeles">University of California, Los Angeles</ref> (UCLA). In 1999 he joined the Department of Electrical Engineering, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_California,_Riverside">University of California, Riverside</ref> (UCR), where he is Professor of Electrical Engineering and Founding Chair of Materials Science and Engineering (MS&amp;E). He is Director of the Nano-Device Laboratory (NDL), which he organized in 2000. In 2005, he was a Visiting Professor at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Cambridge">University of Cambridge</ref>, U.K. As the Founding Chair of the interdisciplinary MS&amp;E program, he led the UCR efforts for introducing BS, MS and PhD degrees in MS&amp;E.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Research</head>
<p>Professor Balandin’s research interests are in the area of advanced materials, nanostructures and nanodevices for electronics, optoelectronics and renewable energy conversion. He conducts both experimental and theoretical research. Balandin and coworkers were among the pioneers of the field of phonon engineering.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> In 1998, he published an influential paper on the effects of phonon spatial confinement on thermal conductivity of nanostructures<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> (where the term “phonon engineering” likely appeared for the first time in a journal publication). Phonon engineering finds application in thermoelectric energy conversion and thermal management of advanced electronics. He has contributed to development of GaN technology by investigating heat conduction in GaN films<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> and studying 1/f noise in GaN devices.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> He advanced ZnO technology by studying excitonic effects, confined phonon and optical properties of wurtzite nanostructures.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> In 2008, Balandin’s group authored a highly cited paper on the first measurement of thermal conductivity of suspended graphene.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> In order to perform the first measurement of thermal properties of graphene, Balandin invented a new optothermal experiment technique based on Raman spectroscopy. He and his coworkers explained theoretically why the intrinsic thermal conductivity of graphene can be higher than that of bulk graphite,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> and demonstrated experimentally the evolution of heat conduction when the system dimensionality changes from 2D (graphene) to 3D (graphite).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> Balandin’s group advanced the graphene field by demonstrating the low-noise top-gate graphene transistor<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> and graphene triple-mode amplifier and phase detector. The layman description of the unusual thermal properties of graphene can be found in IEEE Spectrum feature article.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> Balandin's group has also reported the first "graphene-like" mechanical exfoliation of atomically thin films of topological insulators<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> and other materials.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> Balandin group’s research achievements were highlighted in Nature, Nature Nanotechnology, IEEE Spectrum, MIT Technology Review, Materials Today, Physics World, nationally syndicated radio programs and other media worldwide.</p>
<head>Honors and awards</head>
<p>Balandin received the following honors and awards:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Fellow, The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Physical_Society">American Physical Society</ref> (APS)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></item>
<item>Fellow, IEEE<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref></item>
<item>IEEE <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pioneer_Award_in_Nanotechnology">Pioneer Award in Nanotechnology</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-20">[20]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-21">[21]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-22">[22]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-23">[23]</ref></item>
<item>Fellow, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Institute_of_Physics">The Institute of Physics, U.K. (IOP)</ref></item>
<item>Fellow, The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optical_Society_of_America">Optical Society of America</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-24">[24]</ref></item>
<item>Fellow, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SPIE">The International Society for Optical Engineering</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-25">[25]</ref></item>
<item>Fellow, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Association_for_the_Advancement_of_Science">American Association for the Advancement of Science</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-26">[26]</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Science_Foundation">National Science Foundation</ref> (NSF) Career Award</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office_of_Naval_Research">Office of Naval Research</ref> (ONR) Young Investigator Award</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_California">University of California</ref> Regents Award</item>
<item>The Merrill Lynch Innovation Award for “commercially valuable engineering research”</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CRDF_Global">US Civil Research and Development Foundation</ref>US Civil Research and Development Foundation (CRDF) Young Investigator Award</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eta_Kappa_Nu">Eta Kappa Nu</ref> Engineering Honor Society</item>
<item>Medal from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Materials_Research_Society">Materials Research Society</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-1">[1]</ref></item></list>
<p>In 2018 Balandin had received two grants from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DARPA">DARPA</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semiconductor_Research_Corporation">Semiconductor Research Corporation</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-27">[27]</ref></p>
<head>Nano-Device Laboratory - Balandin Group</head>
<figure><caption>Dr. Balandin's Group logo</caption></figure>
<p>NDL research group conducts theoretical and experimental research on nanostructures and novel materials and their applications in electronics, optoelectronics and renewable energy conversion.</p>
</text>
