<text id="autogum_bio_doc361" title="Tugal Caris" shortTile="tugal-caris" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-04-18" dateModified="2019-05-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tugal_Caris" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tugal Caris</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tugal Caris</hi> (late 16th century – 1665 or 1666), also spelled <hi rend="bold">Carris</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Cariste</hi>, was a 17th-century French sculptor and architect.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Caris was born in the late sixteenth century or early seventeenth century. In 1630, he was associated in a market with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Martinet_(architect)">Jean Martinet</ref> for the purchase of 600 carts of stones from the Couldre and Bootz quarries at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Changé,_Mayenne">Changé</ref>. He then lived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laval,_Mayenne">Laval</ref>. This purchase did not concern the construction of altarpieces.</p>
<p>He was the husband of Jeanne Barais, probably the sister of Catherine Barais, wife of the architect Michel Bellier.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> They had several children, including a son Jacques Caris who moved to Nantes where, after having been associated with his father, he became an architect.</p>
<head>Origins</head>
<list type="ordered"><item>Marie Bellier, wife of Antoine Agenyau, architect.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></item>
<item>Michel Bellier,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> architect, husband of Catherine Barais.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></item>
<item>Louise Bellier, wife of Philippe Bault, lawyer at Rennes</item>
<item>Guillaume Bellier</item>
<item>Renée Bellier, wife of Jean Martinet, architect</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olivier_Martinet">Olivier Martinet</ref>, architect</item></list>
<head>Lavallois Rededos</head>
<p>His first known altarpiece is that of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaiges">Vaiges</ref>, now missing, built in 1634. He can probably also be attributed the realization of the altar Saint-Denis at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint-Denis-du-Maine">Saint-Denis-du-Maine</ref> in 1632, and the altar Saint-Pierre at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soulgé-sur-Ouette">Nuillé-sur-Ouette</ref> in 1633. From 1634 to 1636, he erected the altarpiece<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Redon_Abbey">Saint-Sauveur Abbey of Redon</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> Caris is also attributed the two side altars of this church, but which do not date from the same period.</p>
<p>In June 1636, he was in Laval where he contested the quality of the marble ordered from Étienne Arnoul, and asked for an expertise from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Corbineau">Pierre Corbineau</ref> and Jean Martinet. After Redon's realization, he made an altarpiece at the church of the Cordeliers of Rennes in 1636, then from 1637 to 1639, the high altar of the Saint-Vénérand church of Laval.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> Around 1639, he made the main altarpiece of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tréguier_Cathedral">Tréguier Cathedral</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> At the same time, he raised two altarpieces at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bonchamp-lès-Laval">Bonchamp-lès-Laval</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1640, he realized the high altar and the altar of the Rosary of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Église_Saint-Martin_de_Châtillon-sur-Colmont">Saint-Martin church of Châtillon-sur-Colmont</ref>. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reredos">reredos</ref> of the right altar, representing the Virgin Mary, is composed of small medallions. In each medallion, a mystery of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rosary">Rosary</ref> is represented as a scene.</p>
<list type="unordered">
<item>Altarpiece of the Rosary of the Church of  Chatillon-sur-Colmont.</item>
<item>Main altar and altarpiece (church of Brée), attributed to Tugal Caris.</item>
</list>
<head>Architect at Rennes and Nantes</head>
<p>After the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Retable_lavallois">lavallois reredos</ref>, he moved to architecture, and was entrusted with the realization of the façade of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rennes_Cathedral">Rennes Cathedral</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> He built the large portal and part of the towers from 1640 to 1654. He then became <hi rend="italic">entrepreneur du <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_Brittany">Palace of Rennes</ref></hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> whose construction he resumed after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacques_Corbineau">Jacques Corbineau</ref>. He signed with the community of the city of Rennes on 28 April 1640 for the "continuation of work on the side of the Cordeliers".</p>
<p>He then lived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rennes">Rennes</ref> where he directed the most important works. In 1642 he built two side altarpieces and the main altar<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Availles-sur-Seiche">Availles-sur-Seiche</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> as well as that of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rannée">Rannée</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> He is also attributed the altarpiece of the high altar<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> of the church of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tinténiac">Tinténiac</ref>.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, the work carried out at the Palace of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_Brittany">Parliament of Brittany</ref> was deemed not to conform to the plans and specifications drawn up by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salomon_de_Brosse">Salomon de Brosse</ref> in 1618, and was destroyed in 1647 by order of the Parliament of Brittany. Caris was dispossessed of his office for the benefit of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Corbineau">Pierre Corbineau</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1648 he left Rennes<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> for Nantes where he built a convent and private mansions. It is possible that he was at this time between Nantes, Rennes where he managed the cathedral site until 1654, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaël">Gaël</ref> where he raised the altarpiece of the high altar in 1650-1651. He seems to leave Rennes in 1654 definitively, the cathedral site was also taken over by Pierre Corbineau. The construction of the Cathedral in Rennes was eventful: Tugal Caris must start again in 1651 in granite instead of the tufa initially chosen.</p>
<p>According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Léon_Palustre">Léon Palustre</ref>, Tugal Caris would have led the work to the cornice on the first floor. After him, from 1654 to 1678, Pierre Corbineau completed the superposition of the three orders and placed the coat of arms of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_XIV">Louis XIV</ref> above the immense window in the façade of the monument. Then <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/François_Huguet">François Huguet</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref> cleared the two towers, gave them two independent floors, and in 1703 put the finishing touches to this work. He brought the levels to their current height of 48 metres and added on the pediment at the top of the façade <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_XIV">Louis XIV</ref>'s motto: <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nec_pluribus_impar">Nec pluribus impar</ref></hi>, the unparalleled.</p>
<p>Caris completeed the rededo of the altar <hi rend="italic">Notre-Dame-de-Pitié</hi> in one of the chapels<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nantes_Cathedral">Nantes Cathedral</ref> circa 1656, the same year he was awarded the contract for the cathedral's works<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref> Il meurt à Nantes en 1665 ou 1666.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref></p>
</text>
