<text id="autogum_bio_doc642" title="Moses Botarel" shortTile="moses-botarel" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-30" dateModified="2019-06-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moses_Botarel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Moses Botarel</head><p><hi rend="bold">Moses Botarel</hi> was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spain">Spanish</ref> scholar who  lived in the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries. He was a pupil of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacob_Sefardi">Jacob Sefardi</ref> (the Spaniard), who instructed him in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kabbalah">Kabbala</ref>. </p>
<p>Moses studied medicine and philosophy; the latter, he regarded as a divine science which teaches the same doctrines as the Cabala, using a different language and different terms to designate the same objects. He extolled <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aristotle">Aristotle</ref> as a sage, applying to him the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talmudic">Talmudic</ref> sentence, "A wise man is better than a prophet," and he censured his contemporaries for keeping aloof from the divine teachings of philosophy. He believed in the efficacy of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amulets">amulets</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cameo_(carving)">cameos</ref>, and declared that he was able to combine the names of God for magical purposes, so that he was generally considered a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magician_(paranormal)">sorcerer</ref>. He stated that by means of fasting, ablution, and invocation of the names of God and of the angels prophetic dreams could be induced. He also stated that the prophet <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elijah">Elijah</ref> had appeared to him and appointed him as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Messiah">Messiah</ref>. In this role he addressed a circular letter to all the rabbis, asserting that he was able to solve all perplexities, and asking them to send all doubtful questions to him. In this letter (printed by Dukes in <hi rend="italic">Orient, Lit.</hi> 1850, p.825) Botarel refers to himself as a well-known and prominent rabbi, a saint, and the most pious of the pious. Many believed in his miracles, including the philosopher <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hasdai_Crescas">Hasdai Crescas</ref>.</p>
<p>Botarel was one of those who attended the disputation at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tortosa">Tortosa</ref> (1413–1414), and he is said to have written a polemic against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geronimo_de_Santa_Fe">Geronimo de Santa Fe</ref>. In 1409, at the request of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christianity">Christian</ref> scholar <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maestro_Juan">Maestro Juan</ref>, Botarel composed a commentary on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sefer_Yezirah">Sefer Yezirah</ref>. In the preface, he excuses himself for having revealed the divine mysteries of this work to Maestro Juan by quoting the saying of the sages that a non-Jew who studies the Torah is equal to a high priest. In his commentary, he quotes earlier cabalistic works, including some ascribed to the old authorities, such as the amora <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rav_Ashi">Rav Ashi</ref>. Botarel's commentary on the <hi rend="italic">Sefer Yeẓirah</hi> was printed at Mantua in 1562, with the text and with other commentaries; it was republished at Zolkiev, 1745; Grodno, 1806; and Wilna, 1820.</p>
<p>This Moses Botarel is not <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moses_ben_Leon_Botarel">Moses ben Leon Botarel</ref>, who lived at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref> in the 16th century and wrote the <hi rend="italic">En Mishpat</hi>, containing predictions and being a free paraphrase of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin">Latin</ref> work of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Nostradamus">Michael Nostradamus</ref>.</p>
<head>Jewish Encyclopedia bibliography</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adolf_Jellinek">Adolf Jellinek</ref>, Biographische Skizzen, in Orient, Lit. 1846, pp.187–189;</item>
<item>N. Brüll, in Ha-Maggid, 1878, pp.198–199;</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heinrich_Graetz">Heinrich Graetz</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi> viii. 98;</item>
<item>idem, in Monatsschrift, 1879, pp.78–83;</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steinschneider">Steinschneider</ref>, Jewish Literature, pp.110, 128;</item>
<item>idem, Cat. Bodl. cols. 1780-1783.</item></list>
<p>This articleincorporates text from a publication now in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_domain">public domain</ref>:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isidore_Singer">Singer, Isidore</ref>;  et al., eds. (1901–1906). <ref target="http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?letter=M&amp;artid=848">"Moses Botarel"</ref>. <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Jewish_Encyclopedia">The Jewish Encyclopedia</ref></hi>. New York: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Funk_&amp;_Wagnalls">Funk &amp; Wagnalls</ref>.</p>
</text>
