<text id="autogum_bio_doc349" title="Alessandro Poglietti" shortTile="alessandro-poglietti" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-05-29" dateModified="2019-09-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alessandro_Poglietti" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Alessandro Poglietti</head><figure><caption>A late-17th-century engraving done after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan-Erasmus_Quellinus">Jan-Erasmus Quellinus</ref>' portrait of Alessandro Poglietti (the original painting is lost).</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alessandro Poglietti</hi> (early 17th century – July 1683) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baroque">Baroque</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Organist">organist</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Composer">composer</ref> of unknown origin. In the second half of the 17th century Poglietti settled in Vienna, where he attained an extremely high reputation, becoming one of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leopold_I,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Leopold I</ref>'s favorite composers. Poglietti held the post of court organist for 22 years from 1661 until his death during the Turkish siege that led into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Vienna">Battle of Vienna</ref>.</p>
<p>Poglietti is primarily important for his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keyboard_instrument">keyboard</ref> music, particularly <hi rend="italic">Rossignolo</hi> (1677), a collection of diverse pieces for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harpsichord">harpsichord</ref> that includes a large number of imitations of natural sounds, and a collection of 12 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ricercar">ricercares</ref>, which was widely copied during his lifetime.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Nothing is known of Poglietti's origins and early life. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuscany">Tuscany</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-grove-1">[1]</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bohemia">Bohemia</ref> have been suggested as his possible birthplace. He may have received musical training in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rome">Rome</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bologna">Bologna</ref>. Towards the 1660s Poglietti settled in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vienna">Vienna</ref>: in early 1661 he became organist and Kapellmeister at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesuit">Jesuit</ref> church <hi rend="italic">Zu den neun Chören der Engel</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Nine Choirs of Angels</hi>), and on 1 July 1661 he was appointed organist of the court Kapelle under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leopold_I,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Leopold I</ref> (a post previously held by none other than <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Jakob_Froberger">Johann Jakob Froberger</ref>).</p>
<p>Poglietti held the court position until his death and apparently enjoyed a high reputation. The Emperor (who was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leopold_I,_Holy_Roman_Emperor#Music">a composer himself</ref>) was particularly fond of Poglietti, ennobling him and bestowing upon him the title <hi rend="italic">Comes palatinus Caesareus</hi>, and the composer was also favored by the Pope, who made him a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Order_of_the_Golden_Spur">Knight of the Golden Spur</ref>, i.e., a member of the second highest Order of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papal_Orders_of_Chivalry">Papal Orders of Chivalry</ref>. Poglietti also had friends among Austrian nobility, among them Count Anton Franz von Collalto and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_II_von_Liechtenstein-Kastelkorn">Karl II von Liechtenstein-Kastelkorn</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince-Bishop">Prince-Bishop</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olomouc">Olomouc</ref>—in 1672 Poglietti inherited estates near their residences.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-grove-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> Another important connection of Poglietti's was with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Göttweig_Abbey">Göttweig Benedictine Abbey</ref>, where he stayed as a guest a number of times, and where his only known opera was performed, in 1677. Composer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Kaspar_Kerll">Johann Kaspar Kerll</ref> was a personal friend of Poglietti's, and he may have known <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Pachelbel">Johann Pachelbel</ref>, who visited Vienna in the mid-1670s.</p>
<p>Poglietti died in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vienna">Vienna</ref> in July 1683, during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Turkish</ref> siege that eventually led into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Vienna">Battle of Vienna</ref>. His death was lamented by Kerll in <hi rend="italic">Missa in fletu solatium</hi>, published in Munich in 1689 as part of a collection of masses, <hi rend="italic">Missae sex</hi>. Kerll's work includes <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basso_continuo">continuo</ref> parts that specifically order the performer to "avoid consonances".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>Poglietti's importance lies primarily in his keyboard music. Together with Johann Kaspar Kerll, he represents the transitional period between the time of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Girolamo_Frescobaldi">Frescobaldi</ref> and the late Baroque period.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-grove-1">[1]</ref> Particularly important are two large sets of pieces: an unpublished collection of twelve keyboard ricercares and <hi rend="italic">Rossignolo</hi> (1677), a collection of harpsichord music. The ricercares belong to the tradition of Frescobaldi's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fiori_musicali">Fiori musicali</ref></hi> and Bach's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Art_of_Fugue">The Art of Fugue</ref></hi>. Models of the strict contrapuntal style, they were most probably intended for the organ,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> and were widely copied in the Vienna area.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-grove-1">[1]</ref> The <hi rend="italic">Rossignolo</hi> pieces, on the other hand, are quite different. The collection, which Poglietti presented to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leopold_I,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Leopold I</ref> and his wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleonor_Magdalene_of_the_Palatinate">Eleonor Magdalene</ref>, comprises the following works:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Toccata and Canzona</item>
<item>A standard allemande—courante—sarabande—gigue suite in which every movement has a double (the allemande has two)</item>
<item>An <hi rend="italic">Aria Allemagna</hi> with 20 variations</item>
<item>A set of pieces based on a single theme:
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Ricercar per Il Rossignol</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Sincopatione del Ricercar</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Capriccio per Io Rossignol Sopra'l Ricercar</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Aria bizarra del Rissignolo</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Imitatione del medesimo Uccello</hi></item></list></item></list>
<p>Many of these pieces employ programmatic devices. For example, <hi rend="italic">Aria bizarra</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Imitatione</hi> are very demanding, virtuosic pieces based on Poglietti's adaptation of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nightingale">nightingale</ref> calls. Many of the variations of <hi rend="italic">Aria Allemagna</hi> imitate music for non-keyboard instruments (Variation 5 <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lyra">Lyra</ref></hi>, Variation 11 <hi rend="italic">Bayrische <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shawm">Schalmay</ref></hi>, etc.) or foreign and/or folk traditions (Variation 15 <hi rend="italic">Französische Baiselements</hi>). Poglietti's other pieces include more program music: a canzon and capriccio pair <hi rend="italic">über das Henner und Hannengeschrey</hi>, in which the capriccio imitates <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicken">hens and cocks</ref>, and the suite <hi rend="italic">sopra la ribellione di Ungheria</hi>, which commemorates a Hungarian Protestant rebellion of 1671. Poglietti's suite musically illustrates the rebellion itself, the capture of the rebels, their execution, and closes with an imitation of church bells. Poglietti also provided numerous examples of program music (which were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Incipit">incipits</ref> of possible pieces) in his performance and composition treatise <hi rend="italic">Compendium oder kurtzer Begriff</hi> (1676).</p>
<p>Numerous pieces contain highly original treatments of the form: movements of the <hi rend="italic">Binder Gigue</hi> from an A minor suite begin with repeated chords and include octave triplets in the left hand; the toccatas as well as any other piece may feature rapid modulations to completely foreign keys, highly contrasting sections and sections built on various kinds of repetition.</p>
<p>Poglietti's other music includes chamber music (mostly suites and sonatas), sacred vocal works (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mass_(music)">masses</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motet">motets</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Litaniae Lauretanae</hi> for two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SATB">SATB</ref> choirs) and a single opera (<hi rend="italic">Endimione festeggiante</hi>, 1677). <hi rend="italic">Compendium oder kurtzer Begriff und Einführung zur Musica</hi> (1676) is a treatise on keyboard composition; a sketchbook survives which also serves as a guide to keyboard students.</p>
<head>List of works</head>
<head>Vocal</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Ave regina coelorum à 5</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Endimione festeggiante</hi>, opera (1677)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Litaniae Lauretanae à 8</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Magnificat à 3</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Missa à 3</hi>, for 3vv, violin and basso continuo (1680)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Missa à 4</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Missa à 5</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Requiem aeternam</hi></item>
<item>2 motets</item></list>
<head>Keyboard</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Suite <hi rend="italic">sopra la ribellione di Ungheria</hi>, 8 pieces (1671)</item>
<item>Toccata <hi rend="italic">fatta sopra l'assedio di Filippsburgo</hi> (1676; misspelled "Cassedio" in the source<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref>)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Rossignolo</hi>, a suite of 17 pieces (1677)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Canzon and Capriccio über das Henner und Hannengeschrey</hi></item>
<item>A collection of 12 ricercares</item>
<item>Toccata <hi rend="italic">del 7. tono</hi></item>
<item>numerous other pieces: suites, canzonas, capriccios, preludes and fugues, etc.</item></list>
<head>Other instrumental</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>8 sonatas, various balletti, all for string instruments</item></list>
<head>Writings</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Compendium oder kurtzer Begriff, und Einführung zur Musica</hi> (1676; includes a collection of keyboard pieces)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Regulae compositionis</hi>, a sketchbook containing advice on composition</item></list>
</text>
