<text id="autogum_bio_doc321" title="Abdul Aziz Hotak" shortTile="abdul-aziz-hotak" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-18" dateModified="2019-09-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abdul_Aziz_Hotak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Abdul Aziz Hotak</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shāh Abdul Azīz Hotak</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pashto_language">Pashto</ref>: عبد العزیز هوتک‎; died 1717) was the second ruler of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghilji">Ghilji</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hotak_dynasty">Hotak dynasty</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kandahar">Kandahar</ref>, in what is now the modern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sovereign_state">state</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref>. He was crowned in 1715 after the death of his brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mirwais_Hotak">Mirwais Hotak</ref>. He is the father of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ashraf_Hotak">Ashraf Hotak</ref>, the fourth ruler of the Hotak dynasty. Abdul Aziz was killed in 1717 by his nephew <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahmud_Hotak">Mahmud Hotak</ref>.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Abdul Aziz was born in a well known, rich and political family in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kandahar">Kandahar</ref> area. His family was involved in social and community services since long ago. He was the son of Salim Khan and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nazo_Tokhi">Nazo Tokhi</ref> (also known as "Nazo Anaa"), grandson of Karum Khan and great grandson of Ismail Khan, a descendant of Malikyar, the ancient head of Hottaki or Hotaks. The Hottaki is a strong branch of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghilji">Ghilji</ref>, one of the main tribes among the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pashtun_people">Pashtun people</ref>. Hajji Amanullah Hottak reports in his book that the Ghilji tribe is the original residents of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghor">Ghor</ref> or Gherj. This tribe migrated later to obtain lands in southeastern Afghanistan and multiplied in these areas.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bw-1">[1]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>Greater Kandahar (<hi rend="italic">Candahar</hi>) during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safavid_dynasty">Safavid dynasty</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mughal_Empire">Mughal</ref> period.</caption></figure>
<p>In 1707, Kandahar was in a state of chaos due to it being fought for control by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shi'a_Islam">Shi'a</ref> Persian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safavid_dynasty">Safavids</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sunni_Islam">Sunni</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moghul_Empire">Moghuls</ref> of India. Mirwais Khan, a Sunni tribal chief whose influence with his fellow-countrymen made him an object of suspicion, was held as a political prisoner by the Safavid governor over the region, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_XI_of_Kartli">Gurgin Khan</ref>, and sent to the Safavids court at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isfahan">Isfahan</ref>. He was later released and even allowed to meet with the Shah, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sultan_Husayn">Sultan Husayn</ref>, on a regular bases. Having sown this seed of false trust and having completely ingratiated himself with the Persian Court, Mirwais sought and obtained permission to perform the pilgrimage to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mecca">Mecca</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_empire">Ottoman empire</ref>. He had studied carefully all the military weaknesses of the by then heavily declined Safavids while he spent time there in their court.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Ewans-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Browne-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>It was in 1709 when Mirwais and Abdul Aziz began organizing his countrymen for a major uprising, and when a large part of the Persian garrison was on an expedition outside the city, followers of Mirwais and Abdul Aziz fell on the remainder and killed the greater number of them, including Gurgin Khan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Browne-3">[3]</ref></p><p>
The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pashtun_tribes">Pashtun tribes</ref> rankled under the ruling Safavids because of their continued attempts to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forcefully_convert">forcefully convert</ref> them from Sunni to Shia Islam.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Ewans-2">[2]</ref> After Gurgin Khan and his escort were killed during a picnic in April 1709, the Hotak tribe took control of the city and the province.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Otfinoski-4">[4]</ref> The Pashtun rebels then defeated a large <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qizilbash">Qizilbash</ref> and Persian army, sent to gain control over the area.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Several half-hearted attempts to subdue the rebellious city having failed, the Persian Government despatched <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kaikhosro_of_Kartli">Khusraw Khán</ref>, nephew of the late Gurgín Khán, with an army of 30,000 men to effect its subjugation, but in spite of an initial success, which led the Afgháns to offer to surrender on terms, his uncompromising attitude impelled them to make a fresh desperate effort, resulting in the complete defeat of the Persian army (of whom only some 700 escaped) and the death of their general. Two years later, in. 1713, another Persian army commanded by Rustam Khán was also defeated by the rebels, who thus secured possession of the whole <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kandahar_Province">province of Qandahár</ref>.</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Browne-3">[3]</ref></p>—<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Granville_Browne">Edward G. Browne</ref>, 1924
<head>Death</head>
<p>Abdul Aziz wanted to make a peace treaty with the Persians but his country men were opposed to this idea so they forced Mahmud Hotak to murder him in 1717. In the same year he got succeeded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahmud_Hotak">Mahmud Hotak</ref>.</p>
<p>Abdul Aziz is buried at a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mausoleum">mausoleum</ref> next to his brother in the Kokaran section of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kandahar">Kandahar City</ref> in Afghanistan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
</text>
