<text id="autogum_bio_doc654" title="Martim Afonso Telo de Meneses" shortTile="martim-afonso-telo" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-01-14" dateModified="2018-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martim_Afonso_Telo_de_Meneses" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Martim Afonso Telo de Meneses</head><p><hi rend="bold">Martim Afonso Telo de Meneses</hi> (died in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toro,_Zamora">Toro</ref>, 26 January 1356), was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Portugal">Portuguese</ref> nobleman, member of the Téllez de Meneses lineage, and the father of  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonor_Teles">Leonor Teles</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_consort">queen consort</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Portuguese_consorts">Portugal</ref>.</p>
<p>His parents were Afonso Telles de Meneses, called <hi rend="italic">el Raposo</hi>, vassal of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afonso_IV_of_Portugal">Afonso IV of Portugal</ref>, and Berengáira Lourenço de Valadares,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESotto_Mayor_Pizarro1987240-1">[1]</ref> daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lourenço_Soares_de_Valadares">Lourenço Soares de Valadares</ref> and Sancha Nunes de Chacím.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alcázar_de_Toro">Alcázar de Toro</ref> where Martim Afonso Telo de Meneses was assassinated</caption></figure>
<p>Martim Afonso was the <hi rend="italic">Mayordomo</hi> of  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_of_Portugal,_Queen_of_Castile">Maria of Portugal</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESotto_Mayor_Pizarro1987203-2">[2]</ref> the wife of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfonso_XI_of_Castile">Alfonso XI of Castile</ref> and mother of the only surviving son of this marriage, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_of_Castile">Peter of Castile</ref>.  On 16 January 1356, he and several nobles were at the Alcázar de Toro with the queen when King Peter of Castile arrived, accompanied by several squires, entered the grounds of the fortress and ordered the assassination of several of the men who were there with the queen, including Martim. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pero_López_de_Ayala">Pero López de Ayala</ref> in his chronicles describes the events as follow:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELópez_de_Ayala1780207-208,_6th_Year,_Chapter_II-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>And then the King ordered that Queen Doña Maria, his mother, who was inside the Alcázar, was to go outside and go to him. And the Queen asked for mercy for the gentlemen who were with her and pleaded on their behalf for the king's forgiveness. And the King told her again to come to him since he would know what should be done with the gentlemen who were at her side (...) and the Queen left the Alcázar, and with her, also countess doña <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juana_Manuel">Juana</ref> the wife of count Don <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_II_of_Castile">Henry</ref>,  Don Pero Estevanez Carpentero Grand Master of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Order_of_Calatrava">Order of Calatrava</ref>, and Ruy González de Castañeda, and Alfonso Téllez Girón, and Martín Alfonso Tello (…) Another squire arrived and killed Martim Afonso Telo (...) and the Queen, Doña María, the king's mother, when she saw that these gentlemen had been killed, fell to the ground, unconscious (...) and when they helped her to get on her feet and she saw all the dead gentlemen, naked, all around her, she started to scream, and coursed the King, her son, telling him to dishonor and hurt her forever, and that she would rather die than live. (loose translation)</p>
<head>Marriage and issue</head>
<p>Martim Afonso and his wife, Aldonça Anes de Vasconcelos, daughter of João Mendes de Vasconcelos,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESotto_Mayor_Pizarro1987203_and_241-4">[4]</ref> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alcalde">Alcalde</ref></hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Estremoz">Estremoz</ref>, and Aldara Alfonso Alcoforado, had the following children:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESotto_Mayor_Pizarro1987241-5">[5]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/João_Afonso_Telo,_6th_Count_of_Barcelos">João Afonso Telo</ref> (killed on 14 August 1385 in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Aljubarrota">Battle of Aljubarrota</ref>), 6th <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Count_of_Barcelos">Count of Barcelos</ref> in 1382, mayor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisbon">Lisbon</ref>, admiral of the Kingdom of Portugal, and the husband of Beatriz de Alburquerque, an illegitimate daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/João_Afonso_de_Albuquerque">João Afonso de Albuquerque</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESotto_Mayor_Pizarro1987205_and_232-6">[6]</ref></item>
<item>Gonçalo Teles de Meneses, (died on 28 June 1403), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Count_of_Neiva">Count of Neiva</ref> and lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Faria_(Barcelos)">Faria</ref>, married to Maria Afonso de Albuquerque, also an illegitimate daughter of João Afonso de Albuquerque,;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESotto_Mayor_Pizarro1987204-7">[7]</ref></item>
<item>Maria Teles de Meneses (m. November 1379), wife of Alvaro Dias de Sousa and, after his death, married <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infante">infante</ref></hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John,_Duke_of_Valencia_de_Campos">John of Portugal</ref>, Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valencia_de_Campos">Valencia de Campos</ref>, son of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_I_of_Portugal">Peter I of Portugal</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inês_de_Castro">Inês de Castro</ref>, parents of  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infante_Fernando,_Lord_of_Eça">Infante Fernando, Lord of Eça</ref>;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESotto_Mayor_Pizarro1987204-7">[7]</ref></item>
<item>Leonor Teles, queen consort of Portugal as the wife of King Ferdinand I of Portugal.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESotto_Mayor_Pizarro198724_and_242-8">[8]</ref></item></list>
<p>He was also the father of a daughter born out of wedlock:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Joana Teles de Meneses, who married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_Alfonso_Pimentel">Juan Alfonso Pimentel</ref>, first Count of Benavente.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESotto_Mayor_Pizarro1987242-9">[9]</ref></item></list>
</text>
