<text id="autogum_bio_doc366" title="Asmat Begum" shortTile="asmat-begum" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-07-28" dateModified="2019-06-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asmat_Begum" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Asmat Begum</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Asmat Begum</hi> (died 1621) was the wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mirza_Ghias_Beg">Mirza Ghias Beg</ref>, the Prime minister of the Mughal emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jahangir">Jahangir</ref>, and the mother of Mughal empress <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nur_Jahan">Nur Jahan</ref>, the power behind the emperor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> Asmat Begum was also the paternal grandmother of Empress <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mumtaz_Mahal">Mumtaz Mahal</ref>, for whom the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taj_Mahal">Taj Mahal</ref> was built.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Asmat Begum was the daughter of Mirza Ala-ud-Daula Aqa Mulla<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> and a member of the illustrious Aqa Mulla clan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FindlyP9-3">[3]</ref> She was a wise, well-educated, accomplished and highly cultured lady.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> She had a brother, Ibrahim Khan, who served as the governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bengal">Bengal</ref> during Emperor Jahangir's reign.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Marriage</head>
<p>Asmat Begum was married to the Persian noble, Mirza Ghiyas Beg, the youngest son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khvajeh_Mohammad-Sharif">Khvajeh Mohammad-Sharif</ref>, a Persian noble of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tehran">Tehran</ref> and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vizier">vizier</ref> to the governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greater_Khorasan">Khorasan</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> The couple had four children together: Mohammad Sharif, Asaf Khan, Sahlia and Mehr-un-Nissa (later Empress Nur Jahan).</p>
<p>For unknown reasons, Ghias Beg and his family had suffered a reversal in fortune in 1576 and soon found circumstances intolerable in their homeland of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persia">Persia</ref>. Drawn to the favourable climate of Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Akbar">Akbar</ref>'s court in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agra">Agra</ref>, the family decided to migrate to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/India">India</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FindlyP9-3">[3]</ref> Ghias Beg became a trusted minister under both Akbar and his son Jahangir and was awarded the title of 'I'timad-ud-Daulah' ("Pillar of the State") for his services.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>However, while serving as the <hi rend="italic">diwan</hi> to an <hi rend="italic">amir-ul-umara</hi> in 1607, Ghias Beg was charged with embezzling Rs. 50,000, which led to a decrease in his rank and status at court.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> In 1611, Asmat Begum's second daughter, Mehr-un-Nissa, caught the eye of the reigning emperor Jahangir at the palace <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meena_Bazaar">Meena Bazaar</ref></hi>. The emperor proposed immediately and they were married within the same year.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FindlyP3-10">[10]</ref> This marriage again led to a dramatic rise in the fortunes of Asmat Begum and Ghias Beg's family. Ghias Beg was given a substantial increase in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mansabdar">mansab</ref></hi> and made <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vizier">wazir</ref></hi> of the whole dominion in 1611. Likewise, their sons Asaf Khan and Itiqad Khan were also given high positions and <hi rend="italic">mansab</hi>s in the empire.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<head>Political role at the Mughal court</head>
<p>Mehr-un-Nissa (titled 'Nur Jahan' after her marriage) became Jahangir's most beloved and influential wife and soon became the real <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_behind_the_throne">power behind the throne</ref> after their marriage. Nur Jahan formed a faction known as the <hi rend="italic">junta</hi> which comprised her family members and her step-son, Prince Khurram (the future emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shah_Jahan">Shah Jahan</ref>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> This faction, led by Nur Jahan, took control of the government as Jahangir became increasingly addicted to opium and alcohol.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FindlyP3-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>Asmat Begum, who was a wise and patient counsel in her own right, must certainly have been the nurturing hub of the <hi rend="italic">junta</hi> in its heyday.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> She is also known to have taken a politically active role in the affairs of the court and served as a mother-figure to Jahangir and a counselor to Nur Jahan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> However, Asmat Begum is perhaps best known for having invented the famous rose perfume called <hi rend="italic">Jahangiri-itr</hi>, which was described by Jahangir as the discovery of his reign.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref></p>
<head>Death</head>
<figure><caption>Cenotaph of Asmat Begum alongside that of her husband Mirza Ghias Beg.</caption></figure>
<p>Asmat Begum died in October 1621 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agra">Agra</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref>  Upon her death, her son-in-law Jahangir, who was extremely fond of her, wrote: "Without exaggeration, in purity of disposition and in wisdom and the excellencies that are the ornament of women no Mother of the Age was ever born equal to her, and I did not value her less than my own mother."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref></p>
<p>Asmat Begum's death was a great blow to her family. Heartbroken over his wife's death, Ghias Beg also died a few months later in January 1622. Asmat Begum was buried in her husband's mausoleum, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tomb_of_I'timād-ud-Daulah">Tomb of I'timād-ud-Daulah</ref> in Agra, which was commissioned by her daughter Nur Jahan, for both of her parents.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref> Nur Jahan, who was extremely devoted to her parents, spent large sums in its construction.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref></p>
<head>In popular culture</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Asmat Begum is a character in Usha John's novel <hi rend="italic">The Unknown Lover and Other Short Stories</hi> (1961).</item>
<item>Asmat Begum is a principal character in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indu_Sundaresan">Indu Sundaresan</ref>'s award-winning historical novel <hi rend="italic">The Twentieth Wife</hi> (2002) as well as in its sequel <hi rend="italic">The Feast of Roses</hi> (2003).</item>
<item>Asmat Begum is a pivotal character in Tanushree Podder's historical novel <hi rend="italic">Nur Jahan's Daughter</hi> (2005).</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suparna_Marwah">Suparna Marwah</ref> portrayed Asmat Begum in  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EPIC_(TV_channel)">EPIC</ref> channel's critically acclaimed historical drama <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siyaasat">Siyaasat</ref></hi> (based on <hi rend="italic">The Twentieth Wife</hi>).</item></list>
</text>
