<text id="autogum_bio_doc725" title="Otto of Passau" shortTile="otto-passau" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-08-21" dateModified="2019-02-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto_of_Passau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Otto of Passau</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Otto of Passau</hi> was a medieval German clerical author.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>All that is known of him is in the preface of his work, in which he calls himself a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franciscan">Franciscan</ref> Order, at one time <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lector">lector</ref> of theology at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basle">Basle</ref>, and says that he finished his writing on 2 (1) February 1386, dedicating it to all the "friends of God", both clerical and lay, male and female, and begs for their prayers.</p>
<p>According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sbaralea">Sbaralea</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Suppl. Script. Franciscani ordinis,</hi> Rome, 1806, 571) he was a native of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flanders">Flanders</ref> and belonged to the Franciscan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecclesiastical_province">ecclesiastical province</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cologne">Cologne</ref>. Yet his name refers to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bavaria">Bavarian</ref> city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Passau">Passau</ref>.</p>
<head>Work</head>
<p>His book bears the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_language">German language</ref> title (not <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_language">Dutch language</ref>, as one might expect from a Fleming) <ref target="http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.rbc/rosenwald.0076.1"><hi rend="italic">Die vierundzwanzig alten oder der guldin Tron der minnenden seelen</hi>; <hi rend="italic">The 24 elders or the golden throne of loving souls.</hi></ref> He introduces the twenty-four ancients of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Book_of_Revelation">Apocalypse</ref>, iv.4, and makes them utter sentences of wisdom by which men can obtain the golden throne in eternal life.</p>
<p>The sentences are taken from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Scripture">Holy Scripture</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fathers_of_the_Church">Fathers of the Church</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scholastics">Scholastics</ref> and from heathen authors "whom the Church does not condemn". He thus enumerates 104 "masters", among whom are also some of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mysticism">mystics</ref>, as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugo_of_St._Victor">Hugo</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_of_St._Victor">Richard of St. Victor</ref>. He generally gives accurate quotation of his sources though he also draws from some not specified, e.g., St. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_of_Schönau">Elizabeth of Schönau</ref>. He tries to remain on strictly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholic">Catholic</ref> ground, but sometimes loses himself in dogmatical intricacies and quibbles. To be plain and intelligible he frequently uses trivial expressions.</p>
<p>He writes on the nature of God and of man, on their mutual relation, on the requisites for perfection: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contrition">contrition</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confession_(religion)">confession</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penance">penance</ref>; on internal and external life, purity of motives, shunning <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Idleness">idleness</ref>, love of God and of the neighbour, the necessity of faith and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grace_(Christianity)">grace of God</ref>. He speaks of the Scriptures as the storehouse of Divine wisdom and urges the faithful to read them. In speaking of contemplative life he insists that none can reach it without spending time in the active service of God and man. The term "friends of God" he explains according to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gospel_of_John">John</ref> xv.15 and speaks of prayer, humility, obedience, spiritual life, virtues and vices and shows Christ as the model of all virtues. The longest chapters, eleven and twelve, he devotes to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Eucharist">Holy Eucharist</ref> and to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blessed_Virgin">Blessed Virgin</ref>. The last chapters treat of death and the future life.</p>
<p>The number of manuscript copies of the book (about forty) bears evidence of the estimation in which it was held. It found its way to all "friends of God" in the south of Germany, along the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lower_Rhine">Lower Rhine</ref> and in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref>. It first appeared in print in 1470, probably by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albrecht_Pfister">Albrecht Pfister</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bamberg">Bamberg</ref>. A modernized edition, <hi rend="italic">Die Krone der Aeltesten,</hi> was made in 1835 at Landshut as a tenth volume of <hi rend="italic">Leitstern auf der Bahn des Heils.</hi></p>
</text>
