<text id="autogum_bio_doc663" title="John II, Duke of Opava-Ratibor" shortTile="john-ii-duke-opavaratibor" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-12-06" dateModified="2019-03-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_II%2C_Duke_of_Opava-Ratibor" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John II, Duke of Opava-Ratibor</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">John II, Duke of Opava-Ratibor</hi> (also known as <hi rend="italic">John II of Troppau</hi> or <hi rend="italic">John the Iron</hi>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_language">Czech</ref>: <hi lang="cs" rend="italic">Jan II. Opavský</hi> or <hi lang="cs" rend="italic">Hanuš Ferreus</hi>; after 1365 – 1424) was Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Opava">Opava</ref>-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Racibórz">Racibórz</ref> (Ratibor), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Krnov">Krnov</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Bruntál">Bruntál</ref>. From 1388 to 1397, he was also <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor">governor</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Kladsko">Kłodzko</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ząbkowice_Śląskie">Ząbkowice Śląskie</ref> and from 1397 to 1422 pledge lord of Kłodzko and Ząbkowice Śląskie. He was a member of the Opava branch of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Přemyslid_dynasty">Přemyslid dynasty</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was a son of Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_I,_Duke_of_Opava-Ratibor">John I of Opava-Ratibor</ref>. John I had been the sole heir of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Racibórz">Duchy of Racibórz</ref> in 1365 and had founded the Opava-Ratibor branch of the family. When the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Opava">Duchy of Opava</ref> was divided in 1377, John I had received the Duchies of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Krnov">Krnov</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Bruntál">Bruntál</ref>. John II's mother was Anna, the daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_V_of_Iron">Henry V</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Głogów">Głogów</ref>-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Żagań">Żagań</ref>.</p>
<p>After John I's death, his possession were divided by his sons, John II and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_IV,_Duke_of_Ratibor-Bruntál">Nicholas IV</ref>. Nicholas IV, the younger brother, received a share of Bruntál. As Nicholas IV was still a minor, John acted as his regent until 1385. When Nicholas IV died (between 1405 and 1407), John II inherited his share of Bruntál. John II sold the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Krnov">Duchy of Krnov</ref>, which had been separated from Opava in 1377, to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Władysław_Opolczyk">Władysław II</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Opole">Opole</ref> in 1384. John I had pledged <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mikołów">Mikołów</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Pless">Duchy of Pless</ref> to Władysław II; John II redeemed these possessions.</p>
<p>In 1387, John II founded the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bieruń">Bieruń</ref> and appointed a certain Cussowitz as bailiff over Bieruń. In 1391, he gave the villages of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imielin">Imielin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kosztowy">Kosztowy</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chełm_Śląski">Chełm Śląski</ref> on the eastern border of his duchy to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdiocese_of_Krakow">Bishop of Krakow</ref>. This implied that these villages were no longer part of Silesia. The village of Halemba near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruda_Śląska">Ruda Śląska</ref> developed from an iron works founded by his brother Nicholas IV in 1394. In 1394, John II founded another iron works, named <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_language">German</ref>: <hi lang="de" rend="italic">Bogutzker Hammer</hi>, on the spot of the deserted village of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bogucice">Bogucice</ref>. At the end of the 16th century, this settlement developed into the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katowice">Katowice</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1389, the bishops of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishopric_of_Wrocław">Wrocław</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic_Archdiocese_of_Olomouc">Olomouc</ref> and the Dukes of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Legnica">Legnica</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Oleśnica">Oleśnica</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Głogów">Głogów</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Opava">Opava</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Teschen">Teschen</ref> formed and alliance for mutual protection and to preserve the public peace. John II did not sign this Treaty of Hotzenplotz, because he was a supporter of Margrave <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prokop_of_Moravia">Prokop of Moravia</ref>.</p>
<p>John II was high steward of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslaus,_King_of_the_Romans">Wenceslaus IV</ref> and this made him one of the most powerful men in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Bohemia">Kingdom of Bohemia</ref>. He also held the post of Burgrave of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karlštejn">Karlštejn</ref>. In 1397, John II and other noble councillors accused Wenceslaus IV of neglecting his duties as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_of_the_Romans">King of the Romans</ref> and asked him to summon an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperial_Diet_(Holy_Roman_Empire)">Imperial Diet</ref>. The accusations were dealt with by Wenceslaus's councillors and favourites <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefan_Poduška_von_Martinic">Stefan Poduška von Martinic</ref>, Stefan of Opočno, Burkhard Strnad of Janovice and the Prior of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Order_of_Saint_John_(Bailiwick_of_Brandenburg)">Order of St. John</ref>, Marquard of Strakonice. When these men stood in the way of further demands by John and his companions, he invited them to a banquet at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karlštejn_Castle">Karlštejn Castle</ref> on 11 June 1397. There, he attacked them with the words <hi rend="italic">You, gentlemen, have advised our Lord, the King, not to take care of our German land, because all you want is for him to become <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_of_the_Germans">King of the Germans</ref></hi>. He then killed them. In the same year, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jobst_of_Moravia">Jobst of Moravia</ref> had to pledge the counties of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Kladsko">Kłodzko</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ząbkowice_Śląskie">Ząbkowice Śląskie</ref> to King Wenceslaus, who sold his pledge to John II.</p>
<p>After Wenceslaus's stepbrother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigismund,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Sigismund</ref> besieged Ratibor in 1400, John II used the occasion of a meeting between Kings Wenceslaus IV and King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Władysław_II_Jagiełło">Władysław II Jagiełło</ref> of Poland in Wrocław in 1404 to create an alliance against Hungary. After Wenceslaus's death, John II supported his successor, King Sigismund, and paid him homage in Wrocław in 1420 during the Imperial Diet. Rebellious Bohemians sent envoys to Grand Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vytautas">Vytautas</ref> of Lithuania, to offer him the Bohemian crown. When they traveled through Ratibor on 21 September 1421, they were arrested by the citizens and John II handed them over to King Sigismund. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hussites">Hussites</ref> retaliated by invading Ratibor. Sigismund rewarded Sigismund by transferring the rights to Krnov back to John II, who had to redeem Krnov from Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_II_of_Brieg">Louis II of Brieg</ref>.</p>
<p>John II died in 1424 and was buried in the church of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominican_Order">Dominicans</ref> in Ratibor. It was not until 1427 that his sons agreed to divide his possessions: his son Wenceslaus received the City and Duchy of Racibórz, Nicholas received Krnov, Bruntál, Pszczyna, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Rybnik">Rybnik</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baborów">Baborów</ref>.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>On 16 January 1407, John II married the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Duchy_of_Lithuania">Lithuanian</ref> Princess Helena of Lithuania, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dymitr_Korybut">Dymitr Korybut</ref> and a niece of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Władysław_II_Jagiełło">Władysław II Jagiełło</ref> of Poland. In 1407, she received as her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wittum">wittum</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amt_(country_subdivision)">amts</ref> of Pszczyna, Bieruń and Mikołów. In 1412, he added the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waldhufendorf">Waldhufendorf</ref> villages south of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Żory">Żory</ref>. After John's death, she used the title <hi rend="italic">Baroness of Pszczyna</hi> from 1424 to 1449.</p>
<p>They had three children:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslaus_II,_Duke_of_Opava-Ratibor">Wenceslaus II</ref> (1405 - 29 October 1456).</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_V,_Duke_of_Krnov">Nicholas V</ref> (1409 - 1452).</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margareta_of_Racibórz">Margareta</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_language">Czech</ref>: <hi lang="cs" rend="italic">Markéta</hi>; 1410 - d. 5 July 1459), married firstly Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casimir_I_of_Oświęcim">Casimir I of Oświęcim</ref> (d. 1434) and secondly Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siemowit_V_of_Masovia">Siemowit V of Masovia</ref> (d. 1442)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></item></list>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
