<text id="autogum_bio_doc542" title="Hieromonk Makarije" shortTile="hieromonk-makarije" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-11-07" dateModified="2019-05-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hieromonk_Makarije" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hieromonk Makarije</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Hieromonk Makarije</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_language">Serbian</ref>: Јеромонах Макарије; fl. 1494–d. after 1528) is the founder of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serb">Serbian</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romanians">Romanian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Printing">printing</ref>, having printed the first book in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_language">Serbian language</ref> and the first book in the territory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walachia">Walachia</ref> (part of modern-day <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romania">Romania</ref>).</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>The origins of printing in Serbia are linked to the press established in Obod, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cetinje">Cetinje</ref>, in 1493 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Đurađ_Crnojević">Đurađ Crnojević</ref>, the eldest son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Crnojević">Ivan Crnojević</ref>, the ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeta">Zeta</ref> (the earliest designation of the Serb land of Crnagora (also known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montenegro">Montenegro</ref> in translation). At the time, Zeta was the last free territory of the former powerful Serbian state that began to collapse after the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Kosovo">Battle of Kosovo</ref> in 1389. In an attempt to defend Zeta from Turkish aspirations to the land Đurađ Crnojević sought an ally in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venice">Venice</ref>. He dispatched a monk Makarije to Venice to purchase a printing press and learn the trade of printing.</p>
<p>After Hieromonk Makarije found a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Printing_works">printing works</ref>, he travelled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venice">Venice</ref>, where he learned about printing, probably in the printing works of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aldus_Manutius">Aldus Manutius</ref> or from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrija_Paltašić">Andrija Paltašić</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> After returning to Cetinje, he founded  printing works in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obod">Obod</ref>, then the capital, and later, with the shifting of the capital, moved back to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cetinje">Cetinje</ref> where, in 1494, he printed the first book in Serbian language, an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oktoih">Oktoih</ref> (it is probable that the first two or four parts were printed in Venice, but the last four were printed in Obod, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cetinje">Cetinje</ref>). Serbia, however in straitened circumstances, acquired a press some three decades after the invention of movable type.</p>
<p>After the fall of Zeta to the Turks in 1499, Makarije fled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walachia">Walachia</ref>. It was owing to these circumstances that the second and third Serbian printing presses were established outside Serb lands. In 1511, Makarije started a printing works in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Târgovişte">Targoviste</ref>, where he printed the first books in this principality; and his compatriot Božidar Vuković of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Podgorica">Podgorica</ref> also started printing in Venice in 1519.</p>
<p>After Vuković came <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerolim_Zagurović">Jerolim Zagurović</ref>, formerly a Kotor native, who also printed in Venice in the sixteenth century. Contemporaneously with Vuković, Božidar Ljubavić or better-known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Božidar_Goraždanin">Božidar Goraždanin</ref> and his sons Đurađ and Teodor Ljubavić started the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goražde_printing_house">Goražde printing house</ref>, which worked between 1519 and 1523, at first in Venice and then near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goražde">Goražde</ref> in present-day Bosnia and Herzegovina. In 1544, Božidar's grandson <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dimitrije_Ljubavić">Dimitrije Ljubavić</ref> (Đurađ Ljubavić's son) transferred the printing press from Goražde to Târgoviște, where he printed two books, in 1545 and 1547.</p>
<p>Hieromonk Makarije, a few years later, moved to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilandar">Hilandar</ref> monastery, where he became the abbot. There he helped found the fourth printing press, the well-known <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilandar">Hilandar</ref> printing works at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mount_Athos">Mount Athos</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greece">Greece</ref>.</p>
<p>Makarije also wrote the treatise "On the Borders of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dacia">Dacia</ref>" (<hi rend="italic">O medjah Dacije</hi>) preserved in Hilandar library.</p>
<p>The British Library has what appears to be one of the few complete copies of Makarije's 1495 <hi rend="italic">Psalter</hi> with liturgical appendices in existence, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chester_Beatty_Library">Chester Beatty Library</ref> has a magnificent copy, printed on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vellum">vellum</ref>, of Serb <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Božidar_Vuković">Božidar Vuković</ref>'s 1538 <hi rend="italic">Menaion.</hi> Works by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francysk_Skaryna">Francysk Skaryna</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Fyodorov_(printer)">Ivan Fyodorov (printer)</ref>, and Petr Mstislavich are also well represented. England's early contacts with Serbian and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muscovy">Muscovy</ref> merchants meant that books were acquired by English traders and brought home as curiosities. Their trophies survived undisturbed in libraries, rather than suffering the fate of being handled to destruction by invaders in their native lands.</p>
<p>Serbian-American scientist and inventor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikola_Tesla">Nikola Tesla</ref>'s most prized possession was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Božidar_Vuković">Božidar Vuković</ref>'s 1517 <hi rend="italic">Sluzbenik</hi>, an inheritance from his father, a Serbian Orthodox priest. This rare book is now on display in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harry_S._Truman_Presidential_Library_and_Museum">Harry S. Truman Presidential Library and Museum</ref> at Independence, Missouri.</p>
<head>Works</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Psalter with liturgical appendices (Cetinje, 1495)</item>
<item>Gospels (Târgoviște, 1512)</item></list>
</text>
