<text id="autogum_bio_doc481" title="George Wilkins" shortTile="george-wilkins" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2003-08-20" dateModified="2019-10-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Wilkins" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>George Wilkins</head>For other people named Main Page, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page_(disambiguation)">Main Page (disambiguation)</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">George Wilkins</hi> (died 1618)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> was an English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dramatist">dramatist</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pamphlet">pamphleteer</ref> best known for his probable collaboration with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Shakespeare">William Shakespeare</ref> on the play <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pericles,_Prince_of_Tyre">Pericles, Prince of Tyre</ref></hi>. By  profession he was an inn-keeper, but he was also apparently involved in criminal activities.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Wilkins was an inn-keeper in Cow-Cross, London, an area that was "notorious as a haunt of whores and thieves".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-wilk-2">[2]</ref> Most biographical information about him derives from his regular appearance in criminal court records for thievery and acts of violence. Many of the charges against him involved violence against women, including kicking a pregnant woman in the belly, and knocking down and stomping another woman. The latter appears in other records as a known "bawd", or keeper of prostitutes. These facts have led to the suggestion that his inn functioned as a brothel and that Wilkins was a procurer, or pimp.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-wilk-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Wilkins was associated with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King's_Men_(playing_company)">King's Men</ref>, and their chief playwright <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Shakespeare">William Shakespeare</ref>, during the latter's last working years as a dramatist. Shakespeare and Wilkins were both witnesses in the case of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bellott_v_Mountjoy">Bellott v Mountjoy</ref></hi> in 1612; in his deposition he described himself as a "victualler."</p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>He is first heard of as the author of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pamphlet">pamphlet</ref> on the <hi rend="italic">Three Miseries of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barbary">Barbary</ref></hi>, which dates from 1606.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> He then collaborated in 1607 with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Rowley">William Rowley</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Day_(dramatist)">John Day</ref> in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Travels_of_the_Three_English_Brothers">The Travels of the Three English Brothers</ref></hi>, a dramatisation of the real-life adventures of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Sherley">Sherley brothers</ref>.</p>
<p>In the same year Wilkins wrote <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Miseries_of_Enforced_Marriage">The Miseries of Enforced Marriage</ref></hi>. This play is based on the story of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Calverley">Walter Calverley</ref>, whose identity is thinly disguised under the name of "Scarborough." This man had killed his two children and had attempted to murder his wife. The play originally had a tragic ending, but as played in 1607, ended in comedy and the story stopped short before the catastrophe, perhaps because of objections raised by Mrs. Calverley's family, the Cobhams. The crime itself is dealt with in a short play, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Yorkshire_Tragedy">A Yorkshire Tragedy</ref></hi> of uncertain authorship.</p>
<head><hi rend="italic">Pericles</hi></head>
<p>A number of studies have attributed to Wilkins a share in Shakespeare's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pericles,_Prince_of_Tyre">Pericles, Prince of Tyre</ref></hi> (which does not appear in Shakespeare's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_Folio">First Folio</ref></hi>, but was published only in a textually corrupt <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quarto">quarto</ref>). This may have been collaboration, or perhaps Wilkins was the original author of <hi rend="italic">Pericles</hi> and Shakespeare remodelled it, or vice versa. However it may be, Wilkins published in 1608 a novel entitled <hi rend="italic">The Painful Adventures of Pericles, Prynce of Tyre</hi>, described as "the true history of Pericles as it was lately presented by ... <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Gower">John Gower</ref>" (who serves as narrator in the play). This follows the play very closely. The editors of the 1986 Oxford Edition of Shakespeare make the assumption that Wilkins was the co-author of <hi rend="italic">Pericles</hi> and draw heavily upon <hi rend="italic">The Painful Adventures</hi> in their controversial reconstructed text of the play. Wilkins is thought to have contributed most of the first two acts of the play, while Shakespeare wrote the last three.</p>
</text>
