<text id="autogum_bio_doc354" title="Ii Naotora" shortTile="ii-naotora" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-10-17" dateModified="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ii_Naotora" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ii Naotora</head>In this <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japanese_name">Japanese name</ref>, the family name is Ii.<p><hi rend="bold">Ii Naotora</hi> (井伊 直虎, d. 12 September 1582) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daimyō">daimyō</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sengoku_period">Sengoku period</ref>. She was the daughter and only child of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ii_Naomori">Ii Naomori</ref>, the eighteenth head of their clan. She was primarily the head of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ii_clan">Ii clan</ref> and retainer of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imagawa_clan">Imagawa clan</ref>, because of her efforts, Ii Naotora becomes a daimyō and received the title  "Female Landlord" (女地頭).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>As a relative of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_Tsukiyama">Lady Tsukiyama</ref> (first consort of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tokugawa_Ieyasu">Tokugawa Ieyasu</ref>), Naotora switched sides to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matsudaira_clan">Matsudaira clan</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mikawa_Province">Mikawa province</ref>. The Ii clan that Naotora as guardian of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ii_Naomasa">Ii Naomasa</ref> protected, prospered for over 200 years and became one of the main samurai clans that formed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tokugawa_shogunate">Tokugawa Shogunate</ref> government.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Ii Naotora was a daughter of Ii Naomori, a leader of Iinoya-is a part of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tōtōmi_Province">Tōtōmi</ref>, who had been defeated by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imagawa_Yoshimoto">Imagawa Yoshimoto</ref> and became a vassal of Imagawa.</p>
<p>The Ii family had no male heir, so Natora's uncle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ii_Naomitsu">Ii Naomitsu</ref> tried to betrothe <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ii_Naochika">Ii Naochika</ref> his son to her so that he could inherit the clan. However, Naomitsu planned to rebel against Imagawa. Unidentified <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imagawa_clan">Imagawa clan</ref> retainers carried a report of the plans to Imagawa, who ordered Naomitsu and his son Naochika to commit <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seppuku">seppuku</ref>. Naomitsu died, but Naochika, who was very young, was protected by a Buddhist priest named Nankei. Naochika managed to flee to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shinano_Province">Shinano</ref>. Naotora became a priestess, and was named <hi rend="bold">Jirō Hōshi</hi> (次郎法師) at age of ten by Nankei.</p>
<p>Naomori and Yoshimoto died in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Okehazama">Battle of Okehazama</ref> in 1560, Imagawa clan loses power and the province goes into chaos. Naochika returned to Iinoya about ten years later after he left, he had already married another woman while in exile and could not marry Jiro Hoshi.</p>
<p>Naochika momentarily ruled the clan but, like his father, he planned a rebellion against Imagawa. Again, anonymous traitors carried news of the plans to Imagawa and Naochika was killed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imagawa_Ujizane">Imagawa Ujizane</ref> in 1560. It is said that he was killed because of an anonymous report of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ono_Michiyoshi">Ono Michiyoshi</ref>. In 1563, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ii_Naohira">Ii Naohira</ref> (Naotora's grandfather) and other men from Ii, were ordered to break into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamamatsu_Castle">Hikuma Castle</ref> as proof of their loyalty to Imagawa. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otazu_no_kata">Otazu no kata</ref> who was wife of Iio Tsurutatsu (lord of Hikuma castle) invited Naohira to a meeting with her husband and planned to eradicate it to claim prominence in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tōtōmi_Province">Totomi</ref>. In September 18, Otazu no Kata then poisoned Naohira's tea and he died soon after. Following Naohira's death and many obstacles, Jiro Hoshi returned to secular life, removed her nun costume, was baptized by the male name Naotora and became the nominal head of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ii_clan">Ii clan</ref>.</p>
<head>Reign</head>
<p>She adopted Naochika's daughter and son, Takase and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ii_Naomasa">Ii Naomasa</ref>. Naotora secured Naomasa's future successful career when he succeeds her.</p>
<p>During the early days of her reign, Naotora often tried to mediate with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imagawa_Ujizane">Imagawa Ujizane</ref> and his grandmother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jukei-ni">Jukei-ni</ref>, at which time the Imagawa clan was on warpath with Ii clan. Former Imagawa clan retainer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tokugawa_Ieyasu">Tokugawa Ieyasu</ref> went to war with Ujizane. Ieyasu was successful in forming an alliance with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oda_Nobunaga">Oda Nobunaga</ref> after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imagawa_Yoshimoto">Yoshimoto's</ref> death in 1560. Ieyasu's wife was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_Tsukiyama">Lady Tsukiyama</ref>, who was from the Imagawa family and related to Naotora.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In 1564 Niino Chikanori, a retainer of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ii_clan">Ii clan</ref>, led a siege to Hikuma castle to prove Naotora's loyalty to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imagawa_Ujizane">Imagawa Ujizane</ref>, Otazu and Tsurutatsu fought to defend the castle and Chikanori was killed. Naotora was presumed to have difficulty securing clan leadership because of the innumerable resistances from the Imagawa clan retainers, so she anonymously seeks support from other clans. After numerous threats from Imagawa retainers to Ii, Naotora finally allies with Ieyasu and actively participates in the achievements of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matsudaira_clan">Matsudaira clan</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tōtōmi_Province">Totomi</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mikawa_Province">Mikawa Province</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>Naotora's grave and other Ii family members.</caption></figure><p>Naotora's actions were the most important moment for her clan. She achieves Ii clan independence after more than two centuries serving the Imagawa. Often Naotora is portrayed as an "unconventional lord" because of her numerous strategies and unusual attempts to protect and thrive her domain and people. It is recorded that Naotora, being a former nun, often acted to avoid battles, earning the respect of many civilians. She actively participated in the success of Ieyasu's career that would later become the first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shōgun">shogun</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tokugawa_shogunate">Tokugawa shogunate</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In 1568, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jukei-ni">Jukei-ni</ref> dies and the Imagawa enter a major crisis again and a year later Ujizane surrender to the Ieyasu's Matsudaira clan. Ieyasu led a siege to Hikuma castle and capture it from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otazu_no_kata">Otazu no kata</ref>. Naotora is said to have participated actively in this battle to avenge her grandfather's death, but it is probably a tale from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edo_period">Edo period</ref>. At the same year, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ono_Michiyoshi">Ono Michiyoshi</ref> who was Naotora's ally, removes her from Iinoya's leadership with the help of Imagawa clan retainers. She escapes to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ryōtan-ji_(Hamamatsu)">Ryōtan-ji</ref> Temple in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamamatsu">Hamamatsu</ref>. During her days in Hamamatsu, Naotora gets Ieyasu's help and recaptures Iinoya castle. Michiyoshi was executed and his head was disgraced in public.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In 1572, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Takeda_Shingen">Takeda Shingen</ref> personally invades Iinoya and other castles in Totomi and Mikawa. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Mikatagahara">Battle of Mikatagahara</ref> took place near Naotora's domain. After days of resistance, Naotora surrenders Iinoya castle to the enemy to prevent bloodshed. In 1573, Shingen gets sick and dies in Naotora's domain. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Takeda_clan">Takeda clan</ref> army retreats from Iinoya and Naotora returns to being a Daimyo. In 1582, she died of disease and was buried in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ryōtan-ji_(Hamamatsu)">Ryōtan-ji</ref> temple. Naochika's son, the famed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ii_Naomasa">Ii Naomasa</ref> whom she adopted, succeeded her after her demise.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>In popular culture</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ko_Shibasaki">Ko Shibasaki</ref> portrayed her in the 2017 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NHK">NHK</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taiga_drama">Taiga drama</ref> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Onna_Jōshu_Naotora">Onna Jōshu Naotora</ref></hi>(おんな城主 直虎).</item>
<item>Ii Naotora appears in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capcom">Capcom</ref> video games <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sengoku_Basara_4">Sengoku Basara 4</ref></hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sengoku Basara: Sanada Yukimura-Den</hi>, voiced by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maaya_Sakamoto">Maaya Sakamoto</ref>.</item>
<item>She appears in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Koei_Tecmo">Koei Tecmo</ref> video games <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samurai_Warriors_4">Samurai Warriors 4</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warriors_Orochi_4">Warriors Orochi 4</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dead_or_Alive_5_Last_Round">Dead or Alive 5 Last Round</ref></hi> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warriors_All-Stars">Warriors All-Stars</ref></hi>, voiced by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yuka_Saitō_(voice_actress)">Yuka Saitō</ref>.</item>
<item>Ii Naotora is featured in episode 27 of Meow Meow Japanese History.</item></list>
</text>
