<text id="autogum_bio_doc281" title="Grigory Grigoryevich Skornyakov-Pisarev" shortTile="grigory-grigoryevich" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-10-06" dateModified="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grigory_Grigoryevich_Skornyakov-Pisarev" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Grigory Grigoryevich Skornyakov-Pisarev</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Grigory Grigoryevich Skornyakov-Pisarev</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian_language">Russian</ref>: Григорий Григорьевич Скорняков-Писарев) was an eighteenth-century Russian educator and statesman.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-RBD-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Born in the second half of the seventeenth century, Skornyakov-Pisarev studied in Italy and Berlin, returning to Russia with knowledge of mathematics, mechanics, and engineering. For the next twenty years he oversaw instruction in the art of gunnery. In accordance with a series of decrees between 1714 and 1716, he was put in charge of new schools at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pskov">Pskov</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Novgorod">Novgorod</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yaroslavl">Yaroslavl</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow">Moscow</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vologda">Vologda</ref>. From 1715 he taught at the new Maritime Academy (<ref target="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/Академия%20морской%20гвардии">ru</ref>) in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Petersburg">Saint Petersburg</ref>, becoming its director in 1719. In 1722 he published the first treatise on mechanics in Russian, which included an unfulfilled promise to write more fully on the subject in the future.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-RBD-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-OUP-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Forging a close relationship with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tsar">Tsar</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_the_Great">Peter the Great</ref>, and his close associates, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Danilovich_Menshikov">Prince Menshikov</ref>, in 1717 Skornyakov-Pisarev was entrusted with the initial investigations of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tsarina">Tsarina</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yevdokiya_Lopukhina">Eudoxia Feodorovna Lopukhina</ref>. He was also involved in the hearings against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tsarevich">Tsarevich</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexei_Petrovich,_Tsarevich_of_Russia">Alexei Petrovich</ref>. By 1718 he had been appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Procurator_(Russia)">Chief Procurator</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governing_Senate">Senate</ref>. He was also put in charge of the greatest engineering project of the day, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ladoga_Canal">Ladoga Canal</ref>. In 1723, however, he fell from grace: he was implicated in a conspiracy against Menshikov, progress on the canal was found to be unsatisfactory, and he was arrested, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knout">knouted</ref>, deprived of his rank and estates, and exiled to Siberia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-RBD-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-OUP-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Under Peter's successor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emperor_of_All_Russia">Empress</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna_of_Russia">Anna</ref>, Skornyakov-Pisarev enjoyed partial rehabilitation. Acting on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vitus_Bering">Bering</ref>'s recommendations for further exploration after the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_Kamchatka_expedition">First Kamchatka expedition</ref>, in 1731 Anna appointed Skornyakov-Pisarev commandant of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Okhotsk">Okhotsk</ref> region. By decree of the Senate the following year, the population of Okhotsk was to be augmented, grain cultivation initiated, a landing and wharf constructed, and ships built for trade in furs and other items with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamchatka">Kamchatka</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Lansen-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CSP-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Skornyakov-Pisarev's progress, however, was slow. Making it as far as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yakutsk">Yakutsk</ref>, there he remained for almost three years, engaged in disputes over men, equipment, and supplies, during which he and the local official denounced and even arrested one another. After finally arriving in Okhotsk in 1735 with eighty families of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cossacks">Cossacks</ref> and sixty of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yakuts">Yakuts</ref>, he is said to given himself over to drink and his concubines, and there were also accusations of financial irregularities.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Lansen-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CSP-4">[4]</ref> Nevertheless, as founder of the so-called Siberian Flotilla or Okhostk Flotilla, the first Russian naval group in the Pacific, which numbered some eight vessels by 1742, he is said to have paved the way for the future development of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pacific_Fleet_(Russia)">Pacific Fleet</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>In 1741 he returned to European Russia with his former rank and possessions restored.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-RBD-1">[1]</ref> In August that year <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aleksei_Chirikov">Aleksei Chirikov</ref> sent to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Admiralty_Board_(Russian_Empire)">Admiralty College</ref> a report on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Northern_Expedition">Great Northern Expedition</ref>; Skornyakov-Pisarev wrote an unfavourable short report on Chirikov's report.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> A few years later, some time around the middle of the century, he died.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-RBD-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-OUP-2">[2]</ref></p>
</text>
