<text id="autogum_bio_doc214" title="Charlie Hurley (Irish republican)" shortTile="charlie-hurley-irish" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-08-10" dateModified="2019-03-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Hurley_%28Irish_republican%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Charlie Hurley (Irish republican)</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Charles "Charlie" Hurley</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irish_language">Irish</ref>: <hi lang="ga" rend="italic">Cathal Ó Muirthile</hi>) (died March 1921) was Officer Commanding of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/3rd_Cork_Brigade">3rd Cork Brigade</ref> (West Cork) of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irish_Republican_Army">Irish Republican Army</ref> during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irish_War_of_Independence">Irish War of Independence</ref> (1919–1921)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>:111</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>He was born in Baurleigh, County Cork, near the village of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kilbrittain">Kilbrittain</ref> on March 19, 1892 and was educated in national school and subsequently passed the civil service examinations at aged fifteen.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cambridge.org-2">[2]</ref> According to his brother James, Charlie was one of seven siblings, 'born and reared in a farm of 35 acres'. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In his adolescence he became a clerk working for the government. In 1915 he was offered a promotion and a transfer to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haulbowline_Island">Haulbowline Island</ref>, but declined on the grounds that this entailed enlisting in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Navy">Royal Navy</ref>, albeit in a purely administrative role. Returning to Cork, he became friends with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liam_Deasy">Liam Deasy</ref> who introduced him to the Irish republican movement.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cambridge.org-2">[2]</ref> In 1917 he took a job at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castletownbere">Castletownbere</ref> and it as there that he joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irish_Volunteers">Irish Volunteers</ref> in 1917. He was also a member of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sinn_Fein">Sinn Fein</ref>, the Gaelic Athletic Association and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaelic_League">Gaelic League</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-theirishrevolution.ie-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>IRA commander</head>
<p>In 1918 he was sentenced to five years penal servitude for possession of arms and plans of the British military fortifications at Bere Island. However he was released in 1919 after a hunger strike. In the same year, his brother Willie, also an IRA Volunteer, died of typhoid. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> He first became vice -commandant of the Volunteers or IRA Bandon Battalion and then in August 1920, after the arrest and imprisonment of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom_Hales_(Irish_republican)">Tom Hales</ref>, he became commander of the Third Cork Brigade of the IRA. One of his most important decisions was to establish a full-time guerrilla unit of flying column, under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom_Barry_(soldier)">Tom Barry</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-theirishrevolution.ie-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>The Third Cork Brigade went on to be one of the most active IRA units during the guerrilla war against the British in 1919-1921. According to Barry, Hurley led an ambush of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Irish_Constabulary">Royal Irish Constabulary</ref> at Ahawadda, in April 1920 killing three policemen, wounding one and taking their arms and ammunition. In July of that year, Hurley led a successful attack on Coastguard station at Howes Strand, capturing a large amount of weapons and ammunition.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Barry-6">[6]</ref>:13–14 Barry remarked that Hurley was 'a remarkable man and a lovable personality' and 'continually urged a fighting army policy'.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Barry-6">[6]</ref>:16–17</p>
<p>Hurley was present at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tooreen_ambush">Tooreen ambush</ref> in October 1920 and subsequently was part of an assassination attempt on a judge who gave 'harsh sentences' to IRA members.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Barry-6">[6]</ref>:28–31, 33–34 From December 1920 until January 1921, Hurley took command of the Third Cork Brigade's flying column while Barry was ill. He also toured IRA units to assess the impact of the Catholic Bishop of Cork, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Cohalan_(bishop_of_Cork)">Dr. Colohan</ref>'s decree of excommunication on the guerrilla movement.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cambridge.org-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Death and memory</head>
<p>In February 1921, he led the disastrous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upton_Train_Ambush">Upton Train Ambush</ref> on 15 February 1921, an attack on train carrying British troops. In the action, the attacking IRA party was heavily outnumbered and the fire fight resulted in three IRA men and six civilians being killed. Hurley was also badly wounded in the face and ankle. Tom Barry wrote of the aftermath of the ambush 'he [Hurley] mourned deeply for his dead comrades and for the dead civilians, whom he did not know'.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Barry-6">[6]</ref>:93–95 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-theirishrevolution.ie-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Hurley was killed in action by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_Kingdom_of_Great_Britain_and_Ireland">British</ref> troops just before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crossbarry_Ambush">Crossbarry Ambush</ref> in March 19, 1921.  Hurley was staying in a house with a pro-republican family, where he was recuperating from serious wounds he had received at Upton a month earlier.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-theirishrevolution.ie-4">[4]</ref>  When he realised that he was surrounded by the British forces he fled the house, as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom_Barry_(soldier)">Tom Barry</ref> comments in his book, to reduce the danger to those in the house, and was shot dead by pursuing troops. Barry remarks that Hurley, 'died in the manner in which we expected.'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Barry-6">[6]</ref>:136–137</p>
<p>The British Army placed his body at the workhouse in Bandon but members of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cumann_na_mBan">Cumann na mBan</ref> surreptitiously took away his body and he was given a secret republican funeral in Clogagh.(5) A  local ballad exists that commemorates him. In addition, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaelic_Athletic_Association">Gaelic Athletic Association</ref> grounds in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bandon,_County_Cork">Bandon</ref> was named after him in 1971.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
</text>
