<text id="autogum_bio_doc616" title="Thomas Mortimer" shortTile="thomas-mortimer" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-08-11" dateModified="2019-07-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Mortimer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Thomas Mortimer</head><p>
Sir <hi rend="bold">Thomas Mortimer</hi> (c. 1350–1399) was a medieval English soldier and statesman who served briefly in several important administrative and judicial state offices in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ireland">Ireland</ref> and played a part in the opposition to the reign of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_II_of_England">Richard II</ref>. He was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Legitimacy_(family_law)">illegitimate</ref> member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mortimer#Medieval_magnates">Mortimer family</ref>, which was then one of the leading noble houses in England and Ireland, and he helped to manage the Mortimer  lands during the minority of the family heir, his nephew <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Mortimer,_4th_Earl_of_March">Roger, earl of March</ref>. Sir Thomas was also a close associate of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lords_Appellant">Lords Appellant</ref> who opposed the reign of King Richard II.</p>
<p>Sir Thomas took part in the appellants' rebellion in 1387 against the king, and fought at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Radcot_Bridge">Battle of Radcot Bridge</ref>, during which he killed Sir Thomas Molineux, one of the royal commanders. 10 years later, when the king took his revenge against the rebels, this act ultimately led to his conviction for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treason">treason</ref>. He fled for his life and died in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exile">exile</ref>.</p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>Thomas was an illegitimate son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Mortimer,_2nd_Earl_of_March">Roger Mortimer, 2nd Earl of March</ref> (1328–1360).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEDunn200356-1">[1]</ref> He was described as an esquire in 1367, pointing to a birth date of  around 1350.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEIsaacson191354-2">[2]</ref> He seems to have been treated by his father and brother very much as one of the family. Nothing is known of his mother. By 1380 he had acquired considerable military expertise, and had been <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knighted">knighted</ref>. When his legitimate brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edmund_Mortimer,_3rd_Earl_of_March">Edmund Mortimer, 3rd Earl of March</ref> was made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Lieutenant_of_Ireland">Lord Lieutenant of Ireland</ref> in 1379, Thomas went with him to Ireland and acted as his Deputy, holding in his name a Great Council at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clonmel">Clonmel</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEOtway-Ruthven1968315-3">[3]</ref> Edmund was charged with the task of subduing the Gaelic clans in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulster">Ulster</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Munster">Munster</ref>, but he had only limited success in this task.</p>
<head>Lord Deputy of Ireland</head>
<p>Edmund's sudden death in December 1381 left the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dublin">Dublin</ref> Government in a quandary, since there were very few men willing to assume the office of Lord Lieutenant, at a time of exceptional political turbulence in Ireland. Richard Wyre, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Cloyne">Bishop of Cloyne</ref>, proposed that Thomas Mortimer should be appointed Lord Lieutenant, both for his military experience and his ability to retain the loyalty of his brother's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Retinue">retinue</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEOtway-Ruthven1968315–6-4">[4]</ref> In the event King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_II">Richard II</ref> appointed Thomas's nephew, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Mortimer,_4th_Earl_of_March">Roger Mortimer, 4th Earl of March</ref>, a child of seven, as Lord Lieutenant.  The absurdity of this choice was lessened to some extent by the appointment of Thomas as Lord Deputy and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chief_Justice_of_the_King's_Bench_for_Ireland">Lord Chief Justice</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEOtway-Ruthven1968316-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Return to England</head>
<p>On the appointment of Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Courtenay_(died_1406)">Philip Courtenay</ref> as Lord Lieutenant of Ireland in February 1383, Thomas returned to England. His nephew's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wardship">wardship</ref> had been entrusted to a group of magnates which included <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_FitzAlan,_4th_Earl_of_Arundel">Richard FitzAlan, 4th Earl of Arundel</ref>, of whom Thomas was an intimate friend. It was probably Arundel who appointed Thomas to the position of steward of the Mortimer estates during Roger's minority, thus greatly enhancing his political standing.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEDunn2002162-6">[6]</ref> As Roger grew older he and his uncle became close, going hunting together and exchanging gifts of wine: Dunn suggests that Thomas was the closest Roger ever knew to a father.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEDunn2002164-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>The Appellants</head>
<p>Arundel was a  key member of the group of nobles called the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lords_Appellant">Lords Appellant</ref>, who had emerged as opponents of Richard II and the royal favourite <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_de_Vere,_Duke_of_Ireland">Robert de Vere, Duke of Ireland</ref>. Mortimer was closely associated with them and is known to have visited Arundel's house regularly during 1387, the critical year in the Appellants' rise to power.</p>
<head>The Battle of Radcot Bridge</head>
Main article: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Radcot_Bridge">Battle of Radcot Bridge</ref>
<p>In December 1387, at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radcot_Bridge">Radcot Bridge</ref>, the Appellants clashed with the royal army, headed by Robert de Vere and Sir Thomas Molineux, Constable of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chester_Castle">Chester Castle</ref>; de Vere was defeated and forced to flee the country.  Mortimer himself killed Molineux,  who was one of the few casualties of the fight.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEDunn2002162-6">[6]</ref> According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Walsingham">Thomas Walsingham</ref>, Molineux, who had attempted to flee, pleaded for his life, but Mortimer pulled off Molinuex's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helmet">helmet</ref> and stabbed him in the head with a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dagger">dagger</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEGillespie1975163-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>During the brief rule of the Appellants, Mortimer was in high favour. He was appointed Justiciar of Ireland, but Richard, despite his temporary loss of power, somehow managed to countermand the appointment (no doubt he feared to surrender control of Ireland entirely to his enemies) and it never took effect. Despite the King's mistrust of them,  Thomas and his nephew Roger, with troops, accompanied him on his Irish expedition in 1394;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEOtway-Ruthven1968326-9">[9]</ref> and when Roger was reappointed Lord Lieutenant in 1396, Thomas went to Ireland with him.</p>
<head>Downfall</head>
<p>In 1397 the King at last moved to destroy the surviving Lords Appellant.  Arundel, Mortimer's patron, was convicted of treason and executed. Mortimer was "appealed for" (i.e. charged with) treason, in that his killing of Molineux, the King's commander ten years earlier was deemed in law to be an attempt to murder the King himself. Mortimer was not permitted to stand trial, but ordered to surrender himself within three months. Unsurprisingly Mortimer instead chose to flee the country: the King accused Roger, probably with good reason, of conniving at his uncle's escape.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEOtway-Ruthven1968337-10">[10]</ref> Thomas was declared a traitor and his lands were forfeited to the Crown. He took refuge in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scotland">Scotland</ref> where he died in 1399.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEGiven-Wilson201645_n._41-11">[11]</ref></p>
<head>Marriage</head>
<p>He married Agnes de Poynings, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_de_Poynings,_2nd_Baron_Poynings">Michael de Poynings, 2nd Baron Poynings</ref>, and widow of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Bardolf,_4th_Baron_Bardolf">William Bardolf, 4th Baron Bardolf</ref>. They had no children. She was described as a widow on 9 January 1403, indicating that Sir Thomas Mortimer was dead by then.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicolas1826162-12">[12]</ref></p>
<head>Character</head>
<p>Although the details (if they were accurately reported) of his killing of Molineux show him in a rather sinister light, Mortimer had the respect and esteem of many who knew him, including his brother and his nephew. The chronicler <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adam_of_Usk">Adam of Usk</ref>, who knew him personally, praised him as "a vigorous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knight">knight</ref>".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEDunn2002164-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
