<text id="autogum_bio_doc715" title="Thomas de Strickland" shortTile="thomas-de-strickland" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-19" dateModified="2018-04-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_de_Strickland" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Thomas de Strickland</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sir Thomas de Strickland</hi> (also <hi rend="bold">Stryckeland</hi>; 1367 – 30 July 1455) was an English soldier.  He is best known for carrying the banner of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._George">St. George</ref> at the battle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Agincourt">Agincourt</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>Battle of Agincourt</caption></figure>
<head>At war</head>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>On 21 July 1403, de Strickland fought on the Royalist side at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Shrewsbury">Battle of Shrewsbury</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_IV_of_England">Henry IV</ref> and was awarded by the King, a sum of £38 and two horses which had belonged to the rebel <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_'Hotspur'_Percy">Henry Percy</ref> (Hotspur).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> He was also rewarded for his valiant efforts by being made Keeper of Inglewood royal forest in Cumberland.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HoP-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>He was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_Sheriff_of_Bedfordshire_and_Buckinghamshire">Sheriff of Bedfordshire and Buckinghamshire</ref> for 1410 and for 1414.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HoP-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>He was elected one of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knight_of_the_shire">knights of the shire</ref> (to represent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westmorland_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Westmorland</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_England">Parliament of England</ref>) in 1404, 1429, and 1431.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HoP-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Battle of Agincourt</head>
<p>On 25 October 1415, de Strickland and his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man-at-arms">Men at arms</ref>, including a group of archers known as "the Kendal Bowmen", were part of the army of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_V_of_England">King Henry V</ref> which won a major battle at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Agincourt">Agincourt</ref> in North West <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France">France</ref> against superior numbers. As de Strickland was a knight in training, or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esquire">esquire</ref>, he fought dismounted with a sword, It was a question of honour that a man who carried the banner of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._George">St. George</ref> did so without the protection of a shield, as he would be protected by his men at arms.</p>
<head>Family life</head>
<p>In 1405, de Strickland married Mabel de Beethom, daughter of Sir John de Bethom, and they had several children, including:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-tudorplace1-5">[5]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Walter (1411-1466), married Douce Croft.</item>
<item>Margaret</item>
<item>Cecilia</item>
<item>Robert</item></list>
<p>Strickland had been knighted by 1418, not long after the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Agincourt">Battle of Agincourt</ref>. After that time it became common practice amongst noble families to drop the English "of" and the French "de" from their names, so Sir Thomas de (or of) Strickland became Sir Thomas Strickland.</p>
<head>Later Stricklands</head>
<p>Thomas' son Walter Strickland (described in 1452 as an 'esquire') was an indentured retainer of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Neville,_5th_Earl_of_Salisbury">Richard Neville, 5th Earl of Salisbury</ref>, and his 1452 indenture survives. He contracts to support the Earl of Salisbury with "bowmen horsed and harnessed, 69; billmen horsed and harnessed, 74;  bowmen without horses, 71; billmen without horses, 76". <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> (The term 'harnessed' refers to armour, not a horse harness.) During his father's lifetime he carried his father's banner of <hi rend="italic">sable three escallops argent</hi>, but differenced by the overlay of a <hi rend="italic">label of three points or</hi>.</p>
<p>Succeeding his father as Sir Walter, he is known to have fought for the Yorkists at 1st St Alban's in 1455 and Blore Heath in 1459.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> He married Douce Croft.</p>
<p>Sir Thomas Strickland was Walter's eldest son and he married Agnes Parr and later Margaret, widow of Sir John Byron. He also fought on the Yorkist side at Barnet (1471), where he was knighted by Edward IV, as well as fighting at Bosworth in 1485 for Richard III. He survived the battle and died in 1494. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
</text>
