<text id="autogum_bio_doc308" title="Mattheus van Beveren" shortTile="mattheus-van-beveren" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-04" dateModified="2018-12-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mattheus_van_Beveren" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Mattheus van Beveren</head>
<figure><caption> St Nicholas with children in a tub flanked by angels, main altar of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Nicholas'_Church,_Ghent">Saint Nicholas' Church, Ghent</ref></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mattheus van Beveren</hi> (alternative names: Mathieu Van Beveren, Mathieu Beveren, Matthieu Beveren) (c. 1630, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antwerp">Antwerp</ref> – after 21 January 1696, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brussels">Brussels</ref>) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southern_Netherlands">Flemish</ref> sculptor and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medalist">medalist</ref> who is mainly known for his monumental <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baroque">Baroque</ref> church sculptures and small wood and ivory sculptures.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Details about his life are scarce.  He likely trained with the Antwerp sculptor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pieter_Verbrugghen_I">Pieter Verbrugghen I</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ox-1">[1]</ref> He joined the Antwerp <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guild_of_St._Luke">Guild of St. Luke</ref> in 1649/50.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rkd-2">[2]</ref> He was the mint superintendent of Antwerp in the 1670s and 80s.</p>
<p>He married Suzanna Dooms, by whom he had a son named Judocus and a daughter named Catherina who married the flower <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Still_life">still life</ref> painter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolaes_van_Verendael">Nicolaes van Verendael</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rkd-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bnb-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Mattheus van Beveren ran a large sculpture workshop with a significant output.  Mattheus van Beveren was highly recognized for his artistic work and contributions as an instructor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-iv-4">[4]</ref> He trained Jan Baptist Santvoort.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rkd-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Work</head>
<figure><caption> Allegorical figures representing <hi rend="italic">Virtue, Fame and Time</hi>, funerary chapel of Duke Lamoral of Thurn and Taxis</caption></figure>
<p>Van Beveren was a versatile artist in terms of the subject range of his sculptures as well as the materials in which he worked. He executed monumental works in marble, stone and wood as well as small-scale works in wood, ivory and terracota.  He further was a medalist and produced designs for dies for the Antwerp Mint.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ox-1">[1]</ref> Van Beveren's style combines the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classicism">classicist</ref> tendency of the Brussels sculptors <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerôme_Duquesnoy_(I)">Jerôme Duquesnoy (I)</ref> and his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/François_Duquesnoy">François Duquesnoy</ref> with the baroque realism of his Antwerp contemporaries <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pieter_Verbrugghen_II">Pieter Verbrugghen II</ref> and Artus Quellinus the Younger who were more influenced by the style of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Paul_Rubens">Rubens</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ox-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>His subject matter was mainly religious but he also worked on portraits and allegorical subjects.  An example of the latter is the group of allegorical figures representing <hi rend="italic">Virtue, Fame and Time</hi> created for the funerary chapel of Duke Lamoral of Thorn and Taxis (in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Our_Blessed_Lady_of_Zavel_Church">Our Blessed Lady of Zavel Church</ref> in Brussels) of which a terracotta model is kept at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Museums_of_Fine_Arts_of_Belgium">Royal Museums of Fine Arts of Belgium</ref> in Brussels.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>He executed the main altar in the St Nicholas Church in Ghent.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> He collaborated with some of the leading Flemish sculptors in the execution of large religious sculptures.  He assisted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucas_Faydherbe">Lucas Faydherbe</ref> with the painted wood and stone high altar in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Rumbold's_Cathedral">St Rumbold's Cathedral</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mechelen">Mechelen</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ox-1">[1]</ref> He made an <hi rend="italic">Angel throne</hi> for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cathedral_of_Our_Lady_(Antwerp)">Antwerp Cathedral</ref> (1659–1660) after a design by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artus_Quellinus_II">Artus Quellinus the Younger</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>His designs were used by his large workshop and other contemporary artists in the creation of numerous sculptures. The Brussels sculptor Jan Cosyns, for instance, sculpted the marble statues for the funerary chapel of Duke Lamoral of Thurn and Taxis after a design by van Beveren.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>Matheus van Beveren was known for his small-scale works, and in particular his ivory sculptures.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-iv-4">[4]</ref> Beautiful examples are the <hi rend="italic">Cupid on a lion</hi> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan_Museum_of_Art">Metropolitan Museum of Art</ref> and the <hi rend="italic">Maria Apocalyptica</hi> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rijksmuseum">Rijksmuseum</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> He and his workshop often used paintings by Rubens as models for numerous ivory crucifixes.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></p>
<head>Selected works</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1665: Pillar monument of Gaspard Boest in the Church of St. Jacob in Antwerp.</item>
<item>1677–1678: Main altar of the Church of St. Nicolas in Ghent.</item>
<item>1678: Marble tomb monument for Lamoral Claude-François, Count of Thurn and Taxis in the Our Blessed Lady of Zavel Church in Brussels.</item>
<item>1680 ca.: Madonna and Child with Maria and St. John the Evangelist, ivory, Amsterdam, Rijksmuseum.</item>
<item>1681–1684: Wooden pulpit of the Church of Our Lady in Dendermonde.</item>
<item>Oak doors for the entrance to the Augustinian monastery in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tienen">Tienen</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref></item></list>
</text>
