<text id="autogum_bio_doc348" title="Henry Scobell" shortTile="henry-scobell" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-10" dateModified="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Scobell" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Henry Scobell</head>For the governor of Cape Cod, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Jenner_Scobell">Henry Jenner Scobell</ref>.
<figure><caption>An 1884 drawing of what the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palace_of_Westminster">Old Palace of Westminster</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burning_of_Parliament">destroyed by fire in 1834</ref>), looked like in the time of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VIII_of_England">Henry VIII</ref> when it was the seat of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_England">Parliament of England</ref></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Henry Scobell</hi> (baptised 1610; died 1660)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_England">English Parliamentary</ref> official, and editor of official publications. He was clerk to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long_Parliament">Long Parliament</ref>, and wrote on parliamentary procedure and precedents.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<figure><caption>The title page of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:H.S.E.C.P._(Henry_Scobell),_Memorials_of_the_Method_and_Manner_of_Proceedings_in_Parliament_in_Passing_Bills_(3rd_ed,_1670).pdf">Memorials of the Method and Manner of Proceedings in Parliament in Passing Bills</ref></hi> (3rd ed., 1670),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> written by "H.S. E. C.P." (Henry Scobell, Esquire, Clerk of Parliament)</caption></figure>
<p>Initially under-clerk of the parliaments, Scobell became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clerk_of_the_House_of_Commons">Clerk of the House of Commons</ref> from 5 January 1649, his predecessor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Elsynge">Henry Elsynge</ref> having resigned. Scobell also held a position as censor of publications, and then was Clerk of the Parliament for life with effect from 14 May 1649.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> He was the first editor, from 9 October 1649, of <hi rend="italic">Severall Proceedings in Parliament</hi>, an early official newspaper, and the second of Parliament's publications.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>In the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rump_Parliament">Rump Parliament</ref>, Scobell found himself in the middle of the clashes leading to its dissolution in 1653.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> He remained Clerk to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barebone's_Parliament">Barebone's Parliament</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>From 1655 Scobell became Clerk to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Counsellor_of_State">Council of State</ref>, a large jump in status, in succession to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Thurloe">John Thurloe</ref> and sharing the position with William Jessop.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> Up to then he had been for a period an assistant secretary to the Council.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>In 1658, as a preliminary to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savoy_Assembly">Savoy Assembly</ref>, Scobell called together elders of Independent churches from the London area, in the house of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Griffith">George Griffith</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> He himself was an elder of the Congregational church of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Rowe_(minister)">John Rowe</ref>, meeting in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westminster_Abbey">Westminster Abbey</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>In October 1659 he was one of those calling on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Monck">George Monck</ref> to intervene in the vacuum of power after the death of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oliver_Cromwell">Oliver Cromwell</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Memorials of the Method and Maner of Proceedings in Parliament in Passing Bills. Together with Several Rules and Customs, which by Long and Constant Practice have Obtained the Name of Orders of the House. Gathered by Observation, and out of the Journal Books from the Time of Edward 6</hi>, London: Printed by Henry Hills and John Field, printers to His Highness, 1656, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OCLC">OCLC</ref><ref target="//www.worldcat.org/oclc/606895390">606895390</ref>.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">A Collection of Acts and Ordinances of General Use, Made in the Parliament, Begun and Held at Westminster, the Third Day of November, anno 1640: And since, unto the Adjournment of the Parliament Begun and Holden the 17th of September, Anno 1656, and formerly Published in Print, which are here Printed at Large with Marginal Notes, or Abbreviated: Being a Continuation of that Work from the End of Mr. Pulton's Collection: In 2 Parts: Together with Several Tables of the Titles of, and Principal Matters Contained in the said Acts and Ordinances, and likewise of such as being of more Private and Particular Concernment, or less Use, or Omitted</hi>, London: Printed by Henry Hills and John Field..., 1657–1658, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OCLC">OCLC</ref><ref target="//www.worldcat.org/oclc/802073701">802073701</ref>.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">The Povver of the Lords and Commons in Parliament in Point of Judicature briefly Discours'd. At the Request of a Worthy Member of the House of Commons</hi>, London: [[[sine nomine|s.n.]]], 1680, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OCLC">OCLC</ref><ref target="//www.worldcat.org/oclc/228723004">228723004</ref>.</item></list>
</text>
