<text id="autogum_bio_doc297" title="Stevan Ljubibratić" shortTile="stevan-ljubibratic" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-01-12" dateModified="2019-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stevan_Ljubibrati%C4%87" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Stevan Ljubibratić</head><p><hi rend="bold">Stevan Ljubibratić</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piva,_Montenegro">Piva</ref>, c. 1661-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kostajnica,_Bosnia_and_Herzegovina">Kostajnica</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bosnia-Herzegovina">Bosnia-Herzegovina</ref>, April, 1737) was a Serbian Orthodox bishop of Dalmatia. He was the brother of Bishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savatije_Ljubibratić">Savatije Ljubibratić</ref> of Dalmatia.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Ljubibratić brothers were born in Piva, and belonged to the Ruđić brotherhood, at a time when the region was part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman Empire</ref>. Ljubibratić, as many of his relatives, took monastic vows and later became a bishop.</p>
<p>Since 1687, Stevan and Savatije Ljubibratić were notable participants in the struggle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman–Venetian_Wars">against the Ottomans, in Venetian support</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEVeselinović196678-1">[1]</ref> On 10 December 1687, both Stevan and Savatija were present at Tvrdoš when priest and vojvoda Vukašin Gavrilović with his people came from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikšić">Nikšić</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMihić1975112-2">[2]</ref> In 1690, he and the Tvrdoš brotherhood (including his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savatije_Ljubibratić">Savatije</ref>) left <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trebinje">Trebinje</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herceg_Novi">Herceg Novi</ref>, fleeing the Ottomans, where they renovated the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savina_Monastery,_Montenegro">Savina Monastery</ref>.</p>
<p>The Republic of Venice recognized Savatije's episcopal rule as Metropolitan (<hi rend="italic">vladika</hi>) of Zahumlje in Novi in 1695.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKomar2001-3">[3]</ref> His ecclesiastical province stretched over "newly conquered areas".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKomar2001-3">[3]</ref> The Serbian Church made the first steps to establish an independent Serb municipality in the region of old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dračevica_(župa)">Dračevica</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKomar2001-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Bishop of Dalmatia</head>
<p>Metropolitan Nikodim Busović, the bishop "of all Orthodox Serbs on the Dalmatian continent", was banished from Dalmatia in 1705. On the demand of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Krka_monastery">Krka monastery</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Krupa_monastery">Krupa monastery</ref>, Stevan Ljubibratić's brother Savatije was appointed Nikodim's office by the Venetian government.  Ljubibratić had taken this office in spite of Melentije Tipaldi (1658–1730), the Greek-Catholic bishop who was a driving force of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniatism">Uniatism</ref>; and continued the struggle against the Uniatism of Serbs in Dalmatia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Radojcic-4">[4]</ref> Tipaldi greatly undermined against Ljubibratić, so far that the Church Synod in Constantinople condemned Tipaldi and excluded him from the Orthodox Church as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traitor">traitor</ref>; with this support, Savatije Ljubibratić was able to continue his service.</p>
<p>Stevan and Savatije became friends with colonel Mihailo Miloradović,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMihić1975112-2">[2]</ref> who had along with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan_Danilo_I_Petrović-Njegoš">Metropolitan Danilo I Petrović-Njegoš</ref> been recruited by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_I_of_Russia">Peter I of Russia</ref> to incite rebellion in Herzegovina against the Ottomans in 1710–11 (during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pruth_River_Campaign">Pruth River Campaign</ref>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Savatije Ljubibratić successfully opposed the orders of the Catholic <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curia">curia</ref></hi> against the Orthodox believers in Dalmatia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Radojcic-4">[4]</ref> Savatije declined Venetian official <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Burović">Ivan Burović</ref>'s offers to begin Uniatism, Burović having sent the Catholic bishop of Kotor and his relative <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vićentije_Zmajević">Vićentije Zmajević</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perast">Perast</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKomar2001-3">[3]</ref> He strengthened ties with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_Patriarchate_of_Peć">Serbian Patriarchate of Peć</ref>, whose Patriarch, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mojsije_Rajović">Mojsije Rajović</ref>, visited Dalmatia in 1714, after Ljubibratić's request; this visit proved important for the preservation of Orthodoxy and somewhat paused pressure on the Orthodox church in Dalmatia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Radojcic-4">[4]</ref> After the death of Savatije Ljubibratić in January 1716, in the village of Topla, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herceg_Novi">Herceg Novi</ref>, Stevan Ljubibratić was chosen to take his brother's throne. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKomar2001-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>On September 2, 1719 Cardinal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fabrizio_Paolucci">Fabrizio Paolucci</ref> asked Rome that the Nuncio in Venice bar Bishop Stevan Ljubibratić from visiting the Serbian Orthodox population on Venetian territory.  On January 25, 1720 responding to the demand by Cardinal Paulucci, the Venetian Government ordered the Providur of Dalmatia to expel Bishop Stevan Ljubibratić from Dalmatia.</p>
<p>Following his banishment from Dalmatia, Bishop Stevan went to the Serbian Orthodox Ličko-Krbavska and Zrinopoljska Eparchy which was established in 1695 by metropolitan Atanasije Ljubojević and certified by Emperor Joseph I in 1707. This eparchy was the ecclesiastical centre of the Serbian Orthodox Church in this region, populated by Serbs, the community known at the time as "Rascians". This eparchy was under jurisdiction of the Metropolitan of Dabro-Bosna, directly under the restored Serbian Patriarch in Peć. In Kostajnica, on the 1st of February 1728, Stevan was made Bishop of Licko-Krbavka and Zrinopoljska Eparchy. His contact with his beloved Dalmatia was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simeon_Končarević">Simeon Končarević</ref> who became one of the most important figures in the 18th century Serbian history.</p>
<p>He died in April 1737.</p>
</text>
