<text id="autogum_bio_doc791" title="John, Count of Nassau-Dillenburg" shortTile="john-count-nassaudillenburg" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-09-21" dateModified="2019-10-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%2C_Count_of_Nassau-Dillenburg" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John, Count of Nassau-Dillenburg</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">John, Count of Nassau-Dillenburg</hi> (died 10 August 1328, fell in battle near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wetzlar">Wetzlar</ref>) was the third son of Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto_I,_Count_of_Nassau">Otto I</ref> of Nassau and his wife Agnes (d. 1303), daughter of Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emich_IV,_Count_of_Leiningen-Landeck">Emich IV</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Leiningen">Leiningen-Landeck</ref>. John was a first cousin of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adolf,_King_of_Germany">Adolf</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_of_the_Romans">the Romans</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<head>Inheriting Nassau-Dillenburg</head>
<p>As a younger son, John was the initially destined for an ecclesiastical career and he became a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_(priest)">canon</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Worms_Cathedral">Worms</ref>. However, after his mother's death in 1303, he but left the clergy and disputed the inheritance with his brother Henry. After a lengthy dispute, the county was divided between the three surviving brothers. The oldest, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_I,_Count_of_Nassau-Siegen">Henry</ref> (d. 1343), received <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nassau-Siegen">Nassau-Siegen</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ginsburg">Ginsburg</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westerwald">Westerwald</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emicho_I,_Count_of_Nassau-Hadamar">Emicho</ref> (d. 1334) received <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nassau-Hadamar">Nassau-Hadamar</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hadamar">Hadamar</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Driedorf">Driedorf</ref> and Esterau. John received <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nassau-Dillenburg">Nassau-Dillenburg</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herborn_(Hesse)">Herborn</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haiger">Haiger</ref> and Beilstein. A fourth brother, Otto (d. 1302), had also been a canon at Worms, but he had already died.</p>
<p>In 1306, John enfeoffed his share of the county to his eldest brother Henry, with permission of Landgrave <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_I,_Landgrave_of_Hesse">Henry I</ref> of Hesse, with a provision that this share would fall to Henry at John's death.</p>
<head>Feuds</head>
<p>On 8 November 1308, John was enfoeffed by the Bishop of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Worms">Worms</ref> with the Hundred of Kalenberg. Until then, the Lords of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hachenburg">Hachenburg</ref>-Greifenstein and the Lords of Merenberg had been <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vogt">Vogts</ref> of the area, but John had managed to displace them. Soon afterward, on 31 March 1310, John purchased the hereditary possessions of the Lords of Merenberg in the area from Harrad VII (d. 1328), the last male member of the dynasty. These possessions included justice over Nederoth and Heimau. Count Engelbert I of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sayn">Sayn</ref>, the son-in-law of the last Lord of Hachenburg-Greifenstein reached an agreement with John on 3 May 1325: with permission from his brother Henry, John enfeoffed Engelbert with territories in the counties of Dietz and Solms which had earlier been held by the Lords of Greifenstein, and in return Engelbert renounced his claims in the areas around Kalenberg and Herborn and became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burgrave">Burgrave</ref> of Beilstein.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Like his father, John fought in long and bitter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feud">feuds</ref> against the local nobility, in particular the Lords of Dernbach and Bicken, to impose his sovereignty. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Nassau">Nassau family</ref> had been fighting the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dernbacher_Feud">Dernbacher Feud</ref> about property rights in the <hi lang="de" rend="italic">Herborner Mark</hi>, the area around <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herborn_(Hesse)">Herborn</ref> since c.1230. This feud brought John and his brother Henry in conflict with Landgrave <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_II,_Landgrave_of_Hesse">Henry II</ref> of Hesse, who supported the Lords of Dernbach against the ambitious Counts of Nassau. The Lords of Dernbach had sold their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dernbach_Castle">Dernbach Castle</ref> to Henry II in 1309. On 26 June 1312, a peace treaty was signed by Landgrave <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto_I,_Landgrave_of_Hesse">Otto I</ref> of Hesse and the brothers Henry, Emicho and John of Nassau. They agreed to stop building castles against each other and the Nassaus promised not to infringe on in the rights the Lords of Dernbach and Wilnsdorf had possessed during their father's lifetime.</p>
<head>Feud between Mainz and Hesse</head>
<p>In 1324, Archbishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthias_of_Buchegg">Matthias</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishopric_of_Mainz">Mainz</ref> escalated his feud against Otto I of Hesse. This feud was originally about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lower_Hesse">Lower Hesse</ref>, which had been held by Otto's half-brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John,_Landgrave_of_Lower_Hesse">John, Landgrave of Lower Hesse</ref> as a fief from Mainz. When John of Lower Hesse died childless in 1311, Lower Hesse fell to Otto. The archbishops of Mainz disagreed, arguing that as John had no sons, Lower Hesse should fall back to Mainz as a completed fief.</p>
<p>Matthias formed an alliance with the nobility in central Hesse and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wetterau">Wetterau</ref> area, including the Nassau family. On 24 March 1327, John was appointed as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hauptmann">Hauptmann</ref> of the Mainz-Nassau army. Later that year, he defeated the Hessian army at Seibertshausen in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gladenbach_Uplands">Gladenbach Uplands</ref>. Landgrave Otto I died in January 1328, and his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_II,_Landgrave_of_Hesse">Henry II</ref> continued the feud. On 10 August 1328, Henry II defeated the Mainz-Nassau army in a battle at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wetzlar">Wetzlar</ref>. John fell during this battle. Matthias died four weeks later.</p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>As John was unmarried, his possessions fell to his surviving brothers. Initially, Henry and Emicho administered Nassau-Dillenburg jointly. Later, Emicho renounced his rights, and Henry gave Nassau-Dillenburg to his eldest son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto_II_of_Nassau">Otto II</ref>. In 1343, Otto II also inherited Nassau-Siegen. Thus, John was the only member of the short-lived older Nassau-Dillenburg line, and Otto II found the younger Nassau-Dillenburg line. The main line of this younger Nassau-Dillenburg line died out in 1739; the cadet line <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Orange-Nassau">Orange-Nassau</ref> still rules the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref>.</p>
<head>References</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Karl Menzel (1884), "<ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/s:ADB:Matthias%20(Erzbischof%20von%20Mainz)">Matthias (Erzbischof von Mainz)</ref>", <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allgemeine_Deutsche_Biographie">Allgemeine Deutsche Biographie</ref> (ADB)</hi> (in German), <hi rend="bold">20</hi>, Leipzig: Duncker &amp; Humblot, pp.657–663</item>
<item>Johannes von Arnoldi, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Oranien-Nassauischen Länder und ihrer Regenten,</hi> vol. 3, Neue Gelehrtenbuchhandlung, Hadamar, 1799, p.85-91, <ref target="https://books.google.com/books?pg=PA85&amp;lpg=PA85&amp;dq=Wildenselbach&amp;sig=UxKxhw1RTgSAzwWTTP-oBHTJaLY&amp;ei=qQssS9rWOs6dlAfguPCbBw&amp;ct=result&amp;id=Tl8AAAAAcAAJ&amp;ots=C_N3wDOV_G#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false">Online</ref></item>
<item>P. Wagner: <hi rend="italic">Die Erwerbung der Herborner Mark durch die Grafen von Nassau,</hi> in: <hi rend="italic">Annalen des Vereins für Nassauische Altertumskunde und Geschichtsforschung</hi>, vol. 32, 1901, Rud. Bechtold &amp; Co, Wiesbaden, 1902, p.26-44), <ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=kbw-AAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA26&amp;lpg=PA26&amp;dq=%22Herborner+Mark%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=O7FUyQjJ0T&amp;sig=BfRUW5g1wjRwwR44AXscsa-5c8E&amp;hl=de&amp;ei=kvvzSrnkFdXT8QbnoJDzCQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CAwQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Herborner%20Mark%22&amp;f=false">Online</ref></item>
<item>Jacob Wagner: <hi rend="italic">Die Regentenfamilie von Nassau-Hadamar: Geschichte des Fürstenthums Hadamar</hi>, vol. 1, 2nd ed., Mechitharisten-Congregations-Buchhandlung, Vienna, 1863, <ref target="https://books.google.com/books?pg=PA11&amp;lpg=PA11&amp;dq=&amp;id=Ao8AAAAAcAAJ&amp;ots=OuhtYTDtou#v=onepage&amp;q=false">Online</ref></item></list>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
