<text id="autogum_bio_doc519" title="Mummy Juanita" shortTile="mummy-juanita" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2004-09-23" dateModified="2019-10-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mummy_Juanita" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Mummy Juanita</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Momia Juanita</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_language">Spanish</ref> for "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mummy">Mummy</ref> Juanita"), also known as the <hi rend="bold">Lady of Ampato</hi>, is the well-preserved frozen body of an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inca_Empire">Inca</ref> girl<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> who was killed as an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_Sacrifice">offering</ref> to the Inca gods sometime between 1450 and 1480 when she was approximately 12–15 years old. She was discovered on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ampato">Mount Ampato</ref> (part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andes">Andes</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cordillera">cordillera</ref>) in southern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peru">Peru</ref> in 1995 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthropologist">anthropologist</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johan_Reinhard">Johan Reinhard</ref> and his Peruvian climbing partner, Miguel Zárate. "Juanita" has been on display in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholic_University_of_Santa_María">Catholic University of Santa María</ref>'s Museum of Andean Sanctuaries (Museo Santuarios Andinos) in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arequipa,_Peru">Arequipa, Peru</ref>, almost continuously since 1996, and was displayed on a tour of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref> in 1999.</p>
<p>In 1995, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time_(magazine)"><hi rend="italic">Time</hi> magazine</ref> chose her as one of the world's top ten discoveries. Between May and June 1996, she was exhibited in the headquarters of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Geographic_Society">National Geographic Society</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington,_D.C.">Washington, D.C.</ref>, in a specially acclimatized conservation display unit. In its June 1996 issue, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Geographic_(magazine)">National Geographic</ref></hi> included an article dedicated to the discovery of Juanita.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Discovery</head>
<p>In September 1995, during an ascent of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ampato">Mt. Ampato</ref> (20,700ft, 6309 m), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johan_Reinhard">Johan Reinhard</ref> and Zárate found in the crater a bundle that had fallen from an Inca site on the summit. To their astonishment, the bundle turned out to contain the frozen body of a young girl. They also found many items that had been left as offerings to the Inca gods. The items were strewn about the mountain slope, down which the body had fallen. These included statues and food items. The body and the items were transported to Arequipa, where the body was initially kept in a special refrigerator at the Catholic University.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Two more ice mummies, a young girl and a boy, were discovered in an archaeological expedition led by Dr. Reinhard and Prof. Jose Antonio Chavez in October 1995, and they recovered another female mummy on Ampato in December 1997. Owing to melting caused by volcanic ash from the nearby erupting volcano of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sabancaya">Sabancaya</ref>, most of the Inca burial site had collapsed down into a gully that led into the crater. Reinhard published a detailed account of the discovery in his 2006 book entitled, <hi rend="italic">The Ice Maiden: Inca Mummies, Mountain Gods, and Sacred Sites in the Andes</hi>.</p>
<head>Scientific analyses</head>
<head>Body</head>
<p>As Reinhard and Zárate struggled on Ampato's summit to lift the heavy bundle containing Juanita's body, they realized that her body mass had probably been increased by freezing of the flesh. When initially weighed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arequipa">Arequipa</ref>, the bundle containing "Juanita" weighed over 90 pounds (40.82 kilos). Their realization turned out to be correct; Juanita is almost entirely frozen, making her a substantial scientific find. Like only a few other high-altitude Inca mummies, Juanita was found frozen and thus her remains and garments were not <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Desiccation">desiccated</ref> like those of mummies found in other parts of the world. She was naturally mummified, instead of being artificially mummified, as is the case with Egyptian mummies. Her skin, organs, tissues, blood, hair, stomach contents, and garments are extremely well-preserved, offering scientists a rare glimpse into Inca culture during the reign of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sapa_Inca">Sapa Inca</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pachacuti">Pachacuti</ref> (reigned 1438–1471/1472).</p>
<p>Analysis of her stomach contents revealed that she ate a meal of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vegetable">vegetables</ref>, six to eight hours before her death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Clothing and adornments</head>
<p>Juanita was wrapped in a brightly coloured burial tapestry (or "aksu"). Her head was adorned with a cap made from the feathers of a red <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macaw">macaw</ref>, and she wore a lively woollen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alpaca">alpaca</ref> shawl fastened with a silver clasp. She was fully clothed in garments resembling the finest textiles from the Inca capital city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cusco">Cusco</ref>. This, in addition to evidence of excellent health, suggests that she may have come from a noble Cuzco family. These accoutrements were almost perfectly preserved, providing valuable insight into sacred Inca textiles and on how the Inca nobility dressed.</p>
<head>Tools and equipment</head>
<p>Found with her in the burial tapestry was a collection of grave goods: bowls, pins, and figurines made of gold, silver, and shell.</p>
<head>Genetic analysis</head>
<p>According to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Institute_for_Genomic_Research">Institute for Genomic Research</ref> (TIGR), the closest kin they could find in the database in 1996 were the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ngöbe–Buglé_people">Ngobe people</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panama">Panama</ref>, but the later research has shown her to share genetic patterns found in people from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andes">Andes</ref>. Scientists at TIGR examined two mitochondrial <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA">DNA</ref> D loop sequences and found that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypervariable_region">Hypervariable region</ref> 1 (HV1) was consistent with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haplogroup_A_(mtDNA)">mitochondrial haplogroup A2</ref>, one of the four Native American gene groups. Hypervariable region 2 (HV2) included a unique sequence not found in any of the current mitochondrial DNA databases.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haplotype">haplotype</ref> is 16111T, 16223T, 16290T, 16319A.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> In accordance with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genetic_map">genetic world map</ref> and genetic patterns, her HV2 DNA sequence was also related with the ancient races originally from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taiwan">Taiwan</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korea">Korea</ref>, which supports the theory that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paleo-Indians">Paleo-Indians</ref> had <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pacific">Pacific</ref> links.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Cause of death</head>
<p>Radiologist Elliot Fishman concluded that she was killed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blunt_trauma">blunt trauma</ref> to the head. He observed that her cracked right eye socket and the two-inch fracture in her skull are injuries "typical of someone who has been hit by a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baseball_bat">baseball bat</ref>." The blow caused a massive <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hemorrhage">hemorrhage</ref>, filling her skull with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blood">blood</ref> and pushing her brain to one side.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
</text>
