<text id="autogum_bio_doc056" title="Gul Rahman" shortTile="gul-rahman" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-04-20" dateModified="2019-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gul_Rahman" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gul Rahman</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Gul Rahman</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pashto_language">Pashto</ref>: ګل رحمان‎; died 20 November 2002) was an Afghan man, suspected by the United States of being a militant, who was a victim of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torture">torture</ref>. He died in a secret <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CIA">CIA</ref> prison, or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_site">black site</ref>, located in northern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kabul">Kabul</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref> and known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salt_Pit">Salt Pit</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NationalJournal2014-12-10-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Yahoo-2010-04-06-2">[2]</ref> He had been captured October 29, 2002.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NewYorker-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CbsNews-2010-04-06-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>His name was kept secret by the United States for more than seven years although his death was announced. In 2010 the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Associated_Press">Associated Press</ref> reported that before his death he was left half-stripped and chained against a concrete wall on a night when the temperature was close to freezing.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NewYorker-3">[3]</ref> The United States government did not notify his family (wife and four daughters) of his death, according to the report.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NewYorker-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Capture and death</head>
<p>Gul Rahman was captured and arrested on 29 October 2002 during a joint operation by U.S. agents and Pakistani security forces against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hezb-e-Islami_Gulbuddin">Hezb-e-Islami Gulbuddin</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MSNBC-5">[5]</ref> He was reportedly arrested with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physician">physician</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghairat_Baheer">Ghairat Baheer</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Son-in-law">son-in-law</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warlord">warlord</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gulbuddin_Hekmatyar">Gulbuddin Hekmatyar</ref>, who led the insurgent faction <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hezb-e-Islami">Hezb-e-Islami</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MSNBC-5">[5]</ref> Rahman had traveled from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peshawar">Peshawar</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamabad">Islamabad</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pakistan">Pakistan</ref> for a medical checkup when he was arrested at the home of Ghairat Baheer, and subsequently flown by the CIA to Afghanistan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MSNBC-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>U.S. officials claim Rahman was "violently uncooperative" while in custody at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salt_Pit">Salt Pit</ref>, the CIA code name for an abandoned brick factory that had been turned into a CIA <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_site">black site</ref> or covert interrogation center,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MSNBC-5">[5]</ref> including threatening to kill his guards – who responded by beating him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MSNBC-5">[5]</ref> Rahman was also subjected to "48 hours of sleep deprivation, auditory overload, total darkness, isolation, a cold shower and rough treatment". Gul Rahman reportedly died on 20 November 2002 after being stripped naked from the waist down and shackled to a cold cement wall in the Salt Pit, where temperatures were approximately 36°F (2°C).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CbsNews-2010-04-06-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>This technique of shackling is known as "short-chaining." The detainee is  shackled "in a short chain position, which prevents prisoners from standing upright." A CIA pathologist reported that  Rahman likely froze to death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>His death prompted an internal CIA review and the development of improved guidance.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MSNBC-5">[5]</ref> No one was ever charged in his death.</p>
<head>Rescue of Hamid Karzai</head>
<figure><caption>Redacted version of the CIA investigation of Rahman's death, released June 2016 (.pdf file)</caption></figure>
<p>According to Gul's brother, Habib Rahman, Gul Rahman was involved in a 1994 rescue of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamid_Karzai">Hamid Karzai</ref>, the president of Afghanistan since 2004. Karzai had been imprisoned by the government forces, and Rahman was working for Hekmatyar, whose forces fired rockets at the building while Rahman entered and freed Karzai. Rahman took him to a safe house in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kabul">Kabul</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Yahoo-2010-04-06-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Senate Intelligence Committee's report of CIA torture</head>
<p>On December 9, 2014 the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Senate_Intelligence_Committee_report_on_CIA_torture">Senate Intelligence Committee's report on CIA torture</ref> was published.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NationalJournal2014-12-10-1">[1]</ref> According to that report he had been subjected to total darkness, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sensory_overload">sensory overload</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sleep_deprivation">sleep deprivation</ref>, cold shower, rough treatment, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Short_shackling">short shackling</ref> and finally froze to death.  The report said he was the only captive known to have died in CIA custody.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NationalJournal2014-12-10-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steven_W._Hawkins">Steven W. Hawkins</ref>, the executive director of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amnesty_International_USA">Amnesty International USA</ref>, writing in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Guardian">The Guardian</ref></hi>, reported that he found that the CIA official responsible for Rahman's death, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jose_Rodriguez_(intelligence_officer)">Jose Rodriguez</ref> was not only not punished, or sanctioned, rather, he received a cash bonus for his "consistently superior work".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-TheGuardian2014-12-09-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>On October 13, 2015 the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Civil_Liberties_Union">American Civil Liberties Union</ref> filed a lawsuit <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> on behalf of Rahman's estate and two other former detainees against two psychologists, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Elmer_Mitchell">James Mitchell</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bruce_Jessen">Bruce Jessen</ref>, who they maintain were responsible for designing the protocols that resulted in Rahman's death and the torture of the other two plaintifs.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-seattle-9">[9]</ref> The ACLU case is the first lawsuit brought against significant individuals identified in the Senate report since it was published.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-intercept-10">[10]</ref> On July 28, 2017, U.S. District Judge <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justin_Lowe_Quackenbush">Justin Lowe Quackenbush</ref> denied both parties motions for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summary_judgment">summary judgment</ref>, noted that the defendants are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indemnity">indemnified</ref> by the United States government, and encouraged the attorneys to reach a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Settlement_(litigation)">settlement</ref> before trial.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
</text>
