<text id="autogum_bio_doc339" title="Johann Georg Bendl" shortTile="johann-georg-bendl" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-07-19" dateModified="2019-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Georg_Bendl" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Johann Georg Bendl</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Johann-Georg Bendl</hi> (Czech pronunciation:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Czech">[ˈjohaŋ ˈɡɛorɡ ˈbɛndl̩]</ref>) or <hi rend="bold">Jan Jiří Bendl</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Czech">[ˈjan ˈjɪr̝iː ˈbɛndl̩]</ref>) (before <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1620_in_architecture">1620</ref> - <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prague">Prague</ref>, 27 May <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1680_in_architecture">1680</ref>) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baroque">Baroque</ref> sculptor, who worked mainly in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prague">Prague</ref>. </p>
<p>He was the son of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bohemian">Bohemian</ref> sculptor Georg Bendl (born ca. 1570, Prague, died <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1656_in_architecture">1656</ref>).</p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>The wooden <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pulpit">pulpit</ref> (since destroyed) of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Wenceslas_Church_(Zderaz)">St. Wenceslas Church</ref> (of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augustinians">Augustinian Order</ref>) in Prague, was probably one of his earliest works. He also sculpted the pulpit in the church Kostel Panny Marie pod Řetězem in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prague">Prague</ref> district <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malá_Strana">Malá Strana</ref>. All the most important churches in Prague eventually would order one or more statues.</p>
<p>In 1648 he sculpted the statues for side chapels in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_Our_Lady_in_front_of_Týn">Church of Our Lady of Týn</ref>, the church on the main square of Prague. He decorated the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dome">dome</ref> of the St. Salvator church of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesuit_Order">Jesuit Order</ref> in Prague with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stucco">stucco</ref> in the period 1648-1649. This would later bring in new orders from these Jesuits in 1655-1660 to sculpt the stone statues for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portico">portico</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pediment">pediment</ref> of the façade; at the end of his life, in 1675, he would carve a series of wooden statues of Apostles for confessionals for the same church.</p>
<p>He was commissioned in 1650 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinand_III,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Ferdinand III, Holy Roman Emperor</ref> to produce in Prague a sculpture of the <hi rend="italic">Immaculate Conception</hi> to commemorate the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peace_of_Westphalia">Peace of Westphalia</ref> ending the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thirty_Years'_War">Thirty Years' War</ref> in 1648. Around 1650 he also sculpted a number of wooden angels for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Servite_Order">Servite Order</ref>, now on display in St. George's Convent, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Gallery_in_Prague">National Gallery in Prague</ref>. That same year he was asked to make the statues for the main altar of the Church of the Holy Cross (now on the high altar of the St. Jindrich's (St. Henry's) church) and he carved a statue of a saint for the same church at some time in the 1650s, now at the City Museum of Prague)</p>
<p>His monumental <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marian_and_Holy_Trinity_columns">Marian column</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1650_in_architecture">1650</ref>) on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Town_Square_(Prague)">Old Town Square</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prague">Prague</ref> (destroyed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1918_in_architecture">1918</ref>) would set an example of Baroque style for the next decades. Remaining part can be seen at the Lapidarium of the National Museum of Prague. He sculpted six statues of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctors_of_the_Church">Doctors of the Church</ref> in 1659.</p>
<p>The high-quality bronzed statues of St. Jerome and Mary Magdalen in the Chapel of St. Vincent Ferrer  (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominikanerkirche_(Vienna)">Dominican church</ref>, Vienna) were produced by his workshop. He decorated the façade of the St. Salvator Church in Prague with several statues: (on top) Christ with the four Evangelists, (below) Mary, the Doctors of the Church and Jesuit saints.</p>
<p>In 1662 he sculpted the statue of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslaus_I,_Duke_of_Bohemia">Saint Wenceslaus</ref> in the old deanery of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Vitus_Cathedral">St. Vitus Cathedral</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prague_Castle">Prague Castle</ref>. He added to the façade of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._George's_Basilica,_Prague">St. George Basilica</ref> the statues of the founders of the church: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vratislaus_I_of_Bohemia">Vratislaus I of Bohemia</ref> and Mlada, founder of the convent.</p>
<p>In 1670 he sculpted the <hi rend="italic">Hercules and Cerberus </hi> fountain for the imperial garden in the Belvedere of the same castle, setting again a stylistic example for Bohemian sculpture. He sculpted a statue of a saint for the high altar of St. Stephen's Church in 1678. His last known works are two statues of the national patron saint <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslaus_I,_Duke_of_Bohemia">Saint Wenceslaus</ref> (between 1676 and 1678), one on a column near the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Bridge">Charles Bridge</ref>  and an equestrian statue on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslas_Square">Wenceslas Square</ref> (transferred to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vyšehrad">Vyšehrad</ref> in 1879) .</p>
<p>He is considered the first important Bohemian Baroque sculptor. His sculptural style was imitated by many successors. Some of his statues can be seen at the National Gallery in the St. George Convent in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prague_Castle">Prague Castle</ref>.</p>
</text>
