<text id="autogum_bio_doc093" title="Imran Ali (Indian cricketer)" shortTile="imran-ali-indian" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-06-25" dateModified="2017-11-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imran_Ali_%28Indian_cricketer%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Imran Ali (Indian cricketer)</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Imran Ali</hi> (date of birth unknown) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/India">Indian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cricket">cricketer</ref> who played regularly for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vidarbha_cricket_team">Vidarbha</ref> during the 1960s and 1970s. A talented junior player, he toured Ceylon with an India Schools representative side in April 1964, and made his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First-class_cricket">first-class</ref> debut for Vidarbha during the 1964–65 season. Playing as a middle-order batsman, Imran established himself as a regular player in Vidarbha's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ranji_Trophy">Ranji Trophy</ref> team throughout the next decade, and during the 1968–69 season even played two matches for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_Zone_cricket_team">Central Zone</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duleep_Trophy">Duleep Trophy</ref>, although without much success. He retired at the end of the 1976–77 season after thirteen seasons for Vidarbha, having captained the side in his final two seasons.</p>
<head>Cricket career</head>
<p>Little is known of Imran's early life, including his date and place of birth.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-profile-1">[1]</ref> His first matches at higher levels came for a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vidarbha">Vidarbha</ref> team in the 1962–63 and 1963–64 editions of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cooch_Behar_Trophy">Cooch Behar Trophy</ref>, a school-based tournament.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> His good form for Vidarbha led to his selection first for a Central Zone Schools side, and then for an India Schools side that toured Ceylon (now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sri_Lanka">Sri Lanka</ref>) in April 1964, and included future <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test_cricket">Test cricketers</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surinder_Amarnath">Surinder Amarnath</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramnath_Parkar">Ramnath Parkar</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ashok_Gandotra">Ashok Gandotra</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eknath_Solkar">Eknath Solkar</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Imran scored a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Century_(cricket)">century</ref> in the team's match against a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaffna">Jaffna</ref> Schools side, an innings of 102 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Not_out">not out</ref> batting alongside <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramesh_Nagdev">Ramesh Nagdev</ref>, who scored 85 runs.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Following on from this good form at junior levels, Imran made his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First-class_cricket">first-class</ref> for Vidarbha's senior side during the 1964–65 season of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ranji_Trophy">Ranji Trophy</ref>, and went on to play in each of the team's three matches during the tournament,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-fc-5">[5]</ref> scoring his first half-century, an innings of 83 runs, in the final match against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madhya_Pradesh_cricket_team">Madhya Pradesh</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> He soon established himself as a regular player in Vidarbha's side, usually as a middle-order <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Batsman">batsman</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-seasons-7">[7]</ref> An innings of 94 runs scored against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rajasthan_cricket_team">Rajasthan</ref> during the 1968–69 season led to Imran's selection to play for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_Zone_cricket_team">Central Zone</ref> in that season's edition of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duleep_Trophy">Duleep Trophy</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> However, he played only two matches for Central Zone (the second against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australian_cricket_team_in_Ceylon_and_India_in_1969–70">touring Australians</ref>), and was not selected in the side in later seasons.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-fc-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Imran remained a consistent, although not outstanding, player for Vidarbha throughout the 1970s. Arguably his most successful seasons came towards the middle of the decade: he scored over 200 runs during both the 1974–75 and 1975–76 seasons, averaging 37.91 runs over both seasons combined.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-seasons-7">[7]</ref> Imran's only first-class <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Century_(cricket)">century</ref> was an innings of 104 not out scored against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Railways_cricket_team">Railways</ref> in November 1975. This included a 96-run <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partnership_(cricket)">partnership</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sirish_Najbile">Sirish Najbile</ref> (60 runs) for the fifth wicket.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> The 1976–77 season was Imran's last at first-class level.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-fc-5">[5]</ref> For his final two seasons, he replaced <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murthy_Rajan">Murthy Rajan</ref> as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Captain_(cricket)">captain</ref> of Vidarbha, captaining the side in eight matches for five draws and three losses.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> He finished his career having scored 1,799 runs from 45 first-class matches, at an average of 23.98.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-profile-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
