<text id="autogum_bio_doc266" title="Keshavashram" shortTile="keshavashram" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-06-21" dateModified="2019-09-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keshavashram" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Keshavashram</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Swami Keshavashram</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Devanagari">Devanagari</ref>: केशवाश्रम्, <hi rend="italic"><hi lang="sa-Latn" rend="italic">Ke.sha.vā.shram</hi></hi>) was the fifth <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guru">guru</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chitrapur_Saraswat_Brahmin">Chitrapur Saraswat Brahmin</ref> community,that is, the Fifth <hi rend="italic">Mathādhipati</hi>(Head of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chitrapur_Math">Chitrāpur Matha</ref></hi>) of the community. His reign was from 1785 to 1823, a period of 38 years (42 years including his period as disciple of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shankarashram_II">Swami Shankarāshram II</ref>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-chitrapurmath.net-1">[1]</ref> He became the head of the community after his teacher(<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guru">guru</ref>) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shankarashram_II">Swami Shankarāshram</ref> died in 1785.</p>
<p>Under his administration, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chitrapur_Math">Chitrapur Math</ref> acquired land and property.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-chitrapurmath.net-1">[1]</ref> He was able to consolidate the Sāraswat Community both in numbers(increased the number of followers) and in faith (weaned away many from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dvaita">Dvaita</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaishnava">Vaishnava</ref> practises).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-chitrapurmath.net-1">[1]</ref> He died in 1823 at Shirali. His <hi rend="italic">samādhi</hi>(shrine) is located at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shirali">Shirali</ref>.</p>
<p>(<hi rend="italic">Note: In this article <hi rend="bold">Swamiji</hi> will refer only to Swami Keshavāshram</hi>)</p>
<head>Taking charge</head>
<p>Swami Keshavāshram became the Fifth head of the community after his teacher (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guru">guru</ref>) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shankarashram_II">Swami Shankarāshram II</ref> attained <hi rend="italic">Mahā-samādhi</hi> in 1785 in the month of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maagha">Maagha</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> The official taking over took place on the tenth day of the month. Swamiji had the advantage of being under his guru for 4 years and could hence could easily take charge of the administration of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chitrapur_Math">Chitrāpur Matha</ref></hi> and the community in general.</p>
<p>Swamiji was a very able administrator and he could acquire land and fixed property for the Chitrāpur Matha. This resulted in the expansion of the <hi rend="italic">matha</hi>. He would personally supervise the administration and finance of the <hi rend="italic">matha</hi> whenever he had the spare time. He was well versed with the scriptures but at the same time had a keen mathematical prowess. In the 42 years in charge with the <hi rend="italic">matha</hi> administration(38 years as the <hi rend="italic">Mathādhipati</hi> and 4 as disciple to his guru), he could consolidate the  community as a whole.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-chitrapurmath.net-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>He was considered as a good orator. The knowledge and the speaking skills were very convincing and devotees flocked to hear his discourses.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Divgi_2002_68-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"Poojya Swamiji,truly a JnāniWith Spiritual Knowledge did glow,Discourses filled with wisdom,So smoothly would flow!</hi>
Devotees flocked to listen to the words of wisdom,Our beloved Sadguru they came to meet,In abundance they received from Gurudev,With reverence they prostrated at His Lotus Feet."<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Divgi_2002_68-3">[3]</ref></hi></p>
<p>Swamiji could convince many devotees from getting rid of their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dvaita">Dvaita</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaishnava">Vaishnava</ref> practices.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-chitrapurmath.net-1">[1]</ref> Thus many devotees were united under the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chitrapur_Guru_Parampara">Guru Parampara</ref></hi> and bore allegiance to the Chitrāpur Matha. The devotees never failed to pay a portion of their income to Swamiji and thus the financial stability, that the <hi rend="italic">matha</hi> had lacked for so long, was achieved.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Divgi_2002_85-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Importance to education</head>
<p>During Swamiji's reign, the British got hold of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanara">Canara</ref> Districts(Upper and Lower) (<hi rend="italic">See: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madras_Presidency#Territorial_growth">British control</ref></hi>) where the community was primarily located. Knowing that changing times demanded changes in society, Swamiji encouraged English education.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Thus the Sāraswats could occupy prestigious administrative posts during the British Raj.</p>
<head>Miracles</head>
<p>Swami Keshavāshram is attributed to many miracles. Devotees in distress and in need had their problems redressed due to his divine powers. Two of them are listed below.</p>
<head>The Mute boy from Murdeshwar</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>There lived a pious devotee in the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murudeshwara">Murdershwar</ref> who had a son who was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muteness">mute</ref>. This devotee and his wife tried all sorts of therapy and medication to get the boy to speak, but all that failed. When all hopes seemed to dim, his wife and neighbours asked him to take his son to seek Swamiji's blessings. But this devotee was so pious and considerate that he refused stating that he did not want his burdens to be transferred to Swamiji in any way.</p>
<p>One day both he and his wife had a dream where Swamiji had blessed their son and he was normal again. Since both of them had the same dream, they thought the message was too strong to ignore. So with hopes filled in their hearts, they went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shirali">Shirali</ref> to meet Swamiji. The entire family prayed in utmost humility to Swamiji. The boy was weeping bitterly but silently beside Swamiji. When Swamiji placed his hand on the boy's head, the boy miraculously got back his power of speech. The family was then blessed by Swamiji and they returned to Murdeshwar.</p>
<head>The Cripple from Mangalore</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>In the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mangalore">Mangalore</ref> lived a pious devotee of Swamiji who was physically challenged (feet had a disability). He lived on the charity of people but was truly devout. He had an ardent desire to seek blessings of Swamiji. Despite not having any money or food with him, he started his journey to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chitrapur_Math">Chitrapur Math</ref> on barefoot. Even though his clothes were tattered and poor, his heart was rich with devotion.</p>
<p>En route his feet got swollen and his knees became very tired. With all his energy sapped and the destination still far away, the poor man rested under a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banyan">Banyan</ref> tree very dejected and doubtful of completing his journey. At night he had a dream where Swamiji came to him under the Banyan tree and was massaging his tired feet with oil. At dawn when he woke up, all the pain and agony had disappeared and he could walk normally. With his health and spirits re-energized, the devotee made his way to Swamiji at Shirali and fell at his feet with true devotion. The Swamiji blessed him and the devotee returned with content and happiness.</p>
<head>Shishya Sweekār</head>
<p>When Swamiji's health started becoming frail and weak, the devotees requested Swamiji to accept a <hi rend="italic">shishya</hi>(Disciple). Swamiji graciously accepted the offer. So the search was on to find a suitable successor.</p>
<p>The suitable successor was found in a youngster from the Shukla Bhat family from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shirali">Shirali</ref>. On the <hi rend="italic">Shuddha Panchami</hi> (5th day) of the <hi rend="italic">Ashādhā</hi> month in 1804, the new <hi rend="italic">shishya</hi> was ordained as <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vamanashram">Vāmanāshram</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Divgi_2002_85-4">[4]</ref> He would be under the tutelage of <hi rend="italic">Swami Keshavāshram</hi> for another 19 years. This long period of being under a guru helped <hi rend="italic">Vāmanāshram</hi> attain high proficiency in the Sanskrit scriptures.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>After being the head of the community for 38 long years, Swami <hi rend="italic">Keshavāshram</hi> died on the <hi rend="italic">Shīrsha Navami</hi>(9th day) of the <hi rend="italic">Mārgha</hi> month in 1823. He died with his <hi rend="italic">shishya</hi> by his side.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Divgi_2002_85-4">[4]</ref> His <hi rend="italic">samādhi</hi>(shrine) is located at Shirali.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-chitrapurmath.net-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
