<text id="autogum_bio_doc357" title="Farhad Khan Qaramanlu" shortTile="farhad-khan-qaramanlu" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-01-02" dateModified="2019-06-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Farhad_Khan_Qaramanlu" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Farhad Khan Qaramanlu</head><p><hi rend="bold">Farhad Khan Qaramanlu</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_language">Persian</ref>: فرهاد خان قره‌مانلو‎; died 1598), also known by his honorific title of <hi rend="bold">Rokn al-Saltana</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arabic_language">Arabic</ref>: رکن‌السلطنه‎, "Pillar of the state"), was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkmen_people">Turkoman</ref> military officer from the Qaramanlu family, and was the last member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qizilbash">Qizilbash</ref> to serve as commander-in-chief (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sipah-salar">sipah-salar</ref></hi>) of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safavid_Empire">Safavid Empire</ref>.</p>
<head>Family and origins</head>
<p>The son of Husam Beg, Farhad Khan was descended from Bayram Beg Qaramanlu, a prominent nobleman, who served under the founder of the Safavid dynasty, king (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shah">shah</ref>) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ismail_I">Ismail I</ref> (r. 1501–1524).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMatthee1999-1">[1]</ref> Farhad Khan had a brother named <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zu'l_Fiqar_Qaramanlu">Zu'l Fiqar Qaramanlu</ref>, who would later accompany him in many of his expeditions.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<head>Flight and rise</head>
<p>Farhad Khan was originally a servant of the Safavid prince <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamza_Mirza">Hamza Mirza</ref>, who was the son of shah <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohammad_Khodabanda">Mohammad Khodabanda</ref> and one of the many pretenders to the Safavid throne during the civil war in Iran which had started with the death of shah <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tahmasp_I">Tahmasp I</ref> in 1576. However, Hamza Mirza was eventually murdered in 1586, while Farhad Khan fled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> territory due the jealousy of many nobles, whom Farhad Khan feared that they would kill him. When Mohammad Khodabanda's son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbas_I_of_Persia">Abbas I</ref> ascended the throne in 1588, Farhad Khan returned to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMatthee1999-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Farhad Khan then a loyal servant of Abbas I and quickly rose to high offices. In 1589/90, Farhad Khan was given the task of having the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Safavid_Grand_Viziers">grand vizier</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mirza_Mohammad_Munshi">Mirza Mohammad Munshi</ref> arrested and executed, which he successfully did. He then received the honorific title of "Rokn al-Saltana", and speedily became one of the kings favorites.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMatthee1999-1">[1]</ref> Farhad Khan played an essential role in Abbas I's "reconquest" of Iranian territory. In 1589/90, Yuli Beg, who was the governor of the Safavid capital of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isfahan">Isfahan</ref> and had rebelled, surrendered to Farhad Khan. One year later, Farhad Khan, along with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hatem_Beg_Ordubadi">Hatem Beg Ordubadi</ref>, campaigned in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kerman_Province">Kerman</ref> against the uncontrollable <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afshar_people">Afshar</ref> leader, Yusuf Khan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMatthee1999-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Invasion of Gilan, southern Iran, and Mazandaran</head>
<figure><caption>Map of northern Iran.</caption></figure>
<p>In 1592/3 Farhad Khan and his brother led a punitive expedition to Bia Pish (eastern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilan">Gilan</ref>) against its rebellious vassal, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kia'i_dynasty">Kia'i</ref> ruler <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khan_Ahmad_Khan">Khan Ahmad Khan</ref>. After a successful expedition, Farhad Khan was appointed as the governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Azerbaijan_(Iran)">Azerbaijan</ref> in 1593 and the warden of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheikh_Safi_al-Din_Khānegāh_and_Shrine_Ensemble">shrine</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ardabil">Ardabil</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMatthee1999-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENasiri2008155-2">[2]</ref> However, a rebellion shortly occurred in Bia Pish once again, which forced Farhad Khan to invade the province for the second time. By 1593, the rebellion had been suppressed, and Farhad Khan was appointed as the governor of Bia Pish.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMatthee1999-1">[1]</ref> Still not satisfied with the amount of his control over the Gilan region, Abbas ordered Farhad Khan to invade Bia Pas (western Gilan). After having executed all the local rulers of the region, Farhad Khan went back to Bia Pish, while a certain <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ali_Khan_(rebel)">Ali Khan</ref> was appointed as the governor of Bia Pas. Around this period, Farhad Khan was appointed as the commander-in-chief of the empire.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBlow2009219-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In 1594, Ali Khan revolted, which forced Farhad Khan to invade Gilan for the third time. After the revolt was suppressed, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rumlu">Rumlu</ref> chieftain <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darvish_Mohammad_Khan">Darvish Mohammad Khan</ref> was appointed as the governor of all of Gilan, while Farhad Khan was appointed as the governor of the rich province of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fars_Province">Fars</ref>. Some time later, Farhad Khan and the Safavid <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Safavid_Grand_Viziers">grand vizier</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hatem_Beg_Ordubadi">Hatem Beg Ordubadi</ref> campaigned in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khuzestan">Khuzestan</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kohgiluyeh_and_Boyer-Ahmad_Province">Kohgiluyeh</ref>. In 1595/6, Farhad Khan incorporated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damghan">Damghan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semnan_Province">Semnan</ref>, and several districts of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khorasan_Province">Khorasan</ref> to his domains. In the same year, he was replaced by prominent military officer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allahverdi_Khan">Allahverdi Khan</ref> as the governor of Fars, but was instead given the governorship of Bia Pas.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMatthee1999-1">[1]</ref> According to the chief court astrologer, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jalal_Monajjem">Jalal Monajjem</ref>, at around the same time Abbas requested a daughter from the Georgian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amilakhori">Amilakhori</ref> family, one of the most influential noble families in the subordinate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Kartli">Kingdom of Kartli</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFloorHerzig2012474-4">[4]</ref> Farhad Khan, with the assistance of Prince <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bagrat_VII_of_Kartli">Bagrat Khan</ref>, arranged the match.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFloorHerzig2012474-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>In 1596, Farhad Khan was appointed as the governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mazandaran">Mazandaran</ref>. However, the province was still ruled by various vassal rulers, whom Farhad Khan took action against; before the upcoming year, Farhad Khan had seized <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hezarjarib_District">Hezarjarib</ref> and after a two-month siege, captured the capital of the province, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amol">Amol</ref>, killing its local ruler Sayyid Muzaffar. After having successfully subjugated Mazandaran, Farhad Khan left the province under the control of one of his other brothers, Alvand Sultan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMatthee1999-1">[1]</ref> However, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paduspanids">Paduspanid</ref> ruler <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bahman_of_Larijan">Bahman of Larijan</ref> shortly rebelled against the latter, but was defeated by Farhad Khan, who seized <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larijan_District">Larijan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nur,_Iran">Nur</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kojur">Kojur</ref>. Farhad Khan then advanced to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savadkuh_County">Savadkuh</ref>, which he had by 1597 captured, thus subduing all of Mazandaran.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMatthee1999-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Last expedition and death</head>
<p>In 1598, Farhad Khan was given the governorship of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astarabad">Astarabad</ref> (Gorgan). During the same year, he seized <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mashhad">Mashhad</ref> from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uzbeks">Uzbeks</ref> and then along with Abbas and Allahverdi Khan, fought against a Uzbek army near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herat">Herat</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBlow200950-5">[5]</ref> According to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_people">English</ref> traveler <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Shirley">Robert Shirley</ref>, during the battle, Farhad Khan betrayed the Safavid army by informing the Uzbeks about how they should attack. However, according to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don_Juan_of_Persia">Don Juan</ref>, Jalal al-Din Monajjem, and Jonabadi, Farhad Khan had fled during the battle, which resulted that Abbas had him executed due to his cowardice.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMatthee1999-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iskandar_Beg_Munshi">Iskandar Beg Munshi</ref>, Farhad Khan fled from the battle after being wounded, but was later accused of fleeing due to his cowardice. He was nevertheless forgiven by Abbas, who wanted to appoint him as the governor of Herat, which Farhad Khan refused. According to Oruch Beg, the refusal of Farhad Khan made Abbas feel that he had been insulted. Iskandar Beg further adds that due the arrogant behavior of Farhad Khan and his suspected treason, which had made him become a threat to Abbas, who already did not have much trust to the Qizilbash—made Abbas have him executed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMatthee1999-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>After Farhad Khan's death, Gilan and Mazandaran were converted into the crown domain (<hi rend="italic">khasseh</hi>), while Allahverdi Khan became the new commander-in-chief of the army.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMatthee1999-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
