<text id="autogum_bio_doc092" title="Leslie Gabriel" shortTile="leslie-gabriel" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-04-17" dateModified="2019-11-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leslie_Gabriel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Leslie Gabriel</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Leslie Gabriel</hi> (born 20th century) is an American <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Volleyball">volleyball</ref> coach.</p>
<p>Since 2001, she has served as associate head coach and recruiting coordinator for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Washington">University of Washington</ref> women's volleyball team. In addition to assisting head coach <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim_McLaughlin_(coach)">Jim McLaughlin</ref> with all administrative responsibilities, Gabriel works with the team's setters and defense.</p>
<p>Gabriel is a former UW starter and four-year letterwinner who started for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington_Huskies">Washington Huskies</ref> from 1995 to 1998.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>She helped Woodinville High School to back-to-back Class 4A state volleyball tournament appearances as a sophomore and junior and one trip to the state basketball tournament before dropping the sport as a sophomore. The three-time All-KingCo volleyball pick was the state's top volleyball recruit by her senior year.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Collegiate career</head>
<p>Gabriel, along with All-American Makare Desilets, formed one of the nation's best blocking tandems, leading the Huskies to the top of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NCAA">NCAA</ref> blocking rankings in 1997. A <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pac-10">Pac-10</ref> first-team selection as a junior, Gabriel ranks in the UW career top-10 in five categories, including total blocks (second - 613) and block assists (second - 520).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-profile-2">[2]</ref> She also ranked in the top-25 nationally in blocks per game in each of her four seasons at Washington.</p>
<p>After completing her eligibility in 1998, Gabriel trained with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_women's_national_volleyball_team">United States women's national volleyball team</ref> program and was selected to participate at the 1999 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universiade">Universiade</ref> (also known as the World University Games) in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>.</p>
<p>She returned to Washington to complete her degree and graduated in 2000 with a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bachelor_of_Psychology">Bachelor of Psychology</ref> degree and a minor in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Speech_communications">speech communications</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-profile-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>From August 2000 until May 2001, Gabriel played professional volleyball in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murcia">Murcia</ref>, Spain.</p>
<head>Coaching career</head>
<head>Since 2001: Washington</head>
<p>Gabriel has served as the associate head coach alongside McLaughlin since 2001 and has played a key role in developing Washington's setters, which have ranked among the nation's elite during Gabriel and McLaughlin's tenure.</p>
<p>In 2006, Gabriel helped guide senior setter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Courtney_Thompson">Courtney Thompson</ref> to one of the best individual seasons in Husky history. Thompson was named First Team All-America by both the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Volleyball_Coaches_Association">American Volleyball Coaches Association</ref> (AVCA) and <hi rend="italic">Volleyball Magazine</hi>. In addition, she was named the CVU.com (Collegiate Volleyball Update) National Setter of the Year, and was a finalist for the Honda Award after winning the award in 2005. In 2008, Jenna Hagglund led the Pac-10 and ranked second in the nation in assists per set with 12.17, and finished her career as a two-time AVCA All-American, and was 10th in Pac-10 history in career assists.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-profile-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Gabriel also aided in the development of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tamari_Miyashiro">Tamari Miyashiro</ref> (2006–09) into the top libero in the nation. Miyashiro was twice named the Volleyball Magazine National Defender of the Year in 2007 and 2008, and was a three-time AVCA All-American from 2007-09. She set the school digs record with 2,382 which ranks her ninth in NCAA history.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-profile-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Prior to the 2006 season, Gabriel worked with the team's middle blockers.</p>
<head>Personal</head>
<p>She was born <hi rend="bold">Gabriel Tuiasosopo</hi>, a daughter of former NFL defensive lineman, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manu_Tuiasosopo">Manu Tuiasosopo</ref>, who played collegiately for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_California,_Los_Angeles">University of California, Los Angeles</ref>, then professionally from 1979 to 1986 for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seattle_Seahawks">Seattle Seahawks</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Francisco_49ers">San Francisco 49ers</ref>, being a starter at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nose_tackle">nose tackle</ref> and winning <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super_Bowl_XIX">Super Bowl XIX</ref>. She is the oldest of five children, including former UW football player <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marques_Tuiasosopo">Marques Tuiasosopo</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>She married Anthony Gabriel, an academic advisor at the University of Washington, in the summer of 2010, and has two children, Daylon and Myles.</p>
</text>
