<text id="autogum_bio_doc789" title="Günther I of Schwalenberg" shortTile="gunther-schwalenberg" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-10-18" dateModified="2018-04-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%BCnther_I_of_Schwalenberg" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Günther I of Schwalenberg</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Günther I of Schwalenberg</hi> was a German nobleman.  He was elected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop">Archbishop</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishopric_of_Magdeburg">Magdeburg</ref> in 1277, but had to step down in 1278. He was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop">Bishop</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Paderborn">Bishopric of Paderborn</ref> from 1307 to 15 May 1310.</p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>Günther relatives were the Counts of Schwalenberg.  They were <hi lang="de" rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vogt">Vogts</ref></hi> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Paderborn">Bishopric of Paderborn</ref> and founders of the abbey in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marienmünster">Marienmünster</ref>.  They had a lot of influence on the clerical positions  in Westphalia.  Günther was a son of Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Volkwin_IV,_Count_of_Schwalenberg">Volkwin IV</ref> and his wife Ermengard of Schwarzburg. His parents had eleven children. His brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Volkwin_V_of_Schwalenberg">Volkwin V</ref> was Bishop of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Minden">Minden</ref>.  His cousin <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Widukind_of_Waldeck">Widukind of Waldeck</ref> was Bishop of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Osnabrück">Osnabrück</ref> from 1265 to 1269, and his nephew <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conrad_II_of_Sternberg">Conrad II of Sternberg</ref> was Archbishop of Magdeburg from 1266 to 1277.  Three of Günter's sisters were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbess">abbesses</ref>: Kunigunde in Falkenhagen Abbey in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lügde">Lügde</ref>, Ermengard in Neuenheerse, and Mathilda in Möllenbeck Abbey, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rinteln">Rinteln</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>In 1268, Günther became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provost_(religion)">provost</ref> in the Dionysius monastery in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enger">Enger</ref>, and also <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_(priest)">canon</ref> in Magdeburg where his nephew Conrad was archbishop.  In 1272, he became thesaurer in Minden and cathedral custodian in Magdeburg.  He was also dean in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goslar">Goslar</ref>.  In 1273, he became vice-dominus in Magdeburg, later provost.</p>
<p>Conrad died in 1277 and Günther succeeded him, after a disputed election, in which he defeated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernard_III_of_Wölpe">Bernard III of Wölpe</ref>, the cathedral cellarer.  An important condition for his election was that the finances of the cathedral, for which he had been responsible as thesaurer, should be in order.</p>
<p>Around that time, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feud">feud</ref> broke out, because Margrave <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto_IV,_Margrave_of_Brandenburg-Stendal">Otto IV</ref> of Brandenburg wanted his younger brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric_of_Brandenburg">Eric</ref> elected as Archbishop, and had made an alliance with the Duke of Saxony against Günther.  Otto's troops raided the archbishopric, and the monastery and surrounding areas suffered badly.  Günther, supported by a strong force from the City of Magdeburg, defeated Otto in battles at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aken_(Elbe)">Aken</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Frohse">Frohse</ref> (10 January 1278).  However, Günther grew tired of fighting Otto and in March 1278, he abdicated, even before he had been confirmed and consecrated.  He was succeeded by his former opponent Bernard III of Wölpe.  However, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Martin_IV">Pope Martin IV</ref> appointed Eric as Archbishop of Magdeburg.  In 1282, Bernard abdicated and Eric was consecrated as his successor.</p>
<p>In 1307, Günther was elected Bishop of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Paderborn">Paderborn</ref>.  His election was confirmed by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecclesiastical_province">ecclesiastical province</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishopric_of_Mainz">Mainz</ref> and Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VII,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Henry VII</ref> transferred the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regalia">regalia</ref> of Paderborn to him.  However, he turned out to be a weak ruler.  His provost, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernard_V_of_Lippe">Bernard V of Lippe</ref> <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> administered the bishopric.  In 1308, Bernard vouched for Günther and in 1309, he chaired the Permanent Council as "Defender and Tutor of the safety of the Bishop".  Günther abdicated in 1310 and was succeeded by his cousin <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dietrich_II_of_Itter">Dietrich II of Itter</ref>.</p>
<p>He probably retired to the abbey in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marienmünster">Marienmünster</ref>.  He probably died shortly after his abdication, but the exact date is unknown.  He was probably buried in the church of Marienmünster abbey.</p>
</text>
