<text id="autogum_bio_doc449" title="Joan Fitzgerald, Countess of Ormond" shortTile="joan-fitzgerald-countess" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-13" dateModified="2019-02-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_Fitzgerald%2C_Countess_of_Ormond" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Joan Fitzgerald, Countess of Ormond</head>For other people named Joan Fitzgerald, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_Fitzgerald_(disambiguation)">Joan Fitzgerald (disambiguation)</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Joan Fitzgerald, Countess of Ormond</hi>, Countess of Desmond (ca. 1509 or ca. 1514 – 2 January 1565) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irish_people">Irish</ref> noblewoman and heiress, a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Normans_in_Ireland">Norman</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FitzGerald_dynasty">Fitzgerald</ref> family, who were also known as the "Geraldines". </p>
<p>She married three times. Her first husband was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Butler,_9th_Earl_of_Ormond">James Butler, 9th Earl of Ormond</ref>, who had been proposed as a bridegroom for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_Boleyn">Anne Boleyn</ref> in 1522 to settle a dispute over the title and estates of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Ormond_(Ireland)">Earldom of Ormond</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> Her second husband was courtier Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Bryan">Francis Bryan</ref>. Her third marriage to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerald_FitzGerald,_15th_Earl_of_Desmond">Gerald FitzGerald, 15th Earl of Desmond</ref> brought peace to Ireland for a few years until he broke his truce with her eldest son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Butler,_10th_Earl_of_Ormond">Thomas Butler, 10th Earl of Ormond</ref> and warfare broke out between the rival Butler and Fitzgerald clans, who had been hereditary enemies for many generations.</p>
<p>Joan carried on an amicable correspondence with Queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I_of_England">Elizabeth I of England</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> who recognised Joan's skill in diplomacy, and relied upon her to restore and keep the precarious peace in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Munster">Munster</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Family</head>
<figure><caption>Desmond Castle, Kinsale</caption></figure>
<p>Lady Joan was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Desmond_Castle">Desmond Castle</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kinsale">Kinsale</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_Cork">County Cork</ref>, Ireland in about 1509<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> or 1514,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> the daughter and heiress-general of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_FitzGerald,_10th_Earl_of_Desmond">James FitzGerald, 10th Earl of Desmond</ref> and Amy O'Brien. She had a younger sister, Lady Honora Fitzgerald (died 1577), who later married Pierce Butler.</p>
<head>Marriages and issue</head>
<p>Sometime before 21 December 1532, she married her first husband James Butler, who succeeded as 9th <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Ormond_(Ireland)">Earl of Ormond</ref> on 26 August 1539. James had been proposed as a bridegroom to his cousin Anne Boleyn in 1522 in an attempt to settle a dispute over the title and estates of the earldom of Ormond to which Anne's father, Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Boleyn,_1st_Earl_of_Wiltshire">Thomas Boleyn</ref> had a claim as his mother had been <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_Margaret_Butler">Lady Margaret Butler</ref>, eldest daughter of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Butler,_7th_Earl_of_Ormond">7th earl of Ormond</ref>. For reasons unknown, the marriage negotiations came to a halt and Anne later became the second wife of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VIII_of_England">Henry VIII of England</ref>.
James and Joan had seven sons:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Butler,_10th_Earl_of_Ormond">Thomas Butler, 10th Earl of Ormond</ref> (c.1532- 22 November 1614), married firstly Elizabeth Berkeley; secondly, Elizabeth Sheffield, by whom he had issue; thirdly, Helen Barry</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Butler_of_Kilcash">John Butler of Kilcash</ref> (died 10 May 1570), married Katherine MacCartie, by whom he had a son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Butler,_11th_Earl_of_Ormond">Walter Butler, 11th Earl of Ormond</ref>.</item>
<item>Edward Butler, married Mary Bourke, by whom he had issue.</item>
<item>Walter Butler, married and had one daughter.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Edmund_Butler">Sir Edmund Butler</ref> (1534–1602), married Eleanor Eustace, by whom he had issue.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Butler_of_Duiske">James Butler of Duiske</ref></item>
<item>Piers Butler</item></list>
<p>On 17 October 1546, James went to dine at Ely House in Holborn, London. He fell victim of a mass poisoning along with his steward and 16 of his servants.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> He died on 28 October, leaving Joan a widow in her thirties. As a widow, she could legally act independently and she regained control of her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dowry">dowry</ref>. She sought the help of influential people at court to protect her children's inheritance.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>She had desired to marry as her second husband her cousin <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerald_FitzGerald,_15th_Earl_of_Desmond">Gerald FitzGerald</ref>, heir to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earldom_of_Desmond">Earldom of Desmond</ref> and many years her junior; however, she was forcefully persuaded to marry the English courtier and diplomat <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Francis_Bryan">Sir Francis Bryan</ref> in August 1548. He was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chief_Justice_of_Ireland">Lord Chief Justice of Ireland</ref> and the couple returned to Ireland in November 1548. Due to his reputation of being a rake and libertine at the English court, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Francis_Bryan">Sir Francis Bryan</ref> earned the nickname "Vicar of Hell". Joan is quoted as saying, "While I was a widow and not married [to] an Englishman, I defended and kept my own, or at the least, no man went about to defeat me of my right. Well is the woman unmarried; I am bade to hold my peace, and my husband shall have answer made unto him."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>While Bryan lay dying at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clonmel">Clonmel</ref>, Joan was allegedly out on a hunting expedition with her cousin, Gerald.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> He died on 2 February 1550, and she married Gerald in 1551. Their marriage brought about a temporary peace in Ireland between the rival families of Butler and FitzGerald. Gerald succeeded to the earldom in 1558, making Joan the Countess of Desmond. She used her considerable talent for diplomacy to act as a "peacemaker" between her eldest son and third husband.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Faction fighting between the Butlers and Fitzgeralds</head>
<p>Joan maintained a friendly correspondence with Queen Elizabeth I, who recognised her ability, and relied on her to restore and keep the precarious peace in Munster after her husband, allegedly tired of Joan's domination over him,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> broke the truce with her eldest son, Thomas, who had succeeded his father as Earl of Ormond. After the two factions began making raids against one another, Joan spent nearly two weeks journeying back and forth on horseback to arbitrate between the two enemy camps, before a tenuous peace was finally re-established.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> In 1562, her husband was sent to the Tower of London for his allegedly "insolent" behaviour before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privy_Council">Privy Council</ref>. Joan worked hard to persuade Queen Elizabeth to release him. She was eventually successful in 1564; however, she herself died on 2 January 1565. She was buried at the Friary of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Askeaton">Askeaton</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Limerick">Limerick</ref>.</p>
<p>Following her death, warfare broke out between the Butlers and Fitzgeralds, with her Butler son emerging the victor after the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Affane">Battle of Affane</ref> in 1565.</p>
<p>Joan, in her roles as landowner, household manager, and parent, wielded a powerful influence upon the lives of her tenants, retainers, and children.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> As a countess-albeit by marriage, she participated significantly in the world of Irish politics and the British royal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Tudor">Tudor</ref> court.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref></p>
</text>
