<text id="autogum_bio_doc464" title="Jacqueline de Longwy" shortTile="jacqueline-de-longwy" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-01-06" dateModified="2019-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacqueline_de_Longwy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Jacqueline de Longwy</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jacqueline de Longwy, Countess of Bar-sur-Seine</hi> (before 1520 – 28 August 1561), Duchess of Montpensier, Dauphine of Auvergne was a French noblewoman, and a half-niece of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_I_of_France">Francis I of France</ref>. She was the first wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_III_de_Bourbon,_Duke_of_Montpensier">Louis III de Bourbon, Duke of Montpensier</ref>, and the mother of his six children.  She had the office of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Première_dame_d'honneur">Première dame d'honneur</ref></hi> to the queen dowager regent of France, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_de'_Medici">Catherine de' Medici</ref>, from 1560 until 1561.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Jacqueline was born on an unknown date sometime before 1520, the youngest daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_IV_de_Longwy,_Seigneur_de_Givry,_Baron_of_Pagny_and_of_Mirebeau">Jean IV de Longwy, Seigneur de Givry, Baron of Pagny and of Mirebeau</ref> (died 1520) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeanne_of_Angoulême">Jeanne of Angoulême</ref>, Countess of Bar-sur-Seine (c.1490- after 1531/1538), the illegitimate half-sister of King Francis I of France.</p>
<p>Jacqueline had two older sisters. The eldest, Françoise de Longwy, Dame de Pagny and de Mirebeau (c.1510- after 14 April 1561), married firstly in 1526, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philippe_de_Chabot">Philippe de Chabot</ref>, Seigneur De Brion, Count of Charny and Buzançois, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Admiral_of_France">Admiral of France</ref>, and secondly in 1545, Jacques de Perusse, Seigneur d'Escars, by whom she had a son, Cardinal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_d'Escars_de_Givry">Anne d'Escars de Givry</ref>. Her second eldest sister was Claude Louise de Longwy, Abbess of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jouarre_Abbey">Jouarre</ref>.</p>
<p>Jacqueline's paternal uncle was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claude_de_Longwy_de_Givry">Claude de Longwy de Givry</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Amiens">Bishop of Amiens</ref>.
Her paternal grandparents were Philippe de Longwy, Seigneur of Pagny and Jeanne de Bauffremont, Dame de Mirebeau.
Her maternal grandparents were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles,_Count_of_Angoulême">Charles, Count of Angoulême</ref> and his mistress Antoinette de Polignac, Dame de Combronde, who was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady-in-waiting">lady-in-waiting</ref> to the Count of Angoulême's wife, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louise_of_Savoy">Louise of Savoy</ref>. Antoinette (born c.1460) was the daughter of Foucaud de Polignac, Seigneur des Fontaines and Agnès de Chabanais.</p>
<head>Marriage</head>
<p>In 1538, Jacqueline married Louis III de Bourbon-Montpensier,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTECouchman1997104-1">[1]</ref> who would become <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Montpensier">Duke of Montpensier</ref> on the death of his mother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louise_de_Bourbon,_Duchess_of_Montpensier">Louise de Bourbon, Duchess of Montpensier</ref> on 5 July 1561. On the occasion of the marriage, Jacqueline's uncle, King Francis restored the Montpensier estates and the counties of Forez, Beaujeu, and Dombes to Louis' mother. They had been confiscated by the French Crown following <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_III,_Duke_of_Bourbon">Charles III, Duke of Bourbon</ref>'s treason in 1523 when he defected to the side of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emperor_Charles_V">Emperor Charles V</ref>.</p>
<head>Court career</head>
<p>Jacqueline de Longwy was introduced at court, which she attended from 1533 onward. She became a personal friend of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_de'_Medici">Catherine de' Medici</ref>, who became queen in 1547.  In 1560, Jacqueline de Longwy had been instrumental in the successful negotiations to convince <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antoine_de_Bourbon">Antoine de Bourbon</ref> to relinquish his claims to the regency of Charles in favor of Catherine de' Medici.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMcIlvenna201648-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>She was subsequently appointed <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Première_dame_d'honneur">Première dame d'honneur</ref></hi> and head of the queen's ladies-in-waiting, when Catherine became regent and was able to appoint her own household, in succession to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Françoise_de_Brézé">Françoise de Brézé</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMcIlvenna201648-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Countess of Bar-sur-Seine</head>
<p>Jacqueline succeeded to the title of <hi rend="italic">suo jure</hi> Countess of Bar-sur-Seine upon her mother's death, which occurred on an unknown date sometime after 1531/1538. Her father's titles had passed to her eldest sister, Françoise upon his death in 1520.</p>
<p>In 1543, the dauphinate of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auvergne_(province)">Auvergne</ref> was restored to Louis, Jacqueline therefore became the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dauphin_of_France">Dauphine</ref> of Auvergne. That same year, she was present with other high-ranking members of the Valois court at the baptism of King Francis's grandson, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_II_of_France">Francis</ref>. In 1547, King Francis died and was succeeded by his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_II_of_France">Henry</ref>. In 1556, Jacqueline, together with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diane_de_Poitiers">Diane de Poitiers</ref> and Madame de Montmorency, was appointed by Queen consort <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_de_Medici">Catherine de Medici</ref> to judge the case of misconduct against Mademoiselle de Rohan, a member of the royal family, who was pregnant by the Duke of Nemours under promise of marriage. Three years later, in 1559, Jacqueline and her husband attended the magnificent coronation of King Francis II and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary,_Queen_of_Scots">Mary, Queen of Scots</ref>.</p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>She died in Paris on 28 August 1561. She had been the Duchess of Montpensier for less than two months.</p>
<p>Through her daughter, Charlotte, Jacqueline was an ancestress of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Hanover">House of Hanover</ref>, which reigned in Great Britain from 1714 to 1901, and from which descends the current <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British_Royal_Family">British Royal Family</ref>.</p>
<head>Issue</head>
<p>The marriage of Jacqueline and Louis produced one son and five daughters:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/François_de_Bourbon,_Duke_of_Montpensier">François de Bourbon, Duke of Montpensier</ref> (1542- 4 June 1592), married in 1566, Renée d'Anjou, Marquise de Mézières (21 October 1550- 1597), daughter of Nicolas d'Anjou, Marquis de Mézières and Gabrielle de Mareuil, by whom he had one son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henri_de_Bourbon,_Duke_of_Montpensier">Henri de Bourbon, Duke of Montpensier</ref>.</item>
<item>Françoise de Bourbon (1539–1587), in 1559 married Henri Robert de La Marck (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De_la_Marck">de la Marck</ref>), Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bouillon">Bouillon</ref>, Prince of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sedan,_France">Sedan</ref></item>
<item>Anne de Bourbon (1540 1577), in 1561 married François de Cleves, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Counts_and_Dukes_of_Nevers">Duke of Nevers</ref></item>
<item>Jeanne de Bourbon, Abbess of Jouarre (1541–1620)</item>
<item>Charlotte de Bourbon (1547- 5 May 1582),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTECouchman1997104-1">[1]</ref> on 24 June 1575, married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_The_Silent">William The Silent</ref> of Nassau, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince_of_Orange">Prince of Orange</ref>, by whom she had six daughters</item>
<item>Louise de Bourbon, Abbess of Faremoutier (1548–1586)</item></list>
<head>In art</head>
<p>Jacqueline de Longwy's portrait was drawn in 1550 by French painter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/François_Clouet">François Clouet</ref>.</p>
</text>
