<text id="autogum_bio_doc633" title="Louis Fadrique" shortTile="louis-fadrique" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-12-20" dateModified="2019-10-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_Fadrique" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Louis Fadrique</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Louis Fadrique</hi> (also <hi rend="italic">Luis</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Lluís Frederic d'Aragó</hi>; died 1382) a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catalan_Company">Catalan</ref> nobleman who was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Count_of_Salona">Count of Salona</ref>, as well as lord of various other towns in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_Greece">Central Greece</ref> from ca. 1365 until his death in 1382. In 1375–1381 he also served as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vicar-general">vicar-general</ref> of the twin duchy of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Athens">Athens</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Neopatras">Neopatras</ref>.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Louis was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Fadrique">James Fadrique</ref> and a grandson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfonso_Fadrique">Alfonso Fadrique</ref>. When his father seized the fortress of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siderokastron">Siderokastron</ref> in 1365, Louis became its <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castellan">castellan</ref>, although he was underage. When James died in 1366, Louis in addition received possession of the nearby town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lamia_(city)">Zetouni</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1975206–207,_211-1">[1]</ref> Following the machinations of the agents of the then <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vicar-general">vicar-general</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_de_Llúria_(Duchy_of_Athens)">Roger de Llúria</ref>, in June 1367 King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_the_Simple">Frederick III of Sicily</ref> ordered Louis to surrender Siderokastron to Nicholas de Sosa, but Louis seems to have disregarded this and maintained control of the fortress throughout his life.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1975207,_211-2">[2]</ref> In ca. 1368 he married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helena_Asanina_Kantakouzene">Helena Asanina Kantakouzene</ref>, daughter of  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_Kantakouzenos">Matthew Kantakouzenos</ref>, the former Byzantine co-emperor (1353–1357). The couple had one daughter, Maria.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1975213–214-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Louis also came into conflict with his uncle, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boniface_Fadrique">Boniface Fadrique</ref>, to whom James had willed "all his rights and properties" in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Athens">Duchy of Athens</ref>, including the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Salona">County of Salona</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loidoriki">Loidoriki</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Veteranitsa">Veteranitsa</ref>, and the island of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aegina">Aegina</ref>, which Boniface gave his son Peter.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1975211–212-4">[4]</ref> With the support of most of the Catalan feudatories, rattled following the capture of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Megara">Megara</ref> by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florence">Florentine</ref> adventurer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nerio_I_Acciaioli">Nerio I Acciaioli</ref>, in April 1375, Louis obtained from Frederick III his appointment as vicar-general of the twin duchy of Athens and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Neopatras">Neopatras</ref>. He had apparently exercised the duties of the office since the death or incapacitation of his rather incompetent predecessor, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_of_Peralta">Matthew of Peralta</ref>, in the previous year; and would remain in office until the autumn of 1381.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1975199,_211–212-5">[5]</ref> From this position, Louis was able to defeat his uncle and cousin when they took up arms against him. Louis took over their properties, and sent Peter to exile and prison in Aragon. His uncle Boniface died soon after sometime before September 1380.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1975212-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>After the death of Frederick III, Louis supported the assumption of the ducal crown by King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_IV_of_Aragon">Peter IV of Aragon</ref> in opposition to Frederick's daughter, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria,_Queen_of_Sicily">Maria</ref>. Peter finally succeeded in 1379, and the two duchies of Athens and Neopatras were annexed directly into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crown_of_Aragon">Crown of Aragon</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1975214–215-7">[7]</ref> Although Boniface's widow and his other son, John, obtained a pardon from the new Duke in May 1381 and a promise for the restitution of Boniface's possessions, it is unclear whether this was ever done; at any rate Louis appears as the "Count of Salona" in a list dated to 1380/31.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1975213-8">[8]</ref> Louis was less successful against another powerful feudatory, the castellan of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Athens">Athens</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galcerán_of_Peralta">Galcerán of Peralta</ref>. Apparently enjoying the support of the Catalans of the city, Peralta was able to withstand Louis from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acropolis_of_Athens">Acropolis of Athens</ref>. Having himself firmly supported Peter IV in the dispute over control of the duchies, he was able to secure recognition of his position, possessions and privileges in an agreement with Louis, ratified by Peter IV in September 1380.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1975212–213,_215-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>At the same time, the Catalan duchies faced a new and dangerous opponent: the mercenary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Navarrese_Company">Navarrese Company</ref>, which in spring 1379 invaded <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boeotia">Boeotia</ref> from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morea">Morea</ref>—with the permission, if not connivance, of their ally Nerio Acciaioli, who controlled <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Megarid">the region linking</ref> the Morea with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_Greece">Central Greece</ref>. The Navarrese quickly conquered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thebes,_Greece">Thebes</ref>, the capital of the Duchy of Athens, which had been left unfortified, in May or June 1379.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1975218–219-10">[10]</ref> Despite the fall of Thebes, Louis persistently remained opposed to dealing with the Navarrese. Aside from Acciaioli, the latter also enjoyed the support of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knights_Hospitaller">Knights Hospitaller</ref>, and the soon allied themselves with two of the Catalans' neighbours, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_of_the_Archipelago">Duke of the Archipelago</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_III_dalle_Carceri">Nicholas III dalle Carceri</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marquis_of_Bodonitsa">Marquis of Bodonitsa</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Zorzi">Francis Zorzi</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1975219–220-11">[11]</ref> In late 1380 or early 1381, the Navarrese took the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Livadeia">Livadeia</ref> as well. Louis took up some of the refugees from the city in his fief of Salona, while others fled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euboea">Euboea</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1975222–223-12">[12]</ref></p>
<p>In early autumn 1381, Louis was replaced as vicar-general by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Dalmau,_Viscount_of_Rocaberti">Philip Dalmau, Viscount of Rocaberti</ref>, who had already been appointed in 1379 but had not yet arrived in Greece to take up his position.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1975220–223,_231–232-13">[13]</ref> During Dalmau's residence in Greece, Louis discussed with him the possibility of a marriage between his daughter and Dalmau's son Bernaduch, but he died in mid-autumn 1382. He was succeeded in Salona by his widow, while King Peter IV gave his daughter Maria possession of Siderokastron for life, on the condition that she married Bernaduch. This marriage never materialized, however, and the Catalan sources make no further reference to Siderokastron after that.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1975234-14">[14]</ref></p>
</text>
