<text id="autogum_bio_doc740" title="Margaret of Trent" shortTile="margaret-trent" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-11-02" dateModified="2019-11-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret_of_Trent" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Margaret of Trent</head><p><hi rend="bold">Margaret of Trent</hi> (died 1 June 1307) was the companion of Fra <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fra_Dolcino">Dolcino of Novara</ref>, leader of the heretical <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dulcinians">New Apostles</ref>, from at least December 1303 until her death. She was a native of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trent">Trent</ref> or possibly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arco,_Trentino">Arco</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBenedetti2008-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In a deposition taken in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bologna">Bologna</ref> on 22 September 1304, Rolandino, one of the Apostles, described Margaret as from Trent and a companion of Dolcino for the past year. In 1302–1303, according to Rolandino, Dolcino had been accompanied on his preaching tour of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trentino">Trentino</ref> by Cara da Modena, a woman and fellow preacher. In Dolcino's second letter of December 1303, however, he lists the leaders of his movement in order of precedence with himself first as <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/rector">rector</ref></hi> (leader) and his sister  Margaret second as "his beloved above all". They are followed by the brothers Longino da Bergamo, Alberto da Cimego, Baldrico da Brescia and Federico Grampa di Novara. The same hierarchy is described as current by Rolandino in his deposition.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBenedetti2008-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Margaret's rise to prominence appears to have been rapid, given the presence of another woman, Cara, beside Dolcino earlier in the year. It is not know if the choice of a woman as his companion had significance to the movement or was merely coincidental. No other women leaders are known among the Apostles. The inquisitor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernard_Gui">Bernard Gui</ref> accuses Margaret of being Dolcino's concubine (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/amasia">amasia</ref></hi>), but his accusation is of little worth on its own. He also calls Margaret "his partner in crime and heresy" and a "mischievous woman". He admits that Dolcino denies any physical relationship, claiming that he treated Margaret "in the manner of a sister in Christ, modestly and honestly". According to Gui, when Margaret became pregnant Dolcino claimed that she was impregnated by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Spirit">Holy Spirit</ref>. Gui heightens the implausibility of Dolcino's claim by describing Margaret, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italian_language">Italian</ref> in an otherwise <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin">Latin</ref> text, as "the beauty" (<hi rend="italic">la bella</hi>), a description picked up by the anonymous <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Historia_fratris_Dulcini">Historia fratris Dulcini</ref></hi> and by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benvenuto_da_Imola">Benvenuto da Imola</ref>, who writes of her "immense beauty".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBenedetti2008-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In 1306, Pope <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clement_V">Clement V</ref> declared a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crusade">crusade</ref> against the followers of Fra Dolcino, who took refuge in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Val_Sesia">Val Sesia</ref>. On 23 March 1307, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raniero_Avogadro">Raniero Avogadro</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Vercelli">bishop of Vercelli</ref>, led the final attack on the New Apostles. Dolcino, Margaret and Longino were captured. They were brought to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Biella">Biella</ref> on 25 March. After a secular trial by a council of wise men, according to the <hi rend="italic">Historia fratris Dulcini</hi>, they were burned at the stake on the banks of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cervo_(river)">Cervo</ref> near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vercelli">Vercelli</ref> on 1 June 1307. Margaret was burned first before Dolcino's eyes. Gui gives a slightly different account. He has Margaret torn to pieces before Dolcino's eyes before the latter met the same fate. Their dismembered corpses were then cremated.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBenedetti2008-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>On 31 December 1332, Margaret's brother Boninsegna, son of Oddorico da Arco, a nobleman, testified that about 28 years earlier his sister and four other young women along with several young men had joined the New Apostles and died at the stake. But two years earlier, according to Boninsegna, he had learned that she was alive and living in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vicenza">Vicenza</ref> under the name Maria. She had been imprisoned for three years, released by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medieval_Inquisition">Inquisition</ref>, married and had a fifteen-year-old son. There is no other source that mentions Margaret's survival and it is likely that the story of her escape was concocted to posthumously rehabilitate her.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBenedetti2008-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
