<text id="autogum_bio_doc659" title="Alexander (son of Ivan Shishman)" shortTile="alexander-son-ivan" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-04-16" dateModified="2017-11-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_%28son_of_Ivan_Shishman%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Alexander (son of Ivan Shishman)</head><p><hi rend="bold">Alexander</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarian_language">Bulgarian</ref>: Александър), subsequently <hi rend="bold">Iskender</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Turkish_language">Ottoman Turkish</ref>: اسكندر) (died 1418), was the eldest son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Bulgarian_monarchs">Bulgarian tsar</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Shishman_of_Bulgaria">Ivan Shishman</ref> (r. 1371–1395). Alexander was possibly made co-emperor by his father before the Ottoman conquest of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Bulgarian_Empire">Tarnovo Tsardom</ref> in 1395. After the subjugation of Ivan Shishman's realm and his execution, Alexander converted to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islam">Islam</ref> to avoid his father's fate. He was made governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samsun">Samsun</ref>, where he remained until 1402. From 1413 to 1418, when he was killed in a battle against a local rebel, Alexander was in charge of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smyrna">Smyrna</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/İzmir">İzmir</ref>).</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>There is no information about Alexander's early life in the contemporary sources. Indeed, the only hint as to his existence in a Bulgarian source is an anonymous reference in Ephraim's <hi rend="italic">Prayer Canon to the Tsar</hi>, where he is only mentioned as “the son of the tsar”. It is uncertain whether Alexander was born to Ivan Shishman's first wife, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kira_Maria">Kira Maria</ref>, or to his second wife, a daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Serbian_monarchs">Prince</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lazar_of_Serbia">Lazar of Serbia</ref> (r. 1371–1389).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bozhilov229,241-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Due to Alexander's first-born status, Bulgarian historian Petar Nikov conjectures that at some point before 1395, Alexander was made co-ruler by his father Ivan Shishman. This would have been in line with a custom that dates to the reign of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Alexander_of_Bulgaria">Ivan Alexander</ref> (r. 1331–1371), Ivan Shishman's own father.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bozhilov241-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-andreev10-3">[3]</ref> Alexander had a younger brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fruzhin">Fruzhin</ref>, who, in contrast to Alexander, was a staunch opponent of the Ottomans and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Hungary">Hungarian</ref> subject.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bozhilov242-244-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bakalov100-5">[5]</ref> In addition to Fruzhin, Alexander had other brothers and sisters, of whom practically nothing is known.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bozhilov245-246-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fall_of_Tarnovo">Fall of Tarnovo</ref> in 1393 and the subsequent subjugation of the entire Tarnovo Tsardom in 1395 resulted in the execution of Ivan Shishman by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_sultans_of_the_Ottoman_Empire">Sultan</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayezid_I">Bayezid I</ref> (r. 1389–1402). Though his successor Alexander was spared by the Ottomans, he was forced into accepting Islam and was exiled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asia_Minor">Asia Minor</ref> so as to keep him far from his father's previous domains. Alexander, subsequently referred to as Iskender in Ottoman sources, was installed as governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samsun">Samsun</ref> and the neighbouring territories (“the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beyliks_of_Canik">land of Canik</ref>”). These lands lay along the southern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_Sea">Black Sea</ref> coast, between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sinop,_Turkey">Sinope</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trabzon">Trebizond</ref>, and had been recently conquered by Bayezid.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-andreev10-3">[3]</ref> Alexander possibly remained governor of Samsun until 1402, when this region was conquered by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timurid_Empire">Timurids</ref> in the wake of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Ankara">Battle of Ankara</ref> on 20 July of that year. After the Timurid victory, the Samsun region came under the rule of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seljuks">Seljuk</ref> prince İsfendiyar.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bozhilov242-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Alexander's subsequent fate is unknown until the end of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Interregnum">Ottoman Interregnum</ref> in 1413, when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mehmed_I">Mehmed I</ref> (r. 1413–1421) had established himself as ruler of the Ottoman Empire and had retaken the region of Smyrna on the eastern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aegean_Sea">Aegean</ref> coast. Until then, Smyrna had been ruled by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cüneyt_Bey_of_Aydın">Cüneyt</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bey">bey</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aydinids">Aydin</ref>, who was exiled as governor of the previously Bulgarian city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikopol,_Bulgaria">Nikopol</ref> on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danube">Danube</ref>. Alexander was installed as the ruler of Smyrna in Cüneyt's place. He remained in charge of the city until 1418, when he attempted to suppress a rebellion to the south of Smyrna headed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheikh_Bedrettin">Sheikh Bedrettin</ref>'s follower <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Börklüce_Mustafa">Börklüce Mustafa</ref>. However, Alexander's forces proved insufficient for the purpose. His army was ambushed in a mountain gorge and suffered a great defeat, during which Alexander was killed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bakalov100-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bozhilov242-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-andreev10-11-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>According to the theory of Bulgarian historian Plamen Pavlov, during his time as governor of Smyrna, Alexander may have been in active contact with his possible half-brother, the future <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarch_Joseph_II_of_Constantinople">Patriarch Joseph II of Constantinople</ref>. From 1393 to 1416, Joseph was the metropolitan bishop of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ephesus">Ephesus</ref>, another city on the eastern Aegean coast located not far from Smyrna. Pavlov conjectures that Joseph's selection as patriarch may have been influenced by his ties to Mehmed I via Alexander. In Pavlov's opinion, it is also possible that titular Bulgarian tsar <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantine_II_of_Bulgaria">Constantine II</ref>'s support for Mehmed was in some way related to his relative Alexander's position as an Ottoman governor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
</text>
