<text id="autogum_bio_doc737" title="Bartholomew Burghersh the younger" shortTile="bartholomew-burghersh" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-02-09" dateModified="2019-09-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bartholomew_Burghersh_the_younger" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bartholomew Burghersh the younger</head>
<figure><caption>Arms of Sir Bartholomew de Burghersh, KG -- Gules a lion rampant double-queued or</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bartholomew Burghersh, 2nd Baron Burghersh</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Order_of_the_Garter">KG</ref> (bef. 1329 – 5 April 1369), called 'the younger', was an English nobleman and soldier.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bartholomew_Burghersh_the_elder">Bartholomew Burghersh the elder</ref>, adopted his father's profession of arms and rivalled him in military distinction.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEVenables1886-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>His recorded career begins in 1339, when he accompanied <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_III">Edward III</ref> in his expedition to Flanders and took part in the first invasion of French territory.
We find his name also as attending the king on his third inglorious and unprofitable <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_of_the_Breton_Succession">campaign in Brittany</ref> in 1342-3.
In 1346, he was one of the retinue of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_the_Black_Prince">Edward the Black Prince</ref>, then in his fifteenth year, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Crécy">Battle of Crécy</ref>, and in the following year was present at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Calais_(1346)">siege of Calais</ref>, being rewarded for his distinguished services there by a rich wardship. In 1349, he was in the campaign in Gascony. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEVenables1886-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>On the institution of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Order_of_the_Garter">Order of the Garter</ref> in 1348, he was chosen to be one of the first knights companions.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Shaw-2">[2]</ref>
In 1354, he fulfilled a religious vow by taking a journey to the Holy Land.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEVenables1886-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>On his return home, he joined the Black Prince in the expedition, in 1355.
He was one of the most eminent of the commanders of the invading army, and had a leading share in the events of the campaign, especially in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Poitiers_(1356)">battle of Poitiers</ref>, 19 September 1356.
A daring exploit of Burghersh is recorded by Froissart shortly before the battle.
In company with Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Chandos">John Chandos</ref> and Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Audley">James Audley</ref>, and attended by only four-and-twenty horsemen, he made an excursion from the main body of the army, and, falling on the rear of the French army, took thirty-two knights and gentlemen prisoners.
His prowess and skill were again tried about the same time, when, on his return with a small foraging party at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romorantin">Romorantin</ref> near Berry, he was attacked from an ambuscade by a much more formidable force, which, however, he managed to keep at bay till relieved by the Black Prince.
During this campaign his father, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bartholomew_de_Burghersh,_1st_Baron_Burghersh">Lord Burghersh</ref>, died, and he received livery of his lands as his heir.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEVenables1886-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In 1359, he again accompanied Edward III on his last and most formidable invasion of France, ending in the decisive <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Bretigny">treaty of Bretigny</ref>, 8 May 1360.
He was deputed to aid in the negotiation of this treaty between ‘the firstborn sons of the kings of England and France’ at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chartres">Chartres</ref>, for which letters of protection were given him. He and his brother commissioners were taken prisoners in violation of the bond, and Edward had to interpose to obtain their liberation.
During this campaign Knighton records his successful siege of the castle of Sourmussy in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gascony">Gascony</ref>, in which he appears to have evidenced no common skill.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEVenables1886-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In 1362, he was appointed one of the commissioners on the state of Ireland.
When, in 1364, King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_II_of_France">John II of France</ref>, to make atonement for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_I,_Duke_of_Anjou">Louis I, Duke of Anjou</ref>’s breach of faith, determined to yield himself back to captivity, to die three months alter his Landing at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savoy_Palace">Savoy Palace</ref>, Burghersh was one of the nobles deputed to receive him at Dover and conduct him by Canterbury to Edward‘s presence at Eltham.
In 1366, he was one of the commissioners sent to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Urban_V">Urban V</ref>, who had rashly demanded the payment of the arrears of the tribute granted by King John.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEVenables1886-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>His death took place in 1369.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Shaw-2">[2]</ref>
By his desire, he was buried in the lady chapel of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walsingham_Priory">Walsingham Abbey</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEVenables1886-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>He married before 10 May 1335 Cecily de Weyland, by whom he had one daughter:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_le_Despencer,_Baroness_le_Despencer">Elizabeth Burghersh</ref> (c. 1342–1409), <hi rend="italic">suo jure</hi> Baroness Burghersh, she married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_le_Despencer,_1st_Baron_le_Despencer">Edward le Despencer, 1st Baron le Despencer</ref> before December 1364.</item></list>
<p>After the death of Cecily, he married Margaret Gisors, by whom he had no children.</p>
</text>
