<text id="autogum_bio_doc487" title="Robert Richardson (Lord Treasurer)" shortTile="robert-richardson" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-30" dateModified="2017-01-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Richardson_%28Lord_Treasurer%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Robert Richardson (Lord Treasurer)</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Robert Richardson</hi> (died 1578) was a Scottish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prior_of_St_Mary's_Isle">Prior of St Mary's Isle</ref> and royal administrator.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>He was the son of Robert Richardson, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burgess_(title)">burgess</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jedburgh">Jedburgh</ref> (died ca. 1556). His great grandfather arrived in Scotland in 1424 in the reign of James I. The historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Crawfurd">George Crawfurd</ref> asserts that he was descended of a stock of ancient and opulent burgesses of Edinburgh,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Crawfurd,_383-1">[1]</ref> but there is little to connect him with the city before 1553, when he was made a burgess at the request of the fourth earl of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huntly,_Scotland">Huntly</ref>.</p>
<p>He matriculated at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Salvator's_College,_St_Andrews">St Salvator's College, St Andrews</ref>, in 1531, and graduated MA in 1532. Nothing is known of his early career except that in April 1544 he was involved with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_Stewart,_4th_Earl_of_Lennox">Earl of Lennox</ref> in armed opposition to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent_Arran">Regent Arran</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Glasgow_(1544)">battle of Glasgow</ref>, for which he later received remission. He was presented to the vicarage of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunsyre">Dunsyre</ref> in 1549 and held the vicarage of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eckford,_Scottish_Borders">Eckford</ref> by 1552. In that year he was provided by the Pope to the archdeaconry of Teviotdale, which he held until 1565 along with the appropriated parsonage of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morebattle">Morebattle</ref>. In 1558 he obtained crown presentation to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Mary's_Isle_Priory">priory of St Mary's Isle</ref>, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kirkcudbright">Kirkcudbright</ref>, which he also resigned in 1565, retaining the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usufruct">usufruct</ref>.</p>
<p>Richardson's career as a royal official began around 1549 when he was comptroller clerk. In November 1552 he was an auditor of the treasurer's account. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilbert_Kennedy,_3rd_Earl_of_Cassilis">Gilbert Kennedy, 3rd Earl of Cassilis</ref>, appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treasurer_of_Scotland">lord treasurer</ref> in April 1554, delegated the entire conduct of business to Richardson as treasurer clerk. After Cassillis's death in November 1558 Richardson continued as treasurer clerk and acting treasurer.</p>
<head>Scottish Reformation</head>
<p>As acting treasurer, it was probably in this capacity, rather than as "Maister of the Cunze-house",<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> that he held the coining irons of the mint at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holyroodhouse">Holyroodhouse</ref>. In July 1559 the Protestant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lords_of_the_Congregation">Lords of the Congregation</ref> who occupied Edinburgh seized these, along with great sums of money, claiming that they had done so to stop corruption of the coinage. The irons were returned to him according to the terms of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Articles_of_Leith">Articles of Leith</ref> between the lords and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_of_Guise">Mary of Guise</ref>. </p>
<p>After the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Leith">siege of Leith</ref>, Richardson sat as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prelate">prelate</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish_Reformation_Parliament">Reformation Parliament of 1560</ref> and was listed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Knox">Knox</ref> among those "that had renunceit Papistrie and oppinlie profest Jesus Chryst with us.".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Finally appointed Lord Treasurer on 5 March 1561, he was a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privy_Council_of_Scotland">privy council</ref> from 1561 to 1576. In 1562 he was named as one of the commissioners for receiving rentals of benefices and in October of that year was granted a pension of £1000 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pound_Scots">Scots</ref> from the thirds of benefices pending provision to a benefice of equal or greater value.</p>
<p>The Reformation gave him further opportunities to add to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landed_property">landed estate</ref> he had been acquiring since 1552, mainly in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_Lothian">East Lothian</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Midlothian">Midlothian</ref>. Three charters by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commendator">commendator</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunfermline_Abbey">convent of Dunfermline</ref> on 28 July 1563 conveyed to him extensive lands, mainly in Haddingtonshire, Edinburghshire, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fife">Fife</ref>, amounting to no fewer than seventy-seven farms and scattered holdings. From September 1565 onwards he disposed of a large part of this property to the tenants, no doubt profitably. He retained lands and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coal_mine">coal mines</ref> around <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musselburgh">Musselburgh</ref>, including Smeaton, where either he or his son built what in 1577 was described as a new house. He also acquired some small properties belonging to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jedburgh_Abbey">Jedburgh Abbey</ref>. Crawfurd wrote of Richardson:</p>
<p>He appears to have been a very wise moderate man; for so far as I can observe from the history of these times, he kept himself more in a neutrality, and was less a party-man than any other that held any great office about the court. He was never violent against the Queen, tho' he complied with the Government under the young King.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Crawfurd,_383-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>King's man and Lord High Treasurer</head>
<p>Richardson supported the overthrow of Mary, Queen of Scots; he attended the coronation of the infant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_I_of_England">James VI</ref> in 1567, and was present at Mary's defeat at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Langside">battle of Langside</ref> in May 1568 on the side of her half-brother and opponent, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Stuart,_1st_Earl_of_Moray">James Stuart, 1st Earl of Moray</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref>  In 1569 he voted to refuse <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary,_Queen_of_Scots">Mary, Queen of Scots</ref>' divorce from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Hepburn,_4th_Earl_of_Bothwell">Bothwell</ref>. His support for the new regime is also evidenced by a loan of £3000 to the Earl of Moray, now the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent_of_Scotland">Regent of Scotland</ref>,  on 17 September 1567, secured on the royal jewels. In the following year, as he was "greitlie superexpendit as treasurer and unable to pay his creditors",<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Moray gave him the revenue arising from wards and marriages and vacant benefices. In January 1571 the lease of the mint which he had held since 1566 was renewed for three years, half the profits to be applied to paying off his ˜superexpenses as treasurer. According to a contemporary source, John <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cunningham_of_Drumquhassle">Cunningham of Drumquhassle</ref> had been made "half thesaurer, with Mr Robert Ritchartsone that wes thesaurer of befoir"<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> in July 1570, but Richardson remained in sole charge until 24 June 1571, when he was replaced by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Ruthven,_1st_Earl_of_Gowrie">William, Lord Ruthven</ref>. He retained control of the mint until March 1573, his share of the profits amounting to more than £5400 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pound_Scots">Scots</ref>. Thereafter he continued to receive money from the mint to redeem the royal jewels that had been pledged to him, further payments being made to his sons after his death, which probably took place between May and November 1578.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Richardson was unmarried but his four children, James, Robert, Stephen, and Janet were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Legitimation">legitimated</ref> in 1552; another child (Katherine) may have been born in December 1563, when Randolph reported to Cecil that Richardson was to do public penance in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Giles'_Cathedral">St Giles</ref> for getting a woman with child and Knox was to "mayke the sermonde.".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> James Richardson of Smeaton, the eldest of Richardson's children, received most of his father's lands; he married Elizabeth Douglas, and their second son, Sir Robert Richardson of Pencaitland, was created a baronet in 1630.</p>
</text>
