<text id="autogum_bio_doc204" title="Lillie Goodisson" shortTile="lillie-goodisson" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-01-11" dateModified="2019-08-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lillie_Goodisson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Lillie Goodisson</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Lillie Elizabeth Goodisson</hi> (née <hi rend="bold">Price</hi>; c.1860 - 10 January 1947) was a Welsh Australian nurse and a pioneer of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Family_planning">family planning</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_South_Wales">New South Wales</ref>.</p>
<p>Goodisson was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holyhead">Holyhead</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wales">Wales</ref>. She trained as a nurse and at age 19 married London physician Lawford David Evans. Soon after they moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auckland">Auckland</ref>, New Zealand, where they started a family. The couple and their two children moved to Melbourne in 1895, and in 1897 established in Myrnong private hospital at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Kilda,_Victoria">St. Kilda</ref>. Her husband died in 1903 and thereafter she went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_Australia">Western Australia</ref> where she met and married her second husband, Albert Elliot Goodisson in 1904. They lived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geraldton,_Western_Australia">Geraldton</ref> until Albert Goodisson went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Batavia,_Dutch_East_Indies">Batavia</ref> in September 1913 to receive treatment for an illness, he died in 1914 leaving little to his wife, she borrowed money from her friend <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivy_Brookes">Ivy Brookes</ref> and returned to Melbourne.</p>
<p>She was involved in patriotic causes during <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_War_I">World War I</ref>, however her finances did not improve, and she took another loan from Brookes to establish a library at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elwood,_Victoria">Elwood</ref> in Melbourne. Debts and ill health forced its <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liquidation">liquidation</ref> in 1924. Goodisson moved to Sydney to be with her daughter in 1926. She joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Women's_Reform_League">Women's Reform League</ref> and with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruby_Rich">Ruby Rich</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marion_Louisa_Piddington">Marion Louisa Piddington</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna_Roberts">Anna Roberts</ref> founded the Racial Improvement Society, which later (1928) became the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Racial_Hygiene_Association_of_New_South_Wales">Racial Hygiene Association of New South Wales</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FPA-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Horin-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-thesis-3">[3]</ref> The association was involved in promoting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sex_education">sex education</ref>, preventing and eradicating <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sexually_transmitted_disease">venereal disease</ref> and the education of the public in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eugenics">eugenics</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ADB-4">[4]</ref> Goodisson served as general secretary for the association.  She advocated the selective breeding of future generations for the elimination of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hereditary_disease">hereditary disease</ref>, and defects and campaigned unsuccessfully for the segregation and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_sterilization_(surgical_procedure)">sterilization</ref> of the mentally deficient and for the introduction of pre-marital health examinations.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ADB-4">[4]</ref> Although Goodisson campaigned for her association's eugenics goals, her main interests were in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contraception">contraception</ref> and politics.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-thesis-3">[3]</ref>  The likely catalyst for her campaign interests was her husband's death from general paralysis and derangement (general paralysis of the insane) a symptom of Tertiary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syphilis">Syphilis</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1932 Goodisson unsuccessfully stood for the seat of Newcastle as the Social Reform Party’s candidate.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-thesis-3">[3]</ref> In 1933 the association established a birth control clinic in Sydney which Goodisson described as the first in Australia; however, Piddington had established a birth control clinic in Melbourne two years earlier.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-thesis-3">[3]</ref> The clinic served married women, providing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diaphragm_(contraceptive)">diaphragms</ref> so that unwanted pregnancies would not be terminated by illegal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abortion">abortions</ref>. The activities of the clinic were controversial; it received government subsidies only to have them withdrawn. Piddington's Melbourne clinic was forced to close in 1943 when the rubber used to make diaphragms was needed for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_War_II">war efforts</ref>; the Sydney clinic remained open.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-thesis-3">[3]</ref> Goodisson remained active in the association until her death in 1947; however the organisation's activities were greatly reduced during the war and did not regain momentum until the 1960s.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-thesis-3">[3]</ref> In 1960 the association was renamed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Family_Planning_Association_of_Australia">Family Planning Association of Australia</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Goodisson was also an active member of the National Council of Women of New South Wales, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Travelers_Aid_International">Travellers' Aid Society</ref>, the Good Film League of New South Wales, and the Sydney Health Week and Mental Hygiene Council.</p>
</text>
