<text id="autogum_bio_doc785" title="Vytenis" shortTile="vytenis" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-04-13" dateModified="2019-09-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vytenis" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Vytenis</head>
<figure><caption>Expansion of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania, 13th–15th centuries</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Vytenis</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belarusian_language">Belarusian</ref>: Віцень, Vicień; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polish_language">Polish</ref>: <hi lang="pl" rend="italic">Witenes</hi>) was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Duke_of_Lithuania">Grand Duke of Lithuania</ref> from c. 1295 to c. 1316. He became the first of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gediminids">Gediminid dynasty</ref> to rule for a considerable amount of time. In the early 14th century his reputation outshone that of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gediminas">Gediminas</ref>, who is regarded by modern historians as one of the greatest Lithuanian rulers.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rowell-1">[1]</ref> The rule of Vytenis was marked by constant warfare in an effort to consolidate the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Duchy_of_Lithuania">Grand Duchy of Lithuania</ref> with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruthenia">Ruthenians</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masovia">Masovians</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teutonic_Order">Teutonic Order</ref>.</p>
<head>Warfare</head>
<p>Vytenis is mentioned for the first time in 1292 during his father's invasion of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masovia">Masovia</ref>: an army of 800 men reached as far as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Łęczyca">Łęczyca</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-el-2">[2]</ref> After his father's death, c. 1295, he became Grand Duke. Vytenis was soon involved in succession disputes in Poland, supporting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boleslaus_II_of_Masovia">Boleslaus II of Masovia</ref>, who was married to a Lithuanian duchess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaudemunda_of_Lithuania">Gaudemunda</ref>, and opposing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Władysław_I_the_Elbow-high">Władysław I of Poland</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rowell-1">[1]</ref> In Ruthenia, Vytenis managed to recapture lands lost after the assassination of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mindaugas">Mindaugas</ref> and capture the principalities of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pinsk">Pinsk</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turaŭ">Turaŭ</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-lv-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crusade">crusade</ref> against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuanian_mythology">pagan</ref> Lithuania and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samogitia">Samogitia</ref> intensified and reached a new level in the 1290s as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Prussians">Prussians</ref> and other <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balts">Baltic tribes</ref> were conquered by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teutonic_Knights">Teutonic Knights</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Livonian_Order">Livonian Order</ref>. During Vytenis's reign a network of defensive castles was established and strengthened along the banks of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neman_River">Neman</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jūra">Jūra</ref> rivers; the Knights matched this with their own castles on the opposite bank.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rowell-1">[1]</ref> During this time, the Teutonic Order was attempting to establish a corridor along the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baltic_Sea">Baltic Sea</ref>, in Samogitia, to link up with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Livonian_Order">Livonian Order</ref> to the north. During the reign of Vytenis, the Teutonic Knights organized some 20 raids into Samogitia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-el-2">[2]</ref> Vytenis took measures to undermine influence of local Samogitian nobles, as evidenced by an increasing numbers of traitors and refugees.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-kiaupa-4">[4]</ref> It seems that Gediminas was helping Vytenis to control the nobles, who seriously considered resettling in Prussia as vassals of the Teutonic Knights.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref>  The Order also consolidated its control over <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semigalia">Semigalia</ref>, where Lithuanians had their garrisons since the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Aizkraukle">Battle of Aizkraukle</ref>. The Order captured <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daugavpils">Dynaburg</ref> Castle, controlled by Lithuanians since 1281, in 1313.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-lv-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Alliance with Riga</head>
<p>One of the most celebrated achievements of Vytenis was an alliance with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riga">Riga</ref>. In 1297 disagreements between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishopric_of_Riga">Archbishop of Riga</ref>, burghers of Riga, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Livonian_Order">Livonian Order</ref> grew into an internal war. Vytenis offered help to the citizens of Riga and even made some vague promises to convert to Christianity, to ease religious tensions between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuanian_mythology">pagan</ref> soldiers and Christian residents.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rowell-1">[1]</ref> Vytenis successfully invaded Livonia, destroyed Karkus castle north of Riga, and defeated the order in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Turaida">Battle of Turaida</ref>, killing Livonian Land Master Bruno and 22 knights.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-el-2">[2]</ref> When Livonia was secured, Vytenis organized eleven campaigns into territories of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teutonic_Knights">Teutonic Knights</ref> in Prussia in 1298–1313,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-lv-3">[3]</ref> including one to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brodnica">Brodnica</ref>, where entire population was massacred.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-eric-6">[6]</ref> His cause was helped by the fact that in 1308 the Teutonic Knights conquered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomerania">Pomerania</ref> and started its <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teutonic_Knights#Against_Poland">quarrels with Poland</ref>.</p>
<p>A Lithuanian garrison, situated in a "Lithuanian castle" outside the city, guarded Riga until 1313 when the city residents gave it to the Order and sent the pagans away. Friendship with Riga fostered trade and commerce, and helped to consolidate Lithuanian influence in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daugava_River">Daugava</ref> basin, where c. 1307 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polatsk">Polatsk</ref>, a major trade post, was annexed by Lithuania.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-kiaupa-4">[4]</ref> Due to close contacts with Riga Vytenis invited <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franciscan_order">Franciscan friars</ref> to maintain a Catholic church in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Navahrudak">Navahrudak</ref> for German merchants in 1312.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rowell-1">[1]</ref> In the field of religion, it seems that Vytenis laid the groundwork for the creation of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitanate_of_Lithuania">Metropolitanate of Lithuania</ref> c. 1316.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rowell-1">[1]</ref> The metropolitanate was a tool in the competition between Vilnius and Moscow for the religious leadership in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruthenia">Ruthenia</ref>.</p>
<head>Death and succession</head>
<p>Vytenis died ca. 1315 without an heir. The circumstances surrounding his death are not known. For a long time Russian historians claimed that he was struck by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lightning">lightning</ref>. However, that was a mistake of a Russian scribe: it was an inadequate translation of Teutonic propaganda that Gediminas killed his master Vytenis and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usurper">usurped</ref> his throne.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-el-2">[2]</ref> Vytenis is mentioned for the last time in September 1315 during the unsuccessful <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Christmemel">Siege of Christmemel</ref>, the first castle built by the Teutonic Knights on the right bank of the Neman River. Historians know of only one son of Vytenis, Žvelgutis (<hi rend="italic">Swalegote</hi>), who possibly died before his father.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rowell-1">[1]</ref> Such a situation allowed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gediminas">Gediminas</ref>, brother of Vytenis, to become the Grand Duke of Lithuania. During his reign the Grand Duchy became a major military and political power in the Eastern Europe.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rowell-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
