<text id="autogum_bio_doc704" title="Centurione II Zaccaria" shortTile="centurione-ii-zaccaria" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-31" dateModified="2016-03-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centurione_II_Zaccaria" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Centurione II Zaccaria</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Centurione II Zaccaria</hi> (died 1432), scion of a powerful <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genoa">Genoese</ref> merchant family established in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morea">Morea</ref>, was installed as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince_of_Achaea">Prince of Achaea</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ladislaus_of_Naples">Ladislaus of Naples</ref> in 1404 and was the last ruler of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin_Empire">Latin Empire</ref> not under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_Empire">Byzantine suzerainty</ref>. </p>
<p>Centurione was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andronikos_Asen_Zaccaria">Andronikos Asen Zaccaria</ref> and grandson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centurione_I_Zaccaria">Centurione I Zaccaria</ref>. He succeeded his father in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barony_of_Arkadia">barony of Arkadia</ref> (modern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kyparissia">Kyparissia</ref>) in 1402. Though young, he was ambitious and he overthrew his aunt, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_II_Zaccaria">Maria II Zaccaria</ref>, in Achaea in 1404; a move which was approved by his overlord, the king of Naples. Immediately, he reinforced his power on a local basis by marrying Creusa, the daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonardo_II_Tocco">Leonardo II Tocco</ref>, lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zante">Zante</ref> and niece of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlo_I_Tocco">Carlo I Tocco</ref> whose dominions covered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cephalonia">Cephalonia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lefkada">Lefkada</ref> and extended to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despotate_of_Epirus">Epirus</ref> and the western <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peloponnese">Peloponnese</ref>. Centurione then made his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Zaccaria">Stephen</ref> the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin_Archbishop_of_Patras">Latin Archbishop of Patras</ref>. </p>
<p>However, Centurione was quickly at war with his alienated relatives. His wife's cousin <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlo_I_Tocco">Carlo I Tocco</ref>, duke of Leucas, had Ladislaus absolve him from his feudal obligations to Achaea (1406) and then, allied with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodore_I_Palaiologos">Theodore I Palaiologos</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despot_of_Morea">Despot of Morea</ref>, made war on the principality, conquering <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glarentza">Glarentza</ref> (1408), long the principality's chief seaport. His brother Stephen, however, abandoned the diocese of Patras to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venetian_Republic">Venetians</ref> on loan for five years. Centurione himself was forced to ally with the Venetians and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justinian,_Lord_of_Chios">Justinian, Lord of Chios</ref>, and to hire <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albanians">Albanian</ref> mercenaries to retake the port on 12 July 1414. In return for military protection, he granted the ports of Glarentza and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pylos">Navarino</ref> to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giustiniani">Giustiniani</ref> family of Genoa. </p>
<p>Thereafter, for three years, Centurione could obtain no help from Genoa, pressed by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_of_Milan">Duke of Milan</ref> on land and by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crown_of_Aragon">Crown of Aragon</ref> at sea. In 1417, the imperial army of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref>, led by the despot <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodore_II_Palaeologus">Theodore II Palaeologus</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_VIII_Palaeologus">Emperor John VIII</ref>, invaded Achaea. They took <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Messenia">Messenia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elis">Elis</ref> and holed up Centurione in Glarentza, from which he fled by sea in the spring of 1418. A little later, Patras too fell. Only by the mediation of the Venetians occupying Navarino was the prince able to secure a truce. </p>
<p>All that was left of the principality that once dominated Greece were a few fortresses, such as the ancestral castle and barony of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chalandritsa">Chalandritsa</ref>. In 1429, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Palaeologus">Thomas Palaeologus</ref> of the Morea besieged Centurione in Chalandritsa and extracted a treaty from him whereby his daughter, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_Zaccaria">Catherine</ref>, would marry the despot and thus make him Centurione's heir in Achaea. Centurione was allowed to keep his inheritance, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barony_of_Arcadia">barony of Arcadia</ref> (not to be confused with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arcadia">region of the same name</ref>). Centurione retired to Arcadia in 1430, after the marriage was finalised. He died there two years later. His domains passed to the despotate of Morea and into Byzantine hands.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Centurione left one illegitimate son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Asen_Zaccaria">John Asen Zaccaria</ref>, who was the centre of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morea_revolt_of_1453–1454">later revolts</ref> against Greek authority.</p>
</text>
