<text id="autogum_bio_doc712" title="Fruzhin" shortTile="fruzhin" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-09-10" dateModified="2019-05-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fruzhin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fruzhin</head><hi rend="bold">Warning:</hi> Page using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_royalty">Template:Infobox royalty</ref> with unknown parameter "1 = monarch
" (this message is shown only in preview).
<p><hi rend="bold">Fruzhin</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarian_language">Bulgarian</ref>: Фружин; also transliterated <hi rend="italic">Fružin</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Frujin</hi>; c. 1380s - c. 1460) was a 15th-century <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgaria">Bulgarian</ref> noble who fought actively against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> conquest of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Bulgarian_Empire">Second Bulgarian Empire</ref>. A son of one of the last Bulgarian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tsar">tsars</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Shishman_of_Bulgaria">Ivan Shishman</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Veliko_Tarnovo">Tarnovo</ref> Tsardom, Fruzhin co-organized the so-called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uprising_of_Konstantin_and_Fruzhin">Uprising of Konstantin and Fruzhin</ref> along with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantine_II_of_Bulgaria">Constantine II</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vidin">Vidin</ref>, the last Bulgarian monarchs. Fruzhin was mainly based in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Hungary">Kingdom of Hungary</ref>, where he was the ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Temes_County">Temes County</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bakalov-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Neither Fruzhin's birthdate nor his biography prior to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fall_of_Tarnovo">Fall of Tarnovo</ref> to the Ottomans in 1393 are known, but from his involvement in the 1404 uprising, the former can be narrowed down to the 1380s, the same decade his parents married, and there's no mention of him having been a bastard. He had a brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_(son_of_Ivan_Shishman)">Alexander</ref>, who converted to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islam">Islam</ref> after the Ottoman conquest, adopting the name <hi rend="italic">Iskender</hi> and becoming governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samsun">Samsun</ref> and then <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smyrna">Smyrna</ref>, where he died in 1418. As the capital Tarnovo was captured by the Ottomans, Fruzhin fled initially to the domains of his uncle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Sratsimir_of_Bulgaria">Ivan Sratsimir</ref> at Vidin, in the Bulgarian northwest. He settled in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hungary">Hungary</ref> under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigismund,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Sigismund I</ref> some time after that. Sigismund accepted Fruzhin to his court and recognized his claim to the Bulgarian throne.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bakalov-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecumenical_Patriarch">Ecumenical Patriarch</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_II_of_Constantinople">Joseph II of Constantinople</ref> may also have been an illegitimate half-brother of Fruzhin's.</p>
<figure><caption>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Şoimoş">Şoimoş</ref> castle near modern Lipova, likely the seat of Fruzhin's Hungarian domains</caption></figure>
<p>Probably in 1404, Fruzhin headed an anti-Ottoman revolt in the Bulgarian lands along with his cousin Constantine II, Ivan Sracimir's son and last reigning Bulgarian monarch at Vidin. Despite conflicting historical details regarding the span and size of the revolt, there are hints that Constantine and Fruzhin managed to restore their rule over at least a part of the Bulgarian lands. However, the uprising was crushed (probably in 1413 or 1418) and Fruzhin returned to Hungary.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bakalov-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In 1425, Fruzhin participated in Hungarian service in a joint Hungarian and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wallachia">Wallachian</ref> raid of the cities of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vidin">Vidin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oryahovo">Oryahovo</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silistra">Silistra</ref> on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danube">Danube</ref> along with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dan_II_of_Wallachia">Dan II</ref>. Sigismund rewarded Fruzhin's military service with a noble title, entrusting him with the governance of Temes County and presenting him with a personal domain at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lipova,_Arad">Lippa</ref>. Fruzhin visited the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_of_Ragusa">Republic of Ragusa</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dubrovnik">Dubrovnik</ref>) and the leaders of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albanian_Revolt_of_1432-1436">Albanian revolt</ref> in 1435 as a diplomat of Sigismund.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bakalov-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-akademia-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In 1444, he participated in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Władysław_III_of_Poland">Władysław III of Poland</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crusade_of_Varna">Crusade of Varna</ref>, an attempt to drive the Ottoman Turks away from Bulgaria and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Europe">Europe</ref>. The campaign ended in disaster, as Władysław III died in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Varna">Battle of Varna</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_Sea">Black Sea</ref>, and Fruzhin is not mentioned in any later historical sources.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bakalov-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Fruzhin died in Brașov in 1460.</p>
</text>
