<text id="autogum_bio_doc576" title="Ninot le Petit" shortTile="ninot-le-petit" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-09-15" dateModified="2017-06-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ninot_le_Petit" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ninot le Petit</head><p><hi rend="bold">Ninot le Petit</hi> (also <hi rend="bold">Johannes Parvi</hi>) (fl. ca. 1500 – 1520) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France">French</ref> composer of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renaissance_music">Renaissance</ref>, probably associated with the French royal chapel.  Although a substantial amount of his music has survived in several sources, his actual name is not known with certainty.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Two identifications have been proposed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musicology">musicologists</ref> in the latter half of the 20th century.  The first possibility, suggested by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barton_Hudson">Barton Hudson</ref> in 1979, is that le Petit may have been <hi rend="bold">Johannes Baltazar</hi> alias le Petit, since a singer of that name was in the papal chapel between 1488 and 1502, and his name resembles that in the attribution of some "le Petit" motets in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vatican_City">Vatican</ref> manuscript.  The second possibility is that "le Petit" may be the same as <hi rend="bold">Jean Lepetit,</hi> the singing master at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Langres">Langres</ref> Cathedral between 1506 and 1510.  Baltazar died in 1502, Lepetit after 1529; stylistically the music of le Petit suggests composition in the first two decades of the 16th century.</p>
<head>Music and influence</head>
<p>Le Petit's style is similar to that of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antoine_de_Févin">Antoine de Févin</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Mouton">Jean Mouton</ref>, the two most famous French composers associated with the French royal chapel.  He preferred clear <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harmony">harmonies</ref>, a texture occasionally broken by long <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duet">duets</ref>, and contrasting sections in triple <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meter_(music)">meter</ref>, somewhat blending the styles of Févin and Mouton.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chanson">chansons</ref> are light and open in texture, foreshadowing the developments in the genre later in the century.</p>
<p>Le Petit was listed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Moulu">Pierre Moulu</ref> in his famous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motet">motet</ref> <hi rend="italic">Mater floreat florescat</hi> as one of the leading composers of the day (this work, probably written around 1517, provides to musicologists a particularly useful list of composers working at the time, naming the composers associated with the French royal chapel which Moulu thought the most eloquent of the time).</p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>One <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mass_(music)">mass</ref> by le Petit has survived, as well as four motets and 16 chansons.  Many of his works have also been attributed to others; some, such as <hi rend="italic">Lourdault lourdault garde que tu feras</hi>, are now considered to be reliably the work of others (in that case, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loyset_Compère">Loyset Compère</ref>).  Since one large block of chansons survived in one manuscript, but relatively little sacred music, and yet Moulu listed him as a famous composer, it can be inferred that most of his music has been lost.</p>
<head>Mass</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Missa <hi rend="italic">sine nomine</hi> (mass without a name)</item></list>
<head>Motets</head>
<list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="italic">In illo tempore: Assumpsit Jesus</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">O bone Jesu</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Psallite Noe, Judei credite</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Si oblitus fuero tui</hi> (has also been attributed to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacob_Obrecht">Jacob Obrecht</ref>)</item></list>
<head>Chansons</head>
<p>Many of these are lacking a bass voice part, since the bass part-book has been lost from the manuscript.</p>
<list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="italic">En chevauchant pres d'ung molin</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">En l'ombre d'ung aubepin</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">En revenant de Noyon</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Et la la la, faictez luy bonne chiere</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Et levez vo gambe, Jennette</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Et levez vous hau, Guillemette</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Gentilz gallans adventureulx</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Helas helas helas</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Hellas, hellas, qui me confortera</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Je mi levay l'autre nuytee</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">L'ort villain jaloux</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Mon amy m'avoit promis</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Mon seul plaisir</hi> (a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quodlibet">quodlibet</ref> as well as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ballade_(forme_fixe)">ballade</ref>; has also been attributed to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josquin_des_Prez">Josquin des Prez</ref>);</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">N'as tu poinct mis ton hauls bonnet</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Nostre chamberiere si malade elle est</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Pourtant si mon amy</hi>;</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Si bibero crathere pleno</hi>.</item></list>
</text>
