<text id="autogum_bio_doc631" title="Dafydd ap Gwilym" shortTile="dafydd-ap-gwilym" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2002-04-08" dateModified="2019-08-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dafydd_ap_Gwilym" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Dafydd ap Gwilym</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Dafydd ap Gwilym</hi> (c. 1315/1320 – c. 1350/1370) is regarded as one of the leading <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Welsh_people">Welsh</ref> poets and amongst the great poets of Europe in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middle_Ages">Middle Ages</ref>. (Dafydd ap Gwilym scholar <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/R._Geraint_Gruffydd">R. Geraint Gruffydd</ref> suggests c. 1315-c. 1350 as his dates; other scholars  place him a little later, c. 1320-c. 1370.)</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Tradition has it that he was born at Brogynin, Penrhyn-coch (at the time <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanbadarn_Fawr,_Ceredigion">Llanbadarn Fawr</ref> parish), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ceredigion">Ceredigion</ref>. His father, Gwilym Gam, and mother, Ardudfyl, were both from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nobility">noble</ref> families. As one of noble birth it seems Dafydd did not belong to the guild of professional poets in medieval Wales, and yet the poetic tradition had been strong in his family for generations.</p>
<p>According to R. Geraint Gruffydd he died in 1350, a possible victim of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_Death">Black Death</ref>. Tradition says that he was buried within the precinct of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cistercians">Cistercian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strata_Florida_Abbey">Strata Florida Abbey</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ceredigion">Ceredigion</ref>. This burial location is disputed by supporters of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talley_Abbey">Talley Abbey</ref> theory who contend that burial took place in the Talley Abbey Churchyard:</p>
<p>On Saturday 15 September 1984 a memorial stone was unveiled by a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prifardd">Prifardd</ref> to mark the site in the churchyard at Talley where a deeply-rooted tradition asserts that the poet Dafydd ap Gwilym lies buried. For many centuries the rival claims of Talley and Ystrad Fflur have been debated as the burialplace of Wales’ foremost poet.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Y_Llycha-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>The first recorded observation that Dafydd ap Gwilym was buried in Talley was made in the sixteenth century.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Y_Llycha-1">[1]</ref> Talley is located about 30 miles from Strata Florida (Welsh: Ystrad Fflur).</p>
<head>Poetry</head>
<p>It is believed that about one hundred and seventy of his poems have survived, though many others have been attributed to him over the centuries. His main themes were love and nature. The influence of wider European ideas of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Courtly_love">courtly love</ref>, as exemplified in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Troubadour">troubadour</ref> poetry of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provence">Provençal</ref>, is seen as a significant influence on Dafydd's poetry.</p>
There was in every hollow
A hundred wrymouthed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ignis_fatuus">wisps</ref>.
<p>—Dafydd ap Gwilym (trans. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wirt_Sikes">Wirt Sikes</ref>), 1340.</p>
<p>He was an innovative poet who was responsible for popularising the metre known as the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cywydd">cywydd</ref>" and first to use it for praise. But perhaps his greatest innovation was to make himself the main focus of his poetry. By its very nature, most of the work of the traditional Welsh court poets kept their own personalities far from their poetry, the primary purpose of which was to sing the praises of their patrons. Dafydd's work. in contrast, is full of his own feelings and experiences, and he is a key figure in this transition from a primarily social poetic tradition into one in which the poet's own vision and art is given precedence. </p>
<p>Although Dafydd wrote comparatively conventional praise poetry, he also wrote love poetry and poetry expressing a personal wonderment at nature; Dafydd's poetry on the latter subject in particular is largely without precedent in Welsh or European literature in terms of its depth and complexity. His popularity during his own historic period is testified by the fact that so many of his poems were selected for preservation in texts, despite a relatively short career compared to some of his contemporaries.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Huw-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Many of his poems are addressed to women, but particularly to two of them, Morfudd and Dyddgu. His best-known works include the following poems:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Morfudd fel yr haul</hi> (Morfudd like the sun), a poem to the wife of an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberystwyth">Aberystwyth</ref> merchant who seems to have had a long affair with Dafydd, and whom he addressed in many poems; <ref target="http://cy.wikisource.org/wiki/Morfudd_fel_yr_haul">full text</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Merched Llanbadarn</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Girls_of_Llanbadarn">The girls of Llanbadarn</ref>), in which he speaks of going to church on Sunday purely in order to ogle the local women; <ref target="http://cy.wikisource.org/wiki/Merched_Llanbadarn">full text</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Trafferth mewn tafarn</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trouble_at_a_Tavern">Trouble in a tavern</ref>), in which he recounts an incident in a tavern that would be worthy of any slapstick film; <ref target="http://cy.wikisource.org/wiki/Trafferth_mewn_tafarn">full text</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Yr wylan</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Seagull_(poem)">The seagull</ref>), a poem in which Dafydd asks a seagull to carry a message to his love; <ref target="https://cy.wikisource.org/wiki/Yr_Wylan">full text</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Y Rhugl Groen</hi> (The rattle bag), in which Dafydd's intercourse with a young girl is cruelly interrupted; <ref target="http://cy.wikisource.org/wiki/Y_Rhugl_Groen">full text</ref>; and</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Cywydd y gal</hi> (A poem in praise of the penis), a risqué piece of pure medieval <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erotica">erotica</ref>; <ref target="http://cy.wikisource.org/wiki/Cywydd_y_gal">full text</ref>. Until recently not included in Dafydd's canon for reasons of editorial squeamishness.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></item></list>
<p>According to Charles Johnston's explanatory notes on the Astrée / Naïve CD 'Beethoven: Irish, Welsh &amp; Scottish Songs' (2001), the words to WoO155 '26 wallisische Lieder', Nr.14 'Der Traum' (1810), were "translated from the Welsh of Dafydd ap Gwilym". This would be Dafydd's dream-vision poem 'Y Breuddwyd'.</p>
</text>
