<text id="autogum_bio_doc750" title="Simon Montagu, 1st Baron Montagu" shortTile="simon-montagu-st" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-08-17" dateModified="2019-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_Montagu%2C_1st_Baron_Montagu" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Simon Montagu, 1st Baron Montagu</head>
<figure><caption>Arms of Montagu: <hi rend="italic">Argent, three fusils conjoined in fess gules</hi></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Simon de Montagu, 1st Baron Montagu</hi> (died 1316) (<hi rend="italic">alias</hi> <hi rend="bold">de Montagu, de Montacute</hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Latinized_names">Latinized</ref> to <hi rend="italic">de Monte Acuto</hi> ("from the sharp mountain"), from the French <hi rend="italic">mont aigu</hi>, with identical meaning,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>) was summoned to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament">Parliament</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Writ">writ</ref> and thereby became the 1st <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_Montagu">Baron Montagu</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> He was the ancestor of the great Montagu family, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Salisbury">Earls of Salisbury</ref>.</p>
<head>Origins</head>
<p>His family originated in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Normandy">Normandy</ref>, at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manor">manor</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montaigu-les-Bois">Montaigu-les-Bois</ref>, in the arrondissement of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coutances">Coutances</ref>, which remained in the possession of the family until the death of Sebastien de Montaigu in 1715, without children.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Two persons named Montagu or similar appear in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domesday_Book">Domesday Book</ref> of 1086: Ansger and Drogo de Montaigu, both richly endowed with lands, but Ansger died leaving no heir.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> Drogo's lands were in Somerset, where two of the manors he held in 1086, namely Sutton Montagu and Shipton Montagu, his seat, still retain his name.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> According to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wilhelmina,_Duchess_of_Cleveland">Duchess of Cleveland</ref> (1889): "He had come to England in the train of the Earl of Mortain, and received from him large grants of lands, with the custody of the castle, built either by the Earl or his son William, in the manor of Bishopston, and styled, from its position on a sharp-topped hill, Monte Acuto". (This latter statement seems to forget that the family name derived from the manor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montaigu-les-Bois">Montaigu-les-Bois</ref> in Normandy, not from the shape of the supposed hill in Bishopston, England) In 1211 Drogo's  grandson Drogo II de Montagu certified that he held ten and a half <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knight's_fees">knight's fees</ref> in the Western counties.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was son of William de Montacute and Bertha, his wife. Simon first appears during King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_I_of_England">Edward I of England</ref>'s great campaign in 1277 against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llywelyn_ap_Gruffudd">Llywelyn ap Gruffudd</ref> in Wales. In 1282 he served in a similar campaign in Wales, when Edward finally crushed Llywelyn, and during the autumn attended the king at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhuddlan_Castle">Rhuddlan</ref>. Simon was summoned to the parliament which met on 30 September 1283 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shrewsbury">Shrewsbury</ref> for the trial of Llywelyn's brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dafydd_ap_Gruffydd">Dafydd ap Gruffydd</ref>. In 1290 he was apparently confirmed in the possession of Shipton Montacute, Somerset and received additional grants in Dorset Devonshire, Buckinghamshire, and Oxfordshire. On 14 June 1294 he was summoned to meet the king at Portsmouth on 1 September and accompany him to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gascony">Gascony</ref>, but his services were apparently for the time dispensed with. In 1296, however, he was in command of a vessel, and by his bravery broke through the French fleet blockading <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bordeaux">Bordeaux</ref> and revictualled the town, which caused the siege to be raised. Simon remained in Gascony until 1297.</p>
<p>In March 1298 a truce was made with France, and in May, he was summoned as a baron to an assembly of the lay estates at York; on 26 September he was summoned to serve in the war with Scotland, and again in August and December 1299. In 1299 he was made governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corfe_Castle">Corfe Castle</ref>, Dorset. He attended parliament over the next two years and served in the Scottish war. He was a signatory in 1301 of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barons'_Letter_of_1301">Barons' Letter</ref>, as 'Simon dominus de Monte Acuto'. In 1304 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aufrica_de_Connoght">Aufrica de Connoght</ref>, as an alleged heiress of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnús_Óláfsson">Magnús Óláfsson, King of Mann and the Isles</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quitclaim">quitclaimed</ref> these claimed rights to Simon.</p>
<p>In 1306, for his services in Scotland and elsewhere, he was pardoned a debt of 120/. which his father had owed to the exchequer. On 5 April he was asked for an aid on the occasion of the knighting of Prince Edward, at which he was present, and was serving in the Scottish wars until Edward's death on 7 July 1307. He was summoned to attend parliament at the coronation of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_II_of_England">Edward II of England</ref> and in 1308 was made governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beaumaris_Castle">Beaumaris Castle</ref>, Anglesey. Simon served in 1308-1309 against the Scots, and was also appointed justice to try persons guilty of forestalling in London. In 1310 he was constituted Admiral of the Fleet employed against the Scots; and from 1313 was in constant attendance in parliament and in the Scottish war. Simon sought to seize control of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isle_of_Man">Mann</ref>, and in so doing incurred the wrath of Edward II, who pardoned Simon for his actions against the island in 1313. He was stationed in the north to watch the Scottish frontier during the winter campaign of 1315-16, and was summoned to the parliament of Lincoln in January 1316. He died in 1316.  His final resting place is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bisham_Abbey">Bisham Priory</ref></p>
<head>Marriages and children</head>
<p>Montagu married twice: firstly to Hawise de St Amand (died 1287), daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amaury_de_St_Amand">Amaury de St Amand</ref>; and secondly to Isabel, whose parentage is unknown.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>He had three sons, by which wife is unknown. His eldest son and heir was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Montagu,_2nd_Baron_Montagu">William Montagu, 2nd Baron Montagu</ref> (c. 1285 – 18 October 1319). His other sons were named John and Simon.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-IPM-8">[8]</ref></p>
</text>
