<text id="autogum_bio_doc796" title="Roger de Beaufeu" shortTile="roger-de-beaufeu" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-02-07" dateModified="2018-09-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_de_Beaufeu" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Roger de Beaufeu</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Roger de Beaufeu or Bello Fago</hi> (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floruit">fl</ref></hi>. 1297-1308), judge, was probably of the same family as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_de_Beaufo">Nicholas de Beaufo</ref> of Beaufo's Manor, Norfolk, a contemporary of the judge.</p>
<head>Name and records</head>
<p>One <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radulphus_de_Bello_Fago">Radulphus de Bello Fago</ref> or Bella Fago (both genders are found, though the masculine predominates) is mentioned in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domesday_Book">Domesday Book</ref> as holding extensive estates in Norfolk, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Thetford">bishop of Thetford</ref> also there mentioned we know from other sources to have been <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_de_Beaufo">William de Beaufo</ref>, called by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Godwin">Godwin</ref> inaccurately Galsagus,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> and by others still more corruptly Welson. It may be mentioned in  passing that many other varieties of the name are found, such as Belfagus, Beaufou, Beaufogh, Beaufour, Belflour, Beufo, Beufew, and, in the eighteenth century, Beaufoy. How the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Thetford">bishop of Thetford</ref> stood related to Radulphus de Bello Fago we do not certainly know.
Of Ralph nothing more is known than has already been stated, while of William we know little more than the dates of his appointment to the see of Thetford and his death. That Roger de Beaufo was a lineal descendant of either Ralph or William de Bello Fago cannot be affirmed, nor can his relation to his contemporary Nicholas de Beaufo, of Beaufo's manor, be precisely determined, and we cannot connect him with Norfolk, all the estates which he is known to have possessed being situate in Berkshire and Oxfordshire; but the singularity of the name renders it highly probable that he was derived from the same original stock as the Norfolk family.</p>
<p>The earliest mention of him occurs in the roll of parliament for 1305, when he was assigned with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_de_Mortimer">William de Mortimer</ref> and others as receiver of petitions from Ireland and Guernsey, with power to answer all such as might not require the attention of the king.</p>
<p>In the same year he received, with the same William de Mortimer, a special commission to try an action of "novel disseisin" — i.e. ejectment — brought by one <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Pecche">John Pecche</ref> against the abbot of Westminster for the recovery of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Messuage">messuage</ref> and one <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carucate">carucate</ref> of land in Warwickshire. From the writ it appears that the ordinary justices itinerant for that county were behind with their business, and it would seem that Mortimer and Beaufo were appointed "justices of assize" for that occasion only. In the same year and that following he travelled the large western circuit of that day, which stretched from Cornwall to Southampton in one direction, and Staffordshire and Shropshire in another, as one of the first commission of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trailbaston">trailbaston</ref> issued for those counties. The popular odium which he excited, and of which the memory is preserved by a line, "Spigurnel e Belflour sunt gens de cruelté", in a ballad of the time celebrating the doings of the commission, proves him to have displayed exceptional vigour in the performance of his duty. In a writ of uncertain date he is joined with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_de_Bereford">William de Bereford</ref> and two other judges in a commission to inquire into the obstruction of the Thames between London and Oxford by weirs, locks, and mills, which was considered so serious a grievance by the merchants who were in the habit of travelling or sending goods by water between the two towns, that they had petitioned the king for its redress.</p>
<p>We find him summoned with the other judges to parliament at Northampton by Edward II in 1307, and to attend the coronation of that monarch in 1308. He was not summoned to parliament after that year. He is classed as a tenant of land or rents to the value of £20 or upwards in Berkshire and Oxfordshire in a writ of summons to muster at London for service overseas issued in 1297; in 1301 he was included in the list of those summoned to attend the king at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berwick-on-Tweed">Berwick-on-Tweed</ref> with horses and arms for the invasion of Scotland, as one of the contingents to be furnished by the counties of Bedford and Buckingham. From a grant enrolled in the King's Bench we know that he possessed land at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Multon">Great Multon</ref>, in Oxfordshire, and from the record of an assize of "novel disseisin" preserved in the rolls of the same court it appears that his daughter Isabella acquired by marriage a title to an estate in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Little_Bereford">Little Bereford</ref> in the same county, which a subsequent divorce and remarriage was held not to divest. Later on, one <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humfrey_Beaufo">Humfrey Beaufo</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bereford_St._John">Bereford St. John</ref>, Oxfordshire, is mentioned by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dugdale">Dugdale</ref> as having married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_Hugford">Joan Hugford</ref>, whereby the manors of Edmondscote or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emscote">Emscote</ref> in Warwickshire, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whilton">Whilton</ref> in Northamptonshire, passed into his family in the reign of Henry VII. From him descended the Beaufos or Beaufoys of Edmondscote and Whilton.</p>
<p>The manor of Whilton was sold in 1619 by the then lord, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Beaufo">Henry Beaufo</ref>, mentioned by Dugdale as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_of_the_manor">lord of the manor</ref> of Edmondscote in 1640. His daughter, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martha_Beaufoy">Martha Beaufoy</ref>, married Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Garth">Samuel Garth</ref>, the author of the "Dispensary", and their daughter Martha, who inherited the estates, married, in 1711, William Boyle, grandson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Boyle,_1st_Earl_of_Orrery">Roger</ref>, the first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Orrery">earl of Orrery</ref>.</p>
<head>Attribution</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>This article incorporates text from a publication now in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_domain">public domain</ref>:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_McMullen_Rigg">James McMullen Rigg</ref> (1885). "<ref target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Beaufeu,%20Roger%20de%20(DNB00)">Beaufeu, Roger de</ref>".  In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leslie_Stephen">Stephen, Leslie</ref> (ed.). <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dictionary_of_National_Biography">Dictionary of National Biography</ref></hi>. <hi rend="bold">04</hi>. London: Smith, Elder &amp; Co. pp.36–37. Endnotes:
<list type="unordered"><item>Godwin, De Præsul. 426, 731</item>
<item>Dugdale's Monasticon, iii. 216</item>
<item>Blomefield's Norfolk, i. 200, 404, ii. 465</item>
<item>Rot. Parliamentary. i. 168 <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, 218 <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, 475 <hi rend="italic">b</hi></item>
<item>Rymer (ed. Clarke), i 970</item>
<item>Wright's Political Songs (Camden Society), 233</item>
<item>Parliamentary Writs, i. 155, 291, 353, 408, ii. div. ii. part i. 3, 17, 18, 21, 23</item>
<item>Plac. Abbrev. 214, 299</item>
<item>Dugdale's Ant. Warwickshire, 189</item>
<item>Baker's Hist. Northamptonshire, i. 232</item>
<item>Domesday Book, fols. 190 <hi rend="italic">b</hi>-201 <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, 225 <hi rend="italic">b</hi>-229 <hi rend="italic">b</hi></item>
<item>Coll. Top. et Genesis viii. 361</item>
<item>Foss's Judges of England.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
