<text id="autogum_bio_doc538" title="Helena Kantakouzene, Empress of Trebizond" shortTile="helena-kantakouzene" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-07-09" dateModified="2019-10-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helena_Kantakouzene%2C_Empress_of_Trebizond" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Helena Kantakouzene, Empress of Trebizond</head><figure><caption>Helena buries the corpse of her husband, David Megas Komnenos. (From Ludwig Storch, "Die Kaiserin von Trapezunt", <hi rend="italic">Die Gartenlaube</hi>, 1855)</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Helena Kantakouzene</hi> (died 1463) was the second wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_of_Trebizond">David of Trebizond</ref>, the last <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Empire_of_Trebizond">Emperor of Trebizond</ref>. Recent research has led to doubts regarding her existence.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Donald Nicol has argued that Helena was the sister of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Palaiologos_Kantakouzenos">George Palaiologos Kantakouzenos</ref>, and thus the granddaughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_Kantakouzenos">Matthew Kantakouzenos</ref> and possibly the daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodore_Kantakouzenos">Theodore Kantakouzenos</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodore_Spandounes">Theodore Spandounes</ref> reports that George visited her in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trabzon">Trebizond</ref> after 1437.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>It is unclear which of David's children were also hers; his five children—three boys and two daughters—have been attributed variously to Helena or David's first wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_of_Gothia">Maria of Gothia</ref> by various genealogies. Nevertheless, the oldest sons died with their father 1 November 1463; the youngest son, George, who was three years old, and the daughter Anna were spared. Spandounes states they were sent as a present to Sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uzun_Hassan">Uzun Hassan</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aq_Qoyunlu">Aq Qoyunlu</ref>, where George was converted to Islam, but he eventually escaped and abjured to Christianity.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Spandounes says the name of the king who sheltered George Kantakouzene and gave him his daughter in marriage was named "Gurguiabei", which has been interpreted as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Georgia">king of Georgia</ref> (and either <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_VIII_of_Georgia">George VIII</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantine_II_of_Georgia">Constantine II</ref>), or "Guria Bey", ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principality_of_Guria">Guria</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> Anna's fate is less clear. The historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laonikos_Chalkokondyles">Laonikos Chalkokondyles</ref> contradicts Spandounes, writing that after being "summoned to his bedchamber", Anna was married to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zagan_Pasha">Zagan Pasha</ref>; however, when he learned Zagan attempted to force her to become a Muslim, Mehmet separated them.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> A local tradition connects Anna to a village south of Trabizon called "Lady Village", where in 1870 an inscription bearing Anna's name was seen in the village church dedicated to the Archangels.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Empress</head>
<p>On 15 August 1461, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mehmed_II">Mehmed II</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman Empire</ref> forced Emperor David to surrender his throne in return for a pension. David and his family were settled on estates near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serres">Serres</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Struma_(river)">Struma</ref> valley, comprising an annual income of some 300,000 pieces of silver. Although Helena presumably was with him, Donald Nicol mentions a source which states David had sent her to refuge with the Georgian prince <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mamia_Gurieli">Mamia</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principality_of_Guria">Guria</ref> prior to Mehmed's arrival before the walls of Trebizond.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> After two years, his former retainer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Amiroutzes">George Amiroutzes</ref> accused David of conspiring against Mehmed, and the former emperor was executed with all but one of his sons.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Runciman-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>According to Spandounes, Helena survived her husband and sons. The Sultan reportedly had ordered their corpses to be left exposed outside the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walls_of_Constantinople">Walls of Constantinople</ref>. When she dug the graves with her own hands and buried them, she was condemned to pay a fine of 15,000 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ducat">ducats</ref> or be executed herself. Her retainers raised the money, but Helena dressed in sackcloth and lived out her days in a straw hut near the corpses of her dead family.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Runciman-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Historicity</head>
<p>The historian Thierry Ganchou advanced the theory that Helena had not actually existed, being instead the result of the confusion between David's mother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodora_Kantakouzene_(wife_of_Alexios_IV_of_Trebizond)">Theodora Kantakouzene</ref> and his wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_of_Gothia">Maria of Gothia</ref> by the historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodore_Spandounes">Theodore Spandounes</ref>. Ganchou refers to the historical writings of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angelo_Massarelli">Angelo Massarelli</ref>, the Papal Secretary to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council_of_Trent">Council of Trent</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-BrookP5-9">[9]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[lower-alpha 1]</ref> which state that Theodora was the daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodore_Kantakouzenos">Theodore Kantakouzenos</ref>. This identification is also reinforced by the historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Sphrantzes">George Sphrantzes</ref>, who refers to Theodora's other son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_IV_of_Trebizond">John IV</ref> as a cousin to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mara_Branković">Mara Branković</ref>, herself a granddaughter of Theodore. However, as Theodore is also commonly identified as the father of Helena, this would result in the extremely unlikely scenario where Helena had married her own nephew. In addition to this, given that Theodore had died in 1410, Helena would have been at least fifty years old at the birth of her youngest child. This birth year would also have required that David's first wife Maria, whom he had married either in 1426 or 1429, die very quickly afterwards in order for Helena to have still been young enough to be available for marriage.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-GanchouP215-229-11">[10]</ref></p>
<p>Given that the only contemporary source which mentions Helena is Spandounes, Ganchou posits that these discrepancies can be explained by the fact that Spandounes had unintentionally invented her. Ganchou believes that Spandounes (who was a descendant of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kantakouzenos">Kantakouzenos</ref>) was aware that a member of the house had married an emperor of Trebizond, but that he had not known her name, nor that of the emperor. This would be similar to his contemporary Hugues Busac, another relative of the family, who had also mentioned the marriage but had failed to clarify their identities. It may be that Spandounes had assumed that the emperor in question was the final ruler of the kingdom and then, given that the name Helena appears frequently among the Kantakouzenos, assigned it to the unnamed wife. This was something that the historian had done elsewhere in his works, when he mistakenly also referred to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irene_Kantakouzene">Irene of Serbia</ref>, another daughter of Theodore, as Helena. Ganchou then concludes that since there is no known death date for Maria of Gothia, it may have been her who had outlived David and performed the famous burial.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-GanchouP215-229-11">[10]</ref></p>
</text>
