<text id="autogum_bio_doc671" title="Půta III of Častolovice" shortTile="puta-iii-castolovice" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-04-16" dateModified="2018-05-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P%C5%AFta_III_of_%C4%8Castolovice" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Půta III of Častolovice</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Půta III of Častolovice</hi> (also known as <hi rend="italic">Puota the Younger of Czastolowitz</hi>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_language">Czech</ref>: <hi lang="cs" rend="italic">Půta III. z Častolovic</hi> or <hi lang="cs" rend="italic">Půta mladší z Častolovic</hi>; d. 1434 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pressburg">Pressburg</ref>) was a member of the Bohemian Častolowitz family.  He was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landeshauptmann">Landeshauptmann</ref> and later pledge lord of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Kladsko">County of Kladsko</ref> and the Duchies of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ząbkowice_Śląskie">Ząbkowice Śląskie</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Münsterberg_(Ziębice)">Münsterberg</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>His parents were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Půta_II_of_Častolovice">Půta II of Častolovice</ref> and Anna, a daughter of Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_II_of_Oświęcim">Jan II of Oświęcim</ref>.  Like his father, he owned the Lordship of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Častolovice">Častolovice</ref> and other territories in eastern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bohemia">Bohemia</ref>.</p>
<p>Půta was initially a supporter of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hussites">Hussites</ref>, but soon turned into one of their fiercest opponents.  Probably because of the zeal he distinguished himself with in this war, King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigismund,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Sigismund</ref> of Bohemia appointed him in 1422 as royal governor of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Kladsko">County of Kladsko</ref> and the district of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ząbkowice_Śląskie">Ząbkowice Śląskie</ref>.  In 1424, Půta concluded an alliance with Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_I_of_Münsterberg">John I of Münsterberg</ref> against the Hussites.  This was probably the reason why the Hussites attacked Kladsko and Silesia in December 1425.  In 1426, Sigismund sold the mint right in Kladsko to Půta.  In 1427, Půta fought with a Silesian army in eastern Bohemia against the Hussites.  In 1428, Půta fought in the battle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stary_Wielisław">Stary Wielisław</ref>, where Duke John I was killed.  Münsterberg fell as a completed fief to King Sigismund, who mortgaged it to Půta on 13 August 1429.  In 1431, he also mortgaged the County of Kladsko and the district of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ząbkowice_Śląskie">Ząbkowice Śląskie</ref> to him. In 1434, he enfeoffed him with the Duchy of Münsterberg.</p>
<p>Půta carried out several diplomatic missions for King Sigismund.  Shortly before his death, he accompanied envoys from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council_of_Basel">Council of Basel</ref> to Sigismund's court.</p>
<p>Půta's political aim was to create a territory for his family on both sides of the border between Silesia and eastern Bohemia.  In 1396, he married Anna of Koldice (d. 1467), a daughter of governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_of_Koldice">Albert</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Jawor">Duchy of Jawor</ref>.  This marriage created favourable conditions for his goal.</p>
<p>Půta III died in 1434 without a male heir.  He left three underage daughters:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Anna, married in 1446 to Ulrich of Zajíc of Hasenburg</item>
<item>Catherine (d. before 1467), married:
<list type="ordered"><item>in 1441 or 1442 to Heralt II of Líšničtí, a member of the noble Kunštát family<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></item>
<item>in 1447 to John Zajíc of Hasenburg, who after Catherine's death remarried to a daughter of Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslaus_II,_Duke_of_Opava">Wencelaus II</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></item></list></item>
<item>Salome (d. 1489), married around 1442 to Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William,_Duke_of_Opava">William, Duke of Opava</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Opava">Opava</ref>, a nephew of Duke John I</item></list>
<p>Půta's widow Anna, who held the mortgage bonds for Kladsko, Ząbkowice Śląskie and Münsterberg, administered her estates together with governor Marquard Ahrlik of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Międzylesie">Międzylesie</ref>.  After negotiating with several interested parties, she sold her possessions to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hynek_Krušina_of_Lichtenburg">Hynek Krušina of Lichtenburg</ref>, who also took over her burdensome debts and the obligation to raise her daughters in style.  Three weeks later, he married her.</p>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
