<text id="autogum_bio_doc490" title="Tadhg O Cianáin" shortTile="tadhg-o-cianain" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-06-09" dateModified="2019-08-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tadhg_O_Cian%C3%A1in" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tadhg O Cianáin</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Tadhg Óg Ó Cianáin</hi> (IPA:/taɪɡ ɔːɡ oʊ 'kɪə·nan/)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[Note 1]</ref> (died <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circa">c.</ref></hi> 1614) was an Irish writer.</p>
<p>He was the author of <hi rend="italic">Turas na dTaoiseach/the Departure of the Lords</hi>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diary">diary</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flight_of_the_Earls">Flight of the Earls</ref>, kept from September 1607 to November 1608, from Rathmullen, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_Donegal">County Donegal</ref> to Rome. It is the earliest example in Irish of the diary genre. </p>
<head>Origins</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ó_Cianáin">Ó Cianáin</ref> was a member of a professional Irish learned family who were originally <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erenagh">erenaghs</ref> of the parish of Cleenish, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lough_Erne">Lough Erne</ref>, but who had served for several centuries as historians to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maguire_(surname)">Mag Uidir</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fermanagh">Fear Manach</ref> (2007, p.437).</p>
<p>One of the family's most noted productions was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leabhar_Adhamh_Ó_Cianáin">Leabhar Adhamh Ó Cianáin</ref>, written in or about the 1340s by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adhamh_Ó_Cianáin">Adhamh Ó Cianáin</ref> (died 1373) by and for himself, and out of the book of his teacher, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seán_Mór_Ó_Dubhagáin">Seán Mór Ó Dubhagáin</ref> (died 1372). The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Annals_of_the_Four_Masters">Annals of the Four Masters</ref> cite the deaths of members of the family under the years 1387, 1400, 1405, 1459, 1569, 1483.</p>
<p>Tadhg had at least one sibling, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cu_Chonnacht_Ó_Cianáin">Cu Chonnacht Ó Cianáin</ref>, (died 1615), a rymer or chronicler to Rory Maguire.</p>
<head>In the service of Ó Néill</head>
<p>Ó Cianáin appears to have entered the service of Ó Néill during the course of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nine_Years'_War_(Ireland)">Nine Years' War</ref>; he was one of seven of the surname located in the townland of Portnelligan, Tynan parish, south-west of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armagh">Armagh</ref> pardoned on 6 December 1602 (2007, p.20).</p>
<p>Ó Muraíle relates Ó Fiaich's suggestion that <hi rend="italic">"<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_Ó_Neill,_2nd_Earl_of_Tyrone">Hugh O Neill</ref> had granted them land in Co. Armagh, since it was not the Ó Cianáins' native country. Against that, however, there is a townland called Drumadd, north of Portnelligan and close to Armagh city, whose Irish name is Dromad Uí Cianáin. In addition, it may be noted that one of Co. Armagh's principal surnames in 1659 was O Keenan."</hi> (2007, p.21).</p>
<head>Turas na dTaoiseach</head>
<p>Brady and Cleave made the following assessment:</p>
<p>Tadhg kept a detailed account of the flight from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulster">Ulster</ref> and the journey to Rome, not on a high level of political reason and plans, but a plain man's view of what actually happened each day, what they ate and did, how they felt, what the various towns they passed through were like, culminating with their arrival in Rome and the subsequent arrival there of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_of_France">king of France</ref>.</p>
<p>The miraculous survival of Tadhg's unique manuscript-copy (MS A 21 Ó Cléirigh collection, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_College_Dublin">University College Dublin</ref>). Tadhg in his immediate pre-flight year a resident of Portnelligan, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tynan">Tynan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_Armagh">County Armagh</ref>, listed with six other Ó Cianáins as among the follower of Henry Óg Ó Neill in a pardon list 'fiant' of December 1602 (Cú Chonnacht, Seán mac Conchobhair, Pádraig Óg, Uaithne, Seán mac Pádraig Mhóir). Tadhg's property—fifteen cows, eight calves, one garron, one hackeny, twenty-five swine, all valued at £22.6s.3d—were forfeited but later returned to his wife at the intervention of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Thomond">Earl of Thomond</ref>, who was a relative of hers.</p>
<p>Tadhg died in Rome, apparently late in 1614. He was a brother to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cu_Chonnacht_Ó_Cianáin">Cu Chonnacht Ó Cianáin</ref>.</p>
<head>Relatives in Ireland</head>
<p>In the aftermath of the departure, Ó Cianáin's property, valued at £22 6 shillings 2 pence, was seized, but later returned to his wife at the behest of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donogh_O'Brien,_4th_Earl_of_Thomond">Donogh O'Brien, 4th Earl of Thomond</ref>. Thomond claimed to be a relative of Ó Cianáin's wife, possibly via the mysterious Donnchadh mac Mathgamhain Ó Briain who travelled with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rory_Ó_Donnell,_1st_Earl_of_Tyrconnell">Rory Ó Donnell, 1st Earl of Tyrconnell</ref>. No further information is available on his children, if he had any.</p>
<p>His brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cu_Chonnacht_Ó_Cianáin">Cu Chonnacht Ó Cianáin</ref>, was tortured on the rack and hanged in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Derry">Derry</ref> in July 1615.</p>
<head>Other works</head>
<p>On 28 March 1627, while collecting materials for what would become the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Annals_of_the_Four_Masters">Annals of the Four Masters</ref>,</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mícheál_Ó_Cléirigh">Mícheál Ó Cléirigh</ref> made use of some <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hagiographical">hagiographical</ref> material written by him, since lost. (Walsh, 1996). Ó Muraíle (2007, p.22) identifies this text as <hi rend="italic">Ionnarba Mochuda a Rathain</hi> (<hi rend="italic">The Banishment of St Mochuda from Rahan</hi>)—see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mo_Chutu_of_Lismore">Mo Chutu of Lismore</ref>. The original manuscript does not appear to have survived.</p>
</text>
