<text id="autogum_bio_doc597" title="Arthur Plantagenet, 1st Viscount Lisle" shortTile="arthur-plantagenet" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2004-09-13" dateModified="2019-10-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Plantagenet%2C_1st_Viscount_Lisle" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Arthur Plantagenet, 1st Viscount Lisle</head>
<figure><caption>Arms of Arthur Plantagenet before his first marriage. They are his paternal arms, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baton_sinister">baton sinister</ref> azure for bastardy, of Edward, 4th Duke of York, Later King Edward IV: Quarterly 1st: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_arms_of_England">Arms of King Edward III</ref>; 2nd &amp; 3rd: <hi rend="italic">Or a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross">cross</ref> gules</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_de_Burgh,_4th_Countess_of_Ulster">de Burgh</ref>), 4th: <hi rend="italic">Barry or and azure, on a chief of the first two pallets between two base esquires of the second over all an inescutcheon argent</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_de_Mortimer,_4th_Earl_of_March">Mortimer</ref>)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[lower-alpha 1]</ref></caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Arms of Arthur Plantagenet, Viscount Lisle, KG, after his first marriage. From a manuscript in the collection of the Society of Antiquaries, London.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[lower-alpha 2]</ref></caption></figure>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garter_stall_plate">Garter stall plate</ref> of Arthur Plantagenet, 1st Viscount Lisle, KG, nominated to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Order_of_the_Garter">Order of the Garter</ref> in 1542</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Arthur Plantagenet, 1st Viscount Lisle</hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Order_of_the_Garter">KG</ref> (died 3 March 1542) was an illegitimate son of the English king <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_IV">Edward IV</ref>, half-brother-in-law of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VII_of_England">Henry VII</ref>, and an uncle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VIII">Henry VIII</ref>, at whose court he was a prominent figure and by whom he was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Deputy_of_Calais">Lord Deputy of Calais</ref> (1533–40).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[7]</ref> The survival of a large collection of his correspondence in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisle_Letters">Lisle Letters</ref> makes his life one of the best-documented of his era.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Arthur Plantagenet was born between 1461 and 1475 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calais">Calais</ref>, which was then an English possession in France. He died at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tower_of_London">Tower of London</ref>, where he is buried. The identity of his mother is uncertain; the most likely candidate appears to be the "wanton wench" Elizabeth Wayte, although the historical record is spotty on this issue, and it is not entirely clear that Wayte is distinct from another of Edward's mistresses, Dame <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_Lucy">Elizabeth Lucy</ref>. Another possible candidate is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jane_Shore">Elizabeth Shore</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[8]</ref> His godfather was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_FitzAlan,_16th_Earl_of_Arundel">William FitzAlan, 16th Earl of Arundel</ref>.</p>
<p>He spent his childhood at the court of his father Edward IV. How he passed his youth after his father's death in 1483 is not known. In 1501 he joined the household of his half-sister, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_consort">queen consort</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_of_York">Elizabeth of York</ref>, and moved to the household of Henry VII after her death in 1503. After the accession of his nephew Henry VIII in 1509, he was formally designated an Esquire of the King's Bodyguard and was a close companion of Henry's (despite the age difference).</p>
<p>In 1514 he was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_Sheriff_of_Hampshire">High Sheriff of Hampshire</ref> and made captain of the Vice-Admiral's ship <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HMS_Trinity_Sovereign_(1488)">Trinity Sovereign</ref>,</hi> rising to become <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vice-Admiral_of_England">Vice-Admiral of England</ref>. In 1519 he and his wife, Elizabeth Grey Baroness Lisle, took possession of the lands that had belonged to her father (her brother and niece having both died). In 1520, he attended his nephew, King Henry VIII, at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Field_of_Cloth_of_Gold">Field of Cloth of Gold</ref>.</p>
<p>On 25 April 1523, Arthur Plantagenet was created <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viscount_Lisle">Viscount Lisle</ref>. He was also selected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privy_Councilor">Privy Councilor</ref>, Governor of Calais, and Lord Warden of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cinque_Ports">Cinque Ports</ref> and named as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constable_of_Calais">Constable of Calais</ref> after the death of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Bourchier,_2nd_Baron_Berners">John Bourchier, 2nd Baron Berners</ref> on 16 March 1533.</p>
<head>Constable of Calais</head>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisle_Letters">Lisle Letters</ref> suggest that as Constable he was honest and conscientious but not especially competent. Among the letters is one from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Cromwell">Thomas Cromwell</ref> rebuking him for referring trivial matters back to the king and Council, criticising him for his inability to refuse a favour to anyone who asks for one, and hinting that Lady Lisle's dominant  influence over  him has made him something of a laughing stock. Yet the Crown  itself did not hesitate to employ him on routine errands: in 1537 Queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jane_Seymour">Jane Seymour</ref> during her pregnancy developed a passion for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_Quail">quail</ref>, and since quail were abundant in the marshes around Calais, Lisle  had to devote much time to supplying them to the Queen.</p>
<head>Imprisonment and death</head>
<p>In 1540 several members of the Plantagenet household in Calais were arrested on suspicion of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treason">treason</ref>, on the charge of plotting to betray the town to the French. Suspicion unavoidably fell upon Arthur as well, and he was recalled to England and eventually arrested on 19 May 1540.</p>
<p>The actual conspirators were executed, but there was no evidence connecting Arthur with the plot. Nevertheless, he languished in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tower_of_London">Tower of London</ref> for two years until the king decided to release him. However, upon receiving news that he was to be released he suffered a heart attack and died two days later. The 18th-century historian Francis Sanford commented "Henry VIII's Mercy was as fatal as his Judgments".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESt._Clare_Byrne1983410-11">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Lisle Letters</head>
<p>During his time at Calais, Arthur and his wife had to manage much of their affairs outside Calais by correspondence. Copies of 3,000 of these letters were seized as evidence after Arthur was arrested. They survive in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_Record_Office">Public Record Office</ref>, and were published in abridged form as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisle_Letters">Lisle Letters</ref>, becoming a valuable historical resource for a critical period in English history.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Marriages and children</head>
<p>Arthur Plantagenet married twice, producing children by his first wife only.</p>
<p>His first marriage was on 12 November 1511 to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_Grey,_6th_Baroness_Lisle">Elizabeth Grey</ref> (died 1529), daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viscount_Lisle">Edward Grey, 1st Viscount Lisle</ref> (died 1492). She was the widow of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edmund_Dudley">Edmund Dudley</ref>, treasurer to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VII_of_England">King Henry VII</ref>, who had been executed in 1510 by Henry VIII.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTECommireKlezmer1999529-13">[11]</ref> The next day the king granted Arthur some of the Dudley estates which had come to the crown due to Dudley's attainder. By Elizabeth he had three daughters:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTECommireKlezmer1999529-13">[11]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Frances, who married twice: firstly to her step-brother John Basset (1520–1541)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[12]</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Umberleigh">Umberleigh</ref>, Devon, the son of Arthur's second wife by her first marriage, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honor_Plantagenet,_Viscountess_Lisle">Honor Grenville</ref> (died 1566); secondly Frances married Thomas Monke (c. 1515 – c. 1583)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-V569-15">[13]</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Potheridge">Potheridge</ref>, Devon, of an ancient Devonshire family. Her great-grandson by this marriage was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Monck,_1st_Duke_of_Albemarle">George Monck, 1st Duke of Albemarle</ref> (1608–1670).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-V569-15">[13]</ref></item>
<item>Elizabeth, who married Sir Francis Jobson, Member of Parliament for Colchester<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[14]</ref></item>
<item>Bridget, who married William Carden [Cawarden] <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[15]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[16]</ref></item></list>
<p>Secondly, in 1529 as her second husband, he married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honor_Plantagenet,_Viscountess_Lisle">Honor Grenville</ref> (1493–1566) the daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Grenville_(died_1513)">Sir Thomas Grenville</ref> (died 1513) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stowe_House,_Kilkhampton">Stowe</ref> in the parish of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kilkhampton">Kilkhampton</ref>, Cornwall, by his wife Isabella Gilbert. She was the widow of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_John_Bassett">Sir John Bassett</ref> (died 1528) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Umberleigh">Umberleigh</ref>, Devon. Arthur had no children by Honor, but he helped to bring up her children, including John Basset, who became the husband of his daughter Frances from his first marriage; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_Bassett">Anne Bassett</ref>, an alleged mistress of Henry VIII, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_Bassett_(maid-of-honour)">Elizabeth Bassett</ref>, a royal maid-of-honour also known as Mary Bassett.</p>
</text>
