<text id="autogum_bio_doc445" title="David Pole (bishop)" shortTile="david-pole-bishop" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-10-05" dateModified="2018-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Pole_%28bishop%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>David Pole (bishop)</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">David Pole</hi> (or <hi rend="bold">Poole</hi>) (died 1568) was an English Roman Catholic churchman and jurist; he was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Peterborough">bishop of Peterborough</ref> from 1557 until deprived by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I_of_England">Queen Elizabeth I</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was a fellow of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All_Souls'_College,_Oxford">All Souls' College, Oxford</ref>, in 1520. He devoted himself to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil_law_(common_law)">civil law</ref>, and graduated B.Can.L. on 2 July 1526 and D.Can.L. on 17 February 1527 – 1528. In 1529 he became an advocate in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctors'_Commons">Doctors' Commons</ref>. He was connected with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Lichfield">diocese of Lichfield</ref>, where he held preferments, first under Bishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geoffrey_Blyth">Geoffrey Blyth</ref>, and then under Bishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rowland_Lee">Rowland Lee</ref>. He was made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prebendary">prebendary</ref> of Tachbrook in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lichfield_Cathedral">Lichfield Cathedral</ref> on 11 April 1531, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeacon_of_Salop">archdeacon of Salop</ref> in April 1536, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeacon_of_Derby">archdeacon of Derby</ref> on 8 January 1543.</p>
<p>He received the appointment of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean_of_the_arches">dean of the arches</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vicar-general">vicar-general</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_Canterbury">archbishop of Canterbury</ref> on 14 November 1540. A conscientious adherent of the Roman Catholic faith, he occupied several positions of importance during <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_I_of_England">Queen Mary</ref>'s reign. In her first year he acted as vicar-general of the bishop of Lichfield, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Sampson">Richard Sampson</ref>, and commissioner for the deprivation of married priests, and in his capacity of archdeacon he sat on the commission for the deprivation of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Cranmer">Thomas Cranmer</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Ridley_(martyr)">Nicholas Ridley</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_Latimer">Hugh Latimer</ref>, and the restoration of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edmund_Bonner">Edmund Bonner</ref> and other deprived bishops. He stood high in the favour of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardinal_Pole">Cardinal Pole</ref>, said to have been a relative, who appointed him his vicar-general. During the vacancy of the see of Lichfield on Bishop Sampson's death in 1554, he was appointed commissary for the diocese. In the early part of the same year he took part in the condemnation of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Hooper_(bishop)">John Hooper</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rowland_Taylor">Rowland Taylor</ref>. On 25 April 1556 he was appointed on the commission to inquire after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heretics">heretics</ref>, and to proceed against them.</p>
<p>On the death of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Chambers_(bishop)">John Chambers</ref>, the first bishop of the newly formed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anglican_Diocese_of_Peterborough">diocese of Peterborough</ref>, the queen sent letters commendatory to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Paul_IV">Pope Paul IV</ref> in Pole's favour. He was consecrated at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chiswick">Chiswick</ref> on 15 August 1557 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Heath">Nicholas Heath</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_York">archbishop of York</ref>. He shortly sanctioned the execution of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Protestant_martyrs_of_the_English_Reformation#Protestants_executed_under_Mary_I">John Kurde</ref>, a Protestant shoemaker, who was burnt at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northampton">Northampton</ref> on 20 September 1557.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>On the accession of Elizabeth, he was on the first abortive commission for the consecration of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_Parker">Matthew Parker</ref> as archbishop, 9 September 1559. In the same year he, with Bonner and two other prelates, signed Archbishop Heath's letter of remonstrance to Elizabeth, begging her to return to the Catholic faith. His refusal to take the oath under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Act_of_supremacy">act of supremacy</ref> was followed by his deprivation; but he was treated leniently by the queen. Allowed to live on parole in London or its suburbs, he died on one of his farms in May or June 1568. His property he left to his friends, and his books on law and theology to his college, All Souls'.</p>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
