<text id="autogum_bio_doc620" title="Zeik-Bye" shortTile="zeikbye" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-11-23" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeik-Bye" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Zeik-Bye</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burmese_honorific">Smin</ref> <hi rend="bold">E Bya-Ye Zeik-Bye</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mon_language">Mon</ref>:သ္ငီ အဲာပြရဲာ ဇိပ်ဗြဲာ; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burmese_language">Burmese</ref>: သမိန် အဲပြရဲ ဇိပ်ဗြဲ, Burmese pronunciation:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Burmese">[θəmèiɴ ʔɛ́ bə jɛ́ zeiʔ bjɛ́]</ref>; also spelled <hi rend="bold">Zeip Bye</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-jf-5-2">[2]</ref>) was chief minister of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanthawaddy_Kingdom">Hanthawaddy</ref> in the 1380s in the service of kings <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binnya_U">Binnya U</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Razadarit">Razadarit</ref>. He was a key figure responsible for Razadarit's ascent to power. Though he lost the chief ministership to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byat_Za">Byat Za</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dein_Mani-Yut">Dein Mani-Yut</ref> in 1388, Zeik-Bye continued to serve as a senior minister at least until 1408.</p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>The <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Razadarit_Ayedawbon">Razadarit Ayedawbon</ref></hi> chronicle includes two men who wore the title <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burmese_honorific">Smin</ref> Zeik-Bye in the service of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Binnya_U">Binnya U</ref> (r. 1348–1384).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-378-3">[3]</ref> The subject of this article is the man who became chief minister in the second half of the king's reign,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-82-4">[4]</ref> not Gov. Smin Zeik-Bye of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twante_Township">Dala–Twante</ref>, who died c. 1371.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-60-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>The chronicle does not provide any direct information about the minister's background. It can be inferred from the language used in the chronicle that the minister was of the same generation as King Binnya U (b. 1323), and was likely related to the royal family.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[note 1]</ref></p>
<head>Royal service of Binnya U</head>
<head>Chief minister</head>
<p>The first unambiguous mention of Zeik-Bye the chief minister in the <hi rend="italic">Razadarit Ayedawbon</hi> chronicle is when he was already chief minister c. 1382/83.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-82-4">[4]</ref> (According to Nai Pan Hla, he was governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taikkala">Taikkala</ref> and one of the most trusted senior officers of King Binnya U in the 1360s.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[note 2]</ref>) Nonetheless, his influence as chief minister was limited. Binnya U was in ill health, and the real power belonged to Princess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maha_Dewi_of_Hanthawaddy">Maha Dewi of Dagon</ref>. The king had relied on his elder sister for advice since the death of Chief Minister Pun-So in 1369.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-57-59-8">[6]</ref> Zeik-Bye was not part of Maha Dewi's inner circle; she was closely allied with her nephew-in-law and alleged lover <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smim_Maru">Smin Maru</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-67-68-9">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Aiding Binnya Nwe's rebellion</head>
<p>Zeik-Bye responded by quietly undermining her power. He plotted to put Prince <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Razadarit">Binnya Nwe</ref>, the king's eldest son and Maha Dewi's adopted son, on the throne, and marry his two young daughters to the prince.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-82-4">[4]</ref> The prince had been deeply unhappy that his father had chosen another, younger, son to be the heir-apparent.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-61-10">[8]</ref> In 1383, the minister persuaded the 15-year-old prince that Maha Dewi was planning to put her lover Maru on the throne, and that he would fully support a rebellion by Nwe.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-81-11">[9]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-jf-5-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>The minister kept his end of the bargain. When Nwe fled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dagon_Township">Dagon</ref> with 30 men to raise a rebellion in May 1383,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-94-12">[10]</ref> Zeik-Bye stalled the princess and the court for the next five months, allowing Nwe to garner support amongst local governors around Dagon. When Maha Dewi finally ordered an expedition to Dagon in October, Zeik-Bye led the rearguard army, and undermined the attack.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-129-13">[11]</ref> When Binnya U died in January 1384, he found enough support in the court to hand the power to Nwe.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-157-158-14">[12]</ref> Nwe ascended the throne with the title of <hi rend="bold">Razadarit</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-161-15">[13]</ref></p>
<head>Razadarit years</head>
<head>Chief minister</head>
<p>Zeik-Bye served the new king's chief minister for the next four years. He also became the new king's father-in-law as he gave his two daughters, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burmese_honorific">Mi</ref> Kha-Dun-Mut and Mi Hpyun-Gyo, in marriage to the king.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-137-16">[14]</ref> Nonetheless, his influence on the young king was never great. Even at the beginning, Razadarit knew that he needed more than the Zeik-Bye faction of the court,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[note 3]</ref> and did not punish the factions that did not support him during his rebellion.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-164-18">[15]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-mat-251-19">[16]</ref> In the following years, the young king, who faced several internal and external threats, valued court ministers who could also take the field. Zeik-Bye, who was already in his 60s, did not go the front in any of the campaigns between 1385 and 1391 against the northern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ava_Kingdom">Ava Kingdom</ref> and the rebel forces of Martaban and Myaungmya.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-20">[note 4]</ref> By 1388, two ministers <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dein_Mani-Yut">Dein Mani-Yut</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byat_Za">Byat Za</ref>, who had proved themselves as successful commanders, had overtaken Zeik-Bye as the chief advisers of the king.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-geh-113-114-21">[17]</ref></p>
<head>Senior minister</head>
<p>Nonetheless, Zeik-Bye remained one of the four senior ministers. He was part of the embassy led by Byat Za and Dein to Siam to receive a white elephant for Razadarit presented by the king of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayutthaya_Kingdom">Ayutthaya</ref> in the early 1390s.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-197-22">[18]</ref> In 1401, when Razadarit invaded Ava, Zeik-Bye was entrusted to govern the capital Pegu in the king's absence.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-205-23">[19]</ref> Furthermore, although he had not gone to the front since 1383, he remained part of the Pegu high command. In 1402, he supported the king's position to maintain the siege of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pyay">Prome</ref> (Pyay) while the king's co-chief ministers Byat Za and Dein recommended an immediate withdrawal.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-227-228-24">[20]</ref> Zeik-Bye, who was at least 79, took command of the garrison at Nawin, south of Prome.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-227-228-24">[20]</ref> But it was a complete disaster. Larger Ava forces not only broke the siege but also sacked Nawin. All three regiments defending the garrison were lost; Zeik-Bye himself was captured.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-227-228-24">[20]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-yt-1-220-25">[21]</ref></p>
<p>Zeik-Bye was returned to Pegu after Ava and Pegu signed a peace treaty in 1403. He received a new title, Smin E Bya-Ye but his influence had greatly diminished.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-245-26">[22]</ref> The <hi rend="italic">Razadarit Ayedawbon</hi> includes an episode in which the king made him contribute to the war effort financially. In 1408, Razadarit told the minister, who held the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sittaung,_Mon">Sittaung</ref> in fief, that unless he "lent" funds to the royal coffers, the royal army would not defend the town. His only other choice was to defend the town on his own. After protesting that he was too old to fight, the minister "lent" 7 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viss">viss</ref> (11.43 kg) of gold to the king, and 1 viss (1.63kg) of gold to the army.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-246-27">[23]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-jf-13-14-28">[24]</ref> At least to that year, he remained part of the Pegu high command.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-29">[note 5]</ref></p>
<p>Chronicles do not say when he died but he was most likely dead by 1415. That year, Razadarit appointed Dein governor of Sittaung, Zeik-Bye's fief.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-yt-1-262-30">[25]</ref></p>
<head>List of campaigns</head>
<p>The following is a list of Zeik-Bye's military campaigns. Although he was part of the high command at least until 1408,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nph-246-253-31">[26]</ref> chronicles report that he went to the front only twice between 1383 and 1408.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-32">[note 6]</ref></p>
</text>
