<text id="autogum_bio_doc005" title="Michoel Fisher" shortTile="michoel-fisher" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-04-06" dateModified="2019-08-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michoel_Fisher" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Michoel Fisher</head>
<p>Dayan <hi rend="bold">Michoel Fisher</hi> (c. 1910 – January 7, 2004) was a distinguished <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orthodox_Judaism">Orthodox</ref> rabbi, orator and exceptional <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talmud">Talmudic</ref> scholar, with complete mental mastery of the entire Talmud.</p>
<head>Early years</head>
<p>Born sometime between 1908 and 1912; he was always unsure of his date of birth; in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grodno">Grodno</ref>, then <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian_Empire">Imperial Russia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dayan_(rabbinic_judge)">Dayan</ref> Fisher was the seventh of fourteen children born to the professional fundraiser of the Grodno <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yeshiva">yeshiva</ref>. He claimed to have shared a bench in the Grodno <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheder">Cheder</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meyer_Lansky">Meyer Lansky</ref>.</p>
<p>It is no exaggeration to state that Dayan Fisher studied under the most illustrious institutions and figures of his generation. He was a pupil of the renowned Rabbi <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shimon_Shkop">Shimon Shkop</ref> in Grodno yeshiva, as well as Rabbi <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boruch_Ber_Leibowitz">Boruch Ber Leibowitz</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamyanyets">Kamenetz</ref> yeshiva. Dayan Fisher went to Radin yeshiva in his late teens, serving the world-famous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yisrael_Meir_Kagan">Chofez Chaim</ref> as carer and personal assistant and was one of a select group who prayed daily in his house. He also studied in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Białystok">Białystok</ref> yeshiva and under Rabbi <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chaim_Ozer_Grodzinski">Chaim Ozer Grodzinski</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vilna">Vilna</ref>. In 1930 Dayan Fisher went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mir_yeshiva_(Poland)">Mir yeshiva</ref>, staying for six years.</p>
<head>Rabbinical career</head>
<p>Dayan Fisher was appointed Rabbi of a small <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synagogues">shul</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warsaw">Warsaw</ref> in 1936, where he rapidly acquired a name as an impressive speaker in the "Litvishe" (Lithuanian Jewish) style. He married Sarah Miriam Wloski of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Łomża">Łomża</ref> in June 1937, whose father worked as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shochet">Shochet</ref> in England, following her to England the same year through the rescue efforts of Rabbi Dr <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solomon_Schonfeld">Solomon Schonfeld</ref>. Dayan Fisher thus escaped the impending <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Holocaust">Holocaust</ref>, yet his entire family was wiped out except for a younger brother who escaped from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warsaw_Ghetto">Warsaw Ghetto</ref> and joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jewish_partisans">partisans</ref>.</p>
<p>When Rabbi Fisher arrived in England, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federation_of_Synagogues">Federation of Synagogues</ref>, with some 68 affiliated synagogues, was the largest synagogal body in the United Kingdom, serving some 50,000 souls. He became Rabbi of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alie_Street">Alie Street</ref> Federation synagogue in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_End_of_London">London's East End</ref> in 1939. In 1940, he took over as Rabbi of Yavne synagogue in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London_Borough_of_Hackney">Hackney</ref>, which he led until 1970.</p>
<p>In 1966, Dayan Fisher formed the Federation <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beth_Din">Beis Din</ref>, which he built up into a significant and respected force. As a result of his numerous communal activities and in recognition of his phenomenal Talmudic scholarship, Dayan Fisher became the "Rav Rashi" of the Federation of Synagogues in 1969 following Rabbi Dr Eliezer Kirzner. Upon his retirement in 1980, he retained the post with the addition of the appellation "emeritus".</p>
<p>Dayan Fisher moved with his wife to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edgware">Edgware</ref> in the 1970s, where they became well-known and popular figures. His wife's death in 1987 was a severe blow, yet he continued to speak and teach for the next decade and a half, well into his 90s.</p>
<p>Serving as the Chairman of the Federation of Synagogues Rabbinate for many years, Dayan Fisher's relationship with Federation lay leaders was not always happy. He felt that he and his rabbinic colleagues were often mistreated and undervalued by their constituents, who didn’t recognise the tremendous talent and knowledge of their Rabbis.</p>
<p>Although unbending in his firm old-world Orthodoxy, he was always courteous to those with different views and practices. An ardent religious supporter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israel">Israel</ref>, he was a senior figure in UK <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mizrakhi_(Religious_Zionism)">Mizrachi</ref> for many years, and visited Israel often. Dayan Fisher died on January 7, 2004 in London, survived by two daughters, three grandchildren and one great-granddaughter. One son-in-law is Elkan Levy, ex-president of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_Synagogue">United Synagogue</ref>.</p>
<head>Scholarship and intellect</head>
<p>Dayan Fisher was an intellectually brilliant figure, possessing a photographic memory and an encyclopaedic knowledge of the Talmud and other Rabbinic texts. He knew the 7000 pages of the Talmud by heart, word for word, and could provide the page, line and exact wording for any Talmudic reference instantly. He was also an inspiring orator, erudite, humorous, thought provoking and possessing great wit. </p>
<p>In later life, Dayan Fisher remarked that in retrospect, he was not 'cut out' for the Rabbinate, but rather as a teacher, scholar and educator. He liked nothing better than teaching and learning Talmud. In a eulogy, Dayan Fisher was described by Dayan Lichtenstein, current head of the Federation Beth Din<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>, as a great Talmudic scholar. "He studied the Torah every time as if he were learning it for the first time... The Torah not only brought him his great status but also gave him his youthfulness". <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief_Rabbi">Chief Rabbi</ref> Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonathan_Sacks">Jonathan Sacks</ref> said in tribute, "Dayan Michoel Fisher was one of the great links between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anglo-Jewry">Anglo-Jewry</ref> and the world of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuania">Lithuanian</ref> Jewish piety".</p>
<p>Dayan Fisher published <hi rend="italic">Ateres Mordechai</hi>, a commentary to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pirkei_Avot">Pirkei Avos</ref> in London in 1953.</p>
</text>
