<text id="autogum_bio_doc082" title="Janusz Kozinski" shortTile="janusz-kozinski" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-02-07" dateModified="2019-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janusz_Kozinski" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Janusz Kozinski</head>
<figure><caption>Janusz Kozinski</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Janusz Kozinski</hi>, is a higher education leader, researcher and entrepreneur, and expert in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sustainable_energy">sustainable energy</ref> systems and immune building concepts applied to public safety and security.</p>
<p>He is the Founding President &amp; Vice-Chancellor of the Hereford University of Technology and Engineering, and the former Founding Dean of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York_University">York University</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lassonde_School_of_Engineering">Lassonde School of Engineering</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Education</head>
<p>Kozinski received a Ph.D. in Heat Engineering &amp; Environmental Protection in 1986 from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AGH_University_of_Science_and_Technology">AGH University of Science and Technology</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kraków">Kraków, Poland</ref>, after which he attended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massachusetts_Institute_of_Technology">Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT)</ref> and spent much of his academic career at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McGill_University">McGill University</ref>, where he was Sir William Dawson Scholar and Associate Vice-Principal of Research and International Relations.</p>
<head>Academia</head>
<p>Currently, Kozinski serves as Founding President &amp; Vice-Chancellor of the Hereford University of Technology and Engineering. The new, independent, world-class university is one of the most ambitious new ventures in British higher education. Kozinski has designed an original academic program and developed a master plan for total fundraising and investment of £500 million. The University is considered an ‘incubator of new ideas’, with a focus is on graduating employment-ready, industry relevant, culturally intelligent, creative, ethically aware and financially literate young people.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Prior to his position at Hereford, Kozinski served as Founding Dean of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lassonde_School_of_Engineering">Lassonde School of Engineering</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York_University">York University</ref>. The $250 million initiative is home to the Renaissance Engineering™ program.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Renaissance engineering<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> is a curricular philosophy that includes interdisciplinary learning, industry collaboration and designing for positive social impact. Kozinski was also formerly Dean of the College of Engineering at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Saskatchewan">University of Saskatchewan</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> and Dean of the Faculty of Science and Engineering at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York_University">York University</ref>.</p>
<p>Kozinski held the International Chair in Bioenergy at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Institute_for_Advanced_Study">Institute for Advanced Studies</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centre_national_de_la_recherche_scientifique">Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique</ref> and has completed the Advanced Management &amp; Leadership Program at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxford_University">Oxford University</ref> and the Executive Education Program, Crisis Leadership in Higher Education, at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvard_University">Harvard University</ref>.</p>
<p>Kozinski is a member of the Board of Canadian Mining Innovation Council.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>Janusz Kozinski writes a regular column for the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Huffington_Post">Huffington Post</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Research</head>
<p>Throughout his <ref target="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=AOu5g44AAAAJ&amp;hl=en&amp;oi=ao">academic career</ref>, Kozinski has organized and led multi-disciplinary research teams and programs linking energy, environmental, public health, and security issues<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>At Lassonde School of Engineering, Kozinski leads Energy Lab,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> which focuses on comprehensive research in the areas of energy generation, conversion, analysis, kinetics and management.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> Kozinski's research includes projects related to the next generation of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuclear_reactor">nuclear reactors</ref>, the environmental impact of energy technology, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greenhouse_gas">greenhouse gas</ref> mitigation, fabrication of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nanomaterials">nanomaterials</ref>, public security in buildings vulnerable to bio-agents, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exploration_of_Mars">Mars exploration</ref>.</p>
<head>Entrepreneurship</head>
<p>Janusz Kozinski founded his own energy company and has collaborated with multinational firms around the globe.</p>
<head>Selected works</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Farooq, U., Kozinski, J. A., Khan, M. A., &amp; Athar, M. (2010). Biosorption of heavy metal ions using wheat based biosorbents–a review of the recent literature. Bioresource Technology, 101(14), 5043-5053.</item>
<item>Fang, Z., Sato, T., Smith, R. L., Inomata, H., Arai, K., &amp; Kozinski, J. A. (2008). Reaction chemistry and phase behavior of lignin in high-temperature and supercritical water. Bioresource Technology, 99(9), 3424-3430.</item>
<item>Farooq, U., Khan, M. A., Athar, M., &amp; Kozinski, J. A. (2011). Effect of modification of environmentally friendly biosorbent wheat (Triticum aestivum) on the biosorptive removal of cadmium (II) ions from aqueous solution. Chemical Engineering Journal, 171(2), 400-410.</item>
<item>Koziński, J. A., &amp; Saade, R. (1998). Effect of biomass burning on the formation of soot particles and heavy hydrocarbons. An experimental study. Fuel, 77(4), 225-237.</item></list>
</text>
