<text id="autogum_bio_doc238" title="Hedayat-Allah Khan" shortTile="hedayatallah-khan" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-05-12" dateModified="2019-08-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hedayat-Allah_Khan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hedayat-Allah Khan</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Hedayat-Allah Khan</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_language">Persian</ref>: هدایت‌الله خان‎) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilaki_people">Gilaki</ref> prince, who was the semi-independent ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilan_Province">Gilan</ref> from 1753 to 1782.</p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>Hedayat-Allah was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agha_Jamal_Fumani">Agha Jamal Fumani</ref>, a tribal chieftain from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fuman,_Iran">Fuman</ref> who was descended from the Dubbaj clan, which ruled <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilan">Gilan</ref> in the late 15th-early 16th century, and claimed descent from the pre-Islamic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sasanian_Empire">Sasanian Empire</ref> and the biblical prophet <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isaac">Isaac</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKasheff2001635–642-1">[1]</ref> In 1749, two years after the death of the Iranian emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nader_Shah">Nader Shah</ref> (r. 1736–1747), Agha Jamal Fumani, along with a certain Agha Safi, seized Gilan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELangaroudi2001642-645-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>During the war between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zand_dynasty">Zand dynasty</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qajars_(tribe)">Qajars</ref>, the Qajar chieftain of the Qoyunlu branch, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohammad_Hasan_Khan_Qajar">Mohammad Hasan Khan Qajar</ref>, made Gilan submit to his rule and in 1752 married the daughter of Agha Jamal Fumani. The following year Agha Jamal Fumani was killed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shaft,_Iran">Shaft</ref> by Agha Hady Shafti, who, with the aid of Mirza Zaki, who governed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ziabar_(Gaskar)">Gaskar</ref>, controlled the province. However, his rule was short-lived—4 months later, Agha Hady Shafti was seized and executed in an unexpected attack by Mohammad Hasan Khan Qajar, who appointed Hedayat-Allah as governor of Gilan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELangaroudi2001642-645-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Reign</head>
<figure><caption>Map of northern Iran.</caption></figure>
<p>When the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zand_dynasty">Zand</ref> ruler <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karim_Khan_Zand">Karim Khan Zand</ref> (r. 1751–1779) was conquering Iran, he in 1760 had Hedayat-Allah replaced with a close associate of his.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELangaroudi2001642-645-2">[2]</ref> However, whilst Karim Khan was on an expedition in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Azerbaijan_(Iran)">Azerbaijan</ref>, Hedayat-Allah returned to Gilan and re-established his rule in the province. Karim Khan then shortly had him apprehended and penalized him by demanding 12,000 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iranian_toman">tomans</ref> as payment. He then appointed his cousin Nazar Ali Khan as the governor of the province, but later altered his stratagem and in 1767 restored Hedayat-Allah as the ruler of Gilan under Zand suzerainty. Furthermore, he also arranged the marriage between Hedayat-Allah's sister and his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abol-Fath_Khan_Zand">Abol-Fath Khan Zand</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELangaroudi2001642-645-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In 1782 Agha Mohammad Khan invaded Gilan, Hedayat-Allah had changed his allegiance to the Zand dynasty. Hedayat-Allah then sent two diplomats, Mirza Sadeq and Agha Sadeq Lahiji, to Agha Mohammad to make peace. As a precaution he went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shirvan">Shirvan</ref>. The diplomats were unable to come to favorable terms with Agha Mohammad Khan, who raided Gilan's capital <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rasht">Rasht</ref> and seized its riches.</p>
<p>Agha Mohammad Khan now had to focus on Gilan because Hedayat-Allah had returned to the province (allegedly with Russian help) since the Qajar invasion of the province in 1782.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHambly1991119-3">[3]</ref> In Agha Mohammad Khan's eyes, the whole Caspian coast was under threat by Hedayat-Allah and the Russians. Agha Mohammad Khan and his men easily managed to enter Gilan. While he was marching towards Rasht, he was joined by a local ruler named Mehdi Beg Khalatbari and other people.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the Russian consul in Gilan betrayed Hedayat-Allah by providing weapons to Agha Mohammad Khan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHambly1991120-4">[4]</ref> Hedayat-Allah once again tried to flee to Shirvan, but was captured by men sent by a local ruler named Agha Ali Shafti (or another local ruler according to some sources), who killed him to avenge the slaughter of his family a few years earlier. Gilan was now completely under Qajar rule. Besides the conquest of Gilan, the second most valuable thing for Agha Mohammad Khan was Hedayat-Allah's treasure.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHambly1991120-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Characteristics and policies</head>
<p>Gilan flourished under the rule of Hedayat-Allah, who encouraged foreign trade by tempting a substantial amount of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenians">Armenians</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russians">Russians</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jews">Jews</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_people">Indians</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rasht">Rasht</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELangaroudi2001642-645-2">[2]</ref> He preserved an elegant court in Rasht, funded by the silk industry and the sea commerce between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bandar-e_Anzali">Bandar-e Anzali</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astrakhan">Astrakhan</ref>. Nonetheless, according to the Cambridge History of Iran, "he was treacherous and bloodthirsty, even by the standards of the age, and his eventual overthrow by Mohammad Hasan Khan's son and political heir, Agha Mohammad Khan, passed unmourned."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHambly1991120-4">[4]</ref></p>
</text>
