<text id="autogum_bio_doc798" title="Ulrich IV, Count of Pfannberg" shortTile="ulrich-iv-count-pfannberg" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-03-16" dateModified="2016-05-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulrich_IV%2C_Count_of_Pfannberg" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ulrich IV, Count of Pfannberg</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ulrich IV of Pfannberg</hi> (c.1260 – before 1318) was Count of Pfannberg  from 1287 until his death.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Ulrich was a son of Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry,_Count_of_Pfannberg">Henry</ref>  of Pfannberg and his wife Agnes of Plain.  He was first mentioned by name in 1278, together with his older brother Herman, in a document archived at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Paul's_Abbey_in_the_Lavanttal">St. Paul's Abbey in the Lavanttal</ref>.</p>
<p>After Herman died in 1287, Ulrich inherited his possessions, except Traberg (Unterdrauburg and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dravograd">Dravograd</ref>), which remained in the hands of Herman's widow Elisabeth, née Countess of Heunburg, because Ulrich was in a tight financial situation and could not afford to pay her a pension.</p>
<p>Ulrich married in 1287 or early 1288, to Margaret of Heunburg.  On the Sunday before Ascension Day he confirmed at Bleiburg that his father-in-law, Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulrich_II,_Count_of_Heunburg">Ulrich II</ref> of Heunburg, had paid Margaret's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dowry">dowry</ref> of 1000 silver marks and that he and Margaret would renounce any claims on the inheritance of his in-laws.  A consequence of this marriage was that when the Heunburg family died out in the male line in 1322, a significant portion of their possessions were inherited by the House of Pfannberg.</p>
<p>Ulrich's grandfather had been an energetic man, who had achieved the rank of Count for his family, and his father Henry had been a famous knight with leadership qualities.  By contrast, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chronicler">chroniclers</ref> hardly mention Ulrich IV.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottokar_aus_der_Gaal">Ottokar aus der Gaal</ref> mentions in his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Styrian_rhyming_chronicle">Styrian rhyming chronicle</ref> that Ulrich IV participated in the rebellion against Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_I_of_Germany">Albert</ref> of Austria in late 1291 and early 1292 and had been a member of the delegation sent to Archbishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conrad_IV_of_Fohnsdorf">Conrad</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Salzburg">Salzburg</ref> to persuade him to join the rebellion.  He does not appear to have distinguished himself by his bravery and, unlike his ancestors, who had often been at war with the clergy, Ulrich IV was very generous towards the church and the monasteries, which obviously worsened his financial difficulties and drove him to mortgage almost all of his possessions.</p>
<p>Ulrich IV probably accompanied Duke Albert on his ill-fated campaign in Hungary in 1291.  Later that year a rebellion broke out in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Styria">Styria</ref>, because Duke Albert refused to confirm the privileges of the Estates.  His father-in-law was probably the driving force behind this refusal, since Albert himself did not play a major rôle in this conflict.  The rebellion collapsed in March 1292, after Albert captured <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bruck_an_der_Mur">Bruck an der Mur</ref> and took the rebel leader Frederick of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stubenberg_(family)">Stubenberg</ref> prisoner.  Ulrich IV did not participate in the rebellion against Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meinhard,_Duke_of_Carinthia">Meinhard II</ref> of Carinthia in late 1292 and early 1293.</p>
<p>In 1292, donations by the Counts of Pfannberg to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rein_Abbey,_Austria">Rein Abbey</ref> were recorded.</p>
<p>On 30 May 1292 at Greiffen, his father-in-law, Count Ulrich II of Heunberg, sold a manor named <hi rend="italic">Rain</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Rakkonik</hi> (this was most likely the manor now known as <hi rend="italic">Rainhof</hi> in Raggane, north-east of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sankt_Paul_im_Lavanttal">Sankt Paul im Lavanttal</ref>) to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbot">abbot</ref> Conrad of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Paul's_Abbey_in_the_Lavanttal">St. Paul's Abbey</ref> and promised he would plead with Ulrich IV to allow this sale, as Ulrich IV was still liege lord of this and many other possessions east of the river <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lavant_(river)">Lavant</ref>, for example Puhelarn manor in Unterpichling (which was later acquired by St. Paul's Abbey) and Dachberg, Mühldorf, Lindhof, Götzendorf and Hundsdorf, as well as the castles at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rabenstein_Castle_(Carinthia)">Rabenstein</ref>, Loschental and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lavamünd">Lavamünd</ref>.</p>
<p>Ulrich's brother Rainold, the abbot of Rein Abbey, died on 21 December 1292.  His death made life difficult for Ulrich. Life became even more difficult when in 1293 Duke Albert took his parents-in-law prisoner and banished them to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiener_Neustadt">Wiener Neustadt</ref>.  Ulrich spent a lot of money trying to release them, and was continuously strapped for cash.</p>
<p>On 5 July 1294 at Judenburg castle, Ulrich IV and his wife Margaret pledged their princely fief, the castle at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sankt_Peter-Freienstein">Sankt Peter-Freienstein</ref>, two large manors in Tolling and Welen, and justice over the area from Hohenward and Chieneinöde to the river Kalten Rinne at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Röthelstein">Röthelstein</ref> to Abbot Henry of Admont.</p>
<p>Ulrich IV died before 1318 and was buried at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rein_Abbey,_Austria">Rein Abbey</ref>.</p>
<head>Marriage and issue</head>
<p>Ulrich IV was married to Margaret, the daughter of Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulrich_II,_Count_of_Heunburg">Ulrich II</ref> of Heunburg and Countess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agnes_of_Baden-Austria">Agnes of Baden-Austria</ref> and they had the following children:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulrich_V,_Count_of_Pfannberg">Ulrich V</ref> (1287-1354)</item>
<item>Elizabeth (1290-1363), married before 1332 to Henry of Montpreis (died before 1363)</item></list>
</text>
