<text id="autogum_bio_doc730" title="Pope Gregory XII" shortTile="pope-gregory-xii" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2001-10-02" dateModified="2019-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Gregory_XII" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pope Gregory XII</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pope Gregory XII</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin_language">Latin</ref>: <hi lang="la" rend="italic">Gregorius XII</hi>; c.1326 or 1327– 18 October 1417), born <hi rend="bold">Angelo Corraro</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Corario</hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-eb9-1">[1]</ref> or <hi rend="bold">Correr</hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope">Pope</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholic_Church">Catholic Church</ref> from 30 November 1406 to 4 July 1415 when he was forced to resign to end the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_Schism">Western Schism</ref>. He succeeded <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Innocent_VII">Pope Innocent VII</ref> and in turn was succeeded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Martin_V">Pope Martin V</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Angelo Corraro was born in Venice of a noble family, about 1326 or 1327, and was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic_Diocese_of_Castello">Bishop of Castello</ref> in 1380, succeeding Bishop Nicolò Morosini.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ott-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>On 1 December 1390 he was made titular <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin_Patriarch_of_Constantinople">Latin Patriarch of Constantinople</ref>. On 12 June 1405 he was created cardinal and the Cardinal-Priest of San Marco by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Innocent_VII">Pope Innocent VII</ref>. He was Apostolic Administrator of Constantinople from 30 November 1406 to 23 October 1409.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Papal conclave</head>
Main article: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papal_conclave,_1406">Papal conclave, 1406</ref>
<p>Gregory XII was chosen at Rome by a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papal_conclave,_1406">conclave</ref> consisting of only fifteen cardinals under the express condition that, should <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antipope_Benedict_XIII">Antipope Benedict XIII</ref> (1394–1423), the rival papal claimant at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avignon">Avignon</ref>, renounce all claim to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papacy">Papacy</ref>, he would also renounce his, so that a fresh election might be made and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_Schism">Western Schism</ref> (1378–1417) ended. He became Supreme Pontiff on 30 November 1406, taking the name Gregory XII.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ott-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Pontificate</head>
<head>Negotiations to end the schism</head>
<p>The two pontiffs opened wary negotiations to meet on neutral turf at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savona">Savona</ref> in Liguria, but soon began to waver in their resolve. The Corraro relatives of Gregory XII in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venice">Venice</ref> and King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ladislaus_of_Naples">Ladislaus of Naples</ref>, a supporter of Gregory XII and his predecessor for political reasons, used all their influence to prevent the meeting, and each Pope feared being captured by partisans of the rival Pope.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ott-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>The cardinals of Gregory XII openly showed their dissatisfaction at this manoeuvring and gave signs of their intention to abandon him. On 4 May 1408, Gregory XII convened his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardinal_(Catholicism)">cardinals</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucca">Lucca</ref> and ordered them not to leave the city under any pretext. He tried to supplement his following by creating four of his Corraro nephews cardinals – including the future <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Eugene_IV">Pope Eugene IV</ref>, despite his promise in the conclave that he would create no new cardinals. Seven of the cardinals secretly left Lucca and negotiated with the cardinals of Benedict XIII concerning the convocation of a general council by them, at which both pontiffs should be deposed and a new one elected. Consequently, they summoned the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council_of_Pisa">council to Pisa</ref> and invited both pontiffs to be present. Neither Gregory XII nor Benedict XIII appeared.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Gregory XII stayed with his loyal and powerful protector, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Condottiero">condottiero</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlo_I_Malatesta">Carlo I Malatesta</ref>, who had come to Pisa in person during the process of the council to support Gregory XII. At the fifteenth session, 5 June 1409, the Council of Pisa deposed the two pontiffs as schismatical, heretical, perjured, and scandalous; they elected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antipope_Alexander_V">Alexander V</ref> (1409–10) later that month.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Gregory XII, who had meanwhile created ten more cardinals, had convoked a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council_of_Aquileia,_1409">rival council</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cividale_del_Friuli">Cividale del Friuli</ref>, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aquileia">Aquileia</ref>; but only a few bishops appeared. Gregory XII's cardinals pronounced Benedict XIII and Alexander V schismatics, perjurers, and devastators of the Church, but their pronouncement went unheeded.</p>
<head>Resolution of the schism</head>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council_of_Constance">Council of Constance</ref> finally resolved the situation. Gregory XII appointed Carlo Malatesta and Cardinal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Dominici">Giovanni Dominici</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ragusa,_Sicily">Ragusa</ref> as his proxies. The cardinal then convoked the council and authorized its succeeding acts, thus preserving the formulas of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papal_supremacy">Papal supremacy</ref>.</p>
<p>Thereupon on 4 July 1415, Malatesta, acting in the name of Gregory XII, pronounced the resignation of the Pope, which the cardinals accepted. According to prior agreement, they agreed to retain all the cardinals that had been created by Gregory XII, thus satisfying the Corraro clan, and appointed Gregory XII <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Frascati">Bishop of Frascati</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean_of_the_Sacred_College_of_Cardinals">Dean of the Sacred College of Cardinals</ref> and perpetual legate at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ancona">Ancona</ref>. The Council then set aside <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antipope_John_XXIII">Antipope John XXIII</ref> (1410–15), the successor of Alexander V. After the former follower of Benedict XIII appeared, the council declared him deposed; and the Western Schism was ended. A new Roman pontiff, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Martin_V">Pope Martin V</ref>, was elected <hi rend="italic">after</hi> Gregory XII's death. Therefore, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sede_vacante">the Papal seat was vacant</ref> for two years.</p>
<head>Retirement and death</head>
<p>The rest of Gregory XII's life was spent in peaceful obscurity in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ancona">Ancona</ref>. He was the last pope to resign until <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Benedict_XVI">Benedict XVI</ref> did so on 28 February 2013, almost 598 years later.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
</text>
