<text id="autogum_bio_doc404" title="Maktul Hacı Ibrahim Pasha" shortTile="maktul-haci-ibrahim" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-10-10" dateModified="2017-09-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maktul_Hac%C4%B1_Ibrahim_Pasha" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Maktul Hacı Ibrahim Pasha</head>This article is about the governor of Egypt in 1604. For the earlier governor of Egypt named Ibrahim Pasha, also known by the epithet Maktul ("the Slain"), see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pargalı_Ibrahim_Pasha">Pargalı Ibrahim Pasha</ref>. For other people, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ibrahim_Pasha_(disambiguation)">Ibrahim Pasha (disambiguation)</ref>.
In this <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Turkish_language">Ottoman Turkish</ref> style name, <hi rend="italic">Ibrahim</hi> is the given name, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Ottoman_titles_and_appellations">title</ref> is <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pasha">Pasha</ref></hi>, and there is no family name.
<p><hi rend="bold">Ibrahim Pasha</hi> (also known as <hi rend="bold">Hacı Ibrahim Pasha</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Maktul Ibrahim Pasha</hi> or among his Arab subjects as <hi rend="bold">Ibrahim Pasha al-Maqtul</hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Winter2004-4-1">[1]</ref> <hi rend="italic">Maktul</hi> meaning <hi rend="bold">the Slain</hi>; died 24 September 1604<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CookAhmed2011-2">[2]</ref>) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> statesman who served shortly as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Ottoman_Wālis_of_Egypt">governor of</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egypt_Eyalet">Egypt</ref> in 1604 before he was murdered by mutinying <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sepahi">sepahi</ref> soldiers of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military_of_the_Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman Army</ref>. He also served as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Defterdar">defterdar</ref> (finance minister) of the Ottoman Empire four times (1582–83, 1587–88, 1593–94, 1596).</p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>Ibrahim Pasha appears to have lived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karaman_Eyalet">Konya</ref> in his early life and been a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dervish">dervish</ref> and a follower of the ascetic Muslim mystic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rumi">Rumi</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Winter2004-2-3">[3]</ref> As such, he was sometimes known by the epithet "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sufism">Sufi</ref>" by historians.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Winter2004-2-3">[3]</ref> He was also a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kadı">kadı</ref> (judge) at some point in his life prior to becoming the four-time <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Defterdar">defterdar</ref> of the empire and governor of Egypt.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Winter2004-3-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Tenure as the governor of Egypt</head>
<p>In 1604, sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ahmed_I">Ahmed I</ref> appointed Ibrahim Pasha as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Ottoman_Wālis_of_Egypt">governor of Egypt</ref>, Egypt then being the seat of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egypt_Eyalet">Egypt Eyalet</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman Empire</ref>. His office's title was beylerbey, while governors of a province in general was referred to as a wāli.</p>
<p>Since the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_conquest_of_Egypt">Ottoman conquest of Egypt</ref> and their subjugation in 1517, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mamluk">Mamluks</ref> in Egypt had been silently pushing for more influence in Egypt; they often attempted this by trying to influence the garrisoned Ottoman soldiers over the Ottoman governor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CookAhmed2011-2">[2]</ref> After Ibrahim Pasha was appointed governor in 1604, he began to enforce more stringent rules for the soldiers, especially those from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sipahi">sipahi</ref> corps (an elite cavalry corps of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military_of_the_Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman Army</ref>),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CookAhmed2011-2">[2]</ref> putting some of them to death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Winter2004-5">[5]</ref> Allegedly, Ibrahim Pasha had one such soldier from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fellah">fellah</ref> (Arabic-speaking) class of the local Mamluk populace put to death by hanging and had his body draped in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sirwal">sirwal</ref> (Arabic baggy trousers), which was something both the local sepahis and the Mamluks wore, in order to send a message of his distaste for both groups; furthermore, the body was then allegedly placed in a jar to symbolize the slave class the two groups belonged to.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Winter2004-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Another source states that tensions rose when Ibrahim Pasha refused to pay a briberous "accession tax" to the local sepahis for coming into the office of the governor of Egypt.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DalyPetry1998-6">[6]</ref> Sipahis, in further corruption, self-enacted an illegal tax known as the <hi rend="italic">tulba</hi> on the people of the Egyptian countryside, claiming that the tax was for "facilitating police duties."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DalyPetry1998-1-7">[7]</ref> When Ibrahim Pasha cracked down on this practice and refused to buy into the system, tensions between Ibrahim Pasha, the sipahis, the Mamluks, and the general army grew to enormous levels.</p>
<head>Murder</head>
<p>Tensions came to a head on 24 September 1604, only a few months after Ibrahim Pasha had assumed office.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CookAhmed2011-2">[2]</ref> The pasha, along with many armed companions, left the governor's citadel in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cairo">Cairo</ref> in order to open a dyke or a waterwheel in either the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shubra">Shubra</ref> or the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulaq">Bulaq</ref> district of the city.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CookAhmed2011-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DalyPetry1998-1-7">[7]</ref> Around this time, a number of soldiers in his army gathered at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City_of_the_Dead_(Cairo)">City of the Dead</ref> necropolis and took an oath on the saints' tombs to assassinate the pasha.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CookAhmed2011-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DalyPetry1998-1-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Although warned of the rebels' intentions, Ibrahim Pasha refused to move away or escape from the project to which he was attending.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CookAhmed2011-2">[2]</ref> In the presence of several beys and military officials standing by, 15 rebel cavalry soldiers approached Ibrahim Pasha and killed him with their swords.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CookAhmed2011-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DalyPetry1998-4-8">[8]</ref> Ibrahim Pasha thus became the first governor of the Ottoman Empire to be killed by his own troops,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Winter2004-4-1">[1]</ref> earning the posthumous epithet  <hi rend="italic">Maktul</hi>, meaning "the Slain".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CookAhmed2011-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>After murdering the pasha, the rebel soldiers displayed his and some of his men's heads publicly, parading them through the streets and then placing them on the gate of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bab_Zuweila">Bab Zuweila</ref>, where criminals' remains were normally displayed, allegedly crying, "This is due to [deserved by] those who cause strife in the Sultan's army."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CookAhmed2011-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DalyPetry1998-4-8">[8]</ref> The chief <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kadı">kadı</ref></hi> (judge) in the eyalet became acting governor until the sultan could appoint a new one.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DalyPetry1998-4-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>Ibrahim Pasha's death caused a period of instability and distress in Egypt, and stability was only restored around 7 or 8 years later when the governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kara_Mehmed_Pasha">Kara Mehmed Pasha</ref> finally crushed the rebellion, earning his epithet <hi rend="italic">Kul Kıran</hi> ("the Slavebreaker").<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CookAhmed2011-2">[2]</ref></p>
</text>
