<text id="autogum_bio_doc697" title="Catherine of Alençon" shortTile="catherine-alencon" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-10-24" dateModified="2019-09-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_of_Alen%C3%A7on" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Catherine of Alençon</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Catherine d'Alençon</hi> (bef.1396 – 22 June 1462 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> in Paris) was a younger daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_II_of_Alençon">Peter II of Alençon</ref> and his wife Marie Chamaillart, Viscountess of Beaumont-au-Maine. Catherine was the second wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_VII,_Duke_of_Bavaria">Louis VII, Duke of Bavaria</ref>. Catherine was also <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maid_of_honour">maid of honour</ref> to Louis' sister, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabeau_of_Bavaria">Isabeau of Bavaria</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Catherine came from a branch of the French royal family, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Valois">House of Valois</ref>, her family were known as The House of Valois-Alençon. Her brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_I,_Duke_of_Alençon">John I, Duke of Alençon</ref> was killed at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Agincourt">Battle of Agincourt</ref> against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_V_of_England">Henry V of England</ref>. Catherine married in 1411 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> to the 30-year-old Peter of Évreux, Count of Mortain.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Peter was a brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_III_of_Navarre">Charles III of Navarre</ref>. After only one year of marriage, Peter died, the marriage produced no children.</p>
<p>One year after Peter's death, Catherine was betrothed again to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_VII,_Duke_of_Bavaria">Louis VII, Duke of Bavaria</ref>, brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabeau_of_Bavaria">Isabeau, Queen of France</ref>. The wedding, however, had to be postponed, as Catherine's future husband was taken prisoner. The wedding took place on Louis' release in early October 1413. Catherine's Dowry covered not only the county of Mortain, 60,000 francs but it also created connections between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bavaria">Bavaria</ref> and France.</p>
<p>Louis travelled in early 1415 as head of the French embassy to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council_of_Constance">Council of Constance</ref>. Catherine's husband gave the County of Mortain, from Catherine's dowry to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_the_Fearless">John the Fearless</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_of_Burgundy">Duke of Burgundy</ref>, to free his wife, during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armagnac-Burgundian_Civil_War">Armagnac-Burgundian Civil War</ref> in 1417, she had been taken prisoner by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernard_VII_of_Armagnac">Bernard VII of Armagnac</ref> and did not care for their financial supply.</p>
<p>Catherine lost all of their income by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_V_of_England">Henry V</ref>'s successful invasion. Henry took the county of Mortain and occupied their heritages in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Normandy">Normandy</ref>. Even precious utensils, documents and account books were taken by the English. Help finally came not from her husband, but from the English king, who made an agreement with the French King, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Troyes">Treaty of Troyes</ref>, which gave Catherine 2000 francs per year as compensation for her losses. In 1421 Catherine even travelled to England, as lady-in-waiting to the wife of the King Henry, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_of_Valois">Catherine of Valois</ref>, who was Catherine's niece. Catherine even assisted in the birth of their child, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VI_of_England">Henry VI of England</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Catherine's second husband, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_VII,_Duke_of_Bavaria">Louis VII, Duke of Bavaria</ref>, died on 1 May 1447 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burghausen,_Altötting">Burghausen</ref>.</p>
<p>Catherine joined the household of her sister-in-law, Isabeau. Catherine died 1462 in Paris and was buried in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbey_of_Sainte-Geneviève">Abbey of Sainte-Geneviève</ref>. She is now buried next to her first husband, Peter.</p>
<head>Children</head>
<p>Louis and Catherine had two children:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>John of Bavaria (b. 6 February 1415), died young</item>
<item>unnamed daughter, died young <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></item></list>
<p>Catherine left no surviving children.</p>
<head>Ancestry</head>
<head>Literature</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Claudia Märtl: Frankreich. Herzog Ludwig VII. von Bayern-Ingolstadt (1368–1447) und seine Schwester Isabeau am französischen Königshof. In: Alois Schmid, Katharina Weigand (eds.): Bayern mitten in Europa. Vom Frühmittelalter bis ins 20. Jahrhundert. C. H. Beck, Munich 2005, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/3-406-52898-8">3-406-52898-8</ref>, P. 107-120, especially p.116-117.</item>
<item>Beatrix Schönewald: Die Herzoginnen von Bayern-Ingolstadt. In: Sammelblatt des Historischen Vereins Ingolstadt. Volume 113, 2004, p.35-54, especially p.48-52.</item>
<item>Theodor Straub: Bayern im Zeichen der Teilungen und Teilherzogtümer. In: Max Spindler, Andreas Kraus (eds.): Handbuch der bayerischen Geschichte. 2nd edition. Vol. 2, C. H. Beck, Munich 1988, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/3-406-32320-0">3-406-32320-0</ref>, p.196-287, especially p.245.</item>
<item>Theodor Straub: Die fünf Ingolstädter Herzoginnen. In: Bayern-Ingolstadt, Bayern-Landshut. 1392–1506. Glanz und Elend einer Teilung. Stadtarchiv Ingolstadt 1992, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/3-932113-06-3">3-932113-06-3</ref>, P. 43-50, especially p.47-49.</item></list>
</text>
