<text id="autogum_bio_doc419" title="Cornelius Jacobsen May" shortTile="cornelius-jacobsen" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-07-03" dateModified="2019-08-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cornelius_Jacobsen_May" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cornelius Jacobsen May</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cornelis Jacobsen Mey</hi> (in English often rendered as <hi rend="bold">Cornelius Jacobsen May</hi>) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netherlands">Dutch</ref> explorer, captain and fur trader. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape_May">Cape May</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape_May_County,_New_Jersey">Cape May County</ref>, and the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape_May,_New_Jersey">Cape May, New Jersey</ref>, are named after him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Cornelius May is said to be from the city of  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoorn">Hoorn</ref> but may have been born in the small village of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schellinkhout">Schellinkhout</ref>, just east of Hoorn, as he appears to have been the brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_Jacobszoon_May_van_Schellinkhout">Jan Jacobszoon May van Schellinkhout</ref>, after whom the island of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_Mayen">Jan Mayen</ref> is named.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Muller-2">[2]</ref> Both brothers were the cousin of, in his day, a far more famous sailor, Jan Cornelisz May,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Schel-3">[3]</ref> who led several expeditions to explore the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northeast_passage">Northeast passage</ref> and between 1614 and 1617 circumnavigated the world with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joris_van_Spilbergen">Joris van Spilbergen</ref>.</p>
<head>1614 to 1616 expeditions to New Netherland</head>
<p>May sailed first in the <hi rend="italic">Mauritius River</hi> or "Hudson's river" (so referred to first by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adriaen_Block">Adriaen Block</ref> in 1613) in 1614 where an agreement was made among various competing traders. On October 11, 1614, May became a party to the New Netherland Company which received an exclusive patent from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/States-General_of_the_Netherlands">States General</ref> for four voyages to be undertaken for three years to territories discovered between the 40th and 45th parallels at the exclusion of all other Dutch (until January 1618).</p>
<p>From August until November 1616, the company tried unsuccessfully to obtain a new patent for a territory situated between the 38th and 40th parallels (i.e., the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delaware_Bay">Delaware Bay</ref> area) which in 1614, and 1615 had been surveyed by Cornelis Hendricksz from Monnikendam on the ship <hi rend="italic">Onrust</hi>. In 1616 Cornelis Hendricksen, sailed the <hi rend="italic">Onrust</hi> up the Zuyd Rivier (literally "South River," today known as the Delaware River) from its bay to its northernmost navigable reaches, on a voyage to ransom three fur traders taken from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Nassau_(North_River)">Fort Nassau</ref> on the North River.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Wheeler-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>On behalf of the successor company of the New Netherland Company, Cornelius Jacobsen May had explored and surveyed the Delaware Bay on the ship named <hi rend="italic">Blijde Boodschap</hi> (en. "Joyful Message") from which he carried on trade with the Indians there in 1620. In 1621, he ordered the construction of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Factorij">factorij</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Nassau_(South_River)">Fort Nassau</ref> at the mouth of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Timber_Creek">Big Timber Creek</ref>.</p>
<p>Two of the six business partners of the ships <hi rend="italic">Blijde Boodschap</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Bever</hi> which focused on exploration and trade in the Zuidt Rivier or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delaware_River">Delaware River</ref>, were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thijmen_Jacobsz_Hinlopen">Thijmen Jacobsz Hinlopen</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Godijn">Samuel Godijn</ref>. Cape Hinlopen, now spelled <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape_Henlopen">Cape Henlopen</ref> in Delaware is named after the former.  Cape Hinlopen was New Netherland's most southern border on the 38th parallel. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Godyn">Samuel Godyn</ref> had Godyn's Bay named after him, now renamed Delaware Bay. Also spelled Godijn or Godin, he was one of the first patroons in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Netherland">New Netherland</ref> as well as a director of the West India Company and of the Northern Company.</p>
<head>First colonists to New Netherland</head>
<p>May was unable to trade in the South River (Delaware River) to the exclusion of competing Dutch companies. Though the competing Dutch companies were eventually able to reach agreement in New Netherland, discord arose again which was settled, finally, by a judgment of arbitrators at Amsterdam on December 23, 1623. The 38th and 39th parallels region came under the final jurisdiction of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_West_India_Company">Dutch West India Company</ref> with the delivery of the first settlers to New Netherland in 1624, mostly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walloons">Walloon</ref> and Flemish families.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nni-5">[5]</ref> May was the captain of the ship <hi rend="italic">New Netherland</hi> who delivered the first boat load of colonists to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Netherland">New Netherland</ref>, first at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Orange">Fort Orange</ref>, the trading post near present-day Albany, and then on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governors_Island">Governors Island</ref>, in present-day NYC, that year. In the spring of 1624, Cornelius Jacobsen May returned to New Netherlands in command of the <hi rend="italic">Nieu Nederlandt</hi>, with the first group of settlers, mostly young <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walloons">Walloon</ref> families. Some were sent to company lands in Connecticut, while two families and eight single males took a sloop to the Zuidt (South) River, now the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delaware_River">Delaware River</ref>, and established <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Wilhelmus">Fort Wilhelmus</ref>. Eight men were also left on Nut Island to promote the fur trade, and the remaining eighteen families proceeded upriver to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Orange_(New_Netherland)">Fort Orange</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Klein-6">[6]</ref> Having so transformed the New Netherland territory to a province, he was named the province's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Director_of_New_Netherland">first director</ref>.</p>
</text>
