<text id="autogum_bio_doc516" title="Thomas Neville (died 1471)" shortTile="thomas-neville-died" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-11-02" dateModified="2019-03-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Neville_%28died_1471%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Thomas Neville (died 1471)</head>
For other people named Thomas Neville, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Neville_(disambiguation)">Thomas Neville (disambiguation)</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Thomas Fauconberg</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Thomas Neville</hi>, sometimes called Thomas the Bastard, or the <hi rend="bold">Bastard of Fauconberg</hi> (1429 – 22 September 1471), was the natural son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Neville,_1st_Earl_of_Kent">William Neville, Lord Fauconberg</ref>, who was a leading commander in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hundred_Years'_War">Hundred Years' War</ref> and, until joining his cousin, Richard Neville (“Warwick the Kingmaker“) in rebellion against another cousin, Edward IV, served on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yorkist">Yorkist</ref> side in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wars_of_the_Roses">Wars of the Roses</ref>.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>In his youth Thomas was a notable sailor, receiving the freedom of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City_of_London">City of London</ref> in 1454 for his work in eliminating pirates from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Channel">English Channel</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Sea">North Sea</ref>. In this he was closely associated with his father's relatives: Lord Fauconberg's elder brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Neville,_5th_Earl_of_Salisbury">Richard Neville, Earl of Salisbury</ref> was a commissioner for the keeping of the seas in 1453-5, and in 1455 Salisbury's eldest son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Neville,_Earl_of_Warwick">Richard Neville, Earl of Warwick</ref> was entrusted with sole responsibility for the keeping of the seas, a post he effectively retained for the rest of his life.</p>
<head>The Wars of the Roses</head>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Neville">Nevilles</ref> were the most important supporters of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_of_York">Richard of York</ref>, and instrumental in helping his son gain the throne as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_IV_of_England">Edward IV</ref> in 1461, assistance for which Lord Fauconberg was rewarded with the title of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Kent">Earl of Kent</ref>. When he died in 1463 without a legitimate male heir, the barony of Fauconberg fell into abeyance between his three daughters: Joan, Alice and Elizabeth.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-tait-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In the late 1460s, Thomas continued to back his cousin the Earl of Warwick when tensions arose between Warwick and Edward IV.  When Warwick rebelled and was forced into exile in 1470, Thomas joined him with several armed ships.  While Warwick was in France negotiating an alliance with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Lancaster">Lancastrian</ref> leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret_of_Anjou">Margaret of Anjou</ref>, Thomas took command of his cousin’s ships and raided English shipping.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In 1471 Thomas was back at sea for the Lancastrians, serving under Warwick in defence of the government of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VI_of_England">Henry VI</ref>, who had regained the throne with the Nevilles' help in 1470.  He was directed to patrol the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Channel">Channel</ref> between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dover">Dover</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calais">Calais</ref> to intercept Edward IV, who had fled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burgundy">Burgundy</ref>.  Edward avoided the Lancastrian fleet and landed at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ravenspur">Ravenspur</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yorkshire">Yorkshire</ref>.  Warwick ordered the Bastard to return from the sea and raise the county of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kent">Kent</ref>, where Warwick enjoyed great popularity with the discontented inhabitants.  However, before these reinforcements could intervene, Edward occupied London, taking Henry VI prisoner, and defeated and killed Warwick in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Barnet">Battle of Barnet</ref> on 14 April.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Arrivall_21-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>With his cousin dead, Thomas landed at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandwich,_Kent">Sandwich</ref>, sending his ships to sail around Kent and up the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thames">Thames</ref> Estuary.  He himself advanced over land towards London, gathering troops as he went, and received notable support from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canterbury">Canterbury</ref> and its mayor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Faunt">Nicholas Faunt</ref>.  Edward meanwhile headed west to oppose the Lancastrian army advancing from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West_Country">West Country</ref>.  On 4 May he triumphed in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Tewkesbury">Battle of Tewkesbury</ref>, killing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_of_Westminster,_Prince_of_Wales">Edward, Prince of Wales</ref>, Edmund Beaufort, Duke of Somerset, and John Beaufort, the duke’s younger brother, and capturing the Queen, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret_of_Anjou">Margaret of Anjou</ref>.  Unaware of these events, Thomas reached <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southwark">Southwark</ref>, and on 14 May wrote to the city government of London, asking to be allowed to bring his men into the city.  They refused, and he responded by burning Southwark.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Arrivall_21-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>When London still refused him entrance he prepared a three-pronged assault on the city.  He removed the artillery from the ships and placed it on the south bank of the Thames so that he could bombard the city.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref>  Most of the Bastard’s army was sent upstream to cross the river and come back to attack London at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aldgate">Aldgate</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopsgate">Bishopsgate</ref>.  A third party would try to cross <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London_Bridge">London Bridge</ref>.</p>
<p>His assault ultimately failed.  His bombardment failed to weaken the will of the London defenders, and the assault at London Bridge was beaten back by the fire of artillery placed by the Londoners at their end of the bridge.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref>  The attack on Bishopsgate was disrupted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Bourchier,_1st_Earl_of_Essex">the Earl of Essex</ref>, who arrived as it was under way.  The party that had the most success was the one at Aldgate, which managed to force the gate open but was beaten back by the defenders' counterattack.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref>  Pursued, the Bastard and his army retreated as far as Stratford and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackwall,_London">Blackwall</ref>, where they boarded the ships and crossed back into Kent.</p>
<p>He then made his way westward to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingston_upon_Thames">Kingston upon Thames</ref> to oppose Edward IV.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Woodville,_Lord_Scales">Edward Woodville, Lord Scales</ref>, who held London for Edward, recognized the king's danger, for the Bastard's army was estimated at twenty thousand men, and recruits were stated to be still coming in.  Woodville sent word to the Bastard that Edward IV was quitting England, and thus induced him to return to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackheath,_London">Blackheath</ref>.  From there Thomas journeyed with six hundred horsemen via <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rochester,_Kent">Rochester</ref> to Sandwich, where he learned that the Lancastrian cause was lost.  Edward IV marched on Sandwich and captured thirteen ships with most of the Bastard's immediate followers. Thomas himself escaped to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southampton">Southampton</ref>, where the King took him prisoner. The King was so thankful to the aldermen of London, that he knighted the mayor, the recorder and other aldermen including Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Hampton_(mayor)">William Hampton</ref>, the following year's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Mayor_of_London">Lord Mayor of London</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>He was then taken to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middleham_Castle">Middleham Castle</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yorkshire">Yorkshire</ref>, the principal seat of his Neville relatives, and beheaded on 22 September 1471. His head was set on London Bridge, ‘looking into Kentward’.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Paston_17-8">[8]</ref> A brother is stated to have been a prisoner at the same time, but he managed to take sanctuary at Beverley.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Paston_17-8">[8]</ref></p>
</text>
