<text id="autogum_bio_doc506" title="Peeter Cornet" shortTile="peeter-cornet" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-06-10" dateModified="2019-08-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peeter_Cornet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Peeter Cornet</head><p><hi rend="bold">Peeter Cornet</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Pierre, Pietro, Peter, Pieter</hi>) (ca. 1570-80 – 27 March 1633) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flanders">Flemish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Composer">composer</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pipe_organ">organist</ref> of the early Baroque period. Although few of his compositions survive, he is widely considered one of the best keyboard composers of the early 17th century.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-grove-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Very little is known about Cornet's life. Much of the information comes from a letter by his widow.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Apel,_339-2">[2]</ref> Cornet was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brussels">Brussels</ref>, which was then the capital of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southern_Netherlands">Southern Netherlands</ref>, in the 1570s. The family included numerous musicians, among them a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Violin">violinist</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Singing">singers</ref> and organists.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-grove-1">[1]</ref> From 1603 to 1606 Cornet worked as organist at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Nicholas_Church,_Brussels">Saint Nicholas Church, Brussels</ref>; around 1606 he became court organist to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_VII,_Archduke_of_Austria">Albert VII, Archduke of Austria</ref> and his wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infanta_Isabella_Clara_Eugenia_of_Spain">Infanta Isabella Clara Eugenia of Spain</ref>, also in Brussels. For one month, in March 1611, Cornet was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_(priest)">canon</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soignies">Soignies</ref>, but he gave up his canonry to marry.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-grove-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Cornet is listed as chapel organist in the surviving court account books from 1612–1618.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-grove-1">[1]</ref> His colleagues included important English composers <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Philips">Peter Philips</ref> (who acted as godfather to one of Cornet's children<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Bull_(composer)">John Bull</ref>, as well as fellow Flemish composers <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Géry_Ghersem">Géry Ghersem</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthijs_Langhedul">Matthijs Langhedul</ref>. Apparently Cornet was also active as an organ consultant and builder. In 1615 he provided advice concerning the organ of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Rumbolds_Cathedral">St. Rumbolds Cathedral</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Sint-Romboutskathedraal</hi>) in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mechelen">Mechelen</ref>, and in 1624 he signed a contract to build a choir division for the same organ.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-grove-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>Cornet's surviving output is small and consists only of keyboard music: eight <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fantasia_(music)">fantasias</ref>, two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Courante">courantes</ref> (with variations), a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toccata">toccata</ref>, a setting of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salve_Regina">Salve Regina</ref>,</hi> and one of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tantum_Ergo">Tantum Ergo</ref>.</hi> One of the fantasias, <hi rend="italic">Fantasia del 5. tuono sopra ut re mi fa sol la</hi>, survives incomplete. The style varies from animated, bright music of the courantes, to elaborate polyphony in the fantasias and the mystical, religious feeling of the <hi rend="italic">Salve Regina</hi> setting.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-grove-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>The fantasias use the Italian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ricercare">ricercare</ref> structure, with its imitative treatment of the subjects in several sections. However, Cornet prefers to use a large number of subjects (up to six) or relies on a double subject (a subject the two halves of which can be used as separate subjects); consequently, most of the fantasias are rather large works.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Apel,_339-2">[2]</ref> The style shows the influence of English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virginals">virginal</ref> music, with unexpected fast runs and characteristic figurations (in some fantasias <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ornament_(music)">ornaments</ref> are even notated using the English symbol: two oblique bars), with the exception of wide skips, broken octaves, and other virtuosic figures such as those found in Bull's and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giles_Farnaby">Farnaby</ref>'s music. A characteristic feature is Cornet's use of rhythmic changes. In sharp contrast to his famed contemporary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_Pieterszoon_Sweelinck">Sweelinck</ref>, who developed a pedantic, systematic approach to applying changes such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augmentation_(music)">augmentation</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diminution">diminution</ref> to the subject, Cornet prefers to only use the techniques where they seem appropriate, and avoids schematic treatment. An augmented version of a subject, for instance, will not simply double all the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Note_value">note values</ref>, but rather double some, triple another, leave another intact, etc. The presentation of the subject is almost always varied.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>The settings of <hi rend="italic">Salve Regina</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tantum Ergo</hi> exhibit similar characteristics. The former comprises five sections (<hi rend="italic">Salve</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ad te clamamus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Eia ergo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">O clemens</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pro fine</hi>). The first three are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fugue">fugues</ref> on the initial motifs of the corresponding lines, the fourth is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cantus_firmus">cantus firmus</ref> setting with the melody first stated in the soprano and then in the tenor, and the fifth combines the subject and its inversion. As in the fantasias, figural elements are seamlessly woven into the polyphonic fabric.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Cornet's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Courante">courantes</ref> are both modelled on English examples. One is followed by three variations of the entire piece.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> The only surviving toccata by Cornet consists entirely of various figurations, including among them the then-fashinable echo effect, frequently used by Sweelinck but only encountered here in Cornet's oeuvre.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Editions</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Pieter Cornet: Collected Keyboard Works</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Corpus of Early Keyboard Music</hi> XXVI, ed. W. Apel (1969).</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Peeter Cornet: Complete Keyboard Music</hi>. Monumenta Musica Neerlandica vol. XVII, <hi rend="italic">Koninklijke Vereniging voor Nederlandse Muziekgeschiedenis</hi>, ed. Pieter Dirksen &amp; Jean Ferrard (Utrecht 2001). <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/90-6375-181-8">90-6375-181-8</ref></item></list>
<head>References and further reading</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Mary Armstrong Ferrard. <hi rend="italic">Peeter Cornet (?–1633), organiste à la cour d'Albert et Isabelle à Bruxelles</hi> (Brussels, 1973)</item>
<item>Willi Apel. <hi rend="italic">The History of Keyboard Music to 1700</hi>, pp.338–344. Translated by Hans Tischler. Indiana University Press, 1972. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/0-253-21141-7">0-253-21141-7</ref>. Originally published as <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Orgel- und Klaviermusik bis 1700</hi> by Bärenreiter-Verlag, Kassel.</item>
<item>Mary Armstrong Ferrard. "Peeter Cornet".  In Deane L. Root (ed.). <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_New_Grove_Dictionary_of_Music_and_Musicians">Grove Music Online. Oxford Music Online</ref></hi>. Oxford University Press.(subscription required)</item></list>
</text>
