<text id="autogum_bio_doc042" title="Antonio Bicchi" shortTile="antonio-bicchi" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-09-24" dateModified="2019-07-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonio_Bicchi" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Antonio Bicchi</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Antonio Bicchi</hi> is an Italian scientist interested in robotics and intelligent machines. He is professor at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Pisa">University of Pisa</ref> and Senior Researcher at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Istituto_Italiano_di_Tecnologia">Istituto Italiano di Tecnologia</ref> in Genoa. He is an Adjunct Professor at the School of Biological and Health Systems Engineering of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arizona_State_University">Arizona State University</ref> in Tempe, Arizona, USA. He is a Fellow of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Institute_of_Electrical_and_Electronics_Engineers">IEEE</ref> since 2005,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> and received the IEEE Saridis Leadership Award<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> and the “Ordine del Cherubino” from University of Pisa in 2019.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dii-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>After obtaining a Laurea (magna cum laude) from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Pisa">University of Pisa</ref> in 1984 and a Ph.D. from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Bologna">University of Bologna</ref> in 1988, Bicchi was with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MIT_Computer_Science_and_Artificial_Intelligence_Laboratory">Artificial Intelligence Lab</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massachusetts_Institute_of_Technology">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</ref> in Cambridge, MA, USA.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>From 1990s to 2012 he directed the Research Center “E. Piaggio” at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Pisa">University of Pisa</ref> where he was also chairman of the Robotics in the Department of Information Engineering.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> During his direction, the Center grew in size and in scientific prestige, leading it to count more of 100 researchers and manage over 60 fundamental and applied research projects.  </p>
<p>In 2009 he was appointed as Senior Scientist by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Istituto_Italiano_di_Tecnologia">Istituto Italiano di Tecnologia</ref> in Genoa, where he created and leads the research line on Soft Robotics for Human Cooperation and Rehabilitation.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dii-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>Since 2013 he serves as an Adjunct Professor of the School of Biological and Health Systems Engineering, Arizona State University in Tempe, Arizona, where he collaborates with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco_Santello">Marco Santello</ref> and other colleagues in NSF and DARPA rehabilitation-oriented projects.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dii-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Research</head>
<p>Antonio Bicchi has contributed to the fields of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Automation">Automatic Control</ref> (the science and engineering of systems), to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haptic_technology">Haptics</ref> (the science and technology for the sense of touch), and to Robotics, especially focusing on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Articulated_soft_robotics">Articulated Soft Robotics</ref>. </p>
<p>He has coordinated several important research projects funded by the EU in the FP7 and H2020 programmes, including CHAT (on the scalability, reconfigurability and security of distributed control for heterogeneous cyberphysical systems), PHRIENDS (on dependability and safety of physical human-robot interaction),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> THE Hand Embodied (on natural and artificial hands), and SoftPro (on the theory and open-source technologies for upper limb prosthetics and rehabilitation). He was scientific co-coordinator of several others, including TOUCH-HAPSYS (on haptics science and interfaces),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> WALK-MAN<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> (on humanoid robots for disaster intervention), and SOMA (on soft manipulation systems).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>His 2012-17 ERC AG project SoftHands used neuroscience and soft robotics technologies to develop a new generation of artificial hands.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> Two subsequent ERC PoC projects (SoftHands Pro-H and SoftHandler) explored the translation of these concepts in real-world products for prosthetics and industrial applications, respectively.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref></p>
<p>The ERC Synergy 2019 project “Natural BionicS” will produce the first completely integrated bionic limb system with direct spinal interfacing, through the cooperation of three groups at Imperial College (led by D. Farina), University Hospital Wien (O. Aszmann) and IIT (A. Bicchi).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref></p>
<head>Organizer and Educator</head>
<p>Antonio Bicchi was president of the Italian Society of Automatic Control, twice vice-president of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IEEE_Robotics_and_Automation_Society">IEEE Robotics and Automation Society</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> and collaborates with major centers for technology transfer in the Italian and European industry. He is a consultant for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_Commission">European Commission</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ministry_of_Education,_Universities_and_Research_(Italy)">Italian Ministry of Education and Research</ref> (MIUR) and agencies in many countries in Europe, America and Asia for the scientific evaluation and accreditation of research centers and universities, research projects, and researchers' careers.</p>
<p>In 2005 he founded the WorldHaptics Conference, since then the largest biennial research meeting in the sciences of touch.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dii-3">[3]</ref> In 2011 he started the series of conferences Automatica which is the main Italian event in the field of Automatic Controls.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dii-3">[3]</ref> In 2015 he founded and was subsequently editor-in-chief of the IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters magazine, which in just two years has become the largest scientific journal in the entire field.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></p>
</text>
