<text id="autogum_bio_doc416" title="Edward Martin (Queens&apos;)" shortTile="edward-martin-queens" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-12" dateModified="2018-11-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Martin_%28Queens%27%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Edward Martin (Queens')</head><p><hi rend="bold">Edward Martin</hi>, D.D. (died 1662) was an English clergyman, ejected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Presidents_of_Queens'_College,_Cambridge">President</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queens'_College,_Cambridge">Queens' College, Cambridge</ref>, and at the end of his life <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean_of_Ely">Dean of Ely</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>A native of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cambridgeshire">Cambridgeshire</ref>, he matriculated in the university of Cambridge, as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sizar">sizar</ref> of Queens' College, 5 July 1605. He graduated B.A. in 1608-9, M. A. in 1612, was elected a Fellow of his college 11 March 1617, and proceeded B.D. in 1621.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In 1627 he was chaplain to Archbishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Laud">William Laud</ref>, and he offended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puritan">Puritan</ref> party by licensing a book by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Jackson_(theologian)">Thomas Jackson</ref>, called <hi rend="italic">An Historical Narration</hi>, and also by preaching a sermon at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Paul's_Cross">St. Paul's Cross</ref> against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Presbyterianism">Presbyterianism</ref>. He became vicar of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oakington">Oakington</ref> in 1626 and rector of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conington,_South_Cambridgeshire">Conington</ref>, Cambridgeshire, in 1630. He was elected President of Queens' College 16 October 1631, being in the same year created D.D. by royal mandate. He was also rector of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_St_Peter_and_St_Paul,_Uppingham">Church of St Peter and St Paul, Uppingham</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rutland">Rutland</ref>, from 1631 to 1637, where he was succeeded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeremy_Taylor">Jeremy Taylor</ref>. In 1638 he was instituted to the rectory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Houghton_Conquest">Houghton Conquest</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bedfordshire">Bedfordshire</ref>, and soon afterwards to that of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doddington,_Cambridgeshire">Doddington</ref>, Cambridgeshire.</p>
<p>In August 1642 he sent the college plate to the king. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oliver_Cromwell">Oliver Cromwell</ref> thereupon surrounded several colleges with soldiers, and took away by force the masters of Queens', <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus_College,_Cambridge">Jesus College</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._John's_College,_Cambridge">St. John's College</ref>, and hurrying them to London, incarcerated them in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tower_of_London">Tower of London</ref> by order of parliament. Martin was afterwards removed to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Petre,_4th_Baron_Petre">Lord Petre</ref>'s house in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aldersgate_Street">Aldersgate Street</ref>, where he drew up the mock petition, entitled his <hi rend="italic">Submission to the Covenant.</hi> Subsequently he was remanded to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ely_Place">Ely House</ref> and other places of confinement for more than five years. In the meanwhile he was ejected from the presidency of Queens' College, and lost all his other preferments.</p>
<p>About August 1648 he effected his escape, and went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thorington">Thorington</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suffolk">Suffolk</ref>, where he resided with Henry Cooke, who had been a member of his college. He assumed the name of Matthews, but was discovered by some soldiers from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Yarmouth">Yarmouth</ref>, was brought to London, and on 23 May 1650 was committed to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gatehouse_Prison">Gatehouse Prison</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Bradshaw_(judge)">John Bradshaw</ref>, president of the council of state. Ultimately, by some interest with Colonel Wanton, he obtained his release and a pardon for breaking prison. He then returned to Suffolk and resumed his own name; but subsequently he went abroad for seven or eight years, during most of which time he lived at Paris with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Hatton,_1st_Baron_Hatton">Christopher Hatton, 1st Baron Hatton</ref>. In 1656 he was resident at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Utrecht_University">Utrecht</ref> with many other royalists.</p>
<p>Returning to England at the Restoration, he was formally restored to the presidency of Queens' College, on 2 August 1660. He was one of the managers of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savoy_Conference">Savoy Conference</ref>. In February. 1662 he was nominated to the deanery of Ely, and was installed by proxy, 25 April 1662. He died three days afterwards on 28 April 1662, and was buried in the college chapel.</p>
</text>
