<text id="autogum_bio_doc322" title="Charles Dieupart" shortTile="charles-dieupart" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-12-21" dateModified="2019-10-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Dieupart" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Charles Dieupart</head><p><hi rend="bold">Charles Dieupart</hi> (after 1667 – 1740) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_people">French</ref> harpsichordist, violinist, and composer. Although he was known as Charles to his contemporaries, his real name may have been François. He was most probably born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris">Paris</ref>, but spent much of his life in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, where he settled sometime after 1702/1703. A prominent member of the Drury Lane musical establishment, Dieupart was active both as composer and performer and actively participated in the musical life of the city. However, after about 1712 he earned his income mostly by teaching, and in his later years lived in poverty. He is best remembered today for a collection of six harpsichord suites which influenced Johann Sebastian Bach's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Suites">English Suites</ref></hi>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Details of Dieupart's early life and training are sketchy, and the reason for his emigration to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/England">England</ref> is unknown. The earliest document to refer to the composer is his own <hi lang="fr" rend="italic">Six Suittes de clavessin</hi>, published in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amsterdam">Amsterdam</ref> in 1701. He is next heard of on 11 February 1703 in London, when he performed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arcangelo_Corelli">Corelli</ref>'s music at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drury_Lane">Drury Lane</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gasparo_Visconti">Gasparo Visconti</ref>. Dieupart settled in London and eventually became an important member of the Drury Lane musical establishment. He collaborated with playwright <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Anthony_Motteux">Peter Anthony Motteux</ref>, composer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Clayton_(composer)">Thomas Clayton</ref>, and others; he also participated in performances of music by Italian composers such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Bononcini">Giovanni Bononcini</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domenico_Scarlatti">Domenico Scarlatti</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-grove-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In late 1707 Dieupart became involved in establishing an operatic project at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen's_Theatre">Queen's Theatre</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haymarket,_London">Haymarket</ref>, London. Although he evidently played a significant part in the project, he was dropped by the management after about a year, in late 1708. Dieupart tried organizing a series of concerts at York Buildings in 1711 and 1712, but ended up giving only a few. After 1712 he was mostly active as a teacher, although his music was still performed in concerts until at least 1726, and he was apparently a regular member of the Drury Lane orchestra. Dieupart's last known public appearance was in 1724. According to music historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Hawkins_(author)">John Hawkins</ref>, whose work is the most important source on Dieupart's biography, the composer died at a very advanced age and in poverty.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-grove-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Music</head>
<p>Dieupart's best-known work is <hi lang="fr" rend="italic">Six Suittes de clavessin</hi> (Amsterdam, 1701). As the title indicates, it contains six harpsichord <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suite_(music)">suites</ref>. All of them are in seven movements, always with the sequence <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ouverture">ouverture</ref> – <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allemande">allemande</ref> – <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Courante">courante</ref> – <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarabande">sarabande</ref> – <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gavotte">gavotte</ref>,  a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Menuet">menuet</ref> or a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Passepied">passepied</ref>, and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gigue">gigue</ref> as the final movement. Some of the movements are linked thematically. The music represents a highly successful synthesis of French, Italian and English styles, married with imaginative harmony. The same can be said about most of Dieupart's other music, which has been neglected in recent times. The suites were popular even during the composer's lifetime: they were reissued already in 1702, arranged for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Violin">violin</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recorder_(musical_instrument)">recorder</ref> (voice flute and fourth flute) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basso_continuo">basso continuo</ref>, and then 13 of the movements were published in London in 1705 as <hi rend="italic">Select Lessons for the Harpsichord or Spinnett</hi>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Sebastian_Bach">Johann Sebastian Bach</ref> copied all six suites sometime between 1709 and 1714,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> and was influenced by Dieupart's music, particularly in the famous <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Suites">English Suites</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-grove-1">[1]</ref> Dieupart's suites may have also inspired <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolas_Siret">Nicolas Siret</ref>, whose first book adopts the suite's initial opening as an example.</p>
<head>List of works</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Six suittes de clavessin</hi> (A, D, b, e, F, f) (Amsterdam, 1701)
<list type="unordered"><item>Instrumental arrangements published as <hi rend="italic">Six suittes</hi> (Amsterdam, 1702)</item>
<item>Thirteen individual movements published as <hi rend="italic">Select Lessons for the Harpsichord or Spinnett</hi> (London, 1705)</item></list></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Songs in the New Opera, Call'd Love's Triumph, The Symphonys or Instrumental Parts in the Opera Call'd Love's Triumph</hi> (London, 1708)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">The Overture and Chaconne belonging to</hi> [...] <hi rend="italic">the Opera of Thomyris</hi> (London, 1708; lost)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Six Sonatas or Solos</hi> (G, a, e, B, g, F), for recorder and basso continuo (London, 1717)</item>
<item>Sonata in D minor for oboe, strings and basso continuo</item>
<item>Sonata (Ouverture) in E minor for strings</item>
<item>Concerto in A minor for soprano recorder/flute/oboe, 2 oboes, bassoon, strings, and basso continuo</item>
<item>Concerto in A major for violin, 2 oboes, bassoon, strings, and basso continuo</item>
<item>Concerto in B♭ major for 2 violins, 2 oboes, bassoon, strings, and basso continuo</item>
<item>Concerto in E minor for 2 flutes, 2 horns, strings, and basso continuo</item>
<item>Concerto in B minor for trumpet, 2 oboes, strings, and basso continuo</item>
<item>miscellaneous keyboard pieces and 33 airs published in various collections</item></list>
</text>
