<text id="autogum_bio_doc346" title="Johann Peter Spaeth" shortTile="johann-peter-spaeth" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-06-12" dateModified="2018-11-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Peter_Spaeth" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Johann Peter Spaeth</head><p><hi rend="bold">Johann Peter Spaeth</hi>, also known as <hi rend="bold">Moses Germanus</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Moses Ashkenazi</hi> (1st half of the 17th century in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vienna">Vienna</ref> – April 27, 1701 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amsterdam">Amsterdam</ref>) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Austrians">Austrian</ref> theologian that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religious_conversion">converted</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judaism">Judaism</ref>.</p>
<head>Lutheran convert</head>
<p>Amid rumors of impending war, his father, a poor shoemaker, sought refuge between 1642 and 1645 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augsburg">Augsburg</ref>. He was a pious <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic">Roman Catholic</ref>, and confided his son Peter to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesuit">Jesuits</ref> for his education. Spaeth later went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vienna">Vienna</ref> and earned his living as a private tutor. Becoming dissatisfied with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholic_dogma">Catholic dogma</ref>, he embraced <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lutheranism">Lutheranism</ref> (1680). On that occasion he wrote his first work: "<hi rend="italic">Εκιαγραφια, Theologico-Philosophico Ænigmatica</hi>". The work found much favor with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M._Spitzel">M. Spitzel</ref>, head of the board of theological studies at Augsburg, who recommended Spaeth to many influential personages in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strassburg">Strassburg</ref> and afterward to others in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frankfort-on-the-Main">Frankfort-on-the-Main</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1683 Spaeth returned to Catholicism, which he defended and praised in a work entitled <hi rend="italic">Judicium Amoris de Fundamentalibus Quibusdam, Qui Feruntur Erroribus Ecclesiæ Romanæ</hi>. But this reconciliation did not last. New doubts assailed his mind; and after having mingled with the members of certain <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dissenter">dissident</ref> sects, such as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socinian">Socinians</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mennonite">Mennonites</ref>, and after having taken up the study of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hebrew_literature">Hebrew literature</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kabbalah">cabalistic</ref> writings, he renounced Christianity and vehemently attacked it. Even the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sermon_on_the_Mount">Sermon on the Mount</ref>, as requiring an impossible ideality, did not escape his criticism.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> As for the Christian writings other than the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Testament">New Testament</ref>, he held that until <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantine_I">Constantine I</ref> founded Christianity they were all drawn from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jewish">Jewish</ref> tradition.</p>
<head>Convert to Judaism</head>
<p>It seems that Spaeth did not intend to become a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proselyte">proselyte</ref> to Judaism, and that his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religious_conversion">conversion</ref> was brought about, as he himself relates, through the following incident: Once a crucifix dropped from his pocket, and it was picked up by a Jew, who said: "It is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israel">Israel</ref>, the man of sorrow!" <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> Says Spaeth:</p>
<p>From those words I understood the 53d chapter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isaiah">Isaiah</ref>: the Jews bore the sins of the heathen, while they were daily persecuted by them. From time immemorial they had been treated in a shameful manner. As the whole history of the Passion tended to render the Jews odious, so the same sort of thing happens nowadays. For instance, the Jews are said to have murdered a child, and to have distributed the blood in quills for the use of their women in childbirth. I have discovered this outrageous fraud in time; and, therefore, I abandon Christianity, which permits such things.</p>
<p>Spaeth became converted at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cleves">Cleves</ref>, taking the name <hi rend="italic">Moses Germanus</hi>.</p>
<head>Literary works</head>
<p>Besides the above-mentioned works, Moses published the following:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>A <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Translation">translation</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judah_ha-Levi">Judah ha-Levi</ref>'s poem "<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mi_Kamoka">Mi Kamoka</ref></hi>" into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin">Latin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_language">German</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_language">Spanish</ref>, with an introduction in Spanish;</item>
<item>"<hi rend="italic">Geistiger Dreieckiger Spiegel der Lehre von dem Weiblichen Geschlechte</hi>" ;</item>
<item>"<hi rend="italic">Epistolæ ad Vindicandum Judaismum</hi>" (published by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wachter">Wachter</ref> in his "<hi rend="italic">Der Spinozismus in Jüdenthumb</hi>") ;</item>
<item>"<hi rend="italic">A <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Groote_Hosianna">Groote Hosianna</ref> der Joden, te Verwellkommenden <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Messias">Messias</ref></hi>" ;</item>
<item>"<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maran_Ata">Maran Ata</ref></hi>", a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jewish_Christian">Jewish Christian</ref> mystical writing ;</item>
<item>"<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus">Jesus</ref> Christi Ehre und Lebre, Gerettet Wider Alle Christen</hi>" ;</item>
<item>"<hi rend="italic">Solus ex Judæis Contra Spinosam</hi>" ;</item>
<item>"<hi rend="italic">De Ortu et Progressu Medicinæ per Judæos Diatribe</hi>" ;</item></list>
</text>
