<text id="autogum_bio_doc634" title="Maria of Bosnia" shortTile="maria-bosnia" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-07-18" dateModified="2018-05-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_of_Bosnia" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Maria of Bosnia</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Maria of Bosnia</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_language">German</ref>: <hi lang="de" rend="italic">Maria von Bosnien</hi>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bosnian_language">Bosnian</ref>:Марија, <hi rend="italic">Marija</hi>; d.27 April 1403) was a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Kotromanić">House of Kotromanić</ref> who married into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Helfenstein">House of Helfenstein</ref>.</p>
<head>Parentage</head>
<p>Maria's parentage and connection to the House of Kotromanić is uncertain. King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_I_of_Hungary">Louis I of Hungary</ref>, husband of Ban <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_II_of_Bosnia">Stephen II of Bosnia</ref>'s daughter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_of_Bosnia">Elizabeth</ref>, apparently mentions her in a charter as Stephen's sister.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rabić-1">[1]</ref> Some historiographers have interpreted this literally, considering her a daughter of Ban <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_I_of_Bosnia">Stephen I of Bosnia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_of_Serbia">Elizabeth of Serbia</ref> born in 1315.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-gz1-2">[2]</ref> This, however, is very unlikely: it would mean that she married a (never-married and childless) nobleman in her forties, had her youngest children in her fifties, and lived to be over 90 years old.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rabić-1">[1]</ref> The 16th-century historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oswald_Gabelkover">Oswald Gabelkover</ref> names her a younger <hi rend="italic">daughter</hi> of Ban Stephen II. This view is supported by King Louis and Queen Elizabeth's choice of names for their elder daughters, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_of_Hungary_(1370–1378)">Catherine</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary,_Queen_of_Hungary">Maria</ref>, purportedly named after the Queen's supposed sisters, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_of_Bosnia,_Countess_of_Cilli">Catherine</ref> and Maria. That would make Maria a daughter of Stephen's last wife, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_of_Kuyavia">Elizabeth of Kuyavia</ref>, and place her year of birth shortly after 1335. Two other theories attribute Maria's parentage to Stephen's brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vladislav_of_Bosnia">Vladislaus</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jelena_Šubić">Jelena Šubić</ref> or to another younger brother Ninoslaus.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rabić-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Countess of Helfenstein</head>
<figure><caption>Helfenstein coat of arms</caption></figure>
<p>Maria's marriage to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulrich_V,_Count_of_Helfenstein">Ulrich V, Count of Helfenstein</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-gz1-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ez1-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> was most likely arranged by his overlord, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Roman_Emperor_Charles_IV">Holy Roman Emperor Charles IV</ref>. Maria probably resided for some time at the Hungarian court along with Elizabeth of Bosnia, then fiancée and later wife of the King. On 26 April 1352, the Hungarian noblemen escorted Maria to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Passau">Passau</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Roman_Empire">Holy Roman Empire</ref>. By the time King Louis mentioned her again, in a charter dated 25 March 1353, Maria was already a married woman. The marriage brought considerable prestige to Ulrich. Maria too was aware of her higher status and, in addition to the title Countess of Helfenstein, often referred to herself as Duchess of Bosnia. From 1365 until 1399, she signed her donations as <hi rend="italic">"Maria Herzogin von Bosnien"</hi>. As a compensation for marrying below her status, Maria enjoyed influence and autonomy highly unusual for a married woman. Early in their marriage, Maria pushed her husband to divide the county he had jointly ruled with his cousin and namesake, Ulrich the Younger. The couple were noted benefactors and also enjoyed imperial favour. They had six sons – Frederick (born in 1357), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_of_Helfenstein">Louis</ref>, William, Conrad, Ulrich and John, and three daughters – Agnes, Beatrix and Maria.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rabić-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Ulrich died in 1372 and was succeeded by his and Maria's sons, Conrad and Frederick. Three of their sons had chosen ecclesiastical careers, with Louis becoming <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_Kalocsa">Archbishop of Kalocsa</ref> in 1382, probably thanks to Maria's connection to the Hungarian royal family. Maria's widowhood was burdened with financial difficulties, which forced her and her sons to sell a large part of the Helfenstein patrimony, including Maria's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dower">dower</ref> lands. She spent the rest of her life in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bühringen_Castle">Bühringen Castle</ref>, which she had received as dower, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bad_Überkingen">Bad Überkingen</ref>. She died on 27 April 1403 and was likely buried in Überkingen. The epitaph on her tombstone was illegible already by the mid-16th century.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rabić-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>Maria has traditionally been blamed for the financial downfall of the House of Helfenstein. Gabelkover attributes the family's misfortune following Maria and Ulrich's marriage to the disparity between their ranks, i.e. to Ulrich's marrying up the social ladder. She was accused of wastefulness and of raising her daughters in such manner.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rabić-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>A street in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geislingen_an_der_Steige">Geislingen an der Steige</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baden-Württemberg">Baden-Württemberg</ref>, Germany bears the name <hi rend="italic">Maria-von-Bosnien-Weg</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> There is also a musical titled <hi rend="italic">Maria von Bosnien – eine Hochzeit und ein Todesfall</hi> ("Maria of Bosnia – a Wedding and a Funeral").<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rabić-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ez1-3">[3]</ref></p>
</text>
