<text id="autogum_bio_doc095" title="Tirzah Firestone" shortTile="tirzah-firestone" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-11-16" dateModified="2019-08-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tirzah_Firestone" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tirzah Firestone</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tirzah Firestone</hi> (born May 27, 1954) is a Jungian psychotherapist, author, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jewish_Renewal">Jewish Renewal</ref> rabbi. She is the founding rabbi of Congregation Nevei Kodesh, a Jewish Renewal synagogue in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boulder,_Colorado">Boulder, Colorado</ref>, and is now Rabbi Emerita there.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bio-1">[1]</ref> She was ordained by Rabbi Zalman Schachter Shalomi in 1992 and is a leader in the international Jewish Renewal Movement.</p>
<p>Widely known for her work on Jewish feminism and the modern applications of Jewish mystical wisdom, Firestone teaches nationally on Jewish ancestral healing and the common boundary between ancient Jewish heritage and modern psychology.</p>
<p>Firestone is an active Member of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ALEPH:_Alliance_for_Jewish_Renewal">Aleph: Alliance for Jewish Renewal</ref> (1994–present) and the Ohalah Rabbinic Association (2003–present). She was the National Co-Chair of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T'ruah">T'ruah</ref>: The Rabbinic Call for Human Rights (2009–2010) and is currently serving on the board of the Yesod Foundation (1997–present).</p>
<p>Tirzah Firestone was raised in an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orthodox_Jewish">Orthodox Jewish</ref> family in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Louis">St. Louis</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missouri">Missouri</ref>. Firestone was the fifth of six children born to Sol and Kate Firestone. She is the younger sister of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shulamith_Firestone">Shulamith Firestone</ref>. She went to Hebrew day schools through high school. Firestone earned her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masters_Degree">Masters Degree</ref> in Holistic Counseling from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beacon_College">Beacon College</ref> in 1982; and her doctorate in depth psychology from Pacifica Graduate Institute in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Barbara,_California">Santa Barbara, California</ref>, in 2015.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bio-1">[1]</ref> After graduating, she spent an extended period living in Israel and working on Kibbutz Ma'ale Gilboa and Moshav Amirim. She also apprenticed in Jerusalem with Rabanit Leah Sharabi, the wife of Kabbalist, Rabbi Mordechai Sharabi, who influenced her greatly. In her memoir, Firestone tells the story of how her first husband inspired her return to Judaism by means of his own faith and love of Judaism. Firestone remarried in 1999 to David Friedman. Together they have three grown children.</p>
<head>Publications</head>
<head>Books</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Wounds into Wisdom: Healing Intergenerational Jewish Trauma</hi> (Monkfish Press, 2019)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">The Receiving: Reclaiming Jewish Women’s Wisdom</hi> (Harper San Francisco, 2003)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">With Roots in Heaven: One Woman's Passionate Journey into the Heart of Her Faith</hi> (Plume, 1999)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></item></list>
<head>Articles</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>"Intergenerational Trauma and the Patriarchy," published in <hi rend="italic">Tikkun Magazine</hi>, Spring 2019.</item>
<item>"War and Peace: Intertwining Threads in the Jewish Tradition," in <hi rend="italic">The Warrior and the Pacifist: Competing Motifs in Buddhism, Judaism, Christianity, and Islam</hi>  Lester Kurtz, Ed., Routledge Press, 2018.</item>
<item>"Trauma Legacies in the Middle East", published in <hi rend="italic">Tikkun Magazine,</hi> 2014, 29 (3): 6-10.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></item>
<item>"The Jewish Cultural Complex," published in <hi rend="italic">Psychological Perspectives: A Quarterly Journal of Jungian Thought</hi>, Vol 57, No 3, August, 2014.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></item>
<item>"At the Altar of Consciousness: The Individuation of God and Abraham", published in <hi rend="italic">Psychological Perspectives: A Quarterly Journal of Jungian</hi> <hi rend="italic">Thought</hi>, Volume 56, 2013.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></item>
<item>“Transforming Our Stories Through Midrash”, in <hi rend="italic">New Jewish Feminism: Probing the Past, Forging the Future,</hi> edited by Rabbi Elyse Goldstein, Jewish Lights Publishing, Woodstock, VT, 2009.</item>
<item>“Flatbread in Feeble Times”, in <hi rend="italic">The Women’s Seder Sourcebook: Rituals and Readings for Use at the Passover Seder</hi>, Edited by Anisfeld, Mohr &amp; Spector, Jewish Lights Publishing, Woodstock, VT, 2003.</item></list>
<head>CDs</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>"Ashreynu! (How Lucky We Are!) Jewish Chants for Meditation and Prayer" with Lisa Antosofsky, and Sheldon Sands.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></item>
<item>"The Woman's Kabbalah: Ecstatic Jewish Practices for Women", Sounds True, Boulder, Colorado, 2000.</item></list>
</text>
