<text id="autogum_bio_doc503" title="Archibald Douglas, Parson of Douglas" shortTile="archibald-douglas" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-01-23" dateModified="2018-07-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archibald_Douglas%2C_Parson_of_Douglas" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Archibald Douglas, Parson of Douglas</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Archibald Douglas, Parson of Douglas</hi>, (b.before 1540 – d. after 1587) was also Parson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glasgow">Glasgow</ref>, a Senator of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/College_of_Justice">College of Justice</ref>, Ambassador to Queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I_of_England">Elizabeth I of England</ref>, and a notorious intriguer.</p>
<p>As a clergyman and Master of Arts, he was known as Mr Archibald Douglas throughout his career. He was Parson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas,_Lanarkshire">Douglas, Lanarkshire</ref>, prior to 15 January 1561/2 when he was awarded the income of the Third of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benefice">Benefices</ref> for that parish. He was appointed to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/College_of_Justice">College of Justice</ref> on 13 November 1565 as an Extraordinary Lord in place of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adam_Bothwell">Adam Bothwell</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Orkney">Bishop of Orkney</ref>.</p>
<p>Accused with his brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Douglas_of_Whittinghame">William Douglas</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whittingehame_Tower">Whittingehame</ref>, of involvement in the conspiracy to murder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Riccio">David Riccio</ref>, he was obliged to retire to France for some time. But the husband of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary,_Queen_of_Scots">Mary, Queen of Scots</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Stuart,_Lord_Darnley">Henry Stuart, Lord Darnley</ref>, secured his return to Scotland, where Douglas then successfully negotiated the pardons of the other conspirators, gazetted on 25 December 1566.</p>
<p>He then entered into the intrigues of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Hepburn,_4th_Earl_of_Bothwell">James Hepburn, 4th Earl of Bothwell</ref> for the assassination of Darnley, and acted as the agent between them and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent_Morton">Earl of Morton</ref>. According to the on-the-scaffold confession of his servant Thomas Binning, he was actually present at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kirk_o'_Field">Kirk o' Field</ref> on the night of the murder (9/10 February 1567). In the confusion of the hour Douglas lost his shoes, which he had removed, which were found in the morning and known to be his. No pursuit was however, at that time, instituted against him. Later Morton said that Archibald and his brother Robert had helped find the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casket_Letters">Casket Letters</ref>. When George Dalgleish was threatened with torture he asked to speak to Archibald, and showed Robert where he had hidden the letters.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>On 2 June 1568, he was raised to a Lord Ordinary in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/College_of_Justice">College of Justice</ref> in place of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Leslie,_Bishop_of_Ross">John Leslie, Bishop of Ross</ref>. Archibald was often sent as a messenger to England. He caused concern in January 1569 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allerton,_West_Yorkshire">Allerton</ref> when he let slip that he already knew that Mary was going to be transferred from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolton_Castle">Bolton Castle</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tutbury_Castle">Tutbury Castle</ref>, which meant to be secret.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In September 1570 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent_Lennox">Regent Lennox</ref> sent him to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Radclyffe,_3rd_Earl_of_Sussex">Earl of Sussex</ref>, Governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berwick_upon_Tweed">Berwick upon Tweed</ref> to congratulate him on his victory over the Border friends of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary,_Queen_of_Scots">Mary, Queen of Scots</ref>, and to negotiate support for the Regent's authority. Shortly afterwards he obtained the Parsonage of Glasgow, but with some difficulty as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kirk">Kirk</ref> at first felt him to be unqualified. In January 1572, however, the requisite sanction was obtained, and he received the Thirds of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benefice">Benefices</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newlands,_Glasgow">Newlands, Glasgow</ref> thereafter.</p>
<p>In April 1572 he was arrested following the discovery that he was assisting the party of Mary, Queen of Scots and Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Kirkcaldy_of_Grange">William Kirkcaldy of Grange</ref> who held <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edinburgh_Castle">Edinburgh Castle</ref>, by bringing money sent from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fernando_Álvarez_de_Toledo,_3rd_Duke_of_Alba">Duke of Alba</ref> from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_Netherlands">Spanish Netherlands</ref>. He was at the same time accused of conspiring for the death of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent_Morton">Earl of Morton</ref>. The Marshall of Berwick and diplomat Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Drury">William Drury</ref> regretted his arrest because he had plotted with Douglas to kidnap <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Seton,_7th_Lord_Seton">George, Lord Seton</ref>, who was negotiating for Mary with the Duke of Alba, and their plan did not take effect.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> He was warded (held under house arrest) at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stirling_Castle">Stirling Castle</ref> (another source says <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loch_Leven_Castle">Loch Leven Castle</ref>).</p>
<p>He appears to have lived, if not in prison, at least in privacy, during the Regency of Morton, but was, on 11 November 1578, restored to his former place on the bench, following a request letter from King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_VI">James VI</ref> to that effect. On 31 December, however, he was denounced to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privy_Council_of_Scotland">Privy Council of Scotland</ref> as guilty of Darnley's murder, and orders were given for his arrest. But having been forewarned by his kinsman George Douglas of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Longniddry">Longniddry</ref>, he fled from his wife's tower-house at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morham">Morham</ref> to England. Queen Elizabeth first agreed to have him returned upon the guarantee of "unsuspect judges and other persons on the assise", but this guarantee could not be given so he remained for the time being in England.</p>
<p>On 28 November 1581, he was forfeited by Act of Parliament for the murder of Lord Darnley, which, they argued, was proved by his flight to England, and the evidence of his servant Thomas Binning, who had, in June 1581, already been executed for the same crime.</p>
<p>Owing to the influence of his friend, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Gray,_6th_Lord_Gray">Master of Gray</ref>, he returned on a safe-conduct to Scotland, arriving in Edinburgh on 15 April 1586. His (nominal) trial took place on 26 May, (reported at length in Pitcairn's <hi rend="italic">Criminal Trials</hi>). He was acquitted. There was great uproar. To make matters worse he was then appointed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_VI">James VI</ref> his personal Ambassador to Elizabeth 1st, a post he took up in September.  While in that post it is said that he assisted the Master of Gray, William Keith, and Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Melville,_1st_Lord_Melville">Robert Melville of Murdocairny</ref> to move Elizabeth towards clemency for Mary Queen of Scots, although Dalrymple disputes this. He was at length dismissed from this post, being succeeded by Sir Robert Melville.</p>
<p>After this nothing much appears to be known of him. It is possible he may have died. However, a Mr.Archibald Douglas, Archdeacon of Glasgow (in that post prior to November 1596), is mentioned in the Privy Council Registers on 28 October 1598, and again on 4 December 1599, but it is not known if this is the same person.</p>
<p>Archibald Douglas married, about 1578, (as her third husband) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Hepburn">Jane</ref> (d. before August 1599), daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Hepburn,_3rd_Earl_of_Bothwell">Patrick Hepburn, 3rd Earl of Bothwell</ref>.</p>
</text>
