<text id="autogum_bio_doc385" title="Mark Anthony Galliardello" shortTile="mark-anthony-galliardello" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-05-26" dateModified="2016-06-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Anthony_Galliardello" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Mark Anthony Galliardello</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Mark Anthony Galliardello</hi>, probably <hi rend="italic">né</hi> <hi rend="bold">Alberti</hi> (died 15 June 1585), was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viol">viol</ref> player and member of the English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tudor_dynasty">Tudor</ref> court <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consort_of_instruments">consort of instruments</ref>. Of Italian origin, he settled in London in 1545, remaining in the royal service for the rest of his life.  As a conscientious <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Churchwarden">churchwarden</ref> who compiled unusually detailed records, he is an important source for scholars of late Tudor church history.</p>
<head>Life and career</head>
<p>Galliardello was born in Italy – in or near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venice">Venice</ref> according to one source;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dnb-1">[1]</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brescia">Brescia</ref> according to others.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> In either case he was a subject of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doge_of_Venice">Doge of Venice</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dnb-1">[1]</ref> Brescia being a Venetian possession in the 16th century.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> The Venetian dominions were at the time the centre of the manufacture of string instruments, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consort_of_instruments">consorts</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viol">viols</ref> originated there, becoming established in the rest of Europe in succeeding decades.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref>  In 1542 Galliardello is recorded as being employed in France by the Cardinal of Lorraine.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-h42-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>In 1539 the French ambassador to the court of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VIII_of_England">Henry VIII of England</ref> recorded, "The king … now gives himself up to amusement, going to play every night upon the Thames, with harps, chanters and all kinds of music and pastime. He evidently delights now in painting and embroidery, having sent men to France, Flanders, Italy and elsewhere for masters of this art, and also for musicians."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Cromwell">Thomas Cromwell</ref>, charged with improving the music at court, recruited members of musical families from France – the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lanier_family_tree">Laniers</ref> – and from the Venetian empire –  the Bassanos, Ferraboscos, Lupos and Albertis, the last of whom came to be known in England as the Galliardellos.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dnb-1">[1]</ref> Despite their Italian names, many of these families were of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sephardic">Sephardic</ref> Jewish origin, displaced from Spain or Portugal; is it not certain whether Galliardello's family, though certainly Jewish, was among them.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dnb-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-h42-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Galliardello entered the service of Henry VIII in May 1545.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dnb-1">[1]</ref> The ensemble that he formed with his fellow immigrants is believed to have featured the first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Violin">violins</ref> in England.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> Galliardello settled in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_Smithfield">East Smithfield</ref>, part of a substantial immigrant community. By the accession of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I_of_England">Elizabeth I</ref> he had married, and  moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minories">Minories</ref>, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City_of_London">City of London</ref>. His wife, Margery, gave birth to two daughters,  Lucretia (1563) and Frances (1566) and two sons, Mark Anthony (1565) and Caesar (1568). The elder son died in infancy; the second followed his father into the court musical ensemble.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dnb-1">[1]</ref> A month before Caesar's birth Galliardello was granted letters of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denization">denization</ref> as a royal servant, giving him many of the rights of English nationals.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dnb-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Galliardello converted to Christianity, and became a devoted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestant">protestant</ref>. He is of importance to ecclesiastical historians of the period because of the unusually detailed records he kept as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Churchwarden">churchwarden</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_Holy_Trinity,_Minories">Holy Trinity, Minories</ref>. The historian Brett Usher writes, "His conscientious drudgery provides historians with vital clues to the development of nonconformist activity in London in the aftermath of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vestments_controversy">vestiarian controversy</ref> which divided the capital after March 1566."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dnb-1">[1]</ref> Galliardello became prosperous enough to contribute generously to church funds.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> and was praised as of "most good name and fame and godly report of all his neighbours".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dnb-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Lucretia and Frances both married royal musicians, respectively Henry Troches and John Lanier. Frances's son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Lanier">Nicholas Lanier</ref>, became the first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_the_Queen's_Music">Master of the King's Music</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dnb-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Galliardello died on 15 June at Holy Trinity, where he was buried two days later.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dnb-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
