<text id="autogum_bio_doc293" title="William Hiseland" shortTile="william-hiseland" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-02-11" dateModified="2019-05-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Hiseland" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>William Hiseland</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">William Hiseland</hi> (August 6, 1620 (purportedly)– 7 February 1732), sometimes spelt <hi rend="bold">William Hasland</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Haseland</hi>, was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_England">English</ref> and later <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British_Army">British</ref> soldier and reputed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supercentenarian">supercentenarian</ref>. In 1709, at the purported age of eighty-nine, he fought at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Malplaquet">Battle of Malplaquet</ref> and was believed to be the oldest soldier on the field. He claimed to become the last survivor of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Civil_War">English Civil Wars</ref>, which he had served in from 1642 to 1651.</p>
<p>Hiseland attained the rank of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sergeant">sergeant</ref>. In extreme old age he became a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chelsea_pensioner">Chelsea pensioner</ref>, although he had to give up his place as an in-pensioner when he married at the claimed age of 103. He is buried at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Hospital_Chelsea">Royal Hospital</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chelsea,_London">Chelsea</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>A native of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiltshire">Wiltshire</ref>, Hiseland first became a soldier at the age of thirteen and served all through the English Civil Wars.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-wam-1">[1]</ref> A <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cavalier">Royalist</ref>, he fought for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_I_of_England">King Charles</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Edgehill">Battle of Edgehill</ref> on 23 October 1642.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-winder-2">[2]</ref> As well as his service in the Civil War, he followed the colours again in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Williamite_War_in_Ireland">Williamite War in Ireland</ref> and in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_of_the_Spanish_Succession">War of the Spanish Succession</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> He was the last survivor of Edgehill and retired with the rank of sergeant.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-winder-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Amid the War of the Spanish Succession, Hiseland was one of the seasoned campaigners the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Churchill,_1st_Duke_of_Marlborough">Duke of Marlborough</ref> took into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flanders">Flanders</ref> in June 1709. At the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Malplaquet">Battle of Malplaquet</ref> on 11 September 1709 Hiseland served with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Scots">Royal Scots</ref>, and the regiment claimed the distinction of having both the oldest and the youngest men on the field, as a Private McBain carried his three-week-old baby son throughout the battle in a knapsack.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-scotsman-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Lennox,_1st_Duke_of_Richmond">Charles Lennox, 1st Duke of Richmond</ref>, rewarded Hiseland's long service with a pension of one <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crown_(British_coin)">crown</ref> a week, and this was matched by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Walpole">Sir Robert Walpole</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-wam-1">[1]</ref> until in recognition of his 80 years of service to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Crown">the Crown</ref> Hiseland was given a place as an in-pensioner of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Hospital_Chelsea">Royal Hospital, Chelsea</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NYT-1886-5">[5]</ref> He attained the age of 100 while in the Royal Hospital, but at the age of 103 had to leave and become an out-pensioner following his marriage.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-scotsman-4">[4]</ref> After his wife died he returned as an in-pensioner and died at the claimed age of 111.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-winder-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>On 1 August 1730 Hiseland sat for a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portrait">portrait</ref> in oils by George Alsop.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> This survives in the museum of the Royal Hospital.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-winder-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Monument</head><p>
The inscription on Hiseland's tomb in the Royal Hospital's burial ground reads as follows: </p><p>Here Lies WILLIAM HISELAND  A Vetran if ever Soldier was  Who merited well a Pension  If Long Service be a Merit  Having served <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psalm_90">upwards of the Days of Man</ref>  Antient but not Superannuated  Engaged in a series of Wars Civil as well as Foreign  Yet not maimed or worn out by either  His Complexion was fresh &amp; florid  His Health hale &amp; hearty  His Memory exact &amp; ready  In Stature He exceeded the Military size  In Strength He surpassed the prime of Youth  and What rendered his Age Still more Patriarchal  When above one Hundred Years Old  He took unto him a Wife  Read Fellow Soldiers and Reflect  That there is a Spiritual Warfare  As well as a Warfare Temporal  Born vj of August 1620 Died vij of Feb. 1732 Aged 112<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NYT-1886-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>In this instance, "1732" refers to what is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Style_and_New_Style_dates">now called</ref> 1733, as at that time the calendar year began on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_Day">Lady Day</ref>, 25 March, and not on 1 January.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
</text>
