<text id="autogum_bio_doc788" title="Konrad I, Duke of Głogów" shortTile="konrad--duke-glogow" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-08-14" dateModified="2019-04-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konrad_I%2C_Duke_of_G%C5%82og%C3%B3w" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Konrad I, Duke of Głogów</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Konrad I of Głogów</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polish_language">Polish</ref>: <hi lang="pl" rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Konrad I głogowski</hi></hi>; c.1228/31 – 6 August 1273/74), a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silesian_Piasts">Silesian Piasts</ref>, was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dukes_of_Silesia">Silesian</ref> duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Głogów">Głogów</ref> from 1251 until his death.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Konrad was the fourth son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_II_the_Pious">Henry II the Pious</ref>, Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Silesia">Silesia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Polish_monarchs">High Duke of Poland</ref> from 1238, by his wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_of_Bohemia,_Duchess_of_Silesia">Anna</ref>, daughter of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Přemyslid_dynasty">Přemyslid</ref> king <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottokar_I_of_Bohemia">Ottokar I of Bohemia</ref>. At the time of his father's death in the 1241 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Legnica">Battle of Legnica</ref> against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Horde">Golden Horde</ref>, he and his younger brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ladislaus_of_Salzburg">Władysław</ref> were placed under the guardianship of their eldest brother Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolesław_II_Rogatka">Bolesław II Rogatka</ref>. After Henry's sudden death, the Silesian Piasts were not able to maintain their dominant position: Bolesław II tried to succeed his father on the Polish throne at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seniorate_Province">Kraków</ref>, but eventually could not prevail against his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Piast">Piast</ref> cousin <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konrad_I_of_Masovia">Konrad I of Masovia</ref>.</p>
<p>In order to avoid further fragmentation of the paternal lands, the elder duke, with the approval of their mother, sent Konrad to study in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris">Paris</ref>, where he was to be educated with the intention of becoming a priest in the future. However, in 1248, when the young man found out about the division of the family lands between his older brothers Bolesław II, ruling as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Legnica">Duke of Legnica</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_III_the_White">Henry III the White</ref>, Duke at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wrocław">Wrocław</ref>, he returned to the country and claimed his part of the Silesian inheritance. Soon an preliminary agreement was reached under which Konrad remained under the protection and care of his older brother, who gave him the title of co-ruler in Legnica. </p>
<p>Bolesław II (who wanted to get rid of him) still proposed Konrad for spiritual posts: first, as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provost_(religion)">Provost</ref> of Głogów Cathedral, and then <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic_Diocese_of_Passau">Bishop of Passau</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Bavaria">Bavaria</ref>. Though he had not reached the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Person_(canon_law)">canonical age</ref>, he was elected by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Stephen's_Cathedral,_Passau">Passau cathedral</ref> chapter to succeed the deposed bishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rüdiger_of_Bergheim">Rüdiger of Bergheim</ref>; however, without approval by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Curia">Roman Curia</ref>. Konrad, nevertheless, didn't have any intention of pursuing an ecclesiastical career. He never entered Passau and soon resumed his conflict with Bolesław II.</p>
<figure><caption>Partition of Silesia 1249-1273, Konrad's Duchy of Głogów in green</caption></figure>
<p>In June 1249 Konrad fled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Greater_Poland">Greater Poland</ref>, where he could count on the support of Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Przemysł_I_of_Greater_Poland">Przemysł I</ref>. In 1251 he campaigned Bolesław's ducal lands and he managed to conquer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bytom_Odrzański">Bytom Odrzański</ref>. Konrad's bonds with the Piast dukes of Greater Poland were reinforced after his marriage with Przemysł I's sister Salome. His other brother Henry III the White soon became another ally in the fight against Bolesław II. With the help of his new allies, and thanks to the revolt of the townspeople of Głogów, the campaign against Bolesław II ended in complete success. The Duke of Legnica was forced to accept his defeat and give the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lower_Silesia">Lower Silesian</ref> lands of Głogów up to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Krosno_Odrzańskie">Krosno Odrzańskie</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Żagań">Żagań</ref> to Konrad as a duchy in his own right. </p>
<p>Until the end of his life Konrad's relations with his brother Bolesław II remain strained. In 1257 Konrad made a dangerous move and kidnapped Bolesław from his residence in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Legnica">Legnica</ref>. The duke regained his freedom after a few months, but it is unknown at what price. It can be said that after that the duke never left Bolesław II a moment of happiness, but in 1271 the Duke of Legnica managed to regain the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolesławiec">Bolesławiec</ref> near the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bóbr">Bóbr</ref> river.</p>
<p>From about 1260 Konrad established closer contacts with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Bohemia">Kingdom of Bohemia</ref> and became involved in the expansionist politics of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottokar_II_of_Bohemia">Ottokar II</ref>. Also he promoted the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ostsiedlung">colonization</ref> in his lands, mostly by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Germany">German</ref> settlers. This was a decisive contribution to the institution of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magdeburg_rights">Magdeburg town law</ref> in his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Głogów">Głogów</ref> residence in 1253. In contrast to his brother Bolesław II, Konrad vigorously supported Bishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_I,_bishop_of_Wrocław">Thomas I of Wrocław</ref> in his defence of church rights. However, when the bishop died in 1268 Konrad began to violate the privileges conferred by him, which led to conflicts with the new Bishop Thomas II Zaremba.</p>
<p>At the end of his life he founded a church in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zielona_Góra">Zielona Góra</ref> (now a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Co-cathedral">Co-cathedral</ref>) dedicated to his grandmother, St. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hedwig_of_Silesia">Hedwig of Silesia</ref>. The church was completed only twenty years after his death by his son and heir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_III,_Duke_of_Głogów">Henry III</ref>.</p>
<head>Marriages and Issue</head>
<p>In 1249 Konrad contracted his first marriage to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salome_of_Greater_Poland">Salome</ref> (b. ca. 1225 - d. April 1267?), daughter of Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Władysław_Odonic">Władysław</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greater_Poland">Greater Poland</ref>. They had six children:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna_of_Glogau">Anna</ref> (b. 1250/52 - d. 25 June 1271), married on 24 August 1260 to Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_II,_Duke_of_Bavaria">Louis II of Upper Bavaria</ref>.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_III,_Duke_of_Głogów">Henry III</ref> (b. 1251/60 - d. 9 December 1309).</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konrad_II_the_Hunchback">Konrad II the Hunchback</ref> (b. 1252/65 - d. 11 October 1304).</item>
<item>Euphemia (b. 12 January 1254 - d. bef. 1275), married by 13 May 1266 to Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_I_of_Gorizia">Albert I of Gorizia</ref>.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Przemko_of_Ścinawa">Przemko</ref> (b. 1255/65 - d. killed in battle, Siewierz, 26 February 1289).</item>
<item>Hedwig (b. 1265? - d. 9 June 1318), Abbess of St. Klara, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wroclaw">Wroclaw</ref> (1283).</item></list>
<p>By 1271, Konrad married his second wife, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sophie_of_Landsberg">Sophie</ref> (b. ca. 1259 - d. 24 August 1318), daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodoric_of_Landsberg">Dietrich the Wise</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margrave">Margrave</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margraviate_of_Landsberg">Landsberg</ref> (second son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_III,_Margrave_of_Meissen">Henry III, Margrave of Meissen</ref>) and — according to some sources — widow of the last legitimate male member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Hohenstaufen">House of Hohenstaufen</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conradin">Conradin</ref>, King of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sicily">Sicily</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerusalem">Jerusalem</ref>. They had no children.</p>
</text>
