<text id="autogum_bio_doc711" title="Antonio da Cividale" shortTile="antonio-da-cividale" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-03-14" dateModified="2017-08-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonio_da_Cividale" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Antonio da Cividale</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Antonio da Cividale</hi> (also <hi rend="bold">Antonius de Civitate Austrie</hi>) (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floruit">fl.</ref> 1410–1421) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_of_Italy">Italian</ref> composer of the early <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quattrocento">Quattrocento</ref>, at the end of the musical <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medieval_music">medieval</ref> era and beginning of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renaissance_music">Renaissance</ref>. He is one of a few Italian composers of the early 15th century whose works have survived; they are transitional between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_of_the_Trecento">Trecento</ref> and the early Renaissance styles.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>While a few details are known of his life, both the beginning and end are obscure. There has been confusion over dating of some of his compositions, some of which has been resolved recently, and most of his activity now seems to have been in the first two decades of the 15th century. He was a friar of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominican_Order">Dominican</ref> order; from his name, it can be inferred he was from the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cividale_del_Friuli">Cividale del Friuli</ref>. In 1392 an "Antonius de Civitato" entered the monastery of San Domenico in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venice">Venice</ref>, but he was from Città di Castello rather than Cividale del Friuli. However, Antonio da Cividale did compose the motet <hi rend="italic">Strenua/Gaudeat</hi>, celebrating the marriage of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giorgio_Ordelaffi">Giorgio Ordelaffi</ref>, lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forlì">Forlì</ref>, with Lucrezia degli Alidosi on 3 July 1412. Sometime between then and 1414 Antonio moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florence">Florence</ref>, where he wrote a motet, <hi rend="italic">O felix flos Florencia/Gaude felix Dominice</hi>, in honor of the city of Florence and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonardo_Dati">Leonardo Dati</ref>, the new <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominican_Master_General">Dominican Master General</ref>, who was elected on 29 September of that year (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#CITEREFSchoop_and_Nosow">Schoop and Nosow</ref>). In 1420 he probably went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rome">Rome</ref> along with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Martin_V">Pope Martin V</ref>, who had recently been elected by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council_of_Constance">Council of Constance</ref>; <hi rend="italic">Clarus ortus/Gloriosa matera</hi> a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motet">motet</ref> written in Martin V's honor in 1421, is probably by Antonio (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#CITEREFSchoop_and_Nosow">Schoop and Nosow</ref>). There are no records of Antonio's life or activity after 1421.</p>
<head>Music and influence</head>
<p>Antonio wrote both sacred and secular vocal music. Of the sacred music, four <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mass_(music)">mass</ref> movements and six <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motet">motets</ref> have survived (some of the motets were incidental pieces written for specific occasions; these are the ones with known dates). The motets are for three or four voices, the mass movements for two or three. Stylistically, his lines are short, broken by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rest_(music)">rests</ref>, and depend on repetition as well as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sequence_(music)">sequential</ref> treatment of short <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motif_(music)">motifs</ref>. He was also interested in compositional "tricks" such as phrases which are first sung forward, then backward, and in addition he wrote parts that were sometimes strictly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_(music)">canonic</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isorhythm">Isorhythm</ref> and other traits of the contemporary French style are prominent, but unlike the  French composers, Antonio seems to have written the tenor parts to his motets himself, rather than borrowing them from pre-existing chant. He was a fairly prolific composer, and while it is not known how much of his music is lost, his six surviving motets are one of the largest groups of surviving motets by a single Italian composer of the time. Most of his music survives in sources in northern Italy.</p>
<p>Three <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rondeau_(forme_fixe)">rondeaux</ref>, three <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virelai">virelais</ref>, and one <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ballade_(forme_fixe)">ballade</ref> survive of his secular output. All except the ballade are in French; the ballade, <hi rend="italic">Jo vegio per stasone</hi>, is in Italian, although with the exception of the incipit, the text is lost.</p>
<p>The music of Antonio and his contemporaries was a formative influence on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guillaume_Dufay">Guillaume Dufay</ref> during his years on the Italian peninsula.</p>
<head>References and further reading</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Hans Schoop/Robert Nosow: "Antonius de Civitate Austrie", Grove Music Online, ed. Deane L. Root (accessed August 30, 2017), <ref target="http://www.grovemusic.com">(subscription access)</ref></item>
<item>Hans Schoop, "Antonius de Civitate Austrie", <hi rend="italic">The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians</hi>, ed. Stanley Sadie.  20 vol.  London, Macmillan Publishers Ltd., 1980.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/1-56159-174-2">1-56159-174-2</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gustave_Reese">Gustave Reese</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Music in the Renaissance</hi>.  New York, W.W. Norton &amp; Co., 1954.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/0-393-09530-4">0-393-09530-4</ref></item></list>
</text>
