<text id="autogum_bio_doc295" title="Maria Landini" shortTile="maria-landini" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-07-18" dateModified="2019-05-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Landini" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Maria Landini</head><p><hi rend="bold">Maria Landini</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[lower-alpha 1]</ref> (c. 1668 – 22 June 1722) was an Italian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soprano">soprano</ref> who began her career as a singer at the court of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_Christina_of_Sweden">Queen Christina</ref> in Rome but was primarily active at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_VI,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">the imperial court in Vienna</ref> from 1711 until her death. She created numerous soprano roles in operas and oratorios by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Joseph_Fux">Fux</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caldara">Caldara</ref>, and her second husband, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francesco_Bartolomeo_Conti">Francesco Bartolomeo Conti</ref> and was reputedly the highest paid musician in Vienna at the time.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Sadie-3">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-OML-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Life and career</head>
<p>Landini's mother, Francesca Portui, was the maid of Queen Christina of Sweden and married to Francesco Landini, the captain of Christina's guards. However, Francesco Landini was not her real father. Maria was born from a relationship between her mother and the marquise Orazio Del Monte, Christina's chamberlain. According to 17th-century sources, she was born in Hamburg where Christina's court periodically sojourned, although the date of her birth has variously been given as 1667, 1668, and 1670. Maria spent her entire childhood and youth at the court of Queen Christina where she was trained as a singer and was known by the diminutive "Mariuccia". By the late 1680s there are records of her regularly performing in private musical evenings at Queen Christina's court in Rome. She often sang together with another favourite singer of the queen, Angela Voglia (known as "La Giorgina").<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Zilli-4">[3]</ref></p>
<p>After Queen Christina's death in 1689, Landini entered the service of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sophia_Charlotte_of_Hanover">Sophia Charlotte of Hanover</ref> in Germany. She married an actor named "Chateauneuf" in Hannover in 1695 and sometimes appeared under the name "Landini di Chateauneuf" or its Italian version "Castelnovo".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[4]</ref> According to Francesco Conti's biographer Hermine Williams, Castelnovo was from an aristocratic family and his full name was Mallo di Castelnuovo. Their marriage would produce three children: Ferdinando, Francesca, and Caterina. Landini was active in the opera houses of Italy from 1698 when she was in the service of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinando_Carlo_Gonzaga,_Duke_of_Mantua_and_Montferrat">Duke of Mantua</ref>. Her earliest appearance in Mantua was in 1698 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bononcini">Bononcini</ref>'s <hi rend="italic">Il Trionfo di Camilla</hi>. She also appeared in Venice, Genoa, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casale_Monferrato">Casale Monferrato</ref>, Livorno, Modena, and Bologna before moving to Vienna in 1710 where she became the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prima_donna">prima donna</ref></hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_VI,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Emperior Charles VI</ref>'s court theatre. In 1714, following the death of her first husband, Landini married Francesco Bartolomeo Conti in Vienna's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schottenkirche,_Vienna">Schottenkirche</ref>. In her will, written in the year prior to her death, she asked to be buried in the Schottenkirche next to her first husband.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Williams-6">[5]</ref></p>
<p>In 1725 Conti married Anna Maria Lorenzani who had succeeded Landini as the <hi rend="italic">prima donna</hi> at the imperial court.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Williams-6">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Roles created</head>
<p>Roles created by Maria Landini include:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Clori in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Joseph_Fux">Johann Joseph Fux</ref>'s <hi rend="italic">La decima fatica di Ercole</hi>, Habsburg court theatre, Vienna, 1710<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Kochel-7">[6]</ref></item>
<item>Merope in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francesco_Gasparini">Francesco Gasparini</ref>'s <hi rend="italic">Merope</hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teatro_San_Cassiano">Teatro San Cassiano</ref>, Venice, 26 December 1711<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[7]</ref></item>
<item>Dafne in Johann Joseph Fux's <hi rend="italic">Dafne in Lauro</hi>, Habsburg court theatre, Vienna, 1714<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Kochel-7">[6]</ref></item>
<item>Euridice in Johann Joseph Fux's <hi rend="italic">Orfeo ed Euridice</hi>, Habsburg court theatre, Vienna, 1715<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Kochel-7">[6]</ref></item>
<item>Angelica in Johann Joseph Fux's <hi rend="italic">Angelica, vincitrice di Alcina</hi>, Habsburg court theatre, Vienna, 1716<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Kochel-7">[6]</ref></item>
<item>Ifigenia in Johann Joseph Fux's <hi rend="italic">Diana plaeata</hi>, Habsburg court theatre, Vienna, 1717<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Kochel-7">[6]</ref></item>
<item>Lucinda in Francesco Bartolomeo Conti's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don_Chisciotte_in_Sierra_Morena">Don Chisciotte in Sierra Morena</ref></hi>,  Habsburg court theatre, Vienna, 6 February 1719<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fallows-9">[8]</ref></item></list>
</text>
