<text id="autogum_bio_doc702" title="Pierre de Craon" shortTile="pierre-de-craon" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-09-01" dateModified="2016-05-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_de_Craon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pierre de Craon</head><figure><caption>The Blazon of Pierre de Craon le Grand.</caption></figure><p><hi rend="bold">Pierre de Craon</hi> (c. 1345 - c. 1409), known as "le Grand", was a medieval French aristocrat notorious for his riotous temperament, culminating in his attempted murder of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olivier_de_Clisson">Olivier de Clisson</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constable_of_France">Constable of France</ref>. Events following the assault led to the mental breakdown of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_VI_of_France">Charles VI of France</ref> ushering in a long period of political instability in France.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Craon inherited considerable wealth from his father, Guillaume I de Craon. He held the titles  Lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La_Ferté-Bernard">La Ferté-Bernard</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sablé">Sablé</ref>.</p>
<p>Craon was involved in the expedition of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_I,_Duke_of_Anjou">Louis I, Duke of Anjou</ref> to seize the kingdom of Naples, Craon was entrusted with money to finance the expedition, but he kept the funds himself and spent his time in debauchery in Venice. He was blamed for Louis' premature death and the collapse of the expedition. On his return to Paris, he was publicly upbraided by Louis' brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John,_Duke_of_Berry">John, Duke of Berry</ref>. However, his wealth protected him.</p>
<head>Attack on Clisson</head>
<figure><caption>Olivier de Clisson as depicted on his tomb, Basilique Notre Dame du Roncier, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josselin">Josselin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brittany">Brittany</ref>, France.</caption></figure>
<p>In 1391, Craon was abruptly expelled from the court in Paris, for unknown reasons. He blamed de Clisson, encouraged by Clisson's enemy <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_IV,_Duke_of_Brittany">John IV, Duke of Brittany</ref>. After a period in Brittany, he returned to Paris in secret, planning to murder Clisson. He waylaid Clisson in a narrow street. Clisson's unarmed servants fled, but Clisson was saved from death by his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mail_(armour)">chainmail</ref> coat, and was able to draw his sword and fend off his attackers. In the struggle, he fell from his horse and was knocked out against the door of a baker's shop. Believing him dead, Craon fled Paris for Brittany.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-mic-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In fact Clisson was only superficially injured. In the aftermath of the attack, several of Craon's servants in Paris were arrested and executed for assisting him. Craon's property was seized and his castle in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porchefontaine">Porchefontaine</ref> near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Versailles_(city)">Versailles</ref> was razed to the ground. John V refused to deliver Craon to the king, so Charles and Clisson marched on Brittany, only for the king to have a mental breakdown during the expedition, killing several of his own soldiers in a deranged fit. Clisson's enemies at court blamed him for provoking the disaster, and instituted proceedings against him. Clisson himself then fled to Brittany, to become a lifelong ally of his old enemy John IV.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-mic-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Exile and return</head>
<p>Craon was forced to move from place to place, at last seeking refuge with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_II_of_England">Richard II of England</ref>, who granted him a pension. When the threat of prosecution for the attack on Clisson was lifted, Craon returned to France; however, his enemies instituted legal measures to recover the money that Craon had misappropriated from Louis I, Duke of Anjou. Craon was imprisoned in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louvre_Palace">Louvre</ref>, but was soon released following interventions by the Queen of England and the Duchess of Burgundy. A deal was made over the money and Craon made penance for his crimes. In an unprecedented move, he was made confessor to some monks who had been convicted of bewitching the king. He erected a cross bearing his coat of arms at the gallows of Paris, at which criminals could confess before their execution. He also donated money to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conventual_Franciscans">Conventual Franciscans</ref>, dedicating them to acts of mercy.</p>
<p>The date of Craon's death is not known. His son Antoine de Craon was implicated in the murder of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_I,_Duke_of_Orléans">Louis I, Duke of Orléans</ref> and was killed at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Agincourt">Battle of Agincourt</ref> in 1415.</p>
</text>
