<text id="autogum_bio_doc387" title="Mesrop of Khizan" shortTile="mesrop-khizan" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-03-17" dateModified="2019-03-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mesrop_of_Khizan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Mesrop of Khizan</head><p><hi rend="bold">Mesrop of Khizan</hi> (c. 1560 – c. 1652) was a prominent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenian_illuminated_manuscript">Armenian manuscript illuminator</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persia">Persia</ref>. Mesrop was born in the Ottoman Empire but eventually lived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isfahan">Isfahan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persia">Persia</ref>, where he contributed in the making of  manuscripts for bibles and gospels for four decades. He was also a scribe, clerk, teacher, doctor of theology, restorer and binder. His manuscripts have been displayed in museums throughout the world and are found in many prestigious libraries.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Mesrop of Khizan was born to Armenian parents in circa 1560 and is believed to be from the region of Khizan (now known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hizan">Hizan</ref>) near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lake_Van">Lake Van</ref> located in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman Empire</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vrej-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-minasian-2">[2]</ref> The Armenians of Khizan were noted for illuminated manuscript making and would later be regarded as the <hi rend="italic">Khizan School</hi> of art.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-taylor-3">[3]</ref> After <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbas_I_of_Persia">Abbas I of Persia</ref> defeated the Ottoman Empire around Lake Van, he forcibly relocated many Armenians of the region to his new capital of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isfahan">Isfahan</ref> in 1604. After the family had moved, Mesrop's father Martiros, who was a painter himself, continued to teach his son how to paint in the early stages of his life.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vrej-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cilicia-4">[4]</ref> Mesrop of Khizan's career spans four decades, with his last known artwork dated in 1651.</p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>Among the first works of Mesrop is the Gospel of 1608. The first manuscript was done for a priest named Khatchatur and received many sponsors from various wealthy Armenians.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-taylor-3">[3]</ref> This was soon followed by the Gospel of 1609, which is part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodleian_Library">Bodleian Library</ref>, the main research library of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Oxford">University of Oxford</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vrej-1">[1]</ref> The Gospel of 1609 contains lamentations of the fall of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenia">Armenia</ref> under Shah Abbas:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vrej-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Mourning fell upon Armenia, for he [Shah Abbas] destroyed and made desolate all houses and habitations, so that men fled and hid themselves in fortresses and clefts of rocks. Some he found and slew, others he led captive and sent to that city of Shosh or Aspahan [Isfahan]...And he settled us on the south side of the river Zandar...where we built houses and habitations and churches for our prayers.</p>
<p>Art historian Alice Taylor describes Mesrop's work as "less lively" than other contemporaneous Khizan painters, but his "settings are charged with life and energy".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-taylor-3">[3]</ref> In one such painting, The Baptism of Christ, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus_Christ">Jesus Christ</ref> is featured stepping on the head of a dragon that is swimming in a river.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-taylor-3">[3]</ref> The scene around the baptized Christ is beneath a sky that appears to be melting, and a dove, symbolizing the Holy Spirit, entering the soul of Christ from above of his head.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-taylor-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Saint John the Evangelist</hi>, a painting done in 1615 that is now part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J._Paul_Getty_Museum">J. Paul Getty Museum</ref>, features <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_the_Apostle">John the Apostle</ref> receiving the word of God through a ray of blue light.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-chace-5">[5]</ref> John is surrounded by yellow light and elongated figures.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-baltimore-6">[6]</ref>
About thirty manuscripts done by Mesrob of Khizan survive today.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vrej-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Gallery</head>
<list type="unordered">
<item>The Baptism of Christ, 1615</item>
<item>Saint John the Evangelist, 1615</item>
<item>Armenian Bible by Mesrop of Khizan</item>
<item>Christ's Entry into Jerusalem, 1618–1622</item>
<item>Harrowing of Hell, 1618–1622</item>
</list>
</text>
