<text id="autogum_bio_doc551" title="Agüeybaná I" shortTile="ageyban-i" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2004-07-02" dateModified="2019-10-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ag%C3%BCeyban%C3%A1_I" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Agüeybaná I</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Agüeybaná </hi> (died 1510) was the principal and most powerful <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cacique">cacique</ref></hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[lower-alpha 1]</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tribal_chief">chief</ref>) of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taíno">Taíno</ref> people in "Borikén" (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puerto_Rico">Puerto Rico</ref>) when the Spanish first arrived on the island on November 19, 1493.</p>
<head>Etymology</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Agüeybana</hi>, which has been interpreted by 19th and 20th century authors as meaning "The Great Sun", was the hereditary title shared by the family that ruled the theocratic monarchy of Borikén, governing the hierarchy over the rest of the regional chiefs or caciques. Like other nobiliary recognitions within Taíno culture, it was passed down through the maternal bloodline.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-pcmle.org-1">[1]</ref> The Spanish settlers Hispanicized the title to be the equivalent of the European concept of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King">kings</ref>, with contemporary writers such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_de_Castellanos">Juan de Castellanos</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[5]</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gonzalo_Fernández_de_Oviedo_y_Valdés">Gonzalo Fernández de Oviedo y Valdés</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[6]</ref> employing the title of <hi rend="italic">Rey Agüeybana</hi> (English: "King Agüeybana") when referring to the second monarch to lead the Taíno during the 1510s.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[7]</ref> By the 1800s, the terms "king" and "cacique" were used exchangeably by both local and Spanish authors,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[9]</ref> but a resurgence in the interest concerning Taíno history during the 20th century led to the popularization of native words and the latter term gained more lexical prominence.</p>
<head>Arrival of the conquistadors</head>
<p>Agüeybaná received the Spanish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conquistador">conquistador</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_Ponce_de_León">Juan Ponce de León</ref> upon his arrival in 1508. According to an old Taíno tradition, Agüeybaná practiced the "guatiao," a Taíno ritual in which he and Juan Ponce de León became friends and exchanged names. Ponce de León then baptized the cacique's mother into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christianity">Christianity</ref> and renamed her Inés.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cacique-11">[10]</ref></p>
<p>The cacique joined Ponce de León in the exploration of the island. After this had been accomplished, Agüeybaná accompanied the conquistador to the island of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hispaniola">La Española</ref></hi> (what today comprises the nations of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominican_Republic">Dominican Republic</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haiti">Haiti</ref>), where he was well received by the Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolás_de_Ovando">Nicolás de Ovando</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[11]</ref> Agüeybaná's actions helped to maintain the peace between the Taíno and the Spaniards, a peace which was to be short-lived.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cacique-11">[10]</ref></p>
<p>The hospitality and friendly treatment that the Spaniards received from Agüeybaná made it easy for the Spaniards to betray and conquer the island.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cacique-11">[10]</ref> After a short period of peace, the Taínos were forced to work in the island's gold mines and in the construction of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort">forts</ref> as slaves. Many Taínos died as a result of the cruel treatment which they received.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cacique-11">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Death and aftermath</head>
<p>Upon Agüeybaná's death in 1510, his brother<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-pcmle.org-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-spatial.maine.edu-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-books.google.com-3">[3]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Güeybaná">Güeybaná</ref> (better known as Agüeybaná II) became the most powerful Cacique in the island. Agüeybaná II was troubled by the treatment of his people by the Spanish and attacked them in battle. The Taínos were ultimately defeated at the Battle of Yagüecas.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[12]</ref></p>
<p>Taínos in Puerto Rico either abandoned the island, were forced to labor as slaves, or were killed by the Spaniards to what till recently was thought resulted in a complete extinction.</p>
<p>However, recent genetic studies, revealed that Taino blood/ancestry is still very much present in the genome of Puertoricans. Said studies published in between 2018 and 2019 revealed a narrative more indicative of assimilation and migrations to nearby islands rather than extinction.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Yale-14">[13]</ref> Many succumbed to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smallpox">smallpox</ref> epidemic that attacked the islanders in 1519.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cacique-11">[10]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[14]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>Agüeybaná is admired in Puerto Rico for his dedication to his people and attempting to keep the peace. Puerto Rico has named many public buildings and streets after him:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>The City of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayamón,_Puerto_Rico">Bayamón</ref> has named a high school after him.</item>
<item>There is a street in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caguas,_Puerto_Rico">Caguas</ref> that honors him.</item>
<item>An avenue in the Hato Rey area of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Juan,_Puerto_Rico">San Juan</ref> is named after Agüeybaná.</item>
<item>Puerto Rico once had an equivalent to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grammy_Awards">Grammy Award</ref> which was awarded annually and was called the "Agüeybaná de Oro" (The Golden Agüeybaná), in honor of the great cacique.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[15]</ref></item></list>
<p>Many songs and poems, by poets such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_Antonio_Corretjer">Juan Antonio Corretjer</ref>, among others, have been written about Agüeybaná.</p>
</text>
