<text id="autogum_bio_doc422" title="Patrick Barnewall (died 1622)" shortTile="patrick-barnewall" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-07-04" dateModified="2018-04-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Barnewall_%28died_1622%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Patrick Barnewall (died 1622)</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sir Patrick Barnewall</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Barnwall</hi> (died 1622), was the eldest son of Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Barnewall">Christopher Barnewall</ref> of Turvey, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grace_Dieu_Abbey">Grace Dieu Abbey</ref>, and Fieldston. Christopher in turn was the son of the elder Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Barnewall_(Solicitor_General)">Patrick Barnewall</ref>, who in 1534 was made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serjeant-at-law_(Ireland)">Serjeant-at-law (Ireland)</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solicitor-General_for_Ireland">Solicitor-General for Ireland</ref>, and in 1550 became  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_the_Rolls_in_Ireland">Master of the Rolls in Ireland</ref>. Patrick's mother was Marion Sherle, daughter of Richard Sherle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_Meath">County Meath</ref>: after his father's  death  she remarried the prominent judge Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucas_Dillon">Lucas Dillon</ref>.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Sir Christopher was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheriff_of_County_Dublin">Sheriff of County Dublin</ref> in 1560, and is described by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raphael_Holinshed">Raphael Holinshed</ref>, his son in law, as ‘the lanthorn (i.e. lantern) and light as well of his house’ as of that part of Ireland where he dwelt; who being sufficiently furnished as well with the knowledge of the Latin tongue, as of the common laws of England, was zealously bent to the reformation of his country.’ Sir Patrick Barnewall ‘was the first gentleman's son of quality that was ever put out of Ireland to be brought up in learning beyond the seas’.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> He succeeded his father in his estates in 1575. He married firstly Mary St. Lawrence, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_St_Lawrence,_8th_Baron_Howth_(d._1589)">Christopher, 8th Baron Howth</ref> and Elizabeth Plunkett, but the marriage was annulled in 1579 and in 1582 he remarried Mary, daughter of Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Bagenal">Nicholas Bagenal</ref>, knight mareschal of Ireland and Eleanor Griffith, with whom he had a son and four daughters.  She died in 1609. Her sister Mabel, celebrated for her elopement with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_O'Neill,_2nd_Earl_of_Tyrone">Hugh O'Neill, 2nd Earl of Tyrone</ref> in 1591,  lived with them at Turvey, for a time, and it was from Turvey, with the connivance of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_William_Warren_(died_1602)">Sir William Warren</ref>, that Mabel  fled to Warren's  home at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drumcondra,_Dublin">Drumcondra</ref>,  where her marriage to O'Neill  took place.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> After the death of Mary's eldest brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Bagenal">Henry Bagenal</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_the_Yellow_Ford">Battle of the Yellow Ford</ref> in 1598, Patrick  was appointed guardian of his children.</p>
<head>Early career</head>
<p>Barnewall began to attend the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inns_of_Court">Inns of Court</ref> in London, one ‘of the evident tokens of loyalty’ which led <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I">Elizabeth I</ref> in November 1582 to make him a new <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lease">lease</ref> of certain lands without fine for sixty years. Loyal to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Crown">English Crown</ref> he undoubtedly was, but he had inherited in a great degree both the principles and the disposition of his father, and was thus inclined to ‘demean himself frowardly’ when the true interests of Ireland were threatened by the government, or where he felt the  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic">Roman Catholic</ref> faith, of which he was a strong and open champion,  to be in peril.</p>
<head>Charged and imprisoned</head>
<p>In December 1605 he was brought before the  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privy_Council_of_Ireland">Privy Council of Ireland</ref>  at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dublin">Dublin</ref> on the charge of having organised the petition of the lords and gentlemen of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Pale">the Pale</ref> in favour of those persons who had refused to comply with the enactment requiring attendance at  a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestant">Protestant</ref> church service on Sundays. He denied having been the  author of the petition, but on account of his ‘obstinate and indecent manner of defending it’ was regarded as having been more deeply implicated in  the offence than whoever had actually written it. He was therefore retained in prison, and ultimately was sent to England, where he was committed to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tower_of_London">Tower of London</ref>. The timing of the petition was particularly unfortunate in coming so soon after the discovery of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gunpowder_Plot">Gunpowder Plot</ref>, although it was not suggested that Barnewall had any involvement in  the Plot itself.</p>
<head>Release and later career</head>
<p>On account of illness he was, however, first ‘enlarged (I.e. freed) to his own lodgings,’ and on 31 December 1606 he was sent back to Ireland upon his bond to appear before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Deputy_of_Ireland">Lord Deputy of Ireland</ref> and  Privy Council within four days to make his submission. While in London he was supposed to have acted as the agent of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recusants">recusants</ref> in obtaining a relaxation of the law requiring attendance at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anglican">Anglican</ref> worship, but whether this was so or not, his spirited resistance to it had made it practically a dead letter, and no attempt was ever again made in Ireland to enforce attendance at  a Protestant church through a fine in the council chamber. In 1613 he strongly opposed the creation of new <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boroughs">boroughs</ref> in Ireland ‘as being designed only to pass votes’, and on this account was summoned to England to answer to the council. He died on 11 January 1622. </p>
<head>Children</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>His son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Barnewall,_1st_Viscount_Kingsland">Nicholas</ref> (1692-1663)  became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viscount_Barnewall">Viscount Barnewall</ref> of Kingsland.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></item></list>
<p>Of his four daughters:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Eleanor married Christopher Fleming, 12th <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_Slane">Baron Slane</ref>, and had six sons of whom the eldest <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Fleming_(bishop)">Thomas</ref> renounced the title in favour of his next brother William, 14th Baron; Thomas became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic_Archbishop_of_Dublin">Roman Catholic Archbishop of Dublin</ref>.</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Sarah (died before March 1618)  married as his first wife the statesman  Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piers_Crosby"> Piers Crosby</ref> but had no surviving issue.</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Margaret married  as his second wife Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Bolton_(lawyer)">Richard Bolton</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chancellor_of_Ireland">Lord  Chancellor of Ireland</ref>.</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Mary married Valerian Wellesley in 1602, but the marriage was annulled in 1606. Valerian remarried Anne Cusack, granddaughter of  Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Cusack_(Irish_judge)">Thomas Cusack</ref>,  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chancellor_of_Ireland">Lord Chancellor of Ireland</ref>,  and had issue. The Wellesley name was later adopted by the Colley family, ancestors of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_of_Wellington">Duke of Wellington</ref>.</item></list>
</text>
