<text id="autogum_bio_doc532" title="Giovanni Mangone" shortTile="giovanni-mangone" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-11-12" dateModified="2019-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Mangone" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Giovanni Mangone</head><figure><caption>Palazzo Massimo di Pirro in Rome (today along <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corso_Vittorio_Emanuele_II,_Rome">Corso Vittorio Emanuele II</ref>) is the only building still extant surely designed by Giovanni Mangone</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Giovanni Mangone</hi> (born towards the end of 15th century, died 25 June 1543) was an Italian artist active almost exclusively in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rome">Rome</ref> during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italian_Renaissance">Renaissance</ref>. Mangone's skills were manifold: he worked as sculptor, architect, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stonecutter">stonecutter</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Building_estimator">building estimator</ref>. Moreover, he was a keen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antiquarian">antiquarian</ref> and among the founders of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accademia_dei_Virtuosi_al_Pantheon">Academy dei Virtuosi al Pantheon</ref>. As military engineer, he was renowned among his contemporaries.</p>
<head>Life and works</head>
<figure><caption>Tomb of Cardinal Willem van Enckevoirt at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Maria_dell'Anima">Santa Maria dell'Anima</ref> in Rome</caption></figure>
<p>Born around the end of the fifteenth century by Francesco, a native of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caravaggio,_Lombardy">Caravaggio</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lombardy">Lombardy</ref>, according to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giorgio_Vasari">Giorgio Vasari</ref> he studied under sculptor and architect <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea_Ferrucci">Andrea Ferrucci</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fiesole">Fiesole</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref> In Rome, where he lived in a palace in via delle Coppelle, between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sant'Agostino,_Rome">Sant'Agostino</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palazzo_Baldassini">palazzo Baldassini</ref>, at the beginning of his career had several assignments; from 1527 to 1532 he was superintendent to the spring of S. Peter; until 1541, he was curator of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gold-leaf">gold-leaf</ref> ceiling of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basilica_of_Santa_Maria_Maggiore">Basilica of Santa Maria Maggiore</ref>; since 1528 and until his death, he was architect of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apostolic_Chamber">apostolic Chamber</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref> Moreover, during his whole career he worked also as building estimator.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In 1534 started his collaboration with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonio_da_Sangallo_the_Younger">Antonio da Sangallo the Younger</ref>: together they prepared <hi rend="italic">apparati effimeri</hi> in wood to celebrate the crowning of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Paul_III">Pope Paul III</ref> (r. 1534–49) and in 1536, the visit to Rome of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Roman_Emperor">Holy Roman Emperor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_V,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Charles V</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In 1537 Mangone modified the monastery of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Servites">Servites</ref> near the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Marcello_al_Corso">Church of San Marcello al Corso</ref>, which he completed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref> However, due to subsequent changes in the seventeenth century, his work at the monastery is no longer recognizable.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Perhaps since 1532 he designed for Angelo <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massimo_family">Massimo</ref> a palace south of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piazza_Navona">Piazza Navona</ref>, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rioni_of_Rome">rione</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parione">Parione</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ri120-2">[2]</ref> The building, which in 1537 had been completed until its <hi rend="italic">piano nobile</hi>, was erroneously named after king <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pyrrhus_of_Epirus">Pyrrhus of Epirus</ref> because of a statue (actually of Mars) once on display on a yard's niche and now at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musei_Capitolini">Musei Capitolini</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref> The edifice is adjacent to the palace named <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palazzo_Massimo_alle_Colonne">Palazzo Massimo alle Colonne</ref>, realized in those years by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baldassare_Peruzzi">Baldassare Peruzzi</ref> and commissioned by Angelo's brother Pietro.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ri120-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Palazzo Massimo di Pirro is Mangone's only certain architectural work still extant.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref> In this building his model is Antonio da Sangallo the Younger, of whom he adopts typological schemes and – partially – stylistic features.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref> Anyway, in several elements, like the design of the irregular yard, the adoption of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loggia">loggias</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Architrave">architrave</ref>, the usage of decorative elements as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corbels">corbels</ref>, the equilibrium of the façade, he shows an original style.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-gi144-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ri120-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Based on stylistic analysis, have been attributed to him also the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palazzo_Alicorni">palazzo Alicorni</ref> in Borgo Vecchio (later piazza Rusticucci) in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Borgo_(rione_of_Rome)">Borgo</ref> (demolished in 1931 and later rebuilt) and – more doubtfully – the Palazzetto De Vellis in Piazza <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Maria_in_Trastevere">Santa Maria in Trastevere</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>As a sculptor, only two works have been attributed to him: well-done appears to be the funerary monument to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardinal_(Catholicism)">Cardinal</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Willem_van_Enckevoirt">Willem van Enckevoirt</ref> (dead in 1534) in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Maria_dell'Anima">Santa Maria dell'Anima</ref>, where is evident an influence from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michelangelo">Michelangelo</ref>, while that of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop">bishop</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chiusi">Chiusi</ref> and Governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bologna">Bologna</ref> Gregorio Magalotti in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Cecilia_in_Trastevere">Santa Cecilia in Trastevere</ref>, engraved in 1538, radiates a cold feeling.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>As a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military_architecture">military architect</ref>, in 1542 Mangone was summoned together with other architects by  Paul III, who wanted to enhance the fortifications of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Borgo_(rione_of_Rome)">Borgo</ref>, and in that occasion he presented a project.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref>The following year he was active in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sermoneta">Sermoneta</ref>, working at the town's walls.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref> Mangone was also a keen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antiquarian">antiquarian</ref>, and collected in his palace a good deal of architectural and sculptural pieces.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref> In 1543, defining himself as a sculptor, he was among the founding members of the Congregation of "St. Joseph in the Holy Land at the Rotonda", later known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accademia_dei_Virtuosi_al_Pantheon">Accademia dei Virtuosi al Pantheon</ref>, one of the main centers of discussions about antiquities and architecture in Rome.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>On 25 June 1543 he made his will, dying perhaps on the same day.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Significance</head>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palazzo_Alicorni">Palazzo Alicorni</ref> (here before its demolition in 1931 and later reconstruction) could be attributed to Mangone because of its stylistic resemblance with the Palazzo di Pirro</caption></figure>
<p>As a sculptor, Mangone followed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea_Sansovino">Andrea Sansovino</ref>, reaching mixed results. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref>
As an architect, his former education as a sculptor and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stonemason">stonemason</ref> in the design of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Molding_(decorative)">moldings</ref> allowed him to reach a remarkable equilibrium of proportions.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref> Moreover, Mangone was among the first to spread the "severe" style initiated by Antonio da Sangallo the Younger.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref> With the Palazzo di Pirro, he designed a good example of "everyday" architecture which found many imitators in the second part of 16th century.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref>
As a military architect, although he was praised by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military_engineer">military engineer</ref> Francesco De Marchi, the absence of extant works which can be attributed to him makes difficult to assess its real contribution to this field.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ghi-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
