<text id="autogum_bio_doc570" title="Johannes de Quadris" shortTile="johannes-de-quadris" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-05-05" dateModified="2016-03-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johannes_de_Quadris" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Johannes de Quadris</head><p><hi rend="bold">Johannes de Quadris</hi> (Quatris) (before 1410 – 1457?) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italy">Italian</ref> composer of the early <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renaissance_music">Renaissance</ref>.  He was one of the first composers of polyphony associated with the basilica of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Marco_di_Venezia">St. Mark's</ref> in Venice, and the earliest known composer to write a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyphony">polyphonic</ref> setting of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnificat">Magnificat</ref> for four voices.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cattin,_Grove_online-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was a priest, and originally from the diocese of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valva-Sulmona">Valva-Sulmona</ref>, in the vicinity of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L'Aquila">L'Aquila</ref>, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abruzzo">Abruzzo</ref> region of central Italy.  Sometime before 1436 he began to work as a singer at San Marco in Venice, which was then at the very beginning of its rise to fame; the first mention of a choir there is found in a document of 1403 (by the end of the 16th century, it was one of the most renowned musical institutions in Europe).  Quadris worked at San Marco from at least 1436, the date given on his Magnificat, to the time that a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_See">Vatican</ref> document listed him as "deceased", in 1457.  He made repeated requests (1450, 1452, 1454) to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Nicholas_V">Pope Nicholas V</ref> to obtain a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prebend">prebend</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aquileia">Aquileia</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cattin,_Grove_online-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Music</head>
<p>His musical style is highly varied, and possibly he wrote his surviving pieces over a career of more than the twenty documented years.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motet">motet</ref> <hi rend="italic">Gaudeat ecclesia</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Magnificat</hi> are stylistically related to the music of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Late_Middle_Ages">late Middle Ages</ref>, with a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cantus_firmus">cantus firmus</ref> surrounded by texturally distinct vocal lines; the other works, with their lighter texture, are more characteristic of Italian composers writing later in the century.  Clarity of the text is foremost in these works, as is liturgical utility.  According to Giulio Cattin, writing in the <hi rend="italic">New Grove</hi>:  "Taken as a whole, his output developed in a way typical of the 15th century, from a northern late Gothic idiom to the expressive, tuneful simplicity of Italian music."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cattin,_Grove_online-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>The Magnificat is the earliest polyphonic setting of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canticle">Canticle</ref> for four voices; the few surviving earlier settings are all for two or three only.  It is marked "pbr. Johannes de Quatris: 1436 mensis maij Venet[iis]" – a much-debated notation which may refer to the time and place of composition (May 1436, Venice) or perhaps an occasion for performance, or even the date the manuscript was copied.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Kanazawa,_JAMS-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Quadris's music remained popular for more than half a century, as shown by the many copies made of his hymn <hi rend="italic">Iste confessor</hi>, as well as the printing of his music for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Passion_music">Passion</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottaviano_Petrucci">Ottaviano Petrucci</ref> in 1506 (the only source that gives Quadris as the composer).  The music for the Passion, which includes Lessons for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matins">Matins</ref> as well as a set of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lamentations_(music)">Lamentations</ref>, also has been found in a manuscript, now in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vicenza">Vicenza</ref>, which was copied around 1440.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Kanazawa,_JAMS-2">[2]</ref>  His settings of the Lamentations were in use at San Marco until they were replaced by those by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Croce">Giovanni Croce</ref> in 1603, another indication of the esteem in which they were held.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<head>Attributed to Johannes de Quadris in contemporary sources</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Chants for a Good Friday procession (two voices)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Gaudeat ecclesia</hi> (motet, for four voices)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Iste confessor</hi> (hymn, for three voices; attributed to him in the manuscript <hi rend="italic">I-Fn 112bis</hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonius_Janue">Antonius Janue</ref>, around 1456)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Lamentations</hi> (two voices)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Magnificat</hi> (four voices; signed and dated 1436)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Planctus Mariae:  Cum autem venissem</hi></item></list>
<head>Anonymous, attributed to de Quadris by contemporary musicologists</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Douce speranche</hi> (virelai)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Se je n'é mal</hi> (virelai)</item></list>
</text>
