<text id="autogum_bio_doc539" title="Master of the Aachen Altar" shortTile="master-aachen-altar" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-01-14" dateModified="2019-05-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_the_Aachen_Altar" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Master of the Aachen Altar</head><figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aachen_Altar">Aachen Altar</ref>: Centrepiece with the crucifixion of Christ</caption></figure>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Notname">notname</ref> <hi rend="bold">Master of the Aachen Altar</hi> is given to an anonymous late <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gothic_art">gothic</ref> painter active in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cologne">Cologne</ref> between 1495 and 1520<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> or 1480 and 1520,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> named for his master work, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aachen_Altar">Aachen Altar</ref> triptych owned by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aachen_Cathedral_Treasury">Aachen Cathedral Treasury</ref>. Along with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_St_Severin">Master of St Severin</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_the_legend_of_St._Ursula_(Cologne)">Master of the legend of St. Ursula</ref> he is part of a group of painters who were active in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cologne">Cologne</ref> at the beginning of the sixteenth century and were Cologne's last significant practitioners of late gothic painting.</p>
<figure><caption>Mass of Saint Gregory</caption></figure>
<head>Style</head>
<p>Like all the painters of Cologne in the second half of the fifteenth century, the Master of the Aachen Altar cannot be identified with any of the artists named in archives of the period. Since sure dates and sources are almost entirely lacking, works must be attributed by means of stylistic comparisons.</p>
<p>What distinguishes his work from his contemporaries is the vigorous temperament which he invested in his images. This manifests in the restless movement of his figures, densely packed scenes, turbulent compositions, rich oppositions, atmospheric landscapes, contemporary architectural themes, and the brightness of his colours. Surprising, often drastic external influences characterise his work, such as the naturalistic depictions of the symptoms of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syphilis">syphilitic</ref> man<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> and a child with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Down_syndrome">Down syndrome</ref> on the Aachen altar.</p>
<p>In his depiction of individuals, the Master of the Aachen Altar demonstrates an ability to create individualised portraits, as in the lifelike depiction of the establisher of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stift">Stift</ref> on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reredos">reredos</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liverpool">Liverpool</ref>, as well as the depiction of Johann von Melem the Younger, the son of the Cologne-born Patrician of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frankfurt_am_Main">Frankfurt</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_von_Melem">Johann von Melem</ref>. This image is now on display in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alte_Pinakothek">Alte Pinakothek</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Munich">Munich</ref> and is usually ascribed to the Master of the Aachen Altar. That Johann von Melem the Younger, as well as his father-in-law, the Mayor of Cologne and wholesale merchant Hermann Rinck were among the painter's clients in addition to creating the Aachen Altar for a Carmelite religious order and a wall painting for the Cologne family of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hardenrath">Hardenrath</ref>, shows the high esteem which the Master of the Aachen Altar enjoyed.</p>
<head>Influences and impacts</head>
<p>The roots of the Master of the Aachen Altar in Cologne painting is beyond question. His proximity to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_the_Holy_Clan">Master of the Holy Clan</ref>, which is clear both in stylistic matters and in the adoption of subjects and motifs, leads to the assumption that the Master of the Aachen Altar was educated in the workshop of the Master of the Holy Clan. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_St_Severin">Master of St Severin</ref> also had an important influence on the Master of the Aachen Altar, as similarities in their figures and painting methods indicate. A partnership as journeymen in this workshop is possible. The mature works of the Master of the Aachen Altar, such as the Mary panels, show clear influence from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_the_Saint_Bartholomew_Altarpiece">Master of the Saint Bartholomew Altarpiece</ref>. Further afield, the painter has taken important hints from the Netherlandish painters, such as the art of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugo_van_der_Goes">Hugo van der Goes</ref>.</p>
<p>The impact that the Master had on later painters does not seem to have been great. However, some works of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barthel_Bruyn_the_Elder">Barthel Bruyn the Elder</ref> reveal a detailed awareness of the work of the Master of the Aachen Altar and suggest the Bruyn had frequently interacted with the compositions of the earlier Master.</p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>The time between the earliest work, the <hi rend="italic">Adoration of the Kings</hi> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bonn">Bonn</ref> (1493-1495) or the <hi rend="italic">Portrait of Johann von Melem</hi> (1492-1497) and his last work, the Aachen altar (1515/1520), gives a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floruit">floruit</ref> of a good twenty years. A longer period of activity cannot be attributed to the Master. Only a relatively small number of works can be identified fairly surely as the handiwork of the Master: two retables, a wall painting that has been destroyed, two drawings and seven single panels, some in larger formats:</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Retables</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Passion Triptych</hi>, 1505-1510. Central panel: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Gallery">National Gallery</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London">London</ref>. Left panel, interior <hi rend="italic">Pilate Washing his Hands</hi>, exterior <hi rend="italic">Mass of St Gregory</hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walker_Art_Gallery">Walker Art Gallery</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liverpool">Liverpool</ref>. Right panel, interior <hi rend="italic">Lamentation of Christ</hi>, exterior <hi rend="italic">Kneeling Donors</hi>, Walker Art Gallery, Liverpool. Probably a donation to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Kolumba,_Cologne">St Kolumba, Cologne</ref> by the kneeling donors depicted on the right panel, whose <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coats_of_arms">coats of arms</ref> identify them as Hermann Rinck and his wife Gertrud von Dallem.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aachen_Altar">Aachen Altar</ref></hi>, 1515-1520, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aachen_Cathedral_Treasury">Aachen Cathedral Treasury</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aachen">Aachen</ref>. Probably identical with the altarpiece attested in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carmelite_Cloister,_Cologne">Carmelite Cloister of Cologne</ref>. The donor in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carmelite">Carmelite</ref> habit in the altarpiece cannot be identified with a known historical personage - there is no evidence at all for the idea that it is Theodericus de Gouda, which is uncritically repeated in older literature.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Drawings</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Adoration of the Kings</hi>, 1505-1510, Cabinet des Dessins du <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musée_du_Louvre">Musée du Louvre</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris">Paris</ref>. This pen and ink sketch is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Study_(art)">study</ref> for the <hi rend="italic">Adoration of the Kings</hi> panel displayed in Berlin.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Resurrection of Lazarus</hi>, 1510-1515, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kupferstichkabinett_Berlin">Kupferstichkabinett</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berlin">Berlin</ref>.  Pen and ink.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Single panels</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Portrait of Johann von Melem</hi>, 1492-1497, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alte_Pinakothek">Alte Pinakothek</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Munich">Munich</ref>. The subject, Frankfurt wholesaler Johann von Melem the Younger, was born in 1455-60 and the inscription gives his ages as 37 years, providing a rough date for the work.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Adoration of the Kings</hi>, 1493-1495, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rheinisches_Landesmuseum_Bonn">Rheinisches Landesmuseum</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bonn">Bonn</ref> (loan).</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Adoration of the Kings</hi>, 1505-1510, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gemäldegalerie,_Berlin">Gemäldegalerie</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berlin">Berlin</ref>. The panel is identified by the house mark at lower left as a donation of Johann Petit of Cologne, probably for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cologne_Charterhouse">Cologne Charterhouse</ref>.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Christ as Saviour of the World</hi>, 1505-1510, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wallraf-Richartz_Museum">Wallraf-Richartz Museum</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cologne">Cologne</ref>.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Mary with Child between St Catherine and St Ursula</hi>, 1510, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Private_collection">Private collection</ref>.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Mass of St Gregory</hi>, 1510-1515, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Museum_Catharijneconvent">Museum Catharijneconvent</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Utrecht">Utrecht</ref>.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Mary with Child and Angels playing Music</hi>, 1515, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alte_Pinakothek">Alte Pinakothek</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Munich">Munich</ref>.</item></list>
</text>
