<text id="autogum_bio_doc771" title="Pha Mueang" shortTile="pha-mueang" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-12-08" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pha_Mueang" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pha Mueang</head><hi rend="bold">Warning:</hi> Page using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_royalty">Template:Infobox royalty</ref> with unknown parameter "1 = Monarch
" (this message is shown only in preview).
<p><hi rend="bold">Pha Mueang</hi> (full name <hi rend="bold">Pho Khun Pha Mueang</hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thai_language">Thai</ref>: พ่อขุนผาเมือง; late 13th century – mid 14th century) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thailand">Thai</ref> nobleman and general who was the Lord of Rad and played a significant role in the founding of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sukhothai_Kingdom">Sukhothai Kingdom</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Coedes-1">[1]</ref>:195–196</p>
<head>Origin</head>
<p>Pha Mueang is said to be a descendant of Nam Thum, a hero whose name is mentioned in the legends of many <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tai_peoples">Tai peoples</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> Pha Mueang's ultimate origin is described by his grandfather in the so-called "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inscription_II">Inscription II</ref>":<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> he is the ruler of a city-state called Mueang Rat (เจ้าเมืองราด). The location of Mueang Rat is disputed. Many believe that it could be found in the valley of the Pasak. Therefore, the inhabitants of the Phetchabun district <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lom_Sak_District">Lom Sak</ref> built a large statue of Pha Mueang (อนุสาวรีย์พ่อขุนผาเมือง). The historian Alexander Brown Griswold, however, is of the opinion that Mueang Rat must have been located in the valley of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nan_River">Nan River</ref> near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uttaradit">Uttaradit</ref> due to geographical characteristics.</p>
<p>The "God of Sri Mueang Sodharapura" (God: ผีฟ้า, corresponding to Skt Deva raja),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> the king of Angkor, bestowed the titles of "Sri Indraditya" together with the "sword of victory" (Phrasaeng Chaisri, พระแสงชัยศรี) upon Pha Mueang and he additionally received the Khmer title "Kamrateng At Pha Mueang". At the same time he was given Nang Sikhara Mahadevi, a "daughter" of the king. An "oath of loyalty" to Angkor was probably demanded as well.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Bang Klang Hao</head>
<p>Little is known of the history of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sri_Indraditya">Bang Klang Hao</ref> (full name: Pho Khun Bang Hao, พ่อขุนบางกลางหาว). He was a friend and ally of Pha Mueang. Bang Klang Hao was ruler of the city-state Mueang Bang Yang (เจ้าเมืองบางยาง), its location also unknown. Griswold suspected it was located somewhere between Mueang Rat and Mueang <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Si_Satchanalai">Si Satchanalai</ref>, possibly even at today's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ban_Yang,_Phitsanulok">Ban Yang</ref>, which is situated about seven kilometres south of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sukhothai_Thani">New Sukhothai</ref>.</p>
<head>Liberation from the Khmer rule</head>
<p>After <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jayavarman_VII">Jayavarman VII</ref> died in 1220, the power of Angkor dwindled in the northwestern regions. The commander <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khom_Samat_Klon_Lamphong">Khom Samat Klon Lamphong</ref> (ขอมสมาดโขลญลำพง) held an outpost of the Khmer Empire in Sukhothai.</p>
<p>In "Inscription II" it is described that at some point, probably around 1238–1240, Pha Mueang marched his army united with Bang Klang Hao towards Sukhothai. In the ensuing battle at the gates of the city, Bang Klang Hao fought against Khom Samat Klon Lamphong, both from the back of their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_elephant">war elephants</ref>: "The bold Klon Lamphong was completely defeated".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>After the defeat of the Khmer troops, Pha Mueang entrusted the government of Sukhothai to Bang Klang Hao. He then retired with his men in Sukhothai. A little later Bang Klang Hao was ordained by Pha Mueang as "Chao Mueang Sukhothai" (ruler of Sukhothai, เจ้าเมืองสุโขทัย). Here Pha Mueang transferred his title "Sri Indraditya" to his comrades in arms. The new king of Sukhothai also received the "sword of victory" as a sign of his success and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palladium_(protective_image)">palladium</ref> of the New Kingdom. Sri Indraditya is now regarded as the founder of the Phra Ruang Dynasty, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sukhothai_Kingdom">Kingdom of Sukhothai</ref>.</p>
<head>Consorts</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://km.wikipedia.org/wiki/ព្រះនាងសិង្ខរមហាទេវី">Phra Nang Singkhondevi</ref>, daughter of the king <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jayavarman_VII">Jayavarman VII</ref>. Appointed to the Queen Consorts.</item>
<item>Phra Nang Naovarongdevi, consorts had married before marriage with Phra Nang Singkhondevi.</item></list>
</text>
