<text id="autogum_bio_doc230" title="Mostafa Khan of Shirvan" shortTile="mostafa-khan-shirvan" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-12-04" dateModified="2019-09-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mostafa_Khan_of_Shirvan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Mostafa Khan of Shirvan</head><p><hi rend="bold">Mostafa Khan</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_language">Persian</ref>: مصطفی خان‎) was the last <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shirvan_Khanate">khan of Shirvan</ref>, until 1820.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Mostafa Khan lived in an era of much political upheaval. It was the era of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russo-Persian_Wars">Russo-Iranian Wars</ref> of the 19th century, a period during which the Russians took the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caucasus">Caucasus</ref> territories of Iran. In 1804, the Russians, led by general <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pavel_Tsitsianov">Pavel Tsitsianov</ref>, had invaded and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Ganja_(1804)">sacked the Iranian town of Ganja</ref>, murdered its khan and his son, and had thereby initiated the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russo-Persian_War_(1804-1813)">Russo-Iranian War of 1804-1813</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEDowling2014728-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker20101035-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBournoutian2002215,_238-3">[3]</ref> Having "shown" what Russia is capable of in terms of power and might, Tsitsianov thereafter attempted to force the other khans into submission to Russia by intimidation and enticement.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBournoutian2016a-4">[4]</ref> Promising "Russian protection" and the guarantee that the khans would remain in power in their domains, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karabakh_Khanate">khan of Karabakh</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ibrahim_Khalil_Khan">Ibrahim Khalil Khan</ref> signed an agreement with Tsitsianov on 26 May 1805.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBournoutian2016a-4">[4]</ref> After the massacre in Ganja, Mostafa Khan asked the central government in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tehran">Tehran</ref> for assistance, in order to prevent Tsitsianov's advance.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETapper1997152-153-5">[5]</ref> The government responded by sending an army under general Pir-Qoli Khan Qajar.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETapper1997152-153-5">[5]</ref> However, when the general had reached the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mughan_plain">Mughan plain</ref>, he found out that Mostafa Khan had entered negotiations with the Russians.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETapper1997152-153-5">[5]</ref> Mostafa Khan hoped that the Russians would recognize a Shirvan Khanate "enlarged" to the boundaries of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shirvanshah">Shirvanshah</ref>'s of the Medieval era.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAtkin198087-6">[6]</ref> Though Mostafa Khan was uncomfortable with Tsitsianov's proposal, the latter threatened that if he wouldn't agree with his terms, he would replace Mostafa with his younger brother (who was reportedly enthusiastic about it).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAtkin198087-6">[6]</ref> Anyhow, the Russians invaded the khanate, and on 6 January 1806, Mostafa Khan was forced to submit.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBournoutian2016a-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAtkin198086-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>"I, Mostafa Khan of Shirvan, in my name and that of my heirs, remove myself forever from the vassalage or honors of Persia (Iran) or any other state. I declare before the entire world that I do not recognize anyone as my liege, except His Imperial Majesty, the Emperor of All the Russias and His heirs to the throne. I promise to be a loyal slave to that throne. I swear this by the Holy Qur'an."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBournoutian2016b213-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>Mostafa Khan was allowed to administer the khanate, and had to give an annual tribute in gold rubles to the Russians. Furthermore, he had to send hostages to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiflis">Tiflis</ref> (Tbilisi), which had recently been annexed and transformed into the "base" of the Russian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caucasus_Viceroyalty_(1801–1917)">Caucasus Viceroyalty</ref>. Lastly, he also had to provide food and accommodation for the Russian garrisons.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBournoutian2016a-4">[4]</ref> After Tsitsianov was killed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baku">Baku</ref> in 1806, Mostafa Khan repudiated his allegiance to the Russians, and re-submitted himself to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shah">shah</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETapper1997153-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>Things changed when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aleksey_Petrovich_Yermolov">Aleksey Yermolov</ref> took office as the new Russian commander-in-chief in the Caucasus, in 1816.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBournoutian2016a-4">[4]</ref> A staunch Russian imperialist, Yermolov was committed to bring the entire Caucasus under the Russian sway. He wanted to establish the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aras_(river)">Aras river</ref> as the border between Iran and Russia at all costs, and was therefore determined to conquer the last remaining khanates under Iranian rule; the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erivan_Khanate">Erivan Khanate</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nakchivan_Khanate">Nakchivan Khanate</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBournoutian2016a-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTECronin201363-10">[10]</ref>
When Ismail, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shaki_Khanate">khan of Shaki</ref>, died in 1819 without any heir, Yermolov annexed the entity. Realizing what was going to happen to himself, Mostafa Khan fled to mainland Iran in 1820 with his son; Yermolov did not waste any time to annex the Shirvan Khanate.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBournoutian2016a-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAtkin1980148-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>Several years later, in violation of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Gulistan">Gulistan treaty</ref> (1813), the Russians invaded Iran's Erivan Khanate.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEDowling2014729-12">[12]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTECronin201363-10">[10]</ref> This sparked the final bout of hostilities between the two; the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russo-Persian_War_(1826-1828)">Russo-Iranian War of 1826-1828</ref>. Crown prince <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbas_Mirza">Abbas Mirza</ref> led a full-scale attack in the summer of 1826 order to recover the Iranian territories that had been lost by the Gulistan treaty.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETapper1997161-162-13">[13]</ref> The war started off well for the Iranians; they quickly recaptured <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ganja,_Azerbaijan">Ganja</ref>, Shirvan and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shaki,_Azerbaijan">Shaki</ref> amongst others, and performed attacks on Tiflis.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETapper1997161-162-13">[13]</ref> The government then reinstated Mostafa in Shirvan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETapper1997161-162-13">[13]</ref> However, just a few months later, the tide had completely turned with the Iranian army suffering decisive defeats against the militarily superior Russians. In September 1826, Abbas Mirza was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Ganja_(1826)">defeated at Ganja</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Paskevich">Ivan Paskevich</ref>, and thus the army had to retreat over the Aras. Mostafa Khan, accompanied by a small retinue, fled once again to mainland Iran.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETapper1997161-162-13">[13]</ref></p>
</text>
