<text id="autogum_bio_doc553" title="Francisco Serrão" shortTile="francisco-serrao" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-03-18" dateModified="2019-05-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francisco_Serr%C3%A3o" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Francisco Serrão</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Francisco Serrão</hi>  (died 1521) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portugal">Portuguese</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Age_of_Discovery">explorer</ref> and a cousin of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinand_Magellan">Ferdinand Magellan</ref>. His 1512 voyage was the first known <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Europe">European</ref> sailing east past <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malacca">Malacca</ref> through modern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indonesia">Indonesia</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_Indies">East Indies</ref>. He became a confidante of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sultan_Bayan_Sirrullah">Sultan Bayan Sirrullah</ref>, the ruler of Ternate, becoming his personal advisor. He remained in Ternate where he died around the same time Magellan died.</p>
<head>Voyage to the Indies</head>
<p>Serrão served as captain of one of three vessels (and second in overall command under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/António_de_Abreu">António de Abreu</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HANNARDp7-1">[1]</ref>) sent from Malacca by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afonso_de_Albuquerque">Afonso de Albuquerque</ref> to find the Spice Islands of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banda_Islands">Banda</ref> in Maluku in 1511.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-RICKLEFSp24-2">[2]</ref> Banda was the world's only source of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nutmeg">nutmeg</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mace_(spice)">mace</ref>, spices used as flavourings, medicines, preserving agents, that were at the time highly valued in European markets. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portuguese_Empire">Portuguese</ref> sought to dominate the source, rather than relying on Arab traders who sold it to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_of_Venice">Venetians</ref> for exorbitant prices.</p>
<p>Malay pilots guided the expedition east via <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Java">Java</ref> and along the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lesser_Sunda_Islands">Lesser Sundas</ref> before steering them north to Banda via <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ambon_Island">Ambon</ref>. When Serrão's ship had berthed at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gresik">Gresik</ref> on Java, he married a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Javanese_people">Javanese</ref> woman as his wife, who then accompanied him on the expedition's further journey.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> In 1512 his ship was shipwrecked but managed to reach Luco-Pino island (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hitu">Hitu</ref>), north of Ambon. The expedition remained in Banda for about one month, purchasing and filling their ships with nutmeg and mace, as well as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clove">cloves</ref> in which Banda had a thriving <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entrepôt">entrepôt</ref> trade.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HANNARDp7-1">[1]</ref> Serrão left Banda in a Chinese <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Junk_(ship)">junk</ref> purchased from a regional trader to replace his lost ship.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HANNARDp7-1">[1]</ref> D'Abreu sailed through Ambon while Serrão went ahead towards Maluku islands.</p>
<p>With nine Portuguese crew and nine Indonesians, the ship foundered in a squall and broke up on a reef off a small island. When the island's inhabitants, notorious shipwreck scavengers, surveyed the wreck from a boat, Serrão's crew posed as unarmed and helpless but wealthy castaways. As the scavengers drew near, the Portuguese attacked and commandeered both their craft and crew. Their inadvertent rescuers were then forced to take them to Ambon, where they disembarked in Hitu.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HANNARDp7-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Serrão's armour, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musket">muskets</ref> and marksmanship impressed the powerful chiefs of Hitu who were warring against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luhu,_Indonesia">Luhu</ref>, the principal settlement on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seram">Seram</ref>'s Hoamal Peninsula near Hitu.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> The Portuguese were also welcomed in the area as buyers of food and spices during a lull in the spice trade due to a temporary disruption to Javanese and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malays_(ethnic_group)">Malay</ref> sailings to the area following the 1511 conflicts in Malacca. The visitors were recruited as military allies and their subsequent exploits were heard in the rival neighbours of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ternate">Ternate</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tidore">Tidore</ref> who both rushed emissaries to induce the visitors to assist.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-RICKLEFSp24-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Supporting the territory of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sultanate_of_Ternate">Sultanate of Ternate</ref>, the Portuguese strongest power, Serrão served as the head of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mercenary">mercenary</ref> band of Portuguese warriors under the service of the island's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sultan_Bayan_Sirrullah">Sultan Bayan Sirrullah</ref>, one of two feuding powerful sultans who controlled the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spice">spice</ref> trade. They became close friends and the Sultan appointed Serrão as his personal adviser for all matters, including military (Portuguese document purport) and family issues. Having been well received by the Sultan, Francisco Serrão decided to remain there, not making any efforts to return to Malacca.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-barbosa-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Final years</head>
<p>Francisco Serrão's letters to Ferdinand Magellan, carried to Portugal via <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portuguese_Malacca">Portuguese Malacca</ref> and describing the 'Spice Islands', helped Magellan persuade the King of Spain to finance his circumnavigation.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HANNARDp8-6">[6]</ref> Before they met each other, Serrão mysteriously died in Ternate at almost the same time Magellan was killed in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philippines">Philippines</ref> (in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mactan_Island">Mactan Island</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cebu">Cebu</ref>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-barbosa-5">[5]</ref> One theory suggests Serrão died of poison administered by the Sultan of Ternate.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-HANNARDp8-6">[6]</ref> His family ties with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/João_Serrão">João Serrão</ref> remain unclear in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Historiography">historiography</ref> of Portuguese expeditions to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southeast_Asia">Southeast Asia</ref>. The only written document is a list of captains' names in the fleet of Magellan's.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-barbosa-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>General</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Hannard, Willard A. (1991). <hi rend="italic">Indonesian Banda: Colonialism and its Aftermath in the Nutmeg Islands</hi>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bandanaira">Bandanaira</ref>: Yayasan Warisan dan Budaya Banda Naira.</item>
<item>Muller, Karl (1997).  Pickell, David (ed.). <hi rend="italic">Maluku: Indonesian Spice Islands</hi>. Singapore: Periplus Editions. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/962-593-176-7">962-593-176-7</ref>.</item></list>
</text>
