<text id="autogum_bio_doc675" title="Ulrich V, Lord of Hanau" shortTile="ulrich-v-lord-hanau" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-09" dateModified="2019-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulrich_V%2C_Lord_of_Hanau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ulrich V, Lord of Hanau</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ulrich V, Lord of Hanau</hi> (c.1370–1419 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schaafheim">Schaafheim</ref>) was the ruling Lord of Hanau from 1380 to 1404.</p>
<head>Childhood</head>
<p>His exact date and even the year of his birth were not recorded, because in the medieval view the date the death of a person was far more important, as that was the date a memorial mass would be read. Nevertheless, the exact date of his death was not recorded either, because his family was silent about him after he was deposed.</p>
<p>He was born around 1370, as the eldest son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulrich_IV,_Lord_of_Hanau">Ulrich IV</ref> and his wife, Elisabeth of Wertheim. He inherited Hanau already in 1380.</p>
<p>One of the sons of Ulrich IV was enrolled at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Heidelberg">University of Heidelberg</ref> in 1390. The enrollment entry does not mention a first name — it only names a <hi lang="la" rend="italic">domicellus de Hanaw</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> Since Ulrich V was already ruling Hanau at this time, it would be unlikely that he was this student.</p>
<head>Regency</head>
<p>Since he was a minor when he inherited Hanau in 1380, a regency was set up. The father of his fiancée, Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gottfried_VIII,_Count_of_Ziegenhain">Gottfried VIII</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Ziegenhain">Ziegenhain</ref> acted as regent until c.1388.</p>
<head>Reign</head>
<p>In 1389, he fought on the side of Elector Palatine <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rupert_I,_Elector_Palatine">Rupert I</ref> in the Cities War, a conflict between the emerging cities and the nobility, and on the victorious side in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feud_of_Kronberg">Feud of Kronberg</ref>. In 1400, he was among the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burgmann">Burgmanns</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friedberg_Castle">Friedberg</ref> who were sent to the newly elected King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rupert,_King_of_Germany">Rupert</ref> of the Romans, to negotiate about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homage_(medieval)">homage</ref>, after King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslaus,_King_of_the_Romans">Wenceslaus</ref> had been deposed.</p>
<head>Government crisis and deposition</head>
<p>There were two main reasons why Ulrich V was deposed by his relatives:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>The absence of a male heir threatened the survival of the family. In 1375, his father had confirmed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primogeniture">primogeniture</ref> decree, which <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulrich_II,_Lord_of_Hanau">Ulrich II</ref> had issued in 1339. The threat was reduced by family treaty of 1391, which allowed his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reinhard_II,_Count_of_Hanau">Reinhard II</ref> to marry if Ulrich V still had no male heir ten years later, that is, in 1401.</item>
<item>Ulrich V ran into economic difficulties from 1394, and even more so after 1396, even though he had received compensation payments from the city of Frankfurt after the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feud_of_Kronberg">Feud of Kronberg</ref>. Apparently, he had overstretched himself in his "foreign policy". He mortgaged the village of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maintal-Hochstadt">Hochstadt</ref> to Frankfurt, the district of Joßgrund to the Lords of Thüngen, and in the end, he even mortgaged the two major of the four cities in his territory, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanau">Hanau</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Babenhausen,_Hesse">Babenhausen</ref> to his neighbor, political rival and first cousin once removed, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop">Archbishop</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_II_of_Nassau">John II</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishopric_of_Mainz">Mainz</ref>, effectively making him co-ruler of the Lordship of Hanau.</item></list>
<p>From c.1395, a coalition consisting of Reinhard II and his younger brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Hanau">John</ref> began acting independently and even against Ulrich V. This led to an open dispute, which was settled by a compromise in 1398. However, the dispute emerged again, and grew to the level of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feud">feud</ref>. From 1400, and more so from 1402, Reinhard II and John sought support from Archbishop John II of Mainz, who eventually changed sides and dropped his support of Ulrich V.</p>
<p>In 1404, Ulrich V gradually lost power. On 20 February 1404, Reinhard II and John took up government; on 20 November 1404, Ulrich formally abdicated and ordered his subjects to pay <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homage_(medieval)">homage</ref> to his brothers. His wife had already renounced any claims she might have on Hanau earlier that year, in return for a monetary compensation, without Ulrich V being even mentioned in the contract.</p>
<p>Historians in the 18th and 19th century have suggested that Ulrich V may have suffered from a mental disorder. This disorder would have justified setting aside the primogeniture decree for just one generation. However, there is no contemporary evidence to support this theory.</p>
<p>Reinhard II and John ruled jointly at first. After John died in 1411, Reinhard II ruled alone.</p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>Little is known about Ulrich V after his abdication. He is reported to have resided in Frankfurt for a while, and later in the district of Babenhausen. He probably died in 1419 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schaafheim">Schaafheim</ref>.</p>
<head>Marriage and issue</head>
<p>In 1394, Ulrich V married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elisabeth_of_Ziegenhain">Elisabeth</ref> (c.1375 – 1 December 1431), the daughter of Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gottfried_VIII,_Count_of_Ziegenhain">Gottfried VIII</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Ziegenhain">Ziegenhain</ref>. They had three daughters:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elisabeth_of_Hanau_(d._1475)">Elisabeth</ref> (d. 1475), married in 1413 to Albert I of Hohenlohe (d. 15 June 1429)</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agnes_of_Hanay_(Klarenthal)">Agnes</ref> (d. 22 November 1446), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbess">abbess</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Klarenthal_Abbey">Klarenthal Abbey</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adelaide_of_Hanau_(Klarenthal)">Adelaide</ref> (d. 13 November 1440), a nun at Klarenthal Abbey</item></list>
<head>Ancestors</head>
<head>References</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Reinhard Dietrich: <hi rend="italic">Die Abdankung Ulrichs V. von Hanau – Ursachen und Folgen</hi>, in: <hi rend="italic">Hanauer Geschichtsblätter</hi>, vol. 31, Hanau, 1993</item>
<item>Reinhard Dietrich: <hi rend="italic">Die Landesverfassung in dem Hanauischen</hi> = <hi rend="italic">Hanauer Geschichtsblätter</hi>, vol. 34, Hanau, 1996, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/3-9801933-6-5">3-9801933-6-5</ref></item>
<item>Reinhard Suchier: <hi rend="italic">Genealogie des Hanauer Grafenhauses</hi>, in: <hi rend="italic">Festschrift des Hanauer Geschichtsvereins zu seiner fünfzigjährigen Jubelfeier am 27. August 1894</hi>, Hanau, 1894</item>
<item>Ernst J. Zimmermann: <hi rend="italic">Hanau Stadt und Land</hi>, 3rd ed., Hanau, 1919, reprinted in 1978</item></list>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
