<text id="autogum_bio_doc323" title="Bakshi Ghulam Haider" shortTile="bakshi-ghulam-haider" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-07-05" dateModified="2018-11-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bakshi_Ghulam_Haider" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bakshi Ghulam Haider</head>
<hi rend="bold">Warning:</hi> Page using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_person">Template:Infobox person</ref> with unknown parameter "awards and Titles" (this message is shown only in preview).
<p><hi rend="bold">Khan Bahadur Bakhshi Ghulam Haider Khan</hi> (died 1828 AD) was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Faujdar">Faujdar</ref> of a unit at the time of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Assaye">Battle of Assaye</ref>, which was a major battle of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Anglo-Maratha_War">Second Anglo-Maratha War</ref> under the command of Major General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Wellesley,_1st_Duke_of_Wellington">Arthur Wellesley</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_of_Wellington">Duke of Wellington</ref>). Latterly, he became the royal chief head of the military services hence called the <hi rend="italic">Mir Bakhshi</hi>. He was in charge of intelligence gathering, and also made recommendations to the royal court for military appointments and promotions.</p>
<head>Services</head>
<p>Khan Bahadur Bakshi Ghulam Haider Khan was first employed with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nizam_of_Hyderabad">Nizam of Hyderabad</ref>. He then joined army and became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Faujdar">Faujdar</ref>. He fought in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Assaye">Battle of Assaye</ref>, which was a major battle of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Anglo-Maratha_War">Second Anglo-Maratha War</ref> under the command of Major General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Wellesley,_1st_Duke_of_Wellington">Arthur Wellesley</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_of_Wellington">Duke of Wellington</ref>). Because of his services in the army under the command of (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_of_Wellington">Duke of Wellington</ref>), he was awarded the title ‘Khan Bahadur’ and a land of 1400 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bigha">Bigha</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rewari">Rewari</ref>. He was latterly employed with Appa Sahib alias <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mudhoji_II_Bhonsle">Mudhoji II Bhonsle</ref>. In 1817, he vehemently opposed the action of Appa Sahib when he was conspiring against British forces; as a result Appa Sahib was deposed and forwarded to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allahabad">Allahabad</ref> in custody, while Khan Bahadur Bakshi Ghulam Haider Khan was placed as ‘Kamidan’, a commandant in the army. He remained on this post for 12 years.</p>
<head>Family history</head>
<p>His ancestor ‘Shaikh Umaruddin’ came to India along with the caravan of Sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shahabuddin_Muhammad_Ghori">Shahabuddin Muhammad Ghori</ref> and settled at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sultanpur,_Haryana">Sultanpur</ref>, near the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/River_Sutlej">River Sutlej</ref> and River Bayas. His sons went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delhi">Delhi</ref> and deputed as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mufti">Mufti</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rewari">Rewari</ref>. This profession remained in their family for centuries. Khan Bahadur Bakshi Ghulam Haider Khan was the son of Mufti Noorul Haq ibn Amanul Haq.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Brothers</head>
<p>He had three brothers: Ghulam Hussain, Amanul Haq, and Mohibul Haq. Mohibul Haq was the judge at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nagpur_state">Nagpur state</ref>. Amanul Haq during the reign of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Akbar_Shah_II">Akbar Shah II</ref> (King of Delhi) took service with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raghoji_II_Bhonsle">Raghoji II Bhonsle</ref> (Raja of Nagpur) and served him for many years. He had eight sons: Shamsul Haq, Sanaul Haq, Zafar Ali Khan, Abdul Ali Khan, Imdad Hussain, Ghulam Yahya, Fazlul Haq and Ahsanul Haq. Zafar Ali Khan was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subahdar">Subahdar</ref> for nine years at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nagpur">Nagpur</ref> and received 6000 rupees annually as salary. After his death, his all five sons got pensions. His one son, Inayat Ali Khan received pension of rupees 600 against the services in army and for the same reason, he remained Honorary Magistrate at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rewari">Rewari</ref>, District <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gurgaon">Gurgaon</ref>. The second son of Amanul Haq, Abdul Ali Khan was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Risaldar">Risaldar</ref> in one of the Punjab regimentduring <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1857_War_of_Independence">1857 War of Independence</ref>. The son of Sanaul Haq, Mohib Hussain Khan became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subahdar">Subahdar</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bhandara">Bhandara</ref>, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nagpur">Nagpur</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> In 1853, when Britishers took over Nagpur, he was appointed as Extra-Assistant Commissioner. He died in 1870. His son Nooruddin Hussain Khan was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Risaldar">Risaldar</ref> at Nagpur for many years and another son, Moizuddin Hussain Khan was employed at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nizam_of_Hyderabad">Nizam of Hyderabad</ref>.</p>
<head>Children</head>
<p>He had four sons: Ghulam Mohamamd Khan, Khairat Ali Khan, Jeevan Ali Khan and Auz Ali Khan. Three of his sons were employed in the army of the States of Nagpur. After his death, his elder son Ghulam Mohamad Khan (died 1833 AD) latterly became the ‘Kamidan’ in his place. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sardar_Bahadur_Tafazzul_Hussain_Khan">Sardar Bahadur Tafazzul Hussain Khan</ref> was the son of Ghulam Mohamad Khan.</p>
</text>
