<text id="autogum_bio_doc763" title="Ọranyan" shortTile="ranyan" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-21" dateModified="2019-11-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E1%BB%8Cranyan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ọranyan</head><p><hi rend="bold">Oranmiyan Omoluabi Odede, Great Prince of Ife, King of the Yoruba</hi>, also known as <hi rend="bold">Ọranyan</hi>, was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yoruba_people">Yoruba</ref> king from the kingdom of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ile-Ife">Ile-Ife</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>. Although he was the youngest, he became the prime heir of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oduduwa">Oduduwa</ref> upon his return to claim his grandfather's throne.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sacred-texts-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>According to Yoruba history, he founded <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oyo_Empire">Oyo</ref> as its first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alaafin">Alaafin</ref> at around the year 1300 after he had left Benin where he had been crowned the first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oba_of_Benin">Oba of Benin</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>
Following the Oba Oranyan's death, his family is fabled to have erected the commemorative stele known as the Staff of Oranmiyan - <hi rend="italic">Opa Oranmiyan</hi> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yoruba_language">Yoruba language</ref> - at the place where their grandfather died. This obelisk Is 5.5m tall and about 1.2m in circumference at its base. During a storm in 1884 about 1.2m was broken off from its top and it has fallen down twice and been re-erected on each occasion. It currently stands in a grove in Mopa, Ile-Ife. Radiocarbon tests have shown that this royal marker was erected centuries before the start of the Oduduwa dynasty, during what is known as the "classical" <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ife">Ife</ref> period.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sacred-texts-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Early Life</head>
<p>Not much is known about Oranmiyan's childhood and most of the information about his early life comes from Ife sources. A man of two fathers - <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oduduwa">Oduduwa</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ogun">Ogun</ref> - who both had relations with his mother Lakange Anihunka (a slave captured by Ogun in one of his war expeditions) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref>
The legend further compounds the controversy by stating that Oranmiyan was two-tone in complexion: half his body was light-skinned (like Ogun's), while the other half was ebony-black (like Oduduwa's). Due to this, he was given the name <hi rend="bold">Oranmiyan</hi> (or <hi rend="italic">Oran ni Omo ni yan</hi>, which means "The child has chosen to be controversial"). His other name <hi rend="bold">Odede</hi> signifies a great hunter, something which he was known to be throughout his early life in Ife. He was also a great warrior like his two fathers. He was the first Odole Oduduwa (youth of the house of oduduwa) as he was a strong and outspoken prince of the Oduduwa lineage. His strength and talent in battle made him take up the role of defending Ife - which had no standing military at the time - as the first Akogun of Ife. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Oranmiyan at Benin</head>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edo_people">Edo</ref> chiefs, who had earlier requested the return of their exiled prince izoduwa(oduduwa) from Ife after the death of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ogiso">Ogiso</ref> Owodo of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benin_Kingdom">Igodomigodo</ref>, were given Oranmiyan by his father izoduwa(oduduwa), to serve as their king. He met opposition from the kindred of the Ogiso, and was refused entrance into the city upon his arrival there.  Oranmiyan camped at a place called Use, meaning "making of a city" or "politicking", and began to rule Benin from there. His foreign style of management didn't go down well with the chiefs, and they sent agents to spy on him. All this made Oranmiyan declare that only a son of the soil could cope with the attitude of the Igodomigodo people. He called the land <hi rend="italic">Ile - Ibinu</hi>, meaning "Land of Vexation".
On leaving Ile-Ibinu (later Ibini, and corrupted to "Benin" by the Portuguese), he stopped briefly at Egor where he took Erinmwide, the daughter of the enogie (or duke) of Egor, as a wife. Eweka I was the result of this union. Oranmiyan was never to return to Benin. In his place, Eweka I became king. Oranmiyan, or Oromiyan as pronounced by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edo_people">Edo people</ref>, is recognized as the first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oba_of_Benin">Oba of Benin</ref> a direct linage of the last Ogiso Owodo, Oranmiyan become known as the FIRST Oba of benin, the new dynasty known as the " GOD KING". which is still ruling today. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Oranmiyan at Oyo</head>
<p>After leaving Benin at about 1190, he moved north with his ever loyal entourage and settled close to the river Moshi (a tributary to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niger_River">Niger River</ref>). He founded a city there, Oyo-Ile, which his descendants then expanded into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oyo_Empire">Oyo Empire</ref>. He engaged in war with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bariba_people">Bariba</ref>, his immediate neighbors to the north, and subsequently married Torosi, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nupe_people">Tapa</ref> princess, who became the mother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shango">Sango Akata Yẹri-Yẹri</ref>.</p>
<head>Oranyan festival</head>
<p>The first ever Oranyan Festival of Arts, Culture and Tourism was initiated in 2012 by his descendant and reigning successor, Oba <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lamidi_Adeyemi_III">Lamidi Adeyemi III</ref> of Oyo, who mandated that subsequently the festival was to be celebrated annually between the 8th and 15th days of the month of September in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oyo,_Nigeria">Oyo, Nigeria</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
</text>
