<text id="autogum_bio_doc682" title="Esau de&apos; Buondelmonti" shortTile="esau-de-buondelmonti" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-06-07" dateModified="2019-08-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esau_de%27_Buondelmonti" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Esau de' Buondelmonti</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Esau de' Buondelmonti</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_language">Greek</ref>: Ησαύ Μπουοντελμόντ) was the ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ioannina">Ioannina</ref> and its surrounding area (central <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epirus">Epirus</ref>) from 1385 until his death in 1411, with the Byzantine title of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despot_(court_title)">Despot</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Esau was the son of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florence">Florentine</ref> nobleman Manente Buondelmonti and Lapa Acciaiuoli, sister of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niccolò_Acciaiuoli">Niccolò Acciaiuoli</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corinth">Corinth</ref>. Esau had come to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greece">Greece</ref> to seek success like his Acciaiuoli kinsmen, but in 1379 he had been captured in battle against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Preljubović">Thomas Preljubović</ref> of Epirus.  After he spent several years of captivity, Esau succeeded his captor by marrying the latter's widow, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Angelina_Doukaina_Palaiologina">Maria Angelina Doukaina Palaiologina</ref> in February 1385.</p>
<p>Esau reversed the unpopular policies of the tyrannical Thomas, recalling the exiled nobles and reinstating Matthew, the bishop of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ioannina">Ioannina</ref>.  The new ruler pursued a pacifying policy, and sought accommodation with both the Albanian clans and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_Empire">Byzantine Empire</ref>.  In 1386 a Byzantine embassy arrived at Ioannina and invested Esau with the court dignity of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despotes">despotes</ref></hi> (despot).  Although Esau was fully independent from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref>, this recognition helped strengthen and legitimize his position.</p>
<p>Esau found it difficult, however, to reach an agreement with the Albanians. In 1385 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Spata">John Spata</ref>, despot of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arta,_Greece">Arta</ref>, advanced on Ioannina, but Esau managed to prepare the defences so efficiently, that the Albanian leader withdrew.  Esau was forced to follow Thomas' policy of seeking <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> support against the Albanians, going to the court of Sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murad_I">Murad I</ref> to pay homage in 1386.  This alliance brought a respite to the fighting in Epirus, but the conflict flamed up again after the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Kosovo">Battle of Kosovo</ref> and death of Murad in 1389.  Once again Ioannina was threatened, and once again Esau succeeded in weathering the storm by seeking and obtaining Ottoman support.</p>
<p>Returning to Ioannina after 14 months (1399–1400) at the Ottoman court under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayezid_I">Bayezid I</ref>, Esau was supported by the Ottoman commander <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evrenos">Evrenos</ref> and quickly defeated the Albanians.  This bought him four years of peace interrupted only at the end by a conflict with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_of_Venice">Venice</ref> over a disputed port.  The death of Maria in December 1394 was followed by a new conflict with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Bua_Spata">John Bua Spata</ref>, which was resolved through diplomacy.  In January 1396 Esau married Spata's daughter Irene as part of the peace settlement.  But peace remained elusive.  No longer needing Turkish support, Esau had clashed with the Turks and defeated them, becoming increasingly confident in his power.</p>
<p>In 1399 Esau, supported by some Albanian clans, marched against his wife's brother-in-law <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Zenevisi">John Zenevisi</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gjirokastër">Gjirokastër</ref>.  Now Esau was routed and captured, and much of his land was occupied by Zenebishi. The neighboring magnates determined to restore the captured despotes and secured Venetian intercession in his favor.  Esau returned to Ioannina in 1400, and reigned on in relative peace until his death on February 6, 1411.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Esau does not appear to have had children by his first wife Maria Angelina Doukaina Palaiologina or by his second wife Irene Bua Spata.  By his third wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jevdokija_Balšić">Jevdokija Balšić</ref> he had three children, including:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giorgio_de'_Buondelmonti">Giorgio de' Buondelmonti</ref>, who succeeded as briefly as ruler of Ioannina, before he was deposed by the local nobility, who surrendered their city to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlo_I_Tocco">Carlo I Tocco</ref>.</item></list>
</text>
