<text id="autogum_bio_doc075" title="Jacqulyn Buglisi" shortTile="jacqulyn-buglisi" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-10-11" dateModified="2019-10-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacqulyn_Buglisi" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Jacqulyn Buglisi</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jacqulyn Buglisi</hi> is an American <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Choreographer">choreographer</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artistic_director">artistic director</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dancer">dancer</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Educator">educator</ref>, and founder or co-founder of multiple dance institutions. Buglisi, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terese_Capucilli">Terese Capucilli</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christine_Dakin">Christine Dakin</ref> and Donlin Foreman, founded Buglisi Dance Theatre in 1993/94 (formerly BuglisiForeman Dance).</p>
<head>Choreography</head>
<p>Buglisi's ballets are highly visual and imagistic dances that draw from literature, history and heroic archetypes as primary sources. Buglisi's ballets are rooted in strong physical technique. Her repertoire of more than eighty works has been seen by audiences at venues across the United States including:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_F._Kennedy_Center_for_the_Performing_Arts">John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joyce_Theater">Joyce Theater</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacob's_Pillow_Dance_Festival">Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival</ref></item>
<item>Society of the Performing Arts <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wortham_Theater_Center">Wortham Theater Center</ref> – Cullen Theater, Houston</item>
<item>Kravis Center for the Performing Arts</item>
<item>Spring to Dance Festival, St. Louis</item>
<item>SUNY Purchase Performing Arts Center – Concert Hall</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_B._Fisher_Center_for_the_Performing_Arts">Richard B. Fisher Center for the Performing Arts</ref> – Sosnoff Theater</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Arizona">University of Arizona</ref> – Centennial Hall</item></list>
<p>Internationally, her works have appeared at the Melbourne International Festival- State Theater; during International Dance Week in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prague">Prague</ref>; the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_Republic">Czech Republic</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italy">Italy</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France">France</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israel">Israel</ref>.</p>
<p>Lynn Garafola of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dance_Magazine">Dance Magazine</ref></hi> wrote, "Buglisi is a rarity in today's world, a woman who delights in the many splendid forms of female being. Probably no woman, other than Graham, has plumbed such emotional depths choreographically"<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> and for Buglisi's www.UndertheButtonwoodTree.com commissioned by LMCC, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alastair_Macaulay">Alastair Macaulay</ref> of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_New_York_Times">The New York Times</ref></hi> wrote, "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cecil_B._DeMille">Cecil B. DeMille</ref> would have been proud".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Her commissions include The Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater, Ailey 2, The LMCC River to River Festival, New York Flamenco Festival in Madrid; Sadler's Wells Theater London and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_City_Center">New York City Center</ref>; The Richmond Ballet; pieces for Ananda Shankar Performing Arts Company of India; the Shanghai Song and Dance Ensemble of China; The Juilliard School, The Martha Graham Dance Company; North Carolina Dance Theater; Joyce Trisler Danscompany (charter member/choreographer) and the Teatro Danza Contemporanea di Roma (co-founder/choreographer).</p>
<p>Buglisi collaborated with Venezuelan environmental painter and filmmaker <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacobo_Borges">Jacobo Borges</ref> to create her trilogy, <hi rend="italic">Rain</hi> (score by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glen_Velez">Glen Velez</ref>), <hi rend="italic">Sand</hi> (music by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Glass">Philip Glass</ref>), and <hi rend="italic">Blue Cathedral</hi> (music by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jennifer_Higdon">Jennifer Higdon</ref>. Other collaborations include composers <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tan_Dun">Tan Dun</ref>, Paola Prestini, Andy Teirstein, Daniel Bernard Roumain (DBR), Libby Larsen, Daniel Brewbaker, Reza Vali, cellist Maya Beiser, Flamenco guitarist Gerardo Nunex, the Cassatt String Quartet, Carmen de Lavallade, Claire Bloom, mannequin maker Ralph Pucci and lighting designers Clifton Taylor and Jack Mehler.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">The Table of Silence Project 9/11</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>On September 11, 2011, 2012, 2013, 2014, 2015, 2016, 2017, 2018 and 2019 Buglisi Dance Theatre presented 150+ dancers at Lincoln Center in <hi rend="italic">The Table of Silence Project 9/11</hi>, a public tribute and ritual honoring peace and tolerance, "a magnificent expression of peace". Live streaming around the globe reaching 102 countries and across all 50 states, www.tableofsilence.org.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Other <hi rend="italic">Table of Silence</hi> Site-specific commemorations were presented at the Pan Am 103 Remembrance Wall during the company's NYSCA residency at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syracuse_University">Syracuse University</ref>; in Perugia and Assisi, Italy; and UC Santa Barbara on May 23, 2016, to mark the anniversary of a mass-shooting near the campus.</p>
<p>Her company's repertoire is archived for public viewing at the Jerome Robbins Dance Division of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_Public_Library">New York Public Library</ref>. In recognition of her excellence as a choreographer, dancer, and educator in 2016 Buglisi was awarded a lifetime achievement award from Italian International Dance Award.</p>
<head>Dancer</head>
<figure><caption>Photo credit by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Mitchell_(photographer)">Jack Mitchell</ref></caption></figure>
<p>During her 30-year association with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martha_Graham_Dance_Company">Martha Graham Dance Company</ref>, Buglisi danced as a principal artist for 12 years, performing the classic roles such as the Three Mary's (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_Penitente">El Penitente</ref></hi>), Andromache (<hi rend="italic">Cortege of Eagles</hi>), the Warrior (<hi rend="italic">Seraphic Dialogue</hi>), the Lament (<hi rend="italic">Acts of Light</hi>), the Girl in Yellow (<hi rend="italic">Diversion of Angels</hi>), Leader of the Night Journey Chorus and Jocasta (<hi rend="italic">Night Journey</hi>), Creusa (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cave_of_the_Heart">Cave of the Heart</ref></hi>), The Spectator (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Every_Soul_is_a_Circus">Every Soul is a Circus</ref></hi>) and in <hi rend="italic">Tangled Night</hi> created for her by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martha_Graham">Martha Graham</ref>. She danced in Graham's honor on the nationally televised CBS Presentation of the Kennedy Center Honors and is featured in the PBS film, <hi rend="italic">An Evening of Dance and Conversation with Martha Graham</hi>. Coached by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jane_Sherman">Jane Sherman</ref>, Buglisi performed the solos of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruth_St._Denis">Ruth St. Denis</ref> at Jacob's Pillow and internationally, including Lyon Biennale De La Dancse, on film in <hi rend="italic">Trailblazers of American Modern Dance</hi>, and also in the film, <hi rend="italic">The Spirit of Denishawn</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Educator</head>
<p>Buglisi has been commissioned by The Juilliard School's Emerging Modern Masters Series, Ailey/Fordham University B.F.A. Program, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Richmond">University of Richmond</ref>, California State University/Long Beach, George Mason University, Purchase Conservatory of Dance, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interlochen_Center_for_the_Arts">Interlochen Center for the Arts</ref>, the State Ballet College of Oslo, Oklahoma Arts Institute, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacob's_Pillow_Dance_Festival">Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston_Conservatory_of_Music">Boston Conservatory of Music</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Randolph-Macon_College">Randolph-Macon College</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Dance_Institute">National Dance Institute</ref>, among others.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>In 1970, Buglisi founded the first school of contemporary dance for the community of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spoleto">Spoleto</ref>, Italy, and was the Master Artist-in-Residence at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlantic_Center_for_the_Arts">Atlantic Center for the Arts</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> She has taught for the Dance Aspen Festival from 1990 to 1995, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julio_Bocca">Julio Bocca</ref> Center in Argentina, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victoria_College,_Melbourne">Victoria College</ref> in Melbourne in 1999, and the Chautauqua Institution and Festival from 1995 to 2005.</p>
<p>As a resident teacher in New York City, she has been chairperson of the Modern Department at The Ailey School, has served on the faculty of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Juilliard_School">The Juilliard School</ref> from 1991 to 2005, The Martha Graham School of Contemporary Dance since 1977, and Ballet Hispanico School of Dance. Buglisi guest teaches at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fiorello_H._LaGuardia_High_School">LaGuardia High School of the Performing Arts</ref> (alumna) and instructs workshops at Steps on Broadway and Peridance Capezio Center. She was named honorary chair for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marymount_Manhattan_College">Marymount Manhattan College</ref> 2005 Gala and served as a panelist for both the Heinz Family Foundation and the New Jersey State Council for the Arts. Buglisi holds creative and educational residencies at Kaatsbaan International Dance Center, Munson-Williams-Proctor Arts-Institute, SUNY Purchase, California State University, Long Beach, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Mason_University">George Mason University</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Richmond">University of Richmond</ref>, The Mahayfee Theater Class Act in FSU at Tallahassee, Petersburg Florida, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syracuse_University">Syracuse University</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>Buglisi's awards and honors include the American Dance Guild Award for Artistic Excellence, Italian International Lifetime Achievement Award 2016, Fiorello LaGuardia Award for Excellence in the field of Dance, The 2014 Kaatsbaan International Playing Field Award, The Gertrude Shurr Award for Dance, Altria Group's 2007 Women Choreographer Initiative Award, as well as grants for new work from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Endowment_for_the_Arts">National Endowment for the Arts</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_State_Council_on_the_Arts">New York State Council on the Arts</ref>, NYC Department of Cultural Affairs, Harkness Foundation for Dance, Howard Gilman Foundation, and The O'Donnell-Green Music &amp; Dance Foundation.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>Buglisi served on the Dance/USA's Board of Trustees as Chair of Artistic Director's Council from 2010 to 2013.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
</text>
