<text id="autogum_bio_doc443" title="Robert Wilson (dramatist)" shortTile="robert-wilson-dramatist" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2004-04-15" dateModified="2018-09-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Wilson_%28dramatist%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Robert Wilson (dramatist)</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Wilson</hi> (flourished 1572–1600), was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabethan">Elizabethan</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dramatist">dramatist</ref> who worked primarily in the 1580s and 1590s. He is also believed to have been an actor who specialized in clown roles.</p>
<p>He was connected with sixteen plays intended for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Henslowe">Philip Henslowe</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rose_(theatre)">Rose Theatre</ref>, in partnership with other playwrights who also produced copy for Henslowe. While mentioned as a dramatist by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Meres">Francis Meres</ref> in 1598, most existing information on his dramatic career is derived from Henslowe's papers.</p>
<p>Since the name is common, it is not certain that the Robert Wilson who worked for Henslowe in 1598-1600 is the same man who was a prominent actor and occasional playwright in the 1580s; yet many scholars consider it more likely than not that the records refer to one Robert Wilson and not two. If this is correct, Wilson was acting with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leicester's_Men">Leicester's Men</ref> in the 1570s, and was praised along with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Tarlton">Richard Tarlton</ref> for his "wit." He is generally accepted as the author of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Three_Ladies_of_London">The Three Ladies of London</ref></hi> (published 1584), <hi rend="italic">The Three Lords and Three Ladies of London</hi> (published 1590), and <hi rend="italic">The Cobbler's Prophecy</hi> (published 1594). It has been speculated that he may also have written <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fair_Em">Fair Em</ref></hi> (c. 1590). In <hi rend="italic">Palladis Tamia</hi> (1598), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Meres">Francis Meres</ref> mentions Wilson along with Tarlton, and specifically connects Wilson with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Swan_(theatre)">Swan Theatre</ref>, which was built c. 1595.</p>
<p>In just over two years, from spring 1598 to summer 1600, Wilson worked with other members of Henslowe's stable of house playwrights on sixteen different plays, including three two-part projects. Several of these were never completed.</p>
<list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Earl Goodwin and his Three Sons, Parts 1 and 2</hi>, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Drayton">Michael Drayton</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Chettle">Henry Chettle</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Dekker_(poet)">Thomas Dekker</ref>; March 1598.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Piers of Exton</hi>, with Drayton, Chettle, and Dekker; March 1598.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Black Bateman of the North, Parts 1 and 2</hi>, with Chettle; Part I with Dekker and Drayton also; May–June 1598.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">The Funeral of Richard Cordelion</hi>, with Chettle, Drayton, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony_Munday">Anthony Munday</ref>; June 1598.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">The Madman's Morris</hi>, with Dekker and Drayton, July 1598.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Hannibal and Hermes</hi>, with Dekker and Drayton, July 1598.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Pierce of Winchester</hi>, with Dekker and Drayton, July–August 1598.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Catiline's Conspiracy</hi>, with Chettle; August 1598. Apparently never completed.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Chance Medley</hi>, with Munday, Drayton, and Dekker or Chettle; August 1598.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_John_Oldcastle">Sir John Oldcastle</ref>,  Parts 1 and 2</hi>, with Drayton, Munday, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Hathwaye">Richard Hathwaye</ref>; Oct.-Dec. 1599.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Henry Richmond, Part 2</hi>, with others; never completed.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Owen Tudor</hi>, with Drayton, Hathwaye, and Munday; Jan. 1600. Apparently never completed.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Fair Constance of Rome, Part 1</hi>, with Dekker, Drayton, Hathwaye, and Munday; June 1600.</item></list>
<p>Of Wilson's collaborations for Henslowe, only the first part of <hi rend="italic">Sir John Oldcastle</hi> was published, in 1600 and 1619. None of the other plays has survived. <hi rend="italic">Sir John Oldcastle</hi> was commissioned as a counterblast to the negative depiction of title character in the original versions of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Shakespeare">William Shakespeare</ref>'s plays <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_IV,_Part_1">Henry IV, Part 1</ref></hi> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_IV,_Part_2">Henry IV, Part 2</ref></hi>. Objections from descendants of the historical <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Oldcastle">John Oldcastle</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestant">Protestant</ref> martyr, appears to have been responsible both for the writing of the corrective <hi rend="italic">Oldcastle</hi> play and the alteration of Oldcastle to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Falstaff">Sir John Falstaff</ref> in later versions of the <hi rend="italic">Henry IV</hi> plays.</p>
<p>Also, Wilson has been proposed as a possible author of several anonymous Elizabethan plays, including <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fair_Em">Fair Em</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Pedlar's_Prophecy">The Pedlar's Prophecy</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Larum_for_London">A Larum for London</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Look_About_You">Look About You</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Clyomon_and_Sir_Clamydes">Sir Clyomon and Sir Clamydes</ref></hi>, and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Knack_To_Know_A_Knave">A Knack to Know a Knave</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>As to why a writer would work the way the Henslowe collaborators did: the careers of dramatists who worked mostly on solo projects, like Shakespeare and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ben_Jonson">Ben Jonson</ref>, show that a dramatist working alone could produce one or two plays a year on a dependable basis.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> If one of those plays failed to sell, or flopped with the audience, the writer was severely affected. Collaborative writing spread the risk, and could provide a more certain income for a journeyman author.</p>
<p>A "Robert Wilson, yeoman (player)" was buried at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Giles-without-Cripplegate">St. Giles</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cripplegate">Cripplegate</ref> on 20 November 1600. This is consistent with the view that the two Robert Wilsons, the player with Leicester's Men and Henslowe's dramatist, were one and the same person; it explains why Henslowe's Wilson stopped writing in 1600.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
</text>
