<text id="autogum_bio_doc636" title="Roger Drury (died 1420)" shortTile="roger-drury-died" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-09-14" dateModified="2018-11-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Drury_%28died_1420%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Roger Drury (died 1420)</head>
<p>Sir <hi rend="bold">Roger Drury</hi> (died 1420), of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thurston,_Suffolk">Thurston</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rougham,_Suffolk">Rougham</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suffolk">Suffolk</ref>, was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/England">English</ref> landowner, soldier, administrator and politician.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Woodger-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Origins</head>
<p>Born before 1363, he was the son and heir of Sir Nicholas Drury, of Thurston, and his wife Joan, daughter of Sir Simon Saxham, of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Saxhams">Saxham</ref> in Suffolk.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>The Drury family had settled at Thurston before 1225, being closely associated with the monastery of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bury_St_Edmunds_Abbey">Bury St Edmunds</ref> from which they held land.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Woodger-1">[1]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>Arms used by the Drury family</caption></figure>
<head>Career</head>
<p>On the death of his father in about 1384, he inherited manors in Thurston and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Market_Weston">Market Weston</ref>. His marriage about this time also brought him property in Rougham. He was appointed a tax collector for the county and was knighted.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Woodger-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In June 1386 he was called to military service in Ireland under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_de_Vere,_9th_Earl_of_Oxford">Robert de Vere, 9th Earl of Oxford</ref>, to take 20 men-at-arms and 60 archers. By March 1387 he was serving at sea in the fleet under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_FitzAlan,_11th_Earl_of_Arundel">Richard FitzAlan, 11th Earl of Arundel</ref> and by the end of the year was part of the forces of Arundel and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_of_Woodstock,_1st_Duke_of_Gloucester">Thomas of Woodstock, 1st Duke of Gloucester</ref> which overcame the supporters of Oxford and took control of the government.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Woodger-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In 1391 he first sat as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member_of_Parliament">Member of Parliament</ref> (MP) for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suffolk_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Suffolk</ref>, was appointed a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justice_of_the_peace">justice of the peace</ref> (JP) and was named to various commissions in the county. In 1392 he was again called to military service in Ireland under Gloucester, to take nine men-at-arms and 30 archers. The expedition never sailed, but his links with the opposition to King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_II_of_England"> Richard II</ref> meant that he gained no further appointments and had to buy a royal pardon.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Woodger-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Once King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_IV_of_England">Henry IV</ref> came to the throne, he was able to re-enter public life. In 1401 he was again sent to Parliament for Suffolk, rejoined the bench as a JP and was appointed to various commissions. To both Great Councils of 1401 and 1403 he was summoned as one of the Suffolk knights, and sat a third time as the county's MP in 1407. In Suffolk affairs, among his many associates were the MP Sir Andrew Butler, of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Waldingfield">Waldingfield</ref>, and another MP John Wynter, of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barningham,_Suffolk">Barningham</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Woodger-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>He made his will on 3 October 1420, granting bequests to several churches and friaries and including among his executors his brother Nicholas, his son-in-law William Clopton, and the Ipswich lawyer and MP James Andrew. He was dead by 24 October 1420, when the will was proved at Norwich, and was buried beside his wife in the church of St Mary at Rougham.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Woodger-1">[1]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>Church of St Mary at Rougham</caption></figure>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Around 1384 he married Margaret (died 3 September 1405), daughter and heiress of Sir Thomas Naunton, of Rougham,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Woodger-1">[1]</ref> and his wife Mary, daughter of John Aspall. Her paternal grandmother Eleanor was a daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_de_Vere,_6th_Earl_of_Oxford">Robert de Vere, 6th Earl of Oxford</ref>.</p>
<p>They had five sons and three daughters, including:</p>
Sir William (died about 1450), his son and heir, who in about 1421 married Catherine (died 3 December 1478),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Woodger-1">[1]</ref> daughter of Sir Thomas Swynford and his first wife Jane Crophull, and granddaughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Gaunt">John of Gaunt</ref>'s mistress <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katherine_Swynford">Catherine Roelt</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Woodger-1">[1]</ref>
</text>
