<text id="autogum_bio_doc529" title="Nemequene" shortTile="nemequene" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-04-20" dateModified="2019-03-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nemequene" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Nemequene</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nemequene</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Nemeguene</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> (died 1514) was the third ruler (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zipa">zipa</ref></hi>) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bogotá">Bacatá</ref>, currently known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colombia">Colombian</ref> capital Bogotá, as of 1490. His <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zaque">zaque</ref></hi> counterpart ruling over the northern area of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muisca_people">Muisca</ref> territory was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quemuenchatocha">Quemuenchatocha</ref>.</p>
<head>Etymology</head>
<p>Nemequene in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chibcha_language">Chibcha language</ref> of the Muisca has two possible meanings, derived from the words <hi rend="italic">nymy</hi>, "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaguar">jaguar</ref>"<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> and <hi rend="italic">quyne</hi>, meaning either "bone" or "force".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Nemequene succeeded to the throne of the southern Muisca in 1490 after the death of his predecessor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saguamanchica">Saguamanchica</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Chocontá">Battle of Chocontá</ref> where  the <hi rend="italic">zaque</hi> of the northern Muisca <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michuá">Michuá</ref> had also died. While Nemequene wanted to continue the attacks against the northern Muisca, he had to face the dangers of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panche_people">Panche</ref> to the west of his territory. Nemequene installed his nephew and legal successor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tisquesusa">Tisquesusa</ref> as army general to fight off the Panche with success.</p>
<p>Looking to expand the territory of the southern Muisca, Nemequene succeeded in the conquest of other areas in the central highlands of Colombia; the <hi rend="italic">zipa</hi> defeated the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cacique">cacique</ref></hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guatavita">Guatavita</ref> and submitted the <hi rend="italic">cacicazgos</hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ubaque">Ubaque</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ubaté">Ubaté</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Susa,_Cundinamarca">Susa</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fúquene">Fúquene</ref> to his rule.</p>
<p>At the end of his reign, Nemequene took up arms against the northern Muisca again, with Tisquesusa and his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sagipa">Sagipa</ref> as army commanders. <hi rend="italic">Zaque</hi> Quemuenchatocha gained support of the <hi rend="italic">caciques</hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gámeza">Gámeza</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraca">Iraca</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tundama_Province">Tundama</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sáchica">Sáchica</ref>. The battle of the Arroyo de las Vueltas that followed lasted for half a day and just when Nemequene was about to claim victory, he was hit by an arrow by one of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guecha_warrior">guecha warriors</ref> of the northern Muisca and died five days later of his wounds. Sagipa, the later successor of Tisquesusa and last <hi rend="italic">zipa</hi> of the Muisca ordered retreat. Tisquesusa succeeded his uncle as ruler of the southern Muisca until the arrival of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_colonization_of_the_Americas">Spanish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conquistador">conquistadores</ref> led by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gonzalo_Jiménez_de_Quesada">Gonzalo Jiménez de Quesada</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Code of Nemequene</head>
<figure><caption>Nemequene depicted in 1688</caption></figure>
<p>To impose order, discipline and authority, Nemequene installed a cruel and excessive code. Based on the traditions and customs of the Muisca he ordered that in case of crimes against sexual honour (especially <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Incest">incest</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rape">rape</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sodomy">sodomy</ref>), property or the rule of the state short trials and fierce punishments would be installed. Part of the code was targeted at moral behaviour such as "don't lie" and "don't be lazy".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PueblosNemequene-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>If the defendant was unmarried, he was sentenced to death. In case of being married he would be dishonoured by forcing his wife to publicly live together with two men. Thieves were sentenced to be stabbed with burning sticks. Defaulting indebted Muisca were forbidden to use fire. Who had shown to be a coward in warfare was forced to wear women's clothes and perform the tasks of women. The ordinary Muisca were not allowed to wear expensive clothes or jewelry. It was the Muisca men forbidden to leave their wives and if she died doing labour the spouse was ordered to pay off her family.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PueblosNemequene-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Bishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucas_Fernández_de_Piedrahita">Lucas Fernández de Piedrahita</ref> wrote in the 17th century about the punishment against incest: "<hi rend="italic">When a man committed incest with his mother, daughter, sister or niece, he would be thrown in a narrow pit filled with water where crawling bugs would be thrown in. The pit was covered with a slab and the victim died a horrible death.</hi>"<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PueblosNemequene-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Nemequene in Muisca history</head>
<head>Trivia</head>
See also: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Muisca_toponyms">List of Muisca toponyms</ref>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nemocón">Nemocón</ref>, the second most important <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halite">salt</ref> mining settlement of the Muisca, is named after Nemequene<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></item></list>
</text>
