<text id="autogum_bio_doc573" title="Caleb Afendopolo" shortTile="caleb-afendopolo" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-05-22" dateModified="2019-08-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caleb_Afendopolo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Caleb Afendopolo</head><p><hi rend="bold">Caleb Afendopolo</hi> (born at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrianople">Adrianople</ref> before 1430; lived some time at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belgrade">Belgrade</ref>, and died about 1499 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref>) was a Jewish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyhistor">polyhistor</ref>. He was the brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_ha-Ramati">Samuel ha-Ramati</ref>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ḥakam">ḥakam</ref></hi> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karaite_Judaism">Karaite</ref> congregations in Constantinople and of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judah_Bali">Judah Bali</ref>, brother-in-law and disciple of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elijah_Bashyatzi">Elijah Bashyatzi</ref>.</p>
<p>According to a notice found in a Paris manuscript, he supported himself by giving private instruction; but this is questioned by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steinschneider">Steinschneider</ref>. A pupil of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mordecai_Comtino">Mordecai Comtino</ref> at Adrianople, Afendopolo attained great proficiency in science, and, while lacking depth and originality of thought, distinguished himself by prolific literary production, based on his large library, that included rare manuscripts, partly bought, partly copied by himself. He continued <hi rend="italic">Adderet Eliyahu</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Elijah's Mantle</hi>), a work on Karaite law left unfinished in his charge by his teacher, Bashyatzi, in 1490.</p>
<p>The wife of Bashyatzi, who was Afendopolo's sister, having died before her husband, Afendopolo no longer referred to Bashyatzi as his brother-in-law, but called him teacher. Afendopolo died before completing Bashyatzi's treatise.</p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>Afendopolo's own works give a fair insight into the erudition of the Karaites. Fragments only of many of them have been brought to light by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonah_Hayyim_Gurland">Jonah Hayyim Gurland</ref> in his <hi rend="italic">Ginze Yisrael</hi> (Lyck, 1865), and less exactly by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A._Firkovitch">A. Firkovitch</ref>. His writings are:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>An introductory index to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aaron_ben_Elijah">Aaron ben Elijah</ref>'s <hi rend="italic">Eẓ ha-Ḥayyim</hi> (1497), giving the contents of each chapter under the title, "Derek Eẓ ha-Ḥayyim," published by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delitzsch">Delitzsch</ref> in his edition (1840) of this work.</item>
<item>A similar introductory index to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judah_Hadassi">Judah Hadassi</ref>'s <hi rend="italic">Eshkol,</hi> under the title <hi rend="italic">Naḥal Eshkol</hi> (Koslov, 1836).</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Gan ha-Melek</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Garden of the King</hi>), his principal work, finished in 1495, a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diwan_(poetry)">diwan</ref></hi>, or collection of poetical essays on love, medicine, and the active intellect.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"> 'Asarah Mamarot</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Ten Discourses</hi>), containing homilies on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Passover">Passover</ref> lesson (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Book_of_Exodus">Ex.</ref> xii.14); on the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Song_of_Songs">Song of Songs</ref></hi> as read on the seventh Passover Day; on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psalm">Psalm</ref> cxix, read, according to Karaite custom, on the seven <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shabbat">Sabbaths</ref> between Passover and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentecost">Pentecost</ref>; and on the Pentecost lesson dealing with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sinai_Peninsula">Sinaitic</ref> revelation. The introductory chapter, much of which is reproduced by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mordecai_ben_Nissim">Mordecai ben Nissim</ref> in his <hi rend="italic">Dod Mordecai,</hi> dwells on the origin of the Karaite schism and the main questions at issue between the Karaites and the Rabbinites (see especially Steinschneider, <hi rend="italic">Leyden Catalogue,</hi> pp.127 et seq.). Afendopolo's view of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus">Jesus</ref> given therein is remarkable for its impartial tone. He places Jesus, it is true, a century before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_Era">Common Era</ref>, but adds: "He was, according to the opinion of the lovers of truth, a wise man, pious, righteous, God-fearing, and shunning evil. Neither did he ever teach any law or practice contrary to the written law. Only after his death, a quarrel arose between his followers and those who had opposed him because of his wisdom, which was rooted in the law and not in their rabbinical additions; and many of these disciples of his, sent forth in his name, introduced practices and teachings altogether foreign to him, removing thereby the corner-stone of the Law, though winning the multitudes. Thus the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Testament">New Testament</ref></hi> originated, which separated the Christians from the Jews."</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Abner ben Ner</hi> (1488), a series of Hebrew <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Makama">makamas</ref></hi>, or short, rhymed narratives, introducing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saul">Saul</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David">David</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_of_Sheba">queen of Sheba</ref> into the dialogue.</item>
<item>Under the same title, an allegory on the <hi rend="italic">Song of Songs</hi>, the same being applied to the relation of God to Israel.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Iggeret ha-Sheḥiṭah</hi> (1497), a work on the rites used in slaughtering animals, in the form of letters addressed to his son-in-law, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacob_ben_Judah">Jacob ben Judah</ref>; the same in condensed form written at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kramaria">Kramaria</ref> near Constantinople (1497).</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Seder 'Inyan Sheḥiṭah,</hi> a similar work in rhyme, is extant in manuscript (Firkovitch's MS. No. 569).</item>
<item>On the use of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arak_(drink)">arrack</ref></hi> (in which the passage <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deuteronomy">Deut.</ref> xxxii.38 is applied to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moslems">Moslems</ref>, and the Christian sacrifice is alluded to; see Steinschneider, <hi rend="italic">Leyden Catalogue,</hi> p.233; <hi rend="italic">Polemische Literatur,</hi> p.374).</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Iggeret ha-Kimah</hi> (Letter on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pleiades">Pleiades</ref>), treating of forbidden marriages, and directed against Joshua's work on the subject.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Patshegen Ketab ha-Dat</hi> (1496), on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentateuch">Pentateuch</ref> lessons and the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hafṭarot">Hafṭarot</ref></hi> and other Bible selections.</item>
<item>A rejoinder to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maimonides">Maimonides</ref> in defense of the Karaite calculation of the seven weeks (Steinschneider, <hi rend="italic">Hebr. Bibl.</hi> vii.11).</item>
<item>A defense of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aaron_ben_Elijah">Aaron ben Elijah</ref>'s <hi rend="italic">Gan Eden</hi> against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moses_ben_Jacob_ha-Ashkenazi">Moses ben Jacob ha-Ashkenazi</ref> (Steinschneider, <hi rend="italic">Hebr. Bibl.</hi> xx.122).</item>
<item>A commentary on the Hebrew translation of the arithmetic of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicomachus_of_Gerasa">Nicomachus of Gerasa</ref> (first or second century), made from the Arabic by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalonymus_ben_Kalonymus">Kalonymus ben Kalonymus</ref> in 1317. The manuscript is in the Berlin Royal Library (Steinschneider, in <hi rend="italic">Monatsschrift,</hi> xxxviii.76). Afendopolo has attached to this commentary a sort of general encyclopedia of the sciences. He commences with an analysis of the eight books of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aristotle">Aristotle</ref>'s <hi rend="italic">Logic.</hi> Practical science, as he calls it, deals with man himself, with the house (family), and the state. Speculative science comprises physics, geometry, and metaphysics. In the same manner he runs through the other sciences, giving their various subdivisions. The highest science is theology, which treats of the soul, of prophecy, and of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eschatology">eschatology</ref>. The course of instruction which Afendopolo lays down follows that of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plato">Plato</ref>; namely, logic, arithmetic, geometry, astronomy, music, the science of aspects, metrology, physics, and metaphysics. After discussing future bliss, he deals with two other sciences—law, especially as regards the relation of faith to works, and controversy (<hi rend="italic">Ḥokmat ha-Debarim</hi>). In the latter he cites freely from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Batalyusi">Batalyusi</ref>, without, however, giving his authority (Steinschneider, in <hi rend="italic">Monatsschrift,</hi> xl.90 et seq.).</item>
<item>An astronomical treatise, largely made up of a commentary on the portion of Elijah's <hi rend="italic">Gan Eden</hi> (Neubauer, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue,</hi> No. 2054), under the title <hi rend="italic">Miklal Yofi.</hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Iggeret ha-Maspeḳet,</hi> a work on astronomical terminology, and on the construction of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sundial">sundials</ref>, improving upon the method of his teacher, Comtino, by adding the odd hours (Gurland, <hi rend="italic">Ginze Yisrael,</hi> iii.18, 19).</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Tiḳḳun Keli Rob ha-Sha'ot</hi> (1487), which was known also to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_del_Medigo">Joseph del Medigo</ref>.</item></list>
<p>Afendopolo also wrote some penitential hymns which are to be found in the Karaite <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maḥzor">Maḥzor</ref></hi> (Neubauer, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue,</hi> No. 2369, 3; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zunz">Zunz</ref>, <hi rend="italic">G. V.,</hi> p.425; idem, 2nd ed., p.440); but most of these hymns were taken from Rabbinite poets (see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Kahana">David Kahana</ref> in <hi rend="italic">Oẓar ha-Sifrut,</hi> vol. v, Cracow, 1896). Afendopolo had intended to translate the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elements_of_Euclid">Elements of Euclid</ref></hi>, and to write commentaries on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jabir_ibn_Aflaḥ">Jabir ibn Aflaḥ</ref>'s <hi rend="italic">Kitab al-Ḥiyyah</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Compendium on Astronomy</hi>) and on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ptolemy">Ptolemy</ref>'s <hi rend="italic">Almagest.</hi></p>
</text>
