<text id="autogum_bio_doc207" title="Moheschunder Bannerjee" shortTile="moheschunder-bannerjee" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-07-31" dateModified="2018-05-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moheschunder_Bannerjee" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Moheschunder Bannerjee</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Moheschunder Bannerjee</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bengali_language">Bengali</ref>: মহেশচন্দ্র বন্দ্যোপাধ্যায়, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floruit">fl.</ref> 1850) or <hi rend="bold">Mahesh Chandra Banerjee</hi> was a strong <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess">chess</ref> player from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bengal">Bengal</ref>, many hundred of whose games survive through the writings of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Cochrane_(chess_player)">John Cochrane</ref>, who regularly played Bannerjee between 1848 and 1860, during Cochrane's tenure at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calcutta">Calcutta</ref> bar.  His first name is sometimes misspelled <hi rend="bold">Mohishunder</hi>, though <hi rend="bold">Mahescandra</hi> is a variant. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banerjee">Banerjee</ref> is a common Bengali <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brahmin">Brahmin</ref> surname.</p>
<p>Moheshchunder, also known as "the Brahmin", was a player from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mofussil">mofussil</ref> or suburbs of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calcutta">Calcutta</ref>.  He played traditional <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_chess">Indian chess</ref>, which in Bengal at the time, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pawn_(chess)">pawns</ref> did not have the option of moving two squares from the starting row and pawns would <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Promotion_(chess)">promote</ref> to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_piece">piece</ref> of the square reached.  Also Bengal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_rules">chess rules</ref> did not have <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castling">castling</ref>, but an unchecked king could execute a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knight_(chess)">knight's</ref> move once during a game.  However, there is little difference in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middlegame">middlegame</ref> and many Indian chess players were very strong <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_tactics">tacticians</ref>.  Bannerjee is likely to have transitioned to western rules after contact with Cochrane and other Europeans.</p>
<p>Among his contributions to mainstream chess is the class of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_opening">openings</ref> now called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_Defence">Indian Defence</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sergeant-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>What little is known of Moheschunder comes from articles that John Cochrane, stationed at Calcutta in the 1840s, wrote for the London chess magazines.  It appears that Cochrane, who had defeated every player in England barring his protégé <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Howard_Staunton">Howard Staunton</ref>, had been searching for some worthy opponents for some time.  In the autumn of 1848, a member of the Calcutta Chess club heard of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brahmin">Brahmin</ref> in a village (mofussil) who had never been beaten at chess. He found an opportunity of meeting him, played him, and lost. It was stated that the man, 'Moheschunder Bonnerjee, a Brahmin', of about 50, hardly knew the European rules of chess; yet his play was presumably under European rules.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sergeant-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>This club member brought Bannerjee back to Calcutta with him.  Cochrane played him and won, but was impressed.  Banerjee was engaged as "a paid attaché" of the Chess Club, where he improved wonderfully.  In the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_Player's_Chronicle">Chess Player's Chronicle</ref> for 1851 are published some games between Cochrane and Moheschunder; and "the Brahmin" figures as a player in various collections of games.  The Indian Defences by P-KKt3 coupled with P-Q3, or P-QKt3 coupled with P-K3, were largely taught to European players by the example of Moheschunder and other Indians, to whom the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fianchetto">fianchetto</ref> developments were a natural legacy from their own game.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sergeant-1">[1]</ref>
It is notable that many of Bannerjee's openings were based on single pawn moves, the "legacy" mentioned by Sergeant, as in the rules of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_chess">Indian chess</ref>.</p>
<p>Cochrane is quoted in a letter written by a member of the Calcutta Chess Club, appearing in the <hi rend="italic">Chess Player's Chronicle</hi> in 1850: </p>
The only player here who has any chance whatever with Mr Cochrane, upon even terms, is a Brahmin of the name of Moheschunder Bonnerjee. Of this worthy, Mr Cochrane has himself remarked that he possesses as great a natural talent for chess as any player he ever met with, without one single exception.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref>
<head>Games</head>
<p>Among his recorded games is the first instance of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gruenfeld_Defence">Gruenfeld Defence</ref>, more than 60 years before <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernst_Grünfeld">Ernst Grünfeld</ref> was to launch it against Alekhine at Vienna, 1922:</p>
<p>John Cochrane–Moheschunder Bannerjee, May 1855 <hi rend="bold">1.d4 Nf6 2.c4 g6 3.Nc3 d5 4.e3 Bg7 5.Nf3 0-0 6.cxd5 Nxd5 7.Be2 Nxc3 8.bxc3 c5 9.0-0 cxd4 10.cxd4 Nc6 11.Bb2 Bg4 12.Rc1 Rc8 13.Ba3 Qa5 14.Qb3 Rfe8 15.Rc5 Qb6 16.Rb5 Qd8 17.Ng5 Bxe2 18.Nxf7 Na5</hi> and White <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Checkmate">mates</ref> in three (19.Nh6+ <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double_check">double check</ref> Kh8 20.Qg8+ Rxg8 21.Nf7<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Checkmate">#</ref>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Moheshchunder had a flair for dramatic play evidenced by his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sacrifice_(chess)">sacrifices</ref> in this
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King's_Indian_Defence">King's Indian Defence</ref> game (a variation known today as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King's_Indian_Defence,_Four_Pawns_Attack">Four Pawns Attack</ref>):</p>
<p>John Cochrane–Moheschunder Bannerjee <hi rend="bold">1.e4 d6 2.d4 g6 3.c4 Bg7 4.Nc3 Nf6 5.f4 0-0 6.Nf3 Bg4 7.Bd3? e5! 8.fxe5 dxe5 9.d5 Nxe4!? 10.Nxe4 f5 11.Neg5 e4 12.Ne6 exf3! 13.Nxd8?! fxg2 14.Rg1 Bxd1 15.Ne6 Bg4 16.Nxf8 Kxf8 17.Rxg2 Nd7 18.Bf4 Nc5 19.Kd2 Rc8 20.Kc2 Bf3 21.Rf2 Nxd3 22.Kxd3 Be4+ 23.Ke3 b5 24.cxb5 Bxd5 25.Rd2 Bc4 26.Rad1 Bf6 27.Bh6+ Kg8 28.Kf4 Re8 29.b3 Bxb5 30.Rc1 Be2! 31.Re1 Re4+ 32.Kg3 Bh4+ 0–1</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>The origin of the name "Indian Defence"</head>
<p>Moheshchunder, like other Indian players of the time, favoured <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fianchetto">fianchettoed</ref> openings, trying to control the centre with long-distance pieces rather than occupying it with the pawns.  Possibly these ideas germinated in an environment of chess rules that did not permit the initial two-square move for pawns.  The theory behind these openings were developed in recorded chess history much later, but
Cochrane introduced the term <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_defence">Indian defence</ref> for this class of openings, which has now come to cover the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nimzo-Indian">Nimzo-Indian</ref> and many other popular openings.  Fianchettoes appear to have been a favourite style in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_chess">Indian chess</ref> variants, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen's_Indian_defence">Queen's Indian defence</ref> was also a frequent opening for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mir_Sultan_Khan">Mir Sultan Khan</ref>, who visited England for five years and won the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British_Chess_Championship">British Chess Championship</ref> in 1929, 1932 and 1933.</p>
</text>
