<text id="autogum_bio_doc683" title="Abd al-Qadir Maraghi" shortTile="abd-alqadir-maraghi" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-06" dateModified="2019-10-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abd_al-Qadir_Maraghi" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Abd al-Qadir Maraghi</head><p><hi rend="bold">Abd al-Qadir al-Maraghi b. Ghaybi</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_language">Persian</ref>: عبدالقادر مراغی‎, born middle of 14th – died 1435 AD), was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_people">Persian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musician">musician</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artist">artist</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Donzel1994-2">[2]</ref> According to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Encyclopedia_of_Islam">Encyclopedia of Islam</ref>, he was <hi rend="italic">the greatest of the Persian writers on music</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-encyclopediaofislam-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Abd al- Qadir b. GHaybi al-Hafiz al-Maraghi was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maragheh">Maragheh</ref> in about the middle of the 14th century.  He had become one of the court minstrels of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jalayirid">Jalayirid</ref> Sultan al-Husayn around 1379.  Under Sultan Ahmad <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jalayirid">Jalayirid</ref>, he was appointed the chief court minstrel.  When <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timur">Timur</ref> captured <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baghdad">Baghdad</ref> in 1393, he was transported to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samarqand">Samarqand</ref>, which was the capital of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timurid_dynasty">Timurid</ref> dynasty.  In 1399, he was in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tabriz">Tabriz</ref> at the service of Timur’s wayward son Miranshah.  Abdl al-Qadir was blamed for the erratic conducts of Miranshah, and Timur acted swiftly in order to capture him.  But Abd al-Qadir, was forewarned and escaped to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jalayrid">Jalayrid</ref> court of Sultan Ahmad in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baghdad">Baghdad</ref>.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timur">Timur</ref> again recaptured <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baghdad">Baghdad</ref> in 1401 and took Abd al-Qadir back to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samarqand">Samarqand</ref>.  Abd al-Qadir became one of the brilliant men at the court of Timur’s son, Shahrukh .  In 1421, he also wrote a musical treatise (see below) for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> Sultan Murad II.  He died in Samarqand in 1435.</p>
<head>Works on music theory</head>
<p>Abd al-Qadir was proficient in music, poetry and painting.  This made him to be a highly desired artisan amongst the courts of different dynasties.  It was due to his musical talent that he was named by his contemporaries as the <hi rend="italic">Glory of the past age</hi>.
.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-encyclopediaofislam-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Abd al-Qadir is known for his four works on music theory.  All three surviving works were written in Persian.  His most important treatise on music is the Jami al-Alhan (جامع الالحان) (Arabic for Encyclopedia of Music), autographs of which are preserved at the Bodleian Library and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuruosmaniye_Mosque">Nuruosmaniye Mosque</ref> Library in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Istanbul">Istanbul</ref>. The first manuscript of this work was written in 1405 for his Nur al-din Abd al-Rahman was revised by the author in 1413. The second manuscript was written in 1415, carries a dedication to Sultan Sharukh of the Timurid dynasty.</p>
<p>The second major work of Abd al-Qadir is the Persian book Maqasid al-Alhan (Arabic for: Purports of Music)(مقاصد الالحان). It was dedicated to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> Sultan Murad II.</p>
<p>A third treatise on music, the Kanz al-Tu.af (Treasury of Music) which contained the author's notated compositions, has not survived.</p>
<p>His last work, the Sharh al-Adwar (Commentary on the [Kitab al-Adwar] of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safi_al-Din_al-Urmawi">Safi al-Din al-Urmawi</ref>) (شرح الادوار), is to be found in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuruosmaniye_Mosque">Nuruosmaniye Mosque</ref> Library in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Istanbul">Istanbul</ref>.</p>
<head>Linguistic significance</head>
<p>Hamdollah Mustawafi of the 13th century AD mentions the language of Maragheh as "Pahlavi Mughayr" (modified Pahlavi):<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>The 17th century AD <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> Turkish traveler Evliya Chelebi who traveled to Safavid Iran also states:</p>
<p>“The majority of the women in Maragheh converse in Pahlavi”.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>According to the Encyclopedia of Islam:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref>"At the present day, the inhabitants speak Adhar Turkish, but in the 14th century they still spoke “arabicized Pahlawi” (Nuzhat al-Qolub: Pahlawi Mu’arrab) which means an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iranian_languages">Iranian</ref> dialect of the north western group."</p>
<p>Abd al-Qadir Maraghi not only recorded songs in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_Language">Persian Language</ref>, but also in Arabic, Mongolian, Turkish (Khatai, Chagatay) as well as various regional Iranian dialects (Fahlaviyyat) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamadan">Hamadan</ref>, Mazandaran, Qazvin, Tabriz, and Rayy.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-A.A.Sadeqi-7">[7]</ref>  Thus his work gives us a better view of the regional <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Languages_of_Iran">dialects</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref>.</p>
<p>Four quatrains titled fahlaviyyat from Khwaja Muhammad Kojjani (d. 677/1278-79); born in Kojjan or Korjan, a village near Tabriz, recorded by Abd-al-Qader Maraghi.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-A.A.Sadeqi-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Taffazoli-8">[8]</ref>
A sample of one of the four quatrains from Khwaja Muhammad Kojjani</p>
<p>.</p>
<p>Two qet'as (poems) quoted by Abd-al-Qader Maraghi in the dialect of Tabrz (d. 838/1434-35; II, p.142).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-A.A.Sadeqi-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Taffazoli-8">[8]</ref>
A sample of one these poems</p>
<head>Current Performances</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://web.archive.org/web/20101007104624/http://www.sepidehraissadat.com/anwar/">Anwar, on the footsteps of Maraghi  (Ensemble Maraghi and Sepideh Raissadat)</ref></item></list>
</text>
