<text id="autogum_bio_doc176" title="Evangelos Koukoudeas" shortTile="evangelos-koukoudeas" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-07-13" dateModified="2019-10-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evangelos_Koukoudeas" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Evangelos Koukoudeas</head><figure><caption>Evangelos Koukoudeas in the early 20th century.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Evangelos Koukoudeas</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_language">Greek</ref>: Ευάγγελος Κουκουδέας) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greeks">Greek</ref> chieftain of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macedonian_Struggle">Macedonian Struggle</ref> and hero of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balkan_Wars">Balkan Wars</ref>.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Koukoudeas was bornt in Üstrümce, then part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman Empire</ref> (now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strumica">Strumica</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Macedonia">North Macedonia</ref>) at the end of the 19th century. He came from an old and important family of Strumica. Famous relatives of him were the violinist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dimitrios_Semsis">Dimitrios Koukoudeas or Semsis</ref> and the teacher of Strumica's Girls' School, Aikaterini Koukoudea. After graduating from the Greek school in his hometown, he travelled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Athens">Athens</ref> in 1905 to escape the Bulgarian attacks and to be enrolled in the armed groups being gathered for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macedonian_Struggle">Macedonian Struggle</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> He was also enlisted in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hellenic_Navy">Hellenic Navy</ref> as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leading_seaman">leading seaman</ref>.</p>
<head>Macedonian Struggle</head>
<p>After his military service, he went to Macedonia and fought in the region of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giannitsa_Lake">Giannitsa Lake</ref> under the general command of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ioannis_Demestichas">Ioannis Demestichas</ref>.</p>
<p>On February 14, 1907, the united Greek bodies under Demestichas, Evangelos Koukoudeas, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikolaos_Zafeiriou">Nikolaos Zafeiriou</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chalkidiki">Chalkidiki</ref> and several other Macedonian and Cretan soldiers active in the Lake started from Tsekri (modern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paralimni">Paralimni</ref>) and attacked the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Komitadji">komitadji</ref> K. Delithanasis, in Bozej (modern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Athyra">Athyra</ref>). The attack was successful, killing the komitadji and several of his men barricaded in the former's home. Eventually they left as an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> military detachment appeared in the village.</p>
<p>In March 1907, he was the leader of a small group involved in operations against komitadjis in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Koufalia">Koufalia</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> He fought in the area of the Lake until the end of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macedonian_Struggle">Macedonian Struggle</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>The chieftain Evangelos Koukoudeas</caption></figure>
<p>Ioannis Demestichas wrote about Koukoudeas (translation from Greek):<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-aipos.wikispaces.com-3">[3]</ref></p>
<hi rend="italic">...His long hair, and his modesty remind the hero of the Revolution <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Athanasios_Diakos">Athanasios Diakos</ref>. He overflows from patriotic enthusiasm, controlled enthusiasm , without exaggerations.</hi>
<hi rend="italic">...I had full confidence on him and I was sure he would do his job under the most difficult circumstances. He would rather die fighting than abandon me in case of danger..</hi>
<head>Balkan Wars</head>
<p>Before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balkan_Wars">Balkan Wars</ref>, during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italo-Turkish_War">Italo-Turkish War</ref> (1911-1912) while the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italians">Italians</ref> had occupied the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dodecanese">Dodecanese</ref>, he went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Icaria">Icaria</ref> and helped Ioannis Malachias in the revolution against the Ottomans in July 1912, that set up the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_State_of_Icaria">Free State of Icaria</ref> to prevent the island from being occupied by the Italians</p>
<p>He then created a group of Icarian volunteers for participation in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_Balkan_War">First Balkan War</ref> and disembarked in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chios">Chios</ref> on 14 December 1912, where he took part in the Battle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Volissos">Volissos</ref> and the Battle of Aipos during the Greek occupation of the island.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-aipos.wikispaces.com-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Northern Epirus, First World War and Greco-Turkish War</head>
<p>After the end of the Balkan Wars he fought for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autonomous_Republic_of_Northern_Epirus">Autonomous Republic of Northern Epirus</ref>. He then moved to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_of_America">United States of America</ref>, where after the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Defence_coup_d'état">National Defence coup d'état</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</ref> and Greece's entry into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_War_I">World War I</ref>, he organized a militia to facilitate the transfer of volunteers to Greece. During the World War he fought as a reserve infantry officer, and was eventually commissioned into the Greek Army as a second lieutenant.</p>
<p>He participated in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greco-Turkish_War_(1919–1922)">Greco-Turkish War (1919–1922)</ref>, where he was captured by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkish_National_Movement">Turks</ref>. After his liberation and the end of the war, he continued his career with the Greek Army, reaching the rank of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colonel">colonel</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-aipos.wikispaces.com-3">[3]</ref></p>
</text>
