<text id="autogum_bio_doc020" title="Tasuku Harada (obstetrician)" shortTile="tasuku-harada-obstetrician" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-05-06" dateModified="2019-05-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tasuku_Harada_%28obstetrician%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tasuku Harada (obstetrician)</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tasuku Harada</hi> (原田 省) is a Japanese professor and Chair at the Department of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obstetrics">Obstetrics</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gynaecology">Gynaecology</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tottori_University">Tottori University</ref> Faculty of Medicine, Japan.</p>
<head>Education</head>
<p>Harada obtained his MD degree (cum laude) in 1983 and the same year became a resident in Obstetrics and Gynecology at the Tottori Prefectural Central Hospital. From 1984 to 1985 he served as a medical staff in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tottori_University">Tottori University</ref> and then became a Research Fellow in obstetrics and gynecology at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Leeds">University of Leeds</ref>. From 1986 to 1992 he served as an assistant professor at the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology of Tottori University, prior to which he obtained his Ph.D. in 1991 at the same place.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-seud-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>From 1992 to 1993 he was a Research Fellow in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internal_medicine">internal medicine</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Osaka_University">Osaka University</ref> and from 1994 to 2007 served as a lecturer at the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology of TU. From 2007 to 2008 he was an associate professor at the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology of Tottori University and then served as its professor and chairman until 2008. From 2011 to 2012 Harada had served as a supervisor to a hospital director and then became Head of the Center for Minimally Invasive Surgery. Since 2012 he is a Vice Director of Tottori University Hospital and since 2017 he serves as Vice President of Tottori University and as Director of its hospital.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-seud-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Besides his posts at his alma mater, Harada also is a vice president of the Japan Society of Gynaecologic and Obstetric Endoscopy, managing director of the Japan Society of Reproductive Medicine, and a director of both Japan Society of Obstetrics and Gynecology and Japan Society of Endometriosis. He also served as President of the Asian Society of Endometriosis and Adenomyosis from 2015 to 2016 and since May 2017 serves on World Endometriosis Society<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> and Society of Endometriosis and Uterine Disorders boards.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-seud-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Research</head>
<p>In 2007, Harada had helped colleagues to develop an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oral_contraceptive_pill">oral contraceptive pill</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dysmenorrhea">dysmenorrhea</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>
In 2011, Harada along with Tomio Iwabe and Naoki Terakawa had reviewed the literature on the role of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cytokine">cytokines</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pathogenesis">pathogenesis</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Endometriosis">endometriosis</ref> and associated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infertility">infertility</ref> via <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MEDLINE">MEDLINE</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> In 2013, Tasuku had studied dysmenorrhea and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Endometriosis">endometriosis</ref> in young women and defined how endometriosis causes dysmenorrhea.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>In 2016, he along with Yin Mon Khine and Fuminori Taniguchi had suggested that physicians should be aware of the severity of clinical symptoms that endometriosis might cause. According to them, a physician should take into consideration the age of the patient, the duration of infertility and the stage in which the disease is in, in order to suggest proper treatment. Before considering anything, a clinician should study the patients' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ovarian_reserve">ovarian reserve</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tubal_patency">tubal patency</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sperm">sperm</ref> functionality, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uterine_cavity">uterine cavity</ref>. They also suggested that a surgery for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Endometrioma">endometrioma</ref> should be viewed with caution too.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>In 2017, Takusu had helped his colleagues to develop a new drug treatment for the patients with endometriosis-associated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pelvic_pain">pelvic pain</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>2014 — <hi rend="italic">Endometriosis: Pathogenesis and Treatment</hi> (Springer)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></item></list>
</text>
