<text id="autogum_bio_doc786" title="Florent de Varennes" shortTile="florent-de-varennes" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-07" dateModified="2018-08-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florent_de_Varennes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Florent de Varennes</head><figure><caption>Louis IX of France towards the Eighth Crusade</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Florent de Varennes</hi> (died in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tunis">Tunis</ref> in August 1270) was the first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Admiral_of_France">Admiral of France</ref>, in 1269, and as such, became the head of the fleet during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eighth_Crusade">Eighth Crusade</ref> and the last led by King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_IX_of_France">Saint Louis IX</ref>.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>He was lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Varennes,_Somme">Varennes</ref>, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Picardy">Picardy</ref>.</p>
<p>He was married to Yolande de Nesle, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_II,_Count_of_Soissons">John II de Nesle, Count of Soissons</ref> and Marie de <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chimay">Chimay</ref>. They had a son named Mathieu.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Eighth Crusade</head>
<figure><caption>Florent, lord of Varennes, on the 2nd boat, with his shield "Gules a Cross Or", heading to the Crusade</caption></figure>
<p>In July 1270, King Louis IX set sail from Aigues-Mortes with a large, well-organized fleet of 70 vessels, mostly Genoese and Venetian, stating: "Already old, I begin the overseas journey. I sacrifice to God wealth, honor, pleasure ... I wanted to give you this last example and I hope you will follow it if circumstances dictate ..."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NET-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>The first part of the journey was hectic. They stopped in Sardinia. The King sent Florent de Varennes as a scout towards the Sards. But, since their boats were Genoan, they were unwelcome. Food was delivered at high cost.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>On July 17, the army arrived at the Tunisian coast. According to the royal secretary, Jean de Condé, the King sends Florent de Varennes with a few men to reconnoitre the land. He found an empty harbour, with only a few Muslim and Genoan merchant ships present. He sent a messenger to the King. The royal council was divided on which strategy to adopt: some thought it was a trap, while others wanted to take advantage of the situation and disembark. Florent de Varennes, without referring to the King, disembarks his troops on the platform closing Tunis harbour. Although he was furious, the King joined with the rest of the crew. The operation is a capharnaum, but hopefully, no enemy showed up.</p>
<p>On July 21, the tower of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La_Goulette">La Goulette</ref> was seized, and the army settled in the plain of Carthage. The Castle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carthage">Carthage</ref> was captured by Genoan sailors.</p>
<p>Waiting for the reinforcements of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_I_of_Naples">Charles of Anjou</ref>, King of Sicily, to attack <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tunis">Tunis</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dysentery">dysentery</ref> epidemic decimated the troops, the polluted water and excessive heat not helping. Florent de Varennes and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Tristan,_Count_of_Valois">John Tristan, Count of Valois</ref>, son of Louis IX, were among the victims.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Louis IX himself expired on August 25, by the time of the arrival of Charles of Anjou. The latter defeated the Saracens and signed a treaty with the Sultan on 30 October 1270. Philip, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Count_of_Orléans">Count of Orléans</ref>, Louis' elder son, who became King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_III_of_France">Philip III of France</ref>, sailed home on November 11.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NET-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Heraldry</head>
<p>Florent's coat of arms was "<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gules">Gules</ref> a Cross <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Or_(heraldry)">Or</ref></hi>" (Red with a golden cross) and is still the coat of arms of the village of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Varennes,_Somme">Varennes</ref>, Departement of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Somme_(department)">Somme</ref>, Region <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Picardy">Picardy</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
</text>
