<text id="autogum_bio_doc754" title="Deval Devi" shortTile="deval-devi" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-04-14" dateModified="2019-10-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deval_Devi" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Deval Devi</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Deval Devi</hi> (variantly known as <hi rend="bold">Dewal Devi</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Dewal Rani</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Deval Rani</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Dewal Di</hi>) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaghela_dynasty">Vaghela Rajput</ref> princess and daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karna_(Vaghela_dynasty)">Karan Deva II</ref> (the last sovereign of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaghela_dynasty">Vaghela dynasty</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gujarat">Gujarat</ref>). She was married to Khizr Khan, the eldest son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alauddin_Khalji">Alauddin Khalji</ref>, in 1308. Eight years later, Khizr Khan was executed by his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qutb_ud_din_Mubarak_Shah">Qutb ud din Mubarak Shah</ref> (1316–20), and Deval was taken into the latter's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harem">harem</ref>.</hi> In 1320, Mubarak in turn was stabbed and beheaded by his supposed favourite, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khusro_Khan">Khusro Khan</ref> (the last ruler of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khalji_dynasty">Khalji dynasty</ref>), and his followers. Deval was then married to Khusro Khan. Her story, of a cultured and high-born Hindu Rajput princess being passed from hand to hand amongst a series of ambitious, power-hungry men is the basis of the celebrated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gujarati_language">Gujarati</ref> historical novel <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karan_Ghelo">Karan Ghelo</ref></hi> authored by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nandshankar_Mehta">Nandshankar Mehta</ref>.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>In 1298, the then <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delhi_Sultanate">Sultan of Delhi</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alauddin_Khalji">Alauddin Khalji</ref>, sent an expedition into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gujarat">Gujarat</ref> under the command of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulugh_Khan">Ulugh Khan</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nusrat_Khan_Jalesari">Nusrat Khan</ref>. Karan Deva II of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaghela_dynasty">Vaghela dynasty</ref>, the main ruler of Gujarat, was defeated. His queen, Kamla Devi, fell into the hands of the invaders and was sent as booty to Alauddin Khalji. Karna Deva himself, along with his very young daughter Deval Devi and other surviving followers, fled to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deccan">Deccan</ref> and took refuge in the court of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramachandra_of_Devagiri">Rama Chandra Deva</ref>, ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deogiri">Deogiri</ref> (later known as Daulatabad).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jayapalan2001-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMajumdar1956190-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Meanwhile, in Delhi, Karan Deva's wife Kamla Devi was married to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alauddin_Khalji">Alauddin Khalji</ref> as his third wife.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMahajan2015136-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Niazi1992-4">[4]</ref> She soon became the favourite queen of Alauddin<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMahajan2015136-3">[3]</ref> and often told the sultan of how much she missed her little daughter. Therefore, when in 1308, ten years after mother and daughter had been separated, the Khalji sultan happened to send an expedition to the Deccan, he instructed his general, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malik_Kafur">Malik Kafur</ref>, to bring Deval Devi back with him whether by hook or by crook. By this time, Deval Devi had come of age. The historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Firishta">Firishta</ref> tells us that Rama Chandra Deva, who had granted refuge to Deval's father and his party, had suggested that she be married to his son and heir, Shankara Deva. While in material terms this would be a great match for the refugee princess, her father was not inclined to accept, for reasons related to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caste">Caste</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMajumdar1956191-5">[5]</ref> He initially refused to take the hint, then made polite excuses and demurred; the hosts realized that he was not interested in a matrimonial alliance and dropped the matter. At this point, Deogiri was faced with the invading army from Delhi. and the special interest of the invaders in Deval Devi became known. A deeply agitated Karna Deva now pressed his hosts to accept his daughter as bride for Prince Shankara Deva. They agreed to this, and advised Karna Deva to immediately send his daughter under escort into the fort of Devagiri (the refugee king had been granted an estate comprising a few nearby villages and was living there). Karna Deva immediately did as he was advised; bedecked as a bride, Deval Devi was seated in a palanquin and sent under armed escort towards the citadel to marry the crown prince. However, before reaching the fort, the party was waylaid by a contingent of Sultanate soldiers and Deval Devi was captured. Nizam ud-Din and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/`Abd_al-Qadir_Bada'uni">`Abd al-Qadir Bada'uni</ref> opine that the party was led by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulugh_Khan">Ulugh Khan</ref> personally.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMajumdar1956190-2">[2]</ref> She was sent to Delhi, where she was reunited with the mother whom she had not seen since childhood. Shortly afterwards, at the insistence of Kamla Devi, she was married to Alauddin's eldest son Khizr Khan (her mother's step-son).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Chandra2004-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>Following Ala-ud-Din's death in 1316, his third son ascended the throne as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qutb_ud_din_Mubarak_Shah">Qutb ud din Mubarak Shah</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMahajan2015153-7">[7]</ref> During Mubarak Shah's reign, a conspiracy was made to murder him and put one of the sons of Khizr Khan on the throne. When Mubarak Shah came to know about the plan, he put everyone involved in the conspiracy, including his brother Khizr Khan, to death. Historian Haji-ud-Dabir writes that Mubarak Shah then married Deval forcibly, thus becoming her second husband.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMahajan2015154-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Mahajan1965-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>Mubarak Shah was bisexual, and he was murdered by the associates of his favorite catamite, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khusro_Khan">Khusro Khan</ref>, on the night of 14 April 1320.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Houtsma1993-10">[10]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ziauddin_Barani">Ziauddin Barani</ref>, the contemporary historian, writes that Khusro Khan then married Deval Devi, thus becoming her third husband.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMahajan2015154-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Chaurasia2002-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>The <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karan_Ghelo">Karan Ghelo</ref></hi> tells us that this marriage, her third, was acceptable to Deval Devi, ( though there is not much information available about her first marriage) mainly because <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khusro_Khan">Khusro Khan</ref> came from a background similar to her own. Born into a Rajput family, he had been captured as a young boy during a battle, brought up by Malik Shadi, the naib-i khas-i hajib (deputy royal chamberlain) to Alauddin Khalji in Delhi as muslim, where later his good looks had earned him the favour of Mubarak Shah, all of which is collaborated by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ziauddin_Barani">Barani</ref>. However, after a reign of only five months, Khusro Khan was defeated by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghiyath_al-Din_Tughluq">Ghiyath al-Din Tughluq</ref> and was put to death. This happened in September 1320. Historical sources are silent about Deval Devi's fate thereafter, but the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karan_Ghelo">Karan Ghelo</ref></hi> tells us that she took recourse to poison and joined Khusro Khan in death. However, Karan Ghelo is not an historical text.</p>
<head>In literature</head>
<p>Deval Devi is an important character in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gujarati_language">Gujarati</ref> historical novel <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karan_Ghelo">Karan Ghelo</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nandshankar_Mehta">Nandshankar Mehta</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Scroll-12">[12]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amir_Khusraw">Amir Khusraw</ref> wrote his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masnavi_(poetic_form)">masnavi</ref> <hi rend="italic">Deval Devi—Khizr Khan</hi>, a famous work on the romance between Khizr Khan and Deval Devi and popularly called <hi rend="italic">Ishqiya</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ishqia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ashiqa</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-TH-13">[13]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Scroll-12">[12]</ref> She is the central character in Sudheer Maurya's Hindi book <hi rend="italic">Deval Devi: Ek Aetihasik Upanyaas</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref></p>
</text>
