<text id="autogum_bio_doc270" title="Johann Schobert" shortTile="johann-schobert" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2003-09-20" dateModified="2019-07-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Schobert" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Johann Schobert</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Johann Schobert</hi> (c. 1720, 1735 or 1740 – 28 August 1767) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Composer">composer</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harpsichordist">harpsichordist</ref>. His date of birth is given variously as about 1720, about 1735, or about 1740, his place of birth as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silesia">Silesia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alsace">Alsace</ref>, or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg">Nuremberg</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> He died after eating poisonous mushrooms that he insisted were edible.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>In 1760 or 1761, Schobert moved to Paris where he served in the household of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_François_I_de_Bourbon,_prince_de_Conti">Louis François I de Bourbon, prince de Conti</ref>. He composed many books of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonata_(music)">sonatas</ref> for his instrument, most of them with an accompanying part for one or more other instruments. Schobert also wrote harpsichord <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concerto">concertos</ref>, symphonies and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opéra_comique">opéra comique</ref> <hi rend="italic">Le Garde-Chasse et le Braconnier</hi>.</p>
<p>In Paris, Schobert came into contact with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leopold_Mozart">Leopold Mozart</ref> during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozart_family_grand_tour">family's grand tour</ref>. Reportedly, Schobert was offended by Mozart's comments that his children played Schobert's works with ease. Nevertheless, Schobert was a significant influence on the young <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolfgang_Amadeus_Mozart">Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart</ref>, who arranged a number of movements from Schobert's sonatas for use in his own piano concertos.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Mozart biographer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dyneley_Hussey">Dyneley Hussey</ref> writes that it was Schobert's music that opened up Mozart to the possibility of adopting a poetic stance in his music. Citing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Téodor_de_Wyzewa">Téodor de Wyzewa</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georges_de_Saint-Foix">Georges de Saint-Foix</ref>'s work on Mozart, Hussey points out that the four piano concertos, "which are deliberate studies from Schobert", have a "typically Mozartian" stylized nature which is actually present in the Schobert works that he was emulating. Hussey concludes, "So we may regard Schobert, to whom Wolfgang owes so much of the 'romantic' element which appears in his work alongside of its 'classic' grace and vigour, as being the first of his real masters."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In 1767, Schobert went mushroom picking with his family in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Le_Pré-Saint-Gervais">Le Pré-Saint-Gervais</ref> near Paris. He tried to have a local chef prepare them, but was told they were poisonous. After unsuccessfully trying again at a restaurant at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bois_de_Boulogne">Bois de Boulogne</ref>, and being incorrectly told by a doctor acquaintance of his that the mushrooms were edible, he decided to use them to make a soup at home. Schobert, his wife, all but one of their children, and his doctor friend died.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>op. 1 – 2 Sonatas for Harpsichord, Violine ad libitum</item>
<item>op. 2 – 2 Sonatas for Harpsichord, with violin obbligato</item>
<item>op. 3 – 2 Sonatas for Harpsichord, Violin ad libitum</item>
<item>op. 4 – 2 Sonatas for Harpsichord</item>
<item>op. 5 – 2 Sonatas for Harpsichord, Violin ad libitum</item>
<item>op. 6 – 3 Triosonatas for Harpsichord, Violin and Violoncello ad libitum</item>
<item>op. 7 – 3 Sonatas en quatuor, Harpsichord, 2 Violins and Violoncello ad libitum</item>
<item>op. 8 – 2 Sonatas for Harpsichord with Violin obbligato</item>
<item>op. 9 – 3 Sinfonies for Harpsichord, Violine and 2 Horns ad libitum</item>
<item>op. 10 – 3 Sinfonies for Harpsichord, Violin and 2 Horns ad libitum</item>
<item>op. 11 – Concerto I for Harpsichord, 2 Violins, Viola, Violoncello, 2 Horns ad libitum</item>
<item>op. 12 – Concerto II for Harpsichord, 2 Violins, Viola, Violoncello, 2 Oboes, 2 Horns ad libitum</item>
<item>op. 13 – Concerto III pastorale for Harpsichord, 2 Violins, 2 Horns ad libitum, Viola, Violoncello</item>
<item>op. 14 – 6 Sonatas for Harpsichord, Violine ad libitum (Nr. 1 with Violin and Viola ad libitum)</item>
<item>op. 15 – Concerto IV for Harpsichord, Violine and 2 Horns ad libitum</item>
<item>op. 16 – 4 Sonatas for Harpsichord, Violin and Violoncello</item>
<item>op. 17 – 4 Sonatas for Harpsichord, Violin</item>
<item>op. 18 – Concerto V for Harpsichord and 2 Violins</item>
<item>op. 19 – 2 Sonatas for Harpsichord or Pianoforte, Violin (posthumous)</item>
<item>op. 20 – 3 Sonatas for Harpsichord and Violin (probably by T. Giordani)</item></list>
<p>(<hi rend="italic">New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians</hi>)</p>
</text>
