<text id="autogum_bio_doc169" title="Takashi Komatsu (industrialist)" shortTile="takashi-komatsu-industrialist" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-10-06" dateModified="2019-10-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Takashi_Komatsu_%28industrialist%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Takashi Komatsu (industrialist)</head>
<figure><caption>1933: Japanese Trade Commissioner Takashi Komatsu to World’s Fair arrives in San Francisco.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Takashi Komatsu</hi> was a Japanese statesman and industrialist.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>After graduating from Harvard University, Takashi Komatsu was appointed secretary to the President of Toyo K.K. (1913) and later was sent to San Francisco as branch manager for that manufacturing company.</p>
<p>During 1921-1922, Komatsu was chief interpreter for the Japanese delegation to the Washington Naval Conference. He also served as a secretary to Tomosaburo Kato, the Ambassador Plenipotentiary. Prince Iyesato Tokugawa led the Japanese delegation to this international military arms limitation gathering.</p>
<p>In 1926, Takashi Komatsu was made managing director of Japan’s Asano Shipyard ship building facility.</p>
<p>In 1927, Komatsu attended Naval Disarmament Conference in Geneva as a member of the suite of chief delegate Saitō Makoto.  Saitō Makoto would become the prime minister of Japan from 26 May 1932 – 8 July 1934.
Komatsu was later made vice-president of Japan Steel Tube Company.</p>
<p>In 1933, Komatsu was Japan’s representative at the 1933 Boston convention of Rotary International.</p>
<p>In 1933 Komatsu made Chicago his headquarters as trade commissioner to the Century of Progress Fair (World’s Fair), representing the Japan Economic Federation and the Associated Japanese Chambers of Commerce and Industry. He visited business leaders in American metropolitan centers so as to ascertain their sentiments regarding the increasing trade between America and Japan.</p>
<p>In 1936, Prince Iyesato Tokugawa became Chairman of the Committee that brought a prestigious Japanese Art Exhibition to the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston, Massachusetts. Prince Tokugawa, as President of the America-Japan Society, worked with the Kokusai Bunka Shinkokai (The Society of International Cultural Relations) to assembly and bring this art exhibition to the U.S. The Prince was assisted by many other distinguished Japanese. This special exhibition was part of Harvard University’s 300th Birthday Celebration. The goal was to encourage an appreciation and understanding in America for the history, culture, and creativity of Japan – thereby opening the hearts of both their nations to one another. In the United States, Prince Tokugawa was given assistance by U.S. Ambassador to Japan Joseph C. Grew and by Takashi Komatsu who was the vice president of the Harvard Club. This exhibition presented over 100 pieces of art, including paintings, sculptures, and scrolls, many centuries old. The illustrated biography The Art of Peace by Stan S. Katz highlights the life of Prince Iyesato Tokugawa and his Japanese allies such as Takashi Komatsu who strove to promote good U.S.-Japan relations.</p>
<p>In 1940, with relations between Japan and the United States rapidly deteriorating, Komatsu again visited the United States as a special commissioner representing Japanese exhibitors at the New York World’s Fair. Invited by Monmouth College president James Harper Grier to address the alumni banquet at that summer’s commencement, he expressed hope that Japan and the U.S. could reconcile their differences. The United States, he said, had played a significant role in bringing Japan into the world picture and for this reason should look with kindness upon Japan. The following day, Komatsu was presented with an honorary degree by his alma mater, as was the commencement speaker, Charles Sprague, who had been Komatsu’s classmate and was then governor of Washington State. They spent that night at the home of President Grier discussing the worsening conditions between the two countries.
After the war Komatsu served on the committee formed for the demobilization of Japan, and was the president of <hi rend="bold">Japan-America Society</hi>.</p>
<p>Komatsu assisted General Douglas MacArthur during the postwar occupation of Japan. MacArthur respected Takashi Komatsu and in 1948, MacArthur is quoted in The Rotarian - Feb 1978, page 29, when being asked if Takashi would be a good Japanese translator, MacArthur responded, “You could not have selected a better man. For his helpfulness to me and for his sagacious work throughout the 1940s, Rotary is especially indebted to Takashi Komatsu.” During those occupation years, Komatsu was active in officially bringing the Rotary International organization back to Japan.</p>
<head>Education</head>
<p>1905 - 1910 Monmouth College Monmouth, Illinois, United States</p>
<p>1910 - 1912 Harvard University, of Law Cambridge, Massachusetts, United States. He would become the vice-president of the Harvard Club.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>President, Japan-America Society</p>
<p>1913 Secretary to the President, Toyo Company</p>
<p>1926 Director, Asano Shipyard</p>
</text>
