<text id="autogum_bio_doc072" title="Loretta Claiborne" shortTile="loretta-claiborne" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-01-12" dateModified="2019-10-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loretta_Claiborne" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Loretta Claiborne</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Loretta Claiborne</hi> is an American global speaker and multi-sport athlete who competes in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special_Olympics">Special Olympics</ref>. She has been honored with the 1996 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Ashe">Arthur Ashe</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ESPY">ESPY</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Ashe_Courage_Award">Courage Award</ref> presented to her by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denzel_Washington">Denzel Washington</ref>. Claiborne was the first Special Olympics athlete elected to the Special Olympics International Board of Directors.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-so-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Loretta Claiborne was born on August 14, 1953,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-2">[2]</ref> in York, Pennsylvania.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-3">[3]</ref> She was the fourth of eight children, and she and her siblings were raised by their single mother, Rita Claiborne.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-2">[2]</ref> Loretta Claiborne was born partially <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visual_impairment">blind</ref>, with an intellectual disability and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clubbed_feet">clubbed feet</ref>; she underwent surgeries to correct her feet and visual impairment when she was young, and was unable to walk until she was four years old. She learned to talk when she was seven.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-3">[3]</ref> Although doctors advised Claiborne's mother to institutionalize the girl, Rita steadfastly refused, choosing to raise Claiborne at home with her other children.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:3-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>When Claiborne was 17, a school counselor suggested she participate in the newly-formed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special_Olympics">Special Olympics</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:4-5">[5]</ref> Claiborne subsequently competed as a runner at the Special Olympics of 1970,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:3-4">[4]</ref> where she received her first medal as an athlete.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>She has completed over 25 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marathon">marathons</ref> and has placed in the top 100 women finishers of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston_Marathon">Boston Marathon</ref> twice.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cnn-6">[6]</ref> In 2000, Claiborne's life was the subject of "The Loretta Claiborne Story", a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Television_film">television film</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cnn-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Special Olympic world games</head>
<p>Loretta Claiborne competed in 6 Special Olympics world games.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>In the 1983 world games, she won a gold medal in the mile run.</item>
<item>In the 1991 world games, Loretta won a gold medal in the 13-mile half marathon, and the silver medal in the 5k run.</item>
<item>In the 1995 world games, she won 2 gold medals in singles bowling and in mixed double bowling.</item>
<item>In 1999, Loretta won a gold medal in the 13 mile run, and the silver medal in the 3k run.</item>
<item>In 2003, she won the gold medal in the 3k run, and the bronze medal in the mile run.</item>
<item>In 2005, Loretta won the silver medal in figure skating at the winter world games.</item></list>
<p>She is also a karate black belt, has been competing in the Special Olympics since 1970, and continues to train in running, figure skating, soccer, skiing, golf, basketball, softball, swimming, tennis, and bowling.  Loretta was the 1981 Spirit of Special Olympics award recipient,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> and the 1988 state athlete of the year. She is on the Special Olympics Pennsylvania Board of Directors, and in 2007 returned to the Special Olympics International Board of Directors.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-so-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In May 2009, the Smithsonian's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Portrait_Gallery_(United_States)">National Portrait Gallery</ref> in Washington, D.C., unveiled a historic portrait of Special Olympics founder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eunice_Kennedy_Shriver">Eunice Kennedy Shriver</ref>, the first portrait the Gallery has ever commissioned of an individual who had not served as a U.S. President or First Lady.  The portrait of Mrs. Shriver depicts her with four Special Olympics athletes, including Loretta Claiborne, and one Best Buddies participant and was painted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Lenz">David Lenz</ref>, the winner of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outwin_Boochever_Portrait_Competition">Outwin Boochever Portrait Competition</ref> in 2006.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>At age 60 in 2013, Claiborne remained physically active but was beginning to focus more on connecting with and inspiring others.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>As of 2019, at the age of 65, Claiborne was continuing to compete in ten sports each year at the Special Olympics.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:4-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Honors</head>
<p>Claiborne has received two honorary doctorate degrees, one from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quinnipiac_University">Quinnipiac University</ref> and the other from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Villanova_University">Villanova University</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:3-4">[4]</ref> In 1996, Claiborne was awarded the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Ashe_Courage_Award">Arthur Ashe Courage Award</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ESPN">ESPN</ref>, and in 1999 she became the subject of a made-for-TV Disney film titled <hi rend="italic">The Loretta Claiborne Story</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-3">[3]</ref> In 2001, a medical and educational facility in her home community of York, Pennsylvania was named the Loretta Claiborne Building in her honor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-8">[8]</ref></p>
</text>
