<text id="autogum_bio_doc742" title="Kutlugh Turkan" shortTile="kutlugh-turkan" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-12-02" dateModified="2019-10-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kutlugh_Turkan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kutlugh Turkan</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kutlugh Turkan</hi> (c.1208/1213 - 1283), was a sovereign ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kirman">Kirman</ref> from 1257 until 1282. </p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Different accounts exist regarding her early life. According to "History of Qara-Khitai Shahs" (<hi rend="italic">Tāriḵ-e šāhi-e Qarāḵtāʾiān</hi>) by anonymous author, she might have been born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transoxiana">Transoxiana</ref> between 1208 and 1213 and later sold as a slave to an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isfahan">Isfahani</ref> merchant, who adopter her and raised with excellent education.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-1">[1]</ref> While other sources talk of her as a concubine to Qiyasaddin Pirshah (son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muhammad_II_of_Khwarazm">Muhammad II of Khwarazm</ref>), then of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buraq_Hajib">Buraq Hajib</ref>. Although <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fatema_Mernissi">Fatema Mernissi</ref> proposed that she was Buraq Hajib's daughter.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Mernissi-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>She married to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qutb_al-Din">Qutb al-Din Mohammad</ref> on 5 September 1235, a nephew of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buraq_Hajib">Buraq Hajib</ref> and his successor. However they were sent to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ögedei_Khan">Ögedei</ref>'s court when Buraq Hajib's son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rukn_al-Din">Rukn al-Din Mubarak Khawja</ref> (d. 1252) was recognized as the new ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kerman">Kirman</ref>. They returned to Kirman when Qutb al-Din was confirmed as new ruler in December 1252 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Möngke_Khan">Möngke</ref>. However, she was widowed in September 1257, when their son Hajjaj Sultan was still a minor. </p>
<head>Reign</head>
<p>She was recognized as new sovereign of Kirman bu decision of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hulagu_Khan">Hulagu Khan</ref> and Kirman nobles in 1257. "History of Qara-Khitai Shahs" states she was only supposed to have a say in civil affairs, while her son-in-law Azod-al-Din was in charge of military affairs per order of Hulagu. This situation soon changed when she appealed to Ilkhan to change his decision. She established good connections with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ilkhanate">Ilkhanate</ref> by sending her son to the army of Hulagu. </p>
<p>She was officially confirmed in her title by Hulagu 1264, titled '<hi rend="bold">Ismat al-dunya wa al-din</hi> and had the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khutba">khutba</ref></hi> proclaimed in her name.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Mernissi-2">[2]</ref> She obtained <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sirjan">Sirjan</ref> for her daughter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Padishah_Khatun">Padishah Khatun</ref> when she visited newly crowned Abaqa Khan in 1265.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-1">[1]</ref> They were soon married in 1272. Next years of her reign were troubled by her sons <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muzaffar_al-Din_Hajjaj">Hajjaj</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suyurghatmish">Suyurghatmish</ref>'s contest to her right to rule, who even planned to assassinate her. However, she retreated to Sirjan whe her daughter ruled. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muzaffar_al-Din_Hajjaj">Hajjaj</ref> soon proved an ineffective ruler and had to flee to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delhi_Sultanate">Delhi Sultanate</ref> next year. Her stepson <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suyurghatmish">Suyurghatmish</ref> arrived in Kerman on 19 September 1280 and forced her to make him a co-ruler by 19 October, had the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khutba">khutba</ref></hi> proclaimed in his name too. She soon "complained to her daughter Padishah Khatun and received a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yarligh">yarligh</ref> forbidding her stepson to meddle in the affairs of Kirman".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Mernissi-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Last years</head>
<p>The last years of her reign was described as a golden age of Kirman. She funded public granaries in 1263/4, receiving praise from her subjects. She was involved in construction of various public projects such as fortresses (1279), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madrasa">madrasas</ref>, hospitals, mosques, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qanat">qanats</ref> and at least 16 charitable organizations. In 1282, however, new Ilkhan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tekuder">Ahmad Tekuder</ref> confirmed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suyurghatmish">Suyurghatamish</ref> on the throne of Kirman under influence of her mother Qutui Khatun. Kutlugh Tarkan traveled to the Mongol court at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tabriz">Tabriz</ref> to protest but without success. She died in summer  1283 in Charandab district of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tabriz">Tabriz</ref>. She was buried at Gubba-i Sabz Mausoleum of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kutlugh-Khanids">Qutlughanids</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kerman">Kirman</ref>.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>She was married to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qutb_al-Din">Qutb al-Din Mohammad</ref> on 5 September 1235 and had at least three issues with him<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muzaffar_al-Din_Hajjaj">Muzaffar al-Din Hajjaj Sultan</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Padishah_Khatun">Padishah Khatun</ref> (with Kutlugh Turkan) — married to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abaqa_Khan">Abaqa</ref>, then <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaykhatu">Gaykhatu</ref>.</item>
<item>Bibi Turkan (with Kutlugh Turkan) — married Adud al-Din Amir Hajji, then Shams al-Din b. Malik Tazigu</item></list>
</text>
