<text id="autogum_bio_doc557" title="Ambrosius Benson" shortTile="ambrosius-benson" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-12-30" dateModified="2019-10-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ambrosius_Benson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ambrosius Benson</head><figure><caption>Ambrosius Benson's <hi rend="italic">The Magdalen Reading</hi>, c. 1525.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ambrosius Benson</hi> (c. 1495/1500, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferrara">Ferrara</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milan">Milan</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>–1550, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flanders">Flanders</ref>) was an Italian painter who became a part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northern_Renaissance">Northern Renaissance</ref>.</p>
<p>While many surviving paintings have been attributed, there is very little known of him from records, and he tended not to sign his work. He is believed to be responsible for mainly religious art, but also painted portraits on commission. He sometime painted from classical sources, often setting the figures in modern-dress, or a contemporary domestic setting.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> In his lifetime he was successful; he had a large workshop, his work was sold internationally and he was especially popular in Spain.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-r-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Benson became popular as a source for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pastiche">pastiche</ref> with 19th-century painters, who are sometimes known as the "followers of Benson". In particular his many variations of the Magdalen and Sibilla Persica were further copied and became popular with contemporary buyers.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Death_of_Lucretia_(Benson)">Death of Lucretia</ref></hi>, date unknown. The rape that lead to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucretia">Lucretia</ref>'s suicide can be seen in the background.</caption></figure>
<p>Although Ambrosius Benson (or Ambrose Benzone, as he is named by an early scholar in deference to his
Lombardian origin) was Italian by birth, scholars consider him a painter of the Flemish school.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> Typical of the itinerant manner of many painters of the time, he moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bruges">Bruges</ref> c. 1515 and served his apprenticeship with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Early_Netherlandish_painting">Early Netherlandish</ref> painter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerard_David">Gerard David</ref>. He later became a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naturalized_citizen">naturalized citizen</ref> of Bruges.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-r-3">[3]</ref> Benson worked as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Journeyman">journeyman</ref> before he was made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_craftsman">master</ref> in 1519 and became a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guild">guild</ref> of painters and saddle makers.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> He eventually became a dean and then a governor of the guild. He married Anna Ghyselin, and had two sons with her, Jan and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Willem_Benson">Willem</ref>, both of whom became painters. He later remarried and had a daughter Anna. He is believed to have had at least two other daughters from extramarital affairs.</p>
<p>Benson came into dispute with Gerard around 1519, over a number of paintings and drawings Benson had created -including a book of studies for heads and nudes as well as various patterns- in the older master's workshop without his assistance. David refused to return the material, and after Benson pursued him legally, served time in prison for his appropriation.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>Late 19th-century version of one of his Sibilla Persica paintings, showing a half-length female reading a book held in her hands.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-V&amp;A-8">[8]</ref></caption></figure>
<p>He served as head of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guild_of_Saint_Luke">Guild of Saint Luke</ref> from 1537 to 1539 and 1543 to 1544. Much of his work was at one time attributed to a Spanish artist known only as the Master of Segovia; it is now believed they were the same person.</p>
<p>Perhaps under the influence of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rogier_van_der_Weyden">Rogier van der Weyden</ref>'s 15th-century <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Magdalen_Reading">The Magdalen Reading</ref></hi>, Benson was one of the first artists to popularise images of women reading. It became a motif for him, and he painted the scene many times in his images of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Magdalen">Mary Magdalen</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_Sibyl">Sybil Persica</ref>, whom he treated as almost interchangeable.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-V&amp;A-8">[8]</ref> One <hi rend="italic">The Magdalen Reading</hi> by Benson is held in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Gallery">National Gallery</ref>, London.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Gallery</head>
<list type="unordered">
<item><hi rend="italic">Portrait of Jean Wyts,</hi> 1520-1530, The Phoebus Foundation</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">The Descent from the Cross</hi>, 1528</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">The Magdalen Reading</hi>, 1535</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Portrait of Anne Stafford</hi>, 1535</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Virgin with Pear</hi>, date unknown</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Virgin and Child with Saints</hi>, date unknown</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Deipara Virgo</hi>, date unknown</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Elegant couples dancing in a landscape</hi>, date unknown. Currently exhibited at the Utah Museum of Fine Arts (UMFA).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></item>
</list>
<head>References and sources</head>
References
Sources
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Max_Jakob_Friedländer">Friedländer, Max J</ref>. "Ambrosius Benson as a Portrait Painter". "Yearbook of the Prussian art collections", 1910. 31</item></list>
</text>
