<text id="autogum_bio_doc317" title="James Robson (poet and songwriter)" shortTile="james-robson-poet" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-06-21" dateModified="2017-07-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Robson_%28poet_and_songwriter%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>James Robson (poet and songwriter)</head>
<p><hi rend="bold"> James Robson  </hi> (died c. 6 May 1757) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northumberland">Northumbrian</ref> landowner, poet, songwriter, "political criminal" and one time Jacobite rebel.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>James Robson was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northumberland">Northumberland</ref>, probably in, or near, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thropton">Thropton</ref>, a small village near to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rothbury">Rothbury</ref> and was described as a “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freehold_(law)">freeholder</ref>” (i.e. owner of land), in the village. He became a Jacobite, siding with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Francis_Edward_Stuart">James Francis Edward Stuart</ref> (also called the Old Pretender, son of the deposed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_II_of_England">James II</ref>, and some said rightful heir to the throne of Britain) and took part in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacobite_rising_of_1715">First Jacobite Rising</ref> (or Rebellion).</p>
<p>During this uprising, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Carpenter,_1st_Baron_Carpenter">General Carpenter</ref>, after marching his men and horses into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scotland">Scotland</ref>, returned to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newcastle_upon_Tyne">Newcastle</ref> tired and weary, but was immediately ordered to meet the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacobite_risings">Jacobite</ref> "rebels" at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lancaster,_Lancashire">Lancaster</ref>. He met the rebels at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Preston,_Lancashire">Preston</ref>, where the rebels, after defending the place for some time, surrendered to the King's troops. Among the rebels was Mr James Robson of Throston, who was imprisoned in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Preston_(HM_Prison)">Preston Jail</ref>.</p>
<p>He was a poet, songwriter, but whether this was by natural bent, or because of his incarceration, is not clear. It appears that he may have been a musician, as many of the historical documents describe him as "a (or "the") leader of a (or "the") band in the Pretender’s army", and although these does not make clear whether this means a "group of musicians" or just a "group of rebels", <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Bell_(folk_music)">John Bell</ref> in his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhymes_of_Northern_Bards">Rhymes of Northern Bards</ref>, states that "James Robson ….. was at that time a musician in the rebel army".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rhymes-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Marriage</head>
<p>According to "Archaeologia Aeliana" he married Mary, who died in 1723.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ArchaeAeliansMisc-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Later life</head>
<p>Also according to “Archaeologia Aeliana” James Robson (described as “a Jacobite bandsman”) had eventually been freed. In the Rothbury Parish Records, in the section devoted to Papists and Dissenters, the baptismal records appertaining to Robson, that had been fairly regular,  ceased in 1714, but then in 1723,  in the burial records, is a “Mary, wife of James Robson, Thropton”, and later on 6 May 1757 is the burial of “James Robson of Thropton”<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ArchaeAeliansMisc-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>These include:-</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Satyr Upon Women – described by Bell as “This song is imperfectly compiled from part of a <hi rend="italic">Satire upon Women</hi> wrote in Preston prison in 1715, by Mr James Robson, a freeholder in Thropton, near Rothbury, Northumberland, at that time a musician in the rebel army”.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Rhymes-1">[1]</ref> (note the archaic phrasing)</item></list>
<p>The two descriptions of this song in The Local Historian's Table Book <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> and An historical view of the County by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eneas_Mackenzie">Eneas Mackenzie</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> are identical, and read “<hi rend="italic">Mr James Robson, stone-mason of Thropton, was leader of the band in the Pretender’s army in 1715. He wrote a satire on women, and several other poetical pieces, while confined prisoner at Preston in Lancashire. It is said that he sang the satire at an iron-barred window, looking into a garden, where a lady and her maid were walking. When the song was finished, the former observed, "That young man seems very severe upon our sex, but perhaps he is singing more from oppression than pleasure; go give him that half-crown;" which the girl (sic – her maid) handed through the grating at a period when the captive poet was on the point of starving</hi>".</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>“A Song – composed by Mr James Wilson, of Cawsey Park, on Mr Coughron and family leaving Hebron Hill”. This Mr Coughron was the brother<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> of the celebrated mathematician George Coughron who died of smallpox in Newcastle 7 January 1774 aged 21 (or 23)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></item>
<item>Hobby Elliott – This song is said to have been written by Mr James Robson, Stone Mason, at Thropton, near Rothbury, who was leader of the band in the Pretender's army, in 1715; he wrote a Satyr on women, and several other pieces while confined prisoner at Preston, in Lancashire.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></item></list>
</text>
