<text id="autogum_bio_doc202" title="Simon Kooper" shortTile="simon-kooper" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-07-09" dateModified="2017-11-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simon_Kooper" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Simon Kooper</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Simon Kooper</hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khoekhoe_language">Nama</ref> name: <hi rend="bold">ǃGomxab</hi>, (before 1860–31 January 1913) was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tribal_chief">Captain</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ǃKharakhoen">ǃKharakhoen</ref> (Fransman Nama), a subtribe of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nama_people">Nama people</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Namibia">Namibia</ref> from 1863 to 1909. He became famous for leading the Nama in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herero_and_Namaqua_Genocide">Herero and Nama War</ref> of 1904–1907.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Kooper was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pella,_Northern_Cape">Pella</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northern_Cape">Northern Cape</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NE-1">[1]</ref> It is not known when his clan moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South-West_Africa">South-West Africa</ref> but in the mid-1850s the ǃKharakhoen under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piet_Koper">Piet Koper</ref> already resided there.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-KD-2">[2]</ref>  At that time the ǃKharakhoen were one of the Nama clans allied to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oorlam_people">Orlam Afrikaners</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windhoek">Windhoek</ref>. When this alliance was defeated by merchant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_John_Andersson">Andersson</ref>'s private army in the Battle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otjimbingwe">Otjimbingwe</ref> on 15 June 1863, Piet Koper was killed and Simon Kooper ascended to chieftaincy.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-KD-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Kooper was looking for a place for his clan to settle permanently. Only in 1889 could a missionary be found to stay with them. The Fransman tribe settled at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gochas">Gochas</ref> with him<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-KD-2">[2]</ref> which since then is their clan's main settlement.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Malan-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Conflict with Imperial Germany</head>
<p>After supporting the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ǀKhowesin">ǀKhowesin</ref> (Witbooi Nama) under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hendrik_Witbooi_(Namaqua_chief)">Hendrik Witbooi</ref> in their eventually unsuccessful resistance attempt towards German colonialism in South-West Africa, Kooper was forced to sign a protection treaty with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_Empire">German Empire</ref>, represented by Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodor_Leutwein">Theodor Leutwein</ref>. This treaty was in effect until the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herero_and_Namaqua_Genocide">Herero and Nama War of 1904–1907</ref> began in which Kooper sided with Witbooi again.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NE-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>The Germans defeated the Nama in the Battle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swartfontein">Swartfontein</ref> on 15 January 1905 and forced them to flee first into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalahari">Kalahari</ref> Desert and then to recede into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bechuanaland">Bechuanaland</ref>, the British colony that later became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Botswana">Botswana</ref>. From there they repeatedly and for several years mounted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guerrilla">guerrilla</ref>-style attacks at the colony's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schutztruppe">Schutztruppe</ref></hi> (Protection Force),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NE-1">[1]</ref> actions that made Kooper raise to fame.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-KD-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>After Witooi's death end of October 1905, Kooper and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jakob_Morenga">Jakob Morenga</ref> took over the leadership of the Nama uprising. When Morenga was captured by the British in 1906, Kooper alone led the Nama activities against the Germans. He was imprisoned at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shark_Island_Concentration_Camp">Shark Island</ref> near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lüderitz">Lüderitz</ref> in 1907 but escaped into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Karas_Mountains">Karas Mountains</ref> where Morenga had used the old Nama fortress <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ǁKhauxaǃnas">ǁKhauxaǃnas</ref> as hideout for his rebels.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DierksK2-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Kooper was the last Nama leader still to fight against the Germans until 1908, and the only one never to be captured again after his escape from Shark Island. German troops launched several attacks at his group. In the last of these pursuits at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seatsub">Seatsub</ref> in March 1908, most of the Nama under Kooper were killed and his wife was taken prisoner, but he managed to flee again.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NE-1">[1]</ref> This raid contravened the international law of the time because it took place outside German jurisdiction. German writers <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans_Grimm">Hans Grimm</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fritz_von_Unruh">Fritz von Unruh</ref> took this incident as basis for one of their literary works, respectively, which made this episode known to the German public.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-KD-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>After this last attempt to capture him, German and British colonial forces negotiated a ceasefire, granting an annual allowance for the rest of his life in return for the cessation of all hostilities from his side.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NE-1">[1]</ref> Simon Kooper received 100 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pound_sign">£</ref> in 1908, 75 £ in 1909 and 60 £ in the years thereafter from this agreement. He died in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lokgwabe">Lokgwabe</ref>, Botswana, on 31 January 1913.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NE-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
