<text id="autogum_bio_doc588" title="Veit Stoss" shortTile="veit-stoss" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2002-02-25" dateModified="2019-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Veit_Stoss" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Veit Stoss</head>
<figure><caption>Wooden <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Altar_of_Veit_Stoss">Altar of Veit Stoss</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Mary's_Church,_Kraków">St Mary's Church</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kraków">Kraków</ref></caption></figure>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">Blind Veit Stoss with granddaughter</hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_Matejko">Jan Matejko</ref> (1865), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Museum_in_Warsaw">National Museum</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warsaw">Warsaw</ref></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Veit Stoss</hi> (also: <hi rend="italic">Veit Stoß</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Stuoss</hi>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polish_language">Polish</ref>: <hi lang="pl" rend="italic">Wit Stwosz</hi>; before 1450 – about 20 September 1533) was a leading <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_language">German</ref> sculptor, mostly in wood, whose career covered the transition between the late <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gothic_art">Gothic</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northern_Renaissance">Northern Renaissance</ref>. His style emphasized pathos and emotion, helped by his virtuoso carving of billowing drapery; it has been called "late Gothic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baroque">Baroque</ref>".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Snyder-1">[1]</ref>  He had a large workshop and in addition to his own works there are a number by pupils. He is best known for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Altarpiece_of_Veit_Stoss">altarpiece</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Mary's_Basilica,_Kraków">St. Mary's Basilica</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kraków">Kraków</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poland">Poland</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Stoss was born at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Horb_am_Neckar">Horb am Neckar</ref> before 1450; his exact date of birth is unknown though it may have been in 1447. Nothing about his life is known for certain before 1473 when he moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg">Nuremberg</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franconia">Franconia</ref> and married Barbara Hertz. Their eldest son Andreas was born there before 1477, when Stoss moved to Kraków, the royal capital of Poland, where he was commissioned to produce the enormous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polychrome">polychrome</ref> wooden <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Altar_of_Veit_Stoss">Altar of Veit Stoss</ref> (Ołtarz Wita Stwosza) at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Mary's_Basilica,_Kraków">St Mary's Church</ref> in Kraków. His son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanisław_Stwosz">Stanisław</ref> was also a sculptor. Veit lived and worked in Kraków for the next twenty years. His name is usually <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polish_language">polonized</ref> as Wit Stwosz.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-wzks-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>In Kraków</head>
<p>The altar in Kraków was completed in 1489, and was the largest <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triptych">triptych</ref> of its time. Like Stoss' other large works, it required a large workshop including specialized painters and gilders.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>  Other important works from Stoss' period in Poland were the tomb of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casimir_IV_Jagiellon">Casimir IV</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wawel_Cathedral">Wawel Cathedral</ref>, the marble tomb of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zbigniew_Oleśnicki_(primate_of_Poland)">Zbigniew Oleśnicki</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gniezno">Gniezno</ref>, and the altar of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanislaus_of_Szczepanów">Saint Stanislaus</ref>.  The Polish court was more aware of Italian styles than Nuremberg patrons of that time, and some of Stoss' Polish work used Renaissance classical ornament.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-staropolska-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>During World War II, on the order of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans_Frank">Hans Frank</ref> – the Governor-General of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Government">that region</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Occupation_of_Poland_(1939–1945)">occupied Poland</ref> – the dismantled Altar was shipped to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third_Reich">Third Reich</ref> around 1941. It was rediscovered in 1945 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bavaria">Bavaria</ref>, hidden in the basement of the heavily bombed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg_Castle">Nuremberg Castle</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> The High Altar underwent major restoration work in Poland and was put back in its place at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Mary's_Basilica,_Kraków">the Basilica</ref> ten years later.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-wzks-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Nuremberg</head>
<p>In 1496, Stoss returned to Nuremberg with his wife and eight children. He reacquired his citizenship for three <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhenish_guilder">gulden</ref> and resumed his work there as a sculptor. Between 1500 and 1503 he carved an altar, now lost, for the parish church of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schwaz">Schwaz</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tyrol_(state)">Tyrol</ref> of the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Assumption_of_Mary">Assumption of Mary</ref>".  In 1503, he was arrested for forging the seal and signature of a fraudulent contractor and was sentenced to be branded on both of his cheeks and prohibited from leaving Nuremberg without the explicit permission of the city council. He was pardoned in 1506 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maximilian_I,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Emperor Maximilian</ref> and restored of his civil rights.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angelic_Salutation_(Stoss)">Angelic Salutation</ref></hi> (1517–1518) in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Lorenz_(Nürnberg)">St. Lorenz Kirche</ref>, Nuremberg</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>The Angel Raphael and the young Tobias. Limewood. 97cm (38in), (Germanisches Nationalmuseum, Nuremberg)</caption></figure>
<p>Despite the prohibition he went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Münnerstadt">Münnerstadt</ref> in 1504, to paint and gild the altarpiece that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tilman_Riemenschneider">Tilman Riemenschneider</ref> had left in plain wood ten years earlier, presumably according to his contract (unlike Stoss, his workshop did not include painters and gilders).  Leaving wood sculpture unpainted was a new taste at the time, and "perhaps the tastes of the city council were somewhat provincial."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> He also created the altar for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bamberg_Cathedral">Bamberg Cathedral</ref> and various other sculptures in Nuremberg, including the <hi rend="italic">Annunciation</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tobias and the Angel</hi>. In 1506 he was arrested a second time. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maximilian_I,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Emperor Maximilian</ref> wrote a letter of pardon, but it was rejected by the council of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperial_free_city">Imperial free city</ref> Nuremberg as meddling in its internal affairs.  He was able to resettle in Nuremberg from 1506, but was shunned by the council and received few large commissions from that time onwards.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Snyder-1">[1]</ref> In 1512, the Emperor asked Stoss to help with the planning of his tomb monument, which was eventually placed in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hofkirche,_Innsbruck">Hofkirche</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Innsbruck">Innsbruck</ref>; it seems Stoss's attempts to cast in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brass">brass</ref> were unsuccessful.</p>
<p>During the period 1515–1520, Veit Stoss received a commission for sculptures by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raffaele_Torrigiani">Raffaele Torrigiani</ref>, a rich <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florence">Florentine</ref> merchant.  In 1516 he made <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tobias_and_the_Angel_(Veit_Stoss)">Tobias and the Angel</ref></hi> (now in Germanisches Nationalmuseum, Nuremberg), and a statue of Saint <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roch">Roch</ref> for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basilica_della_Santissima_Annunziata,_Florence">Basilica of Santissima Annunziata</ref> in Florence. This wooden statue represents the saint in a traditional way: in the garb of a pilgrim, lifting his tunic to demonstrate the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plague_(disease)">plague</ref> sore in his thigh. Even <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giorgio_Vasari">Giorgio Vasari</ref>, who did not think much of artists north of the Alps, praised it in his <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lives_of_the_Most_Excellent_Painters,_Sculptors,_and_Architects">Le Vite</ref></hi> and called it "a miracle in wood", though misattributing it.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>Veit Stoss was buried at St. Johannis cemetery in Nuremberg.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> His artistic legacy was continued by his son Stanisław.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<head>In popular culture</head>
<p>Veit Stoss is featured in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judith_Weir">Judith Weir</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opera">opera</ref>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Black_Spider_(opera)">The Black Spider</ref></hi>. He is one of the singing sculptors in Act 3 Scene 2 inside the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wawel_Cathedral">Wawel Cathedral</ref>. He is shown chiseling at the tomb of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casimir_IV_Jagiellon">Casimir IV</ref>.
There is a Polish book (1913) and film (1961) <hi rend="italic">Historia żółtej ciżemki</hi> (<hi rend="italic">The story of a yellow crakow</hi>) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> about Veit Stoss in Cracow.</p>
<head>Notes and references</head>
</text>
