<text id="autogum_bio_doc460" title="Anna Koldings" shortTile="anna-koldings" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-08" dateModified="2019-10-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna_Koldings" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Anna Koldings</head><p><hi rend="bold">Anna (Ane or Anne) Koldings</hi> (died 1590) was an alleged Danish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Witch">witch</ref>. She was one of the main suspects in the witch trial of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copenhagen">Copenhagen</ref> the summer of 1590, which were held as a parallel to the famous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Berwick_Witches">North Berwick Witch trials</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scotland">Scotland</ref>.</p>
<p>The winter of 1589, Princess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_of_Denmark">Anne of Denmark</ref> departed from Copenhagen to marry King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_VI">James VI</ref> of Scotland. A great storm arose, which almost caused the ship to sink. The ship of the princess eventually harbored in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oslo">Oslo</ref> in the Danish province of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norway">Norway</ref>, James VI joined her there, and the wedding took place in Norway instead of in Scotland, as had been planned. In the spring of 1590, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_VI">James VI</ref> returned to Scotland after his marriage. The regal voyage back from Denmark was beset by storms. The Danish court at that time was greatly perplexed by witchcraft and the black arts, and this must have impressed on the young King James.
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In the summer of 1590, a great witch hunt was instituted in Copenhagen. The Danish authorities issued an investigation to the cause of the storms. The Danish minister of finance, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christoffer_Valkendorff">Christoffer Valkendorff</ref>, was accused by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Admiral_of_the_Realm">Admiral</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peder_Munk">Peder Munk</ref> of having equipped the royal ship so insufficiently that it had been unable to withstand storm.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref>  He defended himself by saying that the storm had been caused by witches in the house of Karen the Weaver, who had sent little demons in empty barrows who had climbed up the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keel">keels</ref> of the ships and caused the storm.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Karen was arrested in July. She confessed to have caused the storms which hunted the royal ship by use of witchcraft, and named other women as accomplices. One of them was Anna Koldings. During <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torture">torture</ref>, Koldings described how a group of women had gathered in the house of Karen, where they had caused the storm of the princess' ship by sending small devils up the keels of the ship.
She named five other women as accomplices, among them Malin, wife of the mayor of Copenhagen, and Margrethe Jakob Skrivers. All women were arrested and charged, while the spouse of Skrivers unsuccessfully tried to defend her. Anne Koldings was considered a very dangerous witch, and referred to as Mother of the Devil. She was treated as somewhat of a celebrity in prison and displayed to visitors: she is known to have confessed to two priests and three female visitors while in prison.    </p>
<p>Anne Koldings was judged guilty as charged and executed by burning at the stake at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kronborg">Kronborg</ref>. Twelve women were reportedly executed for involvement in this witch trial. In September, two women were burnt as witches at Kronborg.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> James heard news from Denmark regarding this, and decided to set up his own tribunal.  </p>
<head>Other sources</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Åberg, Alf, Häxorna: de stora trolldomsprocesserna i Sverige 1668-1676, Esselte studium/Akademiförl., Göteborg, 1989 (in Swedish)</item>
<item>Oluf Nielsen: <hi rend="italic"><ref target="http://www.eremit.dk/ebog/khb/3/khb3_5.html">Kjøbenhavns Historie og Beskrivelse III. Kjøbenhavn i Aarene 1536-1660</ref></hi> [The history and description of Copenhagen volume III. Copenhagen in 1536-1660] Kbh., G. E. C. Gad (In Danish)</item>
<item>Rune Hagen: <hi rend="italic"><ref target="http://www.dagbladet.no/kultur/2001/08/19/275636.html">Blant konger og hekser</ref></hi> [Among kings and witches] (In Norwegian)</item>
<item>P. G. Maxwell-Stuart (2007) <hi rend="italic">The Great Scottish Witch-Hunt: Europe's Most Obsessive Dynasty</hi> (Tempus) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/978-0752444253">978-0752444253</ref></item></list>
</text>
