<text id="autogum_bio_doc650" title="Joan of Ponthieu, Dame of Epernon" shortTile="joan-ponthieu-dame" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-04-14" dateModified="2019-07-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_of_Ponthieu%2C_Dame_of_Epernon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Joan of Ponthieu, Dame of Epernon</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jeanne de Ponthieu, dame d'Épernon</hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Counts_of_Vendôme">Countess of Vendôme</ref> and of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castres">Castres</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Jeanne de Ponthieu, dame d'Épernon, comtesse de Vendôme et de Castres</hi>, before 1336 – 30 May 1376)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> was a French noblewoman, the youngest daughter of Jean II de Ponthieu, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Counts_and_Dukes_of_Aumale">Count of Aumale</ref>. She was the wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_VI_of_Vendôme">Jean VI de Vendôme, Count of Vendôme and of Castres</ref>. She acted as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent">regent</ref> for her infant granddaughter Jeanne, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suo_jure">suo jure</ref></hi> Countess of Vendôme from 1371 until the child's premature death in 1372.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Jeanne was born in France sometime before 1336, the youngest daughter of Jean II de Ponthieu, Count of Aumale, and Catherine d'Artois (1296 – November 1368). She had an elder sister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blanche_de_Ponthieu">Blanche de Ponthieu</ref> (before 1326 – 12 April/May 1387) who became <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suo_jure">suo jure</ref></hi> Countess of Aumale on 16 January 1340 upon the death of their father. Blanche was the wife of Jean V de Harcourt, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Count_of_Harcourt">Count of Harcourt</ref>, by whom she had issue.</p>
<p>Jeanne, who was also known as the <hi rend="italic">Dame d'Épernon</hi>, was a direct descendant of King Ferdinand III of Castile by his second wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan,_Countess_of_Ponthieu">Joan, Countess of Ponthieu</ref>. King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_VIII_of_France">Louis VIII of France</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blanche_of_Castile">Blanche of Castile</ref> were also among her many royal ancestors. Her paternal grandparents were Jean I de Ponthieu, Count of Aumale and Ide de Meullent. Her maternal grandparents were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_of_Artois">Philip of Artois</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blanche_of_Brittany">Blanche of Brittany</ref>, also known as <hi rend="italic">Blanche de Bretagne</hi>, herself the granddaughter of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_III_of_England">Henry III of England</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleanor_of_Provence">Eleanor of Provence</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> The seigneury of Épernon was part of her father's inheritance which came into his family about 1256 upon the marriage of his grandmother Laure de Montfort, <hi rend="italic">Dame d'Épernon</hi> to the Infante Ferdinand of Castile, Count of Aumale.</p>
<head>Marriage and issue</head>
<p>On an unknown date sometime before 1351, Jeanne married Jean VI de Vendôme, Count of Vendôme and of Castres, <hi rend="italic">Seigneur de Lézingnan-en-Narbonnois</hi>, and de Brétencourt of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Counts_of_Vendôme">House of Montoire</ref>. He was the son of Bouchard VI de Vendôme, Count of Vendôme and Alix de Bretagne. He succeeded to his titles in 1354; from that time onward, Jeanne was styled as Countess of Vendôme and of Castres. Jean and Jeanne together had two children:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Bouchard VII de Vendôme, Count of Vendôme and of Castres (c. 1351 – 16 November 1371), married in 1368 as her second husband, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_I,_Count_of_La_Marche">Isabelle de Bourbon</ref>, by whom he had one daughter, Jeanne, Countess of Vendôme and of Castres who died in 1372.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_de_Vendôme">Catherine de Vendôme</ref> (1354 – 1 April 1412), <hi rend="italic">suo jure</hi> Countess of Vendôme and of Castres. On 28 September 1364 in Paris, she married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_I,_Count_of_La_Marche">John I, Count of La Marche</ref>, by whom she had seven children, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlotte_de_Bourbon-La_Marche">Charlotte de Bourbon-La Marche</ref>, Queen consort of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyprus">Cyprus</ref>.</item></list>
<p>In 1362, the castle and town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vendôme">Vendôme</ref> were plundered by the Anglo-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gascony">Gascon</ref> troops of Captain Robert Marcault, and Jeanne was taken prisoner. She was later ransomed. In 1367, she ordered that the walls of the castle were to be strengthened, and personally superintended the fortifications.</p>
<p>Upon the death of her husband in February 1364 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montpellier">Montpellier</ref>, Jeanne's son Bouchard became Count of Vendôme and of Castres. When he died in 1371, the titles passed to his infant daughter, Jeanne. Jeanne de Ponthieu acted as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent">regent</ref> for her granddaughter from 1371 until the latter's death in 1372. The titles were inherited by Catherine, the only surviving child of Jeanne de Ponthieu. Catherine held the titles jointly with her husband until 1393, then with her second eldest son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis,_Count_of_Vendôme">Louis, Count of Vendôme</ref>.</p>
<p>Jeanne died on 30 May 1376. Through her daughter Catherine, Jeanne was an ancestress of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_of_France">Anne of France</ref>, Queen consort <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_de_Medici">Catherine de Medici</ref>, King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_IV_of_France">Henry IV of France</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary,_Queen_of_Scots">Mary, Queen of Scots</ref>, and the current <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British_Royal_Family">British Royal Family</ref>.</p>
<head>Ancestry</head>
</text>
