<text id="autogum_bio_doc656" title="Giordano Orsini (died 1438)" shortTile="giordano-orsini-died" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-06-27" dateModified="2016-07-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giordano_Orsini_%28died_1438%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Giordano Orsini (died 1438)</head>For other people with the same name, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giordano_Orsini_(disambiguation)">Giordano Orsini (disambiguation)</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Giordano Orsini</hi> (1360/70 — 29 May 1438) was an Italian cardinal who enjoyed an extensive career in the early fifteenth century.  He was a member of the powerful Roman family of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orsini">Orsini</ref>.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Orsini was Archbishop of Naples from 1400 until 1405, when he was made a Cardinal by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Innocent_VII">Innocent VII</ref>. In 1408 he abandoned the "Roman Obedience" and attended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council_of_Pisa">Council of Pisa</ref>. He was subsequently administrator of the see of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pécs">Pécs</ref> 1409-10, and legate of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antipope_John_XXIII">Antipope John XXIII</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Picenum">Picenum</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bologna">Bologna</ref>. Promoted to the suburbicarian see of Albano in 1412, he had a considerable role in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council_of_Constance">Council of Constance</ref>, where he presided over the fifth session. He was the papal legate appointed to establish peace between England and France in 1418. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_penitentiary">Grand penitentiary</ref> from 1419. In 1420, he was named Abbot Commendatory of the Imperial Abbey of Farfa.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>  Legate of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Martin_V">Pope Martin V</ref> in Bohemia, Hungary and Germany in prosecution of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hussites">Hussites</ref> in 1426. </p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean_of_the_Sacred_College_of_Cardinals">Dean of the Sacred College of Cardinals</ref> in 1428, he presided over the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papal_conclave,_1431">Papal conclave, 1431</ref>. Orsini opted for the suburbicarian see of Sabina on March 14, 1431. As the legate of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Eugenius_IV">Pope Eugenius IV</ref> to open the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council_of_Basle">Council of Basle</ref>, he defended the rights of Pope against the claims of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conciliarism">conciliarist movement</ref>. Archpriest of patriarchal Vatican Basilica from 1434 until his death.  He is buried in a tomb in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Peter's_Basilica">St. Peter's Basilica</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rome">Rome</ref>.</p>
<head>Patron of the arts</head>
<p>Orsini's status put him in a position to be a major patron of the arts,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> and during the pontificate of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Martin_V">Martin V</ref> (1417-31), the Cardinal of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Sabina">Santa Sabina</ref>, as he was called, became the center of an early circle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renaissance_humanism">humanist</ref> culture that included <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonardo_Bruni">Leonardo Bruni</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poggio_Bracciolini">Poggio Bracciolini</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonardo_Dati">Leonardo Dati</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lorenzo_Valla">Lorenzo Valla</ref>, who recalled<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> how the scholars would gather, dressed in antique robes, to discuss topics of human conduct in Classical and Christian terms. This patron of artists and scholars assembled a library that comprised 244 manuscripts, which passed at his death intact to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vatican_Library">Vatican Library</ref>. His seat was the fortress-palazzo crowning "Monte Giordano", a small rise south-east of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ponte_Sant'Angelo">Ponte Sant'Angelo</ref>, which had been built in the twelfth century by the Roncioni, and had been converted and extended into a palatial complex by the Orsini.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Around 1430, Orsini built in the palazzo a <hi rend="italic">sala teatri</hi> for his humanistic gatherings; it was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theater_(structure)">first permanent indoor theatre</ref> built in the Renaissance.  Its walls were painted with an audience of illustrious personages of history, painted full-length in a cavalcade, row upon row, three hundred figures by the time the frescoes were completed, winding their way down the walls. Such a grand scheme was beyond the powers of Roman painters, whose skills and workshops had diminished during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avignon_Papacy">Avignon Papacy</ref>, when the sources of patronage were removed from Rome. The Cardinal turned to the Florentine <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masolino_da_Panicale">Masolino da Panicale</ref>, currently at work in Rome. The young <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paolo_Uccello">Paolo Uccello</ref> also played a part in the enterprise.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Among Orsini's friends was the Danish cartographer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Claudius_Clavus">Claudius Clavus</ref> who lived in Rome.</p>
<p>The humanist circle disbanded when Giordano Orsini followed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Eugenius_IV">Pope Eugenius IV</ref> into voluntary exile from Rome in 1434. He spent the remainder of his life in Florence and northern Italy and never returned.</p>
</text>
