<text id="autogum_bio_doc016" title="David Schonfeld" shortTile="david-schonfeld" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-05-26" dateModified="2019-07-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Schonfeld" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>David Schonfeld</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Joseph Schonfeld</hi> (M.D., FAAP) is a professor of the Practice in the Suzanne Dworak-Peck School of Social Work and
Pediatrics at the University of Southern California and Children's Hospital Los Angeles and director at the National Center for School Crisis and Bereavement.</p>
<head>Education</head>
<p>Schonfeld attended <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston_University_School_of_Medicine">Boston University School of Medicine</ref> and Boston University College of Liberal Arts from which he graduated with B.A. (Summa Cum Laude) and M.D. (Magna Cum Laude) along with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phi_Beta_Kappa">Phi Beta Kappa</ref> and Pediatrics Award - all in 1983.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-1">[1]</ref> Following graduation, he pursued residency in pediatrics at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Children's_Hospital_of_Philadelphia">Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</ref> at which he served until 1986. He quit the residency following the advise of his mentor there, who told him that he should have pursued behavioral pediatrics fellowship after Schonfeld complained to him that he have learned how to take care of children's illnesses, but he didn't go into pediatrics because he loves illnesses.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-usc-2">[2]</ref> He then pursued fellowship in behavioral and developmental pediatrics with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Maryland,_Baltimore">University of Maryland, Baltimore</ref> from which he graduated in 1989.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Career</head>
<head>1990s</head>
<p>Immediately after University of Maryland, David Schonfeld joined the faculty at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yale_School_of_Medicine">Yale School of Medicine</ref> as an assistant professor of pediatrics, a position which he kept until 1995. He then relocated to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yale_New_Haven_Hospital">Yale New Haven Hospital</ref>, where he served as its director until 1998 and from 1990 until 2005 maintained the same position at its Lead Program.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-1">[1]</ref> When <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gulf_War">Gulf War</ref> broke out in 1991, Schonfeld participated at a meeting regarding children cope with war at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yale_Child_Study_Center">Yale Child Study Center</ref>, a department of the Yale School of Medicine. There, he found out that children at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Haven,_Connecticut">New Haven, Connecticut</ref> are more impacted by city violence then war.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-usc-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In an interview with Nicole Wise of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_New_York_Times">The New York Times</ref></hi> in 1992, Dr. Schonfeld had suggested that parents shouldn't be afraid to talk to their children about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HIV/AIDS">AIDS</ref> and should start explaining it to children who are as early as 3-4 year old.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>2000s</head>
<p>After <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/September_11_attacks">September 11 attacks</ref>, he educated fellow teachers' unions, such as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Federation_of_Teachers">American Federation of Teachers</ref>, on how to help children to cope with a loss of their loved one. In the study that was conducted by him, it was revealed that only 7% of teachers had received training and only 3% of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/School_district">school districts</ref> offer such courses.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-usc-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In 2005, David Schonfeld had received funding from the September 11th Children's Fund to establish National Center for School Crisis and Bereavement at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Southern_California_School_of_Social_Work">University of Southern California School of Social Work</ref> and several years prior to it, he obtained additional funding from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_Life_Foundation">New York Life Foundation</ref> to expand the center and construct the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coalition_to_Support_Grieving_Students">Coalition to Support Grieving Students</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-usc-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>From 2005 to 2012 Schonfeld was the Thelma and Jack Rubinstein Professor of Pediatrics and director of the Division of Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-drexel-4">[4]</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cincinnati_Children's_Hospital_Medical_Center">Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center</ref>. From 2006 to 2015 he was a visiting professor at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Eastern_Piedmont">University of Eastern Piedmont</ref> and at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vrije_Universiteit_Brussel">Vrije Universiteit Brussel</ref>.</p>
<head>2010s</head>
<p>When the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012_Aurora,_Colorado_shooting">shooting at Aurora, Colorado</ref> happened in 2012, David Schonfeld was invited to speak at the school the next day.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>From 2013 to 2015 he was pediatrician-in-chief at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Christopher's_Hospital_for_Children">St. Christopher's Hospital for Children</ref> and chairman and professor of pediatrics at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drexel_University_College_of_Medicine">Drexel University College of Medicine</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-1">[1]</ref> Upon expiration of his position at Drexel University, he joined the faculty of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Southern_California">University of Southern California</ref> and its Suzanne Dworak-Peck School of Social Work and Pediatrics.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-usc-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In 2015 he spoke on the Healthy Children Radio regarding natural disasters and gun violence and how to cope with them.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>In 2016 he, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steven_Krug">Steven Krug</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northwestern_University_Feinberg_School_of_Medicine">Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine</ref>) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Fagbuyi">Daniel Fagbuyi</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Washington_University_School_of_Medicine">George Washington University School of Medicine</ref>) had compiled a report in which they criticized the U.S. government for not providing enough funding for the medical needs of children during public health emergencies.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> In March that year he spoke at a free community forum to discuss childhood trauma and crisis of the Our Lady of the Lake Children's Hospital following the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2016_shooting_of_Baton_Rouge_police_officers">2016 shooting of Baton Rouge police officers</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>Following the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2017_Las_Vegas_shooting">2017 Las Vegas shooting</ref>, David Schonfeld and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marleen_Wong">Marleen Wong</ref> had traveled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Las_Vegas">Las Vegas</ref> where they addressed issues on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Post-traumatic_stress_disorder">post-traumatic stress disorder</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anxiety">anxiety</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grief">grief</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>In 2018, Dr. Schonfeld and the New York Life Foundation had launched Grief-Sensitive Schools Initiative which will train New York Life employees to deliver public speaking about grief in public schools.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>When <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nipsey_Hussle">Nipsey Hussle</ref> died in 2019, Schonfeld was quoted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fox_News">Fox News</ref> saying, "People want to come together to support each other. That's really what makes us a community."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<head>Positions</head>
<p>From 1993 to 1994 Schonfeld served on the Nominations Committee of the Society for Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics and from 1996 to 1999 was first chairman of the Research Committee at the same place. From 1997 to 2000 he served as the first SDBP Liaison to the AAP Committee on Pediatric Research and until 2002 was the first SDBP Liaison to the Alliance for Health and Behavior Research. From 1998 to 2002 Dr. Schonfeld served on the Executive Council and since 2000 he is a chair of the Trainee Manuscript Award Committee. David Schonfeld also served on the Task Force on Terrorism from 2001 to 2004 and on the Committee on Resident Research Grants. In addition, he is one of the initial members of the Subboard of Developmental Behavioral Pediatrics, as well as a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Pediatric_Society">American Pediatric Society</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Society_for_Pediatric_Research">Society for Pediatric Research</ref>, American Pediatric Association, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_School_Health_Association">American School Health Association</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sdbp-12">[12]</ref></p>
<p>In 2007, David Schonfeld became President of the Society for Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> and in May of same year served on an Executive Council of the same place.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref></p>
<p>From 2008 to 2010 he served on the Disaster Mental Health Subcommittee of the National Biodefense Science Board Federal Advisory Committee under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homeland_Security_Presidential_Directive_7">Homeland Security Presidential Directive 7</ref> (formerly Presidential Policy Directive 21)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> and Scientific and Program Committee of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Pediatric_Association">International Pediatric Association</ref>. He also served on the National Commission on Children and Disasters from 2008 to 2011<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cv-1">[1]</ref> and since 2009 serves as a member of the expert panel on the Child Development &amp; Behavior Branch.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></p>
<p>In 2013, he was appointed to the Sandy Hook Advisory Commission by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dannel_Malloy">Dannel Malloy</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref> and in February that year became a chairman of the Department of Pediatrics at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drexel_University_College_of_Medicine">Drexel University College of Medicine</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-drexel-4">[4]</ref> Since 2017 he serves as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benefactor_(law)">benefactor</ref> at the Society for Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref> and as its pediatrician-in-chief.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref> Since 2015, David J. Schonfeld is on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Board_of_Psychiatry_and_Neurology">American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology</ref> steering committee.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-20">[20]</ref></p>
<head>Editorial work</head>
<p>Since 1996,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sdbp-12">[12]</ref> David Schonfeld serves on an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Editorial_board">editorial board</ref> of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Journal_of_Developmental_and_Behavioral_Pediatrics">Journal of Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-21">[21]</ref> He was a co-author with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Demaria">Thomas Demaria</ref> on book chapters such as "Child &amp; Disaster" and "Bereavement".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-22">[22]</ref></p>
<head>Personal life</head>
<p>Schonfeld have two grown up daughters<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-23">[23]</ref> one of which is Kim.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-24">[24]</ref></p>
</text>
