<text id="autogum_bio_doc649" title="Yaqub Spata" shortTile="yaqub-spata" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-21" dateModified="2018-10-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yaqub_Spata" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Yaqub Spata</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Yaqub Spata</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Shpata</hi>  (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albanian_language">Albanian</ref>: <hi lang="sq" rend="italic">Jakob Bua Shpata</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_language">Greek</ref>: Γιαγούπης Σπάτας) was the last <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despotate_of_Arta">Lord of Arta</ref>, ruling from 1414/15 until 1416, with a brief interval when he was evicted by the local population. His rule ended after his capture and execution by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlo_I_Tocco">Carlo I Tocco</ref>, who proceeded to incorporate Arta to his domains.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Yaqub was a scion of the Albanian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spata_family">Spata family</ref>. He was a grandson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Spata">John Spata</ref>, the first Albanian ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arta,_Greece">Arta</ref>, and son of John's daughter Irene and an unknown member of the Spata family. He had one brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maurice_Spata">Maurice Spata</ref>, and two half-siblings from his mother's second marriage, Charles and Madalena Marchesano.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26521._Σπάτας_Γιαγούπης-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP5969._Εἰρήνη-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Yaqub was raised at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> court of Sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mehmed_I">Mehmed I</ref>, where he had converted to Islam and acquired his name.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26521._Σπάτας_Γιαγούπης-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFine1994356-3">[3]</ref> In 1414/5, at the time of his elder brother Maurice's death, he claimed the succession over Arta. With the support of his mother Irene, he was successful in securing control over Arta itself, while his half-brother Charles became ruler of nearby <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rogoi">Rogoi</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26521._Σπάτας_Γιαγούπης-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFine1994356-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010185-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>His Muslim faith, however, soon provoked opposition, as the locals feared that he would deliver them to the Ottomans. The local population rose up, imprisoned him and installed his half-brother Charles Marchesano in his place. Released from prison, Yaqub sought refuge in the Ottoman court. There he secured the Sultan's aid. Backed by an Ottoman army under a leader named Ismail, he returned to Arta and recovered the city after a brief siege. He exiled his half-brother in turn, and had the leading men of the city executed for their role in his overthrow.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26521._Σπάτας_Γιαγούπης-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010185-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>After recovering Arta, Yaqub was confronted with the designs of the ambitious <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Count_palatine_of_Cephalonia_and_Zakynthos">Count palatine of Cephalonia and Zakynthos</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlo_I_Tocco">Carlo I Tocco</ref>. Carlo had already acquired possession of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ioannina">Ioannina</ref> and the northern half of the old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despotate_of_Epirus">Despotate of Epirus</ref> a few years previously, posing as the champion of the local Greeks against the Albanian lords who had conquered Epirus, and now set his sights on the southern portions of Epirus around Arta and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aetolia">Aetolia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acarnania">Acarnania</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFine1994356-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010179–185-5">[5]</ref> The chronology of the conflict is somewhat vague, as the main source, the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chronicle_of_the_Tocco">Chronicle of the Tocco</ref></hi>, does not follow a strict chronological order. Nevertheless, it is clear that Carlo, using the fortress of Vobliana as his base, was raiding the Spata domains already before Yaqub's return to power.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010185-4">[4]</ref> Yaqub, along with his father-in-law, Maurice, who had defected from Tocco service, tried to capture Vobliana. The Spatas were then heavily defeated by Carlo's brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonardo_II_Tocco">Leonardo II Tocco</ref> at Mazoma near ancient <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicopolis">Nicopolis</ref>, but Carlo's son Torno suffered setbacks against the Albanians.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26521._Σπάτας_Γιαγούπης-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010186-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>After the Tocchi succeeded in capturing Rhiniasa, Leonardo tried to take Rogoi and Carlo Arta, but Yaqub and his father-in-law succeeded in defending their capital for the time being. Carlo withdrew to Ioannina, but soon after was able to lure Yaqub in an ambush near Vobliana: Yaqub was captured and immediately executed (1 October 1416).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26521._Σπάτας_Γιαγούπης-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010186-6">[6]</ref> Following his death, the magnates of Arta seized control from Yaqub's mother, and offered to surrender the city to Carlo if their existing rights and privileges were respected. Carlo accepted, and entered Arta on 4 October. At the same time, Leonardo took over Rogoi.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPLP26521._Σπάτας_Γιαγούπης-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENicol2010186–187-7">[7]</ref></p>
</text>
