<text id="autogum_bio_doc726" title="William Lyndwood" shortTile="william-lyndwood" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-07-14" dateModified="2019-06-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Lyndwood" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>William Lyndwood</head><p><hi rend="bold">William Lyndwood</hi> (c. 1375 – 21/22 October 1446) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/England">English</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_St._David's">bishop of St. David's</ref>, diplomat and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canonist">canonist</ref>, most notable for the publication of the <hi rend="italic">Provinciale</hi>.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Lyndwood was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linwood,_Lincolnshire">Linwood, Lincolnshire</ref>, one of seven children. His parents were John Lyndwood (died 1419), a prosperous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wool">wool</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merchant">merchant</ref>, and his wife Alice. There is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monumental_brass">monumental brass</ref> to John Lyndwood in the local <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parish_church">parish church</ref> in which an infant William is portrayed decked in the robes of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctor_of_laws">doctor of laws</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ODNB-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Lyndwood was educated at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gonville_Hall,_Cambridge">Gonville Hall, Cambridge</ref> though few details are known.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> He is thought to have become a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fellow#Oxford,_Cambridge_and_Dublin">fellow</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pembroke_College,_Cambridge">Pembroke College, Cambridge</ref> though later he moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxford">Oxford</ref> where he became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctor_of_Canon_Law">DCL</ref> "probably rather by incorporation than constant education". He took <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Orders">Holy Orders</ref> and was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ordination">ordained</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deacon">deacon</ref> in 1404 and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Priest">priest</ref> in 1407.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ODNB-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Lyndwood had a distinguished ecclesiastical career. In 1408, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Hallum">Robert Hallum</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Salisbury">Bishop of Salisbury</ref> appointed Lyndwood to his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consistory_court">consistory court</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ODNB-1">[1]</ref> Then, in 1414, Lyndwood was appointed "Official" of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_Canterbury">Archbishop of Canterbury</ref> (i.e. his principal adviser and representative in matters of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecclesiastical_law">ecclesiastical law</ref>) in 1414, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean_of_the_Arches">Dean of the Arches</ref> in 1426, while holding at the same time several important <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benefice">benefices</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prebend">prebends</ref>. In 1433 he was collated 1434 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeacon_of_Stow">Archdeacon of Stow</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Lincoln">Diocese of Lincoln</ref>, and in 1442, after an earnest recommendation from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VI_of_England">King Henry VI</ref>, he was promoted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Eugene_IV">Pope Eugene IV</ref> to the vacant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_St_David's">See of St. David's</ref>. During these years Lyndwood's attention was occupied by many other matters besides the study of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_law">canon law</ref>. He had been closely associated with Archbishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Chichele">Henry Chichele</ref> in his proceedings against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lollards">Lollards</ref>. He had also acted several times as the chosen representative of the English clergy in their discussions with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Crown">the Crown</ref> over subsidies, but more especially he had repeatedly been sent abroad on diplomatic missions, for example to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portugal">Portugal</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France">France</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref>, besides acting as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King's_Proctor">King's Proctor</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council_of_Basle">Council of Basle</ref> in 1433 and taking a prominent part as negotiator in arranging political and commercial treaties.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-catholic-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>He was also <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Privy_Seal">Keeper of the Privy Seal</ref> from 1432 to 1443.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Powicke92-4">[4]</ref> Despite the fact that so much of Lyndwood's energies were spent upon purely secular concerns nothing seems ever to have been said against his moral or religious character.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-catholic-3">[3]</ref> He was buried in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Mary_Undercroft">St Mary Undercroft</ref>, the crypt of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Stephen's_Chapel">St Stephen's Chapel</ref>, where his body was found in 1852, wrapped in a ceremonial cloth and allegedly "almost without signs of corruption".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-catholic-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>The <hi rend="italic">Provinciale</hi></head>
<p>Lyndwood, however, is chiefly remembered for his great commentary upon the ecclesiastical decrees enacted in English provincial councils under the presidency of the Archbishops of Canterbury. This elaborate work, commonly known as the <hi rend="italic">Provinciale</hi>, follows the arrangement of the titles of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decretals_of_Gregory_IX">Decretals of Gregory IX</ref> in the <hi rend="italic">Corpus Juris</hi>, and copies of much of the medieval English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Legislation">legislation</ref> enacted, in view of special needs and local conditions, to supplement the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jus_commune">jus commune</ref></hi>. Lyndwood's gloss gives an account of the views accepted among the English clergy of his day upon all sorts of subjects.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-catholic-3">[3]</ref>  It should be read together with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Acton_(canon_lawyer)">John of Acton</ref>'s gloss, composed circa 1333-1335, on the Legatine Constitutions of the thirteenth century papal legates, Cardinals Otto and Ottobuono for England, which was published with the Provinciale by Wynkyn de Worde.</p>
<p>The Provinciale was published as <hi rend="italic">Constituciones prouinciales ecclesie anglica[n]e</hi> by Wynkyn de Worde in London in 1496).  The work was frequently reprinted in the early years of the sixteenth century, but the edition produced at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxford">Oxford</ref> in 1679 is sometimes seen as the best.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-catholic-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>The <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholic_Encyclopaedia">Catholic Encyclopaedia</ref></hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-catholic-3">[3]</ref> saw the work as important in the controversy over the attitude of the <hi rend="italic">Ecclesia Anglicana</hi> towards the jurisdiction of the pope. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederic_William_Maitland">Frederic William Maitland</ref> controversially appealed to Lyndwood's authority against the view that the "Canon Law of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rome">Rome</ref>, though always regarded as of great authority in England, was not held to be binding on the English ecclesiastical courts".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> The <hi rend="italic">Catholic Encyclopaedia</hi> also contends that Maitland's arguments had found broader acceptance in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_law">English law</ref>:</p>
<p>In pre-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestant_Reformation">Reformation</ref> times no dignitary of the Church, no archbishop, or bishop could repeal or vary the Papal decrees [and, after quoting Lyndwood's explicit statement to this effect, the account continues] Much of the Canon Law set forth in archiepiscopal constitutions is merely a repetition of the Papal canons, and passed for the purpose of making them better known in remote localities; part was <hi rend="italic">ultra vires</hi>, and the rest consisted of local regulations which were only valid in so far as they did not contravene the <hi rend="italic">jus commune</hi>, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the Roman Canon Law.</p>—<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halsbury's_Laws_of_England">Halsbury's Laws of England</ref></hi> (1910) vol. 11, p. 377.
<p>However, Maitland's view of Lyndwood's authority was attacked by Ogle.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
</text>
