<text id="autogum_bio_doc717" title="Irene Asanina" shortTile="irene-asanina" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-18" dateModified="2018-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irene_Asanina" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Irene Asanina</head><p><hi rend="bold">Irene Asanina</hi> (died after 1354), was the Empress consort of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_VI_Kantakouzenos">John VI Kantakouzenos</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_Empire">Byzantine Empire</ref>.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Asanina was a daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andronikos_Asen">Andronikos Asen</ref> and his wife Tarchanaiotissa. Her paternal grandparents were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Asen_III_of_Bulgaria">Ivan Asen III of Bulgaria</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irene_Palaiologina,_Empress_of_Bulgaria">Irene Palaiologina</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nicol-104-1">[1]</ref> Her maternal grandparents were <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protostrator">protostrator</ref></hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Doukas_Glabas_Tarchaneiotes">Michael Doukas Glabas Tarchaneiotes</ref> and his wife Maria Doukaina Komnene Palaiologina Branaina.</p>
<p>The last names of her maternal grandmother indicate descent from the families <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doukas">Doukas</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Komnenos">Komnenos</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palaiologos">Palaiologos</ref> who each produced several <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_Emperor">Byzantine Emperors</ref>. Her last name however indicates being a member of the Branas family which produced military leaders, like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexios_Branas">Alexios Branas</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodore_Branas">Theodore Branas</ref>, but whose genealogy is poorly recorded.</p>
<p>Her paternal grandmother, Irene Palaiologina, was a daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_VIII_Palaiologos">Michael VIII Palaiologos</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodora_Palaiologina_(Byzantine_empress)">Theodora Palaiologina</ref> which makes Asanina a member of the extended Imperial family of her time.</p>
<head>Empress</head>
<p>Kantakouzenos was a trusted advisor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andronikos_III_Palaiologos">Andronikos III Palaiologos</ref>, grandson of Andronikos II and great-grandson of Michael VIII. Andronikos III died on 15 June 1341 and was succeeded by his eldest son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_V_Palaiologos">John V Palaiologos</ref>, who was only nine-years-old and was placed under the regency of his mother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna_of_Savoy">Anna of Savoy</ref>. However Andronikos III had entrusted the administration of the empire to Kantakouzenos. </p>
<p>At about the same time, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefan_Uroš_IV_Dušan_of_Serbia">Stefan Uroš IV Dušan of Serbia</ref> launched an invasion of Northern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thrace">Thrace</ref>. Kantakouzenos left Constantinople to try to restore order to the area. Anna took advantage of his absence to declare him an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enemy_of_the_state">enemy of the state</ref> and to strip him of titles and fortune. But Kantakouzenos was still in control of part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_army">Byzantine army</ref> and, on 26 October 1341, he answered by proclaiming himself emperor at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Didymoteicho">Didymoteicho</ref>. Irene joined him and was crowned Empress at his side. One of her first acts as Empress was to obtain the release of her two brothers, John and Manuel Asen, who had been imprisoned in Thrace since 1335 on a charge of treason.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nicol-104-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>This was the beginning of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_civil_war_of_1341–1347">civil war that would last until 1347</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Alexander_of_Bulgaria">Ivan Alexander of Bulgaria</ref> soon allied with the faction under John V and Anna while <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefan_Uroš_IV_Dušan_of_Serbia">Stefan Uroš IV Dušan of Serbia</ref> sided with John VI. Both parties were actually taking advantage of the civil war to advance their own political and territorial agendas and John VI even allied himself with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orhan_I">Orhan I</ref> of the nascent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman Sultanate</ref>.</p>
<p>During the war Irene remained at Didymoteicho with her three daughters while John VI was busy campaigning. She defended the city from the attacks of King Ivan Alexander the best she could until her husband, with the help of Sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Umur_Beg">Umur</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aydin">Aydin</ref>, made his way back to Didymoteicho in the winter of 1343. Her courageous efforts impressed many of her contemporaries, such as Umur himself and the historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikephoros_Gregoras">Nikephoros Gregoras</ref>. On 3 February 1347, the two sides reached an agreement. John VI was accepted as senior emperor with John V as his junior co-ruler. The agreement was sealed with the marriage of their daughter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helena_Kantakouzene">Helena Kantakouzene</ref> to John V. John VI entered Constantinople and took effective control of the city with Irene serving as senior Empress at his side.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Later life</head>
<p>However, John V <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_civil_war_of_1352–1357">restarted the conflict in 1352</ref> and gained support as the "legitimate" emperor. On 4 December 1354, John VI abdicated and the former imperial couple retired themselves to separate monasteries. In her case, it was the convent of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hagia_Martha">Hagia Martha</ref> under the monastic name Eugenia. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> In 1356 and the following year, Irene rejected the offer of Ziani, to effect the release of her son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_Kantakouzenos">Matthew Kantakouzenos</ref>, then imprisoned by Emperor John V, and reinstate him as Emperor. In 1359, she was joined at the convent by her daughter Maria, and her granddaughter Theodora, the eldest daughter of Matthew. Nicol speculates that she followed the rest of her family to the Morea where her younger son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manuel_Kantakouzenos">Manuel Kantakouzenos</ref> was <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despot_of_the_Morea">Despot</ref></hi>, but may have returned to Constantinople in 1362 or 1363, where she may have been one of the "Empresses" whom the ambassadors from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Empire_of_Trebizond">Empire of Trebizond</ref> met there in April 1363. Although the date of her death is not recorded, Nicol presumes it happened before 1379 when her husband and other members of her family were taken to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galata">Galata</ref> as hostages by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andronikos_IV_Palaiologos">Andronikos IV Palaiologos</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Marriage</head>
<p>Irene married John Kantakouzenos, a son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Kantakouzenos_(died_1316)">Michael Kantakouzenos</ref> and Theodora Angelina Palaiologina. In his <hi rend="italic">History</hi>, John records his mother being a kinswoman of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andronikos_II_Palaiologos">Andronikos II Palaiologos</ref>, presumably a cousin by one of the siblings of Michael VIII. The marriage produced six children:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_Kantakouzenos">Matthew Kantakouzenos</ref> (c. 1325 – 24 June 1383), co-emperor 1353–1357, later <hi rend="italic">despotēs</hi> in Morea.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manuel_Kantakouzenos">Manuel Kantakouzenos</ref> (c. 1326 – 10 April 1380), <hi rend="italic">despotēs</hi> in Morea.</item>
<item>Andronikos Kantakouzenos (c. 1334 – 1347). The <hi rend="italic">History</hi> of John records that this son died due to "plague". Given the year of his death, Andronikos was probably among the casualties of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_Death">Black Death</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></item>
<item>Maria Kantakouzene (died after 1379), who married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikephoros_II_Orsini">Nikephoros II Orsini</ref> of Epirus.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodora_Kantakouzene,_wife_of_Orhan">Theodora Kantakouzene</ref> (died after 1381), who married Sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orhan">Orhan</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman Empire</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helena_Kantakouzene">Helena Kantakouzene</ref> (1333 – 10 December 1396), who married Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_V_Palaiologos">John V Palaiologos</ref>.</item></list>
</text>
