<text id="autogum_bio_doc300" title="Ismail Pasha al-Azm" shortTile="ismail-pasha-alazm" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-12-08" dateModified="2017-09-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ismail_Pasha_al-Azm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ismail Pasha al-Azm</head><hi rend="bold">Warning:</hi> Page using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_officeholder">Template:Infobox officeholder</ref> with unknown parameter "religion" (this message is shown only in preview).
<p><hi rend="bold">Ismail Pasha al-Azm</hi> was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> statesman who served as the governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damascus_Eyalet">Damascus</ref> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amir_al-hajj">amir al-hajj</ref></hi> in 1725–1730. Prior to this post he served as the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agha_(Ottoman_Empire)">agha</ref></hi> (local commander) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maarrat_al-Nu'man">Ma'arrat al-Nu'man</ref> and steadily moved up the ranks to become the governor of the districts of Ma'arrat al-Nu'man, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hama">Hama</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homs">Homs</ref> in 1719 and then governor of  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tripoli_Eyalet">Tripoli</ref> in 1721 before being assigned to the Damascus governorship. </p>
<p>His consistent promotion was attributed to his successes in restoring order to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Syria">Syrian</ref> countryside after a period of high instability, protecting Syria's farmlands from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bedouin">Bedouin</ref> raids and ensuring the safety of the annual <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hajj">Hajj</ref> pilgrim caravan to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mecca">Mecca</ref>. Although he was deposed from the governorship in 1730, he established his family, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Azm_family">al-Azm</ref>, as a major political household in Syria whose members were frequently appointed as the governors of the Damascus, Tripoli and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sidon_Eyalet">Sidon</ref> provinces and who often served longer than typical terms.</p>
<head>Early career in central Syria</head>
<p>Ismail was the son of a professional Ottoman soldier who settled in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maarrat_al-Nu'man">Ma'arrat al-Nu'man</ref> (Ma'arra) in the mid-17th century.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> Ismail was known as "Ibn al-Azm" (Son of al-Azm) and early in his career as "Ismail Agha".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> He is first mentioned in the history records in 1717, when, as the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agha_(Ottoman_Empire)">agha</ref></hi> (local military commander) of Ma'arra, he sent wheat and barley provisions to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homs">Homs</ref> after that city faced a food shortage following an attack by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bedouin">Bedouin</ref> raiders. In 1719, he was appointed the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mutasallim">mutasallim</ref></hi> (district governor) of the Ma'arra, Homs and Hama <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanjak">sanjaks</ref></hi> (districts); Ma'arra was part of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aleppo_Eyalet">Aleppo Eyalet</ref>, while Homs and Hama were part of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tripoli_Eyalet">Tripoli Eyalet</ref>. Ismail was charged with repopulating villages that had been abandoned due to Bedouin raids and restoring order in the districts. In late 1719, the central authorities commanded him to forcibly settle the nomadic and frequently rebellious <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrian_Turkmen">Turkmen</ref> tribesmen of the region in villages in his territory.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Douwes46-47-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Al-Azm was able to bring order and peace to the districts through forming local alliances and with the support of Aleppo's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wali">wali</ref></hi> (provincial governor). The latter used his influence to persuade the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sublime_Porte">Sublime Porte</ref> (Ottoman imperial government) to send Ismail imperial troops to rein in the nomadic Turkmen and Mawali tribes. The Sublime Porte also granted Ismail and his family certain privileges that guaranteed them significant income. Ismail's restoration of order amid instability marked by frequent Bedouin raids, infighting among various military forces and the brutality of local administrators, gained him a "reputation as a resolute but just and even generous ruler", according to historian Dick Douwes.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Douwes46-47-3">[3]</ref> The 18th-century Homs-based chronicler Muhammad al-Makki praised Ismail's rule and prayed that "God give him strength and make him stand firm and prolong his rule and deliver him and his troops from his enemies".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Douwes46-47-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Although his appointment was for seven years, by his second year in office, in 1721, Ismail was promoted as <hi rend="italic">wali</hi> of Tripoli Eyalet, and was thereafter known as "Ismail Pasha".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Douwes46-47-3">[3]</ref> During his term, he successfully protected Muslim pilgrim convoys on their way to Damascus, from where they would begin their departure to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mecca">Mecca</ref> to perform the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hajj">Hajj</ref>. Ismail Pasha also ensured that the towns of Tripoli Eyalet had sufficient food supplies and he protected the province's farmlands from harvest thieves.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Douwes48-4">[4]</ref> This contrasted with the other governors of Tripoli, who typically neglected their duties in the Homs and Hama districts due to the challenge posed in those regions by frequent Bedouin depredations.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Douwes46-47-3">[3]</ref> During Ismail Pasha's time in office, the central authorities granted him a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malikâne">malikâne</ref></hi> (leasehold for life) over the <hi rend="italic">sanjak</hi> of Hama, while the town of Hama became the countryside headquarters of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Azm_family">al-Azm family</ref> after they moved there from Ma'arra.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Douwes49-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Wali of Damascus</head>
<p>Ismail Pasha was transferred to the governorship of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damascus_Eyalet">Damascus Eyalet</ref> in 1725, after a revolt in the city against Wali <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Çerkes_Osman_Pasha">Çerkes Osman Pasha</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> He was replaced by his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sulayman_Pasha_al-Azm">Sulayman Pasha al-Azm</ref> in Tripoli, while one of his sons was appointed <hi rend="italic">mutasallim</hi> of Hama.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Douwes48-4">[4]</ref> As <hi rend="italic">wali</hi> of Damascus, he was tasked with bringing order to the Syrian interior from Ma'arra in the north to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transjordan_(region)">eastern bank</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jordan_River">Jordan River</ref> in the south. He was also concurrently appointed <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amir_al-hajj">amir al-hajj</ref></hi> and was thus responsible for the safety and provisioning of the annual Hajj caravan from Damascus to Mecca.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Douwes48-4">[4]</ref> In his first four years (1725–1729) as <hi rend="italic">amir al-hajj</hi>, Ismail Pasha successfully countered four attempted Bedouin raids against the caravan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> Throughout his term in Damascus, Ismail Pasha appointed members of his family or their close associates as the <hi rend="italic">mutasallims</hi> of Hama, Homs and Ma'arra.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Douwes49-5">[5]</ref> He established lucrative monopolies as governor,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Burns240-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bidwell58-9">[9]</ref> including on sheep from Hama,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Burns240-8">[8]</ref> and was responsible for a number of building works in the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damascus">Damascus</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bidwell58-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>Ismail Pasha was dismissed from the governorship in late 1730 when the Sublime Porte accused him of embezzling money slated for provisioning the Hajj caravan. However, this charge was deemed "dubious" by historian Karl Barbir.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Barbir157-10">[10]</ref> Ismail Pasha was likely dismissed due to the ousting of Sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ahmed_III">Ahmed III</ref> in a coup and the consequent dismissal of provincial governors appointed under Ahmed's administration. In addition to his imprisonment in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citadel_of_Damascus">Citadel of Damascus</ref>, Ismail Pasha's properties were seized by the authorities,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Barbir157-10">[10]</ref> while his brother Sulayman Pasha was dismissed from the Tripoli governorship. However, in 1731, Ismail Pasha and Sulayman Pasha were pardoned.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Douwes50-11">[11]</ref> Ismail Pasha was appointed <hi rend="italic">wali</hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crete_Eyalet">Crete Eyalet</ref> in 1731 and served until 1732.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> Sulayman Pasha would later succeed Ismail as <hi rend="italic">wali</hi> of Damascus in 1734.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>Ismail Pasha established the foundations of the al-Azm family's prominence in Syria as the most powerful political household in the provinces of Damascus, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sidon_Eyalet">Sidon</ref> and Tripoli in the 18th century. Between 1725 and 1757, the al-Azm family nearly monopolized the offices of <hi rend="italic">wali</hi> of Damascus and <hi rend="italic">amir al-hajj</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Douwes4849-14">[14]</ref> The frequent and consecutive appointments of al-Azm members to Damascus contrasted with the traditionally short, typically one-year-long, terms that most governors of Damascus served. The fact that the al-Azms were from Syria also differed from the mostly non-Syrian officials who traditionally filled the post of <hi rend="italic">wali</hi> of Damascus.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> During those years, the al-Azm family was able to prevent Bedouin raids against Syrian villages and maintained the protection of grain harvests and the grain supply to Damascus.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Douwes4849-14">[14]</ref> Among the al-Azm governors that succeeded Ismail Pasha was his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/As'ad_Pasha_al-Azm">As'ad Pasha al-Azm</ref>, who ruled longer than any other <hi rend="italic">wali</hi> of Damascus, serving for 14 consecutive years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Douwes50-11">[11]</ref></p>
</text>
