<text id="autogum_bio_doc644" title="Constance of Sicily, Queen of Cyprus" shortTile="constance-sicily" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-06-20" dateModified="2019-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constance_of_Sicily%2C_Queen_of_Cyprus" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Constance of Sicily, Queen of Cyprus</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Constance of Sicily</hi> (1304/1306 – after 19 June 1344) was Queen of Cyprus and Jerusalem by marriage to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_II_of_Cyprus">Henry II of Cyprus</ref> and Queen of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenia">Armenia</ref> by marriage to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leo_IV,_King_of_Armenia">Leo IV of Armenia</ref>. </p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Constance was one of the oldest of the eight children born to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_III_of_Sicily">Frederick III of Sicily</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleanor_of_Anjou">Eleanor of Anjou</ref>. Her siblings included <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elisabeth_of_Sicily_(1310–1349)">Elizabeth, Duchess of Bavaria</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_II_of_Sicily">Peter II of Sicily</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manfred_of_Athens">Manfred of Athens</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_II_of_Athens">William II of Athens</ref>.</p>
<p>Constance was originally betrothed to Prince Robert, youngest son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_IV_of_France">Philip IV of France</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_I_of_Navarre">Joan I of Navarre</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> The engagement was broken when Robert died young in the summer of 1308. King Philip sent Constance's father a sorrowful letter announcing the news.
Here is an excerpt from the letter: "We are sure that your Majesty knows that the complicated negotiation about the intended marriage of the Princess Constance and our most beloved son Robert was designed to nurture perpetual peace and create an indissoluble union between our Royal Houses. But see, with what intense bitterness of heart we have to tell you this, destructive Death has lamentably snatched from us our son, whom we loved best of all. No fellow human being could be surprised if we were inwardly desolated by the sting of this bitter grief. But we give thanks to God that one of our own family, free of all stain, whom we have loved with our life, has been sent to Heaven."</p>
<head>Queen consort of Cyprus and Jerusalem</head>
<p>Constance was married on 16 October 1317 to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_II_of_Cyprus">Henry II of Cyprus</ref> and Jerusalem, who was son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_III_of_Cyprus">Hugh III of Cyprus</ref>. He was more than 30 years older than her. By this marriage Constance was Queen consort of Cyprus and Jerusalem. They were married for seven years until 31 August 1324 when Henry died. They had no children.</p>
<head>Queen consort of Armenia</head>
<p>On 29 December 1331 Constance married her second husband <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leo_IV,_King_of_Armenia">Leo IV, King of Armenia</ref>. The Papal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dispensation_(Catholic_Church)">Dispensation</ref> was issued the same day. Leo was strongly pro-Western because he favoured a union of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenian_Orthodox_Church">Armenian</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic_Church">Roman</ref> churches, which deeply displeased the native barons. His marriage to Constance further aroused <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-Western_sentiment">anti-Western sentiment</ref> and anti-Catholic sentiment in Armenia. Constance was Leo's second wife, as his first wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alice_of_Korikos">Alice of Korikos</ref> and her father <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oshin_of_Korikos">Oshin</ref> were murdered on Leo's orders because Oshin had murdered Leo's aunt <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabella_of_Armenia,_Princess_of_Tyre">Princess Isabella</ref> to remove her from possibly inheriting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenia">Armenia</ref>. In Armenia, Constance was frequently ill, suffering from constant coughing, fatigue, and dizziness. The king also neglected her, and all of her pregnancies ended in miscarriage. </p>
<p>On 28 December 1341 Leo was murdered by his own barons. It was the day before the couple's tenth wedding anniversary. They had no surviving children.</p>
<head>Later life</head>
<p>Constance married her third and final husband <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Lusignan">John of Lusignan</ref> in 1343. This marriage was also childless. Constance's illness worsened and she died sometime after 19 June 1344, at the age of about 40. John remarried to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alice_of_Ibelin">Alice of Ibelin</ref>, by whom he had a son and heir, Jacques.</p>
<head>Ancestry</head>
</text>
