<text id="autogum_bio_doc755" title="Bartholomew II Ghisi" shortTile="bartholomew-ii-ghisi" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-07-07" dateModified="2019-07-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bartholomew_II_Ghisi" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bartholomew II Ghisi</head><p><hi rend="bold">Bartholomew II Ghisi</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italian_language">Italian</ref>: <hi lang="it" rend="italic">Bartolommeo Ghisi</hi>; died 1341) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latinokratia">Latin</ref> feudal lord in medieval <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greece">Greece</ref>, lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tinos">Tinos</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mykonos">Mykonos</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triarch_of_Negroponte">Triarch of Negroponte</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Constable">Grand Constable</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principality_of_Achaea">Principality of Achaea</ref>. </p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Bartholomew was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_I_Ghisi">George I Ghisi</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alice_dalle_Carceri">Alice dalle Carceri</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBon1969703-1">[1]</ref> His father died at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_the_Cephissus">Battle of the Cephissus</ref> against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catalan_Company">Catalan Company</ref> in 1311. As Bartholomew was underage, his mother assumed the regency while he was still minor, until her own death two years later. By 11 June 1315, Bartholomew II Ghisi was in direct control of his domains.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBon1969234–235,_241-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTERavegnano2000-3">[3]</ref> From his father, Bartholomew inherited the lordship of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tinos">Tinos</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mykonos">Mykonos</ref>, and parts of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kea_(island)">Kea</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serifos">Serifos</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Naxos">Duchy of Naxos</ref>, and from his mother one of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triarchy_of_Negroponte">triarchies</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euboea">Euboea</ref> (according to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raymond-Joseph_Loenertz">Raymond-Joseph Loenertz</ref> the central triarchy of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chalkis">Chalkis</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELoenertz1975110-4">[4]</ref>), while his father's other possession by his first wife, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barony_of_Chalandritsa">Barony of Chalandritsa</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principality_of_Achaea">Principality of Achaea</ref>, returned to a member of the Dramelay family, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_of_Dramelay">Nicholas of Dramelay</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBon1969235,_241-5">[5]</ref> At some unspecified date, Batholomew married a daughter of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Constable">Grand Constable</ref> of Achaea, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Engilbert_of_Liederkerque">Engilbert of Liederkerque</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTERavegnano2000-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBon1969241-6">[6]</ref> and had a son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_II_Ghisi">George II Ghisi</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBon1969703-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>From 1317 to 1327 Bartholomew and his fellow triarchs, backed by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_of_Venice">Venetians</ref>, confronted the Catalans of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Athens">Duchy of Athens</ref> for the domination in Euboea.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELoenertz1975136–142,_146–150-7">[7]</ref> In spring 1317, Andrea Corner, ruler of one sixth of Euboea, allowed 2,000 Catalans entry into the city of Chalkis. The Catalans were expelled from the city following the intervention of Venice, but the situation on the island remained complicated following the death of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boniface_of_Verona">Boniface of Verona</ref>, lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karystos">Karystos</ref>. His daughter, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marulla_of_Verona">Marulla of Verona</ref>, disputed Boniface's inheritance with her half-brother Thomas. Marulla was married with the Catalan leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfonso_Fadrique">Alfonso Fadrique</ref>, whose men occupied the disputed castles.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTERavegnano2000-3">[3]</ref> Venetian mediation led to the signing of a truce of all involved parties on 19 June 1319; Bartholomew signed it along with the Venetian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bailo_of_Negroponte">Bailo of Negroponte</ref>, Francesco Dandolo, John de Noyer de Maisey, triarch of the southern third of Euboea, Pietro dalle Carceri and Andrea Corner, lords of the two northern sixths of the island, and Alfonso Fadrique for the Catalans.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTERavegnano2000-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Bartholomew later came to hold the post of Grand Constable of the Principality of Achaea as well, probably through his marriage, although he does not appear to have had lands in the principality.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTERavegnano2000-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBon1969241-6">[6]</ref> He held this post in 1320, when the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine">Byzantine</ref> governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mystras">Mystras</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andronikos_Asen">Andronikos Asen</ref>, invaded the territory of Achaea. As a vassal of the Prince of Achaea, Bartholomew Ghisi participated in the army sent against the Byzantines, but in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Saint_George">battle</ref> on 9 September at the castle of Saint George, he was taken prisoner, along with several high-ranking nobles of the Principality, and was sent to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTERavegnano2000-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBon1969202-8">[8]</ref> He remained captive for some years and was released in 1325,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBon1969205-9">[9]</ref> although on 11 May 1321 he appears among the signatories of a new truce with the Catalans in Chalkis.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTERavegnano2000-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In 1326/27, he reached a rapprochement with the Catalans, sealed by the marriage of his son George II to Simona of Aragon, daughter of the Catalan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vicar-general">vicar-general</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfonso_Fadrique">Alfonso Fadrique</ref>. Bartholomew received—probably as Simona's dowry—half the castellany of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castle_of_Saint_Omer">Castle of Saint Omer</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thebes,_Greece">Thebes</ref>, which he held until its destruction in c. 1331/34.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBon1969226_note_1,_241-10">[10]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1976156_note_60-11">[11]</ref> This pro-Catalan attitude led to remonstrances by Venetian officials.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELoenertz1975150-12">[12]</ref> At the same time (1326/27) he had a conflict for unknown reasons with the Duke of Naxos <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_I_Sanudo">Nicholas I Sanudo</ref> and was therefore condemned by the Venetian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bailo_of_Negroponte"><hi rend="italic">bailo</hi> of Negroponte</ref>, who confiscated some of his goods while his wife was imprisoned (by the <hi rend="italic">bailo</hi> or Sanudo). The affair was judged several times at Venice but its final outcome remains unknown; however Bartholomew must have regained his standing with Venice since he was included in its truce with the Catalans in 1331.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELoenertz1975152–153-13">[13]</ref></p>
<p>In 1328, Bartholomew and his brother Marino sold their share of Kea (half the island) to Ruggiero Premarin.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELoenertz1975126-14">[14]</ref> In 1331/32, Bartholomew reverted to an hostile attitude toward the Catalans (perhaps partly because of the dismissal of Alfonso Fadrique from the post of vicar-general) and backed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_VI,_Count_of_Brienne">Walter VI of Brienne</ref> in his abortive attempt to enforce his ancestral claims on the Duchy of Athens.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELoenertz1975154–156-15">[15]</ref> It was precisely in order to avoid the Castle of Saint Omer falling in Brienne's hands that the Catalans destroyed it.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1976156_note_60-11">[11]</ref> According to the prologue of the French version of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chronicle_of_the_Morea">Chronicle of the Morea</ref></hi>, it derives from a prototype that Bartholomew held at the Castle of Saint Omer. It is therefore likely that Bartholomew owned be the original version of the <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi>, whose versions in various languages are the major primary source about the history of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frankish_Greece">Frankish Greece</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESetton1976156–157-16">[16]</ref></p>
<p>Bartholomew II Ghisi died in 1341.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBon1969241-6">[6]</ref></p>
</text>
