<text id="autogum_bio_doc729" title="Henry of Masovia" shortTile="henry-masovia" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-09-25" dateModified="2019-03-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_of_Masovia" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Henry of Masovia</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Henry of Masovia</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polish_language">Polish</ref>: <hi lang="pl" rend="italic">Henryk mazowiecki</hi>) (1368/1370–1392/1393) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nobility">noble</ref> and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop">bishop</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Poland_(1385–1569)">Kingdom of Poland</ref>.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Henry of Masovia, born between 1368 and 1370 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rawa_Mazowiecka">Rawa Mazowiecka</ref> was the youngest child of one of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piast_dynasty">Piast dynasty</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince">princes</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masovia">Masovia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siemowit_III_of_Masovia">Siemowit III of Masovia</ref>, and his second wife, the princess of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ziębice">Ziębice</ref>, Anna (or Ludmiła, sources vary). His childhood was rather tragic, as described by several contemporary chroniclers, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janko_z_Czarnkowa">Janko z Czarnkowa</ref>, although as the facts vary depending on the chronicle, it is assumed parts of that story became dramatised in the years that passed. According to Janko z Czarnkowa, when Anna became pregnant, Siemowit accused her of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adultery">adultery</ref> and imprisoned her in the castle. After the birth of Henry, despite weak evidence, Siemowit ordered his wife strangled and the boy cast away from his court, and raised by a peasant family.</p>
<p>After several years, Siemowit's daughter from his first marriage, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret_of_Masovia">Margareta</ref>, then wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casimir_IV_of_Pomerania">Casimir IV of Pomerania</ref>, decided to rescue her brother and took him to her mansion in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Słupsk">Słupsk</ref>. Eventually, when Henry was about 10 years old and it became evident he was physically very similar to Siemowit, the latter accepted him back as his son. Siemowit, who had already divided his estates among his other sons in his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Last_will">last will</ref>, decided that Henry should become a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Priest">priest</ref>. Nonetheless, possibly driven by feelings of guilt, he convinced his other sons to agree that if Henry would ever abandon the way of priesthood, they would share his inheritance with him.</p>
<p>Eventually all indicated that Henry would become a priest. On 30 May 1378, he received a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parish">parish</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Płock">Płock</ref>. A few years later Siemowit, who wanted Henry to obtain a parish in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Łęczyca">Łęczyca</ref>, became involved in a conflict with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_Gniezno">archbishop of Gniezno</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janusz_Suchywilk">Janusz Suchywilk</ref>, who had already given that parish to one of his supporters. Siemowit did not accept this and, as the Polish kingdom was weakened and in a state of disarray after the death of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_of_Poland">King of Poland</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_I_of_Hungary">Louis I of Hungary</ref>), he took control of the disputed parish with his army and occupied it for several years.</p>
<p>On 18 March 1390, Henry, thanks to the efforts of his father and brothers (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janusz_I,_Duke_of_Masovia">Janusz I, Duke of Masovia</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siemowit_IV,_Duke_of_Masovia">Siemowit IV, Duke of Masovia</ref>), became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Płock">bishop of Płock</ref>, even though he had not received the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Orders">Holy Orders</ref> of priesthood, as required for that position, and refused to accept ordination.</p>
<p>In 1391, Henry, who was known both for his incredible strength and his diplomatic skills, accepted a mission from the hands of the king of Poland, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Władysław_Jagiełło">Władysław Jagiełło</ref>. Jagiełło asked him to convince his brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vytautas_the_Great">Vytautas</ref>, who at that time opposed Władysław's rise to power, to distance himself from his allies — the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teutonic_Knights">Teutonic Knights</ref>, enemies of the Kingdom of Poland (and her ally, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Duchy_of_Lithuania">Grand Duchy of Lithuania</ref>). Henry was successful in convincing Vytautas to abandon the Knights (see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ostrów_Agreement">Ostrów Agreement</ref>), and even more, became friends with Vytautas, who decided to marry him off to his sister, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ryngałła">Ryngałła</ref>.</p>
<p>The marriage led to many repercussions. Henry, by becoming married, had violated his status in minor orders and this became one of the arguments used by the Teutonic Knights to claim that Lithuania and Poland were not really <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christians">Christian</ref> and, as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pagan">pagans</ref>, could be attacked as enemies of Christianity. Further, Henry died in 1392 or 1393 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Łuck">Łuck</ref>, resulting in controversial claims — never verified or disproven — that he was assassinated by the Teutonic Knights (in revenge for luring away their ally, Vytautas), by his brothers (who decided not to share his father's inheritance with him once he abandoned the priesthood), or finally by his own wife, Ryngałła, who was later proven guilty of murdering her second husband. Henry was buried in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cathedral_of_Płock">Cathedral of Płock</ref>.</p>
</text>
