<text id="autogum_bio_doc064" title="Marcia Pally" shortTile="marcia-pally" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-03-16" dateModified="2019-05-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcia_Pally" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Marcia Pally</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Marcia Pally</hi> is an American professor  who teaches at New York University (adjunct)</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Professor <hi rend="bold">Marcia Pally</hi> teaches at New York University (adjunct),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> at Fordham University,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> and is a regular guest professor at the Theology Faculty of Humboldt University zu Berlin.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Her most recent books are <hi rend="italic">Commonwealth and Covenant: Economics, Politics, and Theologies of Relationality</hi> (Eerdmans, 2016)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> and <hi rend="italic">The New Evangelicals: Expanding the Vision of the Common Good</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> (in German: <hi rend="italic">Die neuen Evangelikalen: Freiheitsgewinne durch fromme Politik</hi>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Commonwealth and Covenant</hi> has been selected by the United Nations Committee on Education for Justice “to be distributed in their materials to “educators, academics, policy-makers, parents, students, teacher training institutes, and curriculum developers throughout the world” and it was nominated for a Grawemeyer Award in religion. </p>
<p>Pally's research interests include religion, culture, and politics as well as the intersection of language and culture. During the 1990s, she wrote in critique of government censorship in such works as <hi rend="italic">Sense and Censorship</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> but has stepped away from legal questions in recent years. </p>
<p>Pally spoke at the World Economic Forum<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> in 2010 and has been awarded the prestigious Mercator Guest Professorship (German Research Foundation)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> as well as grants from the German Academic Exchange Service, from the Fritz Thyssen Foundation and the Telos/Paul Piccone Institute. In addition, she is the co-recipient of a German Research Foundation grant to compare the political ethics and activism of American and German evangelicals, the only study of its kind.</p>
<p>In 2007 and 2010, she was a Fellow at the Institute for Advanced Study in Berlin (Wissenschaftskolleg zu Berlin)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> . She earned her doctorate from New York University in 1995.</p>
<head>Author</head>
<p>In addition to her academic work, Prof. Pally has been a columnist in the U.S. and Europe for over 20 years, writing for Religion and Ethics, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> Commonweal,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> and Religion News Service,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref>, among other periodicals. She has published one opinion piece in The New York Times,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> two comments in The Guardian,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> and columns in Internationale Politik (German Council on Foreign Relations,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref> Die Zeit,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref> Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung, Süddeutsche Zeitung, Tageszeitung,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref> Berliner Zeitung,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref> and Frankfurter Rundschau,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-20">[20]</ref> among other publications.</p>
<p>Marcia Pally has given lectures at many universities and professional associations, among them Oxford, The University of Chicago, Harvard, Columbia University, Telos Institute, Humboldt University (Berlin), The Free University-Berlin, The University of Zurich, Eidgenössische Technische Hochschule, Ruhr University-Bochum, Bielefeld University, The Cato Institute, the Aspen Institute-Berlin.</p>
<p>In the field of language acquisition, Pally was the editor of <hi rend="italic">Sustained Content-Based Teaching in Academic ESL/EFL</hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-21">[21]</ref> for which she also wrote several chapters. She is the author of <hi rend="italic">Screening English: Studying Movies for Reading, Writing, and Critical Thinking</hi> (1997, Pearson Press). Other articles in that field have appeared in <hi rend="italic">Language and Education, the Journal of Adolescent and Adult Literacy, Journal of Second Language Writing, and Journal of Basic Writing.</hi></p>
<head>Selective bibliography</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=3k1oCwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=inauthor:%22Marcia+Pally%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiik4eOpu_SAhWiwlQKHYcUAqYQ6AEIIDAB#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">Commonwealth and Covenant: Economics, Politics, and Theologies of Relationality</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=XSIoKQEACAAJ&amp;dq=inauthor:%22Marcia+Pally%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiik4eOpu_SAhWiwlQKHYcUAqYQ6AEIHDAA">The New Evangelicals: Expanding the Vision of the Common Good</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=NWjYAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=inauthor:%22Marcia+Pally%22&amp;dq=inauthor:%22Marcia+Pally%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiik4eOpu_SAhWiwlQKHYcUAqYQ6AEIPDAG">Die hintergründige Religion: der Einfluss des Evangelikalismus auf Gewissensfreiheit, Pluralismus und die US-amerikanische Politik</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://www.amazon.com/Sustained-Content-Teaching-Academic-Esl/dp/B01F827JAS/ref=sr_1_1">Sustained Content-teaching</ref></item></list>
</text>
