<text id="autogum_bio_doc651" title="Francesco I Gattilusio" shortTile="francesco-gattilusio" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-12" dateModified="2018-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francesco_I_Gattilusio" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Francesco I Gattilusio</head><figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Billon_(alloy)">Billon</ref> <hi rend="italic">denaro</hi> of Francesco I, showing the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_Emperor">Byzantine Emperor</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetragrammatic_cross">tetragrammatic cross</ref> as a sign of his vassal status.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Francesco I Gattilusio</hi> (died 6 August 1384) was the first member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gattilusio">Gattilusio</ref> family to rule the Aegean island of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lesbos">Lesbos</ref> as vassal of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_emperor">Byzantine emperor</ref>.</p>
<head>Freebooter</head>
<p>The Gattilusio family came from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_of_Genoa">Republic of Genoa</ref>. The parents of Francesco and his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niccolò_Gattilusio,_Lord_of_Ainos">Niccolò</ref> are not known, although based on the heraldic evidence of their inscriptions, Anthony Luttrell argues that their mother was a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doria_(family)">Doria</ref> family.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Francesco enters historical record as a freebooter or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pirate">pirate</ref>. In 1354, Francesco and his crew landed on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bozcaada_(Tenedos)">Tenedos</ref>. The island served at the time as residence to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_V_Palaiologos">John V Palaiologos</ref>, one of three co-emperors to the throne of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_Empire">Byzantine Empire</ref>, the others being his father-in-law <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_VI_Kantakouzenos">John VI Kantakouzenos</ref> and brother-in-law <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_Kantakouzenos">Matthew Kantakouzenos</ref>. John V and his in-laws were in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_civil_war_of_1352–1357">conflict</ref> at the time.</p>
<p>John V and Francesco entered an alliance to enable John to regain control of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref>. In return he would be given the hand of Maria Palaiologina, a sister of John V, in marriage.</p>
<p>In early December 1354, Francesco led a fleet to Constantinople. They approached the city late at night and pretended that they were in need of assistance. They claimed that one of their ships was sinking and requested help in salvaging the cargo from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shipwreck">shipwreck</ref>, and promised a share of it to the sentries of the city for their help. Seeing a chance to profit, the sentries opened a gate. Francesco then led about five hundred armed men through the gate, took command of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walls_of_Constantinople">Walls of Constantinople</ref> and roused the citizens from their sleep with shouts in favor of John V. Riots in favor of John V soon started. By 4 December 1354, John VI resigned his title and retired to a monastery.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Lord</head>
<p>Francesco had managed to regain control of the capital for John V and removed his main rival from the political field. John V completed their agreement by making Francesco his brother-in-law.</p>
<p>On 17 July 1355, Francesco was further rewarded by the title of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archon">Archon</ref> (Lord) of Lesbos. John V had offered him the island as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dowry">dowry</ref> for his sister.</p>
<p>In 1366, Francesco joined with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amadeus_VI,_Count_of_Savoy">Amadeus VI, Count of Savoy</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_I_of_Hungary">Louis I of Hungary</ref> in a campaign to restore the stability of the Byzantine Empire. Together they captured <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gallipoli">Gallipoli</ref> from  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murad_I">Murad I</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman Empire</ref> after two days of fighting.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In 1369, Francesco accompanied John V on his trip to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rome">Rome</ref>, along with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demetrios_Kydones">Demetrios Kydones</ref>, which concluded with John V personally accepting the Catholic faith on Thursday 18 October, in an unsuccessful effort to attract Western support for the greatly weakened Empire.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>On 6 August 1384, an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earthquake">earthquake</ref> affected Lesbos. Francesco I, Maria and their two eldest sons, Andronico and Domenico, were all killed. In a letter he wrote from Constantinople soon after the event, Kydones describes how the two dead sons' prospective brides arrived from afar and searched among the ruins for the bodies of the intended husbands they had never seen.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> However the third son Jacopo survived and succeeded in the rule of Lesbos under the name <hi rend="italic">Francesco II</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Children</head>
<p>Francesco and Maria Palaiologina had three known children:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Andronico Gattilusio (c. 1356 – 6 August 1384).</item>
<item>Domenico Gattilusio (c. 1358 – 6 August 1384).</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francesco_II_Gattilusio">Francesco II Gattilusio</ref> (c. 1365 – 26 October 1404).</item></list>
</text>
