<text id="autogum_bio_doc681" title="Theodora Kantakouzene (wife of Alexios IV of Trebizond)" shortTile="theodora-kantakouzene" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-07-01" dateModified="2019-06-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodora_Kantakouzene_%28wife_of_Alexios_IV_of_Trebizond%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Theodora Kantakouzene (wife of Alexios IV of Trebizond)</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Theodora Kantakouzene Megale Komnene</hi> (died 12 November 1426) was the Empress consort of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexios_IV_of_Trebizond">Alexios IV of Trebizond</ref>. Said to be very beautiful, according to the chronicle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laonikos_Chalkokondyles">Laonikos Chalkokondyles</ref> she was accused by her son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_IV_of_Trebizond">John Megas Komnenos</ref>, of having an affair with the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protovestiarios">protovestiarios</ref></hi> of the court of Trebizond; however, other accounts describe her as a faithful and loving wife, who kept the peace between Alexios and his sons. In either case, during her lifetime their son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_IV_of_Trebizond">John</ref> fled to Georgia and did not return until after Theodora's death.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Theodora's parentage is described by the Byzantinist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald_Nicol">Donald Nicol</ref> as "obscure". The <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecthesis_Chronica">Ecthesis Chronica</ref></hi> implies she was the daughter of a holder of the military rank of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protostrator">protostrator</ref></hi>, and Nicol notes there are chronological grounds against identifying her father with one Manuel Kantakouzenos who was sent on a diplomatic mission to Sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mehmet_I">Mehmet I</ref> in the winter of 1420-1421.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nicol-168-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>However, Thierry Ganchou has provided evidence that indicates Theodora was the oldest daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodore_Kantakouzenos">Theodore Palaiologos Kantakouzenos</ref>, uncle of emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manuel_II_Palaiologos">Manuel II Palaiologos</ref>, and Euphrosyne Palaiologina, and names her brothers in order of birth as Demetrios, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protostrator">protostrator</ref></hi> Manuel, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Palaiologos_Kantakouzenos">George</ref>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Megas_domestikos">megas domestikos</ref></hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andronikos_Palaiologos_Kantakouzenos">Andronikos</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Kantakouzenos">Thomas</ref>. He argues that this evidence was ignored due to undue reliance on the writings of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodore_Spandounes">Theodore Spandounes</ref>, who wrote long after more reliable contemporary sources.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref> around 1382, Theodora was only thirteen when she became in 1395, the consort of the co-emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexios_IV_of_Trebizond">Alexios IV of Trebizond</ref>, who was approximately the same age. She became ruling empress when her husband became sole emperor in Trebizond at the death of her father-in-law the emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manuel_III_of_Trebizond">Manuel III</ref>, in 1417.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nicol-168-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>A passage in the <hi rend="italic">History</hi> of Chalkokondyles states that Theodora became the mistress of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protovestiarios">protovestiarios</ref></hi> of the court of Trebizond, an act of adultery which provoked her son, John IV, to murder the official then imprison his parents in the palace. His parents were rescued by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archon">archons</ref> of the city who sent John into exile in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Georgia">Georgia</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> However this passage is considered to be one of several interpolations into Chalkokondyles' <hi rend="italic">History</hi>; a scribe in one line of the text's transmission notes the difference in style, adding a note at the beginning of the passage that "this seems to have been written by someone other than Laonikos", and at the end of the passage ends another note reading "from here on it is Laonikos".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> Further, the story is contradicted by the chronology and other sources. It may be the writer of this story has confused with an earlier affair between a member of the imperial dynasty of Trebizond and a <hi rend="italic">protovestiarios</hi>, namely Manuel III, the father-in-law of Theodora.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> This scandal is reported by the Spanish traveller <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruy_Gonzáles_de_Clavijo">Ruy Gonzáles de Clavijo</ref>, who visited Trebizond in 1404 not long after the event. He adds that this scandalous relationship induced the young Alexios IV, Theodora's husband, to rebel against his father Manuel.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>Manuel III died on 5 March 1417. Alexios IV succeeded him with Theodora as his Empress consort. She remained Empress for nearly a decade to her own death at the third hour of the night. Theodora was buried in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_Theotokos_Chrysokephalos">Church of Theotokos Chrysokephalos</ref> in the cemetery of Gidon with the other Emperors of Trebizond.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>It appears that it was only after the death of Theodora (1426) that John IV rebelled against his father, because his late mother could no longer mediate the increasing rivalry between father and son. On the contrary, the virtue, the piety, and the fidelity of Theodora are celebrated by her compatriot, the scholar <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basilios_Bessarion">Basilios Bessarion</ref>, in the three <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monodies">monodies</ref> he dedicated to his benefactress, and in a special discourse of consolation addressed to Alexios IV, devastated by the death of his beloved empress. Last but not least, John IV himself, after his accession to the throne in 1429, paid homage to the virtues of his deceased mother in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chrysobull">chrysobull</ref> benefiting the convent she founded.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Children</head>
<p>Theodora married Emperor Alexios IV with whom she had five known children:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_IV_of_Trebizond">John IV of Trebizond</ref> (c. 1403–1460).</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_of_Trebizond">Maria of Trebizond</ref> (c. 1404–1439); married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_VIII_Palaiologos">John VIII Palaiologos</ref>.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_of_Trebizond">Alexander of Trebizond</ref>, co-emperor with his father; married Maria Gattilusio, a daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dorino_of_Lesbos">Dorino of Lesbos</ref>.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_of_Trebizond">David of Trebizond</ref> (c. 1408–1463).</item>
<item>A daughter, who married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jahan_Shah">Jahan Shah</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kara_Koyunlu">Kara Koyunlu</ref></item></list>
</text>
