<text id="autogum_bio_doc234" title="William Lucombe" shortTile="william-lucombe" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-06-04" dateModified="2019-08-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Lucombe" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>William Lucombe</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">William Lucombe</hi> (before 1720 – after 1785) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Horticulturalist">horticulturalist</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nurseryman">nurseryman</ref>, who discovered and gave his name to the natural hybrid Lucombe Oak (<hi rend="italic">Quercus × hispanica</hi> 'Lucombeana'), a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semi-deciduous">semi-deciduous</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oak_tree">oak tree</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>The Lucombe nursery</head>
<p>William Lucombe began his horticultural career as Head Gardener in the service of merchant Thomas Ball at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mamhead_Park">Mamhead Park</ref> circa 1720. It was while working at Mamhead that he founded his nursery, the first commercial <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plant_nursery">plant nursery</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southwest_England">southwest England</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Harvey-3">[3]</ref> marketing many of the plants collected by Ball during the latter's commercial travels abroad, most famously the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quercus_ilex">Holm Oak</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Stroud-4">[4]</ref>
Lucombe bred his eponymous oak at his nursery in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Thomas,_Exeter">St Thomas</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exeter">Exeter</ref>, which he founded in 1720. In 1794, his son John Lucombe took possession of the nursery on Alphington Road, later known as the Exeter Nursery. In 1801, Benjamin Pince became a partner in the business, and by 1807 the nursery enterprise was trading as 'John Lucombe, Pince &amp; Co'. At this time they bought the adjoining nursery of William Ford and Son on Alphington Street. In 1824, John Lucombe sold the business to Captain Robert Pince for £1500. The nursery flourished under his son Robert Taylor Pince, but began to decline in the late 19th century, and the site was sold to the city of Exeter in 1912. Part of the land became Pinces Gardens, a public park, part allotments and the remainder housing.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Wood-5">[5]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>Main trunk of the Lucombe Oak at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kew_Gardens">Kew Gardens</ref>.</caption></figure>
<head>Lucombe Oaks</head>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_hybrid">natural hybrid</ref> Lucombe Oak was first spotted in 1762 when Lucombe noticed that one of the saplings produced from a Turkey Oak acorn he had planted kept its leaves in winter.  He later observed that these features occurred where both parent species grew, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quercus_cerris"><hi rend="italic">Quercus cerris</hi> (Turkey Oak)</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quercus_suber"><hi rend="italic">Quercus suber</hi> (Cork Oak)</ref>. True Lucombe Oaks are clones of the original tree, but the name 'Lucombe Oak' is also often used to refer to any <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quercus_×_hispanica">Spanish Oak</ref>, a frequently occurring hybrid between Turkey Oaks and Cork Oaks.
A large semi-evergreen tree developing a deeply furrowed bark when mature. Leaves to about 12 x 5cm, glossy dark green above, grey beneath and edged with sharp teeth. Raised at the Lucombe nursery, Exeter from seed of Q. cerris in about 1763. It produces viable seed and many seedlings of it have been distributed.</p>
<p>One of the early Lucombe Oaks went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Botanic_Gardens,_Kew">Kew Gardens</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> Lucombe Oaks along with their descendants, which include back crosses with the naturalised Turkey Oak, are common in the landscape of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_Devon">East Devon</ref>, as well as in parks and gardens. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tree_Register_of_the_British_Isles">Tree Register of the British Isles</ref>−TROBI Champion is at Phear Park in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exmouth">Exmouth</ref>, measuring 26 metres (85ft) in height, with a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diameter_at_breast_height">trunk diameter</ref> of 261 centimetres (103in) in 2008.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref>&gt;</p>
<p>Lucombe felled the original hybrid in 1785, keeping timber from it from which his coffin was to be made when he died. He stored the boards under his bed. However, he lived, for the age, an exceptionally long life, dying at the age of 102 years. By that time the planks had decayed in the Devon dampness.  Instead, on his death, timber from one of his early graft propagations was used to make his coffin.</p>
<p><ref target="http://www.oaksofchevithornebarton.com/detail.cfm/plant_id/1623">http://www.oaksofchevithornebarton.com/detail.cfm/plant_id/1623</ref></p>
</text>
