<text id="autogum_bio_doc087" title="Karen Kane" shortTile="karen-kane" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-08-24" dateModified="2019-04-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karen_Kane" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Karen Kane</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Karen Kane</hi> is an American <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fashion_designer">fashion designer</ref>. Her designs are known for their relaxed, California-inspired feeling.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Personal life</head>
<p>Kane was born in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Akron,_Ohio">Akron</ref> suburb <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barberton,_Ohio">Barberton, Ohio</ref>, the youngest of three children.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> At the age of 9, her family moved from Ohio to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Barbara,_California">Santa Barbara, California</ref>, where she grew up sewing and taking as many fashion-related classes as possible.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> Today, Kane lives in Los Angeles with her husband, Lonnie, and runs her namesake clothing company out of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vernon,_California">Vernon, California</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Karen Kane started her career in fashion when she graduated from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fashion_Institute_of_Design_&amp;_Merchandising">Fashion Institute of Design &amp; Merchandising</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los_Angeles">Los Angeles</ref> at the age of 19. Her first job was as a pattern maker at a junior sportswear company. It was there that she met her husband and future business partner, Lonnie.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> In 1979, Karen and Lonnie married and launched the Karen Kane womenswear collection out of their Studio City garage.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> Initially, the brand was sold only at smaller specialty stores, but as the line expanded, it was picked up by department stores like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macy’s">Macy’s</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belk">Belk</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloomingdales">Bloomingdales</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dillard’s">Dillard’s</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_&amp;_Taylor">Lord &amp; Taylor</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nordstrom">Nordstrom</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Von_Maur">Von Maur</ref>. The line continues to be sold at each of these retailers, as well as online retailers such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon.com">Amazon</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zappos">Zappos</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stitch_Fix">Stitch Fix</ref>, and large national specialty stores. Kane's clothing is most well known for having an easy, relaxed style that is reflective of her native <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California">California</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> Her corporate mission statement reads: "We believe women should feel beautiful and comfortable, always. We create products with passion and integrity, guided by respect for our people and planet."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>Kane has been noted as a leader of the American <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Insourcing">Insourcing</ref> movement. In 2012, she was invited to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_House">White House</ref> to attend US President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>'s "Insourcing American Jobs" summit and later that year, US Trade Representative <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demetrios_Marantis">Demetrios Marantis</ref> toured Kane's headquarters in California to learn more about the challenges of domestically manufacturing apparel in the United States.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> In 2011, 80% of Kane’s line was made in the United States and 20% was imported from other countries.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> In Spring 2012, that percentage increased to 90%.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> As of Fall 2013, Kane continued to manufacture most of her collection in the United States (primarily in Southern California).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref></p>
<p>In addition to her namesake collection, Kane also designs 'Karen by Karen Kane,' which includes casual, activewear-inspired items.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref>  In addition, Kane also produces a plus size division of the lifestyle collection entitled Karen Kane Women’s. In 2013, Kane added a sixth division to her company: Robert Michaels. Named for her two sons (Michael<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref> &amp; Robert), the collection consists of knit dresses, tops, and sweaters, and is sold exclusively at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloomingdale's">Bloomingdale's</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref></p>
<p>Kane also designs a contemporary label. In 2008, she launched Fifteen Twenty, which was a collection of assorted separates primarily made of silk. The brand has been worn by celebrities such as Reese Witherspoon,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref> Jessica Biel,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-20">[20]</ref> Carrie Underwood,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-21">[21]</ref> Jessica Alba,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-22">[22]</ref> Rosie Huntington-Whiteley,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-23">[23]</ref> Alessandra Ambrosio,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-24">[24]</ref> and others. Fifteen Twenty is sold in high-end specialty stores and online boutiques such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neiman_Marcus">Neiman Marcus</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rent_The_Runway">Rent The Runway</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloomingdales">Bloomingdales</ref>. In 2011, Kane introduced a casual complement to her Fifteen Twenty line entitled Red 23. “The line of T-shirts, tank tops, sweaters, jackets and scarves in neutral colors…will be carried by high-end <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Specialty_store">specialty stores</ref>.”<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-25">[25]</ref> In 2015, Red 23 was absorbed into Fifteen Twenty to broaden the main brand into a larger collection. Today, Fifteen Twenty is a full collection of tops, jackets, dresses, skirts, and pants.</p>
<p>In 2013, Kane selected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IMG_(company)">IMG (company)</ref> to represent the brand in developing licensed products.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-26">[26]</ref> Kane's eyewear collection has become one of the most successful licenses for its manufacturer, ROI.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-27">[27]</ref></p>
<head>Family</head>
<figure><caption>Karen, pictured with her husband Lonnie, and son Michael, in her Los Angeles design studio, 2017</caption></figure>
<p>Unlike most other designers of her generation, Kane chose not to sell the rights to her brand; her company continues to be privately owned and family operated.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-28">[28]</ref> In addition to his role as president of Karen Kane, Kane's husband, Lonnie, currently serves as the Chairman of the California Fashion Association.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-29">[29]</ref> Karen and Lonnie's older son, Michael, serves as the brand's Director of Marketing. Their younger son, Robert, attended <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parsons_School_of_Design">Parsons School of Design</ref> between 2012-2016. In 2010, he designed a line of t-shirts that appeared in the 'Karen by Karen Kane' summer collection.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-30">[30]</ref></p>
</text>
