<text id="autogum_bio_doc722" title="Robert Tresilian" shortTile="robert-tresilian" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-23" dateModified="2019-10-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Tresilian" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Robert Tresilian</head>
<figure><caption>The execution of Robert Tresilian, from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Froissart">Jean Froissart</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Froissart's_Chronicles"><hi rend="italic">Chroniques</hi></ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sir Robert Tresilian</hi> (died 1388) was a Cornish lawyer, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief_Justice_of_the_King's_Bench">Chief Justice of the King's Bench</ref> between 1381 and 1387. He was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cornwall">Cornwall</ref>, and held land in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tresillian">Tresillian</ref>, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Truro">Truro</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-1">[1]</ref> Tresilian was deeply involved in the struggles between King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_II_of_England">Richard II</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lords_Appellant">Lords Appellant</ref>, and was eventually executed for his loyalty to the king.</p>
<head>Early career and the Peasants' Revolt</head>
<p>Tresilian appears in the records for the first time in 1354. His early career took place in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxfordshire">Oxfordshire</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berkshire">Berkshire</ref>; in 1367 he was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justice_of_the_Peace">Justice of the Peace</ref> (JP) in Berkshire and in 1368 in Oxfordshire. He also worked in his home county; in 1369 he was recorded as acting counsel in a Cornish assizes case, was also returned to that year's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_England">parliament</ref> as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knight_of_the_Shire">Knight of the Shire</ref> for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cornwall_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">same county</ref>, and in 1370 was a JP for Cornwall.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-1">[1]</ref> In the 1370s he began working in royal administration, and in 1378 he was made a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justice_of_the_King's_Bench">Justice of the King's Bench</ref>. Shortly after he was also <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knight">knighted</ref>. When Chief Justice Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Cavendish">John Cavendish</ref> was killed in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peasants'_Revolt">Peasants' Revolt</ref> in 1381, Tresilian was appointed to take over the position.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>After the rebellion was over, Tresilian was put in charge of punishing the rebels and did so extremely harshly. He followed King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_II_of_England">Richard II</ref> into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Essex">Essex</ref>, where he led what was described as a 'bloody assize' against the rebels.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> He pressured jurors into giving up names of suspects,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> and to maximise sentences, contrived to have charges presented as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Felony">felonies</ref> rather than <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trespass">trespasses</ref>. All in all nineteen men were hanged, while another twelve were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanged,_drawn_and_quartered">hanged and drawn</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> There was a widespread belief in the localities that royal retribution had gone too far, and that reform of government was necessary as well as punishing the rebels, to prevent further uprisings.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Political involvement and death</head>
<p>In the following years, Tresilian became increasingly involved in politics, as a loyal follower of the king. In November 1386 Parliament appointed a commission to review and control royal finances. The king resented this infringement of his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_prerogative">royal prerogative</ref> and, in the so-called 'questions to the judges', he received legal backing for the position that the commission was unlawful.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> It is largely assumed that it was Tresilian who drafted the 'questions', and thereby turned a political controversy into a legal dispute.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> The king's opponents went on the counterattack. On 17 November 1387 Tresilian was among a number of royal loyalists who were charged with treason by the group of noblemen known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lords_Appellant">Lords Appellant</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> When Tresilian's case came up for trial, he had gone into hiding and was not to be found, and was sentenced <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trial_in_absentia">in absentia</ref></hi>. Not long after he was discovered hiding in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanctuary#Sanctuary_in_medieval_law">sanctuary</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westminster">Westminster</ref>. He was dragged into court with cries of 'We have him!' from the mob and, as he was already convicted, was summarily executed, being hanged naked before his throat was cut.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Reputation and family</head>
<p>The charges against Tresilian had consisted of more than simply treason. He was a highly unpopular judge, and among his crimes was also corruption. Several cases were presented from Cornwall and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Devon">Devon</ref>, where the judge had abused his powers to advance his own fortune.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> Tresilian and his wife Emmaline (Emma) had a son, John, and at least two daughters. Through his marriage, but also through corrupt dealings, he acquired great tracts of land in Berkshire, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buckinghamshire">Buckinghamshire</ref>, Oxfordshire, and Cornwall. His land was forfeited at his death but, his son's objections notwithstanding, much of it was regained by John Hawley the elder, a merchant and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pirate">pirate</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dartmouth,_Devon">Dartmouth</ref> who purchased the estates from the Crown. His widow Emma married John Colshull of Cornwall MP.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>In the 1720s, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonathan_Swift">Jonathan Swift</ref>, in his vehement attack on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Whitshed">William Whitshed</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chief_Justice_of_Ireland">Lord Chief Justice of Ireland</ref>, cited Tresilian and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Scroggs">William Scroggs</ref> as examples of judicial corruption.</p>
</text>
