<text id="autogum_bio_doc779" title="John I Orsini" shortTile="john-orsini" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-07-09" dateModified="2016-10-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_I_Orsini" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John I Orsini</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">John I Orsini</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italian_language">Italian</ref>: <hi lang="it" rend="italic">Giovanni Orsini</hi>) was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Count_palatine_of_Cephalonia_and_Zakynthos">count palatine of Cephalonia and Zakynthos</ref> from 1303 or 1304 to his death in 1317. Married to an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despotate_of_Epirus">Epirote</ref> princess, John spent a decade at the Epirote court before succeeding his father, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Orsini">Richard Orsini</ref>, as count palatine. As a vassal of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principality_of_Achaea">Principality of Achaea</ref>, he was involved in its domestic affairs and especially the dynastic dispute between the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infante">infante</ref></hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinand_of_Majorca">Ferdinand of Majorca</ref> and Princess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matilda_of_Hainaut">Matilda of Hainaut</ref> in 1315–16, and participated in a number of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latinokratia">Latin</ref> campaigns against Epirus, which he aspired to rule. A year after his death, his son and heir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Orsini">Nicholas Orsini</ref> seized Epirus and brought it under the Orsini family's rule.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>John was the only son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Orsini">Richard Orsini</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Count_palatine_of_Cephalonia_and_Zakynthos">Count palatine of Cephalonia and Zakynthos</ref>, who in turn was the son of Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_Orsini">Matthew Orsini</ref> and a daughter of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sebastokrator">sebastokrator</ref></hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Komnenos_Doukas">John Komnenos Doukas</ref>, ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thessalonica">Thessalonica</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bon706-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In 1292, he was wed to Maria, the daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despot_(court_title)">Despot</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikephoros_I_Komnenos_Doukas">Nikephoros I Komnenos Doukas</ref>, ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despotate_of_Epirus">Epirus</ref>. Maria had been sent as a hostage to Cephalonia to ensure Nikephoros' loyalty to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latinokratia">Latin</ref> princes when Richard and forces from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principality_of_Achaea">Principality of Achaea</ref> campaigned in Epirus to help raise the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine">Byzantine</ref> siege of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ioannina">Ioannina</ref>. After the Byzantines were repelled, Richard, without consulting Nikephoros, arranged for John's marriage to Maria. This aroused the indignation of Nikephoros, who was not mollified until 1295, when the young couple came to live at his court. There John won his father-in-law's affection, to the extent that he granted him possession of the island of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leukas">Leucas</ref>—Richard had promised to, but probably never did, cede the nearby island of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ithaca">Ithaca</ref> to the couple as well. John and Maria remained at the Epirote court until the murder of Richard in 1303 or 1304.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>After Richard's death, John was immediately engaged in a legal battle with his stepmother, Richard's second wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret_of_Villehardouin">Margaret of Villehardouin</ref>, over his inheritance: Margaret claimed the fief of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katochi">Katochi</ref> in Epirus, as well as mobile property to the sum of 100,000 gold <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperpyron">hyperpyra</ref></hi> from Richard's possessions. Initially, John's suzerain, the Prince of Achaea <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_I_of_Piedmont">Philip of Savoy</ref>, found in his favour, especially after John paid him a "gift" of 3,656 pounds when he swore fealty to him on 7 April 1304. Margaret then sought the assistance of the powerful Marshal of Achaea, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_III_of_Saint_Omer">Nicholas III of Saint Omer</ref>, who was always ready to oppose the authoritarian government of Philip. In the end, after a violent quarrel between Nicholas and the Prince's supporters, a compromise was reached whereby John paid Margaret the sum of 20,000 <hi rend="italic">hyperpyra</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> The <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chronicle_of_the_Morea">Chronicle of the Morea</ref></hi> also reports another episode of quarrel between Saint Omer and John: Saint Omer was married to John's sister, Guillerme, but neglected her and kept her confined to her castle, until John arranged for one of his relatives, William Orsini, to abduct her by night and bring her to Cephalonia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>Soon after his accession, in summer 1304, John and Philip of Savoy were ordered by King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_II_of_Naples">Charles II of Naples</ref> to attack Epirus, where the Byzantine princess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna_Palaiologina_Kantakouzene">Anna Palaiologina Kantakouzene</ref>, mother and regent of the under-age Despot <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_I_Komnenos_Doukas">Thomas I Komnenos Doukas</ref>, had refused to re-affirm Epirote vassalage to Naples and made common cause with the Byzantine Empire. John campaigned in Epirus alongside a large Achaean contingent, but their siege of the Epirote capital, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arta,_Greece">Arta</ref>, failed and the allies withdrew. While Charles II remained determined to repeat the offensive next year, Anna managed to bribe Philip into staying in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morea">Morea</ref>. Philip refused to campaign on the pretext of holding a grand parliament at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corinth">Corinth</ref>, where all the barons and vassals of the Principality, including John, were assembled.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> As a result, Charles II deposed Philip of Savoy and transferred the Principality directly to his own son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_I_of_Taranto">Philip of Taranto</ref>. The new Prince launched another invasion of Epirus in 1307, which failed due to the outbreak of a disease among the Latin troops, but managed to wring some territorial concessions from Anna. According to the Aragonese version of the <hi rend="italic">Chronicle of the Morea</hi>, John not only participated in this second expedition but actively instigated it, perhaps in hopes of replacing Thomas as ruler of Epirus.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>In 1315, the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infante">infante</ref></hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinand_of_Majorca">Ferdinand of Majorca</ref> invaded the Morea and tried to seize the vacant princely throne in right of his wife, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabella_of_Sabran">Isabella of Sabran</ref>. Like most of the barons and vassals of Achaea, John supported him at first but switched back to the legitimate heir, Princess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matilda_of_Hainaut">Matilda of Hainaut</ref>, and her husband <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_of_Burgundy">Louis of Burgundy</ref>, when they arrived in the Morea in early 1316. In the decisive <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Manolada">Battle of Manolada</ref> on 5 July 1316, John led the first line of the loyalist army. Driven by rage over John's betrayal as well as his past mistreatment of Margaret of Villehardouin—Ferdinand's mother-in-law—the <hi rend="italic">infante</hi> launched a furious assault that broke through John's line, but was held by the second line under Louis. In the resulting mêlée, Ferdinand was killed and his supporters routed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> Barely a month later, Louis of Burgundy died at the age of 18, apparently of a disease. However, a pro-Catalan source asserts that Louis was poisoned by John.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref></p>
<p>John died in 1317, and was succeeded by his eldest son Nicholas, who in the very next year managed to turn his father's Epirote ambitions a reality: he murdered his uncle, the Despot Thomas, and assumed his place, bringing Epirus under Orsini rule.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>From his marriage with Maria Komnene Doukaina, John had four children:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bon706-1">[1]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Orsini">Nicholas Orsini</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_II_Orsini">John II Orsini</ref></item>
<item>Guy Orsini</item>
<item>Margaret, lady of one half of Zakynthos, married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guglielmo_Tocco">Guglielmo Tocco</ref></item></list>
</text>
