<text id="autogum_bio_doc743" title="Richeza of Sweden, Duchess of Poland" shortTile="richeza-sweden-duchess" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-02-02" dateModified="2019-05-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richeza_of_Sweden%2C_Duchess_of_Poland" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Richeza of Sweden, Duchess of Poland</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Richeza of Sweden</hi>  (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swedish_language">Swedish</ref>: <hi lang="sv" rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rikissa Valdemarsdotter</hi></hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polish_language">Polish</ref>: <hi lang="pl" rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Ryksa szwedzka</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Ryksa Waldemarówna</hi></hi>; born between 1265 and 1270 – died before 1292), was a Swedish princess member of the House of Bjelbo and by marriage Duchess of Greater Poland during 1285-1292 and High Duchess consort of Poland during 1290-1291.</p>
<p>She was a daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valdemar,_King_of_Sweden">Valdemar, King of Sweden</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sophia_of_Denmark">Sophia of Denmark</ref>, daughter of the King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric_IV_of_Denmark">Eric IV</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Her exact date of birth is unknown, but is generally placed as the third daughter and fifth child born of her parents' marriage (at all, they had seven children, two sons and five daughters). She was certainly born before 1273, because by that year she and her sister Katharina were considered for possible marriage with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto_II,_Duke_of_Brunswick-Lüneburg">Otto</ref>, only son and heir of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John,_Duke_of_Brunswick-Lüneburg">John, Duke of Brunswick-Lüneburg</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jasiński,_p._55-1">[1]</ref> However, the marriage negotiations ended without results.</p>
<p>In 1275, King Valdemar was deposed by his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnus_III_of_Sweden">Magnus</ref>, and a year later his wife Sophia divorced him and returned to Denmark. Apparently, young Richeza and her siblings remained in Sweden probably under the care of their father.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[lower-alpha 1]</ref> Her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marriage_by_proxy">marriage by proxy</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Przemysł_II">Przemysł II</ref>, Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greater_Poland">Greater Poland</ref>, took place in the Swedish city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nyköping">Nyköping</ref> on 11 October 1285. In the same ceremony, Richeza's younger sister Marianne (or Marina), was married to a German nobleman, Count Rudolph II of Diepholz.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[2]</ref> Richeza's marriage, concluded through the mediation of the House of Ascania, rulers of Brandenburg, was performed without the consent of her father, ex-King Valdemar.</p>
<p>In the proxy marriage the Polish Duke was represented by the notary Tylon, one of his closest subjects.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jasiński,_p._55-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[3]</ref> There is no information about when and where the formal marriage took place between Przemysł II and Richeza.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Traditionally, Richeza and Przemysł II's marriage is described as happy. Their only child was born on 1 September 1288 in the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poznań">Poznań</ref>: a daughter, named <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_Richeza_of_Poland">Richeza</ref>, who later became in Queen consort of Bohemia and Poland as a wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslaus_II_of_Bohemia">Wenceslaus II</ref> and after his death, of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rudolf_I_of_Bohemia">Rudolph III of Habsburg</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[5]</ref></p>
<p>The news of the birth of her daughter was also the last information about Richeza. She certainly died between 1 September 1288 and before 13 April 1293,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Balzer,_p.432-7">[6]</ref> most likely between 1289-1292.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[7]</ref> The reports of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_Długosz">Jan Długosz</ref>, who placed her next to her husband in his royal coronation on 26 June 1295, proved to be erroneous.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Balzer,_p.432-7">[6]</ref></p>
<p>The deep and strong feelings of Przemysł II for Richeza are evidenced in two facts: firstly, he named their daughter after her, and secondly, he mentioned her in a document issued on 19 April 1293 where Przemysł II ceded to the Bishopric of Poznań the village of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kobylniki,_Poznań_County">Kobylniki</ref> as payment for a lamp lit eternally at Richeza's tomb, and also expressed his desire to be buried next to her.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[8]</ref></p>
<p>Richeza was buried in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archcathedral_Basilica_of_St._Peter_and_St._Paul,_Poznań">Archcathedral Basilica of St. Peter and St. Paul</ref> in Poznań. After Przemysł II's murder in 1296 and following his wishes, he was buried next to her.</p>
<head>Ancestors</head>
</text>
