<text id="autogum_bio_doc655" title="Cassone della Torre" shortTile="cassone-della-torre" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-06-19" dateModified="2019-04-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cassone_della_Torre" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cassone della Torre</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cassone della Torre</hi> (or <hi rend="italic">Casso</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Cassono</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Castone</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Gastone</hi>), also called <hi rend="bold">Mosca</hi> (died 20 August 1318) was an Italian medieval condottiero and feudal lord. A member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_della_Torre">Torriani</ref> family, he was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_Milan">Archbishop of Milan</ref> from 1308 to 1316 and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarch_of_Aquileia">patriarch of Aquileia</ref> from 1317 to 1318.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Cassone was the second son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corrado_della_Torre">Corrado della Torre</ref> and  grandson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Napo_della_Torre">Napo della Torre</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAndenna201573-1">[1]</ref> In his youth, he stayed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friuli">Friuli</ref>, then ruled by his grand-uncle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raimondo_della_Torre">Raimondo</ref> as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarch_of_Aquileia">patriarch of Aquileia</ref>: here most members of the family lived in exile from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milan">Milan</ref> after their arch-rival <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Visconti">House of Visconti</ref> had been able to seize the power in that city.</p>
<p>Cassone was appointed canon of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cividale_del_Friuli">Cividale</ref> in 1296. When the della Torre were able to return to Milan in 1302, Cassone was appointed canon of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cathedral_of_Milan">Cathedral of Milan</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1308 he succeeded Francesco da Parma as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_Milan">Archbishop of Milan</ref>, being elected by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chapter_(religion)">Chapter</ref> of the Cathedral, of Milan, confirmed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Clement_V">Pope Clement V</ref> and consecrated bishop in Milano by Ugaccione Borromeo bishop of Novara on about 12 October 1308.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fantoni-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>His appointment as Archbishop of Milano spurred a conflict with his cousin <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guido_della_Torre">Guido della Torre</ref>, who was afraid that Cassone could ally with the Visconti against him (two of the archbishop's brothers were married to nephews of Matteo Visconti's wife). In 1309 he took part to a successful papal military expedition against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_of_Venice">Republic of Venice</ref>, returning to Milan with great honors.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fantoni-2">[2]</ref> On 1 October 1309 Guido's troops attacked the archbishop's palace in Milan, and imprisoned him. On 29 October 1309 he was exiled from Milan. He moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bologna">Bologna</ref> where the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papal_legate">papal legate</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Excommunicated">excommunicated</ref> Guido della Torre.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cazzani-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VII,_Holy_Roman_Empire">Henry VII</ref> appointed Cassone mediator between the claims of the families <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_della_Torre">Torriani</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Visconti">Visconti</ref> who were in long conflict for ruling Milan. Cassone find an agreement between the two families but it was not accepted by Guido della Torre; Emperor Henry VII then forced Guido della Torre to flee from Milan and sold the title of imperial vicar for Milan to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matteo_I_Visconti">Matteo I Visconti</ref>. Cassone re-entered in Milan and on 6 January 1311 he crowned Henry VII as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Italy_(Holy_Roman_Empire)">King of Italy</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cazzani-3">[3]</ref> The debt due to the Emperor by the citizens of Milan created dissatisfaction and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torriani_revolt">the Torriani instigated a revolt</ref>, which was suppressed by the Visconti, supported by the soldiers of the Emperor. Cassone then fled from Milan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cazzani-3">[3]</ref> Following the sacking of the episcopal palace in Milan in 1314, he excommunicated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matteo_I_Visconti">Matteo I Visconti</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAndenna201575-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>On 31 December 1316 Cassone renounced the title of See of Milan, and was appointed as secular patriarch of Aquileia by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_John_XXII">pope John XXII</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAndenna201575-4">[4]</ref> However, he never took the post <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friuli">Friuli</ref> since he died in a fall from horse at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florence">Florence</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAndenna201575-4">[4]</ref> There he was buried in the church of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Croce,_Florence">Santa Florence</ref>; his funerary monument is attributed to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tino_da_Camaino">Tino da Camaino</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agostino_da_Siena">Agostino da Siena</ref>.</p>
</text>
