<text id="autogum_bio_doc513" title="Anjirō" shortTile="anjir" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-05-12" dateModified="2019-01-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anjir%C5%8D" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Anjirō</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Anjirō</hi>(アンジロー) or <hi rend="bold">Yajirō</hi>(弥次郎, ヤジロウ), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baptismal_name">baptized</ref> as <hi rend="bold">Paulo de Santa Fé</hi>, was the first recorded <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japanese_Christian">Japanese Christian</ref>, who lived in the 16th century. After committing a murder in his home  domain of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satsuma_Domain">Satsuma</ref> in southern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kyushu">Kyushu</ref>, he fled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portuguese_Malacca">Portuguese Malacca</ref> and he sought out Saint <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Xavier">Francis Xavier</ref> (1506–1552) and returned to Japan with him as an interpreter.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Moffett-1">[1]</ref> Along with Xavier, Anjirō returned to Japan with two other Jesuits, two Japanese companions, and a Chinese companion who had been <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baptism">baptized</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholicism">Catholicism</ref> to form the first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesuit">Jesuit</ref> mission to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Moffett-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Anjirō was originally a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samurai">samurai</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satsuma_Domain">Satsuma Domain</ref>, and was described to be "rich and of a noble extraction",<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-butler-2">[2]</ref> but he killed a man and was forced to go on the run. In the port of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kagoshima">Kagoshima</ref>, he met the Portuguese captain of a trading ship, Alvaro Vas, to whom he confessed his deed and described his hardships as an outlaw. Vas got him a job on a Portuguese ship, but Anjirō reported to the wrong ship and presented himself to Captain Jorge Álvares, a personal friend of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Xavier">Francis Xavier</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Álvares took him to Malacca to see Xavier since he felt Xavier was better suited to hear Anjirō's confession. Upon their arrival, however, they had discovered that Xavier had departed for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moluccas">Moluccas</ref>. Disappointed, Anjirō boarded a ship that would take him back to Japan, but it encountered a storm and had to take shelter on the Chinese coast. There, he met yet another Portuguese captain, who informed him that Xavier had returned to Malacca, and the captain took Anjirō back to Malacca, where he finally met Xavier in December 1547.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>With Xavier</head>
<p>Anjirō had picked up some <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pidgin">pidgin</ref> Portuguese by this time and could communicate with Xavier directly. The priest told Anjirō the word of God while Anjirō described the land of Japan to Xavier, which impressed the priest so much that he became resolved to go to Japan himself. Anjirō then went with Xavier to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goa">Goa</ref>, the headquarters of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portuguese_India">Portuguese India</ref> where he was baptized with the name Paulo de Santa Fé (Paul of the Holy Faith), furthered his training in the Portuguese language, and received <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catechesis">catechesis</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Paul's_College,_Goa">Saint Paul's College</ref>. On 14 April 1549, Xavier left Goa and made his way to Japan with a party of seven, including Anjirō as interpreter, and reached Malacca by 25 April.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> There, they boarded a Chinese pirate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Junk_(ship)">junk</ref> since that was the only craft they could book that would take them to Kagoshima.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head><hi rend="italic">Deus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Dainichi</hi></head>
<p>The party landed in Kagoshima on August 15, 1549 and soon attracted attention as foreigners who came all the way from India, or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenjiku">Tenjiku</ref>, which was where the Japanese understood as the birthplace of Buddhism. Anjirō gathered crowds by vividly describing his experiences in India, and even the Satsuma daimyo <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shimazu_Takahisa">Shimazu Takahisa</ref> became curious and sent for Anjirō and Xavier for an audience at his court.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> Xavier made a good impression on the young daimyo, who allowed his vassals to convert to Xavier's creed. At the time, the Japanese did not realize that Xavier was actually preaching a new religion different from Buddhism since he had come from India. The confusion was compounded by Anjirō's choice of using the term "Dainichi", the Japanese word for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vairocana_Buddha">Vairocana Buddha</ref>, to refer to the Christian God since he mistakenly assumed that Japan had only one creator God.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> Xavier eventually realized the mistake in the summer of 1551 when he was preaching in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yamaguchi,_Yamaguchi">Yamaguchi</ref>, far away from Satsuma. He used the Latin word "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deus">Deus</ref>" henceforth and denounced "Dainichi" as "an invention of the devil". The Buddhist monks, who initially respected Xavier, now resented him, forming an obstacle to the efforts of the Jesuits.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> Xavier acknowledged that Anjirō was uneducated in the written language (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classical_Chinese">Classical Chinese</ref>) and so could not read well enough to give evidence about the religious affairs of his homeland.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>Recently, the circumstances of Anjirō's translation have been complicated by scholars, including Jason Ānanda Josephson. Josephson notes that Anjirō's choice to translate <hi rend="italic">Deus</hi> as <hi rend="italic">Dainichi</hi> reflects earlier <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shingon_Buddhism">Shingon Buddhist</ref> means of coping with religious difference, with which Anjirō may have been familiar.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> Thus Anjirō's terminology may have represented an indigenous Japanese belief that "translation can  bridge  divergence."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref></p>
<head>After Xavier</head>
<p>After less than a year in Kagoshima, Xavier went to Kyoto in hopes of converting the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emperor_of_Japan">Emperor of Japan</ref> to Christianity so the whole nation would follow. He left Anjirō to lead the small congregation that they had managed to gather in Kagoshima.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> After Xavier returned from his unsuccessful endeavour in Kyoto, during which he realized both the Emperor of Japan and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ashikaga_shogun">Ashikaga shogun</ref> were powerless during the chaotic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sengoku_period">Sengoku period</ref> and their conversion would achieve nothing, he was recalled to Goa in 1552 and set his sights on China, dying on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shangchuan_Island">Shangchuan Island</ref> off its coast in the same year. After Xavier's departure from Japan, Anjirō's mission in Kagoshima became deserted in just two years, and Anjirō was driven out by religious persecution. He descended into piracy and died a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wokou">wakō pirate</ref> on a raid in China.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></p>
</text>
