<text id="autogum_bio_doc310" title="Oliver FitzWilliam, 1st Earl of Tyrconnell" shortTile="oliver-fitzwilliam" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-02-05" dateModified="2019-08-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oliver_FitzWilliam%2C_1st_Earl_of_Tyrconnell" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Oliver FitzWilliam, 1st Earl of Tyrconnell</head><p><hi rend="bold">Oliver FitzWilliam, 1st Earl of Tyrconnell</hi> (died 11 April 1667) was an Irish nobleman.</p>
<p>His father was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_FitzWilliam,_1st_Viscount_FitzWilliam">Thomas FitzWilliam, 1st Viscount FitzWilliam</ref> (1581-1650). His mother was Margaret Plunkett, daughter of Oliver Plunkett, 4th <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_Louth">Baron Louth</ref>; through his mother he was related to the powerful Bagenal family. As  a younger son he  did not expect to inherit the title or estates; like many young men in his position  he read law, studying at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gray's_Inn">Gray's Inn</ref>, and then resolved on a military career. With the help of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Butler,_1st_Duke_of_Ormonde">James Butler, 1st Duke of Ormonde</ref> he became a Colonel in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Army">French Army</ref> and showed both courage and military skill. On the death of his eldest  brother Richard he became heir to the title.</p>
<head>Civil War</head>
<p>He was both a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholic">Catholic</ref> and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cavalier">royalist</ref>, and enjoyed the confidence of  Queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henrietta_Maria">Henrietta Maria</ref>, who recommended him to Charles I as "a man deserving of every encouragement." In 1645 he tried to get the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confederation_of_Kilkenny">Confederation of Kilkenny</ref> to support <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_I_of_England">King Charles I</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Civil_War">English Civil War</ref> on the grounds that their demands for full civic  rights to be restored to Roman Catholics  would be met.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> He fought with the Confederates against the Parliamentarians in 1645–6, and led a successful assault on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roscommon_Castle">Roscommon Castle</ref> in 1646. In 1649 he was imprisoned in London but soon released. After some time in France he was allowed to return to England through the pleas of his brother-in-law <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Holles,_2nd_Earl_of_Clare">John Holles, 2nd Earl of Clare</ref>. He is said to have been one of the few Irishmen whom <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oliver_Cromwell">Oliver Cromwell</ref> admired, and was also on good terms with Oliver's  son  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Cromwell">Henry Cromwell</ref>, although Henry refused his request to be allowed to recover possession of  his principal residence,  Merrion Castle. During the Commonwealth he seems to have played a careful double  game- his second marriage into the Holles family put him in the Parliamentarian camp, but he was also suspected of working for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Restoration_of_Charles_II">Restoration of Charles II</ref>.</p>
<head>Restoration</head>
<p>At the Restoration he was in high favour at Court  and was made Earl of Tyrconnell. Whether for personal reasons or because his friendly relations with Henry Cromwell   had made him powerful enemies  at home, and despite a personal  plea  on his behalf by the King,  it was not until 1663 that he recovered all his properties. He devoted his last years to renovating Merrion Castle.</p>
<p>He died at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merrion_Castle">Merrion Castle</ref> on 11 April 1667, and was buried on 12 April 1667 in  the Fitzwilliam Chapel in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donnybrook,_Dublin">Donnybrook</ref> church. His widow,  Eleanor,   returned to England, and died   there in  1681.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>He married firstly  Dorothy Brereton of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malpas,_Cheshire">Malpas</ref>, a cousin of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_William_Brereton,_1st_Baronet">Sir William Brereton, 1st Baronet</ref>, (her sister Jane married Oliver's brother Christopher)
secondly a Miss Penruddock, and thirdly  Lady Eleanor Holles, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Holles,_1st_Earl_of_Clare">John Holles, 1st Earl of Clare</ref> and his wife Anne Stanhope.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>He had no issue by any of his  marriages.  On his death the Earldom of Tyrconnell became extinct, and the viscountcy passed to his brother William.</p>
</text>
