<text id="autogum_bio_doc157" title="Bob Broadhurst" shortTile="bob-broadhurst" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-04-16" dateModified="2019-09-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob_Broadhurst" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bob Broadhurst</head>
<figure><caption>Cmdr Bob Broadhurst</caption></figure>
<p>Commander <hi rend="bold">Robert James Broadhurst</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Officer_of_the_Order_of_the_British_Empire">OBE</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen's_Police_Medal">QPM</ref> was the 2012 Olympics <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gold_–_silver_–_bronze_command_structure">Gold Command</ref> for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan_Police_Service">Metropolitan Police Service</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> He was formerly Commander for Public Order and Pan London Operational Support of London's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan_Police_Service">Metropolitan Police Service</ref>.</p>
<head>Police career</head>
<p>Broadhurst has served with the Metropolitan Police Service for 32 years in uniform, primarily in South-East London. He was, for four years, Sutton Borough Commander and Lambeth deputy Borough Commander for a year.  For four years he was the Link Commander for South East London, with responsibility overall for all eight Boroughs in that area. In July 2006 he was appointed Commander <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan_Police_Public_Order_Operational_Command_Unit">Public Order</ref> and Pan London Operational Support.</p>
<p>He has experience as a hostage negotiator, during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stansted_Airport">Stansted Airport</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2006_Afghan_hijackers_case">Afghan Airlines hi-jack</ref> he was the Negotiator Team Leader.  At the longest siege in the UK, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hackney_Siege">Hackney Siege</ref>, which ended with the death of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eli_Hall">Eli Hall</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> he was the Gold Commander -operational chief officer,.  He speaks at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Siege_Management">National Siege Management</ref> courses, and has contributed to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FBI_Crisis_Negotiation_Unit">FBI Crisis Negotiator Course</ref> at the United States <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FBI_Academy">FBI Academy</ref>.</p>
<p>Since 1990 he has commanded public order events, including many large-scale demonstrations.  He commands ceremonial events such as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/State_Opening_of_Parliament">State Opening of Parliament</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trooping_the_Colour">Trooping the Colour</ref>. At the wedding of the Prince of Wales and the Duchess of Cornwall he was the Gold Commander. In 2007 he was in charge of policing for the London leg of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tour_de_France">Tour de France</ref> and for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008_Summer_Olympics_torch_relay">2008 Summer Olympics torch relay</ref>.  He is leading operational planning for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012_Olympics">2012 Olympics</ref>.
He was involved in policing the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_reaction_to_the_2008–2009_Israel–Gaza_conflict#Civilian_demonstrations_and_protests">2009 Gaza Protests</ref> in London.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Honours</head>
<p>In the 2005 Queens Birthday Honours list, Broadhurst was awarded the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen's_Police_Medal">Queen's Police Medal</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>He was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Officer_of_the_Order_of_the_British_Empire">Officer of the Order of the British Empire</ref> (OBE) in the 2013 Birthday Honours for services to the public order policing of the Olympics.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-gaz31712-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>G20 protests</head>
<p>He was in overall charge (Gold) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation_Glencoe">Operation Glencoe</ref>, during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2009_G-20_London_summit_protests">2009 G-20 London summit protests</ref>. On 9 April he said "The eyes of the world were focused on London. While it was extremely hard work, I am happy with the way the day progressed, as the overall mood of the event was good."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref>  With his team he faces questioning by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan_Police_Authority">Metropolitan Police Authority</ref> about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Death_of_Ian_Tomlinson">death of Ian Tomlinson</ref>, and also face questions about whether the stark warnings of violence he gave before the summit fuelled confrontation.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>He was accused of misleading MP's in a Select Committee report on the G20.  He incorrectly informed them that no undercover police officers were operating after an MP raised concerns about the use of agent provocateurs. Later it was revealed that 25 undercover officers were deployed and were mixing with demonstrators. Once this was revealed, Broadhurst claimed that the deployment of undercover officers was unknown to him, and that the plainclothes officers (some of whom were filmed with extended batons) were "evidence gatherers".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
</text>
