<text id="autogum_bio_doc526" title="Walter Chepman" shortTile="walter-chepman" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-10-14" dateModified="2019-06-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Chepman" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Walter Chepman</head>
<figure><caption> Walter Chepman was a patron of The High Kirk of Edinburgh, also known as Saint Giles' Cathedral.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Walter Chepman</hi> (d.1532) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish_people">Scottish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merchant">merchant</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Notary_public">notary</ref> and civil servant active in the late fifteenth and early sixteenth centuries. Chepman served at the Scottish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Court_(royal)">court</ref> during the reigns of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_IV_of_Scotland">James IV</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_V_of_Scotland">James V</ref>.
In partnership with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Androw_Myllar">Androw Myllar</ref> he established <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chepman_and_Myllar_Press">Scotland's first printing press</ref> in 1508.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-C_and_M_prints-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NLS_Breviary-2">[2]</ref> Chepman was also a significant patron of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Giles'_Cathedral">Saint Giles' Kirk</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<figure><caption>Memorial to Walter Chepman in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Giles'_Cathedral,_Edinburgh">St. Giles' Cathedral</ref> erected in 1879 by William Chambers LLD.</caption></figure>
<p>Chepman's first appearance in the historical record is in the accounts of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_High_Treasurer_of_Scotland">Lord High Treasurer of Scotland</ref> for 1494 in which he is recorded as receiving payment for clerical work at the royal court.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ALHTS-3">[3]</ref> He would continue to receive such payments for the remainder of his life.</p>
<p>The impression that Chepman was well-educated is supported by the fact that he acted as a notary in and around Edinburgh.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-4">[4]</ref> His service at court also suggests that he was trusted by King James IV. In 1503, to coincide with the King's marriage, James presented Chepman with a suit of clothes of English fabric.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ALHTS-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Walter Chepman traded in imported textiles and timber and regularly supplied goods to the King.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ALHTS-3">[3]</ref>
He appears to have been a prosperous man. He owned <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenement">tenements</ref> in Edinburgh's Blackfriars Wynd<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-4">[4]</ref> and, at the southern end of this wynd where it joined the Southgait, he and Androw Myllar would establish their press.</p>
<p>Chepman was married twice. His first wife was Margaret Kerkettle and, after being widowed, he married Agnes Cockburn.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Chepman died in 1532<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> and was buried in the chapel he had established in the south aisle of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Giles_Cathedral">St Giles Cathedral</ref> in Edinburgh, now known as the Chepman Aisle.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>The Southgait Press</head>
<figure><caption>Walter Chepman's device in his print of The Goldyn Targe.</caption></figure>
<p>In September 1507 King James IV authorised Walter Chepman and Androw Myllar to establish a printing press and awarded the two partners a monopoly in printed books within Scotland.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Privy_Seal-6">[6]</ref> Androw Myllar was also a burgess of Edinburgh.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Privy_Seal-6">[6]</ref> He was a bookseller who had previously published books, printed in Rouen, intended for sale in England.</p>
<p>Chepman and Myllar's press was functional by the following Spring and was based in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cowgate">Southgait</ref> of Edinburgh. Its works included a liturgical text known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aberdeen_Breviary">The Aberdeen Breviary</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NLS_Breviary-2">[2]</ref> and 'The Chepman and Myllar Prints'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-C_and_M_prints-1">[1]</ref> which were a series of pamphlets containing popular literature in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scots_language">Scots</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_language">English</ref>.</p>
<p>The press did not have a long working life. The latest surviving example of its work is an edition of the Aberdeen Breviary dating to 1510.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Dawson-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Religious Patronage</head>
<p>Walter Chepman paid for the foundation of two chapels at the Kirk of Saint Giles in Edinburgh.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>The first chapel, founded in 1513 and abutting to the south of the church, offered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office_of_the_Dead">masses for the souls</ref> of Chepman, his first wife and of the King and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret_Tudor">Queen</ref>. The equivalent part of the modern church is now known as 'The Chepman Aisle'. It contains the seventeenth century tomb of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Graham,_1st_Marquess_of_Montrose">The Marquess of Montrose</ref> and a memorial plaque in honour of Walter Chepman donated by the nineteenth century publisher <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Chambers_(publisher)">William Chambers</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>In 1528 Chepman established a mortuary chapel, now lost, in the cemetery of Saint Giles' Kirk. It was dedicated to the performance of masses in honour of Chepman, both his wives, King James V, King James IV and all the Scots who had died at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Flodden">Flodden</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-4">[4]</ref></p>
</text>
