<text id="autogum_bio_doc764" title="Heinrich von Winkelried" shortTile="heinrich-von-winkelried" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-04-16" dateModified="2019-09-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heinrich_von_Winkelried" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Heinrich von Winkelried</head><figure><caption>Winkelriedskapelle (<hi rend="italic">Drachenkapelle</hi>) dedicated to Winkelried (1828 etching). The building depicted here replaces an earlier chapel, constructed in 1893 but destroyed in 1798 in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_invasion_of_Switzerland">French invasion of Switzerland</ref>. The 1672 building may in turn have built on the site of an older chapel.
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Heinrich von Winkelried</hi> (d. after 1303), known as <hi rend="italic">Schrutan</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Strut</hi> "the giant", was a medieval <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knight">knight</ref> in what is now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_Switzerland">Central Switzerland</ref>.</p>
<p>As <hi rend="italic">Strut von Winkelried</hi> he became the subject of a legend which makes him the slayer of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dragon">dragon</ref>.
The legendary <hi rend="italic">Strut</hi> is placed a generation before the historical character, with a <hi rend="italic">flouruit</hi> in the 1240s, and his death due to poisoning by dragon-blood recorded for 1250.</p>
<head>Historical character</head>
Further information: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winkelried">Winkelried</ref>
<p><hi rend="italic">Heinrich von Winkelried, genannt Schrutan</hi> is recorded in a document dated 22 April 1275.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref>
After this date and until 1303, his name figures repeatedly as that of a witness on official documents. Nothing beyond this is known about his life.
The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winkelried">Winkelried</ref> family is well attested in 13th and 14th century, the first known member being the knight Rudolf von Winkelried, attested 1248 as a follower of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_II,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Frederick II</ref>. Heinrich therefore may have been a son of Rudolf's.
The home castle of the Winkelried may have been at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ennetmoos">Ennetmoos</ref> near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stans">Stans</ref>. The modern municipality of Ennetmoos has chosen dragon for its coat of arms due to the legend of Schrutan.</p>
<p>The nickname <hi rend="italic">Schrutan</hi> (also <hi rend="italic">Strutan, Struthan, Struth</hi>, etc.) is derived from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_legend">German legend</ref>, where it is given to a giant, in particular one of the guardians of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rosengarten_zu_Worms">Rosengarten</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heldenbuch">Heldenbuch</ref> literature, but it also occurs as the name of a knight at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Attila_the_Hun">Etzel</ref>'s court in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nibelungenlied">Nibelungenlied</ref> (v. 1880). Why the historical knight was given this nickname is not known, but it was not uncommon at the time for members of the knightly classes of the Holy Roman Empire to adopt pseudonyms taken from heroic fiction.
Heinrich's sons would have been Rudolf and Walther von Winkelried, both d. c. 1325.
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hermann_von_Liebenau">Hermann von Liebenau</ref> further assumes that one <hi rend="italic">Heinrich genannt Schrutan</hi> who was buried with his wife Mechthild in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colmar">Colmar</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alsace">Alsace</ref> must be identical with the knight,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> who therefore would have left Switzerland at some point after 1303, but Oechsli (1898) does not accept the identity and ascribes the equality in name to coincidence.</p>
<head>Legend</head>
<figure><caption>Schrutan's fight with the dragon,  by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_Jauslin">Karl Jauslin</ref> (1842–1904)</caption></figure>
<p>The legend is first mentioned by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chronicle_of_the_Swiss_Confederation">Etterlin</ref> (1507), without the given name <hi rend="italic">Strut</hi> and without a fixed year (but placed "before the time of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rudolph_I_of_Germany">king Rudolf</ref>).
It is expanded into greater detail  in the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chronicon_Helveticum">Chronicon Helveticum</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aegidius_Tschudi">Aegidius Tschudi</ref> (d. 1570), compiled in the 16th century and first printed in 1734. Tschudi now fixes the year of the event as 1250 and speficies the identity of the hero as one <hi rend="italic">Struth von Winkelriedt</hi> (which name he emphasizes is recorded in the annals of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stans">Stans</ref>), who had been knighted by emperor Frederick at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Faenza">battle of <hi rend="italic">Favenz</hi></ref> (1239).
The legend was later included by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brothers_Grimm">Brothers Grimm</ref> in their collection of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_legend">German legends</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Deutsche Sagen</hi> 1865, no. 218).</p>
<p>According to the story as reported by Tschudi, a dragon lived in a cave near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stans">Stans</ref> (the <hi rend="italic">Drachenloch</hi> near the top of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mueterschwandenberg">Mueterschwandenberg</ref>), destroying cattle and causing much damage to the people of <hi rend="italic">Wilen</hi>, to the point where the village had to be abandoned and came to be known as <hi rend="italic">Ödwilen</hi> (deserted Wilen). The people of Unterwalden made several expeditions trying to kill the dragon with crossbows, but each time the dragon saw he was at a disadvantage, he quickly retired into his cave or ran up a steep slope like a lizard, where he was unreachable.
At this point, Winkelried,  who had been banished from Unterwalden for manslaughter, asked whether he would be allowed back into the land if he would kill the dragon.  This was accepted, and Struth attacked the dragon single-handedly, armed with a spear, to the point of which he had attached sharp barbs.
The dragon seeing that the attacker was alone came from his hiding-place and attacked with open jaws, and Winkelried was able to transfix the monster with his spear, hacking at it with his sword until it died.
Glad for his victory, Winkelried lifted his sword over his head, thanking God, and the dragon's blood dripped from his sword blade on his body, poisoning him so that he died a few days later.</p>
<p>Toponymy referring to a dragon is found in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ennetmoos">Ennetmoos</ref>, where the historical  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winkelried">Winkelried</ref> family originated. A <hi rend="italic">Drachenried</hi> (dragon's fen) and  <hi rend="italic">Drachenloch</hi> (dragon's cave) are to the west of the village, and a <hi rend="italic">Drachenkapelle</hi> (dragon chapel), also known as <hi rend="italic">Winkelriedkapelle</hi> dedicated to Struth is south of the village, next to <hi rend="italic">Wychried</hi>, the probable site of the original Winkelried estate.
The story is probably a recontextualisation of a much older dragon myth, put into a new historical context in late medieval folklore.
The "dragon" toponymy in this place has been associated with the older dragon narrative in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nibelung">Nibelung</ref> cycle in 19th-century scholarship.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
</text>
