<text id="autogum_bio_doc727" title="Alexander Leslie, Earl of Ross" shortTile="alexander-leslie" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-11-13" dateModified="2019-10-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Leslie%2C_Earl_of_Ross" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Alexander Leslie, Earl of Ross</head>This article is about the Earl of Ross. For other people named Alexander Leslie, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Leslie_(disambiguation)">Alexander Leslie (disambiguation)</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Alexander Leslie, Earl of Ross</hi> (died 1402) was a Scottish nobleman. Born between 1367 and 1382, he was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Leslie,_Lord_of_Ross">Walter Leslie, Lord of Ross</ref> and  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euphemia_I,_Countess_of_Ross">Euphemia I, Countess of Ross</ref>. In around 1394 he became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Ross">Earl of Ross</ref> and sometime before 1398 he married Isabel Stewart, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Stewart,_Duke_of_Albany">Robert Stewart, Duke of Albany</ref>. They had one child, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euphemia_II,_Countess_of_Ross">Euphemia</ref>. He died at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dingwall">Dingwall</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scotland">Scotland</ref> on 8 May 1402.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Alexander Leslie was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euphemia_I,_Countess_of_Ross">Euphemia I, Countess of Ross</ref> and her husband, the far-travelled <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Leslie,_Lord_of_Ross">Walter Leslie, Lord of Ross</ref>. His exact date of birth is not known. He was born somewhere between 1367, the year following his parents' marriage, and 1382, the year of his father's death. When his father died in 1382 he would have been no more than an adolescent or teenager.</p>
<head>The Wolf of Badenoch</head>
<p>Later in 1382 his mother, now a wealthy widow, remarried, to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Stewart,_1st_Earl_of_Buchan">Alexander Stewart</ref> (the "Wolf of Badenoch"), son of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_II_of_Scotland">Robert II of Scotland</ref>. The marriage significantly undermined the prospect of the young Alexander's inheritance. The marriage of 1382, supported by King Robert, saw the transfer of control of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mormaer_of_Ross">mormaerdom</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Ross">earldom of Ross</ref> and the associated barony of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingedward">Kingedward</ref> to the east (the northern half of the defunct <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Buchan">earldom of Buchan</ref>) from Euphemia's hand's into the hands of Alexander Stewart. Two days after the transfer, Alexander was made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Buchan">Earl of Buchan</ref> by the King.</p>
<p>Alexander received control of the earldom of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ross,_Scotland">Ross</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liferent">liferent</ref> (i.e. for his lifetime), and any heirs to the marriage were entitled to inherit the lordships of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isle_of_Skye">Skye</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isle_of_Lewis">Lewis</ref> and the thanages of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dingwall">Dingwall</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deskford">Deskford</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glendowachy">Glendowachy</ref> and other lands in other parts of Scotland which had been part of Euphemia's property.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Thus the young Alexander Leslie, even if he were to obtain the earldom eventually upon Stewart's death, was faced with a likelihood of being left with an earldom stripped of a large chunk of its most important assets.  These actions by King Robert alienated the powerful Leslie-Lindsay kindred, a Lowland family who had entered the higher ranks of Scottish politics as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Favourite">favourites</ref> of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_II_of_Scotland">David II of Scotland</ref>. King Robert had also deprived this family of the exercise of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justiciar_of_Scotia">Justiciarship of Scotia</ref>. Later in 1382 (November), King Robert's chamberlain, son-in-law and favourite, John Lyon, thane (toiseach) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glamis">Glamis</ref>, was murdered by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Lindsay,_Lord_of_Crawford">James Lindsay</ref>, lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crawford_Castle">Crawford</ref>, head of the Leslie-Lindsay kindred and claimant to the lordship of Buchan. In 1384, Lindsay-Leslie and Douglas disaffection contributed to the <hi rend="italic">coup</hi> by the king's son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_III_of_Scotland">John Stewart</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Carrick">earl of Carrick</ref>, who became Guardian (1384–88).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>The Leslie-Lindsay kindred sought to protect Alexander Leslie's rights in Ross. However, this was difficult while Buchan remained in such a powerful position in the north. The guardianships of Carrick and then of Carrick's brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Stewart,_1st_Duke_of_Albany">Robert Stewart, earl of Fife and Menteith</ref> (1388–93) were both supported by the Leslie-Lindsay kindred and both aimed against Buchan's power. Moreover, Buchan's nominal wife, Euphemia, herself came into the Leslie-Lindsay camp. In 1389, Euphemia, the countess of Ross, complained to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope">Pope</ref> that her marriage to Buchan was meaningless, as the latter was in fact more often with his mistress, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mairead_inghean_Eachainn">Mairead inghean Eachainn</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Clement_V">Pope Clement V</ref> annulled the marriage in late 1392, and ordered the restoration of her lands. With the firm support of the Fife guardianship, Euphemia and her son were able to re-establish their power in Ross. By the year 1394, Buchan's power in Ross seems to have disappeared and Countess Euphemia was once again granting charters from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dingwall_Castle">Dingwall Castle</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Earl of Ross</head>
<p>Alexander succeeded his mother to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earldom_of_Ross">Earldom of Ross</ref> perhaps in the later part of 1394. The key point perhaps is the date of his mother's death. The date is not known, but fell somewhere between late 1394 and 1398. In the November of the latter year, he had granted some lands to his relative (either cousin or uncle)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> George Leslie of Rothes in exchange for the 200 merks he apparently needed to take the control of the earldom out of the crown's hands.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> He controlled the barony of Fitkill in Fife until in 1399, when he resigned this too (via <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_III_of_Scotland">King Robert III</ref>) to Rothes.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> Very little is otherwise known about his activities as earl.</p>
<head>Family life</head>
<p>He had married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Stewart,_Duke_of_Albany">Robert Stewart, Duke of Albany</ref>'s daughter Isobel <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> sometime before 1398. They had only one child, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euphemia_II,_Countess_of_Ross">Euphemia</ref>, who took the veil. She bequeathed her enormous estates not to her father's sister, but to her <hi rend="italic">mother's</hi> half-brother, Albany's second son John (from his second wife), whom his father made Earl of Buchan in 1408.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>According to the <hi rend="italic">Cronicle of the Earlis of Ross</hi> (c. 9), Alexander Leslie, Earl of Ross, died at Dingwall on May 8, 1402. His widow remarried Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_de_Haliburton,_1st_Lord_Haliburton_of_Dirleton">Walter de Haliburton, Knt.</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Notes</head>
<head>References</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Boardman, Stephen, <hi rend="italic">The Early Stewart Kings: Robert II and Robert III, 1371-1406</hi>, (Edinburgh, 1996)</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Balfour_Paul">Paul, James Balfour</ref>, <hi rend="italic">The Scots Peerage</hi>, Vol. VII, (Edinburgh, 1910)</item></list>
</text>
