<text id="autogum_bio_doc344" title="Marco Uccellini" shortTile="marco-uccellini" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-02-23" dateModified="2018-04-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco_Uccellini" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Marco Uccellini</head><p><hi rend="bold">Marco Uccellini</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forlimpopoli">Forlimpopoli</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forlì">Forlì</ref> 1603 or 1610 - 10 December 1680) was an Italian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baroque">Baroque</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Violin">violinist</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Composer">composer</ref>. His output of mainly secular music for solo violin is considered to have been important in the rise of independent instrumental <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classical_music">classical music</ref>, and in the development of violin technique.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Uccellini's life, like many composers of the 17th century, is not well documented; however, enough information exists to create a rough biography. He was born into a reasonably affluent noble family in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forlimpopoli">Forlimpopoli</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forlì">Forlì</ref>, who had owned land in the area since the early 14th century. Many members of the family held ecclesiastical posts locally, including Uccellini's father Pietro Maria, and it is likely that Marco went to study at the seminary in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Assisi">Assisi</ref> sometime in the early 1630s. Evidence from his will suggests that Uccellini began his formal musical education there, possibly under another notable early violinist-composer, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Battista_Buonamente">Giovanni Battista Buonamente</ref>, who was then serving as music director (<hi rend="italic">maestro di cappella</hi>) at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basilica_of_Saint_Francis_of_Assisi">Basilica of Saint Francis of Assisi</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>He became <hi rend="italic">Capo degl’instrumentisti</hi> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Este">Este</ref> court in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modena">Modena</ref> from 1641 to 1662, and was the <hi rend="italic">maestro di cappella</hi> of the Modena cathedral from 1647 to 1665. According to payroll records and remnants of Uccellini's correspondence, it is clear that he was a valued advisor and confidant to the d'Este family, paid almost eight times more than the other court violinists. Following the devolution of the Estense Chapel upon the accession of Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfonso_IV_d'Este,_Duke_of_Modena">Alfonso IV d'Este</ref>, Uccellini was let go from his position. However, he was soon remployed as the <hi rend="italic">maestro di cappella </hi> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Farnese">Farnese</ref> court in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parma">Parma</ref> until his death; he received this job mainly through the assistance of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabella_d'Este,_Duchess_of_Parma">Isabella d'Este</ref>, who recently married into the Farnese family. At the Farnese court, he composed operas and ballets, but none of this music survives; thus, he is mainly known today for his instrumental music.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Uccellini was one of a line of distinguished Italian violinist-composers in the first half of the 17th century.  His sonatas for violin and continuo contributed to the development of an idiomatic style of writing for the violin (including virtuosic runs, leaps, and forays into high positions), expanding the instrument's technical capabilities and expressive range.  Like other 17th-century Italian sonatas, Uccellini's consist of short contrasting sections (frequently dances) that flow one into another.  Uccellini's innovations influenced a generation of Austro-German violinist-composers including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Heinrich_Schmelzer">Johann Heinrich Schmelzer</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heinrich_Ignaz_Biber">Heinrich Ignaz Biber</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Jakob_Walther">Johann Jakob Walther</ref>.</p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>Uccellini mainly composed instrumental music, of which seven collections were published.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Some examples are:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Salmi a 1, a 3, 4, et a 5 concertati parte con istromenti e parte senza con Letanie della Beata Vergine Concertate a 5 con istromenti</hi>, Op. 6 (Venice, 1654)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Ozio regio</hi>, Op. 7 (Venice, 1660 and Antwerp, 1668)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Sinfonie Boscarecie</hi>, Op. 8, a collection of 37 small pieces for violin and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basso_continuo">basso continuo</ref> joined <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ad_libitum">ad libitum</ref></hi> by a second and third violins. The first edition of the sheet music was printed in Venice in 1660 but a version reprinted in Antwerp in 1669 was used in the freely available version <ref target="http://www.lysator.liu.se/~tuben/scores/ucop8/ucop8sc.pdf">Sinfonie Boscarecie</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Sinfonici concerti brevi e facili</hi>, Op. 9</item></list>
<p>He also composed one <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opera">opera</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Gli eventi di Filandro ad Edessa</hi>, which premiered in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parma">Parma</ref> in 1675.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Contributions to Violin Playing</head>
<p>It can be assumed from the highly idiomatic and virtuosic nature of Uccellini's violin compositions that he was himself a brilliant violinist. Besides introducing several technical innovations necessary to play his difficult music, he was an early popularizer of music written explicitly for solo violin and continuo; at the time, it was common for composers not to specify instruments in their works, preferring to write parts adaptable between instruments of similar ranges.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Selected discography</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Don Marco Uccellini: Sonata over Canzoni Op 5 (1649). Performed by Arparla with Davide Monti (baroque violin) and Maria Christina Cleary (arpa doppia). Stradivarius STR 37023, 2015. <ref target="http://www.stradivarius.it/scheda.php?ID=801157037023500">http://www.stradivarius.it/scheda.php?ID=801157037023500</ref></item>
<item>Marco Uccellini: Sonatas. Performed by Romanesca, a trio with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Manze">Andrew Manze</ref> (violin), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nigel_North">Nigel North</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theorbo">theorbo</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archlute">archlute</ref>, Baroque guitar), and John Toll (harpsichord, organ) and excellent liner notes by Manze. Released in 1999. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harmonia_Mundi">Harmonia Mundi</ref> 907196</item>
<item>Marco Uccellini: La Hortensia Virtuosa. Performed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob_van_Asperen">Bob van Asperen</ref> (harpsichord), Lucy Van Dael (violin), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaap_ter_Linden">Jaap ter Linden</ref> (cello), and Toyohiko Satoh (lute). Released in 2007. Aeolus 10096</item></list>
</text>
