<text id="autogum_bio_doc012" title="Septic Tank Sam" shortTile="septic-tank-sam" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-06-13" dateModified="2019-10-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Septic_Tank_Sam" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Septic Tank Sam</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Septic Tank Sam</hi> is the nickname given to an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unidentified_decedent">unidentified murder victim</ref> who was found in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Septic_tank">septic tank</ref> thirteen kilometers west of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tofield">Tofield, Alberta</ref>. Authorities suspect he wasn't from Alberta, but most likely worked as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Migrant_worker">migrant worker</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Discovery</head>
<p>Sam was found wearing a blue <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Levi_Strauss_&amp;_Co.">Levi</ref> shirt with snap buttons, a gray t-shirt, blue jeans, and imitation <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C._&amp;_J._Clark">Wallabee</ref> shoes. His <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decomposition">decomposed</ref> body was wrapped in a yellow bed sheet and tied up with a nylon rope. Sam was found by a local couple scavenging their abandoned property for a septic tank pump. After seeing his leg bobbing in their old septic tank, they alerted the Tofield <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Canadian_Mounted_Police">Royal Canadian Mounted Police</ref> (RCMP) detachment. Two officers came to the scene to recover Sam's body, where they spent an hour emptying the 1.8 meter deep septic tank with empty ice cream pails.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CSI_Alberta-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Autopsy</head>
<p>A medical examiner in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edmonton">Edmonton</ref> determined Sam to be of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_Canadians">European Canadian</ref> descent. His bones and teeth suggested he suffered from an unspecified illness at five years old. Sam's cause of death was two gunshots to the head and chest, although it was possible there could've been more if any of the bullets didn't reach his skeleton. Before his death, Sam had been <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torture">tortured</ref>; he'd been beaten, tied up, burned with a small <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butane_torch">butane torch</ref> and cigarettes, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genital_modification_and_mutilation">sexually mutilated</ref> with farm shears. The sexual mutilation was so severe that the medical examiner took several months to positively identify him as a male. Based on the burn marks on his shirt sleeves, Sam could've been tied to a bed while tortured. After Sam's death, he'd been covered in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calcium_oxide">quicklime</ref>, most likely in an attempt to quicken decomposition.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Investigation</head>
<p>Due to a lack of evidence in the septic tank, Sam was most likely murdered elsewhere and the septic tank was only a dumpsite. Sam's murderers are believed to have known him, due to how viciously he'd been killed. It's also suspected Sam's murderers were Tofield locals or were familiar with the area. due to the location of Sam's dumpsite being on a rural property.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CSI_Alberta-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Sam's body has been exhumed from his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Potter's_field">unmarked grave</ref> in an Edmonton cemetery twice. In 1979, Sam's remains were flown out to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clyde_Snow">Clyde Snow</ref> and Betty Gatliff, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forensic_anthropology">Forensic anthropologist</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medical_illustration">medical illustrator</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal_Aviation_Administration">Federal Aviation Administration</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oklahoma">Oklahoma</ref> who'd been creating 3D <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facial_composite">facial composites</ref> from skulls since 1967. Along with creating a facial composite for Sam, the two could tell by measuring his hands that he was right handed. Snow believed Sam to be of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indigenous_peoples_in_Canada">Indigenous</ref> origin and around 35 years old, contradicting the RCMP's belief of Sam being a European Canadian and between 26 to 32.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CSI_Alberta-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Sam was exhumed and reconstructed for the second time in 2000 by Cyril Chan, who was with the Edmonton medical examiner's office at the time.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-CSI_Alberta-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Aftermath</head>
<p>The 1,200 residents of Tofield at the time were horrified to hear of Sam's murder. Farmers checked their own septic tanks for bodies and business owners worried that Sam's murderers could've been regular customers. Many speculated Sam had been sexually mutilated due to committing a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sex_and_the_law">sex crime</ref> or being <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adultery">unfaithful in a relationship</ref>. Ed Lammerts, one of the officers who helped recover Sam's body, has since retired. He believes Sam will never be identified, despite sending <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X-ray">X-rays</ref> of Sam's teeth to 800 Albertan dentists coupled with publishing them in dental magazines, and spending $1,000,000 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canadian_dollar">CAD</ref> on the case.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
</text>
