<text id="autogum_bio_doc498" title="Federigo Giambelli" shortTile="federigo-giambelli" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-10-21" dateModified="2019-08-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federigo_Giambelli" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Federigo Giambelli</head><p><hi rend="bold">Federigo Giambelli</hi> (or Gianibelli; also given as Genebelli or Genibelli in contemporary English texts), was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italy">Italian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military_engineer">military</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil_engineer">civil engineer</ref> who worked in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_Netherlands">Spanish Netherlands</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_England">England</ref> in the late 16th and early 17th centuries.</p>
<head>Early life and Spanish service</head>
<p>Giambelli was born at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mantua">Mantua</ref> about the middle of the 16th century. Having had some experience as a military engineer in Italy, he went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref> to offer his services to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_II_of_Spain">Philip II</ref>. However, his proposals were given a lukewarm reception, and as he could obtain no immediate employment from the king, he moved to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antwerp">Antwerp</ref>, where he soon gained considerable reputation for his knowledge in various departments of science. He is said to have married while living there.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fall_of_Antwerp">The Siege of Antwerp</ref></head>
<figure><caption>An 18th century engraving, depicting the explosion of one of Giambelli's "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hellburners">hellburners</ref>" on the Duke of Parma's pontoon bridge at the Siege of Antwerp in 1585.</caption></figure>
<p>Giambelli is said to have vowed to be revenged for his rebuff at the Spanish court; and when Antwerp was besieged by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Farnese,_Duke_of_Parma">Alexander Farnese, Duke of Parma</ref> in 1584, he offered his services to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I_of_England">Elizabeth I of England</ref>, who, having satisfied herself of his abilities, engaged him to advise in its defence. His plans for provisioning the town were rejected by the senate, but they agreed to a modification of his scheme for destroying the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pontoon_bridge">pontoon bridge</ref> which closed the entrance to the town from the side of the sea, by the conversion of two ships of 60 and 70 tons into "infernal machines" or "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hellburners">hellburners</ref>". Each ship had a masonry chamber built into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hold_(ship)">hold</ref>, filled with 7,000 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pound_(mass)">pounds</ref> (3,175 kilograms) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gunpowder">gunpowder</ref> and heaped over with millstones, tombstones and scrap iron; stacks of timber and brushwood on the top deck were set alight to give the impression that it was an ordinary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fire_ship">fire ship</ref>. The explosive charge was to be detonated by a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clockwork">clockwork</ref> mechanism activating a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flintlock_mechanism">flintlock</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> One of these ships exploded against the bridge, and besides allegedly killing more than 1000 Spanish soldiers, effected a breach in the structure of more than 200feet (61 Metres) in width. This might have led to the relief of the town by the waiting Dutch fleet, except for the hesitation of Vice-Admiral Jacob Jacobsen (or Jacobzoon).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Service in England</head>
<figure><caption>One of Giambelli's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bastion">bastions</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carisbrook_Castle">Carisbrook Castle</ref>, built between 1597 and 1600.</caption></figure>
<p>After the surrender of Antwerp, Giambelli went to England, where he was employed by the Crown between 1585 and 1602, the last in a line of a number Italian engineers at the English court.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> He was engaged during July and August 1588 in fortifying the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thames_Estuary">Thames Estuary</ref>, which was considered the most likely site for the expected Spanish invasion. Works included the construction of earthen ramparts around the old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blockhouse">blockhouses</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tilbury">Tilbury</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravesend">Gravesend</ref>, and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boom_defence">boom defence</ref> across the river, consisting of a chain supported by 120 ships' masts; also a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pontoon_bridge">pontoon bridge</ref> was constructed to allow the English army to deploy on either shore. The boom broke at the first flood tide after its completion.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref>  The exact contribution of Giambelli to these works is unknown, because he is not mentioned in any of the reports made by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Dudley,_1st_Earl_of_Leicester">Earl of Leicester</ref>, the commander of the English army in Essex;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> however, his name is noted in the accounts, drawing a respectable fee of six <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shilling">shillings</ref> and eight <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pence">pence</ref> (£0.33) per day.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> When the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_Armada">Spanish Armada</ref> was attacked by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fire_ship">fireships</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calais">Calais</ref> roads, the panic which ensued was largely due to the conviction among the Spaniards that the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fireship">fireships</ref> were "infernal machines" constructed by Giambelli; however they were unaware that he was fully occupied by the defensive works in the Thames and that a national shortage of gunpowder prevented its use in the English fireships.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>In 1591, Giambelli presented a plan to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Cecil,_1st_Baron_Burghley">Lord Burghley</ref> for a water system to cleanse the fetid ditches surrounding the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City_of_London">City of London</ref> and another (perhaps a type of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fire_hydrant">fire hydrant</ref>) which would allow fires in the City to be fought more effectively. Neither of these schemes seem to have been acted upon.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>Starting in 1597, Giambelli constructed a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trace_Italienne">trace Italienne</ref></hi> fortification surrounding <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carisbrook_Castle">Carisbrook Castle</ref> on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isle_of_Wight">Isle of Wight</ref>; the work was mostly completed by 1600, but remodelling of two of the castle's original towers was not completed until 1603.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> In 1602 at the request of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privy_Council_of_England">Privy Council</ref>, Giambelli surveyed the fort on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plymouth_Hoe">Plymouth Hoe</ref>, which was sited on the location now occupied by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Citadel,_Plymouth">Royal Citadel</ref>, following complaints that the defences were inadequate.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> Giambelli made three reports on Plymouth. He suggested surrounding the town with a wall with nine ravelins. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></p>
<p>He is said to have died in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, but the year of his death is unknown.</p>
</text>
