<text id="autogum_bio_doc698" title="Walter Stewart, Earl of Atholl" shortTile="walter-stewart-earl" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-02-19" dateModified="2019-04-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Stewart%2C_Earl_of_Atholl" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Walter Stewart, Earl of Atholl</head>
<figure><caption>Arms of Stewart of Atholl</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Walter Stewart, Earl of Atholl, Strathearn and Caithness</hi> (c. 1360 – 26 March 1437) was a Scottish nobleman, the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_II_of_Scotland">Robert II of Scotland</ref>. Stewart was an enthusiastic advocate of the ransom and return to Scotland of the future king in exile, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_I_of_Scotland">James I</ref>, in 1424. In 1425 he served as a member of the jury of 21 which tried and executed his nephew <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murdoch_Stewart,_2nd_Duke_of_Albany">Murdoch Stewart, 2nd Duke of Albany</ref>. Eventually, however, Atholl turned against the King and conspired in his assassination in 1437. He was tried for murder and was executed after 3 days of gruesome torture.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Stewart was a son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_II_of_Scotland">Robert II of Scotland</ref> by his second wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euphemia_de_Ross">Euphemia de Ross</ref>, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aodh,_Earl_of_Ross">Aodh, Earl of Ross</ref>. He was also a younger half-brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_III_of_Scotland">Robert III of Scotland</ref> and an uncle of the above-mentioned James I of Scotland.</p>
<p>Stewart married first, sometime before 1378, Margaret Barclay, Lady of Brechin,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> by whom he had two sons:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Alan Stewart, 4th Earl of Caithness (d. 1431)</item>
<item>David Stewart, Master of Atholl (d. bef. 1437)</item></list>
<p>In 1390, Stewart's niece <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euphemia_Stewart,_2nd_Countess_of_Caithness">Euphemia</ref> resigned to him the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Caithness">Earldom of Caithness</ref>. In 1404, he was created <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Atholl">Earl of Atholl</ref>.</p>
<head>Ransom and return of James I of Scotland</head>
<p>Stewart was energetic in retrieving his nephew James I from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_England">Kingdom of England</ref>, which was accomplished in 1424, and was a member of the jury which tried his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nephew">half nephew</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murdoch_Stewart,_2nd_Duke_of_Albany">Murdoch Stewart, 2nd Duke of Albany</ref>, and which culminated in the execution of Albany and two of his sons.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Stewart was made Great Justiciar of Scotland and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Strathearn">Earl of Strathearn</ref>, with such title being taken from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malise_Graham">Malise Graham</ref>, who subsequently became the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Menteith">Earl of Menteith</ref> in 1427.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>   He resigned Caithness to his son Alan in 1428 but regained it on Alan's death without issue in 1431.</p>
<p>The depth of Stewart's loyalties to James is unclear. The chronicler Buchanan (1582) saw in his efforts to return James to Scotland and support him against Albany and his children a deep-laid plan for those two branches of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Stewart">House of Stewart</ref> to destroy each other – and clear his own way to the throne, reviving the old charge of illegitimacy against his half-brother Robert III. Others aver that it was the imprisonment and subsequent death of his son David that turned him against the king.</p>
<head>Assassination of James I</head>
<p>Whatever the cause of Stewart's rage against the King, he joined with his grandson <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Stewart,_Master_of_Atholl">Robert Stewart, Master of Atholl</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Robert_Graham">Sir Robert Graham</ref> in a conspiracy against James I, which assassinated the king on 20 February 1437. Robert Stewart unbarred the doors to the royal apartments, permitting assassins to enter the King's lodging at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominican_Order">Dominican Friars</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perth,_Scotland">Perth</ref>. The King hid under the floorboards, only to be discovered by Sir Robert Graham, who personally finished him off.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>However, Atholl found little popular support for his cause, and the conspirators were swiftly apprehended. They were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_of_Attainder">attainted</ref> and put to death in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref> by a series of tortures remarkable and hideous even for that era. Walter was tortured over a period of three days. On the first, he was put in a cart with a crane, hoisted up, dropped, and jerked violently to a stop to stretch his joints. He was then placed in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pillory">pillory</ref> and "crowned with a diadem of burning iron"<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> bearing the inscription "King of all Traitors". On the second day, he was bound to a hurdle and dragged along the high street of Edinburgh (some claim he was also blinded and tortured with red-hot iron pincers on this day, but Buchanan speaks only of the hurdle). On the third, he was disembowelled while alive, his entrails burnt before his face, and his heart was torn out and burnt. Finally, his corpse was beheaded and quartered, and the quarters displayed around the realm.</p>
</text>
