<text id="autogum_bio_doc546" title="Mateus (ambassador)" shortTile="mateus-ambassador" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-03-15" dateModified="2018-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mateus_%28ambassador%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Mateus (ambassador)</head><p><hi rend="bold">Mateus</hi> (Portuguese for Matthew), also known as <hi rend="bold">Matthew the Armenian</hi> (died May, 1520), was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethiopia">Ethiopian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ambassador">ambassador</ref> sent by regent queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleni_of_Ethiopia">Eleni of Ethiopia</ref> to king <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manuel_I_of_Portugal">Manuel I of Portugal</ref> and to the Pope in Rome, in search of a coalition to help on the increasing threat that Ethiopia faced from the growing Muslim influence in the region, with the counsel of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pêro_da_Covilhã">Pêro da Covilhã</ref>. Mateus arrived at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goa">Goa</ref> in 1512, and traveled to Portugal in 1514, from where he returned with a Portuguese embassy, along with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francisco_Álvares">Francisco Álvares</ref>. The Portuguese only understood the nature of his mission after they arrived in Ethiopia in 1520, shortly after Mateus' death, a fact that complicated their mission to the new Ethiopian Emperor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Mateus embassy to Portugal</head>
<p>Mateus was dispatched by regent queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleni_of_Ethiopia">Eleni</ref>, following the arrival of two Portuguese at Ethiopia in search of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pêro_da_Covilhã">Pêro da Covilhã</ref> in 1508. Those envoys, including priest João Gomes, João Sanches, and Sid Mohammed were sent by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tristão_da_Cunha">Tristão da Cunha</ref> in 1506. Having failed to cross Malindi, they returned to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socotra">Socotra</ref>, from where <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afonso_de_Albuquerque">Afonso de Albuquerque</ref> managed to land them in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape_Guardafui">Filuk</ref>, arriving in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shewa">Shewa</ref>, Ethiopia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> They were killed or disappeared in the returning travel.
Mateus, of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenians">Armenian</ref> origin, was sent to the Portuguese in India transporting a pious letter from Eleni to king Manuel I of Portugal and a piece of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/True_Cross">True Cross</ref>. He traveled with his wife, brother-in-law, and servants.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Diffie-352-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>After being robbed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zaila">Zaila</ref> and detained in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bijapur,_Karnataka">Bijapur</ref>, Mateus arrived at Dabul, and was received in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goa">Goa</ref> in December 1512 with great honour by Portuguese governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afonso_de_Albuquerque">Afonso de Albuquerque</ref>, as a long sought "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prester_John">Prester John</ref>" envoy. His arrival was announced by king <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manuel_I_of_Portugal">Manuel I of Portugal</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Leo_X">Pope Leo X</ref> in 1513. Although Mateus faced the distrust of some of Albuquerque's rivals, who tried to prove he was some impostor or Muslim spy, he was sent by Albuquerque to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cananor">Cananor</ref>, and from there to Portugal. Mateus arrived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisbon">Lisbon</ref> in February 1514. There, his reports, the letter by queen Eleni and the piece of the cross were much admired by the king and his entourage.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> While Mateus was in Portugal, Albuquerque advanced in an attempt to take <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aden">Aden</ref>, and an expedition into the Red Sea, and is hint that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massawa">Massawa</ref> could be a Portuguese base, may have been influenced by Mateus' reports.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Diffie-352-3">[3]</ref>
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damião_de_Góis">Damião de Góis</ref> translated into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin">Latin</ref> a Portuguese opuscle on the Ethiopian embassy of Mateus, which also included the famous "Letter of Prester John" written by the Ethiopian Queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleni_of_Ethiopia">Eleni</ref> (1509) and a "Confessio illorum fidei".</p>
<head>Return to Ethiopia with Portuguese embassy</head>
<p>In 1515 King Manuel answered with an embassy to accompany Mateus to Ethiopia. The mission was headed by old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duarte_Galvão">Duarte Galvão</ref> and included Father <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francisco_Álvares">Francisco Álvares</ref>, with rich gifts for the king of Ethiopia. They sailed from Lisbon to Goa on 7 April 1515,  with the new governor to be, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lopo_Soares_de_Albergaria">Lopo Soares de Albergaria</ref>. From Goa, a fleet departed for the Red Sea trying to land the ambassadors in February 1517, joined by Italian explorer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea_Corsali">Andrea Corsali</ref>. Corsali wrote several letters about the travel, stating that they stopped near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socotra">Socotra</ref>, and proceeded to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aden">Aden</ref>. Given bad weather and the refusal of Albergaria to go further, getting no closer than the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dahlak_Archipelago">Dahlak Archipelago</ref>, they proceeded to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massawa">Massawa</ref>. Mateus had some contacts in Massawa, but after weeks of stalling, old ambassador Duarte Galvão died and the mission was cancelled.</p>
<p>Álvares and Mattheus were forced to wait until the arrival of Soares' replacement, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diogo_Lopes_de_Sequeira">Diogo Lopes de Sequeira</ref>, who successfully sent the embassy on, with D.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rodrigo_de_Lima">Rodrigo de Lima</ref> replacing Duarte Galvão. The party at last reached Massawa on April 9, 1520, and reached the court of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lebna_Dengel">Lebna Dengel</ref>. There, Álvares befriended several Europeans who had gained the favor of the Emperor, which included <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pêro_da_Covilhã">Pêro da Covilhã</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brancaleon">Nicolao Branceleon</ref>. Álvares' party remained six years in Ethiopia, returning to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisbon">Lisbon</ref> in either 1526 or 1527.</p>
</text>
