<text id="autogum_bio_doc410" title="John of Cologne" shortTile="john-cologne" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-09-19" dateModified="2019-10-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Cologne" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John of Cologne</head>This article is about the Dominican friar and saint, John of Cologne. For the Gothic architect of the same name, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_de_Colonia">Juan de Colonia</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">John of Cologne, O.P.</hi> (Joannes van Hoornaar),  was a friar and priest of the  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominican_Order">Dominican Order</ref>, born in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electorate_of_Cologne">Electorate of Cologne</ref>, part of modern Germany. He later became a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parish_priest">parish priest</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoornaar">Hoornaar</ref>, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_Netherlands">Spanish Netherlands</ref>. He was executed for his faith in 1572 and has been declared a martyr and saint by the Catholic Church.</p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>In the period 1550-1560 the Dutch Provinces were trying to gain their independence from the Spanish empire of King Philip II.</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geuzen">Geuzen</ref> (Sea Beggars) were adventurers, pirates and patriots who fought against the Spanish rule in the Dutch provinces. For several years their bases of operation included the ports of Emden (on the coast of the Dutch Province Friesland), La Rochelle (on the coast of France) and Dover (on the coast of England). The Sea Beggars attacked vessels of almost any nation as well as fishing villages and towns on the coast of the Dutch Provinces.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sea-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>All that is known of John's early life is that he attended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Cologne">University of Cologne</ref>, then recognized as one of the best educational institutions in Europe. He entered the Dominican Order at Cologne and received his formation there. After completing his education, John was assigned to a parish in the Netherlands village of Hoornaar, where he served for the next twenty years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nashville-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>By 1572, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lutheranism">Lutheranism</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calvinism">Calvinism</ref> had spread through a great part of Europe. In the Netherlands this was followed by a struggle between the two denominations in which Calvinism was victorious. On 1 April of that year Calvinists and a group called the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Watergeuzen">Watergeuzen</ref> (Sea Beggars) conquered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brielle">Brielle</ref> (Den Briel) and later <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vlissingen">Flushing</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-sea-1">[1]</ref> In June of that year, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dordrecht">Dordrecht</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gorinchem">Gorkum</ref> also fell into their hands. There they arrested all the Catholic clergy and held them in confinement, in an attempt to get them to deny the Catholic beliefs on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eucharist">Eucharist</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papal_primacy">papal primacy</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-albers-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>As John became aware of what had happened to his fellow priests, he disguised himself and attempted to bring them the comfort of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sacrament">sacraments</ref>. He secretly ministered to the captives but was eventually found out and also taken captive. These nineteen were imprisoned in Gorkum from June 26 until July 6, undergoing much abuse.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nashville-2">[2]</ref> Meanwhile, a letter from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_the_Silent">William the Silent</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince_of_Orange">Prince of Orange</ref>, enjoined all those in authority to leave priests and religious unmolested. Nevertheless <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_II_de_La_Marck">Lumey</ref>, the commander of the Watergeuzen, ordered them to be hanged on the night of 9 July,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nashville-2">[2]</ref> in a turfshed, after cruel tortures.</p>
<p>They are referred by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic_Church">Roman Catholic Church</ref> as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martyrs_of_Gorkum">Martyrs of Gorkum</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-albers-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>The group was canonized by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Pius_IX">Pope Pius IX</ref> in 1867. Their remains are honored at a shrine built to their honor in Brielle.</p>
</text>
