<text id="autogum_bio_doc462" title="Hermann Friedrich Cloedt" shortTile="hermann-friedrich" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-07-27" dateModified="2018-03-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hermann_Friedrich_Cloedt" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hermann Friedrich Cloedt</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Hermann Friedrich Cloedt</hi> (c. 1555–1560, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Killed_in_action"><hi rend="bold">†</hi></ref> 26 July 1586) was commander of the garrison at Neuss (Nuys), near Duisburg, in July 1586, when the city was destroyed by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Farnese,_Duke_of_Parma">Duke of Parma's</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Army_of_Flanders">Army of Flanders</ref>. He died in the defense of Neuss.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Cloedt was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northelen">Northelen</ref>, near Werl, the fourth of ten sons of Johann Cloedt (c. 1527–1587) and Margaretha of Westphalia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Brotze-1">[1]</ref>  As a young man, he served for several years in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henri_III_of_France">Henry III</ref>'s army in France; by 1585, he served under the Dutch provinces, and in 1586, he was in the force of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adolf_van_Nieuwenaar">Adolf von Neuenahr</ref>, when he secured the city of Neuss for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gebhard_Truchsess_von_Waldburg">Gebhard Truchsess von Waldburg</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calvinist">Calvinist</ref> contender for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electorate_of_Cologne">Electorate of Cologne</ref>, during the so-called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cologne_War">Cologne War</ref> (1583–1588).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Brotze-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Sack of Westphalia</head>
<p>In March 1586, accompanied by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Schenck_von_Nydeggen">Martin Schenck von Nydeggen</ref>, who had switched to Dutch Service in 1585, Cloedt went to the County of Westphalia at the head of 500foot and 500horse. After plundering <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vest">Vest</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recklinghausen">Recklinghausen</ref>, on 18 March he and Schenck captured <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Werl">Werl</ref> through trickery. They loaded a train of wagons with his soldiers and covered them with salt. When the wagons of salt were seen outside the city gates, they were at once admitted, salt being a valued commodity. The "salted soldiers" then over–powered the guard and captured the town. Some of the defenders escaped to the Werl citadel, which his troops stormed in vain. When they could not capture the citadel, they thoroughly sacked the city. Count Claude Barclay, also known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haultpenne">Haultpenne</ref>, collected his force of 4,000and besieged them in Werl. Schenck and Cloedt were thus attacked from the outside, and from the several hundred guards in the Werl citadel. They loaded their wagons, this time with booty, took 30magistrates as hostages, and attacked Haultpenne's force, killing about 500of them, and losing 200of their own. After fighting their way through Haultpenne's force, Cloedt returned to Neuss and Schenck to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venlo">Venlo</ref> on the Neuss river.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Defense of Neuss</head>
<p>In late July 1586, the Duke of Parma surrounded Neuss with over 8,000 Italian and Spanish troops of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Army_of_Flanders">Army of Flanders</ref>, and another 2,000 men under the command of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_von_Mansfeld">Karl von Mansfeld</ref>. They grossly outnumbered the defenders of the city, reported variously as 1,600 or 1,800, including largely farmers, citizens, shepherds, clerics, teachers, journeymen, day laborers, and various craftsmen.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Prior to a punishing cannonade, the Duke offered terms, which Cloedt declined. The city, he claimed, had no authority to treat with him, as the city's rights and protection came from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Roman_Emperor">Holy Roman Emperor</ref> himself. As the herald left, the journeymen hurled insults at him and the Duke of Parma.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> At the assault of the Rhine Gate, over 400 men were killed, and Cloedt was gravely injured. In short order, the fortifications were overrun, and 10,000 Spanish, Italian and Germans entered the city, intent on plunder and whatever else they could find. Cloedt was found in the abbey in the center of the town, and hanged from the window with six of his commanders.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Brotze-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Ennen199-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Aftermath</head>
<p>Eight of the buildings in the city remained standing at the end of the battle. A fire consumed most of the town that had not been damaged in the cannonade. The entire garrison of 1,600 defenders was killed, either in battle or subsequently; over 3,000 civilians were also killed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Ennen199-5">[5]</ref></p>
</text>
