<text id="autogum_bio_doc437" title="Cuthbert Burby" shortTile="cuthbert-burby" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-13" dateModified="2017-07-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuthbert_Burby" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cuthbert Burby</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Cuthbert Burby</hi> (died 1607) was a London bookseller and publisher of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabethan_era">Elizabethan</ref> and early <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacobean_era">Jacobean</ref> eras. He is known for publishing a series of significant volumes of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Renaissance_theatre">English Renaissance drama</ref>, including works by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Shakespeare">William Shakespeare</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Greene_(dramatist)">Robert Greene</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Lyly">John Lyly</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Nashe">Thomas Nashe</ref>.</p>
<head>Beginnings</head>
<p>Burby ("sometimes confused with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuthbert_Burbage">Cuthbert Burbage</ref>,"<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> though there is no known connection between the two men) was the son of Edmund Burby, a farmer in Erlsey, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bedfordshire">Bedfordshire</ref>. Cuthbert Burby was apprenticed to the stationer William Wright for eight years as of Christmas 1584, and became a "freeman" (full member) of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Worshipful_Company_of_Stationers_and_Newspaper_Makers">Stationers Company</ref> on 13 January 1592. He did business in London between 1592 and 1607. As his title pages attest, his shops were located 1) "under Saint Mildred's Church in the Poultry," 2) "at the Royal Exchange," and 3) "in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Paul's_Cathedral">Paul's</ref> Churchyard at the sign of the Swan." He had "a large, flourishing, respectable business...."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Early in his career as a publisher, Burby issued works in the famous controversy between Thomas Nashe and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabriel_Harvey#Feud_with_Nashe">Gabriel Harvey</ref>. Curiously, Burby published works in their exchange by both Nashe and Harvey; his connection, it appears, was not personal or ideological – just business.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> He also published Nashe's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Unfortunate_Traveller">The Unfortunate Traveller</ref></hi> (1594) and <hi rend="italic">Lenten Stuff</hi> (1599).</p>
<head>Shakespeare</head>
<p>Regarding Shakespeare: Burby published two key editions of Shakespearean works, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_quarto">first quarto</ref> of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Love's_Labor's_Lost">Love's Labor's Lost</ref></hi> (1598; printed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_White_(printer)">William White</ref>)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_quarto">second quarto</ref> of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romeo_and_Juliet">Romeo and Juliet</ref></hi> (1599; printed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Creede">Thomas Creede</ref>). The title page of the <hi rend="italic">R&amp;J</hi> Q2 states that that edition was "Newly corrected, augmented, and amended" – which has been interpreted to indicate that Q2 was issued as a deliberate correction and replacement for the defective Q1, the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bad_quarto">bad quarto</ref>" printed by John Danter in 1597. The title page of Burby's Q1 of <hi rend="italic">LLL</hi>, the earliest play text to be printed under Shakespeare's name, also claims that that edition was "Newly corrected and augmented" – which has been taken by some commentators as a possible indication of an earlier "bad quarto" of <hi rend="italic">LLL</hi> that has not survived.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Burby had subsidiary connections with the Shakespeare canon as well. He published <hi rend="italic">Palladis Tamia</hi> (1598) by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Meres">Francis Meres</ref>, which contains an important reference to Shakespeare and a list of Shakespearean works produced up to 1598. Burby also published (with no attribution of authorship) the first two quartos of <hi rend="italic">The Taming of a Shrew</hi> (Q1, 1594; Q2, 1596), the early alternative version of Shakespeare's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Taming_of_the_Shrew">The Taming of the Shrew</ref>.</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> Also, Burby issued the two early quartos of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_III_(play)">Edward III</ref></hi> (1596, 1599), the one play of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shakespeare_Apocrypha">Shakespeare Apocrypha</ref> that is most commonly seen as having at least some of Shakespeare's work in it.</p>
<head>Other drama</head>
<p>Burby published a number of other plays, attributed or anonymous, during his career:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">The Cobbler's Prophecy,</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Wilson_(dramatist)">Robert Wilson</ref> (1594)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">George a Greene, or The Pinner of Wakefield</hi> (1599)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">A Knack to Know an Honest Man</hi> (1596)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mother_Bombie">Mother Bombie</ref>,</hi> John Lyly (1594, 1598)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Orlando Furioso,</hi> Robert Greene (1594, 1599).</item></list>
<p>Burby's relationship with the texts of Robert Greene is worth noting; in addition to <hi rend="italic">Orlando Furioso,</hi> Burby issued Greene's pamphlets <hi rend="italic">The Third and Last Part of Coney-Catching</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of Robert Greene</hi> (both 1592). The play <hi rend="italic">George a Greene</hi> has sometimes been attributed to Greene's pen.</p>
<p>Burby often worked with the printers John Danter and Simon Stafford, as with many of the texts listed above.</p>
<head>Other works</head>
<p>Also in 1594, Burby published <hi rend="italic">The Second Report of Doctor Faustus, Containing His Appearances, and the Deeds of Wagner</hi> – an anonymous prose work that elaborated the story of the magician, and which was written to capitalise on the success of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Marlowe">Marlowe's</ref> famous play <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Tragical_History_of_Doctor_Faustus">Doctor Faustus</ref>.</hi> And he published <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Lodge">Thomas Lodge</ref>'s <hi rend="italic">Wit's Misery and the World's Madness</hi> in 1596.</p>
<p>Burby published other books on a range of subjects. He was one of the three publishers who issued Robert Allot's verse anthology <hi rend="italic">England's Parnassus</hi> in 1600 (the other two being <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Ling">Nicholas Ling</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Heyes_(Publisher-bookseller)">Thomas Heyes</ref>). He published many religious works, as did all the publishers of his era; and he issued some of the multi-volume chivalric romances that were the best-sellers of the age, like <hi rend="italic">The Mirror of Knighhood</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Champions of Christendom.</hi></p>
<head>Post mortem</head>
<p>The exact date of Burby's death is not known, though it fell between 24 August and 26 September in 1607. In 1609 Burby's widow assigned his copyrights – mainly of theological works – to the publisher's former apprentice Nicholas Bourne. Bourn had printed no dramatic works in his career, but was a successful publisher of news who worked for many years in partnership with Nathaniel Butter.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>The overall quality of Burby's work as a publisher has been variously evaluated. Commentators have complained about the quality of the printing in some of Burby's texts; while Burby was not a printer, it can be asserted that he should have employed better craftsmen. It has even been argued that the printing in the "bad quarto" of <hi rend="italic">Romeo and Juliet,</hi> Danter's 1597 Q1, is superior to the printing of the Burby/Creede Q2, the "good" quarto of 1599 – that Q2 "is on the whole less carefully printed than Q1."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
</text>
