<text id="autogum_bio_doc635" title="Dabiša of Bosnia" shortTile="dabisa-bosnia" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2003-06-24" dateModified="2019-07-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dabi%C5%A1a_of_Bosnia" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Dabiša of Bosnia</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Stephen Dabiša</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbo-Croatian_language">Serbo-Croatian</ref>: <hi lang="hbs-Latn" rend="italic">Stjepan Dabiša</hi>, Стефан Дабиша; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hungarian_language">Hungarian</ref>: <hi lang="hu" rend="italic">Dabiša István</hi>; died on 8 September 1395) was as a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kotromanić_dynasty">Kotromanić dynasty</ref> who reigned as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_of_Bosnia">King of Bosnia</ref> from March 1391 until his death. Elected to succeed the first king, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tvrtko_I">Tvrtko I</ref>, Dabiša at first maintained the integrity of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Bosnia">Kingdom of Bosnia</ref>. He successfully resisted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Hungary">Hungary</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Naples">Naples</ref>, and even <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Turks">Ottoman Turks</ref>. The latter part of his reign, however, saw the ascent of magnates and considerable loss of Bosnia's territory and influence. </p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>Dabiša's relationship with the rest of the Kotromanić family is uncertain. In a letter, Dabiša called himself younger brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tvrtko_I">Tvrtko I</ref>, who became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ban_of_Bosnia">Ban of Bosnia</ref> in 1353, but this should not be taken literally.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆirković1964170-1">[1]</ref> Influenced by the writings of the 16th century Ragusan chronicler <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mavro_Orbini">Mavro Orbini</ref>, modern historiography usually describes Dabiša as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illegitimate">illegitimate</ref> son of Ninoslav, who was the brother of Tvrtko's father <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vladislav_of_Bosnia">Vladislav</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆošković2009-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>According to Orbini, Dabiša ruled the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Župa">župa</ref></hi> (county) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neretva_(county)">Neretva</ref> (corresponding to the area around the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upper_Neretva">Upper Neretva</ref> and the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konjic">Konjic</ref>) and, supporting Tvrtko's brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vuk,_Ban_of_Bosnia">Vuk</ref>, took part in the rebellion that led to the deposition of Tvrtko in 1366. Dabiša, however, is the only rebel mentioned by Orbini whose name does not appear in contemporary accounts of the uprising. Tvrtko prevailed in 1367 and banished Dabiša, revoking his lands. Dabiša spent the following two decades in obscurity, while Tvrtko had himself crowned King of Bosnia in 1377.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆošković2009-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Election and initial success</head>
<p>Dabiša appears to have mended his relations with King Tvrtko I in the late 1380s, as he is recorded at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_court_in_Sutjeska">royal court</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kraljeva_Sutjeska">Sutjeska</ref> in June 1390. Under unclear circumstances following Tvrtko's sudden death on 10 March 1391, Dabiša was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elective_monarchy">elected king</ref> by the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rusag">rusag</ref></hi>. He immediately notified the authorities of the neighbouring republics of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_of_Venice">Venice</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_of_Ragusa">Ragusa</ref>, which recognized his accession on 1 and 15 June respectively, as well as the kings <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigismund_of_Hungary">Sigismund of Hungary</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ladislaus_of_Naples">Ladislaus of Naples</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆošković2009-2">[2]</ref> Following in his predecessor's footsteps, Dabiša took up using the royal name <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefan_(title)">Stephen</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆirković1964170-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In the first years of his reign, Dabiša successfully maintained the integrity of Tvrtko's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Bosnia">Kingdom of Bosnia</ref>, which included not only <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bosnia_proper">Bosnia proper</ref>, but also <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Croatia_proper">Croatia proper</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dalmatia">Dalmatia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zachlumia">Zachlumia</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raška_(region)">Rascia</ref>. The former two had been conquered from King Sigismund and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary,_Queen_of_Hungary">Queen Mary of Hungary</ref>, and the Republic of Ragusa's immediate attempts to convince the Dalmatian cities to return to the fold of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lands_of_the_Hungarian_Crown">Hungarian Crown</ref> ended in failure. Sigismund and Mary were not the only one claiming Dalmatia - or the Hungarian lands in general. Insisting that Dabiša did not support his bid for the Hungarian throne as effectively as his predecessor had, King Ladislaus of Naples started to enforce his own claim to Dalmatia and Croatia, which Tvrtko I had professed to support when he expanded his realm to include those lands. Dabiša nevertheless remained at Ladislaus' side in his struggle against Sigismund.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆirković1964170-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>From Tvrtko I, Dabiša also inherited the hostility of the Hungarian king, who strived to recover the territories lost to Tvrtko. Sigismund's wish to have his war against Bosnia equated to a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crusade">crusade</ref> obtained <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Boniface_IX">Pope Boniface IX</ref>'s approval.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆirković1964170-1">[1]</ref> Dabiša was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic">Roman Catholic</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFine1994281-3">[3]</ref> but a substantial population of his kingdom consisted of adherents of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bosnian_Church">Bosnian Church</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_Orthodox_Church">Serbian Orthodox Church</ref>, branded "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heretics">heretics</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schismatic_(religion)">schismatics</ref>" respectively in Sigismund's letter to Boniface.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFine1994279-4">[4]</ref> It is not known what came about this planned offensive.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆirković1964170-1">[1]</ref> In the spring of 1392, Dabiša's troops defeated an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Turk">Ottoman Turkish</ref> incursion, reminiscing Tvrtko's victory at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Bileća">Battle of Bileća</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆirković1964171-5">[5]</ref> Within a year, Dabiša and Sigismund had agreed to a truce.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆirković1964170-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Signs of decline</head>
<p>While the Kingdom of Bosnia retained its standing among neighbouring states in the immediate aftermath of Tvrtko I's death, it was already during Dabiša's reign that conditions within the state started deteriorating. The nobility grew stronger and for the first time acted independently of the king, starting with the Zachlumian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanković_noble_family">Sanković noble family</ref>. Dabiša curbed the Sanković power, but the trend was irreversible and eventually led to the weakening of the royal authority.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆirković1964171-5">[5]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hrvoje_Vukčić_Hrvatinić">Hrvoje Vukčić Hrvatinić</ref>, the kingdom's leading magnate, who governed Croatia on behalf of the Bosnian crown and in defiance of Hungarian claims, came into agreement with Sigismund and Mary but remained loyal to Dabiša. Dabiša and his other vassals were coming closer to an agreement with Sigismund as well, and the two kings were expected to make the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compromise_of_Đakovo">Compromise of Đakovo</ref> in May 1393. In the end, the meeting did not take place.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆirković1964173-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>By June 1394, King Dabiša was in open conflict with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Horvat">John Horvat</ref>, a fervent supporter of Ladislaus and enemy of Sigismund. He ordered that men from his islands of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brač">Brač</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hvar">Hvar</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korčula">Korčula</ref> assist in the siege of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Omiš">Omiš</ref>, a city ruled by Horvat.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆirković1964173-6">[6]</ref> Sigismund, who had been amassing an army since April, took advantage of the discord. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Dobor_(1394)">Battle of Dobor</ref> saw John Horvat's defeat and execution as well as destruction of the eponymous town on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/River_Bosna">river Bosna</ref> by Sigismund's troos. Soon thereafter, in a camp near the ruins of the town, Dabiša submitted to Sigismund. He resigned Croatia and Dalmatia to the Hungarian king and, with the agreement of his vassals, recognized him as his feudal overlord as well as heir designate to the Bosnian throne. It is not clear what prompted Dabiša to agree to such harsh terms. In return, as evident from a treaty issued in July 1394, Sigismund included Dabiša among the highest ranking Hungarian officials and named him <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ispán">ispán</ref></hi> (count) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Somogy_County_(former)">Somogy</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆirković1964174-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEEngel1996176-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Death and legacy</head>
<figure><caption>Charter by which Dabiša granted Veljaci to his daughter and her heirs</caption></figure>
<p>The agreement to recognize Sigismund as king following Dabiša indicates that the latter was by then of advanced age.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆirković1964174-7">[7]</ref> Indeed, King Dabiša's health deteriorated in early 1395. At the end of March, writing from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bišće">Bišće</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zachlumia">Zachlumia</ref>, Dabiša requested that Ragusan authorities send a physician. The following month, in Sutjeska, he issued a charter granting the Zachlumian village of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Veljaci">Veljaci</ref> to his daughter Stana, whose daughter Vladika was married to the nobleman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juraj_Radivojević">Juraj Radivojević</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆošković2009-2">[2]</ref> He died on 8 September 1395. Despite initially consenting to his agreement with Sigismund, it was Dabiša's widow, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helen_of_Bosnia">Helen</ref>, who succeeded in ascending the throne with the support of the magnates.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆirković1964176-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>Despite an auspicious start, Dabiša's reign ended with the Kingdom of Bosnia displaying first signs of decay. Much of Tvrtko's extraordinary legacy was lost in the summer of 1394, and the state resumed its previous boundaries. Dabiša left the Bosnian state more dependent on Hungary than ever before, and the kingdom's influence in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balkans">Balkans</ref> waned.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEĆirković1964174-7">[7]</ref></p>
</text>
