<text id="autogum_bio_doc627" title="Jacopo di Cione" shortTile="jacopo-di-cione" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-04-04" dateModified="2018-12-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacopo_di_Cione" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Jacopo di Cione</head>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">Madonna and Child with Saints</hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tempera">tempera</ref> and gold on panel by Jacopo di Cione, 1391, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honolulu_Museum_of_Art">Honolulu Museum of Art</ref>.  This triptych once hung in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_San_Lorenzo,_Florence">Church of San Lorenzo, Florence</ref>.  The four saints may represent (from left to right) St. Amata, St. Concordia, St. Andrew, and Pope St. Mark, each of whose relics are in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_San_Lorenzo,_Florence">San Lorenzo</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jacopo di Cione</hi> (c. 1325 – after 1390) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italian_people">Italian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gothic_art">Gothic</ref> period painter in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_of_Florence">Republic of Florence</ref>.</p>
<head>Life and career</head>
<p>Born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florence">Florence</ref> between 1320 and 1330, he is closely associated with his three older brothers <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea_di_Cione_di_Arcangelo">Andrea di Cione di Arcangelo</ref> (called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orcagna">Orcagna</ref>), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nardo_di_Cione">Nardo di Cione</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matteo_di_Cione">Matteo di Cione</ref>.  The di Cione (pronounced dee choh’ nay) brothers often worked collaboratively.  Jacopo lived in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basilica_of_Santa_Maria_del_Popolo">popolo</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Maria_Novella">Sancte Marie Novelle</ref> and, later in life, in the popolo <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basilica_of_San_Lorenzo,_Florence">Sancti Laurentii</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1366–68 Jacopo worked on a large chamber in the guildhall of the judges and notaries, Florence (a surviving altarpiece with Crucifixion is in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Gallery,_London">National Gallery, London</ref>).  After Andrea's death in 1368 Jacopo took over some of his brother's commissions, for example guaranteeing to complete a painting of the Virgin and assuming responsibility for the altarpiece of St Matthew, both for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orsanmichele">Orsanmichele</ref>, Florence.  He enrolled in the Arte dei Medici e Speziali in 1369, and was one of the consuls of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Painters_guild">guild</ref> in 1384, 1387 and 1392.</p>
<p>Jacopo also worked regularly with the painter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niccolò_di_Pietro_Gerini">Niccolò di Pietro Gerini</ref>.  In 1370–71 they produced the polyptych for the high altar of the church of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Pier_Maggiore,_Florence">San Pier Maggiore, Florence</ref>.  Niccolò was paid for the overall design, while Jacopo seems to have been responsible for the narratives.  The altarpiece is one of the largest commissioned in fourteenth-century Florence, and was probably commissioned by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albizzi">Albizzi</ref> family.  The twelve main panels of the altarpiece are in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Gallery,_London">National Gallery, London</ref>, but the predella showing scenes from the life of Saint Peter has been dispersed.  The two painters again collaborated in 1372–73 on the large panel of the Coronation of the Virgin commissioned by the mint of Florence, and in 1386 they received the commission for a fresco of the Annunciation for the council chamber in the Palazzo dei Priori, Volterra.</p>
<p>Between 1378 and 1380 Jacopo worked in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florence_Cathedral">Florence Cathedral</ref>  – he is recorded as Matteo guarantor – and continued to procure marble for the cathedral workshop after his brother's death.  Later Jacopo probably also executed gilding decoration for twelve marble statues for the jamb of the main porch, and completed other work in the cathedral.  In 1382 and 1385 Jacopo is recorded working at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loggia_dei_Priori">Loggia dei Priori</ref>, Florence, and in 1386 he provided four panel paintings to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avignon">Avignon</ref> office of the merchant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francesco_di_Marco_Datini">Francesco di Marco Datini</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prato">Prato</ref>.  In 1391 Jacopo painted the altar for the Church of San Lorenzo in Florence (now in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honolulu_Museum_of_Art">Honolulu Museum of Art</ref>).  He died in Florence, after 2 May 1398 and before 1400.</p>
<head>Gallery</head>
<list type="unordered">
<item><hi rend="italic">St. Peter Enthroned Between St. Paul and the Faithful</hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tempera">tempera</ref> on wood panel painting by Jacopo di Cione, 1370–1, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vatican_Museums">Vatican Museums</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Madonna and Child with Angels</hi>, by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea_Orcagna">Andrea Orcagna</ref> and Jacopo di Cione, c. 1317, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Gallery_of_Art">National Gallery of Art</ref> (Washington DC)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">The Annunciation</hi> by Jacopo di Cione</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">San Zanobi e una devota</hi> by Jacopo di Cione</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">San Casciano in Val di Pesa</hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_del_Biondo">Giovanni del Biondo</ref> and Jacopo di Cione</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">The Annunciation</hi> by Jacopo di Cione, with upside down lettering</item>
</list>
</text>
