<text id="autogum_bio_doc735" title="Gilbert Cavan" shortTile="gilbert-cavan" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-28" dateModified="2018-07-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilbert_Cavan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gilbert Cavan</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Gilbert Cavan</hi> (died 1420) was a cleric based primarily in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galloway">Galloway</ref> in the early 15th century, a servant of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Douglas">earls of Douglas</ref> and briefly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Galloway">Bishop of Galloway</ref>-elect. His name is also written <hi rend="bold">Caven</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Cawan</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Caben</hi>, with other variants, perhaps representing Gaelic or Irish <hi rend="bold">Cabhan</hi>, although the name is not locational, it is a <hi rend="italic">dictus</hi> rather than a <hi rend="italic">de</hi> name.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-93-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<head>Background</head>
<p>Much about his early background rests on whether or not Gilbert Cavan was the clerk who was granted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expectative">expectative</ref> provision on 1 June 1381, to a vicarage under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holyrood_Abbey">Holyrood Abbey</ref> and then another vicarage under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kelso_Abbey">Kelso Abbey</ref> on 21 December. If this was Gilbert Cavan seeking benefices as early as 1381, then he would have been 24 years old or over at that date, and thus born before 1357.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-9394-2">[2]</ref> Likewise his student days may have begun as early as 1381, but he is not known to have had any academic award until 1 May 1406, and is not given any academic title even as late as 1402.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> It is doubtful that this was Gilbert Cavan, especially as he disappears from records for more than two decades.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-94-4">[4]</ref> A letter from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avignon_Pope_Benedict_XIII">Avignon Pope Benedict XIII</ref> in late summer 1400 provided one <hi rend="italic">Gilbert Oliverei</hi>, "perpetual vicar of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caerlaverock_Parish">Caerlaverock</ref>, to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parish_church">parish church</ref> of <hi rend="italic">Kyrkynner, alias Carnismole</hi>".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> According to the view of Professor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/D._E._R._Watt">Donald Watt</ref>, this Gilbert <hi rend="italic">Oliverei</hi> ("[son] of Oliver") is probably not Gilbert Cavan either, but a namesake rival, though this is admitted to be rather tentative.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-94-4">[4]</ref> It is known for certain though that by 1406, he held a bachelorate in Decrees (i.e. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_Law">Canon Law</ref>); in English safe-conducts dating to 1412/3, he is styled <hi rend="italic">Magister</hi> (i.e. Master), but this title is doubtful as he is never styled so in papal letters.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-93-1">[1]</ref>  He studied at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Paris">University of Paris</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-9394-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Early career in the church</head>
<p>A letter from Pope Benedict XIII, dated 15 September 1402, addressed Gilbert as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rector_(ecclesiastical)">rector</ref> of the parish church of <hi rend="italic">Carnemol</hi> (Carnesmole, now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kirkinner">Kirkinner</ref> in Farines, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wigtownshire">Wigtownshire</ref>), and confirmed him as rector of that church after the death of the previous rector Domhnall MacDomhnaill.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> The letter mentioned that, upon the death of Domhnall, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archibald_Douglas,_4th_Earl_of_Douglas">Archibald Douglas, 4th Earl of Douglas</ref>, who had the right of presentation, presented Gilbert to Stephen [de Malcavston], <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prior_of_St_Mary's_Isle">Prior of St Mary's Isle</ref>, the prelate acting as vicar general of spiritualities in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Galloway">diocese of Galloway</ref> while Bishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_de_Rossy">Thomas de Rossy</ref> was abroad. Gilbert is said to have doubted the validity of this process, and thus the papal letter was issued in order  to confirm Gilbert in his position as rector of Carnesmole.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> A repetition of this letter was issued on 1 May 1406, addressed to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbot_of_Sainte_Geneviève">abbot of Sainte Geneviève</ref> (University of Paris), the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbot_of_Glenluce">abbot of Glenluce</ref>, and the chancellor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noyon">Noyon</ref>, now styling Gilbert a Bachelor of Decrees.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-McGurk-14950-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Bishop and Archdeacon of Galloway</head>
<p>Sometime between 1412 and 1415, probably in the latter year, the chapter of Whithorn elected Gilbert to succeed the late <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elisaeus_Adougan">Elisaeus Adougan</ref> as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Galloway">Bishop of Galloway</ref>; but, despite travelling to the papal court in Spain, Gilbert failed to obtain papal confirmation, and the papal chaplain and auditor, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_de_Buittle">Thomas de Buittle</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeacon_of_Galloway">Archdeacon of Galloway</ref>, was provided to the bishopric instead by Pope Benedict XIII on 14 June 1415.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> This probably occurred against the will of the Douglas family, to whom Cavan was a senior clerk.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> Perhaps in compensation, six days later (20 June) Gilbert received provision to the now vacant archdeaconry of Galloway, a position Cavan held only very shortly, for he resigned it on exchange with John Gray sometime before 20 May 1417.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> On 3 July 1415, he was given a canonry in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Moray">diocese of Moray</ref> with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prebend">prebend</ref> of <hi rend="italic">Invecheclyn</hi> (i.e. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inverkeithny">Inverkeithny</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huntly,_Scotland">Strathbogie</ref>), being permitted to retain Carnesmole.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> The Pope had earlier allowed him to retain the parish church of Carnesmole even after becoming archdeacon.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> He received the church of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kirkandrews,_Dumfries_and_Galloway">Kirkandrews</ref> (Purton), near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Borgue,_Stewartry_of_Kirkcudbright">Borgue</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kirkcudbrightshire">Kirkcudbrightshire</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-94-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Service to the Douglases</head>
<p>Gilbert was a clerk and associate of the earls of Douglas. A papal letter of 1406 mentioned that he was "chaplain and familiar" of Princess Margaret, Duchess of Touraine, and tutor to her first-born son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archibald_Douglas,_5th_Earl_of_Douglas">Archibald</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-McGurk-14950-8">[8]</ref> He made several trips to England in 1412 and 1413 in connection with the earl's ransom,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-94-4">[4]</ref>  and was one of several clerks that the earl used as ambassadors and messengers.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> He remained a clerk of the earl of Douglas until 1420, the year of his death. He died a some point between 19 August and 22 November 1420.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-94-4">[4]</ref></p>
</text>
