<text id="autogum_bio_doc200" title="John Stokoe" shortTile="john-stokoe" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-06-04" dateModified="2019-02-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Stokoe" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Stokoe</head><p><hi rend="bold">John Stokoe</hi> was a 19th-century  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tyneside">Tyneside</ref> (and maybe <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Shields">South Shields</ref>) author and historian. He co-operated with the author <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Collingwood_Bruce">John Collingwood Bruce</ref> in compiling the hugely important “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northumbrian_Minstrelsy_by_Bruce_and_Stokoe,_1882">Northumbrian Minstrelsy</ref>”  published in 1882.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-AllansMisc-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Details</head>
<p>Stokoe lived is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Shields">South Shields</ref> (according to edition of “The North-Country Garland of Song” appearing in the Monthly Chronicle of January 1891.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> In editing the “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northumbrian_Minstrelsy_by_Bruce_and_Stokoe,_1882">Northumbrian Minstralry</ref>” he co-operated with fellow author <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Collingwood_Bruce">John Collingwood Bruce</ref>. The article <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_of_Northumbria">Music of Northumbria</ref>, credits John Stokoe with copying out, in 1950, some of the tunes from John Smith’s tunebook of 1750, a book now long lost, and the pair  creating this comprehensive collection of old Northern Songs. The work was on behalf of, and published by, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Society_of_Antiquaries_of_Newcastle_upon_Tyne">Newcastle Society of Antiquaries</ref>.</p>
<p>According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Allan_(publisher)">Thomas Allan</ref> in his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allan's_Illustrated_Edition_of_Tyneside_Songs_and_Readings">Illustrated Edition of Tyneside Songs and Readings</ref> (page1), “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Keel_Row">(Weel May) The Keel Row</ref>”, described by many as the Tyneside National Anthem, was a popular local melody long before 1760 and is long associated with the area covered by the medieval English kingdom of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northumbria">Northumbria</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tyneside">Tyneside</ref>, and it was not originally Scottish words to a Scottish tune, as several people had been claiming.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-AllansMisc-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In the same book on page 54, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Allan_(publisher)">Thomas Allan</ref> quotes Stokoe from "The North-Country Garland of Song” giving details of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Purvis_(Blind_Willie)">William Purvis (Blind Willie)</ref>. He gives details oh Blind Willie’s father, baptism, life, and music, and goes on to say that although many people have attributed the melody of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broom_Buzzems">Broom Buzzems</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Purvis_(Blind_Willie)">Blind Willie</ref>, there is no evidence of this other than the singer’s partiality for it.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-AllansMisc-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>These include:-</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>“<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northumbrian_Minstrelsy_by_Bruce_and_Stokoe,_1882">Northumbrian Minstrelsy. A collection of Ballads, Melodies and Small Pipe Tunes of Northumbria</ref>” (206 pages) – edited by John Collingwood Bruce and John Stokoe - published 1882.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></item></list>
<p>The article <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_of_Northumbria">Music of Northumbria</ref>, credits John Stokoe with copying out, in 1950, some of the tunes from John Smith’s tunebook of 1750, a book now long lost, and, together with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Collingwood_Bruce">John Collingwood Bruce</ref>, creating this comprehensive collection of old Northern Songs. The work was on behalf of, and published by, the Ancient Melodies Committee of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Society_of_Antiquaries_of_Newcastle_upon_Tyne">Newcastle Society of Antiquaries</ref>.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>“Northumbrian Minstrelsy. A Collection of Bag-Pipe Tunes, chiefly of the Olden Time, adapted to the Northumberland Small-Pipes” - edited by John Stokoe – c1882 by Society of Antiquaries</item>
<item>“Songs and Ballads of Northern England” (216 pages) – by John Stokoe – published 1893</item>
<item>“The North-Country Garland of Song” was written and provided by John Stockoe. It was a monthly item giving details of the history behind a song or songs and any event which inspired them, the songwriter etc. It was also within the monthly edition of “The monthly Chronicle of North-Country Lore and Legend”, printed and published by the Proprietors of the Newcastle Weekly Chronicle, Newcastle upon Tyne (and 24 Warwick Lane, Paternoster Row, London), and edited by Walter Scott. It was in existence c1890 but only for a relatively short period.</item></list>
</text>
