<text id="autogum_bio_doc405" title="Benkos Biohó" shortTile="benkos-bioho" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-19" dateModified="2019-06-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benkos_Bioh%C3%B3" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Benkos Biohó</head>
<figure><caption>Statue of Benkos Biohó</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Benkos Biohó</hi> (late 16th century — 1621), also known as <hi rend="bold">Domingo Biohó</hi>, was born into a royal family that ruled Bioho one of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bissagos_Islands">Bissagos Islands</ref> off the coast of what is today <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guinea-Bissau">Guinea-Bissau</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> He was seized by the Portuguese slave trader, Pedro Gomes Reinel, sold to businessman Juan Palacios, and later, after transportation to what is now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colombia">Colombia</ref> in South America, sold again to the Spaniard Alonso del Campo in 1596, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cartagena_de_Indias">Cartagena de Indias</ref>. He established the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maroon_(people)">maroon</ref> community of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Basilio_de_Palenque">San Basilio de Palenque</ref> sometime in the 16th century. He was betrayed and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanging">hung</ref> by the governor of Cartagena in 1621.</p>
<p>The former African king escaped from the slave port of Cartagena with ten others and founded <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Basilio_de_Palenque">San Basilio de Palenque</ref>, then known as the "village of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maroon_(people)">maroons</ref>". In 1713 it became the first free village in the Americas by decree from the King of Spain, when he gave up sending his troops on futile missions to attack their fortified mountain hideaway.</p>
<p>Biohó made his first escape when the boat that was transporting him down the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magdalena_River">Magdalena River</ref> sank. He was recaptured but escaped again in 1599 into the marshy lands southeast of Cartagena. He organized an army that came to dominate all of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montes_de_María">Montes de María</ref> region. He also formed an intelligence network and used the information collected to help organize more escapes and to guide the runaway slaves into the liberated territory, known as settlement. He used the title "king of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arcabuco">Arcabuco</ref>".</p>
<p>On 18 July 1605, the Governor of Cartagena, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerónimo_de_Suazo_y_Casasola">Gerónimo de Suazo y Casasola</ref>, unable to defeat the Maroons, offered a peace treaty to Biohó, recognising the autonomy of the Matuna Bioho Palenque and accepting his entrance into the city armed and dressed in Spanish fashion, while the palenque promised to stop receiving more runaway slaves, cease their aid in escape attempts, and stop addressing Biohó as "king". Peace was finalized in 1612 under the governorship of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diego_Fernández_de_Velasco">Diego Fernández de Velasco</ref>. The treaty was violated by the Spaniards in 1619 when they captured Biohó as he was walking carelessly into the city. He was hanged and quartered on 16 March 1621. Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/García_Girón">García Girón</ref>, who ordered the execution, argued bitterly that "it was dangerous the extent to which Biohó was respected in the population" and that "his lies and enchantment would drive the nations of Guinea away from the city."</p>
<p>The betrayal contributed to the history of distrust of Colombia’s government.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>By the end of the seventeenth century, the area of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montes_de_María">Montes de María</ref> had over 600 maroons, under the command of Domingo Padilla, who claimed for himself the title of captain while his wife Jane adopted that of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viceroy">viceroy</ref>, and successfully challenged further attempts at sovereignty from the colonial authorities.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Basilio_de_Palenque">San Basilio de Palenque</ref> was declared <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masterpieces_of_the_Oral_and_Intangible_Heritage_of_Humanity">Masterpieces of the Oral and Intangible Heritage of Humanity</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UNESCO">UNESCO</ref> in 2005.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> At about 50 miles east of Cartagena, hills of strategic value, used as lookout posts, still hear the names of the runaway neighborhood: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sincerin">Sincerin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahates">Mahates</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gambote">Gambote</ref>.</p>
</text>
