<text id="autogum_bio_doc668" title="John II, Lord of Polanen" shortTile="john-ii-lord-polanen" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-09-06" dateModified="2018-08-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_II%2C_Lord_of_Polanen" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John II, Lord of Polanen</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">John III, Lord of Polanen</hi> (c.1325 – 3 November 1378 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breda">Breda</ref>) was Lord of Polanen, Lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De_Lek">De Lek</ref> and Lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breda">Breda</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was a son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_I,_Lord_of_Polanen">John I, Lord of Polanen</ref> and Catherine of Brederode.  He succeeded his father in 1342 and also took over his father's position as councillor of the Count of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Holland">Holland</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Zeeland">Zeeland</ref>.  In the autumn of 1343, he accompanied Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_IV,_Count_of_Holland">William IV</ref> on a pilgrimage to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Land">Holy Land</ref>.  He also participated in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crusade">crusade</ref> against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Prussians">Prussians</ref>, but not in the campaign against the West Frisians, so that he was not present when William IV was killed during the disastrous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Warns">Battle of Warns</ref>.  In 1350, John II and his uncle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_of_Duivenvoorde">William of Duivenvoorde</ref> travelled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Hainaut">Hainaut</ref> to pay homage to Countess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret_II,_Countess_of_Hainaut">Margaret II</ref>.  In this way, they supporte the Hook faction in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hook_and_Cod_wars">Hook and Cod wars</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1339, John purchased the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lordship_of_Breda">Lordship of Breda</ref> and built <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breda_Castle">Breda Castle</ref>, together with his father.  Somewhere between 1347 and 1350, John was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burgrave">Burgrave</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geertruidenberg">Geertruidenberg</ref>.  In 1350, he purchased the Land of Breda for 43000 florins from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_III,_Duke_of_Brabant">John III, Duke of Brabant</ref>.  He also acquired <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_justice">high justice</ref> over Breda.</p>
<p>During the Hook and Cod wars, he lost his castle in Polanen and the Lordship of De Lek. In 1358, he was compensated with other fiefs and possessions.  In this period, he concentrated his efforts on extending his holdings in the Breda area.</p>
<p>John II was captured during the Battle of Baesweiler in 1371.  He was released several months later, after his relatives had paid a ransom.  In 1375, he was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stadtholder">stadtholder</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Holme">Great Holme</ref>.</p>
<p>John II died in 1378 and was buried in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grote_kerk_(Breda)">Church of Our Lady</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breda">Breda</ref>.</p>
<head>Marriages and issue</head>
<p>John II of Polanen married three times.</p>
<p>In 1340, he married Oda of Horne-Altena (1318-1353).  They had three children:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_III,_Lord_of_Polanen">John III</ref>, his heir</item>
<item>Beatrice (c.1344 – 1394); married Henry VIII, the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VII,_Lord_of_Bautershem">Henry VII, Lord of Bautershem</ref>, who was also Lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bergen_op_Zoom">Bergen op Zoom</ref> as Henry I, and his wife, Maria Merxheim, Lady of Wuustwezel and Brecht</item>
<item>Oda (c.1351 – 15th century), married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_III,_Burgrave_of_Montfoort">Henry III, Burgrave of Montfoort</ref></item></list>
<p>In 1353, he married Matilda (c.1324 – 1366), an illegitimate daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_III,_Duke_of_Brabant">John III, Duke of Brabant</ref>.  They had two sons:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Dirck of the Leck (d. 1416), married Gilisje of Cralingen.  He was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outlaw">outlawed</ref> for a while, because he was suspected of having participated in the murder of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aleid_van_Poelgeest">Aleid van Poelgeest</ref></item>
<item>Henry of the Leck (d. 1427), married Jeanne of Ghistelles, and was a councillor of Countess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacqueline,_Countess_of_Hainaut">Jacqueline</ref> of Holland</item></list>
<p>In 1370, he married Margaret, a daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto,_Lord_of_Lippe">Otto, Lord of Lippe</ref> and Irmgard of the Marck.  They had one son:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto,_Lord_of_the_Leck">Otto</ref> (d. before 20 October 1428), married before 1396 to Sophia, a daughter of Count Frederick III of Bergh-'s-Heerenberg and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_of_Buren">Catherine of Buren</ref></item></list>
</text>
