<text id="autogum_bio_doc083" title="Víctor Manuel Báez" shortTile="victor-manuel-baez" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-09-20" dateModified="2019-09-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/V%C3%ADctor_Manuel_B%C3%A1ez" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Víctor Manuel Báez</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Víctor Manuel Báez Chino</hi> (died 14 June 2012) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexican</ref> crime journalist and editor for the digital edition of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milenio">Milenio</ref></hi> newspaper in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xalapa">Xalapa</ref> and an editor for the crime-oriented website <hi rend="italic">Reporteros Policiacos</hi>. Báez was abducted 13 June 2012 and found murdered the next day in the main city square of Xalapa, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Veracruz">Veracruz</ref>, Mexico.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bbc-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-utsandiego-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cpjfourth-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>While he was the fifth journalist killed in the state of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Veracruz">Veracruz</ref> in a two-month period in 2012, he was the ninth journalists killed in Veracruz since March 2011 as a result of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mexican_Drug_War">Mexican Drug War</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-guardian-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-milenio-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-elnuevoherald-6">[6]</ref> At the time of his murder, six journalists had been killed in Mexico in 2012.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nytimes2-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Báez was the editor of the crime section for the state digital edition of the national newspaper <hi rend="italic">Milenio</hi> and an editor of the website <hi rend="italic">Reporteros Policiacos</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cpj-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>He was a colleague of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regina_Martínez_Pérez">Regina Martínez Pérez</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vulliamy-9">[9]</ref> a <hi rend="italic">Proceso</hi> crime reporter who was also killed in 2012.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bbcnewsrmp-10">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Death</head>
<figure><caption>Báez's corpse was found on a street named after Úrsulo Galván and near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parque_Juárez_(Xalapa)">Parque Juárez</ref> (pictured), Xalapa, which was close to his office.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-milenio-5">[5]</ref></caption></figure>Mexico CityXalapaMentioned locations within Mexico relative to the capital Mexico City.
<p>Víctor Manuel Báez was kidnapped by three armed men in a gray van outside of the offices of <hi rend="italic">Reporteros Policiacos</hi> at around 11 p.m. when he was leaving work 13 June 2012.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cpjfourth-4">[4]</ref> Báez was found murdered the next day. His body had been dumped on a street by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parque_Juárez_(Xalapa)">Parque Juárez</ref> in the center of Xalapa, which is the capital of Veracruz state.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-guardian-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bbc-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los_Zetas">Los Zetas</ref> drug cartel took responsibility for his murder in a note was left by his body, which read, "This is what happens to traitors and those who act smart. Sincerely, the Zetas."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-guardian-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cpj-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Context</head>
<p>The violence against journalists in Veracruz has been exacerbated by the struggle between the cartels Los Zetas and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sinaloa_Cartel">Sinaloa</ref>, state intervention and the declaration of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mexican_Drug_War">Mexican Drug War</ref>, as well as corruption.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vulliamy-9">[9]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-autogenerated2-11">[11]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-blog-12">[12]</ref> Journalists have been visible targets of all of these forces. Journalists killed in Veracruz since March 2011 include <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noel_López_Olguín">Noel López Olguín</ref> (killed 8 March 2011 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinameca,_Veracruz">Chinameca, Veracruz</ref>) was a crime reporter for <hi rend="italic">La Verdad in Jáltipan</hi>;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miguel_Ángel_López_Velasco">Miguel Ángel López Velasco</ref>, a crime columnist, and his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miguel_Ángel_López_Velasco">Miseal López Solana</ref>, a photojournalist, who both worked for Notiver (killed 20 June 2011 in Veracruz, Veracruz);<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-autogenerated1-14">[14]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nytimes-15">[15]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yolanda_Ordaz_de_la_Cruz">Yolanda Ordaz de la Cruz</ref> (killed 26 July 2011) was a fellow crime reporter who worked for López and with his son at <hi rend="italic">Notiver</hi> and she was abducted 3 days earlier from Veracruz and found decapitated in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boca_del_Río,_Veracruz">Boca del Río</ref>;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Miami-16">[16]</ref> Regina Martínez Pérez was a journalist for the investigative news magazine <hi rend="italic">Proceso</hi> (killed 28 April 2012 in Xalapa);<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-bbcnewsrmp-10">[10]</ref> and the murder of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012_Veracruz_murder_of_journalists">Guillermo Luna Varela</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012_Veracruz_murder_of_journalists">Gabriel Huge Córdoba</ref> of <hi rend="italic">Notiver</hi>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012_Veracruz_murder_of_journalists">Esteban Rodríguez Rodríguez</ref>, as well as newspaper publicist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012_Veracruz_murder_of_journalists">Ana Irasema Becerra Jiménez</ref> (brutally killed 3 May 2012, stuffed into bags and dumped in a canal in Boca del Río).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-elu-17">[17]</ref></p>
<head>Impact</head>
<p>The investigation was declared closed by the state, although press rights organizations and critics have rejected the investigators' reasoning.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vulliamy-9">[9]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nytimes1-18">[18]</ref></p>
<p>After the Mexican navy captured drug cartel member Juan Carlos Hernández Pulido, it announced that evidence found at his arrest linked him to the murder of Ana Irasema Becerra Jiménez in Veracruz and three murdered journalists<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nytimes2-7">[7]</ref> Investigators then announced they had found a link between this crime and Báez's case as witnesses of Báez's murder were able to identify two men killed at a related shootout. A spokesperson for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Committee_to_Protect_Journalists">Committee to Protect Journalists</ref> said he doubted the link between the two cases, the interrogation techniques used, and whether the investigators had evidence that could lead to a prosecution at the federal level.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nytimes1-18">[18]</ref> A spokesperson for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Article_19">Article 19</ref> said, "The government of Veracruz is trying to shelve its worst-ever crisis of violence against the press."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-latimes-19">[19]</ref></p>
<head>Reactions</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irina_Bokova">Irina Bokova</ref>, director-general of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UNESCO">UNESCO</ref> said, "I am deeply concerned about the murder of Víctor Manuel Báez Chino, and call on the authorities to ensure that this crime against freedom of expression, a fundamental human right, does not go unpunished. All too many brave Mexican journalists have been paying with their lives for society’s right to be kept informed. The impunity enjoyed by their murderers must be brought to an end."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-unesco-20">[20]</ref></p>
<p>A Committee to Protect Journalists spokesperson, said, "Perhaps the most devastating effect of this unprecedented wave of violence is the fact that people in Veracruz are being deprived of vital information of one of the issues that is obviously having a very serious effect in the lives of the people, which is the level of violence, the number of killings."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nytimes2-7">[7]</ref></p>
</text>
