<text id="autogum_bio_doc162" title="Jody Turner" shortTile="jody-turner" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-07-28" dateModified="2019-06-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jody_Turner" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Jody Turner</head><figure><caption>Futurist Jody Turner</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jody Turner</hi> is a U.S. West Coast-based <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entrepreneur">entrepreneur</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Futurist">futurist</ref> known for her international brand anthropology <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Insight">insight</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jody_Turner_D\Construct_video_interview_#1-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jody_Turner_D\Construct_video_interview,_#2-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jody_Turner_D\Construct_video_interview_#3-3">[3]</ref> and trend <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Futures_studies">futurism research</ref>, writing<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jody_Turner_for_IDEO-4">[4]</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keynote"> keynote presenting</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Born in the U.S. and raised in part overseas, Turner settled on the West Coast (USA) as a young adult. Turner received a Liberal Arts degree from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Evergreen_State_College">The Evergreen State College</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-linkEvergreenUniversity1-7">[7]</ref> Olympia, Washington, a self-generating curriculum school, where her studies centered on the understanding of current-to-future human endeavors in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Design">design</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Culture">culture</ref>.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Turner began her professional career as a visual communications designer, working 15 years+ from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Francisco">San Francisco</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_City">New York City</ref>, including tenure as communications designer with Nike’s trend resource team. Subsequent design and trend insight work included consulting with Starbucks international retail brand teams and a full-time role instigating a trend library for The Gap/Old Navy with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivy_Ross">Ivy Ross</ref>. In 2003, Turner met Reinier Evers<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> of <ref target="http://Trendwatching.com">Trendwatching.com</ref> at a round table in France, and cites this encounter as critical to launching her career as a trend hunter futurist.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> That same year Turner founded her company <ref target="http://cultureoffuture.com">Culture of Future</ref> (CoF).</p>
<p>Turner speaks at international conferences across the Americas, Europe,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> the Middle East, Australia,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> and within developing nations. She is a regular speaker at the Sustainable Brands Conference in Istanbul. In 2009 she was awarded a World Brand Congress Brand Leadership Award in Mumbai <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> and has worked on numerous global projects focused on empowering women and girls, including the Nike Foundation Girl Effect<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> out of London, and the Forbes Girl Quake project with Denise Restauri.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref></p>
<p>In 2010, Turner mentored then-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/College_for_Creative_Studies">Creative Studies</ref> design student <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Veronika_Scott">Veronika Scott</ref>, and assisted her in the founding of American humanitarian project the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Empowerment_Plan">Empowerment Plan</ref>. The organization provides employment and training to homeless women as they hand-make sleeping-bag coats distributed to the homeless of Detroit, as well as globally via disaster relief programs.</p>
<p>Turner is a strategic insights writer for Fast Company Magazine,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> the Stanford Social Innovation Review,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref> GOOD Magazine<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref> and Shareable.net.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref></p>
<head>Publications</head>
<p>In April 2019 Turner published a global insight trend report entitled <ref target="http://www.impactmania.com/im/jody-turner-a-glimpse-into-your-future/">"Glimpse: Understanding the Future Marketplace"</ref> that summarizes her findings as a cross-generational global trendwatcher.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref></p>
<head>Boards &amp; Associations</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Jody Turner is an adjunct and rotating professor and faculty member at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pacific_Northwest_College_of_Art">Pacific Northwest College of Art</ref> (PNCA) in the MFA in Collaborative Design graduate program.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-20">[20]</ref></item>
<item>Content curator for the San Francisco impact entrepreneur and investor conference <ref target="http://socialcapitalmarkets.net/">SoCap14</ref></item>
<item>Member of Advisory Board for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Empowerment_Plan">Empowerment Plan</ref>, a Detroit-based project aimed at easing homelessness by employing homeless women to create coats that transform into sleeping bags, distributed free of charge to those who need one.</item>
<item>Member of the Advisory Board for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A+D_Museum#Advisory_Board">Architecture and Design Museum (A+D)</ref>, Los Angeles</item>
<item>Former Member of the Advisory Board for <ref target="http://criaglobal.com">Cria Global</ref>, the organization charged with creating the social legacy guidelines for the Rio 2016 Olympics.</item>
<item>Member of the Advisory Board for <ref target="https://www.facebook.com/woman21summit">Women 2.1 Summit</ref>, Ghana, Africa</item>
<item><ref target="http://www.hyperisland.com/community/people/jody-turner">Collaborator</ref> with <ref target="http://www.hyperisland.com">Hyper Island</ref> strategic digital business leadership institution</item></list>
</text>
