<text id="autogum_bio_doc623" title="Mihaloğlu Mehmed Bey" shortTile="mihaloglu-mehmed" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-10-20" dateModified="2019-03-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mihalo%C4%9Flu_Mehmed_Bey" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Mihaloğlu Mehmed Bey</head>In this <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Turkish_language">Ottoman Turkish</ref> style name, <hi rend="italic">Mehmed</hi> is the given name, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Ottoman_titles_and_appellations">title</ref> is <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bey">Bey</ref></hi>, and the family name is <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mihaloğlu">Mihaloğlu</ref></hi>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Mihaloğlu Mehmed Bey</hi> was a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mihaloğulları">Mihaloğulları</ref> family and one of the most important frontier warlords (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uc_beğleri">uc beğleri</ref></hi>) of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balkans">Balkans</ref> during the last phase of the civil war of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Interregnum">Ottoman Interregnum</ref> (1403–1413), and during the early years of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murad_II">Murad II</ref>'s reign.</p>
<head>Life and career</head>
<p>According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franz_Babinger">Franz Babinger</ref>, Mihaloğlu Mehmed was a son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Köse_Mihal">Köse Mihal</ref>, a contemporary and companion of the founder of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_emirate">Ottoman emirate</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Osman_I">Osman I</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBabinger199334-1">[1]</ref> Mehmed had four brothers, Yahşi or Bahşı, Aziz, Hızır, and Yusuf. Of them, only Yahşi, who died in 1413, is somewhat known.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBabinger199334-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBaşar200524-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Ottoman Interregnum</head>
<figure><caption>Mehmed I with court dignitaries, Ottoman miniature</caption></figure>
<p>When <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musa_Çelebi">Musa Çelebi</ref> moved against his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Süleyman_Çelebi">Süleyman Çelebi</ref>, Mihaloğlu Mehmed joined the former, and led the attack against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edirne">Edirne</ref> that resulted in the capture of the city and the overthrow and death of Süleyman in late 1410/early 1411.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKastritsis2007153–158-3">[3]</ref> As a reward, Musa appointed Mihaloğlu as <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beylerbey">beylerbey</ref></hi> (commander in chief and governor-general) for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rumelia_Eyalet">Rumelia</ref>, possibly as a counterweight to two other powerful <hi rend="italic">uc beğleri</hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evrenos">Evrenos</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pasha_Yiğit_Bey">Pasha Yiğit Bey</ref>, who had been major figures in Süleyman's regime.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKastritsis2007162-4">[4]</ref> Mihaloğlu was a close friend of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheikh_Bedreddin">Sheikh Bedreddin</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBabinger199334-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Despite this high favour, Mihaloğlu soon defected to another of Musa's brothers, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mehmed_I">Mehmed Çelebi</ref>, who ruled over <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anatolia">Anatolia</ref>. The date of his defection is unclear; the Serbian historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konstantin_the_Philosopher">Konstantin the Philosopher</ref> places it during Musa's siege of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine">Byzantine</ref> city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Selymbria">Selymbria</ref> in August/September 1411, while the anonymous Ottoman chronicle <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aḥvāl-i_Sulṭān_Meḥemmed">Aḥvāl-i Sulṭān Meḥemmed</ref></hi> ("Affairs of Sultan Mehmed") places it somewhat later, during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_İnceğiz">Battle of İnceğiz</ref>. Other Ottoman sources do not mention his defection at all.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKastritsis2007162-4">[4]</ref> According to Konstantin, Mihaloğlu had aided the escape of the Serbian ruler <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Đurađ_Branković">Đurađ Branković</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref>, and feared Musa's wrath; more likely, Mihaloğlu was worried that Musa might perceive him as a threat and eliminate him. Thus, while Musa was preoccupied with Selymbria, Mihaloğlu took charge of "the most select troops", ostensibly for an attack against Mehmed. Instead, he too went to Constantinople, where the Byzantines welcomed him and ferried him over to Anatolia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKastritsis2007170–171-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>By 1413, according to the <hi rend="italic">Aḥvāl</hi>, Mihaloğlu served as a high-ranking commander under Mehmed Çelebi in the final phase of the civil war. He commanded Mehmed's vanguard in the first clash outside <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bizye">Bizye</ref>, and both there and later at a battle near the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maritsa_River">Maritsa River</ref> he played a major role in the defeat of Musa's forces.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKastritsis2007162,_191–192-6">[6]</ref> Abandoned by his beys, Musa was finally defeated in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Çamurlu">Battle of Çamurlu</ref>. He tried to flee, but his horse got stuck in a rice paddy, where he was captured by Mihaloğlu and other Ottoman lords. Musa was executed soon after.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKastritsis2007194,_215–216-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Given Mihaloğlu's previous treason, however, the victorious <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sultan">sultan</ref> Mehmed distrusted him, and imprisoned him at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tokat">Tokat</ref> in Anatolia—far from Rumelia, where he might cause trouble.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKastritsis2007162–163-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Service under Murad II</head>
<p>After Sultan Mehmed died in 1421, his successor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murad_II">Murad II</ref> faced the rebellion of his uncle, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mustafa_Çelebi">Mustafa Çelebi</ref>. Aided by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Junayd_of_Aydın">Junayd of Aydın</ref>, Mustafa had managed to win over the <hi rend="italic">uc beğleri</hi> of Rumelia, such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turahan_Bey">Turahan Bey</ref>, the sons of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evrenos">Evrenos</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kümelioğlu">Kümelioğlu</ref> family, and had seized Edirne and the European provinces of the empire.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHeywood1993711-9">[9]</ref> On the advice of his councillors—three members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timurtaş">Timurtaş</ref> family, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hacı_Ivaz_Pasha">Hacı Ivaz Pasha</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Çandarlı_Ibrahim_Pasha_the_Elder">Çandarlı Ibrahim Pasha</ref>—Murad released Mihaloğlu from his prison and to assist in the campaign against Mustafa,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEImber199092-10">[10]</ref> and hopefully draw the Rumelian beys to murad's side.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBaşar200524-2">[2]</ref> On his way westwards from Tokat, Mihaloğlu stopped and stayed with the young <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aşıkpaşazade">Aşıkpaşazade</ref>, the future historian, at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dervish">dervish</ref> <hi rend="italic">tekke</hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elvan_Çelebi">Elvan Çelebi</ref>. Aşıkpaşazade accompanied Mihaloğlu Mehmed in his subsequent movements, and is the main source for Mehmed's activities.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEImber199092-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>In 1422, Mustafa crossed over to Anatolia with his army, while Murad moved with his troops from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bursa">Bursa</ref> to confront them at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulubad">Ulubad</ref>, where his men tore down the bridge over the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nilüfer_River">Nilüfer River</ref>, blocking Mustafa's advance.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHeywood1993711-9">[9]</ref> The two armies met at the ruined bridge, with Murad's forces holding the eastern shore and Mustafa's the western. According to Aşıkpaşazade, Mehmed called across the water to the various Rumelian beys in Mustafa's army, accusing them of treachery, while others met with Junayd to convince him to desert with promises of restoring him to his former domains. At the same time, Hacı Ivaz sent false warnings to Mustafa that Murad would go around the nearby lake and attack Mustafa during the night. Junayd indeed abandoned Mustafa's camp, and when Hacı Ivaz feigned an attack during the night, Mustafa fled to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dardanelles">Dardanelles</ref>. The Rumelian beys remained behind with their men, and surrendered to Murad, who pardoned them.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHeywood1993711-9">[9]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEImber199092–93-11">[11]</ref> Murad then pursued his uncle, crossing the Dardanelles on 15 January 1422. His authority in tatters, Mustafa tried to flee to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wallachia">Wallachia</ref>, but was recognized, seized, and hanged at Edirne.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHeywood1993711-9">[9]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEImber199093–94-12">[12]</ref></p>
<p>With his rule secure, Murad now turned against the Byzantines. According to a short chronicle, "on 10 June, Wednesday, at the fourth hour after midday, Mihaloğlu attacked Constantinople", thus beginning the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Constantinople_(1422)">siege of the city</ref>. The eyewitness <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Kananos">John Kananos</ref> describes how the vanguard under Mihaloğlu ravaged the city's suburbs, before Murad himself arrived on 20 June and the siege began in earnest.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEImber199094-13">[13]</ref> In reaction, the Byzantines sponsored the rebellion of Murad's younger brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Küçük_Mustafa">Küçük Mustafa</ref>, in Anatolia. This was supported with men by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anatolian_beyliks">Anatolian beyliks</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Germiyan">Germiyan</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karamanids">Karaman</ref>, who feared the revival of Ottoman power. Mustafa was thus able to gather a significant army, and in late August or early September laid siege to Bursa.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEImber199095-14">[14]</ref> When Murad learned of this, he called off the siege of Constantinople, and Mihaloğlu led the army of Rumelia to Anatolia. Mustafa did not resist long, fleeing to Constantinople on 30 September, whence he seized <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/İznik">İznik</ref>, which he continued to rule until defeated and killed by Murad's forces in January 1423.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEImber199095-14">[14]</ref> During the fighting at İznik in 1423, Mihaloğlu Mehmed was killed by the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kadi_(Ottoman_Empire)">kadi</ref></hi> Taceddinoğlu Mehmed, and was reportedly buried at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pleven">Plevna</ref>, in modern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgaria">Bulgaria</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBabinger199334-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBaşar200524-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>His son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mihaloğlu_Hızır_Bey">Hızır Bey</ref> was a distinguished military commander under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mehmed_II">Mehmed II</ref>, as were two of his grandsons, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mihaloğlu_Ali_Bey">Ali Bey</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mihaloğlu_Iskender_Bey">Iskender Bey</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBabinger199334-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
