<text id="autogum_bio_doc415" title="Anthony Knivet" shortTile="anthony-knivet" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-12-16" dateModified="2019-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony_Knivet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Anthony Knivet</head>For the parliamentary officer, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony_Knyvett_(Black_Rod)">Anthony Knyvett (Black Rod)</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Anthony Knivet</hi>, also <hi rend="bold">Anthony Knyvett</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Antonie Knivet</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fl.">fl.</ref> 1591-1649),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> was an English sailor who fell into Portuguese hands in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref>, lived for a while with a native Brazilian tribe, and wrote about his adventures after his eventual return to Britain.</p>
<p>He was an illegitimate son of Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Knyvet">Henry Knyvet</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlton,_Brinkworth">Charlton, Wiltshire</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-hitchcock-2">[2]</ref> In 1591 he joined an English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privateer">privateer</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Cavendish">Thomas Cavendish</ref>, on a voyage aimed at raiding Portuguese holdings in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Cavendish was at the height of his fame, having completed a successful voyage around the world from 1586 to 1588.</p>
<p>After Cavendish's men had raided the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santos,_São_Paulo">Santos</ref> and destroyed several Portuguese sugar plantations, they traveled on and eventually left Knivet, who had developed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frostbite">frostbite</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strait_of_Magellan">Strait of Magellan</ref>, along with nineteen other sick or mutinous men on the then remote island of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ilhabela,_São_Paulo">Ilhabela</ref>. He was captured by the Portuguese and was put to work as a slave on a sugar plantation. Later he was tasked with traveling inland and contacting natives in order to obtain more slaves. After a failed escape attempt, he was sent back to a plantation, where he attacked his owner and fled again. He met a native who had also fled from slavery, and together they made it to an indigenous Brazilian tribe of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tupí_people">Tupí people</ref>, where they stayed for nine months. Sold for metal tools back to the Portuguese, he was forced to work for the governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rio_de_Janeiro">Rio de Janeiro</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salvador_Correia_de_Sá,_o_Velho">Salvador Correia de Sá, o Velho</ref>. He managed to escape to West Africa (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Congo">Congo</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angola">Angola</ref>). The Rio governor obtained his extradition to Brazil and he then returned with the governor to Portugal, from where he finally made his way back to England in 1601.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-hitchcock-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Economist1-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Upon return, Knivet wrote his memoir and sold it to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Hakluyt">Richard Hakluyt</ref>, who sold it on to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Purchas">Samuel Purchas</ref>. Purchas published an abbreviated version in his <hi rend="italic">Purchas his Pilgrimes</hi> (1613) and a more complete version under the title "The Admirable Adventures and Strange Fortunes of Master Antonie Knivet, which went with Master Thomas Candish in his Second Voyage to the South Sea, 1591" in <hi rend="italic">Purchas his Pilgrimes</hi>, part IV, book 6, chapter 7 (London 1625). This work was reprinted in 1906.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-hitchcock-2">[2]</ref> Excerpts about his time in Africa were published as "Appendix I: Anthony Knivet in Kongo and Angola" of <hi rend="italic">The strange adventures of Andrew Battell of Leigh, in Angola and the adjoining regions</hi>, 1901.</p>
<p>While Knivet's descriptions of Brazil are generally precise and believable,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-hitchcock-2">[2]</ref> his writing about Africa contains several mistakes and contradictions.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> The published memoir suffers from Purchas' deletion of several sections; it is possible that these were motivated by his negative attitude towards Catholicism.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-hitchcock-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Anthony Knivet went on to become co-teller of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Mint">Royal Mint</ref>, thanks to intervention by his uncle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Knyvet,_1st_Baron_Knyvet">Thomas Knyvet</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-hitchcock-2">[2]</ref> who had served as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warden_of_the_Mint">Warden of the Mint</ref> and was famous for having foiled the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gunpowder_Plot">Gunpowder Plot</ref>.</p>
</text>
