<text id="autogum_bio_doc003" title="Emil Polit" shortTile="emil-polit" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-19" dateModified="2019-10-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emil_Polit" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Emil Polit</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Emil Polit</hi> is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poles">Polish</ref> artist best known for his landscapes,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> portraits, allegorical and mystical paintings<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> as well as a number of religious art pieces and frescos in a number of Polish churches including the Rzeszów Cathedral. He contributes to and works with a number of charitable organizations and public media outlets in Poland and the United States. His paintings can be found in Poland, USA,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> the Vatican, Italy, Belgium, Denmark, Germany, France, Switzerland, Austria and Canada.</p>
<p>Polit was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zmysłówka,_Leżajsk_County">Zmyslowka</ref> near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leżajsk">Leżajsk</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poland">Poland</ref>. His passion for art brought him from his family farm to the Fine Arts Preparatory Academy in Jarosław, Poland in 1954. Five years later, he entered Poland's oldest and most renowned school of arts - the Fine Arts Academy in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kraków">Kraków</ref> where he obtained a Master of Fine Arts degree under the supervision of Professor Waclaw Taranczewski (a particularly accomplished Polish colorist).</p>
<p>After graduate school, Polit settled in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rzeszów">Rzeszów</ref>, Poland where he was inducted into the Polish Professional Artists' Association. He initially focused on industrial art design in parallel with his lifelong pursuit of painting and drawing. Later, Polit transitioned to painting full-time. Accepting a teaching position at the Fine Arts Preparatory Academy in Rzeszów, Polit served as an artistic painting and drawing teacher until his retirement in 2006. He also served there as the chairman of the art department for a number of years.</p>
<p>Throughout his career, Polit has actively participated in regional, national and international art exhibits, receiving some of Poland's most prestigious art awards.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Polit's accomplishments include serving as the director of the Rzeszów chapter of the Polish Professional Artists' Association, the 1996 Rzeszów Heritage Award which was presented to him for contributions to shaping and developing the region's art environment through his painting and the 2003 National Art Educator award that was presented to him for his contributions to art education in Poland. Polit's art garnered many other recognitions over the years as well. The Southeastern region of Poland, Massachusetts and Indiana in particular are home to some of Polit's most impressive works, including the Rzeszów Cathedral frescos,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> private collections and works on display at the Przemyśl National Museum.</p>
<p>Emil Polit's support for his community includes donating to a number of organizations through annual art auctions. Some of the more notable events are the Polish Contemporary Art Auctions coordinated through the Polish Consulate in New York City and his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indianapolis">Indianapolis</ref> exhibits supporting public television.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> Others are donations to benefit the St. Albert Society in Rzeszów, where he was awarded in 2002 with the Society's recognition award for exceptional generosity and his continuing support for Children's Hospice charities of Southeastern Poland.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> Polit also actively supports the Catholic Charities of the Rzeszów region and other local charities.</p>
</text>
