<text id="autogum_bio_doc695" title="James Stewart, the Black Knight of Lorn" shortTile="james-stewart-black" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2003-01-08" dateModified="2019-04-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Stewart%2C_the_Black_Knight_of_Lorn" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>James Stewart, the Black Knight of Lorn</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">James Stewart, the Black Knight of Lorne</hi> (c.1399–c.1451) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scotland">Scottish</ref> nobleman.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>The Black Knight of Lorne was born at Innermeath, Scotland. His father was Sir John Stewart (died 26 April 1421), Scotland's Ambassador to England. He was a direct male line descendant of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Stewart,_4th_High_Steward_of_Scotland">Alexander Stewart, 4th High Steward of Scotland</ref>, through his second son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Stewart_of_Bonkyll_(d.1298)">Sir John Stewart of Bonkill</ref>, who was killed at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Falkirk">Battle of Falkirk</ref>. His mother was also a descendant of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_de_Burgh">Elizabeth de Burgh</ref>, second wife/Queen Consort of King Robert I ("The Bruce").</p>
<head>Political career</head>
<p>James was a younger brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_of_Lorne">Robert Stewart, 1st Lord Lorne</ref> (1382–1449), whose descendants bore this title. He was an ally of the Black Douglases, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earls_of_Douglas">Earls of Douglas</ref>. After the murder of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_I_of_Scotland">James I of Scotland</ref> in 1437, power was held by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archibald_Douglas,_5th_Earl_of_Douglas">Archibald Douglas, 5th Earl of Douglas</ref> as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent">regent</ref> for the underage <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_II_of_Scotland">James II of Scotland</ref>. The Stewarts of Lorne were amongst his most trusted supporters, and their power greatly increased while the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clan_Douglas">Douglas family</ref> controlled Scotland and the king was a mere 7 years of age. However the unexpected death of the 5th Earl of Douglas from a fever in 1439 saw power now being uneasily shared between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Crichton,_1st_Lord_Crichton">William, 1st Lord Crichton</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chancellor_of_Scotland">Chancellor of Scotland</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Livingston_of_Callendar">Sir Alexander Livingston</ref>, Governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stirling_Castle">Stirling Castle</ref>.</p>
<p>Stewart married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_Beaufort,_Queen_of_Scots">Joan Beaufort</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen_Consort">Queen Consort</ref>, and became stepfather to James II. Stewart and his Douglas allies planned to remove the young James II, who was being held by Livingston in his stronghold of Stirling Castle. However, Livingston arrested Lady Joan on 3 Aug 1439, imprisoning her in Stirling Castle, while throwing Sir James and his brother Sir William into its dungeon. They were later released on good behaviour. Stewart was given safe conduct to England in 1445, 1447, and 1451. He was supposedly captured at sea by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Flanders">Flemish</ref> pirates and put to death after 1451. But he was still alive in 1453–54 when he carried King James II's offer to Edmund Beaufort, Duke of Somerset to rescue him.  Somerset was then a prisoner in the Tower of London while Richard Duke of York was in charge of the government.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>He married, before 21 September 1439, Joan Beaufort, Queen Consort of Scotland and widow of James I of Scotland. They had a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papal_dispensation">papal dispensation</ref> for both <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consanguinity">consanguinity</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Affinity_(law)">affinity</ref>. She was a daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Beaufort,_1st_Earl_of_Somerset">John Beaufort, 1st Earl of Somerset</ref> (son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katherine_Swynford">Katherine Swynford</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Gaunt,_Duke_of_Lancaster">John of Gaunt</ref>, and a grandson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_III_of_England">Edward III of England</ref>) by his wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_Margaret_Holland">Lady Margaret Holland</ref>, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Holland,_2nd_Earl_of_Kent">Thomas Holland, 2nd Earl of Kent</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_of_Kent">Joan</ref>, 'The Fair Maid of Kent'.</p>
<p>James Stewart and Joan Beaufort had three children:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Stewart,_1st_Earl_of_Atholl">John Stewart, 1st Earl of Atholl</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Stewart,_Earl_of_Buchan">James Stewart, Earl of Buchan</ref>, d. 1499. Married 27 March 1459, to Margaret <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clan_Ogilvy">Ogilvy</ref>, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Ogilvy">Alexander Ogilvy</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auchterhouse">Auchterhouse</ref>.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Stewart_(bishop_of_Moray)">Andrew Stewart</ref>, c. 1443–1501. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Moray">Bishop of Moray</ref> from 1483–1501.</item></list>
</text>
