<text id="autogum_bio_doc327" title="Sarah Basset" shortTile="sarah-basset" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-09-01" dateModified="2019-10-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarah_Basset" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sarah Basset</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sarah Bassett</hi> , also known as <hi rend="bold">Sally</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Sary Bassett</hi> (died 21 June 1730), was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slavery">enslaved</ref> '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mulatto">mulatto</ref>' (mixed-race) woman in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bermuda">Bermuda</ref>. She was declared guilty and executed in 1730 for the poisoning of three individuals. This led her to be well-known in Bermuda and a part of Bermudian history.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Sarah Bassett<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> was a mulatto and raised many grandchildren. In 1713 she was found guilty of killing livestock and was whipped through the parish. Prior to 1727 she was owned by a Southampton blacksmith, Francis Dickinson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pembroke_Parish,_Bermuda">Pembroke Parish</ref>. Dickinson died around 1726, leaving Bassett for his children to inherit.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-2">[2]</ref> In 1729, she was valued as useless because of her age, but she continued to practice her medicinal skills in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southampton">Southampton</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>During the late 1720s, Bermuda's elite began making claims of being victims of poison attacks by their slaves.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-3">[3]</ref> In 1730, Thomas Foster, his spouse Sarah Foster, and a household slave, Nancey, were taken ill. On 2 June, the investigation into the elderly enslaved life of Sarah Bassett began, possibly Bermuda's most notorious case pertaining to an attempted murder of a slaveholder by a slave.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>On 18 December 1729, about six months prior to the illnesses of Thomas and Sarah Foster and Nancey, Bassett visited her granddaughter, Beck, at her slaveholders home, the Fosters. According to the trial records, Bassett had various substances on her that contained several types of poisons including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ratsbane">ratsbane</ref>, manchineel root, and a white substance known as 'white toade'.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-2">[2]</ref> She gave Beck specific instructions on what exactly to do with these substances to poison the Fosters and Nancey. One substance was to be hidden in the kitchen for Nancey to inhale and the other in the Fosters' food for an extended period of time.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-4">[4]</ref> But, Nancey subsequently discovered the hidden poison and told the Fosters.</p>
<p>On 1 June 1730, Bassett's trial began in St. George's Sessions or State House.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-2">[2]</ref> Beck and ten white citizens of Bermuda, including one of the victims, Sarah Foster, testified against Bassett.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:3-5">[5]</ref> Beck stated that Sarah had made her give them the poison. Bassett denied the charges but was declared guilty of attempted murder on 17 June 1730 and sentenced to be burned alive, while Beck was exonerated.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief_Justice">Chief Justice</ref> asked Bassett for any statement that could change her sentence and she stated that she never deserved it.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-2">[2]</ref> He responded, "you are to be conveyed to the place of execution where a pile of wood is to be made and provided, and you are there to be fastened to a siffucient stake and there to be burnt with fire until your body be dead."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-2">[2]</ref> The execution took place at Crow Lane, a busy intersection by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamilton_Harbour,_Bermuda">Hamilton Harbour</ref>. On her way there, she was to have said to the crowd: "No use you hurrying, folks, there'll be no fun 'til I get there!"<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:3-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>About two weeks after the Sarah Bassett trial, on 23 June, <hi rend="italic">An Act for the Further and Better Regulating Negroes and other Slaves and for the more Effectual and Speedy Way of Prosecuting Them</hi> was created by the Bermuda Assembly to have more regulation and control over 'negroes and other slaves'.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>Sally Bassett's notorious act and the burning of her live body became a part of the islands' folklore; she became a Bermuda legend.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-2">[2]</ref> Legend says that when the remains of the stake was cleared, a purple flower (the "Bermudiana", a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_World">New World</ref> iris of the genus <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sisyrinchium">Sisyrinchium</ref></hi>) was found growing from her ashes; before her death Sarah had declared that there would be a sign that she was guiltless and today the flower blooms across Bermuda. Her burning execution led to very hot days in Bermuda to be referred to as 'a Sally Basset day'.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>A historian at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_the_West_Indies">University of the West Indies</ref> has suggested that news of the poisoning inspired <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slave_rebellions">slave rebellions</ref> throughout the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West_Indies">West Indies</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> In 2008, the government of Bermuda put up their very first monument to an enslaved person, created by Carlos Dowling; after some controversy<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> it was finally placed in the Cabinet grounds.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> This sculpture is a ten-foot tall statue of Sarah Bassett to honor her as a well-known figure to the Bermudians.</p>
</text>
