<text id="autogum_bio_doc676" title="Hedwig of Sagan" shortTile="hedwig-sagan" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-08-16" dateModified="2019-09-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hedwig_of_Sagan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hedwig of Sagan</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Hedwig of Sagan</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polish_language">Polish</ref>: <hi lang="pl" rend="italic">Jadwiga żagańska</hi>; before <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1340s">1350</ref> – 27 March <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1390">1390</ref>) was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Polish_consorts">Queen of Poland</ref> as the fourth wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casimir_III_the_Great">Casimir III</ref>. Casimir's lack of male heir spelled the end of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piast_Dynasty">Piast Dynasty</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Poland_(1025–1385)">Kingdom of Poland</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> After Casimir's death in 1370, she remarried <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rupert_I_of_Legnica">Rupert I of Legnica</ref>.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Hedwig was the third of five children born to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_V_of_Iron">Henry V of Iron</ref> and his wife Anna, daughter of Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslaus_of_Płock">Wenceslaus of Płock</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> Her brothers were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VI_the_Older">Henry VI the Older</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VII_Rumpold">Henry VII Rumpold</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VIII_the_Sparrow">Henry VIII the Sparrow</ref>, and her only sister was Anna, wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_I_of_Racibórz">Jan I of Racibórz</ref>.</p>
<head>First marriage</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casimir_III_of_Poland">Casimir III of Poland</ref> had two daughters <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elisabeth_of_Poland_(1326–1361)">Elizabeth</ref> and Cunigunde by his first wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aldona_of_Lithuania">Aldona of Lithuania</ref>. Casimir's second marriage to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adelaide_of_Hesse">Adelaide of Hesse</ref> was loveless and childless; they spent most their marriage apart from each other. His third wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christina_Rokiczana">Christina Rokiczana</ref>, his mistress and a widow of a wealthy merchant, also bore no children. Casimir needed a son and he chose Hedwig as it would to strengthen his ties with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_IV,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Charles IV, Holy Roman Emperor</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Hedwig married Casimir III of Poland around 1365. However, Casimir was committing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bigamy">bigamy</ref> as was still legally married to his second wife (it is unknown whether Christina was still alive at the time). Casimir forged a papal dispensation because he was related to Hedwig by a fourth degree. In 1368 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Urban_V">Pope Urban V</ref> allowed Casimir to stay with Hedwig since his marriage to Christina was invalid. Adelaide died in 1371.</p>
<p>Casimir awaited the birth of a son. If no son was born then Casimir's nephew, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_I_of_Hungary">Louis I of Hungary</ref>. Instead of a son, Hedwig bore three daughters:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna_of_Poland,_Countess_of_Celje">Anna</ref> (1366 – 9 June 1422). Married firstly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_of_Celje">William of Celje</ref>. Their only daughter was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_of_Cilli">Anne of Cilli</ref>. Married secondly Ulrich, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_of_Teck">Duke of Teck</ref>. They had no children.</item>
<item>Cunigunde (1367–1370).</item>
<item>Hedwig (1368 – ca. 1407), reportedly married ca. 1382 but the details are obscure.</item></list>
<p>The question of the legitimacy of the three daughters was raised. Casimir had all three of his daughters legitimised. Casimir managed to have Anne and Cunigunde legitimated by Pope Urban V on 5 December 1369. Hedwig the younger was legitimated by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Gregory_XI">Pope Gregory XI</ref> on 11 October 1371.</p>
<p>On  5 November 1370 Casimir died, leaving Hedwig a widow with three young daughters. Soon afterwards, the middle daughter, Cunigunde died aged three. From Casimir's will, Hedwig received from the treasury of the king's 53 fine silver and 1 / 3 silver vessels in the amount of dowry and 1,000 fineslarge cents. Since Casimir did not have a male heir, his throne passed to his nephew, Louis I of Hungary, though Casimir's sister, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elisabeth_of_Poland">Elisabeth of Poland</ref>, acted as regent for a period of time when Louis was in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hungary">Hungary</ref>.</p>
<head>Second marriage</head>
<p>Hedwig did not remarry straight away. She returned to her home in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Żagań">Żagań</ref> where she lived at the court of her brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VI_the_Older">Henry VI the Older</ref>.</p>
<p>On 10 February 1372, Hedwig married for a second time to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rupert_I_of_Legnica">Rupert I of Legnica</ref>, son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslaus_I_of_Legnica">Wenceslaus I of Legnica</ref> and Anna of Cieszyn. The marriage produced two more daughters:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Barbara (ca. 1384 – Trebitz, 9 May 1436), married on 6 March 1396 to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rudolf_III,_Duke_of_Saxe-Wittenberg">Rudolph III</ref>, Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saxe-Wittenberg">Saxe-Wittenberg</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elector_of_Saxony">Elector of Saxony</ref>. Through this union, Jadwiga was a direct ancestor of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kings_of_Denmark">Kings of Denmark</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Gonzaga">House of Gonzaga</ref>, rulers of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mantua">Mantua</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Montferrato">Montferrato</ref>.</item>
<item>Agnes (before 1385 – after 7 July 1411), a nun in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wroclaw">Wroclaw</ref>.</item></list>
<p>After eighteen years of marriage to Rupert, Hedwig died. She was buried in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silesia">Silesia</ref>.</p>
<head>Ancestors</head>
</text>
