<text id="autogum_bio_doc752" title="Ram Khamhaeng" shortTile="ram-khamhaeng" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2003-11-16" dateModified="2019-08-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ram_Khamhaeng" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ram Khamhaeng</head>For other uses, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page_(disambiguation)">Main Page (disambiguation)</ref>.
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Ram Khamhaeng</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thai_language">Thai</ref>: รามคำแหง, pronounced<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Thai">[rāːm kʰām hɛ̌ːŋ]</ref>) or <hi rend="bold">Pho Khun Ram Khamhaeng Maharat</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thai_language">Thai</ref>: พ่อขุนรามคำแหงมหาราช, pronounced<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Thai">[pʰɔ̂ː kʰǔn raːm kʰam hɛ̌ːŋ má hǎː râːt]</ref>), also spelled <hi rend="bold">Ramkhamhaeng</hi>, was the third king of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_monarchs_of_Thailand#Phra_Ruang_Dynasty_(1238–1368,1368–1438)">Phra Ruang Dynasty</ref>, ruling the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sukhothai_Kingdom">Sukhothai Kingdom</ref> (a historical kingdom of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thailand">Thailand</ref>) from 1279 to 1298, during its most prosperous era. </p>
<p>He is credited for the creation of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thai_alphabet">Thai alphabet</ref> and the firm establishment of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theravada">Theravada</ref> Buddhism as the state religion of the kingdom.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Coedes-1">[1]</ref>:197<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-prince-2">[2]</ref>:25</p>
<head>Birth and name</head>
<p>Ram Khamhaeng was a son of Pho Khun Bang Klang Hao, who ruled as Pho Khun <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Si_Inthrathit">Si Inthrathit</ref>, and his queen, Sueang,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-prasert1-3">[3]</ref> though folk legend claims his real parents were an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ogre">ogress</ref> named Kangli and a fisherman.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Wyatt1995-4">[4]</ref>:23 He had two brothers and two sisters. The eldest brother died while very young. The second, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ban_Mueang">Ban Mueang</ref>, became king following their father's death, and was succeeded by Ram Khamhaeng on his own death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-prasert2-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>At age 19, he participated in his father's successful invasion of the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sukhothai_(city)">Sukhothai</ref>, formerly a vassal of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khmer_Empire">Khmer</ref>, establishing the independent Sukhothai Kingdom. Due to his courage in the war, he allegedly was given the title "<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phra">Phra</ref> Ram Khamhaeng</hi>” or “Rama the Bold”.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Coedes-1">[1]</ref>:196 After his father's death, his brother Ban Mueang ruled the kingdom, assigning Ram Khamhaeng control of the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amphoe_Si_Satchanalai">Si Satchanalai</ref>.</p>
<p>The Royal Institute of Thailand speculates that Ram Khamhaeng's birth name was "Ram" (derived from Rama, the name of the hero of the Hindu epic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramayana">Ramayana</ref>), for his name following his coronation was "Pho Khun Ramarat" (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thai_language">Thai</ref>: พ่อขุนรามราช). Furthermore, the tradition at the time was to give the name of a grandfather to a grandson; according to the 11th Stone Inscription and Luang Prasoet Aksoranit's Ayutthaya Chronicles, Ram Khamhaeng had a grandson named "Phraya Ram", and two grandsons of Phraya Ram were named "Phraya Ban Mueang" and "Phraya Ram".</p>
<p>In English, an alternate spelling of his name is <hi rend="bold">Ramkhamhaeng</hi>. The title <hi rend="bold">Maharat</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thai_language">Thai</ref>: มหาราช) is the Thai translation of “the Great”.</p>
<head>Accession</head>
<p>Tri Amattayakun (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thai_language">Thai</ref>: ตรี อมาตยกุล), a Thai historian, suggests that Ram Khamhaeng should have acceded to the throne in 1279, the year he planted a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sugar_palm_(disambiguation)">sugar palm</ref> tree in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sukhothai_(city)">Sukhothai</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prasert_na_Nagara">Prasoet na Nakhon</ref> of the Royal Institute speculates that this was a tradition of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tai_peoples">Thai-Ahom</ref> monarchs, who planted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banyan">banyan</ref> or sugar palm trees on their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coronation_of_the_Thai_monarch">coronation day</ref> in the hope that their reign would achieve the same stature as the tree. The most significant event at the beginning of his reign, however, was the elopement of one of his daughters, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/May_Hnin_Thwe-Da">May Hnin Thwe-Da</ref>, with the captain of the palace guards, a commoner. The commoner founded the Burmese <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanthawaddy_Kingdom">Hanthawaddy Kingdom</ref> and commissioned compilation of the Code of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wareru">Wareru</ref>, which provided a basis for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_of_Thailand">law of Thailand</ref> used in Siam until 1908,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> and in Burma to the present.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Reign</head>
<p>Ram Khamhaeng sent embassies to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yuan_dynasty">Yuan China</ref> from 1282 to 1323 and imported the techniques to make the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ceramic">ceramics</ref> now known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sangkhalok_ceramic_ware">Sangkhalok ceramic ware</ref>. He had close relationships with the rulers of nearby city-states, especially Ngam Muang, the ruler of neighboring <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phayao">Phayao</ref> (whose wife, according to legend, he seduced), and King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mangrai">Mangrai</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chiang_Mai">Chiang Mai</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Coedes-1">[1]</ref>:206 His campaign against Cambodia left the Khmer country "utterly devastated."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Maspero-9">[9]</ref>:90</p>
<p>According to Thai history, Ram Khamhaeng is credited with creating the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thai_alphabet">Thai alphabet</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Lai Nangsue Thai</hi>) from a combination of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanskrit">Sanskrit</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pali">Pali</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grantha_alphabet">Grantha</ref> alphabets.</p>
<p>It is speculated that Ram Khamhaeng expanded his kingdom as far as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lampang">Lampang</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phrae">Phrae</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nan,_Thailand">Nan</ref> in the north, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phitsanulok">Phitsanulok</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vientiane">Vientiane</ref> in the east, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nakhon_Si_Thammarat_Kingdom">Nakhon Si Thammarat Kingdom</ref> in the south, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mon_kingdoms">Mon kingdoms</ref> of what is now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Myanmar">Myanmar</ref> in the west, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bay_of_Bengal">Bay of Bengal</ref> in the northwest.  However, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mandala_(political_model)"><hi rend="italic">mandala</hi> political model</ref>, kingdoms such as Sukhothai lacked distinct borders, instead being centered on the strength of the capital itself.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Siam_Mapped_1994._p_163-10">[10]</ref> Claims of Ram Khamhaeng's large kingdom were intended to assert Siamese dominance over mainland Southeast Asia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Siam_Mapped_1994._p_163-10">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>According to the Chinese <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_Yuan">History of Yuan</ref></hi>, King Ram Khamhaeng died in 1298 and was succeeded by his son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loe_Thai">Loe Thai</ref>, though <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Cœdès">George Cœdès</ref> thinks it "more probable" it was "shortly before 1318". Legend states he disappeared in the rapids of the rivers of Sawankhalok. Another possible source states he was slain by a Malay warrior princess named Adruja Sriwijayamala Singha during a battle between Thai and Malay armies, in a campaign to conquer Malay lands which make up a third of modern Thailand today.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Coedes-1">[1]</ref>:218–219</p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<head>The Ram Khamhaeng Inscription</head>
Main article: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ram_Khamhaeng_Inscription">Ram Khamhaeng Inscription</ref>
<p>Much of the traditional biographical information comes from the inscription on the Ram Khamhaeng stele, composed in 1292, and contains vague facts about the king.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Coedes-1">[1]</ref>:196–198 It is now found in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bangkok_National_Museum">Bangkok National Museum</ref>. The formal name of the stele is the "King Ram Khamhaeng Inscription". It was added to the Memory of the World Register in 2003 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UNESCO">UNESCO</ref>.</p>
<head>Sangkhalok ceramic ware</head>
Main article: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sangkhalok_ceramic_ware">Sangkhalok ceramic ware</ref>
<p>Ram Khamhaeng is credited with bringing the skills of ceramic making from China and laying the foundation of a strong ceramic ware industry in the Sukhothai Kingdom.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Coedes-1">[1]</ref>:206–207 Sukhothai for centuries was the major exporter of the ceramics known as "Sangkhalok ware" (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thai_language">Thai</ref>: เครื่องสังคโลก) to countries such as Japan, the Philippines, Indonesia, and even to China. The industry was one of the main revenue generators during his reign and long afterwards.</p>
<head>Banknote</head>
<p>The reverse of the 20 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baht">Baht</ref> note (series 16), issued in 2013, depicts images of the royal statue of Ram Khamhaeng seated on the Manangkhasila Asana Throne, and commemorates the invention of the Thai script by the king.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<head>Honour</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramkhamhaeng_University">Ramkhamhaeng University</ref>, the first open university in Thailand with campuses throughout the country, was named after Ram Khamhaeng.</p>
<head>Video games</head>
<p>King Ramkhamhaeng is a playable ruler for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thai_people">Siamese</ref> in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civilization_V">Sid Meier's Civilization V</ref></hi>.</p>
</text>
