<text id="autogum_bio_doc111" title="Dapper Laughs" shortTile="dapper-laughs" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-02-09" dateModified="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dapper_Laughs" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Dapper Laughs</head><p><hi rend="bold">Dapper Laughs</hi> (born 17 June 1984 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingston_upon_Thames">Kingston upon Thames</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, England) is a pseudonym of <hi rend="bold">Daniel O'Reilly</hi>. He is a social media content creator from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Addlestone">Addlestone</ref>, Surrey. He has described himself as the "Moisturiser".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Dapper Laughs became known on the social networking sites <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facebook">Facebook</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vine_(software)">Vine</ref>, where he has around 72,407,000 and 4,575,000 followers respectively.</p>
<head>Career and controversies</head>
<p>In 2014, Laughs released the single "Proper Moist".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> The song entered the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UK_Singles_Chart">UK Singles Chart</ref> at number 15. Starting in 2014, Laughs began his <hi rend="italic">Moist Tour</hi> of the UK; his supporting act on the tour was fellow Viner Joe Charman. In July, he released "Take It To The Base". The music video was released on YouTube, but has since been made private.</p>
<p>In September 2014, his show, entitled <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dapper_Laughs:_On_the_Pull">Dapper Laughs: On the Pull</ref></hi>, began on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ITV2">ITV2</ref>, where he tried to increase the participants' chances of obtaining sex with women.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>In November 2014, Laughs criticised the website <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trinity_Mirror">UsVsTh3m</ref> on Twitter for what he viewed as an unfavourable review of his new album <hi rend="italic">Proper Naughty Christmas</hi>. Laughs suggested that the review could hinder his goal of raising money for homelessness charity <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shelter_(charity)">Shelter</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Shelter-6">[6]</ref> As a result of UsVsTh3m highlighting the lyrics of one of the album tracks as offensive to the homeless, the charity posted on their official Twitter feed that they would be refusing donations from Laughs.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Shelter-6">[6]</ref> Laughs later made an apology in a statement.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Laughs was heavily criticised in November 2014 when, soon after accusations that his ITV show <hi rend="italic">On The Pull</hi> was degrading to women,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> he joked that a female audience member at one of his live shows was "gagging for a rape."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Denham-9">[9]</ref> An online petition eventually gained 68,210 signatures with the hashtag #CancelDapper asked ITV to end the series.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Stephenson-10">[10]</ref> On 10 November, ITV announced they were not renewing the series for a second season as a result.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> A forthcoming Dapper Laughs tour was also cancelled.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Stephenson-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>On 11 November 2014, Laughs announced on <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newsnight">Newsnight</ref></hi> that his Dapper Laughs character had been indefinitely retired. When interviewed on the BBC programme, he claimed he did not realise the problems he had caused. Laughs also claimed that the media played a major role in the anger directed at him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> In December that year, Laughs resurrected the character.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref></p>
<p>On 25 December 2014, a YouTube and Facebook video was posted stating that Laughs' character Dapper Laughs would be making a return with the promise of toned down content. On 15 January 2015, he announced his "The Res'Erection" stand-up show.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> On 8 March 2015 a pilot for a web-exclusive sitcom based on the character was uploaded to YouTube.</p>
<p>On 22 January 2017, Laughs took part in a charity amateur boxing match at Aldershot Princes Hall, where he defeated his opponent marginally, 10/9/10 being the judges score. This was held in support of Help for Heroes.  In an interview, Laughs described how he would be happy to face fellow comedian Jack Jones, also of social media fame, and that he would "have him".</p>
<p>In January 2018, Laughs entered the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Celebrity_Big_Brother_(UK_TV_series)">Celebrity Big Brother</ref></hi> house as a housemate during its <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Celebrity_Big_Brother_21_(UK)">twenty-first series</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> He was the eighth housemate to be evicted.</p>
<head>Personal life</head>
<p>Daniel has two daughters, named Neve O’Reilly and Roux O’Reilly.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref> He proposed to his longtime girlfriend Shelly Broadhurst in January 2018, during his eviction interview on <hi rend="italic">Celebrity Big Brother</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref></p>
<head>Filmography</head>
<head>Discography</head>
<head>Singles</head>
</text>
