<text id="autogum_bio_doc371" title="Pedro de Aguado" shortTile="pedro-de-aguado" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-07-01" dateModified="2019-03-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedro_de_Aguado" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pedro de Aguado</head><p><hi rend="bold">Pedro de Aguado</hi> (1513 or 1538– late 16th or early 17th century) was a Spanish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franciscan">Franciscan</ref> friar who spent around 15 years in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Kingdom_of_Granada">New Kingdom of Granada</ref>, preaching to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indigenous_peoples_of_Colombia">indigenous people</ref>. During this time he collected source material for a history of the region, and began a manuscript, <hi rend="italic">Recopilación historial</hi>, which he completed in Spain between 1576 and 1583 but was unable to publish. The manuscript was used by other historians, but was not published until the twentieth century.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Odyssey-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>De Aguado's date of birth is uncertain. He is believed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_Friede">Juan Friede</ref> to have been baptised in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valdemoro">Valdemoro</ref> on 26 January 1513, whilst <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guillermo_Morón">Guillermo Morón</ref> argues for 16 February 1538.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Arriving in the New World in 1560 or 1561 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cartagena,_Colombia">Cartagena</ref>, his movements are uncertain until his arrival in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bogotá">Bogotá</ref> in 1571, although it is likely he soon left Cartagena to minister to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muisca_people">Muisca</ref>. By around 1564 he was a pastor to the Muisca at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cogua">Cogua</ref>, and he was able to build two churches there. Cogua was considered the first Indian town in New Granada where all the Indians were converted to Christianity, an achievement of Aguado's recognised by King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_II_of_Spain">Philip II</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fals-Borda-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>In 1571, De Aguado moved to Bogotá, and became a "minister provincial" of the local Franciscan Province. In 1575, De Aguado was sent by the Province on a mission to Spain to answer charges that the local monks were greedy and abusive.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Odyssey-1">[1]</ref> He was not able to leave Spain to return to Bogotá until 1583.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Odyssey-1">[1]</ref> During this time he developed a manuscript on the history of the region, <hi rend="italic">Recopilación historial</hi>, begun during his "idle hours" in Bogotá. It is likely that Part I, on Santa Marta and the New Kingdom of Granada, was written in Bogotá, and Part II, on Venezuela and Cartagena, in Spain.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Odyssey-1">[1]</ref> De Aguado tried unsuccessfully to secure publication over a number of years. A series of bureaucratic hurdles around censorship were complicated by a change in the rules, invalidating the royal licence to print which de Aguado obtained in 1581, while a second licence in 1582 was complicated by a new requirement to have the printed copy checked against the original manuscript signed off by the king's secretary. Financial difficulties also played a role, but a definitive reason for publication failing to materialise is not known. A planned Part III appears to have been abandoned, possibly in frustration at the difficulties with publication, with the witness statements that would have been the source material left in Spain on his return to Bogotá in 1583.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Odyssey-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Dates for De Aguado's death are even less certain than those for his birth; dates vary from 1589<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> to 1595<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> to 1608.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-byv-7">[7]</ref> After his death, his work was used directly and indirectly by other authors, notably by Fray <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedro_Simón">Pedro Simón</ref>, who appears to have had access to a copy of Part II of the manuscript which de Aguado took with him on his return to Bogotá.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Odyssey-1">[1]</ref> The manuscript De Aguado left in Spain was obtained in the late eighteenth century by the historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_Bautista_Muñoz">Juan Bautista Muñoz</ref>; his collection became part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Valencia">University of Valencia</ref> on his death, and was transferred to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Real_Academia_de_la_Historia">Real Academia de la Historia</ref> after the university was partly destroyed in 1812 during a French siege of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valencia">Valencia</ref>. There, the manuscript was discovered in 1845 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joaquín_Acosta">Joaquín Acosta</ref>, and it was consulted by some historians in the latter part of the nineteenth century. However, it was not published until 1906 (Part I, <hi rend="italic">Historia de Santa Marta y Nuevo Reino de Granada</hi>) and 1913 (Part II, <hi rend="italic">Historia de Venezuela</hi>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Odyssey-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-byv-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Historia de Santa Marta y Nuevo Reino de Granada</hi> (1906) (<ref target="https://archive.org/details/historiadesantam01agua">Part I</ref>, <ref target="https://archive.org/details/historiadesantam02agua">Part II</ref>– 1916/17 edition by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerónimo_Bécker">Jerónimo Bécker</ref>)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Historia de Venezuela</hi> (1913) (<ref target="http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/39947">Part I</ref>, <ref target="http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/39948">Part II</ref>– 1918/19 edition by Jerónimo Bécker)</item></list>
</text>
