<text id="autogum_bio_doc607" title="Andrew Durie" shortTile="andrew-durie" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-05-10" dateModified="2018-05-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Durie" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Andrew Durie</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Andrew Durie</hi> (died 1558), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Galloway">bishop of Galloway</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbot_of_Melrose">abbot of Melrose</ref>, was the son of John Durie of Durie in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fife">Fife</ref>, and brother to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Durie">George Durie</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbot_of_Dunfermline">abbot of Dunfermline</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeacon_of_St._Andrews">archdeacon of St. Andrews</ref>.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<head>Early career and abbacy of Melrose</head>
<p>Both brothers, Andrew and George Durie, entered the church under the patronage of their uncle, Archbishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Beaton">James Beaton</ref> of Glasgow, who named them abbots in 1526. The appointment of Andrew Durie to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbey_of_Melrose">abbey of Melrose</ref> was made in opposition to the will of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_V_of_Scotland">James V</ref>, who had already asked the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope">pope</ref> to grant the charge to John Maxwell, brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Maxwell,_4th_Lord_Maxwell">Robert Maxwell</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Maxwell">Lord Maxwell</ref>, but letters of commendation to the pope in favour of Durie were obtained by fraud. Sir Christopher Dacre, in a letter dated 2 December 1526, says that Durie, "a monk of Melrose Abbey, will probably hold the place, notwithstanding that the king and the lords in this parliament have enacted that no Scotchman should purchase a benefice at the pope's hand, without license of the king and the lords of council".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fotheringham_1558-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>James wrote to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardinal_Wolsey">Cardinal Wolsey</ref> on the subject, and requested him to lay the matter before <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VIII_of_England">Henry VIII</ref>, so that the English king might use his influence with the pope to annul the appointment of Durie. Maxwell's friends obtained from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish_parliament">Scottish parliament</ref> a revocation of the letters sent to the pope in Durie's behalf. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Arran">Earl of Arran</ref> also wrote to Cardinal Wolsey to remind him that he had promised before to obtain the pope's consent to the appointment of his friends to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Moray">bishopric of Moray</ref> and to the abbey of Melrose, both of which charges were then vacant. The ‘Vatican Papers’ contain a letter from Henry VIII to the pope on the subject, dated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hertford">Hertford</ref>, 2 December 1524, in which he recommends John Maxwell of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dundrennan">Dundrennan</ref> to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbey_of_Melrose">abbey of Melrose</ref>. All these efforts were of no avail.</p>
<p>Maxwell, who had entered on the functions of abbot, had to retire in favour of Durie, who personally had nothing to recommend him as a churchman to any office whatever. He was dissolute and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Profanity">profane</ref>. His talk was mixed with terms derived from dice and cards. He had also a vulgar habit of making trivial <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhyme">rhymes</ref>. In giving his advice to the queen-regent, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_of_Guise">Mary of Guise</ref>, regarding a concourse of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestant">protestant</ref> preachers that had assembled in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref>, he is reported to have said: "Madame, because they are come without order, I rede ye, send them to the border".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fotheringham_1558-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Bishop of Galloway</head>
<p>On 2 July 1541 he was made an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extraordinary_lord_of_session">extraordinary lord of session</ref>, and was on the following day recommended to the pope for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/See_of_Galloway">see of Galloway</ref>. The king stipulated that before receiving the bishopric he should resign Melrose, although he might hold the abbey of Tongland. He is, however, spoken of as bishop and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbot_of_Melrose">abbot of Melrose</ref> in 1556. He accompanied the queen-regent on her visit to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France">France</ref> in 1550. He was an inveterate enemy to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestantism">protestantism</ref>, and vowed openly that, in despite of God, so long as they that then were prelates lived, that word called the gospel should never be preached within the realm.</p>
<p>He died in September 1558 from the shock occasioned by a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riot">riot</ref> in Edinburgh when the Protestants broke up the procession in honour of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Giles">St Giles</ref>. Knox gives Durie a very bad character.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> He was succeeded in the bishopric by Alexander Gordon.
Sources</p>
</text>
