<text id="autogum_bio_doc769" title="Shvarn" shortTile="shvarn" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-05-09" dateModified="2019-06-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shvarn" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Shvarn</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shvarn</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Shvarno</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Svaromir Daniilovich</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuanian_language">Lithuanian</ref>: <hi lang="lt" rend="italic">Švarnas</hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ukrainian_language">Ukrainian</ref>: Шварно Данилович;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MPCK-1">[1]</ref> c. 1230 – c. 1269), was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knyaz">knyaz</ref> of western parts of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Galicia–Volhynia">Galicia</ref> (1264 – c. 1269) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_rulers_of_Lithuania">Grand Duke of Lithuania</ref> (1267 – c. 1269). An influential leader, he became involved in internal struggles of power within neighboring <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Duchy_of_Lithuania">Grand Duchy of Lithuania</ref>. He also held the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chełm">Kholm</ref> (modern Chełm, Poland) in his domain.</p>
<head>Name</head>
<p>Little is known of Shvarn and even his name is not entirely certain. The original documents relating to this ruler are scarce and mention him under a variety of names. For instance the first edition of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuanian_Chronicles">Lithuanian Annals</ref> mentions him as Shkvarno, but the following editions use the names of <hi rend="italic">Skirmont</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Skirmunt</hi>, possibly a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruthenian_language">Ruthenisation</ref> of Lithuanian name <hi rend="italic">Skirmantas</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Latyszonek-2">[2]</ref> Contemporary sources also mention his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian_name">Christian name</ref> of <hi rend="italic">Ioann</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Іоанн</hi>), that is either John or George.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Grala-3">[3]</ref> In modern times the ruler is known by a variety of names in various historiographies, including Lithuanian <hi rend="italic">Švarnas</hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Speciunas-4">[4]</ref> Ukrainian Шварно Данилович, Russian and Belarusian Шварн, and Polish <hi rend="italic">Szwarno Daniłowicz</hi>. All of them are versions of the name of Shvarn, which is likely to be a diminutive of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slavic_name">Slavic name</ref> of <hi rend="italic">Svaromir</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Curtin-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>One of the sons of king <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_of_Galicia">Daniel I of Galicia</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rurik_Dynasty">house of Romanovich</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Horwat-6">[6]</ref> Shvarn inherited the north-western parts of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Galicia–Volhynia">Kingdom of Galicia–Volhynia</ref>, his fathers' domain. This land included the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halicz">Halicz</ref> itself, as well as the land across the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bug_River">Bug River</ref>, that is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_Ruthenia">Red Ruthenia</ref> with the towns of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bełz">Bełz</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czerwień">Czerwień</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#endnote_a">a</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mielnik">Mielnik</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drohiczyn">Drohiczyn</ref> and eventually also <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chełm">Kholm</ref> (since 1264).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Mironowicz-7">[7]</ref> His brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lev_I_of_Galicia">Lev I</ref> inherited the southern part of the land, with the cities of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lviv">Lviv</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Przemyśl">Przemyśl</ref>, while Roman became the heir of duchies of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lutsk">Lutsk</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terebovl">Terebovl</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Mironowicz-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>During the times of king Daniel's reign, the Galician lords were allied with their Polish neighbours against a common threat, the Lithuanian tribes that often raided the neighbouring lands for loot and plunder. However, in 1255 (or the previous year) Shvarn married an unnamed daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mindaugas">Mindaugas</ref>, since 1253 the first (and only) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_of_Lithuania">king of Lithuania</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Dubonis-8">[8]</ref> This allied him to Lithuania and together the two rulers undertook numerous military campaigns against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Poland_(1025–1385)">Kingdom of Poland</ref>. Already in 1255 they raided <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lublin">Lublin</ref>, in 1262 a major campaign against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masovia">Masovia</ref> was started. Shvarn and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treniota">Treniota</ref> captured the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Płock">Płock</ref> and besieged Shvarn's brother-in-law, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siemowit_I_of_Masovia">Siemowit I of Masovia</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jazdów">Jazdów</ref> (modern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warsaw">Warsaw</ref>). In the end Siemowit was killed by Shvarn's troops and his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konrad_II_of_Masovia">Konrad II</ref> was taken prisoner. The Polish relief force did not arrive in time and was later defeated in a battle at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Długosiodło">Długosiodło</ref> on August 5, 1262.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bunar-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>In 1264 king Daniel of Galicia died and Shvarn received nominal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord">overlordship</ref> over all of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Galicia–Volhynia">Kingdom of Galicia–Volhynia</ref> as its duke. Immediately he mounted a major campaign against Poland, this time aiming for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lesser_Poland">Lesser Poland</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Gieysztor-10">[10]</ref> However, although joint armies managed to plunder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skaryszew">Skaryszew</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarczek">Tarczek</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiślica">Wiślica</ref>, this time the campaign was less successful and the allied Ruthenian and Lithuanian armies were repelled. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yotvingians">Yotvingian</ref> auxiliaries were defeated by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolesław_V_the_Chaste">Bolesław V the Chaste</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Brańsk">Battle of Brańsk</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bunar-9">[9]</ref> The following year Bolesław mounted a counter-offensive against Shvarn and his uncle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vasilko_Romanovich">Vasilko Romanovich</ref>, and defeated the earlier on June 19, 1266 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wrota">Wrota</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bunar-9">[9]</ref> This weakened Shvarn's position in his own domain.</p>
<p>In the meantime in 1263 Mindaugas of Lithuania was murdered. In the chaos that followed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mindaugas">Mindaugas</ref>' assassination, the lands of the Grand Duchy were in disarray, with both local and foreign rulers struggling for power. Shvarn gave his support to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaišvilkas">Vaišvilkas</ref>, one of Mindaugas' sons and his brother-in-law. Together they managed to depose <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treniota">Treniota</ref> and expel <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daumantas_of_Pskov">Dovmont</ref> all the way to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pskov">Pskov</ref>. After Vaišvilkas returned to monastic life in 1267,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jasienica-11">[11]</ref> Shvarn became the new Grand Duke. No details are known about Shvarn's rule over Lithuania<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jasienica-11">[11]</ref> and he probably did not gain a strong foothold in that country.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Kiaupa-12">[12]</ref> However, he was apparently fairly successful in expanding his borders. Following successful military campaigns, in 1267 he defeated his brother Mstislav in the battle of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yaselda_River">Yaselda River</ref> and captured <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turau">Turov</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pinsk">Pinsk</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Latyszonek-2">[2]</ref> He then campaigned against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Volga_Tatars">Volga Tatars</ref> and defeated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khan_(title)">khan</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balaklay">Balaklay</ref> in the battle of Kojdanow (modern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dzyarzhynsk">Dzyarzhynsk</ref>, Belarus), which allowed Shvarn to capture the towns of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozyr">Mozyr</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chernigov">Chernigov</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karachev">Karachev</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Starodub">Starodub</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Latyszonek-2">[2]</ref> The struggle for power within Lithuania however continued. Before a clear winner could emerge, Shvarm died in Kholm (nowadays <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chełm">Chełm</ref>, Poland) some time between 1269 and 1271. He was buried in an Orthodox Cathedral that once stood on a place now occupied by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basilica_of_the_Birth_of_the_Virgin_Mary,_Chełm">Basilica of the Birth of the Virgin Mary</ref>. After his death most of his lands reverted to Lithuania<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fennell-13">[13]</ref> and came under the control of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traidenis">Traidenis</ref>, a noble from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aukštaitija">Aukštaitija</ref>.</p>
</text>
