<text id="autogum_bio_doc567" title="Xicotencatl II" shortTile="xicotencatl-ii" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-23" dateModified="2019-06-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xicotencatl_II" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Xicotencatl II</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Xicotencatl II Axayacatl</hi>, also known as <hi rend="bold">Xicotencatl the Younger</hi> (died 1521), was a prince and warleader, probably with the title of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tlacochcalcatl">Tlacochcalcatl</ref></hi>, of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pre-Columbian">pre-Columbian</ref> state of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tlaxcala_(Nahua_state)">Tlaxcallan</ref> at the time of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish_conquest_of_Mexico">Spanish conquest of Mexico</ref>.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>He was the son of the ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tizatlan_(Altepetl)">Tizatlan</ref>, one of the four confederate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Altepetl">altepeme</ref> of the Tlaxcallan state, of which Xicotencatl the Younger was considered to be the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> ruler because of his father's weakened health.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> His <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nahuatl">Nahuatl</ref> name, pronounced <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Nahuatl">[ʃiːkoʔˈteːŋkatɬ]</ref>, is sometimes also spelled <hi rend="bold">Xicotencatl</hi> and means "Person from the bumblebee edge place".</p>
<p>He is known primarily as the leader of the force that was dispatched from Tlaxcallan to intercept the forces of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hernán_Cortés">Hernán Cortés</ref> and his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Totonac">Totonac</ref> allies as they entered Tlaxcallan territory when going inland from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Veracruz">Veracruz</ref> coast.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Diaz-2">[2]</ref>:140–188  His actions are described in the letters of Cortés, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernal_Díaz_del_Castillo">Bernal Díaz del Castillo</ref>'s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Historia_verdadera_de_la_conquista_de_la_Nueva_España">Historia verdadera de la conquista de la Nueva España</ref></hi> and in the histories of Tlaxcala, such as the one by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diego_Muñoz_Camargo">Diego Muñoz Camargo</ref>.</p>
<p>When fighting the Spaniards he used an ambush strategy; he first engaged the enemy with a small force that feigned a retreat, and then lured the Spaniards back to a better fortified position where the main force waited. The Spaniards retreated when too many of their men were killed or wounded, and they sought a peace treaty with the Tlaxcaltecs. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maxixcatzin">Maxixcatzin</ref>, the ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ocotelolco_(Altepetl)">Ocotelolco</ref>, was in favour of allying with the Spaniards, but Xicotencatl II opposed this idea and continued to fight, nearly wiping out the Spanish force. However, in a crucial moment, the soldiers from Ocotelolco retreated from the battlefield following the orders of Maxixcatzin, and Xicotencatl was forced to accept the proposed peace treaty.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>The Spaniards with the Tlaxcaltec forces marched on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenochtitlan">Tenochtitlan</ref>, where they stayed until the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La_Noche_Triste">Noche Triste</ref>, at which time they were forced to flee the city after an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aztec">Aztec</ref> uprising. The remnants of the Spanish forces made it to Tlaxcala where they once again asked for the assistance of the Tlaxcaltec, and where Xicotencatl II once again spoke against helping them. However, Maxixcatzin's faction was again successful, and the Spaniards stayed in his palace while they regrouped and received reinforcements.</p>
<p>When the final stage of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Tenochtitlan">siege of Tenochtitlan</ref> was about to be carried out, Xicotencatl marched on the Aztec capital as the leader of a Tlaxcaltec force,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Diaz-2">[2]</ref>:353–355 attacking from the north and passing by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Texcoco_(altepetl)">Texcoco</ref>. The night before the final march, he was apprehended and accused of treason by Cortés and by the Ocotelolcan warleader Chichimecateuctli, who said that he had tried to flee back to Tlaxcala. He was summarily executed by hanging.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Diaz-2">[2]</ref>:357–358<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>The description of Xicotencatl has been subject to changing attitudes in the understanding of the Spanish Conquest of Mexico. In the early period he was seen mostly as a traitor who tried to halt the arrival of the Spanish "liberation" of the Indians from Aztec dominance.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Later he was romantically construed as an indigenous hero who valiantly opposed the onslaught of the Spanish.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> Recently, ethnohistorian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ross_Hassig">Ross Hassig</ref> (2001) has analysed his actions in terms of Tlaxcaltec politics, and he concludes that Xicotencatl was mostly acting to further the political interests of his own polity, that of Tizatlan, over the opposing faction of Ocotelolco. The charge of treason lodged against him and his subsequent execution were, in this view, the logical result of the Ocotelolcans finally achieving the upper hand.</p>
</text>
