<text id="autogum_bio_doc247" title="Cao Xueqin" shortTile="cao-xueqin" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2003-08-12" dateModified="2019-10-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cao_Xueqin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cao Xueqin</head>
This is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_name">Chinese name</ref>; the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_surname">family name</ref> is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cao_(surname)">Cao</ref>.
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cáo Xuěqín</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Mandarin">[tsʰǎuɕɥètɕʰǐn]</ref>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_language">Chinese</ref>:曹雪芹); (1715 or 1724–1763 or 1764)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Longman-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> was a Chinese writer during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qing_dynasty">Qing dynasty</ref>.  He is best known as the author of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dream_of_the_Red_Chamber">Dream of the Red Chamber</ref></hi>, one of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_Great_Classical_Novels">Four Great Classical Novels</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_literature">Chinese literature</ref>. His given name was <hi rend="bold">Cáo Zhān </hi> (曹霑) and his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Courtesy_name">courtesy name</ref> was <hi rend="bold">Mèngruǎn</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simplified_Chinese_characters">simplified Chinese</ref>:梦阮; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traditional_Chinese_characters">traditional Chinese</ref>:夢阮).</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Cao Xueqin was born to a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Han_Chinese">Han Chinese</ref> clan<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> that was brought into personal service (as <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Booi_aha">booi aha</ref></hi> or bondservants of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cigu_Niru">Cigu Niru</ref>) to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manchu">Manchu</ref> royalty in the late 1610s.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> His ancestors distinguished themselves through military service in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plain_White_Banner">Plain White Banner</ref> (正白旗) of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eight_Banners">Eight Banners</ref> and subsequently held posts as officials which brought both prestige and wealth.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-chinahisciv-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>After the Plain White Banner was put under the direct jurisdiction of the Qing emperor, Cao's family began to serve in civil positions of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperial_Household_Department">Imperial Household Department</ref>.</p>
<p>During the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kangxi_Emperor">Kangxi Emperor</ref>'s reign, the clan's prestige and power reached its height. Cao Xueqin's grandfather, Cao Yin (曹寅), was a childhood playmate to Kangxi while Cao Yin's mother, Lady Sun (孫氏), was Kangxi's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wet_nurse">wet nurse</ref>. Two years after his ascension, Kangxi appointed Cao Xueqin's great-grandfather, Cao Xi (曹璽), as the Commissioner of Imperial Textiles (織造) in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nanjing">Jiangning</ref> (present-day Nanjing), and the family relocated there.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Spence_Ts'ao_Yin-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>When Cao Xi died in 1684, Cao Yin, as Kangxi's personal confidant, took over the post. Cao Yin was one of the era's most prominent men of letters and a keen book collector. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonathan_Spence">Jonathan Spence</ref> notes the strong Manchu element in the lives of these Imperial Household bond servants. They balanced the two cultures: Cao Yin took pleasure in horse riding and hunting and Manchu military culture, but was at the same time a sensitive interpreter of Chinese culture to the Manchus. By the early 18th century, the Cao clan had become so rich and influential as to be able to play host four times to the Kangxi Emperor in his six separate itinerant trips south to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nanjing">Nanjing</ref> region. In 1705, the emperor ordered Cao Yin, himself a fluent poet, to compile all surviving <hi rend="italic">shi</hi> (lyric poems) from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tang_dynasty">Tang dynasty</ref>, which resulted in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quan_Tangshi">The Complete Poems of the Tang</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Spence_Ts'ao_Yin-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>When Cao Yin died in 1712, Kangxi passed the office over to Cao Yin's only son, Cao Yong (曹顒). Cao Yong died in 1715. Kangxi then allowed the family to adopt a paternal nephew, Cao Fu (曹頫), as Cao Yin's posthumous son to continue in that position. Hence the clan held the office of Imperial Textile Commissioner at Jiangning for three generations.</p>
<p>The family's fortunes lasted until Kangxi's death and the ascension of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yongzheng_Emperor">Yongzheng Emperor</ref> to the throne. Yongzheng severely attacked the family and in 1727 confiscated their properties, while Cao Fu was thrown in jail.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-chinahisciv-7">[7]</ref> This was ostensibly for their mismanagement of funds, though perhaps this purge was politically motivated. When Cao Fu was released a year later, the impoverished family was forced to relocate to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beijing">Beijing</ref>. Cao Xueqin, still a young child, lived in poverty with his family.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<figure><caption>Cao Xueqin Memorial Museum in Nanjing.</caption></figure>
<p>Almost no records of Cao's early childhood and adulthood have survived. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Redology">Redology</ref> scholars are still debating Cao's exact date of birth, though he is known to have been around forty to fifty at his death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> Cao Xueqin was the son of either Cao Fu or Cao Yong.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> It is known for certain that Cao Yong's only son was born posthumously in 1715; some Redologists believe this son might be Cao Xueqin. In the clan register (五慶堂曹氏宗譜), however, Cao Yong's only son was recorded as a certain Cao Tianyou (曹天佑). Further complicating matters for Redologists is the fact that neither the names Cao Zhan nor Cao Xueqin—names that his contemporaries knew him by—can be traced in the register.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>Most of what we know about Cao was passed down from his contemporaries and friends.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> Cao eventually settled in the countryside west of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beijing">Beijing</ref> where he lived the larger part of his later years in poverty selling off his paintings. Cao was recorded as an inveterate drinker. Friends and acquaintances recalled an intelligent, highly talented man who spent a decade working diligently on a work that must have been <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dream_of_the_Red_Chamber">Dream of the Red Chamber</ref></hi>. They praised both his stylish paintings, particularly of cliffs and rocks, and originality in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_poetry">poetry</ref>, which they likened to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Li_He">Li He</ref>'s. Cao died some time in 1763 or 1764, leaving his novel in a very advanced stage of completion. (At least the first draft had been completed, some pages of the manuscript were lost after being borrowed by friends or relatives.) He was survived by a wife after the death of a son.</p>
<p>Cao achieved posthumous fame through his life's work. The novel, written in "blood and tears", as a commentator said, is a vivid recreation of an illustrious family at its height and its subsequent downfall. A small group of close family and friends appeared to have been transcribing his manuscript when Cao died quite suddenly in 1763–4, apparently out of grief owing to the death of a son. Extant handwritten copies of this work—some 80 chapters—had been in circulation in Beijing shortly after Cao's death and scribal copies soon became prized collectors' items.</p>
<p>In 1791, Cheng Weiyuan (程偉元) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gao_E_(writer)">Gao E</ref> (高鶚), who claimed to have access to Cao's working papers, edited and published a "complete" <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheng-Gao_Versions">120-chapter version</ref>. This was its first <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woodblock_printing">woodblock print</ref> edition. Reprinted a year later with more revisions, this 120-chapter edition is the novel's most printed version. Many modern scholars question the authorship of the last 40 chapters of the novel, whether it was actually completed by Cao Xueqin.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Longman-2">[2]</ref></p>
</text>
