<text id="autogum_bio_doc713" title="Ingram de Ketenis" shortTile="ingram-de-ketenis" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-28" dateModified="2018-09-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ingram_de_Ketenis" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ingram de Ketenis</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ingram de Ketenis</hi> [<hi rend="bold">de Kethenys</hi>] (died 1407 or 1408) was a medieval cleric from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angus,_Scotland">Angus</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scotland">Scotland</ref>.</p>
<p>A graduate of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Paris">University of Paris</ref>, he was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeacon_of_Dunkeld">Archdeacon of Dunkeld</ref> for over half a century. During his time, he received papal provision to be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Galloway">Bishop of Galloway</ref>, but refused to accept the position.</p>
<p>De Ketenis famously left an inscribed funeral monument. In the event, he did not use it, but it survives to this day.</p>
<head>Early life and career</head>
<p>Born before 1321, Ingram was the son of John de Ketenis, owner of the land of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kettins">Kettins</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angus,_Scotland">Angus</ref>; he had two known brothers, John de Ketenis and Robert de Ketenis, and was the nephew of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_de_Pilmuir">John de Pilmuir</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Moray">Bishop of Moray</ref> and thus also <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_de_Pilmuir">Richard de Pilmuir</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Dunkeld">Bishop of Dunkeld</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> In the 1340s, Ingram studied at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Paris">University of Paris</ref> under the renowned Scottish-born teacher, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_de_Wardlaw">Walter de Wardlaw</ref>, becoming a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Licentiate_(degree)">Licentiate</ref> in the Arts in May 1347, despite not completing a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B._A.">B. A.</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> In his time as a student he and his two brothers pledged surety to the English Nation of the University of Paris for the expenses of fellow-Scot John de Rossy, a pledge that cost them 50 shillings each because in the event Thomas failed to pay.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> In 1347, he briefly went back to his native Scotland, but returned to Paris in May 1349 to obtain an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_Arts">M. A.</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-293-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>He was at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avignon_Papacy">papal court</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avignon">Avignon</ref> in 1344/5 with his uncle Richard de Pilmuir, attempting to gain favours. He received provision to the church of "Blair", that is, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blairgowrie_and_Rattray">Blairgowrie</ref>, on 25 January 1345, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Clement_VI">Pope Clement VI</ref> commanding the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbot_of_Coupar_Angus">Abbot of Coupar Angus</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbot_of_Scone">Abbot of Scone</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prior_of_St_Andrews">Prior of St Andrews</ref> to put him in possession,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> although it is not clear that he managed to possess full control of this church until 1349 or later.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-293-4">[4]</ref> He received a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_(priest)">canonry</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Aberdeen">diocese of Aberdeen</ref> on 18 May 1347, and in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Moray">diocese of Moray</ref> on 10 May 1349, neither of which he seems to have taken up permanently.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-293-4">[4]</ref> He had been at Avignon again in 1349, regarding the Moray canonry, either before or after going to Paris, when he presented petitions for his brother John and his cousin Thomas de Pilmuir.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-293-4">[4]</ref> He was recorded at Avignon again in 1350, when he is described as the secretary of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_of_The_Tower">Queen Joan</ref>; there he was provided to a canonry in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Glasgow">diocese of Glasgow</ref>, though once more it is unclear if this provision ever actualised.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Archdeacon of Dunkeld</head>
<p>At some point between 1352 and 1359 he became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeacon_of_Dunkeld">Archdeacon of Dunkeld</ref>, a position which had become vacant because of the death of the previous archdeacon, Adam Pullur. The latter's death occurred before 13 July 1352 when there is record that one John de Ethie [Athy] was provided to the archdeaconry; the latter provision was unsuccessful, and Ingram is the next known archdeacon.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> On his funeral monument the inscription says that Ingram was 31 (in "his xxxii yhere") when he obtained the Dunkeld archdeaconry, so that he probably obtained at least a claim to the position in 1351 or 1352.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> He had demitted his right to the church of Blairgowrie by 12 February 1357, and was certainly fully in possession of the archdeaconry by 13 August 1359, when he witnessed a charter (as Archdeacon of Dunkeld) of his uncle John de Pilmuir, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Moray">Bishop of Moray</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> The archdeaconry came with the dependent parish church of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tealing">Tealing</ref> in Angus.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-293-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>His next appearance occurs as a sub-collector of papal taxes to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_de_Greenlaw">William de Greenlaw</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeacon_of_St_Andrews">Archdeacon of St Andrews</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean_(religion)">Dean</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glasgow_Cathedral">Glasgow Cathedral</ref>, in 1361.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref>  On 17 April 1371, he is a papal mandatory tasked to adjudicate a dispute between a knight and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paisley_Abbey">Paisley Abbey</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-293-4">[4]</ref> Sometime between 15 July 1378 and 26 February 1379, Ingram was provided as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Galloway">Bishop of Galloway</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avignon_Pope_Clement_VII">Avignon Pope Clement VII</ref> in opposition to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Urban_VI">Urbanist</ref> candidate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oswald_of_Glenluce">Oswald</ref> (see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western_Schism">Western Schism</ref>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> This was done because of the influence of Ingram's old university master, Walter de Wardlaw, now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Glasgow">Bishop of Glasgow</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-293-4">[4]</ref> Ingram however does not appear to have wanted the bishopric, and found objections to his own provision.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> As Clement wrote to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_de_Rossy">Thomas de Rossy</ref>, the man who did become the Clementine bishop, he had "provided Ingeram, archdeacon of Dunkeld, but he refused to accept his provision".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref></p>
<p>Although <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Trail">Walter Trail</ref> had been provided to succeed Ingram as archdeacon in expectation of Ingram becoming Bishop of Galloway, Ingram's refusal of this bishopric meant that he retained the archdeaconal possession.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> He made a grant from the lands of Kettin, which he had inherited from his father, to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dundee">Dundee</ref> chaplaincy of St Thomas the Martyr (i.e. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Becket">Thomas Becket</ref>) on 13 February 1392.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> Ingram held the position of Archdeacon of Dunkeld until at least 1398, and perhaps as late as 1407. Sometime between those two dates he witnessed (as Archdeacon of Dunkeld) a charter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Lindsay,_1st_Earl_of_Crawford">David Lindsay</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Crawford">Earl of Crawford</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-294-16">[16]</ref> At some point after this charter he exchanged the archdeaconry with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_de_Cornell">Richard de Cornell</ref> for the church of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kilmory,_Arran">Kilmory</ref> on the island of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isle_of_Arran">Arran</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_the_Isles">diocese of the Isles</ref>, presumably as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/D._E._R._Watt">D. E. R. Watt</ref> commented "just a formal move to give Cornell a title to [the] Dunk[eld] arch[deaconry]".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-293-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Death and memorial</head>
<figure><caption>19th century sketch of Ingram's inscribed funeral monument.</caption></figure><p>
One of the most notable facts about Ingram is his planned funeral monument. In the 1380s a memorial stone and a partially incomplete inscription were prepared for him at the church of Tealing; this monument has survived, and lay in a recess in the north wall of the modern (early 19th century) church, having been moved from the earlier church one mile away.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DHW-17">[17]</ref> It reads as follows: </p><p>heyr lyis Ingram of kethenys prist maystir in arit ersdene of dunkeldyn made in his xxxii yhere prayis for hym yat deyit hafand lx ... [sic] ... yherys of eld in the yher of cryst M: ccc: lxxx ... [SIC] ...<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref></p><p> Translated into modern English, this is "Here lies Ingram of Kethenys, Priest, Master in Arts, Archdeacon of Dunkeldyn, made in his thirty-second year. Pray for him that died, having (reached) sixty (blank) years of age, in the year of Christ 1380".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DHW-17">[17]</ref></p>
<p>The blanks after his age and the date indicate that he expected death soon (within ten years) in 1380,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Watt-294-16">[16]</ref> but in the event Ingram lived into the second half of the first decade of the 15th century. Ingram was still alive on 6 April 1407, but was dead by July 1408, when a papal document confirms his recent death and the resulting vacancy in the church of Tealing.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref> The inscription is probably the earliest, or earliest known, inscription written in Scotland north of the river Forth in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_language">English language</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-20">[20]</ref></p>
</text>
