<text id="autogum_bio_doc411" title="Roberto Bandinelli" shortTile="roberto-bandinelli" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-10-20" dateModified="2018-11-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roberto_Bandinelli" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Roberto Bandinelli</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Roberto Bandinelli</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polish_language">Polish</ref>: <hi lang="pl" rend="italic">Robert Bandinelli</hi>, died 1650) was a Florentine merchant and postmaster of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lviv">Lviv</ref> (Lwów) in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polish-Lithuanian_Commonwealth">Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth</ref>. He was a competitor to the postal service run by the Montelupi family since <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sebastiano_Montelupi">Sebastiano Montelupi</ref> had been appointed master of the royal post at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kraków">Kraków</ref> in 1568.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Païków-1">[1]</ref> Roberto was the elder brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angelo_Maria_Bandinelli">Angelo Maria Bandinelli</ref>, also a postmaster of the Commonwealth.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Roberto Bandinelli was the son of sculptor Michelangelo Bandinelli and a grandson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bartolommeo_Bandinelli">Bartolommeo Bandinelli</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Païków-1">[1]</ref> group leader of Florentine Mannerists, a self-proclaimed rival of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michelangelo">Michelangelo</ref> and famous Florentine artist in his own right. Roberto, a native of Florence, became a citizen of Kraków in 1618. It is said, that he relocated there to escape lawsuits which threatened him with imprisonment in Florence.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ji.lviv.ua-2">[2]</ref></p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bandinelli_Palace">Bandinelli Palace</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lwów">Lwów</ref></caption></figure>
<p>While in Kraków, he engaged in commercial manipulations and shady trade agreements with local merchants in the textile market, which brought him incredibly large profits, but also resulted in numerous litigations.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ji.lviv.ua-2">[2]</ref> Within a few years he had moved to Lwów (now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lviv">Lviv</ref>, Ukraine). On 4 March 1629 Bandinelli obtained royal license from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigismund_III_Vasa">Sigismund III Vasa</ref> to run two postal services from  Lwów: one, to what is now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gdańsk">Gdańsk</ref> through Zamotja (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zamość">Zamość</ref>), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lublin">Lublin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warsaw">Warsaw</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toruń">Toruń</ref>; and another one, to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kraków">Kraków</ref>, through <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jarosław">Jarosław</ref>, Rjashiv and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarnów">Tarnów</ref>. Each of the services was weekly, with the mails leaving every Saturday. The post office was housed in Bandinelli's home, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamienica_(architecture)">kamienica</ref> on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Market_Square_(Lviv)">Lviv market square</ref> that is now known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bandinelli_Palace">Bandinelli Palace</ref> <hi rend="italic">(pictured)</hi>. In later years he expanded his deliveries to include the entire territory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruthenia">Ruthenia</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ji.lviv.ua-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Tsybenko-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Attempts to enforce a royal postal monopoly against the city of Lviv's existing messenger services led to legal disputes that impeded the implementation of Bandinelli's postmastership. In 1633 his monopoly was reconfirmed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Władysław_IV_Vasa">Władysław IV Vasa</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanisław_Lubomirski_(1583–1649)">Stanisław Lubomirski</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voivode">voivode</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruthenian_Voivodeship">Ruthenia</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanisław_Koniecpolski">Stanisław Koniecpolski</ref>, voivode of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandomierz_Voivodeship">Sandomierz</ref>, issued further patents in support of Bandinelli's postal services.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Païków-1">[1]</ref> These became viable only after 1639, when Bandinelli became the main rival to the postal services that had been run by the Montelupi family since <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sebastiano_Montelupi">Sebastiano Montelupi</ref> had been appointed master of the royal post at Kraków in 1568.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Païków-1">[1]</ref> Bandinelli married twice, while in Lwów. His first wife Constance (Constanza) Ubaldini, helped him obtain royal privileges through her father. He built <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bandinelli_Palace">the palace</ref> with her dowry, but soon divorced her and remarried Anne Sehnio (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ukrainian_language">Ukrainian</ref>: Анна Сеґніо). In 1650 he went to Vienna to negotiate a new postal contract with the city, and died there shortly afterwards.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ji.lviv.ua-2">[2]</ref> He bequeathed his wealth to his four sons, Lauro, Michelangelo, Carlo and Stanislas, with the exception of the kamienica in Lviv, which went to his wife Anna, to be shared with his two daughters, Costanza and Caterina, for as long as they remained unmarried.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Païków-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
