<text id="autogum_bio_doc356" title="Palma il Giovane" shortTile="palma-il-giovane" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-08-27" dateModified="2019-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palma_il_Giovane" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Palma il Giovane</head><hi rend="bold">Warning:</hi> Page using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_artist">Template:Infobox artist</ref> with unknown parameter "imagesize" (this message is shown only in preview).<hi rend="bold">Warning:</hi> Page using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Infobox_artist">Template:Infobox artist</ref> with unknown parameter "bgcolour" (this message is shown only in preview).
<p><hi rend="bold">Iacopo Negretti</hi> (1548/50<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> – 14 October 1628), best known as <hi rend="bold">Jacopo</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Giacomo Palma il Giovane</hi> or simply <hi rend="bold">Palma Giovane</hi> ("Young Palma"),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref>  was an Italian painter from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venice">Venice</ref> and a notable exponent of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venetian_school_(art)">Venetian school</ref>.</p>
<p>After <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tintoretto">Tintoretto</ref>'s death (1594), Palma became Venice's dominant artist perpetuating his style.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Outside Venice, he received numerous commissions in the area of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bergamo">Bergamo</ref>, then part of the Venetian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domini_di_Terraferma">Domini di Terraferma</ref>, and in Central Europe, most prominently from the connoisseur emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rudolph_II">Rudolph II</ref> in Prague.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Palma was born in Venice. Born into a family of painters, he was the great-nephew of the painter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palma_Vecchio">Palma Vecchio</ref> ("Old Palma") and the son of Antonio Nigreti (1510/15-1575/85), a minor painter who was himself the pupil of the elder Palma's workshop foreman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bonifazio_Veronese">Bonifacio de' Pitati</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref>  and who after Bonifazio's death (1553) inherited Bonifacio's shop and clientele; the younger Palma seems to have polished his style making copies after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Titian">Titian</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1567 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guidobaldo_II_della_Rovere">Guidobaldo II della Rovere</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_of_Urbino">duke of Urbino</ref>, recognized Palma's talents, supporting him for four years and sending him to Rome, where he remained until about 1572. Shedding most remnants of Roman manner after his return to Venice, Palma adopted the inescapable models and mannerisms of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tintoretto">Tintoretto</ref>. His early biographers assert that he found a place in the ageing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Titian">Titian</ref>'s workshop; when the master died, Palma stepped in to finish his last work, the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pietà_(Titian)">Pietà</ref></hi> in the Accademia, Venice. Palma's first major public commission arrived after a 1577 fire in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doge's_Palace,_Venice">Doge's Palace</ref>: three scenes in its grand council hall. By the mid-1580s he had digested <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tintoretto">Tintoretto</ref>'s versatile figure postures and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Titian">Titian</ref>'s thick surfaces, emphasis on light, and loose brushstroke. In Palma Giovane's output, Freedberg detects also "an occasional discursive opulence à la <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paolo_Veronese">Veronese</ref>; and inclinations towards descriptive naturalism à la <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacopo_Bassano">Bassano</ref>."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Rejecting Mannerism in the 1580s, he embraced a reformist naturalism<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> he varied the ingeniously synthesised amalgam according to subject matter and patrons' own eclectic and conservative tastes, with "virtuoso skill and a facile intelligence."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>Monument to Palma il Giovane, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santi_Giovanni_e_Paolo,_Venice">Basilica di San Giovanni e Paolo</ref></caption></figure>
<p>He worked alongside Veronese and Tintoretto on the decorations in the Doge's Palace where he came to know fully the Venetian tradition. From 1580-90 he painted cycles of large canvases either for Venetian Schools or sacred buildings (the sacristies of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Giacomo_dall'Orio">San Giacomo dall'Orio</ref> and of the Jesuit church (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gesuiti_(Venice)">Gesuiti</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scuola_Grande_di_San_Giovanni_Evangelista">Scuola di San Giovanni Evangelista</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oratorio_dei_Crociferi,_Venice">Oratorio dei Crociferi</ref>. Thanks to the intelligent way they quoted from Tintoretto and their own narrative drive, these are Palma the Younger's best works. After this he went back to official commissions at the Doge's Palace.
Among these there is the magnificent portrait of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Pope_Pius_V">Saint Pope Pius V</ref>, commissioned by the Bellanti Counts, an influential family who gave four "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capitano_del_Popolo">Capitani del Popolo</ref>" to the city of Siena in the Middle Ages. After three centuries in Tuscany, it was bought by Sir Robert Dick in 1842. After another two hundred years, the portrait was bought from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bonham's">Bonham's</ref> in London, one of the most ancient auction houses in the world, founded in 1793 and thanks to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roberto_Gagliardi"> Roberto Gagliardi</ref> it was brought back to Tuscany where it can be admired at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chianciano_Museum_of_Art">Chianciano Museum of Art</ref>, a few kilometres from Siena.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>Palma il Giovane went on to organize his own, large studio which he used to produce a repetitive series of religious and allegorical pictures that can be found throughout the territory of the Venetian Republic. After 1600 he painted mythologies for a small circle of intellectuals. After the death of Tintoretto in 1594, he remained one of the leading painters in the City of Venice.</p>
<p>He was interred in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santi_Giovanni_e_Paolo,_Venice">Basilica di San Giovanni e Paolo</ref>, a traditional burial place of the doges. Among his followers was the Brescian painter, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camillo_Rama">Camillo Rama</ref>.</p>
<head>Gallery</head>
<list type="unordered">
<item>Crucifixion  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madonna_dell'Orto">Madonna dell'Orto</ref> </item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Venus and Mars</hi> - The National Gallery, London</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yael">Yael</ref> Killing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sisera">Sisera</ref></item>
<item>Madonna and Child... <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Zaccaria,_Venice">San Zaccaria, Venice</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Davide vincitore</hi>...<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San_Zaccaria,_Venice">San Zaccaria, Venice</ref></item>
<item>Saint Pope <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pius_V">Pius V</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
