<text id="autogum_bio_doc363" title="Thomas Legh (lawyer)" shortTile="thomas-legh-lawyer" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-10-22" dateModified="2019-10-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Legh_%28lawyer%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Thomas Legh (lawyer)</head>
For those of the same or similar names, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Leigh_(disambiguation)">Thomas Leigh (disambiguation)</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Sir Thomas Leigh</hi> <hi rend="italic">or</hi> <hi rend="bold">Legh</hi> (?1511-1545) was an English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jurist">jurist</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diplomat">diplomat</ref>, who played a key role as agent of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VIII">Henry VIII</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Cromwell">Thomas Cromwell</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dissolution_of_the_Monasteries">Dissolution of the Monasteries</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>The younger son of John Leigh, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_of_the_manor">lord of the manor</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frizington">Frizington</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cumberland">Cumberland</ref>, he was a cousin of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rowland_Lee">Bishop Rowland Leigh (<hi rend="italic">or</hi> Lee)</ref>, scions of the ancient Leigh family of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_Legh">West Hall, High Legh</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheshire">Cheshire</ref>. </p>
<p>Leigh was educated at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eton_College">Eton College</ref> before entering <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King's_College,_Cambridge">King's College, Cambridge</ref> proceeding LLB in 1527, and LLD in 1531.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Venn-3">[3]</ref> He was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Called_to_the_Bar">called to the Bar</ref> 7 October 1531. In December 1532 he was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ambassador">ambassador</ref> to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_of_Denmark">King of Denmark</ref>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Holy_Roman_Empire_ambassadors_to_England">Imperial Ambassador</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eustace_Chapuys">Eustace Chapuys</ref> was unimpressed with Dr Leigh at this time. He was recalled from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denmark">Denmark</ref> in March 1533, then being employed in 1533 by his cousin the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop">bishop</ref>. He cited <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_of_Aragon">Catherine of Aragon</ref> to appear before <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Cranmer">Thomas Cranmer</ref> and hear the final divorce sentence in 1533, and in the same year also conducted an inquiry at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rievaulx_Abbey">Rievaulx Abbey</ref> which led to the resignation of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbot">abbot</ref>. In January 1533-4 he was sent on another <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Embassy">embassy</ref> to the Low Countries, passing through <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antwerp">Antwerp</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lübeck">Lübeck</ref>. He returned to England in April, went again to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamburg">Hamburg</ref> in May, and must have returned once more in the summer.</p>
<p>On 4 June 1535 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Layton">Richard Layton</ref> wrote to Cromwell recommending Leigh and himself to be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visitor">Visitors</ref> of the northern religious houses. Leigh, however, was first sent with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_ap_Rice">Sir John Price (<hi rend="italic">or</hi> ap Rice)</ref>; in July 1535 they went to Worcester, and then visited, 3 July Malvern, 20 August <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lacock_Abbey">Lacock Abbey</ref> (after Malmesbury, Bradstock, and Stanley), 23 August <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bruton_Abbey">Bruton Abbey</ref>, 3 September Wilton, 11 September Wherwell, 24 September Witney, 25 September Reading, 29 September Haliwell, 17 October Royston, and 19 October Walden. Leigh made a large profit out of the visitation, and complaints of his conduct were numerous. Leigh was always accompanied by fourteen men in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Livery">livery</ref> and his brother, all of whom had to be rewarded. His style was flamboyant, and Cromwell found fault with him. Sir John ap Rice, who thought his treatment of the monks needlessly severe, describes his insolence. To Leigh's suggestion was due the suspension of the bishops' authority during the visitation.</p>
<p>At <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cambridge_University">Cambridge</ref> Leigh's changes were few; he ordered (22 October 1535) the charters to be sent up to London with a rental of the university possessions, tried to pacify the strife among the nations, and established a lecture in divinity. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Goodrich">Thomas Goodrich</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Ely">Bishop of Ely</ref>, wrote approvingly of his proceedings. Leigh went on to Bury, 4 November; Westacre, 11 November, after West Dereham; Norwich, 19 November; Ipswich, 27 November; and meeting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Layton">Richard Layton</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lichfield">Lichfield</ref> at Christmas 1535 he proceeded with him to the northern visitation.</p>
<p>The mastership of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sherburn_Hospital">Sherburn Hospital</ref> in Durham was granted to Leigh on 14 September 1535. He also acquired the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advowson">advowson</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birmingham">Birmingham</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gisborough_Priory">Gisborough Priory</ref> in March 1536; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calder_Abbey">Calder Abbey</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cumberland">Cumberland</ref> was granted to him in 1539, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nostell_Priory">Nostell Priory</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yorkshire">Yorkshire</ref>, with its cell at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tockwith">Stowkirke</ref>, in 1539-40. A letter of May 1536 to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johannes_Aepinus">Johannes Aepinus</ref> shows that he was acquainted with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melanchthon">Melanchthon</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oldendorpius">Oldendorpius</ref>. In 1536 he assisted at the trial of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_Boleyn">Anne Boleyn</ref>.</p>
<p>During the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pilgrimage_of_Grace">Pilgrimage of Grace</ref> in 1536 he was as unpopular as his colleague Layton; they sang ballads about him and Leigh as one of the three L's (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Layton">Richard Layton</ref>, dean of York and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Longland">John Longland</ref>, bishop of Lincoln, were the other two) one ballad; and they hanged his cook. He meanwhile was busy taking money to the forces, and when the rebellion was over he tried the prisoners. In August 1536 he had made a tour through the Midlands archdeaconries of Coventry and Stafford, and was much distressed by the open adultery of the country gentlemen. He married in 1536, and was reprimanded by his friends for not informing them of it.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Some time in the early part of 1537 he became a master in chancery, and throughout 1538, 1539, and 1540 he was engaged in suppressing religious houses. In 1543 Leigh went from York to Canterbury to investigate the plot against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Cranmer">Thomas Cranmer</ref>. He was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knight">knighted</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leith">Leith</ref> by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Seymour,_1st_Duke_of_Somerset">Earl of Hertford</ref>, on 11 May 1544, seemingly on the Scottish expedition.</p>
<p>Leigh was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member_of_Parliament">Member</ref> (MP) of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament_of_England">Parliament of England</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hindon_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Hindon</ref> in 1536 and for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wilton_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Wilton</ref> in 1545.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> He died 25 November 1545,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Venn-3">[3]</ref> and was buried at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Leonard's,_Shoreditch">St. Leonard's, Shoreditch</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, where a tomb with a rhyming inscription was erected in his memory. </p>
<head>Marriage</head>
<p>His widow Dame Joanna (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Cotton) remarried <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Chaloner_the_elder">Sir Thomas Chaloner</ref>, and died 11 January 1557.</p>
<p>Their only child, Catherine Leigh, married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Blount,_6th_Baron_Mountjoy">James Blount, 6th Baron Mountjoy</ref>, and had issue including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Blount,_1st_Earl_of_Devonshire">Charles Blount, 1st Earl of Devonshire</ref>.</p>
</text>
