<text id="autogum_bio_doc008" title="Mark A. Morgan" shortTile="mark--morgan" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-05-05" dateModified="2019-11-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_A._Morgan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Mark A. Morgan</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mark A. Morgan</hi> is an American law enforcement officer who has served as the Chief Operating Officer and acting Commissioner of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S._Customs_and_Border_Protection">U.S. Customs and Border Protection</ref> since July 5, 2019.</p>
<p>Morgan had a long career in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal_Bureau_of_Investigation">Federal Bureau of Investigation</ref>, culminating in appointments as head of the Inspection Division and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FBI_Academy">Training Division</ref>.  He then served as chief of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Border_Patrol">United States Border Patrol</ref> under President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> as the first person to be appointed to that post from outside the border Patrol; he resigned a few days after the inauguration of President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref>. Morgan returned to government when was announced as Trump's pick to be acting director of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S._Immigration_and_Customs_Enforcement">U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement</ref> (ICE), where he served from May 28, 2019 until he moved to Customs and Border Protection.</p>
<head>Education and early career</head>
<p>Morgan was born in 1964 or 1965.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:4-1">[1]</ref>  Morgan received a Bachelor of Science degree in Engineering from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_Missouri_State_University">Central Missouri State University</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-2">[2]</ref> He joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Marine_Corps">United States Marine Corps</ref> at the age of 19,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-3">[3]</ref> and served active duty and reserve for a total of 10 years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>He received a Juris Doctor degree from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Missouri–Kansas_City">University of Missouri–Kansas City</ref>, serving as a Deputy Sheriff with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Platte_County,_Missouri">Platte County, Missouri</ref>, Sheriff's Department, and in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Marine_Corps_Reserve">Marine Corps Reserve</ref> concurrently with his studies.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-3">[3]</ref>  After finishing his law degree, he attended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los_Angeles_Police_Department_Academy">Los Angeles Police Department Academy</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-3">[3]</ref> and served as a police officer with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los_Angeles_Police_Department">Los Angeles Police Department</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>FBI career</head>
<figure><caption>Morgan as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FBI_Academy">FBI Academy</ref> head in 2015</caption></figure>
<p>Morgan entered on duty as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special_agent">Special Agent</ref> in 1996 and was assigned to the Los Angeles Field Office.  While there, he was a member of the Eurasian Organized Crime Task Force, the Crisis Response Squad, and the Special Weapons and Tactics Team. In 2002, Morgan became a Supervisory Special Agent and served as a Crisis Management Coordinator in the Crisis Management Unit in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FBI_Critical_Incident_Response_Group">Critical Incident Response Group</ref>.  In 2005, Morgan returned to Los Angeles, where he supervised an FBI-led Hispanic Gang Task Force that focused on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MS-13">MS-13</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/18th_Street_gang">18th Street</ref> gangs. While in Los Angeles, he also supervised the Critical Incident Response Squad, which had administrative and operational oversight of the division’s critical incident response resources.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Morgan in 2007 became Assistant Section Chief of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Center_for_the_Analysis_of_Violent_Crime">National Center for the Analysis of Violent Crime</ref> Branch, where he managed the FBI’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Behavioral_Analysis_Unit">Behavioral Analysis Units</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Violent_Criminal_Apprehension_Program">Violent Criminal Apprehension Program</ref>.  In 2008, he became the FBI’s Deputy On-Scene Commander in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baghdad">Baghdad</ref>, Iraq, where he was responsible for all FBI personnel deployed to Iraq under the auspices of the Counterterrorism Division.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-2">[2]</ref>  This was his first deployment to a war zone.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In 2009, Morgan was assigned as Assistant Special Agent in Charge of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Haven,_Connecticut">New Haven</ref> Field Office.  In 2010, Morgan became Chief of the FBI <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strategic_Information_and_Operation_Center">Strategic Information and Operations Center</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-2">[2]</ref> From 2011 to 2013, Morgan served as the Special Agent in Charge of the FBI <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_Paso,_Texas">El Paso</ref> Division.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>During 2013–2014, Morgan served as Deputy Assistant Director for the FBI’s Inspection Division, which performs compliance and oversight of all FBI operations. In 2014, Morgan served on a detail to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S._Customs_and_Border_Protection">U.S. Customs and Border Protection</ref> (CBP) in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Department_of_Homeland_Security">Department of Homeland Security</ref> as the Acting Assistant Commissioner for Internal Affairs.  In this role, he oversaw the investigation of criminal and serious administrative misconduct by the CBP workforce.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-2">[2]</ref>  Morgan was assigned to this position after the previous Assistant Commissioner, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_F._Tomsheck">James F. Tomsheck</ref>, was removed for failing to investigate allegations of inappropriate use of force by border agents, and CBP head <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gil_Kerlikowske">Gil Kerlikowske</ref> took the unusual step of requesting an interim appointment from outside the agency to pursue investigations more aggressively.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>In 2014, he was appointed as FBI Assistant Director for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FBI_Academy">Training Division</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantico,_Virginia">Quantico, Virginia</ref>, with responsibility for overseeing policy development and delivery of all law enforcement skills and academic programs for the FBI workforce.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Department of Homeland Security</head>
<head>Chief of U.S. Border Patrol</head>
<figure><caption>Morgan in September 2016</caption></figure>
<p>In June 2016, he was named as the next chief of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S._Border_Patrol">U.S. Border Patrol</ref> by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Presidency_of_Barack_Obama">Obama administration</ref>, and took command in July.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Morgan was the first Chief of the Border Patrol to come from outside the agency, and was intended to be a reformer and increase accountability.  The appointment was opposed by the Border Patrol's union, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Border_Patrol_Council">National Border Patrol Council</ref>.  His decision to wear the Border Patrol uniform was met with some opposition, as he had never been a Border Patrol officer.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:4-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>On December 1, 2016, Morgan stated in a Senate hearing that he supported a comprehensive immigration overhaul, which was met with strenuous criticism from the National Border Patrol Council.  Morgan subsequently clarified that he did not support "blanket amnesty".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:3-6">[6]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>On January 26, 2017, just days after President Donald Trump took office, he was forced to resign.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:3-6">[6]</ref>  He had reportedly desired to stay in his post during the Trump administration, internally criticizing the immigration enforcement policies of the Obama administration after the election.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Gap in government service</head>
<p>In January 2019, Morgan said that he could determine if an unaccompanied minor would become a member of MS-13, a transnational crime gang known for gruesome violence, just by looking at their eyes.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-9">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Acting Director of Immigration and Customs Enforcement</head>
<p>At the end of April 2019, it was reported that Trump was considering Morgan to take over as head of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Immigration_and_Customs_Enforcement">Immigration and Customs Enforcement</ref>. The agency's former acting director, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ronald_Vitiello">Ronald Vitiello</ref>, resigned earlier in April after Trump pulled his nomination for the director's job, telling reporters that he wanted to go with someone "tougher" instead.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>On May 5, Trump announced on Twitter that he had chosen Morgan to become the next director of ICE.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> The <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi> reported that the announcement "caught White House aides and Homeland Security officials by surprise. They had not been informed Morgan was Trump’s choice, and at ICE, senior leaders learned of the decision from the president’s tweet, according to two senior administration officials."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_Albence">Matthew Albence</ref>, who had been acting director of ICE since April 2019 and was previously acting deputy director of the agency, continued in that role until Morgan was formally named acting director on May 28, 2019.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref></p>
<p>He was formally appointed to a newly-created position as Principal Deputy Director that outranked the preexisting Deputy Director position.  This was criticized as avoiding Senate scrutiny for this position through the normal confirmation process.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref></p>
<head>Acting Customs and Border Protection Commissioner</head>
<p>On June 27, 2019, the Department of Homeland Security announced that Morgan would become the acting commissioner of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S._Customs_and_Border_Protection">U.S. Customs and Border Protection</ref>, replacing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_P._Sanders">John Sanders</ref>, who had announced his resignation.  On July 5, 2019, Morgan became acting commissioner.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref>  His formal appointment was as Chief Operating Officer of the agency.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref></p>
</text>
