<text id="autogum_bio_doc694" title="Calandrino" shortTile="calandrino" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-05-07" dateModified="2018-08-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calandrino" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Calandrino</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Calandrino</hi> is a character from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Boccaccio">Giovanni Boccaccio</ref>'s the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decameron">Decameron</ref></hi>, in which he appears in four stories. In these tales he is the victim of the pranks of Bruno and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buonamico_Buffalmacco">Buffalmacco</ref>. He becomes a recurring character in Renaissance literature, especially in Italy.</p>
<head>Appearances in The Decameron</head>
<p>In each of the tales in which Calandrino is a character (VIII, 3; VIII, 6; IX, 3; IX, 5), he is portrayed as a simpleton who believes in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Folk_religion">folk magic</ref> of the time period. In the first tale (VIII, 3), the three painters hunt for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heliotrope_(mineral)">heliotropes</ref>, and Calandrino believes that by finding one he is rendered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Invisible">invisible</ref>. Bruno and Buffalmacco, his friends and fellow painters, pretend they don't see him and kick rocks at him all the way back to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florence">Florence</ref>, where he arrives bruised.</p>
<p>In the second tale (VIII, 6) Bruno and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buonamico_Buffalmacco">Buffalmacco</ref> subject him to a medieval version of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polygraph">polygraph</ref> test. According to common belief at the time, a person who is lying wouldn't be able to swallow the prepared bread and cheese when under examination. However, Bruno and Buffalmacco sour the cheese with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Water-pepper">dog ginger</ref>, a very bitter herb which Calandrino then spits out. This convinces his friends that he is lying about a pig of his being stolen (which in reality they had taken).</p>
<p>Calandrino is convinced that he <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Male_pregnancy">is pregnant</ref> in story IX, 3. To give him a painless miscarriage he takes a potion that is specially prepared by his friends, Bruno and Buffalmacco.</p>
<p>Finally, tale IX, 5 is a story in which Boccaccio uses the Calandrino character to ridicule the folk magic of his time period. To gain a woman's affections, Calandrino casts a spell and prepares a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Potion">potion</ref> from a scroll supplied by Bruno. The potion contains all sorts of absurd ingredients and the scroll is filled with gibberish. When his wife discovers his intentions, she beats Calandrino.</p>
<head>Calandrino in the arts</head>
<p>Calandrino became the main character in several artistic works, including:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernardo_Dovizi">Bernardo Dovizi</ref>'s play <hi rend="italic">La Calandra</hi> (also, known as <hi rend="italic">Il Calandro </hi>and<hi rend="italic"> La Calandria</hi>, 1507) (See <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernardo_Dovizi#Literary_fame:_Calandro">Bernardo Dovizi#Literary fame: Calandro</ref>) - play</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Alberto_Ristori">Giovanni Alberto Ristori</ref>, <hi rend="italic">«<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calandro">Calandro</ref>»</hi> (1726), libretto - <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefano_Benedetto_Pallavicino">Stefano Benedetto Pallavicino</ref> - opera</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonio_Sacchini">Antonio Sacchini</ref>, <hi rend="italic">«L'avaro deluso, o Don Calandrino»</hi> (1778) - opera</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Georg_Schürer">Johann Georg Schürer</ref>, <hi rend="italic">«Calandro»</hi> (1748) - opera</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giuseppe_Gazzaniga">Giuseppe Gazzaniga</ref>, <hi rend="italic">«Il Calandrino»</hi> (1771) - opera</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domenico_Cimarosa">Domenico Cimarosa</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Il ritorno di Don Calandrino</hi> (1778)- opera</item>
<item>Le avventure di Calandrino e Buffalmaco (1975) - mini-series</item>
<item>Paul Calandrino, <ref target="http://paulcalandrino.com/nincompoop.html"><hi rend="italic">The Nincompoop</hi></ref> (2007) - play</item></list>
<head>Historical identity</head>
<p>Calandrino was a historical person, an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italian_Renaissance">Italian Renaissance</ref> painter named <hi rend="bold">Nozzo di Perino</hi> who lived in the fourteenth century. Whether he really was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simpleton_(folklore)">simpleton</ref> portrayed by Boccaccio in his work is unknown, but common belief is that he was a bit gullible. It is unclear whether this belief arose because of the popularity of the <hi rend="italic">Decameron</hi>, or whether it was already popular belief when Boccaccio wrote the tales.</p>
</text>
