<text id="autogum_bio_doc299" title="Hristofor Žefarović" shortTile="hristofor-zefarovic" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-05-15" dateModified="2019-11-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hristofor_%C5%BDefarovi%C4%87" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hristofor Žefarović</head><figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pavle_Nenadović">Pavle Nenadović</ref>'s praise to Hristofor Žefarović in <hi rend="italic">Stemmatographia</hi>:"To the well reputable gentleman Hristofor Zhefarovich, Illyro-Rascian universal icon-painter, zealot of Bulgarian fatherland, lover of Illyrian Empire"</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Hristofor Žefarović</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarian_language">Bulgarian</ref>: Христофор Жефарович, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_Cyrillic_alphabet">Serbian Cyrillic</ref>: Христофор Жефаровић, <hi rend="italic">Hristofor Zhefarovich</hi>) was an 18th-century  painter, engraver, writer and poet and a notable proponent of early <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illyrian_movement">pan-South Slavism</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Born at the end of the 17th century, Hristofor Žefarović (Old Cyrillic: Христофоръ Жефаровичъ) descended from a priestly family from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dojran">Dojran</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman Empire</ref>, (present-day <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Macedonia">North Macedonia</ref>) and became a monk himself. His parents were Dimitrije and Đurđica Žefarović. As a highly educated and well-learned itinerant monk he painted and traded with books, icons and church plate. He spent some time in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sveti_Naum">St. Naum Monastery</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ohrid">Ohrid</ref>. His name was first mentioned in 1734 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belgrade">Belgrade</ref>, where he was well known as an artist. His first well-preserved work are the frescoes in the churches of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bođani_Monastery">Bođani Monastery</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bačka">Bačka</ref> (part of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vojvodina">Vojvodina</ref>, today in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbia">Serbia</ref>) from 1737 and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siklós">Siklós</ref> Orthodox Monastery from 1739. He was exclusively engaged in copper engraving and book illustration after 1740. he engraved copper plates for his books, and printed them in the "etching-typographical workshop" of his collaborator Thomas Mesmer in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vienna">Vienna</ref>. His engraving was of great cultural-historical importance to the Baroque art of the time. His style of 'bright cut' engraving was thoroughly masterly and original, specializing in the higher branches—engraving for printing—of the engraver's art.</p>
<p>Žefarović made a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pilgrimage">pilgrimage</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerusalem">Jerusalem</ref> through <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaffa">Jaffa</ref> and later established himself in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epiphany_Monastery">Epiphany Monastery</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow">Moscow</ref>, where he died on 18 September 1753. Žefarović was the author of two religious works, an instruction to newly appointed priests (Поучение святителское к новопоставленному йерею, <hi rend="italic">Pouchenie svyatitelskoe k novopostavlennomu yereyu</hi>) from 1742 and a description of Jerusalem from 1748 (Описание светаго божия града Йерусалима, <hi rend="italic">Opisanie svetago bozhiya grada Ierusalima</hi>), a book written by Simeon Simonović. Žefarović's name is also associated with two textbooks — a primer and a grammar book, as well as numerous copper gravures of renowned personalities from Vojvodina.</p>
<p>His work was acknowledged in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Europe">Europe</ref> and he became an honorary member of the Imperial Academy in Vienna and the Royal Academy of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Munich">Munich</ref>.</p>
<p>He died at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow">Moscow</ref> on 18 September 1753.</p>
<head><hi rend="italic">Stemmatographia</hi></head>
<p>Žefarović's work of greatest importance for the South Slavic Revival was his <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stemmatografia#Hristofor_Žefarović_edition">Stemmatographia</ref></hi> published in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vienna">Vienna</ref> in 1741. The book was commissioned by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_Orthodox_Church">Serbian Orthodox</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitanate_of_Karlovci">Metropolitan of Karlovci</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arsenije_IV_Jovanović_Šakabenta">Arsenije IV Jovanović Šakabenta</ref>, who also funded its production.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> During its composition Žefarović used the <hi rend="italic">Stemmatographia</hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Croatia_(Habsburg)">Croatian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pavao_Ritter_Vitezović">Pavao Ritter Vitezović</ref> of 1701, who on his part used <hi rend="italic">Kingdom of the Slavs</hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mauro_Orbini">Mauro Orbini</ref> of 1601. <hi rend="italic">Stemmatographia</hi> was illustrated by Žefarović with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copperplate_engraving">copperplate engravings</ref> and black and white drawings. It contains 20 copperplates depicting 28 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbia">Serbian</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgaria">Bulgarian</ref> rulers and saints; 15 of them are Serbian princes, princesses, kings, and tsars (mostly of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nemanjić_dynasty">Nemanjić dynasty</ref>), and 7 of them are Serbian archbishops and patriarchs.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> <hi rend="italic">Stemmatographia</hi> also contains 56 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coats_of_arms">coats of arms</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Slavs#Peoples_and_countries">South Slavic</ref> and other <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balkans">Balkan</ref> countries with descriptive <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quatrain">quatrains</ref> under them, regarded as the first example of modern secular <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarian_language">Bulgarian</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_poetry">Serbian poetry</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Stemmatographia</hi> had a crucial influence on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarian_National_Revival">Bulgarian National Revival</ref> and made a great impact on the entire Bulgarian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heraldry">heraldry</ref> of the 19th century, when it became most influential among all generations of Bulgarian enlighteners and revolutionaries during the period of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_awakening_of_Bulgaria">national awakening of Bulgaria</ref> and shaped the idea for a modern Bulgarian national symbol.</p>
<p>The pattern of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coat_of_arms_of_Bulgaria">Bulgarian coat of arms</ref> of <hi rend="italic">Stemmatographia</hi> was used as the state symbol of the royal Bulgarian administration in 1878, but set in an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ermine">ermine</ref> mantle and with a prince's crown above it. This coat of arms continued to be used on the state <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seal_(emblem)">seal</ref> and the seals of state institutions well after an official one (also influenced by the one in <hi rend="italic">Stemmatographia</hi>) was introduced by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Assembly_of_Bulgaria">National Assembly</ref>. The coat of arms of the short-lived <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> province of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_Rumelia">Eastern Rumelia</ref> was also created after the coat of arms of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref> (called "coat of arms of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romania">Romania</ref>") in Žefarović's work.</p>
<p>Žefarović's coat of arms of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgaria">Bulgaria</ref> is depicted on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obverse_and_reverse">reverse</ref> of the Bulgarian 2 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarian_lev">levs</ref> banknote, issued in 1999 and 2005.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Nationality and ethnicity</head>
<p>Hristofor Žefarović worked for the spiritual resurgence of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarians">Bulgarian</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbs">Serbian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/People">people</ref>, as he considered them to be one and the same "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illyrian_movement">Illyrian</ref>" (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Slavs">South Slavic</ref>) people. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pavle_Nenadović">Pavle Nenadović</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exarch">exarch</ref> of the Serbian Patriarch, had called him "Illyro-Rascian universal painter, zealot of the Bulgarian homeland and kinlover of the Illyrian Empire" ("иллирïко рассïанскому общему зографу, ревнителю отчества Болгарскагѡ и любителю царства Иллѵрïческагѡ"). Žefarović noted "our Serbian motherland" ("отечество сербско наше", <hi rend="italic">otechestvo serbsko nashe</hi>) and signed as a "Illyro-Rascian universal painter" ("иллирïко рассïанскïи общïй зографъ", <hi rend="italic">illirïko rassïanskïy obshtïy zograf</hi>). In his testament, he explicitly noted that his relatives were "of Bulgarian nationality" ("булгарской нации", <hi rend="italic">bulgarskoy natsii</hi>) and from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dojran">Dojran</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> The ethnicity of Žefarović has been the subject of some dispute between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgaria">Bulgarian</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_historiography">Serbian historiography</ref>. Western scholars prefer to emphasize his contributions to the history of both peoples, and maintain that Žefarović belonged to both <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nation">nations</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-hughes-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Honours</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zhefarovich_Crag">Zhefarovich Crag</ref> on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fallières_Coast">Fallières Coast</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antarctica">Antarctica</ref> is named after Hristofor Zhefarovich.</p>
<head>Gallery</head>
<list type="unordered">
<item>Engraving of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Methodius_of_Thessaloniki">Saint Methodius</ref> and Saint Jefrem of Serbia</item>
<item>Coat of arms of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_Empire">Roman (i.e. Byzantine)</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thrace">Thrace</ref></item>
<item>Coat of arms of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> Thrace</item>
<item>Coat of arms of "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romania">Romania</ref>", later adopted as the state symbol of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_Rumelia">Eastern Rumelia</ref></item>
<item>Coat of arms of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgaria">Bulgaria</ref></item>
<item>Coat of arms of the Serbian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Nemanjić">House of Nemanjić</ref></item>
<item>Coat of arms of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macedonia_(region)">Macedonia</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
