<text id="autogum_bio_doc652" title="Isaija the Monk" shortTile="isaija-monk" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-02-21" dateModified="2019-08-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isaija_the_Monk" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Isaija the Monk</head>This article is about the scribe. For the compositor, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isaiah_the_Serb">Isaiah the Serb</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Isaija the Monk</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_language">Serbian</ref>: Инок Исаија; ca. 1300–after 1375), also known as <hi rend="bold">Elder Isaija</hi> (Elder Isaiah) (Старац Исаија) and <hi rend="bold">Isaija of Serres</hi> (Elder Isaiah of Serres)  (Исаија Серски), was a 14th-century <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medieval_Serbia">Serbian</ref> monk, one of many Serbian monk-scribes in the Middle Ages who translated ancient Greek manuscripts into the Serbian recension of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Church_Slavonic">Old Church Slavonic</ref>. His major work is the translation of the works of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pseudo-Dionysius_the_Areopagite">Pseudo-Dionysius the Areopagite</ref> from Byzantine Greek. Isaija's commentaries on political events occur in the context of the fall of the Serbian principality of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serres">Serres</ref> in 1371, which led the descendants of these local governors to accept Ottoman suzerainty.</p>
<p>As a young boy, Isaija joined the monastic life of the Serbian Orthodox Church affiliated to St. Joachim of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Osogovo_Monastery">Osogovo Monastery</ref> on Osogovo Mountain in northern Macedonia, and then to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilandar_Monastery">Hilandar Monastery</ref> on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mount_Athos">Mount Athos</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greece">Greece</ref>, where he spent the rest of his life. In Hilandar, he worked as a translator and became very respected by Serbian rulers as attested to by the anonymous author of <hi rend="italic">The Life of the Monk Isaija</hi>, probably written in late 14th century.</p>
<p>Isaija was a very prominent individual during the reign of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Dushan">Stephen Dushan</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lazar_of_Serbia">Lazar of Serbia</ref>. He was a monk with an excellent reputation and he also excelled as a writer, translator, and diplomat. Between 1353 and 1363 he traveled throughout Serbia; he later served as a Serbian diplomat, and he proved to be very skilled during the negotiations initiated by Prince Lazar in order to reconcile the Serbian and the Greek Church, which was achieved in 1375 after resolving difficult diplomatic and ecclesiastical issues with Patriarch <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philotheus_I_of_Constantinople">Philotheus I of Constantinople</ref>. Isaija's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dragoman">dragoman</ref> on the mission to Constantinople was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicodemus_of_Tismana">Nicodemus of Tismana</ref>, Prince Lazar's relative.</p>
<p>At the end of his Pseudo-Dionysius the Areopagite translation, Isaija added an inscription and used a cryptogram to write his name.</p>
<p>Isaija had an anonymous disciple, known only as Isaija's Disciple, who wrote the biography of "Isaija the Monk". No biographical data of this author is extant. He is known in Serbian literature only as <hi rend="italic">Nepoznati Svetogorac,</hi> the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anonymous_Athonite">Anonymous Athonite</ref>.</p>
<head>Work</head>
<p>The climate of despair which set in after the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Maritsa">Battle of Maritsa</ref> in 1371 is expressed in a long personal comment, written by Isaija the Monk. This literary comment is appended to Isaija's translation of the works of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pseudo-Dionysius_the_Areopagite">Pseudo-Dionysius the Areopagite</ref> into Old Serbian which, he says, he had started <hi rend="italic">"in happy times,"</hi> but had finished it after the battle, <hi rend="italic">"when Ishmelites spread over the entire land as birds  in the air, slaying some of the Christians, sending others into slavery.... And the land became deprived of all that is good, people, beast, fruit of all kind. There was no prince, nor leader or teacher among people, nobody to save them.... And truly were the living envying the dead."</hi></p>
</text>
