<text id="autogum_bio_doc124" title="Natalie Cressman" shortTile="natalie-cressman" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-01-17" dateModified="2019-10-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natalie_Cressman" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Natalie Cressman</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Natalie Cressman</hi> is an American <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jazz">jazz</ref> trombonist and vocalist.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Cressman was born in San Francisco to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandy_Cressman">Sandy</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeff_Cressman">Jeff Cressman</ref> who are jazz musicians as well. Growing up in the San Francisco Bay Area, she began to play her first gigs in her early teens with various Jazz, Afro-Cuban, and Brazilian Jazz groups. Her influences include <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elis_Regina">Elis Regina</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joni_Mitchell">Joni Mitchell</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Simon">Paul Simon</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbie_Hancock">Herbie Hancock</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weather_Report">Weather Report</ref>. When Natalie turned 18 she moved to New York to study at Manhattan School of Music on scholarship, where she studied with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luis_Bonilla">Luis Bonilla</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garry_Dial">Garry Dial</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laurie_Frink">Laurie Frink</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wycliffe_Gordon">Wycliffe Gordon</ref>. In her first semester, she was asked to join <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phish">Phish</ref> guitarist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trey_Anastasio">Trey Anastasio</ref>'s solo project, and has been touring with TAB ever since. Now based in Brooklyn, she is involved in various projects, including longtime mentor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Apfelbaum">Peter Apfelbaum</ref>'s new project S P A R K L E R. She has released 2 albums in her own right, both self-produced, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unfolding_(album)">Unfolding</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turn_the_Sea">Turn the Sea</ref>, which feature primarily her own compositions. Her original music is a blend of singer/songwriter, jazz, funk, and world music.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Performances</head>
<p>In her junior year of high school, she performed at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monterey_Jazz_Festival">Monterey</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Sea_Jazz_Festival">North Sea Jazz Festivals</ref> with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Next_Generation_Orchestra">Next Generation Orchestra</ref>. In 2008-9, she was selected to perform in several youth honor bands, including the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jazz_Band_of_America">Jazz Band of America</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_All_State_Jazz_Band">California All State Jazz Band</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jazz_Band_Classic">Jazz Band Classic</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grammy_Jazz_Ensemble">Grammy Jazz Ensemble</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ksp-2">[2]</ref> Since moving to New York she has performed with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nichoas_Payton">Nichoas Payton</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Television_Symphony_Orchestra">Television Symphony Orchestra</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Apfelbaum's_New_York_Hieroglyphics_Ensemble">Peter Apfelbaum's New York Hieroglyphics Ensemble</ref>.
In May 2012 she played the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apollo_Theater">Apollo Theater</ref> as a soloist in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wycliffe_Gordon">Wycliffe Gordon</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jazz_A_La_Carte">Jazz A La Carte</ref>, which also featured renowned performers <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savion_Glover">Savion Glover</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maurice_Hines">Maurice Hines</ref>. She founded her own band called the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secret_Garden_(band)">Secret Garden</ref>, and released her first recording <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unfolding_(album)">Unfolding</ref>, a modern jazz album with some world music and folk influences.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> She has also appeared with such groups as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Van_Ghost">Van Ghost</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dumpstaphunk">Dumpstaphunk</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lettuce_(band)">Lettuce</ref>, and has spent several years as an Artist at Large at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bear_Creek_Music_Festival">Bear Creek Music Festival</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Recordings</head>
<p>She recorded her first album with Secret Garden, titled "Unfolding", in October 2011 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_6th_Media_Labs">North 6th Media Labs</ref>, which was released on her family's label, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cressman_Music">Cressman Music</ref> in late 2012. She followed her debut up with a second album, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turn_the_Sea">Turn the Sea</ref>, released on March 11, 2014 under her own name. The sophomore release continues her exploration of cross-pollinating jazz with more modern musical styles, resulting in a sound unique to her. Cressman followed up in 2016 with the release of Etchings in Amber with guitarist Mike Bono. The two traveled the country in October and November 2016 in support of the album. On March 3, 2017, her latest release, Traces, melds a sleek and sensuous electronica-laced sound with a trace or two of dance floor sweat. The new 5-song EP, which also includes Bono on the guitar tracks, can be heard on soundcloud <ref target="https://soundcloud.com/natcressman/sets/the-traces-ep">https://soundcloud.com/natcressman/sets/the-traces-ep</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
</text>
