<text id="autogum_bio_doc679" title="Hubert van Eyck" shortTile="hubert-van-eyck" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2002-03-28" dateModified="2019-10-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hubert_van_Eyck" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hubert van Eyck</head><figure><caption>Woodcut portrait of Hubert van Eyck, by Edme de Boulonois, mid-16th century.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Hubert van Eyck</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Huybrecht van Eyck</hi> (c.1385/90 – 18 September 1426) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Early_Netherlandish">Early Netherlandish</ref> painter and older brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_van_Eyck">Jan van Eyck</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[lower-alpha 1]</ref> as well as Lambert and Margareta, also painters. The absence of any single work that he can clearly be said to have completed continues to make an assessment of his achievement highly uncertain, although for centuries he had the reputation of being an outstanding founding artist of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Early_Netherlandish_painting">Early Netherlandish painting</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vb1-2">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Life and career</head>
<p>He was probably born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maaseik">Maaseik</ref>, in what is now the  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Limburg_(Belgium)">Belgian province of Limburg</ref>, into a family in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gentry">gentry</ref>.</p>
<p>As the name was not a very common one, he is probably the "Magister Hubertus, Pictor" recorded as having been paid in 1409 for panels in the church of Onze Lieve Vrouwe, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tongeren">Tongeren</ref>. He is probably also Master Hubert who had painted a panel bequeathed in 1413 by Jan de Visch van der Capelle to his daughter, a Benedictine nun near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grevelingen">Grevelingen</ref>; however he does not appear in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guild">guild</ref> records, and his heirs did not include any children, so it has been suggested that he may have been in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minor_orders">minor orders</ref>, perhaps attached to what was then the abbey, now the cathedral, of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Bavo_Cathedral">St Bavo at Ghent</ref>, where his <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghent_Altarpiece">Ghent Altarpiece</ref></hi> still remains, settling in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghent">Ghent</ref> by c. 1420.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vb1-2">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Around the time of his settlement, or shortly afterward, he began his only surviving documented work, the <hi rend="italic">Ghent Altarpiece</hi> in St Bavo's. However, the painting was not finished until six years after his death, in 1432, so the degree to which the surviving altarpiece reflects his work, rather than that of Jan who took it over, remains much discussed. An inscription on the frame, which was destroyed in the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beeldenstorm">beeldenstorm</ref></hi> in 1566, stated that Hubert van Eyck "maior quo Nemo reports" (greater than anyone) started the altarpiece, but that Jan van Eyck – calling himself "are Secundus" (second-best in the art) – completed it in 1432.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-burr-3">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Writing in 1933, art historian Bryson Burroughs, who at that time attributed to Hubert the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crucifixion_and_Last_Judgement_diptych">Crucifixion and Last Judgement diptych</ref></hi>, describing him as "the fountainhead of northern painting", suggests he did the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Underdrawing">underdrawing</ref> for the <hi rend="italic">Ghent Altarpiece</hi> with Jan painting in after his brother's death;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-burr-3">[2]</ref> some form of this view remains common among specialists. Modern scientific investigation reveals various changes between the finished work and the lower painted levels and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Underdrawing">underdrawing</ref>.  Today the inscription is often regarded as an overgenerous fraternal tribute.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vb1-2">[1]</ref>  Given the circumstances, the Ghent Altarpiece is a difficult work to use for comparison when assessing other attributions, especially as several other artists from the brothers' workshops probably worked on it as well.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[3]</ref></p>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Three_Marys_at_the_Tomb">The Three Marys at the Tomb</ref></hi>, painted or begun by Hubert, perhaps between 1410 and 1420, and completed by another artist.</caption></figure>
<p>The town <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magistrate">magistrates</ref> of Ghent visited his workshop in 1425; the city had commissioned two designs for a painting from him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vb1-2">[1]</ref> He died on or before 18 September 1426,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vbs-5">[4]</ref>  probably still in his thirties, and was buried in Saint Bavo’s Cathedral, next to his sister Margareta according to the 16th-century writer van Vaernewijck, who says she was also a painter and unmarried. His heirs paid taxes relating to properties in Ghent. A copper inscription recording his date of death was engraved on the tombstone, but is now missing.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vb1-2">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[5]</ref>  According to a tradition from the 16th century, his arm was preserved as a relic in a casket above the portal of Saint Bavo of Ghent.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[6]</ref> Van Vaernewijck also records the local tradition that Jan van Eyck was trained by his brother, though when Jan is first documented in August 1422 he was already a "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_master">master</ref>" and working in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hague">The Hague</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vb1-2">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>The division of surviving works between Hubert, early Jan van Eyck, and other painters has been the subject of great debate among art historians, involving the <hi rend="italic">Ghent Altarpiece</hi>, the many different hands that can be detected in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turin-Milan_Hours">Turin-Milan Hours</ref>, and other pieces. In the 19th and early 20th centuries the inscription on the <hi rend="italic">Ghent Altarpiece</hi> was usually taken at face value, and most unsigned works now given to the early years of his brother Jan were attributed to Hubert. After a period in the mid-20th century when there was a strong tendency to attribute work away from Hubert, he has made something of a comeback in recent decades, but there is still a wide range of opinion among specialists.  He is likely to have begun the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three_Marys">Three Marys</ref> at the Tomb</hi> now in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Museum_Boijmans_Van_Beuningen">Museum Boijmans Van Beuningen</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotterdam">Rotterdam</ref>, but this seems to have been finished by another artist some decades later and has suffered from the restoration.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vbs-5">[4]</ref> Drawings in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albertina,_Vienna">Albertina, Vienna</ref> of the Apostles have been attributed to him and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British_Museum">British Museum</ref> has a drawing copying a lost <hi rend="italic">Capture of Christ</hi> that relates to parts of the <hi rend="italic">Ghent Altarpiece</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vb1-2">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
