<text id="autogum_bio_doc376" title="John Sotherton" shortTile="john-sotherton" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-06-13" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Sotherton" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Sotherton</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">John Sotherton</hi> the younger (1562–1631) was an English judge, member of a prominent parliamentary, judicial and mercantile family of London and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_Anglia">East Anglia</ref>, who became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cursitor_Baron_of_the_Exchequer">Cursitor Baron of the Exchequer</ref> in 1610.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was the son of John Sotherton, who was from 16 June 1579 until his death, on 26 October 1605, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_of_the_Court_of_Exchequer">Baron of the Court of Exchequer</ref>, by his second wife, Maria, daughter of Edward Woton, M.D.,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> who was buried by the side of her husband in the church of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Botolph,_Aldersgate">St. Botolph, Aldersgate</ref> Street, London. The Sotherton family originally came from the village of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sotherton">Sotherton</ref> in Suffolk, and many members of it were mercers in London or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norwich">Norwich</ref>. George Sotherton, master of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Worshipful_Company_of_Merchant_Taylors">Merchant Taylors' Company</ref> in 1589, was M.P. for London 1593–8,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> and Nowell Sotherton (d. 1610), John's uncle, was Cursitor Baron of the Exchequer from July 1606.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Nicholas Sotherton, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheriff_of_Norwich">Sheriff of Norwich</ref> in 1572, was author of a history of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kett's_Rebellion">Robert Kett's Rebellion</ref>, <hi rend="italic">The Commoyson in Norfolk, 1549</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>John matriculated from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christ_Church,_Oxford">Christ Church, Oxford</ref>, on 20 November 1580, graduated B.A. on 22 Jan 1582–3, being in the same year incorporated at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Cambridge">Cambridge</ref>, and proceeded M.A. April 1586. He was admitted in November 1587 a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inner_Temple">Inner Temple</ref>, where he was called to the bar in 1597, and elected a bencher in 1610.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> During this period he married twice, first to Anne (a daughter and heir of the Bray family), and secondly to Elizabeth, daughter of Richard Cook,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> by one of whom<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> he had sons John and Valentine, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armigerous">armigerous</ref> heirs, who both followed him in studying at Christ Church, Oxford,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> and several daughters. In 1600 Sotherton purchased the manor of Wadenhall, in the parish of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waltham,_Kent">Waltham, Kent</ref>, from the crown, which became the inheritance of his son John.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> Valentine became a clergyman, and held the living of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spelsbury">Spelsbury</ref>, Oxfordshire, 1636–41.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></p>
<p>He was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Receiver-General">Receiver-General</ref> for the counties of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bedfordshire">Bedfordshire</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buckinghamshire">Buckinghamshire</ref> in July 1604, and was advanced to the post of Cursitor Baron of the Exchequer on 29 October 1610. In that year he assisted in deliberating the special verdict against John Mackalley for the murder of a Serjeant to the Sheriffs.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> He sat regularly as one of the Commissioners of Gaol Delivery for the City of London, was joined with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Julius_Caesar">Sir Julius Caesar</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_Francis_Bacon">Sir Francis Bacon</ref> and others in a Commission of Ways and Means in August 1612, and at a later date was one of the Assessors of Compositions for Defective Titles, and an Inspector of Nuisances for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middlesex">Middlesex</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref></p>
<p>In later life, in 1622,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> Sotherton took as his last wife Elizabeth Rich (daughter of Richard Rich (d.1598) and Jane Machell, and sister of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nathaniel_Rich_(merchant_adventurer)">Sir Nathaniel Rich</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Wroth_(politician,_17th_century)">Dame Margaret Wroth</ref>), who was then widow of Sir John Morgan of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chilworth,_Surrey">Chilworth, Surrey</ref>, who died in 1621.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref> Sotherton died in 1631,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref> his successor on the bench, James Pagitt, being appointed on 24 October of that year.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref> Dame Elizabeth survived him, but remembered her stepson among her bequests.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref></p>
</text>
