<text id="autogum_bio_doc447" title="John Bullingham" shortTile="john-bullingham" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-10-11" dateModified="2019-10-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Bullingham" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Bullingham</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">John Bullingham</hi> (died 1598) was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Gloucester">Bishop of Gloucester</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_England">Church of England</ref> from 1581.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Bullingham was a native of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloucestershire">Gloucestershire</ref>. He was elected a probationer fellow of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magdalen_College,_Oxford">Magdalen College, Oxford</ref>, in July 1550, being then B.A. In the latter part of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_VI">Edward VI</ref>'s reign he went as a voluntary exile to France, staying at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rouen">Rouen</ref>, to avoid the church reforms in England. On the accession of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_I_of_England">Queen Mary</ref> he returned to England and was restored to his place. He received his M.A. degree on 1 June 1554.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Bullingham was in favour as domestic chaplain to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Gardiner">Stephen Gardiner</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Winchester">Bishop of Winchester</ref>, and rector of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boxwell">Boxwell</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Withington">Withington</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloucestershire">Gloucestershire</ref>. On the accession of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I_of_England">Elizabeth I</ref> he remained Catholic and lost his livings. He was subsequently appointed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edmund_Grindal">Edmund Grindal</ref> to the prebendal stall of Wenlocks-barn in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Paul's_Cathedral">St Paul's Cathedral</ref> on 1 August 1565 and admitted to the degree of B.D. at Oxford under the new reformed regime on 8 July 1566. The next year, on 27 December 1567, he was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeacon_of_Huntingdon">Archdeacon of Huntingdon</ref> by his namesake and probable relation, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Bullingham">Nicholas Bullingham</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Lincoln">Bishop of Lincoln</ref>. He held the post until 1576. He was created D.D. by his university on 12 July 1568 and received from Bishop Bullingham the stall of Louth in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lincoln_Cathedral">Lincoln Cathedral</ref> on 10 September of the same year and still retaining his other preferments was installed canon of Worcester on 13 October 1570. He was incorporated D.D. of Cambridge on 7 July 1575. When Grindal held a visitation in 1576 of his province by commission, Bullingham was one of those appointed to visit the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Hereford">Diocese of Hereford</ref>.</p>
<p>He was raised to the episcopate in 1581, being consecrated on 3 September of that year at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Croydon">Croydon</ref> to the see of Gloucester. He was allowed to hold the recently created <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Bristol">bishopric of Bristol</ref> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In_commendam">in commendam</ref></hi> as well as the prebend of Norton in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hereford_Cathedral">Hereford Cathedral</ref>, to which he was installed on 16 January 1582. He held the see of Bristol until the appointment of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Fletcher_(bishop)">Richard Fletcher</ref>, at whose consecration he assisted on 14 December 1589. The rectory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kilmington,_Wiltshire">Kilmington</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Somerset">Somerset</ref> was given him in compensation for the loss of the second bishopric and his Hereford stall. He served as commissioner for the confirmation of Whitgift's election as archbishop on 27 August 1583 and in 1584 was commissioned by the new primate to visit his own Diocese of Gloucester. When the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/See_of_Oxford">see of Oxford</ref> fell vacant in 1592, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Aylmer_(bishop)">John Aylmer</ref>, then <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_London">Bishop of London</ref>, at his request unsuccessfully endeavoured to obtain it for Bullingham. Bullingham died at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kensington">Kensington</ref> on 20 May 1598 and was buried in his own cathedral. He was one of the targets of attack for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Marprelate">Martin Marprelate</ref>.</p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>A letter relating to his friend <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julins_Palmer">Julins Palmer</ref> is printed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Foxe">John Foxe</ref>'s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acts_and_Monuments">Acts and Monuments</ref></hi>. Palmer had also been a Roman Catholic exile but became a Reformation convert and martyr. The only other work attributed to Bullingham is "a translation of John Venerus's oration in defence of the Sacrament of the Aultare" (1554).</p>
</text>
