<text id="autogum_bio_doc155" title="Peter Dorschel" shortTile="peter-dorschel" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-06-24" dateModified="2019-08-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Dorschel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Peter Dorschel</head><figure><caption>The Holy Loch seen across the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Firth_of_Clyde">Firth of Clyde</ref> from Tower Hill, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gourock">Gourock</ref>, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hunters_Quay">Hunters Quay</ref> on the left, and Strone to the right</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Location of the Holy Loch in Scotland</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Peter Dorschel</hi> was an East German spy convicted in Scotland in June 1967 of offences contrary to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Official_Secrets_Act">Official Secrets Act</ref>, involving the sale of information to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USSR">USSR</ref>.</p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>Peter Dorschel was a ship's cook.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bulletin19670826-1">[1]</ref> Little is known of his background other than that he came from what was then the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_Democratic_Republic">German Democratic Republic</ref> (East Germany) and had visited Britain on occasion prior to 1967 when employed as a seaman. He had worked legally under the English <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Work_permit_(United_Kingdom)">permit system</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670624-2">[2]</ref> and in January 1967 had married Christine, an English model, at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lübeck">Lübeck</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19701023-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Some time prior to May 1967, and probably during his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honeymoon">honeymoon</ref>, he had been approached in his home country by two compatriots who were operating as agents for the USSR. They proposed to provide finances enabling Dorschel to acquire a small hotel in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunoon">Dunoon</ref>, Scotland, by use of which he would be able to obtain information from local US service personnel regarding fleet movements and facilities at their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polaris">Polaris</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuclear_submarine">nuclear submarine</ref> base at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Loch">Holy Loch</ref>. The information would be passed on by Dorschel to the agents. In April, Dorschel rented a house at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hunter's_Quay">Hunter's Quay</ref>. This provided him with a good view of activity at the Polaris base.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670624-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Arrest and trial</head>
<p>Dorschel was living at 10 Webster Grove, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prestwich,_Greater_Manchester">Prestwich</ref>, England, when he was arrested on 26 May 1967 in connection with his activities.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19701023-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670531-4">[4]</ref> Then aged 26, he was accused of inciting another man, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Alexander_MacAffer">William Alexander MacAffer</ref> (sometimes spelled <hi rend="italic">McAffer</hi>), "to obtain documents which might be or were intended to be directly or indirectly useful to an enemy, for a purpose prejudicial to the safety or interests of the State."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670603-5">[5]</ref> MacAffer was a 30-year-old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bookmaker">bookmaker</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670530-6">[6]</ref> who lived at Argyll Street in Dunoon. Another who was involved in the conspiracy was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garry_Lee_Ledbetter">Garry Lee Ledbetter</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670620-7">[7]</ref> a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US_Navy">US Navy</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naval_rating">shipfitter</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dexter,_Missouri">Dexter, Missouri</ref>, US<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bulletin19670826-1">[1]</ref> who was stationed on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USS_Simon_Lake">USS<hi rend="italic">Simon Lake</hi></ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Submarine_tender">submarine tender</ref> serving the Polaris fleet at Holy Loch. Ledbetter supplied two documents to MacAffer, who in turn supplied them to Dorschel.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670624-2">[2]</ref></p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USS_Simon_Lake_(AS-33)">USS<hi rend="italic">Simon Lake</hi></ref> at Kings Bay in 1981</caption></figure><p>
Although arrested and initially charged in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manchester">Manchester</ref>, the case against Dorschel was transferred to Scotland when related arrests were made there.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670603-5">[5]</ref> Dorschel pleaded guilty on 19 June 1967 at Dunoon <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheriff_Court">Sheriff Court</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670620-7">[7]</ref> With <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Fairbairn">Nicholas Fairbairn</ref> acting in his defence at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High_Court_of_Justiciary">High Court of Justiciary</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref>, Dorschel was sentenced on 23 June to seven years' imprisonment.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670624-2">[2]</ref> Having heard the prosecutor describe Dorschel as a probably a "little fish" and amateurish, the sentencing judge recorded that </p><p>This case, I am satisfied, is by no means as serious as some which have happened in recent years [in England]. Nevertheless, it appears that this was only through the efficient work of the security services that your activities were stopped before real tragedies occurred. I agree that you were perhaps... a little fish in this particular sea of trouble. Nevertheless, these charges are always grave and serious...<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670624-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Times">The Times</ref></hi> reported that, despite the seriousness of the charge, the court hearing had been "marked by some moments of levity on the public benches and drolleries from the legal participants". One instance giving rise to this was a statement regarding Dorschel's naivety: he had been asked to supply photographs of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hythe,_Kent">Hythe</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poole">Poole</ref> to his spymasters and had instead sent picture postcards. Fairbairn noted that "If this is how foreign espionage in matters as important as nuclear submarines is conducted, we have little to fear from it."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Alleged accomplices</head>
<p>Dorschel had co-operated from the outset with the investigation and Fairbairn said that he had received no training nor had any particular ideological basis for his activities. At the time of Dorschel's sentencing, the US Navy reported that investigations were still proceeding with regard to Ledbetter.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670624-2">[2]</ref> Later, Ledbetter was charged by the Navy with supplying a training booklet and another unspecified document to a man and a woman. Dorschel gave evidence <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In_camera">in camera</ref></hi> against Ledbetter at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Court_martial">court martial</ref> in August 1967.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670825-9">[9]</ref> MacAffer and his sister, Frances Isabella MacAffer (or Hardless],<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> both attended but refused to supply information.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670825-9">[9]</ref> Ledbetter, who had been subjected to a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polygraph">polygraph</ref> test,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> was found guilty. He was sentenced to six months' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hard_labour">hard labour</ref> and discharged from the navy.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670906-12">[12]</ref></p>
<p>Although charges had been laid against MacAffer, they were dropped in September 1967. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crown_Office">Crown Office</ref>, who were responsible for prosecuting, said that it was unable to provide a reason for this.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670906-12">[12]</ref> MacAffer, whose sister was the girlfriend of Ledbetter, then claimed that he had notified the US and British authorities of Dorschel's initial approach to him and had been trying to trap Dorschel since that time. He also claimed that he had been told there were six East Germans involved in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spy_ring">spy ring</ref>. Official bodies of both countries denied his claims of co-operation.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> MacAffer faced further charges in October 1967, relating to alleged avoidance of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Customs_duty">customs duty</ref> and illegal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Off-course">off-course</ref> bookmaking that had been discovered in May.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref></p>
<head>Later events</head>
<p>Dorschel was released in January 1970 and deported to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West_Germany">West Germany</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19701023-3">[3]</ref> Later in that year, his wife, Christine, who had been aged 21 at the time of the trial and had promised to "stand by" him,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19670624-2">[2]</ref> divorced him on the grounds of cruelty. In granting the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decree_nisi">decree nisi</ref></hi>, the judge chose to overlook her admitted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adultery">adultery</ref>. She said at the time of the divorce that she thought Dorschel was possibly serving in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merchant_navy">merchant navy</ref> of the USSR.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Guardian19701023-3">[3]</ref></p>
</text>
