<text id="autogum_bio_doc053" title="Scorpia (journalist)" shortTile="scorpia-journalist" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-12-08" dateModified="2019-10-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scorpia_%28journalist%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Scorpia (journalist)</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Scorpia</hi> is the pseudonym of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Video_game_journalist">video game journalist</ref> who was active from the early 1980s through the late 1990s.  She wrote for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_Gaming_World">Computer Gaming World</ref></hi>, performing reviews on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Role-playing_video_game">role-playing video games</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adventure_game">adventure games</ref>.  Scorpia was known for harsh criticism of video games she disliked.  She was fired after <hi rend="italic">CGW</hi> was sold to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ziff-Davis">Ziff-Davis</ref> in 1999 and subsequently retired from games journalism.  Her pseudonym is based on a character she created in a role-playing game.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Scorpia became interested in computers after attending a computer expo.  Her initial intention was to become a programmer, and she said she bought her first computer games to learn how to program.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rg-1">[1]</ref>  In November 1982, while working as a data processing consultant, Scorpia co-founded an early gaming-related <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special_Interest_Group">Special Interest Group</ref> on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CompuServe">CompuServe</ref>.  It became the eighth most popular forum on CompuServe, and Scorpia received free access to the subscription service in return for maintaining it.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref>  As a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/System_operator">system operator</ref>, she ran online conferences and hosted games.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> The following year, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_Gaming_World">Computer Gaming World</ref></hi> (<hi rend="italic">CGW</hi>) owner Russell Sipe contacted her on CompuServe and invited her to write for the magazine. Scorpia agreed, though she had never read it. She reviewed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Role-playing_video_game">role-playing video games</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adventure_game">adventure games</ref> there for 16 years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rg-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Scorpia became a prominent reviewer in the industry. In addition to her writing and online presence, she provided hints to players who contacted her through a post office box.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-maher20130407-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-maher20140929-5">[5]</ref> <hi rend="italic">CGW</hi> billed her as "controversial",<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rg-1">[1]</ref> and often published a Scorpia review together with another of the same game by a different reviewer.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-crpgaddict20150614-6">[6]</ref> She became known for harsh criticism of video games she disliked. Scorpia's review of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ultima_VIII:_Pagan">Ultima VIII: Pagan</ref></hi> was highlighted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GameSetWatch">GameSetWatch</ref> as one of the harshest video game reviews ever written.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> Her review of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Might_and_Magic_II:_Gates_to_Another_World">Might and Magic II: Gates to Another World</ref></hi> resulted in an angry response from the game's designer, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jon_Van_Caneghem">Jon Van Caneghem</ref>, who named a monster after Scorpia in his next game.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> While usually a fan of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infocom">Infocom</ref>, she so disliked <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infidel_(video_game)">Infidel</ref></hi> that she never mentioned it in print, although lambasting the game during an online chat with creator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike_Berlyn">Mike Berlyn</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-maher20130407-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">CGW</hi> editor Johnny Wilson described Scorpia as "one of the most refreshing people you could ever meet" and praised her encyclopedic knowledge of games' puzzles. He cited one example where the two clashed, the role-playing game <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darklands_(video_game)">Darklands</ref></hi>. Scorpia wrote a negative review that criticized the game's bugs, and Wilson attached an editorial sidebar that gave a more positive view.  Wilson later acknowledged this was a bad idea, saying that Scorpia's fans correctly criticized him for undercutting her review and overlooking the game's flaws. Because the magazine required a reviewer to finish the game before publishing the review, Wilson said Scorpia favored linearity, resulting in unwarranted criticism of some open-ended works; <hi rend="italic">CGW</hi> thus sometimes did not assign her such games.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-wilson-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>Scorpia was fired after <hi rend="italic">CGW</hi> was sold to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ziff_Davis">Ziff Davis</ref> in 1999.  She said it was intimated to her that the magazine wanted to go in a different direction. She neither looked for further work in games journalism nor received any offers; she attributed her reputation for tough reviews as one possible reason for the latter.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-seven-10">[10]</ref> Scorpia started a subscription webzine after this, but it failed when she could not find enough subscribers.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref>  She subsequently started a free website, where she blogged.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rg-1">[1]</ref> She stopped updating the site in 2009 after saying that she was unable to afford a new computer needed to keep reviewing games.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></p>
<head>Personal life</head>
<p>Her pseudonym comes from role-playing games and is based on her astrological sign of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scorpio_(astrology)">Scorpio</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rg-1">[1]</ref>  She said she was already known as Scorpia because of her work in online communities and found it "more fitting" than her real name for her focus on role-playing games and adventure games.  She values her privacy and cited that as another reason for using a pseudonym.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-seven-10">[10]</ref>  At <hi rend="italic">CGW</hi>, only owner Sipe knew her real name.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-wilson-9">[9]</ref>  Her favorite video game is <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ultima_IV:_Quest_of_the_Avatar">Ultima IV: Quest of the Avatar</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rg-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
