<text id="autogum_bio_doc745" title="Shams al-Din Juvayni" shortTile="shams-aldin-juvayni" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-16" dateModified="2019-06-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shams_al-Din_Juvayni" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Shams al-Din Juvayni</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shams al-Din Juvayni</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_language">Persian</ref>: شمس‌الدین جوینی‎; also spelled <hi rend="bold">Joveyni</hi>) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_people">Persian</ref> statesman and member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juvayni_family">Juvayni family</ref>. He was an influential figure in early <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ilkhanate">Ilkhanate</ref> politics, serving as <hi rend="italic">sahib-i divan</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vizier">vizier</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minister_of_finance">minister of finance</ref>) under four <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ilkhanate">Mongol Ilkhans</ref>−<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hulagu_Khan">Hulagu</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abaqa">Abaqa</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tekuder">Tekuder</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arghun">Arghun Khan</ref>. In 1284, Arghun accused Shams al-Din of having poisoned the Ilkhan Abaqa, who may actually died of the effects of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alcoholism">alcoholism</ref>; Shams al-Din was duly executed and replaced as vizier by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buqa">Buqa</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> A skillful political and military leader, Shams al-Din is also known to have patronized the arts. The musician <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safi_al-Din_al-Urmawi">Safi al-Din al-Urmawi</ref> was one of those he supported.</p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>A native of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joveyn_County">Juvayn</ref> area in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greater_Khorasan">Khorasan</ref>, Shams al-Din belonged to the namesake Juvaynis, a Persian family of officials and scholars, that claimed ancestry from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Fadl_ibn_al-Rabi'">al-Fadl ibn al-Rabi'</ref> (d. 823/4), who had served in high offices under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbasid_Caliphate">Abbasid</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caliph">caliph</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harun_al-Rashid">Harun al-Rashid</ref> (r.786–809).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBiran200971–74-2">[2]</ref> The family had previously worked for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seljuk_Empire">Seljuk</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khwarazmian_dynasty">Khwarazmian</ref> empires before serving the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mongol_Empire">Mongol Empire</ref> and its breakaway state, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ilkhanate">Ilkhanate</ref>. The father of Shams al-Din, Baha al-Din Muhammad, originally an official of the last Khwarazmshah, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jalal_ad-Din_Mingburnu">Jalal ad-Din Mingburnu</ref> (r.1220–1231), began working for the Mongol governor (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darughachi">basqaq</ref></hi>) of Khorasan and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mazandaran_Province">Mazandaran</ref>, Chin Temür, becoming his <hi rend="italic">saheb-i divan</hi> in 1235, a post which he held until his death in 1253/4.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBiran200971–74-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Shams al-Din was also the younger brother of the historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ata-Malik_Juvayni">Ata-Malik Juvayni</ref>, who wrote the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarikh-i_Jahangushay">Tarikh-i Jahangushay</ref></hi> ("History of the World Conqueror"). His family is generally portrayed as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shafi‘i">Shafi‘ites</ref> like its ancestor, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Juwayni">al-Juvayni</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBiran200971–74-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>In 1263, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hulagu_Khan">Hulagu Khan</ref> (r.1256–1265) appointed Shams al-Din as his <hi rend="italic">sahib-i divan</hi>. The reason behind influence rising may have been due to his friendship with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nasir_al-Din_al-Tusi">Nasir al-Din al-Tusi</ref>, the famed scholar and Hulagu's close advisor, and his marriage to the daughter of the Mongol governor of Khorasan, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arghun_Aqa">Arghun Aqa</ref>. Shams al-Din's influence soon increased even further; he governed Tabriz and played a prominent role in rebuilding Iran, which had suffered greatly from the Mongol conquest. He had a bridge constructed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Azerbaijan_(Iran)">Azerbaijan</ref> and a dam near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saveh">Saveh</ref>, rebuilt mosques in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref>, and supported the opening of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hajj">Hajj</ref> passages.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBiran200971–74-2">[2]</ref> Shams al-Din also took part in deciding military conclusions; he gave instructions to Hulagu's son and successor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abaqa">Abaqa</ref> (r.1265–1282) before the battle of Herat in 1270 against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chagatai_Khanate">Chagatai Khanate</ref>, and later in 1277 was the head of an army that participated in Abaqa's expedition into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anatolia">Anatolia</ref>, where he made Abaqa's army spare Muslim villages and towns in Anatolia. He also clashed with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caucasus">Caucasian</ref> tribes on his return to Iran.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBiran200971–74-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Shams al-Din was also closely linked with the local vassal states of the Ilkhanids, such as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurt_dynasty">Kartids</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herat">Herat</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qutlugh-Khanids">Qutlugh-Khanids</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kerman_Province">Kerman</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salghurids">Salghurids</ref> of Fars, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hazaraspids">Hazaraspids</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lorestan_Province">Luristan</ref>. He maintained Ilkhanid bureaucrats in each realm, and had an representative in charge of the rejuvenation of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yazd_Province">Yazd</ref> area. Furthermore, he also increased the influence and authority of his family by giving them posts within the country; his eldest son Baha al-Din Muhammad was appointed governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_Iraq">Persian Iraq</ref>, whilst another son of his, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sharaf_al-Din_Harun_Juvayni">Sharaf al-Din Harun Juvayni</ref>, was appointed governor of Anatolia. Shams al-Din's older brother Ata-Malik Juvayni had already been given the governorship of Iraq in 1259 before the latters rise.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBiran200971–74-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>During his term as <hi rend="italic">sahib-i divan</hi>, Shams al-Din amassed a hefty sum of revenue, mainly in properties, but also through marketable investments in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hormuz,_Iran">Hormuz</ref>, which greatly profited Shams al-Din and his associate, Sunjaq, who served as joint vizier under Abaqa. Shams al-Din's illustrious career resulted in much resentment; in 1277, his former apprentice <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Majd_al-Mulk_Yazdi">Majd al-Mulk Yazdi</ref> accused Shams al-Din and Ata-Malik Juvayni of secretly collaborating with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mamluk_Sultanate_(Cairo)">Mamluk Sultanate of Egypt</ref>, which proved unsuccessful due to the lack of proof. However, three years later, Majd al-Molk made a more successful attempt; he not only once again accused the brothers of collaborating with the Mamluks, but also stealing hefty amount of riches from the treasury.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBiran200971–74-2">[2]</ref> Whilst Shams al-Din avoided punishment with the help of Hulagu's widow, his brother Ata-Malik was arrested, but later released in late 1281 due to interference of Mongol princes and princesses, only to return to jail a few months later due being the target of further accusations. The accusations towards Shams al-Din also made Abaqa appoint Majd al-Mulk as his joint vizier, which considerably reduced Shams al-Din's authority.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBiran200971–74-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>A dynastic struggle followed after Abaqa's death in 1282 between his younger brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tekuder">Tekuder</ref> and son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arghun">Arghun</ref>.</p>
<p>His wife Khoshak was the daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Awak_Zak'arean-Mkhargrdzeli">Awak Zak'arean-Mkhargrdzeli</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amirspasalar">Lord High Constable</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Georgia">Georgia</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gvantsa">Gvantsa</ref>, a noblewoman who went on to become queen of Georgia.</p>
</text>
