<text id="autogum_bio_doc473" title="Francesco Maria Guazzo" shortTile="francesco-maria-guazzo" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2003-07-17" dateModified="2018-11-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francesco_Maria_Guazzo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Francesco Maria Guazzo</head><figure><caption><hi rend="italic">The Obscene Kiss</hi>, an illustration of witches kissing the Devil's anus from Francesco Maria Guazzo's <hi rend="italic">Compendium Maleficarum</hi> (1608).</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Francesco Maria Guazzo</hi>, aka Guaccio, aka Guaccius (1570<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>–16??) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italians">Italian</ref> priest. Is most well known for the writing the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compendium_Maleficarum">Compendium Maleficarum</ref></hi> (Book of Witches).</p>
<p>He was a member of one of the oldest of the Catholic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ambrosians">Ambrosian</ref> orders. These religious brotherhoods had appeared at various times since the 14th Century in and around the city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milan">Milan</ref> and were quite plentiful, but the only one to attain more than simply local importance was the ‘<hi rend="italic">Fratres Sancti Ambrosii ad Nemus</hi>’ sometimes known as 'The Brethren of the Grove'.</p>
<p>Before 1441 there were various monasteries that were canonically recognized under the name ‘Fratres Sancti Ambrosii ad Nemus’ but there was little link between them. However, in 1441 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Eugene_IV">Pope Eugene IV</ref> merged them into one congregation called ‘Congregatio Sancti Ambrosii ad Nemus’ of which Francesco Maria Guazzo was a member under the papacy of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Sixtus_V">Pope Sixtus V</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Paul_V">Pope Paul V</ref>.</p>
<p>Guazzo had firsthand experience of the practice and profession of witchcraft and bewitchment and was widely travelled and highly regarded in the field of possessions and demonology and the cures thereof.</p>
<p>During his life he is credited with performing several exorcisms including to members of several ducal and princely families, notably the bewitched <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardinal_Charles_of_Lorraine">Cardinal Charles of Lorraine</ref> and his relative, Eric, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Verdun">Bishop of Verdun</ref>.</p>
<p>On another occasion Guazzo was called to Düsseldorf in order to exorcise the mad <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_William,_Duke_of_Jülich-Cleves-Berg">John William, Duke of Jülich-Cleves-Berg</ref> (1562–1609). Guazzo first diagnosed possession, but after five months of unsuccessful attempts at spiritual healing and in the summer of 1604, the diagnosis was changed to bewitchment as the cause of the poor Duke’s mental illness. Guazzo had been sent to Düsseldorf by Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_III_of_Lorraine">Charles III of Lorraine</ref> (a family with which he had a long running association, having exorcised the Cardinal, Charles of Lorraine) on behalf of his daughter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonia_of_Lorraine">Antoinette</ref> (1569–1610), Duke Johann Wilhelm’s wife.</p>
<p>It was these direct experiences that inspired Guazzo to write his <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compendium_Maleficarum">Compendium Maleficarum</ref></hi> which was published in 1608 and was widely regarded among his contemporaries as the authoritative manuscript on Witchcraft.  Within his text, Guazzo discusses witches’ pacts with the devil, detailed descriptions of witches’ powers and poisons and also prepared his classification of the demons based on a previous work by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Psellus">Michael Psellus</ref>.</p>
<p>In this work, Guazzo was greatly influenced by Duke Charles III of Lorraine’s leading lawyer and demonologist, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Remy">Nicholas Remy</ref> (Remy produced one of the most important early works on demonology and witchcraft in 1595, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daemonolatreiae_libri_tres">Daemonolatreiae libri tres</ref></hi>, and claimed to have sentenced to death over 900 people during witch trials between 1582–1592).</p>
<head>Major works</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compendium_Maleficarum">Compendium Maleficarum</ref></hi> (1628; new edition London 1929, republished 2004 by Book Tree), limited preview <ref target="https://books.google.com/books?id=QnlvkNsQYIIC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=intitle:Compendium+intitle:Maleficarum&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=0&amp;as_pt=ALLTYPES">online</ref></item></list>
</text>
