<text id="autogum_bio_doc100" title="Chris Rice" shortTile="chris-rice" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-08-19" dateModified="2019-09-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Rice" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Chris Rice</head>For the U.S. Virgin Islands sport shooter, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Rice_(sport_shooter)">Chris Rice (sport shooter)</ref>. For the author, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Rice">Christopher Rice</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Chris Rice</hi> is an American <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Singer">singer</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Songwriter">songwriter</ref> who works in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contemporary_Christian_music">contemporary Christian music</ref>, contemporary folk and adult contemporary genres. He became a recording artist as well in 1996 after signing a contract with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rocketown_Records">Rocketown Records</ref> and releasing his debut album, <hi rend="italic">Deep Enough to Dream</hi>.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<head>Early years</head>
<p>Chris Rice, a native of Clinton, Maryland, grew up as the second of four sons born to bookstore owners. His parents, and other adult mentors, influenced Rice's Christian faith and his early work with youth and college students.</p>
<p>Having taken only three years of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piano">piano</ref> lessons as a child, Rice did not aspire to a career in either music or student work. But frequent invitations to speak and lead music at his church's youth group events led to more such invitations throughout his college years at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Maryland,_College_Park">University of Maryland</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grace_College">Grace College</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winona_Lake,_Indiana">Winona Lake, Indiana</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Union_University">Union University</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jackson,_Tennessee">Jackson, Tennessee</ref>. He holds a bachelor's degree in Psychology and Communication.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> While leading music and coaching high school soccer teams he began writing songs. What began as weekend and summer work with youth and college students soon turned into a full-time career during his twenties and thirties, and prompted Rice to write and perform mainly on the guitar.</p>
<p>For those two decades, Rice spent his time as an itinerant speaker and songwriter/musician, playing for high school and college conferences and camps nationwide. This schedule prepared Chris for his career as a signed recording artist, touring the country with a full band.</p>
<head>Career as a songwriter</head>
<p>Rice's songwriting career began in the mid-1980s, after moving from his Washington, D.C., home to Nashville, Tenn. During that period several of Rice's songs were recorded by other artists, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kathy_Troccoli">Kathy Troccoli</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terri_Gibbs">Terri Gibbs</ref>. Rice's "Welcome to Our World", an original Christmas song since recorded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_W._Smith">Michael W. Smith</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amy_Grant">Amy Grant</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Tesh">John Tesh</ref>, moved Smith to urge his new label, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rocketown_Records">Rocketown Records</ref>, to sign Rice as its first artist in 1996.</p>
<head>Solo artist</head>
<p>With the help of Monroe Jones' production skills, Chris Rice recorded <hi rend="italic">Deep Enough to Dream</hi> for a September 1997 release. <hi rend="italic">Past the Edges</hi> followed a year later. Rice's third album, <hi rend="italic">Smell the Color 9</hi>, was issued in late 2000.</p>
<p>In 2001, Rice released two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piano">piano</ref>-only, instrumental releases, <hi rend="italic">The Living Room Sessions</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Living Room Sessions: Christmas</hi>, recorded on Rice's own living room <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_piano">grand piano</ref>.</p>
<p>His sixth album, <hi rend="italic">Run the Earth... Watch the Sky</hi>, released in March 2003, Chris again joined the production talents of his longtime friend and collaborator Monroe Jones. The album's first single was "The Other Side of the Radio".</p>
<p>These four studio releases (plus the two instrumental releases) fulfilled Rice's contractual commitment to Rocketown and they issued several compilation albums, <hi rend="italic">Short Term Memories</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Snapshots: Live and Fan Favorites</hi>, following his departure in June 2004 and February 2005 respectively.</p>
<head>New record label</head>
<p>Rice signed with independent label Eb+Flo Records, and made a marketing and distribution agreement with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fair_Trade_Services">INO Records</ref> who had distribution through Sony/Columbia removed the limitation of catering  his music to Christian radio formats.</p>
<p>His fifth studio album, <hi rend="italic">Amusing</hi>, released in August 2005. For the first time in his career, Rice released radio singles to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adult_Contemporary">AC</ref> and Light Rock stations around the country, the first single being a light romantic song entitled "When Did You Fall (In Love With Me?)" which reached No.8 on the Pop AC radio format and enjoyed Top Ten status throughout the middle of 2006. A second AC hit, "Lemonade", began climbing the AC chart in 2007.</p>
<p>With his success on the AC radio format, Rice released a side project hearkening back to his roots, a vocal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hymns">hymns</ref> album, <hi rend="italic">Peace Like a River: The Hymns Project</hi>, in November 2006.</p>
<p>Rice released <hi rend="italic">What a Heart Is Beating For</hi> in July 2007, further positioning him as a pop artist. Only 2 of its 13 songs contained overt faith themes.</p>
<head>Other</head>
<p>Since 2007, Rice has branched out in the visual arts, including photography and painting.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> In 2016, he self-published <hi rend="italic">Widen</hi>, a book of poetry.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>In December 2018, Rice and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Ripp">Andrew Ripp</ref> pre-released an album, <hi rend="italic">Songs We Wrote on Tuesdays</hi>, as Ripp+Rice as well as a single "This Ain't No Love Song" from that album.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> The album, a mix of adult contemporary and country music and was officially released on January 4, 2019.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Discography</head>
<head>Studio albums</head>
<head>EPs and other releases</head>
<head>Singles</head>
<head>Awards</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>1998 – Nominated for six Dove Awards, including New Artist of the Year, Male Vocalist of the Year, Songwriter of the Year and Pop/Contemporary Album of the Year<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></item>
<item>1999 – Dove Award winner for Male Vocalist of the Year and for participation in Special Event Album of the Year – <hi rend="italic">Exodus</hi></item>
<item>2000 – Dove Award nominee for Recorded Music Packaging</item>
<item>2002 – <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dove_Award">Dove Award</ref> nominee for Instrumental Album of the Year – <hi rend="italic">Living Room Sessions: Hymns</hi></item></list>
</text>
