<text id="autogum_bio_doc605" title="Rui Faleiro" shortTile="rui-faleiro" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-03-21" dateModified="2019-07-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rui_Faleiro" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rui Faleiro</head><p><hi rend="bold">Rui (Ruy) Faleiro</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Portuguese">[ˈʁuj fɐˈlɐjɾu]</ref>, also known as <hi rend="bold">Ruy de Faleira</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTECameron1974-1">[1]</ref>, was a Portuguese <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmography">cosmographer</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astrology">astrologer</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astronomy">astronomer</ref> who was the principal scientific organizer behind <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinand_Magellan">Ferdinand Magellan</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circumnavigation">circumnavigation</ref> of the world.</p>
<head>Early career</head>
<p>Faleiro was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Covilhã">Covilhã, Portugal</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBergreen200322-2">[2]</ref>, at the end of the fifteenth century. In his youth, he served as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Page_(servant)">page</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleanor_of_Viseu">Queen Eleanor</ref>, consort of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_II_of_Portugal">King John II</ref>, alongside Magellan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTECameron197447-3">[3]</ref> Faleiro began serving <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manuel_I_of_Portugal">Manuel I of Portugal</ref> when he succeeded John II in 1495. In 1516, Faleiro applied for the position of royal astronomer, but was rejected by Manuel.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTECameron197447-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Magellan and Faleiro proposed an expedition to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spice_Islands">Spice Islands</ref> repeatedly to King Manuel, but were rejected each time. Frustrated, the two decided to seek assistance from the Spanish crown instead. In October 1517, Magellan relocated to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seville">Seville</ref>, Spain, and Faleiro joined him in December.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBergreen200323-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Faleiro's brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francisco_Faleiro">Francisco Faleiro</ref>, also an accomplished cosmographer, journeyed to Spain as well, and served as a '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hydrographer">hydrographer</ref> and nautical adviser' to the <hi rend="italic">Casa de Contratación</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTECameron197447-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Magellan expedition</head>
<p>Having been rejected by the Portuguese king, Faleiro and Magellan presented their proposal to the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casa_de_Contratación">Casa de Contratación</ref></hi>, which managed expeditions on behalf of the crown.</p>
<p>Faleiro was certain that south of the "Terras de Vera Cruz" (i.e. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref>), at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/40th_parallel_south">40 degrees latitude</ref>, there was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlantic">Atlantic</ref> passage that led to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pacific_Ocean">South Seas</ref>. The sought-after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maluku_Islands">Spice Islands</ref> would, by Faleiro's calculations, fall on the Spanish side of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Tordesillas">line of Tordesillas</ref>.</p>
<p>On March 22, 1518, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_V,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">King Charles of Spain</ref> approved the expedition<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBergreen200334-5">[5]</ref>. Magellan and Faleiro were named co-captains of the expedition.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBergreen200338-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>Fragmentary sources suggest that Faleiro may have suffered from increasing mental instability as preparations for the expedition proceeded. Sebastian Alvarés, a Portuguese spy reporting to King Manuel, wrote that Faleiro was "like a man deranged in his senses".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBergreen200352-7">[7]</ref> An acquaintance of Faleiro wrote that he "sleeps very little and wanders around almost out of his mind".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBergreen200353-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>On July 26, 1519, King Charles, perhaps in response to Faleiro's condition, issued a royal certificate stating that Faleiro would not sail with the expedition, and would instead stay behind in Seville to prepare for another expedition to follow. The later expedition never took place, and may have been a fiction intended to preserve Faleiro's dignity.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBergreen200353-8">[8]</ref> Other sources state that Faleiro chose to remain behind after performing a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Horoscope">horoscope</ref> reading indicating that the voyage would be fatal for him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>The expedition left Seville without Faleiro on August 10, 1519. The fleet kept Faleiro's state-of-the-art navigational tools, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compass">compasses</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astrolabes">astrolabes</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hourglasses">hourglasses</ref>, and charts. Of the 24 charts taken on the voyage, six were personally created by Faleiro. The rest were created by cosmographer Nuño Garcia (seven under the supervision of Faleiro, and eleven supervised by Magellan). In his duties as the expedition's astronomer and astrologist, Faleiro was replaced by the Spanish cosmographer Andrés de San Martín.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBergreen200354-10">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Later life</head>
<p>After Magellan's fleet set sail, Faleiro returned to Portugal, where he was imprisoned. During his imprisonment he suffered a mental breakdown, but was eventually released. He secretly returned to Seville. The <hi rend="italic">Casa de Contratación</hi> awarded him and his brother separation pay "because they had arrived worn out and penniless".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBergreen2003307-11">[11]</ref> His remaining years were lived in obscurity. </p>
<head>Accomplishments</head>
<p>Faleiro was one of the first to apply the most rigorously scientific method of determining <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latitude">latitude</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Longitude">longitude</ref>.</p>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
