<text id="autogum_bio_doc493" title="Kuchum" shortTile="kuchum" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2004-11-10" dateModified="2019-09-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuchum" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kuchum</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kuchum Khan</hi> (<hi rend="bold">Kuchum Khan of Sibir</hi> - <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tatar_language">Tatar</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Küçüm, Күчүм</hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian_language">Russian</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Кучум</hi>; in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siberian_Tatar_language">Siberian Tatar</ref> <hi rend="italic">Köçöm</hi> is pronounced approximately as /kœtsœm/ - <hi rend="italic">Көцөм</hi>; the name in English comes from the Tatar pronunciation)
(died ca. 1601) was the last <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khan_(title)">khan</ref> (ruled 1563–1598) of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khanate_of_Sibir">Khanate of Sibir</ref>.</p>
<p>Kuchum Khan's attempt to spread Islam and his cross-border raids met with vigorous opposition from the Russian Tsar <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_the_Terrible">Ivan the Terrible</ref> (reigned 1547-1584), who sent a force of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cossacks">Cossacks</ref> to confront him head-on (ca. 1580). Kuchum is particularly noted for the vigorous resistance he offered to the Russian invaders.</p>
<head>Background</head>
<p>Kuchum was the son of prince <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mortaza">Mortaza</ref> from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shayban_dynasty">Shayban dynasty</ref> (Şäyban). In 1554, he contested the throne of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siberia_Khanate">Siberia Khanate</ref> against the incumbents brothers <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yadegar_(khan)">Yadegar</ref> (Yädegär) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bekbulat">Bekbulat</ref>, who were both <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vassal">vassals</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref>. In 1563, Yadegar was defeated and Kuchum assumed the throne. In 1573, Kuchum conducted a raid on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perm">Perm</ref>. It was this and other minor raids which prompted the Tsar of Russia to support a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cossack">Cossack</ref> invasion of Siberia.</p>
<head>War with Russia</head>
<figure><caption>The fall of Qashliq to Yermak, and the flight of Kuchum. A miniature from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kungur_Chronicle">Kungur Chronicle</ref></caption></figure>
Main article: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conquest_of_the_Khanate_of_Sibir">Conquest of the Khanate of Sibir</ref>
<p>In 1582, the Siberia Khanate was attacked by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cossack">Cossack</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ataman">ataman</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yermak">Yermak</ref>, who <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Chuvash_Cape">defeated Kuchum's forces and captured</ref> the capital <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qashliq">Qashliq</ref>. Kuchum retreated into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steppes">steppes</ref>, and over the next few years regrouped his forces. He suddenly attacked Yermak on August 6, 1584 in the dead of night, and killed Yermak and most of his army; regaining control of the now ruined Qashliq. Kuchum attempted to unite the rival factions within the khanate nobility but met with resistance. After an unsuccessful attempt on his life by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qarachi">Qarachi</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sayet_khan">Sayet khan</ref> (Säyet), Kuchum was forced to move his horde to the steppe south of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irtysh">Irtysh</ref> river. There he attempted to establish a new khanate, engaging in war against Russian governors. </p>
<p>In 1590 Kuchum raided the Tatars around Tobolsk who were paying <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yasak">yasak</ref> to the Russians. In 1591 Koltsov caught Kuchum on the Ishym River and captured two of his wives and his son Abdul-Khair who was later given estates in Russia. In 1594 the fort at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tara,_Russia">Tara</ref> was built in part to control Kuchum who was in the area. In 1595 Kuchum's followers were raided on the upper Irtysh. In 1597 Kuchum asked for negotiations and the Tsar and Abdul-Khair wrote from Russia offering estates in Russia in return for surrender. Before September 1598 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrey_Voyeykov">Andrey Voyeykov</ref> caught a large group of his followers at a place called Ub Lake and later caught Kuchum on the Ob River. Kuchum fled, but the Russians killed two of his sons and captured five other sons, eight wives and eight daughters. A Muslim cleric was sent to negotiate. Kuchum replied, describing himself as deaf and blind and without subsistence and said that he had not submitted before and would not submit now. This was his last contact with the Russians.  He is believed to have died c. 1605 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bukhara">Bukhara</ref>. In 1620 his son Ishim-khan married a daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kho_Orluk">Kho Orluk</ref> who was then leading his people from Dzugharia to the Volga.</p>
<p>Kuchum is portrayed in numerous Tatar and Russian songs and legends. His descendants remained in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muscovy">Muscovy</ref>, eventually assuming the title of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sibirsky_(surname)">Sibirsky</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1591, Kuchum's son, Abul Khayir was the first of his dynasty to convert to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christianity">Christianity</ref>. His conversion was followed by the conversion of his entire family who eventually assimilated into the Russian nobility. For instance,
although Abul Khayir's son was known as Vasily Abulgairovich, his grandson's name, Roman Vasilyevich, could no longer be distinguished from a native Russian name. </p>
<p>In 1686, the tsar decreed that the dynasties of the ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imereti">Imeretia</ref> in the Caucasus along with the Tatar princes of Siberia and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kasimov">Kasimov</ref> were to be into the Genealogical Book of the Russian nobility.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Khodarkovsky-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In 1661 a man who was said to be a descendant of Kuchum fought the Russians in Bashkiria. In 1739, during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bashkirs">Bashkir War</ref>, Karasakal was said by some to be a Kuchumid.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
</text>
