<text id="autogum_bio_doc794" title="Emicho I, Count of Nassau-Hadamar" shortTile="emicho--count-nassauhadamar" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-17" dateModified="2019-11-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emicho_I%2C_Count_of_Nassau-Hadamar" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Emicho I, Count of Nassau-Hadamar</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Emicho I, Count of Nassau-Hadamar</hi> (also known as <hi rend="italic">Emich</hi>, first mentioned in 1289, died on 7 June 1334), was  the second son of Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto_I_of_Nassau">Otto I of Nassau</ref> and his wife Agnes (d. 1303), the daughter of Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emich_IV,_Count_of_Leiningen-Landeck">Emich IV</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Leiningen">Leiningen-Landeck</ref>.  Emicho was the founder of the elder line of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Nassau">Nassau-Hadamar</ref>.  He was a cousin of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adolf_of_Germany">Adolf of Germany</ref>.  He and his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_I,_Count_of_Nassau-Siegen">Henry</ref> fought on Adolf's side in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Göllheim">Battle of Göllheim</ref> on 2 July 1298.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Count of Nassau-Hadamar</head>
<p>Emicho I was a son of Otto, the founder of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Nassau#The_Ottonian_Line">Ottonian line</ref> of the House of Nassau.  After Otto died in 1290, his sons fought a length dispute over the inheritance. In 1303, the three remaining sons divided the Ottonian lands.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_I,_Count_of_Nassau-Siegen">Henry</ref> (d. 1343), the eldest brother, received <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nassau-Siegen">Nassau-Siegen</ref>, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ginsburg">Ginsburg</ref> and the Lordship of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westerwald">Westerwald</ref>.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John,_Count_of_Nassau-Dillenburg">John</ref> received <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nassau-Dillenburg">Nassau-Dillenburg</ref>, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herborn_(Hesse)">Herborn</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haiger">Haiger</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beilstein,_Hesse">Beilstein</ref>.  Emicho received <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nassau-Hadamar">Nassau-Hadamar</ref>, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hadamar">Hadamar</ref> itself, the Esterau, the Nassau share of the Lordship of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Driedorf">Driedorf</ref> and the justice over Ellar, the Ottonian share of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dausenau">Dausenau</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bad_Ems">Ems</ref> and some dispersed possessions.  As recently as 1290, the Lords of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greifenstein">Greifenstein</ref>, who were co-owners of Driedorf, had forced Henry and Emicho to demolish two of their castles in Driedorf.  On the other hand, a treaty closed in Wetzlar promised an end to the Greinfenstein's resistance to the Nassau expansion in the eastern part of the Westerwald.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref>  In 1316, Emicho finally managed to purchase the Greifenstein share of Driedorf for 250 marks.</p>
<head>Properties in Franconia</head>
<p>In 1299, Emicho acquire considerable properties in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg">Nuremberg</ref> area, when King Albert I of Saxony mortgaged <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kammerstein_Castle">Kammerstein Castle</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schwabach">Schwabach</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Altdorf_bei_Nürnberg">Altdorf</ref>, Kornburg Castle and the town of Kornburg to Emicho and his wife Anna, who was the daughter of Burgrave <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_III,_Burgrave_of_Nuremberg">Frederick III</ref> of Nuremberg<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Hadamar</head>
<figure><caption>South wing of Hadamar Castle</caption></figure>
<p>On 18 December 1320 Emicho purchased a model farm from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cistercian">Cistercian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eberbach_Abbey">Eberbach Abbey</ref>.  This farm was located on the left bank of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elbbach_(Lahn)">Elbbach</ref>, opposite <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hadamar">Hadamar</ref>.  The transaction includes the St. Giles church in Hadamar; the abbey retained various other properties in Niederhadamar, Faulbach and Niederzeuzheim.  Emich expanded the farm to a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Water_castle">water castle</ref> named <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hadamar_Castle">Hadamar Castle</ref>, and built a new farm to the south of the castle.  He moved his residence to Hadamar Castle.  In 1324, Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_IV,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Louis IV</ref> granted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City_rights">city rights</ref>, modeled on Frankfurt, to Hadamar and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bad_Ems">Ems</ref>.  This allowed Emicho to fortify Hadamar with a city wall and a moat surrounding both the town and his castle.</p>
<p>The move to Hadamar was probably intended to make it easier to secure his interests in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Dietz">County of Dietz</ref> and to continue purchasing property and rights from the House of Dietz, which was continually in financial difficulties.  From 1317, Emicho acted as guardian of Count Gottfried V of Dietz (1303–1348), whose bad financial management had caused the decline of his county.  In 1324, Emicho negotiated with Count Gottfried V of Dietz about the intended marriage of Emicho's daughter Jutta with Gottfried's son Gerhard VI (1317–1343).  Emicho demanded extended guardianship rights over the County of Dietz, which was already owed him a considerable amount of money.  When Gottfried reached adulthood in 1332 and Emicho's guardianship ended, Gottfried transferred his rights over Hadamar and the village of Dehrn to Emicho.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref>  On 28 March 1337, Gottfried of Dietz mortgaged the district of Ellar, which he had acquired this district only four years earlier from the Lords of Merenberg, for 1450 Limburgish marks to Emicho's son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John,_Count_of_Hadamar">John</ref>.</p>
<p>On 4 April 1334, only two months before his death, Emicho transferred the Court and Castle of Hadamar to Archbishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baldwin_of_Luxembourg">Baldwin</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishopric_of_Trier">Trier</ref>, who gave it back to him as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fief">fief</ref>.</p>
<head>Mining rights</head>
<p>On 26 February 1298, King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adolph_of_Germany">Adolph of Germany</ref> mortgaged the rights to the Ratzenscheid mine near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wilnsdorf">Wilnsdorf</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siegerland">Siegerland</ref> area and the other silver mines in the Nassau territory to his cousins Henry and Emicho for 1000 marks worth of pennies from Cologne<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>John's inheritance</head>
<p>Emicho's younger brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John,_Count_of_Nassau-Dillenburg">John</ref> was captain in the army from Nassau and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Mainz">Mainz</ref> that fought in the decisive Battle of Wetzlar that ended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dernbacher_Feud">Dernbacher Feud</ref> on 10 August 1328.  John fell in that battle.  Emicho refrained from his share in the inheritance, in favour of his elder brother Henry.</p>
<head>Marriage and issue</head>
<p>Before 1297, Emich married Anna (d. c.1357), the daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burgrave">Burgrave</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_III,_Burgrave_of_Nuremberg">Frederick III</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg">Nuremberg</ref> and his second wife Helen, the daughter of Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_I,_Duke_of_Saxony">Albert I</ref> of Saxony.  They had at least eight children:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Anna (died probably before 1329), married before 1332 to Count Kuno I of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Counts_of_Falkenstein_(Rhineland-Palatinate)">Falkenstein</ref></item>
<item>Jutta (d. after 1359), married before 1324 to Count Gerhard VI of Diez (1317–1343)</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John,_Count_of_Nassau-Hadamar">John</ref> (d. before 20 January 1365), Count of Nassau-Hadamar from 1334 to 1365</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emicho_II,_Count_of_Nassau-Hadamar">Emicho II</ref> (d. 1359), from 1328 to 1336 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_(priest)">canon</ref> in Mainz, from 1337 to 1359 co-ruler of Nassau-Hadamar</item>
<item>Agnes, a nun in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Altenberg_Abbey,_Solms">Altenberg Abbey</ref> in Wetzlar</item>
<item>Helen, also a nun in Altenberg Abbey</item>
<item>Margaret, married before 1349 to a Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Counts_of_Hohenberg_(Swabia)">Hohenberg</ref></item>
<item>Margaretha (d. 1343), a nun in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poor_Clares">Poor Clares</ref> nunnery in Nuremberg</item></list>
<p>Emicho died on 7 June 1334.  His widow reached a compromise with her son John in 1336, in which she received the imperial <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kammerstein_Castle">Kammerstein Castle</ref> as her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wittum">jointure</ref>, plus several manors in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franconia">Franconia</ref>.  She would also receive <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Income_in_kind">income in kind</ref> from John, from his possessions in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laurenburg">Laurenburg</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dausenau">Dausenau</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hadamar">Hadamar</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nentershausen,_Rhineland-Palatinate">Nentershausen</ref> and the bailiwick of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weidenhahn">Weidenhahn</ref> and from farms and land in Hadamar (the manors Schnepfenhaus and Rödchen), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niederzeuzheim">Zeuzheim</ref> and Heftrich.  She resided at Hadamar castle until 1349, then moved to Kammerstein Castle, where she died between 1355 and 1357.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
