<text id="autogum_bio_doc486" title="Stefano Rossetto" shortTile="stefano-rossetto" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-05-14" dateModified="2017-06-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefano_Rossetto" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Stefano Rossetto</head><p><hi rend="bold">Stefano Rossetto</hi> (also <hi rend="bold">Rossetti</hi>) (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floruit">fl.</ref> 1560–1580) was an Italian composer of the late <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renaissance_music">Renaissance</ref>, born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nice">Nice</ref>, who worked mainly in Florence for the powerful <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medici">Medici</ref> family, and in Munich.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>His life has not yet been thoroughly studied. The earliest information available shows that he may have lived and worked on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chios">Chios</ref>, an island in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aegean_Sea">Aegean</ref>, in the service of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genoa">Genoese</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giustiniani">Giustiniani</ref> family; the connection can be made from the dedication to one of his 1560 books of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madrigal_(music)">madrigals</ref>.  In 1560 he assisted at the wedding of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emmanuel_Philibert_of_Savoy">Emmanuel Philibert of Savoy</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marguerite_of_Valois">Marguerite of Valois</ref>, which took place in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nice">Nice</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Haar,_Grove_online-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In 1566 at the latest he went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florence">Florence</ref>, where he served <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinando_I_de'_Medici">Ferdinando I de' Medici</ref> as a composer, alongside <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alessandro_Striggio">Alessandro Striggio</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francesco_Corteccia">Francesco Corteccia</ref>, whose career by then had begun to wane. By 1579 he was in the employ of either <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_V,_Duke_of_Bavaria">Albrecht V</ref>, or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_V,_Duke_of_Bavaria">William V</ref> (Albrecht died in 1579). The <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intermedio">intermedio</ref></hi> performed in Florence in 1583 alongside <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fedini">Fedini</ref>'s play <hi rend="italic">Le due Persile</hi> may have been his work. Connections between the Medici and Bavarian courts were close through the period, and composers often passed between them. Nothing certain is yet known of Rossetto's career after 1580.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Haar,_Grove_online-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Music</head>
<p>All of his surviving music is vocal, and includes madrigals and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motet">motets</ref>, some of which were probably intended for performance as <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intermedio">intermedii</ref>,</hi> musical interludes between acts of plays.</p>
<p>Along with the other Medici composers, taking part in a trend of the time, he wrote gigantic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polychoral">polychoral</ref> compositions. One of the largest polychoral works ever composed, at least prior to modern times, was his huge 50-voice motet <hi rend="italic">Consolamini popule meus</hi>. The date of the composition is unknown, but the manuscript is at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayerische_Staatsbibliothek">Bayerische Staatsbibliothek</ref> in Munich, suggesting he wrote it while in the service of the Bavarian court. Only a handful of larger compositions are known: Alessandro Striggio's colossal 40 and 60 voice <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missa_sopra_Ecco_sì_beato_giorno">Missa sopra Ecco sì beato giorno</ref></hi>, and the 17th century 53-voice <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missa_Salisburgensis_à_53_voci">Missa Salisburgensis</ref></hi> attributed to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heinrich_Ignaz_Biber">Heinrich Ignaz Biber</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Haar,_Grove_online-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Rossetto also composed three books of madrigals, for four, five, and six voices, respectively (all published in Venice in 1560 and 1566), and an ambitious setting of the <hi rend="italic">Lamento d'Olimpia</hi>, in seventeen parts, for from four to ten voices, which he published in Venice in 1567. (Florence, for all its opulence, lacked publishing houses, and most of the Medici composers published their works in Venice, a city with a long publishing history.) In addition to his secular music, he published a book of motets in Nuremberg in 1573, <hi rend="italic">Novae quaedam sacrae cantiones, quas vulgo motetas vocant</hi>, for five and six voices.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Haar,_Grove_online-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In his madrigals he uses <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chromaticism">chromaticism</ref> creatively, and he liked to write both madrigals and motets in groups, as did the other Medici composers (such as Corteccia and Striggio). Much of his music is intended to be accompanied by instruments, another characteristic of Florentine <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyphony">polyphony</ref> of the period.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Haar,_Grove_online-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>References and further reading</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Haar">James Haar</ref>: "Stefano Rossetto", Grove Music Online, ed. L. Macy (Accessed May 14, 2007), <ref target="http://www.grovemusic.com">(subscription access)</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gustave_Reese">Gustave Reese</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Music in the Renaissance</hi>.  New York, W.W. Norton &amp; Co., 1954.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/0-393-09530-4">0-393-09530-4</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Davitt_Moroney">Davitt Moroney</ref>, "Alessandro Striggio's Mass in Forty and Sixty Parts".  <hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Musicological Society,</hi> Vol. 60 No. 1., pp.1–69.  Spring 2007.  ISSN 0003-0139</item>
<item>Stefano Rossetti, <hi rend="italic">"Il lamento di Olimpia" and Other Madrigals from Four to Ten Voices</hi>, ed. and reconstructed by James Chater. Madison, Wisc.: A-R Publications (forthcoming)</item></list>
</text>
