<text id="autogum_bio_doc777" title="Albert of Schwarzburg" shortTile="albert-schwarzburg" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-08-27" dateModified="2019-03-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_of_Schwarzburg" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Albert of Schwarzburg</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Albert of Schwarzburg</hi> (died 15 March 1327), in contemporary sources also <hi rend="bold">Albertus Alamanus</hi> ("Albert the German") or <hi rend="bold">Albertus de Nigro Castro</hi>, was a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saxony">Saxon</ref>–<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thuringia">Thuringian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Schwarzburg">House of Schwarzburg</ref> who became a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knights_Hospitaller">Knights Hospitaller</ref>, rising to be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marshal">marshal</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_preceptor">grand preceptor</ref> of the Order, and fighting with success against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anatolian_beyliks">Turks</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBurgtorf2008466–469-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Albert was the third son of Count Günter V (IX) of Schwarzenburg (died 1292/3) and his first wife, Irmgard. The date of his birth is unknown and can only be approximately placed between his parents' marriage in 1267, and the second marriage of Günter V in 1283.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBurgtorf2008466–467-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Albert appears for the first time in 1306, as witness in a charter at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Limassol">Limassol</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyprus">Cyprus</ref>. He was already a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marshal">marshal</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knights_Hospitaller">Knights Hospitaller</ref>, then based in Cyprus.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBurgtorf2008467-3">[3]</ref> He was a particular favourite and protégé of the then-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Master_of_the_Knights_Hospitaller">Grand Master of the Knights Hospitaller</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foulques_de_Villaret">Foulques de Villaret</ref> (1305–1319), who promoted him steadily to higher offices. Thus in 1307, Villaret made Albert the Order's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Preceptor">preceptor</ref> in Cyprus, and allowed Albert to pay only half the stipulated annual dues ("responsions") to the Order. This act, a sign of Villaret's increasingly authoritarian behaviour and corruption, outraged many of the other leading members of the Order, and contributed to the discontent with Villaret's leadership, culminating in his violent deposition in 1317.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBurgtorf2008428,_467-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELuttrell1975288-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>In 1310, as the Order's highest-ranking representative on Cyprus, Albert played a crucial role in securing the restoration of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_II_of_Cyprus">Henry II</ref> following the death of Henry's brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amalric,_Prince_of_Tyre">Amalric</ref>, who had deposed and exiled the king in 1307. The Hospitallers were among Henry's staunchest supporters, and in July, Albert led a contingent of knights to the capital <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicosia">Nicosia</ref> to secure it in preparation for Henry's return. Henry, still in exile in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenian_Cilicia">Armenian Cilicia</ref>, named Fulk of Villaret as one of his lieutenants in Cyprus (along with the nobleman Aygue of Bethsan), but Villaret, unable to come to Cyprus in person due to the ongoing conquest of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhodes">Rhodes</ref>, gave the post to Albert. In this capacity, Albert served Henry on his return in August 1310, and helped him to secure his rule.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBurgtorf2008161–165,_467-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>In October 1312, Albert was appointed grand preceptor and the Order's representative to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_See">Holy See</ref> and the courts of Western Europe, where he travelled as far as England.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBurgtorf2008446,_467–468-7">[7]</ref> In his letter of accreditation, Fulk of Villaret fulsomely praised Albert's "discretion, honesty, loyalty, good administrative skills, diligence, and hard work". Among his major tasks in this post was the absorption of the property of the recently dissolved <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knights_Templar">Knights Templar</ref>, which had been transferred to the Hospitallers in May 1312.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBurgtorf2008446-8">[8]</ref> By 1315, Albert was back in Cyprus (he may be the grand preceptor who survived from a shipwreck early in the year) as preceptor of the island, a post he kept until his resignation in 1317, when the Pope demanded that the responsions for Cyprus be once again paid in full.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBurgtorf2008468-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>For the next three years, Albert was active in campaigns against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anatolian_beyliks">Turkish</ref> raiders around the Order's new base at Rhodes. In 1318 he defeated a Turkish raid, while in the next year, with assistance from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martino_Zaccaria">Martino Zaccaria</ref>, he scored a major victory in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Chios_(1319)">sea battle</ref> off <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chios">Chios</ref> on 23 July and recovered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leros">Leros</ref>, whose Greek inhabitants had risen in revolt. Finally, in 1320 he turned back an attempted Turkish invasion of Rhodes with great loss.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBurgtorf2008468-9">[9]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELuttrell1975288–289-10">[10]</ref> In 1319, the Pope also granted Albert half of the preceptory of Cyprus (the other half going to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maurice_of_Pagnac">Maurice of Pagnac</ref>) for ten years, as well as the island of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kos">Kos</ref>, in case of its recovery from the Turks.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBurgtorf2008468-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>Between 1323 and 1325, Albert travelled in central Europe, first as a visitor to the Order's lands in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bohemia">Bohemia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denmark">Denmark</ref>, and then in several missions as envoy on behalf of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Roman_Emperor">Holy Roman Emperor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_the_Bavarian">Louis the Bavarian</ref> to the Papal court in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avignon">Avignon</ref>. From 1324, Albert also served as the Order's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prior">prior</ref> in Germany. He died on 15 March 1327 and was buried at the priory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Würzburg">Würzburg</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBurgtorf2008468–469-11">[11]</ref></p>
</text>
