<text id="autogum_bio_doc687" title="Walter Froucester" shortTile="walter-froucester" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-07-02" dateModified="2019-08-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Froucester" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Walter Froucester</head><p><hi rend="bold">Walter Froucester</hi> (died 1412), was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbot">abbot</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Peter's_Abbey,_Gloucester">St. Peter's</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloucester">Gloucester</ref>.</p>
<p>Froucester had previously officiated as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chamberlain_(office)">chamberlain</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monastery">monastery</ref>. On the death of John Boyfield in January 1382, Froucester was elected his successor, being the twentieth abbot. Boyfield's rule had not been successful; he was weak and was in continual trouble with rival ecclesiastics, who, to the disadvantage of his monastery, generally got the better of him. Froucester, on assuming the direction, applied himself to the improvement of the brotherhood's position with marked success, taking and keeping the upper hand over all rivals, and yet without giving offence. By the prudence and economy of his domestic administration he succeeded in wiping off the greater part of the vast debt with which he found the monastery encumbered. From his private purse he supplied the church with ornaments of all kinds, books, vestments, and silver plate.</p>
<p>He is best known for having brought to completion at great expense the beautiful <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloisters">cloisters</ref>, the building of which had been begun in Horton's (abbot 1351–77) time, and left unfinished for several years. With the view of securing for his monastery full title to some of its possessions he despatched to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rome">Rome</ref> one of the brotherhood, William Bryt by name, who, after a stay of some years, succeeded in getting appropriated to the monastery the churches of Holy Trinity and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Mary_de_Lode_Church">St. Mary de Lode</ref>, Gloucester, and that of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chipping_Norton">Chipping Norton</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxfordshire">Oxfordshire</ref>. Froucester also obtained from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Urban_VI">Pope Urban</ref>, through the influence of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_of_Woodstock,_1st_Duke_of_Gloucester">Duke of Gloucester</ref>, the privileges of wearing the pontifical <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitre">mitre</ref>, ring, sandals, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dalmatic">dalmatic</ref>, which his predecessor had requested in vain. The occasion chosen by Froucester for his investment with these ornaments was 10 April 1390, the day on which the remains of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kyneburga,_Kyneswide_and_Tibba">St. Kyneburgh the Virgin</ref> were translated to St. Peter's, the ceremony being celebrated by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Worcester">Bishop of Worcester</ref> and Froucester, and a number of ecclesiastics, in the presence of the Duke of Gloucester and many noblemen and ladies. He also obtained from the pope a dispensation allowing the brotherhood of St. Peter's to eat flesh from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Septuagesima">Septuagesima</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quinquagesima">Quinquagesima</ref> inclusive. By Froucester's orders the registers of the monastery were compiled afresh, and the history of St. Peter's was probably re-edited at the same time. It has sometimes been supposed, but unwarrantably, that this history, early copies of which exist in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen's_College,_Oxford">Queen's College Library</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxford">Oxford</ref>, and among the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cotton_library">Cottonian MSS.</ref>, was written by Froucester, because the chronicle closes during his abbacy; internal evidence shows that it was compiled from time to time. Froucester died in 1412, and was buried beneath an arch in the southwest portion of the choir of St. Peter's. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Atkyns_(topographer)">Sir Robert Atkyns</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> calls him Trowcester.</p>
</text>
