<text id="autogum_bio_doc260" title="Peter the Wild Boy" shortTile="peter-wild-boy" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-10-10" dateModified="2019-10-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_the_Wild_Boy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Peter the Wild Boy</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Peter the Wild Boy</hi> (born <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1713; died 22 February 1785) was a boy from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanover">Hanover</ref> in northern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref> who was found in 1725 living wild in the woods near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamelin">Hamelin</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electorate_of_Hanover">Electorate of Hanover</ref>), the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pied_Piper_of_Hamelin">Pied Piper</ref> legend. The boy, of unknown parentage, had been living an entirely <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feral_child">feral existence</ref> for an unknown length of time, surviving by eating forest <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flora_(plants)">flora</ref>; he walked on all fours, exhibited uncivilized behaviour and could not be taught to speak a language. He is now believed to have suffered from the very rare genetic disorder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pitt-Hopkins_Syndrome">Pitt-Hopkins Syndrome</ref>.</p>
<p>Peter was found in the Hertswold Forest by a party of hunters led by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_I_of_Great_Britain">George I</ref> while on a visit to his Hanover homeland and brought to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Great_Britain">Great Britain</ref> in 1726 by order of his daughter-in-law <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caroline_of_Ansbach">Caroline of Ansbach</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Princess_of_Wales">Princess of Wales</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Life in London</head>
<figure><caption>King George I</caption></figure>
<p>After Peter's transportation to Britain, curiosity and speculation concerning Peter was excited in London. The craze was the subject of a biting satire by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonathan_Swift">Jonathan Swift</ref>, and of another entitled <hi rend="italic">The Most Wonderful Wonder that ever appeared to the Wonder of the British Nation</hi>, which has been attributed to Swift and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Arbuthnot">John Arbuthnot</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Defoe">Daniel Defoe</ref> also wrote on the subject in his pamphlet <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mere_Nature_Delineated">Mere Nature Delineated</ref></hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Burnett,_Lord_Monboddo">James Burnett, Lord Monboddo</ref>, in his <hi rend="italic">Origin and Progress of Language</hi> presents Peter as an illustration of his theory of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolution">evolution</ref> of the human species.</p>
<p>Caroline, Princess of Wales took an interest in Peter's welfare, and in 1726, after the initial public curiosity began to subside, she arranged for Dr Arbuthnot to oversee his education. All efforts to teach him to speak, read or write failed.</p>
<p>The interior designer and painter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Kent">William Kent</ref> included a depiction of Peter in a large painting of King George I’s court that today hangs on the east wall of the King’s Staircase at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kensington_Palace">Kensington Palace</ref> in London. Peter is shown wearing a green coat and holding oak leaves and acorns in his right hand.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-kensington-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Life in Northchurch</head>
<figure><caption>St Mary's Church, Northchurch, Hertfordshire</caption></figure>
<p>After he was discharged from the supervision of Dr Arbuthnot, he was entrusted to the care of Mrs. Titchbourn, one of the Queen's bedchamber women, with a handsome pension annexed to the charge. Mrs. Titchbourn usually spent a few weeks every summer at the house of Mr. James Fenn, a yeoman farmer, at Axter's End, in the parish of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northchurch">Northchurch</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hertfordshire">Hertfordshire</ref>. Peter was left there in the care of Mr. Fenn, who was allowed £35 a year for his support and maintenance. After the death of Mr. Fenn, Peter was transferred to the care of James's brother, Thomas, at another farmhouse, called Broadway, where he lived with the several successive tenants of that farm, and with the same government pension, to the time of his death.</p>
<p>In the late summer of 1751, Peter went missing from Broadway Farm and could not be traced. Advertisements were placed in newspapers offering a reward for his safe return. On 22 October 1751, a fire broke out in the parish of St Andrew's in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norwich">Norwich</ref>. As the fire spread, the local gaol became engulfed in smoke and flame. The frightened inmates were hastily released and one aroused considerable curiosity on account of his remarkable appearance, excessively hirsute and strong, and the nature of the sounds he made, which led some to describe him as an orangutan. Some days later, he was identified as Peter the Wild Boy, possibly through a description of him in the  <hi rend="italic">London Evening Post</hi>. He was returned to Thomas Fenn's farm, and had a special leather collar with his name and address made for him to wear in future, should he ever stray again.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Who_was_Peter_the_Wild_Boy-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Peter lived to an estimated 70 years of age. He was visited in 1782 by the Scottish philosopher and judge James Burnett and was said to have a healthy complexion with a full white beard and apparently understood what was said to him but was himself only capable of saying the words "Peter" and "King George" and humming a few songs. There is a portrait of the "Wild Boy", depicting a handsome old man with a white beard, in Caulfield's <hi rend="italic">Portraits of Remarkable Persons</hi>.</p>
<head>Death and burial</head>
<figure><caption>Gravestone of Peter the Wild Boy at St Mary's Church, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northchurch">Northchurch</ref>, Hertfordshire.</caption></figure>
<p>Peter died 22 February 1785 and is buried in Northchurch. His grave can still be seen in the churchyard of St Mary's Church, Northchurch, directly outside the main door to the church.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Who_was_Peter_the_Wild_Boy-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>On 20 February 2013, it was announced by the Department for Culture, Media and Sport that the grave was to be given <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grade_II_listed">Grade II</ref> listing on the advice of English Heritage.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>In 2007, a blue heritage plaque was placed at the Wild Man pub in Bedford Street, near St Andrew's in Norwich, commemorating Peter and his association with the district.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Modern assessment</head>
<p>In 2011, the condition that afflicted Peter the Wild Boy was suspected to be the chromosomal disorder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pitt–Hopkins_syndrome">Pitt–Hopkins syndrome</ref>, a condition identified only in 1978, nearly 200 years after Peter's death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> Various physical attributes of Peter's which are evident in the Kensington Palace portrait have been matched to the condition, such as his curvy "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cupid's_bow">Cupid's bow</ref>" lips, his short stature, his coarse, curly hair, drooping eyelids and thick lips.</p>
<p>An item on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC_Radio_4">BBC Radio 4</ref> programme <hi rend="italic">Making History</hi> broadcast in March 2011 examined the history of Peter the Wild Boy, tracing his life in Northchurch and later in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berkhamsted">Berkhamsted</ref>, where a leather and brass collar designed to identify Peter in case he should wander away from the village and inscribed "Peter the Wild Man" is preserved at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berkhamsted_School">Berkhamsted School</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Who_was_Peter_the_Wild_Boy-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-radio4-9">[9]</ref></p>
</text>
