<text id="autogum_bio_doc753" title="Malise III, Earl of Strathearn" shortTile="malise-iii-earl-strathearn" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-12-11" dateModified="2019-10-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malise_III%2C_Earl_of_Strathearn" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Malise III, Earl of Strathearn</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Malise III of Strathearn</hi> (Gaelic: <hi rend="italic">Maol Íosa</hi>; c. 1257–1312) was a Scottish nobleman, the ruler of the region of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strathearn">Strathearn</ref>.</p>
<p>He was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malise_II,_Earl_of_Strathearn">Malise II</ref> and his second wife Matilda, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilbert,_Earl_of_Orkney">Gilbert, Earl of Orkney and Caithness</ref>. He succeeded his father on the latter's death in 1271, though for some reason he does not refer to himself as Earl until 1283, perhaps because he had not been formally infeft in the earldom.</p>
<p>Malise helped to keep the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Scotland">Kingdom of Scotland</ref> stable after the death of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_III_of_Scotland">King Alexander</ref>, and in an example of his behaviour, he is recorded as levying the tenants of the land belonging to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inchaffray_Abbey">Inchaffray Abbey</ref> to help preserve the peace. In 1284 he had joined with other Scottish noblemen who acknowledged <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret,_Maid_of_Norway">Margaret, Maid of Norway</ref> as the heir to Alexander.</p>
<p>In the interregnum following Margaret's death, Malise took a prominent part in state affairs, and was involved in most of the political events of the time. Perhaps because of his marriage into the House of Comyn, he took the side of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Balliol">John Balliol</ref> in his competition for the throne with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_the_Bruce">Robert Bruce</ref>, and accompanied John at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Dunbar_(1296)">Battle of Dunbar</ref> in 1296. Later he swore fealty to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_I_of_England">Edward I of England</ref>, and two of his sons were taken as hostages by that king, to ensure their father's good behaviour.</p>
<p>In 1297 he took the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donnchadh_IV,_Earl_of_Fife">Earl of Fife</ref>'s uncle as a prisoner for King Edward, along with his two sons. A close friend of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_II_of_England">Prince of Wales</ref> (later King Edward II), he was invested in 1305 as Lieutenant of the Warden north of the Forth.</p>
<p>In 1306 he was ordered to take the sons of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Stewart,_5th_High_Steward_of_Scotland">Steward of Scotland</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Strathbogie,_Earl_of_Atholl">Earl of Atholl</ref> as hostages, but before he could complete this task, he was imprisoned in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rochester_Castle">Rochester Castle</ref> because of his alleged surrender to King Robert Bruce. According to Malise, King Robert and the Earl of Atholl had marched into Strathearn and deceived and coerced him into paying Robert homage. Notwithstanding this explanation, he remained imprisoned. On petition from the Earl's wife and sons, King Edward ordered an inquiry to be made, but nothing came of this. After having been transferred to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York">York</ref> in 1307, he was finally acquitted and set free in 1310.</p>
<p>Malise was present on the English side when King Robert stormed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perth_Castle">Perth Castle</ref> in 1312. He died later the same year, and was entombed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inchaffray_Abbey">Inchaffray Abbey</ref>, to the right of the high altar.</p>
<head>Marriage and issue</head>
<p>The Earl married a lady named Agnes, likely the second daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Comyn,_Earl_of_Buchan">Alexander Comyn, Earl of Buchan</ref>. The Countess Agnes would later be imprisoned for life for conspiring against King Robert with her nephew <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_II_de_Soules">William Soules</ref>. Malise and Agnes had three sons and a daughter:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malise_IV,_Earl_of_Strathearn">Malise IV</ref>, succeeded as Earl</item>
<item>Gilbert, went with King Edward to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_expedition_to_Flanders_(1297–98)">Flanders in 1297</ref>, and may have died or been killed there</item>
<item>Robert, is recorded as having been imprisoned in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tower_of_London">Tower of London</ref> with other Scottish youths in 1297. Nothing further is known of him</item>
<item>Matilda, married Robert, son of Ralph de Toeni</item></list>
</text>
