<text id="autogum_bio_doc790" title="John Tarchaneiotes" shortTile="john-tarchaneiotes" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-09-24" dateModified="2018-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Tarchaneiotes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Tarchaneiotes</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">John Tarchaneiotes</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_language">Greek</ref>: Ἰωάννης Ταρχανειώτης, fl.1259–1304) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_Empire">Byzantine</ref> aristocrat and general under Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andronikos_II_Palaiologos">Andronikos II Palaiologos</ref> (r. 1282–1328). Although related by blood to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palaiologos">Palaiologos</ref> dynasty, he became notable as one of the main leaders of the "Arsenites", the supporters of the deposed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarch_of_Constantinople">Patriarch of Constantinople</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arsenios_Autoreianos">Arsenios Autoreianos</ref>, who challenged the dynasty's legitimacy. A capable soldier, he was released from prison in 1298 to take command against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anatolian_beyliks">Turks</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asia_Minor">Asia Minor</ref>. His administrative reforms and integrity shored up the Byzantine position, but aroused the ire of the local magnates, who forced him to abandon the province.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<figure><caption>Miniature portrait of Andronikos II Palaiologos</caption></figure>
<p>John Tarchaneiotes hailed from a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarchaneiotes">distinguished family</ref>: his father, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikephoros_Tarchaneiotes">Nikephoros Tarchaneiotes</ref>, had served as <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Megas_domestikos">megas domestikos</ref></hi> (commander-in-chief of the army) under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicaean_emperor">Nicaean emperor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_III_Doukas_Vatatzes">John III Doukas Vatatzes</ref> (r. 1221–1254) and had married Maria-Martha, the sister of Andronikos II's father, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_VIII_Palaiologos">Michael VIII Palaiologos</ref> (r. 1259–1282), whom he had supported in his rise to the throne.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ODB-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PLP-2">[2]</ref> Following the coronation of Michael VIII, John and his brothers had lived in the imperial palace.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PLP-2">[2]</ref> Tarchaneiotes distinguished himself early on as a soldier, fighting under his uncle, the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despotes">despotes</ref></hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Palaiologos_(brother_of_Michael_VIII)">John Palaiologos</ref>, in the 1262 campaign against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_II_Komnenos_Doukas">Michael II Komnenos Doukas</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despotate_of_Epirus">Epirus</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PLP-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Nevertheless, Tarchaneiotes soon came to oppose the Palaiologoi, and by 1266 he had emerged one of the leaders of the Arsenites,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PLP-2">[2]</ref> the supporters of the former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarch_of_Constantinople">Patriarch of Constantinople</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arsenios_Autoreianos">Arsenios Autoreianos</ref>, who had <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Excommunicated">excommunicated</ref> Michael VIII for usurping the rights and the blinding of his predecessor, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_IV_Laskaris">John IV Laskaris</ref> (r. 1258–1261). The Arsenites refused to recognize the Patriarch's subsequent deposition by the Emperor, and were savagely persecuted. They <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ipso_facto">ipso facto</ref></hi> refused to recognize the validity of Andronikos' claim to the throne as well, whom they regarded as "the son of the excommunicated usurper" (Nicol), and who had been crowned by an "illegitimate" patriarch, the anti-Arsenite <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_I_Galesiotes">Joseph I Galesiotes</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bartusis-4">[4]</ref> After the failure of Andronikos' attempt at reconciliation with the Arsenites in the synod of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adramyttion">Adramyttion</ref> in 1284, John Tarchaneiotes became the leader of the radical faction, while the moderates followed a monk, Hyakinthos.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PLP-2">[2]</ref> Consequently, Tarchaneiotes spent long periods in exile or in prison. He was banished to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Şile">Chele</ref> in 1289, then placed under house arrest in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref>. Released ca. 1296, he was arrested again in 1297 and thrown in the palace prison.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PLP-2">[2]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>Map of Asia Minor ca. 1300, showing the Turkish encroachment on Byzantine territory at the time of Tarchneiotes' governorship</caption></figure>
<p>Nevertheless, in 1298, Andronikos was in need of his cousin's military talent in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asia_Minor">Asia Minor</ref>, where the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anatolian_beyliks">Turks</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Menteshe">Menteshe</ref> were encroaching once more on Byzantine territory after having been beaten back in 1293–1295 by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexios_Philanthropenos">Alexios Philanthropenos</ref>. Philanthropenos had ended up rising in revolt, supported by the local populace which still largely cherished the memory of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laskarids">Laskarids</ref> of Nicaea and resented the Palaiologoi; to prevent Tarchaneiotes, an avowed Arsenite, from following the same path as his predecessor, Andronikos first extracted from him a personal oath of loyalty and then appointed him commander in the southern and most endangered sector of the front, along the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maeander_River">Maeander River</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bartusis-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nicol-5">[5]</ref> There Tarchaneiotes achieved swift success, not only in the field, but most importantly in reorganizing the local administration and ending corruption which had allowed the alienation of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pronoia">pronoia</ref></hi> estates, originally intended for the upkeep of the army, from their rightful holders. Tarchaneiotes seems to have engaged in a reassessment and redistribution of these lands, which was so successful that it resulted not only in an increase in the numbers of his army, but also in the equipment of a small squadron of ships.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bartusis-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nicol125-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>Despite his success, Tarchaneiotes was resented by the local magnates, who had mostly profited from the previous situation and were most affected from his reforms and his honest administration, as well as by the anti-Arsenite establishment of the Church. In the end, some of the <hi rend="italic">pronoia</hi> holders, who were deprived of land through John's reforms, approached the anti-Arsenite bishop of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alasehir">Philadelphia</ref>, Theoleptos, and accused Tarchaneiotes of plotting a revolt. Facing the hostility of the local aristocracy, Tarchaneiotes was forced to flee—probably in mid-1300—to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thessalonica">Thessalonica</ref>, where the emperor resided.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bartusis-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nicol125-6">[6]</ref> Apparently Tarchaneiotes was imprisoned again, for he is last recorded as being released again from prison in 1304.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-PLP-2">[2]</ref> Following his flight, the situation in Asia Minor deteriorated rapidly as his reforms were abandoned and reversed, and the army's pay was diverted into the pockets of the local elites. Consequently, within a short time the Byzantine army disintegrated, especially as the numerous mercenaries deserted it for want of pay, opening the path for the complete collapse of Byzantine authority in Asia Minor over the next decade.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
</text>
