<text id="autogum_bio_doc691" title="Eudokia of Trebizond" shortTile="eudokia-trebizond" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-05-07" dateModified="2019-05-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eudokia_of_Trebizond" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Eudokia of Trebizond</head><p><hi rend="bold">Eudokia Megale Komnene</hi> (died after 4 September 1395), was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Empire_of_Trebizond">Trapezuntine</ref> noblewoman and a member of the powerful <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine">Byzantine</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Komnenos_dynasty">Komnenos dynasty</ref> as a daughter of Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexios_III_of_Trebizond">Alexios III of Trebizond</ref>. </p>
<p>She was styled <hi rend="italic">Despoina in Sinop</hi> after her first marriage to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muslim">Muslim</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkmen_people">Turkmen</ref> Tadjeddin Pasha of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sinop,_Turkey">Sinop</ref>, Emir of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Limnia_(Pontus)">Limnia</ref>, which had been arranged by her father to foster peaceful relations between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pontic_Greek">Pontic Greek</ref> Christians and the neighbouring Muslims.</p>
<head>Family and marriages</head>
<p>Eudokia was born on an unknown date, the second daughter of Emperor Alexios III and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodora_Kantakouzene">Theodora Kantakouzene</ref>. She had two brothers, and three sisters; the eldest  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna_of_Trebizond,_Queen_of_Georgia">Anna</ref> later became Queen consort of Georgia as the second wife of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bagrat_V_of_Georgia">Bagrat V</ref>.</p>
<p>The <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Panaretos">Michael Panaretos</ref> records the marriage on "8 October 1378 at Oinaion of Eudokia and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muslim">Muslim</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oghuz_Turks">Turkmen</ref> ruler Tadjeddin Pasha of Sinop, Emir of Limnia" after which "the Emperor took over Limnia".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> Her sisters, Maria and another whose name has not come down to us also married Muslims, but "in this case the bridegroom ... was by far the best."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Zachariadou-345-2">[2]</ref> According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_Zachariadou">Elizabeth Zachariadou</ref>, Tadjeddin was not prince of Limnia, but of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niksar">Niksar</ref>, where the tomb of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melik_Danishmend">Melik Danishmend</ref> is located, and whose territory comprised the fertile plain of Phanaroia, and important fortresses such as Iskefser and Sonusa.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Zachariadou-345-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Tadjeddin had sent an envoy to Alexios, who met with the Emperor June 1362 to discuss a marriage, but popular sentiment was against a possible marriage at the time.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Such an arrangement was not unprecedented. Prior to Eudokia's wedding, at least two of Alexios' sisters had been married to neighboring Muslim rulers: Maria had been married to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qutlugh_bin_Tur_Ali">Fahreddin Kutlug beg</ref>, Emir of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aq_Qoyunlu">Aq Qoyunlu</ref> in 1352, while Theodora became the wife of Hajji 'Umar, Emir of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chalybia">Chalybia</ref> in 1358.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony_Bryer">Anthony Bryer</ref> discussed the diplomatic strategy of marriages like this—for which the later Empire of Trebizond was famous—in his 1975 paper. He documented no fewer than 11 marriages between princesses of the Grand Komnenoi and their Turkmen neighbors, while only five princesses were married to Christian rulers. Tension existed in these relationships not only due to difference over religions, but to marriage customs. "It would be especially interesting to know why popular opinion made Alexios III refuse Tadeddin's first request for a bride in 1362," writes Bryer, then discusses possible political reasons for the extended parley and Eudokia's possible situation in Tadjeddin's court, before admitting that the situation "was probably left as ambiguous as Panaretos is on the subject, for, so far as Alexios III was concerned, the ends amply justified the means."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Zachariadou notes that around 1362 Tadjeddin was an ally of the emir of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amasya">Amasya</ref>, and both faced a dangerous foe in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eretna">Eretna</ref>, the ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sivas">Sivas</ref>; to form an alliance with Tadjeddin at that time, observes Zachariadou, "would openly place them in the anti-Sivas front". Further, Tadjeddin was not on good terms with his neighbor Hajji 'Umar, the husband of Eudokia's aunt Theodora. But the situation changed considerably between 1362 and 1379: Eretna had been succeeded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kadi_Burhan_al-Din">Kadi Burhan al-Din</ref> as sultan of Sivas, and the Kadi had formed an alliance with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kılıç_Arslan_(Turkman)">Kılıç Arslan</ref>, an emir who had raided Trapezuntine territory several times between those two years. By the date of Eudokia's marriage, both Alexios and Tadjeddin needed each other.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>Following her marriage, Eudokia was styled <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despoina">Despoina</ref> in Sinop</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> Although <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Sphrantzes">George Sphrantzes</ref> later notes that she had several children by Tadjeddin,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> only the name of one son, Altamur, is known.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> Altamur himself had children by other women, who left descendants. Tadjeddin died in battle 24 October 1386 fighting his uncle Haji 'Umar, where he was "cut to pieces".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>Not long after Tadjeddin died, she married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantine_Dragaš">Constantine Dragaš</ref>, a regional semi-independent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medieval_Serbia">Serbian</ref> lord. Although <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laonikos_Chalkokondyles">Laonikos Chalkokondyles</ref> states that Eudokia was the second wife of Byzantine Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_V_Palaiologos">John V Palaiologos</ref>, and William Miller repeats the historian's account of how she had been betrothed to John's son but upon meeting her the Emperor decided to marry her himself,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> Chalkondyles' account has been rejected by modern scholars.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> Eudokia's marriage to Constantine set a precedent for a Byzantine to marry a former member of a Turkish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harem">harem</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bryer141-13">[13]</ref> Although she did not bear her second husband offspring, she had stepchildren from his first marriage, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helena_Dragaš">Helena Dragaš</ref>.</p>
<p>On 17 May 1395, she lost her second husband at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Rovine">Battle of Rovine</ref>; and on 4 September of that same year, Panaretos notes that she "came from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref> with brides for her brother, Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manuel_III_of_Trebizond">Manuel</ref> and nephew, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexios_IV_of_Trebizond">Lord Alexios</ref>", entering Trebizond "on Sunday, the following day in a shower of rain".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> After that date there is no further mention of her, but it is presumed she spent her last years in Trebizond.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bryer141-13">[13]</ref></p>
</text>
