<text id="autogum_bio_doc795" title="William Melton" shortTile="william-melton" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2004-04-29" dateModified="2019-07-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Melton" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>William Melton</head>
For other people named Main Page, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page_(disambiguation)">Main Page (disambiguation)</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">William Melton</hi> (died 5 April 1340) was the 43rd <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_York">Archbishop of York</ref> (1317–1340).</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Melton was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_of_Melton">Nicholas of Melton</ref>, and the brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_de_Melton">Henry de Melton</ref>, and John Melton. He was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melton,_East_Riding_of_Yorkshire">Melton</ref> in the parish of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Welton,_East_Riding_of_Yorkshire">Welton</ref>, about nine miles from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingston_upon_Hull">Kingston upon Hull</ref>. He was a contemporary of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Hotham_(bishop)">John Hotham</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chancellor_of_England">Chancellor of England</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Ely">Bishop of Ely</ref>. The two prelates were often associated in public matters and were the most powerful churchmen of their period in England.</p>
<p>Melton was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Controller_of_the_Wardrobe">Controller of the Wardrobe</ref> at the accession of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_II_of_England">Edward II</ref> in 1307 and was a pluralist through and through at the time of his elevation to the see of York. Among other things, he was also <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeacon_of_Barnstaple">Archdeacon of Barnstaple</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provost_of_Beverley_Minster">Provost of Beverley</ref>. He was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Privy_Seal">Lord Privy Seal</ref> from 1307 to about 1312, having been Dean of St. Martin's-le-Grand at that time also.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Handbook93-1">[1]</ref> He was promoted to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keeper_of_the_wardrobe">Keeper of the Household Wardrobe</ref> from 1314 to 1316. He was elected by the chapter of York within a month of Archbishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Greenfield">Greenfield</ref>'s death, in December 1315, but difficulties arose and he was not consecrated until September 1317, at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avignon">Avignon</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_John_XXII">Pope John XXII</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Handbook282-2">[2]</ref> While serving as archbishop, Melton had to deal with numerous cases of fugitive or rebellious nuns at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benedictine">Benedictine</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nunnery">nunnery</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Clement's_by_York">St Clement's by York</ref>, most notably <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_of_Leeds">Joan of Leeds</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEVCH1974129,_131-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Throughout Melton's archiepiscopate, he was actively concerned in the affairs of Scotland. Between 1318 and 1322, the Scots, under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Douglas,_Lord_of_Douglas">James Douglas, Lord of Douglas</ref>, made raids into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yorkshire">Yorkshire</ref>, devastating great parts of the country, destroying churches and sacking the richest monasteries. These continued raids led to a dispute between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City_of_York">City of York</ref> and Melton regarding the responsibility for the upkeep of part of the city's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motte_and_bailey">motte and bailey</ref> defences known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Baile">Old Baile</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref>  During the raid of 1319, the King was at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capture_of_Berwick_(1318)">siege of Berwick</ref> and much of the trained soldiery was there with him. Archbishop Melton was ordered to collect what men he could and to lead them against the Scots. Clergy, friars and citizens of York were accordingly gathered and the result was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Myton">Battle of Myton</ref> (12 October 1319) on the Swale, in which the English were entirely routed. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabella_of_France">Queen Isabella</ref>, who was in York at the time, managed to escape to safety at Nottingham.</p>
<p>Connected with the Scottish raids of 1322 was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Boroughbridge">battle of Boroughbridge</ref>, in which the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas,_2nd_Earl_of_Lancaster">Earl of Lancaster</ref> was taken prisoner, led from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boroughbridge">Boroughbridge</ref> to his own castle of Pontefract and there beheaded. Archbishop Melton had aided Lancaster at one point, and seems, in consequence, to have fallen into some disfavour with Edward II. By 1325 however, the King's good opinion had been recovered, since Melton then became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_High_Treasurer">Lord Treasurer of England</ref> until 1326.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Handbook104-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Melton did not desert Edward II in his latter days, regarding his imprisonment with great displeasure. Nor was he present at the coronation of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_III_of_England">Edward III</ref>, and is said afterwards to have been engaged in a dangerous intrigue to upset the new government, for which he was arrested, though acquitted. In January 1328, Melton married the young king to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philippa_of_Hainault">Philippa of Hainault</ref>. In 1330 he was reappointed Treasurer, but left the office in 1331.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Handbook104-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Work and legacy</head>
<p>Archbishop Melton completed the building of the nave of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York_Minster">York Minster</ref> and his figure still remains above the great western portal. He is said to have assisted largely in building <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Patrick's_Church,_Patrington">St. Patrick's Church, Patrington</ref>, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holderness">Holderness</ref>, and certainly gave much toward the fabric of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beverley_Minster">Beverley Minster</ref>. He died 5 April 1340<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Handbook282-2">[2]</ref> at Cawood Palace, and was buried in the north aisle of the nave at York Minster, a memorial window installed shortly after his death being transferred to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_James'_Church,_High_Melton">St James' Church, High Melton</ref> in the 1790s by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean_of_York">Dean of York</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Fountayne">John Fountayne</ref>.</p>
<p>Melton died very wealthy, having custody of many manors and estates. His heir was his nephew, William Melton of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aston,_South_Yorkshire">Aston</ref>, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheffield">Sheffield</ref>, who was the progenitor of one of the most powerful knightly families in the south of Yorkshire.</p>
<p>Melton kept a detailed log of his activities while he was Archbishop of York, published as <hi rend="italic">The Register of William Melton</hi> in five volumes.</p>
</text>
