<text id="autogum_bio_doc665" title="Elisabeth of Oettingen" shortTile="elisabeth-oettingen" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-09-23" dateModified="2019-09-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elisabeth_of_Oettingen" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Elisabeth of Oettingen</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Elisabeth of Oettingen</hi> also known as <hi rend="italic">Elizabeth of Leuchtenberg</hi> (born: c.1360; died: 9 July 1406) was a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Oettingen-Wallerstein">House of Oettingen-Wallerstein</ref> by birth.  She was a Landgravine of Leuchtenberg by marriage and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_in_waiting">lady in waiting</ref> for Elector Palatine and King of Germany <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rupert,_King_of_Germany">Rupert</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Elisabeth of Oettingen was the daughter of Count Louis X of Oettingen (referred to as Louis XI by some authors)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> (died: 1 May 1370) and his wife Imagina of Schaunberg<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> (died: 1377).  Around 1376,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Elisabeth married Landgrave Albert of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leuchtenberg">Leuchtenberg</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> (died: c.1398).</p>
<p>Little is known about her life.  She served as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_in_waiting">lady in waiting</ref> at the Palatine court.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irmengard_of_Oettingen">Irmengard of Oettingen</ref>, the cousin of her grandfather, Frederick I of Oettingen, was married to Elector Palatine <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adolf,_Count_Palatine_of_the_Rhine">Adolf</ref> and was the grandmother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rupert,_King_of_Germany">Rupert</ref>, the Elector Palatine and King of Germany, so Elisabeth was a third cousin of King Rupert.  She may have received her position at the Palatine court on the recommendation of her elderly great-aunt Irmengard, the elector's grandmother, who at the time lived as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominican_Order">Dominican</ref> nun in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liebenau_monastery">Liebenau monastery</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Worms,_Germany">Worms</ref>.</p>
<p>Elisabeth donated a valuable collection of 52 relics in two silver containers<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> to the collegiate church in Neustadt and der Haardt (now called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neustadt_an_der_Weinstrasse">Neustadt an der Weinstrasse</ref>).  The relics were lost during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reformation">Reformation</ref>.  Members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Wittelsbach">House of Wittelsbach</ref> were buried in the choir of this church, and so was Elisabeth, who was a relative of the Wittelsbach family.  Her damaged grave stone was found in 1907 in the church floor, near the northern entrance into the Catholic part of the church and is now part of the west wall of the south choir chapel.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref>  The church has an "eternal" tradition of celebrating mass in Elisabeth's memory; a contemporary record in the <hi rend="italic">Seelbuch</hi> mentions the donation in connection with this mass.</p>
<p>Elisabeth's son Landgrave Leopold of Leuchtenberg (d. 1463) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electoral_Palatinate">Palatinate</ref> governor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amberg">Amberg</ref> and was later raised to Prince of Leuchtenberg.  This, too, may be due to his remote family connection with the king, or to the reputation of his mother.  Leopold was buried in the parish church of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pfreimd">Pfreimd</ref> in the Upper Palatinate.  His grave is marked with a well-preserved magnificent marble epitaph with a portrait of Leopold as a knight.  The portrait can be seen in the header of the parish's official website.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Elizabeth's brother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_IV_of_Oettingen">Frederick IV of Oettingen</ref> was bishop of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eichstätt">Eichstätt</ref>.  He was considered one of the most pious and most active German prelates of his time.</p>
<p>Her other brother, Louis XI "the Bearded"<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> (he is called "Louis XII" by authors who call her father "Louis XI") served king of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigismund,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Sigismund</ref> for many years as <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hofmeister_(office)">Hofmeister</ref></hi> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confidant">confidant</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref>  At the time, the Hofmeister was the highest official in the Emprire.  He also represented the Emperor at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council_of_Constance">Council of Constance</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
