<text id="autogum_bio_doc569" title="Norman Leslie (soldier)" shortTile="norman-leslie-soldier" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-08-04" dateModified="2016-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman_Leslie_%28soldier%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Norman Leslie (soldier)</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Norman Leslie</hi> (died 29 August 1554), was a 16th-century Scottish nobleman. The leader of the party who assassinated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardinal_Beaton">Cardinal Beaton</ref>, he was forced to flee Scotland, serving the monarchs of England and France. He died serving the latter in 1554.</p>
<head>Family and early life</head>
<p>Norman was the eldest son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Leslie,_4th_Earl_of_Rothes">George Leslie, 4th Earl of Rothes</ref>, by Margaret, only daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Crichton,_3rd_Lord_Crichton">William Crichton, 3rd Lord Crichton</ref>, denominated, 1 April 1517, his 'sponsa affidata.'.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892''Register_of_the_Great_Seal_of_Scotland,''_1513–46,_no._148-1">[1]</ref> No marriage ceremony is recorded to have taken place, and the marriage was in 1520 declared null and void. Norman seems to have been regarded as illegitimate.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>The notices in the 'Lord Treasurer's Accounts' in 1537 and 1539 of dresses furnished to him indicate that he at this time held some office at court. On 7 December 1541 the office of sheriff of Fife, then made hereditary in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Rothes">Rothes family</ref>, was bestowed on him for life, his father personally resigning it.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>He is described by Buchanan as a young man of such accomplishments that he had not his equal in all Scotland.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892Buchanan,_George,_''History_of_Scotland'',_bk._xvi-3">[3]</ref> He fought at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solway_Moss">Solway Moss</ref> in 1542 and was taken prisoner, but received his liberty as the result of the bond signed by the captive Scottish nobles to promote the interests of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VIII_of_England">Henry VIII</ref> in Scotland. To this is perhaps partly traceable his zeal against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardinal_Beaton">Cardinal Beaton</ref>, but it was at least quickened by an act passed, 12 December 1543, at the instance of the cardinal, restoring to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_James_Colville">Sir James Colville</ref> the lands of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castle_Wemyss">Castle Wemyss</ref>, which on the forfeiture of Colville had been bestowed by James V on the Rothes family.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Murder of Cardinal Beaton</head>
<p>On 17 April 1544 Henry VIII received information that the Master of Rothes and others were willing to undertake the slaughter of the cardinal as he passed through <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fife">Fife</ref>, on condition that they had the assurance of Henry's protection afterwards.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892''State_Papers,_Henry_VIII'',_vol._5_(1836)_377.-4">[4]</ref> Obtaining no satisfactory answer, they did not take advantage of the supposed opportunity, and subsequently, with his father, Norman appears to have given a pledge of personal service to the cardinal. He actively supported Charteris, the nominee of Beaton, against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Ruthven,_2nd_Lord_Ruthven">Lord Ruthven</ref>, in their contest for the provostship of Perth.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892Knox,_John,_''Works'',_i._112–14;_''Diurnal_of_Occurrents'',_p._34-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>He also fought against the English at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Ancrum_Moor">battle of Ancrum Moor</ref>, 12 February 1545, when his opportune arrival with three hundred spearmen from Fife, and with the news that the Scotts of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buccleuch,_Scottish_Borders">Buccleuch</ref> were following on his heels, decided the Scots to risk the battle. Negotiations for the murder of the cardinal were, with or without the sanction of Leslie, resumed with Henry on 30 May 1545, and were continued till at least 20 October following.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892State_Papers,_Henry_VIII,_vol._5_(1836),_449,_551-6">[6]</ref> How much longer a blank in Henry's Scottish correspondence renders it impossible to state.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>The execution of Wishart at the instance of the cardinal, 1 March 1546, was apparently rather an opportune pretext for the cardinal's assassination than the direct cause of it. The statement of contemporary writers that Norman Leslie had not long before the murder a violent personal quarrel with Beaton seems probable. Norman Leslie was the leader of the conspirators. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Andrews_Castle">castle of St. Andrews</ref>, where Beaton lived, was seized by men under his command, but he took no personal part in the act of assassination on 29 May 1546, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Leslie_of_Parkhill">John Leslie of Parkhill</ref>, his uncle, struck the fatal blow, after the cardinal had requested that Norman, whom he called his friend, should come to him. A dagger erroneously reputed to have been used by Norman is preserved in Leslie House, Fife.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>After the murder</head>
<p>After the murder Norman and his associates took refuge in the cardinal's stronghold. They were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_St_Andrews_Castle">besieged in St Andrew's Castle</ref> by the governor of Scotland, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent_Arran">Regent Arran</ref>. On 11 March 1547 Norman and his colleagues, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Balnaves">Henry Balnaves</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Kirkcaldy_of_Grange">James Kirkcaldy of Grange</ref>, and Alexander Whitelaw of Newgrange witnessed a pledge made by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Gray,_4th_Lord_Gray">Patrick Gray, 4th Lord Gray</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_VI_of_England">Edward VI</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892''Calendar_of_State_Papers_Scotland'',_vol._1_(1898),_2.-7">[7]</ref> The lairds in the castle, sometimes called the Castilians, were summoned to answer for the murder, and, failing to do so, were on 30 July 1547 denounced as rebels. On the same day the castle was surrendered to the French, and a condition having been made that the lives of all within it should be spared, its principal defenders were carried captives to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France">France</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Norman probably made his escape from France at the same time as Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Kirkcaldy_of_Grange">William Kirkcaldy of Grange</ref>, but there is no direct information on the point. After his release, he, according to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Spottiswood">John Spottiswood</ref>, returned to Scotland, but on search being made for him he escaped by sea to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denmark">Denmark</ref>. Thence he crossed over to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/England">England</ref>, where for some time he was in the enjoyment of a pension from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_VI">Edward VI</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>The accession of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_I_of_England">Queen Mary</ref> in 1553 compelled him to leave England, and he went to France, where he entered into the service of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_II_of_France">Henry II</ref>. He was mortally wounded in an action before the stronghold of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renti">Renti</ref>, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cambrai">Cambrai</ref>, on 14 August 1554. At the head of thirty Scots he heroically charged sixty horsemen armed with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Culverin">culverins</ref>, unhorsing five of them with his spear before it broke. He made his way back to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constable_of_France">constable of France</ref>, his horse dropping down dead at the constable's feet.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>He was brought into the king's tent, and died of his wounds on 29 August, fifteen days afterwards.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892Melville,_James,_''Memoirs_of_Sir_James_Melville_of_Halhill'',_(1830),_25–6.-8">[8]</ref> His bravery and the manner of his death so impressed the French king that he used his influence with the queen-regent and the estates to obtain for the other confederates against Beaton the reversion of their lands.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEHenderson1892-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Leslie was married to Isobel Lindsay, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Lindsay,_5th_Lord_Lindsay">John Lindsay, 5th Lord Lindsay</ref>, but left had no children with her. He did however have two natural sons, named Robert and John.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTESanderson2004-9">[9]</ref></p>
</text>
