<text id="autogum_bio_doc621" title="Íñigo de Alfaro" shortTile="inigo-de-alfaro" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-04-19" dateModified="2019-06-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%8D%C3%B1igo_de_Alfaro" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Íñigo de Alfaro</head><p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fra">Fray</ref> <hi rend="bold">Íñigo de Alfaro</hi> (fl. 1396–1435) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Aragon">Aragonese</ref> nobleman and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knight_Hospitaller">Knight Hospitaller</ref>. He was the defending commander at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Smyrna">Siege of Smyrna</ref> in 1402 against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turco-Mongol">Turco-Mongol</ref> conqueror <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timur">Timur</ref>. He later played a key role in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compromise_of_Caspe">Compromise of Caspe</ref> that settled the Aragonese interregnum in 1412.</p>
<head>Rhodes and Smyrna</head>
<figure><caption>15th-century Persian depiction of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Smyrna">siege of Smyrna</ref></caption></figure>
<p>Íñigo was born into a noble family of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logroño">Logroño</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMorales_Roca199980-1">[1]</ref> During the rule of Grand Master <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_Fernández_de_Heredia">Juan Fernández de Heredia</ref>, a fellow Aragonese, he spent time at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hospitaller">Hospitaller</ref> headquarters in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhodes">Rhodes</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBonneaud1999139–40-2">[2]</ref> One of three coats of arms carved into the lintel above the doorway to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fortifications_of_Rhodes">chapel of Saint George on Rhodes</ref> has been tentatively identified as Íñigo's. The other two belonged to Heredia and his lieutenant, Pierre Culant.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEKasdagli200885-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Íñigo rose in the ranks to become lieutenant of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Draper">draper</ref> (one of the high officials of the central convent), who was also a Spaniard, and then lieutenant to the commander of the island of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kos">Kos</ref>, where he can be traced between 20 March 1400 and 17 February 1401.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBonneaud1999139–40-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEDelaville_Le_Roulx1913284–85-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Íñigo was appointed castellan or captain of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smyrna">Smyrna</ref>, a city in western <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anatolia">Anatolia</ref> and one of the last crusader outposts in Asia, probably on 1 March 1401. Only three documents—22 February, 8 March and 2 May 1402—show him as castellan of Smyrna, but appointment to the office was annual and customarily took place on 1 March. It is for this reason that he is thought to be the castellan in power during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siege_of_Smyrna">siege of the city</ref> in December 1402, since no document that mentions that castellan names him. It would be highly unusual, however, if the castellan in charge in May were not there in December.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEDelaville_Le_Roulx1913284–85-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>The lower town of Smyrna, with the harbour and sea-castle, was under the control of the Hospitallers on behalf of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papacy">Papacy</ref>. The upper town with its fortress was under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> control. In 1400–02, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timur">Timur</ref> attacked the Ottoman Empire and invaded Anatolia. With the Ottomans utterly defeated and the sultan captured at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Ankara">Battle of Ankara</ref>, he turned on Smyrna. Although the defences had been greatly improved in a series of projects going back to 1392, Íñigo had only 200 knights under his command. The siege began on 2 December 1402, and they resisted for two weeks before the walls were breached. At least some of the Hospitallers, Íñigo included, reached their ships and managed to escape, while the population was slaughtered.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELuttrell1975308-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Despite the loss, Íñigo received treatment befitting a victor when he landed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genoa">Genoa</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMorales_Roca199980-1">[1]</ref> He informed King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_of_Aragon">Martin of Aragon</ref> of the loss of Smyrna by February 1403, perhaps having already returned to Aragon by then.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEJackson2014240-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Aragon</head>
<head>Compromise of Caspe</head>
<figure><caption>Íñigo's final post: the castle of Aliaga</caption></figure>
<p>After Íñigo returned to Aragon. he was made commander of the fortress of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ricla">Ricla</ref> in 1407. That same year, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avignon_Papacy">Avignonese pope</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antipope_Benedict_XIII">Benedict XIII</ref> appointed him ambassador of the Holy See to the court of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_I_of_Sicily">Martin I of Sicily</ref> in 1407.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMorales_Roca199980-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>On 31 May 1410, King Martin of Aragon died and the succession was disputed. It was decided that a parliament of representatives from the three components of the crown—Aragon, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principality_of_Catalonia">Catalonia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Valencia">Valencia</ref>—would meet to settle the issue. When the parliament opened in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calatayud">Calatayud</ref> on 8 February 1411, Íñigo de Alfaro escorted the governor and justiciar of Aragon, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan_Ximénez_Cerdán">Juan Ximénez Cerdán</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gil_Ruiz_de_Lihori">Gil Ruiz de Lihori</ref>, respectively, into the assembly. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castellan_of_Amposta">castellan of Amposta</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedro_Ruiz_de_Moros">Pedro Ruiz de Moros</ref>, the most powerful Hospitaller in Aragon strongly favoured the candidacy of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_II,_Count_of_Urgell">James II, Count of Urgell</ref>. The choice of Íñigo to escor the presidents of the assembly may have been designed to show that the Hospitallers were not united behind any single candidate. Íñigo was subsequently sent by this parliament as an emissary to Valencia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBonneaud1999125-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>When a second parliament convened at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alcañiz">Alcañiz</ref>, Íñigo shared responsibility for the defence of the town with the castellan, Guillem Ramon Alemany de Cervelló, a grand commander of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Order_of_Calatrava">Order of Calatrava</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBonneaud1999128-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAlanyà_i_Roig2002216–17-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>Íñigo attended the final parliament met at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caspe">Caspe</ref>, and was present when the famous compromise was publicly read on 28 June 1412. He and Guillem Ramon were then charged with bringing the news to the newly elected king, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinand_I_of_Aragon">Ferdinand I</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBonneaud1999131–32-10">[10]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAlanyà_i_Roig2002216–17-9">[9]</ref> He kissed the king's hand at the ceremony of proclamation and took the oath of homage on behalf of the Aragonese kingdom.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEDelaville_Le_Roulx1913284–85-4">[4]</ref> He was probably present at the coronation in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seo_de_Zaragoza">Seo de Zaragoza</ref> on 11 February 1413.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEMorales_Roca199980-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Trial of the castellan of Amposta</head>
<figure><caption>Tomb of Gonzalo de Funes, died in 1420 and succeeded by Íñigo</caption></figure>
<p>The castellan of Amposta refused to recognise the new king. Ferdinand thus suspended him from the castellany in 1413, and placed it under the regency of Íñigo. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catalan_Corts">Catalan <hi rend="italic">corts</hi></ref> that met in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tortosa">Tortosa</ref> in 1413 summoned Íñigo as "the regent of the Castellany of Amposta" (<hi rend="italic">regenti Castellaniam Emposte</hi>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEBonneaud1999131–32-10">[10]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAlanyà_i_Roig2002221-11">[11]</ref> He was still regent in Amposta as of 11 January 1416, but shortly thereafter Pedro Ruiz was deposed and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gonzalo_de_Funes">Gonzalo de Funes</ref> appointed in his place.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAlanyà_i_Roig2002221-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>In 1414, a tribunal was convoked by Benedict XIII to try Pedro Ruiz. The tribunal was not limited to his refusal to obey Ferdinand and accept the compromise of Caspe. Íñigo and another Hospitaller, Pascasi de Morralla, prior of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monzón">Monzón</ref>, were charged by the tribunal with conducting an inquiry "into the said lord Fray Pedro, castellan, and his houses and rooms in various places in the said castellany" (<hi rend="italic">in dicto domino fratre Petro, castellano, et suis castris seu cameris ac locis dicte Castellanie</hi>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAlanyà_i_Roig2002216–17-9">[9]</ref> In the process of this inquiry into his lifestyle and business dealings, the Hospitallers took down the testimony of 67 witnesses. In the end, Pedro Ruiz was convicted of everything from concubinage to robbery.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAlanyà_i_Roig2002224-12">[12]</ref></p>
<p>Following the removal of Pedro Ruiz and the promotion of Gonzalo de Funes, Íñigo replaced Gonzalo as commander of the castle at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aliaga,_Aragon">Aliaga</ref>. He was seriously ill when, on 3 April 1427, an administrator was appointed for him. He was still ill seven years later on 16 August 1434, when the grand master, a Catalan, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antoni_de_Fluvià">Antoni de Fluvià</ref>, expressed concern. He is last mentioned on 28 March 1435.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEAlanyà_i_Roig2002216–17-9">[9]</ref></p>
</text>
