<text id="autogum_bio_doc797" title="Roger de Beler" shortTile="roger-de-beler" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-03-16" dateModified="2019-10-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_de_Beler" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Roger de Beler</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Roger Beler</hi> was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_of_the_Exchequer">Baron of the Exchequer</ref> and right-hand man of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_le_Despenser,_1st_Earl_of_Winchester">Hugh le Despencer</ref> and King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_II_of_England">Edward II</ref>. Beler was killed by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Folville_gang">Folville gang</ref> in 1326.</p>
<head>Ancestry</head>
<p>Beler was the son of William Beler, and grandson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Beler">Roger Beler</ref>, sheriff of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lincolnshire">Lincolnshire</ref> in 1256. His mother's name was Amicia. A licence obtained in 1316 by Beler allowed him to grant a lay fee in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kirkby-by-Melton">Kirkby-by-Melton</ref>, on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/River_Wreake">Wrethek</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leicestershire">Leicestershire</ref>, to the warden and chaplains of St. Peter, on condition of their performing religious services for the benefit of the souls of himself and his wife Alicia, his father and mother, and other ancestors.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>In the civil dissensions over <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piers_Gaveston">Piers Gaveston</ref>, Beler was of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Lancaster">Earl of Lancaster</ref>'s party, and in October 1318 was included in the amnesty then granted to the earl and his adherents. Shortly afterwards, Beler received a grant of land in Leicestershire as the reward for services for the king. In the same year the offices of bailiff and steward of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stapleford,_Leicestershire">Stapleford</ref>, in Leicestershire, of which apparently he was already the tenant, were entailed upon him. In December 1318 he was one of a commission for the trial of sheriffs and other officers accused of oppression in the counties of Buckingham, Bedford, and Northampton.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEParl_Writs_II_Digest1834-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In 1322 Beler was created baron of the exchequer in the room of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_de_Foxle">John de Foxle</ref>, and placed on a special commission to try certain those who had allegedly broken into and pillaged manors belonging to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_le_Despenser,_1st_Earl_of_Winchester">Hugh le Despenser</ref>, and upon another commission for the same purpose in the following year. In July 1323 he was one of the justices appointed to investigate the conduct of sheriffs, collectors and bailiffs in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northamptonshire">Northamptonshire</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rutland">Rutland</ref>. In 1324 he sat on a commission for the trial of persons charged with complicity in a riot at Rochester.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEParl_Writs_II_Digest1834-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Beler was summoned as a justice to Parliaments at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westminster">Westminster</ref> in January 1324 and November 1325.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEParl_Writs_II_Digest1834-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>On 29 January 1326, while on his way from Kirkby to Leicester, Beler was killed in a valley near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rearsby">Rearsby</ref> by his distant cousin<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENichols1795278-2">[2]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eustace_Folville">Eustace Folville</ref> to whom he had previously made threats of violence.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Lumley-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTENichols1795225-4">[4]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_la_Zouch">Roger la Zouch</ref>, Lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lubbesthorpe">Lubbesthorpe</ref> was named as the instigator of the murder<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEClose_Rolls1224–1468-5">[5]</ref> and accessories included two of his sons, Ivo/Eudo la Zouch, the eldest son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_la_Zouche,_1st_Baron_Zouche">William la Zouche, 1st Baron Zouche</ref> of Harringworth and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_de_Hellewell">Robert de Hellewell</ref> one of William's retainers<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPatent_Rolls1232–1509-6">[6]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFine_Rolls1199–1461-7">[7]</ref> pointing to it having a political element linked to the approaching <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Invasion_of_England_(1326)">rebellion</ref> against the Despencers and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_II_of_England">Edward II</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[lower-alpha 1]</ref> Folville and his gang fled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris">Paris</ref>, and their lands confiscated.</p>
<p>Folville and his followers returned to England perhaps in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabella_of_France">Queen Isabella</ref>'s invasion in September 1326. After the Despencers' executions and Edward II's abdication in early 1327, Folville and his band were pardoned,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEPatent_Rolls1232–1509-6">[6]</ref> and became celebrated, although they were to flirt with outlawry and vigilantism for many years.</p>
<p>Beler's killing had not been an isolated attack on an official of the Despencer/Edward regime in the run-up to the 1326 invasion; in July 1325 the deputy of the keeper of confiscated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Contrariant">Contrariant</ref> castles in the Welsh Marches was brutally attacked and had his eyes torn out and limbs broken and in October the Constable of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conisborough_Castle">Conisborough Castle</ref>, which held imprisoned Contrariants, was besieged in its church.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fryde-9">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Alicia survived her husband by nearly 20 years, dying in 1344. Beler's heir was Roger, who, being an infant, became a ward of the crown. Alicia was placed in possession of the estates in Leicestershire during her son's minority. The elder Beler was buried at Kirkby in the church of St. Peter, where a monument in alabaster, representing him as a knight in complete armour, was extant at the date of publication of Nichols's <hi rend="italic">History of Leicestershire</hi> in 1795.</p>
<head>Attribution</head>
<p>This article incorporates text from a publication now in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_domain">public domain</ref>:"<ref target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Beler,%20Roger%20de%20(DNB00)">Beler, Roger de</ref>". <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dictionary_of_National_Biography">Dictionary of National Biography</ref></hi>. London: Smith, Elder &amp; Co. 1885–1900.</p>
</text>
