<text id="autogum_bio_doc433" title="John Colman" shortTile="john-colman" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-09-04" dateModified="2019-03-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Colman" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Colman</head><p><hi rend="bold">John Colman</hi> (died September 6, 1609) was a crew member of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halve_Maen">Half Moon</ref></hi> under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Hudson">Henry Hudson</ref> who was killed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indigenous_peoples_of_the_Americas">Native Americans</ref> by an arrow to his neck.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>On September 6, 1609, only five days after the arrival of the first Dutch and English sailors, John Colman was reportedly killed by attacking <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indigenous_peoples_of_the_Americas">Native Americans</ref> by an arrow to his neck.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> Colman was an "accomplished sailor" and served as second mate on Henry Hudson's ship. The <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halve_Maen">Half Moon</ref></hi> sailed into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_Harbor">New York Harbor</ref> and was anchored between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coney_Island">Coney Island</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandy_Hook">Sandy Hook</ref>. Colman was part of a 5 man crew that was aboard a rowboat that was scouting the area. Allegedly, two canoes filled with Native Americans attacked and fired a volley of arrows, killing Colman and wounding two others.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> The survivors of the attack returned to the <hi rend="italic">Half Moon</hi> at 10 a.m. on September 7, 1609 with Colman's body. He was buried that day either at what is now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coney_Island">Coney Island</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Staten_Island">Staten Island</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandy_Hook">Sandy Hook</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keansburg,_New_Jersey">Keansburg, New Jersey</ref>. The forgotten location was then named Colman's Point. A contemporary account of his death was written in the journal of Robert Juet, the first mate of the <hi rend="italic">Half Moon.</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Roberts-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> The most likely point of Coleman's burial may have been Sandy Hook, or "Coleman's Point". <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>"He was shot in the throat by an arrow: and as he had been a companion of Hudson's in his Polar adventures, having burind him on the beach, he named Sandy Hook "Coleman's Point," in honor of him" </p>
<p>-Excerpt from "The Catskill Mountains and the Region Around" 1867<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>The murder of John Colman was the basis for a poem by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Frost">Thomas Frost</ref>, "The Death of Colman", where he writes:</p>
<p>Then prone he fell within the boat,
A flinthead arrow through his throat
And now full many a stealthy skiff
Shot out into the bay;
And swiftly, sadly, pulled we back
To where the Half Moon lay;
But he was dead our master wept
He smiled, brave heart, as though he slept. </p>
<p>His death is commemorated by a mural at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hudson_County_Courthouse">Hudson County Courthouse</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jersey_City">Jersey City</ref>. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_York_Times">New York Times</ref> has called it "the first recorded murder in what became metropolitan New York".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Roberts-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>People of the Hudson Highlands area believed that Colman's spirit became the Dwerg, Heer of Dunderberg, a goblin who dressed in Dutch clothing, who raise storms to sink ships at World's End (the area just north of West Point where the Hudson is over 200 feet deep.) The Heer appears in writings by Washington Irving.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>Evan Pritichard, author of "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref>" speculates the attack on Colman occurred because he strayed too near a wampum making outpost, provoking a preemptive strike by wary Native peoples living near Manhattan.</p>
</text>
