<text id="autogum_bio_doc670" title="Magnus I, Duke of Brunswick-Lüneburg" shortTile="magnus--duke-brunswickluneburg" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-11-25" dateModified="2019-06-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnus_I%2C_Duke_of_Brunswick-L%C3%BCneburg" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Magnus I, Duke of Brunswick-Lüneburg</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Magnus I</hi> (1304–1369), called <hi rend="bold">the Pious</hi> (Latin <hi rend="italic">Pius</hi>), was duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brunswick-Lüneburg">Brunswick-Lüneburg</ref>.</p>
<p>The son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_the_Fat,_Duke_of_Brunswick-Lüneburg">Albert the Fat, Duke of Brunswick-Lüneburg</ref>, Magnus was still a minor when his father died in 1318; he and his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernest_I,_Duke_of_Brunswick-Göttingen">Ernest</ref> were put under the guardianship of their elder brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto_the_Mild,_Duke_of_Brunswick-Lüneburg">Otto</ref>, who continued as sole ruler even after his brothers came of age. After marrying <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sophia_of_Brandenburg-Stendal">Sophia</ref>, a niece of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_IV,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Louis IV, Holy Roman Emperor</ref>, Magnus was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margrave_of_Landsberg">margrave of Landsberg</ref> and count palatine of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saxony">Saxony</ref> by the Emperor in 1333. Magnus took residence at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sangerhausen">Sangerhausen</ref>. When Otto died in 1344, Magnus and Ernest jointly took over government of the state; but already on 17 April 1345, they agreed to divide the territory. Magnus received the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principality_of_Wolfenbüttel">Principality of Wolfenbüttel</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1346, a border war between Wolfenbüttel and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishop_of_Magdeburg">Archbishop of Magdeburg</ref> broke out. In exchange for help in this conflict, Magnus sold the Margraviate of Landsberg to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_II,_Margrave_of_Meißen">Frederick II, Margrave of Meißen</ref>. But the Archbishop conquered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schöningen">Schöningen</ref> in 1347, and Magnus had to cede <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hötensleben">Hötensleben</ref> and some other possessions to the Archbishop. Financially ruined by the war, Magnus could not stop the cities in the state from acquiring more and more rights; especially the City of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brunswick_(city)">Brunswick</ref> was becoming more powerful.</p>
<p>In 1348, the Emperor gave Landsberg and the Palatinate of Saxony to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernard,_Prince_of_Anhalt">Bernard, Prince of Anhalt</ref>. The ensuing conflict over these territories between Magnus and Bernard ended amicably with a marriage between Magnus' son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnus_with_the_Necklace,_Duke_of_Brunswick-Lüneburg">Magnus</ref> and Catherine, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernhard_III,_Prince_of_Anhalt-Bernburg">Bernhard III, Prince of Anhalt-Bernburg</ref>.</p>
<p>Magnus attempted to secure the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principality_of_Lüneburg">Principality of Lüneburg</ref> for his son Louis, so that it could be reunited with Wolfenbüttel. The prince of Lüneburg, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_II,_Duke_of_Brunswick-Lüneburg">William II, Duke of Brunswick-Lüneburg</ref>, a member of the same house to which Magnus belonged, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Welf">House of Welf</ref>, did not have sons; however, he had already promised the principality to a son of his daughter, a relative of the Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saxony">Saxony</ref>, before he agreed to Magnus' plan. Louis then married William's daughter Matilda. A lengthy conflict broke out that culminated in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lüneburg_Succession_War">Lüneburg Succession War</ref>, which was resolved only in 1388.</p>
<p>In 1367, Magnus joined <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dietrich,_Archbishop_of_Magdeburg">Dietrich, Archbishop of Magdeburg</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert,_Bishop_of_Halberstadt">Albert, Bishop of Halberstadt</ref>,  Valdemar, Prince of Anhalt, and others in a campaign against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerhard_of_Berg">Gerhard of Berg</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Hildesheim">Bishop of Hildesheim</ref>; they were defeated  by Hildesheim in a battle near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Farmsen">Farmsen</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dinklar">Dinklar</ref> on 3 September.(<ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schlacht%20von%20Dinklar">de:Schlacht von Dinklar</ref>)  Magnus was taken prisoner, and had to buy his freedom. He died in Summer of 1369.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Around 1327, Magnus married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sophia_of_Brandenburg-Stendal">Sophia</ref> (died 1356), the daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_I,_Margrave_of_Brandenburg-Stendal">Henry I, Margrave of Brandenburg-Stendal</ref>. They had the following children that reached adulthood:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnus_with_the_Necklace,_Duke_of_Brunswick-Lüneburg">Magnus</ref> (died 1373)</item>
<item>Louis (died 1367), married Matilda, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_II,_Duke_of_Brunswick-Lüneburg">William II, Duke of Brunswick-Lüneburg</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_of_Brunswick_and_Lunenburg-Wolfenbüttel">Albert, Prince-Archbishop of Bremen</ref> (died 1395)</item>
<item>Henry, Provost of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halberstadt_Cathedral">Halberstadt Cathedral</ref></item>
<item>Ernest</item>
<item>Matilda, married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernhard_III,_Prince_of_Anhalt-Bernburg">Bernhard III, Prince of Anhalt-Bernburg</ref></item>
<item>Agnes, married in 1360 to Count Henry of Hohnstein</item>
<item>Sophie, married Count Dietrich V of Hohnstein</item></list>
<head>Ancestry</head>
</text>
