<text id="autogum_bio_doc320" title="Sourigna Vongsa" shortTile="sourigna-vongsa" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2003-04-12" dateModified="2019-05-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sourigna_Vongsa" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sourigna Vongsa</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Souligna Vongsa</hi> (ສຸຣິຍະວົງສາທັມມິກຣາດ <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/Lao">[suliɲa voŋsaː tʰammikraːt]</ref>) was the king of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lan_Xang">Lan Xang</ref> whose reign is considered the golden age of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laos">Laos</ref>.  He ascended to the throne in  1637.</p>
<head>King of Lan Xang</head>
<p>In 1637, Sourigna Vongsa ascended the throne after the nobles elected him over his two older brothers. King Sourigna Vongsa reigned for 57 years during which Laos experienced “The Golden Age” with regard to territory, prestige and power</p>
<p>He assured stability by immediately banishing any possible rivals, sending one of his brothers to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vietnam">Vietnam</ref> and the other one into a solitary priesthood, and sending his cousins west, towards <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayutthaya_Kingdom">Siam</ref>. He was a strict and austere <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monarch">monarch</ref>, and ran the country according to firm laws. He was greatly respected as a ruler, and within five years of his ascension, his reputation reached the Dutch representatives of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_East_India_Company">Dutch East India Company</ref> who were in Phnom Penh. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Society_of_Jesus">Jesuit</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Maria_Leria">Giovanni Maria Leria</ref> arrived in Vientiane at the same time as the Dutch merchants 1641 and received the first European envoys into Laos.</p>
<p>Much of what we know about seventeenth-century Laos comes from the descriptions of these visitors. Despite the disruptions that spanned the period from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Setthathirath">Setthathirath</ref>'s death to Sourigna Vongsa's ascension, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lan_Xang">Lan Xang</ref>, as Laos was called, apparently recovered very quickly. Both Van Wuystoff, the Dutchman, and Leria, who spent six years in Laos, were impressed with the nation's prosperity. Van Wuystoff noted the great number of monasteries and the monks, "more numerous than the soldiers of the King of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prussia">Prussia</ref>." <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Philip_de_Marini">John Philip de Marini</ref>, who recorded and published Leria's visit, noted that monks went from Siam to Laos "as to University." The support of a large idle population, the monkhood, which harmed Laos' national economic development, nevertheless impressed both visitors. The first chapter of Marini's account is subtitled, The Greatness, Riches and Power of Laos. Both described the free market and flourishing trade, which supplied <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Europe">Europe</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gum_benzoin">gum benzoin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lac">lac</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musk">musk</ref> ("the first musk that has appeared in Europe from this part of the world." - de Marini) and other products. The palace of the king, de Marini would describe,</p>
"the structure and symmetry of which are remarkable can be seen from afar. It is truly vast and is so extensive that one would take it for a city... The King's quarters... have a very beautiful and magnificent façade... embellished inside and out with splendid <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bas_relief">bas relief</ref> gilded so finely that they appear to be covered with gold laminations.... I would have to fill an entire book... to describe all the other parts of the palace in detail, their richness, their apartments, their gardens...."
<p>The king claimed to recognize no other as his equal, though he concluded friendly treaties with neighboring countries. With King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Narai">Narai</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayutthaya_kingdom">Ayutthaya</ref>, he built the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phra_That_Si_Song_Rak">Phra That Si Song Rak</ref> (Stupa of the Affectionate Two) at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dan_Sai">Dan Sai</ref> (now in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loei_province">Loei province</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thailand">Thailand</ref>) to commemorate their friendship and set the boundary of their kingdoms.</p>
<p>In contrast to his friend Narai, however, who received ambassadors with great pomp, wore splendid and elaborate vestments and enjoyed the use of the finest foreign luxuries—velvets and rich <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian_rug">Persian carpets</ref>, Sourigna Vongsa wore no crowns, and preferred sitting on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phragmites">reed</ref> mats. Though the mats of Lan Xang, were evidently more beautiful than they are today; de Marini writes of them, for example, that "the weaving is so delicate and the ornamentation with patterns and various leaf-works so well done that, in my opinion, there is nothing more beautiful and more pleasing to the eye;" it is apparent from the accounts of the foreign visitors that the great king lived a far from decadent life. Rather, they noted that he distributed his wealth in the service of religion.</p>
<p>In the golden age of Lan Xang, wealth was primarily spent on religion, rather than on equipping the army with European weapons.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>  It was one of the crucial reasons why the kingdom declined following his rule.</p>
<head>Death</head>
<p>In 1695, Sourigna died and was heirless. He had 2 sons, the eldest one having been executed for adultery and the other son having fled to Ayutthaya with his mother, step-mother and 600 followers in February 1686, after his father ordered their execution because he was found to be co-habiting with his half-sister with their full knowledge. This was a chaotic time in Laotian history wherein the empire completely collapsed with the kingdom splitting into 3 new kingdoms: Vientiane, Luang Phrabang and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Champasak">Kingdom of Champasak</ref>.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Father: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tone_Kham">Tone Kham</ref></item>
<item>Mother: <hi rend="italic">name unknown</hi></item>
<item>Consorts and their respective issue:</item></list>
<list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="italic">name unknown</hi>
<list type="ordered"><item>Prince Indra Brahma (Enta-Prohm), Chao Raja Yudha (Ratsavuth) - (b.1642) father of Kings of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luang_Phrabang">Luang Phrabang</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingkitsarath">Kingkitsarath</ref> (r.1707-1713) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intha_Son">Intha Son</ref> (r.1737 1738)</item>
<item>Princess Sumangala Kumari - mother of Kings <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sai_Ong_Hue">Sai Ong Hue</ref> of Lan Xang and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nokasad">Nokasad</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Champasak">Champasak</ref></item></list></item>
<item>Princess Kinichandra (Kène Chan) - (m.1652) - daughter of Princess Kham San of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muang_Phuan">Xieng Xouang</ref></item>
<item>a daughter of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lê_Thần_Tông">Lê Thần Tông</ref>  of Annam</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">name unknown</hi>
<list type="ordered"><item>Princess Suman... Kumari - (d.1696) she married (~1694) the King of Lan Xang <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tian_Thala">Tian Thala</ref> (r.1694 or 1695)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">A son,</hi> who fled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayutthaya_Kingdom">Ayutthaya</ref> with his mother, step-mother and 600 followers in February 1686 after his father ordered their execution because he was found to be co-habiting with his half-sister.</item></list></item></list>
</text>
