<text id="autogum_bio_doc577" title="Giovanni Antonio da Brescia" shortTile="giovanni-antonio" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-07" dateModified="2019-01-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Antonio_da_Brescia" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Giovanni Antonio da Brescia</head><figure><caption><hi rend="italic">Hercules and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antaeus">Antaeus</ref></hi>, in the style of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea_Mantegna">Andrea Mantegna</ref>, engraving</caption></figure>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ornament_print">Ornament print</ref> of armour</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Giovanni Antonio da Brescia</hi> was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italy">Italian</ref> engraver of northern Italy, active in the approximate period 1490–1519,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italian_Renaissance">Italian Renaissance</ref>.  In his early career he used the initials "Z.A." to sign some twenty engravings, and until recently <hi rend="bold">Zoan Andrea</hi> was regarded as a distinct printmaker; it is now realized that they are the same person,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> and the "Z.A." stood for Giovanni Antonio, "Zovanni" being a north Italian spelling.  Around 1507 he began to use formulae such as "IO.AN.BX.", and signed some prints more fully.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>  The real Zoan Andrea was a very obscure painter, documented as working in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mantua">Mantua</ref> in the 1470s, who produced no engravings.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>The newly expanded oeuvre comprises at least 150 engravings, making Giovanni Antonio one of the most prolific Italian engravers of this period.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref>  A large number copy other prints, as was then common, and others are probably after drawings by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea_Mantegna">Andrea Mantegna</ref>; "all his major works seem to have been based on designs by other artists" ("major" here presumably excludes the large number of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ornament_(art)#Ornament_prints_and_pattern_books"> ornament prints</ref>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>Beginning his printmaking career in a close but uncertain relationship with the aged <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea_Mantegna">Andrea Mantegna</ref> (c.1431–1506) in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mantua">Mantua</ref>, as some kind of pupil or collaborator, he then may have travelled around north Italy, and certainly spent his later printmaking years in Rome. He developed his technique, becoming a technical influence on other Italian engravers, notably <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcantonio_Raimondi">Marcantonio Raimondi</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Though he was apparently from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brescia">Brescia</ref> in northern Italy,  there are no documentary records of his life other than the prints; the locations and rough timing of his career have been worked out from these.  He began his traceable printmaking career in the circle of Mantegna, arriving in Mantua in the 1490s, and leaving around 1506, perhaps after Mantegna's death that year.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref>  He may have been relatively old and experienced as an artist in another medium when he joined the aged Mantegna.  It is assumed he moved to Rome, as his later engravings depict works available to him only in that city, but the date this happened varies between different accounts. After he left Mantua <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benedetto_Montagna">Benedetto Montagna</ref> and his father <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bartolomeo_Montagna">Bartolomeo Montagna</ref>, both of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vicenza">Vicenza</ref>, become influences, and a period there has been posited.  He also appears to have spent time in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florence">Florence</ref>, as one print copies a drawing by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Filippino_Lippi">Filippino Lippi</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>The date of his arrival in Rome is estimated to be around 1506,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> c. 1509,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> and "likely" by 1513.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref>  One print shows the famous Roman sculpture the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laocoön_Group">Laocoön Group</ref></hi>, which was excavated in 1506.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref>  According to Jacquelyn Sheehan (in 1973), he must have been active there until at least 1525, from the date of a painting he engraved,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> but Zucker and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British_Museum">British Museum</ref> end his activity about 1519 or 1520; another print copies a painting of 1519.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref></p>
<head>Prints</head>
<p>His prints are mainly concerned with the figures, which often occupy most of the picture space.  Unlike many of his contemporaries, who adopted the extensive landscape backgrounds pioneered by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albrecht_Dürer">Albrecht Dürer</ref>, he is, like Mantegna, relatively little interested in the backgrounds, which are often blank or very simple.  According to Sheehan "he never achieves a true unity between figures and setting, as do the more advanced masters of the 16th century".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></p>
<p>In Mantua his relationship with Mantegna was apparently close, but the precise nature of it remains uncertain.  Mantegna had been interested in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Printmaking">printmaking</ref> for decades, probably since the 1460s, and he is "the artist who can best be claimed to have "invented" printmaking in Italy".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered">
<item>Christ Before <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pontius_Pilate">Pontius Pilate</ref></item>
<item>Four dancing Muses</item>
<item>Probably the earliest print of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laocoön_and_His_Sons">the Laocoön Group</ref>, excavated in Rome in 1506.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref></item>
<item>Three <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Putti">putti</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
