<text id="autogum_bio_doc799" title="Ulrich II, Lord of Hanau" shortTile="ulrich-ii-lord-hanau" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-02-23" dateModified="2017-07-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulrich_II%2C_Lord_of_Hanau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ulrich II, Lord of Hanau</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ulrich II, Lord of Hanau</hi> (c.1280/1288 – 23 September 1346<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>) was Lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanau">Hanau</ref> from 1305/1306 until his death.</p>
<head>Childhood</head>
<p>He was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulrich_I,_Lord_of_Hanau">Ulrich I</ref> and his wife, Countess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elisabeth_of_Rieneck">Elisabeth of Rieneck</ref>. Nothing is known about his childhood. He is not mentioned in official documents until he took office. The earliest possibility (c.1279) is derived from the date of his parents' wedding (1278). The latest possibility (c.1288) is derived from the fact that he must have been at least 18 years old when he took office. The fact that he married four years after taking office, suggests a birth date near the end of the range.</p>
<head>Reign</head>
<head>Political Activities</head>
<p>In 1310, Ulrich militarily assisted King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Bohemia">John of Bohemia</ref>, a son of Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VII,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Henry VII</ref>. In return the Emperor mortgaged him the Jews in the cities in his territory (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Babenhausen,_Hesse">Babenhausen</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanau">Hanau</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steinau_an_der_Straße">Steinau an der Straße</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nidderau">Windecken</ref>) for 600 pounds of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heller_(money)">Heller</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1314, Ulrich was at the election of Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_IV,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Louis IV</ref> in Frankfurt, as a member of the entourage of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elector_of_the_Palatinate">Elector of the Palatinate</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_II,_Duke_of_Bavaria">Louis II</ref>. Ulrich II actively participated in the pacification of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wetterau">Wetterau</ref> region. In this process, the local nobility agreed to resolve their disputes in a court of law, rather than fighting a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feud">feud</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1339, Ulrich decreed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primogeniture">primogeniture</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanau">Hanau</ref>. This was one of the earliest decrees of this kind in Germany. The decree was repeated several times by later counts, for example in 1343 and in 1375. Nevertheless, the ruling family would divide the county when this was considered convenient politically, for example in 1456 and in 1685.</p>
<p>Shortly before his death, Ulrich II was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outlaw">outlawed</ref>; the reason for this is unknown. Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_IV,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Louis IV</ref> tasked Frederick of Hutten, the governor of the Wetterau was tasked with implementing this judgement. The issue appears to have been settled amicably soon afterward. Further details are not known.</p>
<head>Acquisition of territory</head>
<p>In 1316, Ulrich purchased <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High,_middle_and_low_justice">justice</ref> over the district of Brandenstein and half of justice over the district of Schlüchtern from the Count of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Rieneck">Rieneck</ref>. The bishop of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Würzburg">Würzburg</ref>, who was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liege_lord">liege lord</ref> of this property, agreed to the sale. Hanau would acquire the other half of the justice over Schlüchtern in 1377, exchanging it for “Büttert Castle“ (Bütthard Castle). In 1457, the Count of Hanau also became protector of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schlüchtern_Abbey">Schlüchtern Abbey</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1317, the owner of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trages_Manor">Trages Manor</ref> put himself under Ulrich II's suzerainty.</p>
<p>In 1320, King Louis IV mortgaged the district of Bornheimerberg to Ulrich II, as a payment for services rendered during a raid in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alsace">Alsace</ref>. This mortgage was renewed by Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_IV,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Charles IV</ref> in 1351. In 1434, Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reinhard_II,_Count_of_Hanau">Reinhard II</ref> was finally <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enfeoffed">enfeoffed</ref> with Bornheimerberg.</p>
<p>The Imperial City of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gelnhausen">Gelnhausen</ref> was mortgaged to Hanau by King Louis IV in 1326. In 1330, the citizens were absolved from their allegiance to the emperor and asked to swear allegiance to the Lord of Hanau. But shortly afterwards this mortgage was released.</p>
<p>Ulrich II's maternal uncle, Count Louis V of Rieneck died in 1333. With his death, his line of the House of Rieneck died out in the male line. Under an agreement Louis V had made with Ulrich I in 1296, Hanau would inherit Rieneck's feudal rights. However, in 1329, Louis V had decreed that his daughter Udelhilt would inherit. This gave rise to a complicated inheritance dispute, which involved other lines of the House of Rieneck and the two largest feudal lords in the area, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electorate_of_Mainz">Electorate of Mainz</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopric_of_Würzburg">Bishopric of Würzburg</ref>. Ulrich II eventually made significant territorial gains:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Half the justice over the district of Bieber</item>
<item>The larger part of the district of Lohrhaupten</item>
<item>Half the district of Partenstein</item>
<item>A quarter of the castle and district of Rieneck</item>
<item>Half the county of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stadtprozelten">Prozelten</ref></item>
<item>A share of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rothenfels_Castle">Rothenfels Castle</ref></item>
<item>The city and district of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lauda-Königshofen">Lauda</ref></item>
<item>The city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Osterburken">Osterburken</ref></item>
<item>The bailiwick of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maintal-Dörnigheim">Dörnigheim</ref></item>
<item>Justice over the district of Schwarzenfels</item>
<item>A number of other fiefs and feudal rights</item></list>
<head>Marriage and issue</head>
<p>Ulrich II married in 1310 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agnes_of_Hohenlohe-Weikersheim">Agnes of Hohenlohe-Weikersheim</ref> (before 1295 – 29 November 1346<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>), a daughter of Kraft I of Hohenlohe-Weikersheim. Ten children from this marriage are known, but not the order in which they were born. Historians have been able to infer the order in which the sons were born.</p>
<list type="ordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulrich_III,_Lord_of_Hanau">Ulrich III</ref> (1310 – 1369/70)</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reinhard_of_Hanau_(custodian)">Reinhard</ref>, custodian of the cathedral in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mainz">Mainz</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kraft_of_Hanau">Kraft</ref> (d. 1382), a canon of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdiocese_of_Cologne">Cologne</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Mainz">Mainz</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Wurzburg">Würzburg</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Worms">Worms</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_of_Hanau">Louis</ref>, (d. after 1386), Archdeacon in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diocese_of_Würzburg">Würzburg</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gottfried_of_Hanau">Gottfried</ref> (d. after 1372), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Komtur">Commander</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teutonic_Knights">Teutonic Knights</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conrad_IV_of_Hanau">Conrad</ref> (killed in 1383), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbot">Abbot</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fulda_monastery">Fulda monastery</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elisabeth_of_Hanau,_Countess_of_Falkenstein">Elizabeth</ref> (d. after 1365), married to Count Philip V of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Counts_of_Falkenstein_(Rhineland-Palatinate)">Falkenstein</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adelaide_of_Hanau,_Countess_of_Katzenelnbogen">Adelaide</ref> (d. after 1378), married to Count Eberhard II of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Katzenelnbogen">Katzenelnbogen</ref> and after his death, to Henry II of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Isenburg">Isenburg</ref></item>
<item>Agnes (d. after 1347), a nun in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patershausen_Abbey">Patershausen Abbey</ref></item>
<item>Irmengard (d. after 1348), a nun in the convent at Gerlachsheim, mentioned between 1343 and 1347</item></list>
<head>Death</head>
<p>Sources give two different dates for the death of Ulrich II: 2 September 1346<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> and 23 September 1346.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> He was buried in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arnsburg_Abbey">Arnsburg Abbey</ref>, the place members of the house of Hanau were buried usually until the 15th century. Already in the years 1343, a deed is created, which gives Ulrich II's daughter Adelaide the right to visit her father's grave twice a year. The grave was located in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enclosed_religious_orders">enclosed</ref> part of Arnsburg Abbey, so it was not generally accessible.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
