<text id="autogum_bio_doc163" title="Marimba Ani" shortTile="marimba-ani" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-07-04" dateModified="2019-09-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marimba_Ani" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Marimba Ani</head><p><hi rend="bold">Marimba Ani</hi> (born <hi rend="bold">Dona Richards</hi>) is an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthropologist">anthropologist</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African_Studies">African Studies</ref> scholar best known for her work <hi rend="italic">Yurugu</hi>, a comprehensive critique of European thought and culture, and her coining of the term "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maafa">Maafa</ref>" for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African_holocaust">African holocaust</ref>.</p>
<head>Life and work</head>
<p>Marimba Ani completed her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bachelor_of_Arts">BA degree</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Chicago">University of Chicago</ref>, and holds <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_Arts">MA</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ph.D.">Ph.D.</ref> degrees in anthropology from the Graduate Faculty of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_School_University">New School University</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-disaspora-1">[1]</ref> In 1964, during <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom_Summer">Freedom Summer</ref>, she served as an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SNCC">SNCC</ref> field secretary, and married civil-rights activist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob_Moses_(activist)">Bob Moses</ref>; they divorced in 1966.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-crdl-3">[3]</ref> She has taught as a Professor of African Studies in the Department of Black and Puerto Rican Studies at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hunter_College">Hunter College</ref> in New York City,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-disaspora-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-crdl-3">[3]</ref> and is credited with introducing the term <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maafa">Maafa</ref> to describe the African holocaust.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-MorrisMorris2002-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head><hi rend="italic">Yurugu</hi></head>
<p>Ani's 1994 work, <hi rend="italic">Yurugu: An Afrikan-Centered Critique of European Cultural Thought and Behavior</hi>, examined the influence of European culture on the formation of modern institutional frameworks, through <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colonialism">colonialism</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperialism">imperialism</ref>, from an African perspective.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bush2004-6">[6]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ConferenceAsumah2002-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hawthorne2002-17-19-8">[8]</ref> Described by the author as an "intentionally aggressive polemic", the book derives its title from a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dogon_people">Dogon</ref> legend of an incomplete and destructive being rejected by its creator.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Howe1999-9">[9]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Ani1994xi1-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>Examining the causes of global <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_supremacy">white supremacy</ref>, Ani argued that European thought implicitly believes in its own superiority, stating: "European culture is unique in the assertion of political interest".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Bush2004-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>In <hi rend="italic">Yurugu</hi>, Ani proposed a tripartite conceptualization of culture, based on the concepts of </p>
<list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Asili</hi>, the central seed or "germinating matrix" of a culture,</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Utamawazo</hi>, "culturally structured thought" or worldview, "the way in which the thought of members of a culture must be patterned if the <hi rend="italic">asili</hi> is to be fulfilled", and</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Utamaroho</hi>, a culture's "vital force" or "energy source", which "gives it its emotional tone and motivates the collective behavior of its members".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hawthorne2002-17-19-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Howe1999-9">[9]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Ani1994xxv-11">[11]</ref></item></list>
<p>The terms Ani uses in this framework are based on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swahili_language">Swahili</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Asili</hi> is a common Swahili word meaning "origin" or "essence"; <hi rend="italic">utamawazo</hi> and <hi rend="italic">utamaroho</hi> are neologisms created by Ani, based on the Swahili words <hi rend="italic">utamaduni</hi> ("civilisation"), <hi rend="italic">wazo</hi> ("thought") and <hi rend="italic">roho</hi> ("spirit life").<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Howe1999-9">[9]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Mazrui2004-12">[12]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hawthorne2002-13">[13]</ref> The <hi rend="italic">utamawazo</hi> and <hi rend="italic">utamaroho</hi> are not viewed as separate from the <hi rend="italic">asili</hi>, but as its manifestations, which are "born out of the <hi rend="italic">asili</hi> and, in turn, affirm it."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Ani1994xxv-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>Ani characterised the <hi rend="italic">asili</hi> of European culture as dominated by the concepts of separation and control, with separation establishing dichotomies like "man" and "nature", "the European" and "the other", "thought" and "emotion" – separations that in effect end up negating the existence of "the other", who or which becomes subservient to the needs of (European) man.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hawthorne2002-17-19-8">[8]</ref> Control is disguised in universalism as in reality "the use of abstract 'universal' formulations in the European experience has been to control people, to impress them, and to intimidate them."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Ani199472-14">[14]</ref></p>
<p>According to Ani's model, the <hi rend="italic">utamawazo</hi> of European culture "is structured by ideology and bio-cultural experience", and its <hi rend="italic">utamaroho</hi> or vital force is domination, reflected in all European-based structures and the imposition of Western values and civilisation on peoples around the world, destroying cultures and languages in the name of progress.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hawthorne2002-17-19-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Higgs2000-15">[15]</ref></p>
<p>The book also addresses the use of the term <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maafa">Maafa</ref>, based on a Swahili word meaning "great disaster", to describe <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slavery">slavery</ref>.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African-centered">African-centered</ref> thinkers have subsequently popularized and expanded on Ani's conceptualization.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Dagbovie2010-16">[16]</ref> Citing both the centuries-long history of slavery and more recent examples like the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuskegee_study">Tuskegee study</ref>, Ani argued that Europeans and white <hi rend="italic">Americans</hi> have an "enormous capacity for the perpetration of physical violence against other cultures" that had resulted in "antihuman, genocidal" treatment of blacks.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Dagbovie2010-16">[16]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Ani1994427434-17">[17]</ref></p>
<head>Critical reception</head>
<p>Philip Higgs, in <hi rend="italic">African Voices in Education</hi>, describes <hi rend="italic">Yurugu</hi> as an "excellent delineation of the ethics of harmonious coexistence between human beings", but cites the book's "overlooking of structures of social inequality and conflict that one finds in all societies, including indigenous ones," as a weakness.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Higgs2000-15">[15]</ref>:175 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Molefi_Kete_Asante">Molefi Kete Asante</ref> describes <hi rend="italic">Yurugu</hi> as an "elegant work".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref> Stephen Howe accuses Ani of having little interest in actual Africa (beyond romance) and challenges her critique of "Eurocentric" logic since she invests heavily in its usage in the book.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Howe1999-9">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Publications</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>"The Ideology of European Dominance," <hi rend="italic">The Western Journal of Black Studies</hi>. Vol. 3, No. 4, Winter, 1979, and <hi rend="italic">Présence Africaine</hi>, No. 111, 3rd Quarterly, 1979.</item>
<item>"European Mythology: The Ideology of Progress," in M. Asante and A. Vandi (eds), <hi rend="italic">Contemporary Black Thought</hi>, Beverly Hills: Sage Publications, 1980 (59-79).</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Let The Circle Be Unbroken: The Implications of African Spirituality in the Diaspora</hi>. New York: Nkonimfo Publications, 1988 (orig. 1980).</item>
<item>"Let The Circle Be Unbroken: The Implications of African-American Spirituality," <hi rend="italic">Présence Africaine</hi>. No. 117-118, 1981.</item>
<item>"The Nyama of the Blacksmith: The Metaphysical Significance of Metallurgy in Africa," <hi rend="italic">Journal of Black Studies</hi>. Vol. 12, No. 2, December 1981.</item>
<item>"The African 'Aesthetic' and National Consciousness," in Kariamu Welsh-Asante (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The African Aesthetic</hi>, Westport, Ct.: Greenwood Press, 1993 (63-82)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Yurugu: An Afrikan-centered Critique of European Cultural Thought and Behavior</hi>. Trenton: Africa World Press, 1994.</item>
<item>"The African Asili," in <hi rend="italic">Selected Papers from the Proceedings of the Conference on Ethics, Higher Education and Social Responsibility</hi>, Washington, D.C.: Howard University Press, 1996.</item>
<item>"To Heal a People", in Erriel Kofi Addae (ed.), <hi rend="italic">To Heal a People: Afrikan Scholars Defining a New Reality</hi>, Columbia, MD.: Kujichagulia Press, 1996 (91-125).</item>
<item>"Writing as a means of enabling Afrikan Self-determination," in Elizabeth Nuñez and Brenda M. Greene (eds), <hi rend="italic">Defining Ourselves; Black Writers in the 90's</hi>, New York: Peter Lang, 1999 (209–211).</item></list>
</text>
