<text id="autogum_bio_doc756" title="Boetius of Dacia" shortTile="boetius-dacia" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-02-10" dateModified="2019-06-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boetius_of_Dacia" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Boetius of Dacia</head>Not to be confused with the Roman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boethius">Boethius</ref> from the early 6th century.
For other people of the same name, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boethius_(disambiguation)">Boethius (disambiguation)</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Boetius de Dacia</hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominican_Order">OP</ref> (also spelled <hi rend="bold">Boethius de Dacia</hi>) was a 13th-century <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danish_people">Danish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philosophy">philosopher</ref>. </p>
<head>Name</head>
<p>The rendering of his name <hi rend="italic">Danske Bo</hi> ("<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bo_(given_name)">Bo</ref> the Dane") into Medieval Latin as <hi rend="italic">Boetius de Dacia</hi> stems from the fact that the toponym <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denmark">Dania</ref></hi>, meaning Denmark, was occasionally confused with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dacia_(disambiguation)">Dacia</ref></hi> during the Middle Ages.</p>
<head>Life and accomplishments</head>
<p>Boetius was born in the first half of the 13th century.  Not much is known of his early life. The attempt to connect him to known persons from Denmark or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref> has been unsuccessful.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> All that is known is that he went to France to teach philosophy at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Paris">University of Paris</ref>. At the university, he associated with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siger_of_Brabant">Siger of Brabant</ref>. He continued to teach for some time as arts masters rather than quickly moving on to study in the theology faculty or finding non-academic employment. He shared this unusual career path with Siger and others like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Bacon">Roger Bacon</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Buridan">Jean Buridan</ref>. He was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Condemnations_(University_of_Paris)">condemned</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Tempier">Stephen Tempier</ref> in 1277 for being a leading member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Averroism">Averroist movement</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> Boetius fled <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris">Paris</ref> with Siger and appealed to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Nicholas_III">Pope Nicholas III</ref>. He was detained at the pontifical <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curia">curia</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orvieto">Orvieto</ref>. He went on to join the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominican_Order">Dominicans</ref> in Denmark.</p>
<p>Boetius was a follower of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aristotle">Aristotle</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Averroes">Averroes</ref>. He wrote on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logic">logic</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_philosophy">natural philosophy</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metaphysics">metaphysics</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethics">ethics</ref>, though some of his works have not survived. His central position was that philosophy had to follow where the arguments led, regardless of their conflict with religious faith. For him, philosophy was the supreme human activity, and in this world only philosophers attained wisdom. In his book <hi rend="italic">On the Highest Good, or On the Life of the Philosopher</hi> he offers a fervently Aristotelian description of man's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Highest_good">highest good</ref> as the rational contemplation of truth and virtue. Among the controversial conclusions that he reached are the impossibility of creation <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ex_nihilo">ex nihilo</ref></hi>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eternity_of_the_world">eternity of the world</ref> and of the human race, and that there could be no <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resurrection_of_the_dead">resurrection of the dead</ref>.</p>
<p>Despite his radical views, Boetius remained a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christianity">Christian</ref>; he attempted to reconcile his religious beliefs with his philosophical positions by assigning the investigation of the world and of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human_nature">human nature</ref> to philosophy, while to religion he assigned supernatural <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revelation">revelation</ref> and divine <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miracle">miracles</ref>. He was condemned for holding the doctrine of "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double_truth">double truth</ref>", though he was careful to avoid calling philosophical conclusions that ran contrary to religion true <hi rend="italic">simpliciter</hi>: in each branch of knowledge, one must be careful to qualify one's conclusions. The conclusions that the philosopher reaches are true "according to natural causes and principles" (<hi rend="italic">De Aeternitate Mundi</hi>, p.351).</p>
<head>Works and translations</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Boethii Daci Opera:
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">Modi significandi sive quaestiones super Priscianum maiorem</hi>, edited by John Pinborg &amp; Henry Roos with the collaboration of Severino Skovgaard Jensen, Hauniae (Copenhague), G. E. C. Gad, <hi rend="italic">Corpus Philosophorum Danicorum Medii Aevi, 4</hi>, 1969.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Quaestiones de generatione et corruptione -- Quaestiones super libros physicorum</hi>, edited by Géza Sajó,  Hauniae (Copenhague), G. E. C. Gad, <hi rend="italic">Corpus Philosophorum Danicorum Medii Aevi, 5</hi>, 1976.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Topica - Opuscola</hi>, Pars 1. <hi rend="italic">Quaestiones super Librum Topicorum</hi>, edited by Nicolas George Green-Pedersen and John Pinborg; Pars 2. <hi rend="italic">Opuscula: De aeternitate mundi. De summo bono. De somniis</hi>, edited by Nicolas George Green-Pedersen, Hauniae (Copenhague), G. E. C. Gad, <hi rend="italic">Corpus Philosophorum Danicorum Medii Aevi, 6</hi>, 1976.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Quaestiones super IV Meteorologicorum</hi>, edited by Gianfranco Fioravanti, Hauniae (Copenhague), G. E. C. Gad, <hi rend="italic">Corpus Philosophorum Danicorum Medii Aevi, 8</hi>, 1979.</item></list></item>
<item>Boethius of Dacia, On the Supreme Good; on the Eternity of the World; on Dreams. Edited by John F. Wippel, Mediaeval Sources in Translation. Toronto, Ont. Canada: Pontifical Institute of Mediaeval Studies, 1987.</item>
<item>Boetius of Dacia, "The Sophisma 'Every Man Is of Necessity an Animal'", in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman_Kretzmann">Norman Kretzmann</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleonore_Stump">Eleonore Stump</ref> [edd &amp; trans.] <hi rend="italic">The Cambridge Translations of Medieval Philosophical texts. Volume One: Logic and the Philosophy of Language</hi> (1988, Cambridge University Press; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/0-521-28063-X">0-521-28063-X</ref>)</item></list>
</text>
