<text id="autogum_bio_doc254" title="Hurshid Pasha" shortTile="hurshid-pasha" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-07-13" dateModified="2019-09-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hurshid_Pasha" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hurshid Pasha</head>
In this <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Turkish_language">Ottoman Turkish</ref> style name, <hi rend="italic">Hurshid</hi> is the given name, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Ottoman_titles_and_appellations">title</ref> is <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pasha">Pasha</ref></hi>, and there is no family name.
<p><hi rend="bold">Hurşid Ahmed Pasha</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> (died 30 November 1822) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> general and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Vizier_of_the_Ottoman_Empire">Grand Vizier</ref> during the early 19th century.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>He was born in the Caucasus and was of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgian_people">Georgian</ref> descent.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> He was taken to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constantinople">Constantinople</ref> as a youth, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Devşirme">converted to Islam</ref> and enrolled in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janissaries">Janissaries</ref>. There he acquired the favour of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_dynasty">Sultan</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahmud_II">Mahmud II</ref> and occupied several high positions.</p>
<head>Egypt (1801–05)</head>
<p>Appointed mayor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexandria">Alexandria</ref> after the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Invasion_of_Egypt_(1798)">French evacuated Egypt</ref> in 1801,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> he was named <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_governor_of_Egypt">governor of Egypt</ref> in 1804 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muhammad_Ali_of_Egypt">Muhammad Ali's</ref> behest. Allied with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_Kingdom_of_Great_Britain_and_Ireland">Britain's</ref> diplomatic representative, Hurshid tried to get Muhammad Ali and his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albanians">Albanians</ref> removed from Egypt, bringing in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deli_(Ottoman_troops)"><hi rend="italic">deli</hi></ref> (lit. "madmen") light cavalry from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Syria">Ottoman Syria</ref> to counterbalance them. Muhammad Ali won the <hi rend="italic">Delis</hi> to his side and, backed by a demonstration of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulema">ulema</ref></hi> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guild">guild</ref> leaders in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cairo">Cairo</ref>, had himself named governor of Egypt in May 1805. Hurshid, abandoned by his troops, was besieged in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cairo_Citadel">Cairo Citadel</ref>, which he left only after he saw the Ottoman <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Firman_(decree)">firman</ref></hi> investing Muhammad Ali as Egypt's governor.</p>
<head>Rumelia</head>
<p>In 1808, Hurshid Pasha served as the governor of Rumelia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Yaycioglu2016-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Suppression of the Serbian Revolution</head>
See also: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_Revolution">Serbian Revolution</ref>
<p>In March 1809, he was sent to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbia">Serbia</ref> (the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanjak_of_Smederevo">Sanjak of Smederevo</ref>) to repress the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_Serbian_Uprising">First Serbian Uprising</ref> led by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karađorđe_Petrović">Karađorđe Petrović</ref>. On 5 September 1812 he was named <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Vizier">Grand Vizier</ref> (Prime Minister), a post he held until 1 April 1815. He remained on campaign in Serbia as commander-in-chief (<hi rend="italic">serasker</hi>), and brought the uprising to an end after recapturing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belgrade">Belgrade</ref> in October 1813. In that year he was named governor of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eyalet_of_Bosnia">Eyalet of Bosnia</ref> and from that position he campaigned with success against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Serbian_Uprising">Second Serbian Uprising</ref> led by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miloš_Obrenović_I,_Prince_of_Serbia">Miloš Obrenović</ref>.</p>
<head>Suppression of Ali Pasha's revolt and Greek Revolution</head>
<figure><caption>Tomb of Ali Pasha in Ioannina.</caption></figure>
<p>In November 1820, he was named <hi rend="italic">Mora valisi</hi>, governor of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morea_Eyalet">Morea Eyalet</ref> (the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peloponnese">Peloponnese</ref>), with seat at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tripoli,_Greece">Tripoli</ref> and <hi rend="italic">serasker</hi> of the expedition against the rebellious <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ali_Pasha_of_Yanina">Ali Pasha</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ioannina">Yanina</ref>. Before he left for Yanina, however, he was disturbed by rumours of a possible revolt among the Greeks of the Morea. His fears were allayed, however, when an assembly of Greek notables visited him on 8 November 1820 in Tripoli. Thus, on 6 January 1821, he left Tripoli for the north, leaving behind his treasury and his harem, while his deputy (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kaimakam">kaimakam</ref></hi>) Mehmed Salih with a force of 1,000 Albanians remained to maintain order. However, only a few months later, while the Ottoman armies were besieging Yanina, the first uprisings of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_War_of_Independence">Greek War of Independence</ref> took place. </p>
<p>Hurshid immediately informed the Sultan of the events, and without waiting for instructions, reacted by sending <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Omer_Vryonis">Omer Vryonis</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Köse_Mehmed_Pasha">Köse Mehmed Pasha</ref> to suppress the revolt first in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_Greece">Central Greece</ref> and then to cross over to the Peloponnese and quell the uprising in its heartland. At the same time, he dispatched his chief of staff Mustafa Bey with 3,000 men to reinforce the garrison of Tripoli. Hurshid himself remained in Yanina to supervise the last stages of the siege. Despite his rapid reaction, his plans ultimately failed: Vryonis and Köse Mehmed failed to suppress the revolt in Central Greece, while the reinforcements of Mustafa Bey were insufficient to save Tripoli, which fell to the Greeks under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodoros_Kolokotronis">Theodoros Kolokotronis</ref> after a prolonged <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fall_of_Tripolitsa">siege</ref>, on 23 September 1821. Despite the general massacre of the Muslim inhabitants, Hurshid's harem and a part of his treasure were saved. Finally, in January 1822, he killed Ali Pasha through treason, and sent his severed head to the Sultan, and his star seemed on the rise again. He assembled an army of 80,000 men (a huge number by Balkan standards) and was about to march in order to finally crush the Greek uprising, when disaster struck. His political enemies in Constantinople, alarmed at the fame and power he had achieved and the prestige that the successful ending of both Ali Pasha's and the Greek revolts would bring him, accused him of misappropriating a large part of Ali's treasure. Hurshid had sent 40,000,000 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Turkish_piastre">piasters</ref>, with a statement that they had been found in Ali's vaults, while the Sultan's ministers calculated Ali's fortune at over 500,000,000 piasters. When they asked him to send a detailed account, the offended Hurshid did not reply. Shortly after that, he was denounced for abuse of public treasure and fell in disgrace. He was removed from his positions, and replaced as <hi rend="italic">serasker</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mora valisi</hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahmud_Dramali_Pasha">Mahmud Dramali Pasha</ref>. Hurshid was ordered to remain in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larissa">Larissa</ref> to attend to the provisioning of Dramali's army.</p>
<p>When news began arriving in Constantinople of the failure of Dramali's expedition at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Dervenakia">Dervenakia</ref>, the Sultan ordered Hurshid to take matters in his own hand and salvage what he could of the situation. However, his opponents continued to plot against him, and agents were sent to kill him. Although he was informed of the threat to his person, Hurshid did not react. Instead, he committed suicide by taking <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poison">poison</ref> on 30 November 1822.</p>
</text>
