<text id="autogum_bio_doc456" title="Walter Calverley" shortTile="walter-calverley" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-11-29" dateModified="2019-10-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_Calverley" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Walter Calverley</head>For other people named Main Page, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page_(disambiguation)">Main Page (disambiguation)</ref>.
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canting_arms">Canting arms</ref> of Calverley: <hi rend="italic">Argent, a fess gules between three calves passant sable</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Walter Calverley</hi> (died 1605) was an English squire and murderer. His story became the basis of more than one literary work of the early 17th century.</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Walter Calverley was the eldest son and heir of William Calverley (d.1572) by his wife, Katherine Thorneholme, daughter of John Thorneholme of Haysthorpe, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yorkshire">Yorkshire</ref>. William Calverley was the son of Sir Walter Calverley and Anne Danby, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Danby">Sir Christopher Danby</ref> (d. 14 June 1571) and Elizabeth Neville, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Neville,_2nd_Baron_Latimer">Richard Neville, 2nd Baron Latimer</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>The Calverleys were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lords_of_the_manor">lords of the manors</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calverley">Calverley</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pudsey">Pudsey</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yorkshire">Yorkshire</ref>. His father died when he was a boy. He inherited land at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burley-in-Wharfedale">Burley-in-Wharfedale</ref>, Fagley, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Farsley">Farsley</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eccleshill,_West_Yorkshire">Eccleshill</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolton">Bolton</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seacroft">Seacroft</ref>; a relative of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Brooke,_10th_Baron_Cobham">William Brooke, 10th Baron Cobham</ref>, became his guardian.</p>
<p>He studied at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clare_College,_Cambridge">Clare Hall, Cambridge</ref> from 5 May 1579, matriculating on 1 October, but he was there only a short time and took no degree. He became engaged to the daughter of a neighbour in Yorkshire.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELee1886-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Marriage, crime and death</head>
<p>When Calverley visited <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, his guardian insisted on his breaking this engagement and on his marrying Philippa, a granddaughter of Lord Cobham. Calverley went back to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calverley_Hall">Calverley Hall</ref> with his wife, whom he disliked, and adopted a lifestyle revolving around drinking and gambling. He soon ran through all his money.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELee1886-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>On 23 April 1605, he received news that a relative, a student at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cambridge_University">Cambridge</ref>, had been arrested for a debt for which he himself was responsible. In a drunken frenzy, he rushed at his two eldest children, William and Walter, the former four years old and the latter 18 months (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baptism">baptised</ref> at Calverley on 4 October 1603) and killed them both; at the same time he stabbed his wife, but not fatally. He then rode off to a neighbouring village where a third infant son, Henry, was out at nurse, intending to kill him as well, but he was stopped on the road and taken before Sir John Savile, a magistrate, who committed him to prison at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wakefield">Wakefield</ref>. After some delay he was brought to trial at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York">York</ref> in August following; he declined to plead, and was therefore <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pressed_to_death">pressed to death</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York_Castle">York Castle</ref> on 5 August.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELee1886-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Aftermath</head>
<p>Calverley's widow remarried Sir Thomas Burton of Stokerston, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leicestershire">Leicestershire</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELee1886-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>His estates escaped forfeiture and descended to his surviving son Henry, later a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royalist">royalist</ref> and fined under the Commonwealth. He was the last of the family to reside regularly at Calverley Hall. He married, first, Elizabeth, daughter of John Moore of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grantham">Grantham</ref>; secondly, Joyce, daughter of Sir Walter Pye. He died on 1 January 1661, and was succeeded by a son Walter, who was knighted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_II_of_England">Charles II</ref> in consideration of his father's loyalty.</p>
<head>In literature</head>
<figure><caption>Title page of <hi rend="italic">A Yorkshire Tragedy</hi> (1608)</caption></figure>
<p>Calverley's position gave his crime wide notoriety. On 12 June Nathaniel Butter published a popular tract on the subject, which was followed on 24 August by an account of Calverley's death. A ballad was also issued by another publisher, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Pavier">Thomas Pavier</ref>, at the same time. Calverley's story was twice dramatised — first by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Wilkins">George Wilkins</ref> in <hi rend="italic">Miseries of Enforced Marriage</hi> (1607), and, secondly, in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Yorkshire_Tragedy">A Yorkshire Tragedy</ref></hi> which was first published by Pavier in 1608, under the title <hi rend="italic">A Yorkshire Tragedy - not so new as lamentable and true: written by W. Shakspeare</hi>. The latter was included in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Folios_and_Quartos_(Shakespeare)">third and fourth folios</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Shakespeare">William Shakespeare</ref>'s works (1664 and 1685), but is no longer considered to be his work (modern scholarship generally favouring <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Middleton">Thomas Middleton</ref>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTELee1886-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aphra_Behn">Aphra Behn</ref> reworked <hi rend="italic">The Miseries of Enforced Marriage</hi> into her 1676 play, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Town_Fop_or,_Sir_Timothy_Tawdry">The Town Fop or, Sir Timothy Tawdry</ref>.</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
</text>
