<text id="autogum_bio_doc609" title="Ulick na gCeann Burke, 1st Earl of Clanricarde" shortTile="ulick-na-gceann-burke" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-02-05" dateModified="2019-09-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ulick_na_gCeann_Burke%2C_1st_Earl_of_Clanricarde" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ulick na gCeann Burke, 1st Earl of Clanricarde</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Ulick na gCeann Burke</hi> (died 1544), 12th <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clanricarde">Clanricarde</ref> and <hi rend="bold">1st Earl of Clanricarde</hi> (styled MacWilliam, and na-gCeann, meaning "of the Heads," "having made a mount of the heads of men slain in battle which he covered up with earth"), was the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Mór_Burke">Richard Mór Burke</ref> the 9th <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clanricarde">Clanricarde</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-EB1911-1">[1]</ref> by a daughter of Madden of Portumna</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Ulick succeeded his father to the headship of his clan, and held vast estates in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_Galway">County Galway</ref>. In March 1541 he wrote to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VIII_of_England">Henry VIII</ref>, lamenting the degeneracy of his family, which had rebelled against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/England">England</ref> in the mid-14th century, and "which have been brought to Irish and disobedient rule by reason of marriage and nurseing[<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sic">sic</ref></hi>] with those Irish, sometime rebels, near adjoining to me," and placing himself and his estates in the king's hands. The same year he was present at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dublin">Dublin</ref>, when an act was passed making <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_VIII">Henry VIII</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_of_Ireland">King of Ireland</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-EB1911-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In 1543, in company with other Irish chiefs, he visited the King at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greenwich">Greenwich</ref> and made full submission in accordance with the King's policy of "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surrender_and_regrant">surrender and regrant</ref>". He was confirmed in the captainship and rule of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clanricarde">Clanricarde</ref>, and on 1 July 1543, he was created <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Clanricarde">Earl of Clanricarde</ref> and Baron of Dunkellin in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peerage_of_Ireland">peerage of Ireland</ref>. He was regranted the greater part of his former estates, with the addition of other lands. The grant of the English titles was conditional upon the abandonment of native titles, the adoptation of English customs and laws, the pledging of allegiance to the English crown, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apostasy">apostasy</ref> from the Roman Catholic Church, and conversion to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anglican_Church">Anglican Church</ref>. In his review of the  state of Ireland in 1553, Lord Chancellor Cusake stated "[t]he making of McWilliam earl of Clanricarde made all the country during his time quiet and obedient."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-EB1911-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>He did not live long to enjoy his new English dignities, but died shortly after returning to Ireland about March 1544. He is called by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Annalist_of_Loch_Cé">annalist of Loch Cé</ref> "a haughty and proud lord," who reduced many under his yoke, and by the Four Masters "the most illustrious of the English in Connaught."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-EB1911-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Marriages</head>
<p>Burke married three times, first to Grany or Grace, daughter of Mulrone O'Carroll, by whom he had <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Sassanach_Burke,_2nd_Earl_of_Clanricarde">Richard</ref>, who eventually succeeded him as Second <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Clanricarde">Earl of Clanricarde</ref>.  This marriage was the only one declared valid. He eventually divorced Grace and then married Honora, sister of Ulick de Burgh, but divorced her as well, marrying <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maire_Lynch">Maire Lynch</ref>, by whom he had John, who claimed the earldom in 1568.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-EB1911-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burke's_Peerage">Burke's Peerage</ref>, he had several other sons, Thomas "the Athlete", shot in 1545, Redmond "of the Broom", died 1595, and Edmund, died 1597.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEChisholm1911-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>As a result of his marriages and relationships there were a number of candidates contending for the titles of Clanricarde and Earl. The eventual successor was Ulick's eldest legitimate son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Sassanach_Burke">Richard Sassanach Burke</ref>, 2nd Earl of Clanricarde.</p>
</text>
