<text id="autogum_bio_doc389" title="Rufim Njeguš" shortTile="rufim-njegus" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-12-03" dateModified="2019-09-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rufim_Njegu%C5%A1" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rufim Njeguš</head>Not to be confused with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rufim_Boljević">Rufim Boljević</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Rufim Njeguš</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serbian_Cyrillic_alphabet">Serbian Cyrillic</ref>: Руфим Његуш; fl. 1594–1631) was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan_of_Cetinje">Metropolitan of Cetinje</ref> between 1594 and 1636. He succeeded the Metropolitan duo of Nikanor and Stevan (s. 1591–93). Rufim Njeguš and Metropolitan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visarion,_Metropolitan_of_Herzegovina">Visarion</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitanate_of_Herzegovina">of Trebinje</ref> (s. 1590–1602) aided the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banat_Uprising">Banat Uprising</ref> (1594). In 1595 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francesco_Antonio_Bertucci">Francesco Antonio Bertucci</ref> tried to convince Rufim to accept union with Catholic Church.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-umetnosti1950-1">[1]</ref> He was succeeded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mardarije_Kornečanin">Mardarije Kornečanin</ref> (s. 1637–59). Rufim is famous as being the first metropolitan who actively took part in armed confrontations with the Ottomans, leading Montenegrin army in three major battles in 1601, 1604 and 1613.</p>
<head>Battle of Lješkopolje (1604)</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanjak-bey">Sanjak-bey</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shkodër">Shkodër</ref>  Ali-beg Mimibegović led an army of 12,000 from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Podgorica">Podgorica</ref> and clashed with 400 Montenegrins in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lješanska_nahija">Lješanska nahija</ref>. Rufim reinforced them with 500 Katunjani during the day and sent dozens of small three-members groups, in total amount of 50 warriors to spy and to attack the opponent from rear. The battle lasted through whole night, when at the dawn Montenegrins launched a sudden charge surprising the enemy. Ali-beg was wounded and retreated with 3,500 casualties, while his second-in-command Šaban Ćehaja was killed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-forum1-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Battle of Kosov lug (1613)</head>
<p>Towards the end of September newly appointed Sanjak-bey of Shkodër Arslan-bey Balićević renewed attacks on Montenegrins, splitting his forces in two, and tasking first army with penetration to Cetinje and second army with suppressing rebellious forces around <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spuž">Spuž</ref>. Both armies failed, as the first one was stopped in Lješanska nahija again without reaching Cetinje, and the second one was defeated when Rufim personally led a side attack of 700 Katunjani in the aid of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piperi_(tribe)">Piperi</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bjelopavlići">Bjelopavlići</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rovčani">Rovčani</ref> forces which were already engaging enemy around the village of Kosov lug. The battle resulted in Sultan's official recognition of Montenegrin autonomy, by issuing a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beratli">berat</ref> which states that: "... no Turkish official, if not authorised by sultan , can enter Montenegro without the permission from Montenegrins themselves" <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-forum1-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>Although informations about his life are scarce, Rufim is one of better known Metropolitans of Montenegrin history from predynastic period. His long tenure is well remembered and he is often mentioned as a contemporary of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pajsije">Patriarch Pajsije</ref>. In his "History of Montenegro" Sima Sarajlija lists as one of his more memorable deeds that he:</p>
<p>This Metropolitan has done an exceptional deed for Orthodox Christianity and thus awoke the Serbdom with no small extent, by converting back to eastern religion <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuči">Kuči</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bratonožići">Bratonožići</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drekalovići">Drekalovići</ref>, from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholicism">Roman faith</ref> to which they were lured shortly before by Albanian priests, with whom they share a border and sibling relations</p>—<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sima_Milutinović_Sarajlija">Sima Milutinović Sarajlija</ref>, History of Montenegro<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref>
<p>It is, thus, possible that it was him, rather than Metropolitan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rufim_Boljević">Rufim Boljević</ref> who famously converted Kuči Vojvode <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lale_Drekalov">Lale Drekalov</ref>. Many authors, most notably <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marko_Miljanov">Marko Miljanov</ref>, cite Boljević as being the one, however the dates don't add up, since being mentioned in 1614, Lale precedes Boljević's tenure as Metropolitan by a couple of decades.</p>
</text>
