<text id="autogum_bio_doc765" title="Alice de la Roche" shortTile="alice-de-la-roche" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-11-16" dateModified="2019-08-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alice_de_la_Roche" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Alice de la Roche</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alice de la Roche, Lady of Beirut</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Regent of Beirut</hi> (died 1282<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>) was the wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_II_of_Beirut">John II of Ibelin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lordship_of_Beirut">Lord of Beirut</ref>, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kingdom_of_Jerusalem">Kingdom of Jerusalem</ref>. She was a daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guy_I_de_la_Roche">Guy I, Lord of Athens</ref>. Alice is sometimes referred to as <hi rend="bold">Alice of Athens</hi>. Alice was Regent of Beirut for her daughter Queen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabella_of_Ibelin_(1252–1282)">Isabella</ref> of Cyprus, during the latter's absence in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyprus">Cyprus</ref>.|.&lt;/ref&gt;</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>Alice was born on an unknown date. She was one of six children of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guy_I_de_la_Roche">Guy I de la Roche</ref>-sur-l'Ongon, Lord of Athens (1205–1263), and his wife, who was the daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_of_Briel">Hugh of Briel</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_of_Karytaina">Lord of Karytaina</ref> by an unnamed woman of the noble House of Villehardouin.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Cawley-Ibelin-2">[2]</ref> Her paternal grandfather was Otho I de la Roche-sur-l'Ongon, Lord of Athens. Her father Guy was created Duke of Athens in 1260 by King  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_IX_of_France">Louis IX of France</ref>.|</p>
<p>Alice had two brothers and three younger sisters:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_I_de_la_Roche">John I de la Roche</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_of_Athens">Duke of Athens</ref> (died 1280), succeeded his father as Duke in 1263. He died unmarried and childless.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_de_la_Roche">William de la Roche</ref> (died 1287), Duke of Athens, married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helena_Angelina_Komnene">Helena Angelina Komnene</ref>, by whom he had one son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guy_II_de_la_Roche">Guy II, Duke of Athens</ref>.</item>
<item>Marguerite de la Roche (died after 1293), married Henry I, Count of Vaudémont.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabella_de_la_Roche">Isabella de la Roche</ref>, married firstly, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geoffrey_of_Briel">Geoffrey of Briel</ref>, Lord of Karytaina. She married secondly, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_of_Brienne">Hugh of Brienne</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Count_of_Brienne">Count of Brienne</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lecce">Lecce</ref>, by whom she had a son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_V_of_Brienne">Walter of Brienne</ref>, who in turn married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeanne_de_Châtillon">Jeanne de Châtillon</ref> and had issue, and a daughter, Agnes of Brienne, wife of John, Count of Joigny. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary,_Queen_of_Scots">Mary, Queen of Scots</ref>, and Queen consort <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_Woodville">Elizabeth Woodville</ref> and her siblings were among Isabella's many descendants.</item>
<item>Catherine de la Roche, married Carlo di Lagonessa, Seneschal of Sicily.</item></list>
<head>Marriage and issue</head>
<p>In 1249/1250, Alice married John II of Ibelin, Lord of Beirut, the son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balian_of_Beirut">Balian of Ibelin</ref>, Lord of Beirut and Eschiva de Montfaucon de Montbéliard. He was the grandson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Ibelin,_the_Old_Lord_of_Beirut">John of Ibelin, the Old Lord of Beirut</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melisende_of_Arsuf">Melisende of Arsuf</ref>. In 1260, he led a massive raid alongside the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knights_Templars">Knights Templars</ref> into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galilee">Galilee</ref>. John and the Templars were defeated  near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiberias">Tiberias</ref> by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkmen_people">Turcomen</ref>. John was taken prisoner and later ransomed.</p>
<p>John and Alice had two daughters:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabella_of_Ibelin_(1252–1282)">Isabella of Ibelin</ref>, Lady of Beirut, Queen of Cyprus (1252- 1282/November 1283), married firstly King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_II_of_Cyprus">Hugh II of Cyprus</ref>, secondly Haymo Léstrange, and thirdly, Guillaume Bervais. All three marriages were childless.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eschive_d'Ibelin_(1253–1312)">Eschive of Ibelin</ref>, Lady of Beirut (1253–1312), married firstly, in 1274, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humphrey_of_Montfort_(died_1284)">Humphrey de Montfort</ref>, Lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tyre,_Lebanon">Tyre</ref>, by whom she had four children, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rupen_de_Montfort">Rupen de Montfort</ref>; she married secondly in 1291, Guy of Lusignan, Constable of Cyprus, by whom she had two children, King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_IV_of_Cyprus">Hugh IV of Cyprus</ref>, and Isabelle de Lusignan. Upon the death of her sister Isabella, who died without issue, Eschive inherited the lordship of Beirut. She unsuccessfully claimed the dukedom of Athens by right of her mother.</item></list>
<p>During her daughter Isabella's absence in Cyprus, from 1274–1277, Alice was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent">Regent</ref> of Beirut.</p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>Alice of Athens, Lady of Beirut, Regent of Beirut died in 1282. Her husband John had died in 1264.
Their numerous descendants included <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_de_Lusignan">Anne de Lusignan</ref>, King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_VIII_of_France">Charles VIII of France</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_of_France">Anne of France</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary,_Queen_of_Scots">Mary, Queen of Scots</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1308, her nephew Guy II, Duke of Athens died without heirs. Alice's daughter Eschive claimed the dukedom, but lost to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_V_of_Brienne">Walter V of Brienne</ref>, the son of Alice's sister Isabella.</p>
</text>
