<text id="autogum_bio_doc183" title="Two Leggings" shortTile="two-leggings" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-04-27" dateModified="2019-08-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Two_Leggings" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Two Leggings</head><figure><caption>Two Leggings captured by photographer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_S._Curtis">Edward S. Curtis</ref> in 1906</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Two Leggings</hi> was born between the years of 1846 and 1851. The actual date is not known because many Native Americans living free in the American West during the mid-19th century had no need to keep accurate records. His death is recorded as April 23, 1923 by William Wildschut, one of the men who created a biography (field manual) of his life. Two Leggings married his wife Ties Up Her Bundle around 1880 according to testimony given by Ties Up Her Bundle in 1924 at a hearing dictating who gained control of Two Leggings' capital. They never had their own children but they adopted Red Clay Woman, the daughter of his wife's sister. They later went on to adopt the son of Red Clay Woman, Amos Two Leggings also known as Sings to the Sweat Lodge. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Warrior Legacy</head>
<p>Two Leggings resided in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crow_Nation">Crow Nation</ref> with the rank of Pipe Holder, equal to platoon lieutenant.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> Once the extermination of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_bison">American bison</ref> began, the competition among the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plains_Indians">Plains Indians</ref> was at its fiercest. War became a struggle of life and death in the many plains societies. War was no trivial matter, in the societies it was a very spiritual matter. War required the proper ceremonies and occult assistance. Triumph in war was contingent on divine arrangements, war medicine, the bravery of the warrior, and the expertise they possessed. Owing to the constant state of war found in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Plains">Great Plains</ref>, death in conflict was a special honor, people who died young were thought to have had a weak sacred helper or that they did not abide by their sacred father. Warriors who lived into old age were believed to have very formidable spiritual helpers.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Two Leggings lived to be quite old, though it was deemed that he did not have a very strong spiritual helper due to the inadequacy of his spiritual manifestations. He eventually went onto buy War Medicine from Sees the Living Bull, but ultimately it did little to help him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Spirituality</head>
<p>Two Leggings conducted many raids before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crow_Nation">Crow Nation</ref> was confined to a reservation. Two Leggings was described as a very modest individual, documented by William Wildschut, in his field manual about Two Leggings. Two Leggings talked about both his triumphs and defeats during his raids against his band's enemies. One of Two Leggings' first raids he tried his luck because he went to battle without War Medicine. This raid almost cost him his life, he lost his horse and blanket, his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moccasin">Moccasin</ref>s and clothing were tattered, though he still held onto his gun and bow.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> Though his spiritual helper may have been considered overall not strong, he still had visions, that were deemed strong by his peers.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Sun Dance Experience</head>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sun_Dance">Sun Dance</ref> is a highly sacred event that occurred within the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plains_Indians">Plains Indian</ref> culture, as well as other indigenous groups in North America. As interaction with whites grew in the 19th century, in order to "civilize" the native peoples, certain practices like the Sun Dance were suppressed because it was determined to be too gruesome. Due to this suppression not everything is known about the Sun Dance. Two Leggings performed his first Sun Dance after his two cousins were killed in a raid against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheyenne">Cheyenne</ref>. His uncle Shows His Face was deranged with heartache over the loss of his two sons. Shows His Face asked a friend Puts Earth On Top Of His Head, to use his Sun Dance Medicine Bundle, which was particularly powerful. Two Leggings did not take part in the preparations of the ritual, while still mourning the loss of his two cousins. Once everything was prepared Two Leggings decided that he would be one of the dancers in the ceremony. He participated in the brutal ritual, and while dancing a skewer came loose and he began to bleed profusely. He tried to dance again but the sheer exhaustion kept him from continuing, only watching from the side while praying for his own vision. The next morning he was awoken and informed of Shows His Face's powerful vision, when asked if he had received a vision Two Leggings admitted that he did not. An elder spoke in a tender tone, explaining that after going through a Sun Dance everyone would acknowledge him as a Man.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
</text>
