<text id="autogum_bio_doc244" title="John Bacon (Loyalist)" shortTile="john-bacon-loyalist" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-05-14" dateModified="2019-03-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Bacon_%28Loyalist%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Bacon (Loyalist)</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">John Bacon</hi> (died April 3, 1783) (also "<hi rend="italic">Bloody John Bacon</hi>"), was a leader of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pine_Robbers">Pine Robbers</ref>, a band of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loyalist_(American_Revolution)">Loyalist</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guerrilla">guerrilla</ref> fighters who hid out in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pine_Barrens_(New_Jersey)">Pine Barrens</ref> of south-central <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Jersey">New Jersey</ref> and preyed upon <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriot_(American_Revolution)">Patriots</ref> toward the end of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Revolutionary_War">American Revolutionary War</ref>. The group was responsible for the October 1782 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long_Beach_Island_Massacre">Long Beach Island Massacre</ref>, which occurred after hostilities between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Kingdom_of_Great_Britain">Great Britain</ref> had been put on hold pending treaty negotiations. He and his band were relentlessly pursued thereafter. Bacon was killed the following March while resisting capture (considered by several historians to be the last casualty of the war).</p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>John Bacon's origins are not known.  He first appeared in public documents in 1775 as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roof_shingle">shingler</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monmouth_County,_New_Jersey">Monmouth County</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Province_of_New_Jersey">Province of New Jersey</ref> required to appear in local court for unpaid debts.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> Bacon was married and had two sons who resided with him in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pemberton,_New_Jersey">Pemberton, New Jersey</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Salter-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>The Pine Robbers</head>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Franklin">William Franklin</ref>, the royal governor of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Province_of_New_Jersey">New Jersey colony</ref>, helped organize <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Associators">associator</ref></hi> military units—including Bacon's Refugees</caption></figure>
<p>Bacon purportedly served at one point in the Patriot militia, but subsequently joined with the Loyalist side. He became a member of the "Board of Associated Loyalists" an organization of associators, which was chartered by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_III_of_the_United_Kingdom">King George III</ref> and overseen by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Franklin">William Franklin</ref>, British royal governor of the New Jersey Colony (and son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benjamin_Franklin">Benjamin Franklin</ref>). Franklin chose Bacon as the military leader of the "<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pine_Robbers">Pine Robbers</ref></hi>" (which later became known as "<hi rend="italic">The Refugees</hi>"), a guerrilla-style fighting unit which financed its operations through war-time plunder.  The organization's purpose was to conduct raids and to seize supplies from the Patriots. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> Bacon readily fulfilled the organization's mission by raiding ground transports, depots, ships, and Patriot homes (including those belonging to members of the Monmouth Militia).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Salter-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Bacon and his band of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partisan_(military)">marauders</ref> were involved in the October 1782 Long Beach Island Massacre, and the following December were in a skirmish at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cedar_Bridge_Tavern">Cedar Bridge Tavern</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Jersey">New Jersey</ref>. Bacon's subsequent death several months after this engagement is often characterized as the last casualty of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Revolutionary_War">American Revolutionary War</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>A skirmish at Manahawkin</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manahawkin,_New_Jersey">Manahawkin, New Jersey</ref> militiamen had heard rumors that Bacon and his men, now known as "The Refugees," were planning to raid the town. The local militia met on December 30, 1781 at Capitan Reuben Randolph's home to plan the town's defense. On the morning of December 31, Bacon and his men, totaling between 30 and 40, arrived from the direction of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barnegat_Township,_New_Jersey">Barnegat Township</ref>. Before the militiamen were fully organized, Bacon and his men opened fire, killing Lines Pangbon and wounding Sylvester Tilton.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
<head>Long Beach Island Massacre</head>
<p>On October 25, 1782, Bacon conspired with a Loyalist sympathizer who was working on the offloading of cargo from a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cutter_(ship)">cutter</ref> which had become stranded at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barnegat_Inlet">Barnegat Shoals</ref>, to hijack the operation.  He and his band stealthily murdered 19 men in their sleep, including Militia Captain Andrew Steelman. This attack, occurring after formal hostilities between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Britain">Great Britain</ref> had paused because of peace negotiations, was considered so atrocious that Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Livingston">William Livingston</ref> put a bounty of fifty pounds on Bacon's head.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Plunder-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Affair at Cedar Bridge</head>
<p>A gun battle involving Bacon and his men near the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cedar_Bridge_Tavern">Cedar Bridge Tavern</ref>, on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jersey_Shore">Jersey Shore</ref>, was the last documented conflict of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Revolutionary_War">American Revolutionary War</ref>. In December 1782, Captain Richard Shreve, heading a Patriot force from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burlington,_New_Jersey">Burlington</ref>, received word that Bacon and his troop were in the area.  They came upon Bacon and his men as they were camped out near a tavern overlooking the Cedar Bridge crossing. The Refugees fired upon Shreve and his men as they approached Cedar Bridge, wounding him and three others. Bacon was wounded along with four of his fighters, but he escaped. Several of his men, however, were captured.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Plunder-8">[8]</ref> The battle came to be known as "The Affair at Cedar Bridge<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Final confrontation and death</head>
<p>On March 31, 1783, Bacon was finally tracked down by armed forces of the new republic on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long_Beach_Island">Long Beach Island</ref> where he was spotted scavenging a shipwreck.  A search party of six men, led by Captain John Stewart, was sent out to find Bacon, who was found at the Rose Tavern. Stewart wrestled him to the ground before Bacon could grab his musket. Stewart stabbed Bacon with his bayonet and quickly shot him, causing his death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>Bacon's body was ceremoniously brought to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacobstown,_New_Jersey">Jacobstown</ref>, where the citizens were preparing a disrespectful burial in the middle of the road, when Bacon's brother arrived begging for a proper burial. His body was taken by his family to a cemetery in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arneytown,_New_Jersey">Arneytown</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>There is an annual re-enactment of the Affair at Cedar Bridge each December 27 at the Cedar Bridge Tavern.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></p>
</text>
