<text id="autogum_bio_doc123" title="Bridget Anne Kelly" shortTile="bridget-anne-kelly" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-01-10" dateModified="2019-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bridget_Anne_Kelly" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bridget Anne Kelly</head>For the American singer, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bridget_Kelly">Bridget Kelly</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Bridget Anne Kelly</hi> is the former Deputy Chief of Staff to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor_of_New_Jersey">Governor of New Jersey</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Christie">Chris Christie</ref>.
Kelly, a New Jersey native, grew up in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ramsey,_New_Jersey">Ramsey</ref> and graduated from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Immaculate_Heart_Academy">Immaculate Heart Academy</ref> in 1990.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> She graduated from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mount_St._Mary's_University">Mount St. Mary's University</ref> in 1994 with a bachelor of arts degree in political science.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nypost1-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Kelly began her government career by working as a legislative aide to Assemblyman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_C._Russo">David C. Russo</ref>, later becoming Russo's chief of staff.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nypost1-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> In 2010, Kelly became Director of Legislative Relations under Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Christie">Chris Christie</ref>. In April 2013, Christie appointed her to be his Deputy Chief of Staff.</p>
<p>On November 4, 2016, Kelly was convicted for her involvement in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Lee_lane_closure_scandal">"Bridgegate" affair</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref>  She was sentenced to 18 months imprisonment (later reduced to 13 months) on March 29, 2017.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Fort Lee lane closure scandal</head>
Main article: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Lee_lane_closure_scandal">Fort Lee lane closure scandal</ref>
<p>On November 4, 2016, Kelly was found guilty in connection with the four-day closures of entrance ramps to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Washington_Bridge">George Washington Bridge</ref> in the late summer of 2013, in part of what has been described as politically motivated retribution against the mayor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Lee,_New_Jersey">Fort Lee, New Jersey</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-zernicke-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>On August 13, 2013, Kelly sent an eight-word e-mail to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Wildstein">David Wildstein</ref>, a Christie appointee to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Board_of_commissioners">board of commissioners</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Port_Authority_of_New_York_and_New_Jersey">Port Authority of New York and New Jersey</ref>, that read, "Time for some traffic problems in Fort Lee."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> Wildstein responded to Kelly's e-mail: "Got it."  In a texting exchange the next day, Wildstein relayed to Kelly a text from Fort Lee Mayor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Sokolich">Mark Sokolich</ref> in which he complained about the traffic jam and said, "The bigger problem is getting kids to school. Please help. It's maddening." "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></p>
<p>On January 9, 2014, after the emails were disclosed, the governor announced that he had fired Kelly, calling her action "stupid" and "deceitful" and claiming her actions had caused him to mislead the public.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> That day, Kelly was named as a defendant in a federal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Class_action">class action</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lawsuit">lawsuit</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S._District_Court_for_the_District_of_New_Jersey">U.S. District Court for the District of New Jersey</ref> that cited a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conspiracy_(civil)">civil conspiracy</ref> and "willful, wanton, arbitrary, and egregious <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Official_misconduct">official misconduct</ref>".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref> In the wake of her firing, police established no parking zones outside of Kelly's home in Ramsey to keep press and gawkers away, while "no trespassing" signs were placed on the lawn of the home.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></p>
<p>When she received subpoenas for documents from the New Jersey legislative committee, Kelly's attorneys indicated she would not comply with the subpoenas, citing their clients' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fifth_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution">Fifth Amendment right</ref> against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-incrimination">self-incrimination</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution">Fourth Amendment right</ref> against unreasonable <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Search_and_seizure">search and seizure</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Stepien_lawyer_objects-17">[17]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Stepien_lawyer_invokes_fifth-18">[18]</ref> The committee voted to compel Kelly to produce the previously requested documents, instructing special counsel Reid Schar to "take all necessary steps" to enforce them.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref> But Superior Court Judge Mary Jacobson found no basis to force Kelly and Bill Stepien, the governor's two-time campaign manager, to comply with the subpoenas. The pair had objected to the requests, issued in January, asserting that being forced to identify and turn over records would violate their Fifth Amendment rights against self-incrimination. They called the committee's requests a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fishing_expedition">fishing expedition</ref>. The Court agreed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-20">[20]</ref></p>
<p>On May 1, 2015, Kelly was indicted on nine charges in connection with her involvement in the scandal.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-21">[21]</ref> She pleaded not guilty. Courts have ruled that evidence provided in discovery by the US Attorney cannot be made public. Courts also ruled that all materials used to prepare the so-called Mastro Report which exonerated the Christie administration must be turned over to the defense.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-22">[22]</ref> The state has denied Kelly's request for reimbursement of legal fees.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-23">[23]</ref></p>
<head>Conviction</head>
<p>On November 4, 2016, the jury in the "Bridgegate" trial returned guilty verdicts on all counts against Bridget Kelly and co-defendant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Baroni">Bill Baroni</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-24">[24]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-25">[25]</ref> On March 29, 2017, U.S. District Judge <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Susan_D._Wigenton">Susan D. Wigenton</ref> sentenced Kelly to 18 months in prison and 500 hours of community service.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-26">[26]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-27">[27]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-28">[28]</ref></p>
<p>On November 27, 2018, the Third Circuit Court of Appeals upheld the majority of the convictions, overturning the determination that Kelly and Baroni had violated the civil rights of travelers, finding there is no established civil right to interstate travel giving rise to a criminal conviction.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-29">[29]</ref> The court directed that Kelly and Baroni be re-sentenced on the remaining seven counts of the indictment.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-30">[30]</ref></p>
<p>On April 24, 2019, Kelly was sentenced to 13 months in federal prison for her role in the George Washington Bridge scandal. Kelly was originally sentenced to 18 months; it was reduced to 13 months after a federal appeals court tossed out some of her charges.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-31">[31]</ref></p>
<p>On June 28, 2019 the United States Supreme Court agreed to take up her case; her prison sentence was delayed pending its ruling. Political and legal commentators have noted this action by the Court as part of a continuingly "more stringent definition of the law" governing corruption cases involving political malfeasance.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-32">[32]</ref></p>
<p>Kelly is a divorced mother with four.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-33">[33]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-34">[34]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nypost1-2">[2]</ref></p>
</text>
