<text id="autogum_bio_doc768" title="Jeanne de Fougères, Countess of La Marche and of Angoulême" shortTile="jeanne-de-fougeres" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-05-05" dateModified="2019-02-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeanne_de_Foug%C3%A8res%2C_Countess_of_La_Marche_and_of_Angoul%C3%AAme" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Jeanne de Fougères, Countess of La Marche and of Angoulême</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jeanne de Fougères</hi> (died after 1273), was ruling <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suo_jure">suo jure</ref> <hi rend="bold">Lady of Fougères</hi> from 1256. She was the wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_XII_of_Lusignan">Hugh XII of Lusignan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Count_of_La_Marche">Count of La Marche</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Count_of_Angoulême">Count of Angoulême</ref>. Jeanne was responsible for the later additions and fortifications of the Chateau of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fougères">Fougères</ref> which provided a greater stability for the town. </p>
<figure><caption>Chateau of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fougères">Fougères</ref>, the birthplace of Jeanne de Fougères</caption></figure>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Jeanne was born at the Chateau of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fougères">Fougères</ref>, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brittany">Brittany</ref> on an unknown date, the only daughter and surviving child of Raoul III, seigneur of Fougères and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabelle_de_Craon">Isabelle de Craon</ref> (born 1212). Her paternal grandparents were Geoffrey, seigneur of Fougères and Mathilde de Porhoet, and her maternal grandparents were Amaury I, seigneur of Craon (1175–1226) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeanne_des_Roches">Jeanne des Roches</ref> (c. 1195- 28 September 1238), daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guillaume_des_Roches">Guillaume des Roches</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seneschal_of_Anjou">seneschal of Anjou</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marguerite_de_Sablé">Marguerite de Sablé</ref>. </p>
<head>Reign</head>
<p>Jeanne had a brother Jean de Fougères, but he died immediately after his birth on 6 December 1230. As no more sons were born to her mother, Jeanne became the heiress to her father's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lordship">lordship</ref> of Fougères, which she inherited <hi rend="italic">suo jure</hi> upon the death of her father on 24 February 1256. She thereafter held the title of <hi rend="bold">Dame de Fougères</hi>. That same year 1256, she issued orders for the expansion of the chateau of Fougères, adding the Melusine and Gobelin towers as well as fortifying the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Defensive_wall">ramparts</ref> and gates. Her efforts provided a greater stability for the town. </p>
<p>On 29 January 1254, Jeanne was married to Hugh XII de Lusignan, seigneur of Lusignan, Couhe, and Peyrat, Count of La Marche and Angoulême. She became the Countess of La Marche and Angoulême upon her marriage, which was recorded in the <hi rend="italic">Chronicon Savigniacense</hi> on 4 February 1254.</p>
<p>Shortly after 25 August 1270, Jeanne became a widow when her husband Hugh was killed while on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crusades">Crusade</ref> with King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_IX_of_France">Louis IX of France</ref>. Jeanne was granted the wardship of her minor children in Nov. 1271.  She died on an unknown date after 1273. She left a will dated 20 May 1269.  She was buried in Savigny.</p>
<p>Upon Jeanne's death, her eldest daughter Yolanda became the Heiress of Fougères.</p>
<head>Issue</head>
<p>Hugh and Jeanne together had six children:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yolande_de_Lusignan">Yolande de Lusignan</ref> (24 March 1257- 30 September 1314), <hi rend="italic">suo jure</hi> Countess of La Marche, Heiress of Fougères, married firstly Helie-Rudel, seigneur of Pons, by whom she had issue; and secondly Robert, seigneur of Mathe.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_XIII_of_Lusignan">Hugh XIII of Lusignan</ref>, Count of La Marche and Angoulême (25 June 1259- 1 November 1303), on 1 April 1276 married Beatrice of Burgundy. Their marriage was childless.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guy_of_Lusignan,_Count_of_Angoulême">Guy I de Lusignan</ref> (died 1308), Count of La Marche and Angoulême, died unmarried and without legitimate issue.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeanne_of_Lusignan">Jeanne of Lusignan</ref> (1260- 13 April 1323), married firstly Bernard Ezi III, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_of_Albret">Lord of Albret</ref>, by whom she had two daughters; she married secondly Sir Piers de Geneville of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trim_Castle">Trim</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludlow_Castle">Ludlow</ref>, by whom she had another three daughters, including the eldest <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_de_Geneville">Joan de Geneville</ref>, who in her turn married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_de_Mortimer,_1st_Earl_of_March">Roger de Mortimer, 1st Earl of March</ref>.</item>
<item>Isabelle de Lusignan (died 1309), before 1288 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognac">Cognac</ref> married Jean de Vesci. She later became a nun at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fontevrault_Abbey">Fontevrault Abbey</ref></item>
<item>Marie de Lusignan (died 1322), in 1288 married Etienne II, Count of Sancerre.</item></list>
<head>Ancestry</head>
</text>
