<text id="autogum_bio_doc221" title="Eyo Honesty II" shortTile="eyo-honesty-ii" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-05-14" dateModified="2019-08-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eyo_Honesty_II" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Eyo Honesty II</head><p><hi rend="bold">King Eyo Honesty II</hi> was the ruler of Creek Town from approximately 1835<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Henshaw-1">[1]</ref> to 1858 when he died.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hackett-2">[2]</ref> Creek Town was part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Calabar">Old Calabar</ref> region in the Bight of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Biafra">Biafra</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nair-3">[3]</ref> Old Calabar was a series of towns up the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cross_River_(Nigeria)">Cross River</ref>, which is in the Southeast edge of present-day <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nigeria">Nigeria</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nair-3">[3]</ref> Honesty is an example of African agency in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlantic_Slave_Trade">Atlantic Slave Trade</ref> because he was a strong, savvy, and intelligent leader who worked with the Europeans instead of against them, which brought about changes that would forever affect the region.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Henshaw-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Early life</head>
<p>Although his exact date of birth is unknown, Eyo was cited to have been born in 1788 by an epitaph located on a tower of the Creek Town Presbyterian Church.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Henshaw-1">[1]</ref> As a child, Eyo served as a cabin boy to English traders in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triangle_Trade">Triangle Trade</ref> network.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nair_a-4">[4]</ref> It was during this time that he learned to speak and write the English language.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nair_a-4">[4]</ref> He also learned the ways of the slave trade and how to do business which would benefit him as a ruler later on in life.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nair_a-4">[4]</ref> After his father lost the throne, his family fell upon hard times and Eyo found himself in the employment of his father's rival, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Duke_Ephraim">Great Duke Ephraim</ref>, after his father died in 1820.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nair_a-4">[4]</ref>  Working for the duke in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_Town">Duke Town</ref>, another town in the Calabar region, allowed him to improve his English and trade skills while establishing himself.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nair_b-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Coming to power</head>
<p>Honesty's father, Eyo Nsa (Eyo I), ruled Creek Town before him but there was a break between them caused by legitimacy claims to the throne.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nair_a-4">[4]</ref> This ultimately resulted in Eyo I being removed from power as the Great Duke Ephraim made claims over the entire Calabar region.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nair_a-4">[4]</ref> Eyo, while serving in Duke Town, began to contact distant family in an effort to get them to come back to Creek Town and re-establish a lineage.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> In 1834, the Eyo II house was formed and the Great Duke Ephraim died allowing Eyo to be crowned in 1835 or 1837, the date is uncertain.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hackett-2">[2]</ref> His rule of the region would be marked with political agency through cooperation instead of confrontation with the Europeans.</p>
<head>European interaction</head>
<p>Honesty welcomed the Europeans with open arms instead of fighting them with everything he had, like some rulers in the area did and had done.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Henshaw-1">[1]</ref>  He saw them as educated, learned men who could help him establish a stronger political hold in the region through economic power.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Henshaw-1">[1]</ref>  Eyo had experience with white traders from the travels of his youth and he continued his connections through the slave trade network that had been in place for decades before him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nair_a-4">[4]</ref> He had dealt in slaves from both selling and buying as he was trying to employ enough men to run his aspiring palm oil industry.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nair_b-5">[5]</ref> His relationships with these "super-cargoes", huge trading outfits of the Triangular Trade Network, were well fostered and even gained him the name "Honesty" for his fair trade policies and willingness to work with the European traders.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> However, in 1842 a Commander Raymond issued Eyo Honesty II and King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eyamba_V">Eyamba V</ref>, another ruler in the region, papers that negotiated the end of the slave trade.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nair_c-8">[8]</ref>  On 4 December 1842, Honesty returned the signed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-Slave_Trade_Treaty">Anti-Slave Trade Treaty</ref> to Raymond but took the opportunity to expand the economic market of Creek Town.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Nair_c-8">[8]</ref> To compensate for the loss of slave trade Eyo invited the Europeans into his lands to set up industries that would diversify the economy. Such industries to come would be cotton, coffee, sugar cane, and an immense increase in palm oil which had existed alongside of the slave trade.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Religion</head>
<p>With the invite extended to the Europeans, missionaries were some of the first to come. These people coming to do "God's work" would influence the politics of the region more than any of the economic changes in the region. In 1846 the first missionaries arrived in Creek Town,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hackett-2">[2]</ref> these missionaries were the precursors to the Presbyterian Church, previously mentioned, that sports Eyo's epitaph.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Henshaw-1">[1]</ref>  Upon their arrival Eyo was cited saying, "Now I am sure God will love and bless me, for I am very glad you come with this book."<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref>  Although Honesty's kingdom was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Efik_mythology">Efik</ref>, a pagan religion, Eyo still appreciated and respected the missionaries and their Christianity.  His respect for the missionaries ultimately resulted in law changes over his domain.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hackett_a-11">[11]</ref> Such reforms include: the elimination of human sacrifice, the allowance of widows and twins to return to Creek Town, the elimination of "Ekpenyong" the household idol of the region, and the ending of Sunday markets.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Hackett_a-11">[11]</ref>  In addition to altering laws, Eyo also translated the church services put on by the missionaries, mainly Rev. Waddell.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref>  Eyo maintained his agency by collaborating with the Europeans who encountered his kingdom and left a reputation that is best stated in Religion in Calabar by Rosalind I.J. Hackett, "The Efik, epitomized by King Eyo Honesty, showed the capacity to adapt internally, to 'modernize' without becoming 'westernized' or 'Christianized'".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref></p>
</text>
