<text id="autogum_bio_doc401" title="James Stewart, Earl of Arran" shortTile="james-stewart-earl" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-08-31" dateModified="2019-10-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Stewart%2C_Earl_of_Arran" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>James Stewart, Earl of Arran</head>
<figure><caption>Arms of James Stewart</caption></figure>
<p>Captain <hi rend="bold">James Stewart, Earl of Arran</hi> (died 1595) was created <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Arran">Earl of Arran</ref> by the young King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_I_of_England">James VI</ref>, who wrested the title from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Hamilton,_3rd_Earl_of_Arran">James Hamilton, 3rd Earl of Arran</ref>. He rose to become <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chancellor_of_Scotland">Lord Chancellor of Scotland</ref> and was eventually murdered in 1595.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>He was the second son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Stewart,_2nd_Lord_Ochiltree">Andrew Stewart, 2nd Lord Ochiltree</ref>, by his wife Agnes, the daughter of John Cunningham, 5th of Capringtoun, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayrshire">Ayrshire</ref>. Stewart's sister, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret_Knox">Margaret</ref>, was married to the reformer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Knox">John Knox</ref>.</p>
<p>In April 1573, James was sent as a "pledge" or hostage to England for the security of the English army and artillery sent to the "Lang Siege" of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edinburgh_Castle">Edinburgh Castle</ref>, which was held by supporters of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Queen_of_Scots">Mary Queen of Scots</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent_Morton">Regent Morton</ref> gave him £55 for his expenses in England.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> He was Captain of the Royal Guard of James VI, served with the Dutch forces in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eighty_Years'_War">the Netherlands against the Spanish</ref>, and returned to Scotland in 1579.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-EB1911-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>James quickly became a favourite of the young king, and in 1580 was made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gentleman_of_the_Bedchamber">Gentleman of the Bedchamber</ref>. He was a follower of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esmé_Stewart,_1st_Duke_of_Lennox">Esmé Stewart</ref>, and in January 1580 he accused the former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent_Morton">Regent Morton</ref>, still the effective power in Scotland, of participation in the murder of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Stuart,_Lord_Darnley">Henry Stuart, Lord Darnley</ref>. Stewart was rewarded as Tutor of Arran, with powers over the earldom of the mentally-ill <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Hamilton,_3rd_Earl_of_Arran">James Hamilton, 3rd Earl of Arran</ref>, then made Earl of Arran on 22 April 1581. He also claimed the position of second person in the land through being nearest to the king by descent, other than the now-insane third earl.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-EB1911-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In July he married Elizabeth Stewart, the divorced former wife of the King's great-uncle, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Stewart,_1st_Earl_of_March">Robert Stewart</ref>, once <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Lennox">Earl of Lennox</ref> and now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_March">Earl of March</ref>. Elizabeth, the Countess of Arran, born 1549, was the daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Stewart,_4th_Earl_of_Atholl">John Stewart, 4th Earl of Atholl</ref>.</p>
<head>The Lennox-Arran administration</head>
<p>Esmé Stewart was made Earl, then <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duke_of_Lennox">Duke, of Lennox</ref>, and he and Arran became partners in government, and rivals for the supremacy.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-EB1911-2">[2]</ref>
Their government of Scotland, and their correspondence with France and Spain, made them unpopular in England and with the "ultra-Protestant" sector at home, although the young King greatly admired Lennox and enjoyed his company.</p>
<head>The Ruthven raid</head><p>
In August 1582 Lennox and Arran held the Privy Council at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perth,_Scotland">Perth</ref>, and then returned to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dalkeith_Palace">Dalkeith Palace</ref> near Edinburgh. James VI was invited to stay hunting in Perthshire, and he was taken at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huntingtower_Castle">Huntingtower Castle</ref> by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Gowrie">Earl of Gowrie</ref> and his political faction on 22 August 1582, a kidnap known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruthven_Raid">Ruthven Raid</ref>. The next day they gave the King their supplication or mandate, which stated;</p><p>We have suffered now about the space of two years such false accusations, calumnies, oppressions and persecutions, by the means of the Duke of Lennox and him who is called the Earl of Arran, that the like of their insolencies and enormities were never heretofore born with in Scotland.</p><p> Arran went to Huntingtower and was arrested by the raiders. Lennox was sent in exile to France and died. Gowrie ran Scotland for ten months, after issuing an indictment against Lennox and Arran that included the detail that the Countess of Arran was "a vile and impudent woman, over famous for her monstrous doings, not without suspicion of the devilish magical art." Arran was permitted to attend some council meetings to bolster support for the new regime.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Arran had obtained a quantity of jewels belonging to James Vi, or to his mother, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary,_Queen_of_Scots">Mary, Queen of Scots</ref>. On 28 May 1583 his wife Elizabeth Stewart, returned sets of pearl, ruby, and diamond buttons, to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Gray,_6th_Lord_Gray">Master of Gray</ref>, who was master of the king's wardrobe. Later, in 1585, they returned more royal jewels, including the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_H_of_Scotland">Great H of Scotland</ref>".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>The Arran supremacy</head>
<p>Arran assembled a force of 12,000 men and regained power in July 1583,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-EB1911-2">[2]</ref> an ascendancy that would last for two years, and the Ruthven Raiders and their followers were banished to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newcastle_upon_Tyne">Newcastle upon Tyne</ref>. Gowrie was executed. After May 1584, Arran was always recorded first in the lists of those attending the Scottish Privy Council. He became governor of Edinburgh Castle, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provost_(civil)#Scotland">provost</ref> of the city, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lieutenant-general">lieutenant-general</ref> of the royal army. He acted against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Presbyterian">Presbyterian</ref> wing of the Scottish church, and the banished lords of the Ruthven Raid, who had returned to assault <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stirling_Castle">Stirling Castle</ref>. The role of his wife in the administration also attracted the censure of Edinburgh <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kirk">Kirk</ref> ministers.</p>
<p>Arran's rule was undermined in part by the machinations of his own diplomat in London, the young <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Gray,_6th_Lord_Gray">Master of Gray</ref>. By February 1585, Elizabeth opened two lines of communication in Scotland, one with Arran and another with the Master.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Arran fell from power after a border incident when the Englishman Francis Russell, son of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_Russell,_2nd_Earl_of_Bedford">second Earl of Bedford</ref>, was killed with a "shot from a dag" on 27 July 1585. Arran was accused of involvement by the English ambassador, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Wotton">Nicholas Wotton</ref> and James VI on first hearing the news had offered to send Arran as a prisoner to England.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> Instead Arran was imprisoned at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Andrews_Castle">St Andrews Castle</ref> and then placed in house arrest at his own <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kinneil_House">Kinneil House</ref>. One account says he went from Kinneil to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayr">Ayr</ref> and embarked on a boat with the royal jewels including the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mirror_of_Great_Britain">Great H of Scotland or 'Kingis Eitche'</ref>, but was forced to give the jewels to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Home,_1st_Earl_of_Dunbar">George Home</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>He was unable to prevent the Banished Lords of the Ruthven Raid returning from England, seizing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stirling_Castle">Stirling Castle</ref> on 4 November 1586, and declaring him a traitor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-EB1911-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Retirement and death</head>
<p>Avoiding plans for his banishment, and despite being ordered to leave the country, he spent the rest of his life in retirement in Ayrshire.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> He did however remain in communication with James, and may have carried out some secret missions for him.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-EB1911-2">[2]</ref> In December 1592 Stewart came to Holyroodhouse and met the king by the kennels. He then entered the presence chamber where some called him 'Lord Chancellor' and then met <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_of_Denmark">Anne of Denmark</ref> and kissed her hand. However, James let it be proclaimed in churches that he would not employ Stewart again.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>He was murdered by Sir <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Douglas_of_Parkhead">James Douglas of Parkhead</ref>, nephew of Regent Morton, on 5 December 1595.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
</text>
