<text id="autogum_bio_doc251" title="William Devaynes" shortTile="william-devaynes" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-02-18" dateModified="2019-06-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Devaynes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>William Devaynes</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">William Devaynes</hi> (baptised 1730 – 29 November 1809) was an Africa trader, London banker, Government contractor, director of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_India_Company">East India Company</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African_Company_of_Merchants">Africa Company</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Globe_Insurance_Company">Globe Insurance Company</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Hospital_(La_Providence)">French Hospital</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> and also five times <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_East_India_Company_directors">Chairman of the East India Company</ref>.  He was also for more than 26 years an undistinguished <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member_of_Parliament">Member of Parliament</ref> in turn for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barnstaple_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Barnstaple</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winchelsea_(UK_Parliament_constituency)">Winchelsea</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Huguenot origins</head>
<p>Devaynes was baptised at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Martin-in-the-Fields">St Martin-in-the-Fields</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westminster">Westminster</ref> 25 October 1730. He was the fifth of six children baptised there for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huguenot">Huguenot</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peruke">peruke</ref> maker John Devaynes and his wife Mary, only surviving child of London's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City_Remembrancer">City Remembrancer</ref>, William Barker.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-histparl-william-devaynes-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>An elder brother, John Devaynes (1726-1801), was apothecary to King George III and Queen Charlotte from 1761 to 1795. He appears in Boswell's Life of Johnson as "that ever-cheerful companion Mr Devaynes, apothecary to his Majesty" and was the Devaynes of Messrs Devaynes &amp; Hingeston, court apothecaries, married to Juliana sister of Chambre Hallowes, son-in-law of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Lovett_Pearce">Edward Lovett Pearce</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-histparl-william-devaynes-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>His first wife, Jane Wintle, provided a daughter (Harriott Augusta born 1773 who married Thomas Monsell) and a son also William Devaynes, born September 1783, who had children but died just 12 months after his father, 8 December 1810, aged 27.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-histparl-william-devaynes-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Mary Wileman, his second wife whom he married 3 February 1806, was said to be 60 years younger than he was.  He is reported to have made a settlement on her by which it was in her interest to keep him alive as long as she could and that proved to be almost four years. He died 29 November 1809 in his 80th year.Years later on 13 April 1813 at Marylebone Mary married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serjeant-at-law">Serjeant</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Wilde,_1st_Baron_Truro">Thomas Wilde</ref> who late in life was made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Chancellor">Lord Chancellor</ref> and 1st Lord Truro. She bore Wilde a daughter and two sons.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-histparl-william-devaynes-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Devaynes was also survived by an illegitimate daughter and grandson, William Devaynes of Liverpool.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-histparl-william-devaynes-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Africa</head>
<p>He was a director of The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African_Company_of_Merchants">African Company of Merchants</ref>. During Parliament's discussion of the slave trade Devaynes made various statements about West Africa:</p>
that there "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sugar#Modern_history">sugar</ref> grew almost spontaneously";<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref>
that he had lately returned from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gold_Coast_(British_colony)">Gold Coast</ref>;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref>
that he had long experience as an agent in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dahomey">Dahomey</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> and the Kingdom of Dahomey he described as the most oppressive tyranny on earth.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref>
<p>It seems he spent his early years in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sierra_Leone">Sierra Leone</ref>; in his will he made provision for a mulatto daughter.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-histparl-william-devaynes-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Banker</head>
<p>Banking was his core occupation. After he had risen to senior partner his firm, which operated from 39 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pall_Mall,_London">Pall Mall, London</ref>, was known as Devaynes, Dawes and Noble. Devaynes died a rich man. However his estate remained a partner in the bank and a year after his death his banking house was bankrupt. Consequential litigation involving his heirs was to persist for 30 years after his death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-histparl-william-devaynes-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Clayton's case</head>
<p>Part of the litigation gave rise to <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">the rule in Clayton's case</hi></hi> still commonly applied in the 21st century arising from the judgment by Sir William Grant in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Devaynes_v_Noble">Devaynes v Noble</ref>. Devaynes in this case was the son 1783-1810 and Noble was his father's former partner in the bank. Clayton was a depositor of the failed bank who hoped for funds from the deceased partner's estate.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>India</head>
<p>Devaynes was active in the East India Company being chosen by his fellow members of the court of directors to be chairman five separate years. He was a friend of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warren_Hastings">Warren Hastings</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-histparl-william-devaynes-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>American wars</head>
<p>Between 1776 and 1782 Devaynes and MPs <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Henniker,_1st_Baron_Henniker">John Henniker</ref> (1724-1803) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_George_Wombwell,_1st_Baronet">George Wombwell</ref> (1734-1780) together with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Wheler">Edward Wheler</ref> (1732-1784) of Wheler Higginson &amp; Co held army victualling contracts for 12,000, sometimes 14,000 men. Like Devaynes Wombwell and Wheler were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_East_India_Company_directors">directors of the East India Company</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-histparl-william-devaynes-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Parliament</head>
<p>In the House he invariably voted with the Government. He spoke very rarely.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-histparl-william-devaynes-3">[3]</ref></p>
</text>
