<text id="autogum_bio_doc090" title="Luis A. Aguilar" shortTile="luis--aguilar" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-12-11" dateModified="2019-02-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luis_A._Aguilar" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Luis A. Aguilar</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Luis A. Aguilar</hi> is an American lawyer and former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S._government">U.S. government</ref> official.</p>
<p>He was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democratic</ref> commissioner of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S._Securities_and_Exchange_Commission">U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission</ref> (SEC) from July 31, 2008, until June 2015 (when his term expired). He had been appointed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States">U.S. President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref> on March 31, 2008, and confirmed by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Senate">U.S. Senate</ref> on June 27, 2008; he was sworn in as a commissioner on July 31, 2008.</p>
<head>Early life and education</head>
<p>Aguilar was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuba">Cuba</ref> and emigrated to the United States in the 1960s.</p>
<p>He is a graduate of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Georgia_School_of_Law">University of Georgia School of Law</ref>, and also received a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_Laws">Master of Laws</ref> degree in taxation from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emory_University">Emory University</ref>. He had earlier earned a bachelor's degree from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgia_Southern_University">Georgia Southern University</ref>.</p>
<head>Career</head>
<p>Prior to his appointment as an SEC commissioner, Aguilar was a partner with the international law firm of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McKenna_Long_&amp;_Aldridge">McKenna Long &amp; Aldridge</ref>, specializing in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Securities_law">securities law</ref>. During his career, his practice included matters pertaining to general corporate and business law, international transactions, investment companies and investment advisers, securities law, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corporate_finance">corporate finance</ref>. He also focused on issues related to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corporate_governance">corporate governance</ref>, public and private offerings (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Initial_public_offering">initial public offerings</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secondary_market_offering">secondary market offerings</ref>), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mergers_and_acquisitions">mergers and acquisitions</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mutual_fund">mutual funds</ref>, investment advisers, broker-dealers, and other aspects of federal and state securities laws and regulations.</p>
<p>Aguilar's previous experience includes serving as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_counsel">general counsel</ref>, executive vice president, and corporate secretary of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Investment_management">investment management</ref> company <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Invesco">Invesco</ref>, with responsibility for all legal and compliance matters regarding Invesco Institutional. He also was Invesco's managing director for Latin America in the late 1990s.</p>
<p>His career also includes tenure as a partner at several national law firms and as an attorney at SEC.</p>
<p>Aguilar's term at the SEC expired in June 2015.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Other activities</head>
<p>He has been active in numerous civic and business associations. From May 2005 to May 2007, he chaired the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin_American_Association">Latin American Association</ref> (LAA), a non-profit organization. He has been active with national organizations, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hispanic_National_Bar_Association">Hispanic National Bar Association</ref>. In 2002, Aguilar was co-chair of the association's annual convention and also served as regional president (for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgia_(U.S._state)">Georgia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alabama">Alabama</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mississippi">Mississippi</ref>) (2002–2006), chair of its financial committee (2003–2005), and a member of its board of governors (since 2002). In addition, he served as the president of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hispanic_National_Bar_Foundation">Hispanic National Bar Foundation</ref> (September 2006 – July 2008).</p>
<p>Aguilar serves as sponsor of the SEC's Hispanic Employment Committee and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African_American_Council">African American Council</ref>.</p>
<head>Honors</head>
<p>Aguilar was named by <hi rend="italic">Hispanic Business</hi> magazine in 2006 as one of the "100 Influential" Hispanics in the United States. Additionally, he was named Member of the Year in 2005 and the Atlanta Hispanic Businessman of the Year in 1994 by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgia_Hispanic_Chamber_of_Commerce">Georgia Hispanic Chamber of Commerce</ref>.</p>
<p>He received the MALDEF's "Excellence in Leadership" Award in April 2005. He was also named the 2005 Latino Attorney of the Year by the Hispanic National Bar Association.</p>
<p>In January 2007, Aguilar received the Justice <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Benham_(judge)">Robert Benham</ref> Award for Community Service by the Chief Justice's Commission on Professionalism of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supreme_Court_of_Georgia_(U.S._state)">Supreme Court of Georgia</ref>.</p>
<head>Personal life</head>
<p>He is married to Denise Traylor Aguilar who hails from Roanoke, Alabama.</p>
</text>
