<text id="autogum_bio_doc446" title="John May (bishop)" shortTile="john-bishop" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-06-13" dateModified="2019-10-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_May_%28bishop%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John May (bishop)</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">John May</hi> (Meye) (died 1598) was an English academic and churchman, who became <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Carlisle">bishop of Carlisle</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was a native of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suffolk">Suffolk</ref> and brother of  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_May_(theologian)">William May</ref>. He matriculated as a pensioner of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queens'_College,_Cambridge">Queens' College, Cambridge</ref>, on 2 May 1544. He was appointed bible-clerk of his college, and in 1550 proceeded B.A., being elected fellow in 1550.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> He commenced M.A. in 1553, and acted as bursar of the college during 1553, 1554, and 1555. Queens' was split in religious sympathies in the Marian period, and May belonged to the Catholic group rather than the reformers.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>At midsummer 1557, he was ordained priest, and on 16 November following he was instituted to the rectory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aston_Sandford">Aston Sandford</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buckinghamshire">Buckinghamshire</ref>, owned by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_de_Vere,_17th_Earl_of_Oxford">Edward de Vere</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> resigning in 1558. In 1559 he was elected to the mastership of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catharine_Hall,_Cambridge">Catharine Hall, Cambridge</ref>. In 1560 he commenced B.D., and was collated to the rectory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long_Stanton_St._Michael">Long Stanton St. Michael</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cambridgeshire">Cambridgeshire</ref>. In 1562 Archbishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_Parker">Matthew Parker</ref> collated him to the rectory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Creake">North Creake</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norfolk">Norfolk</ref>; and he held also the moiety of the rectory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darfield,_South_Yorkshire">Darfield</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yorkshire">Yorkshire</ref>. About 1564 he obtained a canonry of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ely_Cathedral">Ely</ref>, which he held until May 1582. Also, in 1564 he was created D.D.</p>
<p>In 1565 he was nominated one of the Lent preachers at court. On 26 September in that year he was collated by Archbishop Parker to the rectory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Dunstan-in-the_East">St. Dunstan-in-the East</ref>, London, which he vacated in January 1574. He was admitted to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeaconry_of_the_East_Riding_of_Yorkshire">archdeaconry of the East Riding of Yorkshire</ref> by proxy on 3 August 1569, in person on 8 October 1571, and retained it until the end of 1588. He served the office of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vice-chancellor_of_the_University_of_Cambridge">vice-chancellor of the University of Cambridge</ref> for the year from November 1569, and was in a commission to visit <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King's_College,_Cambridge">King's College, Cambridge</ref>, in a state of confusion over the conduct of Dr. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Baker_(Provost)">Philip Baker</ref>, the Provost.</p>
<p>Through the influence of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Talbot,_6th_Earl_of_Shrewsbury">George Talbot, 6th Earl of Shrewsbury</ref>, May was raised to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/See_of_Carlisle">see of Carlisle</ref>, being consecrated on 29 September 1577. He obtained the Queen's licence to hold his other preferments <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In_commendam">in commendam</ref></hi>, but had long-term financial troubles. From his correspondence with Shrewsbury, he appears to have taken a serious interest in Scottish affairs. On 15 February 1593, the Queen presented William Holland to the rectory of North Creake, which May still held, and there arose a suit in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen's_bench">Queen's bench</ref>; it was held that the rectory might be treated as void by reason of May having been subsequently inducted to Darfield.</p>
<p>May died at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rose_Castle">Rose Castle</ref> on 15 February 1598, being about seventy years of age. He was buried at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlisle,_Cumbria">Carlisle</ref>, according to the parish register of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dalston,_Cumbria">Dalston, Cumbria</ref>, a few hours after his death, which was probably caused by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plague_(disease)">plague</ref>.</p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>May wrote some plays, now lost, which were acted by the members of Queens' College in 1551 and 1553. He was concerned in the compilation of the statutes given to the university by Elizabeth in 1570. Among the Tanner manuscripts in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodleian_Library">Bodleian Library</ref> are some notes of a sermon which he preached at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul's_Cross">Paul's Cross</ref> in 1565.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>His wife was Amy, daughter of William Vowel of Creake Abbey, Norfolk, and widow of John Cowel of Lancashire. By her he had issue: John of Shouldham, Norfolk, who married Cordelia, daughter of Martin Bowes of Norfolk; Elizabeth, wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Bird_(canon)">Richard Bird</ref>, D.D.; Alice, wife of Richard Burton of Burton, Yorkshire; and Anne, wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Pilkington_(1568%3F-1631)">Richard Pilkington</ref>, D.D., rector of Hambleden, Buckinghamshire.</p>
</text>
