<text id="autogum_bio_doc269" title="Kekuʻiapoiwa II" shortTile="kekuiapoiwa-ii" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-05-25" dateModified="2019-08-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keku%CA%BBiapoiwa_II" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kekuʻiapoiwa II</head>"Kekuiapoiwa" redirects here. For her aunt, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kekuʻiapoiwa_I">Kekuʻiapoiwa I</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Kekuʻiapoiwa II</hi> was a Hawaiian chiefess and the mother of the king <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamehameha_I">Kamehameha I</ref>.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>She was named after her aunt Kekuʻiapoiwa Nui (also known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kekuiapoiwa_I">Kekuʻiapoiwa I</ref>), the wife of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kekaulike">Kekaulike</ref> of Maui.</p>
<p>Her father was High Chief <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haae-a-Mahi">Haʻae</ref>, the son of Chiefess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalanikauleleiaiwi">Kalanikauleleiaiwi</ref> and High Chief Kauaua-a-Mahi of the Mahi family of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kohala,_Hawaii">Kohala district</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawaii_(island)">Hawaiʻi island</ref>, and brother of Alapainui. Her mother was Princess Kekelakekeokalani-a-Keawe (also known as Kekelaokalani), daughter of the same Kalanikauleleiaiwi and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keaweʻīkekahialiʻiokamoku">Keaweʻīkekahialiʻiokamoku</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alii_Aimoku_of_Hawaii">king of Hawaii</ref>. Her mother had been sought after by many who wished to marry into the Keawe line. She was the niece of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alapainui">Alapainui</ref> through both her father and mother.</p>
<p>She married the High Chief <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keōua">Keōua</ref> to whom she had been betrothed since childhood. Through her double grandmother Kalanikauleleiaiwi, Keōua's own paternal grandmother, she was the double cousin of Keōua. When her uncle was staying at Kohala superintending the collection of his fleet and warriors from the different districts of the island preparatory to the invasion of Maui, in the month of <hi rend="italic">Ikuwa</hi> (probably winter) Kamehameha was born probably in November 1758.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Birth-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Fornander-2">[2]</ref>:135–136
He had his birth ceremony at the <hi rend="italic">Moʻokini Heiau</hi>, an ancient temple which is preserved in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kohala_Historical_Sites_State_Monument">Kohala Historical Sites State Monument</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>Many stories are told about the birth of Kamehameha.</p>
<p>One says that when Kekuʻiapoiwa was pregnant with Kamehameha, she had a craving for the eyeball of a chief. She was given the eyeball of a man-eating shark and the priests prophesied that this meant the child would be a rebel and a killer of chiefs. Alapainui, the old ruler of the island of Hawaiʻi, secretly made plans to have the newborn infant killed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Lonely-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-paiea-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Kekuʻiapoiwa's time came on a stormy night in the Kohala district, when a strange star with a tail of white fire appeared in the western sky. This could have been <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halley's_Comet">Halley's Comet</ref> which appeared near the end of 1758. According to one legend, the baby was passed through a hole in the side of Kekuiapoiwa's thatched hut to a local Kohala chief named Naeʻole, who carried the child to safety at Awini  on the island's north coast. By the time the infant in Naeʻole's care was five, Alapainui had accepted him back into his household.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-paiea-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Alexander-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>After Kamehameha, Kekuʻiapoiwa bore a second son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keliimaikai">Keliimaikai</ref>. A few years later, Keōua died in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilo,_Hawaii">Hilo</ref>, and the family moved with Alapainui to an area near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kawaihae,_Hawaii">Kawaihae</ref>, where she married a chief of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kona,_Hawaii">Kona district</ref> (and her uncle) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamanawa">Kamanawa</ref>.
She had one daughter, Piʻipiʻi Kalanikaulihiwakama, from this second husband, who would later become an important military ally of Kamehameha, who was both step son and cousin through several relationships. Piʻipiʻi became first the wife of Keholoikalani, the father of her son Kanihonui, and later she married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kaikioewa">Kaikioewa</ref>, who she had a daughter Kuwahine with.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Pratt-7">[7]</ref>:18</p>
<head>Kamehameha dynasty</head>
</text>
