<text id="autogum_bio_doc496" title="Wawrzyniec Grzymała Goślicki" shortTile="wawrzyniec-grzymala" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2003-11-06" dateModified="2019-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wawrzyniec_Grzyma%C5%82a_Go%C5%9Blicki" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wawrzyniec Grzymała Goślicki</head><p>
<hi rend="bold">Wawrzyniec Grzymała Goślicki</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin_language">Latin</ref>: <hi lang="la" rend="italic">Laurentius Grimaldius Goslicius</hi>; between 1530 and 1540 – 31 October 1607) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poland">Polish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Szlachcic">nobleman</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Poznań">Bishop of Poznań</ref> (1601–1607), political thinker and philosopher best known for his book <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De_optimo_senatore">De optimo senatore</ref></hi> (1568).</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Born near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Płock">Płock</ref>, after studying at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kraków">Kraków</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jagiellonian_University">Jagiellonian University</ref> and at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Padua">Padua</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bologna">Bologna</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cole-1">[1]</ref> he entered the Roman Catholic Church. In 1569 he also joined the Polish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanclerz">royal chancery</ref> and as a secretary served two kings, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigismund_II_Augustus">Sigismund II Augustus</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Báthory">Stefan Batory</ref>, and was successively appointed bishop of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kamieniec_Podolski">Kamieniec Podolski</ref> (1586), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chełm">Chełm</ref> (1590), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Przemyśl">Przemyśl</ref> (1591), and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poznań">Poznań</ref> (1601).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cole-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Gos_tr-2">[2]</ref> Goślicki was a man of affairs,  highly esteemed by contemporaries, and frequently engaged in active politics. He was also a staunch advocate of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religious_tolerance">religious tolerance</ref> in Poland. It was due to his influence and to a letter that he wrote to the Pope against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesuits">Jesuits</ref> that they were prevented from establishing schools at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kraków">Kraków</ref> during his reign. He was the only <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prelate">prelate</ref> who, in 1587, acceded to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warsaw_Confederation">Warsaw Confederation</ref>.</p>
<p>Goślicki's Latin book <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De_optimo_senatore">De optimo senatore</ref></hi> (published during his stay in Italy in Venice, 1568<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Gos_tr-2">[2]</ref>) and dedicated to King Zygmunt August, subsequently appeared in four English translations: as <hi rend="italic">The Counsellor</hi> ( considered inaccurate) in 1598, <hi rend="italic">A commonwealth of good counsaile</hi> in 1607, <hi rend="italic">The Accomplished Senator... Done into English... By Mr. Oldisworth</hi> in 1733, and most recently as <hi rend="italic">The Accomplished Senator</hi> in K. Thompson's translation in 1992. The book proved immensely important in Britain among forces opposed to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tudor_dynasty">Tudor</ref> monarchy; it was widely quoted and cited in opposition pamphlets and leaflets during the period leading up to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British_Civil_Wars">British Civil Wars</ref> of the 1640s.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In this book Goślicki shows the ideal statesman who is well versed in the humanities as well as in economy, politics, and law. He argued that law is above the ruler, who must respect it, and that it is illegitimate to rule over a people against its will. He equated godliness with reason, and reason with law.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cole-1">[1]</ref> Many of the book's ideas comprised the foundations of Polish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_Poland_(1569–1795)">Nobles' Democracy</ref> (1505–1795) and were based on 14th-century writings by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanisław_of_Skarbimierz">Stanisław of Skarbimierz</ref>.  The book was not translated into Polish for 400 years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cole-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>
The book was influential abroad, exporting the ideas of Poland's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Freedom">Golden Freedom</ref> and democratic system. It was a political and social classic, widely read and long popular in England after its 1598 translation;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> read by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_I_of_England">Elizabeth I of England</ref>, it was also known by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shakespeare">Shakespeare</ref>, who used his depiction of an incompetent senator as a model for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polonius">Polonius</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hamlet">Hamlet</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cole-1">[1]</ref> Its ideas might be seen in the turmoil that gripped England around the times of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glorious_Revolution">Glorious Revolution</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cole-1">[1]</ref> Goślicki's ideas were perhaps suggestive for future national constitutions. Goślicki never wrote that "all men are created equal," but did say, "Sometimes a people, justly provoked and irritated, by the Tyranny and Usurpations of their Kings, take upon themselves the undoubted Right of vindicating their own liberties." The book was allegedly read by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Bellarmine">Robert Bellarmine</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algernon_Sydney">Algernon Sydney</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson</ref> (who had it in his library<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jefflib-5">[5]</ref>), but there is no evidence of a direct link with Jefferson's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Declaration_of_Independence">Declaration of Independence</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cole-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Goślicki argued that distinguished senators were more useful to a state than the king or the common people:</p>
For the king, being alone, cannot see everything and it often happens that either he yields to desires or his emotions disturb his ability of discretion. Also an ignorant crowd without a thought and head (as a proverb says) cannot by any means possess such prudence, while the senate, composed of men distinguished by virtue, prudence, and glory of accomplished deeds is capable from its middle position, as if from an observation point, of caring for the common weal of the state, perceiving those matters which are beneficial, and freeing it from disturbances, rebellions, and dangers.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Gos_tr-2">[2]</ref>
<p>He was an influence in the framing the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitution_of_May_3,_1791">Polish Constitution of 3 May 1791</ref>, which historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman_Davies">Norman Davies</ref> calls "the first constitution of its kind in Europe".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref></p>
</text>
