<text id="autogum_bio_doc775" title="Konrad II the Hunchback" shortTile="konrad-ii-hunchback" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-11" dateModified="2019-08-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konrad_II_the_Hunchback" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Konrad II the Hunchback</head><figure><caption>Konrad II</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Konrad II the Hunchback</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polish_language">Polish</ref>: <hi lang="pl" rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Konrad II Garbaty</hi></hi>) (1252/65 – 11 October 1304) was Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ścinawa">Ścinawa</ref> from 1278 to 1284, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarch_of_Aquileia">patriarch of Aquileia</ref> in 1299, and Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Żagań">Żagań</ref> from 1284 until his death.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>He was the second son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konrad_I,_Duke_of_Silesia-Glogau">Konrad I</ref>, Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Głogów">Głogów</ref> by his first wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salome_of_Greater_Poland">Salome</ref>, daughter of Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wladislaw_Odonicz">Władysław</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greater_Poland">Greater Poland</ref>. His nickname "Hunchback" (<hi rend="italic">Garbaty</hi>) appears in contemporary chronicles probably due to his religious career.</p>
<p>Konrad II first appeared on the chronicles at the ceremony of the canonization of his paternal great-grandmother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hedwig_of_Andechs">Hedwig of Andechs</ref> in 1267. Ten years later he joined his elder brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_III,_Duke_of_Silesia-Glogau">Henry III</ref> in the Battle of Stolec (24 April 1277) which culminated in a disastrous defeat.</p>
<p>Shortly after these events, Konrad was sent to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bologna">Bologna</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italy">Italy</ref> to study in order to take important ecclesiastical posts in the future. During his absence, Henry IV Probus ruled Ścinawa on his behalf.  When Konrad II returned to his Duchy in 1280, the Duke of Wrocław refused to return control. It was not until years later, when thanks to pressure from Bishop <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_II_Zaremba">Thomas II Zaremba</ref> of Wrocław Henry IV finally recognized the sovereignty of Konrad II over Ścinawa.</p>
<p>Four years after Konrad I's death in 1278, the Duchy was divided between Konrad II and his brothers., with the former obtaining <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ścinawa">Ścinawa</ref>. However, in 1284,  Konrad II assumed the rule over Żagań, while his younger brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Przemko_of_Ścinawa">Przemko</ref>, then Duke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Żagań">Żagań</ref>, received Ścinawa. One possible reason for this switch was pressure from Duke <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_IV_Probus">Henry IV Probus</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wroclaw">Wroclaw</ref>, who preferred to have the more trustful Przemko in the neighboring realm.</p>
<p>After returning to Silesia, Konrad II obtained his first church position. In 1281 he was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provost_(civil)">Provost</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lubusz">Lubusz</ref>, and in 1287, with the help of Bishop Thomas II, he became in Provost of Wroclaw. In 1292 he was one of the candidates for the Bishopric of Wroclaw, but because of resistance from the Chapter, the choice fell on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_Romka">Jan Romka</ref>.</p>
<p>The relations of Konrad II with his brother Henry III were ambiguous. Initially, there were no frictions. Konrad II supported his brother in his aim to recover Ścinawa after the death of Przemko in the Battle of Siewierz (1289), but ultimately the land was annexed by Henry IV Probus; also, he supported Henry III in his talks with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Przemysł_II">Przemysł II</ref> of Greater Poland and in his subsequent wars against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_V_the_Fat">Henry V the Fat</ref>. Their good relations were broken in 1296, when Konrad II, after knowing of the involvement of Henry III in Great Poland affairs, joined the military expedition against him led by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolko_I_the_Strict">Bolko I the Strict</ref>; however, Bolko I made an agreement with Henry III in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zwanowicach">Zwanowicach</ref>, by which was compelled to give up the towns of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lubina">Lubina</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wińsko">Wińsko</ref> to Konrad II.</p>
<p>On 5 March 1299 Konrad II received a great opportunity to be raised in his church career. Thanks to the intercession of his brother-in-law, Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_I_of_Gorizia">Albert I of Gorizia</ref>, he was chosen as the new <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarch_of_Aquileia">patriarch/lord of Aquileia</ref>. However, the Duke of Żagań never reached his new lands in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friuli">Friuli</ref>; after having been stopped in the middle of the road in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vienna">Vienna</ref> due to the lack of approval from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Boniface_VIII">pope Boniface VIII</ref>, he returned to his country.</p>
<p>Back to Żagań, Konrad II claimed the effective government of his lands, which had been taken by Henry III during his absence. The Duke of Głogów refused to give up the rule and decided to jail  his brother. However, the knighthood of Żagań, Bolko I the Strict, and Bishop of Wrocław - who even declared the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Excommunication">excommunication</ref> of Henry III and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interdict">interdict</ref> over Głogów - intervened in his favour. Finally, Konrad II regained his freedom and the government of his Duchy, but the relationship between the brothers remained very strained until Konrad II's death.</p>
<p>Konrad II died on 11 October 1304 and was buried in the Cistercian monastery in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lubiąż">Lubiąż</ref>. Żagań was thenceforth acquired by Henry III.</p>
</text>
