<text id="autogum_bio_doc294" title="Hasan-Ali Beg Bestami" shortTile="hasanali-beg-bestami" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-09-02" dateModified="2019-03-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hasan-Ali_Beg_Bestami" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hasan-Ali Beg Bestami</head><p><hi rend="bold">Hasan-Ali Beg Bestami</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floruit">fl.</ref> 18th century) was an important <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safavid_dynasty">Safavid</ref> official, who subsequently became one of the closest associates of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nader_Shah">Nader Shah</ref> (r. 1736–1747), serving as his chief assayer (<hi rend="italic">moʿayyer al-mamālek</hi>).</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<p>Hasan-Ali was a slave of either <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenians">Armenian</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgians">Georgian</ref> origin, and had already gained a prominent position in the late Safavid era, when he entered the royal service during the reign of king <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sultan_Husayn">Sultan Husayn</ref> (r. 1696–1722), and became an important official by the 1720s.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref> In 1726, by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tahmasp_II">Tahmasp II</ref>'s order, Hasan-Ali was sent to report on the activities on the then emerging <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nader_Shah">Nader Qoli Beg</ref> (later known as Nader Shah).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref> Persuaded by Hasan-Ali, Nader became an associate to Tahmasp II as he joined him, and on the latters' behalf, he was appointed deputy governor of Abivard.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref> As the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Encyclopedia_Iranica">Encyclopedia Iranica</ref></hi> states; "This encounter marked the beginning of a long and close connection between Ḥasan-ʿAli and Nāder".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In the early 1730s, Hasan-Ali lived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isfahan">Isfahan</ref>, and functioned as a messenger between Nader and Tahmasp II, and he oversaw the fiscal affairs of Iran from there as well.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref> He later played a role in the removal of Tahmasp II from the throne and the subsequent crowning of then still infant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abbas_III_of_Persia">Abbas III</ref> in 1732.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref> By 1736, when Nader was already the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De_facto">de facto</ref></hi> ruler of Iran for many years, Hasan-Ali was known as one of his most trusted and principal advisors.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref> Nader suggested to his closest intimates, after a great hunting party on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mughan_plain">Moghan plains</ref>, that he should be proclaimed the new king (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shah">shah</ref>) in place of the young Abbas III.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFisherAveryHamblyMelville199134-2">[2]</ref> The small group of close intimates, Nader's friends, included <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tahmasp_Khan_Jalayer">Tahmasp Khan Jalayer</ref> as well as Hasan-Ali.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFisherAveryHamblyMelville199134-2">[2]</ref> Following Nader's suggestion, the group did not "demur", and Hasan-Ali remained silent. When Nader asked him why he remained silent, Hasan-Ali replied that the best thing for Nader to do would be assembling all leading men of the state, in order to receive their agreement in "a signed and sealed document of consent".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFisherAveryHamblyMelville199134-2">[2]</ref> Nader approved with the proposal, and the writers of the chancellery, which included the court historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mirza_Mehdi_Khan_Astarabadi">Mirza Mehdi Khan Astarabadi</ref>, were instructed with sending out orders to the military, clergy and nobility of the nation to summon at the plains.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTEFisherAveryHamblyMelville199134-2">[2]</ref> From the crowning ceremony on the Moghan at which Hasan-Ali was present, up to Nader's death in 1747, he was a permanent resident at the king's camp.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref> After Nader's assassination in 1747, Hasan-Ali managed to escape.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref> This caused Nader's long-time <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesuits">Jesuit</ref> doctor Bazin to form suspicious assumptions regarding Hasan-Ali, and he therefore believed that the latter had a certain involvement in the assassination plot.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Following the death of Nader and the succession to the throne by his nephew <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adil_Shah">Ali-Qoli</ref>, Hasan-Ali briefly served as an important advisor to the latter.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref> Following this short occupation, he returned to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isfahan">Isfahan</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref> There, it is said that Hasan-Ali allegedly "counseled <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karim_Khan_Zand">Karim Khan Zand</ref> to enthrone Abu Torab Mirza as king <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ismail_III">Ismail III</ref> in 1750".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref> The descendants of Hasan-Ali adopted the title of <hi rend="italic">moʿayyer al-mamālek</hi> as their family name.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref> Decades later, one of Hasan-Ali's namesake descendants, would serve as a government official of the then ruling <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qajar_dynasty">Qajar dynasty</ref> of Iran, during the reign of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fath-Ali_Shah_Qajar">Fath-Ali Shah Qajar</ref> (r. 1797–1834).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref> He married one of the latters daughters as well, around 1834.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-FOOTNOTETucker200340-41-1">[1]</ref></p>
</text>
