<text id="autogum_bio_doc365" title="Quinzio Bongiovanni" shortTile="quinzio-bongiovanni" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-07-24" dateModified="2018-09-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quinzio_Bongiovanni" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Quinzio Bongiovanni</head><p><hi rend="bold">Quinzio Bongiovanni</hi> (or <hi rend="bold">Quinto Buongiovanni</hi>) (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tropea">Tropea</ref> c.1550 - <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naples">Naples</ref> 5 June 1612) was an Italian doctor and scholar, active in the disputes between traditional <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scholasticism">scholasticism</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_philosophy">natural philosophy</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernardino_Telesio">Bernardino Telesio</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giambattista_della_Porta">Giambattista della Porta</ref> and members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accademia_dei_Lincei">Accademia dei Lincei</ref>.
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Family background and career</head>
<p>Quinzio Bongiovanni was the son of Giovan Nicola, a doctor, and Lamberta Fazzari. The family had probably originally come from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maida,_Calabria">Maida</ref>, which it left to escape the feudal domination of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Caracciolo">House of Caracciolo</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> and moved into the Palazzo Bongiovanni, home to the Vianeo brothers, pioneering surgeons, who were also from Maida. Quinzio finished his studies in medicine and philosophy under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovan_Bernardino_Longo">Giovan Bernardino Longo</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovan_Girolamo_Polverino">Giovan Girolamo Polverino</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naples">Naples</ref>.  In 1571 he published the work for which he is principally remembered, <hi rend="italic">Peripateticarum disputationum de principiis naturae</hi> (Venice 1571), dedicated to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardinal_Carafa">Cardinal Carafa</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>  He was a member Accademia degli Affaticati ('Academy of the Weary') in his home town of Tropea.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Some time before 1583 he was appointed Protomedico (Chief Physician) to the King (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_II_of_Spain">Philip II of Spain</ref>), a position which required him to licence and regulate all healers, surgeons, midwives and alchemists in the kingdom. He insisted that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apothecary">apothecaries</ref> be prevented from preparing herbal remedies before being properly inspected, otherwise 'they make the compositions up in their own way, without fear of God or justice, and to the detriment of human bodies, which for this reason are daily made to suffer.'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> He apparently also worked for a time for the Prince of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bisignano">Bisignano</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> He returned to Naples in 1588 and was appointed Reader in Philosophy and Medicine at the university. He later became Professor of Medicine, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archiater">Archiater</ref> to Popes <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Pius_V">Pius V</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Gregory_XIII">Gregory XIII</ref>. Among his most distinguished pupils were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco_Aurelio_Severino">Marco Aurelio Severino</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Battista_Cavallari">Giovanni Battista Cavallari</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>In 1608 the German medic Giovanni Custode reported to his colleague <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Faber">Giovanni Faber</ref> the opinion of Bongiovanni that in Rome 'doctors are princes, but in Naples they are paupers, poorly-considered and working very hard to earn anything.'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Opinions on natural philosophy</head>
<p>One story about Buongiovanni suggests that he was firmly in the Aristotelian camp in the discussions about nature, sensation, and the order of the universe.  In 1571 Telesio was debating with his student <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonio_Persio">Antonio Persio</ref> the nature of light, and whether or not the sun was hot. Buongiovanni joined the discussion, arguing it could not be hot, because it was beyond the moon and therefore, in traditional Aristotelian cosmology, beyond the realm of the senses; Telesio argued that the sun's rays both illuminate and heat the earth. When the argument could not be resolved, Telesio took him out into the street in the midday sun and stood with him.  'Can't you feel it?' he asked, but Buongiovanni refused to accept this evidence.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<head>Death and legacy</head>
<p>Bongiovanni died in Naples on 5 June 1612, bequeathing part of his estate to the two sons of his brother Flaminio, Giovancola and Quinzio (junior). He also left provision for the Jesuit Colleges in Naples, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massa_Lubrense">Massa Lubrense</ref> and Tropea; 500 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scudi">scudi</ref> for the education of twelve poor boys of his home town with the Jesuits; 500 scudi to provide dowries for widows and orphans of the same town to marry; and 500 scudi for the rector of the Jesuit College in Naples to clothe and equip impoverished scholars from out of town.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
</text>
