<text id="autogum_bio_doc747" title="John FitzGerald, 1st Earl of Kildare" shortTile="john-fitzgerald-st" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-01" dateModified="2019-10-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_FitzGerald%2C_1st_Earl_of_Kildare" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John FitzGerald, 1st Earl of Kildare</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">John FitzThomas FitzGerald</hi> (c. 1250 – d. 10 September 1316) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irish_nobility">Irish nobleman</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peerage_of_Ireland">Peerage of Ireland</ref>, as 4th <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_of_Offaly">Lord of Offaly</ref> from 1287 and subsequently as 1st <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Kildare">Earl of Kildare</ref> from 1316.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was the eldest son of Thomas Fitz<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maurice_FitzGerald,_2nd_Lord_of_Offaly">Maurice</ref> FitzGerald (died 1271) and Rohesia de St.Michel, he is noticed in 1291 in serious dispute with William Vescy, Lord of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kildare">Kildare</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Justice_of_Ireland">Lord Justice of Ireland</ref>, about whom there were many complaints of oppression and neglect of the country's defences. As champion of the complainants John Fitzgerald, by then 4th Lord of Offaly (having succeeded to the title in 1287, upon the death of his uncle <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maurice_FitzGerald,_3rd_Lord_of_Offaly">Maurice FitzGerald, 3rd Lord of Offaly</ref>), their paths crossed and instead of addressing the issues Vescy charged Fitzgerald with minor charges of slander and libel. Fitzgerald appealed to King Edward I of England, who, to examine and judge the matter impartially, summoned them both to London to hear the cases, where it appears FitzGerald had the advantage, challenging the Lord Justice to clear his name by combat, which was accepted. However, Vescy fled to France, whereupon the King pronounced Lord Offaly innocent, and settled upon him Vescy's lordships and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manorialism">manors</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kildare">Kildare</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rathangan,_County_Kildare">Rathangan</ref>, &amp;c., had been forfeited to the Crown.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>In 1296 and 1299 he was summoned to fight for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British_crown">Crown</ref> in the Scottish campaigns of Edward II. With John Wogan, Lord Justice, and others he went a third time to war in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scotland">Scotland</ref> in 1301-2.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Wills-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In 1307, with his son-in-law Sir Edmund Butler, he dispersed rebels in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Offaly">Offaly</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Wills-2">[2]</ref> who had razed the castle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geashill">Geashill</ref> and burnt the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leix">Leix</ref>. In 1312 he was sent as General at the head of an army into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Munster">Munster</ref> to suppress armed Irish rebels. On 25 May 1315, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Bruce">Edward Bruce</ref>, brother to King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_the_Bruce">Robert the Bruce</ref> of Scotland, entered the north of Ireland with 6000 men, was crowned <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_of_Ireland">King of Ireland</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dundalk">Dundalk</ref>, and wasted the country. Lord Offaly, among others, commenced vigorous sporadic warfare to resist Bruce, leaving "great slaughter" of Scots and the Irish irregulars in his service. Edward Bruce was eventually defeated and killed in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Dundalk">battle of Dundalk</ref>.</p>
<p>King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_II_of_England">Edward II</ref> created Fitzgerald Earl of Kildare by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Letters_Patent">Letters Patent</ref> dated 14 May 1316,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Wills-2">[2]</ref> the year in which he founded the Augustinian priory at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adare">Adare</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_Limerick">County Limerick</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-adare-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>He died that same year, on Sunday 12 September 1316, at Laraghbryan, near Maynooth and was interred in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franciscan">Franciscan</ref> Friary of Clan.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kildare">Kildare</ref>.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>He had married Blanche de La Roche, daughter of John de La Roche, Lord Fermoy and Maud Waley (daughter of Henry Waley),<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-complete-peerage1-kildare-5">[5]</ref> by whom he had two sons and two daughters:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Gerald (d.1303)</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_FitzGerald,_2nd_Earl_of_Kildare">Thomas FitzGerald, 2nd Earl of Kildare</ref>, his successor.</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_FitzGerald">Joan FitzGerald</ref>, married in 1302 to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edmund_Butler,_Earl_of_Carrick">Edmund Butler, Earl of Carrick</ref>.</item>
<item>Elizabeth FitzGerald, married to Nicholas Netterville, ancestor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viscount_Netterville">Viscount Netterville</ref>.</item></list>
</text>
