<text id="autogum_bio_doc596" title="Antoine de Longueval" shortTile="antoine-de-longueval" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-12-12" dateModified="2019-05-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antoine_de_Longueval" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Antoine de Longueval</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Antoine de Longueval</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floruit">fl.</ref> 1498–1525) was a French singer and composer of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renaissance_music">Renaissance</ref>.  A contemporary of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josquin_des_Prez">Josquin des Prez</ref>, he was singing master of the French royal chapel under King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francis_I_of_France">Francis I</ref>, and was important in the history of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyphony">polyphonic</ref> setting of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Passion_(music)">Passion</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Little is known about his early life, not even his approximate birthdate, but he was probably from the village of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Longueval">Longueval</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Somme_(department)">Somme</ref> region of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Picardy">Picardy</ref> (scene of much heavy fighting during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_the_Somme">Somme</ref> battles in 1916).  By 1498, court records indicate that he was employed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne_of_Brittany">Anne of Brittany</ref>, and between 1502 and 1504 he was a singer at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savoy">Savoy</ref> court, where his high pay indicates the respect he was accorded as a musician.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> From there he went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferrara">Ferrara</ref>, where he was a singer between December 1503 and September 1504; therefore he was there at the same time as Josquin des Prez.  It is presumed that he wrote his most famous composition, the passion setting <hi rend="italic">Passio Domini nostri</hi> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holy_Week">Holy Week</ref> of 1504, the same event for which Josquin's famous <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miserere_(Josquin)">Miserere</ref></hi> was likely written.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Why he left Ferrara is not known, but he may have fled an outbreak of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bubonic_plague">plague</ref>, as did Josquin and a large proportion of the town's population.  In 1507 he is listed as a member of the group of private musicians of the French king, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_XII">Louis XII</ref>, and in 1515, Francis I promoted him to <hi rend="italic">maître de chapelle</hi> (singing master) of the royal chapel.  That same year he went to Italy with the French king, along with composer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Mouton">Jean Mouton</ref>, where Pope <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leo_X">Leo X</ref> made both composers <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apostolic_notary">apostolic notaries</ref>.  On returning to France, Longueval was further honored by being made a canon of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Notre_Dame_de_Paris">Notre Dame de Paris</ref>, a position he resigned in 1519 in order to become abbot of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benedictine">Benedictine</ref> priory in Longueval, the probable town of his birth.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfonso_I,_d'Este,_Duke_of_Ferrara">Alfonso I</ref>, the Duke of Ferrara, made one more attempt to get him to return to his opulent musical establishment in Italy, but evidently was not successful.  The last mention of Longueval is at the French court in 1525, and it is presumed he may have died shortly after.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Dean,_Grove-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>His colleague at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chapelle_royale">chapelle royale</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Moulu">Pierre Moulu</ref>, pays tribute to Longueval in his "musicians' motet" <hi rend="italic">Mater floreat</hi> (from a manuscript presented to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lorenzo_II_de’_Medici">Lorenzo II de’ Medici</ref> at his wedding in 1518) which after paying tribute to the leading composers of Europe, from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guillaume_Du_Fay">Du Fay</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johannes_Regis">Regis</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antoine_Busnois">Busnois</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philippe_Basiron">Basiron</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Agricola">Alexander Agricola</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacob_Obrecht">Jacob Obrecht</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josquin">Josquin</ref>, turns to Louis XII's own composers giving first and longest place to Longueval.</p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>Longueval's surviving attributed works consist of two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motet">motets</ref>, two chansons, and attribution of the famous Passion setting <hi rend="italic">Passio Domini nostri Jesu Christi</hi> for four voices.  He wrote at least one <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mass_(music)">mass</ref> setting, which was documented as being sent to Ferrara, but it either has not survived or has survived anonymously.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Passio Domini nostri</hi> is unusual for being a polyphonic setting of much of the Passion text from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gospel_of_St._Matthew">Gospel of St. Matthew</ref> and the other three Gospels, especially that of St. John, with variation in texture, rhythmic character, scoring, and other musical attributes depending on the speaker and the context.  It was enormously influential on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lutheranism">Lutheran</ref> musicians in Germany throughout the 16th century, and was much imitated. The passion was recorded under the direction of Roger Blanchard and Pierre Poulteau in 1964. Finnish ensemble Kuninkaantien muusikot (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musicians_of_the_King's_Road">Musicians of the King's Road</ref>) has performed the Passion as a part of its early passions cycle. The performance took place in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turku">Turku</ref> Cathedral in 2017, the year of the 500th anniversary of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reformation">Reformation</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref>.</p>
<p>The chansons by Longueval show both archaic characteristics, in that they partially abide by the 15th century convention of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Formes_fixes">formes fixes</ref></hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> but they also are progressive in their use of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imitation_(music)">imitation</ref>, which may be an influence of Josquin.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Dean,_Grove-3">[3]</ref></p>
</text>
