<text id="autogum_bio_doc761" title="Marchetto da Padova" shortTile="marchetto-da-padova" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-03-01" dateModified="2017-08-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marchetto_da_Padova" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Marchetto da Padova</head><p><hi rend="bold">Marchetto da Padova</hi> (<hi rend="bold">Marchettus of Padua</hi>;  fl. 1305 – 1319) was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italy">Italian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_theory">music theorist</ref> and composer of the late <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medieval_music">medieval</ref> era.  His innovations in notation of time-values were fundamental to the music of the Italian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ars_nova">ars nova</ref>, as was his work on defining the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musical_mode">modes</ref> and refining <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musical_tuning">tuning</ref>.  In addition, he was the first music theorist to discuss <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chromaticism">chromaticism</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>Most likely he was born in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Padua">Padua</ref>.  Little is known about his life, but he is recorded as being music teacher for the choirboys at the cathedral in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Padua">Padua</ref> in 1305 and 1306, and he left Padua in 1308 to work in other cities in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Veneto">Veneto</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romagna">Romagna</ref>.  His two major treatises seem to have been written between 1317 and 1319, shortly before <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philippe_de_Vitry">Philippe de Vitry</ref> produced his <hi rend="italic">Ars nova</hi> (c. 1322), which gave its name to the music of the age.  Marchetto indicated in the treatises themselves that he wrote them at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cesena">Cesena</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Verona">Verona</ref>.  There are no other reliable records of his life, although his fame was evidently widespread, and his work became hugely influential later in the 14th century.</p>
<head>Music</head>
<p>Only three <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motet">motets</ref> have been reliably attributed to Marchetto, one of them due to his name appearing as an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acrostic">acrostic</ref> in the text for one of the parts (<hi rend="italic">Ave regina celorum/Mater innocencie</hi>).  Based on another acrostic in the same motet, it seems it was composed for the dedication of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scrovegni_Chapel">Scrovegni Chapel</ref> (also known as the Arena Chapel) in Padua on March 25, 1305.</p>
<head>Writings and influence</head>
<p>Marchetto published two major treatises, the <hi rend="italic">Lucidarium in arte musice plane</hi> (probably in 1317–1318), and the <hi rend="italic">Pomerium in arte musice mensurate</hi> (probably 1318).  He also published an abridged version of the <hi rend="italic">Pomerium</hi> as the <hi rend="italic">Brevis compilatio</hi>, though the date of this is not known.  He stated in the <hi rend="italic">Pomerium</hi> that he wrote it while staying at the house of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raynaldus_de_Cintis">Raynaldus de Cintis</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cesena">Cesena</ref>, who was lord of the city from 1321 to 1326, however most scholars believe that the Pomerium was written in 1318.</p>
<p>The meanings of the two titles are; <hi rend="bold">Lucidarium</hi> - an encyclopaedic clarification<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomerium">Pomerium</ref>, the verge or enclosure around the orchard of Rome.</p>
<p>Precise dating of his work has been important to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musicology">musicology</ref> because of the controversy over whether he was influenced by the innovations of the French <hi rend="italic">ars nova</hi>, as written by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philippe_de_Vitry">Philippe de Vitry</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_de_Muris">Jean de Muris</ref> in the 1320s, or whether the influence went the other way.  Most likely Marchetto's work was first, although he was well aware of the French practice – which, like most innovations in music before the 20th century, was only discussed in writing years after the actual musical innovation took place.  All of the treatises except for the abridged version are in a heavily <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scholasticism">scholastic</ref> framework, and were almost certainly collections of oral teachings.</p>
<p>Marchetto's innovations are in three areas:  tuning, chromaticism, and notation of time-values.  He was the first medieval writer to propose dividing the whole tone into more than two parts.  A <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semitone">semitone</ref> could consist of one, two, three, or four of these parts, depending on whether it was, respectively, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diesis">diesis</ref>, an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enharmonic">enharmonic</ref> semitone, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diatonic">diatonic</ref> semitone, or a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chromaticism">chromatic</ref> semitone.</p>
<p>In the area of time values, Marchetto improved on the old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franco_of_Cologne">Franconian</ref> system of notation; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_notation">music notation</ref> was by this time evolving into the method known today where an individual symbol represented a specific time-value, and Marchetto contributed to this trend by developing a method of compound time division, and by assigning specific note shapes to specific time values.</p>
<p>Additionally, Marchetto discussed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhythmic_mode">rhythmic modes</ref>, an old rhythmic notation method from the 13th-century <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ars_antiqua">ars antiqua</ref></hi>, and added four "imperfect" modes to the existing five "perfect" modes, thus allowing for the contemporary Italian practice of mixed, flexible and expressive rhythmic performance.</p>
<p>The <hi rend="italic">Lucidarium</hi> also included one of the earliest texts addressing the relationship between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Composer">composer</ref>  –  Marchetto used the word <hi rend="italic">musician</hi>, borrowing from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boethius">Boethius</ref>'s definition in <hi rend="italic">De institutione musica libri quinque</hi>  –  and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Performance">performer</ref>. He set a distinct hierarchy, defining the "musician" or composer as the artist making judgements in accordance with his learned knowledge, while describing the singer as the instrument on which the musician performs, and likening their relationship to that of the judge and the crier.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Marchetto's treatises were hugely influential in the 14th and early 15th centuries, and were widely copied and disseminated.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rossi_Codex">Rossi Codex</ref>, which is the earliest surviving source of secular Italian polyphony and which contains music written between 1325 and 1355, shows obvious influence of Marchetto, especially in its use of his notational improvements.</p>
<p>Without the innovations of Marchetto, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_of_the_Trecento">music of the Italian Trecento</ref> – for example the secular music of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Francesco_Landini">Landini</ref> – would not have been possible.</p>
<head>Footnotes</head>
<head>References and further reading</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians</hi>, ed. Stanley Sadie.  20 vol.  London, Macmillan Publishers Ltd., 1980.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/1-56159-174-2">1-56159-174-2</ref></item>
<item>Richard H. Hoppin, <hi rend="italic">Medieval Music</hi>.  New York, W.W. Norton &amp; Co., 1978.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Book_Number">ISBN</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSources/0-393-09090-6">0-393-09090-6</ref></item>
<item>Jan Herlinger: "Marchetto da Padova", Grove Music Online ed. L. Macy (Accessed February 28, 2005), <ref target="http://www.grovemusic.com">(subscription access)</ref></item>
<item>Jay Rahn: <hi rend="italic">Practical Aspects of Marchetto's Tuning.</hi> Music Theory Online: The Online Journal of the Society for Music Theory. vol. 4, no. 6, 1998. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Standard_Serial_Number">ISSN</ref><ref target="https://www.worldcat.org/search?fq=x0:jrnl&amp;q=n2:1067-3040">1067-3040</ref> <ref target="http://www.societymusictheory.org/mto/issues/mto.98.4.6/mto.98.4.6.rahn.html">(Accessed January 3, 2006)</ref></item>
<item>Margo Schulter: "Xenharmonic Excursion to Padua, 1318:Marchettus, the cadential diesis, and neo-Gothic tunings"</item>
<item>Joseph L.monzo: "Speculations on Marchetto of Padua's fifth-Tones"</item>
<item>Karol Berger: "Musica Ficta. Theories of accidental inflexions in vocal polyphony from Marchetto da Padova to Gioseffo Zarlino", Cambridge University Press, 1987, especially pp.22–9, 86-87, 141-3.</item></list>
</text>
