<text id="autogum_bio_doc685" title="Boček II of Poděbrady" shortTile="bocek-ii-podebrady" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-06-06" dateModified="2018-04-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bo%C4%8Dek_II_of_Pod%C4%9Bbrady" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Boček II of Poděbrady</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Boček II of Poděbrady</hi> (also: <hi rend="italic">Boček II of Kunštát and Poděbrady</hi>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_language">German</ref>: <hi lang="de" rend="italic">Boček II. von Kunstadt und Podiebrad</hi> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_language">German</ref>: <hi lang="de" rend="italic">Botschek von Podiebrad</hi> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_language">German</ref>: <hi lang="de" rend="italic">Botschek der Ältere von Podiebrad</hi>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_language">Czech</ref>: <hi lang="cs" rend="italic">Boček II. z Poděbrad</hi> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_language">Czech</ref>: <hi lang="cs" rend="italic">Boček II. z Kunštátu a Poděbrad</hi> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_language">Czech</ref>: <hi lang="cs" rend="italic">Boček starší z Poděbrad</hi>; died: 1417) may have been treasurer or even chief treasurer of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bohemia">Bohemia</ref> between 1377 and 1387. Between 1403 and 1408, he held the office of <hi lang="de" rend="italic">Oberstlandschreiber</hi> ("chief administrator") of Bohemia.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>It is not known when and where Boček II was born. His parents were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boček_I_of_Poděbrady">Boček I of Poděbrady</ref> and Elisabeth of Lichtemburk (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_language">German</ref>: <hi lang="de" rend="italic">Elisabeth von Lichtenburg</hi>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_language">Czech</ref>: <hi lang="cs" rend="italic">Eliska z Lichtemburka</hi>), a daughter of Henry of Lichtenburg at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Žleby_Castle">Žleby Castle</ref>.  Boček was named after the founder of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Podiebrad_family">Poděbrady</ref> branch of the House of Kunštát.  Boček is sometimes called "the Elder", to contrast him with his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boček_III_of_Poděbrady">Boček III of Poděbrady</ref>, who was called "Boček the Younger".</p>
<p>Boček II is first mentioned in a deed of 1375, about the division of the inheritance of his father, who died in 1373.  Since Boček II was the first born, he inherited the larger part of his father's possessions, which were mostly in eastern Bohemia.  In 1376 he received <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lipnice">Lipnice</ref> as a fief from the King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_IV,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Charles IV</ref> of Bohemia.  In 1377, he transferred the Lordship of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Potštát">Potštát</ref> to his wife Anna Elisabeth as a dowry.  Between 1377 and 1387, he may have held the position of Treasurer or Chief Treasurer of Bohemia.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>  In 1387 Boček II and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Půta_II_of_Častolovice">Půta II of Častolovice</ref> bought the Lordship of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skuhrov_nad_Bělou">Skuhrov nad Bělou</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rychmberk_Castle">Rychmberk Castle</ref> in the foothills of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orlické_hory">Orlické hory</ref> mountains from the brothers Jan and Jaroslav of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/České_Meziříčí">České Meziříčí</ref>.</p>
<p>During the reign of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslaus,_King_of_the_Romans">Wenceslaus</ref>, Boček II was initially on his side, but later turned away from him. In 1394 he was among the nobles who signed the initiative of the Margrave <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jobst_of_Moravia">Jobst of Moravia</ref>, a joint statement with which they turned against the king, who was eventually captured.  Presumably in return for this support, Margrave Jobst gave Boček possessions in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moravia">Moravia</ref>.  In 1402 he supported King Wenceslaus again, in that he was against the candidacy of Wenceslaus brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigismund,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Sigismund</ref>.  This is probably why he received the position of <hi rend="italic">Oberstlandschreiber</hi> (chief administrator) of Bohemia in 1403.  He also was chairman of the manorial court and member of the royal Council.</p>
<p>Thanks to a mutual inheritance treaty from 1385 between Boček and his relative Gerhard of Kunštát, Boček II was able to strengthen his position in Moravia after Gerhard's death in 1406. From Gerhards he inherited among others <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kunštát">Kunštát</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bouzov">Bouzov</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moravská_Třebová">Moravská Třebová</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pyšolec_Castle">Pyšolec Castle</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boskovice">Boskovice</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Týnec_(Břeclav_District)">Týnec na Moravě</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Velké_Bílovice">Velké Bílovice</ref>.  He sold some of these possessions soon afterwards.</p>
<p>In early 1415, Boček II signed a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Petition">petition</ref>, in which the high Bohemian nobles protested against the capture of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_Hus">Jan Hus</ref>.  Later that year, after Hus was burned at the stake, Boček was the third noble to sign a letter of complaint by the Bohemian nobility.  Also in 1415, Boček acquired the Lordships of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Náchod">Náchod</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lordship_of_Hummel">Hummel</ref> in Eastern Bohemia from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_of_Lazan">Henry of Lazan</ref>, in exchange for the South Bohemian Lordship of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bechyně">Bechyně</ref>.  Since the latter still belonged to Bohemia, Boček came geographically closer to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/County_of_Kladsko">County of Kladsko</ref>, which would be very important to his descendants and would serve as a county seat and seat of power to the sons of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_of_Poděbrady">George of Poděbrady</ref>.  They would become counts of Kladsko, and as Dukes of Münsterberg they would found the Silesian (Münsterberg-Oels) branch of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Podiebrad_family">Podiebrad family</ref>.</p>
<head>Marriage and offspring</head>
<p>Boček II was married with Anna Elisabeth Lipa (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_language">Czech</ref>: <hi lang="cs" rend="italic">Anna Eliška Lipá</hi>), a daughter of Henry of Leipa (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_language">Czech</ref>: <hi lang="cs" rend="italic">Jindřich Lipá</hi>). The couple had four sons:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>John (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_language">German</ref>: <hi lang="de" rend="italic">Johann</hi>; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_language">Czech</ref>: <hi lang="cs" rend="italic">Jan</hi>; died circa 1408), married in 1398 with Elisabeth of Wartenberg (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_language">Czech</ref>: <hi lang="cs" rend="italic">Eliska z Vartenberka</hi>)</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boček_III_of_Poděbrady">Boček III of Poděbrady</ref>, (d. 1429)</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hynek_Boček_of_Poděbrady">Hynek Boček of Poděbrady</ref> (d. 1426), married N. N. of Žerotín</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victor_of_Kunštát_and_Poděbrady">Victor of Kunštát and Poděbrady</ref> (1403–1427), married Anna of Wartenberg (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech_language">Czech</ref>: <hi lang="cs" rend="italic">Anna z Vartenberka</hi>)</item></list>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
