<text id="autogum_bio_doc666" title="Rupert, Count of Nassau-Sonnenberg" shortTile="rupert-count-nassausonnenberg" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-09-16" dateModified="2018-11-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rupert%2C_Count_of_Nassau-Sonnenberg" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rupert, Count of Nassau-Sonnenberg</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Rupert, Count of Nassau-Sonnenberg</hi> (c.1340 – 4 September 1390), nicknamed <hi rend="italic">the Bellicose</hi>, was a son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerlach_I,_Count_of_Nassau">Gerlach I, Count of Nassau</ref> and his second wife, Irmgard of Hohenlohe.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>As a younger son, Rupert was originally destined for a career in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clergy">clergy</ref>.  Gerlach I abdicated in 1344, in favour of his sons, except he kept <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonnenberg_Castle">Sonnenberg Castle</ref>, where he lived.  This castle was to be inherited by Kraft, Rupert's eldest brother.  However, Kraft fell in battle while fighting on the French side in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Poitiers">Battle of Poitiers</ref> in 1356.  It was then decided that Rupert would inherit Sonnenberg.</p>
<p>Rupert's half-brother from his father's first marriage ruled their father's possessions jointly until 1355, and then divided it:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adolph_I,_Count_of_Nassau-Wiesbaden-Idstein">Adolph I</ref> inherited Nassau-Wiesbaden-Idstein (this line died out in the male line in 1605)</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_I_of_Nassau-Weilburg">John I</ref> inherited Nassau-Weilburg (this line died out in the male line in 1912)</item>
<item>Rupert later inherited Nassau-Sonnenberg.</item></list>
<p>From 1355, Rupert was bailiff at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amöneburg_Castle">Amöneburg Castle</ref> for his half-brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerlach_of_Nassau">Gerlach</ref>, who was Archbishop of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archbishopric_of_Mainz">Mainz</ref>.</p>
<p>In 1361, Gerlach I died and Rupert inherited Nassau-Sonnenberg.  Gerlach's widow Irmengard retired to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liebenau_monastery">Liebenau monastery</ref>, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Worms,_Germany">Worms</ref>, where she became a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominican_Order">Dominican</ref> nun.</p>
<p>In 1367, Rupert pledged some of his territory to his half-brother Adolph I, who immediately pledged it to back to Rupert and Anna (Ruper's wife) and Irmengard (Rupert's mother and Adolph's step-mother).  The reasons for this remarkable maneuver are unclear.</p>
<p>In 1369, Rupert started a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feud">feud</ref> against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_I,_Count_of_Nassau-Dillenburg">John I</ref> of Nassau-Dillenburg, about some <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fief">fief</ref> John I held from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landgraviate_of_Hesse">Hesse</ref>.  Rupert claimed these fiefs, and joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Covenant">Star Covenant</ref>, an alliance of knights against Landgrave <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_II,_Landgrave_of_Hesse">Henry II</ref> of Hesse.</p>
<p>In 1370, his half-brother Adolph I died.  In 1371, his mother, Irmengard, died,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> as did his half-brothers John I and Gerlach.</p>
<p>From 1372 to 1374, Rupert fought another feud against John I of Nassau-Dillenburg.  He managed to keep his Sonnenberg Castle intact, whereas the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nassau,_Germany">Nassau</ref> was so badly damaged during the fighting that it was uninhabitable for a while.  Rupert forced John to hand over the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hadamar">Hadamar</ref> to Anna.  They divided the territory.</p>
<figure><caption>Twin towers of Greifenstein Castle</caption></figure>
<p>In 1381, King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslaus,_King_of_the_Romans">Wenceslaus</ref> appointed Rupert governor of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wetterau">Wetterau</ref>.  This triggered a second feud against Nassau-Dillenburg, which lasted until 1382.  In 1382, Rupert and the Counts of Solms-Burgsolms expanded <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greifenstein_Castle">Greifenstein Castle</ref> and added the characteristic twin towers.  Also in 1382, yet another feud against Nassau-Dillenburg broke out, which lasted until 1385.</p>
<p>After the feud he fought in the <hi rend="italic">Hattstein War</hi> on the side of the cities in the Rhine/Wetterau region, against the high nobility in the area.</p>
<p>Rupert died in 1390 and was buried in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kirchheimbolanden">Kirchheimbolanden</ref>.  As he had no children, Nassau-Sonnenberg was inherited by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philipp_I_of_Nassau-Weilburg">Philipp I of Nassau-Weilburg</ref></p>
<head>Marriage</head>
<p>In 1362, Rupert married Anna (d. 1404), a daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John,_Count_of_Nassau-Hadamar">John</ref> of Nassau-Hadamar and Elisabeth of Waldeck.  The marriage remained childless.  After Rupert's death, Anna married Count <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diether_VIII,_Count_of_Katzenelnbogen">Diether VIII</ref> of Katzenelnbogen (d. 1402).</p>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
