<text id="autogum_bio_doc084" title="In-Young Ahn" shortTile="young-ahn" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-06-03" dateModified="2018-06-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In-Young_Ahn" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>In-Young Ahn</head>
The native form of this <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_name">personal name</ref> is <hi rend="italic">Ahn In-Young</hi>.This article uses <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_name#Western_name_order">Western name order</ref> when mentioning individuals.
<p><hi rend="bold">In-Young Ahn</hi> is a South Korean scientist. She is known for being the first South Korean woman to visit <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antarctica">Antarctica</ref> and the first Asian woman to become an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Research_stations_in_Antarctica">Antarctic station</ref> leader (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_Sejong_Station">King Sejong Station</ref>).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref> She is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benthic_zone">benthic</ref> ecologist and is currently working as a principal research scientist for Korea Polar Research Institute.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-6">[6]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-7">[7]</ref></p>
<head>Early life and education</head>
<p>Ahn graduated from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seoul_National_University">Seoul National University</ref> in 1982 (majoring in Biological <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oceanography">Oceanography</ref>) and then received her PhD in Coastal Oceanography from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/State_University_of_New_York">State University of New York</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stony_Brook_University">Stony Brook</ref> in 1990. Ahn started her research at the Korean Polar Research Institute (KOPRI) on July 1, 1991.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Career and impact</head>
<p>Ahn was in charge of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Environmental_monitoring">environmental monitoring</ref> program at the King Sejong Station from 1996 to 2011, and conducted field surveys to obtain scientific data necessary for designation of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antarctic_Specially_Protected_Area">Antarctic Specially Protected Area</ref> (ASPA #171) near the Korean station. Ahn has also served as a representative and a National Contact Point of the Committee for Environmental Protection (CEP) at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antarctic_Treaty_System">Antarctic Treaty Consultative Meetings</ref> from 1997 through 2014, until she was designated as the overwintering officer-in-charge.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> Ahn served as the vice president of the Korea Polar Research Institute (KOPRI) from May 2010 to June 2012. She also served as Vice President of the Korean Society of Oceanography in 2010–2011,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> and Korea Federation of Women's Science &amp; Technology Associations in 2014 and 2015.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> She was expedition leader of the 28th overwintering team (2015) of the South Korean King Sejong Antarctic station, where she served as the station chief for about a year.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:2-6">[6]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:1-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Ahn's research interests include Antarctic marine <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benthic_zone">benthic ecology</ref> with special interests on benthic invertebrates and monitoring on Antarctic coastal marine ecosystems.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-:0-3">[3]</ref> She has studied the Antarctic clam <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laternula_elliptica">Laternula elliptica</ref></hi>, a dominant marine <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bivalvia">bivalve</ref> around Antarctic Continent. Ahn's current research includes studies on the impacts of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glacial_motion">glacier retreat</ref> on nearshore marine benthic communities around the King Sejong Station.</p>
<p>She is currently an adjunct professor at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korea_University_of_Science_and_Technology">University of Science &amp; Technology</ref> (UST), and a principal research scientist at the Korean Polar Institute (KOPRI), which forms part of Korea Institute of Ocean Science &amp; Technology (KIOST).</p>
<head>Awards and honors</head>
<p>The South Korean government awarded Ahn a Medal of Science &amp; Technology Merit for outstanding accomplishment in Antarctic Research in April 2001.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> She was further awarded a Commendation from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ministry_of_Environment_(South_Korea)">South Korean Ministry of Environment</ref> in June 2008 for her contribution in the designation of Antarctic Specially Protected Area (ASPA #171) near the King Sejong station.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref> In 2016, she additionally received South Korea's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orders,_decorations,_and_medals_of_South_Korea">Prime Minister's award</ref> in recognition of her achievement as the station leader at King Sejong station.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref></p>
<head>Selected works</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ahn, In-Young, et al. "First record of massive blooming of benthic diatoms and their association with megabenthic filter feeders on the shallow seafloor of an Antarctic fjord: Does glacier melting fuel the bloom?" <hi rend="italic">Ocean Science Journal</hi> 51. 2 (2016): 273–279.</item>
<item>HW Moon, WMRW Hussin, HC Kim,  In-Young Ahn*. "The Impacts of climate change on Antarctic nearshore mega-epifaunal benthic assemblages in a glacial fjord on King George Island: Responses and implications." <hi rend="italic">Ecological Indicators</hi> 57 (2015): 280–292.</item>
<item>Ahn, In-Young, et al. "Influence of glacial runoff on baseline metal accumulation in the Antarctic limpet Nacella concinna from King George Island." <hi rend="italic">Marine Pollution Bulletin</hi> 49 (2004): 119-141.</item>
<item>Ahn, In-Young, et al. "Growth and seasonal energetics of the Antarctic bivalve Laternula elliptica from King George Island, Antarctica." <hi rend="italic">Marine Ecology Progress Series</hi> 257(2003): 99–110.</item>
<item>Ahn, In-Young, et al. "Baseline heavy metal concentrations in the Antarctic clam, Laternula elliptica in Maxwell Bay, King George Island, Antarctica." <hi rend="italic">Marine Pollution Bulletin</hi> 32.8 (1996): 592–598.</item>
<item>Ahn, In-Young. "Enhanced particle flux through the biodeposition by the Antarctic suspension-feeding bivalve Laternula elliptica in Marian Cove, King George Island." <hi rend="italic">Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology</hi> 171.1 (1993): 75–90.</item></list>
</text>
