<text id="autogum_bio_doc733" title="Mary of Enghien" shortTile="mary-enghien" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-05-26" dateModified="2019-06-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_of_Enghien" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Mary of Enghien</head>
Not to be confused with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_of_Enghien">Maria of Enghien</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Mary of Enghien</hi>, also <hi rend="bold">Maria d'Enghien</hi>, (1367 or 1370 – 9 May 1446) was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Countess_of_Lecce">Countess of Lecce</ref> from 1384 to 1446, and Queen of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_of_Naples">Naples</ref> as well as titular Queen of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sicily">Sicily</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_of_Jerusalem">Jerusalem</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Hungarian_rulers">Hungary</ref> by marriage to Ladislaus of Naples in 1406-1414.</p>
<head>Biography</head>
<head>Family</head>
<p>She was the daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Enghien">John of Enghien</ref>, Count of Castro, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sancia_Del_Balzo">Sancia Del Balzo</ref>. Her father was the third son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabella_of_Brienne">Isabella of Brienne</ref> (who died in 1360) and her husband Walter of Enghien (who had died in 1345).</p>
<p>Her paternal grandmother Isabella survived her brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter_VI_of_Brienne">Walter VI of Brienne</ref>, titular Duke of Athens etc., who died without surviving issue in 1356 at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Poitiers_(1356)">Battle of Poitiers</ref>. As his heir, she became Countess of Lecce and Brienne etc., as well as titular Duchess of Athens. Since her eldest son Walter had died before her brother, her heir was her second son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sohier_of_Enghien">Sohier of Enghien</ref>. She allowed her inherited lands to be divided between her numerous children during her own lifetime. Mary's father, the third (but second surviving) son, had received the County of Lecce and the lordship of Castro.</p>
<head>Countess of Lecce</head>
<p>Mary's father John died in 1380, leaving minor children. Mary's brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_of_Enghien">Peter of Enghien</ref>, also called Pyrrhus (Pyrro or Pirro), became the Count of Lecce. However, Peter died childless in 1384 and was succeeded by Mary and her husband <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raimondo_del_Balzo_Orsini">Raimondo del Balzo Orsini</ref> di Nola, whom she married that same year in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taranto">Taranto</ref>.</p>
<p>Chroniclers describe her as beautiful, intrepid and adventurous: adored by her children, loved by her first husband, besieged by King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ladislaus_of_Naples">Ladislaus of Naples</ref>, and treated cruelly by the king's sister.</p>
<p>She stayed in her castles of Lecce and Copertino when Raimondo travelled, and gave his services to the king against the papal troops and supporters of the junior Angevin line. She was occupied by their children, Marias, Caterina, Giovanni Antonio, and Gabriele.</p>
<p>Raimondo was created <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principality_of_Taranto">Prince of Taranto</ref> (in her hereditary rights) and died in 1406.</p>
<head>Queen of Naples</head>
<p>After his husband's death, she was sieged in Taranto (1406) and resisted the troops of Ladislaus till he decided to propose her to be his wife. So she was forced to marry Ladislaus and the wedding was held in the chapel of the Castle of Taranto. Her second marriage was childless. Ladislaus died on 6 August 1414; his sister and successor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_II_of_Naples">Joan II of Naples</ref>, described as cruel, hated Mary and imprisoned her. Joan's husband <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_II,_Count_of_La_Marche">James II, Count of La Marche</ref>, however, soon allowed her to go.  She returned to Lecce, Joan having driven her and her children from the royal domains, back to Tarentine lands.</p>
<p>Mary lived a long life, dying at the age of 78. She witnessed the marriage of her granddaughter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabella_of_Clermont">Isabella of Clermont</ref>, daughter of Tristan and Catherine and an heiress of remarkable feudal possessions in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southern_Italy">Southern Italy</ref>, to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferdinand_I_of_Naples">Ferdinand of Aragon</ref> in 1444. He was the bastard son of King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfonso_V_of_Aragon">Alfonso V of Aragon</ref>, who had conquered Southern Italy in 1441.</p>
<head>Children</head>
<p>Her children were:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Maria del Balzo Orsini (died after 1410), married Antonio di Acquaviva, Duke of Atri, etc. Childless.</item>
<item>Caterina del Balzo Orsini, also known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_of_Taranto,_Countess_of_Copertino">Catherine of Taranto</ref>. Married with Bartholomew Tristan of Clermont (Bartolomeo Tristano di Chiaramonte or Chiaromonte), a knight of the French family of de Clermont-Lodeve. Tristan became Count of Capertino by the dowry of his wife. (That Catherine del Balzo Orsini who lived almost in the same period and married Giulio Antonio di Aragona di Acquaviva, Duke of Atri, etc., bringing him the dowry of Casamassima and Conversano, apparently was not this Catherine but a kinswoman, perhaps daughter of Giovanni Antonio or daughter of Gabriel, Duke of Venosa.)</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Antonio_del_Balzo_Orsini">Giovanni Antonio del Balzo Orsini</ref>, John, Prince of Taranto. Died childless in 1463, when his niece Isabella brought the fiefs to her husband King Ferrante.</item>
<item>(possibly natural son of her husband) Gabriele del Balzo Orsini (d. 1453), Count of Ugento, etc., Duke of Venosa. Married Giovanna Caracciolo del Sole dei Duchi di Melfi.</item></list>
</text>
