<text id="autogum_bio_doc708" title="Secondotto, Marquess of Montferrat" shortTile="secondotto-marquess" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-12-20" dateModified="2018-07-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secondotto%2C_Marquess_of_Montferrat" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Secondotto, Marquess of Montferrat</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Secondotto Palaeologus</hi> (also <hi rend="italic">Otho</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Ottone</hi>; died 16 December 1378) was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margrave_of_Montferrat">Margrave of Montferrat</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref> from 1372 to his death, the third of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Byzantine_Greece">Greek</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palaeologan_dynasty">Palaeologan dynasty</ref>. His name <hi rend="italic">Secondotto</hi> may derive from his being the second Otto to rule Montferrat in his own right, though he would really be <hi rend="bold">Otto III</hi>. More probably it is derived from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Secundus">Saint Secundus</ref> (<hi rend="italic">San Secondo</hi> in Italian), the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patron_saint">patron saint</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asti">Asti</ref>, which his father treated as the capital of the marquisate.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-will-2">[2]</ref> The <hi rend="italic">Otto</hi> may be in honour of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otto,_Duke_of_Brunswick-Grubenhagen">Otto, Duke of Brunswick-Grubenhagen</ref>, a close ally of his father.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dbi-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>He was born around 1360 as the first son of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_II_of_Montferrat">John II</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isabella_of_Majorca">Isabella of Majorca</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dbi-3">[3]</ref> In December 1361, as part of a peace deal made between John II and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galeazzo_II_Visconti">Galeazzo II Visconti</ref>, co-lord of Milan, he was betrothed to the latter’s four-year-old daughter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Visconti">Maria</ref>. The city of Asti, on which Galeazzo had also had designs, was to count as part of Maria’s dowry, and Montferrat would be allowed to retain control of it. The peace was short-lived, however, as Maria died in the May of the following year.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dbi-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cronica-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>He succeeded as a child of around 12, and ruled originally under the co-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent">regency</ref> of his uncle Otto, Duke of Brunswick-Grubenhagen, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amadeus_VI_of_Savoy">Amadeus VI of Savoy</ref>. His father’s will had stipulated that he should remain under his uncle’s tutelage until the age of 25; however Otto left for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naples">Naples</ref> in 1376 to marry <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan_I_of_Naples">Queen Joan I</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Maestri-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>Weak and inept, Secondotto could not carry the weight of government which devolved on his shoulders with the absence of his uncle. Secondotto thus decided to marry <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Violante_Visconti">Violante</ref> (2 August 1377), the daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galeazzo_II_Visconti">Galeazzo II Visconti</ref>, and widow of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lionel_of_Antwerp,_1st_Duke_of_Clarence">Lionel of Antwerp, 1st Duke of Clarence</ref>, and affirm an alliance with that family against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Savoy">House of Savoy</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_of_Piedmont">Piedmont</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principality_of_Achaea">Achaea</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Maestri-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>When Otto of Brunswick's brother attacked and seized Asti, Secondotto called in the aid of his father-in-law, who, with a huge force, retook Asti and maintained it under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milan">Milanese</ref> control. Secondotto realised at that juncture the danger of his Milanese alliance, but by then it was too late. He gathered a force and led it against the Milanese troops and was defeated. Probably out of fear, he retreated to an unknown destination. He died at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Langhirano">Langhirano</ref> in the vicinity of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parma">Parma</ref> in obscure circumstances: he may simply have been the loser in a brawl (he was famously ill-tempered and violent), or he may have been assassinated by an agent of the Visconti. His body was carried to Parma and buried before the high altar of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parma_Cathedral">the cathedral</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Maestri-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-cook-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>When his uncle received news of his death, he returned at once to the margraviate to handle the succession. He placed Secondotto's brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_III_of_Montferrat">John III</ref> on the Montferrat throne. Despite the involvement of Emperor-elect <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wenceslaus,_King_of_the_Romans">Wenceslaus</ref>, the negotiations which Otto opened with Gian Galeazzo over the recovery of Asti were fruitless.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Maestri-5">[5]</ref></p>
<head>Ancestry</head>
</text>
