<text id="autogum_bio_doc739" title="Anna, Grand Duchess of Lithuania" shortTile="anna-grand-duchess" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-07-09" dateModified="2019-05-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna%2C_Grand_Duchess_of_Lithuania" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Anna, Grand Duchess of Lithuania</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Anna</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuanian_language">Lithuanian</ref>: <hi lang="lt" rend="italic">Ona Vytautienė</hi>; died on 31 July 1418 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trakai">Trakai</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vald-1">[1]</ref>) was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Duchess_of_Lithuania">Grand Duchess of Lithuania</ref> (1392–1418). She probably was the first wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vytautas_the_Great">Vytautas the Great</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Duke_of_Lithuania">Grand Duke of Lithuania</ref>. Anna was mother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sophia_of_Lithuania">Sophia of Lithuania</ref>, the only child of Vytautas and wife of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vasily_I_of_Moscow">Vasily I of Moscow</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vald-1">[1]</ref> She is best remembered for helping Vytautas to escape from a prison in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kreva">Kreva</ref> in 1382 and thus probably saving his life. Little is known about Anna's life and even her origins remain disputed by historians.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<head>During the civil wars</head>
<p>Likely Anna and Vytautas were married around 1370.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vald-1">[1]</ref> Anna first comes to light in 1382 when her husband was imprisoned in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kreva_Castle">Kreva Castle</ref> by his cousin <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jogaila">Jogaila</ref> during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuanian_Civil_War_(1381–1384)">Lithuanian Civil War (1381–1384)</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-el-2">[2]</ref> While all accounts agree that she freed her husband, details vary from source to source. It is unclear how much freedom Anna had in Kreva and if she was guarded. It is written in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuanian_Chronicles">Lithuanian Chronicles</ref> that she had two maids with her. She convinced one of them to exchange clothes with Vytautas who then escaped undetected.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ignasp-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-turnbull-4">[4]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wigand_of_Marburg">Wigand of Marburg</ref> claimed that Vytautas dressed in Anna's clothes rather than one of Anna's maids.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ignasp-3">[3]</ref> It is believed that Anna remained in Kreva and no information is available on how she escaped or was released.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-el-2">[2]</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teodor_Narbutt">Teodor Narbutt</ref> (1784–1864) later added many colorful details to the story, including Vytautas illness and maid Alena, who sacrificed herself to save her master.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ignasp-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>In 1389, when her husband's coup to capture <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vilnius">Vilnius</ref> failed, she was in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hrodna">Hrodna</ref>. After the failed coup Anna followed her husband to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teutonic_Knights">Teutonic Knights</ref>, where Vytautas asked for an alliance against his cousins Jogaila and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skirgaila">Skirgaila</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuanian_Civil_War_(1389–1392)">Lithuanian Civil War (1389–1392)</ref>. For a while she was held hostage to guarantee that Vytautas would not break the alliance.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-urbant-5">[5]</ref> After the disagreements were settled in 1392, Anna confirmed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ostrów_Agreement">Ostrów Agreement</ref>, the peace treaty which made Vytautas the Grand Duke of Lithuania. She signed two letters, one given to Jogaila and another to his wife <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jadwiga_of_Poland">Jadwiga of Poland</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-el-2">[2]</ref> Anna continued to be active in political life and attended negotiations for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Salynas">Treaty of Salynas</ref> (1398).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-el-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Later life</head>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kęstutis">Kęstutis</ref> and his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vytautas">Vytautas</ref> imprisoned in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kreva">Kreva</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jogaila">Jogaila</ref> in 1382. Kęstutis died within a week. Vytautas remained locked up for couple months before being saved by his wife Anna.</caption></figure>
<p>Before 1396, she and her husband traveled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Késmárk">Késmárk</ref> to meet King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigismund_of_Hungary">Sigismund of Hungary</ref> to establish a friendly relationship. While they spoke for a long time, half of the city burned, leading the Hungarian nobles to think that Vytautas's people had to do with it. Sigismund intervened and cleared up the situation, resuming the negotiations. After the visit was finished, the Duke and his wife Anna gave many presents to Sigismund including a coat, a hat and gloves made of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sable">sable</ref>-skin and embroiled with gold. The details of all these presents "given by Vytautas's wife" remained in a chronicle from the end of the 15th century written by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eberhard_Windercke">Eberhard Windercke</ref>, close servant nobleman of the Hungarian King (who later was also King of Bohemia and Holy Roman Emperor).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-wider-6">[6]</ref></p>
<p>In 1400, Anna visited the tomb of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dorothy_of_Montau">Dorothy of Montau</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kwidzyn">Marienwerder</ref> (modern Kwidzyn), and prayed in the churches of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Anne">Saint Anne</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ushakovo,_Kaliningrad_Oblast">Brandenburg</ref> and of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Barbara">Saint Barbara</ref> in Oldenburg.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vald-1">[1]</ref> She was accompanied by her brother-in-law <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigismund_Kęstutaitis">Sigismund Kęstutaitis</ref> and an escort of 400 men.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vald-1">[1]</ref> Anna was greeted with expensive gifts and lavish receptions.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-urban-7">[7]</ref> Anna continued to maintain good relationship with the Teutonic Knights, who sent her expensive gifts, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clavichord">clavichord</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portative_organ">portative organ</ref> in 1408 and rare wine in 1416.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ignas68-8">[8]</ref> After her death all churches in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prussia_(region)">Prussia</ref> were ordered to hold <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Requiem_mass">requiem masses</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-el-2">[2]</ref> Various chronicles and documents recorded much less positive interaction between Anna and Poland.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ignas68-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>It is believed that St. Anne's Church, built in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vilnius_Castle_Complex">Vilnius Lower Castle</ref> before 1390, was so named in Anna's honor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-urbant-5">[5]</ref> It was later known as St. Barbara's Church but did not survive to the present.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-kviklys-9">[9]</ref> Flemish traveler <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guillebert_de_Lannoy">Guillebert de Lannoy</ref> wrote favorably about the Grand Duchess.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-el-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>After her death in 1418 Vytautas wanted to marry her niece <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uliana_Olshanska">Uliana Olshanska</ref>, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Olshanski">Ivan Olshanski</ref>. Polish historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_Długosz">Jan Długosz</ref> asserts that Ivan of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karachev">Karachev</ref>, first husband of Uliana, was murdered by Vytautas in order to marry her.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rowell-10">[10]</ref> The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Vilnius">Bishop of Vilnius</ref> refused the ceremony due to their close relationship (Vytautas was Uliana's uncle-in-law) and demanded they seek approval from the pope. Eventually the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop_of_Włocławek">Bishop of Włocławek</ref> performed the ceremony.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-urban-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ignas68-8">[8]</ref></p>
<head>Origin</head>
<p>There is considerable debate about who the parents of Anna were. According to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bychowiec_Chronicle">Bychowiec Chronicle</ref>, a late and unreliable source, Anna was a sister of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yuri_of_Smolensk">Yuri Svyatoslavich</ref>, the last sovereign ruler of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smolensk">Smolensk</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Хроника_Быховца-11">[11]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ignas-12">[12]</ref> For a long time this was the only theory about her origins. </p>
<p>In 1933, Lithuanian historian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ignas_Jonynas">Ignas Jonynas</ref> published a study in which he attempted to debunk the Bychowiec Chronicle and demonstrate that Anna was not an Orthodox duchess from Slavic lands, but a daughter of a local <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuanian_nobility">Lithuanian noble</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ignas-12">[12]</ref> Jonynas pointed out that no other contemporary source mentions the relationship between Vytautas and Yuri even though Lithuania and Smolensk were at war several times. The First <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithuanian_Chronicle">Lithuanian Chronicle</ref>, the basis for which was written while Vytautas was still alive, describes in detail how wars against Smolensk was waged in 1386, 1395, 1401, and 1404, but mentions nothing about Vytautas and Yuri being in-laws.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ignas-12">[12]</ref> Jonynas argued that Anna was a sister of Sudimantas,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ignas59-13">[13]</ref> a nobleman from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eišiškės">Eišiškės</ref> and commander of Vytautas' army.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-el-2">[2]</ref> Teutonic Chronicle mentions Sudimantas as <hi rend="italic">swoger</hi> of Vytautas.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-did-14">[14]</ref> At the time <hi rend="italic">swoger</hi> meant <hi rend="italic">brother-in-law</hi>. Another document from 1416 refers to Sudimantas as <hi rend="italic">magen</hi>, which denoted a relative, usually related by blood.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-did-14">[14]</ref> Since Jonynas' study, Sudimantas has been variously presented as Anna's brother,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-el-2">[2]</ref> father,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vald-1">[1]</ref> or sister's husband.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-rowell-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>Polish historian Jan Tęgowski disagreed with Jonynas and argued that both Sudimantas and Lev of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drutsk">Drutsk</ref> (who is also mentioned as Vytautas' <hi rend="italic">swoger</hi>) were married to sisters of Vytautas's first wife, Princess Maria of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lukoml">Lukoml</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-teg-15">[15]</ref> Jonynas expressed serious doubts if Maria, daughter of Andrei, existed at all.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ignas47-16">[16]</ref> Information about her is found in the same unreliable Bychowiec Chronicle.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Хроника_Быховца-11">[11]</ref> The only contemporary source that mentions Maria of Lukoml dates from 1440–1443 and concerns division of her estate after her death and makes no mention of her relationship with Vytautas.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ignas47-16">[16]</ref> Tęgowski also pointed out that a document from 1413 mentions a "Russian duke Basil" as Vytautas's brother-in-law. Indeed, one of Yuri's (and, by extension, Anna's) brothers was named Basil.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-teg-15">[15]</ref></p>
</text>
