<text id="autogum_bio_doc088" title="Vernon County Jane Doe" shortTile="vernon-county-jane" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-06-30" dateModified="2019-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vernon_County_Jane_Doe" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Vernon County Jane Doe</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Vernon County Jane Doe</hi> is an American murder victim whose body was found on May 4, 1984. Her identity remains unknown.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jane_Doe_1984_-_Vernon_County-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NamUs_UP_#_4786-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Case_File_261UFWI-3">[3]</ref> Her hands had been removed, probably to prevent identification by means of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fingerprinting">fingerprinting</ref>.</p>
<p>The case has been heavily investigated since discovery of the body, with no progress toward finding either her identity or her murderer.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-new-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>Discovery of the body</head>
<p>The body was found on the night of May 4, 1984, near the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westby,_Wisconsin">Westby, Wisconsin</ref> at 11:15.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-new-4">[4]</ref> It was found by three teenagers within 24 to 48 hours after her death.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-justice1-5">[5]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-fbiwi-6">[6]</ref> There was extensive damage to the victim's head, which left her face unrecognizable until mortuary procedures were conducted.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-asu-7">[7]</ref> After the case was broadcast on the news, a couple stated that they had seen a suspicious man near the location. He was returning to the driver's seat of a yellow car, believed to be a 1982 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Datsun">Datsun</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> When police went to the spot, they found tire tracks from a hasty <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U-turn">U-turn</ref>. A broken <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dentures">denture</ref>, blood, and a man's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Watch">watch</ref> were also found there.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jane_Doe_1984_-_Vernon_County-1">[1]</ref> Because of this evidence, it is believed that she was killed at another location alongside the same road, and that her body was then taken to the location where she was found.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>The victim had been murdered, as she suffered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blunt_force_injury">blunt force injury</ref> to her head, which had broken her jaw, an eye socket and the pair of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dentures">dentures</ref> that she was wearing. There was also sharp-force trauma to the left side of the head, near the ear.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-asu-7">[7]</ref> Her hands had been removed, most likely to prevent identification through <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fingerprint">fingerprint</ref> matching.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Jane_Doe_1984_-_Vernon_County-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Case_File_261UFWI-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Millard-10">[10]</ref></p>
<head>Description and clothing</head>
<p>Vernon County Jane Doe was a white woman between 50 and 65 years old. She had graying brown hair, presumed to have been done in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Permanent_wave">perm</ref>. She was 5 feet 5 to 5 feet 6 inches (approximately 170cm). She did not appear to have any unique physical features.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-new-4">[4]</ref> She weighed 150 pounds (68kg) and had worn dentures, probably those that were found with her body.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-fbiwi-6">[6]</ref> The dentures, missing two teeth, had both raised and indented numbers upon them, believed to be serial numbers. Despite this, investigators have stated that serial numbers for the given product were not assigned to specific recipients, which would not yield clues to the victim's identity.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-asu-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>She was wearing a multicolored coat, a black dress decorated with a blue-and-white <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paisley_(design)">paisley print</ref>, a blue <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turtleneck_sweater">turtleneck sweater</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nylon_stockings">nylon stockings</ref>. The brand labels of the clothing had been removed.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Case_File_261UFWI-3">[3]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vernon-11">[11]</ref> There were  distinctive buttons on her clothes; these had unique stitching.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></p>
<head>Investigation</head>
<p>Over 4,000 leads have surfaced in the case, one recently being the arrest of multiple persons who fraudulently used checks from a missing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amherst,_Wisconsin">Amherst, Wisconsin</ref> woman who disappeared around the same time as when the Jane Doe was found.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref></p>
<p>Despite the possible link to Amherst, police believe that she did not reside in the area where she was found.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-vernon-11">[11]</ref> Seven missing women have been ruled out as possible identities.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-NamUs_UP_#_4786-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-news8000.com-15">[15]</ref></p>
<p>Authorities have used news media multiple times toward identifying the victim. In 2012, officials "pushed" the case to reach areas of both Minnesota and Wisconsin that were linked to Highway 14.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-new-4">[4]</ref> The case was broadcast in a three-day news special, titled as "Catching Her Killer: Justice for Jane Doe," to uncover new leads in 2013. Yet no lead so far has proved useful.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-justice1-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>She was interred in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viroqua">Viroqua</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cemetery">cemetery</ref>. Her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Headstone">headstone</ref> bears the words "Jane Doe" and the date of the discovery of her body.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-justice1-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>On August 12, 2015, her body was exhumed and sent to the crime lab in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madison,_Wisconsin">Madison, Wisconsin</ref>, for testing in hopes of identifying her. The body was returned and buried the next day. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA">DNA</ref> was also harvested and began processing at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_North_Texas">University of North Texas</ref>. A new <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forensic_facial_reconstruction">forensic facial reconstruction</ref> of the victim was released in December 2015 by a University in Arizona that created the likeness based on physical characteristics of the woman's skull.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-new-4">[4]</ref> The rendering was completed by forensic artist Catyana Falsetti, whose husband was also working on the case at the University.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-asu-7">[7]</ref></p>
<p>Forensic testing on the pollen present on the victim's clothing in 2018 indicated she may have originated from Arizona or New Mexico.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></p>
<p>Authorities would later seek assistance from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA_Doe_Project">DNA Doe Project</ref> in hopes to identify the victim.
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref></p>
<head>Gallery</head>
<list type="unordered">
<item>Morgue photograph</item>
<item>Morgue photograph</item>
<item>Morgue photograph</item>
<item>Dress and coat</item>
<item>Upper portions of clothing</item>
<item>Shoe</item>
<item>Upper denture</item>
</list>
</text>
