<text id="autogum_bio_doc510" title="Samuel Brooke" shortTile="samuel-brooke" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-01-07" dateModified="2019-10-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Brooke" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Samuel Brooke</head><p>
Dr <hi rend="bold">Samuel Brooke</hi> (1575-1631) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gresham_Professor_of_Divinity">Gresham Professor of Divinity</ref> (appointed 1612), a playwright, the chaplain of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trinity_College,_Cambridge">Trinity College, Cambridge</ref> and subsequently the Master of Trinity (1629-1631). He was known to be an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arminianism_in_the_Church_of_England">Arminian</ref> and anti-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calvinist">Calvinist</ref>. In 1631 he was appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archdeacon_of_Coventry">archdeacon of Coventry</ref>.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was the son of Robert Brooke of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York">York</ref>,  the brother of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Brooke">Christopher Brooke</ref> who appears in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Wither">George Wither</ref>'s eclogues under the pastoral name of Cuddie. Samuel Brooke was educated at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westminster_School">Westminster School</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trinity_College,_Cambridge">Trinity College, Cambridge</ref>, where he was admitted in 1596; he proceeded M.A. 1604, B.D. 1607, and D.D. 1615.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>He was imprisoned for a short period, by the action of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir_George_More">Sir George More</ref>, for secretly celebrating the marriage of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Donne">John Donne</ref> with More's daughter. He was promoted to the office of chaplain to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Frederick,_Prince_of_Wales">Henry Frederick, Prince of Wales</ref>, who recommended him (26 September 1612) as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gresham_Professor_of_Divinity">Gresham Professor of Divinity</ref>; he was later chaplain to both James I and Charles I.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>On 13 June 1618 he became rector of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Margaret,_Lothbury">St Margaret, Lothbury</ref>, London, and 10 July 1621 was incorporated D.D. at Oxford. He was elected master of Trinity College, Cambridge, 5 September 1629, and on 17 November resigned his Gresham professorship. On 13 May 1631 Brooke was admitted archdeacon of Coventry, and he died 16 September 1632. He was buried without monument or epitaph in Trinity College Chapel.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Works</head>
<p>In 1614 he wrote three Latin plays, which were performed before James I on his visit to the university in that year. The names of the plays were recorded as <hi rend="italic">Scyros</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Adelphe</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Melanthe</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-2">[2]</ref> <hi rend="italic">Adelphe</hi> derives from <hi rend="italic">La Sorella</hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giambattista_della_Porta">Giambattista della Porta</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> A central character in <hi rend="italic">Melanthe</hi> is Nicander, the loutish heir of a rich father, who is laughed at and kicked around by the heroine Ermilla, before she finally decides to accept him as her husband.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> The play also contains a chorus of dancing satyrs.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Prynne">William Prynne</ref> in his <hi rend="italic">Canterburie's Doome</hi> attacked Brooke as a disciple of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Laud">William Laud</ref>, and stated that in 1630 Brooke was engaged on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arminian">Arminian</ref> treatise on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Predestination">predestination</ref>. Laud encouraged him to complete this book, but afterwards declined to sanction its publication on account of a general prohibition on debating the subject.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> None of Brooke's works were printed. Besides the treatise already mentioned, a manuscript of the first three books of which is in Trinity College Library, he wrote a tract on the Thirty-nine Articles, and a discourse, dedicated to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl_of_Pembroke">Earl of Pembroke</ref>, entitled <hi rend="italic">De Auxilio Divinæ Gratiæ Exercitatio theologica, nimirum: An possibile sit duos eandem habere Gratiæ Mensuram, et tamen unus convertatur et credat; alter non: e Johan. xi. 45, 46.</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DNB-2">[2]</ref> The manuscript of this is in the Cambridge University Library.</p>
<head>Manuscripts</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Trinity College, Cambridge, MS B. 15. 13. 'De Natura &amp; Ordine divinæ Prædestinationis in Ecclesiâ, vel intra Ecclesiam Dei.'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref></item>
<item>Cambridge University Library, MS Additional 44, item 16. 'De Auxilio Divinæ Gratiæ Exercitatio theologica.'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></item></list>
</text>
