<text id="autogum_bio_doc309" title="Gabriël Grupello" shortTile="gabriel-grupello" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-02-28" dateModified="2018-05-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabri%C3%ABl_Grupello" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gabriël Grupello</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Gabriël Grupello</hi> (also <hi rend="bold">Gabriël de Grupello</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Gabriël Reppeli</hi>; 22 May 1644 – 20 June 1730) was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southern_Netherlands">Flemish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baroque">Baroque</ref> sculptor who produced religious and mythological sculptures, portraits and public sculptures. He was a virtuoso sculptor who enjoyed the patronage of several European rulers.</p>
<head>Life</head>
<head>Early life and training</head>
<p>Grupello was born as the son of Bernardo Rupelli, an Italian cavalry captain in Spanish service, and his Flemish wife Cornelia Delinck.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nbw-1">[1]</ref> His father, who died at a young age, was a member of the higher non-aristocratic class of society. Grupello later styled himself as Chevalier de Grupello, but a noble ancestry has not been demonstrated.</p>
<p>At age 14, he started a five-year training as a sculptor in the Antwerp workshop of leading Baroque sculptor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artus_Quellinus_I">Artus Quellinus I</ref>. He may have assisted Quellinus with the sculptural decorations in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Palace_of_Amsterdam">Royal Palace of Amsterdam</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ox-2">[2]</ref> He completed a further two years of study in Paris and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Versailles_(city)">Versailles</ref>, where he was in contact with his compatriots <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philippe_de_Buyster">Philippe de Buyster</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerard_van_Opstal">Gerard van Opstal</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Desjardins">Martin Desjardins</ref> and learned the technique of bronze casting. He subsequently worked for two years for the sculptor Johan Larson in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hague">The Hague</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nbw-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>In Brussels</head>
<figure><caption>Head of a horse, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schwetzingen_Castle">Schwetzingen Castle</ref></caption></figure>
<p>He returned to Flanders in 1671 and two years later he became a master of the Brussels Guild. He opened a workshop in Brussels, which became very successful and employed many assistants. He enjoyed the patronage of the city as well as that of various European rulers, including the Spanish king <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_II_of_Spain">Charles II</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_II,_Prince_of_Orange">William II of Orange</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_I_of_Prussia">Frederick III, the Elector of Brandenburg</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ox-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>During his time in Brussels, he also fathered a son (born 1671) and a daughter (born 1674) with his mistress Johanna Louisa Quebault (Tebout).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nbw-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>In Germany</head>
<p>In 1695, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Wilhelm,_Elector_Palatine">Elector Johann Wilhelm</ref> appointed Grupello as his official court sculptor and Grupello then moved to live and work in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Düsseldorf">Düsseldorf</ref>. He created numerous sculptures of the royal couple in marble and bronze, and was responsible for the supervision of craftsmen who worked on the Elector's palaces. Grupello also designed a fountain known as the Grupello pyramid for the Galerieplatz in Düsseldorf (now in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mannheim">Mannheim</ref>).</p>
<p>Grupello married Anna Maria Dautzenberg, the daughter of the Elector's lawyer, in 1698. Five children were born from this marriage.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nbw-1">[1]</ref> The Elector gave Grupello in 1708 a house in the city centre.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-dus-3">[3]</ref> The house, which is still called the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grupello-Haus">Grupello-Haus</ref></hi> or "Grupello House", is believed to have been designed by the Italian architect <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matteo_Alberti_(architect)">Matteo Alberti</ref>. Grupello carried out an important reconstruction of the building and used the house as the living quarters of his family and partially also as a studio. Originally, two busts representing the Greek goddesses <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artemis">Artemis</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aphrodite">Aphrodite</ref> presumed to be by Grupello were placed above the portal of the house. The original bronze statues are now in the local Stadtmuseum Landeshauptstadt Düsseldorf and have been replaced by two concrete cast replicas.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>With the death of Elector Johann Wilhelm in 1716, the employment of the sculptor at the court came to an end. Elector Johann Wilhelm's successor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_III_Philip,_Elector_Palatine">Elector Carl Philipp</ref> introduced austerity measures and dismissed officials and artists.  Grupello continued to live in Düsseldorf and in 1619 the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_VI,_Holy_Roman_Emperor">Holy Roman Emperor Charles VI</ref> appointed him as Imperial sculptor.</p>
<p>In 1725, Grupello and his wife moved into the quarters at Ehrenstein Castle in Kerkrade (now in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref>) of their daughter, who was married to an imperial official. He died there in 1730 at the age of 86years.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nbw-1">[1]</ref></p>
<head>Work</head>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Narcissus_(mythology)">Narcissus</ref>, 1680–85, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Museums_of_Fine_Arts_of_Belgium">Royal Museums of Fine Arts of Belgium</ref></caption></figure>
<p>Grupello was a versatile artist in terms of the subject range of his sculptures as well as the materials in which he worked. He executed works in marble, ivory and wood and was rare among his contemporary Flemish Baroque sculptors in that he also made bronze statues. A prime example is the bronze equestrian statue of the Elector Johann Wilhelm.</p>
<p>His early work shows a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classicism">classicist</ref> tendency, which may be due to his study period in France. In Brussels, his work was influenced by the Flemish Baroque, and in particular <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Paul_Rubens">Peter Paul Rubens</ref>, and developed into a full-blown Baroque style.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nbw-1">[1]</ref> A major work that Grupello created in this style in Brussels is the marble wall fountain, intended for the main ballroom of the wholesale fishmongers guild. It is this Baroque style that he brought to Düsseldorf when he moved there. In his later life, he turned more to religious art and produced crucifixes, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madonna_(art)">Madonnas</ref> and statues of saints.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-nbw-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-ox-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Gallery</head>
<list type="unordered">
<item>Grupello's <hi rend="italic">Verwachting</hi> in de Zavelkerk, rechts van <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hiëronymus_Duquesnoy_de_Jonge">Duquesnoy</ref>'s Heilige Ursula</item>
<item>Gabriël Grupello, Mother of God, c. 1725, linden wood. Museum Schnütgen, Cologne</item>
<item>Muurfontein met zeegoden, detail</item>
<item>Muurfontein met zeegoden, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tethys_(mythologie)">Tethys</ref></item>
<item>Ruiterstandbeeld in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Düsseldorf">Düsseldorf</ref></item>
<item>Grupellopiramide te <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mannheim">Mannheim</ref></item>
<item>Onze-Lieve-Vrouw ten Zavelkzek, Brussel (België). Portaal van de Heilige Ursulakapel (1651-1676). Beelden door Grupello</item>
<item>Galathea (um 1715) von Gabriel de Grupello</item>
</list>
</text>
