<text id="autogum_bio_doc686" title="Pedro de San Superano" shortTile="pedro-de-san-superano" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-11-15" dateModified="2018-03-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedro_de_San_Superano" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pedro de San Superano</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pedro de San Superano</hi> (also spelled <hi rend="bold">San Superán</hi>, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_language">French</ref> <hi rend="italic">Pierre de Saint-Superan</hi>; died 1402) was one of the captains of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Navarrese_Company">Navarrese Company</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morea">Morea</ref> from 1379 until he was made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince_of_Achaea">Prince of Achaea</ref> in 1396, a post he held to his death.</p>
<head>Names</head>
<p>Pedro de San Superano appears with a significant number of names in the bibliography. Below, his name is shown as used by himself, as well as by contemporaries in letters of the period. Furthermore, the multitude of different names in later bibliography is also presented.</p>
<p>In a letter of 17 July 1385, Pedro himself signs as <hi rend="bold">Petro de Sancto Superano</hi>, capitano Principatus de la Morerya (during the time that he was military captain in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principality_of_Achaia">Principality of Morea</ref>, while Mahiot de Coquerel was bailli of the Principality).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>On 12 September 1382, in another letter, he is referred to as <hi rend="bold">lo bort den Sen Subra</hi>, which the author of the book (1947) inscribes with a question mark and explains: «<hi rend="bold">Bort de Sant Cebriá</hi> (also known as <hi rend="bold">Pere de San Superano</hi>)»<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In a letter of 17 April 1387, he is referred to as <hi rend="bold">Petro de Sent Siura</hi> capetano e vicario generali principatus d Acaya <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<p>At the same book of 1947, the author comments a letter of Agnes Acciajuoli, who was writing to her brother Donat) and he refers to Pedro as «<hi rend="bold">Pierre Bordeaux de Saint Superán</hi>, the so-called Bort de Sant Cebriá».<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>In a book of 1907, obtain the information that <hi rend="bold">Pierre de San Superan</hi> and Varvassa, commanders, are mentioned for the first time in 1380, as well as that San Superan received the citizenship of Bordeaux from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward,_the_Black_Prince">Black Prince</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>In another work he appears as <hi rend="bold">Pierre Bordeaux de Saint Superan, Signore de Landirans</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> Saint Superan (in French) or San Superano (in Catalan) refers to a castle, possibly close to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landiras">Landiras</ref> 19 miles south-southeast of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bordeaux">Bordeaux</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref> In the area of Landiras there is a castle (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Château_de_Landiras">Château de Landiras</ref>) built in 1306.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref></p>
<p>In an edition of 1913 Pedro is referred to as <hi rend="bold">S. Superan-Landiras</hi>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>From a reference of 1382, he appears as <hi rend="bold">Pierre Lebourd de Saint-Supéran</hi>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref> together with Bérard de Varvassa and elsewhere just <hi rend="bold">Pierre Lebourd</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref> and in anοther modification as  <hi rend="bold">Petrus Lebord de Sancto Superano</hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref></p>
<p>In a source of 1994 he is referred to as <hi rend="bold">Pedro Bordo de San Superano</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref> and in another from 1885 <hi rend="bold">Pedro Bordo de St. Exupery</hi> with the explanation "or the bastard of San Superano".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref></p>
<p>Finally, in a source of 1883, he is referred to as «<hi rend="bold">Pierre de Saint Exupéry</hi>, called in latin and italian texts as Petrus de Sancto Superano, Petro de San Superano, named Bordo or Bordeaux from the place of his birth».<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-15">[15]</ref></p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>After the remnants of the first Navarrese company moved from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Durrës">Durazzo</ref> to the Morea, probably in 1378, they appeared reorganised under three chiefs, captains, named <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahiot_de_Coquerel">Mahiot de Coquerel</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berard_de_Varvassa">Berard de Varvassa</ref>, and Pedro Bordo. In 1381, Mahiot, the chiefest of the three, was raised to the position of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bailiff">bailiff</ref> of Achaea by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latin_Empire">Latin Emperor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_of_Baux">James of Baux</ref>, while Pedro and Berard appeared as his imperial captains. Following the death (1383) of James, his successors, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_III_of_Naples">Charles III of Naples</ref> and his son <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ladislaus_of_Naples">Ladislaus</ref>, failed to maintain control of their principality of Achaea and the Navarrese Company held the power in the region. The Company negotiated between competing claimants to the principality and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic_of_Venice">Republic of Venice</ref>. Mahiot died in 1386 and Pedro succeeded him as the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> ruler of the Company and the Morea. On 26 July 1387, Pedro, with the backing of both the secular and ecclesiastic authority in Greece, confirmed a treaty with Venice whereby she was ceded rights in the port of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pylos">Navarino</ref>.</p>
<p>On 6 September that year, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_Urban_VI">Pope Urban VI</ref> declared that as James of Baux's successors had forfeited their rights to the Holy See, the principality belonged to him and he devolved its government on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Foscari">Paul Foscari</ref>, the archbishop of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patras">Patras</ref>, who in turn made Pedro <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vicar_general">vicar general</ref>. Pedro was constantly at war with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Despotate_of_Morea">Despotate of Morea</ref>, against whom he even used <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottoman_Empire">Ottoman</ref> pirates, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duchy_of_Athens">Duchy of Athens</ref> under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nerio_I_Acciaioli">Nerio I Acciaioli</ref>. The latter was captured near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vostitsa">Vostitsa</ref> on 10 September 1389 while trying to sit to talks with Pedro concerning <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Argos_and_Nauplia">Argos and Nauplia</ref>. He had to buy his freedom with concessions to the Navarrese ally, Venice. Late in 1394 or early in 1395, the Turkish general <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evrenos_Beg">Evrenos Beg</ref> invaded the despotate and met Pedro's forces at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leontari,_Arcadia">Leontari</ref>. Together the two besieged and took <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Akova,_Argos">Akova</ref> (28 February). After Evrenos returned to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thessaly">Thessaly</ref>, Pedro was defeated by the Greeks and taken captive with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_constable">grand constable</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andronico_Asano_Zaccaria">Andronico Asano Zaccaria</ref>, his brother-in-law. In December, Venice paid 50,000 <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperper">hyperpers</ref></hi> for the release of her allies.</p>
<p>Early the next year, Pedro agreed to pay 3,000 <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ducat">ducats</ref></hi> to Ladislaus in return for the title Prince of Achaea. He was invested with the principality, but never did end up making his payments. In that year, Pedro cooperated with Venice to refortify the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hexamilion_wall">Hexamilion</ref> and settle boundary disputes over <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methoni,_Messenia">Modon</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Koroni">Coron</ref>. Following the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Nicopolis">Battle of Nicopolis</ref>, the Ottoman sultan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bayezid_I">Bayezid I</ref> turned his attention to reducing the remaining Christian states in Greece. This drew Pedro and the despot of Morea, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodore_I_Palaiologos,_Lord_of_Morea">Theodore I Palaeologus</ref>, into alliance. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knights_Hospitaller">Order of St John</ref> was on board, but the Venetian senate refused to aid the Byzantines. In 1399, Pedro defeated an invasive Turkish army and received the titles of papal vicar and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gonfalonier">gonfalonier</ref> of Achaea from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boniface_IX">Boniface IX</ref> (15 February 1400). The Christian alliance did not last, however, and Pedro raided the Venetian possessions of Modon and Coron in 1401. Pedro died the next year, leaving Achaea with his infant son under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent">regency</ref> of his wife, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_II_Zaccaria">Maria II Zaccaria</ref>. Maria gave the regency to her nephew <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centurione_II_Zaccaria">Centurione II</ref>, who promptly paid the outstanding sum required by Ladislaus and received investment as prince.</p>
</text>
