<text id="autogum_bio_doc479" title="William Craven (Lord Mayor of London)" shortTile="william-craven-lord" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-08-20" dateModified="2019-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Craven_%28Lord_Mayor_of_London%29" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>William Craven (Lord Mayor of London)</head>
<figure><caption>Sir William Craven (by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcus_Gheeraerts_the_Younger">Marcus Gheeraerts the Younger</ref>)</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sir William Craven</hi> (1548 – 18 July 1618) was an English merchant, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_Mayor_of_the_City_of_London">Lord Mayor of London</ref> in 1610 (some sources say also in 1618<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-peerage-1">[1]</ref>). It has been noted that the story of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dick_Whittington_and_His_Cat">Dick Whittington</ref> has some similarities to Craven's career, though the story was first published before Craven became Lord Mayor.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
<head>Life</head>
<p>He was the second son of William Craven and Beatrix, daughter of John Hunter, and grandson of John Craven, was born at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Appletreewick">Appletreewick</ref>, a village in the parish of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burnsall">Burnsall</ref>, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skipton">Skipton</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West_Riding_of_Yorkshire">West Riding of Yorkshire</ref>, about 1548. The date is made probable by the fact that he took up his freedom in 1569. At the age of thirteen or fourteen he was sent down to London by the common carrier and bound apprentice to Robert Hulson, merchant taylor, who lived in Watling Street. Having been admitted to the freedom of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merchant_Taylors'_Company">Merchant Taylors' Company</ref> on 4 November 1569, Craven appears entered into business with Hulson, and subsequently quarrelled with him, with an arbitrated settlement in 1583.</p>
<p>In 1588 Craven took a lease from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mercers'_Company">Mercers' Company</ref> of a mansion house in Watling Street, where he carried on business with Robert and John Parker until his death. He was elected warden of his company on 4 July 1593, and on 19 July 1594 he was made one of the court of assistants. On 2 April 1600 he was elected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alderman">alderman</ref> for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishopsgate">Bishopsgate</ref> ward, and on 14 February 1601 he was chosen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheriff_of_London">sheriff of London</ref>. On 15 May 1602 he became alderman of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cordwainer_ward">Cordwainer ward</ref>. He was knighted at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whitehall">Whitehall</ref> by James I on 26 July 1603.</p>
<p>Craven was lord mayor of London for 1610–11, and the show, which had been suspended for some years, was revived with splendour. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian,_Prince_of_Anhalt">Christian, Prince of Anhalt</ref>, was entertained with his entourage at the feast at the Guildhall afterwards. On 14 January 1612 Craven became alderman of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lime_Street_ward">Lime Street ward</ref>; he had moved his residence from St. Antholin's to a house built by Stephen Kirton, in the parish of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Andrew_Undershaft">St. Andrew Undershaft</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cornhill,_London">Cornhill</ref>. This house was on the south side of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leadenhall_Street">Leadenhall Street</ref>; it was leased to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_India_Company">East India Company</ref> in 1620 and pulled down, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East_India_House">East India House</ref> erected in 1726. During Craven's mayoralty his name appears in connection with loans to the king.</p>
<p>In 1616 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady_Elizabeth_Coke">Lady Elizabeth Coke</ref>, wife of Sir Edward Coke, on occasion of her quarrel with her husband, was at his request handed over to the hospitality of Craven, who must have entertained her at his house in Leadenhall Street. The last public act recorded of Craven is the laying of the foundation-stone of the new <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aldgate">Aldgate</ref> on 26 May 1618.</p>
<p>On 1 July 1618 he attended the court of the Merchant Taylors' Company for the last time. He was buried at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Andrew_Undershaft">St. Andrew Undershaft</ref> on 11 August 1618.</p>
<head>Family</head>
<p>He married Elizabeth Whitmore, probably about 1605; she was a daughter of William Whitmore (d.1593) of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apley_Hall">Apley Hall</ref>, Salop and Balmes Manor, Hackney, haberdasher and alderman of London. Her second brother was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Whitmore_(Lord_Mayor)">Sir George Whitmore</ref> (d.1654), Lord Mayor of London. They had five children: Elizabeth, Mary, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Craven,_1st_Earl_of_Craven_(1608–1697)">William</ref> (Baron Craven of Hampstead Marshall, Berkshire and 1st Earl of Craven), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron_Craven_of_Ryton">John</ref> (Baron Craven of Ryton) and Thomas.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-peerage-1">[1]</ref> In 1622 his  eldest surviving daughter Elizabeth married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Percy_Herbert,_2nd_Baron_Powis">Percy Herbert, 2nd Baron Powis</ref>. Her sister Mary married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Coventry,_2nd_Baron_Coventry">Thomas Coventry, 2nd Baron Coventry</ref>. His will was openly read in court on 29 July 1618.</p>
<p>The second son, John Craven, founder of the Craven scholarships at Oxford and Cambridge, was commoner of Trinity College, Oxford, 1626–8. Charles I created him Baron Craven of Ryton, Shropshire, 21 March 1643. He died in 1649, and left no issue by his wife, Elizabeth, daughter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Spencer,_2nd_Baron_Spencer_of_Wormleighton">William Spencer, 2nd  Baron Spencer of Wormleighton</ref> and Lady Penelope Wriothesley.</p>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>In 1596 he made a donation towards the building of the library of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_John's_College,_Oxford">St John's College, Oxford</ref>, recorded on one of the library windows.</p>
<p>He founded the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grammar_school">grammar school</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burnsall">Burnsall</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Yorkshire">North Yorkshire</ref>, in 1602; this building has been in use as a school ever since then and now houses Burnsall <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voluntary_aided_school">V. A.</ref> Primary School.  The inscription "William Craven Alderman of London founder of this Schoole Anno Domini 1601" can still be seen on a panel above the school door.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-school-4">[4]</ref> In 1604 he was one of the patrons of ‘the scheme of a new college after the manner of a university designed at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ripon">Ripon</ref>, Yorkshire’. On 9 January 1611 he was elected president of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christ's_Hospital">Christ's Hospital</ref>, a post he occupied up to his death. His donations to the hospital included lands to the value of £1,000 at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ugley">Ugley</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Essex">Essex</ref>. On 2 July 1613 he conveyed to St John's College the advowson of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creeke,_Northamptonshire">Creeke</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northamptonshire">Northamptonshire</ref> ‘upon trust that one of the ten senior fellows elected from (Merchant Taylors') School should be presented thereto’. In 1617 he joined with others in subscribing £1,000 towards the repair and decoration of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._Antholin's_Church">St. Antholin's Church</ref>.</p>
<p>By John Craven's will, dated 18 May 1647, he left large charitable bequests to Burnsall, Skipton, Ripon, Ripley, Knaresborough, and Boroughbridge, and money for redeeming captives in Algiers. His most important legacy was that of the manor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cancerne">Cancerne</ref>, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chichester">Chichester</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sussex">Sussex</ref>, to provide £100 for four poor scholars, two at Cambridge and two at Oxford, with preference to his own poor kinsmen. The first award under the bequest was made at Cambridge 16 May 1649. The fund was immediately afterwards sequestrated by parliament, and on 7 May 1651 a petition was presented for the payment of the scholarships. In 1654 the sequestration was discharged. The bequest was maintained at both universities.</p>
</text>
