<text id="autogum_bio_doc604" title="Mateus Fernandes" shortTile="mateus-fernandes" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-02-27" dateModified="2019-06-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mateus_Fernandes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Mateus Fernandes</head>For the mixed martial arts fighter, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fatalities_in_mixed_martial_arts_contests#Mateus_Fernandes">Fatalities in mixed martial arts contests §Mateus Fernandes</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Mateus Fernandes</hi> (died 10 April 1515), also called <hi rend="bold">Mateus Fernandes the Elder</hi>, was a Portuguese architect. He was noted for his works in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manueline">Manueline</ref> style at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monastery_of_Batalha">Monastery of Batalha</ref>, Portugal.</p>
<figure><caption>Portal of the Unfinished Chapels in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monastery_of_Batalha">Monastery of Batalha</ref> (close up)</caption></figure>
<p>He became master of works at the monastery of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Batalha_Monastery">Batalha</ref> in 1490 or slightly earlier, during the reign of king <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_II_of_Portugal">John II of Portugal</ref>. Before this date, nothing is known of his private life, as he has left no records to consult other than his architectural marvels. He succeeded the architect Fernão de Évora as architect of the monastery. Mateus Fernandes later became the primary architect of the next king, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manuel_I_of_Portugal">Manuel I of Portugal</ref>, who made him the supervisor of other architectural works in the rest of the country.</p>
<p>However, Mateus Fernandes is best known for his work in "Manueline style" at the entrance <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portal_(architecture)">portal</ref> of the roofless, Unfinished Chapels (<hi rend="italic">Capelas Imperfeitas</hi>) of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monastery_of_Batalha">Monastery of Batalha</ref>. The exceptionally large portal rises to a monumental fifteen m by 7½ m wide (50 x 25ft), overshadowing the rest of the chapels at the monastery. It was originally built in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gothic_architecture">Late Gothic</ref> style, but was transformed beyond recognition by Fernandes into one of the first masterpieces of Manueline style (completed in 1509). The Manueline style would then spread from Batalha throughout all Portugal.</p>
<figure><caption>Tomb of Mateus Fernandes</caption></figure>
<p>The portal is completely decorated into a lacework of sumptuous Manueline motifs, with flamboyant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iconography">iconography</ref> including the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armillary">armillary</ref> symbol of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmos">cosmos</ref>, the cross of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Order_of_Christ_(Portugal)">Order of Christ</ref> (that decorated the sails of the Portuguese ships of the discoverers), spheres, winged angels, ropes, circles, tree stumps, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trefoil">trefoil</ref> arches and florid projections. Fernandes was again original by making the sculptural aspect dominate over the architectural aspect, united in an asymmetrical composition. Mateus Fernandes has tried to represent in stone, the exuberant and expansive spirit in the reign of king Manuel.</p>
<p>In the homage of King Manuel I to his predecessor, king D. Duarte mentions his motto <hi rend="italic">Leauté faray tam yaserei</hi> (I will always be loyal). This motto was then repeated more than two hundred times, carved into the stone arches, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vault_(architecture)">vaults</ref> and pillars of the chapels. The original plans for an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Octagon">octagonal</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dome">dome</ref>, supported by buttresses, to crown this pantheon to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House_of_Aviz">House of Aviz</ref> was never to be finished since funds ran out, and the construction of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerónimos_Monastery">Jerónimos Monastery</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa_Maria_de_Belém">Belém</ref> would gain absolute priority.</p>
<p>Together with the architect <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diogo_Boitac">Diogo Boitac</ref>, he rendered the Manueline style in the tracery of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arcade_(architecture)">arcade</ref> screens in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ambulatory">ambulatory</ref> of the Royal Cloister (Claustro Real) in the Jerónimos Monastery. Fernandes also worked with Boitac to build the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abattoir">abattoirs</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coimbra">Coimbra</ref> in 1511. Boitac was another important Manueline architect and sculptor, who even became the son-in-law of Fernandes by marrying his daughter Isabel Henriques in 1512.</p>
<p>He (or his son, since they carried the same name) is reported to have directed the construction of the church and the hospital of Misericórdia at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Óbidos,_Portugal">Óbidos</ref>, while they were engaged at the same time in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caldas_da_Rainha">Caldas da Rainha</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref></p>
<p>Mateus Fernandes died in Batalha on 10 April 1515 and was buried, with his wife, under a marble tomb-slab close to the portal of the monastery. Diogo Boitac was buried in a tomb close by in 1528. Fernandes was succeeded as master of works at the monastery in 1516 by his son <hi rend="bold">Mateus Fernandes the Younger</hi> (died 1528), who had already been deputized to supervise construction at the monastery in his father’s absence.</p>
<p>Because of East Indian influences in his work and a vague similarity to the design of the Indian Jain temple of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ahmedabad">Ahmedabad</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> scholars have often tried to link Mateus Fernandes to Tomás Fernandes, a military architect in India, or to Diogo Fernandes of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beja_(Portugal)">Beja</ref>, who was a member of the embassy in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gujarat">Gujarat</ref> in 1513. But all this has remained conjecture. The north porch of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Mary_Redcliffe">St Mary Redcliffe</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bristol">Bristol</ref> has a resemblance to his style, which is a possibility because of the frequent contacts between Portugal and England.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref></p>
</text>
