<text id="autogum_bio_doc523" title="Hatuey" shortTile="hatuey" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2002-10-22" dateModified="2019-11-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hatuey" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hatuey</head>
<figure><caption>Monument of Taino chief Hatuey in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yara,_Cuba">Yara</ref> city, depicting the moment he was burnt by Spanish soldiers, bound to a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tamarind">Tamarind</ref> tree planted in 1907.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Plate at the base of the monument. It reads <hi rend="italic">"To the memory of Chief Hatuey, unforgettable native, precursor of the Cuban fight for freedom, he offered his life, glorifying his ideals while tormented by the flames on 2/2/1512. Monuments Delegation of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yara,_Cuba">Yara</ref>, 1999".</hi></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Hatuey</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/English">/ɑːˈtweɪ/</ref>), also <hi rend="bold">Hatüey</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:IPA/English">/ˌɑːtuˈeɪ/</ref>; died February 2, 1512), was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taíno_people">Taíno</ref> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cacique">cacique</ref></hi> (chief) originally from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Island">island</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hispaniola">Hispaniola</ref>, who lived in the early sixteenth century and fled to Cuba during the Spanish conquest. He has attained legendary status for leading a group of natives in a fight against the invading <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spaniards">Spaniards</ref>, and thus becoming one of the first fighters against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colonialism">colonialism</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_World">New World</ref>. He is celebrated as "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuba">Cuba</ref>'s First National Hero".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Running_Fox_1998-1">[1]</ref> The 2010 film <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Even_the_Rain">Even the Rain</ref></hi> includes a cinematic account of Hatuey's execution.</p>
<head>History</head>
<p>In 1511, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diego_Velázquez_de_Cuéllar">Diego Velázquez</ref> set out from Hispaniola to conquer the island of Cuba to find things to steal like gold and money and lives(Taino name, recorded by Columbus). He was preceded, however, by Hatuey, who fled Hispaniola with a party of four hundred in canoes and warned some of the Native people of eastern Cuba about what to expect from the Spaniards.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-historyofcuba.com-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bartolomé_de_Las_Casas">Bartolomé de Las Casas</ref> later attributed the following speech to Hatuey. He showed the Taíno of Caobana a basket of gold and jewels, saying:</p>
Here is the God the Spaniards worship. For these they fight and kill; for these they persecute us and that is why we have to throw them into the sea... They tell us, these tyrants, that they adore a God of peace and equality, and yet they usurp our land and make us their slaves. They speak to us of an immortal soul and of their eternal rewards and punishments, and yet they rob our belongings, seduce our women, violate our daughters. Incapable of matching us in valor, these cowards cover themselves with iron that our weapons cannot break...<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref>
<p>The Taino chiefs in Cuba did not respond to Hatuey's message, and few joined him to fight. Hatuey resorted to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guerrilla_warfare">guerrilla</ref> tactics against the Spaniards, and was able to confine them for a time. He and his fighters were able to kill at least eight Spanish soldiers. Eventually, using mastiffs and torturing the Native people for information, the Spaniards succeeded in capturing him. On February 2, 1512, he was tied to a stake and burned alive at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yara,_Cuba">Yara</ref>, near the present-day City of Bayamo.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref></p>
<p>Before he was burned, a priest asked Hatuey if he would accept <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus">Jesus</ref> and go to heaven. Las Casas recalled the reaction of the chief:</p>
[Hatuey], thinking a little, asked the religious man if Spaniards went to heaven. The religious man answered yes... The chief then said without further thought that he did not want to go there but to hell so as not to be where they were and where he would not see such cruel people. This is the name and honor that God and our faith have earned.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref>
<head>Legacy</head>
<p>The town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hatuey,_Cuba">Hatuey</ref>, located south of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sibanicú,_Cuba">Sibanicú</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camagüey_Province">Camagüey Province</ref> of Cuba, was named after the Taíno hero.</p>
<p>Hatuey also lives on in as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beer">beer</ref> brand name. Beer has been brewed in Santiago de Cuba and sold under the Hatuey brand name since 1927, initially by the native Cuban company, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compañia_Ron_Bacardi_S.A.">Compañia Ron Bacardi S.A.</ref>.  After <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nationalization">nationalization</ref> of industry in 1960 by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castro_regime">Castro regime</ref>, brewing was taken over by Empresa Cerveceria Hatuey Santiago. Beginning in 2011, the Bacardi family again began making beers in the United States to market under the Hatuey label.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref>
Hatuey is also a brand of a type of sugary, non-alcoholic malt beverage called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malta_(soft_drink)">Malta</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref>  Hatuey is also a brand of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soda_cracker">soda cracker</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref></p>
<p>In a 2010 film shot in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolivia">Bolivia</ref>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Even_the_Rain">Even the Rain</ref></hi>, Hatuey is a main character in the film-within-the-film.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-10">[10]</ref></p>
<p>The logo of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cohiba_(cigar_brand)">Cuban cigar</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cohiba_(cigarette)">cigarette brand Cohiba</ref> is a picture of Hatuey.</p>
</text>
