<text id="autogum_bio_doc127" title="Tom Bayer" shortTile="tom-bayer" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-12-13" dateModified="2019-10-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom_Bayer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tom Bayer</head>For the German writer and musician, see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thommie_Bayer">Thommie Bayer</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">Thomas Montgomery Bayer</hi> is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vanuatu">Vanuatuan</ref> banker. A <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_former_United_States_citizens_who_relinquished_their_nationality">former U.S. citizen</ref>, he served in the Vietnam War and thereafter remained in the Asia-Pacific region to pursue a career in the finance sector. He lived successively in Australia and Singapore before coming to Vanuatu (then the New Hebrides) in 1974, where he became a citizen after independence, and has continued to reside there. Previously executive chairman of European Bank and managing director of the Pacific International Trust Company, he is now a member of the board of directors of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reserve_Bank_of_Vanuatu">Reserve Bank of Vanuatu</ref>.</p>
<head>Early career</head>
<p>A native of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</ref>, Bayer graduated from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lehigh_University">Lehigh University</ref> before going on to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wharton_School_of_the_University_of_Pennsylvania">Wharton School of Business</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-GlobalCustodian2001-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> He served in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Army">United States Army</ref> during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vietnam_War">Vietnam War</ref>, attaining the rank of captain.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-SMH20060909-3">[3]</ref> After leaving the U.S. military, Bayer worked in international banking. He moved to Australia in 1967, and later to Singapore.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Senate2001-p496-4">[4]</ref> He moved from Singapore to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Hebrides">New Hebrides</ref> in 1974 to become the vice-managing director of the Pacific International Trust Company, and was promoted to managing director the following year.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-VanuatuNews20111104-5">[5]</ref> His relocation came just as the groundwork was being laid for the islands' independence from the United Kingdom and France;<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-SMH20060909-3">[3]</ref> when Vanuatu became independent in 1980 and asked prominent members of society to take Vanuatu citizenship, Bayer chose to accept in 1982, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Relinquishment_of_United_States_nationality">giving up U.S. citizenship</ref> in the process.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Senate2001-p496-4">[4]</ref></p>
<head>European Bank</head>
<p>Bayer became the executive chairman of European Bank in 1986.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-6">[6]</ref> The bank began expanding its business in the mid-1990s.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Senate2001-p496-4">[4]</ref> European Bank faced investigations by foreign regulatory authorities in July 1999 when one of its account-holders deposited US$7.5 million in funds which U.S. officials believed to be the proceeds of a credit card fraud.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-7">[7]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-8">[8]</ref> This was part of a larger wave of concern about financial institutions in the South Pacific which led a number of U.S. banks, including the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bank_of_New_York">Bank of New York</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JP_Morgan_Chase">JP Morgan Chase</ref>, to suspend dollar transactions not just with Vanuatu but <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nauru">Nauru</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palau">Palau</ref> and eventually <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niue">Niue</ref> as well.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-9">[9]</ref> Bayer was critical of this response, noting that Vanuatu had criminalised money laundering as early as 1989, and voiced his suspicions that both the U.S. government and U.S. banks were insincere in their desire to crack down on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Money_laundering">money laundering</ref>, but rather had turned their attention to Vanuatu because it was a small and distant target, and one of the few <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Offshore_financial_centre">offshore financial centres</ref> which was not a dependency of major foreign powers.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-VanFossen-p247-10">[10]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-11">[11]</ref></p>
<p>Nevertheless, Vanuatu also pursued a diplomatic approach to resolving the situation, in which Bayer played a large role: a Vanuatu delegation headed by Bayer went to the U.S. and met with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Monetary_Fund">International Monetary Fund</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Department_of_State">U.S. State Department</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal_Reserve_System">Federal Reserve System</ref> officials in January 2000 to discuss details of Vanuatu's anti-money laundering laws and practices, and arranged for reciprocal visits by State Department and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Financial_Action_Task_Force">Financial Action Task Force</ref> officials to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Port_Vila">Port Vila</ref> in the following months. This was successful in persuading some banks to resume transactions with Vanuatu, but other correspondent banks in the U.S. continued to apply sanctions.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-VanFossen-p247-10">[10]</ref> Furthermore, in May 2002 the U.S. indicted Bayer and two colleagues on charges including laundering the proceeds of another business through European Bank, and again had the bank's funds in the U.S. frozen. Bayer was confident that the charges would be thrown out, stating in January 2003 that the charge of money laundering was being applied to actions that were nothing more than "normal banking business".<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-12">[12]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-13">[13]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-14">[14]</ref> In March 2012, after nearly a decade of litigation, European Bank successfully unfroze its accounts and had its funds returned, with interest.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DailyPost20120612-15">[15]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-16">[16]</ref></p>
<head>Reserve Bank of Vanuatu</head>
<p>Bayer retired from his position as PITCO chairman in November 2011.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-VanuatuNews20111104-5">[5]</ref> In June 2012, then-Minister of Finance <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moana_Carcasses">Moana Carcasses</ref> appointed Bayer to the board of the Reserve Bank of Vanuatu.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-DailyPost20120612-15">[15]</ref> Opposition politicians including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serge_Vohor">Serge Vohor</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Union_of_Moderate_Parties">Union of Moderate Parties</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeff_Patunvanu">Jeff Patunvanu</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nagriamel">Nagriamel</ref>, and members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vanua'aku_Pati">Vanua'aku Pati</ref> questioned the move due to Bayer's previous association with European Bank.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-17">[17]</ref></p>
<p>In March 2013, new Minister of Finance <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlot_Salawai">Charlot Salawai</ref>, who succeeded to the position after Carcasses lost his seat in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012_Vanuatuan_general_election">October 2012 elections</ref>, attempted to remove Bayer from the RBV board, claiming that he was an agent of European Bank and was thus disqualified from serving under the Reserve Bank of Vanuatu Act Section 8(10)(b).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-18">[18]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-19">[19]</ref> Bayer described the dismissal as illegal and Salawai's claim as misleading and defamatory as he had not been a board member of European Bank for more than a decade, and suggested that the move was tied to party politics.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-20">[20]</ref> The following month, after the collapse of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sato_Kilman">Sato Kilman</ref> government in whose cabinet Salawai served, and the election of Carcasses (who had since <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crossing_the_floor">crossed the floor</ref>) as Prime Minister, RBV Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Odo_Tevi">Odo Tevi</ref> himself was removed after more than ten years in his position. Members of Parliament expressed differing opinions on the issue: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Bohn_Sikol">Robert Bohn Sikol</ref> stated that "Tevi had done a good job and was not sacked", whereas Leader of the Opposition <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ham_Lini">Ham Lini</ref> described it as retaliation for Bayer's removal.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-21">[21]</ref> In August 2013, Bayer was again appointed to the RBV board by new Minister of Finance <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maki_Simelum">Maki Simelum</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-22">[22]</ref></p>
<head>Footnotes</head>
</text>
