<text id="autogum_bio_doc398" title="Martyrs of Gorkum" shortTile="martyrs-gorkum" type="bio" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-01-23" dateModified="2019-07-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martyrs_of_Gorkum" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Martyrs of Gorkum</head>
<figure><caption>19 Martyrs of Gorcum</caption></figure>
<p>The <hi rend="bold">Martyrs of Gorkum</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_language">Dutch</ref>: <hi lang="nl" rend="italic">Martelaren van Gorcum</hi>) were a group of 19 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_people">Dutch</ref> Catholic clerics, secular &amp; religious,  who were hanged on 9 July 1572 in the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brielle">Brielle</ref> (or Den Briel) by militant Dutch Calvinists during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_wars_of_religion">16th century religious wars</ref>—specifically, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_Revolt">Dutch Revolt</ref> against Spanish rule, which developed into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eighty_Years'_War">Eighty Years' War</ref>.</p>
<head>Events</head>
<p>In the first half of the Sixteenth Century, various forms of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protestantism">Protestantism</ref>—particularly, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lutheranism">Lutheranism</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calvinism">Calvinism</ref>—were spreading through a great part of Europe. In the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Low_Countries">Low Countries</ref>, then under the rule of Spain, Emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_V,_Holy_Roman_Emperor"> Charles V</ref> and his son King <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_II_of_Spain"> Philip II</ref> instituted a systematic campaign to root out the new religious movements, which resulted in a certain level of political resentment towards the authorities, including the Catholic Church.</p>
<p>By 1572 the Netherlands were in open revolt against Spanish rule, while in the internal rivalry among the Protestant denominations, Calvinism managed to suppress Lutheranism. On 1 April of the next year, Calvinist forces and a rebel group called the <hi rend="italic">Watergeuzen</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sea_Beggars">Sea Beggars</ref>) <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capture_of_Brielle"> captured Brielle</ref> (Den Briel) and later <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vlissingen">Vlissingen</ref> (Flushing).<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-albers-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>In June, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dordrecht">Dordrecht</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gorkum">Gorkum</ref> fell, and at the latter the rebels captured nine <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franciscan">Franciscans</ref>: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Pieck">Nicholas Pieck</ref>, guardian of Gorkum; Hieronymus of Weert, vicar; Theodorus van der Eem of Amersfoort; Nicasius Janssen of Heeze; Willehad of Denmark; Godefried of Mervel; Antonius of Weert; Antonius of Hoornaer, and Franciscus de Roye of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brussels">Brussels</ref>. To these were added two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lay_brother">lay brothers</ref> from the same friary, Petrus of Assche and Cornelius of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wijk_bij_Duurstede">Wijk bij Duurstede</ref>. At almost the same time the Calvinists arrested the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parish_priest">parish priest</ref> of Gorkum, Leonardus Vechel of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/'s-Hertogenbosch">'s-Hertogenbosch</ref>, and his assistant.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-albers-2">[2]</ref></p>
<p>Also imprisoned were Godefried van Duynsen of Gorkum, a priest in his native city, and Joannes Lenartz of Oisterwijk, a canon regular from a nearby priory and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spiritual_director">spiritual director</ref> for the monastery of Augustinian nuns in Gorkum. To these fifteen were later added four more companions: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joannes_van_Hoornaer">Joannes van Hoornaer</ref> (alias known as John of Cologne), a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominican_Order">Dominican</ref> of the Cologne province and parish priest not far from Gorkum, who when apprised of the incarceration of the clergy of Gorkum hastened to the city in order to administer the sacraments to them and was seized and imprisoned with the rest; Jacobus Lacops of Oudenaar, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norbertine">Norbertine</ref>, who became a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curate">curate</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monster,_South_Holland">Monster, South Holland</ref>; Adrianus Janssen of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hilvarenbeek">Hilvarenbeek</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Premonstratensian">Premonstratensian</ref> canon and at one time parish priest in Monster, who was sent to Brielle with Jacobus Lacops. Last was Andreas Wouters of Heynoord.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-albers-2">[2]</ref></p>
<figure><caption>The Apotheosis of the Martyrs of Gorkum 1572, print made by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean-Baptiste_Nolin">Jean-Baptiste Nolin</ref> after a painting by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johan_Zierneels">Johan Zierneels</ref>, 1675</caption></figure>
<p>In prison at Gorkum (from 26 June to 6 July 1572), the first 15 prisoners were transferred to Brielle, arriving there on 8 July.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Dominicans-3">[3]</ref> On their way to Dordrecht they were exhibited for money to the curious. The following day, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_II_de_la_Marck">William de la Marck, Lord of Lumey</ref>, commander of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gueux_de_mer">Gueux de mer</ref></hi>, had them interrogated and ordered a disputation. In the meantime, four others arrived. It was demanded of each that he abandon his belief in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transubstantiation">Transubstantiation</ref>, the doctrine of the real presence of Christ in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blessed_Sacrament">Blessed Sacrament</ref>, as well as the belief in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Papal_supremacy">Papal supremacy</ref>. All remained firm in their faith. Meanwhile, there came a letter from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince_of_Orange">Prince of Orange</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_the_Silent">William the Silent</ref>, which enjoined all those in authority to leave priests and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religious_(Catholicism)">religious</ref> unmolested. Despite this call, on 9 July, they were hanged in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peat">turfshed</ref>.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-albers-2">[2]</ref></p>
<head>Veneration</head>
<p>A shrub bearing 19 white flowers is said to have sprung up at the site of their martyrdom. Many miracles have since been attributed to the intercession of the Gorkum Martyrs, especially the curing of hernias.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-Dominicans-3">[3]</ref>
The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beatification">beatification</ref> of the martyrs took place on 14 November 1675, and their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canonization">canonization</ref> on 29 June 1867.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-oxford-1">[1]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-4">[4]</ref> Their elevation to sainthood, which took place on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feast_of_Saints_Peter_and_Paul">Feast of Saints Peter and Paul</ref>, was part of grand celebrations marking 1,800 years since the traditional year for the martyrdom of the two apostles in Rome.<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-5">[5]</ref></p>
<p>For many years the place of their martyrdom in Brielle has been the scene of numerous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pilgrimage">pilgrimages</ref> and processions. The reliquary of their remains is now enshrined in the Church of Saint Nicholas, Brussels, Belgium.</p>
<head>The 19 martyrs</head>
<figure><caption>St. Godfried of Mervel, O.F.M.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>St. Anthony of Weert, O.F.M.</caption></figure>
<p>There were 11 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franciscan">Franciscan</ref> friars or <hi rend="italic">Minderbroeders</hi> (Friars Minor), one <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominican_Order">Dominican</ref> friar or <hi rend="italic">Predikheer</hi>, two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norbertine">Norbertine</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canons_regular">canons regular</ref> and a local canon regular, or <hi rend="italic">witheren</hi> and five <hi rend="italic">wereldheren</hi> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secular_clergy">secular clergy</ref>). The 19 put to death on 9 July 1572 were:<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-albers-2">[2]</ref><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-butler-6">[6]</ref></p>
<list type="ordered"><item>Leonard van Veghel (born 1527), spokesman, secular priest, and since 1566 pastor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gorinchem">Gorkum</ref></item>
<item>Peter of Assche (born 1530), Franciscan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lay_brother">lay brother</ref></item>
<item>Andrew Wouters (born 1542), secular priest, pastor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heinenoord">Heinenoord</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoeksche_Waard">Hoeksche Waard</ref></item>
<item>Nicasius of Heeze (born 1522), Franciscan friar, theologian and priest</item>
<item>Jerome of Weert (born 1522), Franciscan friar, priest, pastor in Gorcum</item>
<item>Anthony of Hoornaar, Franciscan friar and priest</item>
<item>Godfried van Duynen (born 1502), secular priest, former pastor in northern France</item>
<item>Willehad of Denmark (born 1482), Franciscan friar and priest</item>
<item>James Lacobs (born 1541), Norbertine canon</item>
<item>Francis of Roye (born 1549), Franciscan friar and priest</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_of_Cologne">John of Cologne</ref>, Dominican friar, pastor in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoornaar">Hoornaar</ref> near Gorkum</item>
<item>Anthony of Weert (born 1523), Franciscan friar and priest</item>
<item>Theodore of der Eem (born c. 1499–1502), Franciscan friar and priest, chaplain to a community of Franciscan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third_Order">Tertiary</ref> Sisters in Gorkum</item>
<item>Cornelius of Wijk bij Duurstede (born 1548), Franciscan lay brother</item>
<item>Adrian van Hilvarenbeek (born 1528), Norbertine canon and pastor in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monster,_South_Holland">Monster, South Holland</ref></item>
<item>Godfried of Mervel, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vicar">Vicar</ref> of Melveren, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sint-Truiden">Sint-Truiden</ref> (born 1512), Franciscan priest, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vicar">vicar</ref> of the friary in Gorkum</item>
<item>Jan of Oisterwijk (born 1504), Augustinian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canon_regular">canon regular</ref>, a chaplain for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beguinage">Beguinage</ref> in Gorkum</item>
<item>Nicholas Poppel (born 1532), secular priest, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chaplain">chaplain</ref> in Gorkum</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicholas_Pieck">Nicholas Pieck</ref> (born 1534), Franciscan friar, priest and theologian, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Custos_(Franciscans)">Guardian</ref> of the friary in Gorkum, his native city</item></list>
</text>
