<text id="autogum_interview_doc1069" title="part1_Vivien Goldman: An interview with the Punk Professor" shortTile="partvivien-goldman" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-30" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vivien_Goldman%3A_An_interview_with_the_Punk_Professor" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You were there with Marley through that time when he really caught on; was it obvious to you then that there was something amazing and unique happening?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  It was really something, and it was huge, but I didn't examine it then.  I believed in Bob with every fiber of my being, but it was hard to realize how everybody in the world would get it in the end, and just how towering a figure and enduring he would prove to be.  He deserves everything and more; the role that he occupies is so central.  It would have been hard to envisage how huge he became, though.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Warhol’s Factory photographer, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Billy%20Name">Billy Name</ref>, once told me he knew that what was going on was amazing, but he never thought Warhol would become the entire <hi rend="italic">fabric</hi> of the art world as he is now.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  Especially in New York.  Warhol was <hi rend="italic">so</hi> associated with the punk scene.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But Marley has become a fabric of sorts...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  Oh, he’s beyond the fabric of reggae, he’s the fabric of the rebel spirit.  Now everybody just puts on a little red, green and gold and they feel it identifies them as being there in the struggle.  Even if it is someone flying to the Hamptons for the weekend, they bring out Marley to expresses the rebel aspect they don’t want to completely lose.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you define punk?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  There are two things.  First, the aesthetic: harder, faster, louder.  But the second thing is what interested me more, which was the rebel spirit and attitude.  That free spirit of punk; that implicit sense of wanting to change a system that is always unfair wherever you are, except for maybe in the Netherlands.  But it's become so commodified</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is the commodified version of punk selling?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  Edgy and dangerous.  It is amazing: you open the New York Times and the free bits fall out and you get <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Urban%20Outfitters">Urban Outfitters</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old%20Navy">Old Navy</ref> with lines of punk kiddie clothes.  K-mart, even.  I was trying to see what was so deeply punk about those clothes.  They were maybe more colorful or something, but they weren’t punk.  It's like the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swarovski%20crystal">Swarovski crystal</ref> take on punk, I mean, please!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That aesthetic is everywhere, as though if one spikes his hair he is punk.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  Well, the punk is in the heart, to paraphrase <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deee-Lite">Deee-Lite</ref>.  I was writing about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Good%20Charlotte">Good Charlotte</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Police">The Police</ref>.  They adopted the trappings of punk.  They aren’t bad groups, but the punk aspect is more manifested by somebody like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manu%20Chao">Manu Chao</ref>.  He’s one of the punkiest artists out there I can think of.  It’s an <hi rend="italic">in</hi>clusionary spirit that is punk.</p>
</text>
