<text id="autogum_interview_doc797" title="part0_Antje Duvekot on life as a folk singer, her family and her music" shortTile="partantje-duvekot" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Antje_Duvekot_on_life_as_a_folk_singer%2C_her_family_and_her_music" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Antje Duvekot on life as a folk singer, her family and her music</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, November 11, 2007</hi></p>
<figure rend="Antje Duvekot 3 by David Shankbone.jpg"></figure>Boston-based singer-songwriter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antje%20Duvekot">Antje Duvekot</ref> has made a name for herself in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Folk%20music">folk music</ref> world with powerful ballads of heartbreak and longing for a deeper spirituality, but coming up empty-handed.  Below is <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>'s interview with the folk chanteuse.  
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  Tell me about your new album.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Antje Duvekot:</hi>  It’s called <hi rend="italic">Big Dream Boulevard</hi> and it’s the first studio album I made.  It’s not so new; I made it in May of 2006.  It’s produced by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Séamus%20Egan">Séamus Egan</ref>, who is the leader of a fairly renowned band named <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solas%20(group)">Solas</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You mentioned you used to explore more dark themes in your work, but that lately you are exploring lighter fare.  What themes are you exploring on this album?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  In the future I am hoping for more light themes.  I feel like I have worked through a lot of the darkness, and personally I feel like I’m ready to write a batch of lighter songs, but that’s just how I’m feeling right now.  My last record, Big Dream Boulevard, was a pretty heavy record and that was not intentional.  I write what is on my mind.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What were you going through that made it so dark?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  The record is drawn from my whole writing career, so it’s old and new songs as well.  I wasn’t going through anything in particular because it was spanning a wide time period.  I think it’s fair to say that over all I turn to music in times of trouble and need as a therapeutic tool to get me through sadness.  That’s why I tend to turn to music.  So my songs tend to be a little darker, because that’s where I tend to go for solace.  So themes like personal struggle with relationships and existential issues.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What personal relationships do you struggle with?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  A lot of my songs are about dating and relationship troubles.  That’s one category.  But a lot of my songs are about existential questions because I struggle with what to believe in.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you believe in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Higher%20power">higher power</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  I’m sort of an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atheism">atheist</ref> who wishes I could believe something.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you believe?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  It’s undefined.   I think I’m spiritual in music, which is my outlet, but I just can’t get on board with an organized religion.  Not even <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unitarian">Unitarianism</ref>.  I do miss something like that in my life, though.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why do you miss having religion in your life?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  I think every human being craves a feeling that there is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meaning%20of%20life">higher purpose</ref>.  It’s a need for me.  A lot of my songs express that struggle.</p>
</text>
