<text id="autogum_interview_doc1054" title="part6_Past Eurovision contestants give advice to this year's performers, speculate on who will win" shortTile="partpast-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-05-06" dateModified="2015-09-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Past_Eurovision_contestants_give_advice_to_this_year%27s_performers%2C_speculate_on_who_will_win" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What projects are you working on? What can your fan base expect to see from you this year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Hanna Pakarinen</hi>: I released my fourth album "Love in a Million Shades" earlier this year, and now I'm doing gigs around Finland.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What were some of the best memories you have from going to Eurovision? What advice would you give to the singers going to Eurovision for the first time this year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Hanna Pakarinen</hi>: I think the best memory is the moment when I got up on stage in the finals. That was amazing! </p>
<p>It's hard to give any advice, but I think the only thing that's important is just to be yourself and have fun. <hi rend="italic">[smile]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The music videos for this year are up at <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/eurovision">youtube.com/eurovision</ref>. Which songs are your favorites and which country do you think has the best chance of winning?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Hanna Pakarinen</hi>: Of course I think the best song is the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lose%20Control%20(Waldo's%20People%20song)">Finnish song</ref>. <hi rend="italic">[smile]</hi> It's very hard to say who is going to win; it's the same thing every year, you never know! </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Apart from music, what are some things that are very close to your heart? How would you like to use your popularity to help others?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Hanna Pakarinen</hi>: My family and friends, of course, and my hometown and the lake there. </p>
<p>I'm not really a big fan of the idea of being a role model but I'm trying to do my best, showing and telling the fans that the most important thing is to love yourself and be who you are. And always trust yourself, of course!</p>
<head id="Charlotte_Perrelli">Charlotte Perrelli </head>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlotte%20Perrelli">Charlotte Perrelli</ref>, originally Charlotte Nilsson, was an alumnus of two popular "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/dansband">dansbands</ref>" in Sweden before winning the Eurovision Song Contest in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%201999">1999</ref> with the song "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Take%20Me%20to%20Your%20Heaven%20(song)">Take Me to Your Heaven</ref>." She quickly became one of Sweden's most popular solo artists, and released six albums which all charted in the Swedish Top 40. In 2008 she returned to Eurovision with the highly favored "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hero%20(Charlotte%20Perrelli%20song)">Hero</ref>," only to be saved at the last minute by jury decision and ranking a low 18th out of 25 nations in the final round. Perrelli, now 34, discusses her achievements and favorite moments of the past decade.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What projects are you working on? What can your fan base expect to see from you this year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Charlotte Perrelli</hi>: I'm searching for new songs to [include on] my upcoming album. I´m also on the jury for the Swedish TV show <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talang">Talang</ref></hi> (<hi rend="italic">Talent; the Swedish version of the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Got%20Talent%20series">___'s Got Talent!</ref>" TV series</hi>). They can expect a new album, hopefully this year.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You went to Eurovision twice, winning the Contest in 1999 and then also entering last year. What were some of the best memories you had from both times you went to Eurovision? </hi></p>
</text>
