<text id="autogum_interview_doc173" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Andy Martin, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-07-28" dateModified="2015-08-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Andy_Martin%2C_U.S._Republican_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Andy Martin: I did indeed found the “Birther” movement questioning Barack Obama’s origins in Hawai’i but because of the need to run a national campaign for president I have not been active in examining Obama’s latest birth certificate. I think it was/is enough that I started the movement that ultimately forced Obama to release a document. I know there has been controversy about the new document but I am not involved in that controversy. It is for others to study and comment on the latest certificate; I am a full-time presidential candidate for the foreseeable future.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">You have stated that it is your personal opinion that Frank Marshall Davis is the father of Barack Obama. What specifically led to this opinion?</hi></item></list>
<p>Martin: My personal opinion that Frank Marshall Davis is Barack Obama’s biological father is based on my extensive research in Hawai’i.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">Where specifically did you obtain the material for your research and what did it entail?</hi>
<p>Martin: Because my Obama research in Hawai’i is ongoing and will be continuing in a research trip later this year I do not discuss my sources or methods of investigation. My writing speaks for itself.</p></p></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">Since announcing he would not seek the Republican nomination, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref> seems to have toned down his statements on the birth certificate issue. What are your current views on Donald Trump?</hi></item></list>
<p>Martin: I did not pay a lot of attention to Donald Trump’s “campaign” for president because his behavior seemed to suggest it was a charade. Mr. Trump has destroyed his political viability by saying initially he would only run as a Republican and then repudiating himself and suggesting he might run as an independent. Public leadership is serious business; Mr. Trump has shown he is not serious.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How would [you] assess the Obama presidency?</hi></item></list>
<p>Martin: The Obama presidency is an abject failure. I predicted Mr. Obama would fail in a Psychological Profile which was the first chapter of my book <hi rend="italic">Obama: The Man Behind The Mask</hi>. Obama’s failure is no surprise to me.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you believe Obama has done any good things as president?</hi></item></list>
<p>Martin: I can’t think of any off the top</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You ask Barack Obama to resign and want Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid to take over. What legal precedent forms the basis of this? And assuming Vice President Biden resigns as well, why should <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Speaker%20of%20the%20House%20of%20Representatives">Speaker</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Boehner">John Boehner</ref> not take over as president?</hi></item></list>
<p>Martin: The president of the Senate is third, not the speaker, so Reid is a practical choice.<ref style="counter-reset: mw-Ref 1;" target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[Editor's note 1]</ref> Boehner is fourth.<ref style="counter-reset: mw-Ref 2;" target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[Editor's note 2]</ref></p>
<head id="Personal_past">Personal past</head>
<p>Martin was asked several questions about his personal past, which he declined to answer. He refused to discuss his two previous presidential campaigns, his past affiliation with the Democratic Party and would not say which candidates he supported in previous elections. When pressed, Martin stated that the questions were irrelevant.</p>
</text>
