<text id="autogum_interview_doc651" title="part1_Wikinews interviews organiser of New Zealand&amp;apos;s Rock2Wgtn festival Phil Sprey" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-25" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_organiser_of_New_Zealand%27s_Rock2Wgtn_festival_Phil_Sprey" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How did you select the acts that would be performing and the other entertainment on offer? What are your personal opinions on the artists present?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Phil:</hi>Originally we were looking at a KISS concert in November. To assist an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australian</ref> promoter we moved this act to the Easter slot and then to make it a festival format added Ozzy on a second day. It then grew from there based largely on availability and the genre. Originally we planned a format with 2 ‘younger’ bands and 4 more mature performers so we were close to where we needed to be.  Have absolutely no issues with the artists and all performed up to expectation or beyond.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is it true that Ozzy demanded the set be repainted from KISS colours to his own?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Phil:</hi>Ozzy made no demands on repainting the Guitar set we had. We in consultation with their production chief did so as it was better ‘form’ not to embarrass the artist on the second night and retain the very happy production of the weekend.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What kind of reaction has there been from fans and the media to the festival?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Phil:</hi>HUGE! We have been bombarded with emails from around the world and from NZ fans. Media too have been very active and other than a few who ‘picked’ at individual performances most enjoyed the experience for what it was.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Three-quarters of a million dollars is a huge loss. Why is the quantity so large if ticket sales were still relatively high, even if they were below anticipated levels? How much did it cost to hire each of the acts present, anyway?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Phil:</hi>The loss figure is only an estimate at this point but yes we sustained a loss. The ratio of ticket sales who bought the discounted two-day package was 30% higher than expected, accommodation in Wellington was at maximum partly due to a conference and another entertainment event booked after our concert that also swallowed up capacity. The fact that no major concert has ever been held in Wellington over Easter was always going to be experimental and risky. We contained other costs very well with the only blowout coming from additional costs of international freight which was doubled on us by airlines who had been supportive then decided to charge premium when demand increased. (That war is still to be fought.)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Who is going to pay the price now?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Phil:</hi>Everyone of our contractors, Artist and suppliers are paid. We are concert promoters and will go onto the next concerts. It is what we do.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You believe Easter trading restrictions are responsible for low sales. Might we then see a future Rock2Wgtn at a different time of the year? If so, what can we expect from it?</hi></p>
</text>
