<text id="autogum_interview_doc529" title="part2_Billy West, voice of Ren and Stimpy, Futurama, on the rough start that shaped his life" shortTile="partbilly-west-voice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2013-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Billy_West%2C_voice_of_Ren_and_Stimpy%2C_Futurama%2C_on_the_rough_start_that_shaped_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Yeah, and sometimes you’ll actually hear stuff that you actually thought of during the audition, because you have to really be on your toes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you paid for that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Not really. Only a couple gigs did I ever get paid to scratch a movie for a celebrity that was going to do it. The stuff that goes on at auditions is despicable.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are there legal remedies that you could pursue for that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  No. I gotta prove it. I used to bring a tape recorder around with me, but still, it’s like trying to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fight%20city%20hall">fight city hall</ref>. It is what it is. But that’s my real issue with it is that this is an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Area%2051">Area 51</ref> for experienced voice-over people who do create characters and not just do who and what they are. It takes away from the creative process.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  There was a similar issue involved with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crispin%20Glover">Crispin Glover</ref>. They had taken a likeness of one of his earlier roles. I think it was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20Zemeckis">Robert Zemeckis</ref> Then they tried to pass it off later as him and he sued them for doing that. Are you familiar with that situation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  It only means anything to me if he won.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  He did.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Oh, he did! That’s very similar. But the thing is, if you could prove that. You can’t prove that somebody deliberately took the stuff and tossed it off to some person that’s acting. But it’s a dirty business and I won’t do it anymore. I never really quite got what it’s all about. It’s to show up and to sound exactly like the character and to read it, yet you’re doing it the way that you would do it. It’s not good business as far as I’m concerned. It’s not my part of town.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Has your speaking out on this issue hurt you in any way?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  In what way?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In your career?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  There’s no reaction against it from the studios or from the ….?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  No they don’t give a shit which voice-over person is in the alleyways beating the piss out of the other one to get a gig. I mean, they don’t care. They really don’t.</p>
<head id="Iconic_characters_and_choosing_projects">Iconic characters and choosing projects</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You discussed in an interview issues about the weight of the character’s legacies, such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pop-Eye">Pop-Eye</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bugs%20Bunny">Bugs Bunny</ref>. You had said that every time they do one of these they say, 'this time it’s going to be different. We’re putting the teeth back in those characters. Nobody is going to tell us what we can’t write and what we can write.' And you said they always blow it. How do they blow it?</hi></p>
</text>
