<text id="autogum_interview_doc1325" title="part2_Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian Party potential presidential candidate R.J. Harris" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-06-16" dateModified="2019-02-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Libertarian_Party_potential_presidential_candidate_R.J._Harris" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What do you feel sets you apart from your fellow contenders for the Libertarian Party presidential nomination?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">RH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I do more than preach Libertarianism, or <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/prognosticate">prognosticate</ref> about all the ways the GOP or the DNC [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic%20National%20Committee">Democrat</ref>] candidates will most certainly carry on with their tyrannies and usurpations of power, given the opportunity. </p>
<p>I articulate bold policy positions, as well as the means to institute them, based upon the Philosophy of Liberty and the Constitution with the aim of restoring Freedom, Liberty and the Republic. This is the definition of political courage, as taking these strong positions makes me a target for the bullets and blows of the enemies of Liberty. </p>
<p>But we are in the fight of our age and we must have champions willing to trade blows with the enemy, not merely repeat Libertarian platitudes.  Educational campaigns have been the mainstay of the Libertarian Party since its founding; but if we are going to take that next step — to actually convince the body politic that we can put into policy that which we preach, then we must nominate a candidate who is not afraid step out, armed with the courage of conviction and lead on every issue. </p>
<p>Of course our ability to do this is tied to cogent articulation of the philosophy which underlies our political ideology, but for too long have our other candidates engaged in academic debates for their own sake, and not actually deigned to apply that for which they argue to that which they will do. That being said, the biggest thing that separates me from my Libertarian Colleagues is that I am not running this race merely to educate or to increase the Party's ballot access; I am running to win and I believe with all my heart that we can be -- and that we must be -- victorious.   </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How often do you campaign and how would that change if you won the nomination?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">RH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I campaign for several hours each day. Once I win the nomination the only thing that will change is that I will have to add much more travel to the schedule. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If elected, what would you do as president?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">RH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I will defend the Republic and the Lives, Liberty and Property of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/We%20the%20People">We the People</ref>. This I will do by way of projecting to the world our strength at home and in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International%20Waters">International Waters</ref>; and by ending all government infringements of the Constitution and of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural%20and%20legal%20rights">People's Natural Rights</ref>. The authority to act on this promise is found in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oath%20of%20office%20of%20the%20President%20of%20the%20United%20States">President's constitutional Oath of Office</ref> to "preserve, protect and defend the Constitution of the United States." I will do no more than this and certainly no less.</p>
</text>
