<text id="autogum_interview_doc1010" title="part6_Wikinews interviews Spain's most decorated Paralympian, Teresa Perales" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-01-19" dateModified="2015-11-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Spain%27s_most_decorated_Paralympian%2C_Teresa_Perales" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Because they are disabled, and the way society treats people with disabilities, sets Paralympians off from able-bodied athletes, does that make it special emphasis that they should be more engaged in the political process than someone like Michael Phelps?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>: Yes, because... I had something very clear when I worked in politics, and it's that you cannot make policies without the people to whom they are directed. It's necessary for the people to whom they are destined work in politics, because that will ensure they are right. If not, no. And the people with disabilities, especially sportspeople with disabilities, that we care least of all about the disabilities really, we've had to overcome so many things, that we are able to contribute so much more. ((es))Spanish language: ‍ Sí, porque... Yo tenía una cosa muy clara cuando trabajaba en política, y es que no puedes hacer política sin contar con las personas a las que diriges la política. Es necesario que la persona que va a recibir la política trabaje en política, porque así estará bien. Si no, no. Y las personas con discapacidad, sobre todo los deportistas con discapacidad, que lo que menos nos importa es la discapacidad en realidad, hemos tenido que superar tantas cosas que podemos aportar mucho más.</p></p>
<head id="Funding_Spanish_sport">Funding Spanish sport</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> The Spanish Paralympic Committee is supported primarily by the Government?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>: No, for us it is the Government and companies. Both do the ADO Paralympic Plan. ((es))Spanish language: ‍No, nosotros es gobierno y empresas. Los dos hacen el Plan ADO paralímpico. </p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Do they give you as an athlete the support that you need to be successful? </p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>: No. No, absolutely not. I don't have a lane for swimming every day, only for me. I have to share it with other, not athletes, not swimmers, people, who come to the swimming pool and then swim, or try to swim. I cannot afford to pay a lane exclusively for my use. It's 30 euros per hour. I have to pay the ticket for the swimming pool, I have to pay all my travels, not with the national team, but my travels for qualifiers, and I can't pay my coach, who is in another swimming pool, in another center, because I can't. Okay, I have to be fair: the ADO Plan pays me 1,900 euros monthly, but I'm a mother, I have a family. I have to pay the school, everything. So this is not enough for me. I have to pay someone to take care of my child when I am competing, when I am in the stages. I remember this year, preparing London, I needed to be out of home for 22 days, twice, ok? I needed to pay someone for being with my baby, and it's very expensive. So it's not enough. I win gold so I have this kind of money — is the same [as] sixth place in [the] Olympics. Someone who was sixth at the Olympics has the same as me with a gold medal. I was recently at the Congress of Deputies, and I was talking about this. ((es))Spanish language: ‍ No. No, absolutamente no. No tengo una calle para nadar cada día, solo para mi. Tengo que compartirlo, no con atletas, no con nadadores, con gente, que vienen a la piscina a nadar, o a intentar nadar. No me puedo permitir pagar una calle reservada para mi. Son 30 euros la hora. Tengo que pagar el ticket de la piscina, tengo que pagar mis viajes, no con el equipo nacional, pero para competir en los clasificatorios, no puedo pagar a mi entrenador, que está en otra piscina, en otro centro, porque no puedo. Vale, he de ser justa: el Plan ADO me paga 1,900 euros al mes, pero soy madre, tengo una familia. Tengo que pagar el colegio, todo. Así que no es suficiente para mi. Tengo que pagar a alguien para que cuide a mi hijo cuando estoy compitiendo, cuando estoy en las concenttraciones. Recuerdo que este año, preparando Londres, tenía que estar fuera de casa durante 22 días, dos veces, ¿vale? Necesitaba pagar a alguien para que cuidara de mi bebé, y es muy caro. Así que no es suficiente. Gané una medalla de oro y recibí la misma cantidad que alguien que fue sexto en los Juegos Olímpicos. Alguien que fue sexto ahí tiene lo mismo que yo con una medalla de oro. Estuve hace poco en el Congreso de los Diputados, y estuve hablando de esto.</p></p>
</text>
