<text id="autogum_interview_doc768" title="part1_Keep your eyes peeled for cosmic debris: Andrew Westphal about Stardust@home" shortTile="partkeep-eyes-peeled" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-05-18" dateModified="2015-10-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Keep_your_eyes_peeled_for_cosmic_debris%3A_Andrew_Westphal_about_Stardust%40home" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Stardust@home is a highly distributed project using a "Virtual Microscope" that is written in html and javascript and runs on most browsers — no downloads are required. Using the Virtual Microscope volunteers can search over the collector for the tracks of the interstellar dust particles. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How many samples do you anticipate being found during the course of the project?</hi></p>
<p>Great question. The short answer is that we don't know. The long answer is a bit more complicated. Here's what we know. The Galileo and Ulysses spacecraft carried dust detectors onboard that Eberhard Gruen and his colleagues used to first detect and them measure the flux of interstellar dust particles streaming into the solar system. (This is a kind of "wind" of interstellar dust, caused by the fact that our solar system is moving with respect to the local interstellar medium.) Markus Landgraf has estimated the number of interstellar dust particles that should have been captured by Stardust during two periods of the "cruise" phase of the interplanetary orbit in which the spacecraft was moving with this wind. He estimated that there should be around 45 particles, but this number is very uncertain — I wouldn't be surprised if it is quite different from that. That was the long answer! One thing that I should say...is that like all research, the outcome of what we are doing is highly uncertain. There is a wonderful quote attributed to Einstein — "If we knew what we were doing, it wouldn't be called "research", would it?" </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How big would the samples be?</hi></p>
<p>We expect that the particles will be of order a micron in size. (A millionth of a meter.) When people are searching using the virtual microscope, they will be looking not for the particles, but for the tracks that the particles make, which are much larger — several microns in diameter. Just yesterday we switched over to a new site which has a demo of the VM (virtual microscope) I invite you to check it out. The tracks in the demo are from submicron carbonyl iron particles that were shot into aerogel using a particle accelerator modified to accelerate dust particles to very high speeds, to simulate the interstellar dust impacts that we're looking for.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">And that's on the main Stardust@home website [see <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#External_links">below</ref>]?</hi></p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How long will the project take to complete?</hi></p>
<p>Partly the answer depends on what you mean by "the project". The search will take several months. The bottleneck, we expect (but don't really know yet) is in the scanning — we can only scan about one tile per day and there are 130 tiles in the collector…. These particles will be quite diverse, so we're hoping that we'll continue to have lots of volunteers collaborating with us on this after the initial discoveries. It may be that the 50th particle that we find will be the real Rosetta stone that turns out to be critical to our understanding of interstellar dust. So we really want to find them all! Enlarging the idea of the project a little, beyond the search, though is to actually analyze these particles. That's the whole point, obviously! </p>
</text>
