<text id="autogum_interview_doc546" title="part4_Wikinews interviews Jeff Jacobsen, creator of LisaMcPherson.org" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-12" dateModified="2012-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jeff_Jacobsen%2C_creator_of_LisaMcPherson.org" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : What do you expect Project Chanology to accomplish and when?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: I am not an Anon, and know little about the movement. But I was extremely impressed that Anonymous brought out thousands of people to protest around the world on short notice. From what I've seen, I believe they can accomplish a lot. I hope a few more protests, then work on Scientology's tax exemption, which I believe is a very vulnerable area for Scientology. Project Chanology is a strong force with able people. It can do a lot.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Anonymous utilized criminal tactics, why should such organizations be trusted and regarded as credible?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: Us long-time critics were initially very frightened of Anonymous. You can tell that from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark%20Bunker">Wise Beard Man</ref>'s first video but since then it appears that Anonymous has dropped the original things we were seeing. So I see it as self-policing happened and things are on track now. I do not condone anything but peaceful, legal methods. And now Anonymous is promoting that as well, so I am happy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : What should be the next step for the Anonymous movement?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: Wow. That's not for me to say. I'm not a part of it.  But I do hope they will do as they have been, which is listening to us who have been in the field for a long time. You can listen and learn from what we've done, then decide where to go from here. My one wish would be to go after Scientology's tax exempt status in the US. Otherwise I have confidence that Anonymous will find the right path.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : What are your crimes?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: religiousfreedomwatch.org tried to find my crimes, most of what they came up with is about my dad. So I like to tell people I'm Scientology-approved! They couldn't find any crimes:)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Justice2</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : What keeps you going? And how much <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fair%20Game%20(Scientology)">fair game</ref> have you got got?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: I've been deposed 3 times by Scientology attorneys. My home has been picketed. My business has been picketed twice. In Clearwater I was followed sometimes daily by PIs [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Private%20investigator">Private investigator</ref>]. Lynn Farney yelled at me "we will raid you and sue you! You are on notice!" after one deposition. I've had my neighborhood leafleted with flyers calling me a bigot. What keeps me going is that Scientology hurts people. When they stop hurting people, I'll stop bugging them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Justice2</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : What advice would you give to those who get "Fair Gamed"?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: Go to the police right away. Keep a record of everything. Carry a video camera. I always had a video camera with me in Clearwater, even going to the grocery store. And another thing I liked to do is post everything that happened online. One time I posted "if I disappear, here's the plate number of a car that's been following me..."</p>
</text>
