<text id="autogum_interview_doc965" title="part4_Wikinews interviews Fred Karger, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-04-23" dateModified="2014-03-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Fred_Karger%2C_U.S._Republican_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">As you've said, it seems very likely that Mitt Romney will win the Republican nomination. Might you support him in the general election?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Fred Karger</hi>: Well, I said that I'm very uncomfortable with anyone who signed this <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/National_Organization_for_Marriage#2012_presidential_pledge">marriage pledge</ref> of the National Organization for Marriage. I asked him specifically to disavow that pledge. They just endorsed his candidacy yesterday. This is a very shady organization that is under investigation for money laundering in Maine.  It has just been revealed by four unsealed documents by a federal judge that were subpoenaed from NOM of their devious and illegal activities. We now know that there have been illegal activities that have taken place by them. And I am uncomfortable with Mitt Romney as long as he is willing to connect with this very very questionable organization. And so I'm going to weigh the field. I am not going to make any decisions if he were to be our nominee as the Republican Party. I liked <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20W.%20Romney">his dad</ref> a lot. I'm not quite there with Mitt Romney, but I'll have to wait and see how things develop.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Your best showing in the Republican primaries so far came in Puerto Rico last month. In terms of campaigning, what did you learn from that experience?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Fred Karger</hi>: Well, Puerto Rico has an open primary as did <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Michigan">Michigan</ref>. I tend to do better in states with an open primary because Republicans that are voting in a primary tend to be far more conservative. So if they have heard of me and know that I'm an openly gay candidate that of course could eliminate a potential vote. So I like that. I like the fact that I got an enormous amount of attention down there.</p>
<p><figure><caption>Karger campaigning in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Puerto_Rico">Puerto Rico</ref> in March.Image: Fred Karger.</caption></figure></p></p>
<hi rend="bold">The [Puerto Rican] media was very interested. I was endorsed by the number one radio talk show host in San Juan, Carmen Jovet, who had interviewed me on her show.</hi>
<p>Puerto Rico is way behind the states in its support for gay civil rights.  There's a gay and lesbian center that's only been open for one year, as opposed to the states where gay centers have been open for 25 or 30 years or more. So they are very much behind the times. But they are coming around. They are very grateful for my presence there. I got a lot of speaking engagements. The media was very interested. I was endorsed by the number one radio talk show host in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/San_Juan,_Puerto_Rico">San Juan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carmen%20Jovet">Carmen Jovet</ref>, who had interviewed me on her show. And she's a very prominent media personality. And when there was a hurricane there, they got her to chair the foundation. We just spoke, having fun with it. I didn't know that after that she would endorse me and that had a lot to do with it. </p>
</text>
