<text id="autogum_interview_doc800" title="part3_Antje Duvekot on life as a folk singer, her family and her music" shortTile="partantje-duvekot" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Antje_Duvekot_on_life_as_a_folk_singer%2C_her_family_and_her_music" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you feel home up in Boston?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>I do, and part of that is the great folk community.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why do you think <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music%20of%20Massachusetts">Boston has</ref> such a well-developed folk scene?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  It’s always historically been a folk hub.  There’s a lot of awesome folk stations like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WUMB">WUMB</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WERS">WERS</ref>.  Legendary folk clubs, like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Club%20Passim">Club Passim</ref>.  Those have stayed in tact since the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1960s">sixties</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is there anything culturally about Boston that makes it more conducive to folk?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  Once you have a buzz, the buzz creates more buzz.  Some people hear there’s a folk scene in Boston, and then other people move there, so the scene feeds itself and becomes a successful scene.  It’s on-going.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have a favorite curse word?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Giggles</hi>]  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cunt">Cunt</ref>.  [<hi rend="italic">Giggles</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Really?!  You are the first woman I have met who likes that word!</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  Oh, really?  I’ll use it in a traffic situation.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Road%20rage">Road rage</ref>.  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you find yourself more inspired by man-made creations, including people and ideas, or nature-made creations?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  I love nature, but it is limited.  It is what it is, and doesn’t include the human imagination that can go so much further than nature.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What are some man made things that inspire you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  New York City as a whole is just an amazing city.  People are so creative and it is the hub of personal creativity, just in the way people express themselves on a daily basis.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think you will return?</hi></p>
<p>In theory I will return one day if I have money, but in theory you need money to enjoy yourself.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What trait do you deplore in yourself?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  Like anyone, I think <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laziness">laziness</ref>.  I’m a bit a hard on myself, but there’s always more I can do.  As a touring singer-songwriter I work hard, but sometimes I forget because I get to sleep in and my job is not conventional, and sometimes I think ‘Oh, I don’t even have a job, how lazy I am!’ [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Then, of course, there are times I’m touring my ass off and I work hard as well.  It comes in shifts.  There are times there is so much free time I have to structure my own days, and that’s a challenge.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When is the last time you achieved a goal and were disappointed by it and thought, “Is that all there is?”  Something you wanted to obtain, you obtained it, and it wasn’t nearly as fulfilling as you thought it would be.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  I was just thinking about the whole dream of becoming a musician.  I want to maybe do a research project about people’s dreams and how they feel about them after they come true.  It’s really interesting.  They change a lot.  When I was 17 I saw <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ani%20DiFranco">Ani Difranco</ref> on stage and I wanted to do <hi rend="italic">that</hi>, and now I’m doing it.  Now I think about Ani very differently.  I wonder how long it took her to drive here, she must be tired; I’m thinking of all the pragmatic things that go on behind the scenes.  The backside of a dream you never consider when you’re dreaming it.  To some extent, having my dream fulfilled hasn’t been a let-down, but it’s changed.  It’s more realistic.</p>
</text>
