<text id="autogum_interview_doc446" title="part0_US presidential candidate Duncan Hunter speaks to Wikinews" shortTile="partus-presidential" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-12" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_presidential_candidate_Duncan_Hunter_speaks_to_Wikinews" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>US presidential candidate Duncan Hunter speaks to Wikinews</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 2, 2008</hi></p>
<figure rend="Duncan Hunter, official photo portrait, color.jpg"></figure><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Duncan_Hunter">Duncan Hunter</ref> is an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">American</ref> politician who has been a Republican member of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_House_of_Representatives">House of Representatives</ref> since 1981 from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref>'s 52nd congressional district in northern and eastern <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/San_Diego,_California">San Diego</ref>. It was previously numbered the 42nd District from 1981 to 1983 and then the 45th District from 1983 to 1993. Hunter was the chairman of the House Armed Services Committee during the 109th Congress. Hunter is currently seeking the Republican Party nomination for President of the United States.  Below is <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>'s interview with the Congressman.
<head id="Running_for_President">Running for President</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How do you handle juggling running the Presidential campaign, acting as a Congressman, and as a husband?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  It all works out well.  I just talked to my wife, who is campaigning in Wyoming right now.  She’s in Casper; I just saw her a couple of nights ago and I came back here [to Washington D.C.] for the votes [on the Defense Bill].  Our son just came back from Afghanistan on Thanksgiving.  He’s a U.S. Marine and finished his third tour there in Afghanistan and Iraq.  We’re all doing well.  We’re all blessed and having a great campaign season.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you ever at night say to yourself, “I can’t believe I am finding the energy for another day of this.”</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  No, actually, listen, most of this stuff is done in air conditioning.  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">[<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  That can’t help the sleep deprivation, though.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Listen, I was looking out the window of the Capitol and I saw two guys laying pipeline across Independence Avenue and I thought all I have to do is straighten my tie and make another speech.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Good point.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  It’s a lot of fun, it’s a privilege and we’re having a great time.  It’s a wonderful family endeavor.  I think we’re getting our message out, too:  strong national defense, enforce our borders;  we’ve got the other guys talking about border enforcement and building my border fence.  Also, we’re talking about bringing back high-paying manufacturing jobs that we pushed off to China with bad trade deals.  Also the need to keep this country strong militarily.  I think it’s a strong message, and I think the message is catching hold well.</p>
<head id="Immigration_and_the_U.S.-Mexico_border_fence">Immigration and the U.S.-Mexico border fence</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Presumably the primary reason one typically gives to run for President is because they think they can win and do some good things for the country, but would you say the second reason after that is for a chance to frame the debate on the issues?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Certainly.  I think you do that every day, so you’re accomplishing something every day of the campaign, which is getting your message out.  For example, I built the border fence in San Diego and I wrote the law that the President signed last October 26 a year ago to extend the border fence—<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States–Mexico%20barrier">my San Diego fence</ref>—854 miles across <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Arizona">Arizona</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Mexico">New Mexico</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Texas">Texas</ref>.  Across the smuggling corridors in those states.  So every day we work that issue and energize the American people to build the fence, which is now the <hi rend="italic">law</hi>.  Every time we get that agenda to complete the border fence picked up by the other candidates, we are accomplishing something.  We’re moving the ball down the field.</p>
</text>
