<text id="autogum_interview_doc019" title="part7_Wikinews attends 2018 Bangalore ComicCon" shortTile="partwikinews-attends" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-11-21" dateModified="2019-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_attends_2018_Bangalore_ComicCon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>Comicbook artist Vanesa Del Rey.Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Acagastya">Agastya</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure><p> Thank you for agreeing to the interview.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Agastya</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So ma'am would you please tell us about yourself?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Vanesa Del Rey</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  My name is Vanesa and I live in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Miami,_Florida">Miami</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Florida">Florida</ref> [<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>]. And I am an illustrator for comics. Um, my current work is called <hi rend="italic">Redlands</hi> and it's a horror book.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Since when did you start [...] drawing <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/concept%20art">concept arts</ref> and got into comics?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">VDR</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Concept art: I started working on that right after I went to school. I got a job at an animation studio, and then there I did concept art like cartoon design, paintings, story boarding; and then while I was working there, a publisher approached me and they wanted me to work on a series for them. And I said, "Yeah", and that's how I got into comics. Like I, it was: I just got an email one day. [Laughs]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So, what was your first job like?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">VDR</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  In comics?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">VDR</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  It was... it was a big learning experience. I had never done anything long term, you know? Like I was just used to just doing a couple of pages. But this was, like, a long series. So I learned a lot about my process and how to be more efficient, you know. With time, especially, because I was taking too long doing the work, because I didn't have a process set. So it was a big learning experience.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How much time does it [drawing concept art] take?   What are the processes like?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">VDR</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  It's very time consuming. Because you go through so many options, so many, like trial and errors. And you don't know what you are look for. You sort of like have to search and, like, look at a lot of things and do a lot of, you know, a lot of work, to find the final thing that matches with what you are trying to express, you know. So, it takes a long time. [Laughs]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What are the projects that you have worked on?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">VDR</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So far?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">VDR</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Okay so I started with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boom!%20Studios">Boom! Studios</ref>, and with them, I did this series called <hi rend="italic">Hit</hi>. Then, with them I did a series called <hi rend="italic">The Empty Man</hi>. And after that, I did the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scarlet%20Witch">Scarlet Witch</ref>, I think. Then after that I did <hi rend="italic">Spider-Women</hi>, and I did a little bit of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Constantine">Constantine</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hellblazer">Hellblazer</ref>. I did a couple of anthologies. I did Daredevil annual in 2016. And after that I have been working on Redlands.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What work are you most proud of?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">VDR</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I would say: my project Redlands, right now it's my most, the one I am most proud of because it's all mine, it's all my work. It's not something that's already been created, you know? It is coming from me. And my collaborators.</p>
</text>
