<text id="autogum_interview_doc167" title="part0_Canada&amp;apos;s Don Valley West (Ward 25) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-don-valley" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2007-06-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Don_Valley_West_%28Ward_25%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Canada's Don Valley West (Ward 25) city council candidates speak</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 3, 2006</hi></p>
<p>On November 13, Torontonians will be heading to the polls to vote for their ward's councillor and for mayor. Among Toronto's ridings is Don Valley West (Ward 25). Three candidates responded to Wikinews' requests for an interview. This ward's candidates include <hi rend="bold">John Blair</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Robertson Boyle</hi>, Tony Dickins, <hi rend="bold">Cliff Jenkins</hi> (incumbent), and Peter Kapsalis.</p>
<p>For more information on the election, read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto%20municipal%20election,%202006">Toronto municipal election, 2006</ref>.</p>
<head id="John_Blair">John Blair</head>
<p>48-year-old <hi rend="bold">John Blair</hi> is a high school English teacher.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> First, I propose a personal property tax freeze. After three consecutive years of increases above the inflation rate, homeowners need some breathing space. Many are in danger of losing their homes due to higher taxes (just as tenants are being evicted from their apartments because of rising rents at a record levels in Toronto). We need to apply the brakes.</p>
<p>Second, developers, who (inspired by nothing other than optimum profit) ignore the wishes of communities in all wards, need to be taken to task. Public appeals to the Ontario Municipal Board (OMB) are almost never successful while appeals by developers are disproportionately successful. Nothing short of dismantling the OMB will start to solve this situation.</p>
<p>Third, the Toronto Council pay raise is inexcusable and I will invest my 8.9% raise in worthwhile Ward 25 causes. Elected officials need to earn the respect of the electorate by showing leadership in their own finances.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Definitely, over-development and intensification. Real two-way communication is necessary between neighbourhoods and the developers who propose to transform a given area. Ward 25 residents like their living spaces and any new development has to "make sense" to the people currently living in the proximity, not just dollars for developers. There must be a vision -- a "fitting in" with the existing character of a community.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> For some time, I have thought about being more involved in the challenges that face Toronto. I want to live to a higher standard than just to live for myself. Public service is an honourable calling. With the demolition of the former Don Mills Centre indoor mall (to be replaced by an outdoor lifestyle centre (courtesy of the Ontario Teachers' Pension Plan and its instrument, Cadillac Fairview), I finally made my decision. The Don Mills Centre was already more than a shopping mall -- it was a friendly village for old and young alike, and now it has been levelled to satisfy the greed of a ruthless developer and its owner.</p>
</text>
