<text id="autogum_interview_doc449" title="part3_US presidential candidate Duncan Hunter speaks to Wikinews" shortTile="partus-presidential" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-12" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_presidential_candidate_Duncan_Hunter_speaks_to_Wikinews" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Don’t you think this is a problem we have in the country with both parties doing it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Well, they have always done it.  I guess my point is that it’s the same as it has always been.  There have been a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California%20Proposition%2077%20(2005)">number of attempts</ref> in which referendums have been offered by the minority party, for example in California, to make redistricting more even, and those initiatives have always been the subject of mass media campaigns by the controlling party, and you’ve usually lost.  So you end up in the end with the elective representatives of the party sometimes overseen by the judiciary, because you end up with judicial panels redistricting if there is a defective redistricting by the state legislature, but in the end the elected representatives of the states are the people who draw the lines.  I don’t know what a valid substitute would be for the elected representatives of the state.  I say that as a guy coming from a state that is dominated by the opposite party that tries to do my party in.  On the other hand, those districts are drawn by people who have been elected by the majority of Californians.  I like the idea of having judicial panels redistrict the states, but I think in the end under this democratic system we have, having the elected representatives do the redistricting is the way it has been done in the past and the way it is going to be done in the future.</p>
<head id="Iran_and_nuclear_capabilities">Iran and nuclear capabilities</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Intelligence%20Estimate">National Intelligence Estimate</ref> came out that Iran has not had a nuclear weapons program in years, but the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20W.%20Bush%20Administration">Bush Administration</ref> has been warning us that Iran is a threat.  Do you think these two pieces of information hurt our international standing?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  No, I don’t.  First, I think the National Intelligence Estimate, which I have seen in classified and unclassified form, is flat-out wrong.  Because a major part of a weapons program is the production of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weapons-grade">weapons-grade uranium</ref>.  You presently have 2,952 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centrifuge">centrifuges</ref> refining <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/uranium">uranium</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natanz">Natanz</ref>, which is three times as many centrifuges as our intelligence service has estimated until an actual inspection was made by the IAEA.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> But the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Atomic_Energy_Agency">IAEA</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mohamed_ElBaradei">Mohamed ElBaradei</ref> have also come out and said that the National Intelligence Estimate jibes with their findings.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  What I’m saying is that the facts  don’t support the facts as alleged—or represented by this last inspection—don’t’ support the conclusion that there is not a weapons program being undertaken.  A major part of a nuclear device is the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Refined%20uranium">refined uranium</ref>, which constitutes the explosive matter in a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nuclear_bomb">nuclear device</ref>.  If that’s a major part of the bomb, right now you have almost 3,000 centrifuges producing that material right now in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natanz">Natanz</ref>, Iran, and not only haven’t they slowed down, but they have been increased to three times our former estimate and they are going—according to the last inspection—full bore.  So if somebody is telling you they are disarming, the next question you want to ask them is, “Then why are your ammunition factories still in production?”</p>
</text>
