<text id="autogum_interview_doc858" title="part3_Q and A with New Zealand Prime Minister hopeful" shortTile="partq-new-zealand" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-05-17" dateModified="2019-09-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Q_and_A_with_New_Zealand_Prime_Minister_hopeful" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>National has a 5-point plan for boosting New Zealand’s economic performance. We will bring discipline to government spending, boost investment in infrastructure, cut bureaucracy and red tape, create an environment to reduce pressure on interest rates and introduce an ongoing programme of personal tax cuts.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What kind of improvements are you looking at making to the health sector, such as hospitals and ambulances?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.K.</hi>: Our health system is currently in a mess. For all of Labour’s extra spending on health, the public still don’t think the services are that much better.  Despite the thousands of extra bureaucrats, the sector continues to lurch from one crisis to the next.  National is committed to delivering better, sooner and more convenient healthcare for all New Zealanders. To do this we will put patients first, move to integrated care, put greater trust in health professionals and encourage innovation and sharing of resources in the health sector.</p>
<p>It is a very complex sector, with complex demands. We have a discussion document currently out for consultation, it sets out ours ideas for health in greater detail.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Your party opposed interest free student loans at the 2005 elections. Should students looking to study in 2009 have anything to fear when considering voting National in 2008?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.K.</hi>: National knows that education and training is the gateway to opportunity and independence. We will be releasing our full education policies closer to the election but we have already announced our intention to lift educational standards and a youth guarantee that promises funding for education or training for all students up to the age of 18 to gain school level qualifications. National will also keep interest-free student loans for tertiary students. As an incentive to encourage faster payment of loans and help borrowers get out of debt sooner, we will also offer a 10% bonus on a loan balance for voluntary lump-sum payments of $500 or more.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you feel the country should not be concerned at your mistakes you made on live television?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.K.</hi>: In public life it is often difficult to please all of the people all of the time, often you have to make calls that some people won’t like.  But unlike many of my opponents, I have not been a politician for decades.  I am comfortable with my style of leadership, which is very future focussed.  No one in National is under any illusion about the task that lies ahead.  I am the first to admit that we’re all human and make mistakes from time to time.  I think most Kiwis appreciate that. The important thing is to learn from your mistakes and I’ve certainly done that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why do you feel the country keeps backlashing when you announce policies? Why did you take so long to start putting out policies?</hi></p>
</text>
