<text id="autogum_interview_doc1217" title="part0_The Onion: An interview with 'America's Finest News Source'" shortTile="partthe-onion-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2013-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Onion%3A_An_interview_with_%27America%27s_Finest_News_Source%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>The Onion: An interview with 'America's Finest News Source'</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, November 25, 2007</hi></p>
<figure rend="The Onion Broadway Office by David Shankbone.jpg"></figure>Despite the hopes of many <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Wisconsin-Madison">University of Wisconsin-Madison</ref> (UW) students, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Onion"><hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi></ref> was not named after their student center.  "People always ask questions about where the name <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> came from," said President Sean Mills in an interview with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>, "and when I recently asked Tim Keck, who was one of the founders, he told me the name—I’ve <hi rend="italic">never</hi> heard this story about ‘see you at the un-yun’—he said it was literally that his Uncle said he should call it <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> when he saw him and Chris Johnson eating an onion sandwich.  They had literally just cut up the onion and put it on bread."  According to Editorial Manager Chet Clem, their food budget was so low when they started the paper that they were down to white bread and onions.
<p>Long before <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Daily%20Show">The Daily Show</ref></hi> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Colbert%20Report">The Colbert Report</ref></hi>, Heck and Johnson envisioned a publication that would parody the news—and news reporting—when they were students at UW in 1988.  Since its inception, <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> has become a veritable news parody empire, with a print edition, a website that drew 5,000,000 unique visitors in the month of October, personal ads, a 24 hour news network, podcasts, and a recently launched world atlas called <hi rend="italic">Our Dumb World</hi>.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al%20Gore">Al Gore</ref> and General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tommy%20Franks">Tommy Franks</ref> casually rattle off their favorite headlines (Gore's was when <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> reported he and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tipper%20Gore">Tipper</ref> were having the best sex of their lives after his 2000 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electoral%20college">Electoral College</ref> defeat).  Many of their writers have gone on to wield great influence on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jon%20Stewart">Jon Stewart</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen%20Colbert">Stephen Colbert</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/News%20parody">news parody</ref> shows.  </p>
<p>And we are sorry to break the news to all you amateur headline writers: your submissions do not even get read.</p>
<p>Below is David Shankbone's interview with Chet Clem and Sean Mills about the news empire that has become <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi>. </p>
<head id="How_The_Onion_writes_an_issue">How The Onion writes an issue</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone  How do you decide on the stories?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet Clem, Editorial Manager:</hi>  We do everything backwards here.  We start with the headline and then flesh out the story, as opposed to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20New%20York%20Times">The New York Times</ref></hi>, which writes the issue and then has a headline editor to make it snappy.  We start with a joke.  We read about six hundred to eight hundred headline ideas on a Monday coming from our staff and a small group of writers outside—a contributing core.  We whittle that down on a Monday to about a hundred, come in Tuesday and pick an issue and brainstorm with the whole editorial staff; all fifteen of us.  Then we assign a headline to a specific writer to execute.  We go through a number of drafts and then have the editors pick it up and assign the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Photojournalism">photojournalism</ref> aspect of it to our graphic design team, who adds the visual aspect to it.  The editors punch it up over the last couple of days and then it goes out over the Internet and into the print edition.</p>
</text>
