<text id="autogum_interview_doc1190" title="part2_BDSM as business: An interview with the owners of a dungeon" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_An_interview_with_the_owners_of_a_dungeon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  We're still looking out for their needs.  They're still human beings, and they have needs.  So each and every person, I look out for their needs.  And they all think I'm their best friend.</p>
<head id="Their_home_life">Their home life</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do your kids feel about this as a business?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  They don't know.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  They don't know.  That's why we want to be anonymous.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What would they think?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  I don't know, but I don't think it'd be healthy.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  I think my almost-seventeen-year-old would be okay with it.  My middle one I don't think would be very happy, and my youngest would probably want to do it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do they think you do?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  They know I'm a psychologist.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have a practice?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  I haven't for a long time.  They know I have some other businesses as well; we run some other businesses.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Kids just don’t care what their parents do.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Right.  Exactly. But in a way, I feel like I'm mothering 30 girls sometimes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is that taxing on you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  It's exhausting.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  That's why people can't do this business.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you handle that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Sometimes, some days I go home and cry.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So when people bring problems into work, which happens in any workplace, you're the one that they probably turn to.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do either of you think ever of leaving this business?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Yeah, we will.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  We will at some point.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  I'll retire and live off my millions.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  At this point, I--we've worked so hard.  I mean, at the beginning, I didn't think I'd actually be proud of it.  Now it's something--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  We have a lot of people that depend on us here.  A lot of girls we put through grad school, a lot of girls.  We've lent money to a lot of people here; we've helped out a lot of people--we've done that.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  It's so much part of who I am, and I would never believe that it was actually me.  I would never have thought this would be part of who I am, and at this point it is.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But your kids know you work nights.  What do you tell them when you're leaving?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  I just try to tell them--I try to condense my work so that I can be home with them also.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But what do they think that you're doing?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Work.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Work. Just--generic work?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  I am doing work.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  A non-issue.  I have an advertising business as well, a little advertising business.</p>
</text>
