<text id="autogum_interview_doc1059" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Marion Schaffer, Oakville" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-24" dateModified="2013-05-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_candidate_Marion_Schaffer%2C_Oakville" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Marion Schaffer, Oakville</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 24, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Marion Schaffer</hi> is running for the Green Party of Ontario in the Ontario provincial election, in the Oakville riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed her regarding her values, her experience, and her campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I joined the Green Party in Oakville because that’s where I choose to live now, close to family. I’ve never been a party member before. The Green Party is the only internationally connected party which is ready, and able, to take positive action to clean up our world. It was essential for me to join and start doing my part in the redesigning of the future.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I think it's a good thing that I have had no prior political experience; the Green Party is re-inventing the word 'politician'.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?</hi></p>
<p>Many people distrust today's politicians. They are seen as people who talk but do not listen; as people who promise but do not deliver on those promises. The Green Party is developing leaders who will be advocates working in partnership with people everywhere to heal our over-stressed world.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>I have functioned as a: speaker/leader/guide/advocate/feminist/pacifist/teacher/pastor in previous careers and I am not afraid of any opponents because I intend to follow the example of our Green Party Federal leader, Elizabeth May, and always speak the truth to the best of my knowledge.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>In my opinion the three most important issues here in Oakville are:</p>
<p>a. controlling urban sprawl</p>
<p>b. preserving what we have in a fiscally responsible way</p>
<p>c. educating local people so that they conserve energy, support local industry, but think globally.</p>
<p>These goals reflect Green Party policy.</p>
<p>I will use all possible resources of The Green Party of Ontario to promote these ends and as well, day by day, change the way I live. I must lead by example and walk the walk or I can't say that I am Green.</p>
</text>
