<text id="autogum_interview_doc647" title="part5_Popular soap opera &amp;apos;The Young and the Restless&amp;apos; celebrates 35 years on the air" shortTile="partpopular-soap" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-25" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Popular_soap_opera_%27The_Young_and_the_Restless%27_celebrates_35_years_on_the_air" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: Do you feel there should be a happy ending for Nikki and Victor?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: No, no, no to the happy ending!  If we languished in happiness for too long, it would be beyond boring.  Tension and conflict is the only way to keep characters interesting.  You may think you want them to be happy, but after a short time, the audience would want to see some fireworks again.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: Your character went from stripper to socialite. How do you feel this change deepened the facets of your character's personality?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: Nikki went through a lot even before the stripper storyline.  In the first few months after I started, she killed her father in self-defense (he had rape on his mind), joined a cult, and was a model for an agency that turned out to be a front for prostitution. Beyond wayward! Being a "socialite" never entered her mind, as she believed Victor was the butler when she fell in love with him. The socialite aspect happened very slowly, but finding herself as the wife of Victor Newman, she had to learn how to present herself properly in this world that was 180 degrees from where she came from.  I think deep down she still feels unworthy of her position in life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: How do you feel about being recognized not only in the U.S., but abroad as well?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: It's amazing.  One of the perks of being on such an internationally successful show has been traveling to other countries (we are [currently] broadcast in 55 countries) on the show's behalf. I'll never forget the mind-boggling reception we received in Istanbul.  Journalists and film crews were actually on the tarmac as we disembarked the plane.  We kept looking behind us to see who they were waiting for. Was Princess Diana on the plane with us? No, they were there for us. We have enjoyed similar receptions in Italy, Belgium, France, Monte Carlo, Canada, the Caribbean, and Australia, to name a few.  It's given us very treasured memories.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: Some of your fans are new to the show, and others have watched since you first appeared in 1979. What would you like to say as an end note to all of your fans?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: Thank you for your support! Keep it up!  You are the only reason that we are thriving.  Thanks for having such good taste!</p>
<head id="Questions_asked_to_Michelle_Stafford">Questions asked to Michelle Stafford</head>
<figure><caption>Michelle Stafford on who really got Phyllis' goat: "Christine by far.  She really really really gets under Phyllis' skin. [Drucilla and Diane] are bad themselves, so they don't get under her skin."(Photo credit: CBS/Monty Brinton)</caption></figure>
</text>
