<text id="autogum_interview_doc057" title="part2_Wikinews interviews painter Pricasso on his art and freedom of expression" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-10-10" dateModified="2019-08-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_painter_Pricasso_on_his_art_and_freedom_of_expression" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: No particular reason on my behalf, it was the organisers of the Sexpo who got me to paint it mainly for publicity. But also to have a portrait on my stand, who people in Cape Town would relate to as I now know she is very popular and has a great sense of humour.</p>
<figure><caption>Cape Town former-Mayor <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Helen_Zille">Helen Zille</ref> Image: Helen Zille, Democratic Alliance, South Africa.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Mayor of Cape Town Helen Zille commented of your portrait painting of her: "This is a free country. A free society throws up these kinds of people, who exercise their freedom in unusual ways. And if this is how he wants to do it, I must accept his constitutional right to do so." — what are your thoughts on her reaction?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: Sounds a bit formal but that is how politicians usually talk, guarded and a totally correct response, the trouble is that if they spoke from the heart it might come back to bite them one day, but I did talk to one of her aides privately and she said they were all really impressed and loved the concept, I really should have offered to paint her too but I was probably flat out all day — I always am at the South African shows.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Mayor Zille further commented about the quality of your painting of her: "[Pricasso] has achieved a good likeness and I can't imagine how he painted it without brushes or conventional equipment." — what do you think of this assessment?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: Most people are impressed when they see it done, skeptical at first but after the initial shock they all usually stop to watch until I finish that particular painting, usually they take about 15 minutes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> If you could speak to Mayor Zille, what would you say to her about her reaction to your painting of her?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: I would say I was impressed with her response, mostly girls are much more impressed than guys only a minority of guys I might add, lots of them love it and me too!! But in general she gave a responsible and educated reply and was not at all offended by the experience.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In 2011, one member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gold%20Coast,%20Queensland">Gold Coast</ref> Sculptors' Society quit in protest due to your participation in the 'Exotic Erotic' show — how do you feel when people react to your artwork in this way?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: I guess I could say; This is a free country. A free society throws up these kinds of people, who exercise their dissaproval in various ways. And if this is how she wants to protest, I must accept her constitutional right to do so. There was that politically correct enough? Or maybe the silly old B***ch — but her reaction did get heaps of publicity for the show and they had record numbers coming through the doors so there was a silver lining.
But obviously it is a bit confronting and not everyone's cup of tea but if they could just see it before they get on their high horse they might have a different point of view.</p>
</text>
