<text id="autogum_interview_doc1402" title="part6_Interview with gay marriage movement founder Evan Wolfson" shortTile="partinterview-gay" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-29" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_gay_marriage_movement_founder_Evan_Wolfson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I don’t see it that way.  I see very clearly we are in fact winning.  The number of people who are wrestling with this question, their desire to be fair but who are also struggling with their conflict and discomfort about gay people. Many don’t understand yet how the denial of marriage really effects real life people who they are increasingly coming to know.  They are having to think about how marriage is something precious and important to same-sex couples and their kids, as well as to them.  They are wrestling with all this.  I have no doubt and I see every day that more people are moving in our direction.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why is momentum in your movement seemingly stalled?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  What hasn’t happened yet is that the decision-makers at a given moment, whether it be judges on a court or the right combination of legislators and a governor, have gotten to the place where they have brought the second state [In 2004 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Same-sex%20marriage%20in%20Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref> became the first state to pass gay marriage].  What hasn’t happened is all those things coming into alignment to get the second state...to get the fifth state.  So you are absolutely right that the victory of the next state has remained a teeny bit beyond our grasp so far, although we continue to come closer and closer.  4-3 in Maryland is not something people thought was going to happen even that close just a few years ago.  On the other hand, 4-3 is not good enough.  It needs to be four to three in our favor, or five to two.  We are this close to getting the second state, and Maryland was very disappointing because we hoped that it might be the next one.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The decision was quite strong.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  No, the decision was quite mediocre.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But the court ruled against even domestic partnerships.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Correct, although the reason the court gave for that is that the plaintiff’s didn’t ask for it.  They could have written more; they encouraged the legislature to move forward; they didn’t preclude a case challenging the denial of the incidence of marriage and unequal treatment generally; they simply ruled on the question before them.  That said, it was a disappointing decision. It was very mediocre and the reasoning was shallow and inadequate.  They never explained how if <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/procreation">procreation</ref> is somehow central to marriage--which legally it clearly is not--how denying gay people the right to marry promotes procreation.</p>
<head id="Freedom_to_Marry’s_role">Freedom to Marry’s role</head>
<figure><caption>Freedom to Marry in 2006.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What role does <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom%20to%20Marry">Freedom to Marry</ref> play in these cases?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  We provide a role as adviser and consultant when asked.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Were you an adviser and consultant to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Equality%20Maryland">plaintiffs</ref> in the Maryland case?</hi></p>
</text>
