<text id="autogum_interview_doc041" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Rocky De La Fuente, U.S. Democratic Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-03-29" dateModified="2016-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Rocky_De_La_Fuente%2C_U.S._Democratic_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>De La Fuente: "I probably best fit the term 'Kennedy Democrat' because I am a strong advocate of social equality and freedom but I believe we must be fiscally responsible as well." Image: The White House.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why are you a Democrat?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">De La Fuente</hi>: I have always considered myself to be a Democrat, although what that term means has shifted over the years. I probably best fit the term "Kennedy Democrat" because I am a strong advocate of social equality and freedom but I believe we must be fiscally responsible as well. While that may not fit the current narrative of modern liberalism that favors social justice and a mixed economy leaning toward an ever increasing presence of government regulation and assistance, it reflects what I truly believe.</p>
<p>I think, during the modern era, Democrats have been the primary political catalyst for social equality and change. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20F.%20Kennedy">President Kennedy</ref> had a unique ability to bring both sides of the aisle together to [make] progress in that regard, but he also recognized that government regulation bore a cost and could pose a threat if it was used in an unbridled fashion. We seem to have forgotten that concept.</p>
<p>Conservatives are relatively adverse to change. I am not. I simply think change needs to [be] achieved in a responsible manner and that federal officials should recognize their [responsibility] to serve as stewards of the taxpayers' money.</p>
<p>I also think we need to figure out how to provide more opportunities for people rather than just mask the symptoms with assistance. The goal of government assistance should always be to provide it as a temporary bridge rather than a permanent foundation. When we lose sight of this, we create programs that deepen our problems rather than resolve them.</p>
<p>I clearly don't fit the Republican mindset when it comes to my position on social issues. However, I'm sure I cause discomfort for some Democrats who think that the government is the solution to every problem. My real world experience in business and my exposure to the economies of other countries have given me a different perspective; one that compels me to assess government programs from a rational basis as well as an emotional one.</p>
<p>I think there's room in the Democratic Party for that type of mindset.</p>
<head id="Campaign">Campaign</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What do you hope to accomplish with this campaign?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">De La Fuente</hi>: Well, imagine if I were to win. If I win, "We all Win" . . . "America Wins" . . . and the World would be a better place.</p>
<p>What I know I can achieve is to broaden the active Democratic base. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hispanic%20and%20Latino%20Americans">Hispanic community</ref> in this country has been relatively inactive from a political perspective. While it represents a sizable element of the Party's foundation, it is somewhat underrepresented in elected office and does not participate in the electoral process to the degree it should. I can spotlight the importance of registering to vote and participating in the process within the Hispanic community because my candidacy has attracted some attention in that regard. I hope I will encourage other minorities and underrepresented groups to become more engaged as well.</p>
</text>
