<text id="autogum_interview_doc192" title="part1_Andrea Muizelaar on fashion, anorexia, and life after &amp;apos;Top Model&amp;apos;" shortTile="partandrea-muizelaar" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Andrea_Muizelaar_on_fashion%2C_anorexia%2C_and_life_after_%27Top_Model%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Andrea_on_her_road_to_modeling,_and_America's_Next_Top_Model">Andrea on her road to modeling, and <hi rend="italic">America's Next Top Model</hi></head>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Who were the people you looked up to and inspired you to pursue modeling? Did they have that thin body type that you hoped to have?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> I looked up to anyone in a media image as well as, and especially, America's Next Top Model contestants.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> That was actually going to be my next question. Who did you look up to on that show?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> All the contestants on the show, minus the plus size girl because I knew modelling was all about thin and not regular people</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Some of the plus sized girls on that show actually went into rather lucrative careers, like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toccara%20Jones">Toccara</ref> from Cycle 3, probably more so than some of the thinner winners. How do you feel about that, and how would you have felt about such an event occurring before you overcame your anorexia?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Like most of the viewers of the show, I had no idea where any of the winners or past-contestants ended up.  Now, I am starting to rebuild my career more than anyone ever helped me to before...and to boot...I am healthy doing it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Definitely. On that note, do you feel there is such a thing as "perfect" in terms of image in fashion?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Absolutely not in real life.  In the fashion world the perfect image is definitely "thin" and it will be for a long time to come.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Even with the Toccaras and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tyra%20Banks">Tyra Banks</ref> of the world?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Tyra Banks started off extremely thin to get to where she is today, I was sick and dying and not able to do the same.  Besides, look at the hype and criticism Tyra is getting for her present size and even Britney Spears for that matter.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> That is true. Do you think Tyra Banks picks the bigger models for "good TV" instead of actually succeeding in modeling?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Absolutely - has any of them ever won yet? ...or come close?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> There was a big hype over Tyra picking Whitney and Diana for ANTM 8, which was the first time two plus sized girls made it into the final rounds. They were both eliminated midway through the competition. That year <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaslene%20Gonzalez">Jaslene</ref> won. Do you think her look is unhealthy in terms of how it's promoted to the public and young girls?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Yes I do.  Look at me and how I looked when I won.  I could not even face the young children that I used to babysit on my crescent, let alone the whole world.  I was ashamed at how I looked.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Do you believe the producers for shows such as Top Model intentionally pick people who are perhaps unstable, whether it be with body image or otherwise?</p>
</text>
