<text id="autogum_interview_doc1310" title="part7_Wikinews interviews former Salt Lake City mayor and 2012 presidential candidate Rocky Anderson" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-12-17" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Salt_Lake_City_mayor_and_2012_presidential_candidate_Rocky_Anderson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<hi rend="bold">[Obama] has greater contempt for the rule of law...than George W. Bush</hi>
<p><p><figure><caption>Anderson speaks at an anti-war rally in 2008.Image: Jeremiah Roth.</caption></figure></p>
<p>And the reason that I said that I felt President Obama should be supported over <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_McCain">McCain</ref> was that he was the lesser of two evils, but I recognized that President Obama had already shown his true colors. Then, I think in the pocket of the nuclear power industry when he was in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illinois%20House%20of%20Representatives">Illinois state house</ref>. He had never really stood up on any major issue. I asked his supporters, they fell for the whole hope and change hype during his campaign, and I was always asking people, so point to one thing that he stood for, where he’s shown any courage in standing up for principle. The entire time he was in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Senate">United States Senate</ref>, he voted for full funding for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq_War">occupation of Iraq</ref>. He never stood up against torture or the other human rights abuses that were occurring during that time. He promised us before he received the Democratic nomination that he would join the filibuster in opposition to Congress providing retroactive immunity for the telecom companies for their illegal participation in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President's%20Surveillance%20Program">Bush surveillance program</ref>. And by the way, not all the telecom companies participated in that, they recognized that it was illegal so it wasn’t a matter of people were fooled about whether it was legal or not. But for those telecom companies that did violate the law, they should have been held accountable. But in the classic American way, the corrupt way that has developed in our system of government, three telecom companies spend some twelve million dollars on lobbyists during the course of three months they put on the press, Congress passed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foreign%20Intelligence%20Surveillance%20Act%20of%201978%20Amendments%20Act%20of%202008">legislation providing for the retroactive immunity</ref> and among those voting for the immunity, now after he received the Democratic nomination was then-Senator Obama, completely betraying those that he had promised to join the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Filibuster%20in%20the%20United%20States%20Senate">filibuster</ref>. But it was just a sign of things to come, they always talked about the rule of law, he has greater contempt for the rule of law, I think, than George W. Bush. He comes into office, says, “oh, we’re going to look forward, not backwards” in terms of holding accountable war criminals? And those were criminals not only under international law, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geneva%20Convention">Geneva Convention</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20Nations%20Convention%20Against%20Torture">Convention Against Torture</ref>, but under our own laws passed by Congress: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War%20Crimes%20Act%20of%201996">War Crimes Act of 1996</ref> and the federal torture statute. Clearly, an illegal act, and he says, “let’s just look forward, not backwards”. But he’s done the same thing for the people who committed such massive financial fraud on Wall Street without holding any one of them accountable.</p></p>
</text>
