<text id="autogum_interview_doc1177" title="part1_Canada's Etobicoke—Lakeshore (Ward 5) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-etobicokelakeshore" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-10-19" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Etobicoke%E2%80%94Lakeshore_%28Ward_5%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The current work done by city staff and council regarding environmental concerns is commendable.  The environmental plan does need some work however, recycling programs are improving and the pesticide ban are a good start.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> If you were elected as a "rookie" councillor, What would you bring to the table beyond the incumbent?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> If I am elected councillor, I will push the public's issues and concerns to the forefront of my work. My work ethic will produce results that will benefit not only our families today but our children tomorrow.</p>
<head id="Peter_Milczyn_(incumbent)">Peter Milczyn (incumbent)</head>
<p>41-year-old Peter Milczyn is the incumbent for Ward 5, Etobicoke-Lakeshore.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The three most important issues in the campaign are:</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Preserving &amp; Enhancing the Quality of Life</hi>: This relates to the fundamentals of we should expect from our local government. Clean and safe streets, a healthy environment, adequate public and green spaces, and controls on development.</p>
<p>As the Councillor for the area I have worked with the community on better road design that would help improve road safety and protect the environment.  I have worked on improving pedestrian safety through increased sidewalks, improvements to pedestrian crossings, and additional traffic lights.  I have helped the community get traffic calming measures installed to curb speeding vehicles near schools and on residential streets.</p>
<p>I have supported the tree protection by-law and the ban on the cosmetic use of pesticides.</p>
<p>I have worked to plant trees along streets and on vacant parcels of City land.  I will continue to do so.</p>
<p>I have fought to maintain mechanical leaf collection in Etobicoke, and for increased street sweeping and litter pick up.</p>
<p>I have supported funds for an additional 250 police officers, and will continue to support ensuring that there are adequate and improved police services in the City.</p>
<p>I have worked to expand and create new local parks.  Dalesford/Winslow Park, Chimes Lane Parkette, Shires Lane Parkette, a new park on Islington Avenue, Michael Power Park.  I have helped to upgrade park facilites such as in Wedgewood Park, Dalesford/Winslow Park, and Kenway Park.  I will be working to create a new park and community recreation centre on the Westwood Theatre Lands.  To create a new park on the Queensway near Zorra Street.  To upgrade playground facilities in Queensland Park, and refurbish the facilities in Queensway Park.</p>
<p>I initiated a new Roof Top Patio Control By-law for Etobicoke to protect residential communities from excessive noise and disruption.  I have spearheaded a crackdown on illegal businesses on The Queensway and strengthening City-wide by-laws to help control them.</p>
</text>
