<text id="autogum_interview_doc1364" title="part2_Teräsbetoni frontman J. Ahola on representing Finland at Eurovision 2008 & more" shortTile="partterasbetoni-frontman" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-03-26" dateModified="2017-05-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ter%C3%A4sbetoni_frontman_J._Ahola_on_representing_Finland_at_Eurovision_2008_%26_more" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<head id="On_Eurovision">On Eurovision</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What does it feel like to be selected to go to Eurovision, especially considering it is mostly an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English%20language">English language</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pop%20music">pop</ref> contest? Is that daunting at all?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Daunting? No way. I’m proud of  being the representative of Finland. Finland has never done too well in Eurovision Song Contest, but Lordi gave the whole show a nice slap in the face. You know, it doesn’t have to be pop to win the number one slot - you can actually play rock music there. We might seem a bit odd to European viewers, ‘cause we have our leatherish looks, metallish music and we sing in Finnish. But in the end, I wish that people will like it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What is the song about?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> The song is set in the Teräsbetoni-world with certain lyrical style. So, there are horses, heroes and battlefields. But in the end the song is about harshness of life, the call of duty and responsibilty.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How do you expect Europe to react to a metal song in Finnish?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Well, you can only guess. I believe they react like Finnish people do – they hate it or love it. Hopely most of them will love it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Of course, Finland has a history of similar Eurovision entries. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nightwish">Nightwish</ref> were second choice to represent Finland once with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sleepwalker%20(song)">Sleepwalker</ref></hi>, and of course Lordi won the whole contest in 2006. What do you think of those entries?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Both of the bands have strong image and style. I’m not too fond of their music, but you can’t really deny their achievements.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Of the entries so far, excluding yourself, who to win?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I haven’t heard any other entries yet. We’ll check them out when we go to Serbia, ‘cause we’ll be there for two weeks. That’s enough of full time Eurovision song focus.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you reckon you have a chance of victory yourself?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> You’ll have to believe in your self if you go to a fight. This is also one of the themes of our ESC-song Missä Miehet Ratsastaa. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">A video for the Eurovision campaign planned to be shown to the press was deemed "too burly" for the contest. Was that anoying?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> You mean our music video? I think the first version of the video was a bit heavy stuff for the people who don’t us. But the new version doesn’t really differ too much from the original, so in that perspective it was a bit annoying… or maybe better word is pointless. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Many people reading this will be thinking about who to vote for at the contest. Why should they vote for you?</hi></p>
</text>
