<text id="autogum_interview_doc1186" title="part2_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Libertarian candidate Zork Hun, Parkdale-High Park" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-02" dateModified="2008-11-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Libertarian_candidate_Zork_Hun%2C_Parkdale-High_Park" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>The tag-line of our party says that we are ‘the party of choice’ To us, this does not mean that we want to change let’s say education or health care, we just want to open the door to change allowing people to make choices for themselves as individuals. This would include allowing private health care and insurance offerings and an unconditional educational voucher system. Allowing the market in is the only thing that can repair the problems of our health care and education systems.</p>
<p>Accountability for me means a lot more than holding politicians and government bureaucrats responsible for their actions; it means to account for and justify the spending of every dollar they handle. Political parties can get away with waste because people do not know what the money is spent on.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>Introducing a bill requiring strict fiscal responsibility from all future governments setting very high requirements (75-80% of all MPPs) for the approval of any deficit spending</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>Absolutely not. Market value based assessment is fundamentally unfair. Since the very essence of the idea is unfair, how could we possibly talk about a fair level? The only ‘fair’ tax is one that is based on services or resource use – a combination of lot size – floor space and - # of inhabitants.</p>
<p>If I reformulate your question to say “are the taxes you pay commensurate with the services you receive” the answer would be no. We are not getting $ 3,500. - worth of services from the city.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>By stopping the redistribution of income between businesses.</p>
<p>A picture a few years ago on my tax return provided a telling example. On two pie charts we saw income and expenses. What was striking in the chart was the similarity in size of two items: the income from corporate taxes and the expense that is paid out as corporate subsidies. The income was 2-3% higher, but the similarity was still striking. What this means is that the government is taking away money from successful businesses and giving it to politically favoured ones.</p>
<p>My answer would be the elimination of both corporate income tax and corporate welfare. The only function of the corporate income tax is to give more power to politicians. Individual taxpayers wouldn’t even notice the difference and a corporate-tax friendly environment would give a tremendous boost to the economy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>My party is divided on the subject and I am personally right in the middle.</p>
</text>
