<text id="autogum_interview_doc1058" title="part10_Past Eurovision contestants give advice to this year's performers, speculate on who will win" shortTile="partpast-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-05-06" dateModified="2015-09-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Past_Eurovision_contestants_give_advice_to_this_year%27s_performers%2C_speculate_on_who_will_win" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>I also love <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/What%20If%20We%20(song)">Malta</ref>, I'm a fan of the big ballads. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chiara%20Siracusa">She</ref> has a beautiful voice. And <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Firefly%20(song)">Cyprus</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christina%20Metaxa">she</ref> "did it" for me too. I also like the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Et%20s'il%20fallait%20le%20faire">French song</ref> as well, but I also love the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French%20language">French language</ref> in general. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bistra%20voda">Bosnia</ref> has a good song too, they have a certain sentiment that they always pull from and it works for them. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lijepa%20Tena">Croatia</ref>, I wasn't too blown away, but I'm proud of them for still singing in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Croatian%20language">Croatian</ref>, even though it may not sound as pretty as English to some people. Everything else, it was like, "It's beautiful, but I've seen it before."</p>
<p>Everything seems like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hollywood">Hollywood</ref> now, I guess because it's the times we live in now. All the girls are so pretty and the hair and makeup are perfect, and now I feel like an old lady, but I miss the characters from different parts of the world. It's influenced so much by Hollywood and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2000s%20in%20music%20industry">Western music industry</ref>. It was inevitable, the melting of it [East and West] all into one, so I'm partial to bringing some sort of local element into it. It comes with finding your identity and finding your place in the world as a country.</p>
<p>I volunteer and give my time to a local school and teach the schoolchildren ethnic dances. I live in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Midwestern%20United%20States">Midwest</ref> now, but I used to live in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los%20Angeles">Los Angeles</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20City">New York</ref> where they are a little more aware of ethnic groups. I'm teaching them these dances to give them a little sense of what's being lost to the new kinds of culture and music. I teach some kids who were adopted from other countries, and I wonder, wow, are they ever going to be able to sing a song in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulgarian%20language">Bulgarian</ref>, or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italian%20language">Italian</ref>, or what have you?</p>
<p>My kids are half-American and half-Croatian, and I see how in my own life, being "globalized" and how people are losing the ethnic folklore and culture and all that, so with my kids, I try to teach them language and how to dance, because it's the way I grew up.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> I watched a clip of your documentary on YouTube, and I noticed one of the comments, asking you "not to forget your home, Croatia," and to come back because the fans there miss you. Now that you've made a life for yourself in America, do you ever see yourself moving back to Croatia with your family? Which country do you feel more ties and loyalty to, the United States or Croatia, and why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tajči</hi>: I want to take the kids and at least spend a year there when they're teenagers, so I can show them my country and so they can learn different things there. But I don't know, once you leave, it's hard to go back. I miss my country, I miss the history. I miss my roots. I miss running into a friend and talking about high school and grade school, stuff that you don't have when you move away. I love what I do, and I love what America has to offer, and what America did offer to me. There's a certain kind of freedom that you have that you can't have in a smaller country.</p>
</text>
