<text id="autogum_interview_doc956" title="part1_Taliban resurgent in Pakistan on enforcement of Sharia law" shortTile="parttaliban-resurgent" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-03-20" dateModified="2019-01-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Taliban_resurgent_in_Pakistan_on_enforcement_of_Sharia_law" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>The Taliban emulated the Saudi system of having a department concerned with citizens’ morals (even the name is the same: the department for the Promotion of Virtue and Prevention of Vice) and this department has, as in Saudi Arabia, an enforcement police, called <hi rend="italic">mutawwa'in</hi>, a morals law-enforcement agency. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Is there a shift from tribal elders to clerics, as the main interpreters of law?</hi></p>
<p>There has been a movement in that direction, but it has started a power struggle between the clerics who traditionally have been at the lowest strata of the social structure. Now when they have seen a bigger role for themselves, first from the Taliban in Afghanistan – but also the government of the MMA in the NWFP, who are nothing more than glorified clerics themselves, only a little smarter in exploiting religion politically. </p>
<p>The MMA is largely non-Pashtun, which is a source of discontent in that they stand in the way of Pashtun nationalism, such as it is, because it only rears its head when non-Pashtuns start to usurp power over what the Pashtun consider their turf.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">The deal made between Pakistan's central government and the North and South Waziristan provinces, where tribal leadership was given the pivotal role in dealing with militants, has been criticized as a failure. What caused this initiative to fail?</hi></p>
<p>First off, I don't agree with the premise of the question, that the "deal" is a "failure" - for the following reasons: </p>
<list type="ordered"><item>In the first place the Pakistan army (govt - same difference) did not have many options. This was the least worst option they had.</item>
<item>And most importantly, I have said this before, this area is literally in a time warp - which means they proceed at (what seems to us in the west) a glacial pace. I will give an example from the folklore:<p><hi rend="italic">The story goes that a Pashtun had to repay (badal) an enemy for a crime against his family and he waited patiently for 20 years (some say 50 years), after this time, he exacted his revenge - but soon after was depressed because he wondered "Did I act too hastily?"</hi></p>So one part of Pashtunwali is to "pay back" - (Badal: literally to exchange) which most people translate as revenge. Yes that is the form that is most visible, but badal is also played out in the exchange of gifts at wedding and other celebrations, and in the exchange of favors like in politics. The rules can be arcane, unwritten and hard to follow -- who did what to whom, when, and so on, and what is the proper recompense -- this same give and take would occur in a peace process pursued by the Tribal Maliks, who rule by consensus. There is no actual leader in the western sense, because all the Maliks, in fact all the others are de facto, so many co-equals is a mind set, a paradigm foreign to the uninitiated, as the concept of consensual gay sex is to the Wazir in Waziristan.</item>
<item>The agreement has not failed, because it has not been given enough time, in Wazir time reference, not American time presidential election cycle controlled. I do not have a crystal ball, but if I did, I would see NATO troops in Afghanistan long after Iraq is over. Afghanistan can be a success ONLY if we accept one thing, the time warp these people live in -- by my reckoning its still 1700 CE over there.</item></list>
</text>
