<text id="autogum_interview_doc1123" title="part1_Dalai Lama's representative talks about China, Tibet, Shugden and the next Dalai Lama" shortTile="partdalai-lamas-representative" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-13" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dalai_Lama%27s_representative_talks_about_China%2C_Tibet%2C_Shugden_and_the_next_Dalai_Lama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  As an autonomous region.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes.  We are seeking a solution within the framework of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese%20Constitution">Chinese Constitution</ref> for a meaningful autonomy.  Until we are able to achieve that goal, we effectively have a government in exile with a charter —a Constitution.  In that charter, his holiness is effectively head of state, and the prime minister is head of government, to use ‘normal terms’.   His Holiness, however, describes himself as semi-retired.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  He’s a symbolic head of the people, whereas Rinpoche would be an administrative head?  I understand you may want to shy away from using government-oriented terminology.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  No, we function as a government in exile.  Nothing to be shy about; we want to be open and transparent.  It is nothing to hide.  Elected parliament, elected leadership; the Tibetan people consider that government as their government, so there is nothing to shy away from.  But as I said, in that charter His Holiness is described as head-of-state, and the elected leadership is head of government, in normal terms.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What would be some of the first actions the Dalai Lama would undertake if he were to return to Tibet?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  He would hand over all of his responsibilities to the new leadership in Tibet.  He made in very clear as far back as 1992, in a public statement, that as soon as we are able to reach an agreement with the Chinese government, the government-in-exile will be dissolved and the responsibility for managing future affairs will be carried out by Tibetans in Tibet.  In other words, people like me who have no claim for leadership and responsibilities by the mere fact that in exile we have been working for Tibet; we will have no claim that we will be in some leadership role when we go back.  His Holiness has made it very clear that the people in Tibet should take the responsibility.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What are the functions or responsibilities of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foreign%20relations%20of%20Tibet">Office of Tibet</ref> in the Americas?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  My responsibilities are to inform the governments, the people of the situation in Tibet and what we are trying to achieve.  Simple as that.</p>
<head id="The_Chinese_invasion_and_occupation">The Chinese invasion and occupation</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How many Tibetans were lost during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genocides%20in%20history#Tibet">Reign of Terror</ref> directly after the Chinese invasion?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  According to our research, we believe that 1.2 million died as a result of Chinese invasion and occupation.  That would include people who were killed in fighting, who died of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/starvation">starvation</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/suicide">suicide</ref>; people who died being tortured in prison, and so on.  1.2 million.  Between March 1959 and the end of 1959, according to China’s own documents—we got hold of the report of a Chinese military officer, an official document—in about nine months, in Central Tibet near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lhasa">Lhasa</ref> alone, 87,000 Tibetans are killed in nine months.  That’s an official Chinese military document.  That document is available and been made public many times.</p>
</text>
