<text id="autogum_interview_doc813" title="part6_Frank Messina: An interview with the &amp;apos;Mets Poet&amp;apos;" shortTile="partfrank-messina" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-03" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Frank_Messina%3A_An_interview_with_the_%27Mets_Poet%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  All evidence is that he was not a predator, but that he was a voice for change of age-of-consent laws.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  To me, it's a non-issue.  Put your hand on my kid and believe me, it's all over for the predator.  That's my policy.  When someone's 18, that's the deal.  I'll stick with the law on that one.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's a lesson your mother taught you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  To never give up.  She was supportive even when I made mistakes, as a good mother will do.  In school my parents were called up a lot.  It was not easy being a parent of Frankie.  Teachers were constantly calling.  I was disruptive, I would talk out of line, I was a class clown.  She taught me to never give up no matter what vocation you choose in your life.  My mother was never critical of my poems and writing.  We're good friends and she's a lot of fun.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How would you choose your death?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  Either in battle or laying in bed with family around me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you ever had a moment where you saw your death?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  Yes, a couple of times.  Once I was on one of those small planes flying to Pittsburgh last year to see the Mets, actually one of those 25-seat airplanes flying out of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newark,%20New%20Jersey">Newark</ref> in a lightning storm.  We had ascended over Newark and the plane was struck by lightning.  There was no panic on the plane at all, but something, we knew, was terribly wrong.  I saw a flash of light when it hit the plane and a fellow across the aisle said, "Did you just see that?" and I said that I thought we were struck by lightning.  He said it felt like something got ripped off the plane.  There was so much turbulence.  The stewardess came out with one of the co-pilots, who announced we were struck by lightning, but that we were going to continue the flight.  There was a moment there, I think a good 30 seconds, where I was certain the plane was going to break apart.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you have any realizations?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  I thought, this is it.  This is it.  There was acceptance.  When my father was diagnosed with cancer in June of 2005 and  I got to see a man who accepted his fate.  He died two months later.  He was like the Captain of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Titanic">Titanic</ref>.  My mother was also calm.  I was the one freaking out inside.  I saw someone who had acknowledged his own demise, accepted it, and died at home.  He was a tough old guy.  It takes a lot to accept that, it takes a very strong person.  In this culture we value life very much, and some people look at death as a failure, but it's going to happen to all of us.  My theory is to help yourself, and help others in life.</p>
</text>
