<text id="autogum_interview_doc207" title="part8_BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2008-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Comfort_levels_in_the_sessions">Comfort levels in the sessions</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you ever act as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Professional%20submissive">Sub</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I have before, yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you feel comfortable as a Sub?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Sometimes, yeah.  I actually realized I am more of a Dom than a Sub, but the way I started out is that you have to try both aspects of it to really get yourself inside the slave’s head during the session.  It helps you understand more what they are going through, what they are feeling, whether it is physical, emotional, psychological.  You understand more, and you are able to go through a session perfectly having subbed before.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  There is never sex involved?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But almost always masturbation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Some, but then you get individuals who are just about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paraphilia">fetish</ref>, it is all they want.  They just want the woman towering over them and telling them what to do.  People who are tired of always being in control of everything.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you ever felt threatened during a session?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I personally haven’t.  I’m not going to say it wouldn’t be an issue in the industry because I am not sure if anyone else has experienced that.  I’ve worked at two other dungeons, the Den of Inequity when I first started Domming.  They relocated to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los%20Angeles,%20California">Los Angeles</ref>. I also started working at Pandora’s Box.  I didn’t really like it there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Any particular reason why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  It was just a feeling.  I decided to come here, and I’ve been here only a few months.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you noticed a difference here at Rebecca’s?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Oh yeah, no dungeon is the same.  No matter what dungeon you go to, from staff to the way they treat you to the type of dungeon they are.  Some dungeons go for that German hostile-looking place like you see in the horror movies, with black walls and chains everywhere.  Whereas here we tend to cater to people just coming into the fetish who are afraid of things like that because they get nervous if the first thing they see is Mistress in a hole in leather and a whip.  It’s like, “Ahh! She wants to hurt me and rip me apart,” or something like that.</p>
<head id="Advice_for_those_who_want_to_be_a_Mistress">Advice for those who want to be a Mistress</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [Laughs]  If you were to give advice to a woman who was looking at becoming a Mistress, what would you say?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I would say they should be open-minded and that they can’t be judgmental in this profession.</p>
<p>[<hi rend="italic">Veronica comes in to join the interview</hi>]
<hi rend="bold">DS:  We were talking about advice for young women looking to become Mistresses.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Someone with no experience with BDSM, or someone with some experience of the lifestyle?</p>
</text>
