<text id="autogum_interview_doc1167" title="part0_Lobby groups oppose plans for EU copyright extension" shortTile="partlobby-groups" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-18" dateModified="2014-12-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lobby_groups_oppose_plans_for_EU_copyright_extension" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Lobby groups oppose plans for EU copyright extension</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 26, 2008</hi></p>
<figure><caption>People from all over Europe came to the Electronic Frontier Foundation's party, which coincided with FOSDEM 2008.</caption></figure>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Commission">European Commission</ref> currently has proposals on the table to extend performers' <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Copyright">copyright</ref> terms. Described by Professor Martin Kretschmer as the "Beatles Extension Act", the proposed measure would extend copyright from 50 to 95 years after recording. A vast number of classical tracks are at stake; the copyright on recordings from the fifties and early sixties is nearing its expiration date, after which it would normally enter the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/public%20domain">public domain</ref> or become 'public property'. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/E.U.">E.U.</ref> Commissioner for the Internal Market and Services <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie%20McCreevy">Charlie McCreevy</ref> is proposing this extension, and if the other relevant Directorate Generales (Information Society, Consumers, Culture, Trade, Competition, etc.) agree with the proposal, it will be sent to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Parliament">European Parliament</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> contacted Erik Josefsson, European Affairs Coordinator for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Electronic_Frontier_Foundation">Electronic Frontier Foundation</ref> (E.F.F.), who invited us to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brussels">Brussels</ref>, the heart of E.U. policy making, to discuss this new proposal and its implications. Expecting an office interview, we arrived to discover that the event was a party and meetup conveniently coinciding with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FOSDEM">FOSDEM</ref> 2008 (the Free and Open source Software Developers' European Meeting). The meetup was in a sprawling city centre apartment festooned with E.F.F. flags and looked to be a party that would go on into the early hours of the morning with copious food and drink on tap. As more people showed up for the event it turned out that it was a truly international crowd, with guests from all over <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Europe">Europe</ref>.</p>
<p>Eddan Katz, the new International Affairs Director of the E.F.F., had come over from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> to connect to the European E.F.F. network, and he gladly took part in our interview. Eddan Katz explained that the Electronic Frontier Foundation is "A non-profit organisation working to protect civil liberties and freedoms online. The E.F.F. has fought for information privacy rights online, in relation to both the government and companies who, with insufficient transparency, collect, aggregate and make abuse of information about individuals." Another major focus of their advocacy is intellectual property, said Eddan: "The E.F.F. represents what would be the public interest, those parts of society that don't have a concentration of power, that the private interests do have in terms of lobbying."</p>
<p>Becky Hogge, Executive Director of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.K.">U.K.</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open%20Rights%20Group">Open Rights Group</ref> (O.R.G.), joined our discussion as well. "The goals of the Open Rights Group are very simple: we speak up whenever we see civil, consumer or human rights being affected by the poor implementation or the poor regulation of new technologies," Becky summarised. "In that sense, people call us -I mean the E.F.F. has been around, in internet years, since the beginning of time- but the Open Rights Group is often called the <hi rend="italic">British E.F.F.</hi>"</p>
</text>
