<text id="autogum_interview_doc320" title="part7_John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing" shortTile="partjohn-reed-orwell" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2015-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell%2C_God%2C_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Once you can envision it, the technology will follow, though.  Once you can start seeing it.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, there are sites that are sort of attempting it, and if you look right now, there are all these new multiplatform shows, that are beginning to do it.  And there won't be just networking capabilities in these shows; they'll be much different than the shows that we see today.  But on another level, they'll still be narrative shows.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  A very common thing for a writer is to be riddled with self-doubt, and that can often ruin a lot of inspiration and creativity and make you lose your way in what you're doing.  How do you handle a challenge like that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Unfortunately, I can't stop myself, whether I'm having self-doubt or not.  This new project of mine is a new play by William Shakespeare; I've taken lines from all the plays and put them together into a new play, essentially.  I liked the idea; I thought it was a cool concept.  But I didn't know if it was a publishable idea.  I didn't want to waste my time doing a non-publishable thing, but then I ended up doing it anyway.  And when I saw it, it was a complete surprise.</p>
<head id="On_changing_the_literary_canon">On changing the literary canon</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have a memory that has stuck with you that--where you continually turn back to it to learn new lessons?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I feel like I have a lot of memories that I turn back to all the time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is there one that stands out?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Right now, there's not.  Although there is a dream I had that's been sticking with me.  Memories that I'm inundated with right now have to do with my childhood, and remembering--actually, I have a picture of me standing on the West Side Highway when I was a little kid.  I was just a street urchin, and now my daughter smells like that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  She smells like a street urchin?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  She smells like a little kid who runs around in the park, you know?  Is a dream too off-base?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And that brings back a lot--the olfactory memories?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, yeah.  Is a dream too off-base?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  No, I'd love to hear your dream.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  So, I was standing in this field--I think it was a polo ground kind of thing.  And there were a lot of sort of petite bourgeoisie/intellectuals/professors--these sorts of people.  It was late afternoon after some kind of sporting event; I think it was polo.  I don't really know.  And everyone's standing around; it's the first cooling off of a hot day.  It didn't really have a time period.  Sort of recent distant past.</p>
</text>
