<text id="autogum_interview_doc1087" title="part8_Vanity Fair contributing editor Craig Unger on the Bush family feud, neoconservatives and the Christian right" shortTile="partvanity-fair-contributing" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2015-08-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vanity_Fair_contributing_editor_Craig_Unger_on_the_Bush_family_feud%2C_neoconservatives_and_the_Christian_right" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did they openly talk to you about these things?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Yes, this alliance is not a secret.  What I do in the book is reframe the entire paradigm.  Everyone talks about “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War%20against%20Islam">Islam vs. The West</ref>” and I say that no, it’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fundamentalism">fundamentalism</ref>—and by that I mean Christian and Jewish fundamentalism, not just Islamic—against the modern, post-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Enlightenment">Enlightenment</ref> world, and it happens that our government is on the wrong side.  We are carrying out a fundamentalist foreign policy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How did the neoconservatives and Christian right come together?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  They play very different roles.  The neocons are an ideological vanguard and the Christian right is a mass electoral base.  You have a couple hundred thousand pastors who can bring them together.  The role is the way the unions used to be for the Democratic Party, for example.  You had Netanyahu calling Jerry Falwell, which I told you about.  You also have people like Rabbi <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yechiel%20Eckstein">Yechiel Eckstein</ref> who formed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20International%20Fellowship%20of%20Christians%20and%20Jews">International Fellowship of Christians and Jews</ref>.  He has worked with a lot of the evangelicals.  It has been fostered by the Israeli right and the neocons.  I asked Michael Ledeen why he was on the 700 Club and he said, “It’s just we like to promote our views.”  People like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gary%20Bauer">Gary Bauer</ref> have participated in a lot of these policy discussions.  You have people like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom%20DeLay">Tom DeLay</ref> proclaiming himself as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian%20Zionist">Christian Zionist</ref> openly, or Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim%20Inhofe">Jim Inhofe</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oklahoma">Oklahoma</ref>.  They would say it’s not a political issue whether Israel should have this land, that it’s a biblical certainty.  This <hi rend="italic">has</hi> to happen.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It would seemingly take a lot of collusion between them.  How does it work?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  The Christian right are not policy-makers in general, though there is a Council for National Policy.  Falwell told me it’s an umbrella group overseeing all these evangelical groups.  It has four or five hundred members and I list some.  They are the big honchos of the Christian right, and within that is a smaller group called The Arlington Group, which has about fifty people.  They were in regular contact with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl%20Rove">Karl Rove</ref> on a regular basis.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Bush is convinced this is all God’s will?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  I go back to the Puritans for a reason because we are the new Zion and what we do is God’s will.  I have a very interesting quote by Rabbi Daniel Lapin, an Orthodox rabbi who met with Bush.  He says that Bush believes God has a mission for America and, “In that belief he is no different from the Founders who actually saw themselves replaying the Israelites crossing the Red Sea…”  When he speaks of the “Founders” he is not talking of Thomas Jefferson and Thomas Paine; he is talking about Cotton Mather and John Winthrop.  When you got to Liberty University you see the halls have portraits of the great Puritans as precursors of the evangelicals.   Yes, I believe that Bush thinks what he has done has been ordained by God.  He’s smart enough not to talk about it in those terms.</p>
</text>
