<text id="autogum_interview_doc1173" title="part6_Lobby groups oppose plans for EU copyright extension" shortTile="partlobby-groups" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-18" dateModified="2014-12-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lobby_groups_oppose_plans_for_EU_copyright_extension" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>The record industry submitted lots of evidence to the Gowers review of intellectual property, but public interests groups set in too. An international group called the Adelphi Charter wrote to Gowers, and they had been sponsored by the Royal Society of Arts, which is the society that promotes arts and culture in the U.K. They had come up with very convincing arguments why you should never extend the term of these exclusive rights retrospectively, much like the arguments that I've given you just now. They got submissions from the Open Rights Group which were sent in its infancy, but also from librarians, from educators, from public domain record labels, from the issue market, from people who needed a base of copyright-free public domain recorded sounds to achieve their creative goals, they got submissions from artists, ... they got submissions from a very wide spectrum of people.</p>
<p>In the end they got so many submissions that they said 'we can't do this by ourselves', and they went to a group of economists, and they said 'look, please, can you look at this for us?', because the Adelphi Charter says that the economic evidence really needs to be there before you make any retrospective change of term. So this group of economists came back and reported back to the Gowers review. They said there was a weak economic case for extending the term, that is that minorities would benefit from this, as we know the recording artists who are still popular 50 years later, the managers of those back catalogues. But there was a very strong economic case for not extending the term, and that was based on the money that was going to come out of consumers' pockets for these recordings, that was based on the costs to follow on innovators, people who remix content, the costs to archivists, ... the cost to culture as a whole. And this would negatively affect the balance of trade. And so this meant that the Gowers review of intellectual property documented that A) copyright term should not be extended, and B) copyright term should never be retrospectively extended, ever. And the U.K. government accepted this in full. And the Open Rights Group and all the other people who had submitted to this evidence were deeply, deeply satisfied with that result.</p>
<p>But we knew that it wasn't going to end there. The recording industry, when this announcement came out -in fact it was leaked a week before it came out- they made it very clear that they would take their fight to Europe anyway. They continued to get politicians on their side in the U.K., they lobbied the culture committee, it's been a history of quite hard lobbying. We knew it was going to happen. </p>
</text>
