<text id="autogum_interview_doc040" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Rocky De La Fuente, U.S. Democratic Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-03-29" dateModified="2016-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Rocky_De_La_Fuente%2C_U.S._Democratic_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Then, I sold 27 of my dealerships and began a new career investing in real estate. I developed the De La Fuente Business Park and began acquiring [...] other properties in San Diego, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San%20Diego%20County,%20California">San Diego County</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/San_Francisco">San Francisco</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Los_Angeles">Los Angeles</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa%20Monica,%20California">Santa Monica</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auburn,%20California">Auburn</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El%20Cajon,%20California">El Cajon</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hemet,%20California">Hemet</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La%20Mesa,%20California">La Mesa</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lemon%20Grove,%20California">Lemon Grove</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20City,%20California">National City</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanton,%20California">Stanton</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yorba%20Linda,%20California">Yorba Linda, California</ref> as well as in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cincinnati">Cincinnati</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ohio">Ohio</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cohoes,%20New%20York">Cohoes</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hartford,%20Connecticut">Hartford</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Connecticut">Connecticut</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West%20Palm%20Beach,%20Florida">West Palm Beach</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Florida">Florida</ref>. In addition, I purchased and own residential complexes in California, Connecticut, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Texas">Texas</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Virginia">Virginia</ref> and have developed assisted living facilities in Los Angeles (San Pedro) and Lemon Grove, California, to care for seniors who are in need.</p>
<p>In between, in an effort to help <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref> during the financial crisis that arose there in 1982, I opened 11 currency exchanges to facilitate free-flowing trade between Mexico and the United States. The network included seven offices in California and four in Texas. Then, over the next five years, I founded three U.S. banks; one being a National Bank approved by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office%20of%20the%20Comptroller%20of%20the%20Currency">OCC</ref> and two State Charter Banks approved by the California Banking Commission and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Deposit%20Insurance%20Corporation">FDIC</ref>.</p>
<p>Some of my efforts were recently recognized when I was awarded an Honorary Doctorate as an "International Corporate Ambassador" by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UNESCO">United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization</ref> (UNESCO).</p>
<p>If you think about that list for a minute, you'll have a pretty good perspective of how many people I've had the pleasure of working with and how many families I've been able to help over the years. And that remains my greatest business accomplishment.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">According to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20San%20Diego%20Union-Tribune">The San Diego Union-Tribune</ref></hi>, the FDIC banned you from banking for "unsafe and unsound banking practices."  Why did this occur and how do you respond to the allegation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">De La Fuente</hi>: Many of the consumer and commercial loan provisions provided by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Depository%20Institutions%20Deregulation%20and%20Monetary%20Control%20Act">Depository Institutions Deregulation and Monetary Control Act</ref> (DIDMCA) of 1980 were reversed by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Economic%20Recovery%20Tax%20Act%20of%201981">Economic Recovery Tax Act of 1981</ref>. Then, the FDIC aggressively brought charges against thousands of small banks and Savings &amp; Loans for practices that had previously been permissible.</p>
<p>The FDIC closed or otherwise resolved (i.e., punished management, etc.) 297 financial institutions. The Resolution Trust Corporation closed or otherwise resolved 747 more.</p>
<p>While I managed to save my bank, I was one of the causalities of the FDIC's "resolution" of the bank's issues. Personally accepting the FDIC's unilateral punishment protected the depositors' funds and allowed the bank to keep operating. You might have noticed in the article that you cited that the bank sold at a lower multiple because it hadn't fully leveraged its assets (i.e., it hadn't aggressively loaned its deposits as compared to other banks). In other words, it had been conservative in its investments.</p>
</text>
