<text id="autogum_interview_doc1030" title="part6_Blown for Good author discusses life inside international headquarters of Scientology" shortTile="partblown-good-author" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-11-12" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Blown_for_Good_author_discusses_life_inside_international_headquarters_of_Scientology" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<hi rend="bold">...they would restrict you to the property with a personal security guard assigned, put you on heavy manual labor, subject you to months or years of interrogation and ultimately declare you a suppressive person anyway...</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Marc Headley</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: When you are in that world, you are indoctrinated into believing that the worst thing you could do would be to get law enforcement involved. The Scientology organization has been doing this for years. Any stories about abuse, being held against one’s will or anything else that goes on there would be met with declarations and affidavits from a hundred people that nothing ever happened. And then after that, they would restrict you to the property with a personal security guard assigned, put you on heavy manual labor, subject you to months or years of interrogation and ultimately declare you a suppressive person anyway and throw you out on your ass.  Think <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WestWorld">WestWorld</ref></hi> meets <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nineteen%20Eighty-Four%20(film)">1984</ref></hi> meets <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Truman%20Show">The Truman Show</ref></hi>. </p>
<p>More practically, it is well known to staff on the property that Security has a police scanner in the main security booth. So they would be alerted to the situation before the police even showed up, and would rapidly concoct a diversion to ensure the staff member did not escape.</p>
<p>In the 15 years I was there, I knew and heard of hundreds of different ways staff attempted to escape. Not once did I hear of someone calling 911 and escaping. Most staff did not have open access to a phone. All base phones were for internal use only, and to call an external number you had to be patched through by the Receptionist, who would only do so if you had authorization.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Do you know if individuals are being held at Gold Base against their will? What do you think would happen if individuals at Gold Base who wanted to leave - simply asked to be allowed to do so?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: At one point in the book, this happened. People were asked if they wanted to leave, several people decided to take the offer. After lengthy interrogations and with lengthy legal documents signed with promises never to expose what occurred at the compound, they were allowed to leave with restrictions. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You describe your experience in the book of receiving Scientology auditing from Tom Cruise (p. 111-15). You note that after your auditing with Cruise had completed a few months later, you were "watched over" to make sure "out-tech" had not occurred that your auditor could have been responsible for. What is "out-tech", and what would have happened if this was recognized to have occurred?</hi></p>
<p>If I were to get into an accident of any kind, this would be investigated and all counseling records would be reviewed to determine if any processes or procedures were done incorrectly. This commonly occurs when scientologists become ill, get in a car accident or in the worst cases, die. “Out tech” is their reference to some considered violation of procedure, resulting in the person doing worse after counseling.</p>
</text>
