<text id="autogum_interview_doc968" title="part0_Interview: PRS, the UK's music royalty collection society" shortTile="partinterview-prs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-01-25" dateModified="2016-12-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview%3A_PRS%2C_the_UK%27s_music_royalty_collection_society" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Interview: PRS, the UK's music royalty collection society</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 26, 2010</hi></p>
<figure></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PRS%20for%20Music">PRS for Music</ref> is the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">UK's</ref> music royalty collection society tasked with working on behalf of copyright holders, specifically authors and music publishers.  Founded in 1914, the PRS is a non-profit organisation with 350,000 UK businesses holding PRS licenses.  The society works in conjunction with PPL which collects fees on behalf of the copyright holders of the actual recording.
So, if a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cover%20version">cover version</ref> of a song is played on UK radio, PRS collect a fee on behalf of the original writer and publisher, whilst PPL collect a fee on behalf of the record company of the cover.  In a recent Wikinews interview, Paul Campbell, founder of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazing%20Radio">Amazing Radio</ref>, an unsigned UK radio station, lambasted PRS for their "barmy standard contract" and their outdated equipment.  That interview can be found <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_Paul_Campbell,_founder_of_Amazing_Radio_UK">here</ref>.</p>
<hi rend="bold">The music industry is changing and the way we use music is continually changing</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—PRS</p>
<p>Wikinews reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tristan_Thomas">Tristan Thomas</ref> interviews PRS, following up on Campbell and others' criticism as well as finding out about future plans.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Firstly, thank you for the time in doing this interview</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Last year, you were involved in a high profile dispute with YouTube.  Can you briefly explain to our audience what that was all about and the final outcome of it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PRS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> PRS for Music was the first collecting society in the world to license the YouTube service, meaning if music videos were watched online then our members – who created them – would receive a small royalty payment.   When we went to renew the licence that YouTube held we couldn’t agree as to how much should be paid and exactly what should be covered within it.   We believed that music had become a much larger part of the YouTube service and that YouTube/Google should reflect the increased use of our members' creative talent in the amount they paid.    </p>
<p>The great thing is that we kept talking to YouTube throughout the dispute and managed to reach an agreement in September which meant that the videos could be accessed again by UK YouTube users and that our 65,000 songwriter, composer and music publisher members would be paid.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How many artists do you represent and how much did you collect during 2009 for them?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PRS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> We represent 65,000 songwriters, composers and music publishers.  We haven’t released our 2009 figures yet but in 2008 we collected over £600m for them.   The main sources of revenue come from recorded media (CDs, DVDs etc), international use, public performance use and use in television, radio and online. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Paul Campbell in a recent interview with us said the following:</hi>
<hi rend="italic">"PRS has a barmy standard contract for using their members' music online. It requires us to pay them a fixed percentage of ALL revenue from that website – whether or not the revenue is derived from their members' work. So if we had 100,000 songs from non-PRS artists on amazingtunes.com, and one song from a PRS artist, we'd have to pay them a percentage of the revenue from ALL 100,000 songs. I.e., we'd have to take money out of the pockets out of non-PRS artists to pay to PRS. That would be immoral."</hi>
How do you respond to that?</p>
</text>
