<text id="autogum_interview_doc1336" title="part1_An interview with Paul Campbell, founder of Amazing Radio UK" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-01-10" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_Paul_Campbell%2C_founder_of_Amazing_Radio_UK" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<figure></figure>
<p>Wise people noticed this.  A few years ago the Governance of the BBC was changed.  A new regulator, the BBC Trust, was created.  It tried to address the problem.  It insists the Corporation does a 'public value test' when it wants to launch a new service, or to expand an existing one.</p>
<p>Here, it hasn't.  Although the BBC has a longstanding commitment to play new music on its local radio stations, and one of its most famous DJs John Peel had an outstanding show on BBC Radio 1 for many years which played new music (and was, incidentally, produced by one of our new presenters), it's suddenly changed the game.  It’s launched a huge expansion and automation of this formerly piecemeal and limited activity, targeted exclusively at unsigned bands. BBC Introducing is a pan-BBC brand, combining local and network radio, television, online, even a special stage at Glastonbury.  There's a very expensive online upload service which I just know would have cost ten times what we had to spend on our similar service. There's a Head of Department, doubtless with dozens of staff.  I’ll bet they have BBC Introducing pens.  It's everywhere. </p>
<figure></figure>
<p>This is, by any reckoning, a ‘new service’.  But it’s not been subjected to a public value test.  Worse, I have it on very good authority from someone inside the BBC that BBC Worldwide - its commercial arm - is planning to launch a BBC Introducing record label – i.e., an overtly commercial expansion of BBC Introducing.  This would be like the BBC trying to create a new version of the music industry, all by itself.  </p>
<p>Whether or not you think it's a good thing for the beeb to champion new music, you may agree it should follow its own rules.  It hasn’t.  There was no Public Value Test; no request to the Trust to be allowed to do this. </p>
<p>So we complained.  It was a bit hilarious.  The Trust said they weren't allowed to investigate until we'd complained to the beeb itself and the BBC had rejected our complaint.  There was a long pause as I tried to understand the logic.  I said ‘I’m guessing the BBC didn’t do a PVT because it didn’t think it needed to do a PVT.  We think they should have done.  We’re asking you to investigate, to see if you agree’.  They said ‘you have to complain to them first.  It’s protocol’. It's all very British - i.e., charmingly polite … ludicrously bureaucratic … and totally useless.   </p>
<p>So we have another hoop to jump through. We're now preparing our formal complaint to the BBC itself - whose Director General is someone I used to work with, when we were both fresh-faced BBC trainees in 1981.  It takes time: I’ll have to write it myself, and I have a business to run.  The beeb will have a small army of staff whose only job is to read it … and reject it.  (They always reject criticism; it's the BBC's default position.  They usually do it with a slightly pained expression, hurt that anyone could fail to understand their brilliance and omniscience.  Either that, or they try to demolish your intellect and cast doubt on your probity.  Either way, they'll reject it).  </p>
</text>
