<text id="autogum_interview_doc1392" title="part15_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Some are in my organization.  You’ve got Tamika Mallory, who heads the Decency Initiative here in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref>.  You’ve got Mark Coleman in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlanta">Atlanta</ref>.  You have Jerry Moffet in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Phoenix,_Arizona">Phoenix</ref>.  I could name you fifteen to twenty in various degrees who have a lot of potential.  Who will become national?  I have no idea.  I tend to work with all of them.  We have thirty-three chapters, offices in seven cities, and 90% of them are under forty years old.  Most of the people who marched with us in Jena and Washington were under forty years old.  There’s a resurgence of activism among young people, and I think a lot of it is they went through this era of blacks making it as CEOs and blacks making it in management, and now that era is over.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard%20Parsons">Richard Parsons</ref> is gone soon; Obama is not dominating the black vote.  So a lot of these people are saying that it’s not happening.  They are going back to that we have to struggle as a unit.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  At Thanksgiving my brother-in-law’s brother made the point that we in white America don’t remember history, and that when we come across people who <hi rend="italic">do</hi> remember history and we are always shocked.  “Why don’t you get over it and move on?”  But that doesn’t take into account that there is a long history of racial problems that have set people behind in the race by half a mile, and suddenly it’s supposed to be, “You’re equal, it’s a fair race now.”</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  “Get over it!”  Yeah.  People are set back half a mile because they were given a disadvantage, not because they fell a half a mile.  Then you tell us to "catch up" and forget that the race was unfair in the beginning.  You’re right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  One sees this problem with history with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian%20Zionism">Christian Zionists</ref> in the right wing.  They have an entirely different perspective on history.  They don’t view <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas%20Jefferson">Thomas Jefferson</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20Washington">George Washington</ref>—who were secular—as our founding fathers.  When they talk about America’s founding fathers they mean <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cotton%20Mather">Cotton Mather</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puritan">Puritans</ref>.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  I think you have to be determined to not allow people to dismiss history.  You have to use every forum to put history into perspective.  People have a reason they want you to forget history, because history does not back up their point.  One of the things <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin%20Luther%20King%20III">Martin Luther King III</ref> and I talked about is that his father died one of the most controversial figures in the history of America, but you would think now forty years later he was revered by white America.  He wasn’t!  The New York Times would write editorials about him telling him to keep his nose out of the Vietnam business.  “Who do you think you are?”  When he died—that’s when I joined the movement—we had to fight to get him a national holiday.  But today you read stories that guys like us aren’t Dr. King.  Well, in Dr. King’s time they didn’t have <hi rend="italic">him</hi> as Dr. King, but that’s the benefit of distorting history.  If you can erase history, erase why there are racial gaps across the board—health care, education, income—if you can erase how that all started, then you can make guys like me look extreme.  But if you look at history and how we got here, we’re really very reasonable to say some of the things we have said.</p>
</text>
