<text id="autogum_interview_doc1223" title="part6_The Onion: An interview with 'America's Finest News Source'" shortTile="partthe-onion-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2013-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Onion%3A_An_interview_with_%27America%27s_Finest_News_Source%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">The Onion's</hi> satirical story about children turning to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satanism">Satanism</ref> after reading <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harry%20Potter">Harry Potter</ref> books was forwarded around the Internet by some Christians as a real story.Image source: The Onion.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  “Congress threatens to leave DC unless new capitol is built” was run verbatim by a Chinese news agency.  With the picture and everything, literally with our illustration.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you do anything about that or do you think it’s just hysterical?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  We’re happy to have our content syndicated by real newspapers in that manner.  I want to say it was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beijing%20Evening%20News">a newspaper in Beijing</ref>.  Somebody pointed it out to them and their response was not to print a correction, but just to say that some newspapers in America make money by printing lies.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is there any one group that does not like <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi>?  Evangelicals?  Gays?   Any particular subculture?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  I think we’re equal-opportunity offenders.  We aren’t going to target one group because we don’t want people picketing outside the office.  We target everyone.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you ever receive hate mail?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  Every now and then.  We’re generally not bombarded by it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is generally the theme of those letters?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  Do you know what I think it is?   It’s whatever affects <hi rend="italic">that</hi> person.  So it’s like, “I love it when you make a joke about murder or rape, but if you talk about cancer, well my brother has <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cancer">cancer</ref> and that’s not funny to me.”  Or someone else can say, “Cancer’s <hi rend="italic">hilarious</hi>, but don’t talk about rape because my cousin got raped.”  I’m using extreme examples, but whatever it is, if it affects somebody personally they tend to be more sensitive about it.  But because we are equal opportunity, we can’t <hi rend="italic">stop</hi> doing that.  The best is we wrote a story—did you ever see the Police Academy when the officer gets thrown off his motorcycle after he brakes really hard and his head goes up a horse’s ass, and he died?  We wrote an Op-Ed about that scene that was, “That’s not funny, my brother died that way.”  That was sort of speaking to how people are offended by things that touch them personally somehow.
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  Almost every piece of hate mail starts with the line, “Usually I love The Onion, <hi rend="italic">but</hi> this time you’ve gone too far…”  We responded to that with, “Normally I love your pornographic website, but this time you’ve gone too far…”  Someone will <hi rend="italic">always</hi> be offended by something.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you get any reaction from public figures and politicians?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  They are always in the public sphere so they are usually used to worse things being written about them all the time.  
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  We get a lot of <hi rend="italic">positive</hi> feedback from politicians who seem to get and enjoy the comedy.  In some ways, if they show up in The Onion it’s kind of a badge of honor.  We had a meeting with Al Gore maybe about a year ago or so, and he was reeling off his favorite Onion headlines that were written about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al%20Gore">Al Gore</ref>.  I think his favorite was, after he lost the election we wrote a story about how Al and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tipper%20Gore">Tipper Gore</ref> were having the best sex of their lives.  He referenced it and he said he gets all the headlines sent from people.</p></p>
</text>
