<text id="autogum_interview_doc1140" title="part2_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Russ Aegard, Thunder Bay-Atikokan" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-24" dateModified="2007-11-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_candidate_Russ_Aegard%2C_Thunder_Bay-Atikokan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>We need to have a fair and representative parliament.  Not a false majority where 10% of the population can actually vote in 100% of our MPPs.  This is not a typo.  It is improbably, but possible.  The fact that it is possible that 10% of Ontarians could conceivably be pushing their agenda through easily is a travesty of justice.  So many groups are not represented in Parliament, especially Aboriginal groups.  The Green Party is polling at 10% currently.  Therefore, about 800000 people will not have their voice heard in Parliament.  The Liberals and Conservatives do not want this to pass.  It would severely disrupt the power base that they have enjoyed for the last 150 years.  This is the reason for the corruptness and antagonistic policies that we have seen over the last 13 years or so.  Canada, the U.S. and England are the last developed countries to maintain this unfair system of voting, and understandably so.  They do not want the people to have the power in their countries.  They want the power to be maintained by the affluent citizens.  It's time for a change;  it's time for every Ontarian to be heard, whether it is someone who is living in the suburbs of Toronto or living on the streets of Ottawa.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does "new media" play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>Honestly, not much.  As a full time teacher, I have not had the time to engage in a lot of the campaigning strategies of my peers.  I really can't answer if it's beneficial or a challenge.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</hi></p>
<p>I think that the investments that they have made at our local hospital has been the most beneficial.  For the province, instituting a rebate for the purchase of fuel-efficient cars was a tiny step in the right direction.</p>
<p>The least beneficial to this riding was the millions of dollars they provided to corporations that have control of the forestry industry.  We need to get control of the industry put back into local interests.  Local ownership encourages better forest stewardship and economic practices as they have a long-term vested interest in making sure that they have a sustainable business for many many years.</p>
<p>To the province as a whole, the decision to give themselves a 40000 dollar a year raise was the biggest slap in our collective faces.  I was physically ill when I heard of this decision.  So many people are struggling in our province, yet they decide to make themselves richer.  Their argument that you need to attract good people for the job does not hold any water.  I am happily willing to serve my government for any price.  I am a good person and am responsible and hard-working.  I must commend Howard Hampton on donating his 40000 dollars back to charity.  I'm not sure if he is going to continue to do that, but his effort this year does not go unnoticed.  Again, this is the arrogance of our current system.  I'm not sure how they can justify to anyone that they are worth twice, three times, even as high as ten times more than the full-time workers of this province.  I am responsible for the instruction and guiding of 25+ young minds every year, yet make half as much as someone who behaves like a child in parliament.  I guess when you're out of touch with reality, you make decisions such as those.</p>
</text>
