<text id="autogum_interview_doc1209" title="part0_CanadaVOTES: NDP candidate Don Davies running in Vancouver Kingsway" shortTile="partcanadavotes-ndp" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-25" dateModified="2008-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_NDP_candidate_Don_Davies_running_in_Vancouver_Kingsway" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>CanadaVOTES: NDP candidate Don Davies running in Vancouver Kingsway</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 26, 2008</hi></p>
<p>On October 14, 2008, Canadians will be heading to the polls for the federal election. <hi rend="bold">New Democratic Party candidate Don Davies</hi> is standing for election in <hi rend="bold">the riding of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vancouver%20Kingsway">Vancouver Kingsway</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>A lawyer, he has spent the last 25 years fighting for human rights. A two-time student government representative, Davies was involved in the anti-apartheid, third world and peace movements. Admitted to the Alberta Bar in 1989, Davies and family moved to Vancouver in 1991, where he became the Director of Legal Resources for Teamsters Canada (Local 31), the next year. He is a long-time volunteer for children's charity Variety, is Chair of the Parent Advisory Council at Mount Pleasant school, and a Director of the Meridian Cultural Society, among other things.</p>
<p>Wikinews contacted Don Davies, to talk about the issues facing Canadians, and what they and their party would do to address them. Wikinews is in the process of contacting every candidate, in every riding across the country, no matter their political stripe. All interviews are conducted over e-mail, and interviews are published unedited, allowing candidates to impart their full message to our readers, uninterrupted.</p>
<p>The riding is vacant, after Conservative Minister of International Trade David Emerson's resignation. Emerson was elected in 2004 as a Liberal, serving as the Minister of Industry. Two weeks after re-election in 2006, he crossed the floor to join then-new Prime Minister Stephen Harper, who had won a minority government. Emerson was the first MP in Canadian history to cross the floor before a new government was sworn in. He has stepped down, after pressure from other parties.</p>
<p>Besides Davies, major party candidates include Liberal Wendy Yuan, Conservative Salomon Rayek, and Green Doug Warkentin. Also putting their hat in the ring are Matt Kadioglu (Libertarian), Kimball Cariou (Communist), and Donna Peterson (Marxist-Leninist).</p>
<p>For more information, visit the campaign's official website, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#External_links">listed below</ref>.</p>
<p>This Saturday at 11 am, Davies will host NDP leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%20Layton">Jack Layton</ref> in the Commodore Ballroom at "rally4change".</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why are you running for political office, why at the federal level, why this party, and why in this riding?</hi></p>
<p>I'm running for office as I believe that I have the necessary commitment to my community and country, that I have the integrity to remain true to the ideals and values that I believe in and am presenting to the constituents, and the proven ability to work hard and effectively for what is right.</p>
<p>I'm running at the federal level, as these are the issues that most interest me, and where I have acquired the most experience from my professional career as a lawyer. I also believe that the federal government plays a critical role in making our community stronger.</p>
</text>
