<text id="autogum_interview_doc978" title="part3_Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian presidential candidate Wayne Allyn Root" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-03" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Libertarian_presidential_candidate_Wayne_Allyn_Root" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>I happen to not smoke, drink or do drugs of any kind- EVER. That's my choice of lifestyle. On the other hand, I love to gamble. I'm a risk taker- whether it's betting on a business idea, a stock, a million dollar real estate investment, or the Dallas Cowboys. That's my chosen form of entertainment. It's none of your business- and it's certainly none of the government's damn business. I would never try to force my choice of lifestyle or my definition of morality upon anyone else. Today's GOP disagrees. They are a big government party playing Big Brother. They spend their time like the busybody old lady peeking out the window to spy on her neighbors. Today's GOP wants to define morality, legislate it and throw people in jail who disagree. I find this disgusting and offensive. It's just plain wrong. It's anything but conservative. It's the Nanny State. I want to lead the battle to stop it- forever. What Americans do in their homes, in their bedrooms, on their computers, watch on their TV sets is none of the government's damn business. The job of government is to protect us from others, NOT to protect us from ourselves. And the job of government is certainly not to criminalize moral behavior. That's why our ancestors left England and fought a revolution. We didn't want the King of England telling us what to do, what religion to worship, or to tax us heavily without representation. But all of that is happening today. It's our own government taxing us to death, wiretapping our phone calls and emails without warrants, and putting Americans in jail for minor offenses, choices of morality and victimless crimes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">There are thousands reading this right now, many of which may not have decided who they are going to vote for. What could you say to encourage them to give you their vote?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mr. Root:</hi> Barack Obama (my college classmate Columbia University Class of '83) talks nonstop about change. So do Hillary and McCain.  None of them are agents of change. They are longtime politicians (and lawyers). They are the problem- not the solution. Barack was just named as the single most liberal member of the entire U.S. Senate. That's based on facts- his voting record. Is that the change we want? That's not change- that's the same old “soak the rich,” “redistribute the wealth,” “spend like a drunken sailor,” and “spend trillions on a failing war on poverty” philosophy of big government, out-of-touch, bleeding heart liberals like Ted Kennedy, George McGovern, Walter Mondale and Michael Dukakis. Is this what America calls change?  While China and Russia turn unabashedly capitalistic, do we want to move towards Socialism?</p>
</text>
