<text id="autogum_interview_doc287" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Steve Kissing, independent candidate for US President" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-16" dateModified="2014-04-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Steve_Kissing%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Through my profession, I have come to appreciate that <hi rend="italic">how</hi> things are communicated is just as important as what is being communicated. Sometimes the words we choose or the method we select to share an idea gets in the way of people appreciating it and embracing it. Why is this important? Because a President who is attentive to not only what he is saying, but how he is saying it, is apt to be more effective at rallying people to a common cause.</p>
<p>My work in advertising, for which I have won many awards, has demanded that I generate creative solutions, and help inspire them in others, virtually every single day. I know how to "think outside the box." Why is this important? We all know that our country and world face major challenges, to put it mildly. Our only hope in overcoming these challenges is our ability to generate innovative solutions.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Identify the three most important issues, what would they be? How will you address these issues?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Global warming.</hi> I endorse tax incentives and government grant programs to support and reward those private-sector initiatives aimed at developing renewable energy sources, or improving the efficiency of traditional, carbon-based energy sources.</p>
<p>In addition, I have proposed that NASA be “repurposed” for two to three decades to help fight global warming. What I envision is asking the very bright scientists and engineers at NASA to direct their gaze down at Earth rather than up in the stars. This way, we can tap into their collective brainpower to help develop new technologies to improve energy efficiency and to slow global warming.</p>
<p>I have long been a fan of NASA and space travel, and I understand and appreciate the many benefits of space exploration. But the need is so great to slow, and eventually halt, global warming, that drastic measures are required.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">National Security.</hi> As President, I would keep a healthy military and intelligence budget, all along making sure that we are training and caring for our soldiers as they prepare and wait for duty, as they are assigned and as they return and adjust to civilian life. Our record on this hasn’t been pretty of late. I would also raise the pay of all military personnel. Finally, I would make sure that we have the best-equipped fighting force in the world.</p>
<p>I would work quickly to secure our borders by putting additional measures in place: monitored fencing; more border crossing guards; small, mobile groups of elite soldiers to “spot check” our borders; more resources for the Coast Guard to protect our shores; and more human and technical resources to monitor those who come to play or work in our country.</p>
<p>We need to talk more with other nations, especially those we consider enemies or those that are particularly influential in world affairs. As such, I will invest in a more robust diplomatic core, particularly with China and the Middle East.</p>
</text>
