<text id="autogum_interview_doc1281" title="part6_Edmund White on writing, incest, life and Larry Kramer" shortTile="partedmund-white" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-08" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edmund_White_on_writing%2C_incest%2C_life_and_Larry_Kramer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I don’t know; I wasn’t really raised by my father.  I lived apart from him and I would spend every summer with him, but not see him much during the year.  My parents were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/divorce">divorced</ref> from my age of seven on.  I think the incest taboo sets in and turns somebody off sexually with somebody they know very well and lives with.  I think with my father he was somebody who every eye in the family was focused on and he was a sort of a tyrant and nice-looking, the source of all power, money, happiness, and he was implacable and difficult.  He was always spoken of in sexual terms, in the sense he left our mother for a much younger woman who was very sexy but had nothing else going for her.  He was a famous womanizer.  And he slept with my sister!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What you describe is power; are you still attracted to power?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  No.  I mean, my idea of power, but not everybody’s idea of power.  In other words, I wouldn’t want to go to bed with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">Bush</ref>…</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Would you let him blow you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why not?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I find him repulsive.  I wouldn’t even let a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20Party">Republican</ref> blow me.  That does cut down on a number of people I <hi rend="italic">guess</hi>—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What did your father’s incestuous relationship with your sister do to you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I was envious of my sister.  I wished I had that kind of access to him.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you try?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And he spurned you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  No, it was so subtle he probably didn’t even know I was longing for him because, I mean, we’re talking about the 1950’s in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cincinnati,%20Ohio">Cincinnati, Ohio</ref>, or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Texas">Texas</ref>.  He didn’t know I was gay until later and he would tell me he had just fired a man because he thought he might be gay, or at least he wasn’t married and he wore a ring.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How would you respond?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  You couldn’t say anything.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did he ever know?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  About me?  Yes.  Fairly early on, when I was about 15.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What was his reaction?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  He was horrified, because he thought it was my mother’s bad influence because I had led an overly sophisticated life with her.  He thought I should lead a simpler life and put in hours and hours of yard work and that would make me straight.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Your mother was attracted to you, right?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Or anybody that was around, I think?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] The old doorknob adage? [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] Yeah. [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think that played a role in your being gay?</hi></p>
</text>
