<text id="autogum_interview_doc1201" title="part13_BDSM as business: An interview with the owners of a dungeon" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_An_interview_with_the_owners_of_a_dungeon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<head id="Is_an_S&amp;M_dungeon_dangerous?">Is an S&amp;M dungeon dangerous?</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If you introduce the girls and you don't know what the clients want, how do you know that it's going to be a safe situation for one of your employees?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Because everybody's filmed as they come in. Have you ever been to a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Topless%20bar">topless bar</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  No.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  You've never been to a topless bar?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Never been to a topless bar.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  No kidding!  Well, if you did, they're probably the safest environment around.  Let's assume you came here, and you have a wife at home or a girlfriend or a family, would you want to get into trouble here?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What if they don't?   What if they're just a mental case?  What if they're a wild card?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  In our dozen years plus, we've never had one.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You've never had one problem</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  No, no, no, we've not had problems--and any problems--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Can you give me an example of a problem that you've had and how you handled it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Yeah, a guy that wants his money back, doesn't like the girl.  Doesn't happen often.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What happens when that's the case?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  We'll give him his money back.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And you've never had a dangerous situation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Have we ever had a dangerous situation here?</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  What do you mean by dangerous?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Instead of dangerous, let's say threatening, where there was concern for either your safety or--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  I want to answer that question by asking you a question.  Do you have a preconceived notion that there could be more danger in this business than let's say, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taco%20Bell">Taco Bell</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I would say that the nature of the desire between eating and the desire for some sort of sexual pleasure, gratification, that there's always more of a chance for a threatening situation.  Someone who wants to go for a taco versus someone who wants to go for a BDSM session--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  So, if I told you--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I would say that my notion would be yes, I would think that there is more of a likelihood of a threatening situation.  Now, if you're talking about a Taco Bell in the middle of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South%20Bronx">South Bronx</ref>, versus this place, I would say they're probably equal in danger.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Taco Bell down the block?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  A Taco Bell on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Park%20Avenue">Park Avenue</ref> versus here, I would say that there's more likelihood of a threatening situation occurring in a place like this than in a Taco Bell on Park Avenue.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  If you look at the holdups, and you look at the robberies at Taco Bells, you take it in the metropolitan area and compare it to us, we've had far fewer problems.  Never had a holdup, never had a--Anybody ever have a gun or anything like that or a knife?</p>
</text>
