<text id="autogum_interview_doc676" title="part19_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is that who you were reading at that age?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  When I became more mature, if that's the word, it was about my senior year, going to college, 17, 18, 19 years of age, I fell under the sway of the classic writers who were the generation or two before my own. Namely, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/F.%20Scott%20Fitzgerald">Fitzgerald</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernest%20Hemingway">Hemingway</ref>, and to a lesser degree Faulkner. I went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alabama%20College">Alabama College</ref>, as you know. I assume you know. And so <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20S.%20Faulkner">Faulkner</ref> was a name I reckoned with. And then, while I was still in college in my third year there, fourth year there, I started reading The New Yorker and reading the great stories of John O'Hara and Irwin Shaw and others ... <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Cheever">John Cheever</ref>. All those stories and all those writers I mentioned give detail. They are really descriptive writers, scenic writers, writers of city life whether it's Fitzgerald invoking the sense of St. Paul, Minnesota or <hi rend="italic">Coming To Princeton</hi>, his novel, or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irwin%20Shaw">Irwin Shaw</ref> walking through the streets of the city of New York or O'Hara getting into New York with a chip on his shoulder from Pennsylvania or later on their literary inheritors, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Updike">John Updike</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20Styron">William Styron</ref>, those other people closer to my generation. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip%20Roth">Philip Roth</ref> is my favorite writer. They all gave a sense of reality. Roth gives a real sense of history. I've read every novel he's written.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I've read <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Plot%20Against%20America">The Plot Against America</ref></hi>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Yeah, well that's a distorted sense of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wendell%20Wilke">Wilke</ref> campaign. But you really get a sense of time and place with Roth, including his latest novel. All of his novels, every one of them. And I've never been tempted, with one exception, to write fiction. One exception being I did write a short story in 1965 and got it published and I was never interested in writing again because I thought reality is so remarkable. All you have to do is spend the time, take the time, and you're going to find things that are hardly believable that are real. At least real to the degree that you say, this is as verifiable as it gets. I'm not saying it's the truth, the full truth, the half truth, but this is at least something that did indeed happen, at least in the minds of those to whom it happened. And you are a chronicler of their reality. And you can write stories without changing names and altering the facts. And they sound as if they are concocted, imagined works of fiction, but they're not. They're not works of fiction. But my reading was fiction and remains fiction. I don't read much non-fiction unless I have to. If I want to write about China then I'm going to read biographies of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mao%20Tse-Tsung">Mao</ref>. Or if I want to write about <hi rend="italic">Unto The Sons</hi>, which is my book about my ancestry in Italy, I have to read all these book about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naples,%20Italy">Naples</ref> or 20th Century <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mafia">Mafia</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palermo,%20Sicily">Palermo</ref> or the English writers who were the great travel writers of the 19th century.</p>
</text>
