<text id="autogum_interview_doc1013" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Jon Greenspon, independent candidate for US President" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-03-01" dateModified="2019-08-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jon_Greenspon%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Wikinews interviews Jon Greenspon, independent candidate for US President</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 1, 2008</hi></p>
<p>While nearly all coverage of the 2008 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> Presidential election has focused on the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democratic</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</ref> candidates, the race for the White House also includes independents and third party candidates. These parties represent a variety of views that may not be acknowledged by the major party platforms.</p>
<p>Wikinews has impartially reached out to these candidates, throughout the campaign. We now interview independent Presidential candidate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jon%20Greenspon">Jon Greenspon</ref>, a veteran and small business executive.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why do you want to be President?</hi></p>
<p>In all honesty, it's about principles. The United States was founded on the principles of a government FOR the people, BY the people, and OF the people. For the last couple of decades, however, it become more and more the government for the corporations, by the hidden agenda, and of the special interest. This needs to stop, and the citizens need to regain control of their house. I am running, not to make a grandiose statement or to become another American potentate, but so that the American people have a government under their control and auspices.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Have you ever run for political office before? Have you ever been a member of a political party? Have you ever campaigned for another political candidate?</hi></p>
<p>Nope. I’ve never run for public office before. During the 1980s, when there was a functioning conservative Republican party, I was a member of the Republicans. I’ve never campaigned for another person before.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What is your current job? What skills or ideas do you bring from this position, or previous positions, that will benefit the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oval%20Office">Oval Office</ref>?</hi></p>
<p>I am a small business executive, and a veteran of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US%20Military">US Military</ref>. Unlike our present Democratic candidates, I HAVE worn and walked in the shoes of the grunt in the field; so I have a decidedly marked advantage in that I know what these people fear and respect. I also have the understanding of how to work within a budget, and can effectively deal with problems within an organization.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Obviously, the next American President and his or her administration will face many diverse issues. But if you were to narrow identify the three most important issues, what would they be? How will you address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>I think three of the most important issues that really face the next President aren’t <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/universal%20healthcare">Universal Healthcare</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/LGBT">Gender issues</ref>. We need to focus on core American issues: National Security, the Economy, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Congress">Congressional</ref> control.</p>
<p>On National Security, America is a sovereign nation and needs to treat itself as one. While globalization is grabbing a foothold around the world, America is loosing its own identity in the mix. We need to deal with this problem in its basest forms. First, we need to bring illegal <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Immigration">immigration</ref>, foreign worker visas and outsourcing of our jobs to a halt. I applaud <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Arizona">Arizona</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Oklahoma">Oklahoma</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Georgia_(US_state)">Georgia</ref> in their efforts to stem the illegal worker situations in their states, and would enjoy seeing other states follow suit. Second, we need to bring a fast stop to the loss of American jobs to corporate greed and the use of semi-skilled, cheap imported labor through a failed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/visa%20policy%20of%20the%20United%20States#H_visa">H</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/visa%20policy%20of%20the%20United%20States#L_visa">L</ref> series visa program. I'm not saying to abandon it, but it needs to be reviewed and regulations placed making it more important to bring American workers onboard, rather then give free rides to every other countries citizens. Lastly, America needs to look at itself and be more commanding of a made in America, supported by American labor approach to work. Let's get some of the 2+ million jobs we sent overseas in the last ten years back here.</p>
</text>
