<text id="autogum_interview_doc1407" title="part1_John Vanderslice plays New York City: Wikinews interview" shortTile="partjohn-vanderslice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-27" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Vanderslice_plays_New_York_City%3A_Wikinews_interview" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You said seventh and eighth grade.  Were you always listening to people like Bowie or bands like the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Velvet%20Underground">Velvets</ref>, or did you have an Eddie Murphy <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Party%20All%20The%20Time">My Girl Wants to Party All the Time</ref></hi> phase?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  The thing for me that was the uncool music, I had an older brother who was really into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressive%20rock">prog music</ref>, so it was like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gentle%20Giant">Gentle Giant</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yes%20(band)">Yes</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King%20Crimson">King Crimson</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genesis%20(band)">Genesis</ref>.  All the new Genesis that was happening at the time was mind-blowing.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phil%20Collins">Phil Collins</ref>'s solo record...we had every single solo record, like the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike%20Rutherford">Mike Rutherford</ref> solo record.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you shun that music now or is it still a part of you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  Oh no, I appreciate all music.  I'm an anti-snob.  Last night when I was going to sleep I was watching <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ocean's%20Thirteen">Ocean's Thirteen</ref></hi> on my computer.  It's not like I always need to watch some super-fragmented, fucked-up art movie like <hi rend="italic">Inland Empire</hi>.  It's part of how I relate to the audience.  We end every night by going out into the audience and playing acoustically, directly, right in front of the audience, six inches away—that is part of my philosophy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think New York or San Francisco suffers from artistic elitism more?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  I think because of the Internet that there is less and less elitism; everyone is into some little superstar on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref> and everyone can now appreciate now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justin%20Timberlake">Justin Timberlake</ref>.  There is no need for factions.  There is too much information, and I think the idea has broken down that some people...I mean, when was the last time you met someone who was into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ska">ska</ref>, or into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/punk%20rock">punk</ref>, and they dressed the part?  I don't meet those people anymore.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Everything is fusion now, like cuisine.  It's hard to find a purely French or purely Vietnamese restaurant.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  Exactly!  When I was in high school there were factions.  I remember the guys who listened to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black%20Flag">Black Flag</ref>.  They looked the part!  Like they were in theater.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You still find some <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emo">emos</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  Yes, I believe it.  But even emo kids, compared to their older brethren, are so open-minded.  I opened up for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sunny%20Day%20Real%20Estate">Sunny Day Real Estate</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedro%20the%20Lion">Pedro the Lion</ref>, and I did not find their fans to be the cliquish people that I feared, because I was never playing or marketed in the emo genre.  I would say it's because of the Internet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You could clearly create music that is more mainstream pop and be successful with it, but you choose a lot of very personal and political themes for your music.  Are you ever tempted to put out a studio album geared toward the charts just to make some cash?</hi></p>
</text>
