<text id="autogum_interview_doc940" title="part0_CanadaVOTES: Liberal incumbent Susan Kadis running in Thornhill" shortTile="partcanadavotes-liberal" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-26" dateModified="2019-07-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_Liberal_incumbent_Susan_Kadis_running_in_Thornhill" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>CanadaVOTES: Liberal incumbent Susan Kadis running in Thornhill</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 27, 2008</hi></p>
<p>On October 14, 2008, Canadians will be heading to the polls for the federal election. <hi rend="bold">Liberal candidate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Susan%20Kadis">Susan Kadis</ref></hi> is standing for re-election in <hi rend="bold">the riding of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thornhill%20(electoral%20district)">Thornhill</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>During the recently disbanded session of Parliament, Mrs. Kadis was the Official Opposition Critic for National Revenue. She served as a member of the Caucus Committee on Economic Prosperity and a member of the Standing Committee on Health. She was elected as Chair of the Greater Toronto Area (GTA) Liberal Caucus. The former publisher of <hi rend="italic">The Thornhill Times</hi> community newspaper, she has served as a school trustee and City Councillor. She has served on the Canadian Breast Cancer Foundation's Board of Directors, being a survivor herself.</p>
<p>Wikinews contacted Susan, to talk about the issues facing Canadians, and what they and their party would do to address them. Wikinews is in the process of contacting every candidate, in every riding across the country, no matter their political stripe. All interviews are conducted over e-mail, and interviews are published unedited, allowing candidates to impart their full message to our readers, uninterrupted.</p>
<p>The incumbent in the riding, Kadis faces three challengers: former broadcaster Peter Kent (Conservative), Norbert Koehl (Green), and Simon Strelchik (NDP). The riding of Thornhill includes the part of the City of Vaughan that is east of Highway 400 and south of Rutherford Road, and the part of the Town of Markham west of Highway 404. The previous MP in the riding was also Liberal, Elinor Caplan, who was the Canadian Minister of Citizenship and Immigration and later Minister of National Revenue.</p>
<p>For more information, visit the campaign's official website, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#External_links">listed below</ref>.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why did you choose to run for office?</hi></p>
<p>As a life-long grassroots community leader, I entered politics to make a difference and improve the lives of others. I am a person of integrity and accountability, and I stand for giving a voice to the issues our community cares deeply about. Thornhill residents know they can rely on me to stand up, speak out, not sit idly by, and get results as proven by my record of service.</p>
<p>I continue to be very dedicated to the ensure that Thornhill residents continue to thrive and prosper.  Theres a lot at stake in this election. We have a great action plan that will secure our future.</p>
<p>I will fight to ensure that we have a strong economy, cleaner environment, which will result in a prosperous and sustainable Thornhill and Canada.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are you satisfied with your time as MP?</hi></p>
<p>Over the last four years Ive and had the privilege to help thousands of residents in Thornhill. Knowing the positive impact I have</p>
<p>made, I am eager to continue to do more. Our community continues to inspire me to improve the lives of Thornhill residents and all Canadians.</p>
</text>
