<text id="autogum_interview_doc765" title="part3_Canada&amp;apos;s Parkdale—High Park (Ward 13) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-parkdalehigh" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Parkdale%E2%80%94High_Park_%28Ward_13%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi>  Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Enough is enough. Our current Councillor seems invisible until election time. I have seen our ward decline in recent years with graffiti, reduced TTC service, ineffective traffic calming measures and inappropriate development. I've read the platforms of the other candidates, and they are just typical things politicians always say with no actual ideas to back them up. I want honesty in government. I believe in transparency. I believe in backing up every statement with a plan. Most of all, I don't see any vision in the other candidates platforms. For example, from Greg Hamara's web site we see under the heading " Building Safe and healthy neighbourhoods" that his big plan is "Better enforcement of traffic rules". Oh yes, very inspiring plan. That just gives me goose bumps. Compare that to my idea of Raised Bicycle Lanes as found in Amsterdam, eliminating graffiti as has been done by the New York subway system. The other candidates do not place the constituent first. Want proof? Check their websites and you'll see that I am the only one that actually lists and links to the websites of my competitors because I want to HELP constituents make the best choice.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Although I have worked in Austin, Texas, San Francisco and other cities, I have lived in Parkdale – High Park for over 35 years and I consider it home. I have seen how great the area once was and how great it could be and I am inspired to make it a truly great place to live again.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> As a freelance journalist I write about issues that concern the community on many levels. I volunteer my time to charity and support local businesses. I have lived in the ward for over 35 years and participate in its activities. I attend the Arts festival and Ukrainian Festival because not for photo ops as some of the other candidates treat the events, but for the experience itself. I do not join a group to just pad my resume or add as a bullet point on campaign literature, I go out and try to effect change. For example, I personally sought the Mayor out to discuss my plan for a raised bicycle lane as discussed in <ref target="http://www.oniszczak.com/index.html#1">http://www.oniszczak.com/index.html#1</ref>. I had a vision and I talked to someone that could get things done. I saw a need for more community interaction – so I designed and built a website ( vividpicture.com) that allows all residents to discuss, comment and vote on each others ideas. The others list groups they join – but ask yourself – what did this group do for the community lately? Did the candidate actually contribute anything, or did he or she join because it looks good in a list.</p>
</text>
