<text id="autogum_interview_doc1026" title="part2_Blown for Good author discusses life inside international headquarters of Scientology" shortTile="partblown-good-author" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-11-12" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Blown_for_Good_author_discusses_life_inside_international_headquarters_of_Scientology" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The foreword to <hi rend="italic">Blown for Good</hi> is by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark%20Rathbun">Mark Rathbun</ref>, a former high-ranking Scientology official and recent critic who has gone public with statements that Scientology's leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Miscavige">David Miscavige</ref> has been physically abusive towards organization staff members. Rathbun notes that he almost emailed you to suggest someone else write the foreword, commenting, "his views of some of Scientology founder Hubbard's writings and my views differed greatly." (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L.%20Ron%20Hubbard">L. Ron Hubbard</ref> was the founder of Scientology.) How do your views differ from Rathbun's? Why did you select Mark Rathbun to write the foreword to your book?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Marc Headley</hi>: While I respect the right for people to believe whatever they want, I myself do not believe that L. Ron Hubbard did anything besides take what other people had already written and revised or repacked it for his own use. </p>
<p>In terms of the space aliens and earth people being inhabited by alien souls held captive in volcanoes from 75 million years ago – 75 million years is a long time to go without visiting, calling or just generally staying in touch. If they had the technology to travel from their own galaxy in spaceships that resembled DC-10’s and drop off millions of beings here, you think they would have come back a few times to check in on these guys. What’s up with that?</p>
<p>While I can respect other people’s beliefs and I mean no disrespect to any other faiths, I am more likely to subscribe to the 72 virgins philosophy than the idea that I or anyone should drop a huge amount of cash to rid myself of rogue space aliens squatting within my soul. </p>
<p>I asked Mark Rathbun to do the foreword for a few different reasons. The first being that he was one of the few people that was there for pretty much the entire time period I worked at the international headquarters. He witnessed and was privy to many of the things that I write about in the book. While we do not subscribe to the same ideas on what is wrong or right about Scientology, we both agree on the truth of what happened where we worked. He also has the respect of many current and former employees/members of organized Scientology who knew him as a high ranking official within the organization, and his endorsement of the book will do a lot to expose the abuse and false information within their ranks internationally.    </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You write in the "Author's note" preface to the book that it took you over a year after leaving to be able to begin to speak publicly about your experiences in Scientology. What was that year-long process like? What experiences did you have that helped you come to the decision that you wanted to speak publicly about Scientology?</hi></p>
</text>
