<text id="autogum_interview_doc1437" title="part3_OpenSync Interview - syncing on the free desktop" shortTile="partopensync-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-05-19" dateModified="2014-01-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/OpenSync_Interview_-_syncing_on_the_free_desktop" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">What was the greatest moment for you?</hi></p>
<p>Cornelius:</p>
<p>I think the greatest moment was when, after three days of concentrated hacking, we had a first working version of the KDE frontend for OpenSync. This was at  meeting at the SUSE offices in Nuernberg and we were able to successfully do a small presentation and demo to a group of interested SUSE people.</p>
<p>Armin:</p>
<p>I don't remember a distinct "greatest moment". But what is a really great feeling is to see that a project catches on, that other people get involved, use the code you have written and improve it in ways that you haven't thought of initially.</p>
<p>Tobias:</p>
<p>Hmm, also hacking on OpenSync/KitcheSync is much fun in general, the greatest moment was when the new KitchenSync frontend synced two directories via OpenSync the first time. But it was also cool when we managed to get the IrMC plugin working again after porting it to OpenSync.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">As we now know the worst problem you faced and your greatest moment, the only one missing is: What was your weirdest experience while working on OpenSync?</hi></p>
<p>Cornelius:</p>
<p>Not directly related to OpenSync, but pretty weird was meeting a co-worker at the Amsterdam airport when returning from the last OpenSync meeting. I don't know how high the chance is to meet somebody you know on a big random airport not related at all to the places where you or the other person live, but it was quite surprising.</p>
<p>Tobias:</p>
<p>Since my favorite language is C++, I was always confused how people can use plain C for such a project, half the time your are busy with writing code for allocating/freeing memory areas. Nevertheless Armin did a great job and he is always a help for solving strange C problems :)</p>
<head id="Devices_and_Programs">Devices and Programs</head>
<p>Now I'd like to move on to some more specific questions about current and planned abilities of OpenSync. As first, I've got a personal one:</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">I have an old iPod sitting around here. Can I or will I be able to use a program utilizing OpenSync to synchronize my calendars, contacts and music to it?</hi></p>
<p>Cornelius:</p>
<p>I'm not aware of any iPod support for OpenSync up to now, but if it doesn't exist yet, why not write it? OpenSync makes this easy. This is a chance for everybody with the personal desire to sync one device or another to get involved.</p>
<p>Armin:</p>
<p>I dont think that there is iPod support yet for OpenSync. But it would definitely be possible to use OpenSync for this task. So if someone would like to implement an iPod plugin, I would be glad to help :)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which other devices do you already support?</hi></p>
</text>
