<text id="autogum_interview_doc1291" title="part2_Wikinews interviews the Wikimania 2010 Poland bid promoter" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-12-28" dateModified="2019-01-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_the_Wikimania_2010_Poland_bid_promoter" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold">  Poland is a part of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Union">European Union</ref>. What about Wikimedians, who are inhabitants of countries requiring a visa?</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>As I stated before, the list of countries, which citizens are not required to have a visa when entering Poland for 90 days is pretty long<ref style="counter-reset: mw-Ref 1;" target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-1">[1]</ref>, and it does not restrict to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schengen%20Agreement">Schengen Agreement</ref> participants. Long list of Polish missions abroad<ref style="counter-reset: mw-Ref 2;" target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-2">[2]</ref> and freely available Visa application form <ref style="counter-reset: mw-Ref 3;" target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#cite_note-3">[3]</ref> should allow easy access to Poland for other countries citizens.</item></list>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold">  Information about Gdańsk application to host Wikimania started to appear in local media. What is local community reaction to this idea?</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>One can see it in the comments to the articles. Those that do not like Gdańsk in general are slightly against but most is for the idea. There are also people and organisations declaring help - I've got already some mails from potential supporters.</item></list>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold">  As you said before some people are objecting, probably not knowing possible benefits. How will Gdańsk and it's inhabitants benefit?</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>In addition of prestige, as we are talking about international event run by the organisation managing a <hi rend="italic">flagship</hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free%20Culture%20movement">Free Culture movement</ref>, world's focus, city presence in world's media, the conference will cause a money influx, new guests who can decide whether to come back to the city or suggest visiting it to their friends. We try not to make any troubles to city inhabitants, hoping that a conference held in one place will not paralyse the whole city.</item></list>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold">  Many possible visitors are not able to cover the cost of travel to Wikimania. What about organizers sponsorship?</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>It will depend on talks with companies willing to be sponsors. But I do not imagine leaving such requests unanswered.</item></list>
<figure><caption>Gdańsk by night Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rafikk">Rafał Konkolewski</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold">  Wikimania is not only lectures, but also a possibility for long night talks with participants from other countries. How does Gdańsk's night-life looks like?</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are plenty of places where you can meet and talk with each other. You can see it in a draft offer where one can see hundreds of places where you can talk while eating and drinking. Proximity of Old Town invites for a walk through streets with a wonderful and unmatched atmosphere, you can only feel by yourself.</item></list>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold">  English is the language of Wikimania. Will the attendants be able to communicate with employees of restaurants, clubs, shops, etc.?</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Personally, I encountered the shop assistant, who couldn't sell the product to foreign people only once; also just once I saw a rough translation of "polska <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/kuchnia">kuchnia</ref>" as "Polish kitchen" instead of "Polish cuisine". The Poles are able to communicate in English, I saw their communicativeness by teaching adults English for seven years. Most of menus and other informations in Old City's venues are translated into English and German, and the waiters know English at a level, which allows the customers to get a trouble-free service.</item></list>
</text>
