<text id="autogum_interview_doc1292" title="part0_David S. Touretzky discusses Scientology, Anonymous and Tom Cruise" shortTile="partdavid-s-touretzky" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-06" dateModified="2012-12-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_S._Touretzky_discusses_Scientology%2C_Anonymous_and_Tom_Cruise" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>David S. Touretzky discusses Scientology, Anonymous and Tom Cruise</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 6, 2008</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20S.%20Touretzky">David S. Touretzky</ref>, prominent free speech activist and critic of Scientology, discussed his opinions on the recent Internet backlash against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church%20of%20Scientology">Church of Scientology</ref> in an interview with former Scientologist and <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:NicholasTurnbull">Nicholas Turnbull</ref>. The recent conflict on the Internet between critics of Scientology and the Church has been spurred on in declarations by a nebulous Internet entity using the name <hi rend="italic">Anonymous</hi> that the Church of Scientology "will be destroyed". <hi rend="italic">Anonymous</hi> has directed recent protests at Scientology centres across the world, which have attracted significant numbers of individuals supporting the cause. In recent e-mail correspondence with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, a representative of the Church of Scientology declared that the Church considers the activities of Anonymous to be illegal, and that Anonymous "will be handled and stopped".</p>
<p>Touretzky, a research professor in artificial intelligence and computational neuroscience at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carnegie%20Mellon%20University">Carnegie Mellon University</ref>, has been a prominent critic of the Church of Scientology since mid-1995, and has been protesting against Scientology vociferously since then; he has also run websites that publish material that Scientology wishes to keep suppressed from the public eye, such as extracts from Scientology's formerly-confidential <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operating%20Thetan">Operating Thetan</ref></hi> (OT) materials. Touretzky views the actions of the Church of Scientology as being "a threat to free speech", and has endured harassment by the Church of Scientology for his activities.  </p>
<p>The Church of Scientology continues to suffer damage to its public reputation through increased exposure on the Internet and vocal protests by Scientology critics such as Prof. Touretzky. A recent event that focused intense attention on Scientology's totalitarian attitude was the leak of an internal Church of Scientology propaganda video to the Internet video sharing site <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YouTube"><hi rend="italic">YouTube</hi></ref>, in which celebrity Scientologist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom%20Cruise">Tom Cruise</ref> spoke heavily in Scientology's jargon and stated that that "we [Scientology] are the authorities" on resolving the difficulties of humanity. The declaration of war by <hi rend="italic">Anonymous</hi> followed shortly after this leak, in the form of a video posted to the Internet. </p>
<p>The ongoing dispute, cast by some as <hi rend="italic">Scientology versus the Internet</hi>, brought Scientology terms such as  "SP" (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suppressive%20Person">Suppressive Person</ref></hi>, an enemy of Scientology) and "KSW" (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keeping%20Scientology%20Working">Keeping Scientology Working</ref></hi>) into general usage by non-Scientologists from the late 1990s onwards; increased attention has been drawn to Scientology by the release of the Cruise video in addition to media coverage. This focus has caused an even greater propagation of these terms across the outside world, as Touretzky comments in the interview.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> asked Prof. Touretzky about the impact that the activities of <hi rend="italic">Anonymous</hi> will have on Scientology, the public relations effect of the Tom Cruise video, the recent departure of individuals from the Church of Scientology's executive management, the strategies that <hi rend="italic">Anonymous</hi> will employ and Touretzky's experiences of picketing the Church.</p>
</text>
