<text id="autogum_interview_doc1289" title="part0_Wikinews interviews the Wikimania 2010 Poland bid promoter" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-12-28" dateModified="2019-01-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_the_Wikimania_2010_Poland_bid_promoter" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews the Wikimania 2010 Poland bid promoter</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 30, 2008</hi></p>
 This article mentions the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>, one of its projects, or people related to it. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> is a project of the Wikimedia Foundation.
<figure><caption>One of the Gdańsk candidature banner projects. Image: <ref target="https://pl.wikinews.org/wiki/w:User:Airwolf">Airwolf</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikimania</hi> is an annual conference for users, developers and other people involved in the wiki projects operated by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>. It is held yearly since 2005. The first conference was held in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frankfurt">Frankfurt</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref>, on August 4-8, 2005. The second one was held in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Boston">Boston</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/USA">USA</ref> (on August 4-6, 2006), the third one was held in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taipei">Taipei</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Taiwan">Taiwan</ref> (on August 3-5, 2007), the fourth Wikimania was held in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Alexandria">Alexandria</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egypt">Egypt</ref> (on July 17-19, 2008) and Wikimania 2009 will be held in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buenos%20Aires">Buenos Aires</ref>.</p>
<p>Melbourne, Daytona Beach, Rio de Janeiro, Amsterdam, Copenhagen, Gdańsk, Montpellier and Oxford are among current unofficial Wikimania 2010 bids. Below is <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi>' conversation with the Gdańsk bid promoter and initiator, Wojciech Pędzich.</p>
<hi rend="bold"><figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure></hi><p><hi rend="bold"> Wikipedians from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tricity,%20Poland">Tricity</ref> are involved in the process of making an offer, which will give <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Poland">Poland</ref> a chance of organizing a world-wide conference of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>, <ref target="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Wikimania">Wikimania 2010</ref>. Among the competing cities are <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington,_D.C.">Washington, D.C.</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rio_de_Janeiro">Rio de Janeiro</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxford">Oxford</ref>. This year the conference was held in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Alexandria">Alexandria</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egypt">Egypt</ref>, where the famous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Library%20of%20Alexandria">Library of Alexandria</ref> is located. Does <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gdańsk">Gdańsk</ref> stand a chance among such known cities?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">Poland is still an interesting, unknown, and a cheap-to-visit country</hi>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/user:Wpedzich">Wojciech Pędzich</ref>: Because of Wikimania continental rotation, Australian and European bids have the biggest chances in 2010. Australian, because they have not hosted Wikimania yet, and Europe, because the first Wikimania was held in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frankfurt">Frankfurt</ref> back in 2005. Do we have a chance among other European cities' proposals? Poland is still an interesting, unknown, and a cheap-to-visit country with a comprehensive list of countries from which their members can visit Poland without requirement of having a visa. We propose the conference to be held inside two adjacent buildings – Polish Baltic Philharmonic and the Polish Maritime Museum buildings, located just few steps from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long%20Market">Long Market</ref> at the city's centre. Yes, I do think that our offer will be attractive and will give us a real chance of organizing the Wikimania 2010 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/gród">grad</ref> upon <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motława">Motława</ref>.</item></list>
<figure><caption>Democrative changes in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gdańsk">Gdańsk</ref> were initiated before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berlin%20Wall#The_Fall">Berlin Wall's Fall</ref>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Yann">Yann Forget</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold">  The tagline of your proposal is <hi rend="italic">Gdańsk - the city of freedom</hi>. Could you tell us, why do you promote yourself with this line?</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Gdańsk is associated by many with freedom, with its political impact. On the other hand, we have the Wikimedia Foundation and its values of sharing knowledge created freely by volunteers. A conjunction of a cosmopolitan city with strong revolutionary and liberal inclinations and a world-wide free culture is in this case, kind of, natural.</item></list>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold">  How many are involved into creating a proposal? Poland is relatively small country. Are you sure you will be able to guarantee the efficiency of conference, if your proposal wins?</hi></p>
</text>
