<text id="autogum_interview_doc502" title="part5_Eric Bogosian on writing and the creative urge" shortTile="parteric-bogosian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-16" dateModified="2014-05-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eric_Bogosian_on_writing_and_the_creative_urge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But do you ever ask yourself that question when you're writing, "Who cares?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] Well, yeah.  I mean, to some degree, you have to wonder, "Who cares?"  But you have to figure that there's gonna be people out there who share your experience.  When writing prose you must come to terms with the fact that Oprah is the queen of the prose world right now, because women are the people who buy most literary fiction.  I'm a guy in his fifties.  The experience of a guy in his fifties is not that interesting to women and there aren't that many men in their fifties reading serious fiction at this point.  So you do kind of box yourself into a corner.  But what can I do about that?  I can only write about what I can write about.  There are wonderful writers out there who are mature men writing wonderful books: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ian%20McEwan">McEwan</ref> or Roth or whoever you want to point your finger at.  It's just that that whole serious fiction world has its own problems.  That's what the online bookseller started to change.</p>
<head id="The_future_of_the_narrative">The future of the narrative</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you look at the arc of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20culture">American culture</ref>, in your experience, where do you see it heading?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Well, technology is what makes all things change.  If there were never any changes in technology, I’m sure everything would reach a sort of stasis, and we'd just live the same way all the time.  So, as technology changes, it's going to feed int--all of a sudden, there'll be some breakthrough thing that no one will suspect.  I mean, when Quentin Tarantino came out of nowhere with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pulp%20Fiction">Pulp Fiction</ref></hi>, it was because of what he had accumulated as a video store guy.  I know right now, my son is on the computer every night watching endless <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref> videos, and he's making videos himself, and he's got the TV set on and the music on at the same time.  Maybe something's going to come out of that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Something that's not apparent.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Somebody, somewhere, all of a sudden, all these elements will fuse, and there will be this new thing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell,_God,_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing">interviewed a novelist named John Reed</ref>, who wrote this book called <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snowball's%20Chance">Snowball's Chance</ref></hi> that was kind of a rip on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20Orwell">Orwell</ref>.  We were talking about how limited the current narrative is--at least in the United States, where it's sin, suffer and redemption.  John said he could foresee at some point these multidimensional narratives almost on a Biblical level come to fruition.  Where you have various dimensions, and where it goes from the Internet to magazines to television and it ends up spanning different mediums.  It's an interesting idea, and when you really think about it you can see it starting to happen.  It's not being done quite yet, but you could envision it.</hi></p>
</text>
