<text id="autogum_interview_doc866" title="part6_Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-22" dateModified="2014-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_World_Wide_Web_co-inventor_Robert_Cailliau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: While Tim Berners-Lee wasn't enthusiastic about it, you called for the first International WWW conference. How did those conferences shape the WWW?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: The conferences still run, the 2007 one was in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banff,%20Alberta">Banff</ref>.  They are an occasion to meet and work very hard for a few days at the exchange of ideas.  The papers of the presentations are published in well-known academic journals.  That incites people to prepare well and present to colleagues.  Many web technologies started at one of the conferences (proxies, VRML, ...)  Working groups are established there.  Because many want to go but can do so only when funded by their institute or company, it often means they have to present a paper.  Vague ideas are then consolidated and cast into programming code, which otherwise might not happen.</p>
<p>In addition the Conference Committee soon convinced the Web Consortium to hold one of its annual meetings in conjunction with the conference.  I am no longer involved with this, but at least during the years 1996 to 2004 this synergy was present and a track of the conference was devoted to the work of the Consortium.  Therefore Tim was also present every year.</p>
<p>I always saw the Consortium as the "church" with Tim as the "pope".  In the Consortium there is a set of rules for arriving at decisions after which everyone has to abide by them.  There are industrial and sometimes political stakes.</p>
<p>The Conferences however, as long as I was member of the Committee, I saw as the "state" of "laymen";  you had freedom of expression and could propose the most wild schemes. Between church and state I prefer a complete separation.</p>
<p>That did not mean of course that we did not collaborate closely between Consortium and Conference Committee:  there always was a delegate of the Consortium member of the Committee although that was not a requirement.  We wanted both to be successful.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: Related to that, I have been told the WWW was initially to run on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/micropayments">micropayments</ref>. Who had that idea, and why do you believe it never came about?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: It never was in the original goals to use micropayments.  However, for keynote speaker of the first conference (May 1994) I had invited David Schaum, an expert in digital money.  I was therefore already then convinced of the need for digital money:  payment with guaranteed value but not traceable origin.  We still do not have anything like that.  To me a much more important reason to introduce digital money than untraceability is a free market for information.</p>
<p>The ideas of digital payments were targeting sales of goods and payment of subscriptions.  To me it is more important to break the vicious triangle of author-reader-advertiser.</p>
<p>In the beginning I was often completely misunderstood.  There were even newspaper articles that led to hate-mail through incomprehension.</p>
</text>
