<text id="autogum_interview_doc1295" title="part3_David S. Touretzky discusses Scientology, Anonymous and Tom Cruise" shortTile="partdavid-s-touretzky" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-06" dateModified="2012-12-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_S._Touretzky_discusses_Scientology%2C_Anonymous_and_Tom_Cruise" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : What is your opinion on the reverse: do you think the CoS will be peaceful and legal in its handling of "Anonymous"? In a recent e-mail exchange with Wikinews, a Scientology staff member said that Anonymous would be "handled and stopped" and that the actions "have been reported". Will Scientology carry out its usual harassment, or do you think that it has learned its lesson that such abusive tactics cause more of a backlash?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: My best guess is that the Scientologists will employ their famous "hiding tech".  Doors locked, lights off, and PIs [private investigators] discreetly filming from a distance.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : I imagine the CoS will attempt their usual approach of trying to turn it into a pro-Scientology rally, as they have done at many smaller pickets, although I feel that it would fail miserably.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: I was at the pickets in 1997 (twice) and 1999. They tried counter-picketing. They tried harassing us and getting in our faces.  Even physically harassed a woman with a seeing eye dog. But eventually they switched to hiding tech. I also did a solo picket on L. Ron Hubbard Way, and they kept trying different ways to "handle" me. I was only planning on spending an hour there, but I was having so much fun I didn't quit ‘till it got too dark to see. I thought about running out to buy a flashlight, but decided to call it a day.  My feet were sore!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : [<hi rend="italic">laughs</hi>] So it sounds like you had quite a day of it, Dave.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: Yes, I have fond memories of that day. For me, it was like going to Disneyland and seeing Mickey Mouse.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : What have been your most effective tactics against the CoS, then, Dave, in terms of impact and education of others?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: The web sites are probably the most effective, but doing radio and TV appearances has also been pretty helpful. I've done over 20 radio interviews and three national TV appearances, two of which were on Keith Olbermann's show. I was gonna say: there's a reason Scientology felt it necessary to counterpicket us in Clearwater.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Presumably because of the public exposure?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: [It] has nothing to do with the public.  It's because they don't want to appear powerless in front of their members.  It was a face-saving gesture.  But it didn't work out the way they'd hope. The public will drive by a picket, honk their horn, and forget about it by time they turn the corner. But the members see their cult being publicly mocked by a bunch of SPs, that makes a deep impression. Especially when there are signs about Lisa McPherson's death, or t-shirts containing the text of OT III.</p>
</text>
