<text id="autogum_interview_doc1175" title="part8_Lobby groups oppose plans for EU copyright extension" shortTile="partlobby-groups" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-18" dateModified="2014-12-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lobby_groups_oppose_plans_for_EU_copyright_extension" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>Erik admitted he was disappointed when he compared the way laws are currently made in the European Union to his experience with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Swedish</ref> politics.</p>
<figure><caption><hi rend="bold">It's one of the worst proposals in a long time, and still it's being proposed, and still it will have members of the European parliament defending it. This is to me, outrageous! I cannot understand, I cannot accept that this is Europe. If the man in the street could see what is happening, he would be appalled. The man in the street expects people to be decent, up until the highest levels of decision making, and unfortunately what we see here in Brussels, is the opposite in many cases.</hi>
-Erik Josefsson, Electronic Frontier Foundation (right)</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Erik Josefsson</hi>: The way things were discussed, prepared and legislated in Sweden before was like a dream compared to what is happening now. The expert advice comes from a limited sector of the spectrum of ideas. In the Swedish tradition, it was the responsibility of the legislator to listen to everybody. I see that tradition is basically wiped away, not necessarily intentionally, but the European project is changing fundamentally in democratic processes and structures, and very fast, in such a way that it's a challenge for any NGO that interacts with European policy makers.</p>
<p>Structurally, you have an inter service consultation, but you really don't know how to be able to interact with that process. [<hi rend="italic">To Becky, ed.</hi>] You're envisioning kind of marching in the streets thing, or at least an online petition campaign of the size of a million signatures, ... I'm saying that it's unfortunate that the respect for rational discussion has been deteriorating to that extent that you have to counteract bad policy with campaigns in that sense. I would like to just underline the problem we have with the lack of discussion, which also means the knowledge distribution within society that finally would reach the political layer. In this case, understanding is close to zero in many segments of the political spectrum.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eddan Katz:</hi> With the lack of democratic processes, I think what's important to demonstrate from the general public in a letter-writing campaign, in making your voice heard, is a reclaim culture, to not allow that term to be captured by people who have very specific interests of how that work should be interpreted, and to reclaim that culture, the culture that's now exploded in the internet age of all of us being able to produce things and publish things and make them available to the world instantaneously and without restrictions. That's the culture that needs to be reclaimed, and that's the feature here that needs to be seen. There's no economic justification -to just return to the copyright term extension. Something has already been created, so since it has already been created, there's no need incentivise creating it. You need to reclaim the democratic processes of Europe, you need to reclaim the term culture.</p>
</text>
