<text id="autogum_interview_doc686" title="part9_Sam Brownback on running for President, gay rights, the Middle East and religion" shortTile="partsam-brownback" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-12" dateModified="2014-12-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sam_Brownback_on_running_for_President%2C_gay_rights%2C_the_Middle_East_and_religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In what country that has passed same-sex marriage has traditional marriage declined?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Same-sex%20marriage%20in%20the%20Netherlands">The Netherlands</ref>--there's--Stanley Kurtz is the lead researcher on this.  He's out at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoover%20Institute">Hoover Institute</ref>, and you see in--I've talked about when you pull the sacredness out of marriage, the marriage rates go down, you've seen this probably as pronounced as anywhere in a number of countries of Northern Europe, where you're now getting close to eighty percent out-of-wedlock birth rates on first children in some counties in Northern Europe.  They've kind of gone from "Well, we don't really need to be married; anybody, any two people can get married"-you've just, you've taken the sacredness out of the institution.  This is the work that I'm citing though, off of that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Got you.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  But it's looking at the totality of--within the last forty years, it's a different societal view of marriage.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why did you vote against the Federal expansion of hate crimes to include sexual orientation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Well, for a couple of reasons.  One, it was in the defense bill, which I didn't think it was appropriate to be in there.  Number two, it's a state issue.  I think it's unconstitutional to put this out at the Federal level.  For the Federal government to enact a crime, there has to be an interstate commerce nexus to it.  Number three, the states are handling this well; the two cases cited--the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew%20Shephard">Shephard</ref> case in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wyoming">Wyoming</ref> and the case in Texas, you've got the death penalty in one case and life imprisonment in the other.  You can't get much harder on somebody there.  And the final issue on this is that there's a substantial possibility of a chilling effect on free speech of people of religion--if there are ministers speaking from the pulpit on their view of homosexuality from a spiritual perspective.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Ministers speaking out against homosexuality would come under the province of a hate crime?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  A number of people believe strongly that it will.  Those are a series of reasons why.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic">See also</hi>: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_gay_marriage_movement_founder_Evan_Wolfson">Wikinews Interview with gay marriage movement founder Evan Wolfson</ref></item></list>
<head id="Brownback_on_Brownback">Brownback on Brownback</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If you could choose your manner of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/death">death</ref>, how would you die?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  I hadn't thought much about that....</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcel%20Proust">Marcel Proust</ref> question.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Gosh, I don't know.  I more just--I want to be prepared to die, that I would pray at that point in time that I'm ready to meet my Maker, that I have a clean soul, that I've done what the Lord would have required of me and have lived as loving and caring a life as possible.</p>
</text>
