<text id="autogum_interview_doc1265" title="part1_Interview with Derek Begley, Regional Council candidate for Wards 9 & 10 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-derek" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-10-10" dateModified="2007-06-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Derek_Begley%2C_Regional_Council_candidate_for_Wards_9_%26_10_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am very active in youth activities and sports in the community, mostly through the Matmen wrestling club, where I am a head coach. One of the biggest challenges facing our community is channeling our youth into positive and life skills building endeavours. I have been involved in the development of  community driven recreation choices, such as skateboard parks and lit, well managed outdoor areas that encourage not only youth physical participation, but gives them opportunities to create their own grassroots organizations and events. Youth invovlement and a sense of ownership in their community is crucial in their development into engaged, well rounded citizens.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Much of Brampton's existing council is quite seasoned in the civic political process. What could you bring to the table as a "rookie", above and beyond the current roster of councillors?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I feel that I can offer the best of both worlds- someone who is energetic and full of fresh ideas, while also still having the experience and knowledge of the process to be an effective public servant right from the beginning. I grew up around the council ( my mother being council secretary before serving five terms herself) and have worked at several part time and seasonal positions over the years within the city.This has given me considerable insight into the overall operation of the city of Brampton and a solid understanding of that which works and those areas I am eager to work to improve once elected.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The Rose Theatre recently launched. What are your thoughts on this facility? Have you had a chance to tour it yet? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have toured the facility, and it is a beautiful structure, but I am concerned about the additional investment needed to bring the surrounding area more in line with the municipalities vision for the Four Corners area, and how much of the burden is expected to be shouldered by the taxpayers still. I am also concerned by our large commitment to a type of facility that have proven to be less than successful both financially and culturally to cities such as North York, Mississauga and Markham. Future councils must take tremendous care to ensure this facility lives up to its promise for our community.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The province has strongly encouraged the development of high-density residences near the downtown. Do these buildings fit in with your vision of the downtown? How much say should other levels of government have in urban planning? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The development of high density, mixed usage buildings are an important part of the Brampton revitalization projects, but I believe that efforts must be taken to ensure this development is in a position to be of the greatest benefit of all Bramptonians, not just the "traditional " four corners section of old Brampton. When Brampton and Bramalea amalgamated, the centre of the city shifted to the Queen and 410 area, and access , land availability and geography would suggest that this is a more appropriate area to focus development in the Central Brampton Area. Our city must work jointly with regional, provincial and federal government institutions as well as the private sector to develop a plan of action that is clear, concise and of maximum benefit to Brampton's tax payers.</p>
</text>
