<text id="autogum_interview_doc230" title="part2_CanadaVOTES: Libertarian John Kittridge in St. Paul&amp;apos;s" shortTile="partcanadavotes-libertarian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-10" dateModified="2016-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_Libertarian_John_Kittridge_in_St._Paul%27s" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Proper government provides an even playing field, applies the same rules to all players and dispenses justice even-handedly, quickly and appropriately. Libertarians would ensure that the relevant laws are actually applied and, in those areas of the regulations where change is required to catch up to technology, to cover omissions or to revise poorly structured statutes we would have it done.</p>
<p>Specifically with respect to atmospheric warming and CO2, once the pertinent regulatory environment had been tightened as noted above we would encouage cases to be brought to court in order to resolve the claims made and the degree to which action is indicated. The current state of the debate has been singularly one-sided and lacking of the true spirit and freedom of scientific inquiry. It would help to clarify it before any government (Liberal, Conservative, NDP or Green) tears the heart out of the economy of the country by taking draconian steps that may not even address the root cause of their concerns.</p>
<p>The programme suggestions currently featured in other party platforms would do more harm than good. Taxes are distorting and disruptive. Cap and trade encourages abuse. Government programs of redistribution inevitably fall under the spell of political decision making and are generally abused, if not corrupted outright. Setting emission levels at something that equates to about 40+% lower than today's is to irresponsibly and knowingly lie to Canadians. Car emissions levels must be driven by cost-benefit considerations and cannot be dictated in an environment of unceretainty <hi rend="italic">[sic]</hi> without, once again, distorting outcomes.</p>
<p>We would do none of these things, even if the jury weren't still out on fundamental issues such as the causes and direction of atmospheric warming, the role of human produced CO2 (the "inverse," after all, of the breath of life, O2), the possibility and potential impact of human CO2 control and its real cost. Libertarians would limit their involvement, as noted above, to providing a framework within which the issue could be resolved and addressed rationally by all the stakeholders.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Are there any misconceptions about you, your leader, or your party and platform?</hi></p>
<p>Most people know very little about the party, the leader, myself or our platform. But one common misconception is that we are "extreme right wing." We are not! Libertarians want to eliminate most of government involvement in both our economic and personal lives, letting Canadians live as free individuals and free traders. No rightist would ever subscribe to our principles. (Our principles are readily available <ref target="http://www.libertarian.ca/">on our web site</ref>.)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">There are more ways than ever to get your message out, from the traditional campaign fliers and lawn signs, to new media like websites, Facebook, and YouTube. The tried-and-true routes get the message out to the masses much easier, but digital alternatives are much more measurable in how many are seeing or interacting with your campaign. What seems to be the most effective, from your experience?</hi></p>
</text>
