<text id="autogum_interview_doc937" title="part3_KKE: Interview with the Greek Communist Party" shortTile="partkke-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-05-13" dateModified="2019-09-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/KKE%3A_Interview_with_the_Greek_Communist_Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>That is also why the working class should not be trapped in a discussion about bonds or interest rates, the simple reason being that it has nothing to gain from this discussion. The international loans will end up in the capital’s pockets, not the working class. The Greeks have suffered when the rates were down, they suffer now that the rates are up. We do not intend to share the capital's 'anxiety' about the <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/bourse">bourse</ref>, because it is becoming clearer every day that if <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/plutocracy">plutocracy</ref> does not go bankrupt, then the people will.</p>
<p>The government is not doing anything wrong – in fact, it is doing a great job representing the interests of its bosses, the Greek capitalists, the imperialists of E.U., the I.M.F. But they want the working class partners to their crime. They are telling us that our sacrifice to live in poverty and work until we die is our patriotic duty. What they are not telling us is that the workers, the farmers, the owners of small shops; we do not have the same country as these E.U. fans of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hellenic%20Federation%20of%20Enterprises">Hellenic Federation of Enterprises</ref>, the City-educated bankers, the corporate media owners. Their country and their god is exploitation and profit. Our people have proven their patriotism in every single crucial point in history for thousands of years now. But this case is different, the working Greek man and women should not make any sacrifices for plutocracy! The only ‘sacrifice’ that should be made is to fight the dangerous fear and hesitation and organise the struggle. That’s what will help our own country and our class.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Iain</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> I have heard that people in Greece are upset that the euro has weakened Greece’s economic position, as the {{w|Drachma]]'s low value actually encouraged spending by foreigners. What steps would a socialist government take to encourage new spending in Greece by both foreign tourists and investors?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Isabella</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> As mentioned earlier, since the agreements signed within the EU do not allow for manoeuvres in favour of the people, our disengagement would be inevitable and would be an essential term in order to plan the economy based on how we will fulfil our contemporary needs. The currency itself is not the main issue.</p>
<p>Tourism is another sector of the economy whose fate depends again on who owns the means of production. Only with a different economy the country will develop the infrastructures and provide quality services that will first of all guarantee decent working conditions, will be accessible to all the population and will be cheap.</p>
<p>So far, the development of Greek tourism has been based on profit. Therefore, the fees for ships and other means of transport are outrageous; many islands are left with no regular connection with the mainland because these lines are not considered to be profitable. Both PASOK [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panhellenic%20Socialist%20Movement">Panhellenic Socialist Movement</ref>] and ND [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Democracy">New Democracy</ref>] governments, under the EU guidance, have implemented policies that led to rough working conditions and wages in tourism. Besides, more than 60% of Greeks at the moment cannot go on any holiday and after the latest measures these numbers will increase; another significant portion reduces the time off work, and a third one relies on the hospitality of friends and family for their holidays, due to their low income.</p>
</text>
