<text id="autogum_interview_doc1267" title="part0_Two-time Eurovision entrant Edsilia Rombley discusses music, love, and her contrasting Contest experiences" shortTile="parttwotime-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-03" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Two-time_Eurovision_entrant_Edsilia_Rombley_discusses_music%2C_love%2C_and_her_contrasting_Contest_experiences" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Two-time Eurovision entrant Edsilia Rombley discusses music, love, and her contrasting Contest experiences</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 3, 2009</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Eurovision '98 and '07 representative Edsilia Rombley on the perceived "Americanization" of Dutch popular music: "I think Dutch pop music has always been influenced by America, this was set in long before I entered the Songfestival; on one hand I think this is a great thing, because America has so many great artists. It's just important that we, while embracing foreign influences, don't forget all the talents in the Netherlands, who make great Dutch music."Photo: Nico Swartz</caption></figure>
<p>When she was barely 20 years old, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Netherlands">Dutch</ref> singer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edsilia%20Rombley">Edsilia Rombley</ref> got her first large taste of international acclaim. Already a winner of the smaller imitation contest <hi rend="italic">Soundmix Show</hi>, she decided to shoot higher. With a great deal of determination, she performed in front of hundreds of millions of television viewers at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%201998">1998 Eurovision Song Contest</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birmingham">Birmingham</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref>. Her song, the R&amp;B flavored "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hemel%20en%20aarde">Hemel en aarde</ref>" (<hi rend="italic">Heaven and earth</hi>), placed fourth and gave her country their highest placing at Eurovision since their last win in 1975. No Dutch contestant after her has been able to place similarly.</p>
<p>After the accolades died down, Rombley set her sights on promoting her vision and passion through her music. Partnering with producer Tjeerd Oosterhuis became a double blessing; eventually they became husband and wife. Even a return to Eurovision at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%202007">2007 Contest</ref>, with less than favorable results, didn't keep her discouraged for long. Today she has finished recording a live CD of her favorite English songs, and a live DVD of selections in Dutch, and is currently touring in singing engagements this spring in theaters across the Netherlands.</p>
<p>Edsilia Rombley granted <hi rend="italic">Wikinews'</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Mike_Halterman">Mike Halterman</ref> an interview; she reflected on her career, her inspirations, what a day is like in her life, and what she would love to do in the future. This is the third in a series of interviews with past Eurovision contestants, which will be published sporadically in the lead-up to mid-May's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%202009">next contest</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow">Moscow</ref>.</p>
<head id="A_day_in_the_life">A day in the life</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You recently had a birthday. Happy birthday! How did you celebrate this year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Edsilia Rombley</hi>: I'm doing a tour across 43 Dutch theatres from January until May. On February 13th, I was doing in a show in Beverwijk. I wasn't planning on much, but I was surprised with a birthday cake before the show and lovely presents and flowers, even from the audience! The whole audience sang a birthday song for me during the show, which was great. I had a wonderful evening.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> I've visited your website and you seem to be very busy with various projects. Can you describe what a typical work day is like for you?</hi></p>
</text>
