<text id="autogum_interview_doc931" title="part6_An interview with gossip columnist Michael Musto on the art of celebrity journalism" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-05" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_gossip_columnist_Michael_Musto_on_the_art_of_celebrity_journalism" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have a theory or philosophy you follow about outing?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  My theory is just that public figures sign an implicit deal with the media that their private lives are to be covered, and to leave out gayness because it is distasteful or there might be homophobes out there is homophobic in itself.  It's hypocritical and it makes 'gay' the last taboo.  But I don't get arguments anymore.  I'm like, 'Come on people!  Yell at me!'</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What about the argument that it is more appropriate for people who are working against the gay community, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larry%20Craig">Larry Craig</ref>, if you will?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  People like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michaelangelo%20Signorile">Michaelangelo Signorile</ref> started by outing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malcolm%20Forbes">Malcolm Forbes</ref>, not anybody anti-gay.  He was just saying 'He's dead, he's gay, let's say so in the obituary.'  I don't believe in outing only the hypocrites and anti-gay people because then the only people the public is going to know are gay are horrible, hateful people.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  There are a lot of gay people who aren't talked about in Hollywood now.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merv%20Griffin">Merv Griffin</ref> was an example.  Do you not feel the need to spell it out for some people who lead very openly gay lives but that nobody talks about?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  Yeah, that was a big uproar after Merv died.  Merv almost came out himself; was it <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vanity%20Fair">Vanity Fair</ref></hi> where he said 'I'm quarter sexual, I'll sleep with anybody for a quarter?' or something?  99% of the obits didn't even address it the fact that even Merv had almost coyly come out.  So yeah, I wrote something to try and rectify that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But why not write something before he died?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  Please!  I totally did.  In the 90's there was a group that put up those 'Absolutely Queer: Jodi Foster' and Merv Griffin posters?  I ran the Jodi and Merv posters in my column.  It was huge.  I was really going places nobody was going; nobody was running pictures of those posters because everybody was so terrified of lawsuits.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you ever come under editorial pressure over those?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  No, and the <hi rend="italic">Voice</hi> staff at the time was very anti-outing, but nobody told me not to go there, and I've never been sued in my life and I've been here for 22 years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You are pretty accessible to your readers as well, right?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  Yeah.  I'm out there.  Tonight I'm doing a reading that is turning into a tribute to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean%20Johnson">Dean Johnson</ref></p>
<head id="On_New_York_City">On New York City</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where do you see Manhattan's culture going?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  It's been weird for me to live in Manhattan and see the transformations.  On one level it's exciting, it's booming, it has a bright future.  On the other hand a lot of the creative energy and starving artists have been pushed to the boroughs.  They're still in New York.  I hate when people say there are no starving artists in New York.  The boroughs <hi rend="italic">are</hi> part of New York: I'm from Brooklyn--<hi rend="italic">it counts</hi>!  But, being someone who is so Manhattan-centric, it's weird being in a place with so many rich people.  It's not what I intended.  I'm looking at buying an apartment now and it's horrifying.</p>
</text>
