<text id="autogum_interview_doc047" title="part8_Wikinews interviews Rocky De La Fuente, U.S. Democratic Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-03-29" dateModified="2016-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Rocky_De_La_Fuente%2C_U.S._Democratic_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>We spend an inordinate amount of time and money intervening in the affairs of other nations. What if we were to redirect our efforts and capital toward improving vital issues at home (i.e., our homeless, our displaced veterans, illiteracy and poverty (which continue to hover around 15%), the availability of health care for every American, etc.)? We could lead by example rather than try to convince the rest of the world why it should follow our model, and at the same time, we would be taking care of our citizens and restoring hope and dignity to their lives.</p>
<head id="Future">Future</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If elected, what would constitute a successful presidency for you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">De La Fuente</hi>: Simplistically, if I could make meaningful progress toward achieving the goals I just listed, I would have a successful presidency.</p>
<figure><caption>De La Fuente: "I don't need to serve in a political office to be happy, but I would be honored to do so if I thought I could give something back to my country." Image: Marc Nozell.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Which individuals would you like to see in a De La Fuente administration?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">De La Fuente</hi>: I would take a fundamentally different approach to staffing the De La Fuente administration. Currently, over 80 percent of the senior White House staff positions and approximately 50 percent of the ambassadorships have gone to individuals who bundled $500 thousand or more for the current Administration. While these people shouldn't be banned from serving the Administration if they are qualified, the disproportionate distribution suggests that the positions are more likely to be a repayment of political debt. I will not do that.</p>
<p>I learned in business that I did best when I hired people who were better than me at what they did. I didn't hire them to be subservient to me nor did I hire them because they were friends. I think that same approach is needed in Washington, D.C. During these difficult times, we need our nation's best and brightest individuals to tackle our problems. I would select people to serve in my administration on a basis of merit.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you plan on ever running for political office again?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">De La Fuente</hi>: I'm a first generation American who is extreme[ly] proud of being a citizen of this great country. To give you some perspective, I once wanted to fly a large <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flag%20of%20the%20United%20States">American flag</ref> over one of my car dealerships, but the city's governing body emphatically said, "No!" For nine years, I fought back before winning the right to honor our country with what has become a prominent landmark; a 3,000 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/square%20foot">square foot</ref> flag flying from the tallest free standing flag pole in the United States.</p>
<p>I don't need to serve in a political office to be happy, but I would be honored to do so if I thought I could give something back to my country.</p>
</text>
