<text id="autogum_interview_doc663" title="part6_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I always wanted to know what the cemeteries are like there. What the funerals are like there. Are they like town meetings in a place where there is so much death? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  The journalists define news and their editors want news....</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It fits a template.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  And the reporting out of Washington is the worst.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The press is often cited for it's laziness and for reporting any source without checking its accuracy.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  The press in Washington got us into this war as much as the people that are controlling it.  They took information that was second-hand information, and they went along with it.  It wasn't only the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judith%20Miller">Judy Millers</ref> who got credit for being in the pocket of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ahmed%20Chalabi">Ahmed Chalabi</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul%20Wolfowitz">Wolfowitz</ref> and the rest of those people.  All of them.  The <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> bureau, not only Miller, but all of them.  They went along.  They don't want to get off <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air%20Force%20One">Air Force One</ref>; they want to have access.  Also, you mentioned Floyd Abrams.  I wouldn't defend what he defended, this kind of sourcing that goes on.  These sources that lie?  The New York Times allows such liars to affect news.  I'll give you several examples:  the story of the so-called Chinese spy, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wen%20Ho%20Lee">Wen Ho Lee</ref>, the guy who four or five years ago in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los%20Alamos">Los Alamos</ref> was supposed to be a spy.  He was locked up with chains around his ankles.  That was leaked information, one of these celebrated reporters--Risen, or something, was the guy.  The story about that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2001%20anthrax%20attacks">Anthrax fellow in Maryland</ref> who was supposed to be identified the source of this anthrax.  Wrong.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2006%20Duke%20University%20lacrosse%20team%20scandal">Duke Lacrosse players</ref>, we were told raped that girl; the New York Times pushed it on their front page.  We didn't know the facts.  You use sources and identify, crucify people who never committed any wrong.  It turned out not true.  Then it's too late.  It's just like that whole period before the Iraq War.  That information--it was leaked, coming in, publish it.  Saddam has an atomic bomb.  And they publish it.  They publish it and we don't know the truth.  Journalists should withhold information like that.</p>
<head id="On_the_Iraq_War">On the Iraq War</head>
What most bothers me are the college students – the worst generation is what I call them. These college students are the worst and I've been to a lot of campuses...this year I was at the University of Pennsylvania and I was at the University of Alabama, and I've been to a number of campuses this year and nobody cares about this war.
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Has the war affected you as a person?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I wish it had. The war hasn't affected America as a person. The only ones affected are the 165,000 troops, relatives, kinfolk, cousins. That's all.</p>
</text>
