<text id="autogum_interview_doc1191" title="part3_BDSM as business: An interview with the owners of a dungeon" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_An_interview_with_the_owners_of_a_dungeon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I got you.  So it's just we're going to work on the business.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Since Rebecca works in the advertising business anyway, she might be there at another time, so it doesn't really matter.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  I'm a really bad liar, so I tell them, "I'm working."  I really am working.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yeah.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  She's not always here.  She may be at the advertising, doing some stuff, working with some print ads.  So it's kind of nice to be able to tell the truth that way--</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  You know, so I'll--maybe I'll bring some papers with me and stuff, but I really am working.  So--work is work.</p>
<head id="Operating_the_business">Operating the business</head>
<head id="The_costs">The costs</head>
<figure><caption>Clothing supply closet.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  There's a misconception in this industry.  Your exposure to this is probably primarily what you see in movies, scanning magazines, scanning the Internet, just snippets everywhere.  It's portrayed as though it's dark, black and evil.  And--</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Oh man, well?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  What's up?</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  I do wear a lot of black.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">chuckles</hi>]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  It's anything but that.  If you look at the rooms, there's all the accouterments you'd find in these types of places--but more than anything, there's a lot of good feeling around here.  We hire the opposite of what you'd think we would hire, what the average person would think we would hire.  We hire educated, nice people.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  I remember one of our ads that I had put in said, "If you think nice girls don't do S&amp;M,"--I forgot what the rest of it said--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  “--think again.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Yeah, "think again" or something like that.  And that ad had pulled so many girls, because they--I think they all thought that nice girls don't do this.  And a bunch of them had called and they said, "Wow."  And I think I remember, a bunch of guys called because of that also.  Do you remember?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  I sure do, I sure do.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What are the startup costs involved?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  It varies; look around Manhattan, look around rents, look around build-outs, look around hiring, look around advertising...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's your greatest non-fixed cost?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  The single most costly thing we spend on is rent and advertising, those two together make up the bulk of what we spend.  There's supplies, and there's wear and tear and maintenance, and bookkeeping and things like that that you have to do.  That's about it.  The hardest thing in running this business, which is why people can't do it, is the relationship that my wife has with the gals and with the customers.</p>
</text>
