<text id="autogum_interview_doc521" title="part1_Wikinews interviews U.S. Constitution Party presidential candidate Max Riekse" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-01" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Constitution_Party_presidential_candidate_Max_Riekse" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>We need to end the lock on this countries domestic and foreign policy that the military industrial complex, the international banks, multi-national corporations, big oil, and even Israel has on our country to the detriment of the people of America.  I am not anti-military, but I am totally against endless wars for the wealthy elite, going back to the Spanish American War.  We can have $1.00 a gallon gas;  I can do it. This is America.  When all is said and done, I think that I will be a reasonable and informed choice for the millions of American voters who will not like to vote for either the Democrat or Republican in November. I'm qualified and ready to serve.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">If elected, how would you handle America's public school system?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Lt. Colonel Riekse:</hi> I retired out of the Michigan Public School system with over 23 years of service; K-12;  I can help bring our public schools to a higher level of achievement.  First, eliminate all illegal aliens from the system.  We have no duty or obligation to feed or educate them. None what so ever.  They have help destroy most of our inner city public school systems.  They have stressed out our public schools  and local school can not deal with them.  They do pay the taxes needed to support our schools and don't greatly appreciate the free education they get; also, we need to reduce by around 90% the amount of Federal education money we collect and then send back to the states for  education.  The huge amount of Federal paperwork is also stressing out our public schools and we need to end it.</p>
<p>Local school boards and the people they are responsible to are the best judge of what is needed; this with state oversight, will help boost  public school quality &amp; education.  I support public school education, along with schools of choice and home schooling.  The Federal government has done little to increase the quality of education.  For the most part, it has been a waste of money.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">How would you handle abortion?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Lt. Colonel Riekse:</hi> Push this issue back to the states.  I remember when the states controlled the issue of abortion, there was very little of it;  When the Federal government got involved, millions of the unborn died.  As President, I would not spend or authorized one red cent for abortion.  This is a state issue; period.  There will always be some states that will allow it to some degree, but that is up to the people of that state to decide, not the federal government or Fed. Courts.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">Do you think you have a good shot at winning the Constitution Party nomination? If so, do you think that you could be in the White House this time next year?</hi></p>
</text>
