<text id="autogum_interview_doc917" title="part2_Scientology protest group celebrates founder&amp;apos;s birthday worldwide" shortTile="partscientology-protest" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-05" dateModified="2019-02-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology_protest_group_celebrates_founder%27s_birthday_worldwide" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Other Boston galleries</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="http://www.flickr.com/photos/24697244@N03/sets/72157604127061533/">flickr page</ref></item>
<item><ref target="http://www.maj.com/cgi-bin/gallery.cgi?f=170824">maj gallery</ref></item>
<item><ref target="http://www.flickr.com/photos/24735055@N06/">another flickr page</ref></item>
<item><ref target="http://www.maj.com/cgi-bin/gallery.cgi?f=170847">another maj gallery</ref></item></list>
<head id="Brussels,_Belgium"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brussels">Brussels</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Belgium">Belgium</ref></head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Correspondents: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Brianmc">Brian McNeil</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Stevenfruitsmaak">Steven Fruitsmaak</ref></hi></p>
<p>Starting off from a meeting point at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brussels-Central%20railway%20station">Brussels Central Station</ref>, the anonymous protesters proceeded on foot to arrive at their licensed protest point outside the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brussels%20Stock%20Exchange">Brussels Stock Exchange</ref> around 12:30 local time. The turnout was about half that of the previous protest with only 20 or so people present.</p>
<p>Per advice from the police, cake was not on offer. It had been pointed out that this would likely get the protesters overrun by children and vagrants. Unlike other countries, Belgium has laws prohibiting protesters to cover their faces, leaving the protesters to wear sunglasses and shawls.</p>
<p>The protest could not take place in front of Scientology's headquarters because an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/E.U.">E.U.</ref> summit was scheduled to continue until today. Scientology members were allowed to be active outside their headquarters, for their "open door day". No special activities inside their building was observed, just volunteers handing out flyers to perhaps a dozen passers-by. The press release for this open door day was devoted to Anonymous: </p>
<figure><caption>The police didn't allow Anonymous near the Scientology headquarters, but the Scientologists were allowed to stage an 'open door day'.</caption></figure>"Anonymous", a group of cyber-terrorists hiding their identities behind masks and computer anonymity, has targeted the Scientology religion, its Churches, leaders and parishioners with hate speech and hate crimes. ... Death threats and threats to plant nitroglycerin bombs in Churches have made it necessary to take security precautions and identify members of this group responsible for these crimes.
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right;">—Scientology press release</p>
<p>The Scientologists said the event was inspired by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Universal_Declaration_of_Human_Rights">Universal Declaration of Human Rights</ref>, which is however remembered on December 10 (also mentioned on the flags outside their office, see photo). The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20Nations%20Human%20Rights%20Council">United Nations Human Rights Council</ref> was established on March 15 (2006), a date closer to this weekend.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> spoke to a Scientology representative in the European headquarters, which are located in the political heart of Brussels; <hi rend="italic">Law Street</hi>, just next to the Belgian and European parliament. Since Scientology was devoting the afternoon to human rights, we asked for Scientology's opinion about human rights controversies in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> (such as the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Guantanamo_Bay_detention_camp">Guantanamo Bay</ref> detainees). The representative told <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> that the Church is a religious movement and avoids taking general political stances.</p>
<p>The representative was also confident about the outcome of a pending lawsuit from the Belgian federal prosecutor. After an eight-year investigation, the Belgian justice said that the local and European chapters, as well as, members would be accused of blackmailing, swindling members, breaking trade and privacy laws, unlawfully practising medicine, and forming a criminal organisation.</p>
<p>"The file is empty," said the Scientology representative, who asserted that the inquiry had been so lengthy because the state could not prove any wrongdoings by the Church. He said that unlike in the US, Scientology is not seeking official recognition in Belgium, which recognises only six religions. He also claimed that there were more than 1,000 Scientologists in Belgium.</p>
</text>
