<text id="autogum_interview_doc1357" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Finnish 'Rock 'N' Troll' band Kivimetsän Druidi" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-06-07" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Finnish_%27Rock_%27N%27_Troll%27_band_Kivimets%C3%A4n_Druidi" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Antti:</hi> After composing and recording the first song we decided to upload it to mikseri.net (Finnish site where people can upload their own songs) and we, of course, needed name for the project. Joni just shouted “Kivimetsän Druidi” (The Druid of The Stoneforest) as a joke. I laughed and added it. We were supposed to change it later, but here we are.</item></list></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>What sort of things do you sing about?</item></list>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Joni:</hi> The lyrics of our first songs are stories from the imaginary fantasy world I created for the novel back then, but as our music has “evolved” so has our lyrics. The most recent songs are about battles, honour and one’s final faith. I’ve still tried to keep the fantasy aspect in those lyrics, though.</item></list></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>With music sung mainly in Finnish, do you worry that some international fans may be put off?</item></list>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Joni:</hi> I think it doesn’t really matter at all that we sing mainly in Finnish. Nowadays there’s more and more bands that choose to sing with their native language instead of English and it seems that many of those bands are getting more and more popular. Finnish is quite mystical and fascinating language, so I guess some foreign people like it even more that we sing in Finnish. We are proud that we are granted this opportunity to make our language more known outside Finland.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Antti:</hi> No, not at all. We have noticed that international fans, especially in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central%20Europe">Central Europe</ref> really enjoy Finnish language. They have said that it sounds really atmospheric and reminds them of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tolkien">Tolkiens</ref> elf-language. So it’s not any problem at all, I think!</item></list></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Will there be more music with lyrics in English or another language in light of your new worldwide deal, or are you sticking to your native language?</item></list>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Joni:</hi> I think we’ll keep Finnish as our main language, but there will be more songs in English in the future. I’d say maybe seven out of ten songs will have lyrics in Finnish and the rest would be in English then. It really depends pretty much of my mood. If I feel like writing in English I write in English and vice versa. Sometimes there’s periods when the poetrical river for Finnish is all dry and I’m forced to write the lyrics in English, hah hah. I think that was the main reason I wrote the first English lyrics. ☺</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Antti:</hi> In the future we will make songs both in English and Finnish.</item></list></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Folk metal has exploded in popularity over the last decade, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turisas">Turisas</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finntroll">Finntroll</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korpiklaani">Korpiklaani</ref> among others rising to prominence. What do you have to offer that other bands don't?</item></list>
</text>
