<text id="autogum_interview_doc1447" title="part6_Interview: Danny O'Brien of the Electronic Frontier Foundation" shortTile="partinterview-danny" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-01-24" dateModified="2012-02-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview%3A_Danny_O%27Brien_of_the_Electronic_Frontier_Foundation" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><p>[Danny O'Brien] I have a long answer to that, with my EFF hat off.</p>
<p>Okay, so the reason I'll take my EFF hat off to answer your question, is because I'm also involved in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open%20Rights%20Group">ORG</ref> which is one of those organisations in Europe. The conclusion is that advocacy needs resources. One of the strengths of EFF and other US advocacy groups is they are permanent, with a paid staff. <ref target="http://openrightsgroup.org">http://openrightsgroup.org</ref></p>
<p>I think that now there are sites like <ref target="http://www.pledgebank.com">http://www.pledgebank.com</ref> around, and facts like the Wikipedia funding drive show that we're getting to the point where we can turn volunteer organisations into groups that have that flexibility, plus financial resources. Which means you get to the situation where the group of volunteers who formed ORG can now work on projects like submitting to UK parliamentary inquiries: <ref target="http://www.openrightsgroup.org/orgwiki/index.php/APIG_DRM_Public_Inquiry">http://www.openrightsgroup.org/orgwiki/index.php/APIG_DRM_Public_Inquiry</ref></p>
<p>There are fantastic groups in Europe, like <ref target="http://www.edri.org/">EDRI</ref> and <ref target="http://www.ffii.org/">FFII</ref> and I think the time is now right for those groups to be given more resources by everyone. And I speak as someone who traditionally comes out in hives when money is mentioned. It's a big leap, but I think it's one we all have to work at getting right. Give to them, at exactly the same time as you join the EFF: <ref target="http://www.eff.org/support/">http://www.eff.org/support/</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Danny O'Brien puts EFF hat back on.</hi></p>
[Question] "Danny O'Brien "once successfully lobbied a cockney London pub to join Richard M. Stallman in a spontaneous demonstration of Bulgarian folk dance." Can you give details?"
<p>[Danny O'Brien] RMS is a great fan of folk-dancing, and was teaching me and some friends the dance moves to the Free Software Song in a pub in Shoreditch. Maybe it was the alcohol, all the allegedly viral nature of the GPL, but by the end, we had most of the pub doing them. He loves it, although recently I believe he's hurt his leg and can't do it so much any more</p>
[Question] Wikipedia was earlier attacked by a group, which has launched a website, claiming that Wikipedia should be upheld by law to have 100% factuality in their website (relating to an earlier case where a bogus biography was posted to Wikipedia).  What is the EFF's stance on the issue?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] I'm not sure of the site that you refer to, but obviously we'd support Wikipedia on this matter. We don't see any problem with Wikipedia's process.</p>
[Question] There is an article on de.wikipedia (German) about the hacker "Tron". His full offline name is included in the article. A German court has issued an injunction preventing the Wikipedia.de website (the website of the German Wikimedia Foundation) from linking to the de.wikipedia site, which is outside the jurisdiction of that court. What does EFF think about such extranational effects of local laws? Does a person's name, especially a figure as well known as Tron, deserve special privacy? The order was obtained based on a proposal by the deceased hacker's family. And it should be pointed out that the hacker's real name was known for a long time.
</text>
