<text id="autogum_interview_doc1211" title="part2_CanadaVOTES: NDP candidate Don Davies running in Vancouver Kingsway" shortTile="partcanadavotes-ndp" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-25" dateModified="2008-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_NDP_candidate_Don_Davies_running_in_Vancouver_Kingsway" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I would be a strong voice in Ottawa for all of these concerns, using the solid NDP platform as the base from which to amplify the voice of the constituency of Vancouver Kingsway.</p>
<p>The NDP would reverse some of the $50 billion in corporate tax cuts brought in under the Conservative government. Jack Layton's plan to move Canada forward starts with protecting good jobs and fostering new ones in a new energy economy. This is a plan for change that tackles the growing gap between the rich and the rest — with policies that'll help families like ours make ends meet.</p>
<p>The NDP has already launched a plan to phase in universal prescription drug coverage to protect today's families from soaring costs — including measures to reduce drug costs at source. The NDP have exposed and challenged Harper's failure to stop US-style privatization — calling for reliable federal funding linked to provincial commitments not to subsidize the expansion of for-profit care. Jack Layton has consistently advocated more long-term care spaces and expanded home care coverage — to offer seniors dignity in their later years and take pressure off scarce hospital beds.</p>
<p>The NDP would invest $1.45 billion in a national child-care network from coast to coast. Jack Layton noted that "[e]very day, families across our country struggle to find good quality child care they can afford. You shouldn't have to worry about whether your child is going to be safe and get good care…" The NDP would offer provinces and territories a binding commitment to stable, long-term funding for post-secondary education through a dedicated transfer, in return for an equally binding commitment to better access and lower tuition fees.</p>
<p>The NDP would create a cap and trade system to help combat global warming, which would ensure "that big polluters pay their fair share, and it makes it possible for more people to afford green solutions," explained Jack Layton.</p>
<p>The NDP plan to dedicate one cent a litre of the federal gas tax to transit would mean $100 million for Vancouver transit over four year and Vancouver's share of the transit revenue from our cap-and-trade plan would mean an additional $106 million over four years.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Are there any misconceptions about you, your leader, or your party and platform?</hi></p>
<p>The single most persistent misconception about our party is that it is fiscally irresponsible. However, <ref target="http://www.fin.gc.ca/frt/2005/frt05_e.pdf">a 2005 federal government report</ref> shows that NDP governments have the best fiscal track-record among all parties, balancing the books more than twice as often than Liberal governments. Manitoba's NDP government has posed surpluses every year it has been in office and Saskatchewan's NDP government posted 11 consecutive balanced budgets after ending a decade of Conservative mismanagement and corruption.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">There's a more ways than ever to get your message out, from the traditional campaign fliers and lawn signs, to new media like websites, Facebook, and YouTube. The tried-and-true routes get the message out to the masses much easier, but digital alternatives are much more measurable in how many are seeing or interacting with your campaign. What seems to be the most effective, from your experience?</hi></p>
</text>
