<text id="autogum_interview_doc1311" title="part8_Wikinews interviews former Salt Lake City mayor and 2012 presidential candidate Rocky Anderson" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-12-17" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Salt_Lake_City_mayor_and_2012_presidential_candidate_Rocky_Anderson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>He has reinforced this notion that there’s this narrow special aristocracy in this country, who are the most wealthy and the most powerful, and the contributors to his campaign, by the way, who aren’t going to be held accountable to the law while the rest of us oftentimes suffer just the most extreme consequences from the application of the laws, especially in the area of drugs, where tens of thousands, hundreds of thousands, people have in our prisons because of violations of our drug laws.</p>
<head id="The_GOP_race">The GOP race</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What is your take on the GOP field, particularly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jon%20Huntsman,%20Jr.">Jon Huntsman, Jr.</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</ref>, both of whom you’ve endorsed in past elections?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Rocky Anderson</hi>: They both have been good friends of mine. The Mitt Romney I knew is a very different Mitt Romney than the one who's been running for president. The Mitt Romney I knew believed in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roe%20v.%20Wade">Roe v. Wade</ref></hi>, that it came to the right result and with that ought to be established law and that we should just move on with it. This Mitt Romney, who, the last time he ran said we shouldn’t politicize <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Guantanamo_Bay_detention_camp">Guantanamo</ref>, he doesn’t seem to have any regard for human rights, he’s gone back and forth and back and forth…Well, he did it as governor before the time he announced that he was going to run for president. But he’s even done it while he’s been running for president, this time, in terms of climate change. Out of one side of his mouth, he’s talking about how climate change is a problem, we need to deal with it. By the way, George W. Bush even said that. And then later on, he says, well we don’t really know the causes of climate change. But, he knows very well the causes of climate change. He knows how the scientific community feels on that issue.  But he’s doing whatever he can to win the election.</p>
<figure><caption>Former Utah governor Jon Huntsman, Jr. Anderson referred to Huntsman as "a bright, good man."Image: United States Department of State.</caption></figure>
<p><p><figure><caption>Anderson addresses the GLBT community of Utah in 2005.Image: Jere Keys.</caption></figure></p>
<p>I think Jon Huntsman is on the whole very different than that. He stood by his views. He was governor of the state of Utah, advocating <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domestic%20partnership%20in%20the%20United%20States">domestic partnerships</ref>, that is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Equality%20before%20the%20law">equal treatment under the law</ref> for members of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/LGBT">GLBT</ref> community. And I say equal, wasn't quite equal because he still hasn’t reached a point where he embraces the idea of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Same-sex_marriage">marriage equality</ref> as I have for decades. And actually had marriage equality when I ran for Congress in 1996, it became a core part of the opposition against me and probably led to my defeat in 1996. But he’s stood up on these issues, he’s stood up on the issue of climate change when he was governor. I think it was fantastic when he stood up during a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20Party%20presidential%20debates,%202012">debate</ref> and talked about how the Republican Party should no longer be the anti-science party. What an amazing thing. I mean one would think the bar is set that low that it would be amazing, but in this environment right now, for him to say that to the Republican Party while he’s running for their nomination. And then of course he was one of only two people who had the moral courage and sense to say “we should never be torturing”, and that is so counter to our nation’s heritage from the very beginning <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20Washington">George Washington</ref> prohibited torture of British soldiers, and that’s been not only the law, but the ethic of our country from the very beginning. It’s only changed during this last decade and that’s part of a very dangerous trend toward an imperial presidency and the disregard for human rights, and it’s really so undermined our standing and not only undermined our standing, but created so much hatred toward the United States in many parts of the world.</p></p>
</text>
