<text id="autogum_interview_doc556" title="part8_Ingrid Newkirk, co-founder of PETA, on animal rights and the film about her life" shortTile="partingrid-newkirk" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-20" dateModified="2018-02-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ingrid_Newkirk%2C_co-founder_of_PETA%2C_on_animal_rights_and_the_film_about_her_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Controlled%20Atmosphere%20Killing">Controlled Atmosphere Killing</ref> means they are gassed in the boxes when they arrive at the slaughterhouse so that that they are not conscious when they are hung up on the shackles and have their legs broken.  So that they are not conscious when they go live into the scalding tank.  We have Wendy’s—their egg production is just disgusting.  They have battery cages for their hens, who are just crammed in.  [<hi rend="italic">Sighs</hi>].  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Covance">Covance</ref>, which is the world’s biggest testing lab.  You see them in the film.  They are the ones shoving the monkeys into the Plexiglas tubes and the monkeys are screaming and they are holding their arms behind their backs.  The universities who have grants from the federal government for animal research for the sheer reason that they want money for their football team and money for their President’s flowers in the office, they will not examine whether or not there are more sophisticated modern tests.</p>
<head id="Animal_Enterprise_Terrorism_Act">Animal Enterprise Terrorism Act</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Tell me how the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Animal%20Enterprise%20Terrorism%20Act">Animal Enterprise Terrorism Act</ref> impedes you, and what you are doing to defeat the Act.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Sooner or later we’ll have a test case.  It was designed specifically to thwart our undercover investigations.  That’s where it came out of.  It’s a slap shoot that has been made into a criminal action.  It’s a criminal action now in over a dozen states to videotape or audiotape inside an animal industry, which is just <hi rend="italic">extraordinary</hi> protection for one particularly section of society’s pursuits.  It also makes it a federal crime to remove documents, for example, even if those documents show wrong-doing on the part of the business.  You can’t even Xerox them and take them out to give to a reporter.  That’s a federal crime, now, in over twelve states.  It’s all designed so that you can’t get the goods on an industry that is hurting animals in violation of the law, and to make that information public without facing a jail sentence and a hefty fine.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Would you do a target investigation in a state where they have that act passed just to test its Constitutionality?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  We might well.  Because this is supposed to be a free country; there is supposed to be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free%20speech">free speech</ref> and a public spotlight on what’s happening in our name with our tax money.  At least if they are telling consumers, “Trust us, because we are being kind to the animals” because everyone knows now that a large percentage of consumers wants to know when they are buying something how animals are treated.  If they are stringing the consumer along and giving them a false security that animals weren’t harmed in the making of whatever it is, then I think the public has a right to know <hi rend="italic">exactly</hi> what is going on in those places.  That is in the public interest.</p>
</text>
