<text id="autogum_interview_doc1427" title="part2_Judging the Courts: Wikinews interviews Prof. Lawrence Douglas" shortTile="partjudging-courts" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-11-20" dateModified="2015-09-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Judging_the_Courts%3A_Wikinews_interviews_Prof._Lawrence_Douglas" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: The trial has been criticized by Saddam's defense lawyers as having a "pre-determined verdict". What is the line dividing a trial with a "pre-determined verdict" and a trial where there is a widespread belief that the accused is guilty? Can there be a fair trial in this latter circumstance?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: Clearly the likelihood of a guilty verdict cannot be a measure of the fairness of a trial.  If it were, then the strongest cases could be deemed the least fair.  It's important, then, to distinguish between the assumption of guilt, as a factual matter, and the presumption of innocence – the legal norm that requires the state to assume the burden of proving guilt, even in cases in which many people may assume that the accused is guilty.  The assumption of guilt can never replace the state's obligation to assume the burden of proof.  If it does, the trial is a farce.</p>
<head id="International_criminal_and_humanitarian_courts">International criminal and humanitarian courts</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: How significant is the Saddam trial to international criminal jurisprudence? Will it impact other trials?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: Taken in tandem with the Milosevic trial (which ended, after more than three years of trial, with the death of the former Yugoslav president in March), the Saddam trial makes clear how difficult it is to control the court behavior of former strongmen.  Saddam clearly took a page from Milosevic's playbook, mounting a defense of disruption that continuously challenged the legitimacy of the tribunal.  I think prosecutors and judges need to come up with new ways of dealing with such recalcitrant defendants.  As a further matter, I suppose the irregularities of the Saddam trial will lead some jurists to strengthen the call for international trials of former dictators; clearly, opponents of the death penalty will likewise petition in favor of relying on international courts to deal with the legacy of atrocious crimes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: Do international tribunals such as the ones set up to try crimes committed in the former Yugoslavia, Rwanda, Sierra Leone, Cambodia... etc do a good job? What have they succeeded in? What problems have they experienced?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: We should distinguish between international tribunals, such as the International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia (ICTY) and the International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda (ICTR) and the hybrid courts that have been constituted in Sierra Leone and now in Cambodia.  None of these courts have compiled perfect records, but mostly they have been quite effective.  Notwithstanding the missteps and disappointments associated with the Milosevic trial – the former president's death in March cheated the tribunal of the opportunity of ever passing judgment – the ICTY has brought other high level perpetrators to justice and has contributed importantly to the growth of international criminal law.  One problem that all these courts have faced are the start-up costs.  As ad hoc tribunals, these courts have been created out of nothing, and the cost of building courts, hiring staff, establishing competence has been extraordinarily high.  As a permanent institution, the International Criminal Court (ICC) promises to solve some of these problems.</p>
</text>
