<text id="autogum_interview_doc1391" title="part14_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<figure><caption>"<hi rend="bold">I hate to admit it. I always thought I would probably get killed before now. After I got stabbed in 1991 I was sure that if I got to forty, I would never make it to fifty. Now I’m fifty-three, which is probably why I work as hard as I do.</hi>"Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why do you think that happens?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Because they know that there is a market for it.  They know they can get air time for it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you ever do a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA">DNA</ref> test to see if you were related to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strom%20Thurmond">Strom Thurmond</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  No, I just accepted the documents; I never did the DNA.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you keep in contact with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Essie%20Mae%20Washington-Williams">Essie Mae Washington-Williams</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  I only met her one time.  Because again, I don’t know that we are related.  I know that my great-grandfather was a slave of the Thurmonds, I don’t know that there was any blood.  When they came and told me I went down to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Carolina">South Carolina</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edgefield,%20South%20Carolina">Edgefield</ref>, and visited the cemetery.  The cemetery at the First Baptist Church of Edgefield is all Sharptons—of course the white Sharptons—and Thurmonds.  While I was there, a man came up and said, “You know, the plantation that your great-grandfather worked on is still intact.  A doctor bought it and he didn’t change anything.  He told me if you’d like to see it we can go over there.”  It’s on Sharpton Road in Edgefield.  [<hi rend="italic">Sharpton shows Shankbone the photos of him at the plantation</hi>].  I look at it to remind me of how far we’ve come. [<hi rend="italic">Sharpton shows Shankbone photos of civil rights leaders and his family</hi>].  This is the last time James Brown was on stage at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apollo%20Theater">Apollo</ref>, to do my fiftieth birthday in 2004.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you ever think you’d reach fifty?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  No.  I hate to admit it.  I always thought I would probably get killed before now.  After I got stabbed in 1991 I was sure that if I got to forty, I would never make it to fifty.  Now I’m fifty-three, which is probably why I work as hard as I do.  I work 17, 18 hour days.  Rachel [Noerdlinger, his assistant] will tell you 20, but she’s lying because she feels I overwork.  I feel every day I live is a day I never expected to live, so I try to do everything I can.  I think that part of the problem with a lot of civil rights leaders is that this is the first generation that actually lived to be gray.  What do gray civil rights leaders do?  Because in the era before us, they were all dead by now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who are some up-and-coming civil rights leaders under thirty?</hi></p>
</text>
