<text id="autogum_interview_doc039" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Rocky De La Fuente, U.S. Democratic Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-03-29" dateModified="2016-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Rocky_De_La_Fuente%2C_U.S._Democratic_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Rocky De La Fuente, U.S. Democratic Party presidential candidate</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 31, 2016</hi></p>
<figure><caption>De La Fuente at the Lesser-Known Candidates Forum, January 2016. Image: Marc Nozell.</caption></figure>
<p>Businessman <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rocky_De_La_Fuente">Rocky De La Fuente</ref> took some time to speak with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> about his campaign for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democratic Party</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2016">2016 presidential nomination</ref>.</p>
<p>The 61-year-old De La Fuente resides in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/San_Diego,_California">San Diego</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref>, grew up in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tijuana">Tijuana</ref>, and owns multiple businesses and properties throughout the world. Since getting his start in the automobile industry, De La Fuente has branched out into the banking and real estate markets.  Despite not having held or sought political office previously, he has been involved in politics, serving as the first-ever <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hispanic">Hispanic</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/superdelegate">superdelegate</ref> to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1992%20Democratic%20National%20Convention">1992 Democratic National Convention</ref>. </p>
<p>De La Fuente entered the 2016 presidential race last October largely due to his dissatisfaction with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</ref> front-runner <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref>.  He argues he is a more accomplished businessman than Trump, and attacks Trump as "a clown," "a joke," "dangerous," and "in the same category as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Adolf_Hitler">Hitler</ref>."  Nevertheless, De La Fuente's business background begets comparisons with Trump. The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Alaska">Alaskan</ref> <hi rend="italic">Midnight Sun</hi> blog described him as the Democrats' "own Donald Trump."</p>
<p>While receiving only minimal media coverage, he has campaigned actively, and according to the latest <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Federal_Election_Commission">Federal Election Commission</ref> filing, loaned almost <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Dollar">US$</ref> 4 million of his own money to the campaign.  He has qualified for 48 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic%20Party%20presidential%20primaries,%202016">primary and caucus</ref> ballots, but has not yet obtained any delegates to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2016%20Democratic%20National%20Convention">2016 Democratic National Convention</ref>.  Thus far, according to the count at <hi rend="italic">The Green Papers</hi>, De La Fuente has received 35,406 votes, or 0.23% of the total votes cast.  He leads among the many lesser-known candidates but trails both Senator <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bernie_Sanders">Bernie Sanders</ref> who has received nearly 6.5 million votes and front-runner <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hillary_Clinton">Hillary Clinton</ref> who has just shy of 9 million votes.</p>
<p>With <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:William_S._Saturn">William S. Saturn</ref>‎, De La Fuente discusses his personal background, his positions on political issues, his current campaign for president, and his political future.  </p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<head id="Background">Background</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are some of your achievements in your business career?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Rocky De La Fuente</hi>: From my perspective, my greatest achievements in business are tied to the people and families I have helped. I've had the good fortune to create dozens of business that created thousands of jobs across the United States as well as in other countries. I always paid a fair wage, provided access to healthcare, and tried to create opportunities for advancement for those who demonstrated the desire to improve their lot in life.</p>
<p><figure><caption>Aerial view of De La Fuente's hometown San Diego. Image: U.S. Navy.</caption></figure></p>
<p>If you're asking for a more traditional answer with respect to what I have personally done, at the age of twenty, I got a job selling automobiles. Less than two years later, I became the General Manager of a dealership. Two years after that, I acquired my first dealership and, over the next 16 years, I added 27 more dealerships to my portfolio. And at the age of 28, I was honored to be elected by my peers in that industry as Chairman of the National Dealer Council for the third largest Automotive Company in the world at the time.</p></p>
</text>
