<text id="autogum_interview_doc1126" title="part4_Dalai Lama's representative talks about China, Tibet, Shugden and the next Dalai Lama" shortTile="partdalai-lamas-representative" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-13" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dalai_Lama%27s_representative_talks_about_China%2C_Tibet%2C_Shugden_and_the_next_Dalai_Lama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<hi rend="bold">They can’t keep their Panchen Lama in Tibet. They tried to bring him to his monastery many times but people would not see him. How can you have a religious leader like that? When a Panchen Lama goes to his monastery thousands and thousands of people will come from all over Tibet and outside. He is an important Buddhist leader. But when they brought their Panchen Lama, they had to force government officials and the public to attend certain public functions.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right"><hi rend="bold">—Tashi Wangdi</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So at age six, Gedhun Choekyi Nyima just disappeared?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  When the final decision came close, there was a lack of willingness on the part of the Chinese leadership to involve His Holiness.  Unfortunately, we then ended up having two people.  Now we don’t know because since the age of six he has disappeared.  It is totally ridiculous on the part of the Chinese officials, who say he is kept in hiding at the request of his parents, for his security.  That makes no sense.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And nobody knows where he is.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  No, nobody.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think will happen to him?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  I have no idea.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think he is aware of his status?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  I’m sure.  He is mature now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But at six years of age, it is probable he was not able to completely comprehend the fight between the two governments over who he was and what role he is to play.  If they were to take him at the age of six and place him somewhere in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manchuria">Manchuria</ref>, re-educate him and deny him his heritage, it is possible he does not even know who he is?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  I suppose.  It’s speculative, but there are apprehensions on the part of the Tibetans that this was the plan for taking him away and keeping him in isolation.  To <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/brainwash">brainwash</ref> him.  At the same time, by deduction, one could say neither he nor his parents and other relatives have given in to the Chinese government.  Because if they had, they would have made some kind of public statement to say, “We do not think he is Panchen Lama, we have been treated well and we are ordinary people.”  Nothing has happened like that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  There have been no rumors, no words through the grapevine as to his status?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  No.  The logical deduction would be there is no cooperation from the Panchen Lama’s side to follow the official line.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That’s pretty amazing when you consider it.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  It is amazing!  It’s also very silly.  Unnecessary.  It’s a religious matter.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reincarnation">Reincarnation</ref> is purely religious, and it is a very unique tradition in Tibet.  If that is allowed to be followed-through, it is the best way of winning the hearts and minds of people.  It’s the best diplomacy and a wise way of dealing with things.  Now they have screwed it up.  Unnecessary.</p>
</text>
