<text id="autogum_interview_doc1176" title="part0_Canada's Etobicoke—Lakeshore (Ward 5) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-etobicokelakeshore" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-10-19" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Etobicoke%E2%80%94Lakeshore_%28Ward_5%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Canada's Etobicoke—Lakeshore (Ward 5) city council candidates speak</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 30, 2006</hi></p>
<p>On November 13, Torontonians will be heading to the polls to vote for their ward's councillor and for mayor. Among Toronto's ridings is Etobicoke—Lakeshore (Ward 5). Two candidates responded to Wikinews' requests for an interview. This ward's candidates include John Chiappetta, Joseph Mignone, Peter Milczyn (incumbent), Arthur Roszak, and Bojidar Tchernev.</p>
<p>Interviewed are newcomer <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada's_Etobicoke—Lakeshore_(Ward_5)_city_council_candidates_speak#Joseph_Mignone">Joseph Mignone</ref>, and incumbent <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada's_Etobicoke—Lakeshore_(Ward_5)_city_council_candidates_speak#Peter_Milczyn_(incumbent)">Peter Milczyn</ref>. Click on either of their names to read their responses.</p>
<p>For more information on the election, read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto%20municipal%20election,%202006">Toronto municipal election, 2006</ref>.</p>
<head id="Joseph_Mignone">Joseph Mignone</head>
<p>37-year-old Joseph Mignone is employed in quality assurance.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The three most important issues in my campaign are the issue of the six point interchange proposal.  The city will spend $35 million dollars on an intersection that already works well.  Secondly, not only environmental concerns in general but how pollution and smog might be increased because of the increased traffic lights.  Accessibility and accountability at city hall must be addressed.  I believe residents should have a voice in matters that concern their neighbourhoods.  Too often we see that the community might object to a certain matter, but the matter in question still gets council approval.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The one election issue that is most relevant is the one mentioned above.  Residents believe that $35 million could be better spent elsewhere, rather than on intersection that may or not need reconfiguration depending on redevelopment that will occur in the area.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have chosen to get involved in the political process because I believe I can make a difference at city hall.  Secondly, I believe that representing the people of the ward would be an honour and consequently, their views would be expressed by my voting record.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> This is the ward that I have called home my entire life.  How could I represent any other ward?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Community is important.  I frequent local business to promote their well being.  Furthermore, I can be seen at local baseball and hockey games cheering on the kids.  I think that local organizations that promote health and fitness for kids is vital for the community.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Toronto is the greatest city in the country.  It is the city that has it all.  There is a reason why half the immigrants that come to Canada settle in Toronto. The diversity that Toronto offers can not be equivocated in any other city in the world.</p>
</text>
