<text id="autogum_interview_doc1221" title="part4_The Onion: An interview with 'America's Finest News Source'" shortTile="partthe-onion-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2013-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Onion%3A_An_interview_with_%27America%27s_Finest_News_Source%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Kelly?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  That is Kelly.  He has a very unique take on what is going on in the world, and it does tend to upset some people, but that’s the job of an editorial cartoonist, to be a provocateur.
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  That’s right.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Kelly is actually <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ward%20Sutton">Ward Sutton</ref>, correct?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  It might be…I don’t know…
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  It’s Kelly.  As a newspaper, it’s our responsibility to give equal voice to everyone, so we don’t shut out one viewpoint just because he is controversial.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  For a long time, that cartoon confused me, which perhaps speaks to the humor of it.  I thought it was a real right-wing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian%20Zionism">Christian Zionist</ref> syndicated cartoonist who truly exists and that you all were putting it in The Onion out of a sense of irony.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  We do have one cartoon that runs in the paper called <hi rend="italic">The Leftersons</hi>, which is a syndicated cartoon from a right wing guy who writes about this lefty family and all the trouble they get in for being so far to the left.  But no, Kelly is unique to <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi>.</p>
<head id="The_photojournalism">The photojournalism</head>
<figure><caption>The Onion's photojournalists: "They are wizards."Image source: The Onion.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How does your graphics department find the people for news stories and come up with the images?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  We’ve always had a two person graphics team and it has always been about—depending on the graphic—going out and finding the right person or creating the right situation.  Sometimes taking an original image to a little <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Photoshop">Photoshop</ref> photojournalism to create the right photo and using the photos that are out there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are the images created using professional models or people on the street?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  Always people on the street and never professional models.  There’s always that element of reality to it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you approach people?  Do you ask them if they want to be in an <hi rend="italic">Onion</hi> article?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  Everyone in this office and our other <hi rend="italic">Onion</hi> office in the city has been in the paper at least once.  Most of their roommates, siblings, loved ones, neighbors, will always end up in there some time.  We usually pull them from friends and family of <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi>.  A lot of our Op-Ed headshots are people who have come to <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi>.  Our photographers will grab them and ask them to pose for some headshots and tell them they’ll end up in <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> some day.  We don’t really use any professional network.  It’s casual—people who like <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> and know us.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  One of my favorites is of a <ref target="http://www.theonion.com/content/node/28047">troubled teen whose parents are always arguing</ref> and it shows them shooting the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double%20bird">double bird</ref>.  So your graphics department will set up the scene and direct them to do that?</hi></p>
</text>
