<text id="autogum_interview_doc945" title="part0_Interview with Sean Semper-Whyte, City Council candidate for Ward 6 in Mississauga, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-sean" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-09-23" dateModified="2008-01-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Sean_Semper-Whyte%2C_City_Council_candidate_for_Ward_6_in_Mississauga%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with Sean Semper-Whyte, City Council candidate for Ward 6 in Mississauga, Canada</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 23, 2006</hi></p>
<p>The upcoming <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mississauga%20municipal%20election,%202006">2006 Mississauga municipal election</ref>, to be held November 13, features an array of candidates looking to represent their wards in city council.</p>
<p>Wikinews contributor Nicholas Moreau has contacted as many candidates as possible, including <hi rend="bold">Sean Semper-Whyte</hi>, asking them to answer common questions sent in an email. There is no incumbent in the ward; also competing for the position are Matanat Khan, Olive Rose Steele, Terry Pierce, Jr., Ron Starr, and former MP Carolyn Parrish.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> List the three most important issues in your campaign, and briefly explain why these are important.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> 1. Long-term Care and access for seniors, which includes transportation for seniors around the region.</p>
<p>We have an aging region, which is also evident on council.  We must have structure in place to anticipate the needs of our aged community and the strategic plans to acquire funding from federal and provincial budgets to meet those needs.  If we are not able to meet the needs of this often, vulnerable area of our community, we neglect the very foundation of our current community legacy.  This important acknowledgement of the seniors, within our community, also helps us to build for the future of our community.  This will establish a community best practice, and perspective of real security for those often twilight (uncertain) years of our vulnerable aged citizens.</p>
<p>2. Overall Safety and Security:</p>
<p>"Our age is one of trouble and tension and violence.  It is also one of great progress and achievement. It holds both the promise of a far better life for all men and the threat of no life at all for mankind.  Which is it to be?"  Lester B. Pearson.</p>
<p>What has been through our society has been consistent even to today.  Though some would say crime numbers are down, they also in the same breath acknowledge violent crimes are up.  This is not acceptable to me, nor due I believe the community is accepting of this.  It would seem we have not learned very much if we are not able to make change to age old issues.  This is the very reason we need to see council have a greater youthful presence, as we look to utilize resources previously unavailable to address these very issues.  This issue identifies the whole community is at risk, due to the emotional disturbance of a few within.</p>
<p>3. Building Growth:</p>
<p>This is an exhaustive agenda; which speaks to individuals, families, neighbourhoods, Wards, City, Region, Province, and Nation.  It all starts with the individual; we must all choose to be greater than the sum of our individual abilities through collaborative partnerships, which speaks of communion (the act of sharing or holding in common participation).</p>
</text>
