<text id="autogum_interview_doc528" title="part1_Billy West, voice of Ren and Stimpy, Futurama, on the rough start that shaped his life" shortTile="partbilly-west-voice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2013-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Billy_West%2C_voice_of_Ren_and_Stimpy%2C_Futurama%2C_on_the_rough_start_that_shaped_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="The_use_of_celebrities_for_voiceovers">The use of celebrities for voiceovers</head>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>:  You’re known for speaking about the use of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Celebrity">famous actors</ref> to do <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voice-over">voice-over</ref>. What is your central problem with their use?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Billy%20West">Billy West</ref>:</hi>  My problem is that if they were judged by the same standards we were, that we have to try and get work with, they would be pretty piss poor as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voice%20actor">voice performers</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What standards are those?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  The standards are that you have a really special voice that you can go around and do that voice and make a living that people just instantly love it. Nobody is just instantly in love with the usual suspects. Voices that we see in the cartoon movies now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robin%20Williams">Robin Williams</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  No, he's different, he understands character. I mean he understands characterization and voice changes. And so does <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike%20Myers">Mike Myers</ref> and so does <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eddie%20Murphy">Eddie Murphy</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerry%20Seinfeld">Jerry Seinfeld</ref> as well in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bee%20Movie">Bee Movie</ref></hi>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  No, that’s not it because he‘s doing a character that looks exactly like him and sounds exactly like him. I mean, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Will_Smith">Will Smith</ref> does characters that are drawn to look like him and sound like him. I wish I had that luxury. Nobody draws a character that looks like me and sounds like me for me to just step in and be the perfect person for the role. You know what I mean?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What’s the solution? Not to do characters around stars?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  The thing is, I don’t have an issue with the fact that these movies are being made. If I could audition for them and I didn’t get them, I still wouldn’t have an issue with them. But this is the thing: they audition us for these movies and then they play it for the A-list people, for these celebrities, so they can strip my talents’ abilities and kind of toss them over to the celebrity just to make it look better than it would be. And I’m not a teacher. Not a paid teacher. I don’t like that stuff.</p>
<hi rend="bold">They audition us for these movies and then they play it for the A-list people, for these celebrities, so they can strip my talents’ abilities and kind of toss them over to the celebrity just to make it look better than it would be.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right"><hi rend="bold">—West on laying down cartoon characters in auditions, only to have a celebrity end up doing the voice with the quirks West's voice introduced.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They’ll have you come in, or someone of your caliber come in, and actually shape the voice around the character and then they’ll present it to the celebrity as the template?</hi></p>
</text>
