<text id="autogum_interview_doc746" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Lloyd Helferty, Thornhill" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-07" dateModified="2013-04-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_Party_candidate_Lloyd_Helferty%2C_Thornhill" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>I have the most through grasp of the issues that will truly affect the population in the long-term and understand what needs to be done to help mitigate the worst affects of them.  The other candidates are running to get elected and will say whatever is necessary to bring them into a position where people will vote for them, even if they do not personally believe in all aspects of their own Party policies or platform.  I do, on the other hand, thoroughly believe in the Green Party Values from which we base our policies and platform and will always work toward achieving them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>The voters believe that transportation (increased transit/easing gridlock), school funding (faith-based, status-quo or merging the two systems) and urban intensification (development) are the three most important issues, along with Health Care (access to Doctors) being of general concern.</p>
<p>Personally, the issues of transportation and development are very closely interlinked with the issues of health and energy.  They are all a consequence of our addiction to oil and to our energy-intensive lifestyles.  We are living further and further from where we work, shop and play, yet we insist on driving everywhere to do everything, not really because there are no options, but because this is generally the most convenient way to do it given the circumstances under which we insist on living.  Much of our problems are a consequence of our built environment and our fixation on designing our living environments to accommodate automobiles.</p>
<p>Many of our health problems are a consequence of our sedentary and convenience-based (service-based/fast-food) lifestyles as well as the stresses we are putting on our bodies [in various ways, including through chemical loading and self-induced (mental) stresses, among others].</p>
<p>I believe that we need to rapidly wean ourselves from the one thing which makes our lives so convenient, pollutes our environment with toxic chemicals, sours our air, allows us to pave over our best farmland and expand outward incessantly in a manic urge to “grow our economy” for no other reason than to expand for the sake of expansion: oil.  The discovery of the power of oil has been on of the greatest assets to mankind this millennium, but we are at a juncture in human history where oil is now becoming our nemesis, and is no longer making our lives better.  No further improvements to our lifestyles can be had be increasing the number of people driving nor by increasing the number of houses being built (for we are paving over our very best farmland where we will need to grow more of our food in the not-so-distant future and/or destroying essential habitat that is necessary to maintain the proper functioning of our ecosystems), nor by increasing the density of houses (for this only increases the concentration of the pollutants and increases the burdens on our infrastructure, including roads, transit, water, sewer, electricity and other essential services).  We need to undertake a crash-course in (energy) “conservation” while at the same time looking at restoring the proper functioning of both our human and natural ‘ecosystems’ in order to come back into “balance” with the natural world’s (including the human mind’s) ability to accommodate our (massive) presence.  This requires a new set of thinking, which I believe many members of the Green Party have started to grasp and understand and is reflected in both our values and our policies.</p>
</text>
