<text id="autogum_interview_doc1315" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Darcy Richardson, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-11-24" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Darcy_Richardson%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">In 1980, to the surprise of many, Senator McCarthy endorsed Republican <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ronald_Reagan">Ronald Reagan</ref> for president.  Did you agree with this decision?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Richardson</hi>: No, I didn't agree with that endorsement.  In fact, I had campaigned for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ted%20Kennedy">Ted Kennedy</ref> in the New Hampshire and Pennsylvania primaries earlier that spring and later ran for statewide office in Pennsylvania on a ticket headed by environmentalist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barry%20Commoner">Barry Commoner</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Citizens_Party_(United_States,_1980s)">Citizens Party</ref> nominee for president.  Some Democrats never forgave Gene for endorsing Reagan.  I wasn't one of them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You are (or were at one time) a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Boston_Tea_Party_(political_party)">Boston Tea Party</ref>, a minor third party whose platform supports "reducing the size, scope and power of government at all levels and on all issues, and opposes increasing the size, scope and power of government at any level, for any purpose." Do you agree with this platform?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Richardson</hi>: My involvement with the Boston Tea Party — a freedom-oriented, limited government entity — was relatively short-lived.  I assisted them a bit here in Florida because of Tom Knapp's personal involvement.  Tom, a self-styled <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anarchism%20in%20the%20United%20States">anarchist</ref> and original thinker, had founded the party shortly after the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libertarian_Party_(United_States)">Libertarian Party</ref>'s mid-term convention in 2006.  An edgy and contemplative guy, Tom is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libertarianism%20in%20the%20United%20States">libertarian</ref> writer and activist for whom I have tremendous respect.  He's one of the smartest people I know and is also probably one of the most talented writers that I've ever encountered.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Which presidential candidates have you supported over the past twenty years?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Richardson</hi>: There are probably too many to mention here, but Eugene McCarthy, who sought the Democratic presidential nomination again in 1992, and U.S. Rep. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dennis_Kucinich">Dennis Kucinich</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ohio">Ohio</ref> would be the two that I've been most enthusiastic about during the past twenty years.  We need more Democrats like them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How have your political views changed in the past twenty years?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Richardson</hi>: We all change, of course, but my political views have always remained consistently progressive.</p>
<head id="Policy">Policy</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If you had been elected president in 2008, what would you have done differently than Barack Obama?</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Richardson.Image: Darcy Richardson.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Darcy Richardson</hi>: The fact that President Obama initially appointed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lawrence%20Summers">Larry Summers</ref> as chairman of his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20National%20Economic%20Council">White House Economic Council</ref> shortly after taking office, should have given everybody pause.  Summers is probably more responsible for the country’s current economic mess than any other individual.</p>
<p>As <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bill_Clinton">President Clinton</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Secretary%20of%20the%20Treasury">Secretary of the Treasury</ref> from 1999 to January 2001, Summers shaped and pushed the financial deregulation that unleashed the near-collapse of Wall Street in the autumn of 2008, particularly when he pushed through the repeal of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glass-Steagall%20Act">Glass-Steagall Act</ref> of 1933 during the final years of the Clinton Administration — legislation, as you know, that had prohibited banks from doing both commercial and investment banking.</p>
</text>
