<text id="autogum_interview_doc1208" title="Wikinews interviews Great Britain men's national wheelchair basketball player Joni Pollock" shortTile="wikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-07-20" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Great_Britain_men%27s_national_wheelchair_basketball_player_Joni_Pollock" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Great Britain men's national wheelchair basketball player Joni Pollock</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 25, 2012</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homebush%20Bay">Homebush Bay</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_South_Wales">New South Wales</ref> —
<hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> sat down with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">Great Britain</ref> men's national <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wheelchair_basketball">wheelchair basketball</ref> player Joni Pollock before a practice session at the Rollers &amp; Gliders World Challenge in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sydney">Sydney</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption> Pollock during the interview Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Bidgee">Bidgee</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption> Wikinews reporter LauraHale interviewing Pollock Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Bidgee">Bidgee</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Pollock showing his tattoos Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Bidgee">Bidgee</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Wikinews reporters <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:LauraHale">LauraHale</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Bidgee">Bidgee</ref> interview Great Britain men's national wheelchair basketball player Joni Pollock</caption></figure>
<p>British-born Pollock was born with the condition <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/spina%20bifida">spina bifida</ref>. He explained he could walk with difficulty up until age twelve or thirteen, after which he began using a wheelchair. Shortly after this, he began playing wheelchair basketball. He attended a disabilities tournament for children with disabilities in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref>, where he tried both wheelchair basketball, since he came from a town where team sports were popular; and wheelchair tennis, as he'd played with an able-bodied friend. Ultimately, he chose wheelchair basketball as it was a team sport.  </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> asked Pollock about being loud towards his team mates during the match on July 20 between the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia_men's_national_wheelchair_basketball_team">Rollers</ref> and the Great Britain <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Great_Britain_men's_national_wheelchair_basketball_team">Bulldogs</ref>.  He said he was out of wheelchair basketball for nine months due to a pressure sore and surgery on his shoulder, and has been making a comeback since January, with the doctors and physiotherapists giving him the all-clear in April. On that night, he said, the Australian team used bullying tactics and some of his teammates on the British team didn't step up to win the game. He also said that no matter what team his team plays against, he has a target on his back because of his calibre of playing in the game, and his team failed to to understand it that night, leaving him frustrated with his team and himself; and, he hates coming to Australia during a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paralympics">Paralympic</ref> year since the home town —that is, Australian— referees do not protect the visiting team from the home team's dirty playing, which puts the British team's gold medal prospects in jeopardy.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> also asked Pollock his opinions regarding <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oscar%20Pistorius">Oscar Pistorius</ref>. Pollock believes Pistorius shouldn't be competing in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Olympics">Olympics</ref> if other Paralympic athletes can't compete. He also mentioned reservations about certain technical aspects, such as whether Pistorius would be the same height if he still had his legs rather then his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prosthesis">prosthetic</ref> legs. Asked about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/4.5%20point%20player#Beyond_4.5">5 point players</ref> playing in wheelchair basketball, he said he believes 5 point players can play with other point players but not in the Paralympics, and said 5 point players currently play in the domestic league but not at the elite level, to boost the number of players participating and to help the development of the game.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> also questioned him about tattoos worn by members of the British team. In previous years, he said, only one or two forwards had tattoos, but now almost everyone has one as having tattoos is currently in fashion. He said he got his first tattoo at the age of sixteen and only recently had it removed. He also has tattoos on his right arm, depicting the logos of the Paralympics and World championships in which he competed.</p>
<p>Pollocks's team begins its <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2012_Summer_Paralympics">London campaign</ref> on August 30, against the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref> men's national wheelchair basketball team.</p>
</text>
