<text id="autogum_interview_doc715" title="part0_Author of My Billion Year Contract reflects on life in elite Scientology group" shortTile="partauthor-billion" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-13" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_of_My_Billion_Year_Contract_reflects_on_life_in_elite_Scientology_group" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Author of My Billion Year Contract reflects on life in elite Scientology group</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 14, 2010</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> interviewed author Nancy Many about her book <hi rend="italic">My Billion Year Contract</hi>, and asked her about life working in the elite <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology">Scientology</ref> group known as the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sea%20Org">Sea Org</ref>". Many joined Scientology in the early 1970s, and after leaving in 1996 she later testified against the organization. Published in October, Many's book has gone on to become one of the top selling new books on Scientology at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon.com">Amazon.com</ref>.</p>
<head id="Background">Background</head>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">My Billion Year Contract</hi> by Nancy Many Image: <ref target="http://mybillionyearcontract.com/">Nancy Many</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Scientology was founded by writer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L.%20Ron%20Hubbard">L. Ron Hubbard</ref> in 1952. At the time Many joined in the early 1970s, she was a college student attending <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salem%20State%20College">Salem State College</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref>. She agreed to become a member of the elite Scientology group known as the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sea%20Org">Sea Org</ref>" in 1972 – the title of her book refers to a document she signed when joining that group. </p>
<p>She moved to Scientology's base of operations in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clearwater,%20Florida">Clearwater</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Florida">Florida</ref>, and rose to a high-ranking position within the organization. Many describes how she recruited others into the organization, and sold Scientology products to celebrities. She participated in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intelligence%20agency">intelligence operations</ref> as a spy working for a secret unit within Scientology, and she writes that she covertly became part of the mental-health-care community in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston,%20Massachusetts">Boston, Massachusetts</ref>.</p>
<p>Many recounts how Scientology executives decided to remove her from her leadership position within the organization. As laid out in the book, she was instructed to reside in a parking garage, remove herself from family, and perform hard labor. Her account highlights she was ordered to perform these tasks by Scientology officials whilst five-months pregnant. These experiences led her to later have a mental breakdown and eventually leave Scientology.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">My Billion Year Contract</hi> was first published in October. Since then it has risen to the second spot among recent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bestseller">best selling books</ref> about Scientology on the website <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon.com">Amazon.com</ref> – the number one spot is held by Marc Headley's book, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blown%20for%20Good">Blown for Good</ref></hi>. </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Catholic Online</hi> associate editor and former Archbishop of the Charismatic Episcopal Church, Randy Sly, compared <hi rend="italic">My Billion Year Contract</hi> to other insider accounts by former Scientologists, including Headley's and that of Monica Pignotti. "Their books and essays, along with many others, have publicly called into question a number of Scientology beliefs, claims and practices over many years," wrote Sly.</p>
<p>In an article this month about the book for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Boston%20Phoenix">The Boston Phoenix</ref></hi>, Chris Faraone wrote, "even if just some of her trials really happened [...] her new memoir might <hi rend="italic">still</hi> be the most shocking nonfiction work featured at this week's American Library Association (ALA) Midwinter Meeting in Boston." Faraone commented, "<hi rend="italic">My Billion Year Contract</hi> is a horror story."</p>
</text>
