<text id="autogum_interview_doc1105" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Tad Brudzinski, Newmarket-Aurora" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-02" dateModified="2007-12-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Tad_Brudzinski%2C_Newmarket-Aurora" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Tad Brudzinski, Newmarket-Aurora</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 2, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tad Brudzinski</hi> is running for the Family Coalition Party in the Ontario provincial election, in the Newmarket-Aurora riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>He did not answer the question "Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your riding? To the province as a whole?"</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I had enough of the political circus on the provincial and federal level and was tired of having only a choice of a smaller evil, when voting for politicians, that were not representing me, nor the people I associate with, and who (not even sharing my values) were not going to keep their campaign commitments anyway.  The political landscape has been shared by overpresent, virtually monopolistic parties, that compete with each other in degrees of corruption and levels of scandal scoring.</p>
<p>The reality of life in Ontario is quite different from the Canada of my dreams and the gap continues to grow.  It has costed me a great deal of effort to arrive in this fine country in December 1989 and I do not want to let it be wasted.  Therefore I jumped at the opportunity to have a chance to positively change the politics of Ontario, by becoming a candidate at the Newmarket-Aurora Electorial Riding.</p>
<p>In my opinion we cannot afford to stay away from politics anymore.  We have to act, while the opportunity is there.  People like myself need to regain our voice in this province, as we have been ignored for too long. We must change and regain our democratic right to participate in the government decisions, which affect us on a large scale at both, public and (more and more in the) private areas of our lives.  We need to be represented by individuals, who would stand for the values we commonly share, and would work with our best interest in mind.  I believe it is up to us to have our voices heard and acted upon in the provincial government.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?</hi></p>
</text>
