<text id="autogum_interview_doc982" title="part0_Canada's Scarborough East (Ward 43) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-scarborough" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-23" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Scarborough_East_%28Ward_43%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Canada's Scarborough East (Ward 43) city council candidates speak</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 4, 2006</hi></p>
<p>On November 13, Torontonians will be heading to the polls to vote for their ward's councillor and for mayor. Among Toronto's ridings is Scarborough East (Ward 43). One candidates responded to Wikinews' requests for an interview. This ward's candidates include Paul Ainslie, Amarjeet Chhabra, Mujeeb Khan, <hi rend="bold">Glenn Kitchen</hi>, John Laforet, Abdul Patel, Jim Robb, and Kumar Sethi.</p>
<p>For more information on the election, read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto%20municipal%20election,%202006">Toronto municipal election, 2006</ref>.</p>
<head id="Glenn_Kitchen">Glenn Kitchen</head>
<p>54-year-old <hi rend="bold">Glenn Kitchen</hi> has been a carpenter for 30 years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Our Youth: Our youth cannot suffer another cut to their educational programs. The results of the cutbacks to after school programs are showing their negative effects. If our youth do not have positive activities to participate in, they are more likely to be involved in negative activities. We need to re-introduce and re-open after school programs that have been closed. After school programs need to be run by staff and councillors who will act as positive role models and help our youth to find their way to positive choices. Our youth deserve better than what this city is currently providing them with.</p>
<p>Public Transit: Public transit in this ward is either non-existent or very limited. Navigating through this community is very difficult, and in many cases means numerous transfers. Scarborough has been given the short end of the transit line too many times. People in Scarborough want to travel within their community; they need to go grocery shopping, to go to work, to take their children to school. TTC needs to recognize these needs and work with Scarborough to create a more extensive route system to service people in this community.</p>
<p>Garbage: As the city of Toronto grows, the amount of waste we produce also grows. Looking into the future, we cannot rely on the methods we have used in the past. We must create new and innovative ways to deal with our waste. We must look at the waste as a resource, using every recyclable product to preserve materials that can be re-used. In order to be effective we must require all residents to contribute to an extensive and responsible recycling system. All houses, apartments, condominiums, as well as, commercial residents can participate and help lower our garbage levels. We must work as a team to ensure that we are being responsible with our waste.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Our Youth. As new families move into this community, they are bringing their young children. The children in this community now, will be our youth in the future and we must help them to grow into positive members of the community. As I stated earlier, youth need positive activities, not just a basketball court or field, with no councillors. Our children need leaders, coaches, and role models to mentor them.  The children need clubs for homework, reading, chess, music, dance, and sports.  Our children are the future of this area and we must help them grow to be positive members of society.</p>
</text>
