<text id="autogum_interview_doc1370" title="part2_One year on: IFALPA's representative to ICAO, pilot and lawyer on ongoing prosecution of Garuda Indonesia Flight 200 pilot" shortTile="partone-year--ifalpas" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-08" dateModified="2014-04-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/One_year_on%3A_IFALPA%27s_representative_to_ICAO%2C_pilot_and_lawyer_on_ongoing_prosecution_of_Garuda_Indonesia_Flight_200_pilot" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Early in February Mr Komar was arrested; he has subsequently been charged with manslaughter charges which carry a maximum sentence of five years' imprisonment. The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>-based <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International%20Federation%20of%20Air%20Line%20Pilots%20Associations">International Federation of Air Line Pilots Associations</ref> (IFALPA) issued a press release condemning this move, saying that further investigations are needed into the crash, and that criminal proceedings could prevent an accurate version of events from ever being known. Specifically, the release said that "IFALPA believes that the circumstances of the accident as set forth in the final report of the Indonesian investigation authority leaves many serious questions concerning the crew actions prior to the accident. Central to these concerns are the underlying reasons for the reported behavior of Captain Marwoto Komar. Experienced pilots have considerable difficulty in attempting to explain what is reported in the context of normal airline operations. The Federation believes that the explanations proffered by the report do not square with the collective experience of our members." The release went on to state the opinion that prosecution may bring total foreclosure to the case and could only be counterproductive. It also said "He remains a professional who was involved in an unfortunate tragedy."</p>
<p>One possible explanation had previously been suggested by the head of the Garuda pilots association, Stephanus Geraldus. He said that marital problems between Mr Komar and his wife Norma Andriani were "common knowledge" and was backed up by an industry analyst and pilot who said he believed the couple had been arguing late into the night, and expressed concern that the report had not addressed psychological issues. Mr Geraldus also said sleep deprivation could have contributed, with the flight crew reporting for duty at 4:30 am and the flight departing an hour and a half later.</p>
<p>The report had hinted at problems, saying The pilot was probably emotionally aroused because his conscious awareness moved from the relaxed mode “singing” to the heightened stressfulness of the desire to reach the runway by making an excessively steep and fast, unstabilised approach,” and "His attention was fixated or channelised on landing the aircraft on the runway and he either did not hear, or disregarded the GPWS alerts, and warnings, and calls from the copilot to go around." It is also known that Mr Komar had been under police surveillance, during which time he was receiving psychological treatment. </p>
<p>The Indonesian Pilot's Association has also said that the criminal prosecution should be avoided, arguing that the only people who can judge whether mistakes were made in aviation are those professionally involved and not the police. There were protests in Jakarta demanding his release and dozens of pilots across the nation also campaigned. Meanwhile, two survivors, Adrianus Meliala and Retno Gunowati, went to the House of Representatives (DPR) to challenge those opposed to legal processes against the pilot.</p>
</text>
