<text id="autogum_interview_doc1248" title="part11_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When did you lose it, though?  When did you lose the belief in the higher power?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I couldn't--it's very diff--It wasn't even that much of an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Existential%20crisis">existential crisis</ref>.  It was much more like, um, it's just hard for me to believe--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I meant more so in recovery, when you said to yourself, ‘I'm just not getting the higher power thing’, or, ‘I just have to give up on the cartoon Jesus.’</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  It sort of faded away, I think. It sort of faded away.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Once you were stronger.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah.  It's difficult for me to believe in something when I don't; when I don't have evidence.  Now, that's obviously the point of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Faith">faith</ref>.  Faith is not meant to be logical:  faith is meant to be.  The argument for faith is it's meant to be a higher form of human functioning.  We don't use our base intellect, that we're supposed to go beyond that.  And…and… what more proof do you need?  I mean, someone would say, what proof do you need?  My God, the glass is not elevating off the table--there's your proof.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravity">Gravity</ref>!  You know?  And maybe that's true.  It very well may be true.  It may be true.</p>
<p>I certainly know that--that if there is God, that God does not care that the person I watch TV with also has hairy arms.  I mean, that's a ridic--the idea that a God would not like homosexuals, now, is patently absurd.  That doesn't even begin to become logical in any way.  The idea that the architect of gravity, the being that created the ability for elemental particles that are absolutely nothing to come together and create living organisms and bricks and buildings and cars and jets--the architect of absolutely everything would care--the sex of the person the little human loves?  It's a pitiful thought.  It's pitiful.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's a very small thought.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  It's an absolutely, profoundly small thought.  And there's no way it's true.</p>
<head id="On_the_gay_community">On the gay community</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What are your feelings about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/gay%20community">gay community</ref>? Do you feel part of it?</hi></p>
<p>[<hi rend="italic">Waiter stops by</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  No, I've never really felt like part of the gay community.  I never questioned my sexual orientation.  I didn't go to school, so I didn't have that high school indoctrination.  I was raised without a formal religion.  When I was religious as a child, it was on my own.  I was the one asking the questions, and I was the one believing in Jesus.  It wasn't because I went to church.  If we went to church, it was because I wanted to go.  So I never had that indoctrination to believe it was wrong, and then I was plunged into such extraordinary living, uh, circumstances, that my--and I then had to think about my very survival and my very sanity--that sexual orientation just was--I didn't even think about it.  It was just like totally on the back burner.  And as a result of that, it was never really an issue.</p>
</text>
