<text id="autogum_interview_doc623" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Zahra Stardust about the upcoming by-election in the Bradfield electorate of the Australian parliament" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-10-29" dateModified="2014-09-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Zahra_Stardust_about_the_upcoming_by-election_in_the_Bradfield_electorate_of_the_Australian_parliament" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Sending asylum seekers to Indonesia: good or bad?</hi> <hi rend="bold">/</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is the Australian dollar's near parrity with the UD dollar a sign that the Australian economy is healthy, the US economy in chaos or both?</hi> <hi rend="bold">/</hi> <hi rend="bold">How do you rate the governments economic stimulus package?</hi> <hi rend="bold">/</hi> <hi rend="bold">Should it be wound back?</hi> <hi rend="bold">/</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is Kevin Rudd a better Prime Minister than John Howard?</hi> <hi rend="bold">/</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is the Carbon Pollution Reduction Scheme an effective solution to climate change? Why?</hi> <hi rend="bold">/</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is there a better solution?</hi></p>
<p>As a party in its infancy who is not yet in the House of Representatives, we are focusing predominantly on niche issues relating to sex and gender, in which we have expertise. We look forward to formulating policies on wider issues in the public discourse such climate change, the economy and  refugee issues if and when the occasion arises. Currently we are seeking to raise awareness of important topics that are remain hidden or absent from the public political agenda.</p>
<p>However, we would make the following comments in response to your questions. For a country that prides itself on multiculturalism, we believe that instead of utilizing law and order rhetoric that stigmatises people who have every right under international law to seek asylum, we should see this instance as an opportunity to  welcome the incredible cultural diversity asylum seekers can bring to our country, and to open up discussion about the root causes of refugee and immigration movements, such as climate change, civil war, famine and persecution. Despite being elected largely because of their compassion and empathy towards refugees and asylum seekers, Rudd's 'hard line' approach is reminiscent of John Howard's stance in this area and risks creating a disillusioned public. We urge the Rudd Government to call on Indonesia to sign and ratify the Refugee Convention if it continues to fund detention centres there, and press for asylum seekers to be processed on the mainland with view to Australia being a progressive role model in the international community, as opposed to maintaining its current detention policies which continue to seek attention from human rights bodies worldwide.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why should the electorate vote for you?</hi></p>
<p>There is a lot of lip service paid currently paid by the major political parties to gender equality that is not followed through with substantive policy and law reform. We know that the vast numbers of Australians are tolerant, respectful, celebratory people, with their individual backgrounds, preferences and lives, and we hope to seek resonance with people in Bradfield electorate who care about social justice issues and injustices in areas of health, education, censorship, workplace relations and child protection. We hope to represent people in Bradfield who support the human rights, respect, dignity and equality of all people, no matter what gender, sexual preference, race, class, ability, or any other factor. </p>
</text>
