<text id="autogum_interview_doc897" title="part3_Eurovision &amp;apos;04 winner Ruslana discusses her paths as singer, spokesmodel, stateswoman and source of inspiration" shortTile="parteurovision--winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-30" dateModified="2015-05-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2704_winner_Ruslana_discusses_her_paths_as_singer%2C_spokesmodel%2C_stateswoman_and_source_of_inspiration" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Ruslana</hi>: We're trying to build a new energy generation using the book <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wild%20Energy.%20Lana">Wild Energy - Lana</ref></hi>. This new project means a new album, new videos, new songs.</p>
<p>My new project <hi rend="italic">Wild Energy</hi> is based on the science fiction novel by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marina%20and%20Sergey%20Dyachenko">Marina and Sergey Dyachenko</ref>...They are very good friends of mine. The main idea of this novel is that in a [futuristic] city which experiences a global energy crisis, far more threatening than lack of oil and gas, people are lacking their will for life, their energy of the heart – the fuel for people. Lana, one of the synthetic inhabitants, sets out to find the mystical energy source. After many adventures she discovers that the wild energy comes from her own heart.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> How did you cross paths with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T-Pain">T-Pain</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missy%20Elliott">Missy Elliott</ref>, and how did your musical collaboration with them come to fruition?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ruslana</hi>: [The] <hi rend="italic">Wild Energy</hi> album was recorded at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hit%20Factory%20Studio">Hit Factory Studio</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miami,%20Florida">Miami</ref>. [The] song featuring T-Pain [is] called "Moon of Dreams." "Moon of Dreams" is first and foremost an exotic mix of Slavic tunes and American R&amp;B grooves. It's dance but romantic, temperamental and gentle simultaneously. The song that I sing with Missy Elliott is called "The Girl that Rules" and is a big departure [from] ethno-infused pop and dance sounds.</p>
<figure><caption>Ruslana performing her <hi rend="italic">Wild Energy</hi> show in Berlin in 2006, while a Member of Parliament for the ruling <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/People's%20Union%20&quot;Our%20Ukraine&quot;">People's Union "Our Ukraine"</ref> party.</caption></figure>
<head id="Goodwill_work_and_politics">Goodwill work and politics</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> One of the messages of <hi rend="italic">Wild Energy</hi> is that you want to bring to a wider audience the dangers of the global climate change, and the importance to use renewable energy. Do you feel Ukraine has been "a victim" to other energy resources that have been more expensive or more mortally damaging, specifically with the Chernobyl disaster and Ukraine's feud with Gazprom in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ruslana</hi>: The thing is that I started the project in the Parliament [for] renewable energy. I, as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member%20of%20Parliament">deputy</ref>, thought that if there are so many conflicts around the gas, we need to introduce solar panels. For [the project], I [became versed in] all alternative energy [forms]. Can you imagine, me, [a] musician, [getting] into all economic and technical nuances. Me and my team tried to [promote] this project. But the parliament was so incapable [of working properly] that it was wiser [to] go out, [which] I actually did. My policy [now] – it's my new show <hi rend="italic">Wild Energy</hi>. That [is] how I will appeal to people.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You have also served as a UNICEF Goodwill Ambassador for the Ukraine, and your platform has been increased awareness of human trafficking. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ruslana</hi>: I released two video clips which aim to make potential victims aware of the dangers of human trafficking, [and I] performed at an anti-human trafficking event in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vienna">Vienna</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Austria">Austria</ref>, organized by <ref target="http://www.ungift.org">UN.GIFT</ref> in front of 117 international delegations. My song "Not For Sale" became the anthem of the anti-trafficking campaign.</p>
</text>
