<text id="autogum_interview_doc893" title="part18_Author Amy Scobee recounts abuse as Scientology executive" shortTile="partauthor-amy-scobee" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-11" dateModified="2015-12-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_Amy_Scobee_recounts_abuse_as_Scientology_executive" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>In the August 2009 publication of "Freedom", they slandered both the <hi rend="italic">St. Petersburg Times</hi> reporters and the "defectors" (myself, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marty%20Rathbun">Marty Rathbun</ref>, Mike Rinder and Tom DeVocht). Note: they did not use the name "Amy Scobee" in this magazine. Instead, they refer to me as "the Adulteress". This slanderous character assassination appears in more than 20 places in their publication. It's painfully obvious that they were referring to me since I was the only female that spoke out in the article they were protesting. I'm not "an adulteress". As a member of Scientology's Sea Organization (age 16 to 42), I had sexual intercourse with my first husband, my second husband and my current husband. Regardless, my "sexual purity" has nothing to do with my reporting the fact that I witnessed the head of the Church of Scientology commit repeated assault &amp; battery on specific church executives while I was employed there. It's just their attempt to "annihilate credibility" for exposing this crime. In my view, the Freedom magazine is used to help carry out Miscavige's private agenda to try to remain in a position of power in that organization.</p>
<figure><caption>Amy Scobee in 2009 Image: <ref target="http://www.scobeepublishing.com/">Amy Scobee</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> BBC News reported on September 26, that during an interview for the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panorama%20(TV%20series)">Panorama</ref></hi> special, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Secrets%20of%20Scientology">The Secrets of Scientology</ref></hi>, yourself and reporter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Sweeney%20(journalist)">John Sweeney</ref> were photographed, and such photographs of the two of you hugging after completing the interview were sent by Scientology UK lawyers from the firm Carter-Ruck to the BBC. What do you think Scientology was attempting to accomplish by sending these photos to the BBC? Is such behavior by the Scientology organization with regard to monitoring of journalists, critics, or former members such as yourself common? What do you do to cope and/or respond to such behavior from the Scientology organization?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold"> To me, it's more important to prevent anyone else from being hurt by making Scientology's human rights violations known</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Amy Scobee</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: Yes, this type of intimidation is common practice by Scientology. As a witness in an on-going court case against Scientology, I was recently in a deposition with Scientology's lead counsel. He pulled out the photo that their private investigators took of John Sweeney giving me a hug on the highway outside of the Scientology compound in Hemet after nearly two full days of interviews. He proceeded to ask me how much "alone time" I spent with Mr. Sweeney (which was none) and when I explained that we all gave each other hugs goodbye before we went our separate ways and that my husband was right there with me, the lawyer said, "We'll see what the jury says about that!" All they are trying to do is intimidate us into silence through constant trails by PI's, slandering our names with ridiculous accusations, etc., so we'd become cowed, be quiet and let their criminality go on, unchecked. Well, it hasn't worked to keep me silent. To me, it's more important to prevent anyone else from being hurt by making Scientology's human rights violations known than to worry about them tarnishing my personal reputation in retaliation. I believe that the truth must be brought to light, despite consequences.</p>
</text>
