<text id="autogum_interview_doc1094" title="part2_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with independent candidate Charles de Kerckhove, St. Paul's" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-01" dateModified="2014-03-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_independent_candidate_Charles_de_Kerckhove%2C_St._Paul%27s" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>Against. The MMP proposes adding new members to the legislature from lists compiled by the main political parties. This rewards the “party hack” sort of individual, and further detracts from personal accountability at voter doorsteps.</p>
<p>The existing parties have enough control of the process as it is. It’s been said of this campaign: “Charles de Kerckhove has a PLAN that challenges flaws in our social and political systems that will definitely bring attention and positive change towards a safer world for all kids. No child deserves to be hurt, ever”. Along with whatever the candidates from the smaller parties had to say, this PLAN has been shut out of three out of three so-called All-Candidates debates. It’s difficult when one of the hosting organisations that shut out all of the smaller campaigns also actively endorses one of the main three candidates.</p>
<p>A concerned citizen should have the right to run on an issue of conviction, with at least some token inclusion into the process. Additionally considering the larger ridings under the proposed plan, the option of an independent political campaign could become effectively unavailable.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does “new media” play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>New media is the best thing an independent campaign has got! It levels the playing field that much more, and provides voice to people outside the main party lines – new media is keeping the democratic spirit alive more than anything else.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</hi></p>
<p>For the most beneficial decision, that would be a tough choice between the $ 5 million strategy to better support police agencies against child pornography, the creation of the CYBERCOPS program for helping kids against internet offences, and the end of the statute of limitations for fiduciary relationships in civil litigation. That last one is significant, because it means that once a former sexual abuse victim becomes conscious of the effects of the abuse on personal development, he or she no longer is limited to two years for the option of seeking damages. As there is a lot that a defendant can do to discredit and further humiliate a plaintiff – especially if the defendant happens to be something like a powerful religious organisation – the end to the statute of limitations makes the imbalance of power that much less unacceptable.</p>
</text>
