<text id="autogum_interview_doc1001" title="part0_An interview with Jimbo Wales" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-02-21" dateModified="2014-10-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_Jimbo_Wales" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>An interview with Jimbo Wales</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 22, 2006</hi></p>
 This article mentions the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>, one of its projects, or people related to it. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> is a project of the Wikimedia Foundation.
<p>Just five years ago, when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jimmy%20Wales">Jimbo Wales</ref> founded <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref>, the project's goal of 100,000 articles  seemed ambitious.  Yet today, the project, now one of the top 25 websites in the world according to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexa%20Internet">Alexa</ref>, is nearing closer 1,000,000 articles in English, and 3.5 million articles across all languages.  This week, we interviewed Jimbo Wales.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_Jimbo_Wales/Color-free">Color-free version</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews:</hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Raul654">Raul654</ref> asks: "Recently, there were revelations about organized attempts by US Congressmen to whitewash their articles. What is your take on this, as well as earlier reports of Corporate astroturfing?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jimbo Wales:</hi> The question is invalid.  There were no revelations of organized attempts by US Congressmen to whitewash their articles.  Not any evidence of "corporate astroturfing" of which I am aware.  There was evidence that some congressional staffers edited Wikipedia in inappropriate ways.  But the internal evidence of the type and style of these edits do not suggest "organized attempts".</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN:</hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Nichalp">Nichalp</ref> asks: "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Budget">Budget</ref> permitting, are there any plans to increase the number of Wikipedia <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Server%20(computing)">servers</ref>, specifically into the less developed countries?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JW:</hi> We are always buying new servers.  There are no specific plans to add servers in less developed countries, but we have looked into it as a possibility.  We are particularly interested in doing so if it helps increase access and reduce costs for those users.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN:</hi> <hi rend="italic">An anonymous reader asks: "How much of a role do you feel the Wikipedia community (and the communities of its sister projects) should have in the running of the Wikimedia Foundation? Do you see an increasing separation of the organization from the projects? If so, do you regard that as beneficial or a potential problem?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JW:</hi> The community has always been and will always be absolutely crucial to the running of the Wikimedia Foundation. We are increasing the community input and activity in the foundation through a new series of committees to delegate things to community members which have traditionally been handled by me or the Board. I do not see any increasing separation of the organization from the projects, quite the opposite.  I consider the increasing integration of the community and the foundation as overwhelmingly beneficial.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN:</hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:ALoan">ALoan</ref> asks: "English Wikipedia is approaching 1 million articles, but less than 1 in a thousand are Featured articles. The list of featured articles English Wikipedia should have has few featured articles, and recent surveys of articles chosen at random show that many articles are poorly written. How can we get from here to an encyclopedia of well-written articles? Or should we not worry too much about coverage and content?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JW:</hi>  We should be tightly focused on the quality of our coverage and content. The goal of Wikipedia is to create and distribute a freely licensed high quality encyclopedia. The path to that goal will require us to be flexible and thoughtful. The first steps will come soon with the article review system, which will initially be used simply to gather data. After we have data, we can begin to work on how we will focus our attention to improve quality.</p>
</text>
