<text id="autogum_interview_doc769" title="part2_Keep your eyes peeled for cosmic debris: Andrew Westphal about Stardust@home" shortTile="partkeep-eyes-peeled" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-05-18" dateModified="2015-10-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Keep_your_eyes_peeled_for_cosmic_debris%3A_Andrew_Westphal_about_Stardust%40home" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>And this is the huge advantage with this kind of a mission — a "sample return" mission. </p>
<p>Most missions rather do things quite differently... you have to build an instrument to make a measurement and that instrument design gets locked in several years before launch practically guaranteeing that it will be obsolete by the time you launch. Here exactly the opposite is true. Several of the instruments that are now being used to analyze the cometary dust did not exist when the mission was launched. Further, some instruments (e.g., synchrotrons) are the size of shopping malls — you don't have a hope of flying these in space. So we can and will study these samples for many years. AND we have to preserve some of these dust particles for our grandchildren to analyze with their hyper-quark-gluon plasma microscopes (or whatever)!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">When do you anticipate the project to start?</hi></p>
<p>We're really frustrated with the delays that we've been having. Some of it has to do with learning how to deal with the aerogel collectors, which are rougher and more fractured than we expected. The good news is that they are pretty clean — there is very little of the dust that you see on our training images — these were deliberately left out in the lab to collect dust so that we could give people experience with the worst case we could think of. In learning how to do the scanning of the actual flight aerogel, we uncovered a couple of bugs in our scanning software — which forced us to go back and rescan. Part of the other reason for the delay was that we had to learn how to handle the collector — it would cost $200M to replace it if something happened to it, so we had to develop procedures to deal with it, and add several new safety features to the Cosmic Dust Lab. This all took time. Finally, we're distracted because we also have many responsibilities for the cometary analysis, which has a deadline of August 15 for finishing analysis. The IS project has no such deadline, so at times we had to delay the IS (interstellar, sorry) in order to focus on the cometary work. We are very grateful to everyone for their patience on this — I mean that very sincerely. </p>
<p>And rest assured that we're just as frustrated!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">I know there will be a "test" that participants will have to take before they can examine the "real thing". What will that test consist of?</hi></p>
<p>The test will look very similar to the training images that you can look at now. But.. there will of course be no annotation to tell you where the tracks are! </p>
</text>
