<text id="autogum_interview_doc1350" title="part0_Van Canto's Stefan Schmidt on a capella metal, Wacken, Nightwish, piracy & more" shortTile="partvan-cantos-stefan" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-09" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Van_Canto%27s_Stefan_Schmidt_on_a_capella_metal%2C_Wacken%2C_Nightwish%2C_piracy_%26_more" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Van Canto's Stefan Schmidt on a capella metal, Wacken, Nightwish, piracy &amp; more</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 27, 2008</hi></p>
<p>"Five singers, one drummer. No guitars, no bass, no keyboards but nevertheless an unbelievable melodic metal experience."</p>
<p>That's how the official website of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/van%20Canto">van Canto</ref> describes the band. Hailing from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref>, van Canto are what is called an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/a%20capella">a capella</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/metal%20music">metal</ref> band, the pioneers of this new genre.</p>
<p>The band released their debut, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A%20Storm%20to%20Come">A Storm to Come</ref></hi>, in December 2006. Exactly a year later, van Canto announced a global signing to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gun%20Records">Gun Records</ref>/<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sony%20BMG">Sony BMG</ref>, and their debut was released worldwide on December 14.</p>
<p>Van Canto are now experiencing considerable success. They recently provided support for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Finland">Finnish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/symphonic%20power%20metal">symphonic power metal</ref> band <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nightwish">Nightwish</ref>, as well as receiving a slot at the internationally famous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wacken%20Open%20Air">Wacken Open Air</ref> festival in Germany. The prestigious event sees them sharing the bill with acts such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hatebreed">Hatebreed</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonata%20Arctica">Sonata Arctica</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/As%20I%20Lay%20Dying">As I Lay Dying</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soilwork">Soilwork</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Children%20of%20Bodom">Children of Bodom</ref>, Nightwish, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lordi">Lordi</ref> and headline act <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iron%20Maiden">Iron Maiden</ref>.</p>
<p>Van Canto's second album will be recorded across this month and next, with famed producer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie%20Bauerfeind">Charlie Bauerfeind</ref>, although no release date has yet been confirmed.</p>
<p>In light of recent events, van Canto member and founder Stefan Schmidt has given the band's first interview in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English%20language">English</ref>, all previous interviews being in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German%20language">German</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italian%20language">Italian</ref>. Wikinews now exclusively brings you that interview below.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<head id="On_the_early_days">On the early days</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>How did you decide on the concept for the band?</item></list>
<p>After the split of my former band Jester’s Funeral I wanted to do something vocal oriented with a heroic attitude. It wasn’t planned to leave out all instruments in the beginning, it was an idea developed in the studio turning out to work great.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Are there any similar bands you could say inspired you, or was it an original idea?</item></list>
<p>We are playing melodic metal, so my inspiration as a composer can be found in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blind%20Guardian">Blind Guardian</ref> and Nightwish. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metallica">Metallica</ref> has always been a great influence for me, too. I don’t listen to many a capella bands, though. There’s a German a capella band called the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wise%20Guys">Wise Guys</ref> which I like, but it’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pop%20music">pop</ref> and doesn’t have to do much with our style of singing or performing. Combining the metal style with the performing style a capella is the original part of the idea.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>In the music world, as with all aspects of life, new or rare ideas often meet with difficulties. How hard was it to get people to take you seriously at first?</item></list>
<p>It wasn’t that hard because we did not do much for it. We just presented our idea and many people liked it, some others didn’t. We don’t put much time in convincing people starting their argumentation with “you don’t use guitars, this is no metal”. I think everyone who takes the time to listen to our songs or to visit us performing live can see that we really love metal music and love to sing.</p>
</text>
