<text id="autogum_interview_doc1431" title="part6_Judging the Courts: Wikinews interviews Prof. Lawrence Douglas" shortTile="partjudging-courts" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-11-20" dateModified="2015-09-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Judging_the_Courts%3A_Wikinews_interviews_Prof._Lawrence_Douglas" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: How about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Truth%20commission">truth and reconciliation commissions</ref>, which are usually explicitly charged with the task to record events in addition to punishing those guilty of a crime?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: Again, I see the work of trials and truth commissions as complementary, not antagonistic.  Trials are about adjudicating guilt; they issue in the imposition of a coercive sanction.  This fixation on fixing guilt and imposing punishment may serve the interests of reconciliation and transition, but that is not its principal purpose.  Moreover, because trials assign blame and impose sanctions, it is critical that they be performed fairly. Truth commissions, by contrast, are often explicitly geared toward advancing the goals of reconciliation: they are part of an instrumental calculus that seeks a smooth transition to a more humane political order.  Truth commissions may, then, be better suited to the experiences of certain nations than trials.  That said, the two are not mutually exclusive and can often work in tandem with one another.  As time passes, a nation that, in the interests of stabilizing a fledgling democracy, originally accepted a truth commission may come to see, as its institutions strengthen, the attractions, if not the necessity, of trials, too. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: You have written that law has responded to the Holocaust by creating and expanding on the concepts of genocide and crimes against humanity. Are these additions to legal discourse and legal apparatus adequate to handle the events since then, such as the Rwandan genocide, the breakup of Yugoslavia? Do these events show a need for, or did they spawn, a fresh expansion?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: I think we need to distinguish between the substantive crimes that high-level perpetrators stand accused of having committed – e.g., genocide, crimes against humanity, war crimes – and the principles of criminal accountability that prosecutors use to organize and prove their case.  Here I have in mind concepts such as the "joint criminal enterprise," which has been usefully elaborated by prosecutors at the ICTY to facilitate complex prosecutions of high-level perpetrators.  Some have called for the expansion of the substantive crimes to include novel offenses, such as "the crime of atrocity."  I, for one, think it counterproductive to proliferate the number of major international crimes; "genocide" and "crimes against humanity" are both clearly enough defined yet capacious enough to embrace the full spectrum of atrocity.</p>
<head id="Back_to_Saddam's_trial">Back to Saddam's trial</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: How well did the Saddam trial fare in writing history?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: The tribunal's written decision is yet to appear, so it's difficult to answer this question.  Perhaps more to the point, the trial dealt with a relative minor set of crimes, those pertaining to the reprisal killings of 148 Shias in Dujail in 1982.  While such a focus made for a more manageable case for the prosecution, it did not serve the broader interest of demonstrating the full sweep of atrocity perpetrated by Saddam's regime.</p>
</text>
