<text id="autogum_interview_doc1288" title="part13_Edmund White on writing, incest, life and Larry Kramer" shortTile="partedmund-white" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-08" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edmund_White_on_writing%2C_incest%2C_life_and_Larry_Kramer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have a relationship with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larry%20Kramer">Larry Kramer</ref> at all?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  We’re enemies.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  We were friends and I think I stayed friends with him longer than anybody else, but even I finally gave way because he attacked me in print in the most vile and disgusting terms.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What did he say?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  When I first moved back to America 10 years ago—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michael:</hi>  It was before that, the year before that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  The year before.  I had a book that came out called <hi rend="italic">The Farewell Symphony</hi>, which I think was maybe my most important book.  I sent Larry an early <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/manuscript">manuscript</ref> of it because I wanted his opinion of it.  All he said to me was, “Did you really have that much sex?” and I said, “Well, Larry, everybody did in the seventies except you.”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michael:</hi>  Although that’s not what he was saying in that documentary last week.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Yeah, there was a documentary about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fire%20Island">Fire Island</ref> where he was talking about he, too, was part of the scene.  Which wasn’t true because he wasn’t; he’s too ugly.  [<hi rend="italic">Chuckles</hi>]  Anyway, suddenly he decided to attack my book and me months before it came out in America in these really disgusting terms.  "Edmund White’s mouth is busier than his toilet—“</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michael:</hi>  No it was your ass.  Your ass has been busier than a toilet seat.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Oh, right, that’s right.  And all this stuff.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michael:</hi>  It’s kind of a mixed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metaphor">metaphor</ref>...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Right, it doesn’t even make sense.  He’s an idiot.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michael:</hi>  But before that, he denounced you in front of a live audience, before it reached print.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But up until then—before that, you had been…</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Yeah, we had been friendly-ish</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michael:</hi>  Larry was resentful that he had gone to Paris in the middle of the crisis.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  And he was mad that I had written a biography of Jean Genet when <hi rend="italic">every</hi> gay writer should be thinking about AIDS and only about AIDS.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michael:</hi>  He thought Ed had alighted himself out of the situation.  He doesn’t know what real writers are, because what they do is spend their time writing and not yelling in public.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I only have an issue with him because he attacked my work at a time when I was very vulnerable.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why were you so vulnerable?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I was just moving back to America and it was my biggest and best book, and it was a book about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AIDS%20crisis">AIDS crisis</ref>... [<hi rend="italic">Sighs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michael:</hi>  And you hadn’t published a novel in about ten years</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michael:</hi>  And he really did go in to attack mode at this conference in Key West, and sitting next to Ed at the table, hogging the microphone, and yelling and denouncing him to the audience and telling them, “Where are our <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tolstoy">Tolstoys</ref>?  Where are our <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flaubert">Flauberts</ref>?”  I mean, as if he were anything close to that.  Using it as a platform to talk about his own novel, which he has been promising for such a long time.</p>
</text>
