<text id="autogum_interview_doc985" title="part0_Wikinews holds Reform Party USA presidential candidates forum" shortTile="partwikinews-holds" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-01-02" dateModified="2016-09-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_holds_Reform_Party_USA_presidential_candidates_forum" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews holds Reform Party USA presidential candidates forum</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 3, 2012</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Logo for the Reform Party of the United States of America.Image: Reform Party National Committee.</caption></figure>
<p>Three men are currently seeking the presidential nomination of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Reform_Party_of_the_United_States_of_America">Reform Party of the United States of America</ref>: small business owner <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Andre_Barnett">Andre Barnett</ref>, Earth Intelligence Network CEO <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20David%20Steele">Robert Steele</ref>, and former college football coach <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robby%20Wells">Robby Wells</ref>.  <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reached out to these candidates and asked each of them five questions about their campaigns. There were no space limits placed on the responses, and no candidate was exposed to another's responses before making their own. The answers are posted below in unedited form for comparison of the candidates.</p>
<p>The Reform Party is a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/third%20party%20(United%20States)">third party</ref> that was founded in 1995 by industrialist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ross%20Perot">Ross Perot</ref>.  Perot ran as the party's first presidential nominee in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%201996">1996</ref>, and won over eight percent of the popular vote, the highest percentage for a third party candidate since. In 1998, professional wrestler <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesse%20Ventura">Jesse Ventura</ref> ran on the Reform Party ticket and was elected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor%20of%20Minnesota">Governor of Minnesota</ref>.  The party fell in prominence during the lead-up to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202000">2000 presidential election</ref> when it was plagued by infighting between ideological factions. In 2000, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/paleoconservatism">paleoconservative</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pat_Buchanan">Pat Buchanan</ref> won the presidential nomination, and went on to receive only 0.4 percent of the popular vote in the general election. In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202004">2004</ref>, the party opted to endorse consumer advocate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ralph%20Nader">Ralph Nader</ref>, but ended the year nearly bankrupt.  In 2008, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ted%20Weill">Ted Weill</ref> won the party's presidential nomination, but appeared on the ballot in only one state and won a total of 481 votes.      </p>
<p>The party is currently trying to rebuild and has opened several new state chapters. They will attempt to appear on the ballot in more states for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2012">2012 presidential election</ref>. The party is expected to nominate its presidential ticket during the National Convention this summer.</p>
<head id="The_candidates">The candidates</head>
Candidates for the Reform Party USA presidential nomination
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Andre_Barnett">Andre Barnett</ref></hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Poughkeepsie,_New_York">Poughkeepsie, New York</ref> served in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Army">U.S. Army</ref> until he was injured in a helicopter incident in 2000.  Since that time, he has worked as a fitness model, has assisted several federal agencies and corporations in information technology services, and founded the company WiseDome, Inc. He considers himself a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conservatism%20in%20the%20United%20States">conservative</ref>.
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20David%20Steele">Robert Steele</ref></hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oakton,%20Virginia">Oakton, Virginia</ref> is CEO of the non-profit Earth Intelligence Network, which promotes <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/open-source%20intelligence">"public intelligence in the public interest"</ref>.  He previously served as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Marine%20Corps">Marine Corps</ref> infantry officer, national intelligence officer, and in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marine%20Corps%20Intelligence%20Command">Marine Corps intelligence</ref>. For his presidential campaign, he focuses on his plans for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/electoral%20reform">electoral reform</ref>, the creation of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coalition%20government">coalition cabinet</ref>, and the creation of an open forum for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Participatory%20democracy">participatory democracy</ref>.
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robby%20Wells">Robby Wells</ref></hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlotte,%20North%20Carolina">Charlotte, North Carolina</ref> is the former head football coach for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savannah%20State%20University">Savannah State University</ref> and former assistant coach for
</text>
