<text id="autogum_interview_doc1033" title="part0_Wikinews interviews team behind the 2,000th featured Wikipedia article" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-10" dateModified="2009-12-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_team_behind_the_2%2C000th_featured_Wikipedia_article" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews team behind the 2,000th featured Wikipedia article</head>
 This article mentions the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>, one of its projects, or people related to it. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> is a project of the Wikimedia Foundation.
<p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, April 13, 2008</hi></p>
<p>This week saw the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main%20Page">English-language version</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref>, the collaboratively written online encyclopedia, reach 2,000 featured articles with the inclusion of the article <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El%20Señor%20Presidente">El Señor Presidente</ref></hi>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Featured%20articles">Featured articles</ref> (FAs) meet Wikipedia's highest standards for quality, accuracy, neutrality, completeness, and style, and thus are considered the best articles on Wikipedia. </p>
<p>The Wikipedia team that carries out the assessment and quality control before conferring the status of featured articles promoted five articles to FA status at the same time: <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walter%20de%20Coventre">Walter de Coventre</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maximian">Maximian</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic">El Señor Presidente</hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord%20of%20the%20Universe">Lord of the Universe</ref></hi>, and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red-billed%20Chough">Red-billed Chough</ref></hi>. With five promoted at the same time, conferring the status of 2,000th on one is an arbitrary decision and in some respects any of these articles could actually make a claim to the honour.</p>
<p>The article <hi rend="italic">El Señor Presidente</hi> was created and developed by a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20British%20Columbia">University of British Columbia</ref> class, "<hi rend="bold">Murder, Madness, and Mayhem: Latin American Literature in Translation</hi>". While an important milestone, the 2,000th featured article is also symbolic of Wikipedia's growing role in the 21st century learning arena. </p>
<p>The professor of the class, Jon Beasley-Murray, began using Wikipedia as a collaborative space where his students could both do coursework and provide a type of virtual public service. Thus, he created a Wikipedia project, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:WikiProject%20Murder%20Madness%20and%20Mayhem">Murder Madness and Mayhem</ref></hi>, that focussed on creating articles relating to the Latin American literature covered in his class. Not surprisingly, <hi rend="italic">El Señor Presidente</hi> is considered one of the most important books in Latin American literature, written by Nobel Prize-winning <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Guatemala">Guatemalan</ref> writer, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miguel%20Ángel%20Asturias">Miguel Ángel Asturias</ref>. </p>
<p>The Wikinews team contacted Prof. Beasley-Murray, who agreed to be interviewed for this story. His responses can be found below. Included are sections soliciting responses from three students who took the class and helped create and bring <hi rend="italic">El Señor Presidente</hi> to Feature Article status. Thus far the project has created seven good articles in addition to the 2,000th featured article.</p>
<head id="Murder_Madness_and_Mayhem">Murder Madness and Mayhem</head>
<figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure><p> Professor Beasley-Murray, thank you for giving us some of your valuable time and agreeing to talk to us. Can you give some background on what prompted you to start this project?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Prof. Jon Beasley-Murray</hi></hi>: I should say first that I've written some reflections at the project on Wikipedia itself, as an essay I entitled <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Jbmurray/Madness">"Madness"</ref>.</item></list>
<p>In short, however, I'd done some editing on Wikipedia a year ago.  I'd got into that rather by accident--after finding to some surprise that some of my academic work had been written up at the site.  I then spent some time trying to organize and expand articles and categories relating to Latin America, particularly Latin American culture, which is my area of expertise.  I discovered that Wikipedia's coverage of this area was uneven at best.  It was while I was involved in this that it came to me that students could usefully participate on the site.  They use Wikipedia anyway; why not find ways in which they could also participate?  And I'd come to realize that it's only by participating and contributing that you can really understand the Encyclopedia, both its strengths and its weaknesses but above all the way it comes to be how it is.</p>
</text>
