<text id="autogum_interview_doc957" title="part2_Taliban resurgent in Pakistan on enforcement of Sharia law" shortTile="parttaliban-resurgent" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-03-20" dateModified="2019-01-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Taliban_resurgent_in_Pakistan_on_enforcement_of_Sharia_law" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Is the Talibanization of Pakistan partly due to a perception of corruption among the system of Maliks and Political Agents?</hi></p>
<p>The corruption is in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inter-Services%20Intelligence">ISI</ref>, the Pak army and the Pak system of Political Agents (PA) assigned to these tribal zones (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federally%20Administered%20Tribal%20Areas">FATA</ref> &amp; PATA). </p>
<p>These PA have budgets that are much like the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central%20Intelligence%20Agency">CIA</ref> in that they are a single line item in the national budget, there is no accountability of where or how the PA spends the money. If one followed the IRS rules and looked at the lifestyles of the PA and compared them with their income, you would soon understand what was going on. </p>
<p>Musharraf critics are a larger issue. Republicans have coddled Pakistan with the belief that "as long as they are pro America" then democracy in Pakistan will come in due course. Democrats have, I think, insisted Democracy first, and then we can discuss the other issues later.</p>
<p>The Talibanization of Pakistan has more to do with graduates of "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raiwind">Raiwind</ref>", a place near Lahore, where the "Tablighi Jamaat" conducts brainwashing camps. It was graduates of this place, in my opinion, that are responsible for Britain's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/7%20July%202005%20London%20bombings">7/7 attacks</ref> as an example.</p>
<p>Corruption amongst the Maliks is self limiting because of the egalitarian society they live in and because of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corruption%20amongst%20the%20Maliks%20is%20self%20limiting%20because%20of%20the%20egalitarian%20society%20they%20live%20&amp;%20because%20of%20Pashtunwali">Pashtunwali</ref>.  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What is your view on Musharraf suspending judge <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Protests_in_Pakistan_as_Chief_Justice_appears_before_judges'_panel">Iftikhar Chaudhry</ref>?</hi></p>
<p>I believe, and this is widely held belief, that Musharraf has no constituency of his own for his power base. He wanted legitimization from the Supreme Court, and Mr Choudhry as Chief Justice (their system is not like ours) would not give it. </p>
<p>So Musharraf has had to hang on to his Army Chief of Staff position to get his power from the Army. If some one else were Chief of Staff, that person could refuse to support Musharraf.</p>
<p>The Justice favorable to the general is Justice Iqbal, who was not the next in line for Chief Justice. The next in line is a Hindu. That presented problems of its own for Musharraf. So when the Hindu judge went for a trip to India, Iqbal became the "available" senior most Supreme Court judge, and hence the haste and lack of decorum with which Justice Chaudhry was removed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What is the prevailing sentiment regarding Pakistani government efforts in the provinces and the international effort in Afghanistan to combat Taliban and affiliated militants?</hi></p>
<p>In my dealings and inquires, <hi rend="bold">one</hi> thing stood out like a sore thumb - the conspiracy theories vis-à-vis anything having to do with America. I mentioned to one of my close friends that events that were previously ascribed as acts of God were now considered acts of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central%20Intelligence%20Agency">CIA</ref>. Some even believed that the Earthquake in the northern areas was because of some sort of underground secret "bomb" used by the CIA. Lack of evidence is further proof that the CIA did it. I was flabbergasted, and started to give this kind of thinking as an example in speaking to "educated" Pakistani's - and among these, those that did agree that the earthquake was NOT the work of the CIA, they would start giving other examples, notably the Blow up of the plane carrying Zia ul Haq an ex President of Pakistan, in which the US Ambassador also perished. When I would point this out, the response would be that that is the sort of thing they do to take away suspicion from themselves.</p>
</text>
