<text id="autogum_interview_doc1049" title="part1_Past Eurovision contestants give advice to this year's performers, speculate on who will win" shortTile="partpast-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-05-06" dateModified="2015-09-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Past_Eurovision_contestants_give_advice_to_this_year%27s_performers%2C_speculate_on_who_will_win" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Garlick</hi>: Some of my best memories from doing Eurovision would be visiting <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Estonia">Estonia</ref>, I don't think it's a place I'd ever have visited if it wasn't for performing there, and it really is beautiful. While I was there during the week I had the opportunity to fly out into the Baltic Sea via helicopter and spend the afternoon on board <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HMS%20Chatham%20(F87)">HMS Chatham</ref> too. I was allowed to drive the frigate, and got to perform to the troops on board, who were so appreciative. </p>
<p>I have so many more, and met such amazing people during the whole promotion and run-up period as well as the Eurovision week itself. My only regret is not taking as many photos as I would have liked to. So my advice to others doing Eurovision would be [to] definitely take lots of pictures, and really enjoy your performance and everything that representing your country brings with it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The music videos for this year are up at <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/eurovision">youtube.com/eurovision</ref>. Which songs are your favorites and which country do you think has the best chance of winning?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Garlick</hi>: I have been fortunate enough to have been able to perform alongside some of this year's Eurovision entries, and was totally impressed! I <hi rend="italic">love</hi> the Iceland entry this year...the song "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Is%20It%20True%3F">Is it True?</ref>" is a really beautiful ballad, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jóhanna%20Guðrún%20Jónsdóttir">Johanna</ref> sings it really well! I would say that from a song point of view, this is definitely my favourite song. </p>
<p>I do, however, think that the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukraine</ref> could win this year! <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Svetlana%20Loboda">Svetlana</ref>'s performance is <hi rend="italic">crazy</hi>!! She's absolutely wild! Her live performance is out of control! She is definitely "in it to win it", and is going all out to ensure she does everything to make this happen. She is one to watch on the night for sure! There will definitely be something amazing going on on stage during her performance. She'll keep you captivated, and make it memorable!!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> A lot of the fans you had from when you were on <hi rend="italic">Pop Idol</hi> and Eurovision 2002 don't know the reason why you dropped out of music and out of sight. What happened? Also, do you find it difficult returning to the music industry after being away for six years?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Garlick</hi>: After Pop Idol and Eurovision I started to write songs...something I had never done before, and didn't think I would be any good at. But I have been fortunate enough to travel the world since, co-writing with some of the world's best songwriters. I decided to take a step out of the industry for a while in 2004 when I got married to my teenage sweetheart Owen. </p>
</text>
