<text id="autogum_interview_doc274" title="part0_Eurovision &amp;apos;09 competitor Chiara talks about her current song &amp;quot;What If We&amp;quot; and her past accolades" shortTile="parteurovision--competitor" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-05" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2709_competitor_Chiara_talks_about_her_current_song_%22What_If_We%22_and_her_past_accolades" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Eurovision '09 competitor Chiara talks about her current song "What If We" and her past accolades</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 5, 2009</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Chiara on her initial success after Eurovision '98: "Everything came like rain in my life, from one thing to the other, and before I knew it I became <hi rend="italic">Chiara of Malta</hi>. I loved it, but I didn't have much time to think about it."Photo: The Foto Grafer/Television Malta</caption></figure>
<p>The small archipelago of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Malta">Malta</ref> in the Mediterranean Sea takes the Eurovision Song Contest very seriously. Leading a fight to remove a cap on the number of competing countries brought them back to the Contest in 1991 after a 16-year absence, and ever since the nation has had perfect attendance. </p>
<p>Since then, Malta's dependable "shining star" has been <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chiara%20Siracusa">Chiara Siracusa</ref>, who goes by her first name in her music career. First competing in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%201998">1998</ref> at the age of 21, she was pushed to the brink of victory until the votes from the final country that evening leveled her placement to third. Her rendition of the song "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20One%20That%20I%20Love">The One That I Love</ref>," and the recognition she received not only for herself, but for her country, made her a star in Malta overnight, and helped her launch a singing career in Europe.</p>
<p>She would later return to the Contest in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%202005">2005</ref> with "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angel%20(Chiara%20song)">Angel</ref>," an anthem she penned herself, and achieved second place. Now, in 2009, she will be going back to Eurovision for a third try, hoping for the "3-2-1" charm and a victory — something that has eluded her thus far. Her entry, the ballad "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/What%20If%20We%20(song)">What If We</ref>," has special memories for Chiara; it is dedicated to her father, who is recently deceased. </p>
<p>What if Chiara could take home the gold in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow">Moscow</ref>; for Malta, for her father, and for herself? Only time will tell. Chiara took time out of her Eurovision promotional schedule to answer some questions from <hi rend="italic">Wikinews'</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Mike_Halterman">Mike Halterman</ref> about her past performances, and most importantly, her upcoming one.</p>
<p>This is the fourth in a series of interviews with past Eurovision contestants, which will be published sporadically in the lead-up to mid-May's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%202009">next contest</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow">Moscow</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You'll be going to Moscow for a third try at possibly winning Eurovision. Why did you decide to compete this year? How did your partnership with Marc Paelinck and Gregory Bilsen come about?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chiara</hi>: Well, I met Marc Paelinck long time ago through a friend in Belgium. We started working together and it brought us to this collaboration today. I was thinking of going back to the festival [for a long time] and this year felt like the right year to do so.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Eurovision fans from across Europe picked you as the wide favorite to win Malta's preselection this year. Were you as confident? Were you nervous about competing in the semi-final rounds this time around, or did you think this was something you could handle?</hi></p>
</text>
