<text id="autogum_interview_doc1155" title="part9_Obesity and the Fat Acceptance Movement: Kira Nerusskaya speaks" shortTile="partobesity-fat-acceptance" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-09" dateModified="2014-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Obesity_and_the_Fat_Acceptance_Movement%3A_Kira_Nerusskaya_speaks" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why do you feel the need to know why they come back?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Probably more as a time saver for me.  If I have to go and meet somebody when all they’re interested in is just getting you in bed or whatever, that’s just not where I am in my life.  If that’s a five-minute phone call, then it’s much better than a 20-minute coffee date.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think it’s good to sometimes question motivations and not just let things happen?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  I think that ultimately we know in some ways.  There are some people that you’ve met in your life who you thought you would be perfect for or perfect with, but for whatever reason timing is poor and maybe you change within that time frame.  You’re a different person and so it doesn’t work.  It depends.  A lot of times you know why somebody’s calling.  You know, but it depends.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is it more challenging for a larger woman to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/orgasm">orgasm</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  No, it’s quite the opposite and it’s been scientifically proven.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why is that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  From reading and talking to women across the globe, it is true that fat women have higher <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hormones">hormonal</ref> levels and a much stronger libido than our skinny counterparts. Our ability to achieve orgasm is much quicker and the ability to have multiple orgasms is generally always there. There have been some articles that have come out about that I've read across the years. Men have a pretty strong <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/libido">libido</ref> from what I understand and are just so shocked by that. Would you concur? According to my research, and that being the case, they're almost always shocked that they find a partner who matches them. According to  the interviews I have done, if a man is more turned-on by somebody who is multi-orgasmic.</p>
<head id="What_do_fat_people_want_to_be_called?">What do fat people want to be called?</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do fat people prefer to be called?  In Spain if you’re fat you’re <hi rend="italic">gordo</hi> or <hi rend="italic">gorda</hi>.  It’s not 'pleasantly plump'.  It’s not 'carrying a few extra pounds'.  We have so many euphemisms in this culture—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  —that we’ve created ourselves—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  —to get around saying that somebody is fat. Do you think that trying to come up with so many euphemisms in the end stigmatizes the actual natural state to be able to just say someone is fat much like someone -- gay people went through this, too -- oh, he’s “light in the loafers,” or, “he’s funny,” as opposed to being like, “He’s gay.”</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  And what are they trying to do?  Are they trying to soften the blow for themselves or for the rest of America?</p>
</text>
