<text id="autogum_interview_doc327" title="part14_John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing" shortTile="partjohn-reed-orwell" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2015-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell%2C_God%2C_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Especially based in New York.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Especially based in New York, yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you find that when you have friends outside the city, and they know you're raising kids here, they bate their breath?  So many people still have this vision of New York from like "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Warriors%20(film)">The Warriors</ref>,"; from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abe%20Beame">Abe Beame</ref> days of New York.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  That's true, it's true.  The funny thing is we were just in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San%20Diego">San Diego</ref> and my daughter, who's three, would just lie on the floor moaning in boredom, because it's so boring there.  We were in a couple of houses, one of which had a pool.  She was fine when there was a pool.  But the driving--she just hated it!  You have to drive to go anywhere, and we couldn't find our health-food-store food…and we're driving around for forty minutes, and she just would sit in the back saying, "I don't want to live in the suburbs."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So many parents think that--my sister would be one--the preference of that controlled atmosphere is better for the kids.  They don't realize what they lose not living in an urban center.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  People creating this thriving environment where we can influence each other, and kids --</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  --They love it--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  --have more stimulus.  When you see news reports that on the discovery of an Earthlike planet does that affect your perspective or does it go unnoticed?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I don't know; there's so much out there that we don't understand that it's hard for me to imagine there isn't some larger relationships, somehow.  Let me see if I can phrase it better: there's a lot out there we don't understand.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If you had to choose, and you had to choose or both would be devastated and destroyed, which continent would you have blown up, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Asia">Asia</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Africa">Africa</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Asia or Africa!  I don't know, I have to blow up one of them??</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Or they both go.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I would just do it based on population, I guess.  I don't know their population figures, but I think that there are more people in Asia, so I think I'd blow up Africa.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So it would be a sum total of human life, as opposed to your judgement of cultural significance, or--?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I'm not sure.  The land mass thing might figure in, but mainly yeah, just the populations.</p>
<head id="On_paedophilia_and_the_death_penalty">On paedophilia and the death penalty</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you regard as the lowest depth of misery?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Before I was a parent, I was sort of wishy-washy on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Death%20penalty">death penalty</ref>; but being a parent makes you conservative about some things.  My wife is very progressive.  But then when we talk about a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedophilia">paedophile</ref> priest or something, and someone suggests that they be executed, she doesn't say anything.  I don't think it's just because there's a sense of vengeance.  I think it's because that would be the most miserable you could possibly be, that I can imagine.  To a person with such a damaged soul that you would harm a child--I can't imagine anything worse.</p>
</text>
