<text id="autogum_interview_doc344" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Jim Hedges, U.S. Prohibition Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-01-26" dateModified="2016-11-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jim_Hedges%2C_U.S._Prohibition_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">According to the <ref target="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/01/politics/campaign/01candidate.html?_r=2"><hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi></ref>, you were heavily involved in the 2004 split of the party that centered around five-time presidential nominee <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl%20Dodge">Earl Dodge</ref>. What exactly caused the split, and has the party since healed?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> To answer the last part first:  It has largely healed.  A few months after Dodge died, his hand-picked vice-chairman also died.  The man who was third in line refused to carry on.   That man, and the Dodge relatives, then dropped out completely; the other folks mostly are now working with the regular organization.</p>
<p>The split was caused by dissatisfaction with Dodge’s management.  Dodge was a somewhat paranoid person who trusted no one to help him.  For  example, he made one of his daughters "treasurer" of the Prohibition National Committee, but he did not allow her access to the bank account.  He was the only "signer" listed on the check card.   Another example:  He used money from a bequest to purchase a small office condominium, then without telling even his vice-chairman, he mortgaged the condo, cashed it out, and after a time lost it (because the mortgage was not being paid); the vice-chairman discovered all this only after Dodge died.   Dodge could sell the office condo undetected, because he held it in the name of a shell corporation controlled by himself and the said daughter.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">The late <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gene%20Amondson">Gene Amondson</ref>, the 2004 &amp; 2008 presidential nominee of the Prohibition Party was the national face of the party for a number of years. How well did you know Mr. Amondson, and what is the current state of the party with his absence?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I met Amondson at a couple of conventions; otherwise, I knew him only from correspondence and from telephone calls.  </p>
<p>Amondson was a congenial person, warm and approachable.  He was recommended to us by one of our supporters.  He had an act, a re-creation of Rev. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Billy%20Sunday">Billy Sunday</ref>’s sermon on booze, which he performed at conservative churches and other sympathetic venues.  We hoped that his name recognition and the audience appeal of his act would enhance the Party’s appeal.</p>
<p>As it turned out, he had a handicap, analogous to dyslexia, which prevented him from stringing words together into fluent sentences.  His act was great.  His public speaking and his writing were, um, unremarkable.</p>
<p>We miss his ability to attract attention to us.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Mr. Amondson stated that "<ref target="http://www.seattlepi.com/local/197609_dry01.html">Prohibition was America's greatest 13 years</ref>" and that he would "<ref target="http://www.usatoday.com/news/politicselections/nation/president/2004-09-09-prohibition-feud_x.htm">rather have 100 Al Capones in every city than alcohol sold in every grocery store</ref>". Do you agree with these comments, and additionally, do you second his projection that "<ref target="http://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Gene_Amondson,_Prohibition_Party_presidential_nominee">Prohibition will come again for the fourth time</ref>"? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I expect that national prohibition will come again "someday," because nothing we've tried since then has worked as well in reducing per-capita consumption of alcoholic beverages and the related social problems.</p>
</text>
