<text id="autogum_interview_doc1089" title="part10_Vanity Fair contributing editor Craig Unger on the Bush family feud, neoconservatives and the Christian right" shortTile="partvanity-fair-contributing" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2015-08-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vanity_Fair_contributing_editor_Craig_Unger_on_the_Bush_family_feud%2C_neoconservatives_and_the_Christian_right" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Exactly, they recycle the same thematic stories over and over and that one has been written before.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Right.  I also try to weave it through the father-son battle.  Although I have written critically of Bush Sr. in the past, he certainly is within the framework of the post-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Enlightenment">Enlightenment</ref> reason and reality-based world.  There is this quiet <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/Sub-rosa">sub-rosa</ref> battle in which he uses intermediaries in the book like Scowcroft.  If there’s a tragic hero in the book, it’s Scowcroft, who is in a very delicate position because he doesn’t want to jeopardize his close friendship with Bush Sr.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But Scowcroft is loathed by George W.’s administration for coming out against his foreign policy.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Right, and now Scowcroft speaks out early and often.  He’ll see what’s happening and does what he can, but ultimately he fails.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What does Bush Sr. think or say about Scowcroft’s public statements?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  They are still friends.  He rarely comments on them, and he doesn’t like to be called out about it.  There have been a couple of incidents that I open the book with, statements by Bush Jr. that have been perceived as digs at his father, such as saying “We don’t want to cut and run again.”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why would Bush Sr. not feel he has a moral obligation to the nation to make his feelings known to his son instead of keeping quiet and not speaking up?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  I’m wary of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychoanalysis">psychoanalyzing</ref> him, but I believe they don’t discuss it.  He’s come forth several times and said, “Look, why don’t you talk to Scowcroft or James Baker” and he kind of leaves it at that.  The Iraq Study Group report did have some earmarks of anger venting .  Scowcroft actually goes to Egypt and Saudi Arabia to get their support of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20Study%20Group">Iraq Study Group</ref> plan.  He also goes to Condi Rice, who is the last person from that world who seems to have real access to Bush, and talks to her about it.  She seems to sign on and at one point she says something like, “Well, when do you think we should do this?” and Scowcroft says, “Not we, you.”  She never really does anything; she never stands up.  She has become an enabler for the neocons such as Wolfowitz, who have convinced Bush to believe that we have to democratize the entire Middle East, topple Saddam, and only then can we deal with the Israeli-Palestinian issue.  Of course, that’s absolutely disastrous.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The neoconservative’s policies are so high-risk and there are so many things that could make it go even more wrong.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grover%20Norquist">Grover Norquist</ref> came out and said that nothing the supporters of the war said would happen with Iraq has happened, and that everything the critics said would happen <hi rend="italic">has</hi> happened.  If <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hosni_Mubarak">Mubarak</ref> suddenly dies in Egypt and that country erupts into a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamic%20Brotherhood">civil war</ref>, which is a scenario that is often discussed as likely, that would implode the region even further.   How do they account for all these risks they are laying in the lap of the United States?</hi></p>
</text>
