<text id="autogum_interview_doc966" title="part5_Wikinews interviews Fred Karger, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-04-23" dateModified="2014-03-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Fred_Karger%2C_U.S._Republican_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><p>And we did things in Puerto Rico well: we campaigned in the big towns that were competitive right before the election; did a lot of speaking; a lot of meeting the voters; colleges that we'd go to all over. So we did a blitz there in six days that was successful and I was proud to beat Ron Paul. And of course, what Romney did, and what Santorum didn't do was to listen to the voters and listen to the citizens of Puerto Rico, which you have to have respect for their heritage. And to come in and say this whole territory must learn English in order to be eligible for statehood is just not smart, spin politics. So I listened. I do. And I respect their heritage especially years of Spanish speaking that can't expect to transform that as a bargain, a negotiating bargain for statehood. So I just had regard for the culture and the people, and responded to what I think was a good fit for Puerto Rico. But I also, along with statehood, which is still a mixed issue down there, a lot of the younger people want independence than even want statehood, but I'm open to whatever that would be and to whatever the Puerto Ricans really would like to be for themselves.</p></p>
<head id="Political_views">Political views</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Let's get into policy. You proposed that the voting age be reduced. How might you convince Republicans to support this when polls suggest that the youth generally support Democrats?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Fred Karger</hi>: Well, it's something that I've not advocated as a particular constitutional amendment. I suggested that we should hold a discussion for lowering the voting age to 16 or 17. And that's one of the things I've been doing for our campaign. And in regards to your question, the Republican Party is doing everything it can to drive away this younger generation. Candidates like Rick Santorum, Newt Gingrich, or Mitt Romney are doing and saying things that are so anathema to younger voters. Ron Paul is doing the opposite.  That's why he gets 6400 people at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UCLA">UCLA</ref>. He gets thousands of students coming out. And I applaud him because he's the only one who has the foresight to realize there's a future to this Republican Party beyond November.</p>
<p><figure><caption>Karger speaking with youth in Puerto Rico.Image: Fred Karger.</caption></figure></p>
<p>So one of the things I've tried to do, I've tried to reach out to students in high school and college. I've spoken at a lot of high schools. There are 18 year old voters there. And I'm looking to the future of the Republican Party. And I think we need to do and say things and put the policies that will appeal to young voters. Currently jobs is the number one issue and I talk about that. That's a concern of younger voters in high school, college, wherever they are. So we just need to be a little more aware of that generation, so if there are 16 or 17 year old voters someday, they will be split, and that we will have welcomed them as Ronald Reagan did. There's a 70 year old man that just completely brought back a younger generation to the Republican Party that they had been driven away by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Watergate%20scandal">Watergate</ref>. I know because I was a younger voter then who was working with then-Republicans to bring younger voters into the Republican Party. And if they think it's tough now, it was ten times tougher then.</p></p>
</text>
