<text id="autogum_interview_doc736" title="part3_Randall Munroe, writer of xkcd, talks about the comic, politics and the internet" shortTile="partrandall-munroe" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-09" dateModified="2016-06-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Randall_Munroe%2C_writer_of_xkcd%2C_talks_about_the_comic%2C_politics_and_the_internet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You've had comics that have included actual people such as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Richard_Stallman">Richard Stallman</ref>  . What has been your reaction to meeting people you’ve discussed or mentioned or made fun of, or gently poked in the comic?</hi></p>
<p>RM: It’s extremely surreal. And I mean just discovering that my, this is a normal person, and this is someone from my history books and I’m sitting here eating food with them. And that has not stopped being weird. And a lot of the time I feel like I should be having more substantial conversation than I am.  I’m almost at a loss because it's such an enormous feeling. It makes me realize why people act so weird when they meet me, because I might be the same to them. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">So is there anyone you’ve put in the comics that you’d like to meet but haven’t?</hi></p>
<p>RM: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janeane%20Garofalo">Janeane Garofalo</ref> for a while now. My fans have been acting out my comics and I was making them weird and the fans were still acting them out. So I was just like, I’m going to make one that is impossible for you to make happen and then that can be the standing challenge. If someone can do that then I can start worrying about this again. And so I had <ref target="http://www.xkcd.com/254/">Janeane Garofalo jumping a motorcycle off of a crashing space station</ref> towards a volcanic island with dinosaurs while she is armed with a tranquilizer gun. I figured that would be good. The reason I mentioned her was because I’ve been watching some of her movies and she’s just adorable. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Somewhat on that topic, there was—I don’t know if you saw it—there was a website that had a fake news article about a hundred xkcders commit suicide by imitating one of your comics.</hi></p>
<p>RM: I read that, I forgot exactly what site it was maybe BBspot. </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Note it was BBspot. See</hi>
</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">So that's the sort of thing you're thinking of in terms of people imitating things? </hi></p>
<p>RM:  I generally don’t worry about you know, that people are going to do something deadly because I mention it. That would be bad but I don’t think that would be my responsibility if that happened.  I do sort of wonder about is, people acting out something that has negative effects on the community. If I put some kind of prank that in real life that would be mean-spirited or hurtful and if someone does that to someone famous and would lead to tension and bad feelings, then I would feel bad.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You did say on your blag at one point that “But remember, I am not advocating doing anything dangerous unless it’s really cool.”.</hi></p>
</text>
