<text id="autogum_interview_doc1313" title="part10_Wikinews interviews former Salt Lake City mayor and 2012 presidential candidate Rocky Anderson" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-12-17" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Salt_Lake_City_mayor_and_2012_presidential_candidate_Rocky_Anderson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What is the single most important issue facing Americans right now and how will you address this as president?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Rocky Anderson</hi>: The single most important issue facing our country is providing jobs, education, enhanced infrastructure, and encouraging innovation because we are falling so far behind the rest of the world. And part of that innovation and investment needs to be addressing climate change because in the long run, the impacts from climate change are going to be greater than…from any other shorter term issue right now.</p></p>
<p><p>Fiscal policy of course relates to all of that. We need to bring in adequate revenues so that we’re not passing off on to the next generation this enormous debt and interest burden, and we also need to get our spending under control, but still with an eye toward priming the pump during this recession and providing the kind of infrastructure, education, and innovation that’s going to serve this country not only for the present but far out into the future.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">This is my last question. What necessary freedoms are currently lacking in American society?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Anderson</hi>:There has never been a time in our nation’s history when the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20government%20of%20the%20United%20States#Executive_branch">executive branch</ref> has claimed so much power and abused that power and that runs the gamut. Our president has asked for the legal authority to point to anybody, even citizens of this country; have them taken away, essentially kidnapped, disappeared, detained without any limit; no legal representation, no charges, no trial. It is so absolutely contrary to what our <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Constitution">constitution</ref> is based upon and what our system of government is based upon. It’s contrary to our nation’s heritage, to our most dearly held values. The Senate just passed this incredible bill, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Defense%20Authorization%20Act%20for%20Fiscal%20Year%202012">Federal Military Authorization Act</ref> that would allow for that detention based on who-knows-what kind of information, no standard of proof, no public hearing. It’s not like these people are infallible.</p></p>
<hi rend="bold">The rule of law has been denigrated to the point never before experienced in this country.</hi>
<p><p>The rule of law has been denigrated to the point never before experienced in this country. People can commit war crimes and if they’re rich and powerful enough, the United States says let’s just look forward and not backwards and let them off the hook. Not even an investigation. So we the American people have lost the freedom to even know what our government is doing and to know whether or not they’re going to be held accountable under the law.</p></p>
<p><p>All three branches of government have been part of this deterioration of the law. Courts through the very subversive <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/State%20secrets%20privilege">state secrets doctrine</ref> will dismiss cases, not on the merits, but on the basis of the very perpetrator, the executive branch, coming to it and saying that the case cannot move forward because to do so would mean the disclosure of state secrets that would be contrary to national security, and so the courts throw the cases out. That is perhaps the most subversive thing that’s ever happened in this country because our system of government is based on the system of separation of powers and checks and balances. The courts are there in large part to protect against abuses of power including illegal conduct by the executive branch. If that check isn’t there, that spells tyranny. That means the executive branch can do whatever it wants, regardless of the law, even domestic laws and treaty obligations that have been passed by Congress.</p>
<p><figure><caption>Anderson (right) shakes hands with a peace activist and Iraq War veteran.Image: Jeremiah Roth.</caption></figure></p>
<p>So there have been torture victims, and by the way, these torture victims it has been established, they have zero connection to terrorism. Torture victims have come to our courts with the claims and they’re proven claims by the way that they were kidnapped by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CIA">CIA</ref>, disappeared from their families and other loved ones, whisked off, one to an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref> prison and another one to a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syrian</ref> prison. They were tortured. They were held for several months: one five months, the other one a year. One was a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">German</ref> citizen, the other a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canadian</ref> citizen. They come to our courts to challenge that illegal conduct, and by the way, the United States has assured the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20Nations%20Convention%20Against%20Torture#Committee_against_Torture">United Nations Committee Against Torture</ref> that we provide these kinds of remedies for victims of torture. So they come in, seek justice, seek a means of getting the truth out, and what is the response of the both the Bush and the Obama administration? They oppose the lawsuits even moving forward on the merits because, among other reasons, the state’s secret doctrine and the courts dismiss the cases. That is absolutely un-American.</p></p>
</text>
