<text id="autogum_interview_doc1090" title="part11_Vanity Fair contributing editor Craig Unger on the Bush family feud, neoconservatives and the Christian right" shortTile="partvanity-fair-contributing" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2015-08-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vanity_Fair_contributing_editor_Craig_Unger_on_the_Bush_family_feud%2C_neoconservatives_and_the_Christian_right" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  I’m not sure I have a good answer for that, but I can say they are REAL ideologues.  It’s worth going back to their history and a lot of this stuff is toxic, third-rail stuff.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Brooks">David Brooks</ref> attacked me as a conspiracy nut.  The point isn’t that the neocons had this weird Communist conspiracy or anything like that, but that they were trained ideologues and trained in ideological battles and sectarian disputes.  They purge people who disagree with them and work in an echo-chamber environment where they don’t admit any facts that contradict their preconceived ideas.  You see them operate as this ideological cadre.  They purged people in the State Department who were part of the Realist crowd, and I go into that.  They’ve had the same ideas for thirty years.</p>
<head id="On_the_press">On the press</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What sort of reaction do you get to your work?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  That’s a good question.  The reaction to my previous book was actually terrific, but it’s interesting the patterns.  In Europe—England, Spain, The Netherlands—it was terrific and I am thought of as a reasoned Centrist.  I am not thought of as particularly left-wing in any way.</p>
<figure><caption>German artist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas%20Demand">Thomas Demand</ref> speaking with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Craig%20Unger">Craig Unger</ref> about <hi rend="italic">The Fall of the House of Bush</hi>.photo: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You painstakingly researched this—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  I have over 2,000 footnotes there.  So in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref> my publisher, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planeta%20DeAgostini">Planeta</ref>, is considered a center-right company and they made me the big book of their season.  In Europe I am considered a straight-ahead reporter.  In the United States I tend to be shunned by the mainstream media, almost completely, especially by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White%20House%20press%20corp.">White House press corp.</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who have lost almost all credibility with the public...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  But they are still there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  We’re stuck with them.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Right, but they haven’t changed, so I will get almost nothing from them.  This includes the supposedly liberal New York Times.  I deal with the press to a fair extent in the book; not as much as I would like because that’s a whole interview in itself.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism,_Iraq_and_his_life">I interviewed Gay Talese</ref>, who had nothing but contempt for the Washington press corps.  He feels they should be broken up and dispersed around the country to report on the federal government.   Report on Washington from Denver, from Austin...national reporting from the states.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  It’s shocking the difference between the British and the Americans.  The huge part of it is the addiction to access.  It’s opportunism—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You get to go to a party; you get to ride in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air%20Force%20One">Air Force One</ref>—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Right!  “I want that interview with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald%20Rumsfeld">Donald Rumsfeld</ref> so I’m not going to do anything to alienate him by writing a story that is critical of him.”  And when you get that story you end up writing exactly what he tells you and it ain’t the truth.</p>
</text>
