<text id="autogum_interview_doc1285" title="part10_Edmund White on writing, incest, life and Larry Kramer" shortTile="partedmund-white" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-08" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edmund_White_on_writing%2C_incest%2C_life_and_Larry_Kramer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why did he drop you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  He found a new lover and he discovered he wasn’t really a top, but a bottom.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How does having a relationship like that fit in yours and Michael’s?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Nobody seems to understand it very well, and I’m not sure we’ve even articulated it.  Michael has a full time boyfriend who is a German who is quite a bit younger than he is.  He’s a historian, he’s a PhD student in history.  And I have a fulltime boyfriend who is a PhD student at Harvard in philosophy.  We both like each other’s boyfriends.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think not articulating it is what makes it work?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Yes.  We’re very very affectionate and we’re both bohemian.  Neither of us ever had an ideal of getting married and having a white picket fence, adopting a Korean girl or being respectable, or anything like that.  When we first met we both realized we are each sluts, so we cheerfully acknowledged that and went our way.  We’re in it for the long haul with each other.  Most couples, straight of gay—50% of all straight couples end in divorce—I think it would be even higher if people could afford to get divorced.  Partly the people who stay together are limited financially.  Anyway, I think that if you’re really in it for the long haul, you have to give each other a tremendously long leash.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you always practice safe sex?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I do.  Well, unless it’s somebody who is also positive.  If I’m positive, and somebody else is positive and he wants to bareback, that’s fine.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But there’s different strains of the virus, correct?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Or so they say.  I don’t think so.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You’ve never known of anyone who has said, “Oh, now I have a different strain and none of the drugs are working.”</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  No.  I think that’s something doctors told people because they were trying to scare the ones who are already positive and weren’t responsible towards their partners.  They were trying to give them a personal reason for practicing safe sex.  “Oh, your own health will deteriorate more if you don’t watch out.”  I think that’s bullshit.  I don’t always tell my partners I’m positive, but I always practice safe sex with somebody I don’t’ know and I just assume that’s enough.  If they ask, I always say the truth.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What difficulties have you encountered physically from being HIV positive?  Has it been a difficult row to hoe?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  No.  I found out I was positive in 1985, and I was probably positive already for five or six years at that point because I was very active sexually in the late seventies, early eighties.  I would go to the St. Mark’s baths, which was very close to where I lived, and get fucked 20 times in an evening, so why would I have not been positive then?  The first test became available in 1984, but I moved to Paris in late 1982 and I wasn’t really living near any place.  So when I had the test done in 1985 in Zurich, the results had to be sent to America to be analyzed; we had to wait three months to get the results.  That’s when I found out I was positive.  I only started taking meds a few years ago.</p>
</text>
