<text id="autogum_interview_doc157" title="part4_Wikinews interviews Australian Glider Amanda Carter" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-09-26" dateModified="2017-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Glider_Amanda_Carter" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Who was that?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> It was Brendan Stroud at the time, who was coaching the Dandenong Rangers women's team. I just happened to cross him at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northland%20Shopping%20Centre">Northland</ref>, the shopping centre. And he said: "Why don't you come out and play for Dandenong?" I was looking fit and everything else, so I thought "Okay, I'll come out to one training session and see how I go." And from there played in the 2008 Women's National League. And was voted MVP — most valuable one-pointer, and all-star five. So at that point, in 2009, after that, they went to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Beijing">Beijing</ref>, so I watched Beijing from home, because I wasn't involved in the Gliders program.  I just really came back to do women's league. In 2009, I received some phone calls from the coaching staff, John Trescari, who was coaching the Gliders at that point, who invited me back in to the Glider's training program, about February, and I said I would come to the one camp and see how I went. And went to the one camp and then got selected to go to Canada. So, since then I've been back in the team.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Back in the Gliders again.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yeah!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  And of course you got selected for 2012... </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  My recollection is that you weren't on the court a great deal, but there was a game when you scored five points?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yeah! Within a couple of minutes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  That was against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yes. That was a good win, actually, that one.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   The strange thing was that afterwards the Mexicans were celebrating like they'd won...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Oh yeah! It was very strange. I guess one of the things that, like, I am in some ways the backup one pointer in some ways, but what gives me my one point classification, because I used to be a two, is my arm, the damage I received, and the quadriplegia from the transverse myelitis. So despite the fact I probably shoot more accurately that most people in the team, because I've just had to learn to shoot, it also slows me down; I'm not the quickest in the team for getting up and down the court, because of having trouble with grip and stuff on my right hand to push. I push reasonably quick! Most people would say I'm reasonably quick, but when you at me in comparison to, say, the other eleven girls in the team, I am not as quick.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The speed at which things move is quite astonishing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yeah, and my ability is more in knowing where people want to get to, so I aim to get there first by taking the most direct route. [laughter]</p>
</text>
