<text id="autogum_interview_doc421" title="part0_&amp;quot;Avast ye scurvy file sharers!&amp;quot;: Interview with Swedish Pirate Party leader Rickard Falkvinge" shortTile="partavast-ye-scurvy" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-06-19" dateModified="2015-10-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/%22Avast_ye_scurvy_file_sharers%21%22%3A_Interview_with_Swedish_Pirate_Party_leader_Rickard_Falkvinge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>"Avast ye scurvy file sharers!": Interview with Swedish Pirate Party leader Rickard Falkvinge</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 20, 2006</hi></p>
<p>MP3s for the people? The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pirate%20Party%20of%20Sweden">Pirate Party</ref>, a new <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Swedish</ref> political party first publicized in January, wants to legalize sharing music, movies, and other copyrighted content using the Internet.  What may seem like a doomed effort by a small group of idealists is attracting significant media attention, in part due to a recent police raid on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Pirate_Bay">The Pirate Bay</ref>, an extremely popular <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BitTorrent%20tracker">BitTorrent tracker</ref> (see <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Pirate_Bay_and_Piratbyrån_raided">Wikinews coverage</ref>). </p>
<p>The Pirate Bay allows people to download content listed in its database using the BitTorrent protocol (including the latest Hollywood movies or computer games) and has gained something of an international cult status, in part for its public and irreverent responses to legal threats received from copyright lawyers of major corporations.  The site was reopened days after the raid on Dutch servers (but is now back in Sweden again). Rickard Falkvinge, leader of the Pirate Party, argues that regardless of the legal outcome in the case, the web site demonstrates that copyright law in its current form is not sustainable.</p>
<p>Adopting the moniker of the maligned "Internet pirates", the party argues for drastically limiting the scope and enforcement of copyright law, abolishing patent law, and protecting privacy in what it sees as a "control and surveillance society". The party is hoping to garner enough votes in the September election to become a small but important faction in the next Swedish parliament.  Rickard Falkvinge found some time in between interviews and party work to answer our questions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">There are rumours that the Swedish government was indirectly acting on behalf of the U.S. MPAA in shutting down the site. Do you feel that your government is beholden to U.S. interests?</hi></p>
<p>Oh, the MPAA said so themselves in a press release, it's more than a rumor. Check their press release "Swedish authorities sink Pirate Bay". <hi rend="italic">[Ed.: see <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#External_links">below</ref>]</hi></p>
<p>And yes, this particular fact has caused something of an uproar in Sweden. It's widely believed that Swedish authorities were more or less ordered by a foreign power to act forcefully against an entity that was in, at worst, a legal gray area according to Swedish law.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">The raid must have boosted your recognition. How many members do you currently have, and how successful has your fundraising effort been so far?</hi></p>
<p>Our member count is at 6540, no, 6541, no wait, 6543... well, you get the picture. Our members register themselves on our website after paying the membership fee electronically, which helps reduce our admin load considerably.</p>
<p>Fundraising brought in 108,000 SEK <hi rend="italic">[Ed.: approx. 14,700 USD or 11,600 EUR]</hi>, enough to buy 3 million ballots, which is some kind of at-least-we're-not-starving minimum. We're not full, but we're not starving, either. Following the raid on the Pirate Bay, we have received another 50K in donations. My sincere thanks to everybody who wants to help out; we are now looking into getting more ballots to make sure we don't run out on election day. (10 million ballots was our initial full-score aim.)</p>
</text>
