<text id="autogum_interview_doc939" title="part5_KKE: Interview with the Greek Communist Party" shortTile="partkke-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-05-13" dateModified="2019-09-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/KKE%3A_Interview_with_the_Greek_Communist_Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>A few days ago, being annoyed by the fact that the seamen prevented the strike breaking in a cruise ship, the bourgeoisie and its journalists accused the seamen of anti-patriotism for attacking tourism which is ‘the only thing we have left’. They even encouraged the government to ban the organisation of strikes. Despite the media efforts to turn even the tourists against the seamen, the majority of travellers expressed their solidarity to the strike. Their problem is not the historical meaning of Acropolis or tourism, their problem is organised struggle.</p>
<p>We have said it before and we'll say it again: the images broadcast by the media of our struggle are an honour for the working people of our country. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Iain</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How would you respond to the criticisms levelled by Petros Tzomakas of Xekinima, who denounced the KKE's lack of co-operation with SYRIZA [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coalition%20of%20the%20Radical%20Left">Coalition of the Radical Left</ref>] in a recent interview?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Isabella</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> SYRIZA are the tail of social democracy in Greece. Their analysis on the crisis is similar to PASOK. According to them, the way out is a more ‘human capitalism’, where ‘people will come first’ and profits will follow. What they are hiding from the people is that capitalist profits cannot co-exist with pro-popular policies, the basic contradiction between capital and labour cannot be overcome.</p>
<p>SYRIZA, being consistently pro-E.U. (it has voted for the Maastricht treaty after all), prefers the implementation of the same measures by the E.U. rather than the IMF and fights for different versions of the '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stability%20Pact">Stability Pact</ref>'. As if the E.U. is the good cop and the IMF the bad one. We say: this is a fake dilemma; there is no good or bad imperialism. All of them are good for serving their own monopolies, their own fat cats. The bottom line is that there is increasing antagonism between the different imperialist centres and the Greek government is trying to play the game with all of them. KKE has warned that this leads to our even deeper involvement in the inter-imperialist rivalries, and this can be a very dangerous path. They all agree 100% on the measures taken by the government and they ask for more blood now. Contrary to the party of Syriza, we do not plan to choose our assassin or negotiate the terms of the assassination with any of them.</p>
<p>It is also important to notice that for years now, in the trade union movement and during the latest strikes and rallies, SYRIZA has been following the compromised leaderships of GSEE [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General%20Confederation%20of%20Greek%20Workers">General Confederation of Greek Workers</ref>] and ADEDY (the Greek <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TUC">TUC</ref> in the private and public sector respectively, controlled by PASOK) who originally boycotted the strikes, went on strike breaking and then dragged them in unwillingly under public pressure, in order to minimise the damage to the government. </p>
</text>
