<text id="autogum_interview_doc288" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Steve Kissing, independent candidate for US President" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-16" dateModified="2014-04-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Steve_Kissing%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I will also work with diplomats as well as community and religious leaders to create an atmosphere of mutual respect and understanding among the great faiths of the world, particularly, though not exclusively, between Christianity and Islam.</p>
<p>Finally, as noted above, I will be an advocate for new technologies and more eco-friendly ways of living that can drastically reduce our dependence on foreign oil.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Education and Healthcare.</hi> I combine these issues because, if America is to remain a vibrant nation, our citizens must be strong and nimble when it comes to both mind and body.</p>
<p>I support vouchers and privatized education. Let’s allow the free market and competition improve the effectiveness and efficiency of our educational system.</p>
<p>We need to also better compensate our teachers, <hi rend="italic">but</hi> we must also hold them to higher standards of excellence. Teachers have an important, tough job, but too many have "tuned out". I would love our culture to evolve to the point where teaching is given the respect, admiration and financial incentives that, say, doctors and lawyers do.</p>
<p>We absolutely need universal health care, but the free market should remain at the helm, with private companies competing for the government’s business.</p>
<p>In addition, our national healthcare program must focus on patient education, motivation and preventative health. Treating people via the emergency room for conditions that could have easily been prevented with some attentive care, need to be eliminated.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Campaigning for the American presidency is one of the most expensive exercises in the world. How do you deal with the cost and fundraising?</hi></p>
<p>The fact that it costs so much to run for President should alarm every American. The huge sums of money required to be a viable candidate only serve to keep politics and politicians focused on money, and those who provide it and the special interest they represent.</p>
<p>I am hoping to rely on my own creativity and that of my supporters to get our message out. With any luck, our "untainted" message will breakthrough. I'm not foolish enough to expect that this will be easy, or that it’s likely. But my longing for a different kind of politics, and a different kind of politician keeps me hopeful.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Do you have a running mate yet? Who are they? What are you looking for in a running mate?</hi></p>
<p>I do not have a running mate, but I am seeking nominations on my website (kissing4prez.org). I’m looking for someone who shares my fundamental belief that politics as usual needs to go, and fast. I am looking for someone with a proven track record in generating creative thoughts and solutions; someone who is open-minded and willing to make compromises; some who is hopeful and optimistic. Since my campaign doesn't have a significant budget, I would love to have a vice-presidential candidate who has some forum, be that via celebrity, a popular blog or even just being in a band. Personally, I would love to have a candidate who is a person of color, and, ideally, a non-Christian. In fact, I would be most pleased to have a Muslim on my ticket.</p>
</text>
