<text id="autogum_interview_doc1179" title="part3_Canada's Etobicoke—Lakeshore (Ward 5) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-etobicokelakeshore" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-10-19" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Etobicoke%E2%80%94Lakeshore_%28Ward_5%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in
this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Protecting our quality of life is the most fundamental issue a City Councillor has to address.  Therefore all of those elements which I have explained in the previous question  are the most relevant issues which affect the daily lives of my neighbours in Ward 5.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I became involved in election campaigns as a teenager, at age fourteen in fact.  I have always found politics to be an intriguing and engrossing endeavour.  I firmly believe that every citizen has an obligation to engage in the political process to some degree.</p>
<p>After graduating from the University of Toronto with a degree in Architecture and working in architecture, design, and development I realized the fundamental link between the shape and form of our cities and the political process at the municipal level.</p>
<p>I first ran for City Council at age 25, and was first elected at age 28.  I believed then, and still do today that I can make a positive impact on the quality of our built environment.  Beyond that I have also found public service to be a very fulfilling and meaningful vocation.  Helping one's neighbours and fellow residents with their daily problems, and plan for the future is an extraordinary opportunity to contribute to society.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> This is my home.  I live in Ward 5, and I have lived in or within a few hundred metres of the ward's current boundaries my entire life.  I grew up and was educated in area schools such as Islington Junior Middle School and Etobicoke Collegiate.  I want to protect the neighbourhoods in Ward 5 and I want to shape the future of the parts of the Ward that are in transition because I plan to continue to live here.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> As the current City Councillor I am intimately involved with all parts of the community, and the entire range of issues that our area faces.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Toronto is my home.  This is a City with wonderful greenery and space.  The waterfront (in Etobicoke) provides us with an escape from the congestion of the City with views that stretch to the horizon.  I can find rest and relaxation here and also great excitement and activity.</p>
<p>Our city is a city of great opportunities, it is open and free.  Within our borders we can experience all that the world can offer through cuisine, language, and interaction with people from all over the globe.</p>
</text>
