<text id="autogum_interview_doc1278" title="part3_Edmund White on writing, incest, life and Larry Kramer" shortTile="partedmund-white" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-08" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edmund_White_on_writing%2C_incest%2C_life_and_Larry_Kramer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Earlier you were saying what makes a book a certain genre is a marketing function.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Yes, but I think that what she is doing is trying to create readers who will then buy gay…I’m not saying all gay and lesbian books are cynically marketed.  There were a lot of books when I was young that weren’t marketed as gay books; books by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcel%20Proust">Proust</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas%20Mann">Thomas Mann</ref> and so on.  Andre Gilde.  They had gay themes but the “gay novel” didn’t exist then.  The problem is we have an awfully lot of good gay writers and very few good gay readers.  I don’t know why that is, but it’s true.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who are some good gay writers?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Vestal McIntyre, Patrick Ryan are just two.</p>
<head id="On_sex">On sex</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You said in an interview that the smartest people are the best sex—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  —what is sex to you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  The most important thing in the world.  I had a sex partner who I thought was really great sex but one day he said to me, “I really enjoy playing basketball more than having sex,” and I was so offended.  I thought that was like somebody saying, “I’d rather go shopping than go to church.”  It seemed to be so trivializing of this sacred thing of sex that it was hard to see him again after that.  So what is it for me?  Something very transcendent and I turn my life upside down to have it as frequently as possible.  No, it’s not frequency, it’s quality that’s important.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How can something repeated so often still be considered sacred?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  What about the mass?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you only have sex once a week?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  They have mass every day.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  People don’t go to mass every day, typically.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  They can.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They could.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  No, I’m having sex more often than once week.  It’s hard to defend the position logically, I just mean to me it’s important.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is that the main criterion for a partner?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  No.  I’ve lived with Michael for 12 years and I don’t think that has ever been the key issue between us.  He’s a writer, compatible and he’s one of the most interesting people I know.  He’s always unpredictable.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You have an open relationship?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think that’s a necessity in order to have a successful relationship?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I wouldn’t preach for anybody else; I mean, everybody’s different.  But for me, yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where do you tend to find your sexual partners?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  On-line, now.  Silverdaddies.com; daddyhunt.  That’s where you go if you’re older.  Or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manhunt.net">Manhunt</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gay.com">gay.com</ref>.  Or slavesformaster.  Those are all sites where I’ve met people.</p>
</text>
