<text id="autogum_interview_doc667" title="part10_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Recently Obama and Clinton were down there marching...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Bullshit!  It's all total bullshit.  The city of Selma--not to just single it out, the country is racist.  New York is racist.  This neighborhood!  I've lived in this house for fifty years, where you and I are now, and this neighborhood.  When I first moved in here in 1957, it didn't have any black neighbors.  I'm speaking in 2007.  No black neighbors.  Does that mean Michael Jackson couldn't move in?  I guess.  I don't see them.  I guess you could have stars.  But even they would have trouble.  And we still have a Harlem.    We wouldn't have a Harlem if we had an integrated and assimilated society.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And that's going.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  If they drive them out...they'll go.  But what I'm saying is they are sectioned off.  So we talk about the segregated south, the black ghettos--the black quarter--of Birmingham. We still have that. We aren't so up front about it, meaning they are less honest and more devious in undemocratic ways.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you see the election in Alabama when the Christian Coalition defeated the ballot measure to remove the segregation language from the Alabama Constitution that said nobody is guaranteed a right to an education?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Such a high level of hypocrisy that has existed in this country from decade to decade.  I'm 75 years old, and it wasn't so different when I was 25 years old.  That's a 50 year difference--what's so different?  I don't know.  I travel and I don't see much change.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you changed?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I've gotten older and maybe more cynical.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you were 25 did you look at black people the same way as you look at them now?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Yeah.  When I was 25 or 15, it was the same, because in my town Ocean City, New Jersey, I went to school with black people.  It wasn't segregated.  I was born in 1932 and when I was in eight or nine I saw the Klan in their white sheets on the Boardwalk.  This is not Birmingham, this Ocean CIty, New Jersey.  I saw the Klan.  My father was a tailor and he was a practicing Catholic.  A cross was burned across from his story; I was six or seven.  And we knew who the Klan were.  The leading pharmacist was a Klansman, my father told me that.  Two firemen in the town.  They would meet publicly, and black people were in the town.  They had their own Harlem in Ocean City.  So there is a real estate racism.  Ocean City, New York City, Selma, Alabama.  They all have their black quarters still.</p>
</text>
