<text id="autogum_interview_doc1150" title="part4_Obesity and the Fat Acceptance Movement: Kira Nerusskaya speaks" shortTile="partobesity-fat-acceptance" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-09" dateModified="2014-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Obesity_and_the_Fat_Acceptance_Movement%3A_Kira_Nerusskaya_speaks" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What sorts of things are said to you on the street?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  A lot of times people will say things like, “Fat ass!” or “Hey fatty,” or whatever.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  People will actually yell out to you, “Hey, fat ass!”</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Yeah.  But there are also a lot of men that go, [<hi rend="italic">makes kissing sound</hi>] "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mami">Mami</ref>!" or whistle or wink or whatever.  It’s a spectrum, and I think if you’re confident in the way you’re holding yourself, smiling, you look nice, that kind of a thing, then you’re not buying into that.  You’re not feeding that negative stigma of fat people, and of fat women in particular.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you feel if people stare at you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  It doesn’t bother me.  I usually make eye contact with them, and then if it's negative, they stop.  In such a variety of ways and a variety of places people will stare at me and people will turn their heads.  Somebody who I dated was like, “Dating you is like dating a freaking celebrity because wherever we go people are turning their heads!  A lot of times they’re not necessarily doing anything negative or they’re complimenting you or they’re coming up to talk to you and you have that energy that people are drawn to in whatever capacity.”  And he’s like, “I never met somebody so freaking exciting or been so excited to be out with somebody!’  We could be going out for coffee, we could be at a bar, just wherever we would be it would always happen and he just was so astounded about that, which is kind of an interesting thing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I think people reading that would think that people are looking at you because they’re disgusted that you’re fat.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Well, some could be.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But that’s not your experience?  That’s not what you’re getting from it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Sometimes, but not always.  I know what it’s like to walk into a store and have people roll their eyes at me or have somebody look at me on the subway and smirk talk to their friend and burst out laughing.  It’s not because they’re saying, “Ooh, that lipstick looks horrible.”  You know what it is.  You know what it is.  You’ve been fat long enough you know.  It’s not like it’s some freaking secret.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you ever confront people?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Yes, I do and I’ve become more confrontational as times goes on.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you confront them what happens?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  It depends.  Usually they shut the hell up.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do they apologize?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Sometimes.  Sometimes people are too scared to apologize because I’m calling them on it.  They think you’re supposed to be defenseless because you’re fat.  You’re not supposed to defend yourself because you’re fat.  That’s one thing that I’ve noticed in my work.  In my life I did not always defend myself, even though it would have been right.  I think I was the better person on more than one occasion, and more polite on other occasions, but in a way I feel like I am defending everyone here.  That’s one of the key components to my film:  for us to defend ourselves.  If something happens in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African-American">African-American</ref> community that’s discriminatory or racial, my friends <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesse%20Jackson">Jesse Jackson</ref> and Reverend <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9-1-1">9-1-1</ref>, which is my love name for Reverend <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al%20Sharpton">Al Sharpton</ref>, will turn around and say, “This isn’t right.  We demand justice.”  But fat people don’t have a voice.  There’s nobody coming to our aid when somebody says something negative. Or if they do, no one is hearing them, they aren't getting the media attention-- or maybe it isn't loud enough. There’s nobody that’s coming to our aide when we are treated poorly because we’re fat.  That we’re not getting health insurance or companies are badgering fat employees because of health insurance.  I can’t tell you how many calls Lynn McAfee gets a day -- from the Council on Size Discrimination -- just because people are overweight.  It’s really sad.</p>
</text>
