<text id="autogum_interview_doc1257" title="part0_CanadaVOTES: Christian Heritage Party leader Ron Gray running in Langley" shortTile="partcanadavotes-christian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-09-18" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_Christian_Heritage_Party_leader_Ron_Gray_running_in_Langley" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>CanadaVOTES: Christian Heritage Party leader Ron Gray running in Langley</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 19, 2008</hi></p>
<p>On October 14, 2008, Canadians will be heading to the polls for the federal election. <hi rend="bold">Christian Heritage Party candidate Ron Gray</hi> is standing for election in <hi rend="bold">the riding of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Langley">Langley</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>Wikinews contacted Ron Gray, to talk about the issues facing Canadians, and what they and their party would do to address them. Wikinews is in the process of contacting every candidate, in every riding across the country, no matter their political stripe. All interviews are conducted over e-mail, and interviews are published unedited, allowing candidates to impart their full message to our readers, uninterrupted.</p>
<p>Mr. Gray has been leader of the Christian Heritage Party since 1995. He first ran for office in 1988.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why are you running for political office, why at the federal level, why this party, and why in this riding?</hi></p>
<p>I'm not a 'new' candidate, having run eight times before; but neither am I an incumbent.</p>
<p>I'm running for office because I believe Canada desperately needs to restore respect for time-tested, proven biblical principles as the foundation for public policy; because the Conservatives have now made themselves the defenders of the abortion industry and the "gay rights" lobby... with Stephen Harper's statement (in december, 2005): "I will use whatever influence I have to ensure that no legislation on abortion comes into Parliament"; and Justice Minister Rob Nicholson's statement, when he introduced a government bill designed to trash Conservative MP Ken Epp's Unborn Victims of Crime bill: “Let me be clear, our government will not reopen the debate on abortion… the government will introduce legislation that will punish criminals who commit violence against pregnant women but do so in a way that leaves no room for the introduction of fetal rights.”</p>
<p>Of course, the other parties are all in complete accord with this, which leaves the 40-70% of Canadians (depending on how the survey is framed) who are pro-life with no one to represent them.</p>
<p>In addition, the so-called "Conservatives: broke their promise on income trusts... on defending the traditional definition of marriage... and they even broke their own LAW on fixed election dates.... and all the other parties are equally vapid and culpable.</p>
<p>Why? Because they have no principled basis for shaping policies!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Previous to this campaign, have you been politically involved? How will you apply your previous work/volunteer/life experience to serving your constituents?</hi></p>
<p>Yes. As stated above, I have run for office 8 times. My background as a journalist involved covering politics, as well as BC Supreme Court. My background in public information services (especially Information Canada) brought me into frequent direct contact with Canadians from many walks of life, and acquainted me with their needs and the ways in which the government bureaucracy (and, often, Cabinet venality) frustrated them.</p>
</text>
