<text id="autogum_interview_doc589" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic skiers Jessica Gallagher and Eric Bickerton" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-10" dateModified="2017-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_skiers_Jessica_Gallagher_and_Eric_Bickerton" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The two of you train together all the time?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> Pretty well, yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> Yes, everything on snow basically is together. One of the difficult things I guess is we have to have that 100 per cent communication and trust between one another and a lot of the female skiers on the circuit, their guide is their husband. That's kind of a trust relationship. Eric does say that at times it feels like we're married, but...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> I keep checking for my wallet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> ...it's always about constantly trying to continue to build that relationship so that eventually I just... You put your life in his hands and whatever he says, you do, kind of thing.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Of the two sport, winter sports and summer sports person, how do you find that balance between one sport and the other sport?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> It's not easy. Yeah, it's not easy at all. Yesterday was my first day on snow since March 16, 2010. And that was mainly because of the build up obviously for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2012_Summer_Paralympics">London</ref> and the times when I was going to ski I was injured. So, to not have skied for that long is obviously a huge disadvantage when all the girls have been racing the circuit since... and it's vice versa with track and field. So I've got an amazing team at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Victoria,_Australia">Victorian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victorian%20Institute%20of%20Sport">Institute of Sport</ref>. I call them my little A Team of strength and mission coach, <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/physiotherapist">physio</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/osteopath">osteopath</ref>, soft tissue therapist, sport psychologist, dietician. Basically everyone has expertise in the area and we come together and having meetings and plan four years ahead and say at the moment <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2014_Winter_Paralympics">Sochi</ref>'s the goal, but <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2016_Summer_Paralympics">Rio</ref>'s still in the back of the head, and knowing my body so well now that I've done both sports for five years means that I can know where they've made mistakes, and I know where things have gone really well, so we can plan ahead for that and prepare so that the things that did go wrong won't happen again. To make sure that I get to each competition in peak tone.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What things went wrong?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> Mainly injuries. So, that's the most difficult thing with doing two sports. Track and field is an explosive power; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/long%20jump">long jump</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/javelin%20throw">javelin</ref> are over four to six seconds of maximum effort. Ski racing, you are on a course, for a minute to a minute and a half, so it's a speed endurance event. And the two couldn't be further apart in terms of the capabilities and the capacities that you need as an athlete. So one of the big things I guess, after the Vancouver campaign, being in ski boots for so long, I had lost a lot of muscle from my calves so they weren't actually firing properly, and when you're trying to run and jump and you don't have half of your leg working properly it makes it pretty difficult to jump a good distance. Those kind of things. So I'm skiing now but when I'm in a gym doing recovery and rehab or prehab stuff, I've got calf raising, I've got hamstring exercises because I know they're the weaker areas that if I'm not working on at the moment they're two muscle groups that don't get worked during ski. That I need to do the extra stuff on the side so that when I transition back to track and field I don't have any soft tissue injuries like strains because of the fact that I know they're weaker so...</p>
</text>
