<text id="autogum_interview_doc008" title="part2_Male Magellanic penguins pine for pairings: Wikinews interviews biologist Natasha Gownaris" shortTile="partmale-magellanic" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-01-03" dateModified="2019-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Male_Magellanic_penguins_pine_for_pairings%3A_Wikinews_interviews_biologist_Natasha_Gownaris" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>The victorious male departs with the female.Image: Natasha Gownaris.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You suggest conservation efforts should look at protection of feeding grounds. What sort of measures do you think might be beneficial?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NG</hi>: Because penguins migrate such long distances over the non-breeding season, a mixture of tools (including no-take marine protected areas and traditional fisheries management tools, like catch limits) is likely to be needed. Although there is currently some spatial protection surrounding the species’ breeding colony, this protection does not extend to their migratory route. And, of course, everyone can contribute to penguin conservation by reducing their plastic waste, making more sustainable food choices, and reducing their <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/carbon%20footprint">carbon footprint</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What do you think might be causing pressure on food sources for the penguins?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NG</hi>: The two main threats to the food sources of this colony are <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Climate_change">climate change</ref>, which cause shifts in primary productivity and fish stocks, and fisheries. Fisheries compete with penguins for fish species such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/hake">hake</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/anchovy">anchovy</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Have you noticed differences in behavior among the penguins as the ratios become increasingly skewed?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NG</hi>: In a separate study currently under review, we have shown that aggression between males of Magellanic penguins is higher when the sex ratio at the colony is more skewed towards males. We also showed that nearly all females at the colony breed but that, over time, fewer and fewer males find mates. Single male penguins sometimes intrude [on] nests of mated pairs and interrupt the incubation of eggs or feeding of chicks, leading to mortality. In some cases, they will even attack and kill chicks. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Your release mentioned sexing the penguins was problematic; how did you achieve it with confidence?</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of a Guanaco surrounded by penguins on Punta Tombo.Image: <ref target="https://www.flickr.com/people/furlin/">furlin</ref> via <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flickr">Flickr</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">NG</hi>: We have some methods of sexing penguins that we feel confident about — using genetics or measures of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cloaca">cloaca</ref> size around egg laying, for example. However, these methods are time intensive, so we have also developed visual cues for sex penguins (bill size, behavior, forehead shape). We looked at individuals that had been sexed using both a certain method (e.g. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/genetics">genetics</ref>) and visual methods to calculate how often we got it right based on visual cues alone and found that we have very high accuracy. We also used statistical tools to help to deal with uncertainty in the sex of some individuals. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How well can you extrapolate population trends at Punta Tombo based on the birds you tagged? More broadly, how well do you think this work represents global populations?</p>
<hi rend="bold">everyone can contribute to penguin conservation by reducing their plastic waste, making more sustainable food choices, and reducing their carbon footprint</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Natasha Gownaris</p>
</text>
