<text id="autogum_interview_doc406" title="part4_Bat for Lashes plays the Bowery Ballroom: an Interview with Natasha Khan" shortTile="partbat-lashes-plays" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-27" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bat_for_Lashes_plays_the_Bowery_Ballroom%3A_an_Interview_with_Natasha_Khan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How are you received in the Pakistani community?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  I have absolutely no idea!  You should probably ask another question, because I have no idea.  I don't have contact with that side of my family anymore.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you see artists like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pete%20Doherty">Pete Doherty</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amy%20Winehouse">Amy Winehouse</ref> out on these suicidal binges of drug use, what do you think as a musician?  What do you get from what you see them go through in their personal lives and with their music?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  It's difficult.  The drugs thing was never important to me, it was the music and expression and the way he delivered his music, and I think there's a strange kind of romantic delusion in the media, and the music media especially, where they are obsessed with people who have terrible drug problems.  I think that's always been the way, though, since <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Billie%20Holiday">Billie Holiday</ref>.  The thing that I'm questioning now is that it seems now the celebrity angle means that the lifestyle takes over from the actual music.  In the past people who had musical genius, unfortunately their personal lives came into play, but maybe that added a level of romance, which I think is pretty uncool, but, whatever.  I think that as long as the lifestyle doesn't precede the talent and the music, that's okay, but it always feels uncomfortable for me when people's music goes really far and if you took away the hysteria and propaganda of it, would the music still stand up?  That's my question. Just for me, I'm just glad I don't do heavy drugs and I don't have that kind of problem, thank God.  I feel that's a responsibility you have, to present that there's a power in integrity and strength and in the lifestyle that comes from self-love and assuredness and positivity.  I think there's a real big place for that, but it doesn't really get as much of that "Rock n' Roll" play or whatever.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is it difficult to come to the United States to play considering all the wars we start?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  As an English person I feel equally as responsible for that kind of shit.  I think it is a collective consciousness that allows violence and those kinds of things to continue, and I think that our governments should be ashamed of themselves.  But at the same time, it's a responsibility of all of our countries, no matter where you are in the world to promote  a peaceful lifestyle and not to consciously allow these conflicts to continue.  At the same time, I find it difficult to judge because I think that the world is full of shades of light and dark, from spectrums of pure light and pure darkness, and that's the way human nature and nature itself has always been.  It's difficult, but it's just a process, and it's the big creature that's the world; humankind is a big creature that is learning all the time.  And we have to go through these processes of learning to see what is right.</p>
</text>
