<text id="autogum_interview_doc580" title="Interview with Frank Warren, founder of PostSecret" shortTile="interview-frank-warren" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-01-07" dateModified="2019-01-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Frank_Warren%2C_founder_of_PostSecret" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with Frank Warren, founder of PostSecret</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 7, 2006</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PostSecret">PostSecret</ref> is a community art project where people release their secrets by anonymously mailing them on a homemade postcard. Frank Warren started PostSecret in November, 2004 and has since received thousands of secrets from all over the world. The cards appeared in an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All-American%20Rejects">All-American Rejects</ref> music video for the song <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dirty%20Little%20Secret">Dirty Little Secret</ref>, and PostSecret's fee? a $2,000 donation to The National Hopeline Network 1(800)SUICIDE, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/suicide">suicide</ref> hotline. PostSecret has recently published a book of some of the postcards with some of the proceeds also going to the hotline.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews: What is PostSecret for you?</hi></p>
<p>Frank Warren: PostSecret is a community art project where anyone can write a secret on a postcard and mail it in.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">You originally sent out 3,000 postcards at the projects inception in November, 2004.  Over a year later, approximately how many cards have you received?</hi></p>
<p>20,000.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Geographically, how far away have you received postcards?</hi></p>
<p>The cards come from all over the world; Hong Kong, Afghanistan, Australia, Ireland, India...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">You let the All-American Rejects use the postcards in their video for a donation to the National Hopeline Network, a suicide hotline.  You also have a book out now with some of the proceeds going to National Hopeline.  Is depression the most common theme in the secrets that you have received?</hi></p>
<p>I do not know if depression is the most common theme, but I picked the charity because of my own experiences with suicide and because I have first-hand knowledge of the good work done by 1(800)SUICIDE.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What, in your opinion, is the motivation for people to send you their secrets?</hi></p>
<p>I think some people are looking to share a funny story, others want to talk about a secret kindness they performed but most people, I believe, are looking to better understand their own secrets and perhaps use this project as a first step in taking action upon their secrets.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Have you ever gotten into any sort of trouble or controversy because of what you have posted on your site? If so, what has happened as a result?</hi></p>
<p>I once received a postcard from a girl saying, "I worked really hard to get into [Ivy League School] but now I hate it here."  She later contacted me and said her friends and family recognized her handwriting and the posting was causing her distress.  She asked me to remove it and I did.  But I asked her to let me know how things turned-out  in the long-run.  Maybe this event will cause her to change schools or find new ways to appreciate where she is now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Finally, PostSecret has touched and aided the lives of many people.  How can people help the project?</hi></p>
<p>I hope people just continue to bravely share their secrets on the site and visitors continue to express their understanding and compassion.</p>
</text>
