<text id="autogum_interview_doc1189" title="part1_BDSM as business: An interview with the owners of a dungeon" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_An_interview_with_the_owners_of_a_dungeon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>"The best way to describe it," says Bill, "is if you had a kink, and you had a wife and you had two kids, and every time you had sex with your wife it just didn't hit the nail on the head.  What would you do about it?  How would you handle it?  You might go through life feeling unfulfilled.  Or you might say, 'No, my kink is I really need to dress in women's clothing.'  We're that outlet.  We're not the evil devil out here, plucking people off the street, keeping them chained up for days on end."  </p>
<p>Below is David Shankbone's interview with Bill &amp; Rebecca, owners of Rebecca's Hidden Chamber, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeon%20(BDSM)">BDSM dungeon</ref>.</p>
<head id="Meet_Bill_&amp;_Rebecca,_owners_of_a_BDSM_dungeon">Meet Bill &amp; Rebecca, owners of a BDSM dungeon</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  What first attracted you to this business?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Nothing other than it seemed like it would be profitable; we had a third partner who knew someone who was involved in this business.  It was supposed to be a business that we weren't going to run, if you recall.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  We were going to be absentee.  Nothing but money.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You would provide start-up costs and get it going?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Precisely.  But there were some setbacks; we ended up running it ourselves, learning a lot about the business and doing it really well.  I had a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PhD">doctorate</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychology">psychology</ref>; my wife is probably the best salesperson I've ever seen in the world.  Together, we've been able to put together a nice model business.  We're probably the best S&amp;M-fantasy-role-playing dungeon in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manhattan">Manhattan</ref>.  We are that way because we think of the client first.  What makes us different than all the other dungeons:  we treat them like human beings first.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  We're not--the typical.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  We are atypical.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What makes you atypical?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  A couple of things.  We run it like a business.  We do not run it like a club.  We did our homework and found most of the places in the city are run by people that aren't the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/intellgence">smartest</ref>, aren't the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/sanity">sanest</ref>, aren't great businesspeople; they don't have a business background.  They are people more inclined to be interested in S&amp;M.  Where my wife and I, we're sort of interested in money first.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You don’t a have personal interest in S&amp;M?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  No, I don't.  I do not.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Shakes her head no</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How is it that you're able to run a business that's centered around S&amp;M and caters to those clients, when you don't have that inclination for yourselves?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Good question for you.</p>
</text>
