<text id="autogum_interview_doc485" title="part1_ACLU, EFF challenging US &amp;apos;secret&amp;apos; court orders seeking Twitter data" shortTile="partaclu-eff-challenging" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-04-06" dateModified="2019-09-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU%2C_EFF_challenging_US_%27secret%27_court_orders_seeking_Twitter_data" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Bradley Manning, at the time a specialist from Maryland enlisted with the United States Army's 2nd Brigade, 10th Mountain Division, was arrested in June last year in connection with the leaking of classified combat video to WikiLeaks.</p>
<p>The leaked video footage, taken from a US helicopter gunship, showed the deaths of <hi rend="italic">Reuters</hi> staff <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saeed%20Chmagh">Saeed Chmagh</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Namir%20Noor-Eldeen">Namir Noor-Eldeen</ref> during a U.S. assault in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Baghdad">Baghdad</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref>. The wire agency unsuccessfully attempted to get the footage released via a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom%20of%20Information%20Act">Freedom of Information Act</ref> request in 2007.</p>
<p>When WikiLeaks released the video footage it directly contradicted the official line taken by the U.S. Army asserting that the deaths of the two <hi rend="italic">Reuters</hi> staff were "collateral damage" in an attack on Iraqi insurgents. The radio chatter associated with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AH-64%20Apache">AH-64 Apache</ref> video indicated the helicopter crews had mistakenly identified the journalists' equipment as weaponry.</p>
<p>The US government also claims Manning is linked to CableGate; the passing of around a quarter of a million classified diplomatic cables to WikiLeaks. Manning has been in detention since July last year; in December allegations of torture were made to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations">United Nations</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office%20of%20the%20United%20Nations%20High%20Commissioner%20for%20Human%20Rights">High Commissioner for Human Rights</ref> regarding the conditions under which he was and is being detained.</p>
<p>Reports last month that he must now sleep naked and attend role call at the U.S. Marine facility in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantico,%20Virginia">Quantico</ref> in the same state, raised further concern over his detention conditions. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip%20J.%20Crowley">Philip J. Crowley</ref>, at-the-time a State Department spokesman, remarked on this whilst speaking at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Massachusetts_Institute_of_Technology">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</ref>; describing the current treatment of Manning as "ridiculous and counterproductive and stupid", Crowley was, as a consequence, put in the position of having to tender his resignation to Secretary of State <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hillary_Clinton">Hillary Clinton</ref>.</p>
<head id="The_United_States_Government_versus_WikiLeaks">The United States Government versus WikiLeaks</head>
<figure><caption>Logo of WikiLeaks.</caption></figure>
<p>Despite his native <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref> finding, in December last year, that Assange's WikiLeaks had not committed any criminal offences in their jurisdiction, the U.S. government has continued to make ongoing operations very difficult for the whistleblower website.</p>
<p>The result of the Australian Federal Police investigation left the country's Prime Minister, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Julia_Gillard">Julia Gillard</ref>, having to retract a statement that WikiLeaks had acted "illegally"; instead, she characterised the site's actions as "grossly irresponsible".</p>
<p>Even with Australia finding no illegal activity on the part of WikiLeaks, and with founder Julian Assange facing extradition to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref>, U.S. pressure sought to hobble WikiLeaks financially.</p>
<p>Based on a State Department letter, online payments site <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/PayPal">PayPal</ref> suspended WikiLeaks account in December. Their action was swiftly followed by Visa Europe and Mastercard ceasing to handle payments for WikiLeaks.</p>
<p>The online processing company, Datacell, threatened the two credit card giants with legal action over this. However, avenues of funding for the site were further curtailed when both <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Amazon.com">Amazon.com</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Switzerland">Swiss</ref> bank PostFinance joined the financial boycott of WikiLeaks.</p>
</text>
