<text id="autogum_interview_doc1283" title="part8_Edmund White on writing, incest, life and Larry Kramer" shortTile="partedmund-white" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-08" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edmund_White_on_writing%2C_incest%2C_life_and_Larry_Kramer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolas%20Sarkozy">Nicolas Sarkozy</ref>: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fascism">fascist</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liberator">liberator</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Neither, but he’s better than a lot of people thought he would be.  He’s appointed a lot of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialism">Socialists</ref> and even <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communism">Communists</ref> to his government.  I think people feel he is not part of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grandes%20Écoles">Grandes Écoles</ref></hi> system, even though I think he went to one, but he doesn’t seem quite as much a part of the establishment.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So you have no issue with him?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  No, not at all.  Maybe I will, and we all thought we <hi rend="italic">would</hi>, but he’s turned out to be better than that idiot <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ségolène%20Royal">Ségolène Royal</ref> with her frozen smile.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How has the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq War</ref> affected you?’</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  It’s very depressing.  Michael is more conservative than I am and he’ll get mad at me—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michael:</hi>  But it is depressing.  It’s very depressing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  It’s depressing—this is where he’ll get mad at me—I think it makes it depressing to be an American.  Especially when you’re abroad, because most Europeans we know are very sophisticated in that they can separate an individual from his country’s politics better than most Americans can.  Remember everybody talking about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom%20fries">Freedom Fries</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michael:</hi>  It’s all ridiculous.  I don’t get embarrassed being an American, but I definitely avoid going places where Americans aren’t popular.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  But aside from all that, just living here year after year when you have a government that you hate, and that is systematically destroying the fabric of our society, and just taking apart everything they can think of.  “Health care for children?  Veto that.  School system?  Let’s destroy that.”  Whatever you can think of.  “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prisoners%20rights">Prisoners rights</ref>?  Let’s create <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guantanamo%20Bay">Guantanamo Bay</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abu%20Ghraib">Abu Ghraib</ref>.”  Everything!  I just sent a check today to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ACLU">ACLU</ref>.  It’s really the time to be doing that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion,_drugs,_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush">Nadine Strossen is such a believer</ref>.  I guess you need to be a believer to be President of the ACLU.  What trait do you deplore in yourself?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  It sounds ironic because I have been publishing recent years a book every year, but I actually feel I am lazy.  I’m very unfocused, so I guess I get things done because I’m broke all the time, so I have to do it for money.  Another trait I don’t like about myself is an “I’m right and your wrong” quality.  There’s a slight dictatorial side, probably because I’m a teacher and I’m given that authority based upon my position.  I can run roughshod over other people’s opinions and not really take enough time to tease out what they are really trying to say, what is valuable, or what I can learn from them even though I completely disagree with what they are saying.</p>
</text>
