<text id="autogum_interview_doc1258" title="part1_CanadaVOTES: Christian Heritage Party leader Ron Gray running in Langley" shortTile="partcanadavotes-christian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-09-18" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_Christian_Heritage_Party_leader_Ron_Gray_running_in_Langley" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">As you campaign around your riding, it's likely that some issues are mentioned more often by voters, than other issues. What would you say are the three hottest topics this election, in your riding? What would you and your party do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>1 - A deep, deep sense of betrayal and mistrust... the Tories 'Gardasil' program -- delivering up 9-12-year-old girls as guinea pigs to be vaccinated with an inadequately-tested vaccine that trats only four of the 36 forms of HPV, a sexually-transmitted disease -- a vaccine promoted by a 'friend' of the Prime Minister, and a program that delivered $300 million of taxpayers' money to Big Pharma... this scandal is seen as the Tories equivalent to the Liberals' 'Adscam'...</p>
<p>2 - High gasoline prices, a result (in the view of most constituents) of government inaction on energy and a too-close relationship to Big Oil...</p>
<p>3 - The revolving door of the court system pumps criminals back onto the streets faster than the police can arrest them; brainless court decisions handcuff the police, and we are not allowed to protect ourselves...</p>
<p>4 - When I tell them, (because the mainstream media won't) constituents are infuriated that the courts are unconstitutionally violating the exclusive right of Parliament to make laws, even unconstitutionally altering the Constitution...</p>
<p>5 - When I tell them, (because the mainstream media won't) constituents are infuriated that the four parties now in Parliament have voted themselves $30 million a year of taxpayers' money to finance their re-election campaigns, but at the same time they strangled the ability of the smaller parties to raise voluntary contributions, cutting the ceiling from $5,000 to $1,000 and outlawing all business contributions, even those from small sole proprietorships...</p>
<p>What would we do to address these issues:</p>
<p>1 - we would keep our promises</p>
<p>2 - Eliminate federal gasoline taxes (including GST) on prices higher than 75 cents a litre; mount a Royal Commission on energy marketing, to determine if pricing collusion exists.</p>
<p>3 - Make penalties for Criminal Code offenses mean what they say; mandate that penalties for crimes are automatically doubled if the offender carries a firearm; doubles again if it is loaded; and tripled on top of that if it is discharged.</p>
<p>Adopt the National Firearms Association's "Practical Firearms Control System", and allow any citizen who does not have a criminal record or mental illness, after taking the appropriate safety training program, to own and keep at home, or carry a firearm for personal and family protection. The NFA can provide $4 million of a liability coverage to its members for $9 a year; that proves that their system works!</p>
<p>4 - Parliament MUST establish a Standing Committee on the Judiciary, and arm it with the authority to examine any court decision on the sole grounds of conformity to the Constitution. This limitation of grounds would protect judicial independence in matters of law and fact; but if the SCJ considered a decision to violate the spirit of letter of the Constitution, they would have the authority to brig into Parliament a bill amending that decision (so that the body of precedent would not be contaminated by unconstitutional rulings). This would make the courts accountable to the SCJ for the constitutionality of their ruling; the SCJ accountable to Parliament; and Parliament is accountable to the electorate.</p>
</text>
