<text id="autogum_interview_doc469" title="Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Mark Morin, Chatham—Kent—Essex" shortTile="ontario-votes--interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-26" dateModified="2007-11-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Mark_Morin%2C_Chatham%E2%80%94Kent%E2%80%94Essex" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Mark Morin, Chatham—Kent—Essex</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 26, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mark Morin</hi> is running for the Family Coalition Party in the Ontario provincial election, in the Chatham—Kent—Essex riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>He did not reply to the questions "Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?" and "Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?" Some spelling corrections have been made.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I have been conflicted in past elections because there were no candidates I could vote for with a clear conscience.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I have been an elected committee person for the Canadian Security Union and an appointed Rep for the CAW. I am experienced in responding to the concerns of those I represent.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>My best asset is that I am not a modern day politician. I believe in saying straight out where I stand on the issues. I believe in truth as opposed to the moral relativism that is so prevalent today.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>Education</p>
<p>Economy</p>
<p>Agriculture and industry</p>
<p>I would add fighting to end the tragedy of abortion and providing women with choices they can live with when facing an unexpected pregnancy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>Ending legalized abortion.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>Providing incentives to businesses to create jobs and encouraging the feds to reintroduce good legislation like the Autopact. We are reaping the rewards of bad agreements like FTAA and NAFTA. Capital is flowing out of Canada to countries with cheap labour and poor conditions for workers. In return we get substandard products like antifreeze flavoured toothpaste.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mixed%20member%20proportional%20representation">mixed member proportional representation</ref> (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>In favour.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does “new media” play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>Any medium that makes our message more accessible is very positive. I am excited by the potential to reach more youth by these means.</p>
</text>
