<text id="autogum_interview_doc988" title="part3_Wikinews holds Reform Party USA presidential candidates forum" shortTile="partwikinews-holds" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-01-02" dateModified="2016-09-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_holds_Reform_Party_USA_presidential_candidates_forum" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I have a fully articulated strategy that we need now:  Electoral Reform, a Coalition Cabinet and a Balanced Budget announced by 4 July 2011, and a commitment to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Full%20cost%20accounting">True Cost Economics</ref>--this is an approach that seeks to create a We the People Reform Coalition that is attractive to moderates from both parties, to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent%20(politician)">Independents</ref>, and to all the parties excluded from US politics today, Libertarians and Greens included.  I am running less as a Reform Party candidate and more as a team-building candidate.  I have already named my preferred <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cabinet%20of%20the%20United%20States">Cabinet</ref> members—subject of course to changes as the coalition evolves—and I am well on my way to crowd-sourcing a balanced budget that connects the true needs and priorities of the public with their money – the two-party tyranny has been using the public's money to enrich themselves and their cronies across America (not just <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wall%20Street">Wall Street</ref>); the two-party tyranny is out of touch with ethics, the public, and reality.  I have the capacity to engage Independents and all others with a new direction not offered elsewhere – not from any party including the Democratic Party.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robby Wells</hi>: Coaching is a complex job involving strategic thinking, leadership ability, obtaining and keeping respect, and judging the abilities of the people you have at your disposal. My career in coaching has well prepared me for a leadership position in government. A good coach knows that his players have skills he doesn't have, but he understands what abilities they DO have. He uses good judgement in choosing the right people for the task at hand, and knows how to use them effectively. He knows when to let them do their job while he watches, and when to step in and take a hands-on approach.</p>
<p>As president, I will bring the same mentality to the White House. I will look across the political spectrum and choose the best partisan and nonpartisan people; people with knowledge, expertise, and credibility who have already earned your trust, for all cabinet positions. And I will use my long years of leadership to know when to let them do their job, and when to step in and take a more direct role to get the most out of that team for the American people. Because we all deserve a White House that can go up against America's problems and WIN - not fumble at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glossary%20of%20American%20football">4th and ten</ref>.</p>
<head id="Question_4">Question 4</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WIKINEWS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If nominated, what will you do to gain <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ballot%20access">ballot access</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Andre Barnett</hi>: I will be working to unify this party during the course of this campaign. With unification we will better be able  to utilize the ground game for petitioning. I also believe I will be able to acquire other ballot access lines.</p>
</text>
