<text id="autogum_interview_doc1366" title="part4_Teräsbetoni frontman J. Ahola on representing Finland at Eurovision 2008 & more" shortTile="partterasbetoni-frontman" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-26" dateModified="2017-05-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ter%C3%A4sbetoni_frontman_J._Ahola_on_representing_Finland_at_Eurovision_2008_%26_more" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you plan a tour this year to support the album?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> We’re already gigging around Finland and summer tour is in the making . Visiting countries abroad would be great, too.</p>
<head id="Northern_Kings">Northern Kings</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How did you come to be involved with Northern Kings?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> The whole thing began with Raskasta Joulua –tour that I was in. We also did an album called “Raskaampaa Joulua”. Anyway, there was some talk about doing something else together. You know, not just Christmas carrols in metal mode. Nobody really had the time to start writing new songs, so a cover album seemed to be a nice way of proceeding. </p>
<p>Everybody agreed that the album should sound massive and orchestrated. At first we had no other direction than covering the music we liked. I did a demo of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Procol%20Harum">Procol Harum</ref>’s “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A%20Salty%20Dog">Salty Dog</ref>” with Erkka Korhonen. It was a good example of what we should sound like, but our record label’s A &amp; R Osku Ketola thought that we should do something more defined. After few thoughts we decided to concentrate on pop hits of the 80’s.  That’s how it all began. I had a chance to arrange my own atcs which was lots of fun. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What's it like working with the other three established rockers?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Unfortunately we didn’t see each other while making the record. That may sound crazy, but that’s how it goes nowadays. It’s so easy to record your parts and send them to the studio for mixing. Happily, we saw each other while the photo &amp; video shoot. Marco Hietala, Tony Kakko and J-P Leppäluoto are all great musicians and great persons. If we ever get to do any shows together, I’m sure it would be wonderful in music and in brotherhood.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is it hard to divide your time between the projects?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> It all depends on what you have going on already. While making Northern Kings album “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reborn%20(Northern%20Kings%20album)">Reborn</ref>” Teräsbetoni was having a break. I try to do things smoothly and avoid booking too much stuff on my calendar. You shouldn’t be too greedy and accept all the stuff offered. </p>
<p>Of course there are exceptions. For example while we were recording Myrskyntuoja, I had to leave studio early or not go there at all ‘cause of promotional actions agreed by our record label. I can understand the meaning of promotion, but nothing sucks more than bothering an intensive studio session with another project. It screws up your focus. But fortunately that kind of shit is rare enough, so I don’t care complaining about it. And the bottom line is that projects like Northern Kings bring great variety to your life as an artist. </p>
</text>
