<text id="autogum_interview_doc808" title="part1_Frank Messina: An interview with the &amp;apos;Mets Poet&amp;apos;" shortTile="partfrank-messina" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-03" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Frank_Messina%3A_An_interview_with_the_%27Mets_Poet%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I spoke with the person <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bowery%20Poetry%20Club">Bowery Poetry Club</ref> founder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Holman">Bob Holman</ref> called the "Rock n' Roll Poet Laureate" recently in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington%20Square%20Park">Washington Square Park</ref>:</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You have received a good deal of attention recently.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>Even though I'm not Michael Jackson or somebody, when people come up to me and introduce themselves and say, 'Hey Frank, my name is John,' I say, 'Hey John, my name is Frank' and they laugh.  It's a funny phenomenon.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What goes through your head when that happens?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  I understand it.  I've gone to readings and concerts.  I look at it as human interaction.  Over the years I have performed in 32 countries and 40 states.  I've been doing this professionally since I was in my twenties, and before that since I was sixteen doing little tidbit poetry readings in coffeehouses.  The band I started in 1993, Spoken Motion, received a lot of recognition as a spoken word band born out of the New York spoken word scene.  I worked with some great musicians and performed around the world.  I remember signing my first autograph to a kid when I was 25 years old.  As time went on, I came out with books and CDs, and I became used to that kind of thing.  To me, the ultimate feeling of success as an artist, is to move somebody enough where they thank you.  When someone comes up and says, 'Frank, thank you, your work is great."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You have a long career in poetry, but as of late the attention you have garnered is for the Mets-inspired work.  How do you feel about having a lot of your work overshadowed by the Mets work?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>It's ironic.  Some of the greatest poetry has been born out of failure and the depths of adversity in the human experience.  Walt Whitman, the first great American poet, wrote about the Civil War.  He went looking for his brother, George Whitman, after he a telegram telling him his brother was injured in the South.  When he started out his poems were about beating drums, and blow, bugle, blow.  Real patriotic.  Then he started to see the real horrors of war. He was able to tap into the human condition and the situation at that time.   Eventually when he found his brother he had resolution.</p>
<p>I experienced that kind of adversity during 9/11 being a civilian volunteer.  I loaded ferry boats in Jersey City across the river to deliver goods to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ground%20Zero">Ground Zero</ref>.  I turned to Whitman to find some understanding of what is happening in the world right now.  When I wrote my 9/11-related poems, that was true adversity.  I realize baseball is just a game.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Can you recite a stanza that expresses how you feel right now?</hi></p>
</text>
