<text id="autogum_interview_doc773" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Ray Scott, Algoma-Manitoulin" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-01" dateModified="2010-06-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Ray_Scott%2C_Algoma-Manitoulin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Ray Scott, Algoma-Manitoulin</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 2, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ray Scott</hi> is running for the Family Coalition Party in the Ontario provincial election, in the Algoma-Manitoulin riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I first became involved in politics because of my pro-life beliefs. I had no candidate that I could vote for that truly believed in the sanctity of human life. When I found the Family Coalition Party, and saw a well-rounded party platform, I supported the FCP. When there was no candidate in my area, I felt conscience-bound to run. I am running in Algoma-Manitoulin because we need pro-lifers in government and none of the other candidates can offer that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>In terms of elections, I have run twice before. In my professional life, as a public school teacher, I have vast experience in moving agendas forward and resolving conflicts. As a pro-life, and union activist, I frequently engage in the political process and understand how decisions are made, and how to positively influence those processes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>The incumbent Liberal candidate has held the riding for 20 years and has a very strong campaign organization. The NDP candidate has the best set of promises, though I don’t think they can be paid for. I am the best candidate because my party’s policy on healthcare realistically addresses the primary needs of Ontarians. The health policy for the Family Coalition Party is called “Medical Savings Accounts”.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>Issue #1: Healthcare</p>
<p>The Family Coalition Party proposes a system of Medical Savings Accounts (MSAs).</p>
<p>Basically, imagine your health card as a debit card. The government puts $2000 in your own MSA. Every time you visit the doctor or access health services, you present your health card and the cost of service is withdrawn from your MSA. You may only spend that money on healthcare. If you deplete your account, there is a user-pay portion roughly equivalent to the Liberal Health Tax. After that, government run catastrophic healthcare insurance kicks in, similar to OHIP.</p>
</text>
