<text id="autogum_interview_doc1206" title="Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Peter Ormond, Hamilton Centre" shortTile="ontario-votes--interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-18" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_candidate_Peter_Ormond%2C_Hamilton_Centre" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Peter Ormond, Hamilton Centre</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 18, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Peter Ormond</hi> is running for the Green Party of Ontario in the Ontario provincial election, in the Hamilton Centre riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Ormond did not answer three questions: "Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?", "Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?", and "Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?"</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>We read about the green revolution in newspaper headlines, yet we continue to pursue mega-projects that do not benefit society, the environment, or the economy. I live in Hamilton Centre, and therefore naturally chose this riding.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I have canvassed for various candidates in past campaigns. This includes the Liberals and NDP. Now I realize that to actually start moving towards a sustainable Ontario, innovation is required. The Green Party has that ability to make this transformation happen.</p>
<p>Remember that all issues are interdependent through the social, economic and environmental pillars.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>Remember that all issues are interdependent through the social, economic and environmental pillars. Key issues in Hamilton are:</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Poverty and Homelessness</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Local Green Jobs for Sustainability</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Transportation</hi></p>
<p>More details are available on our website www.gpo.ca</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>A moratorium on all new nuclear facilities and cancellation of any planned upgrades of nuclear facilities beyond regular maintenance.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>Local projects. Keep the money in the communities. Education and training of immigrants of the underemployed. Get the citizens engaged in projects that improve neighbourhoods. This includes local manufacturing. For example, in Hamilton, deployment of solar hot water systems would be a tremendous opportunity to align local manufacturers and train installers. Then each household saves a few bucks that can in turn be invested in the community.</p>
<p>No more paving of valleys. No more mega-projects. Decentralization is where it's at.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mixed%20member%20proportional%20representation">mixed member proportional representation</ref> (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>The Green Party supports electoral reform fully. This will bring a balanced and representative voice to parliament.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does "new media" play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>We're working on it.</p>
</text>
