<text id="autogum_interview_doc984" title="part2_Canada's Scarborough East (Ward 43) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-scarborough" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-10-23" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Scarborough_East_%28Ward_43%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Toronto is where I was born and raised and has always been my home. I feel Toronto gave me a colourful childhood full of great experiences. I learned to swim in the water, explore in the forests, I was educated here, and started my family here. This city has provided me with pride in my accomplishments, including my involvement in the building of landmarks such as the Sky Dome, the Eaton Centre, the Reference Library and retrofit of Osgoode Hall. Above all, Toronto has shown me the value of community and I would like to show this to its residents.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of? Which was the least desirable?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The council of 2003 made many decisions but the most favourable was to end the use of pesticides for cosmetic use on lawns. This was a step forward for the protection of the environment. While people thought it would mean jobs lost, I have not seen this occur. Furthermore, it has meant the return of birds and wildlife. In fact I have seen chipmunks, rabbits and deer in growing numbers. I have seen more butterflies and insects that do not harm but are a product of a healthy earth.</p>
<p>The least desirable was the elimination of open bidding on TTC subway car replacement contracts. As in all bidding processes, the lowest is not always the winning bid. I would have voted in favour of the Canadian workers, because I feel it is important to support our economy. However, I feel that bidding is an important part of the process.</p>
<p>Additionally, The lack of action on the Guild Inn has been disappointing, because the potential is there for the Guild Inn to be an important part of Toronto again.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> If you were elected as a "rookie" councillor, what would you bring to council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I would not refer to a new councillor as a rookie, but a new way of looking at the issues, new set of values, and a new perspective. As a new councillor I would bring an open window, so people could have a sense of accountability. I would foster communication between Scarborough and City Hall, which has been lacking for many years. I would propose community ventures that are thought of by the residents, for the residents. I would propose new ways for the community to become involved with city hall, including Saturday and evening meetings, to ensure that working citizens are able to participate. I would also propose innovative ways to involve the public, utilizing new technologies.  The political process requires the involvement of the public and I would strive to strengthen that involvement.</p>
</text>
