<text id="autogum_interview_doc852" title="part0_CanadaVOTES: CHP candidate Vicki Gunn in York—Simcoe" shortTile="partcanadavotes-chp" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-10" dateModified="2016-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_CHP_candidate_Vicki_Gunn_in_York%E2%80%94Simcoe" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>CanadaVOTES: CHP candidate Vicki Gunn in York—Simcoe</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 10, 2008</hi></p>
<p>In an attempt to speak with as many candidates as possible during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008%20Canadian%20federal%20election">2008 Canadian federal election</ref>, Wikinews has talked via email with Vicki Gunn. Gunn is a candidate in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario">Ontario</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York—Simcoe">York—Simcoe riding</ref>, running under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian%20Heritage%20Party%20of%20Canada">Christian Heritage Party of Canada</ref> (CHP) banner. The CHP is a minor, registered political party running a significant number of candidates across the country, looking to earn its first ever seat in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canadian%20House%20of%20Commons">House of Commons</ref>.</p>
<p>The riding has existed from 1968 to 1979, from 1988 to 1997, and from 2004 to present. As of the next provincial election in Ontario, it will be recognised as a provincial electoral district as well. Over the years, the riding has been represented by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liberal%20Party%20of%20Canada">Liberal Party</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressive%20Conservative%20Party%20of%20Canada">Progressive Conservative Party</ref>, again by the Progressive Conservatives, again by the Liberals, and since its recreation, the seat has been held by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conservative%20Party%20of%20Canada">Conservative Party of Canada</ref>.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter%20Van%20Loan">Peter Van Loan</ref>, the Conservative incumbent, is the Minister Responsible for Democratic Reform and Leader of the Government in the House of Commons. The other candidates in the riding, besides Van Loan and the CHP's Gunn, are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Democratic%20Party">New Democrat</ref> Sylvia Gerl, Liberal Judith Moses, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%20Party%20of%20Canada">Green Party</ref>'s John Dewar.</p>
<p>The following is an interview with Gunn, conducted via email. The interview is published unedited, as sent to Wikinews.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why are you running for political office, why at the federal level, why this party, and why in this riding?</hi></p>
<p>I am serving for the 3rd time as candidate because I believe in principles which do not change. I believe in strong families and I believe is social order. When we as a country supported our families and enabled them to raise their children without fear of government interference then we had a strong social order. We had 4 levels of government, self government, family government, church (spiritual) government, and civil government) which created healthy, balanced social order. The government did not interfere in family and spiritual government unless there was good reason. Today we have government interference in our homes, in our places of worship, in our thoughts, how we express ourselves. This is a dangerous precedent! Government has been allowed to grow unfettered in this country for too long. The CHP genuinely believes in 4 levels of government... each operating within it's sphere of authority. We believe in smaller government. We believe in healthy families. We believe in a future for this country free from the all pervasive power of the state!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Previous to this campaign, have you been politically involved? How will you apply your previous work/volunteer/life experience to serving your constituents?</hi></p>
<p>I served as candidate in York Simcoe for the Christian Heritage Party in both 2004 &amp; 2006.</p>
</text>
