<text id="autogum_interview_doc1142" title="part1_Canada's Davenport (Ward 18) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-davenport" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Davenport_%28Ward_18%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>When I arrived at City Hall, I opened and have since maintained a community office, so people have ready access to their councillor.  I have continued to work with community groups across the ward and provided ALL residents with the kind of information in correspondence and newsletter that they were not accustomed to getting.</p>
<p>In a very culturally diverse community, I have also worked with many cultural communities in many languages to ensure that everyone, regardless of background or language, is well served by City Hall.</p>
<p>I have worked successfully with the community to establish 3 Business Improvement Areas so that our struggling main streets have a fair chance to grow and succeed.</p>
<p>I have increased local democracy by not only consulting, but often balloting neighbourhoods about very local decisions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> This is a community that cares about the health of our environment.  Of the decisions Council made this term, I think it's unfortunate that we didn't get to our goals in adding recycling and "green bin" facilities in apartment buildings.</p>
<p>I think this Council should be proud that we made a very responsible decision to keep our Transit plan on track by establishing the St. Clair Right-of-Way.  There was a lot of fear-mongering about it, but in the end, Council made the right decision.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Toronto is a city that has a proud history of distinct neighbourhoods and cultural diversity.  We are a city that has occasionally struggled against a Provincial instinct to cut back and destroy the things we have built together over generations.  I think many people who don't know Toronto would be surprised at the progressive, community-minded nature of our people.  It's a city I'm intensely proud of.</p>
<head id="Jim_McMillan">Jim McMillan</head>
<p>Aged "39 &amp; holding" Jim McMillan is currently self employed in sales.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> 1) Elevators or ramps in Lansdowne, Dufferin, Ossington subway stations now.</p>
<p>2) Turning the contaminated 640 Lansdowne Ave - the police rejected it, the city &amp; the T.T.C. are left neither wanting to pay the clean up costs (60,000,000.00) sixty million dollars. It should be capped with afoot of concrete and trees planted every 20 feet to suck out contaminates and the site used for a multi use park.</p>
<p>3) Split the 14 Division police force into two groups, leave one group in the old Dundas/Dovercourt Sts. site with the administrative staff remaining there, the other half to set up a large satelite <hi rend="italic">[sic]</hi> station at Bloor/Lansdowne Sts.saving gas reducing pollution and putting police in the face of the hoodlums who terrorize Lansdowne/Bloor area residents.</p>
</text>
