<text id="autogum_interview_doc900" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Mike Lebowitz, Chairman of the Modern Whig Party" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-12" dateModified="2009-03-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mike_Lebowitz%2C_Chairman_of_the_Modern_Whig_Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: How does The Modern Whig Party differ from America's major political parties <hi rend="italic">(Republican, Democratic, Constitution, Green, Libertarian)</hi></hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chairman Lebowitz:</hi> The Modern Whig Party differs from the other political parties because our members come from across the political spectrum. Our common sense approach has found a way to reconcile actual common ground among individuals from all political stripes. The Modern Whig Party strives to remain mainstream and practical. Unlike other parties, we don't expect our members to agree with everything, and in fact encourage them to remain independent minded. In a way, the Modern Whig Party is different in that it is designed to provide a palatable home to independents and those who want to be independent. Another element to look at is the diversity of our members. Our state leaders include retired Vietnam veterans, Iraq/Afghanistan veterans, attorneys, college students, a retired CEO, a prominent rock musician, a golf professional, teachers and many others.</p>
<p>What we have found is that even though someone is socially liberal, they also may be very conservative when it comes to other issues. Same for our conservative members. This goes back to our theory that most people find themselves cherry-picking between issues of both major parties, but ultimately end up on one side of the fence. In the end, we offer a realistic and mainstream home for those who want to pick and choose from various ideals and solutions from across the political spectrum.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: Currently, are there any elected officials in the United States that are members of The Modern Whig Party?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chairman Lebowitz:</hi> By design, we have held off on running or endorsing candidates this year. The established third parties are essentially marginalized because they consistently trot out candidates just to lose. Our goal is to avoid such traps as we attempt to build a mainstream and practical organization that in time will be strong and credible enough to actually be a force in politics and our communities.</p>
<p>Our plan from the beginning is to operate methodically and gradually. The Modern Whig Party leadership is comprised of people who are not deluded into thinking that we are somehow entitled to members. We also are not deluded into thinking that the majority of voters are ready to take that plunge and actually vote for a third party, let alone a group called the "Whigs." We understand the reality, and perhaps that is our biggest asset. As we grow, our name will slowly filter back into the mainstream mentality. Our longterm strategy is nuanced but includes initially running a few candidates who are members of the Modern Whig Party but will initially run on the Democratic and Republican tickets. The plan is to run a few candidates on state and local ballots in 2009 and then support three candidates for Congress in 2010. If our members can win a few during this time, while at the same time our membership ranks continue to rise, we will have accomplished a winning track record from which to really make our move. We believe that we need to be innovative in order to succeed as we know the odds are stacked against us. But nothing ever came out of doing nothing.</p>
</text>
