<text id="autogum_interview_doc995" title="part0_YouTube accounts of Scientology critics suspended" shortTile="partyoutube-accounts" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-04-17" dateModified="2012-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/YouTube_accounts_of_Scientology_critics_suspended" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>YouTube accounts of Scientology critics suspended</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, April 18, 2008</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Screenshot of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark%20Bunker">Mark Bunker</ref> from one of his YouTube postings Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User%20talk:XENU%20TV">XENU TV</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Two well-known critics of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church%20of%20Scientology">Scientology</ref> have had their user accounts on the video sharing website <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref> suspended. The YouTube accounts of both <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tory%20Christman">Tory Christman</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark%20Bunker">Mark Bunker</ref> were suspended this week. In a statement to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi>, YouTube explained why accounts are suspended, but did not specifically state why these particular accounts were suspended. Neither Christman nor Bunker received a notice or explanation from YouTube as to why their accounts were suspended.</p>
<p>On Tuesday April 15, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tory%20Christman">Tory Christman</ref> a former Scientologist and volunteer for their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office%20of%20Special%20Affairs">Office of Special Affairs</ref>, and known as <hi rend="italic">ToryMagoo44</hi> on YouTube, had her account suspended for unknown reasons. On Wednesday, after complaints to YouTube from other YouTube users and from members of the group <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anonymous%20(group)">Anonymous</ref>, Christman's account was restored.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> confirmed Friday that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark%20Bunker">Mark Bunker</ref> known as 'xenutv1' on <hi rend="italic">YouTube</hi>, a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Television">television</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Category:Journalism">journalist</ref> and critic of Scientology, had his user account suspended. This is the second time that Bunker's account was suspended. He was formerly known as 'xenutv' when his account was suspended the first time.</p>
<p>"I want to see the complaint and on what grounds did YouTube suspend my account. I have done nothing on that account that would violate any of their terms and my videos and account should not have been pulled. The only caveat to this is my first account "XenuTV" was suspended a while back for a Stephen Colbert video I had from Comedy Central. At that time I created XenuTV1 and according to YouTube's terms you can only have one account. Any time I have ever been asked to remove something that may violate their terms for copyright materials, I comply immediately. It would be wrong and a misuse of power to pull my account because of this lone loophole in their terms," said Bunker exclusively to <hi rend="italic">Wikinews.</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">I want to see the complaint and on what grounds did YouTube suspend my account.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark%20Bunker">Mark Bunker</ref></p>
<p>Bunker, who is also the owner of the anti-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientology">Scientology</ref> website www.xenutv.com, has become known as <hi rend="italic">Wise Beard Man</hi> to Anonymous. He was interviewed by <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> in February. Bunker started XenuTV in 1999 and began to make videos that he provided for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisa%20McPherson%20Trust">Lisa McPherson Trust</ref>. Bunker has been a critic of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church%20of%20Scientology">Church of Scientology</ref> since 1997.</p>
<p>In 2006, he won a  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emmy%20Award#Regional_Emmys">Regional Emmy Award</ref> after he and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KUSI-TV">KUSI-TV</ref> news reporter Lena Lewis produced a documentary news video on the issues with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> - <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref> border with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San%20Diego,%20California">San Diego</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref>.</p>
<p>With permission from Christman, Bunker responded to his account's suspension with a video post to her YouTube channel on Thursday. Bunker stated: "This afternoon at 2:41, I found out YouTube canceled my account. No justification was given to me, I got no notice from them, and there appears to be no recourse. And why did this happen? Because the Jason Beghe interview was about to be posted - and Scientology did not want anyone to see that. My tease for the Jason Beghe interview went up on Sunday, and by this afternoon we had almost six hundred thousand views, and it had been profiled in newscasts around the world. There is a lot of tension being drawn to this video, and Scientology wanted to stop it."</p>
</text>
