<text id="autogum_interview_doc1417" title="part2_Interview with U.S. Republican Presidential candidate Tom Tancredo" shortTile="partinterview-us" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-25" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_U.S._Republican_Presidential_candidate_Tom_Tancredo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Aside from becoming President, if you could be granted three wishes, what would they be?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  It was the other night that I saw for the third or fourth time <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saving%20Private%20Ryan">Saving Private Ryan</ref></hi> and in the last scene Private Ryan asks, "Have I been a good man, have I earned it?"  My greatest wish is to be a good father and to have earned everything I have been given in this life.  And to be a better Christian.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Farmers rely heavily on seasonal manual labor. Strict enforcement of immigration laws will inevitably reduce the pool of migrant labor and thus increase costs. Do you support tariffs or other government intervention to keep American farm products competitive?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  No, I don’t , because I challenge the premise of the question.  The ability for farmers to obtain workers in the United States is only minimally hampered by the immigration process because there is, in fact, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H-2A%20Visa">H-2A</ref>, the visa that is designed specifically for agricultural workers.  We can bring in 10,000,000 if we want to.  There are no caps.  There are restrictions in terms of pay and healthcare benefits, and that’s what makes hiring illegal aliens more attractive.  The costs would increase for certain agricultural interest, but it would be regional.  You would also see a very aggressive movement toward the mechanization of farm work.  We are seeing it today in a lot of areas.  We saw it in the tomato industry with the Bracero Program.  That was a program many growers relied heavily upon:  workers, primarily from Mexico would come up seasonally, work,  and then went back home.  It was successful.  But liberals ended the program as a bad idea because the immigrants couldn’t bring their families.  When that happened, tomato growers said they’d go out of business.  Lo and behold they developed machinery that can harvest citrus fruit, and now they are genetically engineering trees that have a thicker bark but are more flexible so they can be shaken by these machines.  You’ll see it more and more.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you agree that our forefathers intended birthright citizenship?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  No, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourteenth%20Amendment">Fourteenth Amendment</ref>, upon which the concept of birthright citizenship is based, was a response to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dred%20Scott%20v.%20Sandford">the Dred Scott decision</ref>.</p>
<p>During the original Senate debate there was an understanding that it wouldn’t be provided to people simply because they were born here, but instead to people under our jurisdiction.  For instance, nobody assumes a child born to an embassy employee or an ambassador is a citizen of this country.  There was an understanding and a reference to "under the jurisdiction" of the United States.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl%20Rove">Karl Rove</ref> engaged, in your words,  in a screaming match over immigration, and Rove said that  you would never again "darken the doorstep of the White House." Are you still considered <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/persona%20non%20grata">persona non grata</ref></hi> at the White House?</hi></p>
</text>
