<text id="autogum_interview_doc983" title="part1_Canada's Scarborough East (Ward 43) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-scarborough" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-10-23" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Scarborough_East_%28Ward_43%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Since childhood, politics have been a big part of my life. My parents were believers in the political process, and encouraged our involvement. Voting was always emphasized and modeled in our household. In a family with seven boys, the democratic process was always modeled in our home.</p>
<p>In the last decade I have felt discouraged by the lack of accountability in politics, and the lack of regard for the needs of the voters. Learning from my childhood the value of the democratic process, I feel we need to speak out to preserve it. The Toronto municipal government has made many irresponsible decisions that have affected the residents of Toronto. Transit development should have been done in areas where there are current riders, not future riders. Scarborough is in dire need of extensions of TTC services, and new routes. Our youth need stronger leaders to look up to, and they need to be engaged. Our current municipal government is not doing enough to ensure they have services available to them. The political process must serve the people who it affects the most, and I feel it is my duty as a resident to get involved to ensure this takes place.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I want to represent this ward, because I live here. I am familiar with the communities, including problems and strengths. I believe in the concept of local representation and I do not agree with politicians who run in any area, simply to be elected. If you live here, you understand the community. At this level of government it is important that the politician walks the same street as the people they represent, and get your hands dirty in the same dirt.  This ward is my home and I want to make it feel like home for everyone in this ward.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am involved in the community in the most important way, I engage with my neighbours. I am always ready and willing to help my friends and neighbours with problems they may have. I have always been willing to lend my hand or skill to people who need help. As councillor, I feel I would be able to help more people than I am able to now.</p>
<p>I am currently also involved with the Scarborough General Hospital, in order to Save the Scarborough Grace unit. I feel this is important because if this hospital is closed to the general admissions the public at large will suffer. Community based preventative care will be phased out and the risk of community illness will increase. This unit will then redirect its basic and emergency care to the general division and the overcrowded conditions will continue to grow.</p>
</text>
