<text id="autogum_interview_doc1220" title="part3_The Onion: An interview with 'America's Finest News Source'" shortTile="partthe-onion-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2013-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Onion%3A_An_interview_with_%27America%27s_Finest_News_Source%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They are such a perfect representation of a broad spectrum of people, that it’s funny that you found them all randomly in just one day.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  I wasn’t there at the time, but they were people around the office or around downtown Madison.  The UPS driver, for instance, was a guy who always made deliveries to the office, and he happened to come by right when they were shooting and agreed to do the photo.  He still works for UPS and still lives in Madison and was the subject of a feature in the UPS <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teamsters">Teamsters</ref> magazine about that face in The Onion…our UPS guy, still at UPS and still in Madison.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you heard if it has affected their lives?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  There have been a few pieces that I’ve read that people have done research and talked to a lot of them, and most of them are pretty delighted about it and they hear about it all the time.  There are six takes on it, but most of it is pretty positive.</p>
<figure><caption>Columnist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbert%20Kornfeld%20(character)">Herbert Kornfeld</ref> was murdered in an episode of white-on-white violence.  "There was almost a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Notorious%20B.I.G.">Notorious B.I.G.</ref>-like upset [amongst readers]," according to Chet Clem.Image source: The Onion.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are there certain columnists who are reader favorites?  Are there columnists where you receive consistently positive or consistently negative responses to?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  From what I have seen, it’s pretty consistently positive for all of them.  The only negative reaction we have gotten is one of our columnists was unfortunately killed this year, tragically, so a lot of people—
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbert%20Kornfeld%20(character)">Herbert Kornfeld</ref> was killed this past summer.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How did he die?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  He was killed in an episode of white-on-white violence.  
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  He was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accounts%20receivable">accounts receivable</ref> and he was pretty hardcore.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  He died at work at Midstate Office Supply.  He was struck down, leaving us with a hole in our editorial staff.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You had a big reaction from the readers upset that Herbert Kornfeld was dead?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  Yeah, people get pretty attached.  A lot of these columnists have been writing for us ten plus years.  
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  Some of them have a huge following, there was almost a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Notorious%20B.I.G.">Notorious B.I.G.</ref>-like upset.  They really responded to his death.  A lot of calls of condolence, there were movements across the country.  A lot of flowers.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  A lot of people wearing "Mourn Ya Til I Join Ya" t-shirts.  His memory will be alive forever at <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So there is no columnist that people write in and say that they aren’t funny, or that they are boring—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  We have an editorial cartoon we have introduced in the last year that tends to get a lot of heat—</p>
</text>
