<text id="autogum_interview_doc1120" title="part5_Murray Hill on the life and versatility of a New York drag king" shortTile="partmurray-hill-life" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Murray_Hill_on_the_life_and_versatility_of_a_New_York_drag_king" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You think RuPaul’s perspective is coming from a show-tour world?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  I’m not sure, but he’s not in a daily New York scene as much as Michael is, or as much as I am.  It is different now.  If you go to a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gay%20pride">gay pride</ref>, and I just did gay pride in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baltimore">Baltimore</ref>, it’s a whole different ball game.  You’ve got your butch, you’ve got your femme, you’ve got your <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In%20the%20closet">closeted people</ref> who are coming out at Pride and being feminine for that one day only.  It’s very different.  The club scene now is more queer than it is gay and lesbian.  It’s more trans.  The lesbians, the Trans and the gay guys all hang out together.  If you go to this club called Metropolitan on Wednesday night you’ll see it.</p>
<head id="Drag_queens_and_drag_kings:_the_differences">Drag queens and drag kings: the differences</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  With <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drag%20queens">drag queens</ref> it seems like almost anything is on the table.  If they want to butch it up, if they want to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fem">fem</ref> it up.  In the craft, are there boundaries you feel you can’t cross?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  I will never take off my shirt and tie.  That’s about as far as it goes.  I take off my jacket and every once in a while when the audience is screaming for me to do it, I’ll take off my pants at shows.  I really don’t have too many rules.  My rules are more about the environment I create for the shows.  I’m very strict about having a positive environment.  I will never put somebody down in a negative, crass way, which you’ll see at comedy clubs and drag queen shows pretty much all the time.  I make fun of everybody, but I do it in a way where we all feel good about it instead of a way where somebody thinks, ‘Wow, somebody is really getting it.’  I’m very aware that women come to the show and they feel safe and  that it’s a fun place.  That’s my biggest rule.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What about in terms of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gender%20roles">gender roles</ref>, how you use gender?  Are there boundaries for a drag king when they are performing in terms of what they should or shouldn’t do?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  I don’t know.  When there was a consolidated drag king scene here—1997—there was a heavy scene but now it’s faded away.  There isn’t really a group anymore.  But all across the country there are groups everywhere.  Their performances are very different than what I’m doing.  It’s overtly about gender, sexuality, politics and a reveal.  They’ll show the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dildo">dildoes</ref>, strip down and do a transformation.  A lot of it is about transformation.  There’s even a new group that’s with—I’ve got to get the terms right—drag kings, boyz, and now there’s a scene of lesbians doing F2F drag.  That’s all about challenging the gender stuff.  It’s part of the act; whereas my stuff doesn’t make that the core of the act. Obviously it’s there, but I don’t hit the kids over the head with it.  Which is why more people come to my show.  They’re not threatened by the sexuality aspect of it.</p>
</text>
