<text id="autogum_interview_doc789" title="part4_Eurovision &amp;apos;73 winner Anne Marie David discusses her four-decade career and the Contest, past and present" shortTile="parteurovision--winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-02-15" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2773_winner_Anne_Marie_David_discusses_her_four-decade_career_and_the_Contest%2C_past_and_present" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Competing at the Eurovision in 1979, you ended the voting on the wrong end of a close three-way finish, being beaten by the songs from Israel and Spain. Considering your victory helped Luxembourg win twice in a row, were you happy for Israel as they also achieved the same feat? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: Of course! It's once again a rule fixed ahead of time, and which does not prohibit a country from winning several times in a row.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Many Eurovision fans on sites like YouTube feel the 1979 Contest was one of the strongest years ever for Eurovision. Apart from your own song, were there any songs you remember that you really liked? Also, which song do you feel was a stronger entry, "Je suis l'enfant soleil" or "Tu te reconnaîtras"?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: I have indeed seen how much Internet users appreciate "Je suis l'enfant soleil"... let them be reassured, so do I! That year, in 1979, I particularly liked Milk and Honey and Gali Atari who won, and the German group who sang "Dschinghis Khan", which was a very strong title and sold well. With time, singing my songs from Eurovision continue to give me pleasure. "Je suis l'enfant soleil" tells a very beautiful tale and allows me to play comedy [<hi rend="italic">Editor's note: "Comedy" in the theatrical sense, aiming to denounce the faults and vices of society using humor</hi>] a lot. But I adore "Tu te reconnaîtras" for what it has in singing, pulling in, being direct with the audience. In fact, each [song] brings me something different and to the public as well.</p>
<head id="1980s:_Retirement">1980s: Retirement</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> During the 1980s, you competed in some more song festivals, including one in Norway and one in Chile. Anabela, the 1993 entrant from Portugal, felt she was eventually typecast as being "the song festival girl." Did you ever feel restricted in the same way? Were there ever any other facets to your musical repertoire that you would have liked to explore?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: I always assumed the image of a competitor, maybe because I grew up in a place where I was very happy, but where we were not very rich; so I always had to make choices and needed to earn each thing that life gave me. Also, it's great to know that others count on you and think that you can bring them a victory; it's not given to everyone. As for the facets of my personality, for a long time I had to struggle (again!) against a face which refused to age, and which thus prevented me from being credible in certain repertoires. </p>
<p>Today time has passed, I am totally free in my choices, my voice has ripened well, and my silhouette too, my mastery of the scene is much more elaborated and thus I take on all the styles if the song touches or pleases me. And also I take on challenges like the song which I recorded with Jean Renard, [called] "Federico" which is totally "gypsy" and totally unlike my usual image. I am currently preparing a song for my English[-language] dance floor album (yep!) which is being [released] by Energise Records. [Dance music] is totally the opposite of what I do... but that amuses me and also the producers convinced me that I'd be great in it... so I hope not to disappoint them. [Here's a] scoop: it's called "You Came to Me."</p>
</text>
