<text id="autogum_interview_doc099" title="part3_Wikinews interviews specialists on Russian intervention in Ukraine" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-02" dateModified="2016-11-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_Russian_intervention_in_Ukraine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>Soldiers without insignia guard buildings in the Crimean capital, Simferopol, March 2, 2014. Image: Voice of America.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  There are reports that Russia could be ejected from the G8 group of developed economies. Would this be a major blow for Putin's domestic popularity?</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Morris</hi>: Not really.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Brandist</hi>: In present circumstances not. There is a substantial constituency in Russia that is nostalgic about its imperial status, especially after the humiliation inflicted on the state during the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Boris_Yeltsin">Yeltsin</ref> period, and these conflicts are presented in this context. Certainly recognition of Russia at the G8 was a prestige factor, but there are clearly compensations on an ideological level in the present situation. This is an illustration of Russia's ascendency vis-a-vis the US and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/EU">EU</ref> [European Union] in one sense. What it all means in the longer term depends on a significant amount of variables, however.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Blank</hi>: Ejecting Russia from the G8 is necessary but insignificant in its own right.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Kotsonis</hi>: No, it would probably increase his popularity in an us-v-them dynamic. Putin thrives politically on <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/autarky">autarky</ref> and it may be treated as an attack on Russian prestige. But less on Putin's reputation at home.</item></list></p>
<figure><caption>File photo of interviewee Stephen Blank. Image: Stephen Blank.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Is the Russian general public in full support of the deployment of their own troops into Ukraine, a separate sovereign nation?</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Morris</hi>: No, this is a distraction by Putin from increasing economic and political problems in Russia. A minority of Russians support deployment and I think support from ordinary Russians will fall when they realise deployment may result in the killing of fellow <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slavs">Slavs</ref>.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Burbank</hi>: There is no such thing as a united Russian public.  There are many views in Russia, as elsewhere.  Clearly, some people in Russia oppose this assault on Ukraine, as we have seen from the arrests and beating of demonstrators in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Moscow">Moscow</ref>. There is a section of the academic "community" — also a deceptive word — that is opposed to the invasion.</item></list></p>
<p>If you are interested in this, read the discussion on Ab Imperio's Facebook site, where many young academics are expressing their views.</p>
<p>I would like to repeat one point:  the notion of a simple nationalized divide between East and West Ukraine is both false and counter-productive.  There are nationalists in many areas of the country, but there are also people with other political commitments.  It is dangerous for the Western media to reinforce the notion that nationalist sentiment  (pro-Russian or pro-Ukrainian) is the only political force in Ukraine.  A whole generation has grown up since Ukraine's independence and many people, old and young and in the middle, have ideas about sovereignty and politics that are not simply "ethnic."</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Brandist</hi>: Russia does not have a unified or stable 'public opinion' any more than anywhere else. Moreover, the Crimea and east of Ukraine are not necessarily viewed as fully a separate nation among many Russians. Many Russians have relatives there and go there for vacations. At present the majority are in support for the reasons I've just outlined. However, we have seen significant opposition movements in recent years, which shows that if things turn out badly then Putin may be vulnerable. There is clearly an assessment of risks that has been carried out by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow%20Kremlin">Kremlin</ref>, and so far it has paid off. Indeed, it probably strengthens Putin's compromised standing at home, but if things do go wrong then this could change quickly.</item></list></p>
</text>
