<text id="autogum_interview_doc1204" title="part16_BDSM as business: An interview with the owners of a dungeon" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_An_interview_with_the_owners_of_a_dungeon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why would it not be good for the girls or the guys?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Rebecca and I both like to sleep at night and feel that we have a good conscience.  We don't want to burn anybody out.  I don't want anybody working here and in a bad position when they leave.  I tell them right before I hire them, ‘You know, I'm open to the exchange.  When you leave here, I'll meet you somewhere.  I always tell them, I'd like to be able to buy you a meal or a cup of coffee at the very least somewhere, and hope that you'll take something out of here.’  What happens is, they get so involved with this stuff and so quickly that they it’s like they just overfeed on it.  And they--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  --need a break?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  I don't want them looking at a pair of stilettos and this and that--they see enough of it.  What I call "Hairy Ass Syndrome."  What that means is a girl can only look at so many hairy asses until after a while you want to, like, explode!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Give me a smooth one.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Or give me no ass, give me a Disney film!</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  You have to know, most other people that own these type of places don't think about it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  They really don't.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  No, they don't.  They don't care.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are there people who would not be attracted to this kind of an environment, that want the crazier--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Yeah, oh yeah, sure.  They want the, uh--the hardcore crew.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And probably so you wouldn't see them, but you'd probably have an idea about the--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  We have--I'll call the black room.  We have that room for them that looks heavier.  And we have girls that--</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  I want to tell you.  We also have girls that work at other places, like Jada, and the girl who said, "Hi, nice to meet you."  And she's a darling girl!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  You might wanna talk to some--see--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yeah, I'd love to talk to them, too.  What's their average length of employment?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  It's usually pretty long.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  We have one girl that's been--how long has Tracy been here?  Ten years?  Eleven years?  There's nowhere to go if they leave here.  If you want to stay in the industry--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is it usually a temporary job, until they move on to something else?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like "I'm putting myself through school." </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Well, no, probably most of our girls are post-college.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Paying debts down?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  I guess.</p>
<head id="Criticism_of_BDSM">Criticism of BDSM</head>
</text>
