<text id="autogum_interview_doc1037" title="part4_Wikinews interviews team behind the 2,000th featured Wikipedia article" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-10" dateModified="2009-12-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_team_behind_the_2%2C000th_featured_Wikipedia_article" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Meanwhile, as for the topic of credentials, which I know has been much debated on Wikipedia, I think that's a real <hi rend="italic">canard</hi>.  I don't think credentials matter much.  My students don't have much in the way of credentials, but they've done superior work.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Would you describe your students as receptive to the idea of doing coursework where the general public could view their works in progress?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">JBM</hi></hi>: I'd often asked students to write blogs in previous courses, which are also of course visible to the general public.  But not too many people bump into such student blogs, except on rare occasions.  Here, the point wasn't so much that the Wikipedia articles were public, but that they were editing one of the Internet's top ten sites.  So one day I'd poked around and found out how many people had visited particular pages that we're editing.  (I compiled and later updated these numbers <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:WikiProject_Murder_Madness_and_Mayhem#Google_page_rank">here</ref>.)  And the next class we played two little guessing games.  One involved what percentage of Wikipedia's articles they thought were classified as "Good Articles"; they started at 30%, and it took them a while to get down to 0.15%.  This was just after <hi rend="italic">El Señor Presidente</hi> had made Good Article status, so it gave them a sense of the achievement, I think.</item></list>
<p>The other little guessing game concerned how many page views they thought their articles attracted per month.  I can't remember exactly the figure they started off with in this case, but I can tell you it was a lot lower than the 50,000 plus that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabriel%20García%20Márquez">Gabriel García Márquez</ref> actually receives.  When we figured out that that article must have something over 600,000 visits a year (I now reckon it's almost three-quarters of a million), the team who were editing that page were somewhat shocked.  But my sense is that the realization was also rather exciting.  And I know that the students who will shortly find their article on the <hi rend="italic">mainpage</hi> of the English Wikipedia (it'll be there on May 5th) are absolutely thrilled.  Though frankly I think they (and the other students) are less interested in the fact that the "general public" can see what they've done, than in telling their friends and family to take a look at their work.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Did any students fail to fit in and find themselves unable to work with Wikipedia?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">JBM</hi></hi>: Yes.  There was a wide range of responses.  Some were very enthusiastic.  Others took a while to get into it.  And there were a few who never really found themselves at home editing Wikipedia.  I'm not sure of the reasons in each case.  For some the technology stayed too intimidating, or rather (I suspect) they just didn't put in enough time to get past that first hurdle.  As this was group work, however, some of the effects could be worrisome at times.  So it's something I'd have to think over before trying a similar experiment again.</item></list>
</text>
