<text id="autogum_interview_doc1168" title="part1_Lobby groups oppose plans for EU copyright extension" shortTile="partlobby-groups" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-18" dateModified="2014-12-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lobby_groups_oppose_plans_for_EU_copyright_extension" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="The_interview">The interview</head>
<head id="Cliff_Richard's_pension">Cliff Richard's pension</head>
<p>Becky explained to us that she was in Brussels to gather support for a European movement against this proposal. She pointed out to us that compelling economic evidence shows that this measure will not help the E.U. single market, and she hopes that other Directorates will oppose it once they get wind of this fact. We asked Becky Hogge to tell us about the new proposal and why she thinks it is not a good idea. </p>
“
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">From left to right</hi>: Becky Hogge (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open%20Rights%20Group">Open Rights Group</ref>), Erik Joseffson (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Electronic_Frontier_Foundation">Electronic Frontier Foundation</ref>), <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Brianmc">Brian McNeil</ref> (Wikinews) and Eddan Katz (EFF, right).</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Becky Hogge</hi>: The legislation we are talking about is about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/copyright%20term">copyright term</ref>, as in the length of time a piece of, in this case music, remains in copyright, and in particular the term for sound recorders. Apparently the term for that in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Union">European Union</ref> is 50 years. That means that after 50 years, sound recordings enter the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/public%20domain">public domain</ref>. That's the body of work that includes <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20Shakespeare">Shakespeare</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann%20Wolfgang%20von%20Goethe">Goethe</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann%20Sebastian%20Bach">Bach</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludwig%20van%20Beethoven">Beethoven</ref>, ... the cultural heritage of human culture."</p>
<p>In <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/America">America</ref> the term is 95 years but in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">U.K.</ref> the term is 50 years, and those in the recording industry and the performer's union were getting together and going to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Commission">European Commission</ref> and saying 'we would like the terms extended'. Now, in the U.K. we knew about copyright term extension. There's a process by which governments say: 'When this cartoon was drawn, we said that that could be in copyright for 45 years, but now it's about to fall out of copyright, so we'll give you another 45 years, or we'll give you another 10 or another 20... and continually stopping those pieces of our cultural heritage from entering the public domain, along with their brothers Shakespeare, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozart">Mozart</ref> and Beethoven, like an afterlife in the public domain where we knew they could be mixed, they could be shared, and that they become a public part of our culture.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The reason why I think this is unfortunate, is because is actually, it's very hard to see who gains from extension</hi>. Well, it's very easy to see who gains from copyright extension on the one hand; those that are still mastering cultural iconography, you know, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Beatles">The Beatles</ref> back catalogue or if you are in possession of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elvis">Elvis</ref> back catalogue, or whatever it is, they're all going to gain substantially from that. But if you think about what other sound recordings that were made at that time, all the other bits that were written, all the other plays that were written, not all of them are going to be successful 50 years after they were laid down, and it's only a tiny minority of tracks that are going to be commercially successful.</p>
</text>
