<text id="autogum_interview_doc1025" title="part1_Blown for Good author discusses life inside international headquarters of Scientology" shortTile="partblown-good-author" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-11-12" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Blown_for_Good_author_discusses_life_inside_international_headquarters_of_Scientology" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Headley describes a form of Miscavige's management previously related in the <hi rend="italic">St. Petersburg Times</hi>, where the Scientology leader made his staff play <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/musical%20chairs">musical chairs</ref> to the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen%20(band)">Queen</ref></hi> song "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bohemian%20Rhapsody">Bohemian Rhapsody</ref>". Miscavige told 70 Scientology executives that they were to compete for chairs, and that only the last individual left after several rounds would remain at the compound, while the other executives would be assigned to remote locations. After a dramatic competition with multiple staffers in tears that they would be separated from their families, Miscavige stated no one would be removed from the compound.</p>
<p>In 2005, Headley left the Scientology compound in Hemet on a motorcycle, and fell off his vehicle after being chased by Scientology security guards. Riverside County police helped Headley escape from the Scientology security. Headley traveled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kansas%20City">Kansas City</ref> to meet his father. He was later joined by his wife Claire who had also worked at the Gold Base compound.</p>
<p>Headley filed suit against Scientology in January 2009. In the legal case, he asserts that Scientology violated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20labor%20law">United States labor law</ref> with regard to his treatment while an employee of the organization. Headley and his lawyer Barry Van Sickle succeeded against attempts by the organization to get the suit dismissed. Headley's lawsuit is set to begin in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20district%20court">U.S. federal court</ref> in November 2010.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">American</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/talk%20radio">talk radio</ref> hosts John Kobylt and Ken Chiampou discussed the book on the November 4 edition of their program <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20John%20and%20Ken%20Show">The John and Ken Show</ref></hi> on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KFI">KFI</ref>. "This is, the Scientology cult, is I guarantee you, a thousand times more bizarre than you could have ever imagined. And what these celebrities do, like Tom Cruise, is a thousand times more strange than you could ever imagine. I have never read about behavior like this in my life, I can't imagine it. It's really weird," commented one of the hosts about material revealed by Headley in the book. Headley writes in the book that he started to question his involvement in Scientology when secretly listening to <hi rend="italic">The John and Ken Show</hi> and watching <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conan%20O'Brien">Conan O'Brien</ref> make fun of Scientology celebrities. <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20National%20Enquirer">The National Enquirer</ref></hi> reported on the release of <hi rend="italic">Blown for Good</hi>, calling it an "explosive new book".</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Editor%20in%20chief">Editor in chief</ref> of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Village%20Voice">The Village Voice</ref></hi>, Tony Ortega, reviewed the book, and characterized it as a "remarkable account". "Headley's book also provides stunning material that has rarely been collected in one place, even with the Internet's deep resources on L. Ron Hubbard's strange creation. Headley's story provides a damning account of life working for Scientology leader David Miscavige at the secretive desert base", wrote Ortega in the review. He commented, "Perhaps the best service that Headley provides with <hi rend="italic">Blown for Good</hi> is giving non-Scientologists the sense of what it's really like to work, day in and day out, in such a strange organization, from the lowliest laborer mucking out excrement in a Gold Base pond (Headley says shit was coming out of his ears and pores for days) to what kind of luxuries the celebrities and high-ranking members enjoy."</p>
</text>
