<text id="autogum_interview_doc1238" title="part1_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You started drinking when you were 13, but 16 was when you were really--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  That was when I was going all the time, and then at 17 it was every night.  I would drink every single night.  And by 18, 19, I was an alcoh--I needed it.  I needed to always drink.  So I went to rehab when I was 30, and when I got out I was living over here on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third%20Avenue,%20Manhattan">Third Avenue</ref> and Tenth Street, in this really crappy little apartment.  I didn't know how to do anything at all.  I was horrified by that.  I couldn't date anybody, because I was so damaged.  I have my background, my history--I could never get through the third date with that.  "Tell me about your family.  Tell me about your past."  You know?  It was like a deal-breaker by the third date, because it was just too much for one person to go through and remain sane.  So I felt already ruined.  And then, on top of that, I was now sober for the first time, so--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How did you get over the problems of dating?  Just by being sober-?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Well, no [<hi rend="italic">nervous laugh</hi>], what happened is I got sober, I was sober for about a year and a half, and then I relapsed.  I relapsed in just a huge way--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Which is what one tends to do.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yes.  I was much worse than I ever had been.  First of all, when I got sober, that's when I started to write.  I had this just manic energy; if I went downstairs to get cigarettes--I smoked at that time-- I would be gone ten minutes, and I would spend the next four hours writing about it, just the tiniest detail, everything.  Everything I did, I wrote about.  I was working, so I would email the document to myself, pick it up at work and keep on writing.  It was like a security blanket.  Everything I had was this stupid journal.  When I relapsed, I stopped writing completely, and I started drinking and doing drugs I had never done before.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  As happens.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah, as happens, and I got to the point where I started to develop really serious physical symptoms.  I began hallucinating; I had cardiac symptoms, and I got alcohol poisoning--and I knew that I'd end up having a heart attack.  My heart started beating very irregularly and then stopping and starting--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I know that feeling.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I knew, this is how you die.  This is it.  I always wondered, how do you die from alcohol?  They always say it's a terminal illness, but assuming you don't drive, how do you actually die?  Well, now I was starting to see how.  My system was shot, you could see my liver outlined in the mirror when I stood up, and I was a real mess, and--</p>
</text>
