<text id="autogum_interview_doc1287" title="part12_Edmund White on writing, incest, life and Larry Kramer" shortTile="partedmund-white" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-08" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edmund_White_on_writing%2C_incest%2C_life_and_Larry_Kramer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  A baby voice.  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  I think because flatulence I guess I could see as part of normal human physiology.  It’s not an affectation if you fart.  If you talk in a baby voice it’s a deliberate affectation and I think affectations in general are repellent.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is that one especially repellent to you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  It’s funny that you mention it because I have a character in my new book <hi rend="italic">Hotel de Dream</hi> who is an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/androgyne">androgyne</ref>, and it’s based upon a real person.  I wrote a book called memoirs of androgyne.  Not only did she want men to treat her—him—as a BABY, but he would give a blow job to anybody if they would say to him, “Isn’t this the cutest whittle baby that every did live,” and so on, and bounce him on their knee.  I suppose if somebody was really kinky and dirty and wanted to be powdered and burped I could get into it, because I tend to like things that are demented like that.  But if you were just in bed with a guy with a five o’clock shadow like you and all of a sudden he started going, “Goo goo goo goo” it would be a little alarming.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What trait do you deplore in other people?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Injustice.  It can be anything like if it’s the laundry man refusing to pay up to a little old lady, and he’s lost ten of her shirts and gives her some rigmarole and gives her forms to fill out…I’ll defend her.  I get really hot under the collar.  It’s not injustice done to me, it’s anybody.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you value most in your friends.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Loyalty is very important, but I’m very easy-going with people.  For instance, we have a friend who really was impossible recently, but I guess if I really like the person I see why he does these things and I’m not going to reproach him.  I don’t give advice and I don’t reproach people.</p>
<head id="On_Larry_Kramer">On Larry Kramer</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What role do you think you play in the gay community?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I don’t think I’m very prominent in the gay community.  A typical Ed White moment was—I was one of the six founders of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gay%20Men's%20Health%20Crisis">Gay Men’s Health Crisis</ref>.  Last summer they had the 25th anniversary of the organization.  I went to the party because I was invited.  There are only three of us who are still alive of the six original founders.  Everybody was dressed in black, they were all in their thirties, they were all AIDS professionals, and nobody knew who I was.  I just wandered around completely by myself.  Hillary Clinton whizzed past me, looked at me in kind of a strange way as if she might know me, gave this very clever, very well-informed, very rehearsed talk, and whizzed out.  Then I looked in this dining room where I saw six hundred chairs where they would all be thanking each other and congratulating each other, and I thought, “Get me out of here!” and I left.  And nobody noticed.</p>
</text>
