<text id="autogum_interview_doc325" title="part12_John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing" shortTile="partjohn-reed-orwell" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2015-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell%2C_God%2C_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  An afterlife?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I don't know if it's in those terms, exactly, but there are a lot of things we don't understand.  We're all part of the same thing.  For various Gnostic reasons, saying that there's this thing that existed before all of us, that we're all part of it, and that each of us is made up of a piece of this thing--it's appealing to me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's a trait you deplore in yourself?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  The trait I hate most in myself is probably one of my best traits --</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Isn't that always the case?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, probably.  Probably.  I've always been loyal to people, and I think it's one of my worst and best traits.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How is it your best trait?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I stand behind people who are really quite troubled and messed up. [laughs nervously]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is that also how it's one of your worst, then?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, yeah.</p>
<figure><caption>Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What’s a time that this trait screwed you over.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  As a young writer, I knew a lot of extremely talented, amazing people who were hell-bent on self-destruction, as are a lot of people at that age who are creative people, and yet I still believed in them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How so?  Typical drug, alcohol problems, or--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, or just really self-sabotaging.  A novelist, let's say, who refused to finish the novel and kept rewriting until it was ruined.  Or an artist who--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like Joseph Grand in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Plague%20(novel)">The Plague</ref> where he was rewriting the same sentence over and over?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, yeah, or just doing a gigantic revision when it was really finished, or an artist who was doing quite well and then started dating their art dealer and cheated on them.  People have all kinds of ways of destroying themselves.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think it is that drives many artists to sink their own ships?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Well, because partially, I think the inclination to be a creative person is to blow things up, right?  And of course the nearest thing around you is yourself.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman%20Rockwell">Norman Rockwell</ref> had that inclination?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I don't know his history that well.  Did he?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I don't know, either.  No by his popular image.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  There's also a lot of bullshit in our culture, which pushes the idea that to be a successful artist you have to be utterly self-destructive.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's your most treasured possession?  You can't include kids, because they're not really possessions.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  My most treasured possession?  Well--I like this painting right here.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is it your most treasured?</hi></p>
</text>
