<text id="autogum_interview_doc916" title="part1_Scientology protest group celebrates founder&amp;apos;s birthday worldwide" shortTile="partscientology-protest" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-05" dateModified="2019-02-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology_protest_group_celebrates_founder%27s_birthday_worldwide" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Around 2:30PM a young man arrived in front of the Church to counter the Anonymous group with a yellow sign reading "Freedom of [Religion]" on one side, and "It's Their Choice" on the other.  He began by calling out "It's their Choice" to which the protesters across the street replied "We Agree" and then "Right to join, Right to leave!"  Some Anonymous members swarmed over to confront the man, but were restrained to one-on-one talks with him by another Anonymous member.  He later left the area after talks with the protesters.</p>
<p>BBC News drove by taking video of the protesters, but did not stop for interviews.</p>
<head id="Boston,_Massachusetts"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Boston,_Massachusetts">Boston</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref></head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Correspondent: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:TUFKAAP">TUFKAAP</ref></hi></p>
<p>Over 250 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Anonymous_(group)">Anonymous</ref> protesters were out in force once more on the corners, at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Boston">Boston</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology">Scientology</ref> church at the corners of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beacon%20Street">Beacon</ref> and Hereford Streets. Protesters only took up three corners, instead all four like they did on February 10th as police asked them politely to leave the street in front of Church vacant. Even though the protesters had a permit for all streets, they complied.</p>
<p>Wikinews talked to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston%20Police">Boston Police</ref> and was denied a video statement by one officer telling the reporter, "Get out of here," and brushing him off. However, the reporter asked another officer if there had been any trouble. The officer responded that there had been "no trouble, just people walking back and forth." Most the protest consisted of protesters handing out information pamphlets, DVDs, viral marketing cards for their campaign, talking to pedestrians who were passing by, shouting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet%20meme">Internet memes</ref> to one another and shouting various chants.</p>
<p>Some Anonymous put forward concerns about Scientology plants in the crowd trying to incite disruption, however, none was noted. Other protesters mentioned there were rumors that the Scientologists were going to bus in Scientology students to disrupt the protester, however, that did not occur. </p>
<p>Scientologists were outside taking photos of the protesters, unlike February 10th, where they remained inside and photographing from the building. The Wikinews reporter asked a Scientologist why he taking pictures, he took the reporter's photograph and noted that he "was just taking pictures." Wikinews asked a church member if he would like to give a statement to Wikinews on camera, they denied the request and told the reporter they would send a statement via email to him. However, Wikinews has not yet received a statement from the Boston church.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VdAJl8I2xNI">YouTube video of TUFKAAP's report</ref></hi> (Video)</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Boston Galleries</hi></p>
<list type="unordered">
<item style="width: 155px;">A protester confronts a Scientolgist cameraman.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Protesters were forbidden by police from protesting on the sidewalk in front of the church</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">A protester holds a sign calling the church an organized crime front</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">A protester dressed as "Anonymous" encourages people to honk their horns</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Protesters in Boston stand across the street from the church</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">A "nun" casting thetans out</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">A protester dressed as a Charmeleon from Pokemon holds a sign parodying Rick Astley's "Never Gonna Give You Up" and the "Rickroll" meme while making references to Scientology's tax-exempt status and their "Fair Game" policy</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Protester hold signs asking for Scientology to be taxed and that "Religion should be free"</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Protesters hold signs next to the church</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Protesters hold signs on the sidewalk next to the church</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Protesters hold signs advertising websites and birthday wishes</item>
<item style="width: 155px;"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Anonmyous_protesters_pose_for_group_picture.JPG">File:Anonmyous protesters pose for group picture.JPG</ref>Protesters pose for group pictures near the end of the protest</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Protesters share a group hug with each other</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">A protester's sign laying on the ground suggests other names for the Church.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">This protester's sign accuses Church leader, David Miscavige of being a "suppressive person" or "SP"</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">A protester with a V mask and a plastic afro</item>
</list>
</text>
