<text id="autogum_interview_doc1374" title="part0_Interview: Drupal founder Dries Buytaert balances community and company interests" shortTile="partinterview-drupal" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-28" dateModified="2015-10-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview%3A_Drupal_founder_Dries_Buytaert_balances_community_and_company_interests" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview: Drupal founder Dries Buytaert balances community and company interests</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, February 24, 2008</hi></p>
<p>In the year 2000, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dries%20Buytaert">Dries Buytaert</ref> created <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drupal">Drupal</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/FLOSS">freely licensed and open source</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Content%20management%20system">tool to manage websites</ref>, as a bulletin board for his college dorm. Since Dries released the software and a community of thousands of volunteer developers have added and improved modules, Drupal has grown immensely popular. Drupal won the overall Open CMS Award in 2007, and some speakers in Drupal's spacious developer's room at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FOSDEM">FOSDEM</ref> 2008 were dreaming aloud of its world domination.</p>
<p>Buytaert (now 29) just finished his doctoral thesis and has founded the start-up Acquia. The new company wants to become Drupal's best friend, with the help of an all-star team and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20dollar">US$</ref>7 million collected from venture capitalists. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Stevenfruitsmaak">Michaël Laurent</ref> sat down with Dries in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brussels">Brussels</ref> to discuss these recent exciting developments.</p>
<head id="The_interview">The interview</head>
<head id="On_FOSDEM">On FOSDEM</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : How important is an event like FOSDEM for yourself and for the Drupal community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Dries Buytaert</hi>: I think it's more important for the Drupal community than for me personally. It is important because we work together day and night through mailing lists, fora etc., and when you meet each other face-to-face you can understand one and another better, it gives more depth to your relationship. It's also important as a forum were many ideas can be discussed in a shorter time. With the growth of Drupal, the community has grown, and even for me it has become impossible to follow all communication, all forum posts etc. So it is also a way to filter new ideas.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Do you go and visit other projects as well?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DB</hi>: Normally, I would. I've been coming here for seven years from start to finish, but this year I'm only here today and purely for the Drupal DevRoom. My job is to be present in the corridors, to chat with people, to do networking and to connect people. So FOSDEM is important to share information, to improve our relationships, and thirdly to promote Drupal. Drupal is both an end-user product and a framework for developers, and the latter is certainly a direction in which I'd like to see Drupal grow more.</p>
<head id="On_Drupal">On Drupal</head>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Can you give some examples of websites that use Drupal?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DB</hi>: In Belgium: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Studio%20Brussel">Studio Brussel</ref>, Donna [<hi rend="italic">both radio stations, ed.</hi>], <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indymedia">Indymedia</ref>. Internationally you have for example <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amnesty%20International">Amnesty International</ref>, but it ranges from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ozzy%20Osbourne">Ozzy Osbourne</ref>'s to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Britney%20Spears">Britney Spears</ref>' site. Also <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greenpeace">Greenpeace</ref>, a lot of universities,... oh and zattevrienden.be in Belgium.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Wow, it must be everywhere if it ranges from Britney to Ozzy. Tell me, how has your role changed over the years?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DB</hi>: My role has changed a lot. At first I did everything myself from the first to the last thing, I wrote every letter of code, I managed the infrastructure, I did <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revision%20control">source control</ref>, public relations, etc. Today, there is a team of thousands of people who write the code, and a lot more who work for example on the infrastructure, there is a group of people concerned with PR and marketing, etc. Nowadays I write little code myself, but I continue to review a lot of code, giving <hi rend="italic">yes, no or yes but...</hi> answers. So I've become more of a code reviewer.</p>
</text>
