<text id="autogum_interview_doc1252" title="part15_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah.  Not the thing to do.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  No!  So--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Get her drunk and get her tattooed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] I should--it would only take one drink with her.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I think it'd be cool to have razor stubble tattooed here on my head, so that it'd look like I have really thick hair, but choose to have it very short.</p>
<head id="On_losing_his_hair">On losing his hair</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Was it difficult losing your hair?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  It was funny, because I've always been really good--I'm not--I'm not someone who goes into denial a whole lot.  Even though I was a big lush, I knew it.  I'm really honest with myself.  And when my hair cutter told me, "Oh, you're losing your hair," I said, "Oh, no, I'm not.  I've always had a high peak."  Then I went home and looked at it, and I saw that I was really losing it.  And I was horrified.  It was my--it mattered too much.  And so I deserved to lose it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's really hard.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  It is hard.  Women don't--it's like losing your breasts.  Imagine if your breasts shrank up and shriveled away to cork nubs.  I mean, it would really be--it's traumatic, it is.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I freaked out on my mom one time because she made a joke about it.  I went overboard, I just freaked out.  This was years ago, when it was just first starting to go a little bit. But I also always had a high peak,  always.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  As a matter of fact, people made fun of me about it in my Georgia high school.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  That is something that people would make fun of you about in a Georgia high school.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yeah.  [<hi rend="italic">In a southern accent</hi>] "Sportin' a pretty big forehead, there, Day-vid."</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah, yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I freaked out.  "You don't know what it's like!  You don't have any idea!”  It was Christmas.  But a person has to get to a point where he accepts it.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  You do.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like when you see guys who try all these creative styles to--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You know, pushing all their hair forward, when it's really--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Not good.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You know, and you think--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  You need to let it go.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Let it go. It makes it seem like they have trouble dealing with things.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Oh, yeah!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  There's wider implications.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Hair becomes your psychological issue, you know?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Or reflection of psychological issues.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Exactly.  Yeah, exactly.  It's the externalization of your denial.  Better just to chop it off, although, you know, I have to say…</p>
</text>
