<text id="autogum_interview_doc025" title="part3_Wikinews attends ComicCon in Bangalore, India" shortTile="partwikinews-attends" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-12-03" dateModified="2019-08-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_attends_ComicCon_in_Bangalore%2C_India" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Would you mind if I take a photo?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Absolutely not.</p>
<head id="Interview_with_freelancer_comic_writer_John_Layman">Interview with freelancer comic writer John Layman</head>
<figure><caption>Freelance comic writer John Layman. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Acagastya">Acagastya</ref>. (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:2017_Bangalore_ComicCon_(media)_IMG_0115.JPG">Reuseterms</ref>.)</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure><p> How did you get into comics?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">John Layman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  My first job, I moved to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/San_Diego,_California">San Diego</ref> because that is where the comic book con is. After college, I moved to San Diego, at it was much smaller, but I didn't know how to get into comics because it was the pre internet or internet was just coming in to being and it was like 1990. So I got a job at the newspaper, and I would do geek stories. Whenever like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spawn%20(comics)">Spawn</ref> had a TV show, or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judge%20Dredd">Judge Dredd</ref> had a movie or the Comic Con rolled in town, I would write an article about it. And eventually I attracted attention of the local comic book company which was Jim Lee's WildStorm productions. They hired me as an assistant editor and then I worked my way up to editor, and then DC bought us. And suddenly I was a DC editor. So I had done that for about five years and then I had always wanted to write, I figured I knew how so I went freelance and then I started writing in about 2001. And I have been writing ever since.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What other companies do you have worked for?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  DC, Marvel, Dark Horse, IDW, Avatar, Dark Horse, Dynamite, ...[a fellow volunteer suggests X-Men] well, companies, like Boom! I have basically worked for  every, nearly every major comic book company in America.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Why did you choose freelancing and not stick to one company?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Because I don't want to work for a boss. I don't want to wear pants. I don't want people to tell me what to do. Like if I don't want a job, I can just [shows middle finger] you know, I can just walk away. But, it's hard because if you don't have work, you don't get paid. So you are always hustling. But there is a freedom of being your own boss.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  If you had an option, like, if there was no one to command you, would you still continue freelancing?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I, no. I actually, a few years ago, I got a company job and after being freelancer, like no I don't wanna go into an office, I don't wanna do hours, like you get being used to be your own boss, I could never go back to a real job.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Which is the first character you'd created when you were a kid?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JL</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Oh! You know, I can't — that's been so long ago I don't even keep track that anymore. I mean I had some old dumb things that I don't even pay attention to anymore because I look back at them and they are so amateurish, you know I don't have a certain character I have created at an age that I remember.</p>
</text>
