<text id="autogum_interview_doc1383" title="part6_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You are saying that when you become involved you are fighting to ensure that there is a fair investigation into whatever has happened, and that sometimes you are paired with the fact that not everything turns out in favor of the person being investigated?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  That’s exactly right.  You get the downside, like the Brawley jury didn’t believe her.  I’ll give you one worse.  Amadou Diallou was killed, forty-one bullets.  The <hi rend="italic">jury</hi> said they weren’t guilty.  He’s still dead.  So on paper was I wrong about Amadou Diallo?  He’s dead, forty-one bullets killed him, but the <hi rend="italic">jury</hi> said that those cops were right, so when do we decide?  My comeback always is: I disagreed with the  grand jury on Brawley.  I believed there was enough evidence to go to trial.  Grand jury said there wasn’t.  Okay, fine.  Do I have a right to disagree with the grand jury?  Many Americans believe <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/O.%20J.%20Simpson%20murder%20case">O.J. Simpson</ref> was guilty.  A jury said he wasn’t.  So I have as much right to question a jury as they do.  Does it make somebody a racist?  No!  They just disagreed with the jury.  So did I.  I happened to not believe a fifteen year old girl could have made all that up and <hi rend="italic">guess</hi> the names of the people who admitted they were together.  I just don’t believe that.  Now, what happened?  I don’t know.  But I don’t believe <hi rend="italic">that</hi>.  So, we’ll just disagree.</p>
<head id="Sharpton_and_the_African-American_media">Sharpton and the African-American media</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl%20Ofari%20Hutchinson">Earl Ofari Hutchinson</ref> recently wrote a relatively laudatory column about you in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Huffington%20Post">The Huffington Post</ref></hi>. In it he said, "When Sharpton toppled Jesse Jackson from the top spot as black America's main man, the notoriety, and the hostility, that that title carries with it, insured that he'd take the heat for whatever went right or wrong when blacks took to the streets in protest."   What do you think happened to Jesse Jackson’s place in the black community?   Hutchison is a prominent black man saying you toppled Jackson.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Well, that’s a hard thing for me to comment on.  When I was growing up Reverend Jackson was a hero to me and a mentor.  I’d rather not get into that.  I’ll let Earl and others give their opinions.  I’ll stay out of that.  That’s difficult for me to answer.</p>
"<hi rend="bold">The main thing [black columnists] write about is criticism of black leaders. If you read their columns you understand what their job is. 'White leadership is never at fault. Government is never at fault. It’s black leaders.'"</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right"><hi rend="bold">—Al Sharpton</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Clarence Page again in reference to this wrote, "'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/gangster">gangsta</ref>' culture punishes those who don't '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stop%20Snitching">Stop Snitching</ref>,' to quote a popular inner-city T-shirt slogan, even when the victims are innocent neighbors. A lot of us black Americans would like to take back our streets. We could use a little more help from our leaders."  </hi></p>
</text>
