<text id="autogum_interview_doc953" title="part4_Exclusive: 'The Scientology Reformation' author examines Tom Cruise and David Miscavige" shortTile="partexclusive--scientology" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-10-18" dateModified="2012-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Exclusive%3A_%27The_Scientology_Reformation%27_author_examines_Tom_Cruise_and_David_Miscavige" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>[Note: Clark Carr is currently president of Narconon International; Gary Smith is currently CEO of Narconon Arrowhead in Oklahoma and has been active in Narconon in Oklahoma since at least 1989.]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Soon after the June 11, 2008 death of Patrick W. Desmond, Director of Narconon in Georgia Mary Rieser sent a memo to the Scientology Office of Special Affairs (OSA). Why would OSA have been notified of a death of a former Narconon patient? Is this standard practice? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "Because Church of Scientology Inc controls every aspect of Narconon."</p>
<p>[Note: Per an August 29, 1972 letter by L. Ron Hubbard, subject "Narconon", heading "Sea Organization", "The incomparable Guardian's Office has been running the Narconon (drugs no!) Program over the world."]</p>
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_Miscavige">David Miscavige</ref> Image: <ref target="http://www.flickr.com/photos/49629298@N07/5959054610">Scientology Media</ref>.
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tom_Cruise">Tom Cruise</ref> Image: <ref target="http://www.flickr.com/photos/caroline_bonarde/1876730826/">Caroline Bonarde Ucci</ref>.
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology">Scientology</ref> leader <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_Miscavige">David Miscavige</ref> and celebrity member <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tom_Cruise">Tom Cruise</ref>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The description of your new book, <hi rend="italic">The Scientology Reformation: What Every Scientologist Should Know</hi>, states it will answer questions including, "Why does Tom Cruise continue to support Miscavige despite international media reports of his increasingly sociopathic conduct?". Can you give us a little taste and explain in brief why Tom Cruise still supports David Miscavige after the reporting of controversy in the Scientology organization from news sources including the 2009 <hi rend="italic">St. Petersburg Times</hi> "The Truth Rundown" series, and the 2010 <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anderson%20Cooper%20360">Anderson Cooper 360</ref></hi> piece on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CNN">CNN</ref>, "Scientology: A History of Violence"? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "It is covered in excerpts posed on my blog markrathbun.wordpress.com."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You published an excerpt of <hi rend="italic">The Scientology Reformation</hi> on your blog, "Chapter Eight: The Gates of Hell", where you write: "After I had spent more than two years recovering Tom Cruise to the Scientology Bridge, auditing him for dozens of hours, indoctrinating his children to choose him over their mother (his former wife), auditing and guiding him through the entirety of OT V, OT VI, and onto OT VII (three of the highest levels of Scientology spiritual advancement), Miscavige became impatient." What was it that caused Tom Cruise to need to be "recovered" back to the "Scientology Bridge"? How were you able to convince him to come back? Do you now think in the end this result was to his benefit?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "The end result in 2003 was definitely to his benefit. What Miscavige did to him after that will be his undoing."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In <hi rend="italic">The Scientology Reformation</hi>, Chapter Eight, you write, "As much as Miscavige’s head swelled in the Tom Cruise inner circle, he became more and more detached and individuated from the Sea Org members of international management who had built the empire he was profiting from. They slaved on in squalid communal quarters, working long hours with no time off and next to no pay." Is Tom Cruise aware of the real working and living conditions of Sea Org members?</hi></p>
</text>
