<text id="autogum_interview_doc836" title="part6_ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush" shortTile="partaclu-president" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-30" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion%2C_drugs%2C_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I remember years ago when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Kinsley">Michael Kinsley</ref> was the co-host of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CNN%20Crossfire">Crossfire</ref></hi> and I was debating Jerry Falwell, and he interrupted and said, “Come on, guys, you know you <hi rend="italic">need</hi> each other; your <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Direct%20mail%20fundraising">direct mail campaigns</ref> <hi rend="italic">need</hi> each other.” [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<head id="The_abortion_debate">The abortion debate</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Don’t you think the way both sides go about engaging each other harms America?  Take the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gonzales%20v.%20Carhart">partial-birth abortion Supreme Court case</ref>.  Did you read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Paul%20Stevens">Justice Stevens'</ref> <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> interview with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeff%20Rosen">Jeff Rosen</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Yes, I read that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  He said it was a silly decision that wasn’t particularly important—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I don’t remember that—he said that?!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yes.  He said it was, in the end, not a particularly important case.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Oh, I totally disagree with that, unfortunately, it’s a very important decision.  I’m wondering whether he had a strategic reason for making that point; maybe he is trying to get people to implement it in a not-serious way?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  He was talking about in terms of the effect, that it didn’t have much of an effect because there were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abortion%20in%20the%20United%20States">other legal alternatives</ref> to that particular method of abortion.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  That’s not what the medical profession says, so even if you are talking about a tiny percentage of women, it’s still that there are some women—and every single medical organization said this—the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Medical%20Association">American Medical Association</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20College%20of%20Obstetricians%20and%20Gynecologists">College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Nurses%20Association">American Nurses Association</ref>, that for some cases this is the necessary method in order to either preserve the woman’s life or preserve her future fertility.  So the only option they have under this decision is for the doctor to leave the operating room and run to court to get an injunction because the Supreme Court said—the Court acknowledged that in the opinion and said but those women can bring in an “As Applied” challenge, that they aren’t going to strike down the entire statute on its face.  But realistically, is that going to happen?  And what doctor is going to take the risk of criminal prosecution?  I beg, with the greatest respect for him, I really beg to differ.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The question I have is that on its face it was deciding one particular issue in the abortion debate, but a lot of pro-choice organizations paint this as, “We are now getting ready to ban abortion; this is the first step on what might be a short road—“</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  A <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slippery%20slope">slippery slope</ref> argument.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yes, a slippery slope.  Isn’t it almost the same thing when the evangelicals say, “They are coming for your prayer, your kids aren’t going to be able to pray or allow God in schools.”</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I understand what you are saying, David, but I think—</p>
</text>
