<text id="autogum_interview_doc1131" title="part9_Dalai Lama's representative talks about China, Tibet, Shugden and the next Dalai Lama" shortTile="partdalai-lamas-representative" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-13" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dalai_Lama%27s_representative_talks_about_China%2C_Tibet%2C_Shugden_and_the_next_Dalai_Lama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Shugden_worship">Shugden worship</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Christopher_Hitchens">Christopher Hitchens</ref> criticized the Dalai Lama for his supposed suppression of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dorje%20Shugden">Shugden</ref> worship?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  There’s no suppression!  His Holiness made it very clear that according to his own observations over many years—in fact, he himself used to worship Shugden—and over many years of his own experience and observation and investigation, he found that this practice is not according to Buddhist practice.  That practice is also bringing in divisions within the Buddhist traditions.  The practitioners are attaching more importance than the basic Buddhist practice, and therefore he felt that it’s a practice that he would not approve of and therefore he advised people to not engage in it.  But he made it very clear right from the beginning it was up to the individuals.  He has a responsibility to explain the negative aspects of it and then it’s up to the individuals to decide on their own.  Officially there has never been any repression or denial of rights to practitioners.  But after His Holiness’ advice many monastic orders adopted rules and regulations that would not accept practitioners of Shugden worship in their monastic order.  The followers have set up their own groups and they are free to function.  But it’s in the right of institutions to make their own decisions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Was Lozang Gyatso, the director of Institute of Buddhist Dialectics murdered by Shugden worshipers?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes, that’s a fact.  There’s some misunderstanding that groups taking their own actions is the policy of the Tibetan government, but it’s not. Institutions take advice and it is within their right to say they do not want Shugden worship.  But now if a group of people say they want to set up their own institution because they are different practitioners, which is within their right.</p>
<head id="Karmapa_controversy">Karmapa controversy</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is the reason for the Dalai Lama's decision to become involved in the dispute over the identity of the current <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karmapa%20controversy">Karmapa</ref> [<hi rend="italic">the leader of the largest sub-school of one of the four main schools in Tibetan Buddhism - ed.</hi>] by endorsing one candidate? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  There was no special decision.  His Holiness was approached.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  By all sides?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes.  And then later on there was unfortunately some disagreement.  Even <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shamarpa">Shamarpa</ref>—who had disagreements with the other regents at that time—even he did not dispute His Holiness’ decision as to who should be the throne holder.  There should be no dispute.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Does he still play a role as a peacemaker?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  No, there’s no need.   It’s accepted by the vast majority of that tradition.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ogyen%20Trinley%20Dorje">Ogyen Trinley Dorje</ref> [<hi rend="italic">one of the two contestants in the Karmapa dispute - ed.</hi>] will be able to travel freely to visit his followers?</hi></p>
</text>
