<text id="autogum_interview_doc884" title="part9_Author Amy Scobee recounts abuse as Scientology executive" shortTile="partauthor-amy-scobee" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-11" dateModified="2015-12-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_Amy_Scobee_recounts_abuse_as_Scientology_executive" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: I read several quotes from Steven Hassan from the internet that made total sense to me, so I ordered his book. It's a fantastic read. I learned quite a lot about mind control and particularly found it interesting and true that a key aspect of mind control is INFORMATION CONTROL. If one can control the information that you are allowed to receive, then you can really control their thinking. They wouldn't be equipped with all of the ACTUAL information to be able to analyze and made a sane decision about something. In Scientology and especially in the Sea Organization, information is controlled intensively. This includes ALL communication via telephone or mail – incoming and outgoing – being screened through security personnel in order to detect any antagonism regarding Scientology from the "outside", no televisions allowed, no internet access, not being permitted to listen to or read any article that said anything negative about Scientology.</p>
<p>"News" was obtained by the numerous Scientology events, covering the "unprecedented expansion and world-wide acceptance of Scientology". It was a lie, but it kept those not in-the-know thinking that we were doing well, so we need to keep working our guts out. It was astonishing to see when I left that Scientology had a BAD reputation of tearing apart families, of attacking critics, of scamming people out of their money, etc.</p>
<p>I saw how Tom Cruise (supposedly the BEST Scientology disseminator in the world) was losing it on Oprah Winfrey's couch and with Mat Lauer. He was actually a laughing stock in the "real world". But to Scientology, per David Miscavige, Tom Cruise is the most dedicated Scientologist he knows and was responsible for booming Scientology around the world. Well, the statistics I saw while in management for two decades didn't have a Tom Cruise "boom" of expansion. In fact, we were constantly trying to find what was causing a lack of expansion in the various sectors of Scientology.</p>
<p>So, information control is a very important aspect of mind control to understand and watch for.</p>
<p>Another book I found to be very beneficial after leaving Scientology was <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man's%20Search%20for%20Meaning">Man's Search for Meaning</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viktor%20Frankl">Viktor Frankl</ref>. It answered a lot for me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You described in chapter 6, being assigned to a sub-division of the Rehabilitation Project Force, called the "RPF's RPF". How was this different from the main RPF itself? What typical tasks were you ordered to perform? Were there many other women assigned to this unit? Were women given different roles or treated differently than men while on the RPF or the RPF's RPF?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: The Rehabilitation Project Force (or RPF) is described by the church as a program offering a second chance to Sea Org members who have become unproductive or have strayed from the church's codes, involving intensive physical labor at church facilities and auditing and study sessions to address the individual's personal problems. I have a much harsher definition after spending a total of 5 ½ years on this program: A controlled slave labor camp to which is assigned anyone arbitrarily deemed a liability for actions (or thoughts) considered to be in opposition to the group.</p>
</text>
