<text id="autogum_interview_doc510" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Jim Babka, chair of Libertarian organization Downsize DC" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-02" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jim_Babka%2C_chair_of_Libertarian_organization_Downsize_DC" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Jim Babka, chair of Libertarian organization Downsize DC</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 3, 2008</hi></p><p>A reporter from <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> recently interviewed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim%20Babka">Jim Babka</ref>, chair of Libertarian organization <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Downsize%20DC">Downsize DC</ref>. The organization claims to have arranged for 22,158 people to send a message regarding the "American Freedom Agenda Act" proposed by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ron_Paul">Ron Paul</ref>, in addition to supporting many other laws. The full text of the interview can be found below.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What is Downsize DC?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jim Babka</hi>: DownsizeDC.org is an organization that makes it easy for every day citizens, with jobs and busy lives, to express their wishes to their two Senators and Representative. It's free and quite easy to use. The DownsizeDC.org system combines education, recruitment, and activism into one simple, seamless process. And once someone sends a message, they begin receiving our free email newsletter, or as we prefer to describe it, they become part of the Downsize DC Army. Voltaire said, "God tends to be on the side of the bigger battalions." And we're looking to build the Downsize DC Army so large that Congress cannot afford to ignore us – so big that we can get our message of small, Constitutionally-limited government out everywhere</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why do you believe the federal government has grown too large?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JB</hi>: Big government at all levels steals about half of everything Americans earn. We don't believe politicians know best how to spend your money or run your life. We want you to be able to keep what you earn; to spend, to save, to invest, and to give away as you see fit.</p>
<p>We recognize that big government really doesn't work well. Big government has damaged education and health care. It has made us more vulnerable to terrorism while trading away our liberty. It has served the interests of large corporate conglomerates at the expense of individuals. We want to make better education and health care more readily available to you. We want you to live in safety and keep your civil liberties. We want to put an end to corporate welfare.</p>
<p>The Constitution is our guide, and it limits the powers of the federal government. We want the Constitution restored. We believe that we must Downsize DC so that we can have greater peace and human progress.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If you could change one aspect of government what would it be and why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JB</hi>: What a terrible question to ask someone like me! It would've been much easier to ask me what parts of government I would like to keep.</p>
<p>But seriously, if you're going to put a gun to my head like that I would say real legislative reform. Each year and every crisis, government will grow. The legislative rules are written so that the results are virtually guaranteed – more expensive and intrusive government. The incentives in the current legislative environment are all wrong.</p>
</text>
