<text id="autogum_interview_doc195" title="part4_Andrea Muizelaar on fashion, anorexia, and life after &amp;apos;Top Model&amp;apos;" shortTile="partandrea-muizelaar" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Andrea_Muizelaar_on_fashion%2C_anorexia%2C_and_life_after_%27Top_Model%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> To be honest -  I don't think that I should have been in the final two; however if I was on the show now - it would have been an extremely tight competition.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> One constant criticism by the judges and by fans was that you lacked confidence, and certain times in the series you questioned why you were competing against girls you felt were "better than you." Why did you feel that way? Was your body image a factor, and if so, how much of a factor? What other factors were there in the way you felt?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Let's just say that 99% of [the time I was] filming CNTM, I was only focused on hiding my eating disorder, therefore affecting everything from the way I walked on runway to my confidence level.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> The CityTV final episode online viewer poll had the question "Should Andrea have won CNTM?" and the response was overwhelmingly in favor of "No, Andrea shouldn't have been CNTM! She's too skinny and the crying gets annoying!" Was hiding your anorexia the reason why you were as emotional as you were?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Correct.  I was so emotionally unstable that the only person I could talk to was my Mom because she knew what I was going through.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> You made a comment during the series that you felt Stacey McKenzie was the most critical and belittling of the judges. Toward the second half of the competition, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canada's_Next_Top_Model,_Cycle_1#Episode_6:_Beauty_Is_As_Beauty_Poses">you spent an entire afternoon alone with her</ref> at the house and it was shown that you two bonded. Do you feel that day really made you feel better about how Stacey viewed you? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> No, because after wrapping up the day with Stacey I went to give her a hug in front of all the other girls and her true colours shone through.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Please elaborate. Her "true colors" in what sense?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> The bonding was completely TV material and not really there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Which judge do you feel was perhaps the most genuine in terms of behavior on-screen and off?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Tricia Helfer and Ron (one of the producers).</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> There's been criticism on America's Next Top Model that Tyra Banks and the care that she shows to her models is an act for TV. Do you think Tricia Helfer is the opposite?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Absolutely, and don't you think it is weird that she no longer hosts CNTM?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Jay Manuel now hosts, and it's weird to see because he's in a different mode than he is on America's Next Top Model, where he's often very blunt and sarcastic. [...] Toward the end, there was a lot of rather cruel teasing towards you coming from Alanna and Brandi. As you may remember, it culminated in the night <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canada's_Next_Top_Model,_Cycle_1#Episode_7:_Get_Ready.2C_Get_Set.2C_Go_See.21">they went through your belongings</ref> and then tampered with a "treat" they prepared for you and Sisi. It wasn't a complete 180 in behavior, per se, but it did get very nasty very quickly. Why do you think they acted the way they did? Also, you were never shown confronting them for what they did. Did you end up doing so? Finally, did you know the extent of all they had done right away, or did you not find out until you actually saw the episode on television?</p>
</text>
