<text id="autogum_interview_doc1125" title="part3_Dalai Lama's representative talks about China, Tibet, Shugden and the next Dalai Lama" shortTile="partdalai-lamas-representative" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-13" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dalai_Lama%27s_representative_talks_about_China%2C_Tibet%2C_Shugden_and_the_next_Dalai_Lama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is the status of the monks who were arrested after the Dalai Lama received the Congressional Gold Medal?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  According to the reports I have seen, a large number of people have been detained.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  At the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drepung%20Monastery">Drepung Monastery</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes, one of the monasteries was completely surrounded by troops.  The movement of people was highly restricted and party members—retired people—were warned that they would lose their pension.  I’m sure many of them who, despite these strong warnings, expressed their happiness may have suffered.  I have no recent report on that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How difficult is it to receive information from Tibet?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Not very difficult.  Our job is to represent people in Tibet, so our main effort is to try to understand the situation and their feelings, their views.  Therefore, it is very important to us to keep in touch with them and receive accurate, objective information from inside Tibet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you know the situation with Ronggay A'drak, the Tibetan nomad who was arrested?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  What he said is nothing—it was the basic asking for the release of prisoners, that His Holiness should be allowed to return to Tibet.  Because of some democratic change there has been land pressures with Tibetan nomads, so he also appealed to them to not fight amongst themselves for land ownership, which would never have happened in the past.  In this country, nobody would even notice what he said.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What will happen to him?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  He has already been sentenced to prison.  I think it was 10 years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is that standard?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes.  It’s almost a treasonable act to make that kind of a call; unfortunately, it is a very serious crime in Tibet.</p>
<head id="The_disappearance_of_Gedhun_Choekyi_Nyima,_the_eleventh_Panchen_Lama">The disappearance of Gedhun Choekyi Nyima, the eleventh Panchen Lama</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where is Chadrel Rinpoche, the man who selected <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gedhun%20Choekyi%20Nyima">Gedhun Choekyi Nyima</ref> as the eleventh <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panchen%20Lama">Panchen Lama</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  I have no information.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Does anyone?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  There was a report, but I have no confirmed information.  At one point I heard he was not in good health.  He was appointed by the Chinese government to search for the new Panchen Lama and he was in touch with us with the knowledge of the Chinese government.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The Chinese government knew he was in touch with the Dalai Lama over the selection?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes.  Some of his people went to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Beijing">Beijing</ref> when His Holiness’ delegation was in Beijing.  They met and even sent some offerings to His Holiness to pray for the quick discovery of the Panchen Lama.  His Holiness has always made it very clear to the Chinese government that the search for the genuine—the important thing is we have to follow all the procedures to make sure that the genuine reincarnation is discovered.  It was made very clear to the Chinese government that His Holiness and the Tibetan leadership outside was willing to work with the Chinese government in this search. At that time I was His Holiness’ representative in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Delhi">Delhi</ref>, so I had a number of meetings with Chinese officials to convey these messages.  There were no behind-the-scenes.</p>
</text>
