<text id="autogum_interview_doc139" title="part1_Wikinews interviews USA wheelchair curler David Palmer" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-04-08" dateModified="2014-03-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_USA_wheelchair_curler_David_Palmer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What is the nature of your disability? Do you use a wheelchair for most daily activities?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DP</hi>: I am a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thoracic%20spinal%20nerve%204">T4</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/paraplegia">Paraplegic</ref>, due to a motorcycle accident in 1993. Yes I am dependent on my wheelchair for mobility.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How does being a parent impact your ability to compete at elite levels?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DP</hi>: I am married and have three children. Having a family does make it a harder to compete at elite levels,  not only being away traveling, when I am home I am on the ice training a lot. But thanks to the support from my family I have been able to do so. Hopefully it has a positive impact on my children, showing them you can achieve anything you put your mind to.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Does participating in wheelchair curling cost a lot money?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DP</hi>: Well that depends! At a recreational level, if you have a wheelchair already all you need is a delivery stick which is about <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_dollar">$</ref>60.00  and to join a club which has dues usually 300.00 to 500.00 per year. To compete at the highest level, there is travel and lodging involved which can get quite expensive.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How do you afford to compete at the highest level? Do you have any sponsorship deals?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DP</hi>: Getting started was tough, I got help through the members of cape cod curling club and a grant from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Challenged%20Athletes%20Foundation">Challenged Athletes Foundation</ref> (CAF) and some out of my pocket. But once I made the National team there is funding  to help with expenses. I have no sponsorship deals at the moment, but I am open to negotiation!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you think USA Paralympic competitors get enough financial support to enable the country to compete at the highest level?  Is funding equitable in the United States across sports and competitor visibility?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">DP</hi>: No, there is funding, but not nearly enough for an athlete to compete at the highest level.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DP</hi>: Not from what I hear. I believe the higher viewed sports get a lot more funding. I have been told curling is at bottom for funding.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What are your thoughts on the classification system and processes for your sport? Do you know of anyone who has been impacted as a result of it?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">DP</hi>: I am not really clear on how the classification system works. I feel that they should make it as equal as possible for everyone who competes in wheelchair curling. Everyone one has different disabilities and different situations, but as long as they are delivering the stone from a stationary wheelchair with a delivery stick from the same position it should be equal.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DP</hi>: I know of a young man from  state of Washington who uses a wheelchair most of the time but is able to walk and has mobility, that he probably would not qualify for the national team.. Yet I know of a man in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref> that uses a wheelchair only for curling and competes on the National team.</p></p>
</text>
