<text id="autogum_interview_doc005" title="part1_US study finds correlation between youth suicide, household gun ownership" shortTile="partus-study-finds" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-01-18" dateModified="2019-02-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_study_finds_correlation_between_youth_suicide%2C_household_gun_ownership" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Given that some key data is from 2004, how well do you think your results can be applied to the situation today?</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of a handgun in a woman's hands as she prepares to open fire at a shooting range in the US.Image: Corporal Corey Dabney.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">MS</hi> Although we used gun ownership data from 2004 for the primary analysis, we repeated the analysis using a household gun ownership proxy averaged over the years 2005–2015, and the results were similar. Thus, we do not believe that there is any reason to think that the results do not apply to the situation today.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  To what extent do the results of this study match up to your expectations?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MS</hi> We did not actually have a pre-conceived idea of whether or not we would find an association after controlling for the proportion of youth who were depressed, had made a suicide plan, or had attempted suicide. We were surprised, however, to find that the percentage of households with a gun was a stronger predictor of the youth suicide rate than the percentage of youth who made a suicide attempt.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What influence would you like to see these results having on policymakers?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MS</hi> The results suggest that decreasing the access of youth to firearms may lower youth suicide rates. Thus, our findings support efforts to encourage gun owners to store their guns in a manner that prevents youth from accessing them. Policy makers should consider <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gun_control">enacting policies</ref> that reduce youth access to improperly stored firearms.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  If you had access to more recent data than that from 2004, what would you hypothesize the difference might be, if any?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MS</hi> We don't hypothesize that there would be any substantial difference because when we used the proxy data on gun ownership from 2005–2015, we did not find any major difference in the results. </p>
<hi rend="bold">Policy makers should consider enacting policies that reduce youth access to improperly stored firearms</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Professor Siegel</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Did you notice any significant trends in the data year-by-year, and, if so, what were they and what do you think might account for them?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MS</hi> In this article, we did not examine trends by year. The study was cross-sectional and combined (averaged) data from 2005 through 2015. Thus, we are not able in this study to examine trends in suicide rates over time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You noted suicide attempts by youth were not as accurate a prediction method for youth suicide rates as the household gun ownership rates were. Why do you think that might be?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MS</hi> Our hypothesis is that the most important predictor of the youth suicide rate in a state is the extent to which youth in that state have access to the most lethal means (i.e., firearms). Having a high level of access to firearms, which is the most lethal means for suicide, apparently has a far greater impact on suicide rates and can negate the fact that a state has a low rate of youth suicide attempts (and vice versa).</p>
</text>
