<text id="autogum_interview_doc828" title="part13_Satanism: An interview with Church of Satan High Priest Peter Gilmore" shortTile="partsatanism-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-04" dateModified="2018-10-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Satanism%3A_An_interview_with_Church_of_Satan_High_Priest_Peter_Gilmore" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s not all <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gene%20Loves%20Jezebel">Gene Loves Jezebel</ref> sounding.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  No.  Satanic music is specific to each person.  So to me, Satanic music is the symphony, which to me is the highest art form.  So Beethoven, Mahler, Bruckner, Shostakovich — to me that’s some of the most Satanic music ever written because the architecture is there, the expressivity is there; the reflection on the human condition is all present and it’s not idealistic. It’s mostly questioning or showing what a human is capable of doing.  And I love architecture.  Cathedrals are wonderful.  I have no hatred of those because they are put to religious use.  They have symbols on them, but I know those are just symbols.  I love skyscrapers too.</p>
<head id="Anton_LaVey's_children_and_estate">Anton LaVey's children and estate</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do Dr. LaVey’s children have anything to do with the church at all?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  His son Xerxes is a member because he asked to be.  We generally don't let people under 18 join.  We used to let people whose parents allowed them to join, but because people are so litigious we changed that.  We just don't want to take the chance that some parents say, “Yes, it’s okay if my kid joins the Church of Satan,” and then decides that’s the reason they can't control their kid.  We’re just not willing to go there.  But if our members have children who are interested, they can participate and become members, but that’s the only way you can if you’re not legally an adult.  So Xerxes could become a member because his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blanche%20Barton">mother was High Priestess</ref> at one point, and still remains a member.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But not <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeena%20Schreck">Zeena</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  No, she left years ago.  She’s not very bright and is very jealous.  She and her paramour, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikolas%20Schreck">Nikolas Shreck</ref>, got married I think.  They wanted to take the Church of Satan over at one point and wanted Anton LaVey to retire, but he was a feisty guy and said "Hell no!"  So they quit in high dudgeon and ran off to Europe and said, “America is corrupt and horrible and we’re going to Fortress Europa!”  They played with being Nazi occultists, which is kind of funny because both of them have Jewish blood.  They’re just like clowns.  They then joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Temple%20of%20Set">Temple of Set</ref>, which was an organization  that split off from the Church of Satan years ago, in 1975, when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Aquino">Michael Aquino</ref>—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Based on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Set%20(deity)">Egyptian god</ref>?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">His oldest daughter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karla%20LaVey">Karla</ref> isn't a very bright girl.  She kind of hung around the background and once in a while she would come out to speak in public and support her father.  When Xerxes was born she kind of got miffed because she wasn’t the center of attention.  Karla is also a jealous type.</hi>
</text>
