<text id="autogum_interview_doc317" title="part4_John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing" shortTile="partjohn-reed-orwell" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2015-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell%2C_God%2C_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  He coined a philosophy for a terrorist.  Like ‘<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trotskyite">Trotskyite</ref>’--there never really existed this phrase "Osama bin Ladenist."  Do you think it elevated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Osama%20bin%20Laden">bin Laden</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, it was so bizarre.  He was selling <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20Why%20Orwell%20Matters">Why Orwell Matters</ref></hi> at the time.  With that book they were trying to reorient Orwell away from this Cold War model.  I don't know if they can do it, really.  They've done so much damage to his canon.  I don't know if they can shift it out of a sort of Cold War emphasis.  Maybe they can.  The idea that Snowball brings capitalism to the farm--we see the pitfalls there--it's anathema to a sort of CIA model of the Cold War.  But they've got to change it, because the Cold War is over.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But the thinking is there.  Right after the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soviet%20Union">Soviet Union</ref> ended--you could sense it, you could feel it in the air--this "Who do we set our sights on?"  I think that all of us felt that way to a degree, if not just because we were socialized to think that way.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah.  Yeah.  I think that's what they were trying to do, to by--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Denouncing ‘<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamofascism">Islamofascism</ref>’...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah.  I think that there's a little bit of that.  I don't know if it's quite as transparent as it was with the Cold War, the Dark Empire model, but it's still there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think it's a little bit trying to fit a square peg through a round hole, like the old paradigm of the Soviet Union as the evil empire, and now the evil empire is this very disparate range of peoples from Indonesia to Iran and trying to make them into a ‘Soviet Union?’</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, it's a tough sell.  But they're doing it, they're all over it over there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's worked.  It's sold.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, they're doing it.  I can't even believe how much money they've spent over there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They are going to be spending a lot more; it'll be a trillion dollar war.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, and that's the other thing: this whole idea that we're in this capitalist country.  We're not really in a capitalist country; we're in something else.  Because if it were pure capitalism, then these decisions would be terrible decisions.  That's why <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron%20Paul">Ron Paul</ref> is so interesting.  Because he's up there just with steam coming out of his ears, saying, "We're spending too much money!  This is crazy!"  And it is.  It's not fiscally responsible.  We're bolstering these <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oil%20companies">oil companies</ref>, who peddle a vestigial energy source, when we have all kinds of other options.  We know it's not where we should be.  But we're there because that's where the economy is; that's what these large corporations are.  But that's not capitalism.  That's some kind of weird version of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corporate%20welfare">corporate socialism</ref>--our whole government is now buoying antiquated technologies.</p>
</text>
