<text id="autogum_interview_doc221" title="part2_Wikinews interviews former New Mexico governor Gary Johnson, presidential nominee of the Libertarian Party" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-11-05" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_New_Mexico_governor_Gary_Johnson%2C_presidential_nominee_of_the_Libertarian_Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Let's say it's like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Adolf_Hitler">Hitler</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref>, would intervention be necessary then?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Johnson</hi>: Well yeah. The notion of...Well first of all, let me borrow from a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Supreme_Court">Supreme Court</ref> Justice that was asked his definition of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pornography">pornography</ref>. [He said] You know what, I can't give you a definition of pornography but I'd like to think that when I see it I recognize it. And so when you talk about humanitarian, when you talk about atrocities, when you talk about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/genocide">genocide</ref>, when you talk about the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Holocaust">Holocaust</ref>, I don't think any of us want to stand by and watch something like that happen. How do you define that? Well as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/commander-in-chief">commander-in-chief</ref>, I'd like to think I'd be the first one that would recognize it if it actually was occurring. And of course, as the leader of the United States, I would have to be articulate in that and make my case for intervention. If we were to intervene, first and foremost would be Congress vetting that and actually approving that, but look, I just think that we militarily intervene as a result of our military intervention, but I think we have hundreds of millions of enemies to this country that look for our military intervention that otherwise would not exist. We kill tens of thousands of innocent civilians in the countries where we militarily intervene. Our men and service women end up dying. Our men and service women come back with their limbs blown off.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You were the governor of a border state. As president, what would you do to prevent the violence in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref> from spilling over into the United States?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Johnson</hi>: That violence is a prohibition phenomenon. If you legalize <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Marijuana">marijuana</ref>, arguably 75 percent of that border violence with Mexico goes away. These are disputes that are being played out with guns rather than the courts. Forty thousand deaths south of the border over the last four years. These are disputes that are being played out with guns rather than the courts.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">But as president, would you increase border security or would you keep it the same?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Johnson</hi>: No. I would not build a fence. I think there would be less of a need for border security if we had a moving line for immigrants that would want to come into this country and work to get a work visa. So my pledge is I'm going to create a moving line for immigrants that want to come into this country and work to get a work visa. That would entail a background check and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social%20Security">Social Security</ref> card so that applicable taxes would get paid. I am espousing eliminating income tax, corporate tax, abolishing the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IRS">IRS</ref> and replacing it all with one federal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/consumption%20tax">consumption tax</ref>: the fair tax. If we adopt the fair tax, taxes will not be an issue. Whether you're illegal, legal, a visitor to the U.S., or a U.S. citizen, nobody is going to avoid paying one federal consumption tax.</p>
</text>
