<text id="autogum_interview_doc975" title="part0_Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian presidential candidate Wayne Allyn Root" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-03" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Libertarian_presidential_candidate_Wayne_Allyn_Root" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian presidential candidate Wayne Allyn Root</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 6, 2008</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> held an exclusive interview with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wayne%20Allyn%20Root">Wayne Allyn Root</ref>, one of the candidates for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libertarian%20Party%20(United%20States)">Libertarian Party</ref> nomination for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20presidential%20election,%202008">2008 U.S. presidential election</ref>.</p>
<p>Root is the founder and chairman of Winning Edge International Inc., a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/handicapping">sports handicapping</ref> company based in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Las%20Vegas">Las Vegas</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nevada">Nevada</ref>. In addition, he is an author and a television producer, as well as an on-screen personality both as host and guest on several talk shows.</p>
<p>Root, a long-time <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20Party%20(United%20States)">Republican</ref>, declared his candidacy for the Libertarian Party on May 4, 2007.</p>
<p>He says he is concerned about the qualities of many who run for president, and fears that they do not know the needs of American citizens. He also says that they cater to big businesses instead of small ones.</p>
<p>He has goals of limiting the federal government and believes that the US went into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref> for wrong reasons. A strong supporter of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War%20on%20Terror">War on Terror</ref>, he feels that it was mishandled. He has conservative values and came from a blue collar family in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York">New York</ref>. He graduated from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbia%20University">Columbia University</ref> with fellow presidential hopeful <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barack%20Obama">Barack Obama</ref> in 1983.</p>
<p>Root believes that America is in trouble and hopes to change that if elected.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">Why do you want to run for president? How would you help your fellow Americans if elected?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mr. Root:</hi> I decided to run for President of the United States because the same people keep running (and being elected) who have screwed everything up in the first place! Every recent President or Presidential candidate falls into one of these same categories: lifelong government bureaucrat or politician (people who have never started a business, funded a business, created jobs, paid health insurance for employees, paid millions in taxes, fought through government regulations, or added millions of dollars to the American economy)她r lawyer (same lack of qualifications在ut worse- they make their living by suing the people and companies that create jobs)她r big businessman (out of touch millionaires or billionaires like George W. Bush, Mitt Romney, Ross Perot)她r spoiled brats who have never experienced pain, failure or adversity like the rest of us. I break that mold. I'm a small businessman (I built a company with 35 employees) and self-made son of a butcher. The entire U.S. economy is fueled by small business. Small businesses now create the majority of jobs in the USA. Small business creates the jobs, pays the taxes, pays the health insurance, makes the U.S. economy go and grow.</p>
<p>Politicians are always far behind the curve. They fawn over big business, big unions, huge corporations, like GE, Microsoft, Exxon or Halliburton. They ignore a small businessman like me with 35 employees. I can't afford lobbyists or huge campaign contributions. So we're left out of the national political dialogue. But guess what? Put all of America's small businessmen together and we're far more important than GE or Microsoft or Exxon or Halliburton. America is a nation of small business owners (and the tens of millions of people that we employ). Small business owners are the heroes of the American economy- we are the risk takers and daring innovators and business leaders. We risk our own money on our own ideas, putting everything we own on the line. We are the CEO's and Generals of our own small worlds- we have no Board of Directors, Ivy League lawyers, layers of big shot executives, or highly-paid lobbyists and consultants to assist us. We make decisions all by ourselves on pure gut instinct- and either hit a homerun or strikeout. We're the last of the rugged individualists. We are like the Wright Brothers or Lewis &amp; Clark. Small businessmen are the courageous explorers who tamed the Wild West on sheer guts, instincts and chutzpah. We are what America is all about.</p>
</text>
