<text id="autogum_interview_doc616" title="part4_Wikinews interviews Joe Schriner, Independent U.S. presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-04-16" dateModified="2019-08-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Joe_Schriner%2C_Independent_U.S._presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If you had complete power at this moment, what would you do? How would you change America?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> If this means complete power, as opposed to having to deal with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/checks%20and%20balances">checks and balances</ref> built into our federal government, this is some of what I'd do:  I'd end abortion and all the precipitating factors leading to it (poverty, dysfunctional family dynamics, relaxed sexual mores, alcohol and drug addiction...).  I'd mobilize a set of dramatic initiatives to, not just curb <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/global%20warming">global warming</ref>, but to actually start to reverse it.  I would unilaterally disarm our nuclear weapons.  I'd stop the production of nuclear energy.  (Anybody hear of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chernobyl">Chernobyl</ref>?)  I would grant amnesty and family reunification to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illegal%20Immigration%20in%20the%20United%20States">illegal immigrants</ref>.    (During a talk at an immigration rally in Arizona several years ago, I said we walked through the slums of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ciudad_Juárez">Juarez</ref>, where violence is off the charts and many of the children are extremely hungry.  If I was their parent, I'd do everything I could to get these children out of harms way and get them something to eat – even if it meant risking crossing the border illegally.) I would end the death penalty.  Also in Arizona, I read a newspaper story about a death penalty protester who posed:  “Why do we kill people who kill people to show that killing people is wrong?”  Good question.  I would increase, exponentially, American foreign aid (it is currently only 4% of the budget) to try to help stem world hunger much more – 24,000 people starve to death every day in the world – and to help realize <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Habitat%20for%20Humanity">Habitat for Humanity</ref>'s goal of providing adequate housing, (“…for every person in the world.”)  I would bring peace to urban war zones around the country.    (In part of this effort, our family moved into a dangerous part of Cleveland, Ohio, to be part of the solution.)  I would end <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/homelessness">homelessness</ref>.  (We take homeless people into our home.  And we will be doing the same in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West%20Wing">West Wing</ref>.  I mean the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lincoln%20Bedroom">Lincoln bedroom</ref> is free, as an example.)  I would tremendously jack down and simplify the economy, shifting America back to much more of a local production for local consumption orientation, like it was in the “old days.”  I would mobilize efforts for a tremendous come back of the small family farm and the practice of growing organically.  This was once the backbone of our country, I told the newspaper Country Today in Wisconsin.  And it should be again.   I would get people to tighten their belts and pay off the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Debt">National Debt</ref> so our children don't inherit it.  During a talk at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Notre%20Dame">University of Notre Dame</ref> recently, I said I would redirect the technical smarts at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref> toward coming up with better water filtration systems, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/solar%20panel">solar panels</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/wind%20turbine">wind turbines</ref>..., as opposed to working on things like going to space destinations where we: can't breathe the air, there's no gravity and there's no food! “That might be, oh, a hint God doesn't want us there,” I said.  I would give some of the land back to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Native%20Americans">Native Americans</ref> so it's equitable, like it should have been from the beginning.   And I would give the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African%20Americans">African Americans</ref> tangible <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reparations%20for%20slavery">reparations for past atrocities</ref> and the ongoing trans-generational problems <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/slavery">slavery</ref> caused.  And, I would ensure – as impossible as this seems – that the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cleveland%20Browns">Cleveland Browns</ref> had a winning season, soon...  For a look at how I would actually try to make a lot of this happen, the Cleveland Browns notwithstanding, go to my rather extensive position papers at </p>
</text>
