<text id="autogum_interview_doc1077" title="part2_Canada's Toronto—Danforth (Ward 30) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-torontodanforth" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-11-04" dateModified="2013-05-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Toronto%E2%80%94Danforth_%28Ward_30%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The cancellation of a fixed link to the Toronto Island Airport was a positive step toward preventing a more active airport and a major air and noise polluter on the waterfront and in the downtown. Ward 30 and all residents of Toronto will benefit from not having this airport.</p>
<p>The most detestable decision since the 2003 election was the bylaw passed at the insistence of Mayor Miller to prohibit homeless from sleeping or congregating in Nathan Phillips Square. Poverty and homelessness will not be eradicated by making them invisible to the law makers at City Hall.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> If you were elected as a "rookie" councillor, what would you bring to the table beyond the incumbent?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am a resident of Ward 30 and have an intimate knowledge and self-interest in making it a better place.</p>
<p>I am not affiliated with any political party, and this would provide me the ability to stand up for my ward each time there is a vote on any given issue. Many councilors are aligned with a political party, and will vote to support motions that their party supports, even when it is not in the best interest of the ward they represent.</p>
<p>I bring a unique set of skills and experience to this role. I am enthusiastic, committed and have a strong desire to make our City a better place.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you?  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Toronto is diverse, vibrant and full of energy. It represents hope, opportunity and excellence. It has the potential to be even greater, to be a leader in Canada and the world. There are so many challenges that need to be addressed that we must take the opportunity to do something about it. We have the knowledge, technology and resources to achieve so much. I believe in Toronto and believe we can play an even stronger leadership role.</p>
<head id="Daniel_Nicastro">Daniel Nicastro</head>
<p>62-year-old <hi rend="bold">Daniel Nicastro</hi> is a restoration architect, writer, artist, and translator.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi></p>
<p>1) Revitalising Commerce on the Danforth Jones going East ; Inventory of housing stock for state of maintenance, for illegal buildings and use, for rentals, for absent landlords, for compliance to density per bedroom, for historically significant properties and/or districts, identifying and developing areas that can generate local employment</p>
<p>2) Having the grassroots participate in the governance of the city through a system of neighbourhood townhalls and participation in the future of the Portlands asking for transparency and participation in the decision making and spending process.</p>
<p>3) Improving TTC service, including a surface bus service Broadview to Main Street, Subway stops are too far apart for the elderly and non motorised handicapped, general rationalisation of parking and parking enforcement.</p>
</text>
