<text id="autogum_interview_doc123" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Dr. Michael Mazilu on creating world&amp;apos;s fastest spinning manmade object" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-09-09" dateModified="2015-01-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Dr._Michael_Mazilu_on_creating_world%27s_fastest_spinning_manmade_object" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How challenging is research of this sort? What kind of difficulties are encountered?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM</hi>: One of the challenges in this experiment is that it brings together many different parts of physics such as vacuum science, optical micro-manipulation, thermodynamics and potentially quantum mechanics. The main difficulty experimentally and theoretically is to combine all these fields simultaneously and make them work together to create a "clean" system that can test ‘friction’ or other theories.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Previous research on the boundary between conventional and quantum physics has used atoms and individual molecules. Why was a sphere in excess of a million atoms appropriate for this experiment? Would that not move further away, rather than closer to, the boundary between the two?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM</hi>: Quantum physics should not just be the remit of the world of atoms or molecules but should apply at all scales in some way. One of the main drives in present quantum technology is to create what is called mesoscopic or macroscopic quantum states, that is quantum states that can be see in a microscope. It is in the hope to achieve this that we chose to work with the micrometer sized vaterite crystals. The other reason for the size of the sphere is that we experimentally found that smaller spheres are presently more difficult to levitate.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How likely is this result to be an anomaly? Might a similar ball break up more quickly, or be unable to spin as fast?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM</hi>: With respect to the sphere break-up, these are interesting questions. One can expect that, depending on the mechanical failure property of the sphere, it would breakup sooner or later. Optically, we can make the sphere rotate at any speeds smaller than the maximum speed. So it would be very interesting to fabricate a series of spheres that have same optical properties but different mechanical failure points.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Where would you like to see the research go next? More spheres?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM</hi>: Indeed, two or more spheres would bring an additional degree of freedom to the experiments that would allow the study of the rotation rate as a function of the distance between them. Some theoretical predictions suggest that quantum friction effects might be enhanced in this case.</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of the buildings housing the maths (near building) and physics and astronomy (far building) schools within the university. Image: Jim Bain.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  If confirmed, what applications might quantum friction have?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM</hi>: It is relatively easy to dream up applications for an effect that has not been observed yet! In general, friction dissipates energy and is seen as a detrimental effect. However, there are applications that use friction in a useful way. Indeed, velocity dependent friction could also be used to slow down microscopic objects to the point where these objects would reach what is called the quantum ground state for their centre of mass. Creating these states on demand would bring quantum technology a step closer and might lead us to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/quantum%20coupling">"couple" quantum mechanically</ref> [macroscopic] objects — a phenomenon more accurately termed entanglement.</p>
</text>
