<text id="autogum_interview_doc1048" title="part0_Past Eurovision contestants give advice to this year's performers, speculate on who will win" shortTile="partpast-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-05-06" dateModified="2015-09-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Past_Eurovision_contestants_give_advice_to_this_year%27s_performers%2C_speculate_on_who_will_win" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Past Eurovision contestants give advice to this year's performers, speculate on who will win</head><figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, May 10, 2009</hi></p>
<p>It happens once a year. Nearly all of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Europe">Europe</ref>'s eyes are on 25 musical acts on finale night. Whether you love it or you hate it, it has your attention. Hundreds of millions are watching them. Whether viewers are waiting for the performance of a lifetime or a hilarious slip-up, for those three minutes their attention is owned by each respective singer.</p>
<p>That's the feeling that the entrants in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow">Moscow</ref> will know on Saturday, and it's also the same feeling the eight singers who were interviewed by <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> have experienced. Last week, eight singers from eight different countries took time out of their various schedules to discuss their favorite moments from competing, their own personal anecdotes, advice they give to the performers this year in Moscow, who they think will win, and most importantly to them, what they're doing now and what they're offering to their audience.</p>
<p>This is the sixth and final interview set the English <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> will publish in the run-up to the semi-final and final rounds of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest">Eurovision Song Contest</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Mike_Halterman">Mike Halterman</ref> conducted all interviews, and will conduct additional interviews after the Contest. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%202009">final round</ref> airs May 16 at 9 p.m. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central%20European%20Summer%20Time">CET</ref>; check with your national broadcaster's website for possible delays. Where available, the Contest's final round will also be broadcast on national radio.</p>
<head id="Jessica_Garlick">Jessica Garlick </head>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jessica%20Garlick">Jessica Garlick</ref>, originally from Kidwelly in Wales, became famous in 2001 for her participation in the singing competition</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pop%20Idol">Pop Idol</ref>, <hi rend="italic">where she finished in ninth place. Four months later, she won A Song for Europe, the British national selection for the Eurovision Song Contest, and went on to represent the United Kingdom two months later at the Eurovision <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%202002">2002</ref> final in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tallinn">Tallinn</ref>, with the song "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Come%20Back%20(Jessica%20Garlick%20song)">Come Back</ref>." She placed third, which turned out to be the best result for the United Kingdom for the decade. Now 27, married and a mother, Jessica Garlick is returning to music with a new set of priorities.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What projects are you working on? What can your fan base expect to see from you this year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Garlick</hi>: Right now I'm busy promoting my new single "Hard Not to Fall" which is due to be released this month...it's available to download from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/iTunes">iTunes</ref> from 9th May, with the official release being 25th May. I'm also currently co-writing my album, which will be released later on this year. It really does feel great to be back in the music industry.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What were some of the best memories you have from going to Eurovision? What advice would you give to the singers going to Eurovision for the first time this year?</hi></p>
</text>
