<text id="autogum_interview_doc1178" title="part2_Canada's Etobicoke—Lakeshore (Ward 5) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-etobicokelakeshore" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-10-19" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Etobicoke%E2%80%94Lakeshore_%28Ward_5%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Making the City Government Work Better</hi>: As Chair of the City's e-City Committee I have spearheaded the use of technology to make government more accessible and efficient, and to boost the productivity of City staff.   The City is increasing the number of online services and transaction available to the public to increase convenience and reduce costs.  In late 2007 the City will launch its 3-1-1 Telephone system which allow residents to call City Hall 24 hours a day/7 days a week and always be greeted by a live Citizen Service Representative who will be able to take a complaint, generate a work order, or answer a question.  Again the goal is to increase convenience to residents, reduce costs, increase efficiency, and boost productivity.</p>
<p>I have opposed the Councillor pay raise and if re-elected will move to reopen the matter and have the raise rescinded.  I have consistently voted to reduce Councillor's office budgets.</p>
<p>As a member of the Budget Committee I fought to reduce costs, control spending, cut staff, and contract out services to the private sector wherever possible.  I supported the successful extension of the contract to pick up garbage in Etobicoke by a private contractor.</p>
<p>We need a comprehensive plan to deal with our waste decades in to the future.  We must expand and improve recycling and composting programmes, particularly to multi-residential buildings.  We must also develop a long-term solution to dealing with our waste.  I believe energy from waste must be a significant component of that solution.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Providing a Vision and Planning for the Future</hi>: Whether looking at the Waterfront, the Gardiner Expressway, Nathan Phillips Square, or in Ward 5 the City-owned lands in the Etobicoke City Centre planning for the future is central to what local government must do.</p>
<p>Ensuring that the Portlands are developed as a cohesive community with great public spaces, parks, and access to the water is aone priority.</p>
<p>Implementing Design Review Panels to better control the quality of the architecture in our city is one of the exciting new initiatives that will begin in 2007.</p>
<p>In Ward 5 the comprehensive review of all city lands, public transit, infrastructure, new parkland and community services in the Etobicoke City Centre area is the greatest challenge and opportunity the community faces.  The future of the Six Points interchange, Westwood Theatre lands, Islington Subway station, and Etobicoke Civiv Centre has the potential weave neighbourhoods together into an even stronger community with better public spaces and much need facilities.  The fision for this community includes office employment, better retail, enhances streetscapes, and a major community recreation facility.</p>
<p>Similarly work on The Queensway will improve the street, create new and enhanced parks and public facilities and bring new mid-scale residential developments.</p>
<p>New zoning by-laws for Dundas Street between Royal York Road and the Humber River will ensure new development will be in greater harmony with the existing stable residential neighbourhood.</p>
</text>
