<text id="autogum_interview_doc1372" title="part4_One year on: IFALPA's representative to ICAO, pilot and lawyer on ongoing prosecution of Garuda Indonesia Flight 200 pilot" shortTile="partone-year--ifalpas" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-03-08" dateModified="2014-04-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/One_year_on%3A_IFALPA%27s_representative_to_ICAO%2C_pilot_and_lawyer_on_ongoing_prosecution_of_Garuda_Indonesia_Flight_200_pilot" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> It depends on the rules of evidence in Indonesia. It should not be possible to call the active investigators as expert witnesses. To do so would subvert both the investigation and the court proceeding.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Based on your own experience, what structure is Mr Komar's defence likely to take?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> Again, the Captain has a legal team.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  If convicted, what kind of appeals process does Indonesian law supply to Mr Komar?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> I have no idea.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  There are a number of other individuals and organisations that could potential also face legal action for their roles in the disaster, but only Mr Komar has. Why do you believe this is?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> I once again will not speculate in this area.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Despite not having faced trial, Garuda Indonesia have recently forced Mr Komar to resign. Do you feel this move was justified?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> It was expected and is quite common in many parts of the world, with or without establishment of culpability. It is a matter of face for the corporation.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you feel Mr Komar's case sets a precedent for the industry?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> Unfortunately, it is simply the most recent example of  this attitude that somehow prosecution will improve safety. It will not.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Have there been any previous cases in other nations that could in any way be compared to this? How were they resolved?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> Each accident has a different fact situation, so it is difficult if not impossible to use one as precedent. The most famous is probably the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Zealand">New Zealand</ref> case at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palmerston%20North%20International%20Airport">Palmerston North (International Airport)</ref> where the captain was prosecuted following a crash. Even though he seemed guilty under the applicable statute, the jury refused to convict.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you believe Australia was right to push for prosecution so soon after the report was published?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> No. If this accident was in Australia, their own laws would preclude much of what has happened. In fact, the Australian position could be viewed as a cynical political move.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Had the co-pilot been adequately trained he would have taken over the operation of the plane and averted an accident. Does this have any bearing on Mr Komar's case?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> To answer this one must compare cultures and the ability to train cultural bias out of the reactions of a crewmember. Once again, the investigation should have addressed this issue but did not.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Why do you feel the final report fails to address the issues IFALPA are calling for it to consider?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> I would restate my answers above to the questions concerning the crew actions. The investigation has not addressed them in a way that will be useful as a guide for the industry to act to prevent a reoccurrence.</item></list>
</text>
