<text id="autogum_interview_doc286" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Steve Kissing, independent candidate for US President" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-16" dateModified="2014-04-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Steve_Kissing%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Steve Kissing, independent candidate for US President</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 16, 2008</hi></p>
<p>While nearly all coverage of the 2008 Presidential election has focused on the Democratic and Republican candidates, there are small political parties offering candidates, and those who choose to run without a party behind them, independents.</p>
<p>Wikinews is interviewing some of these citizens who are looking to become the 43rd person elected to serve their nation from 1600 Pennsylvania Avenue NW.</p>
<p>Our second interview is with Cincinnati, Ohio's <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.kissing4prez.org/">Steve Kissing</ref></hi>, a divorced father of two who is a creative director at an advertising agency.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why do you want to be President?</hi></p>
<p>In a very real sense, I <hi rend="italic">don’t</hi> want to be President of the United States. It's not something I've been planning or hoping to do. (Though I have long-fantasized about "sleeping with" my wife in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lincoln%20Bedroom">Lincoln Bedroom</ref>.) But I know, at the very core of my being, that true and dramatic change is required and that someone, a non-politician, must step forward. Rather than stand on the sidelines and wonder why no one was volunteering to lead the revolution, I thought it only fair and responsible to toss my own hat into the ring.</p>
<p>I want to help bring about a true sea change, one that will lead to a better America, and a better world. Specifically, I want to help lay to rest, permanently, the political class and establishment. This blood-sucking behemoth, which many of us have resigned ourselves to living with, is more concerned about power than prosperity, more interested in power than peace, more vested in power than eradicating poverty.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Have you ever run for political office before?</hi></p>
<p>I have never run for a political office, outside of student government. I consider this a strength, not a weakness.</p>
<p>We keep expecting politicians to bring about real change as it relates to health care, education, the environment and other key concerns of all Americans. But real change rarely comes from our politicians who often seem more eager to appear on the Sunday morning talk shows than to get real, bi-partisan work accomplished. This is also why one of my slogans is: "Elect a person, not a politician."</p>
<p>Over the years (I am 44 years old), I have voted for Republicans, Democrats and Independents. I have done a small bit of campaigning for candidates running for local offices at the city or county level. But it has been years since I have done so.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What is your current job? What skills or ideas do you bring from this position, or previous positions, that will benefit the Oval Office?</hi></p>
<p>I have spent nearly 25 years in the advertising industry, and I am currently a creative director at an ad agency called <ref target="http://www.thinkbarefoot.com">Barefoot</ref>, located in Cincinnati.</p>
</text>
