<text id="autogum_interview_doc722" title="part7_Author of My Billion Year Contract reflects on life in elite Scientology group" shortTile="partauthor-billion" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-13" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_of_My_Billion_Year_Contract_reflects_on_life_in_elite_Scientology_group" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Several popular culture references are made in the book to illustrate your experiences. You talk about the film <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poltergeist%20(film)">Poltergeist</ref></hi> and how your husband compared it to his experience of pulling you out of your psychosis (p. 219). You reference the film <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Omen">The Omen</ref></hi> as a way to describe <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L.%20Ron%20Hubbard">L. Ron Hubbard</ref>'s view in a purported version of the Scientology level "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OT%20VIII">OT 8</ref>" that you read on the Internet, writing, "[Hubbard] said that he had his next mission lined up that was to come back in a healthy body and join politics - a modern-day Damien from The Omen." (p. 202) Scientology has itself been the subject of depictions in popular culture, for example the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obie%20Award">Obie Award-winning</ref> satirical musical <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A%20Very%20Merry%20Unauthorized%20Children's%20Scientology%20Pageant">A Very Merry Unauthorized Children's Scientology Pageant</ref></hi>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primetime%20Emmy%20Award%20for%20Outstanding%20Animated%20Program%20(for%20Programming%20Less%20Than%20One%20Hour)">Emmy-nominated</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parody">parody</ref> episode "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trapped%20in%20the%20Closet%20(South%20Park)">Trapped in the Closet</ref>" by the comedy program <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South%20Park">South Park</ref></hi>. Have you seen any parodies or depictions of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientology%20in%20popular%20culture">Scientology in popular culture</ref>? What are your thoughts about them?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: These were all great shows.  I went to the "Unauthorized Children’s Scientology Pageant", with my youngest son who had been through the roughest parts of my mental collapse with me, and we just laughed and laughed.  It was so great.  If it’s in your town, don’t miss it.</p>
<p>The <hi rend="italic">South Park</hi> episode was great.  I kept it on my replay for months so I could watch again with friends (ex Scn or never Scn) who had missed it.</p>
<hi rend="bold">I wish the public, especially America, would not be so star struck that they ignore the Human Rights Abuses happening within our own borders...</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Nancy Many</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Do you have any thoughts or advice for others either curious to find out more information about Scientology or those seeking to leave the organization?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: If you are thinking about joining, stick to the internet for a while, a long while – they have their own websites, so you can see both sides.</p>
<p>For those seeking to leave the Sea Organization, just get up and walk out.  If they touch you you have a million dollar lawsuit – but how to get the information inside to you????</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Are there any other points regarding your experiences that you would like to elaborate on or explain?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: I wish the public, especially America, would not be so star struck that they ignore the Human Rights Abuses happening within our own borders, or just find it too had to believe.</p>
<p>A friend of mine told a famous actress my story, and she couldn’t believe it, come to find out another friend of theirs had reported the same thing and they had simply thought she was delusional.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Nancy Many, thank you for taking the time to participate in this interview with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>.</hi></p>
</text>
