<text id="autogum_interview_doc726" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Christopher Beyette, prince of the Principality of Vikesland" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-07-10" dateModified="2009-02-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Christopher_Beyette%2C_prince_of_the_Principality_of_Vikesland" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Tell us about the Vikeslandic culture.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Prince Christopher:</hi> Vikeslandic culture is an ever evolving thing. We speak English and our lifestyles are a quintessential westerners life, but as more and more people become citizens they bring a variety of new things with them. We heavily condone the arts in all forms and the majority of us love some part of the outdoors, be it camping, hiking or boating.</p>
<p>I am currently going to have an official Vikeslandic food recipe compilation made and posted on our website. I hope to have authentic Vikeslandic food up there for everyone to try. Being socially conscious and having a good time in this life is top of the list.   </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Does Vikesland belong to any international organizations?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Prince Christopher:</hi> Yes, we currently belong to an intermicronational organization called The League of Small Nations. It is an organization designed to advance the rights of small sovereign states and provide a platform from which their voices can be heard among the larger more powerful states.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Can one become a citizen of Vikesland? Is honorary citizenship granted?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Prince Christopher:</hi> Yes, you can become a citizen of Vikesland by applying on our citizenship page. We have two types of citizenry, cyber citizens (honorary) or full citizens.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Can people visit Vikesland?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Prince Christopher:</hi> Yes they can but it is only by appointment. Anyone showing up unannounced will be most likely turned away. Requests can be made directly to myself via e-mail only.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are your duties as prince? What is it like to run your own country?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Prince Christopher:</hi> It is stressful being the head of state, it is a lot of fun but equally testing as well. I oversee most government workings and provide leadership and direction for those under me. I am also the face of Vikesland so I take care of all media related issues and some foreign diplomacy as well as keep the citizens informed via or website with video or write-ups. I also head various projects within our security force and our Department of Aeronautics and Space. It can be tough but it is equally rewarding.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">There are thousands reading this right now. Is there anything else you would like us to know about your nation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Prince Christopher:</hi> I would just like to reiterate that we are not secessionists or unpatriotic rebels of any-kind. I personally am a very patriotic Canadian but I am also equally a patriotic Vikeslandic. This nation project is a new frontier and immensely fun on top of it. I consider myself a dual citizen of both Canada and Vikesland and I am law abiding. It is with hope that one day we can achieve our own autonomy peacefully with our distinct culture and small land-base. Semi-autonomy is even an acceptable outcome in the end. The first and foremost of all of this is that everyone involved enjoy what they are doing. I am not willing, nor am I asking anyone to ruin their health or professional life by relentlessly pursuing an impossible goal. I believe that if it is not fun or beneficial, why do it. Yes taking the sour with the sweet is a fact of life, but we should have at least 80 percent sweet when building up Vikesland.</p>
</text>
