<text id="autogum_interview_doc1412" title="part6_John Vanderslice plays New York City: Wikinews interview" shortTile="partjohn-vanderslice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-27" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Vanderslice_plays_New_York_City%3A_Wikinews_interview" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Depression breeds apathy, and your music seems geared toward anger, trying to wake people from their apathy.  Your music is not maudlin and sad, but seems to be an attempt to awaken a spirit, with a self-reflective bent.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  That's the trick.  I would say that honestly, when Katrina happened, I thought, "okay, this is a trick to make people so crazy and so angry that they can't even think.  If you were in a community and basically were in a more or less quasi-police state surveillance society with no accountability, where we are pouring untold billions into our infrastructure to protect outside threats against via terrorism, or whatever, and then a natural disaster happens and there is <hi rend="italic">no</hi> response.  There is an <hi rend="italic">empty</hi> response.  There is all these ships off the shore that were just out there, just waiting, and nobody came.  Michael Brown.  It is one of the most insane things I have ever seen in my life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is there a feeling in San Francisco that if an earthquake struck, you all would be on your own?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>   Yes, of course.  Part of what happened in New Orleans is that it was a Catholic city, it was a city of sin, it was a black city.  And San Francisco?  Bush wouldn't even visit California in the beginning because his numbers were so low.  Before Schwarzenegger definitely.  I'm totally afraid of the earthquake, and I think everyone is out there.  America is in the worst of both worlds: a laissez-fare economy and then the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grover%20Norquist">Grover Norquist</ref> anti-tax, starve the government until it turns into nothing more than a Argentinian-style government where there are these super rich invisible elite who own everything and there's no distribution of wealth and nothing that resembles the New Deal, twentieth century embracing of human rights and equality, war against poverty, all of these things.  They are trying to kill all that stuff.  So, in some ways, it is the worst of both worlds because they are pushing us towards that, and on the same side they have put in a Supreme Court that is so right wing and so fanatically opposed to upholding civil rights, whether it be for foreign fighters...I mean, we are going to see movement with abortion, Miranda rights and stuff that is going to come up on the Court. We've tortured so many people who have had no intelligence value that you have to start to look at torture as a symbolic and almost ritualized behavior; you have this...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Organ failure.  That's our baseline...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  Yeah, and you have to wonder about how we were torturing people to do nothing more than to send the darkest signal to the world to say, Listen, we are so fucking weird that if you cross the line with us, we are going to be at war with your religion, with your government, and we are going to destroy you.</p>
</text>
