<text id="autogum_interview_doc941" title="part1_CanadaVOTES: Liberal incumbent Susan Kadis running in Thornhill" shortTile="partcanadavotes-liberal" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-09-26" dateModified="2019-07-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_Liberal_incumbent_Susan_Kadis_running_in_Thornhill" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">What would be the biggest highlights of the roughly two years since the last election?</hi></p>
<p>I had the opportunity to travel across the country to consult Canadians about security needs for at-risk communities, and to develop a policy to strengthen the safety of Canadians. This inclusive and comprehensive Liberal plan, which is part of our commitment in our platform, would not only benefit residents of Thornhill but all Canadians.  I introduced a private members bill to establish a national holocaust monument in the nations capital to honour the victims and survivors, and to teach next generations about the consequences of state sanctioned genocide.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">The biggest disappointment?</hi></p>
<p>As someone who has served on the Industry Committee and an Ontario MP, I was very disappointed to see Minister Harper and Flaherty attack Ontario and suggest that Ontario is the last place to invest. Thornhill residents who are worried about losing their jobs need a new Liberal government that is prepared to be a real partner especially in these challenging times. I will always stand up for Thornhill and Ontario.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">As you campaign around your riding, it's likely that some issues are mentioned more often by voters, than other issues. What would you say are the three hottest topics this election, in your riding?</hi></p>
<p><list type="ordered"><item>Economy</item>
<item>Environment</item>
<item>Health care</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What would you and your party do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>"Richer, Fairer, Greener," the Liberal Party of Canada's fully-costed, fiscally-responsible platform, lays out a progressive, inclusive vision to make Canada a stronger country for the next generation. Fiscal discipline is part of the Liberal DNA. We were the party that turned a huge deficit into eight years of surpluses, and we will continue to put fiscal responsibility first. A Liberal government will never put Canada into deficit.</p>
<p>We are committed to balanced budgets, which is why all the commitments in this platform are set within a prudent fiscal framework that includes a contingency reserve of $3 billion a year to be applied to the debt if it's not used  a prudent measure irresponsibly abandoned by the Conservative government.</p>
<p>The cornerstone of the Liberal platform is the Green Shift plan. This innovative and forward-thinking plan will cut income taxes, put a price on pollution, fight poverty and position Canada to be a leader in the 21st-century global economy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Richer, Fairer, Greener</hi> Includes: An Action Plan for the 21st Century A Greener Canada to fight the Climate Change Crisis, Clean Air, Safeguarding our Water, Protecting our Health from Toxic Substances, Protecting Our Natural Heritage, Empowering Canadians</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A Fairer Canada</hi> Includes: The 30-50 Plan, Investing in Our Children, Health Care, Womens Equality, Immigration: Welcoming New Canadians, EI Changes, A New Relationship with Canada's First Nations, Inuit and Metis, Minority Language Rights, A Safer Canada, Respectful Federalism</p>
</text>
