<text id="autogum_interview_doc1360" title="part4_Wikinews interviews Finnish 'Rock 'N' Troll' band Kivimetsän Druidi" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-06-07" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Finnish_%27Rock_%27N%27_Troll%27_band_Kivimets%C3%A4n_Druidi" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<list type="unordered"><item>Who are your influences as an artist?</item></list>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Joni:</hi> As for the many others of my age <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metallica">Metallica</ref> was the kick that I needed to start playing guitar. Since then I’ve adored <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hetfield">Hetfield</ref> and I guess you could say he’s my idol. For my music writing then, I guess the music of the bands like Metallica, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slayer">Slayer</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Megadeth">Megadeth</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iron%20Maiden">Iron Maiden</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ensiferum">Ensiferum</ref>, Moonsorrow, Turisas and Finntroll have huge affect on it.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Antti:</hi> Music of Moonsorrow, Ensiferum and Finntroll. That’s my top 3. But I also listen to, for example, instrumental Celtic music.</item></list></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Is there anything else you'd like to say to any fans reading this now?</item></list>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Joni:</hi> Visit <ref target="http://www.kivimetsandruidi.com/">our website</ref> and <ref target="http://www.myspace.com/kivimetsandruidi">our MySpace</ref>. We hope to see you all at gigs soon and always remember to Rock ’n’ Troll!! Cheers!</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Antti:</hi> When you’ll hear our debut album your ears will drop!! We love ya!!</item></list></p>
<head id="Leeni-Maria_Hovila">Leeni-Maria Hovila</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>You recently came to the band from Exsecratus in March. What was it like, entering a new, established band?</item></list>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Leeni-Maria:</hi> This band works quite smoothly so there were not much practical matters but I was <hi rend="italic">terrified</hi> they might not accept me.</item></list></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>You've also sung for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swallow%20the%20Sun">Swallow the Sun</ref> on the album "<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hope%20(Swallow%20the%20Sun%20album)">Hope</ref></hi>". What was it like working with such a major band?</item></list>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Leeni-Maria:</hi> I was thrilled of the chance, since I already was a fan when they contacted me. Other than that, it was like any other studio session, making up harmonies as we go, cursing Aleksi’s little surprises in the keyboard tracks.</item></list></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Why did you want to join Kivimetsän Druidi‏?</item></list>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Leeni-Maria:</hi> I am easy to arouse.:-D To tell you the truth, since first song ever that I heard was “<hi rend="italic">Blacksmith</hi>” from the Myspace- site, I was slightly put off by the intro. My reaction might have been something along the line “oh dear, not <hi rend="italic">this</hi> shit”. But I was turned around as soon as the first verse. Also the guys impressed me much as devoted and sharp players who know their stuff well.</item></list></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Is it difficult being the only woman in a men's band?</item></list>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Leeni-Maria:</hi> Nope. Being in a band is quite the same heaven and hell be there other women or not - thus have I seen with Exsecratus. It is all up to whether the people involved are mature individuals or not.</item></list></p>
<p>Although sometimes it feels as if some guys were a little shy of me- hope he doesn’t mind me telling this, but our manager of affairs of Europe (didn’t that sound cool!) almost swallowed his tongue when he happened to walk to the backstage in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leipzig">Leipzig</ref> while I was changing - I don’t expect to get privacy and I don’t need it, au contraire, I do need someone with keen fingers to do the lacing (though I wish the guys could make knots that can be opened as well).</p>
</text>
