<text id="autogum_interview_doc1331" title="part2_Wikinews investigates the reconstruction of Pichilemu, Chile after February earthquake" shortTile="partwikinews-investigates" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-10-23" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_investigates_the_reconstruction_of_Pichilemu%2C_Chile_after_February_earthquake" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>A local worker, Ricardo Vivanco, also known as "El Gordo" ("The Fat one"), almost was killed by a tsunami, ignoring warnings by the Police and the Fire Bureau. Vivanco was drunk, and went down to the Las Terrazas beach with his friends. The wave washed him away, and was hit on the Agustín Ross Balcony's wall. His friends recorded a video and uploaded it to <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OO6JHRPw0Xw">YouTube</ref>.</p>
<head id="Damage_in_Punta_de_Lobos_and_villages">Damage in Punta de Lobos and villages</head>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Punta%20de%20Lobos">Punta de Lobos</ref>, Pichilemu's most popular surfing beach, is located at about four kilometers south of the city's centre. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>It was reported by <hi rend="italic">Radio Entre Olas</hi> on February 27, that the tsunami had provoked massive damage in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Punta%20de%20Lobos">Punta de Lobos</ref>, Pichilemu's most popular beach. The owner of <hi rend="italic">Entre Mar</hi>, an hotel and restaurant in that beach, said the tsunami had destroyed all of his buildings there. </p>
<p>The village of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Espinillo,%20Chile">Espinillo</ref> was badly damaged, and approximately 600 people were made homeless by the earthquake, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canal%2013%20(Chile)"><hi rend="italic">Teletrece</hi></ref> reported on March 16. "We are keeping the government informed, we're also organized with some churches [<hi rend="italic">sic, religious organizations</hi>] that are working voluntarily in Espinillo, Los Boldos, Alto Ramírez [...] We thank a lot their work, that is not to give them <hi rend="italic">mediaguas</hi> [temporary tenements], but something definitive, but I also think they need resources to do it," Mayor Córdova said.</p>
<head id="'We_are_here_because_we_fear_about_our_safety':_Residents_scramble_after_second_earthquake">'We are here because we fear about our safety': Residents scramble after second earthquake</head>
<p>On March 11, Chile was hit by a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2010_Pichilemu_earthquake">second earthquake</ref>, that reached a magnitude of 6.9, and that occurred 40 kilometers southwest of Pichilemu. It occurred at 11:39 local time (14:39 UTC), while the new <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President%20of%20Chile">President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sebastián_Piñera">Sebastián Piñera</ref> was sworn in.</p>
<p>A tsunami warning was issued by SHOA, between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coquimbo%20Region">Coquimbo</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los%20Lagos%20Region">Los Lagos</ref> regions. People in Pichilemu fled again to La Cruz Hill. Military authorities assured people in the hill they were going to be safe there, and that it was unlikely a tsunami was going to hit again Chile's coast. The tsunami warning was lifted at 15:50 local time (18:50 UTC).</p>
<p>People stayed in La Cruz Hill for a longer time than after the previous earthquake, and several activities were made there, such as a concert by Chilean-Brazilian singer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe%20Vasconcellos">Joe Vasconcellos</ref>. People were also given food, wood (mostly remains from the destroyed kiosks), and electricity.</p>
<p>"We are here because we fear about our safety. We don't want it [a possible tsunami] to catch us. We have to settle down here and to accommodate," Edith Larraín told to <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>. Mayor Córdova estimated that at least 2,000 people were staying at La Cruz Hill. Militaries and provincial authorities asked them to leave the hill on March 15, but most refused the deal. People eventually left the hill, due to complaints by the Mayor.</p>
</text>
