<text id="autogum_interview_doc1420" title="part5_Interview with U.S. Republican Presidential candidate Tom Tancredo" shortTile="partinterview-us" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-25" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_U.S._Republican_Presidential_candidate_Tom_Tancredo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You recently spoke out against the Black and Hispanic Congressional caucuses, stating, "It is utterly hypocritical for Congress to extol the virtues of a color-blind society while officially sanctioning caucuses that are based solely on race. If we are serious about achieving the goal of a colorblind society, Congress should lead by example and end these divisive, race-based caucuses."  Do you also believe there is no longer a need for the NAACP?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  No, I think it’s fine, because it’s a private organization, and people can belong to whatever private organization they want, and the need will be determined to a great extent by reality.  If in fact people feel committed to an organization that they believe represents their interest, and it’s a voluntary association, that’s fine.  All I’m saying is that for Congress to support these things, that run on money that is appropriated--though they fund them in a convoluted way, but it gets there-- my point was about leading by example.  If people said we don’t think it’s a good idea, maybe that would have an impact on how people feel about things like the NAACP.  I would hope there would be, and I would assume Martin Luther King hoped--that’s his quite about a colorblind society--that there will come a time we don’t need them.  That it’s an anachronistic organization.  I also don’t believe in the creation of districts on race.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You were one of a handful of Republicans who voted for a bill proposed by Maurice Hinchey and Dana Rohrabacher to stop the Department of Justice from raiding medical marijuana patients and caregivers in states where medical marijuana is legal, citing states' rights concerns.  On the other hand, you have suggested state legislators and mayors should be imprisoned for passing laws contrary to federal immigration law, and you support the Federal Marriage Amendment to ban gay marriage nationally.  How do you reconcile these seemingly contradictory positions?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  We are talking about issues that are legitimately based upon the Constitutional roles of the state and federal government.  I believe there is no Constitutional provision that suggests the federal government has a role to play in preventing states, or punishing states, over laws with regards to medical marijuana.  I believe absolutely there is a role for the federal government for punishing states or laws when they contravene federal jurisdiction.  For instance, protecting states against invasion. Immigration is federal policy, and there’s a law actually called “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accessory%20(legal%20term)">Encouragement</ref>”: you can’t encourage people to come in illegally or stay here illegally.  I believe that is constitutionally a federal area.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If you had to support one of the Democratic candidates, which one would it be and why?</hi></p>
</text>
