<text id="autogum_interview_doc1020" title="part1_Wikinews interviews John Taylor Bowles, National Socialist Order of America candidate for US President" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-19" dateModified="2019-08-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_John_Taylor_Bowles%2C_National_Socialist_Order_of_America_candidate_for_US_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What is your current job?</hi></p>
<p>I am a retired federal officer of the United States Department of Agriculture.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What skills or ideas do you bring from this position, or previous positions, that will benefit the Oval Office?</hi></p>
<p>As a former federal officer of the United States Department of Agriculture and United States Air Force, I know the inner-workings of the federal government in all areas and familiar with the enforcement of its laws and regulations. In addition, I was elected as a union representation of one of America's largest unions: United Auto Workers, Local #1400. Being a union representative taught valuable skills regarding labor. Lastly, I have been a White political activist for over 34 years and raised a family and know the problems that the average White family must endure.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Obviously, the next American President and his or her administration will face many diverse issues. But if you were to narrow identify the three most important issues, what would they be? How will you address these issues?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">1.) Illegal immigration.</hi></p>
<p>The federal government must adopt a zero tolerance policy regarding any illegal immigrant and remove them from American soil immediately. Also, the illegal immigrants crossing the southern border is a military problem and the USA military should be patrolling it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">2.) Iraq War.</hi></p>
<p>The federal government has lied to its citizens regarding the Iraq War and needs to pull all troops out of Iraq and help Iraq rebuild its infrastructure. As President, I would pull all military troops out of every foreign country and close every military base outside the USA to save taxpayers money and put them on the USA borders to guard and assist in natural disasters when they occur. The current President needs to be put on trial for constitutional violations and crimes against humanity.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">3.) Health care.</hi></p>
<p>The first step in medical reform and the medical insurance is giving American citizens who are workers and life-long taxpayers first preference in medical care and services. No taxpaying American person who suffers a costly, life-threatening illness in his/her family should face bankruptcy or loss of his home while even one illegal alien gets free medical care.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Campaigning for the American presidency is one of the most expensive exercises in the world. How do you deal with the cost and fundraising?</hi></p>
<p>My campaign is financed by grassroots supporters throughout the USA. I won’t accept any corporation donations or any type of donation not allowed by the Federal Election Commission. My controversial politics draws donations from exposure on the Internet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Do you have a running mate yet? Who are they? What are you/were you looking for in a running mate?</hi></p>
<p>I had a Vice-Presidential candidate when the campaign officially began on December 7, 2006; but, unfortunately he was killed in a mysterious automobile accident 10 hours later. His name was William (Wild Bill) and he served in the USA military and was decorated with over 15 medals. Early in his political life, Mr. Hoff served as Grand Dragon for the Ku Klux Klan in New York and ran for the Senate in New York.</p>
</text>
