<text id="autogum_interview_doc1415" title="part0_Interview with U.S. Republican Presidential candidate Tom Tancredo" shortTile="partinterview-us" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-25" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_U.S._Republican_Presidential_candidate_Tom_Tancredo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Interview with U.S. Republican Presidential candidate Tom Tancredo</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 25, 2007</hi></p>
<figure rend="Tom Tancredo, official Congressional photo.jpg"></figure><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom%20Tancredo">Tom Tancredo</ref> has been a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20House%20of%20Representatives">United States House of Representatives</ref> since 1999, representing the 6th Congressional District of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Colorado">Colorado</ref>. He rose to national prominence for his strong stance against illegal immigration and his announcement that he was a Republican candidate in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008%20Presidential%20election">2008 Presidential election</ref>.  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> recently spoke with the Congressman and posed questions from Wikipedia editors and Wikinews reporters:
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Throughout my life my father, a lifelong Republican and an avid listener of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rush%20Limbaugh">Rush Limbaugh</ref>, told me that all we needed in this country was a Republican Congress, Republican Senate and a Republican White House to get this country on the right track.  Last year he expressed his disappointment to me.  So many Republicans, like my father, feel lied to or let down by the party.  The rationale for the Iraq War, the sex and bribery scandals, the pork barrel projects, and, as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan%20Greenspan">Alan Greenspan</ref> recently pointed out, the fiscal irresponsibility.  People feel there have been many broken promises.  Why should someone vote Republican today?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  The best reason I can give:  we’re not the Democrats.  The best thing we have going for us is the Democrats.  Maybe that’s as far as I can go; I hope that there are candidates out there who will reflect and carry out the values that your father believes in when he votes Republican.  To the extent you can ferret those people out from the others, that’s who he should vote for.  The party was taught a pretty harsh lesson in this last election.  I have noticed in the last several months we have done a better job of defending Republican principles as the minority than we ever did in the majority.  I feel more in tune with the party now than I have throughout the Bush Presidency.  Even before he came in, we were in the majority and we were still spending too much.  Hopefully we can say that we were spanked by the American public and that we learned our lessons.  There are true believers out there who will stick to their guns, and it’s a matter of principle.  What’s the alternative?  Hillary Clinton?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You yourself said you would only serve three terms in Congress, but then broke that promise.  What caused you to reverse yourself?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  What happened was this: having ‘lame duck’ stamped on your forehead in Congress when they know you are not going to be around.  Then the committee assignments become less meaningful.  That was just one of the factors.  Far more significant was my becoming the most visible Congressional member on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Immigration%20reform">immigration issue</ref>.  When I came into Congress I approached <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lamar%20S.%20Smith">Lamar Smith</ref>, who was “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Man">The Man</ref>” on immigration, and said to him, “I’ve come to help you on this issue.” I felt it was one of the most serious we face as a nation.  Lamar said, “It’s all yours!  I’ve had it with 10 years of busting my head against the wall!”  I started doing special orders---that’s when you speak to an empty chamber and whoever is watching <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CSPAN">CSPAN</ref>--and I did that night after night and wondered if it was worth it; was anyone paying attention?  Then I’d go back to my office to pick up my keys and I’d see all the telephone lines illuminated, and the fax machine would be going, and a pile of e-mails would be handed to me the next day.  I realized:  people pay attention.  I started picking it up, speaking around the country, leading the caucus on it.  In time it became apparent there was nobody to hand the baton to; there were supporters, but not one single soul was willing to take it on as their issue.  It was the first year of my second term that I sent a letter to every supporter I had.  I said I had come to this conclusion that at the end of my third term (which is three years away) I don’t know if I will run again or not, but that the decision would not be based upon the term limit pledge, because immigration issue makes me feel I have a responsibility I can not shirk.  I said that if anybody who gave me money based upon my term limits pledge wanted it back, I would do so.  I received maybe three requests.</p>
</text>
