<text id="autogum_interview_doc1280" title="part5_Edmund White on writing, incest, life and Larry Kramer" shortTile="partedmund-white" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-08" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edmund_White_on_writing%2C_incest%2C_life_and_Larry_Kramer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="On_incest_in_his_family">On incest in his family</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In an interview you said that you are known for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Incest">incestuous</ref> feelings that were in your family—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  —what advice would you give to couples pursuing an incestuous relationship?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  You mean like a father and daughter who want to have a love affair?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Or a brother and sister.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  God, move to a more tolerant country, first of all.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think there is a problem with it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I think incest becomes more difficult if it’s intergenerational than if it’s in the same generation.  And it becomes more difficult if it crosses the sex barrier.  For instance, two brothers who have sex with each other when they are growing up, for instance—they’re 14 and 16—it is never a very big deal.  Whereas if a brother and sister have sex and are both teenagers, it is often traumatic, especially for the girl, and it will show up in her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychoanalysis">psychoanalysis</ref> later, and problems with her marriage, with frigidity and so on.  If it’s her father she is sleeping with, it becomes a <hi rend="italic">very</hi> big problem for her psychological adjustment.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is that because there is an intrinsic problem with it, or because of societal reactions to it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I think that it probably comes to the same thing because in every society it’s a problem.  So whether it’s genetic or societal, I don’t know.  But it’s universal.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social%20anthropology">Anthropologists</ref> try to speculate why that would be.  Some people say that it has to do with the divisions of authority and power; for instance, if a daughter is sleeping with her father then her mother has no authority over her because the daughter has in a sense replaced the mother because she’s the ideal partner—she’s younger, prettier, whatever.  It screws up the whole <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sociology%20of%20the%20family">family system</ref>.  It’s a very interesting subject.  But I think I’m right: two brothers, no big deal; two sisters, no big deal.  Brother-sister becomes a problem, or mother-son it becomes a <hi rend="italic">huge</hi> problem.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So you’d advise an incestuous couple not to pursue it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Oh, I don’t give advice! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You had mentioned particular issues about a father may arise in a slave-master relationship.  You were sexually attracted to your father, so do you think you worked through your own issues with him?</hi></p>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where do you think that attraction came from?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I don’t know; I think it’s very hard to explain attraction.  If I’m attracted to you right now, why?  I don’t know why.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But that’s something people could perhaps explain more readily than attraction to one's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Father">father</ref>.</hi></p>
</text>
