<text id="autogum_interview_doc038" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Augustus Sol Invictus, Libertarian Party candidate for U.S. Senate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-05-15" dateModified="2016-12-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Augustus_Sol_Invictus%2C_Libertarian_Party_candidate_for_U.S._Senate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are your thoughts on the job Marco Rubio has done as Senator and what would you have done differently than him?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Invictus</hi>: I think Rubio has done just as good a job as any Senator — and that is exactly the problem. Rubio is a horse-trader, a slimy smiler, the quintessential politician. He believes in nothing, save what his advisers tell him to believe in. I would have stuck to my positions and acted as a Senator, rather than simply setting myself up for a run for the presidency.</item></list></p>
<head id="Political_views">Political views</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/political%20correctness">political correctness</ref> as a problem in today's society?  If so, what can you do as a Senator to address it?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Invictus</hi>: I see political correctness as a huge problem in today's society. But whether fortunately or unfortunately, there is nothing a Senator can do to address it. I am a firm believer in the separation of powers, and the Senate has a very limited set of responsibilities. Moreover, this PC phenomenon we are witnessing is a cultural problem that must be addressed at a cultural level, not a legal one. That is up to the American people themselves, not the legislature.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Whereas the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_House_of_Representatives">House of Representatives</ref> is the house of the people, the Senate was originally meant to be the house of the States.  What are your views on the 10th Amendment and how will you reflect the interests of Florida through your votes?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Invictus</hi>: I am a big believer in States rights, and my <hi rend="italic">modus operandi</hi> as Senator will be to repeal as many laws as possible that hinder the ability of the States to govern their own affairs.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What specifically will you do as a Senate candidate and Senator to promote libertarianism?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Invictus</hi>: Simply leading by example is enough to promote libertarianism. I do not believe in shoving political ideology down people's throat anymore than I believe in doing so with religion. Being a Pagan, I do not feel the need to evangelize and convert <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Christianity">Christians</ref>; neither do I, as a Libertarian, feel the need to evangelize and convert Republicans and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(US)">Democrats</ref>. The proof of a thing is in its fruits. Repealing laws, correcting the balance between the Federal Government and the States, reinforcing the separation of powers, destroying the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Reserve%20System">Federal Reserve</ref>: these acts will in themselves promote our political philosophy.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">For you, what would constitute a successful term as Senator?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Invictus</hi>: The System is so corrupted that the destruction of even one Department, Bureau, or Administration could be considered a great success.</item></list></p>
<head id="Campaign">Campaign</head>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franklin%20D.%20Roosevelt">Franklin D. Roosevelt</ref> delivers a "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fireside%20Chat">Fireside Chat</ref>" in 1934.  Invictus describes the chats as a "brilliant idea" he has replicated in his campaign.Image: Public domain.</caption></figure>
</text>
