<text id="autogum_interview_doc601" title="part6_Wikinews interviews John Wolfe, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-19" dateModified="2013-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_John_Wolfe%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Will you support him during the November election or somebody else?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: Well, if he says he'll support me if I win, then I might reciprocate.  I think we'll just have to look at it and see how far and wide he appeals. But I certainly would expect to.  I certainly would like to.  Sure.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">But if it was a choice between him and [Mitt] <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Romney</ref>, who would you favor?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: Well if it came down to those two, I would just have to see where they are. I expect to support the president, but to me, there's not a lot of difference between him and Romney on the economy and there's not that much difference between him and Romney on foreign affairs. There's not that much difference between him and Romney on civil liberties. The differences are a lot narrower than people think and they mostly arise in areas again of identity politics. It seems to me like Romney is wanting to repeal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/abortion%20debate">abortion rights</ref>. He even wants to cut back on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/birth%20control">birth control</ref>.  It seems to me that he wants us to get involved in even more wars. He wants to actually to increase military spending by 20 percent. His foreign policy advisers are interventionists. They're <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neoconservatism">neo-cons</ref>. They're dangerous people, who don't even see <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref> as a mistake, who would like to get us involved even more deeply in areas like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syria</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_Korea">North Korea</ref>, places like that. Romney alarms me a lot more than Obama does in that area. I think Romney would probably give too many tax cuts to the well-to-do, the ones that are already very wealthy. I think that Obama would at least put an end to that. I don't think he pushed quite that hard for a tax increase, but I don't think he'd even fight for tax reductions either.</p>
<p><figure><caption>Corporate taxes as a proportion of GDP has decreased since the 1950s.Image: Guest2625.</caption></figure></p>
<p>Corporations and things are very powerful. The one message Obama has failed to get out is that the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corporate%20tax%20in%20the%20United%20States">corporate tax rate</ref> in this country may be 35 percent on paper, see the effective tax rate that these corporations pay, if you just look at the average of what the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fortune%20500">Fortune 500</ref> pay it's only 16 percent. So that's the way it really works because you got lobbyists in Washington that write the accounting rules, that write the tax rules and everything, so the 35 percent thing is just a mirage. All it's done is whip up ... to make people think we're non-competitive because we have a higher rater on paper than people like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref> or maybe some like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref> or some <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/third%20world">third world</ref> country. Right now if you look at the corporate tax collective, they make up the lowest percentage of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gross%20domestic%20product">GDP</ref> than ever.  I think we've paid $200 billion on a $15 trillion economy. So you're talking about maybe one and a half percent. Under [President Dwight] <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dwight%20Eisenhower">Eisenhower</ref>, the federal tax was collected and corporations made up about 25 percent of the budget receipts. Now they make up maybe nine percent, and corporations now are 15 times as big and powerful as they were under Eisenhower. So the corporation is ... they want to make people look like they're victims. I mean it's just pathetic.</p></p>
</text>
