<text id="autogum_interview_doc1380" title="part3_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What would you do?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Just mad, just react.  And achieve nothing.  You’ve got to say that life is about stated goals, benchmarks, and what you want to achieve at the end of life.  Because everybody comes to an end.  What was the purpose of your life and what did you achieve?  So if my goal was to build a social justice network, and to change things, at the end of life in the social justice arena, did I do that?  It won’t matter if I was angry or happy, it will matter if I have achieved that.  That’s what I learned from James Brown.  <hi rend="italic">You</hi> got to decide what your purpose is, not others.  Much of the media criticism of me  assumes <hi rend="italic">their</hi> goals and the impose them on me.  Well, those might not be my goals.  So they will say, “Well, Sharpton has not won a political office.”  But that might not be my goal!  Maybe I ran for political office to change the debate, or to raise the social justice question.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Which you see today.  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dennis_Kucinich">Dennis Kucinich</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tom_Tancredo">Tom Tancredo</ref>, they’re not there because they think they are going to win; they are trying to frame the issues.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Right.  And if they are there to frame the issue, then they <hi rend="italic">are</hi> successful.  One of the things I learned from James Brown is don’t let others determine your success.  Your success is based upon <hi rend="italic">your</hi> goals, not the goals they impose upon you.</p>
<head id="Criticism:_Sharpton_is_always_there">Criticism:  Sharpton is always there</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  A lot of the criticism that is lodged at you is that you always seem to pop up around hot button issues, or where there is some race issue.  My interview with you came up during my Thanksgiving dinner with my family, and I’d like that dinner to inform our discussion because it illustrated many of the typical perspectives about you.   My brother-in-law made that point, that there you always are around the controversial race issue.  I responded with, “Well, what was he saying?  Was he wrong about what he said?  Why do we focus on Sharpton and not the issue he is talking about?”</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Your answer is right, but let me give you something even deeper than that.  If you asked the average critic, “Where is he?”  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jena%20Six">Jena</ref>,  Imus, whatever.  You know what they won’t recognize?  Not only was I there, but I <hi rend="italic">created</hi> it into being an issue.  There was <hi rend="italic">no</hi> Jena until we went into Jena.  There was nobody else fighting Imus.  The misconception is these these issues got hot and then I came in; no, I came in and I made them hot.  There was nobody in Jena; nobody heard of Jena until we went down there.  Nobody ever questioned Imus <hi rend="italic">but</hi> us, which is why Imus came to our show.  The reason why this becomes important is because not only are you right, ‘Do you disagree with him,’ but do you begrudge him being in front of an issue that he helped create?  So who is supposed to be in front of it?  I create an issue and then somebody <hi rend="italic">else</hi> is supposed to lead it?  Last Friday we had a huge 50,000 person march in Washington against the Justice Department .  We went out there organizing with our chapters, got 150 buses from around the country paid for.  Who is supposed to lead the march?  You got people saying, “There he is leading the march.”  Well, he organized it.  Who is supposed to lead the march?  And the thing that gets me is, you get blamed for stuff you did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> do.  A lot of people think I led <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2006%20Duke%20University%20lacrosse%20case">the Duke case</ref>.  I <hi rend="italic">never</hi> went to Duke; I <hi rend="italic">never</hi> went to North Carolina.  Never ever.  They asked me to come, but I said unless I talk to the victim I’m not going.  So you get criticized for what you <hi rend="italic">do</hi> organize and lead, and you get criticized for stuff you had nothing to do with, just because people <hi rend="italic">assume</hi> you were there.  And it’s crazy!</p>
</text>
