<text id="autogum_interview_doc335" title="part0_Wikinews interviews DuckDuckGo, Opera, Mozilla, Wikimedia about DoNotTrack feature" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-23" dateModified="2019-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_DuckDuckGo%2C_Opera%2C_Mozilla%2C_Wikimedia_about_DoNotTrack_feature" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews DuckDuckGo, Opera, Mozilla, Wikimedia about DoNotTrack feature</head>
 This article mentions the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>, one of its projects, or people related to it. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> is a project of the Wikimedia Foundation.
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 5, 2013</hi></p>
<p>Following the introduction of a "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Do%20Not%20Track">Do Not Track</ref>" feature in modern browsers at the end of last year, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed several companies and groups about the feature.</p>
<head id="DuckDuckGo">DuckDuckGo</head>
<figure><caption>DuckDuckGo founder Gabriel Weinberg Image: Gabriel Weinberg.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>DuckDuckGo logo Image: Gabriel Weinberg.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>DuckDuckGo office Image: Gabriel Weinberg.</caption></figure>
<p>A crowdsourced <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/search%20engine">search engine</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DuckDuckGo">DuckDuckGo</ref> reviewed the feature and launched a <hi rend="italic">whatisDNT</hi> microsite in December. The review involved checking answers to basic questions such as whether websites stop shaping a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/user%20profile">user profile</ref> based on users' online actvitity or stop displaying <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/targeted%20advertising">targeted advertising</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed DuckDuckGo founder Gabriel Weinberg about the microsite launch and the DuckDuckGo opinion on the feature.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What prompted the launch of DuckDuckGo (I think it was around 2006?)?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Gabriel Weinberg</hi>: We launched on Sep 25, 2008, though I had been working on it for about a year prior. The initial motivation was to try a search engine with a different UI that did a better job of using more structured content (like from Wikipedia) and also more aggressively removed spam.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What does the DuckDuckGo Team use instead of Gmail?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GW</hi>: We do not have company mail accounts (beyond forwarding ones), so everyone uses what they want. I personally use outlook.com right now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  When and how did DuckDuckGo start using Perl? What influenced this decision and language choice?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GW</hi>: We started out in Perl. I picked it up at MIT where it was prevalent in the late 90s, and pretty much never looked back. It worked really well for a project like this that is text heavy and can use a lot of existing helper (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CPAN">CPAN</ref>) libraries.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How did you first hear about "DoNotTrack" feature?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GW</hi>: I do not remember, but it was a long time ago:). The Do Not Track concept was proposed many years ago.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  When did you launch http://whatisDNT.com/? Who worked on it? What researches, tests and studies did it involve?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GW</hi>: We launched the What Is Do Not Track micro-site on Dec 19, 2012, and various members of the DuckDuckGo Team worked on it (including myself). We had been following it closely for a while, and so have been up to date on everything that is going on with it. It honestly doesn't take any tests to prove its ineffectiveness since companies like Google tell you straight up they don't honor it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  A search engine that does not track users sounds good. What do you recommend users to do to not be tracked by *other* websites, such as blogs with targeted ads in sidebar?</p>
</text>
