<text id="autogum_interview_doc930" title="part5_An interview with gossip columnist Michael Musto on the art of celebrity journalism" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-05" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_gossip_columnist_Michael_Musto_on_the_art_of_celebrity_journalism" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  The body fascism thing actually <hi rend="italic">did</hi> originate as a health phenomenon, because people were reacting to AIDS.  People were like, 'I'm going to build up my body so that AIDS can't get me,' and we were being bashed at the same time by people saying we deserved AIDS.  So that was a way of saying I'm not a "sissy."  But it became totally obsessive and absurd, and it didn't protect you from bashing or AIDS or anything else.</p>
<p>In this case, I did notice a shift where everybody is boring in bed, where everyone is like, 'Oh, I'm kind of a versatile top.'  But then I got a lot of response from people saying, 'Are you <hi rend="italic">crazy</hi>?! Everyone on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manhunt.net">Manhunt</ref> is a bottom!'  One guy said, 'I'm a bottom, the problem is the tops don't know how to do it the right way, the tops just kind of stick it in.'  I can't picture this on Wikipedia...</p>
<p>Then the Michael Moore thing; <hi rend="italic">Sicko</hi> was great, but the opposite would also make a great movie.  That people who are sent to hospitals or become part of the medical system are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overmedication">over-medicated</ref> because one part of the system washes the other.  So a doctor will give you too many prescriptions.  If you go to a hospital they will keep you there a week longer than you need to be, to get the money for the bed.  I got responses to that, too.  Somebody sent me a book called <hi rend="italic">Overmedicated</hi>, so that topic has been written on.</p>
<head id="On_outing_gay_celebrities">On outing gay celebrities</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What stands out as a story that you did where you were bowled over by the reaction to it.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi> In the 1990s I was one of the few people outing celebrities—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  —You outed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rosie%20O'Donnell">Rosie O'Donnell</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ellen%20Degeneres">Ellen Degeneres</ref>—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  —I outed Rosie and Ellen, and it's hard to even <hi rend="italic">imagine</hi> now that they ever were in the closet.  You have to educate the new people and say, 'Guess what, they were in the closet at one point.'  It's hard to believe that Rosie was doing this delicate dance on her talk show where she was the 'Queen of Nice' and the single mother who had a crush on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom%20Cruise">Tom Cruise</ref> and I was pointing out the absurdity of it.  I was even more angry at the media than people like Rosie, because the media would play along with it.  They would do huge profiles of her without even addressing the fact that she was obviously a lesbian.  I just spoke at Yale a couple of weeks ago and talked about outing, and nobody argued.  I was like, 'Come on!  Somebody argue!'  I used to get so many arguments over this that I used to have a list printed out with an answer to each argument.</p>
</text>
