<text id="autogum_interview_doc075" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Indiana State Senator Mike Delph" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-26" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Indiana_State_Senator_Mike_Delph" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I have five daughters. My oldest daughter is 19 and a freshman at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indiana%20University%20–%20Purdue%20University%20Indianapolis">IUPUI</ref> here in Indianapolis. She's our first proud graduate of Delph Academy for Girls. She did really well her first semester of college, making the Dean's List. So mom and dad were obviously very ecstatic there. I have a 17-year-old daughter, who just turned 17. She told dad that she wanted a boyfriend for her birthday, and so I went out and got a little stuffed animal of the good guy from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frozen%20(2013%20film)">Frozen</ref> [a film], which I said you can take to bed with you every night and cuddle with. So her name is Evelyn. I have a 14-year old named Anna, a 10-year old named Emma, and my 7-year-old, who will probably — well her name is Lilly, that she believes she will be the next <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rock%20and%20Roll%20Hall%20of%20Fame">rock star</ref> of rock music. And she and I play my guitar and sing every night. So that's a little bit about my family.</p>
<p>I work as general counsel for a second-generation family-owned business based out of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloomington,%20Indiana">Bloomington</ref>, Indiana, named CarDon &amp; Associates. And we are in the business of senior housing and long-term care, post-acute care, nursing homes, assisted-living facilities and independent living facilities.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Behnke: We understand that you and your wife home educate your children. How did you decide to home educate your children?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: Well the name of our home school is the Delph Academy for Girls. Originally my 19-year old was part of the Carmel school system and attended Carmel Elementary and had a real challenging year, her first grade year. We were actually told by her first grade teacher that she would have a hard time graduating from high school and that college was not in the cards, which obviously was a lot for mom and dad to take with our first grader. We went and had a battery of tests done. And there was a dispute within the school system as to what, if any, learning disabilities that she might have, and what we should do about it. So we finished out that school year and went a little bit into the next, and then we just made the decision as a family that we weren't going to fight the system. We were going to take matters into our own hands and start homeschooling our daughter. Then we just started homeschooling the rest of our kids. It's turned out to be a very big blessing in the life of the Delph family for obvious reasons because our daughter has turned around her academic life in a very positive fashion and is doing very well in college, as I mentioned before.</p>
<p>Another reason why we homeschool our students, is we teach <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bible">Bible</ref> in our school. And obviously you can't do that in the public school system. Our faith and Christian values are very important to Beth and I and to our daughters.</p>
</text>
