<text id="autogum_interview_doc1423" title="part2_Interview with dismissed Ocean Drive columnist Trisha Posner" shortTile="partinterview-dismissed" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-22" dateModified="2013-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_dismissed_Ocean_Drive_columnist_Trisha_Posner" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Has any other employee of <hi rend="italic">Ocean Drive</hi> appeared publicly before and been identified as such?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TP:</hi>   As far as I know I’m the first one, that’s why I made history.  But I wasn’t talking about <hi rend="italic">Ocean Drive</hi>.  I hadn’t thought that under my name were the words 'Columnist for Ocean Drive'.  I didn’t see anything.  Later I had e-mails from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tina%20Brown">Tina Brown</ref>, everybody...they were really supportive.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Your husband, author <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerald%20Posner">Gerald Posner</ref>, wrote a piece in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Huffington%20Post">The Huffington Post</ref></hi> about your dismissal.  Several of the comments to it state that since <hi rend="italic">Ocean Drive</hi> is a large glossy magazine dependent upon advertising from the entertainment industry, that you bit the hand that fed you.  How do you respond to such criticism?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TP:</hi>   That’s the stupidest thing I have ever heard, because it had nothing to do with <hi rend="italic">Ocean Drive</hi>.  There is another world.  I'm not against development; if you listen to my statement I talk about how much I love the nightlife, how I love entertainment.  But we all have to learn to live together.  I know South Beach is party town, but we can live together.  Let’s clean up our shit, take our garbage out, be respectful to our neighbors and also to the entertainment industry.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Some of the comments that were made in HuffPo were that even though it was despicable that you were fired for expressing your opinion on a civic matter, that you should have expected it. Do you think comments like that are par for the course of apathy in the United States today, where people disagree with something, but shrug their shoulders instead?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TP:</hi>  I think we live in dangerous times because of corporate America—people are really scared to speak out about anything; it is really dangerous.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom%20of%20speech">Freedom of speech</ref>.  I came to live here in this country because it was for freedom of speech.  I love America, and it has everything I could have dreamed of: the most incredible husband, friends, everything.  But they are chipping away at it.  One company is one company, but it shows how dangerous it is.  What happens when the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rupert%20Murdoch">Rupert Murdochs</ref> own everything?  They are trying to gag us.  It is very dangerous.  Whether it is the film industry, the music industry, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington,%20D.C.">D.C.</ref>, they are trying to strangle all of us.  All these regulations of what we can or can’t do.  Does it mean if I have an opinion that I have to be gagged or not say who I am or what I think?  What can and can’t I say?  Maybe I’m just too black and white.  I think we need to just chill out here.  It wasn’t about <hi rend="italic">Ocean Drive</hi> or Jerry Powers.  It was about my home and my friends.  I was helping out Frank.  It was about the loophole and the Bijou [hotel].  I think what really freaked them out was that the video was professionally done.</p>
</text>
