<text id="autogum_interview_doc031" title="Wikinews interviews producer of horror film &amp;apos;6:66PM&amp;apos;" shortTile="wikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-07-17" dateModified="2017-08-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_producer_of_horror_film_%276%3A66PM%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews producer of horror film '6:66PM'</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 1, 2017</hi></p>
<figure><caption>File photo of a film production clapboard.Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:ListFiles/Runner1616">Runner1616</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> recently caught up with screenwriter and film producer Chad Ridgely to discuss his latest <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/indie%20film">indie</ref> horror film, <hi rend="italic">6:66PM</hi>. The film is scheduled to show at the Buffalo Dreams Fantastic Film Festival in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Buffalo,_New_York">Buffalo</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref> in November.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I've watched the teaser trailer. Tell us about the film's story line.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Chad Ridgely</hi> 6:66 P.M. is about a team of ghost hunters making a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/reality%20TV">reality</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/TV">TV</ref> show about <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/paranormal">paranormal</ref> activity. The problem is, none of them are really ghost hunters. They stage the house to make it seem like the house they're exploring is haunted, except it turns out that the house really is haunted by the ghost of a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Serial_killer">serial killer</ref>. The serial killer isn't letting them get out of there without a fight. He tries to kill them and take possession of their bodies. So the crew is forced to try to capture some amazing footage for their show but at the same time avoid getting killed by this demon. It has some scary moments, but at the same time it's a comedy. We tried to blend the two together for a nice mix of scares and laughs and I think we did a really nice job of it. Many of us had worked together before so there was already a strong foundation in place and it let us play to everyone's strengths.</item></list>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Who is producing the film?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">CR</hi> The film was produced by my company, Full Auto Films, and Code 3 Films, which is Jim Klock's company. Producers are Jim Klock, Chad Ridgely, and Darrell Martinelli.</item></list>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Will you guys be making the rounds at film festivals soon?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">CR</hi> Yes, the film will world-premiere at the Buffalo Dreams Fantastic Film Festival in Buffalo, New York in early November 2017. We premiered our previous horror/comedy feature there, <hi rend="italic">Massacre on Aisle 12</hi>, last year and we absolutely loved it. It's a great festival and Buffalo is amazing. I fell in love with the food there, especially the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/beef%20on%20weck">roast beef on weck</ref> sandwiches. I think I gained ten pounds while I was there. The food was that good.</item></list>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Who wrote the script?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">CR</hi> The script was written by Tommy McLaughlin and Chad Ridgely.</item></list>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Where was the film shot primarily?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">CR</hi> We filmed outside of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Atlantic_City,_New_Jersey">Atlantic City</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Jersey">New Jersey</ref>. It was a little town called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egg%20Harbor%20City,%20New%20Jersey">Egg Harbor City</ref>, which was a bit strange because I didn't see any eggs there, or a harbor, and the place was definitely too small to be a city. They did have a fantastic diner, though. We ate there every day before and sometimes after shooting. I'm beginning to see a pattern with food.</item></list>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Have you signed any distribution deals? What are the hoped-for plans in terms of distribution?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">CR</hi> Yes, the film will be distributed by Indican Pictures in late fall of 2017. Indican Pictures also distributed our previous horror/comedy, <hi rend="italic">Massacre on Aisle 12</hi>, as well.</item></list>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Any weird or funny events happen during filming?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">CR</hi> Yes! We lived in the set house while we were filming, and we were convinced the place was really haunted. It was a secluded old farm house back in the woods, and late at night all sorts of weird things would happen. For instance, the door to my room would slowly creak open all by itself while I was sleeping. Jim Klock kept hearing footsteps creaking on the floorboards above his room, except there was no room above his. It was just the roof. There was also a very strange animal out in the woods that would make an incredibly creepy noise that we were never really able to identify. And of course, no one was going out there to look. In addition to scaring the crap out of us, it helped us bring additional authenticity to the film, which I think shows on screen.</item></list>
</text>
