<text id="autogum_interview_doc135" title="Wikinews interviews Spanish Paralympic track and field athlete Alberto Suárez Laso" shortTile="wikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-07-16" dateModified="2013-08-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Spanish_Paralympic_track_and_field_athlete_Alberto_Su%C3%A1rez_Laso" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Spanish Paralympic track and field athlete Alberto Suárez Laso</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 17, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:LauraHale">Laura Hale</ref> interviews Alberto Suárez Laso for Wikinews</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Alberto Suárez Laso at the airport in Madrid before departing for France Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:LauraHale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>With the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/IPC_Athletics_World_Championships">IPC Athletics World Championships</ref> scheduled to start this Friday, Wikinews interviewed <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spanish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T12%20(classification)">T12 classified</ref> long distance runner <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alberto%20Suárez%20Laso">Alberto Suárez Laso</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Madrid–Barajas_Airport">Madrid–Barajas Airport</ref> Monday before he departed for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lyon">Lyon</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref>. Suárez is scheduled to compete in two events, the T12 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/5,000%20meters">5,000 meters</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Marathon">marathon</ref> events.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Hi this is Laura Hale. I'm interviewing Alberto Suárez, who is a visually-impaired runner competing for Spain in the IPC World Championships. What events are you doing? ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿En qué eventos estás?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alberto%20Suárez%20Laso">Alberto Suárez Laso</ref></hi>: Marathon and 5000m. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Maratón y 5000m.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You have a World Record? Are you going to smash it and give Spain a gold medal? ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿Vas a romper el record mundial y darle a España un oro?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alberto Suárez Laso</hi>: This time it's a bit complicated because I'm going a bit injured. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Esta vez está un poco complicado porque voy un poco lesionado</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Ah. You finished second in London [the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2012_Summer_Paralympics">2012 Summer Paralympics</ref>]? ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿Terminaste segundo en Londres?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alberto Suárez Laso</hi>: I finished first.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The injury has impacted you training? ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿La lesión ha perjudicado tu entrenamiento?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alberto Suárez Laso</hi>: For the last three weeks I've been doing gym and walking machine only. I have pain in my <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Achilles%20tendon">Achilles tendon</ref>. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Llevo tres semanas solo con gimnasio y elíptica. Tengo dolor en el tendón de Aquiles.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   So, as someone who writes from an international perspective,  do you think Spain's got all that stuff to help you properly? The medical support, stuff to help you recuperate and be a great runner?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alberto Suárez Laso</hi>: I hope so. We're there, they've been treating me very well and I hope to be able to run without pain, which is the most important thing. I've got the training, but I need to remove that pain. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Espero que sí. Estamos ahí, me están tratando bastante bien y espero correr sin dolor, que es lo fundamental. La preparación la tengo, pero hay que quitar ese dolor.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you run with a guide?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alberto Suárez Laso</hi>: No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Okay, so are you <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T13%20(classification)">T-13</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alberto Suárez Laso</hi>: T-12.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   Oh. So it's optional for a guy at T-12?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Translator</hi>: He could, but he's not too badly impaired. He can run by himself.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So is your preference to run without a guide?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alberto Suárez Laso</hi>: It's complicated because of the pace I run at. I would require several guides, and it's hard to find them. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Es una complicación por el ritmo al que corro. Necesitaría varios guías y es dificil conseguirlos.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do most of your competitors run with guides? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alberto Suárez Laso</hi>: Not among the first ones. Well, there are a couple that do run with guides, but the rest don't. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Los primeros no. Bueno, hay un par de ellos que corren con guía, los demás no.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   Is there anything you would like to say about this competition coming up that people from an international sporting community would find valuable to know?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alberto Suárez Laso</hi>: Mm, I don't know what to say!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Okay. Thank you very much! ((es))Spanish language: ‍¡Muchas gracias!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alberto Suárez Laso</hi>: You're welcome! ((es))Spanish language: ‍De nada.</p>
</text>
