<text id="autogum_interview_doc1294" title="part2_David S. Touretzky discusses Scientology, Anonymous and Tom Cruise" shortTile="partdavid-s-touretzky" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-06" dateModified="2012-12-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_S._Touretzky_discusses_Scientology%2C_Anonymous_and_Tom_Cruise" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: She has nothing to do with Chanology [the recent anti-Scientology movement that has gathered on Internet message boards], but what we're seeing here is a "perfect storm" of entheta [material considered negative by Scientology]. It's all coming together in a chain reaction:  The Tom Cruise video, Andrew Morton's bio, Kirstie Alley's craziness, Kimora Lee Simmons, Jenna Miscavige, and there's more to come!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : I believe the things like disconnection, fair game, the RPF [Rehabilitation Project Force, a Scientology penal system within the paramilitary Sea Org] etc. are all more captivating to the hearts and minds of the general public than Xenu... so do you think that the Church of Scientology will ever be able to recover from this blow to their reputation? In other words, will this be the "beginning of the end" of the Church seriously being able to promote themselves to the general public?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: I've learned it's impossible to predict what will happen next with CoS [the Church of Scientology]. We try, but we always get it wrong.  They have capabilities for self-destructive behavior that far exceed those of normal individuals. Now that Mike Rinder has blown, anything is possible. And he's not the only exec out there who has a gripe with DM.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Indeed. There have been many high-profile blows [departures] from upper exec [executive] strata and I wonder how many more the CoS can cope with.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: Yes, these folks are starting to go public.  John Peeler has already done so. And who could have predicted Jenna Miscavige would turn SP? Amazing!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : A further question, if I may, regarding the impact on Scientology: do you think that the recent activities of Anonymous will have a profound effect on the Sea Org hierarchy and possibly make it harder for the Church of Scientology to continue maintaining their PR image to their own staff members? Could this trigger a massive series of "blows" from the Sea Org?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: You're probably in a better position [as a former member] to assess the affect on Sea Org members, but my guess is that they won't even be aware of Anonymous actions, or will write them off as crazy Internet hatemongers. I think a bigger impact will come from Jenna Miscavige [leader David Miscavige's niece].</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : What exactly is Anonymous going to do on the 10th? Are their intentions peaceful? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: Oh yeah, they appear to be *very* concerned about avoiding any kind of violence or unlawful behavior. From what I can see, they understand that any kind of violence or criminality would play into CoS' hands. It would allow CoS to portray themselves as victims and score a PR win. One anonymous person suggested that the policy towards all participants should be: "If you do anything illegal, WE will call the cops on you ourselves."</p>
</text>
