<text id="autogum_interview_doc1228" title="part11_The Onion: An interview with 'America's Finest News Source'" shortTile="partthe-onion-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2013-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Onion%3A_An_interview_with_%27America%27s_Finest_News_Source%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  There has not been, but I think it will be interesting to see how it will evolve the way you see mainstream media has evolved with people crossing the lines there.  Brian Williams on SNL, for example.  A lot of cross-over between the different mediums.  Who knows what the future holds there.  I think as we go between the different satirical news mediums, there might be something fun in the future.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is there ever a story that has divided the staff, something the writers look back on and say, “Remember ‘Old Soul Goes to Cobbler’ and <hi rend="italic">that</hi> whole issue?!”   Something where half of the people thought it should never have been done and the other half thought it was really great?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  We are a team, there are almost 15 of us and you are almost never going to get all fifteen people on board behind a joke.  Someone is not going to be too hot on it.  There are some cases—again, I wasn’t here—but I know the September 11 issue was an obviously very large challenge to approach.  Do we even put out an issue?  What is funny at this time in American history?  Where are the jokes?  Do people want jokes right now?  Is the nation ready to laugh again?  Who knows.  There will always be some level of division in the back room.  It’s also what keeps us on our toes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think your writers are more optimistic or pessimistic about American culture?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  It’s hard to apply the word optimistic to any of our writers.  I don’t know if I could classify it like that.
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  They are great lovers of American culture.  I find really enthusiastic support for certain artists, but I don’t know if they sit around thinking about the culture at large, and whether they are optimistic or pessimistic.  There are good things every year that come out, and there are bad things that are part of the culture.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  Yeah, everyone has their favorite writers, their favorite artists; what they really hate are stupidity and mediocrity.  They are really sick of people getting away with repackaged drivel, so they are not going to hesitate to call people out on that.  If it’s just another big box sitcom, then yeah we’re going to take a shot at it because it’s not different than every other “Two guys and a child, or a horse, or a donkey, or a monkey, in a two bedroom apartment in New York or Chicago or San Francisco.”  Those sort of Madlibs pitches on sitcoms.</p>
<head id="Unsolicited_material">Unsolicited material</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Rory Covey:  I was curious about how much unsolicited material you guys get bombarded with?</hi></p>
</text>
