<text id="autogum_interview_doc501" title="part4_Eric Bogosian on writing and the creative urge" shortTile="parteric-bogosian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-16" dateModified="2014-05-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eric_Bogosian_on_writing_and_the_creative_urge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Would you say it comes from emotion and character?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Yeah--how well you can convey to the audience your point of view.  You could be living in a box, but if you can really convey it well then it makes for exciting reading.  But, you know, you have to be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcel%20Proust">Proust</ref> to do that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you draw any inspiration from the current political climate, either in the country or in the world?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Politically, I'm an activist, but  my work is always about sort of the attitude that underlies it all.  I rarely deal with topical stuff.  It feels topical, but it isn't.  I mean, <hi rend="italic">Talk Radio</hi> kind of surprised people, because they revived it last year, twenty years after it had been written, and it felt fresh.  But that's because I don't really write about topical stuff; I write about American attitudes, American values, my values, my attitudes.  And to the degree that anybody sees things the way I see things, they can relate.  But I'm not going to set out and say, "Okay, now what can I write about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20Bush">George Bush</ref> today?" I just think there's enough people writing blogs about that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think narrative is one of the more challenging aspects of writing?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Telling a good story is a dying art.  Not just in fiction, but in book writing, where you're given a little bit of a leeway because it's the nature of fiction; you can meander a little bit.  But in films and in plays, it's hard to know how to tell a good story.  It's sort of one those basic things you have to know how to do before you even sit down to write.  You're juggling a lot of balls if you want to a good literary writer.  Obviously, you have to have control of the prose itself, the rhetoric of the whole thing, the way you put it forth.  Then there's the storytelling.  Then it's like who cares that you have something to say unless you have a good reason to say it?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you ever ask yourself that question about your writing? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Like a lot of artists, I started out with a particularly strong point of view, coming from where I was coming from, wherever that might be.  Like a suburban kid moving into the city or whatever you want to say I was twenty years ago.  But I became successful, and then I found it more and more interesting to write about those things that are part of my successful life, which actually are less and less interesting for an audience to read about. So I mean--you know what I'm saying?</p>
</text>
