<text id="autogum_interview_doc315" title="part2_John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing" shortTile="partjohn-reed-orwell" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2015-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell%2C_God%2C_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Vanderslice_plays_New_York_City:_Wikinews_interview">I interviewed a musician named John Vanderslice</ref>, and off-the-record he talked about how the mainstream music press has almost lost all influence--<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spin%20(magazine)">Spin</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rolling%20Stone%20(magazine)">Rolling Stone</ref></hi>; those kinds of magazines.  He said that whenever he did some small blog interview his web site jumped up in hits.  But when he got a favorable review in <hi rend="italic">Rolling Stone</hi> he said, “I barely heard a word about it.”  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  The whole music industry has shifted over into networking sites, the Internet, and it's just extremely comparable.  The way that it's functioned--and now half of the music industry is made up of this kind of independent record label--that's what's happening with books.  You don't have mid level artists recording at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sony%20Records">Sony</ref>, and you don't have many mid-list authors at the large houses.  The little presses are snapping them up.  Of course, the large houses are aware of this, in the same way that the large record labels are aware of it, and I think that they're gearing themselves to either take them over or have imprints address it.  Like, MTV Books now has Vice books.  They do like cool, beautiful books, and they've given Vice a real platform to do what they want.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think it's becoming like the pharmaceutical industry?  There the really big drug companies don't have a lot of drugs in the pipeline, but there are all these like little drug companies that are existing for one-or-two-drug clinical trials, and the big drug companies are watching them.  Once they have a seller, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big%20Pharma">big pharma</ref> goes in and snaps up the little companies.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  That's exactly what it is.  I don't know if it's all bad, though.  When a big press buys a small press, the small press sort of loses its identity.  But it doesn't happen right away.  Right now, the distribution of the small presses is so piss poor for the most part, that it's just very hard for them to move units.  It's a real challenge.  Most of them don't care that much; they want to have one or two books that are hits, but to sell big numbers of books, distribution is a real problem.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How does the business model for small presses make up for a lack of blockbuster books?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  They need one or two, but most small presses that don't care.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's more of an idealistic enterprise, then?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Yeah, if it's a non-profit--they get some grants.  For the functional small presses--let's say <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Akashic%20Books">Akashic Books</ref>, or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archipelago%20Books">Archipelago Books</ref>--which are very small but I believe run at a profit, the business model is to put all these books out there, and if one or two of them hits every couple of years, they're fine.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soft%20Skull%20Press">Soft Skull</ref> is another one.  I love <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacAdam%20Cage">MacAdam Cage</ref>; I don't know how they're making any money, but they do wonderful books.  They've got to have a few titles that sell a lot of copies.  One press who used to have this theory of publishing is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint%20Martin's%20Press">Saint Martin's Press</ref>, a sort of "Throw shit at the wall and see what sticks" phenomenon.</p>
</text>
