<text id="autogum_interview_doc1165" title="part3_Wikinews interviews journalist Konrad Godlewski, who uncovered BATUTA hoax" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-02-08" dateModified="2010-02-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_journalist_Konrad_Godlewski%2C_who_uncovered_BATUTA_hoax" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold"> When I read some recent texts about Batuta I often come across different mutations of the story. The most common is the one which says the journalists were the ones who uncovered the hoax, in spite of the fact that your text was published several days after the uncovering made by the Wikimedians themselves. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> That's correct. It is quite common to attribute different things to the journalists because of their job which is to go around, look and investigate. I've seen Batuta being quoted in many publications on Wikipedia and the Internet. This is part of a broader problem of credibility of sources. It's horrifying but we are surrounded by the half-truths and lies. </p>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold"> Roman, Władysław, Marek – the names of the members of Batuta's Army were obviously false as well? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Yes, they were "alternative".</p>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold"> Was the term "Batuta's Army" created after you had already begun to talk? Or maybe they came to you already with this term? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Batuta's Army was invented by the hoax' creators as we spoke. Probably they wanted it to sound like some well-know political terrorist organizations like IRA or Red Army Faction. It was a kind of joke.</p>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold"> News about Batuta became a "good meme" and later it began to live a life of its own. Many legends originated from this story. Do you think it will become a "hard" urban legend?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I had thought so, but fortunately the Wikimedians woke up right in time and put an end to this. Today the original Batuta article is like an antibody in a vaccine – accompanied by a secure commentary, it can be used by anyone for the sake of his/her own immunity against such a "virus". However, another "Jewish conspiracy" theory is still thriving. It has something to do with Batuta's article, as in the hoax he was a communist activist with you-know-what origin. The theory I'm talking about was made popular by Okhrana (Russian secret police from the tzars times) with the publication of "The Protocols of the Elders of Zion". It has made its way as far as to Japan. Recently I've been following its spread in China. A book called "The Currency Wars" has recently been published there. The author used to work at American financial institutions. When he came back to China, he wrote the book describing how America's finances are under control by a group of friends with common ancestry.
I don't think there's any way of defense against a good hoax. I'm sure at least a few such Batutas are hiding somewhere in Wikipedia. It's a classical evolutionary arms race. </p>
</text>
