<text id="autogum_interview_doc1428" title="part3_Judging the Courts: Wikinews interviews Prof. Lawrence Douglas" shortTile="partjudging-courts" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-11-20" dateModified="2015-09-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Judging_the_Courts%3A_Wikinews_interviews_Prof._Lawrence_Douglas" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: How effective have national courts and individual countries been in bringing high-level leaders to account for abuses?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: The record is uneven.  In the wake of the atrocities of World War II, thousands of domestic trials were staged.  The most spectacular of these – the Eichmann trial in Jerusalem in 1961, the Barbie trial in Lyon in 1987 – were enormously important, despite their flaws, in establishing a responsible account of terrible crimes.  Other countries have been less successful.  The fact that Pol Pot died peacefully without ever having to answer for his crimes is regrettable, indeed, but not entirely unexpected.  A country that is still very much in the grips of its traumatic history is hardly in the position to engage in a reckoning with its past in a manner that accords with the rule of law.  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: How do the two (domestic versus international courts) compare?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: Clearly there are tradeoffs.  International trials inevitably arouse resentment in the nations most directly implicated in the commission of the adjudged crimes; international tribunals convey the message that domestic national courts are not up to the task of doing justice.  Moreover, as these trials may unfold thousands of miles removed from the site of the crimes, they fail to be organically connected to the communities that should be most involved in the case.  Conversely, domestic national courts invite the charge of being insufficiently distanced from the crimes under consideration; these courts thus may be assailed as partisan instruments of victor's justice, or, conversely, as instruments lacking the legal resources and political will to bring perpetrators to justice.  If – and it's a big if – we can trust domestic national courts, I think they are to be preferred over international tribunals for the reasons suggested above.  International tribunals should be courts of last resort, relied upon in situations in which domestic courts should not be taxed, or cannot be trusted, to deal adequately with the legal legacy of atrocity. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: One of the reasons for setting up the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Criminal_Court">International Criminal Court</ref> and other international courts has been to serve as a deterrent against committing crimes under international humanitarian law; to work around the impunity enjoyed by some leaders in their home countries. How well is this purpose being served?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: I'm not sure I would necessarily associate the goal of deterrence with the goal of ending impunity – that is, I believe it is critical to fight impunity, even if bringing perpetrators to justice appears to do little by the way of deterring other leaders from engaging in atrocious acts.  That said, I think it's awfully difficult to measure deterrence inasmuch as it's a negative effect.  The fact that atrocities continue to occur around the globe doesn't mean that some potential perpetrators might not have thought twice about engaging in criminal acts.</p>
</text>
