<text id="autogum_interview_doc1138" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Russ Aegard, Thunder Bay-Atikokan" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-24" dateModified="2007-11-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_candidate_Russ_Aegard%2C_Thunder_Bay-Atikokan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Russ Aegard, Thunder Bay-Atikokan</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 24, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Russ Aegard</hi> is running for the Green Party of Ontario in the Ontario provincial election, in the Thunder Bay-Atikokan riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>The main reason I have chosen to involve myself in the political process is my daughter.  She is now 3 years old, and the world is becoming more polarized, more dangerous and more unhealthy.  This pattern of human behaviour has got to cease.  We are destroying the environment on which we depend upon to maintain a standard of living.  We are exploiting other cultures in order to receive cheap goods.  I want a better world for my daughter, and I figure the best way to do that is to make the changes myself.  I have ran in this constituency because I have lived in Northwestern Ontario all of my life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I have run federally twice in my riding for the Green Party.  I have sat on a few boards of various operations to assist in the management of the organizations.  As a teacher, I can draw upon a variety of skills in order to be an effective politician.  Having excellent listening skills is imperative in the role of a MPP.  Working cooperatively in a professional setting is another skill that makes an effective MPP.  Seeing first-hand how the policies of today's governments has affected children provides me with the insight that change is needed and is needed quickly.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>All three of my competitors are going to have the challenge of being elected.  As someone who is new to the race, and the Green Party being relatively new, my goal is to spread the Green message.  In my riding though, the seat will be hotly contested by the three other parties.  I feel that my youth, honesty and reliability makes me the most desirable of the candidates.  Our platform has a vision for the future; not just to get elected for the short term.</p>
</text>
