<text id="autogum_interview_doc895" title="part1_Eurovision &amp;apos;04 winner Ruslana discusses her paths as singer, spokesmodel, stateswoman and source of inspiration" shortTile="parteurovision--winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-30" dateModified="2015-05-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2704_winner_Ruslana_discusses_her_paths_as_singer%2C_spokesmodel%2C_stateswoman_and_source_of_inspiration" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I loved <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen%20(band)">Queen</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deep%20Purple">Deep Purple</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pink%20Floyd">Pink Floyd</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A-ha">A-ha</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Beatles">Beatles</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Police">Police</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cher">Cher</ref> and many others. I still love them. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You were trained in classical piano at the Music Conservatory in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lviv">Lviv</ref>. How did the skills you learned while studying there impact your musical style now?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ruslana</hi>: When I graduated from the conservatory, I obtained two educational qualifications in the field of music as a piano player and a symphonic orchestra conductor. My music education helps me very much to create my own music. For example, [a] few years ago at Lviv's 750th anniversary, I performed "Energy Source" as conductor of a symphonic orchestra that played my own composed music in a beautiful light show. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> I interviewed <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Two-time_Eurovision_entrant_Edsilia_Rombley_discusses_music,_love,_and_her_contrasting_Contest_experiences">Edsilia Rombley</ref> last month and she has a situation similar to yours, in that the main collaborator and producer of her music became her husband as well. How did you meet your husband and what led you to form a musical partnership? Also, how did the two of you fall in love?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ruslana</hi>: Both of us were born in Lviv. We had the same friends, the same interest, objectives and the same love – music. I wanted to work with professionals and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oleksandr%20Ksenofontov">Sasha</ref> was [a] famous singer [at] that time in Lviv. He had his own band. So we met about work. From the first second I understood that we have [a] kindred spirit. Music connects us. And with our first song appeared our first feelings...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> When you first started receiving recognition and becoming successful in the Ukraine in the mid-1990s, was it overwhelming? What was your main motivation in your career during this time? Was there ever a time where you considered leaving the music industry to live a quieter life?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ruslana</hi>: No, I was born for music. I love what I'm doing with all of my heart. The first thing [about] recognition [is that] I should be very truthful with myself and with people. It's very important. I'm always honest with my fans. If you work only for money and you sing a song that you must sing but you don't feel it all of your heart and soul – you will be [a] singer for [only] one day.</p>
<head id="Wild_Dances"><hi rend="italic">Wild Dances</hi></head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Ruslana_at_concert_1.jpg">File:Ruslana at concert 1.jpg</ref></p><figure><caption>Ruslana performing her song "Wild Dances," in which she incorporates the musical styles of the Hutsul ethnic minority from the Carpathian Mountains in western Ukraine.<hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Ruslana_at_concert_1.jpg">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=File%3ARuslana+at+concert+1.jpg">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In more than one project, including your <hi rend="italic">Wild Dances</hi> CD, you have worked extensively in the unique musical tradition of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hutsul">Hutsul</ref> people. What caused you to pursue such a niche? Also, are there any important things about the Hutsul people and tradition that people may not know, that you wish you could bring awareness to?</hi></p>
</text>
