<text id="autogum_interview_doc1260" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Libertarian candidate Alan Mercer, Scarborough—Rouge River" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-03" dateModified="2008-11-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Libertarian_candidate_Alan_Mercer%2C_Scarborough%E2%80%94Rouge_River" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Libertarian candidate Alan Mercer, Scarborough—Rouge River</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 3, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alan Mercer</hi> is running for the Ontario Libertarian Party in the Ontario provincial election, in the Scarborough—Rouge River riding. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref>' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I live in Scarborough—Rouge River. I'm involved in the political process because of my desire to promote the message of individual liberty during provincial and federal elections, and to help build the libertarian political movement in Ontario and Canada. There is more information about me at <ref target="http://www.libertarian.on.ca/Elec2007/A_Mercer.htm">http://www.libertarian.on.ca/Elec2007/A_Mercer.htm</ref> and <ref target="http://www.thestar.com/ontarioelection/ridings/candidateprofile/252984">http://www.thestar.com/ontarioelection/ridings/candidateprofile/252984</ref> and <ref target="http://www.canadianliberty.com/blog">http://www.canadianliberty.com/blog</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I ran in the provincial by-election in Scarborough—Rouge River in 2005, and I was a candidate in the 2006 federal election for the Libertarian Party of Canada. I was elected to the Board of Directors of the Libertarian Party of Canada in May, 2005, and I was appointed president of the LPC in February, 2006. I have also served on the executive of the Ontario Libertarian Party. I have had opportunities to explain libertarian principles and positions to various media.</p>
<p>I helped to write the Ontario Libertarian Party's <ref target="http://www.libertarian.on.ca/platform/Environment.htm">current environment policy</ref> and the Libertarian Party of Canada's <ref target="http://www.libertarian.ca/english/lpc-platform-may-2007.html">current platform</ref></p>
<p>I have contributed press releases for both the Ontario LP and LP of Canada, which include "<ref target="http://libertarian.ca/english/news/06jan09-candidate-alan-mercer.html">Scarborough-Rouge River Libertarian on crime, restitution, foreign policy and civil liberties</ref>", "<ref target="http://libertarian.ca/english/news/05aug8-emery.html">Block the Extradition of Marc Emery: The War on Drugs is a War on Liberty</ref>", "<ref target="http://www.libertarian.on.ca/ann/PRs/2006_07_12_growth_plan.html">Libertarian Party Rejects 'Smart Growth' as a Dumb Idea</ref>", "<ref target="http://www.libertarian.on.ca/ann/PRs/bodyownership.htm">Ontario Organ Donation Bill Seeks Government Ownership of your Body</ref>", "<ref target="http://www.libertarian.on.ca/ann/PRs/throne_speech_2_06.html">Response to the Liberal Government's Agenda</ref>", "<ref target="http://www.libertarian.on.ca/ann/PRs/throne_speech_I_02.html">Response to Statements in the Liberal Throne Speech Concerning Education</ref>", and "<ref target="http://libertarian.ca/english/news/05aug22-thalidomide.html">Thalidomide Cancer Drug Only 9 Cents in Brazil while Canadians Spend their Life Savings</ref>".</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>The incumbent has all the advantage, and after that the NDP candidate and Conservative candidate in that order. Literally, there is no other candidate in the riding who is even going to come close to presenting a libertarian message. My candidacy represents liberty and allows the electors to hear this message. The Conservatives do not even come close to voicing free market positions or any opposition to infringements on personal liberties and property rights – such as the Smoke-Free Ontario Act or the Greenbelt Act or the Liberals forcing teens to stay in school until they’re 18. The major political parties still advocate price controls on the economy and the Greens are just the most extreme kind of control-freak mentality that the major parties represent with their corporatist-socialist policies. There is a complete vacuum and libertarians need to get involved right now and get their own pro-liberty message out to the Canadian public which is starved of this.</p>
</text>
