<text id="autogum_interview_doc1381" title="part4_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Nadine Strossen, the President of the ACLU, brought up <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion,_drugs,_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush">in our interview</ref> that their critics intentionally distort their work to serve their own purposes.  For instance, many people believe the ACLU works to keep religion out of the school, yet they have consistently fought for the right for religion to be in schools.  She debated Falwell and Robertson on these issues, and they will still say that the ACLU is fighting to remove God from the public sphere.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  She’s right!  That’s not their position!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you come across people who intentionally misinform the debate in order to scuttle your goals, what do you do?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  The only thing you can do is straighten the record out, but you come to expect it.  The advantage I have is that I grew up in the movement and watched people from Reverend Jackson to James Brown.  James Brown as the dominant father in my life; Jackson as the dominant teacher, who had to deal with the same misconceptions and controversies.  When it came my time, I almost expected it because that is what they are going to do, which is to try and change the debate.  What you learn is you don’t let them change the premise.  Because if you start with the wrong premise, you arrive at the wrong conclusion.   I’ll give you an example.  A guy says to me the other day in an airport, “I admire you, but I’d like to see you on more than civil rights issues.”  I said, “Let me ask you a question:  what do I do?”  He said, “Well, you lead a civil rights organization.”  So what am I supposed to do?  That’s like getting on a plane and telling the pilot I’d like to see you do more than fly the plane.  That’s what I do—I’m a civil rights leader!  What is a civil rights leader <hi rend="italic">supposed</hi> to do?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That’s the same response <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ingrid_Newkirk,_co-founder_of_PETA,_on_animal_rights_and_the_film_about_her_life">Ingrid Newkirk gave in an interview</ref> when I told her people say she cares more about fighting for animals than for humans.  She responded that’s what PETA does:  give a voice to those who do not have one.  She said that criticism is like telling a homeless shelter they care more about the homeless than people who live in mansions.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  That’s exactly right!  I tell staff here and all the other cities where we have offices, don’t complain when people come in here with problems because that’s what you do.  That’s like a nurse saying, “Why do sick people come here?”  Because you work in a doctor’s office!  Why do people who are in trouble go to a lawyer’s office?  Because that’s what lawyers do.  That’s what I do:  civil rights.  So in many ways, what they consider criticism is complimenting my job.  An activist’s job is to make public civil rights issues until there can be a climate for change.  So when people get angry at me for raising these issues and making them public, well, that’s my job!  That’s what I’m <hi rend="italic">supposed</hi> to do.  If I could not get the public’s attention on an issue, then I’m not a good activist.</p>
</text>
