<text id="autogum_interview_doc1172" title="part5_Lobby groups oppose plans for EU copyright extension" shortTile="partlobby-groups" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-18" dateModified="2014-12-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lobby_groups_oppose_plans_for_EU_copyright_extension" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Becky Hogge</hi>: If you imagine every time there was a school play, the nativity play, or the works of Shakespeare, or a concert was put on by Mozart... people have been taking advantage of the public domain a lot more than they realise. There's so much that people do with the public domain every day, but they just don't realise it. This is something I've thought about for a long time: I'm not a lawyer, I'm not a creator, I'm not a programmer, and so what is it about this debate that has gotten me into it. It's this idea of what it would be like. Sound recordings are a good example: we didn't really have great sound recordings until about 50 years ago. I see this move now to extend the term in sound recordings as just one of many. After 95 years, is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RCA%20Records">RCA</ref> really going to want to give up the Beatles then? Or will we get another extension to 150 years, or to 200 years, or to 250 years? What would the world look like if everything was in perpetual copyright or in a perpetual patent? Even though we all accept that artists need to be given incentive, I think all fair humans have a natural ability to want to share knowledge. What would have happened if the invention of fire was under a perpetual patent? I think we'd all still be living in caves. I think there's actually something in the balance between keeping stuff and sharing that keeps us human and keeps us developing and civilised and that's my best argument at the moment towards the man on the street.</p>
<head id="The_fight_moves_from_the_U.K._to_Europe">The fight moves from the U.K. to Europe</head>
<p>We asked Becky Hogge to tell us the history behind this proposal from a U.K. perspective.</p>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Becky Hogge</hi>: Where this started was back in 2006... well in fact even before that, the Labour government in the U.K. made a manifesto pledge to examine the issue of copyright term extension in a previous election. What that turned into is called the Gowers review of intellectual property. It actually got the most submissions to an independent review ever. There were a lot of submissions from the recording industry, and if I remember Andrew Gowers' words specifically, he said they took the prize for the amount of submissions they got from the recording industry.</p>
<p>They were saying: we want this copyright extension now. I think what's motivating it is a golden age of recorded sounds, seminal soul, rock and roll, reggae recordings, are about to enter the public domain; the recording industry recognises it, and recognises that actually they probably didn't plan for this to happen in their own business models, they're going to lose a small percent of their income.</p>
</text>
