<text id="autogum_interview_doc233" title="CanadaVOTES: NDP candidate Max Lombardi running in Cambridge" shortTile="canadavotes-ndp-candidate" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-22" dateModified="2009-03-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_NDP_candidate_Max_Lombardi_running_in_Cambridge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>CanadaVOTES: NDP candidate Max Lombardi running in Cambridge</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 26, 2008</hi></p>
<p>On October 14, 2008, Canadians will be heading to the polls for the federal election. <hi rend="bold">New Democratic Party candidate Max Lombardi</hi> is standing for election in <hi rend="bold">the riding of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cambridge%20(electoral%20district)">Cambridge</ref></hi>. Lombardi is an information technology specialist who has lived in Cambridge for 25 years.</p>
<p>Held since 2004 by Conservative Gary Goodyear, the riding of Cambridge includes the city of Cambridge, Ontario and the Township of North Dumfries, Ontario. Also running in the riding are Gord Zeilstra (Liberal) and Scott Cosman (Green).</p>
<p>Wikinews contacted Max Lombardi, to talk about the issues facing Canadians, and what they and their party would do to address them. Wikinews is in the process of contacting every candidate, in every riding across the country, no matter their political stripe. All interviews are conducted over e-mail, and interviews are published unedited, allowing candidates to impart their full message to our readers, uninterrupted.</p>
<p>For more information, visit the campaign's official website, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#External_links">listed below</ref>.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why are you running for political office, why at the federal level, why this party, and why in this riding?</hi></p>
<p>I am running for the New Democratic Party of Canada in the riding of Cambridge because 140 straight years of Liberal-Conservative promise-breaking governments have fueled intense voter cynicism. To restore confidence in our democracy, we need a real change in direction on the bread and butter issues of the economy; the environment and health care -- a change that moves your family forward -- not backward. Cambridge has been my home for most of my life. My wife Josie and I want our community to be more prosperous, healthy and fair for our triplets and for all the citizens.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Previous to this campaign, have you been politically involved? How will you apply your previous work/volunteer/life experience to serving your constituents?</hi></p>
<p>I have served in my local school council and ran for school board trustee in 2006. I understand the jobs crisis and that JOB LOSSES HURT FAMILIES. When my previous employer MTD Products in Kitchener announced massive layoffs in 2007, it was a direct blow to my family as well as to many friends and co-workers. My family roots are deeply entrenched in the farmer and labour working class.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">As you campaign around your riding, it's likely that some issues are mentioned more often by voters, than other issues. What would you say are the three hottest topics this election, in your riding? What would you and your party do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p><list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Affordability and bread-and-butter issues:</hi> change direction on global trade deals to set standards high (not low) on wages; labour standards and environmental protection; invest in good-paying green-collars jobs of the future; we would create an independent watch dog to monitor and regulate gas prices if necessary.</item>
<item>Address climate change: set firm caps on emissions with a cap and trade system; make big polluters pay for their emissions; use the revenue to invest in new-tech environmental solutions like building and home retrofit programs.</item>
<item>Improve Health Care: train more doctors and nurses to reduce wait times; invest in innovation like modern home care; provide seniors with free drug and dental coverage.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Is there any misconceptions about you, your leader, or your party and platform?</hi></p>
<p>On the contrary, citizens are more responsive to our message than ever before.</p>
</text>
