<text id="autogum_interview_doc1130" title="part8_Dalai Lama's representative talks about China, Tibet, Shugden and the next Dalai Lama" shortTile="partdalai-lamas-representative" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-13" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dalai_Lama%27s_representative_talks_about_China%2C_Tibet%2C_Shugden_and_the_next_Dalai_Lama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s that he believes he is a reincarnation, but whether he is the whole and sum of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/13th%20Dalai%20Lama">13th Dalai Lama</ref> is another question?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes.  Yes.  Something to that effect.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have thoughts to share on the situation in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Burma">Burma</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  His Holiness issued a statement soon after the recent crackdown in which he expressed his deep concern and sadness over the violation, and he expressed solidarity with the Buddhist monks and people asking for democracy.  He appealed to the generals to refrain from using violence—they are Buddhists—and as Buddhists they should follow the teachings of Buddha and enter into meaningful dialog.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you any information on their current status?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  No, we follow whatever comes into the media very closely.  It’s a Buddhist country and historically Tibet and Burma have good relations.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s such a difficult region with many complex disputes.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  There are ethnic differences, different religions, but through democratic process things can be resolved.  Let’s look at India and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pakistan">Pakistan</ref>.  India is a huge country, so many ethnic, religious—they have the second largest Muslim population after Indonesia—but through a democratic process and the federal structure that came into being the last six years, that’s through democratic process.  Unfortunately on the Pakistan side with the same people, same culture, the political system is not fully developed and you see more ethnic problems.  With Burma if you see more democratic process I’m sure these problems will be worked out.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  All over <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Asia">Asia</ref> so many people have long-lasting conflicts and memories never seem to die.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  I think it’s a problem that is remnant of the British rule and all these new states came into existence when British rule was withdrawn.  But where democratic process came into place things are better.  In places where interest groups came into rule, they divide.   But democracy reduces special interest.</p>
<head id="Arunachal_Pradesh,_an_historically_Tibetan_area_of_India_claimed_by_China">Arunachal Pradesh, an historically Tibetan area of India claimed by China</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is your view on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arunachal%20Pradesh">Arunachal Pradesh</ref>? Is the Government-in-Exile's relative silence over the issue due more to a recognition of India as a friendly government, or does the Government-in-Exile view the area as less Tibetan than the areas controlled by China?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  We are bound by the 1914 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simla%20Convention">Simla Convention</ref> under which the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McMahon%20Line">McMahon Line</ref> was formed between India and Tibet.  It has been accepted.  Both by British India and the Tibetan government, so we are treaty bound.  At that time the Tibetan government entered into and signed that agreement.  We can’t change.  The McMahon Line is the international boundary and whatever falls on either side of that line is the territory of either India or, as of now, the People’s Republic of China (Tibet).</p>
</text>
