<text id="autogum_interview_doc1224" title="part7_The Onion: An interview with 'America's Finest News Source'" shortTile="partthe-onion-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2013-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Onion%3A_An_interview_with_%27America%27s_Finest_News_Source%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did he say that story was spot on?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  He didn’t get into too much detail, which was fortunate.  After the Iraq War we had a story about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tommy%20Franks">Tommy Franks</ref> leaves the army to focus on solo bombing projects, and he quoted to The Washington Post and others that it was his favorite news coverage ever about him.  
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  We just launched a print edition in DC this year, and the launch party was co-hosted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grover%20Norquist">Grover Norquist</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russ%20Feingold">Russ Feingold</ref>.  So if there is ever a better example of our bipartisan appeal I can’t think of it.</p></p>
<head id="The_Presidential_Seal">The Presidential Seal</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Speaking of federal issues, what is the status on the use of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Presidential%20Seal">Presidential Seal</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  The U.S. Postal Service is actually the only federal authority that governs us.  We have actually been allowed to use the Presidential Seal since [it was raised as an issue].  Our response was that we felt the federal government had much <hi rend="italic">bigger</hi> issues on their hands that the President’s counsel should be focused on.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But you actually did ask formal approval to use the seal.  Did that come through or did it just die in the water?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  We did ask for formal approval; we fundamentally weren’t aware of it at the time it was pointed out to us, but we did go back and get approval for it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So you actually received approval?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  You know, I think, uh, that they were trying to put together on the spot a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Emergency%20Management%20Agency">Federal Emergency Management Agency</ref> that week, and that might have gotten in the way.  And then was it that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scooter%20Libby">Scooter Libby</ref> got indicted?  Yeah, so I think it’s probably on the bottom of some pile in Washington, but no.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You have always asserted that you don’t need formal approval to use it in parody; that you were only asking for approval as a courtesy?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  Well, I don’t know about the legal side of it, but parody is generally covered and protected by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First%20Amendment">First Amendment</ref> and it is clear what our editorial mission is to our readers, so we did not feel it conflicted with that in any way, so we felt the First Amendment protected us to use it.
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  And whoever was in charge of filing that paperwork has probably since resigned from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20White%20House">White House</ref>, so…</p></p>
<head id="The_Onion's_readership">The Onion's readership</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is your readership?  Since you are a free weekly without hard subscribers, and then you have the Internet site and podcasts, how do you determine your readership?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  Our website has never been more popular.  Just on <hi rend="italic">The Onion’s</hi> website in October we had over five million unique users as measured by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Omniture">Omniture</ref>, which is our in-house measurement system.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20AV%20Club">The AV Club</ref>, which is an entertainment site owned by <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi>, had over a million for the first time.  So our readership has never been stronger.  In print we put out 720,000 newspapers every week, and that readership is much harder to manage.  Generally speaking, it is assumed that at least three people read each issue on average, so it’s over 2,000,000 there, conservatively.  Every joke that gets written in <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi>—sorry, every news story—is probably read by 7,000,000 people, somewhere around there.</p>
</text>
