<text id="autogum_interview_doc373" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Australian Statistician Brian Pink" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-19" dateModified="2008-04-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Statistician_Brian_Pink" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Australian Statistician Brian Pink</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 7, 2008</hi></p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australian%20Bureau%20of%20Statistics">Australian Bureau of Statistics</ref> is responsible for some of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref>'s largest surveys, including the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Census%20in%20Australia">Census of Population and Housing</ref>, held every five years. At its head is the Australian Statistician. The current Statistician, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brian%20Pink">Brian Pink</ref>, started in his position on March 5, 2007, following the retirement of predecessor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dennis%20Trewin">Dennis Trewin</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> recently caught up with Brian Pink to talk with him about his first year in the position, as well as his previous tenure as Government Statistician at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Statistics%20New%20Zealand">Statistics New Zealand</ref>, and the state of mathematical education in Australia.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WikiNews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Good afternoon.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Brian Pink</hi>: Good afternoon.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : And congratulations on spending a year as Australian Statistician.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: Yes, it's gone very quickly. <hi rend="italic">(laughs)</hi></p>
<head id="Statistical_services_in_Australia_and_New_Zealand">Statistical services in Australia and New Zealand</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : So firstly, just for the benefit of Wikinews readers, can you give a bit of a background as to what the Bureau of Statistics does, and what your responsibilities are as the Statistician?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: OK, so the Bureau of Statistics is the national statistical agency here in Australia, and we provide a very wide range of statistical services to the Australian and state and territory governments, to business, to community more generally, and we cover a very broad range of economic, social, population and more recently environmental statistics, and a lot of analysis and research around various themes and topics within those general domains.</p>
<p>And my role is as Chief Executive of the organisation, so I have management roles that are associated with running a big complex organisation - a little under three thousand people and a budget of something around three million dollars a year - and I also provide the leadership from a statistical policy point of view for official statistics in Australia, and of course I operate under the authority of the Statistics Act, so I have statutory responsibilities as well under the Statistics Act to meet.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : You used the word "leading", and I know that in 2005 the Bureau's mission statement changed from "providing ... a national statistical service" to "leading ... a national statistical service". So what does it actually mean to be a statistical leader over a statistical provider?</p>
<hi rend="bold">... there was a strong support [...] for the ABS to take a stronger leadership role ...</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—On the results of the Allen Review</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: I think what we saw there was a change that reflected the results of a review that was undertaken, known as the "Allen Review", that was undertaken as the role of the ABS was playing in statistics in Australia and official statistics, and talking to a very broad range of our stakeholders, both public and private. With the feedback that came from that review, one very key thing that came back was that there was a strong support, and in fact almost a demand from quite a lot of people who were involved with the statistical work of the nation, for the ABS to take a stronger leadership role, and that change in the wording that occurred back in 2005 actually reflected the decision the organisation took, and the Statistician at the time, that they would in fact look at taking a stronger leadership role in official statistical activities in Australia. We had a statutory responsibility to co-ordinate the statistical activities of government agencies, but this was taking a broader leadership role in a whole range of dimensions for all of the different players that contribute to statistics in Australia, particularly from Government.</p>
</text>
