<text id="autogum_interview_doc1141" title="part0_Canada's Davenport (Ward 18) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-davenport" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Davenport_%28Ward_18%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Canada's Davenport (Ward 18) city council candidates speak</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 3, 2006</hi></p>
<p>On November 13, Torontoians will be heading to the polls to vote for their ward's councillor and for mayor. Among Toronto's ridings is Davenport (Ward 18). Two candidates responded to Wikinews' requests for an interview. This ward's candidates include Lloyd Ferguson, <hi rend="bold">Adam Giambrone</hi> (incumbent), Nha Le, <hi rend="bold">James McMillan</hi>, and Simon Wookey.</p>
<p>For more information on the election, read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto%20municipal%20election,%202006">Toronto municipal election, 2006</ref>.</p>
<head id="Adam_Giambrone_(incumbent)">Adam Giambrone (incumbent)</head>
<p>29-year-old Adam Giambrone is the incumbent councillor for Ward 18, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Davenport%20(electoral%20district)">Davenport</ref>, Ontario Canada.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi></p>
<p>1. Some of our neighbourhoods have struggled with crime and community safety for more than a generation.  We have begun to change that, but there's still much to do.</p>
<p>2. Our streets and public spaces have cleaner. We must redouble the effort to make them beautiful and attractive--and yes, cleaner--so people will use them.</p>
<p>3. The people of our city depend on reliable infrastructure--both physical and social--and we move by transit.  We must continue to protect and invest in these priorities if we are to build a city we can continue to be proud of.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Continued investment in crime reduction and safer neighbourhoods.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> For our government to work, it needs direction from problem-solvers with a strong dedication to public service and accountability, and an energetic optimism about the good things we can do together. I admire the work of these people, and I have a strong drive to contribute in the same way.</p>
<p>When these people have not provided this kind of leadership, I have considered it my responsibility to take up the challenge.</p>
<p>I have also felt the need to have the voices of younger people represented at City Hall. Being the youngest member of Council, I have encouraged other young leaders to take up the challenge of political responsibility as well.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I've lived in this ward all my life and feel a strong personal attachment to the people here.  The sense of community here is very strong, but we have not always been well represented at City Council in the past, and we know it.  I want to continue to give it the high level of care and attention it rightly deserves.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Before I was the city councillor, I was actively involved in community groups and our parks associations.  Our previous councillor was not responsive to the community, so with research and hard work with others, I was able to provide the kind of service we were lacking.</p>
</text>
