<text id="autogum_interview_doc980" title="part5_Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian presidential candidate Wayne Allyn Root" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-03" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Libertarian_presidential_candidate_Wayne_Allyn_Root" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">How would you handle the situation in Iraq?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mr. Root:</hi> There are no good or simple answers for Iraq. It's a tough situation. We shouldn't be there. It was the wrong war. We won Afghanistan- then we made a big mistake by adding Iraq to the equation. Now we're losing ground in Afghanistan too. We should have stayed focused on the only true enemy- the Taliban, Al Queda and the terrorists. We should have won big in Afghaistan and then gone after the remaining terrorists- not Saddam. He was just a distraction. An evil, cruel, murdering dictator who bragged of having weapons of mass destruction- so it's good he's gone. But nonetheless Iraq was the wrong war at the wrong time. Now we've spent a trillion dollars and lost thousands of lives on a big mistake. But we're there. I believe it would e a mistake to turn tail and run. I agreed with the recommendation of the Generals on the ground- to build up a troop surge. We did and it's been a great success. The enemy is on the run. I'm proud that even though I didn't support the war, I supported the surge. We were correct. It worked. Now let's use the success to declare victory and get out as soon as possible. That won't be tomorrow, but it can realistically be 12 to 18 months from now. Let's give the Iraqi government time to build up its own security, police and military- and then “get the hell out of Dodge.” That's the best answer I can come up with for a difficult, disastrous and complicated problem with no easy way out. I think my support of the surge was reasonable, fair and commonsense. My compromise solution above is reasonable, fair and based on commonsense. It's about the best choice we have right now.</p>
<p>But there are some important lessons to be learned here. All is not lost. A tragedy becomes a positive if you can learn from your mistakes. I call it “The Black Box Theory.” What good could come f a plane crash where 100 passengers die? Actually, a lot of good. If we recover the “black box” and study it, we can learn from the tragedy and prevent millions of future deaths. Those 100 victims suddenly become heroes. They didn't die in vain. Their deaths will save many others in the future. We can turn Iraq into a “black box.” I've learned that “Nation Building” is a failure. We can't force Democracy down the throats of other countries. We should mind our own business. Most importantly, we can't afford to be the world's policeman.</p>
</text>
