<text id="autogum_interview_doc750" title="part2_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Libertarian candidate Larry Stevens, Kitchener-Conestoga" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-04" dateModified="2008-11-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Libertarian_candidate_Larry_Stevens%2C_Kitchener-Conestoga" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>We have to stop listening to the lies of our politicians and governments and we definitely have to stop letting them run more and more of our lives. We have to start analyzing problems to find out what's really causing them, and then working cooperatively to remove the causes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>The top priority should be to end government coercion and only allow force to be used to defend a person or their property. Those who use threats or force offensively should be made to compensate their victim(s) for the harm done to them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>There is no such think as a fair tax level. All taxes are theft.</p>
<p>If a government agency offers a service they should charge for that service the same as any private service provider would. In addition, anyone who wished to offer a service in competition with the government agency should be allowed to do so.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>To stimulate job creation, the provincial government should get out of the way and allow the private sector to create jobs without government interference.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>I'm for MMP voting as it decreases the chances of a single party (and hence a few individuals) from having free reign in our government.</p>
<p>However, I feel MMP should be implemented with far fewer seats. Increasing the number of seats is part of the major political parties' plan to make this alternative unpopular. If they oppose it so strongly, it's obviously a very good idea, so I'm all for it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does “new media” play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>The more alternatives available the better. Our primary objective in this campaign is to let voters know that: there is an alternative to ever more government, higher taxes and more regulations controlling their lives, and that this alternative will make all aspects of their lives better as it will bring more prosperity, less crime, a cleaner environment and all the other good things most people want.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your  this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</hi></p>
<p>No government decisions are beneficial. Most are a costly nuisance. The rest are harmful.</p>
</text>
