<text id="autogum_interview_doc1171" title="part4_Lobby groups oppose plans for EU copyright extension" shortTile="partlobby-groups" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-18" dateModified="2014-12-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lobby_groups_oppose_plans_for_EU_copyright_extension" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>Are the record companies sitting on their back catalogues because they can no longer earn the same income in the digital age? I think if they are doing that, I credited them with more intelligence than that. Because number one: what's the point of having copyright when everyone is infringing them? It doesn't matter if we have one record of the Beatles or if we have 500 records if everyone shares the one copy of the Beatles that we have already. So I would imagine that's not why they're doing this. And number two, and I think more fundamentally, actually what people inside the industry that I speak to are realising, is if they continue to push this side of the bargain, all they do is to serve to grow people's disrespect for the law even more, such that nobody wants to respect copyright any more. If we see copyright as a law that is written on behalf of the recording industry for politicians, then -and this is not my point, this is Andrew Gowers' point- you have to make the law something that people can understand and respect. You do that by making the balance right. Soon the recording industry, or some of them will see that if they continue doing this, they're going to hurt themselves more.</p>
<p>We also noted that the term public domain seems to have a more profound meaning in the United States, and that many Europeans don't even know the term.</p>
<hi rend="bold">After 95 years, is RCA really going to want to give up the Beatles then? Or will we get another extension to 150 years, or to 200 years, or to 250 years? What would the world look like if everything was in perpetual copyright or in a perpetual patent? What would have happened if the invention of fire was under a perpetual patent? I think we'd all still be living in caves.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Becky Hogge, Open Rights Group</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eddan Katz</hi>: European civilisation had a lot of innovation and creativity before the legal mechanisms of copyright and patents were produced. There's been a long history of productivity, innovation and creativity that has happened without a specific exclusive rights system. Talking about culture in Europe and that depth of history: the degree of which people do create and write on the shoulders of giants, they work off the great works that we know in history, build off of what was before, reference it and build on it, and that's what makes it meaningful -that's something that I think is particularly something to defend in Europe. You said that the terms public domain are foreign to Europeans: I'm actually trying to point out that the public domain existed in Europe before the concept of America existed.</p>
</text>
