<text id="autogum_interview_doc811" title="part4_Frank Messina: An interview with the &amp;apos;Mets Poet&amp;apos;" shortTile="partfrank-messina" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-03" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Frank_Messina%3A_An_interview_with_the_%27Mets_Poet%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  I've never been for any war.  I try to avoid altercation on any level, be it emotional, physical, or political.  But there are some wars I think that are necessary.  History has shown this.  Was this one necessary?  I don't know.  Twenty years from now we'll have to figure that out.  I hope that we've all learned something from it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is your feeling toward the Iraq War now?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi> It's a mess.  It's a mess.  We went in to get a job done, get Hussein out of there, liberate the Iraqi people as was dictated in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20Liberation%20Act">1998 Liberation Act</ref> that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph%20Lieberman">Senator Lieberman</ref> helped draft and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill%20Clinton">President Clinton</ref> put out there.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20W.%20Bush">President Bush</ref>, Congress and the American people supported going in there.  I'm not going to backtrack: I did support going in there, and even as an artist and a poet, and as a freak, I made a decision, that it was time to take this guy out.  I spoke with many Iraqi Americans who live in my neighborhood who also supported that.  Lebanese and Iranian friends I have supported it.  One of my childhood friends, Adel Nehme, came out of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beirut">Beirut, Lebanon</ref> around 1972.  We met in kindergarten and we've been friends ever since.  He was someone who escaped that turmoil.  His family brought him to New Jersey specifically to pull him out of that hell, like the way my father took us out of the gangland hell of the South Bronx.  Like any father would do, to protect his family.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you still feel the Iraq War is protecting us, and that the original reasons you supported it are still valid?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  It's a mess.  The original reasons?  Yes.  Looking back, hindsight is always 20/20.  Unlike many artists, I have vocally supported the war.  Many artists who support this war won't say that.  Ron Whitehead is a dear friend.  We have mutual respect for each other but we disagree on a lot of issues.  Nevertheless, there's only one man I want fighting in the trenches of life with me, and that's Ron Whitehead.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you look at the state of the world, what five descriptors come to mind?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  Chaos.  Yearning for peace.  Confusion.  Desperation.  Hope.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And are you hopeful?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where do you get that hope from?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  My faith in the human spirit.  I think people are inherently good.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe%20Benigno">Joe Benigno</ref> said, "No one would question a poet writing about love for a woman, but when you’re a fan of a team, the emotional attachment is even stronger, because women come and go, but your team never changes."  Do you think that analogy really holds, because you are attracted to the Mets, and you are attracted to women, and the players on both of those teams in your life change. </hi></p>
</text>
