<text id="autogum_interview_doc398" title="Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate John Ogilvie, Carleton—Mississippi Mills" shortTile="ontario-votes--interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-07" dateModified="2007-12-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_Party_candidate_John_Ogilvie%2C_Carleton%E2%80%94Mississippi_Mills" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate John Ogilvie, Carleton—Mississippi Mills</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, October 7, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">John Ogilvie</hi> is running for the Green Party of Ontario in the Ontario provincial election, in the Carleton—Mississippi Mills riding. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref>' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>"History is made by those who show up" (Benjamin Disraeli)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I have no political experience, but I have built several tech businesses in the past decade and attracted CAD5 million in venture capital to these firms.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>The incumbent, Norm Sterling, is a political survivor. He has been elected eight time for a total of thirty years. Nobody really knows why.</p>
<p>I am the only businessman and entrepreneur among the candidates, and I have a vision and a plan. My opponents have their party briefing books.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>Catching up to California on emissions-standards and other pollution/climate measures. I refuse to have Arnold come up here again and lecture us on how California is leading N. America on environmental issues.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>Local property taxes are rising way too fast for value delivered.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>By helping our local tech community lead the next global tech boom: green-tech.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>We support it 100%. Without it, in the past, our province has lurched hard to the left or to the right with each election, like a car with only two gears, reverse and forward. MMP would smooth out these destructive swings.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does "new media" play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>I have helped two dozen Green candidates put up a web presence (<ref target="http://vote-green.ca">http://vote-green.ca</ref>). I blog every couple of days, and people seem to enjoy it. Facebook is a waste of time. Youtube is good, but it is very time-consuming to produce really good content.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</hi></p>
<p>The cancellation of the Labour-Sponsored Investment Fund tax credit, without consultation, put the boot to a recovering tech startup industry. This was very harmful.</p>
<p>I have been campaigning too long - I can't think of anything good to say about the Liberal govt:-) </p>
</text>
