<text id="autogum_interview_doc1286" title="part11_Edmund White on writing, incest, life and Larry Kramer" shortTile="partedmund-white" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-08" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edmund_White_on_writing%2C_incest%2C_life_and_Larry_Kramer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why did you start?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  My doctor advised me to because my counts had dropped below 500, or something.  They had always been around 700 for years and years.  Suddenly it seemed like they were drifting faster and faster down.  I thought if I took meds I would have more energy, and I did.  I used to take two naps a day.</p>
<head id="On_Edmund_White">On Edmund White</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How would you like to die if you could choose your own death?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  A heart attack in my sleep.  That’s the most beautiful death.  You’re not conscious of it, the pain, and you’re gone in a second.  It’s no fuss for anybody else, either.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What about dying consciously makes you uncomfortable?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Nothing, except that usually if you’re conscious you have a long, lingering disease.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You could be hit by a train.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  That’s fine, but I that would be more painful than dying of a heart attack.  Maybe not, that might be good.  A lot of times when I’m in a storm in a plane, I think I wouldn’t mind if it goes down.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you believe in a higher power?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  No, not at all.  I’m glad people do believe who are in the recovery programs.  I was an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alcoholic">alcoholic</ref>—I guess you have to say I <hi rend="italic">am</hi> an alcoholic—and stopped drinking in 1983 and I never went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alcoholics%20Anonymous">AA</ref> or anything.  I was living in Europe where it was awfully hard to find AA in English, or even in French.  It just isn’t part of their mores.  It was very easy for me to stop.  It was impossible for me to moderate, and very easy to stop.  Same thing with smoking.  I smoked four packs a day for twenty-some years, and from one day to the next nothing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If you’re going to sin, you’re going to fuck the devil?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Well, I think I’m very compulsive.  So it’s not like I’m defiantly smoking four packs a day or defiantly drinking three bottles of wine, but it’s just what happens when I start doing those things.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What’s your favorite curse word?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi> I don’t curse very much and everybody agrees with that.  Don’t you agree with that Michael?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michael:</hi>  His favorite curse word is fuck.  There’s a lot of fucking.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you ever altered your opinion of somebody based upon their star sign?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  If they brought up their star sign that would alter my opinion of them. [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What would you find a bigger turn-off in bed:  somebody who was flatulent or somebody who spoke in a baby voice?</hi></p>
</text>
