<text id="autogum_interview_doc544" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Jeff Jacobsen, creator of LisaMcPherson.org" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-12" dateModified="2012-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jeff_Jacobsen%2C_creator_of_LisaMcPherson.org" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: Again, critics aren't (I hope) persecuting anyone. It's to inform. I've seen in several of the Anonymous protest videos where Anons say they're not there to ridicule the beliefs but to complain about their actions. That's a correct stance.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : It is claimed by some anti-Church of Scientology campaigns that some Scientology doctrine is flawed or inconsistent, could not the same be said of the arguments put forward by those campaigns. (or indeed the ideological doctrines of any number of other religions)?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: I'm a Christian. I actually like reading about the inconsistencies of my religion, so I can understand it better.  If any organization promotes some belief or teaching, then it's fine to point out inconsistencies. In fact, it's good. I just happen to know a lot about Scientology, so that's what I deal with.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : The German Government continues to pursue it's investigation into Church of Scientology, why should law enforcement waste time on such investigations?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: Obviously, they don't think they're wasting their time. If there is evidence of illegality, it should be pursued.  Remember Operation Snow White, for example. Scientology railed against the FBI as being anti-religion and bigoted when the raids happened. Yet the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Bureau%20of%20Investigation">FBI</ref> turned out to be right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : One aspect of Scientology, is a rejection of modern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychiatry">psychiatry</ref>, would you not agree that even the best of shrinks can still get things badly wrong? (even when implementing so called ethical practices)?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: Psychiatry definitely has problems. And if people think that's something that should be researched, great. But I deal with Scientology.  They reject psychiatry so much that they made a video of themselves blowing up psychiatry with a grenade. Their goal is to eradicate psychiatry. As a whole group, not just get rid of the bad practices. That's wrong.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : When an organization faces an ideological challenge from specific individuals, is it not reasonable to have sufficient information to mount a robust defense?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: Is this referring to Scientology defending itself I guess? Hopefully, the information being used in defense is correct information. And sure, I've been on radio with a Scientologist before. I enjoy it when they debate. But that's very seldom, unfortunately. If you could set up a debate I'd love it</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : How does campaigning against Church of Scientology materially differ from '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hate%20crime">hate crimes</ref>' as defined by many laws?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: Critics of Scientology are more like whistleblowers or muckraking journalists. We're not doing it out of hate. We're doing it out of concern for the truth. People get hurt so we try to prevent it. Ted Kennedy eulogized his brother Robert saying "he saw a wrong, and tried to right it."  I think that's what critics are doing. It's not a hate crime to expose wrong.</p>
</text>
