<text id="autogum_interview_doc921" title="part6_Scientology protest group celebrates founder's birthday worldwide" shortTile="partscientology-protest" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-05" dateModified="2019-02-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology_protest_group_celebrates_founder%27s_birthday_worldwide" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>We are taking part to demonstrate our beliefs that freedom of knowledge and information are basic human rights. Most of us have also done our own research regarding the CoS, and come to the conclusion that it is a malign cult, that harms its members and tries to subvert public opinion to further its own ends.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> How many people do you expect to attend the protests worldwide?</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Anon. 1</hi>: No real way of knowing until the day and head counts are done, but we are hoping to exceed Feb 10th due to a lot of Anonymous members not turning up due to fear of retaliation, laziness, or generally not being sure of what to do. Videos of the Feb 10th have shown how peaceful yet fun the protests are, so we are hoping to do quite well on the 15th.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Why are you protesting against CoS?</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Anon. 1</hi>: We are protesting the CoS, not the religious doctrine itself. Whilst many of us may disagree with some of the faith's tenants, we believe freedom of religion is every person's right. However the CoS uses this sacred human right to perform immoral and illegal actions, whilst labeling anyone who criticises it as Religious bigots, terrorists, or criminals.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Many people consider some of the actions taken by anonymous illegal. Do you think your actions are justified?</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Anon. 2</hi>:The problem with this question is the way Anonymous is organised, as it isn't organised. It's just a collection of people from various corners of the Internet. If someone makes a threat to the CoS and says they're Anonymous there's nothing we can do to stop them saying that, Anonymous doesn't have a membership card.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Anon. 1</hi>: Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Manchester Gallery</hi></p>
<list type="unordered">
<item style="width: 155px;">A close up map of the protest location.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">The protest location, on a map showing a larger area.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">The protest location, on a map showing much of the UK.</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">The message you get when trying to view the Manchester section of Anonymous' website (with Camino as web browser).</item>
</list>
<head id="New_York,_New_York"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York,_New_York">New York</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref></head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Photographer: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Rankun">rankun</ref></hi></p>
<head id="Buffalo,_New_York"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Buffalo,_New_York">Buffalo</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref></head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Correspondent: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:DragonFire1024">DragonFire1024</ref></hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>(<ref target="http://youtube.com/user/buffaloanon">Videos of the protest in Buffalo</ref>)</item></list>
<p>Throughout the day, nearly 100 protesters including ex-Sea Org Scientology member Chuck Beatty, turned out in Buffalo with signs and enthusiasm. It was a cold and foggy day with temperatures in the low 30's (F) which is significantly warmer than the previous February 10 protests that drew only about 50 people. People filled Main Street across from the Church in a line which extended an entire city block. A radio was on hand playing 'Rick Roll' and also the audio recording of the Scientology interview with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tom_Cruise">Tom Cruise</ref>.</p>
<p>The day started off with an off duty Buffalo Police detective instructing the crowd to protest peacefully. The detective, who was identified to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref> only as 'Detective Tim' then immediately told protesters to remove masks that could be considered threatening. Scarves were allowed as it was a cold day, but bandannas were not permitted to be worn.</p>
</text>
