<text id="autogum_interview_doc1290" title="part1_Wikinews interviews the Wikimania 2010 Poland bid promoter" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-12-28" dateModified="2019-01-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_the_Wikimania_2010_Poland_bid_promoter" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<hi rend="bold">We can say we have a great community potential here.</hi>
<list type="unordered"><item>Poland is not exactly small - of course we cannot be compared to the USA, India, or China, but we are not a small country either. Let's remember that according to the old way of presenting the Wikipedia language editions' ranking, we were the fourth edition. Even after committing a change to this ranking system, we are still in the first ten. Therefore, we can say we have a great community potential here. Moreover, other Polish Wikimedia projects also place themselves within first tens of respective projects.</item></list>
<p>Speaking about people involved – so far we have only few, and sometimes I lament about that. Every next person is a possibility of sending few mails, talking with other people, additional pair of eyes looking at the offer, some ideas, contacts, knowledge. That's why <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pl:Wikipedysta:Patrol110">Patrol110</ref> has <hi rend="italic">spammed</hi> Pomeranian Wikipedians, so they could get involved, and so am I giving a weight to this: we need more people. Especially if our offer will win, but then I believe in another famous Polish "national spurt".</p>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold">  Were there, in Gdańsk, already some world-wide conferences? Did the city manage to organize them?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">I do have a hope that we will get a world-wide coverage thanks to the Wikimania</hi>
<list type="unordered"><item>On December 5 and 6, 2008, the 25th anniversary of awarding president <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lech%20Wałęsa">Lech Wałęsa</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nobel%20Peace%20Prize">Nobel Peace Prize</ref> was held. Furthermore, it was held <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi> inside the Polish Baltic Philharmonic, which we propose as a place of the Wikimania 2010 conference. It was an event with over one thousand attendants from all over the world, and the city, in my humble opinion, did manage to organize this very well. The mayor of the city, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paweł%20Adamowicz">Paweł Adamowicz</ref>, has confirmed it, by saying <hi rend="italic">After successful celebrations of 25th anniversary of awarding Lech Wałęsa with the Nobel Peace Prize we see that we can organize big events. [...] Ołowianka does its job as a big congressional place perfectly. [...] Gdańsk will, once again, get a world-wide coverage</hi> in Dziennik Bałtycki interview. I do have a hope that we will get a world-wide coverage thanks to the Wikimania.</item></list>
<p>The City organizes a lot of cultural and trade events. There are Gdańsk International Fair, St. Dominik Fair, Shakespeare Festival, Good Humor Festival. We should also not forget other parts of the Tricity: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sopot">Sopot</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gdynia">Gdynia</ref> which are also rich in cultural events.</p>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold">  Lately Poland tried to get a bid for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European%20Institute%20of%20Innovation%20and%20Technology">European Institute of Innovation and Technology</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euro%202012">Euro 2012</ref>. Both actions have brought a large government support. How is it this time?</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>We've contacted the city's authorities. After a meeting with representatives of the Mayor's Promotion and Chancellery Department we have got assurance about supporting our actions, what was confirmed by Mayor's letter sent to us. The representatives assure us about their support all the time. They even have made an initial reservation of both buildings for July 9-11, 2010. They also offer an organizational support, which will be extremely important in case or city is chosen.</item></list>
</text>
