<text id="autogum_interview_doc1401" title="part5_Interview with gay marriage movement founder Evan Wolfson" shortTile="partinterview-gay" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-29" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_gay_marriage_movement_founder_Evan_Wolfson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are too many resources going toward marriage fights?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  That’s completely untrue.  To the contrary, the work to win the freedom to marry, particularly in some of states that are primary battlegrounds right now, is under-funded.  We need more resources to go to winning public opinion.  I also don’t believe that money goes to one fight done right takes away from other fights we care about.  I think when we do one fight right our movement’s work rises collectively.  Gay people should not have to choose which is more important to them:  their love or their job.  That’s a false choice.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Some argue that marriage fights are "too much, too soon" and that it hurts the other fights; that it causes a backlash.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  If you look at the successes of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2007%20in%20LGBT%20rights">this year</ref>, we have won more non-discrimination measures, we have won more protections for transgender people, we have won more—or at least as many—gains for youth protection this year than any other year in our movement.  All of it fueled by and accelerated by the marriage work and the discussions it engenders about gay people and our common humanity.  That helps move the benchmarks about what is fair.  Richard Kim and some of the others--not all--but some of the others have a false choice framing that continually undermines the common effort.  Many of the goals that they support I also support.  That said, I don’t think they speak for everybody that signed that statement, and the proof is that it went out there and went nowhere.  Meanwhile, those of us who feel differently continue to move forward and rack gains for the movement, including, for example, the win in Iowa just a few weeks ago.</p>
<head id="The_Iowa_and_Maryland_decisions">The Iowa and Maryland decisions</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Was it a win in Iowa, or was it a brief respite?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  It was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Same-sex%20marriage%20in%20Iowa">judge in Iowa finding</ref> that the denial of couples and families in Iowa of the freedom to marry has to change and end, and that same-sex couples should have the same freedom to marry as different sexed couples.  That’s a win.  It’s not a final win, because the case is being appealed.  But just a few years ago if people were asked if we could get a judge in Iowa to strike down the exclusion from marriage, right there in the heartland, I think most people would have said we couldn’t.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Last week, Maryland's Court of Appeals became the latest high court, after New York, Washington and New Jersey, to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Same-sex%20marriage%20in%20Maryland">refuse to grant marriage rights</ref> to gay couples.  What’s your reaction to the decision?  There haven’t been many gay marriage gains recently.</hi></p>
</text>
