<text id="autogum_interview_doc1363" title="part1_Teräsbetoni frontman J. Ahola on representing Finland at Eurovision 2008 & more" shortTile="partterasbetoni-frontman" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-03-26" dateModified="2017-05-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ter%C3%A4sbetoni_frontman_J._Ahola_on_representing_Finland_at_Eurovision_2008_%26_more" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Which artists would you say inspired you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> We all have our inspiration. I can’t tell who have inspired other band members, but I’ve always been inspired by the hard rock bands of the seventies: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deep%20Purple">Deep Purple</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rainbow%20(band)">Rainbow</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uriah%20Heep">Uriah Heep</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black%20Sabbath">Black Sabbath</ref>… you know, all the 70’s classics. From the eighties bands like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dio">Dio</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manowar">Manowar</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helloween">Helloween</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accept">Accept</ref> have been on my CD- player. Nowadays I’m inspired just by good music. No matter what kind of music it is, if it sounds great.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Did the early reaction on the Internet surprise you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> It sure did. We knew we had something special on our hands, but there’s always something special somewhere all the time, you know. We had this “not-so-pro”-looking site with a picture of us and three demo songs…and that was enough! All the basic pieces were so fit, that nothing else was needed. And of course there was also this “Are these guys serious?”-thing going on. It still is.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">When you made your debut releases you became an instant hit in Finland. What was that like for you at the time, and how is it now, still being a big success there?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Well, you always tend to think that when you hit big, your life changes and everything is cool and crazy. But to us it really didn’t change. After our first hit song “Taivas Lyö Tulta” reigned the air, we were still playing in the small clubs with low prices. I guess many facets believed that we were just a fucking joke. It took some time for the gig organizers to realize that people wanted to see and hear us live. Anyway, it was all clear when we visited summer festivals and got huge audiences. Since then it has been pretty steady. </p>
<p>Now with all this Eurovision stuff and publicity it’s much more bigger than it was with our first hit and first album. Of course we aren’t newbies to success and publicity now, so we take it causually. None of us really love being some kind of small celebs, but what we like is playing our music to our fans that never seem to let us down. It’s great to meet them after gig and have few beers. So, if publicity is required for that, we’ll accept it happily. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Some people have described your music as "corny" or "camp". How do you respond to that? Would you agree with the view by some people that much of what you do is in fact a parody?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Let’s put it this way. If we would sing in English, that kind of thinking would be much less common. The problem seems to be the fact, that most of the people actually seem to understand our lyrics and they think that we can’t be serious with this stuff. Hell, thousands of bands do the same thing in other language and nobody’s laughing. Of course we have fun when play live or give interviews, but when we write new songs and record them, it’s all real and true.</p>
</text>
