<text id="autogum_interview_doc874" title="part14_Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-22" dateModified="2014-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_World_Wide_Web_co-inventor_Robert_Cailliau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>What we need to clarify is where the rights and duties are.  As guide we still have <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles%20de%20Secondat,%20baron%20de%20Montesquieu">Montesquieue</ref>.  Furthermore I have been pleading for years now for an "internet driving licence".  Last week I heard something similar said in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British%20House%20of%20Commons">British House of Commons</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: Wikipedia says the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/semantic%20web">semantic web</ref> "derives from W3C director Sir Tim Berners-Lee's vision of the Web as a universal medium for data, information, and knowledge exchange," yet you're not a fan of the semantic web, right? Is that because the semantic web will have as a result that "our daily lives will be handled by machines talking to machines"? Or, are you in favour of a spread of protocols for different types of transactions and data?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: A difficult question.  I would like to have a good semantic web.  But I think that the possibilities for abuse and misleading are greater with a semantic web (Tim agreed with that when I submitted the problem to him, but he is a steady believer in the goodness of humanity).</p>
<p>It's a theme that runs through this interview:  whom can you trust and how do you make the rules that will keep "problematic behaviour" within bounds?  Only a world-wide convention can help and we are far away from it.</p>
<hi rend="bold">It's also a little early to use intelligent machinery. ... You have no idea how "half witted" machines can be. ... Maybe here too we should think and experiment first before we let the beast loose!</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Robert Cailliau</p>
<p>It's also a little early to use intelligent machinery.  Before we reach artificial intelligence we need to cross the desert of the half-witted machines.  And you have no idea how "half witted" machines can be.</p>
<p>My attitude towards the semantic web is also liked to the remark that we went too fast:  maybe here too we should think and experiment first before we let the beast loose!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: Can you predict the future of the internet? Are you optimistic, or will it be "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Matrix">The Matrix</ref>, but worse"?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: Matrix but worse.  Flight from reality is an unavoidable side effect of our brain structures. Since thousands of years people prefer to listen to fairy tales than face the boring realities.  Still I think Web 2.0 is a good trend: blogs, Wikipedia, rings, all these achievements come from simple people sitting behind their home computers who share with others what they experience, and above all learn from others! This learning outside school is the biggest strength of the web and most hopegiving.</p>
<head id="Final_question">Final question</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: You've worked at CERN for 33 years: miss it? How do you spend your days now? Do you spend a lot of time on the internet? In which projects are you still involved?</p>
</text>
