<text id="autogum_interview_doc1066" title="part2_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Progessive Conservative candidate Tyler Currie, Trinity-Spadina" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-01" dateModified="2007-11-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Progessive_Conservative_candidate_Tyler_Currie%2C_Trinity-Spadina" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><list type="ordered"><item>Health Care. Nowhere has Dalton’s broken promises affected peoples’ lives more than in health care. Saying the ‘health tax’ was going to health care was his first irresponsible doing, as that money just went to a general tax revenue stream. Then he spent $2-million more on an advertisement to say that wait times were decreasing…only to have the Auditor General and the Ad Standards Council of Canada tell him to take the advertisement off the air because it was false and misleading advertising.  He said he’s hire 8,000 nurses, and then barely reached half of that…but still spun the numbers to mislead the public some more. This is unacceptable. We will put $8.5-billion more into health care, hiring nurses and operating seven nurse-led clinics in the province. We will implement a comprehensive doctor recruitment strategy to ensure that more Ontarians have access to a family physician (the number of physicians accepting new patients has dropped 50% since the Liberals took office). We will invest $100-million into both Long-Term Care and Home Care so that people have the dignity to live their lives in comfort, so they can get the urgent care they need, and so that their families are at peace knowing their loved ones are looked after.  Leadership matters in this province, and nowhere is it more evident that we have been lacking it than in the vital area of health care.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>To begin the removal of Dalton McGuinty’s regressive, punitive health tax.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>Absolutely not. There are two issues here. One is that property assessments are rising at an absurd level, which is why we propose to cap them at 5%. Secondly, Toronto is using this property tax revenue to pay for services that go above and beyond what a municipality should be in charge of. We look forward to the provincial-municipal review to be presented in December so that a John Tory government can upload services off of the municipalities so that these property tax dollars aren’t spread so thin.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>We need to make this province attractive to invest in once again. Manufacturers struggle under escalating energy costs. 140,000 well-paying manufacturing jobs have been lost. The CD Howe Institute cites Ontario’s tax system as the worst in the country in terms of stimulating an economy. We will remove Dalton’s Capital Tax that stifles job and business growth. We will provide incentives for business to invest in our province, as opposed to the Liberal strategy which includes tripling taxes for a diamond mine that described the action as being something they’d see in a third world country. There are many reasons why we are dead last in the country in economic growth, and all of them are tied directly to the mismanagement of the Dalton McGuinty government.  Fair taxing, reliable energy, and real economic leadership is required in Ontario, and John Tory, a man who has experience as the head of a multi-billion dollar company, is the one to provide just that.</p>
</text>
