<text id="autogum_interview_doc1312" title="part9_Wikinews interviews former Salt Lake City mayor and 2012 presidential candidate Rocky Anderson" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-12-17" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Salt_Lake_City_mayor_and_2012_presidential_candidate_Rocky_Anderson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><p>So, Jon Huntsman is a bright, good man. We differ on a lot of things: I differ with him on offshore drilling, I differ with him on the keystone pipeline, on drilling in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arctic%20National%20Wildlife%20Refuge">Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</ref>. But I think Jon, especially having served as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Ambassador%20to%20China">U.S. ambassador to China</ref> understands all the amazing progress <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref> has made in the area of green technology. China is just beating us in every possible way when it comes to green technology. They’re producing more than half of world’s solar panels, they’re producing more than half of the world’s wind turbines. Now, they’re incorporating these green technologies in their buildings and they’re insisting every mayor find ways to cut down on the use of energy in their communities. They know how to get the job done, and in this country, I mean, we look at our country and say well that they’re totalitarian, and yeah they have people who can say this is what we have to do, this is our goal, and now you have to go get it done or you’re not going to hold your job anymore. In this country, we have the pretense of democracy, but we know that it’s with corporations that are benefiting so much from these disasters in public policy that are calling the shots. And we're not moving toward what would serve the public’s interest, and that’s clearly shown in the area of climate change and energy policy as it is when we see the work that we’re paying a lot more for drugs than other countries because of the corrupting influence of the pharmaceutical industry and the way that we’ve been sold out by those in Congress, both Republicans and Democrats who are feeding at the same special interest trough of corrupting money.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Did you watch last night’s [December 15] GOP debate?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Anderson</hi>: No. I didn’t.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Well, one candidate that was not invited to the debate was former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Louisiana">Louisiana</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor%20of%20Louisiana">governor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Buddy_Roemer">Buddy Roemer</ref>, who like you, is limiting individual campaign contributions to $100. Did your idea to do this come from Roemer?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Anderson</hi>: No. No I didn’t, frankly, I didn’t realize that he was doing that. I heard <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeffrey%20Sachs">Jeffrey Sachs</ref> talking about how these races could be won and the message to get across to people, and I said, absolutely that’s what we ought to do. Just set a $100 limit and let everybody know: they’re equal players, we’re all shareholders, we’re all shareholders in this, and no special interest is going to come along and have any special access or influence.</p></p>
<head id="Public_policy_and_the_state_of_democracy">Public policy and the state of democracy</head>
</text>
