<text id="autogum_interview_doc621" title="part9_Wikinews interviews Joe Schriner, Independent U.S. presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-04-16" dateModified="2019-08-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Joe_Schriner%2C_Independent_U.S._presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Anything else you want to add?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Anything else I want to add…  My wife Liz and I are running for president as “concerned parents from the Midwest.”  What we’re concerned about is the alarming increase in climate change, the scary levels of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/nuclear%20proliferation">nuclear proliferation</ref> (including in this country, even with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuclear%20Security%20Summit">new treaty with Russia</ref>), mounting violence in our inner cities and stark abject poverty in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third%20World">Third World</ref>.  Then there’s astronomical national debt, 4,000 babies being killed in their mothers’ wombs here each day, endless war, terrorism…  During Campaign 2004, I told a newspaper reporter in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La%20Cross,%20Wisconsin">La Cross</ref>, that I didn’t want to be sitting on my death bed someday, staring our children in the eye and saying:  “I knew all this stuff was going on, but I was too busy making money.”  So our family gave up our normal lives and took to the roads of America to look for solutions to these dilemmas.  And we found them, in the most unlikely of places at that.  We found how to balance the National Budget in tiny <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atwood,%20Kansas">Atwood</ref> (pop. 1,500).  We found how to stop abortion in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portland,%20Indiana">Portland</ref>.  We found how to end nuclear proliferation in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luck,%20Wisconsin">Luck</ref>.  We found how to stop terrorism in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comers,%20Georgia">w:Comers, Georgia</ref>. And we found how to realign most of the rest of America in Bluffton (pop. 3,857), ‘America’s best town.’   and   And as these were the most unlikely of places, the people behind the projects were often the most unlikely of people.  That is, they were often common sense people with the common good in mind.  Not profit.  Not fame.  Just the common good.  We’ve done, maybe, more than 1,000 interviews with these types of people.  And from these interviews, as I mentioned before, we’ve developed a solid platform.  The best platform out there for where the country needs to go at this point, we believe.  You see, in the face of all the pressing problems I describe at the outset of this particular answer, a lot of the current policies seem to me to be “rearranging deck chairs on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Titanic">Titanic</ref>.”  What we need is leadership at this point that can steer the boat away from the iceberg altogether, and quick.  (That is, ironically enough, if there’s going to be any iceberg’s left in the wake of global warming.)  Our common sense platform does that, in spades.  So Americans have a choice this next election.  They can go with yet another <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivy%20League">Ivy League</ref> type choice, contemplating the refrain:  “If you always do what you’ve always done, you’ll always get what you’ve always got.”  Or they can go with this quite “average” family from Cleveland, who will bring good old fashion common sense (think <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mr.%20Smith%20Goes%20to%20Washington">Mr. Smith Goes to Washington</ref></hi>) to a White House that will look, oh, a bit different—including perhaps even the color.  I mean knowing my wife (soon to be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First%20Lady%20of%20the%20United%20States">First Lady</ref>), she’ll have me painting stuff there on the weekends.  I’m thinking about going with, like, a soft green on the outside.   --Joe  P.S. Don’t let the occasional humor fool you.  This is, indeed, a very serious attempt by an average citizen to run for president.  And wouldn’t it be refreshing if someone like me won?</p>
</text>
