<text id="autogum_interview_doc1085" title="part6_Vanity Fair contributing editor Craig Unger on the Bush family feud, neoconservatives and the Christian right" shortTile="partvanity-fair-contributing" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2015-08-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vanity_Fair_contributing_editor_Craig_Unger_on_the_Bush_family_feud%2C_neoconservatives_and_the_Christian_right" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Was Powell aware of this?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Yes, and he didn’t act.  He could easily have fired Bolton.  He failed to act.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  He has to answer for that and in the end it was moral cowardice or weakness.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Department%20of%20State">State Department</ref> has its own intelligence apparatus, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bureau%20of%20Intelligence%20and%20Research">Bureau of Intelligence and Research</ref>, and they were finding fault again and again with the intelligence that was coming out of the new Pentagon unit.  INR wanted to discredit <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20Rafid%20Ahmed%20Alwan">Curveball</ref>, for instance; they wanted to discredit the aluminum tubes and the Niger documents.  So Bolton and his people forbade INR director <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greg%20Thielmann">Greg Thielmann</ref> from attending various key meetings.  Now you would think Powell would have stood up for his own intelligence unit, but he did not.  When it came to the week before the United Nations meeting in which he made his speech, Colin Powell could have had his people there.  He did call them to go over the material somewhat, but they were not present to argue out these points of conflict, and as a result, Cheney’s information got in.  When they were preparing for the UN meeting, all the intelligence data came from Cheney’s office and not from the CIA.</p>
<head id="What_the_neoconservatives_want">What the neoconservatives want</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is the end goal with all of these machinations?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  You can see it in the neocon foreign policy papers that they have been writing as early as 1992.  The first one was a Defense Department policy guidance paper.  Cheney was Defense Secretary and he had under him Wolfowitz, Khalizad and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas%20Feith">Feith</ref>, key neocons who helped formulate this policy, which was considered so radical that Bush Sr. rejected it out of hand.  Then you see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duplicity">duplicity</ref> on Cheney’s part: publicly he sides with Bush Sr. and Scowcroft , who were very very deliberate.   One of the most important foreign policy decisions they made was to not topple Saddam.  They had a REAL <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1991%20Gulf%20War%20coalition">coalition</ref>—unlike the one we have today—of thirty-four countries, eight of which were Arab who supported us throwing Saddam out of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuwait">Kuwait</ref>.  They decided, and it was very deliberate, that if they went after Saddam and continued on to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baghdad">Baghdad</ref> they would ruin their coalition, alienate their Arab partners, and be mired in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/quagmire">quagmire</ref> forever.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Saddam was so unpopular in the region; how did they foresee they would ruin the coalition if they rid Iraq of a very brutal dictator?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  American troops occupying an Arab country is a real, real problem, especially in view of Israel.  Notice they kept Israel out of it; they were not part of that coalition.  They handled it with certain dexterity and were much tougher on Israel, who was unhappy to some extent.  This is where you see enormous bifurcation.  Out of this comes the effort to sabotage the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israeli-Palestinian%20peace%20process">Israeli-Palestinian peace process</ref>.  The term “a clean break” comes out of a very important neocon policy paper called “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A%20Clean%20Break:%20A%20New%20Strategy%20for%20Securing%20the%20Realm">A Clean Break from the Land for Peace Process</ref>.”  It means they are throwing that out, which is very interesting because that was official American policy, it was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oslo%20Accord">Oslo policy</ref>, and it was even Israeli policy at that point.</p>
</text>
