<text id="autogum_interview_doc244" title="part2_Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy" shortTile="partdr-joseph-merlino" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-04" dateModified="2013-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dr._Joseph_Merlino_on_sexuality%2C_insanity%2C_Freud%2C_fetishes_and_apathy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Homosexuality_and_psychiatry"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homosexuality%20and%20psychology">Homosexuality and psychiatry</ref></head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The declassification of homosexuality as a mental disorder was a controversial debate in the psychiatric community, and it is still presented 30 years later as if it is this raging debate, and that it is just activism that was the impetus for change as opposed to any real hard science.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  It's true!  It was.  It <hi rend="italic">was</hi> activism.  But there was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> hard science to say that homosexuality was a disorder or an illness, and that was the reason why activists took aim at psychiatry and psychoanalysis and challenged them to come up with the data to support that position.  And they couldn't!  The only data they could come up with were psychoanalytic <hi rend="italic">theories</hi> that were not data.  The data that they called data was presented from small groups of clinical populations of people who are gay who didn't like or didn't want or couldn't accept being gay.  That was the population from which this so-called data was extracted.  What the gay activists did in the 1970's was pull out the true data, the scientific data that they <hi rend="italic">could</hi> find, and presented it to the diagnosis committee of the American Psychiatric Association and persuaded them that the science that <hi rend="italic">did</hi> exist was on the side of homosexuality <hi rend="italic">not</hi> being a disease or a disorder.  That is why the diagnosis committee--the Nomenclature Committee, which is what it was called--suggested to the Board of the American Psychiatric Association that it be removed, and it was.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: If the issue was presented today, would it be 58% still, or would it be a greater number that do not believe homosexuality is a mental illness?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  I think so.  There are still clusters of holdouts who believe--and it's traditionally a psychoanalysts who still see it as a disorder--but those people who are really dwindling.  In fact, one of the last leaders of that movement, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles%20Socarides">Charles Socarides</ref>, died a few years ago.  I think that particular view is dying out.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But it still has credence?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  It still has credence in groups that consider themselves scientists, but really aren't.  It's more of a religious movement.  I think we've come full circle.  Psychiatry thinking there is something wrong with being homosexual really came out of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judeo-Christian">Judeo-Christian</ref> movement for the past 2,000 years.  We moved away from that and to organized medicine through psychiatry, taking the position that it's not an <hi rend="italic">evil</hi> in terms of the individual; it's an illness.  The thinking it was a problem of the individual came from the psychoanalytic movement, which held sway in American psychiatry through the 1950's.  American psychiatry beforehand never took up the issue of homosexuality; it was never even something that was thought about in terms of <hi rend="italic">was</hi> it an illness or <hi rend="italic">wasn't</hi> it an illness?   It was just presumed, it was accepted it was an illness.  Until that was challenged in the late 1960's, early 1970's.</p>
</text>
