<text id="autogum_interview_doc927" title="part2_An interview with gossip columnist Michael Musto on the art of celebrity journalism" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-05" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_gossip_columnist_Michael_Musto_on_the_art_of_celebrity_journalism" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have celebrities who simply will not talk to you no matter what you do or say, because you pissed them off so royally?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  Oh yeah, I mean, there's so many names I can't even list them [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>].  When I walk into a room half the room runs away, and that's a good thing.  But the longer you do it, the more people come around because I don't think I'm as bitter as I used to be in my column.  I think I'm a little more willing to show my appreciation.    Some people would rather it go back to having more sting to it.  But I'm still a risky person because there is so much media out there now that they can pick and choose; these publicists really are the editors now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you ever punish people for an infraction against you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  Sure.  My column is very personal; it's <hi rend="italic">La Dolce Musto</hi> so it's all based on personal grudges.  If somebody can play the game well with me and give me good copy then I love them, and if they slight me I'll get them back.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Can you give an example?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  Oh, gosh, I have telegrams from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whoopi%20Goldberg">Whoopi Goldberg</ref> and...I think <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gwyneth%20Paltrow">Gwyneth Paltrow</ref> was smart.  She said, "I admire your rage."  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vincent%20Gallo">Vincent Gallo</ref>, who hates everybody, was leaving me nasty messages on my home machine, calling me Miss Musto.  I don't know.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tinsley%20Mortimer">Tinsley Mortimer</ref> just called me yesterday.  She's a hot socialite, the new <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris%20Hilton">Paris Hilton</ref>.  She called me at home because I said something to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Observer">The Observer</ref></hi> that came out today in which I kind of paraphrased something she said to me, and she was angry with me.  She's actually right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What did you say?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  We were co-presenting an award at some nightclub award show, and I told <hi rend="italic">The Observer</hi> that she said, 'Don't queer me, don't go off the script.'  She didn't actually say 'don't queer me,' so it somehow became a gay issue where they made it sound like she is anti-gay.  And she's not.  She loves the gays, except for me.  But the weirdest thing is Paris Hilton I have trashed mercilessly, but then when they were doing the cover story for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Out%20Magazine">Out Magazine</ref></hi> I heard she hand-picked me.  So, fly to the L.A., do the interview, be shot for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Simple%20Life">The Simple Life</ref></hi>, so...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have a sense that celebrities are paying much attention to the war, that there's a consciousness they have, as a community or individually, outside of the glitz centers of New York and Los Angeles?</hi></p>
</text>
