<text id="autogum_interview_doc1256" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Bob Ely, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-25" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Bob_Ely%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You have proposed increased taxes on energy. Since businesses require energy to transport their goods to market, this likely would result in an increase in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cost%20of%20living">cost of living</ref>. In such an environment, will people making minimum wage under your jobs plan, be able to afford basic necessities?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ely</hi>: Actually I propose to increase taxes on gasoline and, if the rest of the world will get on board, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/coal">coal</ref>.  If I could make the numbers work I would eliminate the tax on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diesel%20fuel">diesel</ref> for just the reasons you cite plus the ridiculous way in which diesel has to be dyed different colors for tax purposes.  That in itself is an example of government inefficiency.  What to do about diesel engines in automobiles and light trucks?  Tax the engines (like the gas guzzler tax) to make them about equivalent to gasoline engines of comparable life.  People smarter than me may have a better solution.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Most <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schools%20of%20economic%20thought">schools of economics</ref> agree that during a time of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/recession">economic downturn</ref>, government should <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fiscal%20policy">cut taxes</ref> to increase <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/aggregate%20demand">aggregate demand</ref>. You propose tax increases to help balance the budget. With that in mind, how can you prevent a continuation of the current economic downturn?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ely</hi>: First, most economists didn’t see the financial crisis coming nor the rebound.  I did and invested accordingly.  Now I don’t know how to invest for what I see coming, which is why I embarked on this Quixotic endeavor.  That’s a bit melodramatic.  I do have some ideas.  But many of them are not "patriotic."  I believe when you’re in a situation you don’t like, you either have to effect change or adapt.  Getting on the ballot was my attempt to effect change.  Second, I did pretty well in sixth grade math.  With that learning, I conclude that we cannot borrow $1–1.5 trillion each year indefinitely.  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref> has proven it can go on for a long time, although they borrow mostly (93%) from themselves.  Even they won’t be able to keep it up forever (watch that space closely).  Our debt is a growing tumor.  It’s either chemotherapy today or death tomorrow.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">For your "easier to get fired" plan, which allows businesses to fire employees in the first 180 days of employment for any reason, must Title VII of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil%20Rights%20Act%20of%201964">1964 Civil Rights Act</ref> be repealed since "any reason" could be construed to include the "race, color, religion, sex, or national origin" of an employee?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ely</hi>: No.  Any business person stupid enough to fire someone for their race when they could fire them for "no reason" should be punished to the fullest extent of the law.  I know women business people, however, who are reluctant to hire women because of the potential liability if the employee ends up being a dud.</p>
</text>
