<text id="autogum_interview_doc154" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Australian Glider Amanda Carter" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-09-26" dateModified="2017-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Glider_Amanda_Carter" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> That would have been about right. It was pretty packed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  That must have been awesome.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> It was. It was. I guess also because it was the USA. It was their home crowd and everything, so it was a very packed game.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  They also have a fondness for the sport.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> They do. They love basketball. But Atlanta again was done very well. Would have been nice to get the medal, ‘cause I think we sort of had bigger expectations of ourselves at that point, ‘cause we weren't the new kids on the block at that point but still finished fourth.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  They kept on saying in London that the Gliders have never won.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> We've never won a gold, no. Not at World's or Paralympics.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So that was Atlanta. Then there was another tournament, the 1998 Gold Cup. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yes. Which was the World Championships held in Sydney.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How did we go in that?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Third.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  But that qualified... no, wait, we didn't need to qualify...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> We didn't need to qualify.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You were the second leading scorer in the event, with thirty points scored for the competition.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yes. Which was unusual for a low pointer.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  In basketball, some of the low pointers do pretty well.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yeah, but in those days I guess it was more unusual for a low pointer to be more a scorer.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I notice the scores seem lower than the ones in London.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yes. I think over time the women's game has developed. Girls have got stronger and they're competing against guys. Training has got better, and all sorts of things. So teams have just got better.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How often do the Gliders get together? It seems that you are all scattered all over the country normally.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yes. I mean we've got currently three in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Perth">Perth</ref>, four in Melbourne, four in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_South_Wales">New South Wales</ref>, and one in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brisbane">Brisbane</ref> out of the twelve that were in London. But the squad is bigger again. We usually get together probably every six or eight weeks.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  That's reasonably often.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Cost-wise it's expensive to get us all together. What we sometimes do is tack a camp on to the Women's League, when we're mostly all together anyway, no matter where it is, and we might stay a couple of extra days in order to train together. But generally if we come into camp it would be at the AIS.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I didn't see you training in Sydney this time... then you went over to...</p>
</text>
