<text id="autogum_interview_doc562" title="Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Freedom Party candidate Wayne Simmons, Don Valley East" shortTile="ontario-votes--interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-03" dateModified="2008-10-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Freedom_Party_candidate_Wayne_Simmons%2C_Don_Valley_East" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Freedom Party candidate Wayne Simmons, Don Valley East</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 3, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wayne Simmons</hi> is running for the Freedom Party in the Ontario provincial election, in the Don Valley East riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Wayne did not answer "Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?"</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I was inspired to enter politics by reading authors, Ayn Rand and George Orwell. Soon after, I looked at the political landscape in Canada and noticed it was - and still is- a haven for Statists.</p>
<p>I felt that those of us that understand the ideological roots of liberty need to involve ourselves in the political process.</p>
<p>I'm running for Don Valley East because Don Mills has been my home for 31 years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I've been studying philosophy, history, politics and economics for approximately 20 years. I bring the insight of having a historical understanding of individual rights in the West.</p>
<p>This knowledge has armed me with the ability to make sound, principled, policy decisions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?</hi></p>
<p>I have no illusions about winning in this election. I'm running so that those living in my riding have an opportunity to vote for a principled, non-statist, candidate.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>I'm the only rationally principled, non-statist, candidate running.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>There's is no way for any Politician to know with certainty what the three most important issues are in their riding. The question has smuggled into it a collectivist premise that a Politician is some kind of Rousseuian grand legislator who has mystical insight into the "General Will" of his community. Many people are concerned about excessive taxation. Many are concerned about the lack of choice in Education and Healthcare.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>Cutting taxes, specifically, property and income taxes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>No. There is no "fair" level. Who can determine the "fair" level? This question presupposes some kind mystical collective way of determining fairness with regard to taxation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>Abolish the provincial income tax and scrap property taxes, for starters.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>MMP would make majority Governments difficult - if not impossible. It is only by Freedom Party forming a majority Government where the necessary uncompromising changes can be made to restore Government respect for the individual's right to life, liberty and property.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does "new media" play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>They're all beneficial. The party uses practically all methods of new media.</p>
</text>
