<text id="autogum_interview_doc1067" title="part3_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Progessive Conservative candidate Tyler Currie, Trinity-Spadina" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-01" dateModified="2007-11-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Progessive_Conservative_candidate_Tyler_Currie%2C_Trinity-Spadina" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>Personally, I will be voting ‘no’ in this referendum. This is not a statement that says I am pleased with the current FPTP system, nor is it my opinion that FPTP is without its inequities.  I will certainly respect whatever decision the public makes on this referendum question, and I do feel that the posed question was constructed in a democratically fair process. My issue is that we’d be eliminating one problem, but ushering in a whole new set of problems to replace it. The new system would bring in 39 ADDITIONAL politicians --- more politicians is never a good idea! Similarly, the additional representatives will not be accountable. They will not answer to a local riding. They will not be selected by the public, but rather by a Party’s bureaucracy. And I am concerned that a situation may exist where multiple members could be from a given geographical region, allowing them to use their collective influence to get more infrastructure, investment, and problem-solving solutions to the regions from which they hail, at the expense of the areas that are represented by a sole representative.  In summary, I’m not aware of any electoral system in the entire world that is ‘perfect’, and granted that there are imperfections in our current system, it does not warrant bringing in a system that has as many (if not more) flaws.  I am more in favour of pursuing internal reform, increasing accountability of local representatives, ensuring more ‘free votes’ in the legislature, and finding ways for the governing and opposition parties to govern this province more efficiently and respectfully.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does "new media" play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>In a riding as young, creative and tech-savvy as Trinity-Spadina, we certainly see the new media as an opportunity to reach our constituents and also help our goal to get more youth interested in the political process. Much of our campaign material has a ‘call to action’ to our website, preserving trees with a one-sheet flyer that asks recipients to look for further information on tylercurrie.com.  Similarly, on this website I have my own blog that I update regularly, a link to my Facebook profile and Campaign Group, a link to our MySpace page, a link to our Flickr album, and most importantly, a series of short YouTube videos where I speak to the issues that are important to our community.  The new media is a great opportunity to expand our political process and I think it is imperative that more candidates and parties take advantage of this in the immediate years to come.</p>
</text>
