<text id="autogum_interview_doc1081" title="part2_Vanity Fair contributing editor Craig Unger on the Bush family feud, neoconservatives and the Christian right" shortTile="partvanity-fair-contributing" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2015-08-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vanity_Fair_contributing_editor_Craig_Unger_on_the_Bush_family_feud%2C_neoconservatives_and_the_Christian_right" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are there any Republican front-runners that would not undertake an assault on Iran?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  The only one is not a front-runner:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron%20Paul">Ron Paul</ref>.  I don’t think there is a single Republican who has tried to discredit Bush’s policies.   One of my concerns addressed in this book is I don’t want people to think, “Oh, the Bushs are gone, it’s all over.”  No, no, no.  We’re going to be paying for this for decades.  The Christian right and the neocons: that is the Republican Party today.  It transcends Bush.  Bush became the vehicle through whom they carried out their policies.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So it could have been anybody but they ingratiated themselves with Bush?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  He was an ideal vehicle.  Partly he has a name that was identified with the <hi rend="italic">old</hi> Republican establishment—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And he wasn’t particularly well-informed, giving them an “in” to educate him?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  That’s for sure.  A lot of voters thought they were getting his father.  Wall Street Republicans thought of him as a moderate.  He used terms like “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20Compassionate%20Conservative"> Compassionate Conservative</ref>” that were perceived as moderate.  I have a chapter called “Dog Whistle Politics” where he’s speaking one language to the general public, and another to his base.  So compassionate conservatism is precisely that.  It really was a program for taking away the social safety net and giving it to right-wing churches.  It was a movement that was about anything but a liberal safety net.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Within the United States, what are the neoconservatives and Christian right concerned will happen that could scuttle their agenda?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  The Democrats winning, obviously, which is one reason they might bomb Iran before the election.  That would change the dynamic of the entire election.  I think there are two possibilities: are they going to do it before the next election?  I don’t have the answer and I can’t predict it, but it would be a disaster.  It would change the dynamics of the election that they are soft on terrorism, they want to throw Israel to Iran—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Would that still work after all this time?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  The Zogby Poll <ref target="http://time-blog.com/middle_east/2007/11/americans_its_ok_to_bomb_iran.html">just showed 52% of Americans think we should bomb Iran</ref>. The media has not improved at all since the Iraq War, and 90% of Americans were behind that.  Part of the problem is that this <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jingoism">jingoist</ref> stuff you might expect from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fox%20News">Fox News</ref>, but when <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi> becomes a mouthpiece for Dick Cheney, you then form a consensus in the national conversation and anyone critical is marginalized.</p>
<head id="This_history_behind_the_Bush_family_feud">This history behind the Bush family feud</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is there a movement within the Republican Party that is working against the fundamentalism in the party?</hi></p>
</text>
