<text id="autogum_interview_doc1275" title="part0_Edmund White on writing, incest, life and Larry Kramer" shortTile="partedmund-white" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-08" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edmund_White_on_writing%2C_incest%2C_life_and_Larry_Kramer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Edmund White on writing, incest, life and Larry Kramer</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 8, 2007</hi></p>
<p>What you are about to read is an American life as lived by renowned author <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edmund%20White">Edmund White</ref>.  His life has been a crossroads, the fulcrum of high-brow <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classicism">Classicism</ref> and low-brow <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brett%20Easton%20Ellis">Brett Easton Ellisism</ref>.  It is not for the faint.  He has been the toast of the literary elite in New York, London and Paris, befriending artistic luminaries such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salman%20Rushdie">Salman Rushdie</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sir%20Ian%20McKellen">Sir Ian McKellen</ref> while writing about a family where he was jealous his sister was having sex with his father as he fought off his mother's amorous pursuit.  </p>
<p>The fact is, Edmund White exists.  His life exists.  To the casual reader, they may find it disquieting that someone like his father existed in 1950's America and that White's work is the progeny of his intimate effort to understand his own experience.      </p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> understood that an interview with Edmund White, who is professor of creative writing at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Princeton%20University">Princeton University</ref>, who wrote the seminal biography of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean%20Genet">Jean Genet</ref>, and who no longer can keep track of how many sex partners he has encountered, meant nothing would be off limits.  Nothing was.  Late in the interview they were joined by his partner Michael Caroll, who discussed White's enduring feud with influential writer and activist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larry%20Kramer">Larry Kramer</ref>.</p>
<head id="On_literature">On literature</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  What questions are you tired of answering?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Edmund White:</hi>  Is there a gay sensibility?  People ask it all the time…the best answer to that I ever saw was somebody said, “There is no gay sensibility and it has had an enormous impact on society.”  Otherwise, I’m pretty easy.  I try to rethink the question each time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you noticed your answers change much?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Oh, yeah.  I’m a philosophical spirit, so that means you think through everything each time, unless you’re doing ten interviews a day and your own book tour.  Otherwise, if it’s like this, you try to think it out.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you notice you are very flexible in your thought and change notions easily, does it have broader implications for you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Sure, I think I am often working out things that I later will write.  To the degree that I write in an essayistic way, or even in my novels, I work up opinions I try out and use later.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  One interview I did was with a young novelist named <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell,_God,_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing">John Reed</ref>—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I know him.  Cute boy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yes, married, kids.  But he feels a problem with creating a new generation of readers today is that the literary canon does not have many modern works at the grade school and high school level, and young readers feel disconnected from reading.</hi></p>
</text>
