<text id="autogum_interview_doc1064" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Progessive Conservative candidate Tyler Currie, Trinity-Spadina" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-01" dateModified="2007-11-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Progessive_Conservative_candidate_Tyler_Currie%2C_Trinity-Spadina" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Progessive Conservative candidate Tyler Currie, Trinity-Spadina</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 1, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tyler Currie</hi> is running as an Progressive Conservative candidate in the Ontario provincial election, in the riding of Trinity-Spadina. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I have been involved in the political process for a number of years now, stemming from my father’s two terms as a city councillor.  My decision to run as a candidate was based on two things. First, I am very concerned with the cynicism I hear from people about politics, the political process, and most importantly, the politicians. With voter turnouts going down each and every year, and then four years of a McGuinty government that only made peoples’ cynicism worse, I was motivated to do what I could to change that. And that brings up my second reason, and his name is John Tory. He represents everything that politics and leadership should be. It’s about selfless public service, accountability, respecting tax payers, carrying a strong social conscience, and keeping your word.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I have served on the Executive of the local Riding Association for the Progressive Conservative Party, and was an elected member of the student government at the University of Toronto. I bring a badly needed level of energy to office, matching the requirements of a young, vibrant riding in downtown Toronto, and something that is sorely lacking by the current representative who has been stale with his ideas, lacking in his momentum, weak in his influence, and dwindling in his motivation and effort to represent this riding to the level that it deserves. In a riding with so many students and young professionals, I offer a voice that reflects their interests, while understanding and appreciating the greater diversity of our area as well. I’m driven by results, and we have not had results in this riding for the past 17 years under the current representation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?</hi></p>
<p>They are all fine people and worthy opponents. The incumbent is always the biggest challenge in an election, and I welcome the opportunity to compare ideas, thoughts, and visions for this city and our province. And regardless of the end result, it is imperative that we all maintain our commitment to improving our community by working together.</p>
</text>
