<text id="autogum_interview_doc376" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Australian Statistician Brian Pink" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-19" dateModified="2008-04-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Statistician_Brian_Pink" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: Yes, in digital form and searchable.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : That must have been a huge effort.</p>
<hi rend="bold">... you go back and read history and you find that quite often we're reinventing [...] challenges that people dealt with back then as well.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—On reading past Year Books</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: Yes. That obviously started before I came back from New Zealand, but a very large effort, but also a wonderful resource now available, free, on the ABS web site, to all of our community and society, both individuals and obviously it will be a very valuable research environment for historians, for economic historians, for statisticians as well, and I think so far it's been pretty low-key in terms of the way in which the value of that particular initiative is yet to be fully recognised. Probably we need to find ways of getting the availability of all those Year Books, now digitally on the web site, out there and understood by a wider range of potential users. Perhaps forums like the Wiki forum that we're talking about here is a good way to help do that.</p>
<p>Myself, I've gone in and looked at some of the early Year Books, and some of the Statistician's Reports at the beginning of each of the Year Books, and one of the things that I found really interesting was the extent to which issues that we might feel are pretty new and that we've discovered for the first time in recent years, you go back and read history and you find that quite often we're reinventing, perhaps in a different context, but still reinventing challenges that people dealt with back then as well.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Have you heard of any results from people looking through these Year Books and finding any interesting statistics?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: I haven't, I think that as I said the large majority of people don't realise yet that that enormous resource is there, and I think our challenge is to get the knowledge out there that they are there, and then I think we'll see the use pick up quite substantially.</p>
<head id="The_impact_of_changing_governments">The impact of changing governments</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Obviously the ABS doesn't exist in a vacuum, and it has to work in the wider political world in Australia, and of course last year the November Federal election saw a change of government. Has this impacted much on how the Bureau works?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: I think one of the really important values of a national statistical organisation is that it has an enduring role in its society, and an important part of that role is to support the information needs of government, and governments change, and their focus can change, some of their priorities obviously change, and our role is to be able to support the information needs. But a great deal of what a national statistical office like the ABS does is to provide a window on different parts of economic and social dimensions of our society that all governments need, and value, and use, and so whilst it's quite possible that we will see some shifts in areas of interest and priority from the new government that came in late last year, in the main the large part of what the ABS is doing will continue to support the new government in the ways that is has previous governments.</p>
</text>
