<text id="autogum_interview_doc1375" title="part1_Interview: Drupal founder Dries Buytaert balances community and company interests" shortTile="partinterview-drupal" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-01-28" dateModified="2015-10-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview%3A_Drupal_founder_Dries_Buytaert_balances_community_and_company_interests" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>We have founded the Drupal Association, a Belgium-based non-profit organisation which aims to do promotion, organisation of things like conferences, etc. The organisations takes on a lot of these tasks. There are eight or nine directors, so it has really become a bigger organisation that's operating and developing Drupal. It's also international: it's based in Belgium but there are only two Belgian directors I think.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Do you think Drupal is important for software in Belgium? Countries like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref> have a big software industry but we don't.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DB</hi>: Drupal was created in Belgium, but it has become really international. Most contributions come from the United States now I think. There are a few other open source projects from Belgium, maybe not on the same size scale, but still there are definitely some projects. The fact that we organise the largest open source conference in Europe shows that there is a lively interest.</p>
<head id="Acquia:_company-community_interaction">Acquia: company-community interaction</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Looking at your new start-up Acquia, there are some people in the Drupal community who are concerned that you're combining your leadership role with that of Acquia <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief%20technical%20officer">CTO</ref>. You could have done like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jimmy%20Wales">Jimmy Wales</ref>, who started <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikia">Wikia</ref> and took a step back from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DB</hi>: I admit that combining these positions complicates matters, both for myself as for Acquia. But I have always fought hard for what the Drupal community has achieved. The Association still has the right to use the domain name and such; Acquia will not have special privileges. I have always fought hard to keep the play field open.</p>
<p>Of course we will be a major player, simply because of the money and there are some highly visible people involved. But if we do things with which the community does not agree, we will not force them. That's built into our corporate DNA. We want to be seen as the best thing that ever happened to the Drupal community. Our goal is to work together closely. I'm glad to see that the community has faith in us. There are a number of important people from the community in our company: they will not suddenly turn to the evil side! They know better than anyone else what lives in the community. Openness and transparency are very important. People will simply have to give us a chance.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : If I listen to some community members, I get the impression that they trust you, and that they believe it will be all right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DB</hi>: It will be like that. Of course there are a number of challenges, but I have full confidence. I will do everything to make the community succeed. And if a problem arises, then we'll organise ourselves; we're very good at that.</p>
</text>
