<text id="autogum_interview_doc1404" title="part8_Interview with gay marriage movement founder Evan Wolfson" shortTile="partinterview-gay" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-29" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_gay_marriage_movement_founder_Evan_Wolfson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/domestic%20partnership">domestic partnerships</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/civil%20unions">civil unions</ref> not adequate?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Civil unions, domestic partnerships, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LGBT%20union">other legal mechanisms</ref> can serve a value in helping end discrimination and helping achieve protections and some degree of security for families.  But they are no substitute for the tangible and intangible security, protection, responsibility and respect that come with the freedom to marry.  I’m all for partnerships, civil unions and other mechanisms that help families meet their needs and do better.  But not as a substitute for ending discrimination in marriage.  Gay people should not have to go in the back door and settle for less; they should not have to take a legal mechanism that is separate and lesser, when we already have one system in our country that fully provides protections and responsibilities and respect.  That’s called marriage.  Most non-gay people would not trade their marriage for a civil union, and gay people shouldn’t have to, either.  Especially when there is no good reason for the government sending some families around the back while others come in the front.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  People like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan%20Dershowitz">Alan Dershowitz</ref> have raised an argument that the word 'marriage' should be reserved for religious contexts, and in civil and legal contexts we should use a uniform concept of civil unions.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Is Alan Dershowitz married? [he is]  For those same reasons he found it important to be legally married, and entitled to respect for that, so should gay people be married.  If it’s good enough for Professor Dershowitz, it’s good enough for us.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  He’s not arguing against marriage, but against marriage as a civil institution.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Why do we suddenly have to throw out the entire system, invent some whole new thing, just because gay people want to get married?  I don’t actually see Alan Dershowitz <hi rend="italic">doing</hi> anything about this, other than writing an article, because he probably rightly understand it would be an <hi rend="italic">immense</hi> project to go around the country and convince 200 million plus people to trade in their marriage for something new and explain why we are doing this when we actually have a legal system that already clearly distinguishes between civil and religious marriage.  Government doesn’t issue <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/bar%20mitzvah">bar mitzvah</ref> licenses or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/holy%20communion">communion</ref> licenses, but it issues <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marriage%20license">marriage licenses</ref> because marriage is a legal institution that is distinct from whatever ceremonies or important meaning people find when they celebrate their <hi rend="italic">religious</hi> marriage in church, synagogue, temple or mosque.</p>
<p>Marriage in the United States <hi rend="italic">is</hi> a civil union; but a civil union, as it has come to be called, is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> marriage.  It is a proposed hypothetical legal mechanism, since it doesn’t exist in most places, to give some of the protections but also withhold something precious from gay people.  There’s no good reason to do that.  We don’t need to invent a whole new system because we already have a distinction between civil and religious.</p>
</text>
