<text id="autogum_interview_doc1403" title="part7_Interview with gay marriage movement founder Evan Wolfson" shortTile="partinterview-gay" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-29" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_gay_marriage_movement_founder_Evan_Wolfson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Does Freedom to Marry play more of a coordinating function?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  That’s one role Freedom to Marry plays.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lambda%20Legal">lawyers in our movement</ref> know how to handle these cases; in Maryland it was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ACLU">ACLU</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20Ken%20Choe">Ken Choe</ref> did a brilliant job at argument.  My role is as an adviser and consultant, but is almost as much about being a friend and colleague as it is about the need for one more opinion.  The more important role Freedom to Marry plays is to remind all of us in this movement that winning a lawsuit, winning a legislative battle, winning a ballot measure and winning the hearts and minds of the public are not things to be  done in an isolated fashion.  We need to integrate all the work of what Martin Luther King called the methodologies of social change.  To make sure they are all being done in concert, so that when the lawyers are doing a brilliant job in court, the rest of us are doing a serious, persistent engagement of the public and opinion leaders.  The way a lawsuit turns out is at least as much effected by the work that is done in the food court as it is by what is done in the law court.  The conversations we have around the court are important as the briefs we file in the court.  So Freedom to Marry's more important role in cases like Maryland is to support the leaders on the ground and to have the engagement that creates the climate for the court to rule in our favor.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you handle losses such as the one in Maryland?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  What eased the pain of Maryland was the truly striking and compelling video of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerry%20Sanders%20(politician)">Mayor of San Diego</ref> signing a measure in support of gay marriage, even though literally just hours before the press conference he said he would veto it.  He’s a Republican ex-police chief, but when he looked his gay staffers and his gay daughter in the face and talked with them, he realized he couldn’t do it, and came out for the freedom to marry.  He talked about how civil unions--the position he had hours before--was not good enough.  He provided a moral witness, a living testimony, of a person thinking deep and the power that gay people have to change minds when they speak to people like him and get them to look deep in their heart.  That moment last week is an indication of how more gay people and more non-gay people can play <hi rend="italic">more</hi> of a role in moving this momentum toward marriage equality even faster.</p>
<head id="Domestic_partnerships_and_civil_unions">Domestic partnerships and civil unions</head>
</text>
