<text id="autogum_interview_doc1327" title="part4_Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian Party potential presidential candidate R.J. Harris" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-06-16" dateModified="2019-02-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Libertarian_Party_potential_presidential_candidate_R.J._Harris" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Our repeated Petitions have been answered only by repeated Injury [after TARP came bailouts for a host of corporations, the social welfares are too numerous to list, the War in Libya goes on despite its gross unconstitutionality as does the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War%20in%20Afghanistan%20(2001–present)">War in Afghanistan</ref> despite having met the objectives contained in the Letter of Reprisal authorizing our actions there, the debt limit is about to be raised once again, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Reserve%20System">Federal Reserve</ref> continues its <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/quantitative%20easing">quantitative easing</ref> (money printing), the Civil War on Drugs rages on despite the previous failure of prohibition and trillions spent to curb private behavior in the name of morality all to no avail, the sexual assaults being perpetrated by the TSA continue despite several state legislatures attempting to nullify them, the Patriot Act was just extended and all of this despite most of these actions not having the approval of the VAST majority of the People]. </p>
<p>A Prince [or central Government] whose Character is thus marked by every act which may define a Tyrant, is unfit to be the Ruler of a free People." </p>
<p>It should be clear then by the enumeration of this "long Train of Abuses and Usurpations," which represents but a tiny fraction of the same which our central government is using to pursue "invariably the same Object" and that it "evinces a Design to reduce [us] under absolute Despotism." </p>
<p>Thus by the precedent established by the Declaration of Independence, and the Founding of the Republic itself under similar, if not even less trying circumstances, that it is the Right and Duty of We the People to use the political process still available to us to "throw off such Government, and to provide new Guards for [our] future Security" as well as restore our Constitution and our Republic. </p>
<p>As a potential Candidate for the Libertarian Party's Presidential Nomination I would encourage the People to begin this restorative political process by electing to the Office of President the MOST Constitutionally Libertarian Candidate available and to continue it by doing the same in the election of all future federal representatives to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Congress">Congress</ref> REGARDLESS of their perceived political experience. </p>
<p>For certainly it is the case that nearly every single member of all three branches of the federal government are very experienced career politicians and yet the state of our Republic and the condition of our Freedom and Liberty are worse off now that they have been at any time since our founding.                </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">When is government necessary?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">RH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> To protect the Lives, Liberty and Property of the Citizens of the Republic.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">In a market with little or no government regulation, what prevents an entity from seizing the entire means of production and becoming the new main regulator?</hi></p>
</text>
