<text id="autogum_interview_doc001" title="part1_Wikinews interviews 2020 US Libertarian Party presidential candidate Adam Kokesh" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-09-01" dateModified="2019-09-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_2020_US_Libertarian_Party_presidential_candidate_Adam_Kokesh" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>Kokesh at an anti-war rally in 2007 Image: Sage Ross.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Which historical or contemporary figures do you admire and consider as role models?  Why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kokesh</hi>: I don't believe in having role models because it can limit you in your own self-actualization. This might sound semantic, but it's a meaningful difference to me to have teachers instead of role models so we can get useful lessons and inspiration from many people and still be ourselves. I admire a lot of people for a lot of different things and learn from everyone I can. Right now, I think about how I learned to distrust authority from my parents, courage from people like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ross%20Ulbricht">Ross Ulbricht</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edward_Snowden">Ed Snowden</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chelsea_Manning">Chelsea Manning</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Julian_Assange">Julian Assange</ref>, patience from people like Ron Paul, intellectual persistence from people like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murray%20Rothbard">Murray Rothbard</ref>, and compassion from people like my girlfriend.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">At what point during your time in Iraq did you realize the effort there was immoral?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kokesh</hi>: While I was in Iraq, I didn't have the presence of mind or the awareness to come to the conclusion that it was immoral. I identified as a "Libertarian" at the time, but I can look back now and see that I was really an arrogant militant <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/minarchism">minarchist</ref> with poorly thought out libertarian principles. I was against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2003%20invasion%20of%20Iraq">invasion of Iraq</ref> before it happened as a matter of policy more than principle. I supported the ongoing occupation because I thought of it as cleaning up our mess. It wasn't until I came home and got out of the Marines that I was able to get the right moral perspective.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">In what ways do you believe you have accomplished what you have sought through activism?  In what ways have you failed?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kokesh</hi>: I define an activist as anyone whose work is primarily motivated by a deep-seated sense of injustice. In that sense, most of us have some ideology or global vision for justice in mind, some unachievable ideal. Short of that, I have a realistic ideal that the Libertarian Party defines as, "a world set free in our lifetime." To me that means a voluntary society, not one that is perfectly voluntary in every interaction, but that recognizes the ideal of <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/voluntarism">voluntaryism</ref> and in which there is no institutional coercion. So obviously, we haven't achieved that yet! I see the evolution towards a voluntary society as a mission for all of humanity in which no single one of us can accomplish anything alone, so I can't take credit for any of my successes, but I am very satisfied in what I have been able to accomplish as a media producer, author, and civil disobedience activist as a contribution to that mission. As for failures, I could point to many, but I don't think you're asking for a deep personal psychoanalysis here! I would say all my failures as an activist have stemmed from forgetting the true nature of our mission as libertarians, which is to bring peace and harmony to humanity through freedom.</p>
</text>
