<text id="autogum_interview_doc1406" title="part0_John Vanderslice plays New York City: Wikinews interview" shortTile="partjohn-vanderslice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-27" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Vanderslice_plays_New_York_City%3A_Wikinews_interview" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>John Vanderslice plays New York City: Wikinews interview</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 27, 2007</hi></p>
<figure rend="John Vanderslice by David Shankbone.jpg"></figure><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Vanderslice">John Vanderslice</ref> has recently learned to enjoy America again.  The singer-songwriter, who <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Public%20Radio">National Public Radio</ref> called "one of the most imaginative, prolific and consistently rewarding artists making music today," found it through an unlikely source:  his French girlfriend.  "For the first time in my life I wouldn't say I was defending the country but I was in this very strange position..."  
<p>Since breaking off from San Francisco local legends, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/mk%20Ultra">mk Ultra</ref>, Vanderslice has produced six critically-acclaimed albums.  His most recent, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emerald%20City%20(album)">Emerald City</ref></hi>, was released July 24th.  Titled after the nickname given to the American-occupied <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%20Zone">Green Zone</ref> in Baghdad, it chronicles a world on the verge of imminent collapse under the weight of its own paranoia and loneliness.  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> recently went to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bowery%20Ballroom">Bowery Ballroom</ref> and spoke with Vanderslice about music, photography, touring and what makes a depressed liberal angry.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How is the tour going?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  Great!  I was just on the Wiki page for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inland%20Empire%20(film)">Inland Empire</ref></hi>, and there is a great synopsis on the film. What's on there is the best thing I have read about that film.  The tour has been great.  The thing with touring: say you are on vacation...let's say you are doing an intense vacation.  I went to Thailand alone, and there's a part of you that just wants to go home.  I don't know what it is.  I like to be home, but on tour there is a free floating anxiety that says: Go Home.  Go Home.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Anywhere, or just outside of the country?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  Anywhere.  I want to be home in San Francisco, and I really do love being on tour, but there is almost like a homing beacon inside of me that is beeping and it creates a certain amount of anxiety.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I can relate:  You and I have moved around a lot, and we have a lot in common.  Pranks, for one.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Bowie">David Bowie</ref> is another.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  Yeah, I saw that you like David Bowie on your <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MySpace">MySpace</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When I was in college I listened to him nonstop.  Do you have a favorite album of his?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  I loved all the things from early to late seventies.  <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hunky%20Dory">Hunky Dory</ref></hi> to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Low%20(album)">Low</ref></hi> to <hi rend="italic"><ref target='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/"Heroes"'>"Heroes"</ref></hi> to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lodger%20(album)">Lodger</ref></hi>.  <hi rend="italic">Low</hi> changed my life.  The second I got was <hi rend="italic">Hunky Dory</hi>, and the third was <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diamond%20Dogs">Diamond Dogs</ref></hi>, which is a very underrated album.  Then I got <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Rise%20and%20Fall%20of%20Ziggy%20Stardust%20and%20the%20Spiders%20from%20Mars">Ziggy Stardust</ref></hi> and I was like, wow, this is important...this means something.  There was tons of music I discovered in the seventh and eighth grade that I discovered, but I don't love, respect and relate to it as much as I do Bowie.  Especially <hi rend="italic">Low</hi>...I was just on a panel with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve%20Albini">Steve Albini</ref> about how it has had a lot of impact.</p>
</text>
