<text id="autogum_interview_doc1103" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Freedom Party candidate David McGruer, Ottawa-Orleans" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-02" dateModified="2007-12-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Freedom_Party_candidate_David_McGruer%2C_Ottawa-Orleans" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Freedom Party candidate David McGruer, Ottawa-Orleans</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 2, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">David McGruer</hi> is running for the Freedom Party of Ontario in the Ontario provincial election, in the Ottawa-Orleans riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I have long had the urge to speak out when I see wrongs being done. For the last two years a monthly column in the <hi rend="italic">Orleans Star</hi> has been an outlet. I have a client who moved to Ottawa from London Ont. years ago and who introduced me to the Freedom Party's principles, which meshed with my own. The party leaders asked if I would run in this election.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>No prior political experience. My insight comes from working in the real world as a teacher and then a financial advisor. I have read considerably on economics and philosophy and come to understand the deep flaws in the current popular thinking.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>I do not expect to gain more than 1% of the vote. My objective is to plant a small seed in the minds of those voters who care to think about and challenge belief systems and the status quo. Hopefully, over time, those seeds will grow until the day when it is common to talk about individual rights in political circles and the discussion turns to how to make government less instead of more intrusive.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>Let me preface my response. The Freedom Party is very different from all the others because we wish to get government intrusion out of people's lives instead of extending its tendrils even deeper. As such, I am not attempting to tackle so-called "riding issues" because all these are a function of the problems created by poor thinking and poor government. For me the only issue is the promotion of a province and country which protects individual rights, and all other issues tie in and are solved by a proper understanding of rights and creation of a government suitable for the protection of rights.</p>
</text>
