<text id="autogum_interview_doc006" title="part0_Male Magellanic penguins pine for pairings: Wikinews interviews biologist Natasha Gownaris" shortTile="partmale-magellanic" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-01-03" dateModified="2019-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Male_Magellanic_penguins_pine_for_pairings%3A_Wikinews_interviews_biologist_Natasha_Gownaris" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Male Magellanic penguins pine for pairings: Wikinews interviews biologist Natasha Gownaris</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, January 27, 2019</hi></p>
<p>In findings published earlier this month in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecological%20Applications">Ecological Applications</ref></hi>, scientists from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Washington">University of Washington</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Center%20for%20Ecosystem%20Sentinels">Center for Ecosystem Sentinels</ref> examine the reason for the plummeting numbers of female <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magellanic%20penguins">Magellanic penguins</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Spheniscus magellanicus</hi>, that have been reported at the birds' breeding sites in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_America">South America</ref> over the past twenty years and more. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> caught up with postdoctoral researcher and study co-author Natasha Gownaris to learn more.</p>
<figure><caption>A mated pair of Magellanic penguins on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Punta%20Tombo">Punta Tombo</ref>, showing the visual similarity between male and female birds. Image: Natasha Gownaris.</caption></figure>
<p>In a press release, Gownaris said, "Two decades ago, there were about 1.5 adult male Magellanic penguins for every adult female at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Punta%20Tombo">Punta Tombo</ref>[...] Today, it's approaching three males for every female." The findings suggested a disparity in the death rate of juvenile and adult penguins, rather than differences in chick survival, account for this difference. </p>
<p>Punta Tombo is one of the annual breeding sites for the species; it is in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Argentina">Argentina</ref>. The penguins travel thousands of miles each year to reach these sites.</p>
<p>The work involved building population models out of over thirty years of data collected by tagging individual penguins.  Findings also suggested the pronounced sex disparity might make population models used to predict survival among other birds with a more even gender balance inappropriate for use on Megallanic penguins.</p>
<p>According to the data, since 1987, overall population of Magellanic penguins in Punta Tombo at one of their annual breeding sites in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Argentina">Argentina</ref> has declined 40%, while the male-to-female ratio has greatly increased.</p>
<p>Since 1983, the research team has been putting stainless steel bands on tens of thousands of chicks hatched at the Punta Tombo breeding site in Argentina, noting which juvenile and adult birds make it back to the site the next year and extrapolating how many lived and died.  Among juveniles, there was a 17% survival rate for males and 12% for females.  Among adults, it was 89% and 85%.  These effects became compounded every year, reaching as high as six males to one female among older penguins.</p>
<p>The researchers noted implications for penguin conservation: Gownaris remarked, "Over the years, this team has helped preserve the land and waters around breeding colonies like Punta Tombo[...] But now we're starting to understand that, to help Magellanic penguins, you have to protect waters where they feed in winter, which are thousands of miles north from Punta Tombo."</p>
<figure><caption>Two bloodied males at Punta Tombo fighting over a female in the background. Gownaris told our correspondent about increased aggression from male birds. Image: Natasha Gownaris.</caption></figure>
<p>Gownaris answered a series of questions for our correspondent.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What prompted your curiosity about Magellanic penguins? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Natasha Gownaris</hi>: I've wanted to be a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Marine_science">marine scientist</ref> since I was a child, when I would collect sand crabs (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emerita%20talpoida">Emerita talpoida</ref></hi>) from local beaches in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York_State">New York</ref>. I studied fish as a graduate student, but I have a pair of adopted parrots and I am generally fascinated by birds. Plus, penguins eat fish! Studying penguins seemed like a great way to merge my love for the ocean and my love for birds. Penguins and other seabirds are also important to study because they tell us something about the health of the ocean ecosystems they feed in, similar to the use of canaries to test air quality in coal mines. Unfortunately, the decline of many seabird species worldwide is yet another warning sign of the negative and widespread impacts humans are having on the ocean.</p>
</text>
