<text id="autogum_interview_doc239" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Torbjorn Zetterlund, Willowdale" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-06" dateModified="2013-05-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_Party_candidate_Torbjorn_Zetterlund%2C_Willowdale" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Torbjorn Zetterlund, Willowdale</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 6, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Torbjorn Zetterlund</hi> is running for the Green Party of Ontario in the Ontario provincial election, in the Willowdale riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>Seven years ago, I had a life-changing experience. I was paralyzed from the Guillain Barre Syndrome   and spent weeks in hospital unable to move around. I've since recovered but those weeks put things in perspective. I had time; I was removed from my daily life, where like many others I was spending my time chasing a dream of a bigger salary, bigger house. I watched TV; I saw programs about the environment and the effects of global warming and decided I should personally do "something" about it. I joined the Green party because the party's platform reflects my own values with its strong concern for the environment. I would like my children and others like them to enjoy clean air, clean land, and clean water and a sustainable future.</p>
<p>I also believe in serving my community. Willowdale is important to me, I have lived in the neighbourhood for seven years, most of the time I've been in Canada. It is place that is welcoming community that represents the best of Toronto. I founded [www.findmore.ca a community neighbourhood website], where I write articles on the environment and social issues and engage with members to form neighbourhood groups to discuss how they impact on local concerns. I am a volunteer coach for my kids’ soccer and ice hockey teams because I believe that involving children in a healthy life style is essential to their life-long well-being.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>My grandfather was involved in city politics in Sweden and I learnt from, during my military service in Sweden, I was the union leader of the soldiers rights. I am a resource manager at a Toronto software firm. Coming from the world of project management, I know how to manage, motivate and empower people. My business experience has also taught me, that it’s important to fulfill promises you make to people, a crucial skill for a political representative.</p>
</text>
