<text id="autogum_interview_doc1329" title="part0_Wikinews investigates the reconstruction of Pichilemu, Chile after February earthquake" shortTile="partwikinews-investigates" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-23" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_investigates_the_reconstruction_of_Pichilemu%2C_Chile_after_February_earthquake" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews investigates the reconstruction of Pichilemu, Chile after February earthquake</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, October 24, 2010</hi></p>
<p style="text-align:left;"><hi rend="bold">Left:</hi> A recently constructed kiosk with the new design. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.<hi rend="bold">Right:</hi> The original design of the kiosk, as shown in the plans by the Municipality. Image: Ilustre Municipalidad de Pichilemu.</p>
<p>Eight months after a catastrophic earthquake, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> has investigated the devastation caused in February and the reconstruction of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pichilemu">Pichilemu</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chile">Chile</ref>. The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2010_Chile_earthquake">February 27 earthquake and a subsequent tsunami</ref> completely destroyed Pichilemu's most coastal street and its oldest villages. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> has also had access to the original design plans of the new <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/kiosk#English">kiosks</ref> in Pichilemu, and conducted an interview with merchant Alejandro Mella, known locally as the King of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Durvillaea%20antarctica">Cochayuyo</ref> ("El Rey del Cochayuyo"), who lost his kiosk after the earthquake.</p>
<p>Pichilemu is a coastal city in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/O'Higgins_Region">O'Higgins Region</ref> of Chile, known as one of the "best surfing spots" in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_America">South America</ref>. Its current <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mayor%20of%20Pichilemu">Mayor</ref> is <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Roberto_Córdova_Carreño">Roberto Córdova Carreño</ref>, who was elected internally by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Councillor%20of%20Pichilemu">Councillors</ref> of the city in September 2009, after several <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2003–2009%20Pichilemu%20political%20controversies">political controversies</ref> that ended with three Mayors being displaced.</p>
<p>The territory of Pichilemu has a surface of 7,491 square kilometers, and comprises at least 24 villages, such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ciruelos">Ciruelos</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rodeíllo">Rodeíllo</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Espinillo,%20Chile">Espinillo</ref> (the latter two also severely damaged by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2010_Pichilemu_earthquake">March 11 earthquake</ref>). Pichilemu is the most popular beach in O'Higgins Region, and many tourists visit it every summer.</p>
<head id="'The_house_moved_from_side_to_side._I_really_thought_it_was_going_to_fall':_First_earthquake_strikes">'The house moved from side to side. I really thought it was going to fall': First earthquake strikes</head>
<figure><caption>People in Pichilemu fled to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La%20Cruz%20Hill">La Cruz Hill</ref>, the village of Pueblo de Viudas, or simply they left the city, risking themselves because roads were very damaged. In the picture, people near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los%20Navegantes">Los Navegantes</ref>, going to La Cruz Hill. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The earthquake took place in what is considered the "last weekend in the summer;" on Saturday, February 27, 2010 at 03:34 local time (06:34 UTC), while almost all Chileans were sleeping. Hours earlier, on Friday, thousands of people had arrived at Pichilemu. "The house moved from side to side. I really thought it was going to fall. It was 3 or 4 minutes long," Diego Grez, a Chilean student who was in Pichilemu at the time of the quake, told <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Diego_Grez,_Chilean_earthquake_survivor">an interview</ref>.</p>
<p>A concert was being held at the <hi rend="italic">One Discotheque</hi> when the earthquake occurred. It is said that the audience panicked and fled outside the discothèque, and then to the La Cruz Hill. Most tourists fled outside the city right after the earthquake occurred, but many others opted to stay in the La Cruz Hill or the village of Pueblo de Viudas, which are the higher points in the city.</p>
<p>"Pichilemu is the symbolic beach resort in the Sixth Region [of O'Higgins], so it was not strange to even think that [during] the last weekend before the entrance to school, many people would be going to take advantage of it to take a vacation; and that's what happened," reported <hi rend="italic">El Rancagüino</hi>, the most important newspaper in O'Higgins Region, on February 28.</p>
</text>
