<text id="autogum_interview_doc724" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Christopher Beyette, prince of the Principality of Vikesland" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-07-10" dateModified="2009-02-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Christopher_Beyette%2C_prince_of_the_Principality_of_Vikesland" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Christopher Beyette, prince of the Principality of Vikesland</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 10, 2008</hi></p>
<p>Over the past few months, Wikinews reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User_talk:WNewsReporter">Joseph Ford</ref> has held several interviews with Kevin Baugh, president of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic%20of%20Molossia">Republic of Molossia</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/micronation">micronation</ref> located near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dayton">Dayton</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nevada">Nevada</ref>. This week, Ford had the opportunity to interview another intermicronational leader, Christopher Beyette, prince of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principality%20of%20Vikesland">Principality of Vikesland</ref>, another micronation located in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manitoba">Manitoba</ref>. </p>
<p>At only three years old, the Principality is a relative newcomer to the intermicronational community.</p>
<p>When asked if he considers Vikesland a serious micronation, Prince Christopher said that his country is "a new nation project. Our goal is to eventually become an internationally recognized state with hopefully some sort of small sovereign land base."</p>
<p>He went on to tell much more about Vikesland, which can be read in the interview below.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Today, there are hundreds of micronations that are little more than online chat groups or role playing games. Is the Principality of Vikesland a serious land-claiming micronation? Do you have the goal of eventual international recognition?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Prince Christopher:</hi> The Principality of Vikesland was created as a new nation project. Our goal is to eventually become an internationally recognized state with hopefully some sort of small sovereign land base. Right now we do have land owned by various members of the Royal family and nobility that are declared Vikeslandic territory. This territory is unfortunately not sovereign territory but simply privately owned land in other older larger and more established Macro-nations. We are not secessionists and have no desire to forcefully take any land from any country that is not willing to give it to us. The current goal is to build the nation to the point where we can be successfully recognized by the international community. The issue of sovereign land will then be easier to negotiate with friendly countries. We plan on gaining the capacity to purchase an island or tract of land that equals at least 20 square miles to then establish ourselves on a full national scale.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Where is the Principality of Vikesland located?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Prince Christopher:</hi> The main land base for Vikesland is in Manitoba, Canada near the Riding Mountian national park on the eastern side. Looking on a map, it is approximately 3 miles west of the small town of Kelwood and about 1/2 mile to the south. We also have other declared lands in Europe, the U.S.A. , Australia and Africa.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How large is Vikesland?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Prince Christopher:</hi> Vikesland's main Land base in Manitoba Canada is approximately 169 acres. Land size in Europe tallies to a larger 1,200 acres! When all is said and done we have an approximate current total of 1,400 acres between all Royalty and nobility.</p>
</text>
