<text id="autogum_interview_doc889" title="part14_Author Amy Scobee recounts abuse as Scientology executive" shortTile="partauthor-amy-scobee" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-11" dateModified="2015-12-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_Amy_Scobee_recounts_abuse_as_Scientology_executive" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In chapter 10, "Assault and Battery", you recount witnessing instances of violence by David Miscavige towards Scientology officials including: Ray Mithoff, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mike_Rinder">Mike Rinder</ref>, and Jeff Hawkins. You write, "I am ashamed that I did not have enough courage at the time to inform the authorities or call the police, which would have been the logical thing to do." Why do you think you decided not to report these instances to the police? What do you think law enforcement would have done if you had reported the matter to police? Knowing what you know now, and revisiting your memories of these incidents in hindsight, would you have acted differently if you were in the same situation again?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: As I mentioned above, I learned at an early age that Scientology "handles its own" and that one of the biggest crimes you can commit is to bring about bad publicity for the organization as that is directly counter to the expansion plans of eradicating the reactive mind on the entire planet before it's "too late". At first, I justified the abuse – making excuses for why it could possibly be occurring. I thought, "Miscavige is the head of the religion and he's having to handle so much that all the stress and non-compliance is putting him over the edge". But when it kept occurring and kept occurring, I ran out of justifications. I could finally see that it was a pattern of an abusive sociopath. When I first started exposing the abuse after I left Scientology, several of the Scientology executives who I used to work with put together sworn affidavits claiming Miscavige never laid a hand on anyone. These were typed up and signed under the penalty of perjury. They know it's a blatant lie, but they think they're defending their religion by doing this.</p>
<p>Regarding whether or not I would have done things differently were I in the same situation today – ABSOLUTLEY. I would have called the police. I would have filed criminal reports. I would have alerted the authorities that the head of the organization is hurting people in many ways and I would have gotten the agreement from my peers that Miscavige needed to come off any position of authority and has no right to lead in this fashion. I know that I would have been removed for Treason and declared a suppressive person for making that stand, but I'd be proud of the title because the one thing I would have left intact is my personal integrity.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The last chapter of your book describes your emotional reunion with your family after leaving Scientology - first meeting your father and then calling and meeting your mother - and finally reuniting with Mark "Mat" Pesch, now your husband. At any point in time did you feel unsafe during your journey to reunite with these people? Did Scientology's intelligence agency, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office%20of%20Special%20Affairs">Office of Special Affairs</ref> (OSA), monitor you or your family after you left the organization?</hi></p>
</text>
