<text id="autogum_interview_doc1239" title="part2_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You saw all this, but how long did it take before you started saying, 'I need to stop'?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  What happened is I got <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/alcohol%20poisoning">alcohol poisoning</ref>; I began hallucinating spiders on my ceiling.  I went up and Googled 'spiders, alcohol' and saw that that was a symptom of late-stage alcoholism, when it's chronic.  People in the very last stages of their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/alcoholism">alcoholism</ref>, of their illness, often hallucinate spiders; it's a common hallucination.  And it freaked me out.  I developed hives, I was shaking and I was more physically sick than I've ever been in my life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rosacea">Gin blossoms</ref> kind of stuff.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  And I remember it took me maybe four or five hours to get the strength, the physical strength to go downstairs to get a six-pack of hard cider.  Brought it back up to the apartment and downed a couple of them, just really fast.  That took the edge off.  Then over the next forty-eight hours, I drank the rest of that six-pack--not to get a buzz, but to detox.  I was working my way through withdrawal in a very unhealthy way; I mean, you should never do that.  But that's what I was doing, and so, it was shortly after that that I woke up one morning and I was drinking again.  But I was not drinking quite as much.  I woke up one morning hung over, and I sat down and I wrote something.  It was two pages and it made laugh, and I hadn't laughed for years at that point, and that turned out to be the first couple pages of my first book, which was <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sellevision%20(novel)">Sellevision</ref></hi>.  It's a novel about the home shopping world, that whole world--and, I didn't know what I had written.  But it amused me, so I kept on writing, and I wrote until very late that night.  And I drank a little bit less.  And the same thing the next day.  Again, I had no idea what I was doing or where it was coming from, but by the seventh day, I was not drinking at all.</p>
<p>[food arrives]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Because the drinking just got in the way of this writing that I was doing, and I knew I wasn't writing the next great work, but it was--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You were proud of it.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  It was something.  I'd never written anything beyond an ad, you know, that was long, and  so by the seventh day I had finished the book.  I didn't know if it was a good book or a bad book, but I'd finished the book.  And that’s really when my life changed.  That's when I decided, I'm going to do this the rest of my life.  I'm gonna be a writer, I've just finished writing a book.  Now, it may be a piece of shit, but that doesn't matter, it's 150 pages, and they're in order--</p>
</text>
