<text id="autogum_interview_doc1195" title="part7_BDSM as business: An interview with the owners of a dungeon" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_An_interview_with_the_owners_of_a_dungeon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They choose one?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  They choose one or two, and then they get--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How many girls typically work on one night?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Anywhere between four to eight.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And whoever's not currently engaged will be there.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Even the girls that are busy will sometimes just come in to say, "Hi, how are you?"</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How large is your client base?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  That's a good question.  Would you say thousands?</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Thousands.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Of repeat people.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  That come at different times, and--</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  And I probably know ninety percent of them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How many times would a regular be considered?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Once a month?  Once every two months?  Do you have guys every six months?  You have guys every six months, right?</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  More than that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  No, no, you can--If you had ten thou--let's say you had five thousand clients, and they came twice a week.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  That would be--you'd do ten thousand sessions a week.  Right?  You follow what I'm saying?</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  No--I do, but I see them more often than that.  I can't tell you.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Okay.  Probably we do have guys that come twice a week.  Like a regular percentage of them come twice a week.  But the bulk of the--</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  I have guys come every day.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Do you?</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Yeah.  I have guys that I know that--every day, 10:30 in the morning, they will be here.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  We have a lot of wealthy, wealthy people who--</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  I can't tell you how insane of a business it is.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  But what I was trying to tell you is, it's not that we're that great.  It's that everybody else out there--</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Is that bad.  And so unkind.  So unsympathetic, and so nasty.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Are you familiar with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Africa">Africa</ref> and what goes on in Africa and when one warlord takes over, what happens?  They get a power hold and they just goes to their heads. Well, that's what happens in these places.  You give a twenty-five-year old, thirty-year-old girl in power, and it goes to their head.  And so these places, what happens is they get nasty, nasty girls.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Which is not what the clients are coming for.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  No.</p>
<head id="What_happens_when_a_client_walks_through_the_door">What happens when a client walks through the door</head>
<figure rend="BDSM business cards.jpg"></figure>]
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So I'm that person, and I walk in the door, and I'm nervous as anything--what do you do?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Right.  I let you go to the bathroom--My wife lets you go to the bathroom, because you probably have to pee, because you've been holding it--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Holding it and didn't realize it.</hi></p>
</text>
