<text id="autogum_interview_doc1410" title="part4_John Vanderslice plays New York City: Wikinews interview" shortTile="partjohn-vanderslice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-27" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Vanderslice_plays_New_York_City%3A_Wikinews_interview" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is it a problem for you to work with people who are using drugs? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  I would never work with them.  It is a very selfish decision to make and usually those people are total energy vampires and they will take everything they can get from you.  Again, this is all in theory...I love that stuff in theory.  If Amy Winehouse was my girlfriend, I would probably not be very happy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Your latest CD is <hi rend="italic">Emerald City</hi> and that is an allusion to the compound that we created in Baghdad.  How has the current political client affected you in terms of your music?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi> In some ways, both <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pixel%20Revolt">Pixel Revolt</ref></hi> and <hi rend="italic">Emerald City</hi> were born out of a recharged and re-energized position of my being....I was so beaten down after the 2000 election and after 9/11 and then the invasion of Iraq, Afghanistan; I was so depleted as a person after all that stuff happened, that I had to write my way out of it. I really had to write political songs because for me it is a way of making sense and processing what is going on. The question I'm asked all the time is do I think is a responsibility of people to write politically and I always say, My God, no. if you're <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morrissey">Morrissey</ref>, then you write Morrissey stuff.  If you are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel%20Bejar">Dan Bejar</ref> and Destroyer, then you are Dan Bejar and you are a fucking genius.  Write about whatever it is you want to write about.  But to get out of that hole I had to write about that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  There are two times I felt deeply connected to New York City, and that was 9/11 and the re-election of George Bush.  The depression of the city was palpable during both.  I was in law school during the Iraq War, and then when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hurricane%20Katrina">Hurricane Katrina</ref> hit, we watched our countrymen debate the logic of rebuilding one of our most culturally significant cities, as we were funding almost without question the destruction of another country to then rebuild it, which seems less and less likely.  Do you find it is difficult to enjoy living in America when you see all of these sorts of things going on, and the sort of arguments we have amongst ourselves as a people?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  I would say yes, absolutely, but one thing changed that was very strange:  I fell in love with a French girl and the genesis of <hi rend="italic">Emerald City</hi> was going through this visa process to get her into the country, which was through the State Department.  In the middle of process we had her visa reviewed and everything shifted over to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homeland%20Security">Homeland Security</ref>.  All of my complicated feelings about this country became even more dour and complicated, because here was Homeland Security mailing me letters and all involved in my love life, and they were grilling my girlfriend in Paris and they were grilling me, and we couldn't travel because she had a pending visa.  In some strange ways the thing that changed everything was that we finally got the visa accepted and she came here.  Now she is a Parisian girl, and it goes without saying that she despises America, and she would never have considered moving to America.  So she moves here and is asking me almost breathlessly, <hi rend="italic">How can you allow this to happen</hi>--</p>
</text>
