<text id="autogum_interview_doc698" title="Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Progressive Conservative candidate Dan McCreary, Brant" shortTile="ontario-votes--interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-02" dateModified="2009-04-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Progressive_Conservative_candidate_Dan_McCreary%2C_Brant" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Progressive Conservative candidate Dan McCreary, Brant</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 2, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Dan McCreary</hi> is running for the Progressive Conservative in the Ontario provincial election, in the Brant riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I have been interested in the political process all my life; and involved in the political scene for over 20 years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I am serving my second term on Brantford City Council.</p>
<p>I believe that my experience at the municipal level will be very helpful in taking the concerns of Brant to the Provincial level.</p>
<p>As a small business person I know the challenges that small business face. I can use this experience to make sure that the provincial government is aware and responds to the need of the economy in our area.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?</hi></p>
<p>I am faceing an incumbent and that is often thought to be an advantage.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>As I said above I believe that my municipal experience will give me considerable insight into the needs of Brant and my interaction with other levels of government while a city councillor will be most helpful in understanding how government works, so I will be able to get down to work right away.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>The three most important local issues are:
<list type="ordered"><item>The growing lack of respect for the law and increasing local crime rate. The PC platform is clear that everyone must obey the law; that there must be tougher penalties for those who break the law and more resources are needed to increase the number of police.</item>
<item>The number of people who do not have a family doctor. While this is a complex issue, we will increase the number of places in medical schools, speed up the accreditation of suitably trained foreign doctors and provide sufficient funding for the health care system and still eliminate the so called Liberal healthtax that is not all being spent on health.</item>
<item>Job loss. We have lost a large number of manufacturing jobs lately, as indeed has the whole province. A PC government will take those steps to create a productive economy by reviewing the tax system to see that we are competitive. We will invest in education to see that we have the best work force available.We will stimulate business investment in machinery and equipment as well as the latest technology. We believe that are policies will help people to find and to keep jobs.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>To get a grip on out of control Liberal spending and to eliminate waste such as the Liberal "slush fund" that went to friends of the Liberal Party.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>Yes, but they are too high since we are paying for things that should be the responsibility of the province, such as court security.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>See #3 above</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>personally I think it will create more problems than it will solve, but I will respect the will of the electorate and if that is what they want we will implement it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does "new media" play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>Our campaign has a website and uses Facebook. These can be great ways to connect with the public.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</hi></p>
<p>I cannot think of one decision that was particularly beneficial to Brant or the province. As to what was the most harmful it would be hard to choose, but the habit of the Dalton McGuinty Liberal government to make promises that they knew they would not be able to keep and then later break them while offering a feeble excuse, has done little to improve the opinion of people in the political process.</p>
</text>
