<text id="autogum_interview_doc391" title="part4_The Raveonettes on love, death, desire and war" shortTile="partthe-raveonettes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-16" dateModified="2010-12-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Raveonettes_on_love%2C_death%2C_desire_and_war" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think the religion adds an element of beauty or a fearful element to the culture?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Fearful element!  They have all their God fearing...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  It really depends on which kind of religion and which kind of place...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The kind practiced here, the kind of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christianity">Christianity</ref> found here. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Yeah!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  The extreme within the religion here in the U.S., that can be a little terrifying, I think.  But religion can also add a lot of purpose to people, and when they have purpose they can be more balanced and open-minded.  I don't know....</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  I like the televangelists a lot.  It's really entertaining for me to watch a show like that; it's really just like <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benny%20Hill">Benny Hill</ref></hi> and you watch it and can't believe it.  It's so far away from anything I've ever known.  And they talk about Islam being a dangerous religion but you look over here and it's just the same!  It's the same thing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They just aren't in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madrassah">madrassahs</ref>...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>   No, it's so crazy; it's fascinating.</p>
<head id="On_death">On death</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If you could choose your own <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Death">death</ref>, how would you die?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Oh, man.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  I would just like to go to sleep one night and not wake up.  I'm definitely scared of pain and diseases; I wouldn't want to wither.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  I'll go with Sharin.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You wouldn't want to experience it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  No way.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is fearful about it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  It's because if you are a creative person it's the fear you can never be creative again.  It's a terrifying feeling.  I don't like it all.  I think about it sometimes, where I think about, "One day you are going to die, you are never going to be here again, you're never going to do this..." and a whole weird feeling comes down through the body.  It's the only experience you can get when you think about death.  It's a crazy feeling, but obviously something draws me to it sometimes to experience to really get into my mind frame and think, "I'm really going to die, I'm never going to be here, I'm never going to get up again, <hi rend="italic">I'm really going to die</hi>!"  It's scary.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Especially at a young age, but if you are creative and have an imagination, it makes it that much scarier.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  But I had a near-death experience when I was in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hawaii">Hawaii</ref>.  I almost drowned, and I came to a point where I accepted my own death.  So, in a way now, when I think about death, that comforts me a little bit, even though it was such a scary experience at the time, it comforts me a little bit that you can actually accept your own death and actually feel comfortable about it.  Because I wasn't frightened at the time.  I was basically just comfortable that this it, you know, that this is the end.  And I was very relaxed, actually.  So I guess that's pretty cool.</p>
</text>
