<text id="autogum_interview_doc1057" title="part9_Past Eurovision contestants give advice to this year's performers, speculate on who will win" shortTile="partpast-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-05-06" dateModified="2015-09-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Past_Eurovision_contestants_give_advice_to_this_year%27s_performers%2C_speculate_on_who_will_win" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What were some of the best memories you have from going to Eurovision? What advice would you give to the singers going to Eurovision for the first time this year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tajči</hi>: I really enjoyed performing, I enjoyed the energy, everyone coming together and singing, talking with other people about their careers. That was the highlight. I didn't care for the press or the competition aspect, but there's so much to think about, the whole country is looking at you. I don't think it could ever be just about music, it's more political. But there's always stuff that comes with it when you have any kind of gathering like that.</p>
<p>The time I was there, I was the last representative before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breakup%20of%20Yugoslavia">fall of Yugoslavia</ref>, and it was during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revolutions%20of%201989">unification of Europe</ref>, and everyone was a bit more tense and elevated in that regard...and I was so young to experience all of that. I don't think I knew what to quite make of it. But it was a great experience, I'll always remember it. The night of my life, one of them anyway.</p>
<p>It's also very emotional because the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toto%20Cutugno">singer who won</ref> that year sang about "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Insieme:%201992">unite unite, Europe</ref>." It was perfect at that time. After he won, in the green room, he pulled a red rose from the bouquet and gave it to me, and he paid me some compliments. For a 19-year-old girl, that meant a lot.</p>
<p>My advice is to have fun, and do it with all your heart. Don't do it for the sole reason to win, not to launch your career, but because you love it, and it's what you do and you're good at it. You can be an inspiration to someone and it can be more than just providing entertainment.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The music videos for this year are up at <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/eurovision">http://www.youtube.com/eurovision</ref> . Which songs are your favorites and which country do you think has the best chance of winning?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tajči</hi>: Since we're in the middle of a tour, I kind of scrolled through, and I think the quality of the songs are really wonderful. I feel like I want to pack my bags and go to Europe for the summer, because I think this is going to be a summer for some great club music!</p>
<p>I'm partial to countries [who sing] in their original language, and I can see how a lot of countries, how even when they do the dance number and include ethnic elements, I like that.</p>
<p>I like the guy from Norway, I think he's so sincere and didn't look to me like he was "trying" anything, he was just being himself. The song is nice and happy. It doesn't hurt that he's really handsome, and has a good aura about him. He had so much energy, and he grabbed me right away, the way he moved, the way he sang, it just pulled me in. </p>
</text>
