<text id="autogum_interview_doc1254" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Bob Ely, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-05-25" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Bob_Ely%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Wikinews interviews Bob Ely, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 26, 2012</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democratic Party</ref> presidential candidate <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bob_Ely">Bob Ely</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Illinois">Illinois</ref> took some time to answer a few questions from Wikinews reporter William S. Saturn.</p>
<figure><caption>Bob ElyImage: Bob Ely.</caption></figure>
<p>Ely, a graduate of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Yale_University">Yale University</ref>, worked for 18 years as an investment banker in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chicago">Chicago</ref> before leaving the industry in 2000 to become a full-time investor and entrepreneur. Last year, he opened a campaign website and filed with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Federal_Election_Commission">Federal Election Commission</ref> (FEC) as a candidate challenging President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> for the Democratic Party presidential nomination. </p>
<p>Thus far, Ely has appeared on the Democratic primary ballot in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Hampshire">New Hampshire</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Louisiana">Louisiana</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Oklahoma">Oklahoma</ref>. His strongest showing occurred in Louisiana, where he won 6.57 percent of the vote, finishing in third place behind Obama and attorney <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Wolfe,_Jr.">John Wolfe, Jr.</ref>. Discussing the primary, he told <hi rend="italic">Politico</hi> that despite being "a candidate who bought no ads and did exactly zero campaigning," he won 120 of Louisiana's 4,395 voting precincts, and defeated President Obama in 457. Overall, Ely has won a total of 15,502 primary votes. </p>
<p>On Tuesday May 29, Ely will appear on the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Texas">Texas</ref> primary ballot alongside Obama, Wolfe, and historian <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Darcy_Richardson">Darcy Richardson</ref>, who suspended his campaign last month. It will be Ely's last chance to qualify for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012%20Democratic%20National%20Convention">Democratic National Convention</ref> delegates. Four of his fellow challengers have already done so: anti-abortion activist <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Randall_Terry">Randall Terry</ref> and perennial candidate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim%20Rogers%20(Oklahoma%20politician)">Jim Rogers</ref> both qualified in Oklahoma, Wolfe qualified in Louisiana and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Arkansas">Arkansas</ref>, and prison inmate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keith%20Russell%20Judd">Keith Russell Judd</ref> qualified in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/West_Virginia">West Virginia</ref>. For various reasons, the Democratic Party stripped the delegates from each of these candidates.</p>
<p>On his campaign website, Ely outlines a plan for a "job's bank", which would use the existing organization for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unemployment%20benefits#United_States">unemployment benefits</ref> to create a program where businesses can hire individuals to new positions with government salaries of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum%20wage%20in%20the%20United%20States">minimum wage</ref>. He also wants to make it easier for businesses to terminate employees, and has proposed an increase in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taxation%20in%20the%20United%20States">taxes</ref> and tariffs. He is concerned about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20federal%20budget">federal budget</ref> deficit and wishes to significantly reduce government spending. On other issues, Ely has proposed a plan for "basic health care" coverage, endorses "amnesty" for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illegal%20immigration%20to%20the%20United%20States">illegal immigrants</ref> in certain situations, and supports a strong, but frugal military used only to "protect America, Americans and America’s clear national interests"</p>
<p>With <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, Ely discusses his personal background and views of President Obama, a few details about his campaign, and such political issues as jobs, energy, taxes, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nuclear_proliferation">nuclear proliferation</ref>.</p>
<head id="Personal">Personal</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are some of your proudest accomplishments?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Bob Ely</hi>: #1, convincing my wife I would be a worthy husband in 1982. #2, Stealing a 10 foot tall 1-ton bronze statue as part of a college event (prank) in 1979.  Sadly, that bit a foolish mayhem is probably one of the high-lights of my life.</p></p>
</text>
