<text id="autogum_interview_doc877" title="part2_Author Amy Scobee recounts abuse as Scientology executive" shortTile="partauthor-amy-scobee" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-11" dateModified="2015-12-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_Amy_Scobee_recounts_abuse_as_Scientology_executive" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I told my mother about the invitation and asked if I could go in with her to meet Brett, to which she agreed. Brett was a very handsome man, posted as the Public Registrar, responsible for signing new people up for service and collecting their money. He interviewed me and said that he could tell I had a lot of potential and would go very far in life, but that I needed to learn several tools to be able to do so successfully. I really wanted to find out all about this. Brett called my mother into his office and had her pay for my first course so I could get started immediately. And so, I enrolled on my first course – the "Communications Course", on 17 May 1978.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Do you still see positive benefits out of some aspects of Scientology methodology? How so? What courses, programs, do you consider beneficial?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: There are some things that I consider to be basic truths, such as that one is a spiritual being, but that's not unique to Scientology. I honestly no longer consider the methodology to be beneficial since I have seen the results of its application in broken families and broken individuals. I do have many friends who still very much believe in the technology, but consider the organization has turned criminal. To me, people should be free to believe in what they'd like. It's when the practices begin to hurt people is where I object.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Why did you decide to join the elite Scientology group, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sea%20Org">Sea Org</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: I thought that it sounded like an exciting adventure where I could help "salvage the planet" on a much larger scale than just in my home town. The "Sea Organization" (also Sea Org or SO for short) is defined on the official Church of Scientology web site as follows:</p>
<p>"The Sea Org was established in 1967 and once operated from a number of ships. It was set up to help L. Ron Hubbard with research of earlier civilizations and supervise Church organizations around the world. The first Sea Org members formulated a one-billion-year pledge to symbolize their commitment to the religion as immortal spiritual beings. It is signed by all members today. The Sea Organization is also entrusted to minister the advanced services of Scientology. The Sea Organization retains its name in celebration of the fact that Mr. Hubbard’s life was frequently connected to the sea. Although today the majority of Sea Organization members are based on land, in keeping with the tradition of the order’s inception, they still wear maritime-style uniforms and have ranks and ratings. Sea Org members work long hours and live communally with housing, meals, uniforms, medical and dental care provided by the Church. They participate in Scientology training and auditing during a portion of each day, but otherwise dedicate themselves to furthering the objectives of Scientology through their particular functions."</p>
</text>
