<text id="autogum_interview_doc1093" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with independent candidate Charles de Kerckhove, St. Paul's" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-01" dateModified="2014-03-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_independent_candidate_Charles_de_Kerckhove%2C_St._Paul%27s" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>Issues of highest importance naturally differ from one voter to another, and all heard to date have been deserving of consideration and corrective action. Voter concerns have included the need for Toronto’s city revenues to better reflect current provincial and federal taxation levels, specifically an end to the financing of provincially mandated programs through municipal property taxes, also unacceptable accessibility to GPs and to certain medical procedures, questionable standards of leadership in the environment as compared to international initiatives, inadequate community representation within the police force in areas concerned about gun violence, and also basic trust in the accountability of government programs. Voters of all ages have been responsive to this campaign’s proposals to better support and protect children from abuse, I am proud to be advocating positive change on this issue.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>All Members of Provincial Parliament should support a bill mandating a comprehensive in-school prevention program to be accessed by every child in Ontario, bar none. It would combine the best available age-specific research addressing all potential sexual offences, from offenders unknown or well-known to a child (whether acquaintance, relative, peer, stranger, internet predator, etc.). Organisations with excellent preventive initiatives are currently not receiving any public funding, detracting not only from this outreach but from other programs as well (support of troubled children, teen runaway prevention, community responses to child abuse and family violence, relationship skills for teenage females at risk of violence, etc.). As such an initiative would be promoting children’s well-being, it could be named “Remembering Holly” so as to honour the memory of the much-missed Holly Jones. With the help of the organisations above, social workers, and educational assistants, it could be integrated into current in-school programs such as the Safe Schools Action Team.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>No. The city of Toronto claims that 32% of its budget is absorbed by provincially mandated / cost shared programs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>By investing in the health and well-being of every Ontarian child. The Government of Canada supports a study accounting for the national costs of child physical and sexual abuse as $ 15.5 billion dollars a year, much of which is traced to lost earnings potential comparing formerly abused children to formerly non-abused children from the same socio-economic backgrounds.</p>
<p>Job creation in the more short-term could be stimulated by supporting the more promising new service industries. Manufacturing companies could be evaluated for support based on due diligence towards the Occupational Health and Safety Act, due diligence towards environmental protections and cogeneration initiatives, viability of the long-term business plans, and re-usability of input materials.</p>
</text>
