<text id="autogum_interview_doc250" title="part8_Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy" shortTile="partdr-joseph-merlino" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-04" dateModified="2013-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dr._Joseph_Merlino_on_sexuality%2C_insanity%2C_Freud%2C_fetishes_and_apathy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  No, she's just another co-worker, who I've never even met.  We've just spoken on the phone once.  She has a kind voice.  But I have acted this out in my head often, as a way to give myself a chuckle.  To actually do it would be mortifying.  It might scare her and I wouldn't want to do that.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi> Maybe you would.  That's what Freud would say.  There's a dynamic behind that, which is not so easily apparent, but when you think about it or you analyze it, there might be some reason behind it.  Or Barbara might actually be a stand-in for somebody else that you really <hi rend="italic">would</hi> like to have somebody from the living dead come and...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  But would that be a pathology, that I've acted this harassing phone call out in my head?  And if it's not a problem, is it because the act is relatively harmless, as opposed to wanting to drown my baby?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  No.  You are enjoying it, you are laughing about it, it's doing something for you.  It's not causing anybody pain or grief.  It's not like you are staying up nights worrying about Barbara is going to see your name and you are going to lose your job, and you can't eat anymore.  Based on this scenario...it's a joke!  But as Freud would say, jokes aren't just jokes.  They have a meaning.  And if you can get beyond that and understand it, you might learn something that's a little different than what you are saying.  There might be a meaning.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Such as, why do I find violating a social norm or more amusing?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi> Yeah.  It might be particular to Barbara, or who 'Barbara' represents.  When you talk about <hi rend="italic">Night of the Living Dead</hi> there's a connection immediately there to this person and this wish.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is there always a connection?  For instance, just that opening of the movie sticks in my head and I don't meet many Barbaras.  It was just something that popped into my head, synapses fired.  And that movie <hi rend="italic">did</hi> play a role in my life, trust me.  But would it always signify something deeper than that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  An orthodox analytic position would be that there is always something deeper than that.  I think practically, sometimes a cigar is just a cigar.</p>
<head id="Cultural_psychology_in_the_United_States_today">Cultural psychology in the United States today</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you noticed any affect that the current political culture has had on your patients, in terms of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq War</ref>?  Either in pathologies where the war is manifesting itself, or in just a general discomfort with the state of the culture and society as it is?</hi></p>
</text>
