<text id="autogum_interview_doc1100" title="part0_US Nazi leader talks about Barack Obama, the economy and more" shortTile="partus-nazi-leader" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-11-18" dateModified="2015-01-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Nazi_leader_talks_about_Barack_Obama%2C_the_economy_and_more" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>US Nazi leader talks about Barack Obama, the economy and more</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 22, 2008</hi></p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Socialist%20Movement%20(United%20States)">National Socialist Movement</ref> is, according to its website, the largest and most active Nazi party in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>. Accordingly, it refers to itself as 'America’s Nazi Party' and aims to instigate major change in the US.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> was able to conduct an interview with the head of the party, Commander Jeff Schoep. Fresh back from a march in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missouri">Missouri</ref>, Commander Schoep told <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> his views on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>, the economy and much more.</p>
<p>Read the full exclusive interview below:</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure> <p><hi rend="bold">Does your party believe America will be a better or worse place with Obama as President?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Commander Schoep:</hi> Here is my answer to this: <ref target="http://www.nsm88.org/activities/why%20obama%20is%20good%20for%20our%20movement.html">Why Obama is Good for Our Movement</ref></item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How will the National Socialist Movement react to the election of Barack Obama - will there be co-operation or will you be opposed to him?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Commander Schoep:</hi> Obongo is just another figurehead. He answers to International jewry just like McCain, it does not matter what color his skin is, he is more of the same old same old system that has crippled our Nation.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Obama says he wants to close <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Guantanamo_Bay">Guantanamo Bay</ref> - what are your views on this?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Commander Schoep:</hi> Our Position on Guantanamo is that it is a National disgrace and should be shut down completely. The Prison was set up to torture and avoid U.S. laws of fair treatment of prisoners, it should be closed. Furthermore many Soldiers (P.O.W.'s) are being held there in violation of International P.O.W. laws, instead these soldiers are classified as enemy combatants or terrorists. For example the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taliban">Taliban</ref> was the legitimate Government in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref>, yet their soldiers are not classified as soldiers. It is a violation of the rules of warfare, and it is criminal. For those reasons the Prison should be closed and the soldiers returned to their homelands.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">There are fears Obama may be assassinated. What do you think that would mean for America and for your party?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item>Commander Schoep declined to answer this question.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why do you think Obama succeeded over <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_McCain">McCain</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Commander Schoep:</hi> McCain is an out of touch fool who openly crusaded for his beloved 3rd World invaders, who did not vote for him anyways because he is white. The Republicans lost many votes not just due to McCain's lack of charisma, but mainly because the common man is sick of the Republican lies and same old dog and pony show that was King <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George Bush</ref>. Voters see McCain as an extension of the policies that got us into the current economic mess/hardship in our Nation. Obama came across to the masses as someone who would change things. Whereas the voters believe he will change things and make America prosperous once again, I think his idea of change will likely be similar to the change <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kwame%20Kilpatrick">Kwame Kilpatrick</ref> did for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Detroit">Detroit</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marion%20Barry">Marion Barry</ref> did for DC, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Robert_Mugabe">Robert Mugabe</ref> did for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Zimbabwe">Zimbabwe</ref>. Time will tell if he rules the land honestly, or if he attempts to further corrupt it, perhaps installing a communist like agenda to uplift the ghetto into the Suburbs. We will see...</item></list></p>
</text>
