<text id="autogum_interview_doc1389" title="part12_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<head id="The_Iraq_War">The Iraq War</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think there should be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/conscription">conscription</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  I don’t know.  I don’t know.  That’s debatable to me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you consider our military a volunteer army?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Yeah.  I think that a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Volunteer%20military">volunteer army</ref>—I’m against drafts, even when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles%20Rangel">Charlie Rangel</ref> came out with it.  Even understanding the reasoning, to make rich as well as poor go, I just think the rich will find a way to get around it and there will still be a disproportionate amount of poor.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Which you saw in Vietnam, and many national leaders now found ways not to go.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Exactly right.  I was in high school at the time of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vietnam%20War">Vietnam War</ref>, there was a draft, and the rich kids didn’t go.  They found a way around it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How has <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq_War">the war</ref> affected you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  I think it has affected me in that I have seen and actually preached at soldiers’ funerals.  I’ve seen the families suffer for absolutely no reason.  There never was <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Weapon_of_mass_destruction">Weapons of Mass Destruction</ref>, there never was eminent danger, so I have seen it up close and personal in terms of families losing their sons.  I’ve also seen resources that we could have used to provide training and jobs in this country just sent over there arbitrarily.  I also watched when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hurrican%20Katrina">Katrina</ref> happened the way people who were relocated around the country couldn’t vote at home, but Iraqis could vote from America in the elections in Iraq.  I think it brought out the glaring contradictions of American democracy as practiced by people like the Bush administration.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you optimistic for the future?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Absolutely.  There is no doubt in my mind as I sit here today that the world will be better, America will be better, and that those like us—no matter how controversial—will be redeemed in history.  There is no doubt in my mind.  Whether we live to see it physically or not, I have no doubt in my mind.</p>
<head id="Sharpton_as_a_symbol">Sharpton as a symbol</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I interviewed <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Obesity_and_the_Fat_Acceptance_Movement:_Kira_Nerusskaya_speaks">documentary filmmaker Kira Nerusskaya</ref>, who is one of the leading voices in the fat acceptance movement.  She is what she calls a “BBW”.  A <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big%20Beautiful%20Woman">Big Beautiful Woman</ref>.  Your name came up in that interview and she called you "Reverend <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9-1-1">9-1-1</ref>" and mentioned that fat people don’t have their own "Al Sharpton", someone they can turn to when they are being hassled at work because they are a drain on their insurance, or when fat people are discriminated against or harassed.  When you hear that you have become a symbol that transcends your community, what do you think?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  I thought you were going to say she is disappointed that I’m not as fat as I used to be.  On one level I think it is flattering.  It is something you never think about when you jump into this.  Again, I joined the movement <hi rend="italic">way</hi> before I was old enough to understand all of that—</p>
</text>
