<text id="autogum_interview_doc592" title="part5_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic skiers Jessica Gallagher and Eric Bickerton" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-10" dateModified="2017-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_skiers_Jessica_Gallagher_and_Eric_Bickerton" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  On some national competitions they have a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B4%20(classification)">B4</ref> class. Do you think those should be eligible? In terms of the international competition?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> Which sports have B4s?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  There's a level down, it's not used internationally, I think it's only used for domestic competitions. I know the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">UK</ref> uses it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> I think I... A particular one. For social reasons, that's a great thing, but I think if it's, yeah. I don't know if I would... I think socially to get more Paralympic athletes involved in the sport if they've got a degenerative condition on that border then they should be allowed to compete but obviously... I don't think they should be able to receive any medals at a national competition or anything like that. So I was, after Beijing, I was able to fore-run races. I was able to transition over to skiing even though at that stage I wasn't eligible. So that was great for us. The IPC knew that my eyesight was going to get worse. So I was able to fore-run races.  Which was a really good experience for us, when we did get to that level. So I think, with the lack of numbers in Paralympic sport, more that you should encourage athletes and give them those opportunities, it's a great thing. But I guess it's about the athletes realizing that you're in it for the participation, and to grow as an athlete rather than to win medals. I don't think the system should be changed. I think three classes is enough. Where the B3 line is compared with a B4 is legally blind. And I think that covers everything. I think that's the stage where you have low enough vision to be considered a Paralympic sport as opposed to I guess an able bodied athlete. And that's with all forms of like, with government pensions, with bus passes, all that sort of stuff, that the cut off line is legally blind, so I think that's a good place to keep it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Veering away from this, I remember watching the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melbourne%20Cup">Melbourne Cup</ref> stuff on television, and there you were, I think you were wearing some hat or something. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> Yeah, my friend's a milliner. They were real flowers, real orchids.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Are you basically a professional athlete who has enough money or sponsorship to do that sort of stuff? I was saying, there's Jessica Gallagher! She was in London! That's so cool!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> There are two organizations that I'm an ambassador for, and one of them is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vision%20Australia">Vision Australia</ref>, who were a charity for the Melbourne Cup Carnival. So as part of my ambassador role I was at the races helping them raise money. And that involves media stuff, so that was the reason I was there. I didn't get paid.</p>
</text>
