<text id="autogum_interview_doc1017" title="part2_Interview with BBC Creative Archive project leader" shortTile="partinterview-bbc" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-06-20" dateModified="2010-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_BBC_Creative_Archive_project_leader" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>“The ambition is to think about creating a single portal where people can search and see what stuff is out there under the same licence terms, from a range of different suppliers. The idea is that if we can create something compelling like that, we will attract other archives in the UK to contribute their material, so we’d be aggregating quite a large quantity.”</p>
<p>The Creative Archive project has captured the interest of many Internet users, who are growing increasingly, used the idea of being able to ‘remix’ technologies and content. Some groups have been frustrated with the speed at which the project is developing though, and with some of the restrictions imposed in the licence. An open letter to the BBC urges the dropping of the UK-only limitation, the use of ‘open formats’, and to allow the material to be usable commercially. </p>
<p>Mr Gerhardt has publicly welcomed debate of the licence, but makes it clear to me that the whole BBC archive will never all be available under the Creative Archive terms. “We will make all our archive available, under different terms, over the next five to ten years, at a pace to be determined. There would be three modes in which people access it – some of the content would only be available commercially, for the first five year or so after broadcast, say. The second route is through a ‘view again’ strategy where you can view the programmes, but they’d be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DRM">DRM</ref>-restricted. And the third mode is Creative Archive. Over time, programmes would move from one mode to another, with some programmes going straight to the Creative Archive after broadcast.”</p>
<p>Others who disagree with the ‘UK-only’ restriction within the licence include <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suw%20Charman">Suw Charman</ref>, from the Open Rights Group, who has said “it doesn't make sense in a world where information moves between continents in seconds, and where it is difficult for the average user to exclude visitors based on geography.” On the project generally, though, she said “I think that it is a good step along the way to a more open attitude towards content. It is a toe in the water, which is far preferable to the attitude of most of the industry players, who are simply burying their heads in the sand and hoping that lawsuits and lobbying for new legislation will bolster their out-dated business plan.”</p>
<p>Other organisations currently participating in the Creative Archive scheme include the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British%20Film%20Institute">British Film Institute</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open%20University">Open University</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teachers'%20TV">Teachers' TV</ref>. Two artists have been awarded scholarships to create artworks using BBC archive material, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC%20Radio%201">BBC Radio 1</ref> has held a competition asking people to use the footage in creative ways as backing visuals to music. The process of making the BBC’s archive material fully available may be a long one, but it could end up changing the way that people interact with the UK’s public service broadcaster.</p>
</text>
