<text id="autogum_interview_doc670" title="part13_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I don't have an opinion on Woodward; he's been successful.  I mean, when I was a young man there was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20Reston">James Reston</ref>.  I wrote about him in The Kingdom of Power a lot.  He was the most important reporter when I was coming up in the 1950's, and he was in Washington and in bed with the enemy all the time.  He had sources in the administration of Kennedy, of Eisenhower before Kennedy, or Johnson.  He was a guy who liked power and liked being around power, and he was very much a patriot writer.  He was very popular and wrote easy-to-read pieces.</p>
<head id="On_travel_to_Cuba">On travel to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cuba">Cuba</ref></head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When I was in my teens and early twenties my travels were very Europe-centric.  But as an adult I have been drawn to places either seemingly "dangerous" to me or places that I don't feel like I know because I've read so much about them or seen so often in books and magazines. So Europe is off my map now, though I did sneak into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuba">Cuba</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  You have? When?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In 2002.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  How did you sneak into Cuba?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Through the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caymans%20Islands">Caymans Islands</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  How did you do it?</p>
<figure><caption>Gay Talese at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Strand%20bookstore">The Strand</ref> bookstore promoting <hi rend="italic">A Writer's Life</hi> in 2006.photo: David Shankbone</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Just took a flight on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aero%20Caribbean">Aero Caribbean</ref>.  Now they've stopped using the dollar. But back then, they were very much encouraging American tourists to come via <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  When was this you were there? 2002?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  2002.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  They stopped using the dollar?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They stopped using the dollar.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I was there in '96. I was there in '82. And I didn't sneak in, but I had to get a visa from the Czechoslovakian Embassy in Washington to get in there in '82. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ronald%20Reagan">Reagan</ref> was in power then and he didn't want me to go to Cuba. I went. My wife also went for two weeks. And then in '96 I went. And now you don't have the dollar. What do you have?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You have the Cuban pesos. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Where do you get them?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I'm not really sure now because when I was there they had the system where you could actually just use dollars. That's what we used.  The local currency was called <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuban%20convertible%20peso">pesos convertibles</ref></hi> that were convertible into dollars. Of course they have no value anywhere else in the world except in Cuba, but then they stopped doing that. Castro has kind of created <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fulgencio%20Batista">Batista</ref>'s society in some ways; not in every way. The poor are certainly a lot better off than they were under Batista. But with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuban%20embargo">embargo</ref>, the economy is now very tourist-based, which creates this tourist class. We didn't stay in the hotels. We wanted to stay in what they call <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casa%20particular">casa particulars</ref></hi> and I remember talking to a woman who made $30 a month as a doctor. But running this <hi rend="italic">casa particular</hi>, she was making around $300, $500 a month, which made her very rich.</hi></p>
</text>
