<text id="autogum_interview_doc1276" title="part1_Edmund White on writing, incest, life and Larry Kramer" shortTile="partedmund-white" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-08" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edmund_White_on_writing%2C_incest%2C_life_and_Larry_Kramer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I think he’s wrong; I don’t know where he is living.  If you go to high schools now—because I teach 18, 19, 20 year olds—they don’t know the classics.  All they know is <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Color%20Purple">The Color Purple</ref></hi> and stuff like that.  They all know <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Color%20Purple">The Color Purple</ref></hi> but they don’t know <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Fairy%20Queen">The Fairy-Queen</ref></hi>.  They have never read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Milton">Milton</ref>, but they have read <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction,_writing,_his_family_and_his_new_book">Augusten Burroughs</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Sedaris">David Sedaris</ref>.  So, he’s wrong.  [<hi rend="italic">Chuckles</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But what’s taught is not modern—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  No, it is!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Augusten Burroughs is taught?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Absolutely!  Absolutely!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That would seem like racy material for grade school or high school.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I don’t mean in Alabama; in America the curriculum is determined by each community, which is unlike every other country in the western world.  So, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tuscaloosa,%20Alabama">Tuscaloosa</ref> they are not going to teach something racy, but in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darien,%20Connecticut">Darien, Connecticut</ref> they are.</p>
<head id="On_work_as_a_gay_writer">On work as a gay writer</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Does it bother you to be considered a gay writer?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Well there is a question I have asked many many times.  I think it would be unrealistic to say I’m not a gay writer.  I emerged with a gay literary movement—<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Violet%20Quill">The Violet Quill</ref>—which was a group of gay writers who all started publishing in 1978, and I was labeled from the very beginning a gay writer.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And you embrace that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Embrace is another thing, but it would be unrealistic to deny it or act like it is some terrible offense, because if I am known at all it is because of the idea of gay literature.  Sometimes you wish you could have a wider readership, but every writer wishes that.  More women and straight men, but we all wish we had a wider readership.  In America, especially, everything is niche marketing and identity politics.  That’s not true in England, so much, and it’s certainly not true in France.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In England you have kids reading Afro-Caribbean literature because they don’t have a sense that it’s a “black thing”?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Yes, that’s right.  For instance, most of the well known writers in England under 50 are former colonial people, whether it’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kazuo%20Ishiguro">Ishiguro</ref>—he’s Japanese and that wasn’t part of the empire, but still—or David Hogue Davies.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caryl%20Phillips">Caryl Phillips</ref>, who is a black man from the islands who lives now in New York but is one of England’s most important writers.  Also <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salman%20Rushdie">Salman Rushdie</ref>.  In other words, the way we categorize people and dismiss them is not true of England because in fact the major winners of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Booker%20Prize">Booker Prize</ref> over the last thirty years are people who would not have been allowed in a private men’s club in England 50 years ago.</p>
</text>
