<text id="autogum_interview_doc263" title="part2_Wikinews interviews US National Archives Wikipedian in Residence" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-06-11" dateModified="2014-04-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_US_National_Archives_Wikipedian_in_Residence" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Wikimedia's projects can do more than just reach people, though. It's not merely a content host or a forum, like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flickr">Flickr</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Facebook">Facebook</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Twitter</ref>, and blogs. Wikimedia is a <hi rend="italic">community</hi> with an intellectual mission. It will not only make holdings findable, but it will add value to them. They write encyclopedia articles related to the holdings of cultural institutions, or to subjects for which holdings are valuable source material or illustrations; they organize, categorize, and even sometimes digitally restore images; they transcribe and proofread textual documents. They are doing this for their personal fulfillment, nearly always without the knowledge and cooperation of associated cultural institutions. Indeed, thousands of Wikimedians are already engaged in their own little projects which donated content or expertise can help along; both parties are interested in adding value to their work by partnering with the other.</p>
<p>Finally, Wikimedia is unique among the major online fora and hosts for cultural content in that it shares cultural institutions' commitment to open access and public education. Wikipedia is a non-profit, and creating free public knowledge is its sole purpose. All original content is released under a free copyright license so that it can be widely disseminated without permission or fee. In fact, its commitment to freedom of information is so strong that it often cannot even accept works from some cultural institutions which restrict their use in some way (such as by disallowing derivative works or requiring non-commercial use), and making institutions truly free and compatible with Wikipedia is one of the jobs of Wikipedans in Residence. Wikipedia is not just a venue for presenting our cultural heritage, it is an active ally for all institutions that seek to do so.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What aspect of having a Wikipedian in Residence is seen as most valuable to the National Archives? What would you, personally, say is the greatest benefit to any cultural institution from engaging with the Wikimedia community?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DMP</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> For the National Archives, all of the above apply. This is about public outreach and increasing access and use. NARA wants to find users where they are, not just wait for them to visit, and the people are on Wikipedia. According to David Ferriero, the National Archives would like this collaboration with Wikipedia to exemplify their "commitment to the Open Government principles of transparency, participation, and collaboration." Wikimedia partnerships are so promising because they can be extensions of any institution's mission in a number of conceivable ways. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You have already <ref target="http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/politics/conversations-dominic-mcdevitt-parks-national-archives-connects-with-wikipedia/2011/06/02/AGCYDWHH_story.html">told</ref> <hi rend="italic">The Washington Post</hi> that other institutions have hired Wikipedians in residence, including the British Museum, the Museu Picasso, and the Archives of American Art. Do you know of any other institutions that may develop similar relationships with Wikipedia in the near future?</hi></p>
</text>
