<text id="autogum_interview_doc390" title="part3_The Raveonettes on love, death, desire and war" shortTile="partthe-raveonettes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-16" dateModified="2010-12-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Raveonettes_on_love%2C_death%2C_desire_and_war" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="On_America">On America</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Sune, you went through a period where you got really tired of LA and New York and traveled around the United States.  What did you find when you traveled across the country?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  It struck me how different the country was as I went south and north, and towards the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middle%20America%20(United%20States)">middle</ref>.  It just struck me how really, really different it was.  Even when I was driving up to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref> once to get my visa, I rented a car from here and I was barely an hour outside of New York City everything changes so dramatically. The way people were, the way people looked at you in a "Who are you, stranger?  Get out of my town..." kind of thing.  It was so strange.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How did you react to that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  It always frightens me a little bit.  I never got comfortable.  I never like it when people are annoyed with you because of the way you look.  It just seems so dramatic.  I don't walk down the street and see a person and get so upset.  I don't know where that hatred comes from, or that mistrust of strangers or whatever it is.  I could never understand it and that's why it makes me uneasy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sharin:</hi>  Although you find that everywhere, including in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Denmark">Denmark</ref>, very much so.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  Yeah, but we're talking about the States here, Sharin!  I'm sure you can find it in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Africa">Africa</ref>, too! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  No, but seriously, people used to always tell me, "Oh, don't go down south, they are all racist," blah blah blah.  I had the <hi rend="italic">best</hi> time in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southern%20hospitality">south</ref>; people were <hi rend="italic">so</hi> hospitable to me.  Everywhere I went they were like, ‘Oh, you come from Denmark?  That's great...I'll give you this for free!'  And when I go north, people treat me like I'm crazy.  It's so weird, so strange.  So I guess the answer to your question is that I was very surprised at how different it was from place to place, and then I started understanding when the election came up and people were voting Democratic here, Republican there, it all made sense to me all of a sudden.  I was like, "Oh, I see, those are people who never leave their state, never leave their town..."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you find the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blue%20states">blue states more hospitable than the reds states</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sune:</hi>  It's a little bit of both, I would say, but people's attitude...same thing with 9/11.  People were like, "That happened in New York, there's no terrorist coming to my town and we hate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muslims">Muslims</ref> anyway, and they are not even welcome here."  They have that really brutal attitude some times; it's really <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Racism">racist</ref> and crazy.  Also because it is such a religious country in such a crazy way, so it's a very interesting country to travel in.</p>
</text>
