<text id="autogum_interview_doc831" title="part1_ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush" shortTile="partaclu-president" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-30" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion%2C_drugs%2C_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Nadine Strossen:</hi>  To be a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/civil%20libertarian">civil libertarian</ref> to affect individual rights in a positive way.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  As far back as I can remember I have always had an innate belief in what I now would call <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Individual%20rights">individual rights</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Equal%20justice">equal justice</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Due%20process">due process</ref>, and it came out in my family experiences and in my experiences in school as a young child.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What family experiences?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I shouldn’t say so much direct experiences—well, to some extent—but the stories I was brought up on as a kid.  My father was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holocaust%20survivor">holocaust survivor</ref> and my mother’s father was a protester during <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20War%20I">World War I</ref> when he came to this country as an immigrant, and he was literally spat upon for not going to fight in the war.  His official sentence for being a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/conscientious%20objector">conscientious objector</ref> was to be forced to stand against the courthouse in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hudson%20County,%20New%20Jersey">Hudson County, New Jersey</ref> so that passers-by could spit on him.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What were you taught about him?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I knew him as a kid and he told me these stories, and my mother told me, and it was very upsetting to me, but very inspiring to think about trying to rectify injustices.  When I say my own family, my own personal experiences are so trivial compared to those, but having teachers not allow different viewpoints come out in class and seeing kids tormenting other kids that were different.  When I got a little bit older there was an experience with a teacher who was exposing students to different viewpoints about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vietnam%20War">Vietnam War</ref>, and there was a call for him to be fired and he was editorialized against; I led a campaign to defend his free speech rights, and our free speech rights.  Once I had the idea that I could go to law school to get professional skills to advocate for values that I had always believed in, it just seemed the right thing to do.  There are many other paths, I realize, but it certainly has been a good path to try to work with the values I care deeply about that I have had throughout my whole life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvard%20Law%20School">Harvard</ref>, were you an activist on campus?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Not so much.  I should say, I was an activist, but it wasn’t like I was a leader of something.  Probably because I was involved in so many organizations and I was glad that I was exploring so many different forms of activism.  In college I was involved in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-war_movement#The_Vietnam_Era:_1962-1975">anti-war movement</ref>, and I was very involved in the women’s movement.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reproductive%20freedom">Reproductive freedom</ref> was a really big deal then; it was before <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roe%20vs.%20Wade">Roe vs. Wade</ref></hi>.  I remember there was a very high profile prosecution of a doctor for performing an abortion in Massachusetts, where I was in college.  Then in law school I was very active in a lot of organizations.  I wasn’t sure of which direction I actually wanted to go, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prisoner%20rights">prison legal assistance</ref> project, the voluntary defenders, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Legal%20aid">legal aid</ref> bureau…and I was also earning my way through law school so I had to do a lot of work.</p>
</text>
