<text id="autogum_interview_doc1073" title="part5_Vivien Goldman: An interview with the Punk Professor" shortTile="partvivien-goldman" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-30" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vivien_Goldman%3A_An_interview_with_the_Punk_Professor" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M.I.A.%20(musician)">M.I.A.</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tanya%20Stephens">Tanya Stephens</ref>.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan%20Jett">Joan Jett</ref>, still.  The Slits, who still suffer from the system and they are still brilliant.  Male bands of that statute would have more deals.  Big-tittied in terms of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cojones">cojones</ref>, as opposed to cleavage as such.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have moments of extreme self-doubt where you wonder if anything you do matters to anyone?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  I have a lot of moments of extreme self-doubt, but you have to be humble and listen to what people say.  Although I was never top of the New York Times book chart, I know people have liked my stuff, and that keeps me going.  The classes have been amazing.  I had done a lot of television and media, but it was the first time I had done something one-on-one.  It was the old cliche that a person learns as much as they teach.  Loads of my old students keep in touch with me; one wrote to me to tell me he is free-lancing for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XXL%20(magazine)">XXL</ref> and some other rap magazines, and how the classes really have been useful and he always refers to them.  Even just one person is gratifying and encourages me to continue my work.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You have worked for two corporations that are seen by many as the least punk in their respective communities, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC">BBC</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20University">NYU</ref>.  How does one remain punk in such environments?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  I'm a freelancer.  I go in, do my thing, and if they don't like it then I don't do it anymore.  I stay true to myself, and if it doesn't work out then I guess 'fuck off' on both sides.  I haven't had to compromise myself; nobody has asked me to.  BBC America is a different animal than the BBC.  As long as I can say what I want to say; I think people come to me because they know what they are getting.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you ever been in a situation where you feared for your life, where you thought, this may be the way I go?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  There was a lot of violence in the punk times and I got beaten up in street brawls.  I particularly remember once in Nigeria...  I was there to make a documentary for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Channel%204">Channel 4</ref> about Fela Kuti.  He was in jail at that time and he wanted to draw attention to his plight to showcase what was going on in Nigeria.  It was hard to get through customs because my guides weren't there to meet me.  I found them hiding in the carpark because the police were after them.</p>
<p>We went to Fela's house where I was going to stay; we went to the shrine and it was amazing.  The whole house was covered in people sleeping.  I was woken up by this little girl very early in the morning, only about two hours later.  She was tapping me on the shoulder and when I looked around there was <hi rend="italic">nobody</hi> there, whereas it had been covered in people.  She said, "Come! Come!  The army is here!"</p>
</text>
