<text id="autogum_interview_doc114" title="part0_Wikinews interviews specialists on China, Iran, Russia support for al-Assad" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-09-15" dateModified="2015-10-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_China%2C_Iran%2C_Russia_support_for_al-Assad" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews specialists on China, Iran, Russia support for al-Assad</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 23, 2013</hi></p>
<p>Over the past week, diplomatic actions have averted — or, at least delayed — military strikes on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syria</ref> by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> sought input from a range of international experts on the situation; and, the tensions caused by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref>'s support for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bashar_al-Assad">al-Assad</ref> regime despite its apparent use of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chemical_weapons">chemical weapons</ref>.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Ghouta_chemical_attack_map.svg">File:Ghouta chemical attack map.svg</ref></p><figure><caption>Map of areas affected by chemical weapons in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2013%20Ghouta%20attacks">Ghouta</ref>, Syria. Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:FutureTrillionaire">FutureTrillionaire</ref>.<hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Ghouta_chemical_attack_map.svg">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=File%3AGhouta+chemical+attack+map.svg">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure>
<p>Tensions in the country increased dramatically, late August when it was reported between 100 and 1,300 people were killed in an alleged chemical attack. Many of those killed appeared to be children, with some of the pictures and video coming out of the country showing — according to witnesses — those who died from apparent suffocation; some foaming at the mouth, others having convulsions.</p>
<p>Amongst Syria's few remaining allies, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref>, and Russia continue to oppose calls for military intervention. In an effort to provide a better-understanding of the reasoning behind their ongoing support, the following people were posed a range of questions.</p>
<head id="Interviewees">Interviewees</head>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Stephen Blank</hi></hi>, Senior Fellow at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Foreign%20Policy%20Council">American Foreign Policy Council</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington,_D.C.">Washington, D.C.</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Kerry Brown</hi></hi>, Professor of Chinese Politics from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/University_of_Sydney">University of Sydney</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Farideh Farhi</hi></hi>, an Affiliate with the Graduate Faculty of Political Science, and lecturer, at the ̣̣<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/University_of_Hawai'i">University of Hawai'i</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Honolulu">Honolulu</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Mehran Kamrava</hi></hi>, Professor and Director of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Center%20for%20International%20and%20Regional%20Studies">Center for International and Regional Studies</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Georgetown_University">Georgetown University</ref> in Washington D.C.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20C.%20Martel">William Martel</ref></hi></hi>, Professor of International Security Studies at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tufts_University">Tufts University</ref> near <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Boston">Boston</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rana Mitter</hi></hi>, Professor of the History and Politics of Modern China at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/University_of_Oxford">University of Oxford</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Walter Posch</hi></hi>, an Iran expert at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German%20Institute%20for%20International%20and%20Security%20Affairs">German Institute for International and Security Affairs</ref> (SWP) in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Berlin">Berlin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref>; and,</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Sam Roggeveen</hi></hi>, a fellow of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lowy_Institute_for_International_Policy">Lowy Institute for International Policy</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sydney">Sydney</ref>, Australia</item></list></p>
<head id="Wikinews_Q&amp;A"><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> Q&amp;A</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref> have remained as allies to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bashar_al-Assad">al-Assad</ref> government despite the alleged use of chemical weapons in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2013%20Ghouta%20attacks">Ghouta</ref> on August 21, 2013. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> queried the listed subject-matter experts regarding the diplomatic relations between these nations, and the reasoning behind such.</p>
<head id="China">China</head>
<figure><caption>File photo of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations_Security_Council">United Nations Security Council</ref> Chamber in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York_City">New York</ref>. Image: Patrick Gruban.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  There are suggestions China wants to maintain its financial ties with Syria as its third largest importer in 2010. Would you agree with this?</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Brown</hi>: I don't think that is China's key priority. China has a massive economy, and Syria is a very minor player in this. It has some, but not much, energy from Syria. Its real concerns in the current conflict are for stability, and geopolitical.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Farhi</hi>: China's conduct in Syria has been similar to its conduct elsewhere. It has given support to Russia in international forum such as the UNSC [<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations_Security_Council">United Nations Security Council</ref></hi>] and has acted opportunistically wherever its economic interest could be pursued. But, Syria is really not an area of interest for China. Its actions and support for the Russian position is derived from its general concerns regarding American imperialism and unilateralism.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Mitter</hi>: China will want, in general, to maintain financial ties with Syria as it does with many countries.  China's general position is that internal politics of countries should not interfere with economic ties.</item></list></p>
</text>
