<text id="autogum_interview_doc1002" title="part1_An interview with Jimbo Wales" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-02-21" dateModified="2014-10-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_Jimbo_Wales" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN:</hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:GeorgeStepanek">GeorgeStepanek</ref> asks: "You've said that 'Wikimedia's mission is to give the world's knowledge to every single person on the planet in their own language.' But very few of the wikipedias in the languages of third-world countries are seeing as much activity as the first-world language wikipedias. Do you have any ideas on how this could be turned around?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JW:</hi>  I am a believer in outreach. I would like for the Foundation to raise money specifically to pay one or more minority language co-ordinators. The goal would be to reach out in a more organized way to professors and graduate students and expat communities who have good Internet access, to seed projects for languages where the majority of speakers have poor internet access.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN:</hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Jacoplane">Jacoplane</ref> asks: "How do you feel we will be able to reach Wikipedia 1.0? The tools currently available for vetting our articles are crude at best. The Featured article process seems too slow, and the article validation feature seems to have died a quiet death. Are you planning a big push on this front?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JW:</hi>  Isn't that the same question as the quality question?  The article validation feature has not died a quiet death at all.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN:</hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Quadell">Quadell</ref> asks: "Most important decisions on Wikimedia projects are handled with consensus. However, we sometimes have to deal with legal issues, especially related to copyright law. For instance, we as a community may need to decide whether to consider a certain use "fair", or how to deal with conflicting copyright claims. Dealing with this through consensus is problematic, since we can't do something illegal even if there is widespread misguided support for it. In general, how can we as a community deal with these issues?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JW:</hi>  I don't think there is any real problem with this. The community is strongly in support of following the law. I don't know of any particular cases of widespread misguided support for something illegal. In particular cases, there can of course be [dis]agreement, but I have never seen anyone in the community argue that we should not listen to the advice of our legal team.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN:</hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Raul654">Raul654</ref> asks: "Where do you see Wikipedia in 10 years?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JW:</hi>  I don't know. My favorite answer to this is to say, the real question is: where will the world be after 10 more years of Wikipedia.:)  Seriously, I think we'll eventually see a tapering off of new article creation in the large language wikipedias as more and more "verifiable" topics are covered. At this point, most changes will be expansions and updates and quality improvements to existing articles.  But in 10 years, it seems likely to me that many languages which are now quite small will have very large Wikipedia projects. Our community will continue to become more diverse as more and more people worldwide come online.</p>
</text>
