<text id="autogum_interview_doc1439" title="part5_OpenSync Interview - syncing on the free desktop" shortTile="partopensync-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-05-19" dateModified="2014-01-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/OpenSync_Interview_-_syncing_on_the_free_desktop" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>The syncing logic itself resides in the sync engine, which is a separate part. The sync engine is responsible for deciding when to call the connect function of a plugin, when to read or write from it. The engine also takes care of invoking the format conversion functions so that each plugin gets the items in its required format.</p>
<p>If you want more information and details about the inner workings of OpenSync, you should really visit the opensync.org website or ask its developers.</p>
<head id="Takeoff">Takeoff</head>
<p>To add some more spice for those of our readers, whose interest you just  managed to spawn (or to skyrocket), <hi rend="bold">please tell us where they can get more information on the OpenSync Framework, how they can best meet and help  you and how they can help improving sync-support for KDE by helping OpenSync.</hi></p>
<p>Cornelius:</p>
<p>Again, the OpenSync web site is the right source for information. Regarding the KDE side, the kde-pim@kde.org mailing list is probably the right address. At the moment the most important help would be everything which gets the OpenSync 1.0 release done.</p>
<p>[And even though] I already said it, it can't be repeated too often: OpenSync will be the one unified syncing solution for the free desktop. Cross-device, cross-platform, cross-desktop.</p>
<p>It's the first time I feel well when thinking about syncing ;-).</p>
<p>Armin:</p>
<p>Regarding OpenSync, the best places to ask would be the opensync mailing lists at sourceforge or the #opensync irc channel on the freenode.net servers.</p>
<p>There are always a lot of things where we could need a helping hand and where we would be really glad to get some help. So everyone who is interested in OpenSync is welcome to join.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Many thanks for your time!</hi></p>
<p>Cornelius:</p>
<p>Thanks for doing the interview. It's always fun to talk about OpenSync, because it's really the right thing.</p>
<p>Armin:</p>
<p>Thank you for taking your time and doing this interview. I really appreciate your help!</p>
<p>Tobias:</p>
<p>Thanks for your work. Publication and marketing is something that is really missing in the open source community. We have nice software but nobody knows ;)</p>
<p>Further Information on OpenSync can be found on the OpenSync Website: <ref target="http://www.opensync.org">www.opensync.org</ref></p>
<p>This Interview was done by <ref target="http://draketo.de/">Arne Babenhauserheide</ref> in April 2006 via e-mail and <ref target="http://koffice.kde.org/">KOffice</ref> on behalf of himself, the OpenSource Community, SpreadKDE.org and the Dot (<ref target="http://dot.kde.org/">dot.kde.org</ref>).
It was first published on the Dot and is licensed under the <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5/">cc-attribution-sharealike-license</ref>.
A pdf-version with pictures can be found at <ref target="http://draketo.de/dateien/texte/opensync-interview.pdf">opensync-interview.pdf</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenDocument">OpenDocument</ref> version: <ref target="http://draketo.de/dateien/texte/opensync-interview.odt">opensync-interview.odt</ref>)</p>
<hi rend="bold">This page has been automatically <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews:Archive_conventions">archived</ref> by a robot, and is no longer publicly editable.</hi>
<p>Got a correction? Add the template {{<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Editprotected">editprotected</ref>}} to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Talk:Main_Page">talk page</ref> along with your corrections, and it will be <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews:Admin_action_alerts#Edits_to_protected_pages">brought to the attention of</ref> the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews:Administrators">administrators</ref>.</p>
</text>
