<text id="autogum_interview_doc977" title="part2_Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian presidential candidate Wayne Allyn Root" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-03" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Libertarian_presidential_candidate_Wayne_Allyn_Root" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>Third, while I believe the war on terror is real and I strongly support it, I believe Bush and the GOP have completely screwed it up. The Dept of Homeland Security is just a new bungling bureaucracy. Making me take off my shoes and getting rid of my toothpaste won't prevent terrorism. Neither will hiring hundreds of thousands of new government employees- most of whom could never find a good job in the private sector. The people that work for Homeland Security are for the most part bungling idiots. So is the Bush administration. They are so busy fighting the wrong war in Iraq, that as a recent study proved, we are completely unprepared, in case of national emergency or terrorist attack here at home. Very little of our weaknesses and vulnerabilities to terrorism have been dealt with- our port security is lax, cargo on airplanes goes virtually unchecked, and seven long years after 9/11 we have only 50 FBI agents out of 10,000 who speak Arabic. How could that be possible?  Worse, we've used the war on terror to justify taking away our own civil liberties in America. Winning the war against terrorism is not a victory if we give up freedom in our own country to achieve it.</p>
<p>And finally, the war on terror should be fought NOT by invading entire countries, but through the use of specially trained rapid-strike teams and special forces taking out terrorist leaders wherever they may be hiding. Spending a trillion dollars on occupying Iraq was a costly mistake. It's been a disaster in terms of money wasted, lives lost and instability at home. The military forces of the United States are stretched to the brink. The National Guard has been plundered- it is now virtually useless to defend our homeland. I've come to realize that Bush and this entire administration are incompetent “Keystone Cops.” I believe in the war on terror- but not the way it's being run right now.</p>
<p>Fourth, I'm a spiritual person. I love God. I believe in the power of prayer. I've seen the studies that prove the healing power of prayer. I've seen the studies that prove religious people are happier and healthier. So I pray every day. My kids start and end every day with prayer. I believe that America has been blessed by God. But God and religion are personal issues made by each individual. I don't want politics to be used as a tool by religious people to stuff religion down our throats. I would fight to the death to protect your right to be religious, to practice any religion of your choice…or to practice no religion at all. I'm a great believer in personal freedom. Your choices are your choices- and none of the government's business.</p>
</text>
