<text id="autogum_interview_doc1086" title="part7_Vanity Fair contributing editor Craig Unger on the Bush family feud, neoconservatives and the Christian right" shortTile="partvanity-fair-contributing" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2015-08-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vanity_Fair_contributing_editor_Craig_Unger_on_the_Bush_family_feud%2C_neoconservatives_and_the_Christian_right" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It still is.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Theoretically, but they have sabotaged it so badly.  Netanyahu did not make good on a lot of the promises…</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yasser%20Arafat">Arafat</ref> didn’t—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Arafat backed out.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So what is the end goal?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  It’s a strategic vision of the Middle East.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  To control it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Yes, and they saw Iraq becoming at worst something like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jordan">Jordan</ref>, which is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hashemite%20Kingdom">Hashemite Kingdom</ref> that is pro-west and reasonably nice to Israel.  We’d have military bases there and we’d have oil deals.  Iraq would be a beachhead from which we could go on to Iran.  And Iran is a great prize.  In 1996 Netanyahu comes to Washington, he’s presented with the Clean Break policy by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard%20Perle">Richard Perle</ref>, and a couple of days later he makes an address before a joint session of Congress and borrows from A Clean Break, but he adds a new country and says ‘the most important country in the region is Iran.’</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Was that a surprise?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  What’s interesting is that you start to hear the terms “Democracy in the Middle East” and “Democratization” and what you realize is that it’s not about democratization at all, it’s about strategic dominance of the region, and that’s what their policy has been about.</p>
<head id="The_Christian_right_and_the_neoconservatives">The Christian right and the neoconservatives</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In your book you talk about a confluence of social forces.  You have the Christian right and you have the neoconservatives, who came together to assist each other in their agendas.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Absolutely.  This goes way, way back.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  To the 1970s?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Certainly to the 1970’s.  The Christian right is part of the DNA of America.  I go back to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20English%20Puritanism"> English Puritanism</ref>, and you see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20John%20Winthrop"> John Winthrop</ref> in the 1630’s saying, “We are starting a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20shining%20city%20on%20a%20hill"> shining city on a hill</ref>.”  Shining city on a hill means we’re the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20New%20Jerusalem"> New Jerusalem</ref>, we’re the new <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zion">Zion</ref>.  America is the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Promised%20Land"> Promised Land</ref>.  What we do is ordained by God.  This is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20Christian%20Zionism"> Christian Zionism</ref>.  It is a phrase that has never appeared in the New York Times, but it is an incredibly powerful force that is operative today.  It has been picked up by the Christian right and unites them with Israel.  It brings together the Christian right, the neocons and the Israeli right: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Likud">Likud</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benyamin%20Netanyahu">Benyamin Netanyahu</ref>.</p>
<p>You see it come alive in the seventies.  Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Menachem%20Begin">Menachem Begin</ref>, the first  non-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israeli%20Labor%20Party">Labor</ref> Prime Minister in Israel, called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerry%20Falwell">Jerry Falwell</ref> realizing that America is only 2.5% Jewish and they need a broader base.  About 30% of America is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evangelical">evangelical</ref>.   If you read the Bible, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abrahamic%20covenant">Abrahamic covenant</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Book%20of%20Genesis">Genesis</ref> where God says to , “ I give to you this land between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euphrates%20River">Euphrates</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nile%20River">Nile</ref>.”  If you believe in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Biblical%20inerrancy">biblical inerrancy</ref>, as evangelicals do, then you have to believe, “I shall bless those who bless thee; I shall curse those who curse thee.”  That’s in Genesis, and I talked to Falwell and a lot of evangelicals.  I traveled undercover with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim%20LeHay">Tim LeHay</ref>.</p>
</text>
