<text id="autogum_interview_doc1249" title="part12_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You had bigger issues to--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah.  I think of it as I'm right-handed.  I'm right-handed and attracted to men.  To me, it's the same thing.  I'm not "proud" of it, because it's not an accomplishment.  It's like being--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I always found the idea of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gay%20pride">pride</ref>--I mean, I understand the genesis of it.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I do understand where it came from.  But now when I hear it, it sounds like such an anachronism.  It's like--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Well, we needed it originally, so that we could--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  "I proudly serve <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Starbucks">Starbucks</ref> coffee."  The word "pride" is so bandied about in so many venues, and it's like, what do you mean, you “proudly” serve Starbucks coffee?  What do you mean that you're “proud” about being gay, or --</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Right.  Where's your personal accomplishment?  Here's the thing:  I would be proud if I had been raised <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evangelical%20Christian">Evangelical Christian</ref>, and I had been taught from birth that it was wrong, and against the backdrop of that history, I was gay.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You accepted yourself--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Then, I would be proud.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yeah.  I can understand that.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  That's the difference.  It was handed to me basically on a silver platter that was stuffed with mental illness--that's not a good metaphor, I mean it was--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] That's great…</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I never dealt with it.  It was never an issue.  I had so many other more life-critical issues to deal with that it was never something I thought about.  And therefore I never worked for it.  I never had to struggle to be gay.  It was the easiest thing, it was just like writing with my right hand.  So I'm not entitled to really be proud, but if I had to fight for it, I would be.  And I think that's the difference--</p>
<head id="On_his_new_book,_A_Wolf_at_the_Table,_a_memoir_about_his_father">On his new book, <hi rend="italic">A Wolf at the Table</hi>, a memoir about his father</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How did you teach yourself to write about difficult things in your life with such humor?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Well, there was no teaching involved with that.  That's just the way that I wrote about myself.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But originally you didn't, right?  I heard an interview where you said  you started writing something and you were like, 'Oh, God, this is just so depressing'--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Oh, well--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And then you put it away, and decided that you were going to write something funny, which I think was <hi rend="italic">Sellevision</hi>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah, I didn't probably explain that well--no, no, that wasn't <hi rend="italic">Sellevision</hi>.  That was when I was working on <hi rend="italic">Running with Scissors</hi>, when I sat down to begin writing it.  I began writing the book with a scene that was me and Bookman in a cornfield kissing, and it was so depressing to go back there and remember that.  It just felt so ugly that I thought, no, this--I can't do this.  I've got to start with something funnier.  So I started with a funnier scene from the book, and I focused on the parts of my life that to me, were fun and funny and wild.  So, that was really about that specifically.  The humor has always been such a part of my survival mechanism; that it was really organic to the writing.  It was just sort of one step back and removed and then, judging or commenting on, is something I do when I'm in a horrible situation.  I distance myself from my life this way, so that I can get through it.  So that's really where the humor comes from.  My next book, which is a memoir about my father, is not funny at all.  It's deadly serious.  And it's, um, just devastating.</p>
</text>
