<text id="autogum_interview_doc919" title="part4_Scientology protest group celebrates founder&amp;apos;s birthday worldwide" shortTile="partscientology-protest" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-05" dateModified="2019-02-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology_protest_group_celebrates_founder%27s_birthday_worldwide" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Despite a larger police presence at the Tottenham Court Road protest, the protesters and Scientologists were both peaceful. Police officers, when asked if they had had any problems with the protesters, replied, somewhat jovially, "I can't really speak to you, the only thing I can say is 'No comment'. No problems. I mean no comment."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Interview</hi>
This interview was carried out with members of Anonymous at the Tottenham Court Road protest. Church of Scientology representatives refused an interview and have not made any comment at the time of going to press.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> What has the public's reaction been to the protest, and what are your views on it?</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Anonymous Member 1</hi>: Lots of people have been taking leaflets, you can see some people stopping to look at signs, it's very interesting. The ground covered- from nothing to this in six weeks is stunning. It's an internet phenomenon, definitely. It's people around the planet, they've suddenly realised they can communicate, and I think the whole Anonymous thing is the start of something different, it definitely feels like something's happening.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> In terms of Anonymous's lack of organisation as a collective in their protests towards the Church of Scientology, how do you feel about that and how has it really come together?</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Anonymous Member 2</hi>: Well, everyone here is an individual, there's actual people behind the masks, even though we all look like the same person. As far as Scientology is concerned, I can't really say what any one person's motivations are because we don't have motivations as a group. Everybody is here as individuals, and for their own reasons... I think the great thing is the fact that with all our individual motivations and reasons we still manage to come together; we're a ton of people from the Internet, we don't know each other in real life; and we get together and have this kind of giant protest. It's amazing.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> In terms of the Church of Scientology as an entity, what's your personal motivation- as a member of Anonymous- for protesting against the Church?</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Anonymous Member 2</hi>: Personally, the thing I feel most strongly about is the way they abuse their members. Cases like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lisa_McPherson">Lisa McPherson</ref>, for example, and people in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rehabilitation%20Project%20Force">RPF</ref> camps, and all the people who have died as a result of the Church's actions.That, I think, is the biggest thing for me. But there's also their status as a religion. Well, really, it's not. It's a business, and they need to acknowledge that.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> What would you say are the main objections of Anonymous against the Church of Scientology?</item></list>
</text>
