<text id="autogum_interview_doc1369" title="part1_One year on: IFALPA's representative to ICAO, pilot and lawyer on ongoing prosecution of Garuda Indonesia Flight 200 pilot" shortTile="partone-year--ifalpas" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-08" dateModified="2014-04-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/One_year_on%3A_IFALPA%27s_representative_to_ICAO%2C_pilot_and_lawyer_on_ongoing_prosecution_of_Garuda_Indonesia_Flight_200_pilot" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>There were fierce calls for prosecution of both pilots immediately after the report's release, with Downer himself pressuring the Indonesian authorities, citing the "very credible report" and saying "I've asked our ambassador today (October 24) to make it absolutely clear to the Indonesians that we want people prosecuted for this accident. I want to see people who have negligently allowed Australians … to be killed, I want to see those people brought to justice."</p>
<p>Australian Opposition Leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kevin%20Rudd">Kevin Rudd</ref> also made clear a desire for prosecutions, saying he had telephoned secretary-general of Indonesia's foreign affairs department and former ambassador to Australia Imron Cotan, telling him that he wanted those responsible "prosecuted to the absolute full". "This is a serious matter, many Australians visit Indonesia, Garuda is an often used airline and there is a basic national interest at stake here as well," he said.</p>
<p>National Transport Safety Committee chairman Tatang Kurniadi said at the time that no information from the report could be used in any criminal or civil liability investigations. "I would like to go back to the objective of this, the report was made by NTSC for safety purposes only, not for blaming, he said. "If any institution wants to ... follow up that accident, that's their own decision. The report contained the results from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cockpit%20voice%20recorder">cockpit voice recorder</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/flight%20data%20recorder">flight data recorder</ref>, but according to international regulations on aviation these black boxes are not allowed to be used for... liability purposes. We will not give police or any institution (information) other than for safety purposes only - it's in international regulations and we want to follow those regulations." He also confirmed that investigators cannot speak to the police, with the only permitted testimony under the legislation being to testify at a court hearing, and pointed out that the document does not actually appoint any blame.</p>
<p>The international legislation he was referring to is probably the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convention%20on%20International%20Civil%20Aviation">Convention on International Civil Aviation</ref>, which stipulates that accident reports and related material, specifically transcripts of interviews, communications with crew and cockpit voice recorder and flight data recorder (collectively known as black boxes) readouts, must not be used for any purpose other than determining the cause of an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/aviation%20accidents%20and%20incidents">accident or incident</ref>. The only possible exception to this is where potential benefit would outweigh the "adverse domestic and international impact" on the investigation in question or any other either in progress or in the future. This legislation is in place to provide protection to witnesses on the basis that without it they may be less likely to cooperate with investigational procedures.</p>
<p>The law caused was actively opposed by some. Aridono Sukman, the police member in charge of the criminal investigation, said that the contents of the black box were vital evidence. Officials commented that some relatives had expressed their frustration over the legal challenges involved in the prosecution effort.</p>
</text>
