<text id="autogum_interview_doc1050" title="part2_Past Eurovision contestants give advice to this year's performers, speculate on who will win" shortTile="partpast-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-05-06" dateModified="2015-09-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Past_Eurovision_contestants_give_advice_to_this_year%27s_performers%2C_speculate_on_who_will_win" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I lost my passion for music for a while if I'm honest and we wanted to travel together for a bit, and actually moved to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref> for a short time, before I got totally broody. So in 2007 I gave birth to my little girl Olivia, and have been doing the wife and at-home mummy thing since, which I absolutely <hi rend="italic">love</hi>!! </p>
<p>I made the decision to get back in the studio and start writing again in January of this year and it felt so good, and when I recorded "Hard Not to Fall" I knew it was a song that I wanted everyone to hear, and I completely got my passion and drive back for it. The music industry has changed a lot since I was last in it...but in actual fact it's working better for me this time. </p>
<p>I have a lot more control, which is important to me, especially with Olivia being my main priority...I am first and foremost a mum, and I want to be a good one at that, and I'm also working with people that I really like and trust, which makes working together fun, and music should be fun. It's definitely a lot harder this time around, as I am juggling "real life" too, and I can't afford to be the selfish person that being successful in the industry can sometimes mean you have to be. I'm having the most wonderful time being back though, and am almost astounded by the great support I have from all my old fans. They're the best!!</p>
<head id="Ani_Lorak">Ani Lorak </head>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ani%20Lorak">Ani Lorak</ref>, born Karolina Kuiek (the name "Ani Lorak" is "Karolina" spelled backwards), first became famous for her vocal talent in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref> and her native <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukraine</ref> in 1995. She took part in arguably the biggest performance of her career at Eurovision in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%202008">2008</ref>, placing second with the song "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shady%20Lady">Shady Lady</ref>." Celebrating her 30th birthday in September, she has kept up a busy schedule, including the release of a new album.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What projects are you working on? What can your fan base expect to see from you this year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ani Lorak</hi>: I've just released my new album called "Sontse" (<hi rend="italic">The Sun</hi>). The album was written and recorded in Greece at the "VOX studio" by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dimitris%20Kontopoulos">Dimitris Kontopoulos</ref>, who also helped with the song "Shady Lady" for Eurovision 2008. The album will be released not only in Ukraine but also in Russia. </p>
<p>In the autumn I plan to start a large tour of 25 cities in support of the new album. Also, we are planning to play some solo concerts in the <ref target='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palace%20"Ukraine"'>Palace "Ukraine"</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiev">Kiev</ref>. I was pleasantly surprised when, at the beginning of the year, an award came to my office from the British radio station "Eurovision Song Contest Radio." By audience vote, its listeners named me the "Best Female Singer for 2008" for my song "Shady Lady." I don't like to think ahead and to anticipate, but I'll try to do as much as my energies will allow so people can be fulfilled in the future.</p>
</text>
