<text id="autogum_interview_doc1218" title="part1_The Onion: An interview with 'America's Finest News Source'" shortTile="partthe-onion-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2013-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Onion%3A_An_interview_with_%27America%27s_Finest_News_Source%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So you don’t have writers coming up with a story and headline, but you will instead have a team of writers choosing the best headlines and then assign it to a particular writer who was not necessarily involved?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  Writers will <hi rend="italic">occasionally</hi> write their own headlines, but we come up with a list of 15 or 20 headline ideas, what we think will make a good story and then we assign it based upon what people’s writing strengths are.  We have some people who are great at politics; some people we give all the war stuff to; someone who is in charge of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Britney%20Spears">Britney Spears</ref> story of the week—the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entertainment%20journalism">entertainment stories</ref>.</p>
<head id="The_headlines">The headlines</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It seems like some publications, like <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AM%20New%20York">AM New York</ref></hi>, always have a Britney Spears story; is there anything similar with The Onion where they continually revisit a topic or person?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  No, not necessarily.  We are a little less reactionary.  We tend to target the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeitgeist">zeitgeist</ref> more than anything.  We’ll hit the mainstream media’s portrayal of the entertainment world as much as we’ll hit characters in the entertainment world.  We’ll attack <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/People%20Magazine">People Magazine’s</ref></hi> coverage of Britney as much as Britney.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In an interview with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terry%20Gross">Terry Gross</ref>, Stephen Colbert said of his time at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second%20City">Second City</ref> that they had decided on not doing political humor and, in particular, hackneyed political humor such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ted%20Kennedy">Ted Kennedy</ref> drinking jokes.  They felt it was overdone, mean-spirited and not funny.  Do your writers have similar rules of thumb?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  We don’t have any rules or known lines we won’t cross.  We have an understanding based upon having the same writers in the back room for years, and those writers training the new writers as they come in.  There is an understanding in the room.  If it makes the room laugh, it probably ends up in the paper.  One example is we ran an article a couple of years back that was, “No <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jennifer%20Lopez">Jennifer Lopez</ref> News Today.”  That was our reaction to all of the J-Lo stuff.  We weren’t going to touch on her dress, or who she was dating.  Just the fact that those were the lead stories for so many days, in everything from <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US%20Weekly">US Weekly</ref> to </hi><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time%20Magazine">Time Magazine</ref><hi rend="italic">.  </hi>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean Mills, President:</hi>  I think it’s important we have an original take on those things.  I think it’s similar to what Colbert said to Terry Gross.  We don’t want to just traffic in the same 24 hour news cycle.  There’s a 24 hour comedy news cycle that exists on all the late night talk shows.  <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> has a different creative process where we are not trying to hit everything in the 24 hours and on the same notes.  We want an original take.  If we choose to do something on J-Lo, it’s going to be something like that, something less obvious.</p></p>
</text>
