<text id="autogum_interview_doc1197" title="part9_BDSM as business: An interview with the owners of a dungeon" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_An_interview_with_the_owners_of_a_dungeon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>That's why I need the pen or a pencil in the room.  They never say, "The redhead," or "The one with the short blue skirt," or--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do they say?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  It's usually in order.  They'll say oh, the third one, or the fourth one.  Guys have this thing about in order, which order they are in.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Really?  Right, okay.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  It's always that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Probably easier for them to remember.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  It's a guy thing.</p>
<head id="Motivations_of_the_clients">Motivations of the clients</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is it important to establish the motivations of the clients at the outset, such as whether they're looking for something that's a sheer thrill or whether it seems that they are maybe depressed and looking for self-abuse?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  No, because that's not who comes.  It's not abusive at all to come here.  It's somewhere between--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What if they want it to be abusive, though?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  What's abuse in your mind?  Is striking someone with a paddle abuse?  Is that what you mean--do you mean physical abuse, or--see, we--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Well, that's the idea:  I don't know.  I think it would be the motivation of the person who's on the receiving end.  But there must be people out there who do want abuse--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Right.  I'll give you a good example of somebody.  There used to be a fellow who used to come in here, and I won't even mention his name, he used to come in here with a big bag, full of really big implements.  Frying pans.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Mention no names.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  I mean, really big implements.  I mean, he wanted--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Frying pans?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Yeah.  He wanted raw emotion; he wanted people to beat the living crap out of him.  And, like I said, he wanted raw emotion. He would only come in like once every six, seven months.  But he felt that it was a good, healthy outlet for him.  He would feel bad about himself, and he got this massive beating two, three times a year, and he was fine.  You know, once in my life I was having a tough time and I was feeling pretty crappy.  He says, “I get, you know, my good beating, I feel great about myself, and look at you, you're a mess.  You're having a tough time.”  I said, “You know, you're kind of right.”  So who is the better of the two?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So it's not really possible to establish why they're coming in here.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  I think most of the time it's somewhere between taking it to the next level of looking at the girl--of looking at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Playboy%20(magazine)">Playboy magazines</ref>--and turning the pages.  After that, you have the girl lying in front of you, and you're talking to her.  Because once they masturbate and it's over, there's still plenty of time in the appointment.  They go on and talk about normal things.  They dump their problems, they talk about them, and the girls are, you know, listening about it.  And that's why Bill said, he doesn't want pictures of all this stuff hanging on the walls.  Because the girls can get really emotional.  After three, four sessions, five sessions, you kind of get, you know…</p>
</text>
