<text id="autogum_interview_doc1400" title="part4_Interview with gay marriage movement founder Evan Wolfson" shortTile="partinterview-gay" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-29" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_gay_marriage_movement_founder_Evan_Wolfson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In July of 2006 there was a proclamation that went out called <ref target="http://www.beyondmarriage.org/full_statement.html">Beyond Same-Sex Marriage</ref>.  It was signed by a lot  of well-known people: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cornel%20West">Cornel West</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armistead%20Maupin">Armistead Maupin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloria%20Steinem">Gloria Steinem</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terrence%20McNally">Terrence McNally</ref>.  All friends of the gay movement—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  —and all supporters of the freedom to marry—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  —That proclamation said too many resources are going toward gay marriage.  In a similar vein, one Wikipedia editor asked, "Should we be fighting for the ultimate 'prize' of same-sex marriage when most states haven't even given the basic gay rights of non-discrimination in employment, non-discrimination in housing and non-discrimination in public places/accommodation?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Well, first of all, the signers you mentioned who signed that Beyond Marriage statement also are strong supporters of the freedom to marry.  The statement itself did not actually say what you just said.  Some of the organizers of Beyond Marriage who have their own political agenda took that broad coalition of people who signed off on the generically good goals laid there and presented it as a focused attack on the marriage work.  More than the statement or many of the individual signatories themselves believe in.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have any of the signatories rescinded their support of the Beyond Marriage statement?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I don’t know that anyone has been asked to do that.  I think the reason why people sign statements like that is because they are in agreement with the general goals.  They are not necessarily responsible for or paying attention to what some of the people with a more focused or stronger agenda have to say.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What was the motivation behind the letter?  People such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard%20Kim">Richard Kim</ref>, associate editor of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Nation">The Nation</ref></hi> and one of the organizers, said it supported the notion that too many resources were going toward marriage fights.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I think some of the organizers had an agenda.  Richard Kim clearly has an agenda that is very different from what Gloria Steinem or Armistead Maupin have.  I think if Terrence McNally, Steinem and the others were actually shown some of Richard Kim’s articles as opposed to the broad, conciliatory and coalition-building goals found in that statement, they would not endorse his articles nor his views.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why not?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Kim’s articles are dismissive of the importance of marriage and the aspiration to marry that millions of people have, and that people like Gloria Steinem and Terrence McNally support.  What I said to the Beyond Marriage organizers is that 90% of what is in that document we agree with and, in fact, I have worked for.  In their schema I am supposedly the antithesis of everything they stand for, yet I would argue I have done more to attain their goals than they have.</p>
</text>
