<text id="autogum_interview_doc505" title="part8_Eric Bogosian on writing and the creative urge" shortTile="parteric-bogosian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-16" dateModified="2014-05-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eric_Bogosian_on_writing_and_the_creative_urge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Yeah, well that--and also, it reflects sort of where people are at in their lives, and so, you know, romances will perennially be interesting to people because most people that are really actively looking for movies and books are in their twenties and thirties, and they're--that's what their life is all about.  But I want to say one other thing, which I--I actually ran a symposium at the Public Library a couple of years ago, which nobody seemed to find very important, but I really think is important, which is:  If you really want to look for the new literature, you got to look at graphic novels, which are wildly popular.  Just look at them, look at the way they're structured--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yeah.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  --and look at the way they tell the story: you're completely outside Psychological Character-land.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neil%20Gaiman">Neil Gaiman</ref> is the king of that world as well as a number of other guys, and then they're making movies based on that stuff.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/30%20Days%20of%20Night%20(film)">30 Days of Night</ref></hi> is a good example of that, too, where you did have a central character, but you didn't really go into the psychology of anything.  It was based on a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/30%20Days%20of%20Night">graphic novel</ref>.  It's vampires in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barrow,%20Alaska">Barrow, Alaska</ref>.  You don't go into the vampires at all.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  No?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  One of the criticisms that somebody told me was that they really didn't go into the vampires.  You had these creatures show up; they wanted to kill.  They were interesting, but you didn't go into what motivated them--it became more about survival.  You had all of these different scenarios and how people's lives affected how they reacted to this sudden threat that had entered their town.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It was sort kind of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pinwheel%20narrative">pinwheel narrative</ref>, but you didn't get into, "What's driving them?  What can stop them?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Yeah, that's our little symposium on the future of narrative.</p>
<head id="Collaborations_with_Steven_Spielberg_and_Frank_Zappa">Collaborations with Steven Spielberg and Frank Zappa</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is something you notice missing from your Wikipedia article?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  There are two items that are interesting that aren't on my Wikipedia article.  I don't know how big that page has to be, but I made an album with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank%20Zappa">Frank Zappa</ref> in 1986.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's it called?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  It's called <hi rend="italic">Blood on the Canvas</hi>.  I also co-created a TV series with Spielberg in 1996 that ran for two years on ABC called High Incident.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you come across these projects?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  They get in touch with me.  There were times when I was sort of an interesting person and I'd get a call from somebody who's working with Frank Zappa and ask me if I would like to meet with him?  Very often I'll meet with somebody and there's really nowhere to go with it, or you can't really figure out how to make it happen and it would be great if it did, but--it doesn't.  But in the case of Zappa, I mean he's one of my greatest heroes; I would do whatever he wanted to do, and that's what we ended up doing.</p>
</text>
