<text id="autogum_interview_doc292" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Frank McEnulty, independent candidate for US President" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-15" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Frank_McEnulty%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>The problem of illegal immigration actually has a very simple solution.  Start enforcing the penalties against the hiring of illegal immigrants and you will remove the major attraction that draws people to this country illegally - jobs.  Without jobs and the prospect of a much better life the vast majority of people will stay home.</p>
<p>As President I would do one thing to ensure that this situation doesn't happen again, I would make sure our laws are enforced.</p>
<p>First, I would instruct all agencies under my jurisdiction to strictly enforce and apply the rules against hiring illegal immigrant workers.</p>
<p>Second, I would direct that all instances of hiring of illegal aliens be subject to penalty by jail time - real jail time, not a "country club" jail.  It's real simple for an employer to pay a fine and move on - that's just a cost of doing business.  It's not so simple to ignore the threat of real jail time in a real criminal jail.  No one wants to face that prospect.</p>
<p>Third, there would be no Federally funded benefit programs available to illegal immigrants further removing incentives to come here illegally.</p>
<p>Fourth, I believe we need to change the Constitution so that only those born of American citizens become citizens of this country upon birth.  The founders of our country could and would have never envisioned the fact that there are hundreds of thousands of babies being born each year in United States hospitals solely so their parents can use their anchor babies as an excuse to demand to stay here and take benefits from the rest of us.</p>
<p>It's really that simple.  If the laws are enforced and there aren't any jobs or free government benefits for illegal aliens then there will be no reason for them to sneak across the border and come here.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Campaigning for the American presidency is one of the most expensive exercises in the world. How do you deal with the cost and fundraising?</hi></p>
<p>The Internet is a wonderful vehicle for getting the word out about my campaign.  The Internet is the base and then I rely on individuals to tell those they know and before long you build up a real snowball effect.  The vast majority of the money spent by the major candidates is a complete waste of money.  When was the last time that someone listened to an entire political campaign ad, didn't hang up on a computer generated phone call or actually read the campaign literature that was received in the mail before tearing it up?  Unfortunately, today’s major party politics believe in spending vast quantities of money, but rarely spending it smart.  Sounds like how our government operates as well.</p>
</text>
