<text id="autogum_interview_doc719" title="part4_Author of My Billion Year Contract reflects on life in elite Scientology group" shortTile="partauthor-billion" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-13" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_of_My_Billion_Year_Contract_reflects_on_life_in_elite_Scientology_group" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I think they are spread a little too thin and there is nothing in my book that was not posted on the internet, either under my pseudonym “Kathryn”, or in internet posts.
In addition I was on the stand in court for one of the Lisa McPherson hearings on her death, and they had free opportunity to question me on these matters. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Towards the end of your book you describe how you still kept in touch with a son who was still actively taking Scientology courses - and that you had friends still working in the organization. Have you experienced the Scientology practice of "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disconnection">Disconnection</ref>"? Have any of these people been instructed by Scientology to cease communication with you?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">It is so freeing to now be able to decide who is a friend and who is not – on my own with no other influences.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Nancy Many</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: My son is his own person, and I am proud he makes his own decisions.  We don’t discuss it other than the discussion I described in the book.  </p>
<p>Yes I have had people Disconnect from me, and it is sad.  I used to be a member of this group, so I also disconnected from others.  It is so freeing to now be able to decide who is a friend and who is not – on my own with no other influences.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> During the recounting in the book of your mental breakdown, you cite your husband and family as key factors in helping and supporting you. What else, or who else - what other factors have helped you recover from your mental break after disengaging from Scientology?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: The other factors that helped were that I did have a lot of friends who were not and had never been Scientologists, so I could hang with them and the subject would never come up.  Thereby not "triggering" me back to Scientology language or way of life.</p>
<p>I also have/had a deep faith in God and an internal strength that made me pull my way out of the intermittent hell that lasted for years.  I knew this was life or death.  There were simply people or places I could not be around.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Recently another book by a former member of Scientology's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sea%20Org">Sea Org</ref> was published, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blown%20for%20Good">Blown for Good</ref></hi> by Marc Headley. Have you read other books on Scientology? What other books about the organization (other than those produced by it) stand out for you as important in understanding its impact and the internal workings of the movement?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: I love Marc Headly's book and feel very strongly that our books are so different that they  (together) give a vivid and 3 dimensional view of the world of Scientology.</p>
</text>
