<text id="autogum_interview_doc1097" title="part2_In the land of the open source elves: Interview with "Battle for Wesnoth" creator David White" shortTile="partin-land-open" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-05-29" dateModified="2015-10-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/In_the_land_of_the_open_source_elves%3A_Interview_with_%22Battle_for_Wesnoth%22_creator_David_White" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>Content only makes it to (1) if the developers happen to like it very much. We don't have any firm rules as to what is allowed and disallowed, and a campaign that has short-comings from the developer's point of view might still be allowed if it is exceptional in other areas. As an example of this, the campaign 'Under the Burning Suns' contained explicit references to religion. To avoid controversy, we wanted to avoid references to religion in Wesnoth. However, recognizing the exceptional quality of the campaign, we decided to accept it into the official version of Wesnoth in spite of this one aspect we didn't like.</p>
<p>Artwork containing nudity has also been a controversial point in the past, as has violence (particularly explicit depiction of blood). We generally take the point of view that we will review each item as it comes, rather than making blanket rules.</p>
<p>With regard to whether we allow things onto the campaign server, (2), our general policy is that to be allowed onto the campaign server, the content need only be licensed under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU%20General%20Public%20License">GPL</ref>. However, we reserve the right to remove content that we consider to be distasteful in any way. Fortunately, our content submitters are generally very reasonable, and we haven't had to exercise this right.</p>
<p>Our aim is to keep Wesnoth appropriate for users of any age and background — of course, it contains some level of violence, but this is not depicted very explicitly, and only parents who do not want to expose their children to animated violence of any level need be concerned. For this reason, we also do not allow expletives on our forums or IRC channels.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How do you feel about games like "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second%20Life">Second Life</ref>", where players trade user-generated content for money?</hi></p>
<p>I've never understood the appeal of games like that. I don't enjoy cheating in games, and to me buying items with real money seems like cheating — except worse, since it actually costs money.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What changes to the game or gameplay do you anticipate in the coming months and years?</hi></p>
<p>Well, we've avoided making many gameplay changes at all, since very early on in Wesnoth's development. Wesnoth is meant to be a simple game, with simple gameplay, and 'changing' gameplay will probably lead to it being more complex. We want to keep it simple.</p>
<p>Changes will probably focus on improving existing features, and making the engine a little more customizable. Enhancing the multiplayer component is big on the list — we've progressively added more and more features on the server. We also want to add more graphical enhancement. For instance, a particle system to allow various combat effects.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">If you had unlimited resources at your disposal to improve the game, what would you change about it?</hi></p>
</text>
