<text id="autogum_interview_doc707" title="part3_Canada&amp;apos;s Beaches—East York (Ward 32) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-beacheseast" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-21" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Beaches%E2%80%94East_York_%28Ward_32%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="italic">Mr. Gallos did not respond to numerous questions. Instead of emailing Wikinews with his sole answer, as was asked, he posted it directly to Wikinews.</hi></p>
<head id="Erica_Maier"><ref target="http://www.ericamaier.ca/">Erica Maier</ref></head>
<p>44-year-old <hi rend="bold">Erica Maier</hi> is general manager of Kathite Industries, makers of a chimney cleaner; "As Kathite is a seasonal occupation, I am also a full time Letter Carrier for Canada Post, I love the exercise and could certainly use it, and it keeps me in touch with the public."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Ward 32 is a unique family community within a major city.</p>
<p>In order to preserve our quality of life, we must be ever vigilant to ensure we aren't overrun by oversized building developments, graffiti, vandals or petty crime.</p>
<p>My aim is to hire a graffiti removal team that would be available daily.  Eradicate the graffiti and keep it away.  Continue to work with police and have police more visible in the area, walking along our streets, parks and school yards. Police would get to know our neighbours, business owners and the local children which would return a sense of well being to our inhabitants.</p>
<p>I encourage taking art to the streets.  Have billboards in various locations that locals can contribute to monthly.  Thus promoting our area and the artists of our community.  We need additional programs for teenagers that get them involved and keep them interested in community development.</p>
<p>Finally I would continue the work of preserving the heritage of our neighbourhoods, while helping the local businesses get the much needed assistance to grow and develop into thriving commerce   This could be achieved by having events and venues that add to our uniqueness and increasing consumer traffic and spending.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?   </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> At present I feel graffiti is my biggest concern.  It is a small issue that has been left to fester and could balloon into all sorts of problems for our area and the city.   If graffiti is left as a ‘broken window'</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am a person who involves myself in my community.  If things need to be done, I am a volunteer for the job.  This has always been fine in the past, as we have a terrific area with very few needs.  Unfortunately, things have changed, although crime is down for Toronto, petty crime is ever increasing.  Vandals attack cars, spray paint graffiti everywhere, and if left unchecked, it will escalate to major crimes.  Citizens are concerned and feel the need to stay indoors and not enjoying their neighbourhoods as they have in the past.  I intend to retire in my neighbourhoods, but it won't be a happy retirement if I don't act now and stop this neglect.</p>
</text>
