<text id="autogum_interview_doc571" title="part0_Wikinews interview with America&amp;apos;s Got Talent finalists Celtic Spring" shortTile="partwikinews-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-08-19" dateModified="2014-02-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interview_with_America%27s_Got_Talent_finalists_Celtic_Spring" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interview with America's Got Talent finalists Celtic Spring</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 31, 2006</hi></p>
<p>Irish American dance and fiddle band <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Celtic%20Spring">Celtic Spring</ref></hi> was recently a finalist in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/America's%20Got%20Talent">America's Got Talent</ref></hi>. <hi rend="italic">Talent</hi> was a NBC television series search for America's next big talent, featuring singers, dancers, magicians, comedians and other talents of all ages. The series was hosted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regis%20Philbin">Regis Philbin</ref>, and judged by former tabloid editor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piers%20Morgan">Piers Morgan</ref>, singer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brandy">Brandy</ref>, and actor/singer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Hasselhoff">David Hasselhoff</ref>.</p>
<p>The mother of the family, Mary McCauley Wood, talked to Wikinews about their group's performances and the <hi rend="italic">America's Got Talent</hi> experience.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<figure><caption>Celtic Spring; interviewee Mary Wood is top row, center.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> For readers who didn't watch America's Got Talent, how did Celtic Spring first start?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Celtic Spring had its beginnings in my interest to pass on the culture of my grandparents to our children.  My grandparents were from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ireland">Ireland</ref>, and they loved their culture and passed on a love of the culture to me. I wanted to pass the love on to our children so when each one turned four years old, he or she began to learn to play the fiddle and to Irish dance. We never intended to be a performing family, but the children loved the music and dance and became quite accomplished at an early age.  We also began going to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fiddle">fiddle</ref> camps when the children were very young.  At the camps great fiddlers are brought in from Ireland, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scotland">Scotland</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape%20Breton">Cape Breton</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shetland%20Islands">Shetland Islands</ref>, etc. and the children would learn the tunes "by ear" from amazing musicians who would teach the music and provide enough inspiration for the whole year. Ten years ago our children began fiddling at a local <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Farmers'%20market">farmers' market</ref> to earn money for fiddle camp and thus Celtic Spring was born.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Celtic Spring was consistently a fan-favorite, as one of the Viewer's Choice in the semi-finals, and in the top 5 of the finals. Why do you think America loved your performance as it did?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> America loved Celtic Spring's performance because the Irish fiddle music is beautiful to listen to and the Irish stepdancing is awesome; furthermore, Celtic Spring members are excellent musicians and dancers.  I think people love that they are all one family and that they also fiddle and dance at the same time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Overall, are you satisfied with the experience <hi rend="italic">America's Got Talent</hi> provided?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Celtic Spring had a wonderful experience with <hi rend="italic">America's Got Talent</hi>.  We were thrilled that our audience liked our performance so much!  We also had a great time getting to know the other performers and all the staff at the show. The talent and the staff became like a big family.  Most of all, we liked having all that time together as a family.  We are sad that the show has ended and all the family have expressed the sadness. We are grateful for all the friends and fans we have made through the show and hope to meet them as we perform around the country.</p>
</text>
