<text id="autogum_interview_doc1261" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Libertarian candidate Alan Mercer, Scarborough—Rouge River" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-03" dateModified="2008-11-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Libertarian_candidate_Alan_Mercer%2C_Scarborough%E2%80%94Rouge_River" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>I'd say that poverty, education and the economy are all important issues to both myself and to voters. The welfare state mentality, along with forced wealth transfer through taxation, and restrictions on people through ever-increasing authoritarian regulations are just going to push us towards worse conditions. I advocate the separation of school and state. People should not be forced to pay for the public or separate school system if they do not want to use it. Property tax is highly unjust and oppressive and should be abolished. I oppose the Tory plan to impose government control over faith-based schools.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>Rolling back government taxes and regulations. Increasing opportunities for health care and educational freedom. Liberty in all areas of life. Justice reform so that the needs of victims of crime are addressed through the principle of restitution.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>No property tax is fair. Property tax violates property rights, and they oppress those who are least able to afford them. People need to be able to pay for the services they use and opt out of those they don’t.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>Free up the economy. Eliminate price controls such as minimum wage and rent controls, which respectively stop people from finding low-wage employment and stop landlords from being able to maintain low-income housing. Eliminate the professional monopolies that impose one standard for certification and lock out immigrants from the economy. Let young people into the economy and stop imprisoning them in schools if they would rather work or start their own businesses. Reduce taxes and reduce the size of government drastically right now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>If MMP leads to more diversity in the legislature and allows more representation by smaller parties (they need to pass 3% which is still a real obstacle), that may be a positive thing, but the proposed system may also decrease the level of representation in parts of Ontario, and there is a problem with accountability to the electorate.  Unfortunately, MMP is a distraction from freedom issues, i.e. personal sovereignty vs. authoritarianism.   To reform our society in a libertarian direction, since we have to appeal to the majority anyway, I think political libertarians should consider the pros and cons of direct democracy.  In other words, each citizen being their own representative in a virtual legislature.  This may act as a check on the power of government through allowing more voices of dissent, more ideological diversity and more opinions to be heard in the legislature.  I don’t believe things are really heading this way with MMP.  MMP might have the opposite effect and empower the establishment parties even more.  But a movement towards direct democracy could open up an opportunity for libertarians to appeal more directly to the public rather than to the special interests who use the major parties to milk the public.</p>
</text>
