<text id="autogum_interview_doc659" title="part2_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think happens when we die?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I was raised as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catholic">Catholic</ref>, and while I didn't marry within the church, my wife is also Catholic.  It doesn't necessarily hold that there dies within you all that you believe when you were shaped by the process of being born Catholic, so I do believe--I comfort myself, I comfort myself--with the notion of an eternal life.  But as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20Eliot">George Eliot</ref> said in that great novel you probably read, religion is a fear of the hereafter.  Religion is a fear of the hereafter.  That's what it is.  It provides you a conviction or belief that there is something there in the hereafter, or else you won't have any long view.  Religion gives you a long view that what you do on Earth is going to shape your destiny in heaven.  That's comforting.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have religion?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  To the degree I stated I do, but to the degree that the Pope...I don't go to church, and I don't abide by anything the church preaches.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you pray?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Privately I do, sometimes, yes, I do.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In certain moments more than others?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  In moments when I feel that I'm out of control.  That I can not affect the result.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When do you feel out of control?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  When I fear I am going to die.  I remember praying on an airplane between Denver and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa%20Fe,%20New%20Mexico">Santa Fe</ref>.  It was a small commuter flight.  The co-pilot came back and said we are going to have turn back because our left landing gear will not go down, and we are going to have to dump gas over the dessert because we need to go back to Denver, because it is better equipped as an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stapleton%20Airport">airport</ref> to deal with this crash landing we need to have.  More foam and the fire department is bigger.  We had twenty minutes before our crash landing.  During that time I prayed. I wrote a letter to my wife.  I was just about 50.  I wrote a letter to my wife and daughters and prayed and thought, "This is it."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What did the letter say?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  How much I loved them.  How sorry I was I didn't have more time.  How happy I was with the time I had.  How lucky we were, and how sad I was that I wasn't going to be back.  I feared that the letter was going to burn with me.  It was ridiculous to be writing a letter, but I did.  What a fucking place for the end of me, Denver airport!  So that was fear.  Fear of the hereafter?  Religion and prayers.</p>
</text>
