<text id="autogum_interview_doc1203" title="part15_BDSM as business: An interview with the owners of a dungeon" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_An_interview_with_the_owners_of_a_dungeon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  It's very, very small.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is that because their desire--when they have a desire to come here--it's usually something that they plan out?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  It's because honestly, they're so respectable.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  I guess that's the point.  The people that come here--[you wouldn't hear screaming; you might hear they’ve got a big spanking going, but they have money.  We're not getting the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sociopath">sociopathic</ref> group--pathological group--they probably wouldn't have the money--the people, the maniacal crazies--they're not going to have the money to come up and do this type of session.  If they would like to come here a second, third and fourth time, they know how to behave and fly straight.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Well, we in turn treat them well.  What has been printed out from that script.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  But David's question is very interesting.  And your question really is asking another question.  How dangerous, how heavy is this?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If I went to a Taco Bell and I said, "Can you name a dangerous situation?" they would say, "Oh, that time I got held up."  So I guess I'm curious about a threatening situation that you might encounter or have encountered.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  And I guess that's the interesting thing.  Given what we do, it's probably not as threatening as Taco Bell.  In the first place, we had all sorts of bolts and deadbolts on the door.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  I mean, it’s like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort%20Knox">Fort Knox</ref>.  I mean, you can get hurt anywhere.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Sure.  Sure.  But all that aside, what would be a threatening situation that you've had to handle?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Has anybody ever attacked you with a gun or a knife--</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  No, I mean--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Have we ever had to call the cops on anybody?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you ever had to kick somebody out?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  No, I've said to people, "Listen, I'm going to ask you to leave," and they'd be like, "Okay, fine."  I--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why have you had to ask people to leave?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Um, because they're being obnoxious.  Because they're--but I do think having the dog with me has made things--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's preventative.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Yeah.  Yeah.  I've always had the dog with me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  You didn't have the dog in the other place always.</p>
<head id="On_S&amp;M_burnout">On S&amp;M burnout</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  But back to the room.  I don't want them going into a threatening room, and looking around and seeing threatening black, dark objects that you would just think, "Oh, my God--"</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20The_Divine_Comedy#The_Circles_of_Hell">seven circles of Hell</ref> . . . .</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Yeah, yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  We used to have a lot of S&amp;M pictures, and we thought it was not good for the girls or the guys--</p>
</text>
