<text id="autogum_interview_doc343" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Jim Hedges, U.S. Prohibition Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-01-26" dateModified="2016-11-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jim_Hedges%2C_U.S._Prohibition_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Jim Hedges, U.S. Prohibition Party presidential candidate</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 29, 2011</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Public domain image of Jim Hedges from the <ref target="http://www.prohibitionists.org/">Partisan Prohibition Historical Society website</ref></caption></figure>
<p>U.S. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Prohibition_Party">Prohibition Party</ref> presidential candidate Jim Hedges of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thompson%20Township,%20Fulton%20County,%20Pennsylvania">Thompson Township</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</ref> took some time to answer a few questions about the Prohibition Party and his <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2012_United_States_presidential_election">2012 presidential campaign</ref>. </p>
<p>The Prohibition Party is the third oldest existing political party in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>, having been established in 1869. It reached its height of popularity during the late 19th century. The party heavily supported the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eighteenth%20Amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution">Eighteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution</ref>, which banned the sale of alcohol, and resulted in the US period known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prohibition%20in%20the%20United%20States">Prohibition</ref> (1919–33). It was repealed in 1933.  The party has declined since this period, but has continued to nominate candidates for the presidential election.</p>
<p>In 2003, the party split into two factions. Preacher <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gene%20Amondson">Gene Amondson</ref> and perennial candidate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earl%20Dodge">Earl Dodge</ref> were nominated for the presidency by their respective factions. After Dodge's death in 2007, the party reunified and named Amondson as its sole presidential nominee for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2008_United_States_presidential_election">2008</ref>. During the election, Amondson was interviewed by <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>.  He died in 2009, leaving an opening in the party for 2012.</p>
<p>Jim Hedges is a longtime <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prohibition">Prohibition</ref> activist, who holds the distinction of the first individual of the 21st century (and the first since 1959) to be elected to a political office under the Prohibition Party banner. In 2001, he was elected as the Thompson Township <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tax%20assessment">tax assessor</ref>, and was re-elected to the post in 2005.  He served until his term expired in 2010. Hedges declared his intent to run for the Prohibition Party presidential nomination on February 18, 2010.  This marks his first run for the presidency.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">When and why did you decide to join the Prohibition Party?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jim Hedges</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I have identified with the Prohibition Party since being in high school, in the 1950s.  Being "a member" is trickier to specify, as I’ve sometimes registered to vote in other parties for temporary pragmatic reasons (or have not been registered, at all). I could not be active in the Party until after I retired from the military, in 1980.</p>
<p>Why?  Well, I liked, and still like, the Prohibition platform better than I do the platform of any other political group.  Partly, this is because of the anti-alcohol plank, but more generally because it seems more principled and more reasonable.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You are the first (and only) member of the Prohibition Party to be elected to any office in the 21st century. How were you able to accomplish such a feat?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I ran for an insignificant local office which no one else wanted.  Minor party people are always complaining that they can’t get elected – they can, if they start at the beginning instead of aiming at impossible goals.</p>
</text>
