<text id="autogum_interview_doc035" title="part0_Wikinews interviews India&amp;apos;s first female Paralympic medalist Deepa Malik" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-09-13" dateModified="2018-01-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_India%27s_first_female_Paralympic_medalist_Deepa_Malik" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews India's first female Paralympic medalist Deepa Malik</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 14, 2016</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Deepa Malik completing in the Women's shot put F53 final Image: Bidgee.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> on Sunday interviewed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deepa%20Malik">Deepa Malik</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">India</ref>'s first female <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paralympics">Paralympic</ref> medalist, who won the silver medal in the Women's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/shot%20put">Shot Put</ref> F53 event finals, at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2016_Summer_Paralympics">2016 Summer Paralympics</ref> being held in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rio_de_Janeiro">Rio de Janeiro</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref>.</p>
<p>Malik lost the gold medal to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bahrain">Bahrain</ref>'s Fatema Nedham, who had the best throw 4.76 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/metre">metres</ref>, setting a new regional record in paralympic women's shot put.</p>
<p>Arriving in Rio, Malik had initial trouble due to the airline losing her luggage; it didn't all arrive until three days later: clothes, opening ceremony outfit and equipment including competition belts.</p>
<p>In early August there was a possibly that Malik might lose her spot on the Indian team going to Rio, with fellow female para athlete Karam Jyoti challenging Malik's selection and the Sport's Authority of Indian's selection process at the High Court of Delhi. The high court ruled against the plaintiff.</p>
<p>Both of these events occurred against the wider backdrop of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paralympic%20Committee%20of%20India">Paralympic Committee of India</ref> being suspended by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Paralympic_Committee">International Paralympic Committee</ref>.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sports%20Authority%20of%20India">Sports Authority of India</ref> took final authority over the Paralympic Committee of India for sending a team to Rio, with agreement from the International Paralympic Committee; this arrangement allowed India to compete under their own flag at the 2016 Summer Paralympics.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   Congratulations on your result.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Deepa Malik</hi>: Thank you so much.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Even though you are currently waiting in terms of the end result of the protest.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DM</hi>:  Absolutely, but I'm happy with my performance, I'm happy that I could improve and I could prove myself, there were a lot of questions back home on my selection and on my hard work. My single-minded focus that I had put into this journey of being a Paralympian. Well, I am just so anxious about the results.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So how much did the court case and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KLM">KLM</ref> losing your luggage impact on your preparations and your result today?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DM</hi>:  Yes, but I'm happy that my husband was my coach here, and, so, I had huge moral support in terms of keeping my mind and everything in peace. Most of the equipment was available in the gym, we had to alter the training a bit like the throw days couldn't happen, so we instead exercised. No, I think that is what sports teaches you, you can't live on excuses, I never lived on excuses.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You work around things.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DM</hi>:  Yes, that's what we do, that's what a sportsman is suppose to do, rise again, and then fall and rise, and run, and I did exactly that.</p>
</text>
