<text id="autogum_interview_doc1076" title="part1_Canada's Toronto—Danforth (Ward 30) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-torontodanforth" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-11-04" dateModified="2013-05-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Toronto%E2%80%94Danforth_%28Ward_30%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Poverty – its sources and consequences, is a serious issue for Toronto. There are hundreds of thousands of Torontonians that are currently unemployed. Not only is this a loss of much productive power in our city, it has devastating impacts on individuals and families and pushes many people into poverty, homelessness and subject to numerous social stressors. Homelessness is also a product of low welfare payments, lack of affordable housing and inadequate medical and psychiatric services. These are just a few of the issues related to poverty and as City Councilor I will advocate unequivocally for the cause of eradicating poverty and the effects of poverty.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election? </p>
<p>Energy and conservation. Not only does the Portlands Energy project in Ward 30 need to be halted, the City has the opportunity to become a leader in addressing energy usage and emissions of green house gases. I am a proponent of achieving our energy goals through an aggressive energy conservation program using incentives, tax policy and other tools to achieve it. Ward 30 could be the leader in this area rather than being the Ward that could becomes the highest new green house gas emitter in 2007.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I believe I have the experience, education and desire to provide the leadership needed in the role of Councilor. I have always had a keen interest in politics and have taken many opportunities to be involved in various groups/boards/initiatives to help make a positive difference in our society. Toronto City Council is in need of leadership and I pledge to serve in this capacity to push forward a progressive agenda of change.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> This is where I live and where my wife and I are raising our family. We have a self interest in making this a better place. I want to help make our community better for the many friends, businesses, cultural activities, recreational facilities and neighbourhoods that are a part of this vibrant and energetic Ward.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am actively involved with Pro Bono Law Ontario having offered free legal advice to such groups as Somali Canadian Association and Television for the Environment. I am a member of Legal Aid of Ontario offering legal services to people who would otherwise not be able to afford it. I have been involved in several community gardens. I have been a member of the Toronto Choral Society, am a regular aphaeresis donor with Canadian Blood Services and have helped raise money for numerous charities including Toronto's Daily Bread Food Bank.</p>
</text>
