<text id="autogum_interview_doc564" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Suzanne Fortin, Nepean-Carleton" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-26" dateModified="2013-03-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Suzanne_Fortin%2C_Nepean-Carleton" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Suzanne Fortin, Nepean-Carleton</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 26, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Suzanne Fortin</hi> is running for the Family Coalition Party in the Ontario provincial election, in the Nepean-Carleton riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed her regarding her values, her experience, and her campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I decided to run because I like to tackle problems when I see them, and not sit on the sidelines. I like to take the initiative to contribute to my community.</p>
<p>Nepean-Carleton needs a candidate to represent fiscal and social conservatism and I wanted to give voters the chance to express their support for those views.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I was involved in the federal NDP youth caucus when I was in college, as well as the provincial Liberals in Quebec (I lived in Quebec City at the time). I also volunteered for the Conservative Party in the last federal election.</p>
<p>I think my background in customer service is an asset. When I was in the paid labour force (I am now a stay-at-home mom) I was a very conscientious employee, always trying to give good service and finding ways to do my job better. I had a lot of initiative and good problem-solving skills. I’m not the kind of person who just does a job for the sake of a paycheque. I find that boring. I think that this attitude will make me attentive to my constituents’ concerns.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?</hi></p>
<p>I believe that the Progressive Conservative party is the biggest challenger because they do attract social conservatives who want to fend off the election of a  Liberal government. The social conservative voters cling to the hope that if the PC’s don’t actually implement social conservative policies, they’ll at least forestall a further slide into social breakdown. It’s a natural reaction in our First-Past-the-Post System, where voters tend to vote according to the perceived leader and not according to what they really want. Unfortunately, the PC’s just about never deliver on social conservatism, and their fiscal conservatism isn’t very strong this time around.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
</text>
