<text id="autogum_interview_doc1237" title="part0_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 12, 2007</hi></p>
<figure rend="Augusten Burroughs by David Shankbone.jpg"></figure>I had an unofficial phone call from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gay%20Talese">Gay Talese</ref> last Tuesday.  He had just flown back from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colombia">Colombia</ref> and he was cranky.  "I'm happy to do an interview with you," he said, "but <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism,_Iraq_and_his_life">what the hell could you ask me</ref> that's not already out there?  Have you even bothered to look?!”   
<p>"Jeez, Mr. Talese, lots of things," was my response.  I lied.  The truth is that when I call people to interview them, I do not have a set of preconceived questions.  My agenda is to talk to them and gain a sense of who they are; to flesh them out as humans.  To find out what they think about the world around them at that moment.  With Gay Talese I had little interest in talking about <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank%20Sinatra%20Has%20a%20Cold">Frank Sinatra Has a Cold</ref></hi> and with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augusten%20Burroughs">Augusten Burroughs</ref> I had little interest in discussing <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Running%20with%20Scissors">Running with Scissors</ref></hi>.  I want to know what they think about things outside of the boxes people have placed them in.</p>
<p>With a memoirist like Burroughs, even this is a challenge.  What parts of his life he has not written about himself, other interviewers have strip-mined.  When we met for dinner at Lavagna in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East%20Village,%20Manhattan">East Village</ref>, I explained to Augusten this issue.  I suggested we make the interview more of a conversation to see if that would be more interesting.  "Instead of you in the catbird seat," I said, "let's just talk."  </p>
<p>We struck an instant rapport.  What set out to be an hour and half interview over dinner had turned into four hours of discussion about our lives similarly lived. I removed half of the interview: the half that focused on me.</p>
<p>Below is <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>’s conversation with writer Augusten Burroughs.</p>
<head id="On_addiction_and_getting_sober">On addiction and getting sober</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  It's difficult to be creative and innovative.  When you come up with an idea and then come across a place where it has already been done, how do you overcome disenchantment that can ruin your inspiration?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Augusten Burroughs:</hi>  It's funny; back when I was in advertising that was the one thing I wanted to be:  original.  I didn't own a television and I never watched commercials.  In advertising everyone studies the awards annuals, which are hardcover compendiums of all the best advertising examples.  I would never read them when I first got in.  I didn't want to be polluted, and I think it’s like that with the writing, but much less--I don't think about it to that extent.  The way I work best is not the way I wish I worked best.  The way I actually work best is to not think, but just to do.  <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dry%20(memoir)">Dry</ref></hi> was really the first book I ever wrote, and the reason for that is because I was 30, and I got out of rehab, and it was the first time I had been sober in my adult life.  I hadn't been sober since I was …16…I had been a nightly drinker from 16 on.  And I was 30--</p>
</text>
