<text id="autogum_interview_doc1158" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Cecile Willert, Ajax—Pickering" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-07" dateModified="2007-12-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_Party_candidate_Cecile_Willert%2C_Ajax%E2%80%94Pickering" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>Property tax rates are set at the municipal and regional levels of government. The tax assessment system is a provincial responsibility. This system requires overhauling. The Green Party proposes introducing a Location Value Tax to replace the existing property tax system. Under the Green Party’s Location Value Tax plan, municipalities will capture the increased value of land that results from infrastructure and development financed by the surrounding community. Location Value Tax will separate property assessment into the value of the building and the value of the land. The municipality will tax the land at a higher rate than the buildings, which will increase taxes on underused and vacant land. Location Value Tax will encourage intensification, deter sprawl and protect precious farmland. Rate differentials for zoning, such as for agriculture land, will remain within the Location Value Tax system.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>The opportunities are unlimited. The Green Tax Shift plan is a good first step in creating the conditions for a prosperous and sustainable economy that produces green jobs. By shifting taxes from employment to the resource use, Ontario will receive a double dividend: improved environmental performance and more jobs.</p>
<p>The Green Party of Ontario’s Green Jobs Plan will increase employment, competitiveness and innovation, while establishing worker protection. By adjusting market signals to reflect environmental costs, the GPO’s plan will create markets for new, innovative green businesses, technologies and products. Greens realize that small businesses, coops and non-profit social enterprises are important engines of a vibrant green economy. The threats of climate change, pollution and energy shortages can create opportunities for green jobs and healthy communities.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the mixed member proportional representation (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>Ontario’s voters deserve better representation at Queen’s Park. Our current first-past-the-post voting system does not reflect the political will of all voters because it discounts the votes of everyone who did not vote for a winning candidate. A Mixed Member Proportional (MMP) system will create a stronger democracy with more choice, fairer election results and better representation for all citizens. MMP has already been used successfully in several countries, including Germany, Scotland and New Zealand, where it has produced stable and effective governments.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does “new media” play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>The ability to put up a web site to disperse information quickly and broadly, to direct email and take donations is a huge asset. My website can be found by linking from the Green Party website (www.gpo.ca) or directly at www.vote-green.ca/cecile.willert .</p>
</text>
