<text id="autogum_interview_doc138" title="part0_Wikinews interviews USA wheelchair curler David Palmer" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-04-08" dateModified="2014-03-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_USA_wheelchair_curler_David_Palmer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews USA wheelchair curler David Palmer</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 8, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption>David Palmer of Team USA Image: David Palmer.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>David Palmer of Team USA Image: David Palmer.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed David Palmer, a member of the USA <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2013%20World%20Wheelchair%20Curling%20Championship">2013 World Wheelchair Curling Championship</ref> team, about the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2014_Winter_Paralympics">2014 Winter Paralympics</ref> being held in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sochi">Sochi</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> qualified a team for the Sochi Games. How likely are you to be on the final team?  As these games would be your first, how excited are you about the possibility of representing your country?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">David Palmer</hi>: It is very likely that I and the team that went to Sochi in 2013 will be the team in the Paralympics 2014 as long as no sickness or injury and we all continue to perform at our level.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DP</hi>: I am very happy and honored to represent my country.  After competing in the last two world championships which were very exciting, I can not wait for the chance to compete at the Paralympics.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Were you happy with your team's fourth place finish at this year's World Championships?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DP</hi>: I was happy with the way the team played, we all thought we should have medaled. We finished third in the round-robin with a record of 7–2 and the closest behind us was 4–5. We all made a few mistakes and did not finish as well as we would have liked, but we are looking forward to next year.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What steps is the team taking to try to get a gold medal in Sochi?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DP</hi>: We will be training harder and hopefully playing more <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bonspiel">bonspiels</ref> (tournaments). Because this is a Paralympic year we hope to get more funding, to travel for more high level bonspiels. Because the team is scattered across the country it is hard to get together for practice and bonspiels so we have to do the majority of it on our own. We will be reviewing the tapes from the worlds [World Wheelchair Curling Championship] and video conferencing with team and discussing strategy and performance.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Why do you participate in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wheelchair_curling">wheelchair curling</ref>?  Why not <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/wheelchair%20fencing">wheelchair fencing</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/wheelchair%20tennis">tennis</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wheelchair_basketball">basketball</ref> or athletics?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DP</hi>: I do participate in other sports at a recreational level. I have done waterskiing, monosking, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/wheelchair%20tennis">wheelchair tennis</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wheelchair_basketball">basketball</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Handcycle">handcycling</ref>. I played and competed in sled hockey for about 12 years, but I found as I got older and the competition got younger it was pretty physical on the body. I went and tried curling at Cape Cod Curling Club in 2009, I found that I not only liked it but I was also pretty good at it. A member there (Tony Colacchio) took me under his wing and showed me the possibilities there were to compete at the National level. I thought he was crazy at first, but four years later here I am curling on team USA and traveling the world.</p>
</text>
