<text id="autogum_interview_doc307" title="part0_Interview with Sue Gardner of the Wikimedia Foundation" shortTile="partinterview-sue" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-19" dateModified="2012-01-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Sue_Gardner_of_the_Wikimedia_Foundation" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with Sue Gardner of the Wikimedia Foundation</head>
 This article mentions the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>, one of its projects, or people related to it. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> is a project of the Wikimedia Foundation.
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 24, 2007</hi></p>
<p>Wikinews reporters interviewed <ref target="https://foundation.wikimedia.org/wiki/Sue%20Gardner">Sue Gardner</ref>, an employee of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikimedia%20Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>, the project that runs <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref> and several other projects, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref>.</p>
<p>Before coming to Wikimedia, she ran <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canadian%20Broadcasting%20Corporation">CBC</ref>.CA, the website of Canada's national public broadcaster. She was also a radio and television journalist for 10 years.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Matt">Matt</ref>: Hi Sue, could you explain what you do for the Wikimedia Foundation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sue Gardner:</hi> Sure. I am a consultant &amp; special advisor to the board. Essentially, I am here to help the organization professionalize and improve. It's a young organization with a lot of normal 'young-organization' challenges—and I am here to help fix them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Matt: What was your job position for <ref target="http://www.cbc.ca">cbc.ca</ref>, and what did you work on while you were there?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  I was senior director of CBC.CA. (That means I ran it.) Do you want me to explain a little about what it is?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Thunderhead">Dodge</ref>: Please do</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  It's the website of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canadian%20Broadcasting%20Corporation">Canadian public broadcaster</ref>, the only national public broadcaster in Canada and the equivalent to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC">BBC</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australian%20Broadcasting%20Corporation">Australian Broadcasting Corporation</ref>, the French pubcaster. etc. CBC is mainly a news organization, and CBC.CA is mainly a news website.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Dodge: How did you come to work for the Wikimedia Foundation? Were you asked to join by someone? And if so, who?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  I actually first got interested in the Wikimedia Foundation in a serious way, when I saw it do such a good job on the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/33_dead,_15_injured_in_Virginia_Tech_shootings">Virginia Tech story</ref>. On the morning of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virginia%20Tech%20massacre">Virginia Tech massacre</ref>, I was following the story on Wikipedia/Wikinews, and reading the talk page. And it was a really excellent level of conversation that was being had there. I was really seriously impressed. So I started doing a little reading about the organization, which resulted in me talking with Brad Patrick [then General Counsel to the Board of Trustees] and then Florence [Nibart-Devouard, Chair of the Board]. Which resulted in me coming here.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Brianmc">Brian</ref>: In joining WMF was there anything you brought from CBC.ca's policies that you feel have influenced your contributions to the foundation? Can you give Wikinews any tips? I am assuming their similar balance/neutrality policies as the BBC's</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  Yes, I think so. CBC is an extremely thoughtful, intentional, deliberate organization. I have borrowed from it liberally thus far—our code of conduct owes something to the CBC's, as does our travel policy, travel approvals policy, reimbursement policy etc. So there are a lot of new policies here (and there will be more) that have been heavily influenced by the CBC. In terms of journalistic policy, I have had no influence on how Wikinews handles things. And Brian, you are correct that CBC's editorial policies are very similar to those of the BBC.</p>
</text>
