<text id="autogum_interview_doc1405" title="part9_Interview with gay marriage movement founder Evan Wolfson" shortTile="partinterview-gay" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-29" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_gay_marriage_movement_founder_Evan_Wolfson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  People argue that system is already broke.  Half of marriages end in divorce.  If that system isn’t working for straights, why should we introduce it for gay people?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I don’t accept that at all. The system works for individuals who seek the freedom to marry, enter into marriages, and find enrichment and love and support and public affirmation and a vast array of legal and economic consequences.  Many marriages may fail individually, but as an institution it works and many individual marriages work.  Most people who divorce also remarry.  That every marriage doesn’t work does not mean that marriage as an institution isn’t serving very important functions for people.  What Alan Dershowitz proposes is something people say when they don’t bite the bullet of simply saying we should end the exclusion of gay people from marriage.  Instead, they go off into some whole other academic abstraction that sounds good, but that they themselves don’t follow.  They give no political plan for achieving it, and they can’t even articulate a reason for why we need to do it.  That proposal to create something brand new out of cloth called civil union, there’s no reason why that would actually work better or worse to affect the current divorce rate.  Why would that be any different than it is for marriage?</p>
<head id="Transgender_people_and_marriage">Transgender people and marriage</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Transgender people face specific issues in marriage since <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Legal_aspects_of_transsexualism#North_America">what constitutes a man or a woman is often legally defined</ref>.  How does the marriage movement address this issue?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Our understanding of how you define a man and a woman should absolutely be true to people’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gender%20identity">lived experience</ref> and should not be laced with archaic gender roles and discriminatory attitudes about men and women or about people who are transgender.  Second, we all have an interest in ending sex discrimination in marriage.  How you come to be a same-sex couple, whether by transition as a transgender person, or simply by falling in love with a person of the same sex, really shouldn’t affect your ability to get a marriage license.  It should not matter to the government because there is no good reason for the government to impose a different sex restriction on a couple who wants to marry.  That’s true whether it be a couple that includes a  person who is transgender or a couple who happened to get there by falling in love.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you see the issues interrelated, or does winning the freedom to marry itself usurp any problems faced by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intersexuality">intersexed</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transgender">transgender</ref> people?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I think ending the different sex restriction on who can marry and ending sex discrimination in marriage would significantly help people who are transgender, people who are gay and people who fall in love with somebody of the same sex.  Let’s remember: we don’t fall in love with categories, or an entire sex.  A man doesn’t marry <hi rend="italic">women</hi>, he marries a particular <hi rend="italic">woman</hi> he loves.  You marry the <hi rend="italic">man</hi> you love, and that’s true of transgender people, straight people and gay people.  So ending discrimination in marriage would help <hi rend="italic">all</hi> of us, but of course ending discrimination in marriage doesn’t solve every problem for everybody.   It’s not like ending discrimination in marriage is the only thing that matters.</p>
</text>
