<text id="autogum_interview_doc1446" title="part5_Interview: Danny O'Brien of the Electronic Frontier Foundation" shortTile="partinterview-danny" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-01-24" dateModified="2012-02-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview%3A_Danny_O%27Brien_of_the_Electronic_Frontier_Foundation" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><p>[Danny O'Brien] Our take on Sun's DRM: <ref target="http://www.eff.org/news/archives/2005_08.php#003929">http://www.eff.org/news/archives/2005_08.php#003929</ref></p>
<p>Essentially, our disagreement isn't with DRm per se: it's DRM backed up by the DMCA's anti-circumvention laws. If users had the right to circumvent DRm to exercise their fair use rights, we think the market would quickly sort out what controls on media use were acceptable and what were not.</p>
[Wikinews] A follow-on question from the French one: does eff plan to set up some chapters in Europe ?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] France like many countries, has a great core of activists and advocates already. We'd be delighted to help them in any way we can.</p>
[Wikinews] A follow-on question regarding the Sony BMG case: Does EFF have a response to the Register article <ref target="http://www.theregister.co.uk/2005/12/06/eff_needs_to_die/">http://www.theregister.co.uk/2005/12/06/eff_needs_to_die/</ref>
<p>[Danny O'Brien] Sigh. I wondered if this would turn up. It's a really odd article, given that it includes a bunch of cases that aren't ours, ones that we didn't lose, and other oddities. I think we'd rather let the facts speak for themselves. Here's a list of our [ <ref target="http://www.eff.org/legal/victories/">http://www.eff.org/legal/victories/</ref> victories]. There's a longer list at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EFF">wikipedia entry</ref>.</p>
[Wikinews] Are there any questions I should have asked you, which I did not?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] Hahah!  No, but I'm happy to take additional questions. I'm actually trying to think of some of the harder questions.</p>
[Wikinews] Well, I think I'll ask MrM to unmoderate now, and let everyone mob you.
<p>[MrMiscellanious]:) Alright, here we go...</p>
<p>MrMiscellanious made this room no longer moderated for normal users.</p>
<p>[Danny O'Brien] I guess the question we often get asked is "Why aren't you doing something about X?"  where X is a matter that really is important—the simple answer to that is that we have limited resources. Which is why I'm really happy to see lots of other organisations spring up.</p>
[Question] Does EFF support TOR, financially or otherwise, anymore?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] We host Tor's website, but direct funding was for last year. Actually, the Tor questions really are so frequentlyl asked that they're best answered on Tor's FAQ (including the legal FAQ we wrote for them.)  <ref target="http://tor.eff.org/faq.html.en">http://tor.eff.org/faq.html.en</ref></p>
[Question] en.Wikipedia prevents TOR endpoints from editing on the site; does EFF consider such class-blocking an acceptable response to behavior, or is it generally inappropriate?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] We're disappointed. We hope there's a way of providing a technical solution that would work to support Tor's aims, and would be practical for Wikipedia. If we can work as an intermediary in that discussion, we'd be happy to.</p>
[Question] European organisations which have similar goals like the EFF were not successful in preventing Telecommunications data retention. What conclusions does the EFF draw for their own campaigns?
</text>
