<text id="autogum_interview_doc595" title="part0_Wikinews interviews John Wolfe, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-19" dateModified="2013-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_John_Wolfe%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews John Wolfe, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, May 20, 2012</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democratic Party</ref> presidential candidate <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Wolfe,_Jr.">John Wolfe, Jr.</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tennessee">Tennessee</ref> took some time to answer a few questions from <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter William S. Saturn.</p>
<figure><caption>John Wolfe.Image: Marc Nozell.</caption></figure>
<p>Wolfe, an attorney based out of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chattanooga,%20Tennessee">Chattanooga</ref>, announced his intentions last year to challenge President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic%20Party%20presidential%20primaries,%202012">Democratic Party presidential primaries</ref>. So far, he has appeared on the primary ballots in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Hampshire">New Hampshire</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Missouri">Missouri</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Louisiana">Louisiana</ref>. In Louisiana, he had his strongest showing, winning 12 percent overall with over 15 percent in some congressional districts, qualifying him for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012%20Democratic%20National%20Convention">Democratic National Convention</ref> delegates.  However, because certain paperwork had not been filed, the party stripped Wolfe of the delegates. Wolfe says he will sue the party to receive them.  </p>
<p>Wolfe will compete for additional delegates at the May 22 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Arkansas">Arkansas</ref> primary and the May 29 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Texas">Texas</ref> primary. He is the only challenger to Obama in Arkansas, where a May 10 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hendrix%20College">Hendrix College</ref> poll of Democrats shows him with 38 percent support, just short of the 45 percent for Obama. Such an outing would top the margin of Texas prison inmate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keith%20Russell%20Judd">Keith Russell Judd</ref>, who finished 18 percent behind Obama with 41 percent in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/West_Virginia">West Virginia</ref> Democratic primary; the strongest showing yet against the incumbent president. Despite these prospects, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic%20Party%20of%20Arkansas">Democratic Party of Arkansas</ref> has already announced that if Wolfe wins any delegates in their primary, again, due to paperwork, the delegates will not be awarded.  Wolfe will appear on the Texas ballot alongside Obama, activist <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bob_Ely">Bob Ely</ref>, and historian <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Darcy_Richardson">Darcy Richardson</ref>, who ended his campaign last month.</p>
<p>Wolfe has previously run for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Congress">U.S. Congress</ref> as the Democratic Party's nominee. On his campaign website, he cites the influence "of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/the%20Pentagon">the Pentagon</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wall%20Street">Wall Street</ref>, and corporations" on the Obama administration as a reason for his challenge, believing these negatively affect "loyal Americans, taxpayers and small businesses."  Wolfe calls for the usage of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20antitrust%20law">anti-trust laws</ref> to break up large banks, higher taxes on Wall Street, the creation of an "alternative <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Reserve%20System">federal reserve</ref>" to assist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Community%20bank">community banks</ref>, and the implementation of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single-payer%20health%20care">single-payer health care</ref> system.</p>
<p>With <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, Wolfe discusses his campaign, the presidency of Barack Obama, corporations, energy, the federal budget, immigration, and the nuclear situation in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref> among other issues.  </p>
<head id="Campaign">Campaign</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What is the status of your lawsuit concerning Louisiana delegates?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">John Wolfe</hi>: Yeah. We're still going to file it. I mean the convention is not until September. Now it's May. So we got what, four months until the convention starts? And all we're going to ask for relief is to get awarded the delegates.</p>
<p>So yeah we're getting it ready. We have other campaigning to do. And I'm a lawyer so I'll be able to do the suit right.  But it does take time and energy. It will be filed. I hope to file it Monday [May 14].</p>
</text>
