<text id="autogum_interview_doc1111" title="part2_'Top Model' winner CariDee English on her modeling career and her battle with psoriasis" shortTile="parttop-model-winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-07" dateModified="2014-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/%27Top_Model%27_winner_CariDee_English_on_her_modeling_career_and_her_battle_with_psoriasis" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="On_her_former_photography_work">On her former photography work</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> You've worked behind the camera before you stepped in front of it; has this helped you as a model?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CE:</hi> It's helped me to understand the relationship and connection you need to have between a model and photographer, and what the photographer wants out of the model, like what art they want to create, and the importance of it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Would you like to step back behind the camera at some point?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CE:</hi> For fun, absolutely. I love doing that for fun, and...recreational, for sure. It'll always be a hobby of mine.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Experiencing both the photography side of the spectrum as well as being in front of the cameras, what do you deem extraordinary in terms of the aesthetic? What is beauty to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CE:</hi> Beauty is having confidence. If a woman is confident in front of the camera, and exudes that confidence, then there's no room for error. So, confidence, definitely.</p>
<head id="Top_Model_and_her_modeling_career"><hi rend="italic">Top Model</hi> and her modeling career</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Obviously your experience on Top Model was very positive. However, has the experience impacted you negatively at all?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CE:</hi> I think the only negative thing about it is that fans seem to think that if you're not on the cover of all these magazines, that you're not getting work. Not everything is covered equally. It's a different age now that a lot of celebrities are on the covers of magazines, and people go "Oh, well, this show hasn't produced a Top Model!" We've been doing a lot of work in a lot of different things and I think people forget that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> I've been following your career, and I've noticed you haven't been doing a lot of runway work as opposed to print modeling, which you've done a lot of. Do you have any fashion shows lined up in the near future?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CE:</hi> I've actually done a lot of runway work, but the thing is that the runway work never gets as much press as the print work does, so I've done a lot more shows than what people have seen on the Internet. It's difficult now too, because a lot of girls have to be <hi rend="italic">skinny</hi> skinny now, and I think I have a good walk and a good spring/summer look, but you know, I'm a size 0. 0 or a 2. I went in to see a fashion designer for the winter designs and I knew I wouldn't be thin enough for this job, and I'm 125 pounds at 5'10". I'm a grown woman, I'm not prepubescent anymore, so if that means I'm not thin enough and that means I'll lose a job, then you know, I'll take that risk. I'm healthy.</p>
</text>
