<text id="autogum_interview_doc1144" title="part1_Eurovision '82 winner Nicole talks about 'Ein bißchen Frieden', her success and the Contest today" shortTile="parteurovision--winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-02-02" dateModified="2019-09-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2782_winner_Nicole_talks_about_%27Ein_bi%C3%9Fchen_Frieden%27%2C_her_success_and_the_Contest_today" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: He was the first one who believed in me after hearing my voice and I had no doubt that he was the right person for a [musical] partnership.</p>
<head id="Eurovision_'82_and_mainstream_success">Eurovision '82 and mainstream success</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Did any of your inspirations and goals change when you signed your record contract, or appeared in Eurovision?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: I was trying to find my own way. After I signed my record contract everything changed. Especially after winning the Eurovision Song Contest. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Were you ever torn about eventually putting your singing over your guitar skills?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: I liked playing the guitar in "Ein bißchen Frieden". It was a good combination, wasn't it? Afterwards I put the guitar "into the corner" so I could be more mobile on stage.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The bookmakers Ladbrokes had the United Kingdom as the favorite to win back in 1982. Going into the Contest, especially knowing that Germany hadn't won at that point, did you feel daunted?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: I expected to win. After the first rehearsal, everybody could feel the magic of the song and its message. It was <hi rend="italic">my</hi> song!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Many of the songs and performers who performed for Germany before you performed sweeping ballads, with dramatic melodies, in sometimes very showy performances. And here you come in, a young girl from the Saarland, guitar in hand, singing a modest offering, asking for peace. Do you feel the lack of complexity in the song and performance perhaps gave it a special kind of appeal?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: I was honest in everything [I said] and sang what the people were thinking at that time. Asking for peace was also in their minds.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> During the 1980s, you had a string of hits in Germany, and released singles and albums across Europe and into Asia as well. Whose idea was it to give you exposure in Asia? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: It was the idea of the record company and Ralph Siegel.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Did you have pleasant experiences doing promotional tours over there? What thing do you remember most fondly?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: We went to the Tokyo Yamaha Festival and won second place there with "So viele Lieder sind in mir" (<hi rend="italic">There are so many songs inside me</hi>). I learned to introduce myself [to people] in Japanese. That's what I remember fondly and I haven't forgotten one word to this day.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You've continued to release albums nearly every year since the early 1980s, but a lot of your mainstream chart success ended in that decade as well. Did you feel discouraged when that started to happen? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: Not really. I've now been in this business for 29 years. I take it as an Olympic swimming competition. There's an A-final and a B-final. You don't have to be first every time, but you have to take care and swim with the others in the A-final.</p>
</text>
