<text id="autogum_interview_doc950" title="part1_Exclusive: 'The Scientology Reformation' author examines Tom Cruise and David Miscavige" shortTile="partexclusive--scientology" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-10-18" dateModified="2012-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Exclusive%3A_%27The_Scientology_Reformation%27_author_examines_Tom_Cruise_and_David_Miscavige" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Request_for_comment">Request for comment</head>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reached out to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church%20of%20Scientology%20International">Church of Scientology International</ref> for a comment about <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology">Scientology</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_Miscavige">David Miscavige</ref>, and to representatives of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tom_Cruise">Tom Cruise</ref> for a comment related to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mark_Rathbun">Mark Rathbun</ref>. As of this article's original publication no response was received. A subsequent response if received within 24 hours of this article's publication would be appended to this article as an addendum.</p>
<p>Update: 24 hours from time of article publication, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> had not received a response from representatives for Church of Scientology International, David Miscavige, or Tom Cruise.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> If David Miscavige were to leave the Scientology organization, what would happen to the leadership structure of the organization? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mark Rathbun</hi>: "Nothing. It would just fade away under the do-less bureaucracy Miscavige created."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Who would take over the way things are set up at the present time? Is there a succession plan in place?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "Who knows? For the past twenty years it has been organized under the principles of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Lord%20of%20the%20Flies">The Lord of the Flies</ref></hi> — whoever the collective, bee hive, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/stimulus%20response">stimulus response</ref> mentality collective that is left will do as they will. Might as well flip coins."</p>
<hi rend="bold">I have no interest in organized religion.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mark_Rathbun">Mark Rathbun</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> If you could be plopped into the Scientology organization position of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chairman%20of%20the%20Board">Chairman of the Board</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religious%20Technology%20Center">Religious Technology Center</ref> (COB RTC) and replace David Miscavige, right now, would you do it, or who else would you suggest who would be capable in that role? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "No, I have no interest in organized religion. Because of that I am the last person qualified to answer the second question."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What are your thoughts on the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/disconnection">disconnection</ref>" policy in organized Scientology? Do you think it should be discontinued?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "Yes. But it never will because Scientology management has correspondence from Hubbard from 1983 re-instating; making it impossible for such literalists to cancel it."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In your view, what top 5 things would you change from the leadership policies of David Miscavige, and why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "There are no five single things. There are literally hundreds, if not thousands, of arbitrary whims of Miscavige effectively chiseled in their minds as 'policy'. That is why I say 'Scientology Inc is dead', way past the point of possible rehabilitation."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Your first book on this subject, <hi rend="italic">What is Wrong with Scientology?</hi>, displayed on its cover the "Squirrel Busters" group who showed up on your doorstep in Texas. In a statement to the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corpus%20Christi%20Caller-Times">Corpus Christi Caller-Times</ref></hi>, they admitted that their goal was to make your life "a living hell". What are your thoughts on using Scientologists and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/private%20investigator">private investigators</ref> in this manner? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "It is reprehensible and unjustifiable in the twenty-first century."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Do you think there is any situation which would justify using <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office%20of%20Special%20Affairs">Office of Special Affairs</ref> (OSA) <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Intelligence_agency">intelligence operatives</ref>, private investigators hired by the Scientology organization, high-ranking Scientologists, or some combination thereof, surveil, monitor, or gather information on former members of Scientology or critics of the organization? If so, can you describe what situations would warrant this type of response?</hi></p>
</text>
