<text id="autogum_interview_doc935" title="part1_KKE: Interview with the Greek Communist Party" shortTile="partkke-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-05-13" dateModified="2019-09-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/KKE%3A_Interview_with_the_Greek_Communist_Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Iain</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> How, given the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/collapse%20of%20the%20Soviet%20Union">Soviet collapse</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref> being communist in name only, would your vision of a communist system have been better for the majority of citizens?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Isabella</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Despite the various problems of socialist countries, the socialist system of the 20th century proved the superiority of socialism over capitalism and the huge advantages that it provides for peoples’ lives and working conditions. The Soviet Union and the world socialist system constituted the only real counterweight to imperialist aggression – we recently celebrated the 65th anniversary of the Anti-fascist victory. The achievements of workers in the socialist states were a point of reference for many decades and contributed to the gains won by the working class in capitalist societies as well. In this way, everyone had guaranteed work, public free health care and education, housing, and access to intellectual and cultural creativity. The complete eradication of the terrible legacy of illiteracy, in combination with the increase in the general level of education and specialization and the abolition of unemployment, constitute unique achievements of socialism. In the Soviet Union in 1975 it was guaranteed by law that the hours of work could not surpass 41 per week, among the lowest in the world. All workers were guaranteed days for rest and relaxation and annual paid holidays. Non-working time was extended and its content was changed. It was transformed into time for the development of the cultural and educational level of the workers, for the enhancement of their participation in workers’ power and in the control of the administration of productive units. Social Security for working people was of utmost priority for the socialist state. A comprehensive system of retirement benefits, with the important achievement of low age limits for retirement (55 years for women, 60 for men), was created. Socialist power laid the foundation for the abolition of inequality of women, overcoming the great difficulties that objectively existed. Socialism ensured in practice the social character of motherhood and socialized childcare. It instituted equal rights for women and men in the economic, political and cultural realm, although not all forms of unequal relations between the two genders, which had become entrenched over a long period of time, had been successfully eradicated.</p>
<p>Our critical approach regarding various issues of building socialism in the USSR, namely decisions in the economy in critical times, or the extend of workers’ control and participation, do not change the fact that the first historical attempt to abolish the exploitation of man by man had many achievements for the majority of people and many of the rights that Soviet people had in 1975 seem like a dream for us today. Also, it does not change the fact that the contradictions of the capitalist way of production become deeper. The counter-revolution may have won one fight, but it has not won the war. As long as there is socialised production combined with capitalist property of the means of production, there will be crisis, unemployment and poverty – and socialism will remain the only way out.</p>
</text>
