<text id="autogum_interview_doc1036" title="part3_Wikinews interviews team behind the 2,000th featured Wikipedia article" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-10" dateModified="2009-12-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_team_behind_the_2%2C000th_featured_Wikipedia_article" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">JBM</hi></hi>: Over the course of this semester, I've come up with a response of my own to this question.  If a Wikipedia article is a good one, then you won't need to quote it, as it will have links to all the relevant sources.  And if it doesn't have those links, then it isn't a good article, and shouldn't be quoted in any case.</item></list>
<p>Before this semester, I explicitly banned students from quoting Wikipedia articles in their essays.  And I will continue to do so.  I also look askance at them citing dictionary definitions.  And though they don't quote Britannica (I think Wikipedia has now for all intents and purposes replaced Britannica), I would likewise be unimpressed if they were to do so.</p>
<p>On the other hand, of course, as you say, Wikipedia can be an excellent starting point for research.  I personally use it often precisely for that reason.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Was the experience of using a wiki for collaboration something you would repeat? There have been suggestions for something you might call "EduWiki" for the collaborative development of course material. Would you get involved with something like that? Do you see potential for use of the MediaWiki software in other areas of education? Such a project could be hosted under Wikimedia Foundation projects such as Wikibooks or Wikiversity. Would you favour that over a closed project within academia where contributors' credentials could be verified?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">JBM</hi></hi>: I'm not sure.  As is perhaps already obvious, I'm horribly suspicious of almost anything that has "edu" in the title.  And I say that with all due respect to my friends who are in "EduTech"--though I should add that they are often equally suspicious, if not more so!  I've had a couple of other experiences with wikis, in relatively closed environments, and they weren't particularly successful.  I think that was because there was never a critical mass.  The one thing that Wikipedia really has going for it is critical mass.  (Even then, of course, only a tiny fraction of the people who read Wikipedia ever edit it.)</item></list>
<p>The other thing is that too many academics still don't get the wiki ethos.  It's hard for them (us) not to be possessive about our work.  This I think is what causes most of the antagonism and frustration when academics do get involved in Wikipedia.  The issue is seldom "expertise," and much more often ownership.  I realize I'm talking in broad strokes here, but for instance a wiki was set up in my faculty, and it proved impossible to edit anyone else's texts.  We might as well have been putting up .pdfs.  It was an exercise in presenting position papers, rather than in collaborative writing.</p>
</text>
