<text id="autogum_interview_doc477" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic wheelchair basketballer Shelley Chaplin" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-01-03" dateModified="2014-06-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_wheelchair_basketballer_Shelley_Chaplin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yeah! I think people are often quite surprised by wheelchair basketball, what it is when they actually see it. I think the name "wheelchair" basketball means disability obviously, but when you watch it there's nothing about disability to it at all. Just that we use wheelchairs, and that's it. It's just another sport.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  People in the press gallery were saying "I've just got to get out in a chair and..."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Try it! Yeah!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So how did you get to go to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Illinois">Illinois</ref>? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> After the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2004%20Summer%20Paralympics">Athens Paralympics</ref>...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You won the bronze medal there?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> No, we won silver in Athens...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Silver in Athens, bronze in Beijing. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yeah, while I was over there I met one of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">American</ref> girls, and she was about to take up a scholarship there. And so I ended up meeting the coach, who was in Athens coaching the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canadian</ref> men's team. So I ended up meeting him, and chatting to him about maybe going over there, and then when I got home I followed it up, and they offered me a scholarship, so I took it. So he'd already seen me play at the Paralympics, and knew who I was, so it was good.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Which lead to what we ran on the front page of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Oh yeah! I saw that! That was great!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  That's why I rang up up and asked for your birth place. Somebody raised an objection, and said maybe she was born in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Nope!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I thought that was pretty spectacular, because there's not a lot of athletes in any sport that have done that [been All-American without being American].</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Cool. Definitely cool.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How did your team go while you were there?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> While I was there we... I was there for five years. The first three years we were national champions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  For five years from 2004 to 2009?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> No, I didn't actually go until 2005. So I went in August of 2005. And I finished up in May of 2010. I went to five national championships, and we won three and came runners up in two.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Wow!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yeah! We had a good team.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So you said you played for a club here in Melbourne as well?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yeah, I play for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dandenong%20Rangers">Dandenong Rangers</ref> here. We've just won two championships in a row. So... hopefully three this year.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Wow!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yeah! It's pretty cool.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  That's a pretty amazing record. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  And then of course there's the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia_women's_national_wheelchair_basketball_team">Gliders</ref> as well. You've got the gold... no wait...</p>
</text>
