<text id="autogum_interview_doc861" title="part1_Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-22" dateModified="2014-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_World_Wide_Web_co-inventor_Robert_Cailliau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: In the beginning, what challenges did you face inside and outside CERN in the development of this cutting-edge technology?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: A lot of incomprehension, later also some jealousy. And at the start it was difficult to convince the managers that it would grow into a useful tool.</p>
<p>There were a number of factors against us. First, the period of home-grown IT solutions was over.  The trend was to buy off-the-shelf software.</p>
<p>Secondly, the entire future of high-energy physics was precarious:  there were troubles around the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Superconducting%20Super%20Collider">SSC</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Superconducting Super Collider, red.</hi>) in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> and from the plans of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Large%20Hadron%20Collider">LHC</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Large Hadron Collider, red.</hi>) it was clear that something had to give. The SSC was finally scrapped in 1993, but during the entire period the physicists were worrying about other things than hypertexts.</p>
<p>Thirdly, there was always the problem of justifying a project in pure computing within an institute whose mandate is very clearly the science of pure physics.</p>
<p>Outside CERN there was a desert of hopelessly confused networking.  Universities wanted TCP/IP but the telecoms of the European countries were still governmental monopolies, and they resisted this because they were used to different payment schemes.</p>
<p>I remember a funny exchange between a person from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deutsche%20Telekom">Deutsche Telekom</ref> and a group of academics at a conference:  they complained about the costs and the slow links.  The telecom person replied: "What do you want?  We give you the best <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X.25">X-25</ref> lines and then you run <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet%20protocol%20suite">TCP/IP</ref> on top of that!"  But we had no choice:  TCP/IP was the only protocol usable with all universities of the world.</p>
<hi rend="bold">Sir, I hope you do not expect that France Telecom will support the internet ?</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—a representative of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France%20Telecom">France Telecom</ref> to Robert Cailliau</p>
<p>At another occasion I asked a representative of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France%20Telecom">France Telecom</ref> for his e-mail address.  He gave me an X-400 address and I asked for an internet address.  He raised his eyebrows and said:  "Monsieur, vous ne pensez quand-même pas que France Telecom va soutenir l'internet?" ("Sir, I hope you do not expect that France Telecom will support the internet?").  And all that happened when the web was already a success, though indeed only in the academic world.
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Premier_serveur_Web.jpeg">File:Premier serveur Web.jpeg</ref></p><figure><caption>The first web server.<hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Premier_serveur_Web.jpeg">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=Image%3APremier+serveur+Web.jpeg">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: Early browsers were web editors at the same time right? What browser do you use today? Does it have tabbed browsing? How does it compare to the early browsers you've worked with?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: It is true that the browser of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NeXT">NeXT</ref> was also the editor, though it was restricted to the pages on the local server.</p>
<p>The current complexity of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XHTML">XHTML</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ajax%20(programming)">Ajax</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cascading%20Style%20Sheets">CSS</ref> etc. precludes I think the efficient combination of the functions of editing and browsing in a single application.</p>
</text>
