<text id="autogum_interview_doc1358" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Finnish 'Rock 'N' Troll' band Kivimetsän Druidi" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-06-07" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Finnish_%27Rock_%27N%27_Troll%27_band_Kivimets%C3%A4n_Druidi" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Joni:</hi> The most visible difference compared to these bands you mentioned is that we have a female singer. Then what makes us different compared to all these female fronted metal bands which are quite many as well these days? Well, we are heavy and will be even more heavier in the future. We are not in to this pop-metal thing and we like to keep our music as heavy as possible. Back in to your original question, we play fantasy metal, in which we combine different styles of metal into a mix that’s never heard before. Sure, some of our songs may sound like something that’s made already, but you can find such songs from every band. We combine <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/black%20metal">black</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/thrash%20metal">thrash metal</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/folk%20music">folk</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/celtic%20music">Celtic</ref> melodies and spice it all up with epic and symphonic atmosphere. Then we add beautiful female vocals, destructive growls and mystical Finnish language. There you have a genre called Kivimetsän Druidi.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Antti:</hi> Well these bands have each quite straight own style and line what they do, but we like to include many different things in our music, but still keep the folk thing in it. For example mixing blackmetal riffs, blastbeat and banjo is not a problem for us..:) That’s why we call our music fantasymetal. We also have a classically trained female singer in the band.</item></list></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Speaking of Korpiklaani, you did a major tour with them recently. What was that like as an experience?</item></list>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Joni:</hi> It was an amazing experience and we can’t thank Klaani guys enough for granting that opportunity for us. It was indispensable possibility to see what’s it like out there on the “big fields.” I can honestly say that it made us grow up as a band and we saw that people really like what we are doing. There was not one gig where people didn’t welcome us warmly.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Antti:</hi> It was totally awesome. It was really a dream come true! 100% best moments of my life! We all got really much experience and progressed as musicians.</item></list></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Will there be international re-releases of your previous independent stuff? Would you like to see that?</item></list>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Joni:</hi> Haven’t thought about that really yet, but now that I think of it I’m not so sure if that’s a good idea. Sure, some fans would love to get their hands on our earlier stuff, but... I think I’d like those recordings to remain as our past and there’s no need to re-release them.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Antti:</hi> In my opinion they will stay as they are. Demos and eps! The future collectors’ treasures!</item></list></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Will the new album be all new material, or will there be some of your previous stuff there as well?</item></list>
</text>
