<text id="autogum_interview_doc1411" title="part5_John Vanderslice plays New York City: Wikinews interview" shortTile="partjohn-vanderslice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-27" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Vanderslice_plays_New_York_City%3A_Wikinews_interview" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  --you, John Vanderslice, how can you allow this---</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  --Me!  Yes!  So for the first time in my life I wouldn't say I was defending the country but I was in this very strange position of saying, Listen, not that many people vote and the churches run fucking everything here, man.  It's like if you take out the evangelical Christian you have basically a progressive western European country.  That's all there is to it.  But these people don't vote, poor people don't vote, there's a complicated equation of extreme corruption and voter fraud here, and I found myself trying to rattle of all the reasons to her why I am <hi rend="italic">personally</hi> not responsible, and it put me in a very interesting position.  And <hi rend="italic">then</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolas%20Sarkozy">Sarkozy</ref> got elected in France and I watched her go through the same horrific thing that we've gone through here, and Sarkozy is a nut, man.  This guy is a nut.</p>
<figure><caption>"I was so beaten down after the 2000 election and after 9/11 and then the invasion of Iraq, Afghanistan, I was so depleted as a person after all that stuff happened, and I had to write my way out of it; I really had to write political songs because for me it is a way of making sense of processing what is going on."photo: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But he doesn't compare to George Bush or Dick Cheney.  He's almost a liberal by American standards.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  No, because their President doesn't have much power.  It's interesting because he is a WAPO right-wing and he was very close to Le Pen and he was a card-carrying straight-up Nazi.  I view Sarkozy as somewhat of a far-right candidate, especially in the context of French politics.  He is dismantling everything.  It's all changing.  The school system, the remnants of the socialized medical care system.  The thing is he doesn't have the foreign policy power that Bush does.  Bush and Cheney have unprecedented amounts of power, and black budgets...I mean, come on, we're spending half a trillion dollars in Iraq, and that's just the money accounted for.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's the reaction to you and your music when you play off the coasts? </hi> </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi> I would say good...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you ever been <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dixie%20Chicks:%20Shut%20Up%20and%20Sing">Dixiechicked</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  No!  I want to be!  I would love to be, because then that means I'm really part of some fiery debate, but I would say there's a lot of depressed in every single town.  You can say Salt Lake City, you can look at what we consider to be conservative cities, and when you play those towns, man, the kids that come out are more or less on the same page and politically active because they are fish out of water.</p>
</text>
