<text id="autogum_interview_doc1038" title="part5_Wikinews interviews team behind the 2,000th featured Wikipedia article" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-04-10" dateModified="2009-12-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_team_behind_the_2%2C000th_featured_Wikipedia_article" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you feel that doing this part of the course in such a radically open way encouraged any of the students to work to a higher standard than the might otherwise have?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">JBM</hi></hi>:  Absolutely.  No question of it.  The most active students, at least, have helped produce articles of c. 4,000-8,000 words that are comprehensively researched, repeatedly revised, and with a meticulous attention to detail.  The standard of every single article is far better than any term paper that they would have written otherwise.  Of course, some students have been more actively engaged, and so have both learned more and been pushed more than others.  But the constant reminders and questions from other Wikipedia editors, particularly the members of the FA-Team who have done much of the copy-editing, has forced them consistently to reflect upon what they are saying, how they are saying it, and what their sources are.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  In reflecting on the project, is there anything you would have done differently?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">JBM</hi></hi>: There were aspects of the groupwork that didn't work out as they could have.  And we did get off to a rather slow start: I'd have to think about how to remedy that.  Moreover, once the project is over, the FA-Team and I (plus, of course, any students who are interested) plan to have a post-mortem on all aspects of the collaboration.  So there are certainly things that could be improved.  I know I've also learned a lot on this project, and next time would hope to benefit from what I've learned.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You've hit about 6,000 edits personally, have you caught the "wiki bug"? Will you keep editing?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">JBM</hi></hi>: 7,000 now!  I'll need to stop editing for a while once the project is over: it has been very time-consuming.  But I plan to be back in the Fall.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  In light of the apparent success of your project what would you say to other academics to try and persuade them to try similar experiments?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">JBM</hi></hi>: Absolutely.  I don't want to come across as too much of a Wikipedia booster.  I can understand exactly why many academics' engagement on the encyclopedia has proven to be disappointing or frustrating or worse.  But I think that, especially if academics take some time to understand aspects of Wikipedia's culture, there are forms of engagement that can be very rewarding.  We were rather fortunate to run into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WP:FAT">the FA-Team</ref>, a group of experienced Wikipedia editors that had recently been established in order to help others promote articles to Featured Article status.  Their involvement has been an absolute Godsend.  But I see no reason why something similar (or even unpredictably different, and perhaps better) might not emerge in other circumstances.</item></list>
</text>
