<text id="autogum_interview_doc936" title="part2_KKE: Interview with the Greek Communist Party" shortTile="partkke-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-05-13" dateModified="2019-09-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/KKE%3A_Interview_with_the_Greek_Communist_Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>Our Party in 2009 held its 18th Congress, during which we discussed and studied socialism and the causes of counter-revolution in the USSR. The conclusions we drew have been published and we have enriched our programme based on them. See <ref target="http://inter.kke.gr/News/2009news/18congres-resolution-2nd">here</ref> for more information.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Iain</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> For right or for wrong, we have now reached a situation where Greece is on the brink of an international bailout. If you were given power tomorrow, what steps would you take immediately to get Greece back on track?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Isabella</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> At the moment we are trying to build a front of workers, small farmers, the self-employed and working young people. This front needs to become a huge social and political anti-imperialist anti-monopoly coalition with only one duty - to bring the working class into power and socialise the basic means of production, namely energy, telecommunications, mines, manufacturing, and transportation.  We would implement public and free education, health and national insurance systems. Next to the socialised sectors, there can be the co-operatives of small farmers and small tradesmen in sectors of the economy where concentration is still low. The production and distribution in both the socialised and the co-operative sectors will be under workers’ control as part of a centrally planned economy. This is a vital need in order to fulfil our contemporary needs, in order to ensure that all productive forces are mobilised, that science and technology will develop in favour of the people, and that all international economic co-operation will be used, on the basis of mutual benefit. The government, which will be the organ of the popular power, will have to ensure the participation of the people in building this new society. The debt is due to the power of monopolies. There will be no solution if the capitalist profits remain untouchable, if we don’t disengage from EU and NATO, if the capitalists continue to rule at the expense of the working class.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Iain</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Why do you oppose the current austerity measures? What has the government, in your view, got so wrong?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Isabella</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Massive and drastic cuts to public and private sector salaries and pensions, further cuts of benefits, reduced overtime payments, increase of the VAT up to 23%, increase of the indirect taxes, abolishment of collective labour agreements, massive redundancies to public services and merges, right of unrestricted redundancies to private companies, and increases to the retirement age: Huge masses will be condemned to unemployment and extreme poverty. Health and Education will become a privilege only for a small minority. The recovery phase will lead to new concentration of wealth to the capital, to an increase in the degree of exploitation. The recovery, when it happens, will not have a positive impact on the people on one hand, and will lead relatively soon to a new crisis on the other. That is why we oppose the measures.</p>
</text>
