<text id="autogum_interview_doc710" title="part0_Canada&amp;apos;s Don Valley East (Ward 33) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-don-valley" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-17" dateModified="2009-04-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Don_Valley_East_%28Ward_33%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Canada's Don Valley East (Ward 33) city council candidates speak</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 4, 2006</hi></p>
<p>On November 13, Torontonians will be heading to the polls to vote for their ward's councillor and for mayor. Among Toronto's ridings is Don Valley East (Ward 33). One candidates responded to Wikinews' requests for an interview. This ward's candidates include Zane Caplan, <hi rend="bold">Shelley Carroll</hi> (incumbent), Jim Conlon, Sarah Tsang-Fahey, and <hi rend="bold">Anderson Tung</hi>.</p>
<p>For more information on the election, read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto%20municipal%20election,%202006">Toronto municipal election, 2006</ref>.</p>
<head id="Shelley_Carroll_(incumbent)">Shelley Carroll (incumbent)</head>
<p>49-year-old Shelley Carroll is the incumbent for Don Valley East, Ward 33, and has served either in this position or as a school board trustee for the last decade. More information can be found on <ref target="http://www.shelleycarroll.ca/">her website</ref>, or <ref target="http://councillorcarrollupdates.blogspot.com/">her blog</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Locally, completing a storm-water retention system for North York's flooded areas. Controlling and mitigating the impacts of subway-induced development. Globally, completing a long-term solid-waste strategy for the city of Toronto. A comprehensive environmental assessment process has already been launched, under my leadership of the Works committee and I intend to see it through.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Part of mitigating development impact is bringing about better traffic and transit management. Residents of Don Valley East are passionate about both these elements of city life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I entered politics in 1995, concerned about a better education system and ultimately a better City for my own children. I felt that a better future for them could only be achieved by building a stronger community for everyone. After 10 years, I find the work constant but endlessly rewarding.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Ward 33 always feels like a microcosm of the whole City of Toronto to me. Residents of all backgrounds are engaged in civic issues like never before. They they [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] want a city that supports the next generation economically and socially, and we need a City that supports their hard work.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Serving first as a School Board Trustee and now as City Councillor has spread my community involvement across a broad range of activities. I visit and participate in multi-cultural seniors organizations, childrens' service providers, and residents' associations. I have created two new additions to the list of resident/ratepayer associations as well as running my own Ward Advisory Council.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Toronto is at the edge of becoming the North American City that shows all of the others how to grow without compromising the quality of life and the environment. The decisions we make will serve as an example of how a progressive city should act. Our Youth Strategy, which I helped author, asks that we never create another City initiative without asking if we are leaving youth or the marginalized behind. As Works Committee Chair, I always ask, "How does this benefit the environment?" We have to lead by example, and I hope to build a city that does.</p>
</text>
