<text id="autogum_interview_doc159" title="part6_Wikinews interviews Australian Glider Amanda Carter" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-09-26" dateModified="2017-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Glider_Amanda_Carter" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  To me... London... the coverage on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Television">TV</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">Britain</ref>, but also here, some countries are ahead of others, but basically it's being treated like the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Olympics">Olympics</ref>. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yeah! Yeah. There wasn't a lot of difference between.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Huge crowds...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Huge crowds! We played for our silver medal in a sell-out crowd... you couldn't see a vacant seat around the place.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I was looking around the North Greenwich Arena...
And that arena! The seats went up and up and up! And as it was filling on the night, you could see that even that top deck had people sitting in it. I guess in 2000 even, to fill stadiums, which we did, we gave APC and school programs, a lot of school kids came to fill seats and things. We didn't necessarily see that in London. They were paid seats! People had gone out and spent money on tickets to come and see that sport. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I saw school groups at the football and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Goalball">goalball</ref>, but not at the basketball.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> No.  Which is a big difference also, that people are willing to come and pay to watch that level of sport.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I was very impressed with the standard of play.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> The standard, over the years, has improved so much. But the good thing is, we're looking at development. So we've got the next rung of girls, and guys, coming through the group. Like, we've got girls that weren't necessarily up to selection for London but will probably be right up there for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2016%20Paralympic%20Games">Rio</ref>... Our squad will open, come January, for the first training camp. That will be an invitational to most of the girls who are playing women's league and those sorts of things, and from there they'll do testing and stuff, cutting down and they'll select a side for Osaka for February, but the program will remain open leading into the next world championship, which is in Canada.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What's in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Osaka">Osaka</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> The Osaka Cup. It's held every year in February, so that will be the Gliders' first major tournament...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  After the Paralympics. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yeah. So everyone's taking an opportunity now to have a bit of a break.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  And then after that?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> It's the world championships in 2014 in Canada. So that will be what they're next training to.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How many tournaments do they normally play each year?  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> We've played a few. And you often play more in a Paralympic year, because you're looking to see the competition, and the other teams, and those sorts of things, so... This year we did Osaka, which Canada went to, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref> went to... <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref>, and us. We then went to — and we'd previously just been to Korea last November for qualification. We've been over to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref>. We've been to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Manchester">Manchester</ref>. So we've had a few tournaments where we've travelled. And then we've had of course a tournament in Sydney about three weeks before we went to London. And then of course we went to the Netherlands, before we went on to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cardiff">Cardiff</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wales">Wales</ref>.</p>
</text>
