<text id="autogum_interview_doc923" title="part8_Scientology protest group celebrates founder's birthday worldwide" shortTile="partscientology-protest" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-05" dateModified="2019-02-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology_protest_group_celebrates_founder%27s_birthday_worldwide" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Other members carried picket signs and leaflets. Early on, many of the crowd members were chatting with each other, sometimes taking pictures of each other. Passers by gave the assembled crowd mixed reactions to being approached. One of the members of the public expressed concern that a protest in Seattle would not do much, "They oughta be picketing Tom Cruise's house." </p>
<p>Curiously, a few members actually took pictures of me standing off to the side with my camera. A few accused me of being from the church, attempting to gain identifiable information, and were therefore cautious. Others saw me as the only person around without a mask, and in this crowd I was the outsider.</p>
<p>At about 11:00 PDT, the crowd started to proceed north, up 5th Avenue in downtown Seattle. At no point did I witness any of the Anonymous group committing a crime. I however, could probably have been cited on multiple counts for jaywalking, in attempts to get a decently framed shot from my digital camera without being seen as marching with the crowd. Numerous car horns blared during the crowd's exodus down 5th Avenue. As the street took a turn north, the crowd passed Fischer Plaza, home to local ABC affiliate KOMO-TV. I noted that I had not seen any mainstream media coverage of the event. The march turned down Broad Street, and at this point I gave up trying to keep pace in front of the crowd. I pulled over to the side of the sidewalk, next to a chain link fence to get the last photos of this phase of the protest. Afterwards, I followed the procession as it turned onto Aurora, and reached the Scientology center.</p>
<p>The center itself is situated on one end of an overpass, Aurora Avenue crosses over Mercer Street here, and eastbound traffic on Mercer was treated to a large banner proclaiming "HONK AGAINST SCIENTOLOGY" The banner generated a considerable number of car horns, which resulted in an equal number of cheers from the crowd. On the north side of the center, more protesters positioned themselves around the parking lot. Very few members were visible, for a long time there was only one standing near the entrance back in a fenced off area. Members of the crowd would level jeers at the man, such as "What are your crimes?" Eventually two police officers arrived, who stationed themselves in the parking lot, observing the crowd and calmly turning back any protester who crossed into the parking lot with a warning. No Scientology personnel approached the crowd, or a member of the press.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Seattle Gallery</hi></p>
<head id="Sydney,_Australia"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sydney">Sydney</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref></head>
<p>The protest in Sydney gathered approximately 300 activists. The masked protesters gathered in Hyde Park and moved through the city to the Church of Scientology. Two large trucks obstructed the view of the Scientology office from across the street.</p>
</text>
