<text id="autogum_interview_doc1339" title="part4_An interview with Paul Campbell, founder of Amazing Radio UK" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-10" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_Paul_Campbell%2C_founder_of_Amazing_Radio_UK" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>So far as the iTunes comparisons go, the facts are already public domain. An artist on iTunes can expect to make 8p from a 79p download.  The same artist on amazingtunes.com will make about 52p.  We only deduct the VAT and the cost of the transaction: 70% of what’s left goes to the artist.  What’s more, their income will improve over time - the more downloads we sell, the less the transactions cost us, so the more cash there is to give to the artists.  That’s one reason we ask people to buy eight or more songs in one transaction – it’s much more cost-effective, less of their cash goes to VISA, more to the artist.  (See my Blog post on this here - ). </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Amazing Radio launched in mid-2009.  How has it grown since then and what are your current listening figures?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PC</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> It’s gone mad since then.  I’ve worked in broadcasting and the media since 1978 (I was very very young then, mind you).  I’ve never known anything like it.  The reaction has been absolutely incredible – and it’s growing faster than ever right now.  The most humbling thing has been the audience feedback – masses of long emails from people we’ve never met, saying they found it by accident, and they love it.</p>
<hi rend="bold">the best guess I've heard in the industry is that we have something like 600,000 listeners in the UK on DAB.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Paul Campbell</p>
<p>We’ve not yet paid for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RAJAR">RAJAR</ref> audience figures because – well, because we’re a bit mean really, and I’m not convinced they would accurately measure our audience.  I think RAJAR is very good at coming out with figures for radio stations that have been going for 40 years, but not very accurate when it comes to new and innovative stations which are also listened to a lot online and especially popular with young people.  But the best guess I’ve heard in the industry is that we have something like 600,000 listeners in the UK on DAB.  That’s an estimate, but it came from a very wise source.  We have slightly more than that number on top as regular users online, and a weekly reach for amazingtunes.com of about two million users. But it’s all growing so fast, those numbers will be out of date by the time you read this. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital%20Audio%20Broadcasting">DAB</ref> transmission costs are well over half a million pounds a year.  How is this being funded currently and how are you planning to fund it in the future?</hi></p>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PC</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> We’re not contractually allowed to tell you what we pay, so we can’t confirm or deny the cost.   Whatever the true figure, it is undeniably expensive; but it gives our musicians a chance to be on national radio. We figure it’s worth it.  I’m reminded of that wonderful teachers’ union bumper sticker: ‘if you think education’s expensive, try ignorance’.   If you think creating the world’s first radio station playing 100% new music is expensive …. try being inaudible. </p>
</text>
