<text id="autogum_interview_doc599" title="part4_Wikinews interviews John Wolfe, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-19" dateModified="2013-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_John_Wolfe%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>If you look at what Obama said, it wasn't even progressive. All he said was this is my personal statement.  He didn't say that <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_Carolina">North Carolina</ref> was wrong [for passing a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North%20Carolina%20Amendment%201">ban</ref> on same-sex marriage]. You have to read the tealeaves when this guy talks. All the guy said was I think that gay marriage is fine with me personally. He didn't say that we're going to make a federal law that makes it incumbent upon the states not to outlaw it. He didn't do that.  He's fine with those kind of laws. He's not going to go out there and do any more than say what he said. So he didn't give us an agenda like: are you going to go ahead and have it where you're going to have a situation, are you going to allow homosexual or same-sex couples to go ahead and have tax deductions?  Are you going to allow them to have the same kind of income tax return as a traditional family? He didn't go through all that. He just made a general statement. Now he's off the floor as some kind of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caesar%20(title)">Caesar</ref>; someone vindicating the rights of gay people.  His statement was very vague. It's just very Obama-like.  He didn't really commit to anything. He just said that was his personal opinion.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Well, personally, do you believe it is a federal or state issue?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: I think it's a state issue. But I think it's something that I need to study more because I'm a person really that tries to get beyond <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/identity%20politics">identity politics</ref>. I'm interested mostly in three things. My interests are: number one, the economy. You get people back to work, then we can quite fighting each other on these social issues. Some of these social issues are accented because there's a lot of unrest with the economy. We need to worry about three things I think: getting the economy back right, getting out of these commitments like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref> and dictators abroad, we need to get out of that, then we need to protect our civil liberties at home. Those are the three main things that John Wolfe has on his agenda. So I think those are the most important.</p>
<p>The economy is <hi rend="italic">the</hi> most important. And I think the economy can't be reformed until you reform the bank. You noticed yesterday [May 11], <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JPMorgan%20Chase">JP Morgan</ref> lost two billion dollars because they're pouring billions of dollars into all this speculation, and some of the credit default swaps and derivatives. Well guess what? We're underwriting that. That's casino capitalism. I've been talking about this all last year and all this year about how bad that's getting. Now, the chickens are coming home to roost. That's just JP Morgan. We don't know what the next bank is going to report. We got to underwrite all that.  See, Obama's never made an effort really to separate that out because he's so ensconced in Wall Street money, and so persuaded by Wall Street advisers right there in the oval office. He won't even go back to traditional banking to make these people separate casino capitalism from traditional banking. He hasn't done it. As long as he doesn't, we're going to have to underwrite these things.  We're going to have to keep bailing them out, bailing them out, bailing them out. We shouldn't have to do that. Obama ought to do something about that. People want that done, but he can't do. He's handcuffed because he's afraid of Wall Street.</p>
</text>
