<text id="autogum_interview_doc264" title="part3_Wikinews interviews US National Archives Wikipedian in Residence" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-06-11" dateModified="2014-04-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_US_National_Archives_Wikipedian_in_Residence" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DMP</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> You can see a listing of other Wikipedian residencies <ref target="https://outreach.wikimedia.org/wiki/Wikipedian%20in%20Residence">here</ref>. There have been several, but still less than ten, and each situation has been unique. I can't really speak to any specific future collaborations being worked on, as I am not privy to those negotiations. However, I will say more generally that these relationships are only going to become more common. Wikimedians and chapters around the world have been in touch with various institutions interested in working with us. I saw and met many of these people firsthand at <ref target="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/GLAMcamp%20NYC">GLAMcamp NYC</ref>, which was attended by dozens of excited representatives from cultural institutions attracted by the prospect of a relationship with Wikipedia and just as many incredibly motivated Wikimedians who are involved in reaching out to these institutions. </p>
<figure><caption>The National Archives is reaching out to other crowdsourced projects for scanning and transcription. During a program on citizen archivists, Jessica Zelt (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North%20American%20Bird%20Phenology%20Program">North American Bird Phenology Program</ref>), Matthew Knutzen (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20Public%20Library">New York Public Library</ref>), and Darla Adams (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ancestry.com">Ancestry.com</ref>) are shown with moderator Meredith Stewart (National Archives). Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Archives%20and%20Records%20Administration">National Archives and Records Administration</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Are there other — non-Wikimedia — opportunities online you feel the National Archives should look for?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DMP</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> The goal of cataloging, describing, digitizing, and transcribing the entire holdings of the National Archives is an impossible one using traditional methods and within traditional budget constraints. Cultural institutions need to engage the interested public to become active partners in preserving cultural heritage, rather than simply consumers. The work with Wikimedia is an important aspect of that new thinking, but there are all sorts of allied projects out there that would also make good partners. This includes similar crowdsourced projects for scanning and transcription, <ref target="http://blogs.archives.gov/aotus/?p=2938">which the National Archives is already seeking out</ref>, as well as other specialized groups interested in digital history or particular topic areas.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How have your experiences — both in school and in Wikipedia — prepared you for this job?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DMP</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I am a history geek and an archivist-in-training. In my life off of Wikipedia, I have an undergraduate history degree, have worked in library/archive settings before, and am currently pursuing master's degrees in both history and library science (archives management). I think these real-life experiences in their field are one of the main reasons that the National Archives was comfortable letting me on to their staff. I hope to be able to relate to the people and the practices here on a higher level than the average Wikimedian. I believe strongly in the work and the mission of the National Archives completely apart from how it syncs up with Wikipedia.</p>
<p>As a Wikimedian, I have been deeply immersed in various aspects of the project for many years now. I first started back in 2004, and have been an administrator since 2005. Along the way, I served as arbitrator, CheckUser, oversighter, and OTRSer, gaining a useful perspective on some of the project's inner workings and (for lack of a better word) governance. I've also done outreach to real people as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Campus%20Ambassadors">Wikipedia Campus Ambassador</ref> for university students in Boston. I am cross-project Wikimedian, having also been very involved in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiktionary">Wiktionary</ref> over the years, where I am also an administrator. I have written content ranging from dictionary definitions of modern colloquialisms to articles on Chilean revolutionaries. But, most importantly, I hope that my familiarity with the culture and practices of Wikimedians will help facilitate this National Archives collaboration. </p>
</text>
