<text id="autogum_interview_doc354" title="part0_Creator of website satirizing Glenn Beck on winning domain name case" shortTile="partcreator-website" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-11-09" dateModified="2019-02-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Creator_of_website_satirizing_Glenn_Beck_on_winning_domain_name_case" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Creator of website satirizing Glenn Beck on winning domain name case</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 10, 2009</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> interviewed the creator of a parody website satirizing <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">American</ref> political commentator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glenn%20Beck">Glenn Beck</ref>, about his thoughts after prevailing in a domain name dispute brought by Beck before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20Intellectual%20Property%20Organization">World Intellectual Property Organization</ref> (WIPO) in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geneva">Geneva</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Switzerland">Switzerland</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Florida">Florida</ref> resident Isaac Eiland-Hall created the website in September, and it asserts Beck uses questionable tactics "to spread lies and misinformation". Eiland-Hall was represented in the case by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom%20of%20speech">free speech</ref> lawyer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marc%20Randazza">Marc Randazza</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed Randazza for the article "<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_free_speech_lawyer_Marc_Randazza_discusses_Glenn_Beck_parody">US free speech lawyer Marc Randazza discusses Glenn Beck parody</ref>", and previously reported on the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beck%20v.%20Eiland-Hall">Beck v. Eiland-Hall</ref></hi> case in articles, "<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_free_speech_lawyer_defends_satire_of_Glenn_Beck">US free speech lawyer defends satire of Glenn Beck</ref>",  "<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Satirical_website_criticizes_Glenn_Beck_for_'hypocritical'_attempts_to_silence_free_speech">Satirical website criticizes Glenn Beck for 'hypocritical' attempts to silence free speech</ref>", and "<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Glenn_Beck_loses_domain_name_case_over_parody_website">Glenn Beck loses domain name case over parody website</ref>".</p>
<head id="Background">Background</head>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glenn%20Beck">Glenn Beck</ref> in 2007 Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Mark87">Mark87</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Eiland-Hall registered the website at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/domain%20name">domain</ref> "www.GlennBeckRapedAndMurderedAYoungGirlIn1990.com". Its premise was derived from a joke statement made by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilbert%20Gottfried">Gilbert Gottfried</ref> about fellow comedian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Saget">Bob Saget</ref>. Users of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Internet">Internet</ref> discussion community <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fark">Fark</ref> first applied the joke to Beck, and it then became popular on several social media sites. Eiland-Hall saw the discussion on Fark, and created a website about it. The website asserts it does not believe the rumors to be true, commenting, "[b]ut we think Glenn Beck definitely uses tactics like this to spread lies and misinformation." The website was created on September 1, and just two days later attorneys for Beck's company <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mercury%20Radio%20Arts">Mercury Radio Arts</ref> took action. Beck's lawyers sent letters to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain%20name%20registrar">domain name registrar</ref> where they referred to the domain name itself as "defamatory", but failed to get the site removed.</p>
<p>Beck filed a formal complaint with the Switzerland-based agency of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations">United Nations</ref>, WIPO, who operate under regulations laid out by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet%20Corporation%20for%20Assigned%20Names%20and%20Numbers">Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers</ref>. Beck asserted the website's usage is libelous, bad faith, and could confuse potential consumers. Beck's complaint was filed under the process called the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uniform%20Domain%20Name%20Dispute%20Resolution%20Policy">Uniform Domain Name Dispute Resolution Policy</ref>. This policy allows trademark owners to begin an administrative action by complaining that a certain domain registration is in "bad faith". Beck argued the site should be shut down because it is an infringement upon his trademark in his own name, "Glenn Beck".</p>
<p>Eiland-Hall retained Randazza as his attorney after receiving threatening letters from legal representatives of Beck. On September 28, Randazza filed a response brief to WIPO, contending the site is "protected political speech", due to it's "satirical political humor". Randazza stated, "even an imbecile would look at this Web site and know that it’s a parody." Randazza's brief commented on Beck's style of reporting, and highlighted a controversial statement made by him when interviewing a Muslim US <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Congress">Congressman</ref>. Beck said to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20House%20of%20Representatives">Representative</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keith%20Ellison">Keith Ellison</ref>, "I like Muslims, I've been to mosques. ... And I have to tell you, I have been nervous about this interview because what I feel like saying is, sir, prove to me that you are not working with our enemies." According to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citizen%20Media%20Law%20Project">Citizen Media Law Project</ref>, the website's joke premise takes advantage of "a perceived similarity between Beck's rhetorical style and the Gottfried routine".</p>
</text>
