<text id="autogum_interview_doc1442" title="part1_Interview: Danny O'Brien of the Electronic Frontier Foundation" shortTile="partinterview-danny" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-01-24" dateModified="2012-02-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview%3A_Danny_O%27Brien_of_the_Electronic_Frontier_Foundation" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><p>[Danny O'Brien] We're currently looking into every possible avenue. One of the difficulties is trying to ascertain exactly what the government program involved. The EFF has a battery of lawyers, with different areas of interest.</p>
[Wikinews] Is this in the same vein as the recent requests for Google to pony up its search database?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] No, that's a great question. The two issues are very different, but I think speak to the problems that the Internet is now being seen as a resource for government surveillance and research, which we think that all Net companies have to become aware of. There's a real danger in simply logging everything: you end up risking being a tool for the invasion of your own customer's privacy.</p>
[Wikinews] Google alone of the largest search engines refused the Justice Department's demands to turn over user data. The EFF is on record as criticizing Google's privacy policy. How does the EFF feel about that privacy policy now? What does EFF feel about the other search engine's behaviour—did they comply with their own privacy policies? Does this incident reflect the strength or weakness of corporate privacy policies online?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] Privacy policies largely extend at the moment to merely the descriptions of what information is stored. We've long warned against companies collecting large amounts of data about their customers, and doing nothing to anonymise or aggregate it. We think that companies are storing up trouble for themselves this way.</p>
[Wikinews] Does the EFF have any material or programs that seek to educate employers and companies on the advantages of privacy?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] We do -- hold on, I should be handing out more URLs <ref target="http://www.eff.org/osp/">http://www.eff.org/osp/</ref> is our guide to "online service providers" for the best practices in logging data. I'm also speaking at the MySQL conference later this year on what *not* to include in your schema. It's an interesting area, because it's one where coders have a degree of power over what can be done.</p>
<p>Personally, I'd like to see a great deal more knowledge about how to aggregate and anonymise data being spread among the community. I'm constantly recommending the book <ref target="http://www.wayner.org/books/td/">Translucent Databases</ref>, which covers this very nicely. Also, the OSS source would do a great service by setting reasonable defaults for software logging behaviours. The trouble is, and I think we all fall into this trap; we assume the more logging the better. How many of us are casually logging this, for instance?</p>
[Wikinews] I'd like to talk about the Sony BMG case for a bit, if that's okay.  First, congratulations to EFF in regard to some of the successes in the Sony BMG case. There are some questions, clarifications about the case, however. The settlement appears to cover the XCP and SunComm software delivered on CDs. What about OpenMG XCP, DRM used by Sony BMG's SonicStage software for Sony Connect?
</text>
