<text id="autogum_interview_doc209" title="part10_BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2008-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Yeah, sure, totally.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  My favorite kinds of sessions are when people want to punish me for being a Mistress!  That was one of the hottest sub sessions I had ever done, because it was an interrogation session and I had to confess everything I had done to men, and all that stuff.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  And by being a sub, you understand more what they are going through and what they are feeling.  So if I <hi rend="italic">was</hi> to have a session where it was like, “Oh, you filthy little wetback!  Figure out if you want to be a commonwealth or a state, bitch!” something like that, you know.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  That’s kind of hot! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Yeah! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who is Mental Dental?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  He’s a very, very old man and he likes to have his teeth pulled on and have you pretend that you are a dental hygienist and talk about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/bicuspids">bicuspids</ref> and all that stuff.  It’s not that uncommon; other people have that fetish.  You have to really act like you are well-trained as a dental assistant.  The question about boundaries you asked earlier, though, goes back to the question about somebody who had no experience.  Boundaries are the most important thing you have to develop, and I’m sorry I have to speak so abstractly about it, but you don’t really learn that unless you go into session and discover what you will and won’t do.</p>
<head id="What_they_discover_in_themselves">What they discover in themselves</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you also think you find out more about yourself in those types of sessions?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Oh yes.  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Definitely</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  And more about what I do, because it’s playing with taboos, especially with psychological role plays like that.  As much as people want to deny it, taboos are kind of hot.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Well, they typically are, right?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Yeah…yeah!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who wants to do the missionary position their whole fucking lives, kind of thing, right?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Yeah!  Yeah! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I don’t know if I’ll put that in - it makes me sound like I'm getting into it!   [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Maybe I’ll do some photos of you two beating me!  Just for the article!  Just for the article!  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Tie me up and pinch my nipples for knowledge! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you been asked to carry out any War related fantasies?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  That’s a good question.  I have sessioned with a few veterans, but it hasn’t revolved around being in a war.   It’s people who would be coming here regardless of whether they had been in a war or not.  Under a larger umbrella of people who come here who have experienced a trauma have similar sessions.  It is interesting for people to come back and want to live certain traumatic events.  It’s challenging.  You have to play a role.  I have people who want me to be a Nazi who experienced that in some way.</p>
</text>
