<text id="autogum_interview_doc1212" title="part0_Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian presidential candidate James Burns" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-23" dateModified="2012-05-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Libertarian_presidential_candidate_James_Burns" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian presidential candidate James Burns</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 23, 2008</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> held an exclusive interview with James Burns, one of the candidates for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libertarian%20Party">Libertarian Party</ref> nomination for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008%20U.S.%20presidential%20election">2008 U.S. presidential election</ref>.</p>
<p>Burns, the former chairman of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nevada">Nevada</ref> Libertarian Party, was asked if he thinks he has a good shot at winning the Libertarian nomination and ultimately the presidency. He replied, "My chances of winning are not all in my hands. I shall do my best, but it comes down to what others will do. What will you do?"</p>
<p>When asked about America's shrinking <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/middle%20class">middle class</ref> he said, "The economic policies of the US government are the cause our troubles. When I am President, the only economic policy I shall pursue is to be frugal with the funds of the United States."</p>
<p>Burns believes that the President "is not 'the leader of the free world,' rather....a person who attempts to protect our rights to life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness."</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">Why do you want to run for president?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mr. Burns:</hi> I am running for President because I am not uniquely qualified to be President nor is anyone else. We elect neither a dictator, a king, nor a god. The President is the chief administrator of the government of the United States (Article 2, Section 1), an important job for now, but still just a person who has taken an oath to uphold the constitution, an employee of the United States Government.</p>
<p>The President is not “the leader of the free world,” rather the President should be a person who attempts to protect our rights to life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness. One reason you should vote for me and the reason I am running for President is because I know the above and most others do not.</p>
<p>Another thing I believe is: "Certainly the game is rigged. Don't let that stop you; if you don't bet, you can't win." --Robert A. Heinlein</p>
<p>I hope for your consideration, and please take the time to look me up at: jimburnsforpresident.com</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">If elected, how would you handle the illegal immigration crisis?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mr. Burns:</hi> I believe the problems we are experiencing with immigration are assimilation and the inconsistency of government law and enforcement.</p>
<p>The United States immigration policy should eliminate quotas, require inspections for contagious disease, and the immigrant should be required to understand and agree that he or she must obey United States law, that he or she does not qualify for voting rights, and that immigrants do not qualify to receive United States welfare.</p>
<p>Green card identification costs money to produce: The immigrant should pay a fee that covers the cost of their green card that gives them the privilege to live and work within the United States and he or she must deposit a bond to cover the cost of their possible deportation.</p>
</text>
