<text id="autogum_interview_doc1202" title="part14_BDSM as business: An interview with the owners of a dungeon" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_An_interview_with_the_owners_of_a_dungeon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Well, don't forget I have the dog, and I've always had a dog.  Before I had her, I had a black lab.  I've always--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Before you go down that road, David--see, David is inclined, I think, this is what I'm thinking--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I would make an assumption that yes, all things equal, that there might be more of a chance of a dangerous situation happening here.  You are rooting around in people’s psychology here.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  You're more likely to get yourself into trouble in a regular straight bar at night, a regular--a local bar at night, than you would at a topless bar.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Maybe because we're not a typical place.  I have had clients tell me of places that they've gone to--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where they didn't feel safe.  And that's part of the main business model at Rebecca’s, right?  That it needs to be a safe environment for the client?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  We don’t leave a lot of money on the table by not being open that late.  We're not open past--</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  And we haven't.  We've been open 'til one, two, three, four; most of our competition, which I don't ev--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  We're not open until four.  When have we ev--</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  No, at times, we've tried--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Only if we had a client here.  We--</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  No, we--in the past, we've tried different hours.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  We never tried staying open until four in the morning.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  I think three was the latest.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  No, we tried until one.  When we've had special clients, we've stayed open.  We've never tried to stay open 'til three or four in the morning.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  I think that one time we stayed open until--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  We may have stayed open for a special client.  We never set our hours until three, because we know that two o'clock, three o'clock in the morning is when the crazies come out in life.  When you're in a bar, you see the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alcoholic">drunks</ref>, you see the guys doing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cocaine">blow</ref> at that time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is it usually appointments, or is it walk-ins?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Always appointments.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  No, it's always appointments.  Always appointments.  Even though we do have clients who know us very well who will come up and say, "I'm sorry, I was in the neighborhood . . . ."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Right, right.  That's true.  That's true.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  But I have--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You make exceptions for certain clients.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Even then, what percentage would you say that is?</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  It's nothing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Like what percentage?  Give him a percentage he could go on.</p>
</text>
