<text id="autogum_interview_doc551" title="part3_Ingrid Newkirk, co-founder of PETA, on animal rights and the film about her life" shortTile="partingrid-newkirk" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-20" dateModified="2018-02-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ingrid_Newkirk%2C_co-founder_of_PETA%2C_on_animal_rights_and_the_film_about_her_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="PETA,_animal_rights_groups_and_the_Animal_Liberation_Front">PETA, animal rights groups and the Animal Liberation Front</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you feel when you hear other animal rights organizations coming out against PETA?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Oh, I don’t mind.  I think somebody has to push the envelope.  If you say something someone already agrees with, then what’s the point?  So we make some more conservative animal protection organizations uncomfortable.  They don’t want to be associated with us because it will be embarrassing for them.  I understand that.  Our own members write to us sometimes and say, “Oh, why did you do this? I don’t want anybody to know I’m a PETA member.”  For some of us we agree cordially, like that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humane%20Society">Humane Society</ref> man.  We exchange e-mails all the time and I nag him that he needs to take a stronger position on some things and stop mealy-mouthing, and he nags me in his e-mails that it’s about time I condemn such-and-such.  “It doesn’t do any good for you to stick up for such-and-such.”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is something you have been asked to condemn?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  He wants us to condemn illegal acts.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  By the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Animal%20Liberation%20Front">Animal Liberation Front</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  Yes, those getting the animals out of the laboratories, and I won’t do it because if it was my animal I would be happy.  If it was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chihuahua%20(dog)">Little Man</ref> [<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>’s dog, pictured in the lead photo</hi>] I would be happy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So you are okay with ALF activities?  Some of that was covered in the film.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  It was only marginally covered.  There was only so much you could focus on and in such a way.  There weren’t rebuttals to many things, which was disturbing.  Like when that woman said PETA is not doing any good, I would love to have seen the whole list of endless victories we have had, starting with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General%20Motors">General Motors</ref> switching to mannequins in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crash%20test">crash tests</ref>—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L’Oreal">L’Oreal</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maybelline">Maybelline</ref>—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  All of it.  There’s a huge huge list of everything.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you feel about the ALF?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">IN:</hi>  I wrote a book called <hi rend="italic">Free the Animals</hi>, and it’s about the Animal Liberation Front since its inception in the United States.  Not about the ALF overseas, where it began, but its inception here going to about 199-something.  I talked about how I <hi rend="italic">do</hi> support getting animals out in the same way I would have supported getting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slavery">human slaves</ref> out, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Child%20labor">child labor</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sex%20slaves">sex slaves</ref>, the whole lot.  But I don’t support burning.  I don’t support <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arson">arson</ref>.  I would rather that these buildings weren’t standing, so on some level I understand.  I just don’t like the idea of that.  Maybe that is wishy-washy of me, because I don’t want those buildings standing if they are going to hurt anyone.  And the ALF has never hurt <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mice">mice</ref> nor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mankind">man</ref>.</p>
</text>
