<text id="autogum_interview_doc799" title="part2_Antje Duvekot on life as a folk singer, her family and her music" shortTile="partantje-duvekot" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Antje_Duvekot_on_life_as_a_folk_singer%2C_her_family_and_her_music" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The struggle to be original in art is innate.  When you are coming up with an idea for a song and then you all of a sudden stumble across it having been done somewhere else, how do you not  allow that to squelch your creative impulse and drive to continue on.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  That’s a good question.  I started writing in a vacuum just for myself and I didn’t have a lot of feedback, and I thought that what I’m saying has been said so many times before.  Then my songs got out there and people told me, ‘You  say it so originally’ and I thought ‘Really?!’  The way I say it, to me, sounds completely <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/trite">trite</ref> because it’s the way I would say it and it doesn’t sound special at all.  Once my record came out I got some amount of positive reviews that made me think I have something original, which in turn made me have writer’s block to keep that thing that I didn’t even know I had.  So now I’m struggling with that, trying to maintain my voice.  Right now I feel a little dried-out creatively.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction,_writing,_his_family_and_his_new_book">I interviewed Augusten Burroughs</ref> he told me that when he was in advertising he completely shut himself off from the yearly ad books that would come out of the best ads that year, because he wanted to be fresh and not poisoned by other ideas; whereas a band called <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Raveonettes_on_love,_death,_desire_and_war">The Raveonettes said</ref> they don’t try to be original they just do what they like and are upfront about their influences.  Where do you fall in that spectrum?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  Probably more towards Augusten Burroughs because when I first started writing it was more in a vacuum, but I think everyone has their own way.  You can’t not be influenced by your experience in life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who would you say are some of your biggest influences in the last year.  Who have you discovered that has influenced you the most?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  Influence is kind of a strong word because I don’t think I’m taking after these people.  I’ve been moved by this girl named <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anais%20Mitchell">Anais Mitchell</ref>.  She’s a singer-songwriter from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vermont">Vermont</ref> who is really unique.  She’s just got signed to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Righteous%20Babe%20Records">Righteous Babe Records</ref>.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patty%20Griffin">Patty Griffin</ref> just moves me deeply.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You moved out of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20City">New York</ref> because you had some difficulty with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music%20of%20New%20York%20City">music scene here</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AD:</hi>  I feel it is a little tougher to make it here than in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston">Boston</ref> if you are truly <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acoustic%20music">acoustic</ref> folk lyric driven.  I find that audiences in New York like a certain amount of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bling">bling</ref> and glamor to their performances.  A little more edge, a little cooler.  I felt for me Boston was the most conducive environment.</p>
</text>
