<text id="autogum_interview_doc1235" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Australian blind Paralympic skier Melissa Perrine" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-10" dateModified="2017-10-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_blind_Paralympic_skier_Melissa_Perrine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Not going to become a B1 any time soon?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> Oh God, I hope not. No, I'm pretty stable so I don't envision getting much blinder than I am now unless something goes wrong.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  And you're trying for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2014_Winter_Paralympics">Sochi</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> Definitely.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  And you think your chances are really good?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> I think I've got a decent chance. I just have to keep training like I have been.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Win a medal this time?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> I'd like to. That's the intention. (laughs)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you like the media attention you've gotten? Do you wish there was more for yourself and winter sports, or of women athletes in general?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> I think that promoting <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Women's_sports">women in sport</ref> and the winter games is more important than promoting myself. I'm quite happy to stay in the background, but if I can do something to promote the sport, or promote women in the sport, especially because we've got such a small amount of women competing in skiing, especially in blind skiing. I think that's more important overall.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Most skiers are men?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> There's more men competing in skiing, far more. The standards are a bit higher with the males than with the females.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Para-alpine%20skiing%20classification">classification system</ref> for everyone else is functional ability, and you guys are a medical classification. Do you think you get a fair shake in terms of classification? Are you happy with the classification? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> I think I'm happy with it, the way it's set out. With vision impairment I'm a B2, against other B2s. It may be the same category, but we have different disabilities, so there's not much more they can do. I think it's as fair as they possibly can.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You like the point system? You're okay with it? Competing against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B1%20(classification)">B1s</ref> and B3s even though you're a B2?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> The factors even all that out. The way they've got it at the moment, I don't have any issues with them, the blind categories.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What was it that got you skiing in the first place?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> An accident, basically. Complete by chance. A friend of mine in the Department of Recreation used to run skiing camps in the South West <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sydney">Sydney</ref> region, and she had a spare spot at one of the camps. Knew that I was vision impaired, and: "Do you want to come along?" "Yeah, why, not, give it a go." This was back when I was about twelve, thirteen. I went, and I loved it. Went back again, and again, and again.  And for the first five or six years I just skied for like a week a season sort of thing, like, you're on a camp. Fell in love with the sport; my skiing and the mountain atmosphere, I love it, and then, when I finished my HSC, I decided to take myself off to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref>, and skiing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kimberley,%20British%20Columbia">Kimberley</ref>, the disabled race program that was run by the ex-Australian who coaches Steve Boba, and I'd heard about it through Disabled Winter Sports Australia. And I thought I'd spend some time in Canada, which is for skiing, and had a year off between school and uni, so... first time I ran through a race course actually. It was pretty awesome. So I went back again the next year, and Steve [Boba] recommended me to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve%20Graham">Steve [Graham]</ref>, and he watched me skiing in September in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South%20Island">South Island</ref>, and invited me on a camp with the Australian team, and I trained for Vancouver, and I qualified, and I said "sure, why not?"  And here I am!</p>
</text>
