<text id="autogum_interview_doc1039" title="part6_Wikinews interviews team behind the 2,000th featured Wikipedia article" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-04-10" dateModified="2009-12-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_team_behind_the_2%2C000th_featured_Wikipedia_article" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Before moving on to bringing your students into the discussion, I'd like to close with your thoughts on making this a regular part of the curriculum. Do you intend to do so? Do you feel other institutions should examine your project with a view to emulating it?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">JBM</hi></hi>: I certainly intend to repeat the experiment.  The one downside for an instructor is that, if it is to be done right, it is very labour-intensive.  On the other hand, in terms of capital resources it is essentially free.  My university (and many others) pays millions of dollars per year for site licences for educational software such as WebCT.  That's a massive waste of money, as far as I'm concerned; though it's a lucrative racket for the people selling the software.  It's also, I'd say, an abdication of an important aspect of the university's mission: to invest in the Commons.  The trend in contemporary academia is too often towards privatization and enclosure.  (Though I should note that there are valiant exceptions, and my former colleague <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Willinsky">John Willinsky</ref>'s work on open access is exemplary.)  The more universities engage with Wikipedia, and the more they realize that they can do so without necessarily dropping the high standards of research and academic rigour that it is also their duty to safeguard, the more they benefit not only their own students, but also the public good.</item></list>
<head id="Good_and_Featured_Articles">Good and Featured Articles</head>
<figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure><p> In addition to the one featured article, seven made "Good Article" status. How much of an encouragement was that to those of you involved in the project?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Monica Freudenreich</hi></hi>: I honestly cannot speak for the rest of the class but I think that everyone involved was a little bit weary (Ed: wary?) of this project. None of us had ever embarked on this sort of thing in our undergraduate careers before and to say the least, were unsure of how this would all turn out. Being students, we are prone to leave things to the last minute and with this project that was definitely not a possibility. So, despite a slow start in general, I think the status most of the articles in our project achieved is really impressive and that is a huge encouragement in itself</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Katy Konyk</hi></hi>: I can't speak for the rest of the class but I think seeing so many articles achieve good status proved that he goal was very achievable. I think the only downside was that in class people are going to work at their own speeds so having others reach good article status, if you are not there yet, sometimes added to the pressure.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Elyse Economides</hi></hi>: I think it was a form of encouragement, but also made the task seem a bit daunting. It was exciting to see that so many of the groups could attain the goal of "Good Article" status at the end of four months, but it also spoke to the amount of time and effort needed to reach that point. Hopefully seeing their classmates achieve "Good Article" status encouraged the individual groups that the same achievement was also possible.</item></list>
</text>
