<text id="autogum_interview_doc448" title="part2_US presidential candidate Duncan Hunter speaks to Wikinews" shortTile="partus-presidential" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-12" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_presidential_candidate_Duncan_Hunter_speaks_to_Wikinews" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Where did they come from?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Mostly Mexico.  The vast majority came from Mexico and last time I looked 27% of the federal penitentiary population are criminal aliens.  So there is a large criminal contingent that moves back and forth across the border, and we pay $3 billion a year to incarcerate those folks.  One year’s incarceration costs would build a thousand miles of border fence.  That’s another reason why you have to have a real border.  The other aspect is that we have the biggest open door in the world, that is the biggest front door, the legal immigration system is very liberal in this country and very open, so it is only appropriate that when people want to come into this country, they knock on the front door.</p>
<head id="Concentrating_the_political_power_in_Congressional_redistricting">Concentrating the political power in Congressional redistricting</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You were originally elected as part of the Reagan Revolution and you came from a historically competitive district—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Actually a non-competitive <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California's%2052nd%20congressional%20district">district</ref>; it was 2 to 1 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_of_the_United_States">Democrat</ref>.  It was so noncompetitive that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lionel%20Van%20Deerlin">my opponent</ref> announced two weeks before the election that it was so Democrat that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abraham%20Lincoln">Abraham Lincoln</ref> couldn’t beat him! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> But you won!  So it sounds competitive.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Well, it wasn’t competitive until 1980.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Districts nationwide have become solidly leaning toward one party or another.  Do you think that since our districts are being drawn in ways—and both parties do this—in ways that ensure one party wins, do you think that hurts our democracy?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Well, actually, it’s always happened since the original <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerrymander">Gerrymander</ref> by Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elbridge%20Gerry">Elbridge Gerry</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref>, which they named the Gerry Salamander and then the Gerrymander.  The district I ran in had been gerrymandered by the Democrats of the legislature to be heavily Democrat; I was just able to win it.  You have the same thing now.  You have very polarized seats, but it’s not much different than it was in 1980.  In fact, it’s no difficult at all.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Congressional%20stagnation%20in%20the%20United%20States">But studies have shown</ref> that districts <hi rend="italic">have</hi> become more concentrated, that the votes have become more lopsided toward one party, whereas it used to be more that you would find percentages of 47/53, whereas now it is 60/40 or 65/35.  You consistently win more than 60-70% of the vote in your district.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Yeah, well, that’s true, but that’s what the old guy used to get in my district in 1980.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> But then they changed it.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Yeah, but my point is that the district was actually moved—the Democrat legislature actually cut my house out and moved it around and moved it into East County with a narrow connector.  SO I have always been subject to the Democrat party controlling redistricting in California.  They have done what is most expeditious for the party.</p>
</text>
