<text id="autogum_interview_doc1251" title="part14_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How can anyone--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  You know?  I like being able to just-- I like that this book is going to show another side.</p>
<head id="On_women's_breasts_and_tattoos">On women's breasts and tattoos</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's your favorite curse word?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  My favorite curse word?  Let me think about that . . . . I like "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cunt">cunt</ref>."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">Chuckles</hi>] That's always the one that--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  It seems to offend so many people still.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It <hi rend="italic">does.</hi></hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  There's something about it I like, or--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s a cutting word.  Do you have a favorite euphemism for women's breasts?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Oh yeah, let's see…what do I call them…?  I like the old-fashioned words for breasts, like "boobies."  I like "boobies," um "girls," "my girls" or "your girls”;  I like the idea of naming breasts, like "Jen" and "Stacy."  I think every girl should name each breast.  "Stacy hangs a little lower"; "Stacy needs a tuck, but Beth doesn't."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">Chuckles</hi>] What would you name your breasts?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I would name them--"Regina" and "Claire."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Would Claire be the bigger one? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I'm glad I don't have them--actually, if I had them, I would have them sawed off.  I wouldn't be able to stand it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Really?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah, I'd be like, "Chop these fucking things off."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You're not like most gay men who have a fascination with breasts?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I would want them gone.  They look uncomfortable.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you like them on other people?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah, I do.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have a breast fetish?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  No, because you know what, I saw this picture of this woman who had breast cancer, and she had a <hi rend="italic">radical</hi> mastectomy, and she had these <hi rend="italic">massive</hi> scars, and then she had them tattooed.  And I thought that it looked soooo cool.  She looked great and she was in shape.  And I thought it would make me want breast cancer if I'd seen that picture; I would have thought, "I want it!"</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  My sister has stretch marks on her stomach that she's really self-conscious about--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi> <hi rend="italic">Tattoo it.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  We've been talking about that!</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  It's a good look.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I had suggested to her tattooing a band of stars across it, that--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Oh, what a great idea!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yeah, like where it starts out small, and goes like bigger over the marks?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yes.  Yep.  That's a beautiful idea.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And she was all for it.  We were going to take her to my tattoo guy, over here on First Avenue--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Such a good idea.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And she all of a sudden has been like, "Mmmmm, I don't really know."  And she's like,  "Maybe I'm going to get a belly button ring."  But that's going to <hi rend="italic">highlight</hi> it!  </hi></p>
</text>
