<text id="autogum_interview_doc480" title="part4_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic wheelchair basketballer Shelley Chaplin" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-01-03" dateModified="2014-06-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_wheelchair_basketballer_Shelley_Chaplin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yeah, well our biggest strength was our defence, so if we can play the defence, we can.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The defence was where you won those games. You blocked them off. Particularly <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref>, they couldn't... Canada was even better. You kept on forcing turnovers, forcing timeouts. That was the defensive game, was the way you won it.   </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Absolutely.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  But Germany had a good defensive game as well. It must have been good, playing on your birthday.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> It was really cool. The whole team, the whole Australian Paralympic team wished me happy birthday, the whole crowd sang me happy birthday and this sort of stuff. It was pretty special, but once you get into it, it's just another game. I know all the people were talking about the fact that it was my birthday, but it didn't [get to me]. It was fun. It was fun. Not a bad place to have your birthday.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So how do you compare London with Beijing and Athens?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Well, I think every games gets a little bit better anyway. Like, Beijing was better than Athens and I think London was a lot better than Beijing again. But I think the special thing about London is that it was <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">British</ref>, and so they obviously support Australians, <hi rend="italic">but</hi> we were just athletes to them, I think. Whereas in Beijing we were still disabled athletes. But in London we were just athletes and they loved our sport and they understood our sport, which was really cool. The crowds... it was amazing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  We have a lot of statistics on the response to it. Unfortunately, being in London I couldn't see the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Television">TV</ref> coverage.  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Back here the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australian_Broadcasting_Corporation">ABC</ref> did a fantastic job with us. Everybody knows about the Paralympics. Everybody saw something.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Apparently there was extra requests for the Gliders. So more people wanted to see you.  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> People like basketball. Basketball is very easy to relate to. Team sports are good to watch. But I think, like I was saying earlier, if you take away the wheelchair, there's nothing to do with disabilities. If an able bodied jumped into a wheelchair, it's exactly the same as us. Whereas an able bodied can't run against someone with blades. You know?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yes.  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> So I think that's why; it's very relatable, and obviously it's fun to watch.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  It seems be be getting bigger with each set of games. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Definitely.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I've got figures from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Google">Google</ref>. London is twice as big. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yep. Absolutely. The Paralympic movement is exciting because we're all amateur athletes, and we're all doing it because we love the sport. I think, during Beijing, I know in the Australian media they tried to get everyone to look away from our disabilities and look at us just as athletes, but I think in London they were like, here's their disabilities, here's what they are doing athletically, and combining the two, which made for amazing coverage, right? Cause everyone understood our disabilities but our sport as well.</p>
</text>
