<text id="autogum_interview_doc1270" title="part3_Two-time Eurovision entrant Edsilia Rombley discusses music, love, and her contrasting Contest experiences" shortTile="parttwotime-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-03" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Two-time_Eurovision_entrant_Edsilia_Rombley_discusses_music%2C_love%2C_and_her_contrasting_Contest_experiences" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Whose idea was it to participate in <hi rend="italic">Dancing with the Stars</hi>? Your experience was short overall, but did you have a fun experience? What did you take away from your time on the show?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">ER</hi>: It was my idea. I used to watch dance contests on TV and loved the amazing dresses of the female dancers. This was my chance to wear some of those great dresses myself! I had a great experience. The most important thing I learned [was that] professional dancing is much more difficult [than] I thought it would be!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You've released albums in a variety of different genres, in both English and Dutch. What genre do you feel best describes your innermost feelings? Do you prefer singing in Dutch over English? Have you considered starting a music career in the United States? You could give Jennifer Hudson a run for her money...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">ER</hi>: English and Dutch both feel good to me, it's very difficult to choose a favourite language. I love to see people party to my up-tempo Dutch repertoire, but can also put all my emotion into a Dutch ballad. With English it's especially the soul repertoire that touches me, and if I get the chance to take my musical career abroad, I would jump at the opportunity! I am very happy with what I've accomplished so far, but am of course always striving for more.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Recently you released a CD and DVD, where you performed your past hits. How did the idea for a live album come about? Listening to some of the tracks, the sound is very intimate and personal; was this something that was a selling point for you? How did you feel revisiting your entire repertoire?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">ER</hi>: The DVD is called "Live @ The Wisseloord Studios" and contains these studio sessions, which are all Dutch songs from my album "Meer dan ooit". As a bonus there are English songs from my 2005 tour, and songs from Anita Baker, Betty Wright, Gladys Knight and Oleta Adams.</p>
<p>The album is simply called "Edsilia Rombley LIVE" and contains a selection of my favourite English songs from the same tour, and I am so proud that these songs are finally on CD, because before I could not let people hear the English repertoire (unless I sang live to them).</p>
<head id="Eurovision_'07_and_thoughts_about_the_Contest_today">Eurovision '07 and thoughts about the Contest today</head>
<figure><caption>Edsilia Rombley performing "On Top of the World" at Eurovision 2007 in Helsinki.Photo: Loe Beerens</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In 2007, you returned to the Eurovision, and as someone fondly remembered from a past contest, there were high hopes placed on you. However, your song "On Top of the World" did not advance from the semi-finals. How disappointed were you that you didn't advance? Did you feel "On Top of the World" was as strong of a song as "Hemel en aarde" was?</hi></p>
</text>
