<text id="autogum_interview_doc999" title="part2_'Big Brother' contestant Parker Somerville sounds off about the show and his aspirations" shortTile="partbig-brother-contestant" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-03-25" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/%27Big_Brother%27_contestant_Parker_Somerville_sounds_off_about_the_show_and_his_aspirations" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">PS</hi>: I didn't really have a strategy when I went into the house. I was definitely myself for the duration of my stay. I was very relaxed with everyone, cracking jokes and enjoying everyone's company. The great thing about me is that I can be your best friend, and your worst enemy. I'm cool, but the moment you cross me, I'll do a 180 on you. I guess that's the Aries in me! When I woke up everyone in the house, I wanted to let everyone know, "Don't take my kindness for weakness." When I heard that whole "snake" comment, it really pissed me off because I did absolutely nothing to make someone judge me so quickly.  So I guess my direct approach to certain situations didn't help our current situation. But I know for a fact I wouldn't have been as pissed off as I was if I had control of my own fate in the house. Yes, I wasn't right for having a crappy attitude, but I don't believe I made a major contribution to our demise.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: How do you feel about Jen telling other HouseGuests that her real-life boyfriend Ryan was racist to ensure that she stayed in the game? Did you think that behavior crossed a line?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PS</hi>: [<hi rend="italic">laughs</hi>] I was like, damn, could you drive the stake in any harder? I felt like we had Sheila's vote, and when Jen told her that, it only hurt us. I really didn't think it was any of the HouseGuests', or America's, business to know what Ryan's racial issues were. I felt like she was not being fair to him because like it or not, he was there to play the game, just like she was. And even if he was racist, who cares?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: You had said after leaving the house that you felt Matt didn't keep his word to you as far as vetoing your nomination. Now that you've watched past footage, do you still believe Matt wronged you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PS</hi>: I never said that Matt didn't keep his word.  I knew he wasn't going to use the veto because he didn't want to become an early target. Well, at least that's what he told me beforehand.</p>
<p>In my speech, which they edited out, I asked him not to use it because the reason why we were nominated was because of trust issues. When I got out of sequester, I was talking with a few friends, and I was telling them about how Matt was cool as hell, and they said, "obviously you haven't seen the show."</p>
</text>
