<text id="autogum_interview_doc1385" title="part8_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  No, I disagree with that.  I’m glad you had that discussion.  Do you know why I disagree with you?  In the Latino community you don’t have an Al Sharpton, you have <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La%20Raza">La Raza</ref>.  <hi rend="italic">Every</hi> community <hi rend="italic">does</hi> have an organization or institution.  So number one, that’s not true.  Second, in the black community—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But there’s no one voice.  It seems like the others never have a singular voice.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Yeah, but that one voice is always the head of some group.  Believe me, if I could not prove that we could deliver the bodies to these protests, the press wouldn’t cover me.  The only reason the press covers me is we create the issue.  The press ignored Jena until we put 40,000 people down there.  So if we have the organizational muscle, they aren’t doing me a favor.  The white media didn’t <hi rend="italic">create</hi> me, they <hi rend="italic">covered</hi> me.  When I went to Howard Beach, there were hundreds out there and they threw bananas at us and all.  The press didn’t contact me and say, “We’ll tell you what, Sharpton, you go out there and we’ll cover you.”  No!  I created the drama like King did in Selma, Alabama.  So what they are really saying is, “Let’s be selective because if we don’t like Sharpton let’s not cover Sharpton because we want somebody else.”  Usually even the black critics that criticize charismatic leadership are blacks without <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/charisma">charisma</ref> who can’t do it themselves.  We’ve always had charismatic leadership, whether it was Mandela in South Africa or King in the south.  The question is what you use the charismatic leadership for; what’s wrong with that?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Shane Johnson is an African-American blogger who was protesting your Washington, D.C. Department of Justice march. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clarence%20Page">Clarence Page</ref>, who is one of your critics within the African-American community, wrote a column about it.  He wrote, "Why do we black folks get so much more agitated about occasional white-on-black insults than about the black-on-black assaults that constantly terrorize certain neighborhoods?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  My answer is why doesn’t Clarence Page do something about it when we everyday deal with that.  That is dealt with every day and every way.  Not only have we dealt with black on black assaults, not only do we do crime rallies, not only do we denounce it, we’ve even been the ones to go as far as to march on black rappers about the N-word, misogyny and violence to women that a lot of them glorify.  Clarence Page and them don’t do that, we do.  My critics were <hi rend="italic">totally</hi> silent when we were marching on the rappers, the records companies and all of that this summer.  But when I do a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Department%20of%20Justice">Justice</ref> march, they criticize.   Well, where were they when we were marching on some of these rappers who glorify violence?  That’s why they have no credibility in our community.  Because <hi rend="italic">we</hi> are marching on the record companies that glorify violence; we <hi rend="italic">are</hi> marching on black on black violence.   <hi rend="italic">They are not</hi>.  They wait for us to do an issue that is race-based, and act like that’s all we did.  We spent half this year fighting lyrics in records, the glorification of violence, drugs in our community.  I’m the one who painted the crackhouses, saying get them out of our community.  Where was Clarence and them then?</p>
</text>
