<text id="autogum_interview_doc1441" title="part0_Interview: Danny O'Brien of the Electronic Frontier Foundation" shortTile="partinterview-danny" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-01-24" dateModified="2012-02-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview%3A_Danny_O%27Brien_of_the_Electronic_Frontier_Foundation" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Interview: Danny O'Brien of the Electronic Frontier Foundation</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 24, 2006</hi></p>
<p>January's second <ref target="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Wikinews/Interview%20of%20the%20month">Interview of the Month</ref> was with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danny%20O'Brien">Danny O'Brien</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Electronic_Frontier_Foundation">Electronic Frontier Foundation</ref> (EFF) on 23 January in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IRC">IRC</ref>. </p>
<p>The EFF is coming off a series of high-profile successes in their campaigns to educate the public, press, and policy makers regarding online rights in a digital world, and defending those rights in the legislature and the courtroom. Their settlement with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2005%20Sony%20CD%20copy%20protection%20controversy#Legal_situation">Sony/BMG</ref>, the amazingly confused <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MGM%20Studios,%20Inc.%20v.%20Grokster,%20Ltd.">MGM v Grokster</ref> decision by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Supreme_Court_of_the_United_States">Supreme Court of the United States</ref>, and the disturbing cases surrounding Diebold have earned the advocacy organization considerable attention.</p>
<p>When asked if the EFF would be interested in a live interview in IRC by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref>, the answer was a nearly immediate yes, but just a little after <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Brazilian_blogger_Ricardo_Serran_Lobo">Ricardo Lobo</ref>. With two such interesting interview candidates agreeing so quickly, it was hard to say no to either so schedules were juggled to have both. By chance, the timing worked out to have the EFF interview the day before the U.S. Senate schedule hearings concerning the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broadcast%20flag">Broadcast flag</ref> rule of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Communications%20Commission">FCC</ref>, a form of digital rights management which the recording and movie industries have been lobbying hard for - and the EFF has been lobbying hard to prevent.</p>
<head id="Interview_questions">Interview questions</head>
[Wikinews] I'd like to jump into some direct questions which were suggested by people on the research page. These first ones relate to the US government and online privacy.
Since 9/11 the US administration has been progressively violating privacy standards in online communications, including circumventing its own surveillance laws and developing—and possibly implementing—the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information%20Awareness%20Office">Total Information Awareness</ref> project.  What is EFF's position regarding government monitoring of private communications such e-mail, instant messaging, and voice over IP?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] Since the very beginning, the EFF has worked hard to keep the traditional laws regarding wiretapping and monitoring away from the Internet, not just because we believe in strong 4th Amendment rights  but because technologically, a wiretap on an individual line is miles away from what is needed to do the equivalent on the Internet. That's why, for instance, we fought against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communications%20Assistance%20for%20Law%20Enforcement%20Act">CALEA</ref> being extended to the Net, and why we're fighting the FCC's extension of it now.</p>
<p>A lot of simple approaches to surveillance that the gov't would like to take are far from reasonable, to use the language of the 4th amendment.</p>
<p>I should say that I'm using American examples here, but we're obviously concerned more generally.</p>
[Wikinews] A related question - Will EFF be involved in cases, even as amicus, such as the cases filed by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/American_Civil_Liberties_Union">ACLU</ref> Detroit and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Center%20for%20Constitutional%20Rights">Center for Constitutional Rights</ref> New York, which allege the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/National_Security_Agency">National Security Agency</ref> violated US law prohibiting wiretaps without a warrant?
</text>
