<text id="autogum_interview_doc1444" title="part3_Interview: Danny O'Brien of the Electronic Frontier Foundation" shortTile="partinterview-danny" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-01-24" dateModified="2012-02-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview%3A_Danny_O%27Brien_of_the_Electronic_Frontier_Foundation" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>This ghetto has to be created in every audio-visual device, by government mandate.  So that affects the Net a couple of ways. Firstly, you essentially curtail the Net's use. But secondly, these flags are easily (though illegally) circumventable, so they generally prompt even more draconian laws (which are just as easily circumventable.)</p>
<p>One of our biggest problems with the flags is they <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crossing%20the%20Rubicon">cross a Rubicon</ref>. They create a government technological mandate in user tech. Once you start down that path—especially when you discover your initial mandate doesn't actually work—you just ask for more and more control.</p>
[Wikinews] Isn't this already the case, considering the HDTV standard and others? Isn't standards an element of the FCCs mandate?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] Standards for broadcast and reception, but not standards for what you do *after* you receive something. Remember the FCC's primary job is to prevent interference, and to manage the commons of the public airwaves. It's a huge overreach for it to take over what you do with what comes from over those airwaves.</p>
[Wikinews] Because this is a rule, not a law, how does the EFF plan to approach it in the US Congress?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] Well, the initial regulation was thrown out by the courts, who agreed with us that this was agency overreach. So what we've seen now is groups like the MPAA and RIAA attempt to extend the FCC's powers by law.</p>
<p>For all of last year, they attempted to do that by -- well, for want of a better word, sneakily attaching the necessary language to other bills. As you say, it can potentially be a very small amendment, so I suppose they felt that they could do this. Everyone fought an incredibly effective campaign to prevent this. And a lot of <hi rend="bold">that</hi> had to do with the Net—we'd hear from the Hill of a lobbyist attempt to include the regulation, and we'd be able to organise calls and letters from constituents very quickly.</p>
<p>Most politicians, strangely enough, don't like it when something is sneaked past them. And we managed to alert a lot of them to arguments they weren't hearing from broadcasting lobbyists.</p>
<p>Now, we're seeing a second stage. Which is Hollywood coming out into the open, and presenting the flags openly. That stage begins tomorrow, with Senate hearings on the topic.</p>
[Wikinews] The Senate will begin hearings on this rule tomorrow. What does EFF expect to happen during this legislative process? How might this affect online communities? to get specific and personal, what does it mean to Wikinews readers and contributors?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] If the law passes, it'll have dramatic effects. Particularly to Wikinews' future, actually: I think we can all foresee a time when Wikinews would take fair use samples of the news and public affairs, both audio and visual. With a broadcast or audio flag in place, that usage - while legal - would effectively disappear or at least be much much harder.</p>
</text>
