<text id="autogum_interview_doc660" title="part3_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How many times have you seen your own death?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Well, sadly, my best friend was killed this year.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Halberstam">David Halberstam</ref>.  We were brothers.  I was his first friend when he came to New York to join <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>.  He lived in this house when he first came.  He lived upstairs.  When he got married to his present widow, who I was with last night, I was the best man.  That was the late 1970's.  And the last year we traveled together as a foursome, his wife and mine.  Then he gets killed.  Jean calls me up, "Some student in San Francisco...he got killed just like that!"  So that's a death!  Now that is horrible, but that's not so bad.  I wouldn't mind dying like that.  The way I would <hi rend="italic">not</hi> want to die...every time I go flying I see the porters by the plane waiting for some old crippled person to get off the plane and then they roll them through the airport.  I don't want to go like that.  I'd rather go like Halberstam.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You wouldn't want to be a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terri%20Schiavo">Terri Schiavo</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I don't even want to be a cripple who gets pushed across the airport!  Forget <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brain%20damage">brain damage</ref>.  I'm just talking about infirm, getting along and can't walk.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You're quite sprite.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Yeah, I wouldn't want that.  That's why I'd like to go to Iraq.  Why?  I don't care about dying.  I'd rather go out like Halberstam.  Quick--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Doing what you love</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Yeah.  Yeah.  Even if I was on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Jazeera">Al-Jazeera</ref> with a gun to my head, I wouldn't be pleading with those bastards!  I'd say, "Go ahead.  Make my day."  Because when you're 75 you see around you your own generation, some of them hobbling along.  Some writers I know--<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gore%20Vidal">Gore Vidal</ref>; poor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman%20Mailer">Norman Mailer</ref>.  Not that he's feeling sorry for himself, I was just with him in Texas earlier this year.  He gave his papers to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Texas%20at%20Austin">University of Texas at Austin</ref>.  I saw someone has to push him in a chair.  I've known Norman Mailer for some fifty years, and this is the first time someone has to push him.  I had a dinner party for him as recently as a year ago, here.  And I said, "Norman, you have to come up the steps, maybe we should go some place where there's an elevator."  He said, "No, no."  So he had to come up the steps outside where you did with his canes.  But in Austin with the campus there was someone who needed to push him in a chair.  That may happen to me soon enough, but I don't like to think about it.  Halberstam...he finished his work, <hi rend="italic">The Coldest Winter: America and the Korean War</hi>, was also thinking of another book and was in the process of researching it, and he gets rammed by a student who shouldn't have been driving him in the first place.  But he went out like that--quick!  And he had a great life.</p>
</text>
