<text id="autogum_interview_doc037" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Augustus Sol Invictus, Libertarian Party candidate for U.S. Senate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-05-15" dateModified="2016-12-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Augustus_Sol_Invictus%2C_Libertarian_Party_candidate_for_U.S._Senate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Augustus Sol Invictus, Libertarian Party candidate for U.S. Senate</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 16, 2016</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Augustus Sol InvictusImage: Bryan Rapoza.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Augustus%20Sol%20Invictus">Augustus Sol Invictus</ref>, an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Orlando,_Florida">Orlando</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Florida">Florida</ref> attorney currently seeking the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libertarian_Party_(United_States)">Libertarian Party</ref>'s nomination for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Senate">U.S. Senate</ref> seat being vacated by former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</ref> presidential candidate <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Marco_Rubio">Marco Rubio</ref>, took part in a short interview with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter William S. Saturn to discuss his background, political views, and unorthodox campaign for the Senate. </p>
<p>Invictus, whose name was changed from his birth name to the Latin for "majestic unconquered sun", has received media coverage for previously expressing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fascism">fascistic</ref> views and participating in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/paganism">pagan</ref> rituals. While in law school, he penned an article advocating a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/eugenics">eugenics</ref> program, and in 2013, he wrote a "departure memo" renouncing his U.S. citizenship and law license while announcing plans to go into the wilderness until a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/civil%20war">civil war</ref>.  He returned after making a pilgrimage from Orlando to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mojave%20Desert">Mojave Desert</ref>, where he fasted for a week.  Upon his return to Florida, he sacrificed a goat and drank its blood.  Former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libertarian%20Party%20of%20Florida">Libertarian Party of Florida</ref> chairman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian%20Wyllie">Adrian Wyllie</ref> resigned his chairmanship in protest of Invictus's candidacy. </p>
<p>Though initially uncontested for the nomination, Invictus has recently received a challenge from information technology specialist Paul Stanton.  Political operative <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Roger_Stone">Roger Stone</ref> opened an exploratory committee to consider running for the nomination but has not shown further interest.  The primary election is to be held August 30.  To qualify for the ballot, a candidate must either pay a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>10,000 fee or collect 100,000 signatures.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<head id="Background">Background</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why did you change your name to Augustus Sol Invictus?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Augustus Sol Invictus</hi>: I was given my name in a religious initiation when I was twenty-one. I usually analogize it to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Roman_Catholic_Church">Roman Catholics</ref> taking a new name at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confirmation">Confirmation</ref>. No one ever changes their name <hi rend="italic">legally</hi> after such an initiation, as it is usually reserved for religious pursuits. But I changed my name legally to my religious name so that my mundane and religious lives would be one.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What is your history with electoral politics?  Which political candidates have you previously supported or endorsed?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Invictus</hi>: I have no such history, and I have never made an endorsement. I consider myself an outsider. Truth be told, I consider myself a revolutionary more than a politician.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How do you feel about Republican front-runner <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref> and his campaign for president?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Invictus</hi>: Donald Trump is a cultural icon, and for that I love him. As for his presidential campaign, I am forced to remain neutral, as I cannot endorse anyone for President without it being thought that I have adopted their platform as my own.</item></list></p>
<figure><caption>Invictus says outgoing Senator <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Marco_Rubio">Marco Rubio</ref> (shown above), "is a horse-trader, a slimy smiler, the quintessential politician. He believes in nothing, save what his advisers tell him to believe in."Image: Gage Skidmore.</caption></figure>
</text>
