<text id="autogum_interview_doc1393" title="part16_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Then the focus is on gangsta culture and instead of looking at how that came about, it is talked about as if it is a phenomenon that just <hi rend="italic">happened</hi>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Nobody is looking at that, and the fact that if you didn’t have gangsta culture, we’d still be in the back of the bus.  Should we have stronger family ties?  Of course.  Should we stress education?  Of course!  Should we stress responsibility?  Of course!  But people who had self-contained families that were very responsible still had to sit in the back of the bus and couldn’t check into a hotel.  Let’s not act like gangsta is what caused racial inequity in our society.  It’s like saying you’ve got cancer, but you’ve also got a head cold, so the reason you’ve got cancer is you’ve got a head cold.  No, you have cancer <hi rend="italic">and</hi> a head cold.  You take <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tylenol">Tylenol</ref> for the head cold, but you’ve still got to deal with the cancer.  What they are trying to act like is taking head cold medicine is going to solve cancer.  It’s a bunch of crap!  If every black in America had strongly family ties, and there were no out-of-wedlock births, which I strongly advocate and preach, it still wouldn’t solve the racial inequality in the social fabric.  Let’s be honest about that.</p>
<head id="Blacks_and_whites_and_talking_about_race">Blacks and whites and talking about race</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  At the end of the Thanksgiving discussion, I said that if a black person was sitting at the table with us, we would never have had the entire conversation.  We talked about that.  Do you think there is a nervousness amongst the races to engage each other?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  A lot of the nervousness is that white America is uncomfortable with having to deal with the guilt and history of racism, and they certainly don’t want to admit it is still here, and black America in large part has for so long has had to try and act like it's not there to get along.  It’s almost like our silence will get us access so that we don’t offend you.  And those of us that are offensive have to then carry the burden of trying to push the envelope.  That’s why Bill Tatum, who publishes the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20New%20York%20Amsterdam%20News">Amsterdam News</ref></hi>, said if we didn’t have a guy like Al Sharpton we’d have to invent one.  Because every generation has to have somebody who pushes the envelope.  We just do.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I think it was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lani%20Guinier">Lani Guinier</ref> who used to talk about the problem is the races too afraid to talk to each other about race.  </hi></p>
</text>
