<text id="autogum_interview_doc803" title="part1_Alex Necochea and Bryn Bennett: the &amp;apos;Guitar Heroes&amp;apos; of Bang Camaro" shortTile="partalex-necochea" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-06" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Alex_Necochea_and_Bryn_Bennett%3A_the_%27Guitar_Heroes%27_of_Bang_Camaro" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How does it feel to be looked-up to by the kids, by America's future?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  It's terrifying! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you see parents at the show?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  Oh, yeah, oh yeah.  Parents with their kids—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That must reduce the crotch grabbing.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Yeah, a little bit of macho posturing. I tell you man, it's a <hi rend="italic">really</hi> big thrill, just to go out and play in towns we've never been to.  Kids come out and they know all the songs.  We've had situations where we've played New York and girls are in the front row singing along to our guitar solos.  Like, wow...we're on stage playing and we can hear them singing back at us.  Something else Bryn and I have noticed is at larger festival shows when we get to the end of our shows we play <hi rend="italic">Push Push Lady Lightning</hi>, the kids would just light up and start <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/air%20guitar">air guitaring</ref>!  But not <hi rend="italic">actually</hi> playing air guitar, but playing air guitar hero--like, they knew where all the notes were!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Which is a <hi rend="italic">lot</hi> different for audiences of many bands.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  Absolutely!  I can't imagine other bands having the same experience, because we come from such a unique perspective that a large part of our music is driven by the instrumentals, and that sort of thing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Your fans are so engaged with your music, far more than most bands have.  Most bands they have fans who feel their music speaks to them, but your fans can say, 'I learned to play guitar on <hi rend="italic">your</hi> shit and not on <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleanor%20Rigby">Eleanor Rigby</ref></hi>!'</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  It's an honor.  It's still unbelievable to me.  I had a message from a friend of mine who was at Guitar Center and he heard one of the kids cranking out one of our songs when he was trying out the guitar.  To me, it's like we made it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  At this point of your career, you're not playing stadiums, but you're also not playing Otto's Tiki Lounge on a Tuesday night.  When you reflect upon it, what do you think about?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  In the past two years, since Bryn and I started this project, we've both been playing in bands locally in Boston for years.  We had some mixed success, we played large venues in and around Boston.  We got to the point where we said fuck it, we just want to have some fun and we'd laugh a lot going over old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ozzy%20Osbourne">Ozzy Osbourne</ref> stuff we listened to as kids, just giggle about it.  Bang Camaro started that way, something for us to do and invite our friends to come sing on it.  Now, just two years later, it's amazing what happens when you stop trying.  It's something not contrived or born of any desire to reach an audience.  We just did it for fun, and that spoke to people more than anything else we worked on.</p>
</text>
