<text id="autogum_interview_doc328" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Progressive Conservative candidate John O&amp;apos;Toole, Durham" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-09" dateModified="2007-12-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Progressive_Conservative_candidate_John_O%27Toole%2C_Durham" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Progressive Conservative candidate John O'Toole, Durham</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 9, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">John O'Toole</hi> is running for the Progressive Conservative in the Ontario provincial election, in the Durham riding. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref> interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I originally become involved in politics when members of the community suggested I stand for election as a local school trustee. As a parent, I was naturally interested in school board issues. This later led to my involvement as an elected municipal councillor for Clarington. One of my responsibilities on Council was as Chair of the local budget process. I was first elected to the Ontario Legislature in 1995.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I have experience at both the local and provincial level.  In addition, my 30 years with General Motors has given me a strong background in the business sector, especially within the auto industry and related manufacturing enterprises that are so important to Durham Riding.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?</hi></p>
<p>In my most recent campaigns, the Liberal Party candidate has placed second and the New Democratic Party candidate third. However, when I first ran for office in 1995, the incumbent MPP was a New Democrat. I try to learn from previous campaigns, but take nothing for granted and try to treat each campaign like it’s a new beginning – a new opportunity to win the support of local citizens.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>I have direct experience in the Ontario Legislature for three terms, and have a solid background in ensuring constituents get the help they need when dealing with provincial issues. Given the fact that I have over 25 years of elected experience, I also have the advantage of many contacts within community organizations and local government.  In other words, I understand the community and work hard to ensure Durham Riding has the best possible representation at Queen’s Park.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
</text>
