<text id="autogum_interview_doc847" title="part0_CanadaVOTES: Liberal Sandra Gardiner running in Perth—Wellington" shortTile="partcanadavotes-liberal" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-25" dateModified="2019-07-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_Liberal_Sandra_Gardiner_running_in_Perth%E2%80%94Wellington" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>CanadaVOTES: Liberal Sandra Gardiner running in Perth—Wellington</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 26, 2008</hi></p>
<p>On October 14, 2008, Canadians will be heading to the polls for the federal election. <hi rend="bold">Liberal Party candidate Sandra Gardiner</hi> is standing for election in <hi rend="bold">the riding of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perth—Wellington">Perth—Wellington</ref></hi>. A Stratford resident for the last 17 years, she has worked as a Registered Nurse for the last 14, in hospital, long term, and community care settings. She is a member of Registered Nurses Association of Ontario, Canadian Association of Physicians concerned about the Environment, FarmGate5, Common Action for the Restoration of the Environment, Autism Ontario, the Planning Committee for Rotary Respite House, and board member of Optimism Place, the local women's shelter.</p>
<p>Wikinews contacted Sandra, to talk about the issues facing Canadians, and what they and their party would do to address them. Wikinews is in the process of contacting every candidate, in every riding across the country, no matter their political stripe. All interviews are conducted over e-mail, and interviews are published unedited, allowing candidates to impart their full message to our readers, uninterrupted.</p>
<p>The riding is currently held by Conservative Gary Schellenberger, who was also MP for the previous riding, Perth—Middlesex. Perth—Wellington includes the County of Perth, and the Town of Minto and the townships of Mapleton and Wellington North in the County of Wellington. Also challenging Schellenberger are John Cowling (Green), Irma DeVries (Christian Heritage), Julian Ichim (Marxist-Leninist), and Kerry McManus (NDP).</p>
<p>For more information, visit the campaign's official website, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#External_links">listed below</ref>.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why are you running for political office, why at the federal level, why this party, and why in this riding?</hi></p>
<p>I am running for office because I care about Canada and my fellow Canadians.  I am worried about the future we are leaving behind to our children.  I am running for Member of Parliament because it is Canada?s top level of government that carries the responsibility of overseeing which path we take in dealing with the following issues: the direction we chose for our Economy and ensure it stays on course; the way we chose to deal with the Environment; protection of our Universal Health Care System and many other issues.  The Federal Government sets the tone for the rest of the Country to follow.  I want to be a part of how we shape the future.  The Liberal Party of Canada has come to match my values best.  I support our plans addressing the following issues Economy, Environment, Healthcare, Poverty Reduction, continued support for our Arts and Culture Community, our policy on immigration  and our role Internationally.  I have just touched on just a few of the reasons I have come to embrace the ideas of the Liberal Party of Canada.  I am running in this riding because I have been a resident here for almost 20 years.  As a result I have first hand experience with some of the issues here locally.  I am passionate about my community.</p>
</text>
