<text id="autogum_interview_doc1409" title="part3_John Vanderslice plays New York City: Wikinews interview" shortTile="partjohn-vanderslice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-27" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Vanderslice_plays_New_York_City%3A_Wikinews_interview" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>The ultimate problem—sort of like the only <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philosophical%20views%20of%20suicide">philosophical problem is suicide</ref>—the only philosophical problem is whether to be assigned to a major label because you are then going to have so much editorial input that it is probably going to really hurt what you are doing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you believe the only philosophical question is whether to commit suicide?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  Absolutely.  I think the rest is internal chatter and if I logged and tried to counter the internal chatter I have inside my own brain there is no way I could match that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you see artists like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pete%20Doherty">Pete Doherty</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amy%20Winehouse">Amy Winehouse</ref> out on suicidal binges of drug use, what do you think as a musician?  What do you get from what you see them go through in their personal lives and their music?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  The thing for me is they are profound iconic figures for me, and I don't even know their music.  I don't know Winehouse or Doherty's music, I just know that they are acting a very crucial, mythic part in our culture, and they might be doing it unknowingly.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Glorification of drugs?  The rock lifestyle?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  More like an out-of-control <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Id,%20ego,%20and%20super-ego">Id</ref>, completely unregulated personal relationships to the world in general.  It's not just drugs, it's everything.  It's arguing and scratching people's faces and driving on the wrong side of the road.  Those are just the infractions that land them in jail.  I think it might be unknowing, but in some ways they are beautiful figures for going that far off the deep end.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  As tragic figures?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  Yeah, as totally tragic figures.  I appreciate that.  I take no pleasure in saying that, but I also believe they are important.  The figures that go outside—let's say <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GG%20Allin">GG Allin</ref> or Penderetsky in the world of classical music—people who are so far outside of the normal boundaries of behavior and communication, it in some way enlarges the size of your landscape, and it's beautiful.  I know it sounds weird to say that, but it is.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They are examples, as well.  I recently covered for Wikinews the Iranian President speaking at Columbia and a student named Matt Glick told me that he supported the Iranian President speaking so that he could protest him, that if we don't give a platform and voice for people, how can we say that they are wrong?  I think it's almost the same thing; they are beautiful as examples of how living a certain way can destroy you, and to look at them and say, "Don't be that."  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  Absolutely, and let me tell you where I'm coming from.  I don't do drugs, I drink maybe three or four times a year.  I don't have any problematic relationship to drugs because there has been a history around me, like probably any musician or creative person, of just blinding array of drug abuse and problems.  For me, I am a little bit of a control freak and I don't have those issues.  I just shut those doors.  But I also understand and I am very sympathetic to someone who does not shut that door, but goes into that room and stays.</p>
</text>
