<text id="autogum_interview_doc1422" title="part1_Interview with dismissed Ocean Drive columnist Trisha Posner" shortTile="partinterview-dismissed" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-22" dateModified="2013-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_dismissed_Ocean_Drive_columnist_Trisha_Posner" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you receive a call from Jerry Powers?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TP:</hi>  I never heard from Jerry Powers; he never phoned me, e-mailed.  I still have never heard from him.  I phoned the office the next day, and [Managing Editor]  Eric Newill tells me my services would no longer be required.  I had one piece ready, and one piece in the issue.  The saddest thing is that I lost my friendship with Eric.  Eric was my friend before he was my editor.  He is friends with Jerry Powers.  Eric wrote me an e-mail that it had played out too publicly and that he wished me good luck in my future endeavors.  What kind of friendship is that?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Had you informed the magazine of your appearance beforehand?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TP:</hi>  Eric knew I was doing a video, and I did it in my friend’s hotel.  I don’t remember if I told them what it was for.  But the video wasn’t a secret.  In the future I will ask permission.  But it’s childish.  I can’t believe Jerry Powers took this and made it an issue.  Nobody would have known about it, and now I’m all over the place.  He made Trisha Posner a star.  I can’t go anywhere without people saying, 'Yay, good for you!'  And they still have not paid me for my last piece.  I sent them another e-mail on the 17th.  They owe me $1,000.  They have not written back to me, they have not phoned me.  Why are they being so childish?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you ever have any other problems at the magazine?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TP:</hi>  No, I never had an issue and I had the best working relationship with this magazine.  I have nothing bad to say about the magazine. I had a fabulous relationship—a unique relationship with my editor.  I had never worked so well with an editor of a magazine my entire career.  It was so easy, he is so smart, cerebral...it’s unbelievable.  But they also got a lot out of me.  They got <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tina%20Brown">Tina Brown</ref> through me.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill%20Maher">Bill Maher</ref>.  I have an incredible track record.  It was not hard for me to phone people and get them for the magazine.  And I never used them for my advantage at all; I never used the magazine to get into restaurants or events.  People say you never went to the parties, but I’m over that.  I used to be a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Studio%2054">Studio 54</ref> girl.  I just really enjoyed my health column.  They allowed me to write in my own voice.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why do you think Powers fired you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TP:</hi>   It’s all advertising driven, but I’m interviewing people for a new book who have advertised in his magazine.  It wasn’t a big deal for anybody.  The very next day <hi rend="italic">Miami Magazine</hi> picked me up.  He had a knee-jerk reaction.  He didn’t even phone me.  Wouldn’t you think he would phone me and say, 'What the hell are you doing?' and I would have been like, 'Oh, I didn’t realize.'  Besides, I was crazy about my editor!  Why would I try to hurt him?   I hope one day I can work with Eric again.</p>
</text>
