<text id="autogum_interview_doc491" title="part7_ACLU, EFF challenging US &amp;apos;secret&amp;apos; court orders seeking Twitter data" shortTile="partaclu-eff-challenging" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-04-06" dateModified="2019-09-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU%2C_EFF_challenging_US_%27secret%27_court_orders_seeking_Twitter_data" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> consulted a Belgian IT security expert who said it was most likely companies such as Facebook, Microsoft, and Google, would have complied with similar court orders *without advising the 'targets*'. Does that disturb you?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Jonsdottir:</hi> This does disturb me for various reasons. The most obvious is that my emails are hosted at google/gmail and my search profile. I dont have anything to hide but it is important to note that many of the people that interact with me as a MP via both facebook and my various email accounts don't always realize that there is no protection for them if they do so via those channels. I often get sensitive personal letters sent to me at facebook and gmail. In general most people are not aware of how little rights they have as users of social media. It is those of uttermost importance that those sites will create the legal disclaimers and agreements that state the most obvious rights we lose when we sign up to their services.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Has there been any backlash within Iceland against US-based internet services in light of this? Do you expect such, or any increase in anti-American sentiments?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Jonsdottir:</hi> No, none what so ever. I dont think there is much anti-American sentiments in Iceland and I dont think this case will increase it. However I think it is important for everyone who does not live in the USA and uses social services to note that according to the ruling in my case, they dont have any protection of the 1st and 4th amendment, that only apply to USA citizens. Perhaps the legalities in relation to the borderless reality we live in online need to be upgraded in order for people to feel safe with using social media if it is hosted in the USA. Market tends to bend to simple rules.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Does this make you more, or less, determined to see the IMMI succeed?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Jonsdottir:</hi> More. People have to realize that if we dont have freedom of information online we won't have it offline. We have to wake up to the fact that our rights to access information that should be in the public domain is eroding while at the same time our rights as citizens online have now been undermined and we are only seen as consumers with consumers rights and in some cases our rights are less than of a product. This development needs to change and change fast before it is too late.</item></list>
<head id="Ongoing_U.S._Government_versus_WikiLeaks_fallout">Ongoing U.S. Government versus WikiLeaks fallout</head>
<p>The U.S. Government continues to have issues internationally as a result of material passed to WikiLeaks, and subsequently published.</p>
<p>Within the past week, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ecuador">Ecuador</ref> has effectively declared the U.S. ambassador <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heather%20Hodges">Heather Hodges</ref> persona-non-grata over corruption allegations brought to light in leaked cables. Asking the veteran diplomat to leave "as soon as possible", the country may become the third in South America with no ambassadorial presence. Both <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Venezuela">Venezuela</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bolivia">Bolivia</ref> have no resident U.S. ambassador due to the two left-wing administrations believing the ejected diplomats were working with the opposition.</p>
</text>
