<text id="autogum_interview_doc992" title="part7_Wikinews holds Reform Party USA presidential candidates forum" shortTile="partwikinews-holds" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-01-02" dateModified="2016-09-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_holds_Reform_Party_USA_presidential_candidates_forum" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><p>At the tactical level--the grassroots level where America is nearly comatose, I want to work with the Governors, whom I will elevate to be co-equal to the Senate as an advisory chamber--there is a great deal to be done.  46 million Americans are on food stamps today, we have destroyed not just the middle class but also the once proud and vital senior blue collar class, and we have lost an entire generation if not too to an educational system that is mediocre at best, pathologically inept at worst.  I have been developing a plan with a former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Deputy%20Secretary%20of%20Labor">Deputy Secretary of Labor</ref> to fund a full year of employment and training for every unemployed American, using a mix of academic, private sector, and military induction centers to get every citizen off the streets, on a payroll, and learning what they need to know to make their own way in the 21st Century.  We need to kill most of the regulations that prevent state-based businesses from flourishing--butchers, for example--we need to push back hard on absentee and mega farming, and we need to work very very hard toward resilience across every state.  Larger cities need to be broken up into smaller cities, suburbs need to be restored to farming, I could go on--we need to redesign our Republic for people--for the good of the many--rather than what we have now, a pig farm that profits only a few.</p></p>
<p><p>Technically I am very enthusiastic about Open Everything.  I have a book coming out from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Random%20House">Random House</ref> / Evolver Editions, the same group that published Charles Eisenstein's <hi rend="italic">Sacred Economics: Money, Gift, and Society in the Age of Transition</hi>.  My title is <hi rend="italic">THE OPEN SOURCE EVERYTHING MANIFESTO: Transparency, Truth, &amp; Trust</hi>.  The book will come out in June 2012, and it is a manifesto for all of us--it is a book that along with others marks the beginning of Epoch B, the restoration of bottom-up multi-cultural consensus, of decisions made by people of good will acting on all available information and thinking long-term.  I will turn the US Government into the world's first open source software, open source hardware, and open spectrum engine of prosperity, migrating all of this out to the other intelligence tribes (academia, commerce, local and state government, law enforcement, media, military, and non-government / non-profit).  My primary instrument for doing this will be the Open Source Agency that I have advocated since the early 1990's.  We will create the World Brain Institute and the Global Game--I have <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medard%20Gabel">Medard Gabel</ref>, co-creator of the analog <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20Game">World Game</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buckminster%20Fuller">Buckminster Fuller</ref> ready to go--and we will harness the distributed intelligence of every human mind in every language all of the time.  This will eradicate corruption and be the technical foundation for creating a prosperous world at peace.</p></p>
</text>
