<text id="autogum_interview_doc674" title="part17_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And it's so basic.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  So basic. And who are the Chinese prostitutes? Are they from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mongolia">Mongolia</ref>...those are the things I wonder.</p>
<head id="On_the_literary_canon">On the literary canon</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell,_God,_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing">I spoke with a young novelist named John Reed</ref>. He wrote a book called <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snowball's%20Chance">Snowball's Chance</ref></hi> that was an attack on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20Orwell">Orwell</ref> and we were talking about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Literary%20canon">literary canon</ref> that's taught in grade school and high school. He raised an interesting idea that I wanted to run by you. His point was that kids are not becoming readers. So much of what they learn with books and reading doesn't seem applicable to their lives. I read in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newsweek">Newsweek</ref></hi> that your five favorite novels and there was a lot of classics – <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Scarlet%20Letter">The Scarlet Letter</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Great%20Gatsby">The Great Gatsby</ref></hi>, things like that. Reed's point was that kids have a hard time bonding with these materials. What should be taught at those levels is modern literature. At the more senior levels, once they've developed acumen for reading and they relate to it on a personal level, then they'll go exploring the classics and it's almost more pertinent to them being able to understand it. An analogy would be as if you had children and they only watched <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bette%20Davis">Bette Davis</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joan%20Crawford">Joan Crawford</ref> movies and then the film genre would wither because young people found it difficult to relate to it. What do you think about that idea?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I think if you delay the reading of the classical works or whatever is defined as enduring in value, you postpone it. It's too late. As to reading, what is contemporary? People do that anyway.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Not kids.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  God, starting with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J.%20K.%20Rowling">Ms. Rowling</ref>, you've got <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harry%20Potter">Harry Potter</ref>. What's more contemporary than that?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That's a phenomenon. It's not really that typical; I mean, it stands out because it's a billion dollar author.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I think so much of what we read that's in the canons is pretty political, more now than ever. I mean you have to have women in there, you have to have blacks in there, you have to have Latinos in there. Go, if you should dare...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And they can't say certain things.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  That's right. Of course, I grew up as a Catholic.  When I was a boy you couldn't read certain things, say certain things, think certain things. So it's not that we need this political correctness to remind me of restriction, restraint, guidance, governments. I grew up with them. It didn't much matter. Do what you want to do anyway, but it's covert. We were all in the closet in those days, one way or another.</p>
</text>
