<text id="autogum_interview_doc1222" title="part5_The Onion: An interview with 'America's Finest News Source'" shortTile="partthe-onion-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2013-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Onion%3A_An_interview_with_%27America%27s_Finest_News_Source%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  It could be that, or it could be that they take her pictures and juxtapose it in the photo.  It’s directed, though, to get the right effect.
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  Or it could be an image of a girl who we have had on file, and she’ll be perfect so then we’ll just get someone in the office to shoot the double bird and Photoshop those hands in.  They are wizards; I just enjoy watching our crack photojournalism squad work.</p></p>
<head id="What_The_Onion_will_not_publish">What <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> will not publish</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you decide when going through the headlines what will be fleshed out as a full story and what goes into the “News in Headlines” section?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  Just general writers room feel, what people think needs a full-length story to cover it, and what’s just a one-off funny headline with a photo of a person.  There are no real set guidelines of what makes a top story for us, and what makes a neb, it’s just the general support of the staff behind it.</p>
<figure><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Furby.JPG">File:Furby.JPG</ref><caption>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Furby">Furby</ref> will never make it into <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:DO'Neil">DO'Neil</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What are some topics you have come across that people almost always say, “Oohh, let’s not do that, that’s going into territory we don’t want to go into”?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  Well, we do have a list of no-no words of things that just keep coming up that we refuse to print anything about.  There are always some areas where there is a line you don’t want to cross.  We <hi rend="italic">definitely</hi> push that line hard and continuously.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: What are some of those?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  There will always be the big item controversial issues: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gay%20rights">gay rights</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abortion">abortion</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">war in Iraq</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedophilia">pedophilia</ref>.  As long as the joke lands on the right person, then we are okay with it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What are your no-no words?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  It’s a written, top-secret list.  I’m afraid I can’t share it with you.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Can you give us two?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thesis">Thesis</ref>” and “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Furby">Furby</ref>” are both on there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why would Furby be on there?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  Again, top secret list.  It’s just one of the no-no words.
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  It’s not like ‘<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fuck">fuck</ref>’, ‘<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shit">shit</ref>’, ‘<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cunnilingus">cunnilingus</ref>.’  This is a totally different type of no-no that has a logic and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/algorithm">algorithm</ref> all to its own.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  We can’t say ‘Fuck’ in a front page headline.  We’ve been told that by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Postal%20Service">U.S. Postal Service</ref>.</p>
<head id="Reactions_to_Onion_stories">Reactions to Onion stories</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When your stories are taken as real—such as your story about the child who, <ref target="http://web.archive.org/web/20000815214418/http://www.theonion.com/onion3625/harry_potter.html">after reading Harry Potter</ref>, decided to practice magic since she found out the Bible is just a bunch of ‘boring lies’—</hi></p>
</text>
