<text id="autogum_interview_doc963" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Fred Karger, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-04-23" dateModified="2014-03-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Fred_Karger%2C_U.S._Republican_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Fred Karger</hi>: Well, the Mormon Church as I discovered by documents that were given to me, official Mormon Chuch documents going back to 1995, has led the way on all the anti-Gay initiatives, constitutional amendments in the country. All thirty one that have been successful, the Mormon Church was instrumental in efforts. So I have announced. I don't do things secretly like they do. I've been very up front about it. I signed my name to everything.</p></p>
<p><p>And I am determined to try and get them to reconsider their vehement opposition, not just to gay marriage, but the way they treat gay and lesbian members of the Mormon faith. And there's a wonderful new video out with a dozen students from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brigham%20Young%20University">BYU</ref> talking about that and how difficult it is to be gay and Mormon. And this church, which is on the cusp of having a President of the United States, is cruel [through] activities that have been done to LGBT members and followers and as well as all of us non-members, who have been critical of their activism.</p></p>
<p><p>I think it is the wrong direction and I will continue to shadow that and keep them honest in politics, which they have not been as we found in California. And I think as their public affairs director had invited, which is why I put that website up, the public doesn't know enough about the Mormon Church, so I wanted to help make them aware because there are some very interesting parts of that religion that I think it’s certainly open for discussion with Mitt Romney as the likely Republican nominee.</p></p>
<head id="2012_presidential_campaign">2012 presidential campaign</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Let's talk about the campaign. I've seen from your photos that while campaigning, you've encountered such candidates as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jon%20Huntsman,%20Jr.">Jon Huntsman, Jr.</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Michele_Bachmann">Michele Bachmann</ref>. Do they recognize you and/or acknowledge the historical significance of your campaign?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Fred Karger</hi>: I've met every single candidate running and have general pictures with all. The only one [exception] I think is Ron Paul, who I did meet with in his office in Washington. He was the one, who actually set up a formal meeting with me in January of 2011. We had a wonderful meeting.  He had not made up his mind yet.</p></p>
<figure><caption>Karger with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jon%20Huntsman,%20Jr.">Jon Huntsman, Jr.</ref> in 2011.Image: Fred Karger.</caption></figure>
<p><p>But yes, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rick_Santorum">Rick Santorum</ref> knew me well. We would run in to each other all the time. Everyone was very courteous to me. Some I became more friendly with: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gary_Johnson">Gary Johnson</ref> or Jon Huntsman, very, very cordial to me. I would actually say that Gary Johnson and me became friends. We would see each other all the time, went to meals together.</p></p>
</text>
