<text id="autogum_interview_doc566" title="part2_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Suzanne Fortin, Nepean-Carleton" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-26" dateModified="2013-03-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Suzanne_Fortin%2C_Nepean-Carleton" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>I would say de-fund abortion and review government spending and departments to find savings and cut taxes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>No, because the jump in property taxes has not been accompanied by an increase in services. The downloading of social services had a very negative impact on municipal finances and they have difficulty in balancing their budgets. Municipal taxes should not go to pay for services that are of provincial jurisdiction. The system has been especially unfair to rural citizens whose cities were forcefully merged without their consent.</p>
<p>As an aside, my party favours eliminating the school portion on property taxes, as it is an unfair system.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>The province should create a favourable business climate by paying off the debt and eliminating unnecessary government bodies, or merging others, which in turn would lead to lower taxes and more incentive to do business in Ontario.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mixed%20member%20proportional%20representation">mixed member proportional representation</ref> (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>I strongly support MMP as it would lead to a legislature that reflects the wishes of the people of Ontario. One of the reasons why Ontarians don’t get the government they want is that the First-Past-the-Post system provides an incentive to vote for or against the perceived front-runner, but essentially penalizes voting for a smaller party because it gives the impression of wasting one’s vote if the candidate does not win. MMP allows people greater choice in that sense—you do not have to vote for the first- or second-place party for your vote to count.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does “new media” play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>Given the fact that I work for a small party, it’s very beneficial. Voters can now have easier access to our candidates and we, as a party, can create more visibility. I operate SoConBlogs.com, which is an aggregator of blogs that support the Family Coalition Party. This has helped raise the party’s presence, especially in the blogosphere, where many politically savvy people get their information and exchange views. Facebook has also been very useful in helping me find supporters and people willing to help out with the party.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</hi></p>
</text>
