<text id="autogum_interview_doc870" title="part10_Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-22" dateModified="2014-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_World_Wide_Web_co-inventor_Robert_Cailliau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Future_of_the_WWW">Future of the WWW</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: I've read that scientists at CERN are currently working on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/grid%20computing">grid computing</ref>, mainly to process the huge amounts of data from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Large%20Hadron%20Collider">Large Hadron Collider</ref> project. Do you think grid computing will be the next generation web? Are there restrictions that limit the use of grid computing, for example working over large distances?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: About grid computing I have not much to say.  The first intention of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ARPANET">ARPANET</ref> and later the intenet was the use of computing resources at a distance.  Grid computing is an extrapolation of that idea.  I don't know if the average user will use grid computing.  Most probably not.  It seems to me that personal computing stands to grid computing like serial computing stands to parallel computing.  There are useful applications of parallel computing, but I don't think my second processor is busy while I'm typing this.  Grid computing can be used behind the scenes in certain services, but I find it hard to see what the web surfer will use it for.  Google knows what to do with it, I'm sure.  So I'll shut up about it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: You've said before that you don't care a lot about the concept of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/web%202.0">web 2.0</ref>, because it was something you envisioned from the beginning, and it was something bound to happen: correct? If not, what is your vision for The Web? What would be a real web Renaissance?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Freely contributing to web content was one of the original goals:  the web should be as easy to write as it is to read.  Another function we lost due to too fast development.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Robert Cailliau</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: Web 2.0 is something that indeed "exists", but it is not a technology.  It is a social phenomenon that requires the simultaneous deployment of a number of technologies to build the so-called 2.0 websites.  Delivering web content via blogs and the like is a "new" happening in which the individual participates, often in very original ways. Freely contributing to web content was one of the original goals:  the web should be as easy to write as it is to read.  Another function we lost due to too fast development.</p>
<p>I'm much more worried about data.  All my data are on my home computer and I regularly back them up.  I have nothing important on a server:  no e-mail, no photos, videos or whatever.  But I'm an exception:  most people never back up their machines and actually cannot handle a computer.  They use the machine as a terminal to the internet.</p>
<p>Services such as gmail, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref>, and in fact every site having some kind of "My-..." where one leaves a bit of oneself, bring us back to the archaic model of computing:  central mainframes and storage, used through terminals on which no local applications run.</p>
</text>
