<text id="autogum_interview_doc996" title="part1_YouTube accounts of Scientology critics suspended" shortTile="partyoutube-accounts" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-04-17" dateModified="2012-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/YouTube_accounts_of_Scientology_critics_suspended" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jason%20Beghe">Jason Beghe</ref> is a television and film actor who joined Scientology in 1994. He gave <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USD">USD</ref>1 million to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church%20of%20Scientology">Church of Scientology</ref> over the years, and told Roger Friedman of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FOX%20News">FOX News</ref></hi> that Scientology head <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Miscavige">David Miscavige</ref> called him "the poster boy for Scientology". Beghe appeared in promotional videos for Scientology in 2005. In April 2008 he left Scientology, and contacted <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andreas%20Heldal-Lund">Andreas Heldal-Lund</ref>, who put him in touch with Mark Bunker. Bunker arranged an interview with Beghe, which was uploaded to Bunker's YouTube account on April 7. The posted video is a 3-minute portion of a larger 3-hour interview with Beghe about his criticism of Scientology. In the video Beghe states: "Scientology is destructive and a rip-off. ... It’s very, very dangerous for your spiritual, psychological, mental, emotional health and evolution. "</p>
<figure><caption>Actor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jason%20Beghe">Jason Beghe</ref>, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tory%20Christman">Tory Christman</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andreas%20Heldal-Lund">Andreas Heldal-Lund</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark%20Bunker">Mark Bunker</ref>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andreas%20Heldal-Lund">Andreas Heldal-Lund</ref> of <ref target="http://www.xenu.net">Operation Clambake</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Listen to quote from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tory%20Christman">Tory Christman</ref> Image: <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi>.</caption></figure>
<p>In an interview with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, Tory Christman commented on the suspension of her account, and now Bunker's: "Well having worked for the Office of Special Affairs which is part of the Church of Scientology, they used to have me go out and open up phony accounts, I didn't know they were stopping free speech on the net but once I realized that ... I said 'I can't do this, I didn't get into Scientology to stop free speech'. ... I'm pretty sure, you know, I'm quite sure, that it's Scientology. That's what they do, that's their view is just 'shut em down' they have no morals on it or anything. They just figure 'screw em, shut em down'."</p>
<p>Christman said she found out her YouTube account had been suspended on Tuesday: "I came back from lunch at four and Mark called me and said 'Do you know your account is suspended?', and by the morning of yesterday it was back up."</p>
<hi rend="bold">I would like to know, why was it suspended, why is Mark's suspended, what are the violations.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tory%20Christman">Tory Christman</ref></p>
<figure><caption>Listen to quote from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tory%20Christman">Tory Christman</ref> Image: <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi>.</caption></figure>
<p>When asked if she had received a notice about the suspension from YouTube, Christman responded: "I never got anything, and I've looked through everything, I never got any kind of a notice, either way. ... I never heard from YouTube either way - suspending it, or putting it back. And I've written them, and it was only put back thanks to Anonymous and all the critics and people that wrote in to them, I'm quite sure - Because tons of people did, it wasn't like they just put it back up." </p>
<p>"I would like to know, why was it suspended, why is Mark's suspended, what are the violations, okay, because if the Church of Scientology is just paying them off that's kind of weird, isn't it?," added Christman.</p>
</text>
