<text id="autogum_interview_doc094" title="part21_Wikinews interviews Indiana State Senator Mike Delph" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-26" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Indiana_State_Senator_Mike_Delph" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>In the terms of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BP">BP</ref>, BP is a great corporate citizen. They made a mistake and immediately went to rectify and restore the ecology of the mistake that they made. And so I’m very proud of BP and I’m very proud for the way that they handled that, and I thought this political <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/scapegoat">scapegoatism</ref> of them was pretty shameful. This is a company that provides a lot of jobs, a lot of economic development, a lot of good things to the community. They had a tough time and they immediately used corporate assets and their ingenuity to aggressively address and correct what they had done negatively to the environment. And I felt like they should be applauded and lifted up and not condemned.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Dennis Marshall is here with our last question tonight, Dennis —</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Dennis: Senator you are well known for your support of the single class basketball here in Indiana, why is that such an important issue for you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: Dennis you're going to make me cry. I love this issue, love it. I grew up in a time that is not, obviously, today, and I just fell in love with Indiana high school basketball. I didn't play basketball in high school myself. I was a football player and I was slow and bulky and that sort of thing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Tew: You were a wrestler, too?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: I actually was a cheerleader for the high school basketball team my senior year.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Tew: Senator, were you a wrestler?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: I love basketball, I always have. But when I was growing up I remember watching the state tournament with my grandmother. It was almost like a holiday. We'd play cards and have a cheeseball and you know salami and crackers. We'd bet a dollar a game on the games.</p>
<p>That was the time when guys like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott%20Skiles">Scott Skiles</ref> were bringing Plymouth (High School) to the state championship tournament, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve%20Alford">Steve Alford</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Castle%20High%20School%20(New%20Castle,%20Indiana)">New Castle [High School]</ref>, and Mike and Chris Heineman over at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Connersville%20High%20School">Connersville [High School]</ref>. There was just a tremendous amount of great basketball stories. And then I got to learn about the story of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1954%20Milan%20High%20School%20basketball%20team">"Milan Miracle"</ref>, of the state championship run that led to the story of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoosiers">Hoosiers</ref> [a film]. Then, later on, right before I left and started growing up more after college and graduate school, the story of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damon%20Bailey">Damon Bailey</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bedford%20North%20Lawrence%20High%20School">Bedford North Lawrence</ref> [High School] team. These are stories were high school basketball teams would captivate and grab the attention of the entire state. I remember when the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marion%20High%20School%20(Indiana)">Marion Giants</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jay%20Edwards%20(basketball)">Jay Edwards</ref> and Lyndon Jones dominated for a couple years.</p>
<p>And so these are things that are very important and then when they went to this touchy feeling everybody has to have a trophy and a championship multi-class system, it took something away from our Hoosier identity. So it was something that I always felt pretty strongly about.</p>
</text>
