<text id="autogum_interview_doc411" title="part1_Canada&amp;apos;s Scarborough East (Ward 44) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-scarborough" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-19" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Scarborough_East_%28Ward_44%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I want to move forward with fresh new ideas to make our city and our community a better, more vibrant and safer place in which to live and raise our families.  Being on City Council means making difficult choices.  I believe I have the experience, the understanding of our community, and the track record of working with everyone to be able to make the best choice.  I believe we should move forward, not backwards.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have lived in the community for 23 years and have worked at City Hall for the past 3 years so I know this community, the people and the issues. I know this job.  I've listened and heard residents' concerns. I am now ready to act on their behalf because I know the priorities will be to address infill development, property standards and traffic. I will support finding solutions to garbage, transit and crime.  We need to invest in our City's future.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Currently I am an unpaid leave of absence from the City of Toronto.  Prior to that I was a Resource to 2 Local Erosion Control Projects and to the East Scarborough Storefront Steering Committee.</p>
<p>My other previous community commitments include:
<list type="unordered"><item>Centennial Community and Recreation Association (CCRA) Executive</item>
<item>Heart and Stroke, Fundraising Chair</item>
<item>West Hill Softball League, Volunteer</item>
<item>Parent Council and Teacher's Assistant</item>
<item>Scouts Canada, Vice Chair and Key Leader</item>
<item>West Hill Community Advisory Panel</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The completion of phase one of the new waterfront trail at the foot of Port Union Road is the best accomplishment in Ward 44 over the past three years.  The completion of this trail was a cooperative effort of the Toronto Waterfront Revitalization Corporation, the Federal and Provincial Governments and the City of Toronto and the Toronto and Region Conservation Authority. It is truly a waterfront park we can all be proud of.</p>
<p>I believe the decision not to build a subway in Scarborough and to run a dedicated light rail line on the Scarborough RT is a disservice to Ward 44 – we need better transit in the eastern part of Scarborough.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> If you were elected as a "rookie" councillor, What would you bring to the table beyond the incumbent?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I'm currently the assistant to the outgoing City Councillor and sometimes there is the assumption that I would be a carbon copy.  I'm not.  I have my own views on the issues and my own way of getting the job done.  Too often politicians get into office and we never hear from them except at election time.  I always have been accessible and will continue to do so.</p>
</text>
