<text id="autogum_interview_doc1377" title="part0_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 3, 2007</hi></p>
<figure rend="Al Sharpton by David Shankbone.jpg"></figure>At <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thanksgiving">Thanksgiving dinner</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> told his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White%20American">white</ref> middle class family that he was to interview <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al%20Sharpton">Reverend Al Sharpton</ref> that Saturday.  The announcement caused an impassioned discussion about the civil rights leader's work, the problems facing the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African%20American">black</ref> community and whether Sharpton helps or hurts his cause.  Opinion was divided.  "He's an opportunist."  "He only stirs things up."  "Why do I always see his face when there's a problem?"
<p>Shankbone went to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Action%20Network">National Action Network</ref>'s headquarters in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Harlem">Harlem</ref> with this Thanksgiving discussion to inform the conversation.  Below is his interview with Al Sharpton on everything from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tawana%20Brawley">Tawana Brawley</ref>, his purported feud with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>, criticism by influential African Americans such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clarence%20Page">Clarence Page</ref>, his experience running for President, to how he never expected he would see fifty (he is now 53).  "People would say to me, 'Now that I hear you, even if I disagree with you I don’t think you’re as bad as I thought,'" said Sharpton.  "I would say, 'Let me ask you a question: what was "bad as you thought"?' And they couldn’t say. They don’t know why they think you’re bad, they just know you’re supposed to be bad because the right wing tells them you’re bad."  </p>
<head id="Sharpton's_beginnings_in_the_movement">Sharpton's beginnings in the movement</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  You grew up around so many great American musicians and singers like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahalia%20Jackson">Mahalia Jackson</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20Brown">James Brown</ref>. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Al Sharpton:</hi> I grew up in the black church.  I started preaching at four as a wonderboy preacher.  The church that I grew up in, Washington Temple <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church%20of%20God%20in%20Christ">Church of God in Christ</ref> in Brooklyn, was a hot spot for gospel singers. It was probably a mega-church before there were mega-churches. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop%20F.D.%20Washington">Bishop F.D. Washington</ref>, who was the bishop of the church, had about 5,000 members in the late fifties and early sixties. All the gospel greats would come to the church. Because I was the wonderboy preacher, and I had my own little church celebrity, I got to know all the gospel singers. It began my early dealing with the entertainment world, through the gospel singing. In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1964%20New%20York%20World's%20Fair">1964 when the World’s Fair came to New York</ref>, Mahalia Jackson had me preach and she sang there that night. Then I did a few other cities with her.</p>
<figure><caption>"<hi rend="bold">All the gospel greats would come to the church. Because I was the wonderboy preacher, and I had my own little church celebrity, I got to know all the gospel singers.</hi>"Mahalia Jackson in 1962.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What was that like touring with Mahalia Jackson?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi> It was fascinating to me.  Here I am a little kid, I’m not even ten years old, and Mahalia Jackson was arguably the preeminent gospel artist of that time. It was quite a charge to me. A lot of times now I land into <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/LaGuardia_Airport">LaGuardia Airport</ref> and you see the circular, which was the New York pavilion of the World’s Fair, and that’s where I preached when I was nine years old. I think about that a lot flying in, that night with Mahalia Jackson. Now that’s wow, 47-years ago.</p>
</text>
