<text id="autogum_interview_doc785" title="part0_Eurovision &amp;apos;73 winner Anne Marie David discusses her four-decade career and the Contest, past and present" shortTile="parteurovision--winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-02-15" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2773_winner_Anne_Marie_David_discusses_her_four-decade_career_and_the_Contest%2C_past_and_present" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Eurovision '73 winner Anne Marie David discusses her four-decade career and the Contest, past and present</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 16, 2009</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Anne Marie David on the perseverance that built her career: "I always assumed the image of a competitor, maybe because I grew up in a place where I was very happy, but where we were not very rich; so I always had to make choices and needed to earn each thing that life gave me."Photo: Anne Marie David/Dave Goodliffe</caption></figure><p>In the 1970s, she was one of the most popular female vocalists in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref>, and became well-known internationally. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne%20Marie%20David">Anne Marie David</ref>, from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arles">Arles</ref> in the south of France, parlayed her initial success from playing Mary Magdalene in the French production of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus%20Christ%20Superstar">Jesus Christ Superstar</ref></hi> into taking home the "grand prix" at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%201973">Eurovision Song Contest</ref> in 1973. Her winning song, "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tu%20te%20reconnaîtras">Tu te reconnaîtras</ref>" (<hi rend="italic">You will recognize yourself</hi>), became a Europe-wide hit that spring.</p>
<p>At the height of her popularity, David perfomed world tours, and even lived abroad in Turkey for a time. In 1979, she tried once again to win the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%201979">Eurovision</ref>, and placed a respectable third. Her song "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Je%20suis%20l'enfant%20soleil">Je suis l'enfant soleil</ref>" (<hi rend="italic">I'm a child of the sun</hi>) became similarly popular across France and in the Francophone nations.</p>
<p>As time went on, however, her place in the French music scene became less certain. Touring the world had taken a personal toll, and David decided to retire from music completely in 1987. However, with the help of her fan base, she was coaxed out of retirement in 2003 and is returning to a part of her life that she tried to leave, but never left her. Celebrating four decades in the music scene, David is looking forward to adventurous new projects and a newfound zest for life.</p>
<p>Anne Marie David corresponded with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews'</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Mike_Halterman">Mike Halterman</ref> about her eventful career, her personal anecdotes regarding living abroad, her successes in past Eurovision contests and her grievances with the way the show is produced today. This is the second in a series of interviews with past Eurovision contestants, which will be published sporadically in the lead-up to mid-May's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%202009">next contest</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow">Moscow</ref>.</p>
<head id="Early_career">Early career</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> I saw the photos on your website, and I must say, you hardly look older than when you did Eurovision 30 years ago. Has anyone told you that back then, you looked a lot like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marie%20Osmond">Marie Osmond</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Anne Marie David</hi>: Thank you for the compliment, but I don't recall anyone alluding to a resemblance with Marie Osmond. I would have taken that as a compliment, no?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> When did you first start singing? Who were your musical inspirations while you were growing up?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AMD</hi>: I was already singing as a young child; my mother said that when she was pregnant with me, she sang lullabies to me... My [own] musical culture is very large. At home we listened to a lot of opera and operettas, but also French <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fr:Musique%20de%20variétés">variété</ref></hi> or the accordion. But my big revelation was my discovery of Barbra Streisand in <hi rend="italic">Funny Girl</hi>. That changed everything for me... I absolutely wanted to approach [the level of] this great artist, the greatest in my opinion, and try to pull myself to the heights of her talent. Not by imitating her, but by succeeding in acquiring this vocal perfection she possesses, and by orienting all my efforts towards the acting that I could present by interpreting my songs whenever the [lyrics] allowed me to.</p>
</text>
