<text id="autogum_interview_doc833" title="part3_ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush" shortTile="partaclu-president" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-30" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion%2C_drugs%2C_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So there isn’t any opposition to having religious groups meeting inside of public schools?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Would you defend someone’s right to have a religious meeting in a public school?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Yes. But I have to add a qualification and stress that the ACLU’s position here has been reflected not only under Supreme Court decisions under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First%20Amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution">First Amendment</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom%20of%20Religion%20in%20the%20United%20States">religious freedom</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom%20of%20speech%20in%20the%20United%20States">freedom of speech</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Establishment%20Clause%20of%20the%20First%20Amendment">nonestablishment of religion</ref>, but also through a federal statute that was passed in the 1980’s called the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Equal%20Access%20Act">Equal Access Act</ref>.  It basically sets out the general principle I have stated, but the important qualification is that you always have to look at all the facts of the circumstances.  If, for example, in a particular school there is theoretically an open forum and all student groups are free to meet, but in fact the <hi rend="italic">only</hi> student groups that are meeting are religious or of a particular religion, you know enough law to know that the conclusion could be that a reasonable observer could look at as school endorsement of religion and not a school endorsement of an open forum.  You always have to look to see that the teachers, government and public school officials aren’t channeling the students.  But if it is truly open and not an endorsement, then let a thousand flowers bloom.  Religious, non-religious and anti-religious.</p>
<head id="Religious_symbols">Religious symbols</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The ACLU has been involved in removing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religious%20symbolism">religious symbology</ref> from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public%20sphere">public forum</ref>.  Can you state your views on that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  I completely support all the cases we’ve taken in this area, a lot of which have to do with <hi rend="italic">allowing</hi> religious symbology in public places.  The law is a little complicated so that it is very easy for politicians and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demagogue">demagogues</ref> to distort it.  The key principle that unites the whole First Amendment including non-establishment and free exercise of religion and free speech, is that the government has to remain <hi rend="italic">neutral</hi>.  The government can not squelch certain ideas because it disagrees with the ideas, and with respect to religion government can neither favor religion nor disfavor religion.  It may not promote or encourage religion on the one hand, it may not stifle or discriminate against religion on the other hand.  So, when you are talking about a public place, it all depends on what kind of public place it is.  If it is a public school that is having a public forum where the individual students and voluntary students groups can meet, then the school is simply providing a neutral forum.  It is not endorsing religion if it allows religious groups to meet.  Likewise, if you are talking about a public park.  Religious groups have the right to meet in public parks to pray, to give sermons in public parks; in fact, if you look at every case that the Supreme Court has decided on these issues, the ACLU has <hi rend="italic">always</hi> been in support of the rights of religious groups and a lot of the early free speech cases happened to be on behalf of religious groups who were seeking to use the streets, the sidewalks, the parks, other public forums to convey their messages.</p>
</text>
