<text id="autogum_interview_doc1225" title="part8_The Onion: An interview with 'America's Finest News Source'" shortTile="partthe-onion-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2013-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Onion%3A_An_interview_with_%27America%27s_Finest_News_Source%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Similar to <hi rend="italic">The Daily Show</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Colbert Report</hi>, your readership has to be informed to be in on the jokes.  How do you feel about being seen as a real news source?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  First of all, we enjoy being the most important newspaper in the world and being a trusted news source like that.  But I do think we have a really smart readership, so if we can help them learn about the world, that’s a beautiful thing.  It’s not necessarily the mission we set out to do, but if that happens in the process that’s a wonderful thing.
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  We are able to bring some pretty horrific things into the light in a manner that opens it up for millions of people, whereas they may otherwise shy away from it.</p></p>
<head id="Future_features">Future features</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You guys are always coming out with new features, whether it is a podcast, a newscast, a sports section.  Is there anything under development right now?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  Yeah, we’re going to soon launch our world atlas on-line.  We just debuted Our Dumb World, our new book, and it will then be brought to life on the web and you can access a lot of that content through <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google%20Maps">Google Maps</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google%20Earth">Google Earth</ref>, so that will be cool.  In January we will be launching our election coverage for 2008, called <hi rend="italic">War for the White House</hi>.  That’s pretty exciting.
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  We’re really branching out.  We’ve covered local and national news for a long time, so we have now  branched out to the world with this book.  It will give us a chance to bring trusted, non-biased journalism to every nation in the world.  I know in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zimbabwe">Zimbabwe</ref>, for example, most of their media is controlled by the government, so they are really looking for a solid newspaper they can trust.</p></p>
<head id="Handling_national_tragedies">Handling national tragedies</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When things like the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9/11">September 11</ref> attacks happen, how do you gauge when is the time to start addressing it through parody?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  It’s too soon to answer that question, even!  It’s before my time, so I’m hesitant to answer that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I mean anything that is a national horror, like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hurricane%20Katrina">Hurricane Katrina</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  The issue with Katrina is that it was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mother%20Nature">Mother Nature</ref>’s fault, but it was the administration’s failure, which was as damaging as the hurricane.  So quite quickly government failure and stupidity came to light that needed to be reported upon.  We’re going to have a much faster response time to something like that, than something that is like a terrorist attack that catches us out of the blue.
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  We can talk about issues that are sensitive in a way that aren’t—you have to look at what you are talking about.  When you are talking about Katrina, you are talking about the government’s reaction.  When you are talking about September 11, if you read our September 11 issues you see, “Bush urges calm and restraint amongst nation’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ballad">ballad</ref> singers,” or “Woman doesn’t know what to do so she bakes an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20flag">American flag</ref>.”  There was a lot of art to it.  With a lot of creative stuff and comedy it’s just gut.  It’s the instincts of a really smart and creative editorial staff who have to know both what the take is and how and when to approach it.  September 11 was unique.  Generally, there’s not a lot of hesitation to approach things.  It’s more do we have a take that is consistent with what <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> does, and once that comes to light we publish it.</p></p>
</text>
