<text id="autogum_interview_doc853" title="part1_CanadaVOTES: CHP candidate Vicki Gunn in York—Simcoe" shortTile="partcanadavotes-chp" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-10" dateModified="2016-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_CHP_candidate_Vicki_Gunn_in_York%E2%80%94Simcoe" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>My earlier experience was... I worked for 15 years with the Royal Bank of Canada ending my banking career as a Branch Administration Officer. This was great training in financial management, administration and supervision.</p>
<p>I have, together with my husband, built the small business which has supported our family for the past 20 years. I am very aware of the challenges which face small businesses. There are many small businesses in York Simcoe that would benefit from my experience and understanding of the challenges they face.</p>
<p>I volunteered for about 11 years with a local distress centre, life is very difficult for some of our constituents in York Simcoe. When people are in times of crisis it is important that programs are in place to help them to get to the highest quality of life they can achieve. I also served on the local executive and the national executive which was great use of my administrative skills.</p>
<p>I served as foster parent to young offenders for 7 years which gave me opportunity to work with many troubled youth. I am aware of the challenges young people face as they grow up and also the need for strong, intact families to support them through those volatile years.</p>
<p>I have been a member of Speak for Success York Simcoe Toastmasters since 2004. I have served as Secretary, Vice President Education and President, which has further developed both my communication and leadership abilities. I have served as District Secretary for District 61 and Secretary of Northern Lights Advanced Toastmaster Club. I am currently serving as Club Coach to Simcoe Shores Toastmasters in Keswick. I would use the experience garnered in all of these roles as Member of Parliament because the type of government I envision would be strong on leadership and accountability.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">As you campaign around your riding, it's likely that some issues are mentioned more often by voters, than other issues. What would you say are the three hottest topics this election, in your riding? What would you and your party do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Constituents in York Simcoe spend a lot of time travelling to and from work.</hi> Gas prices are high and the other political parties offer no real solutions. We offer a "Fair Tax". This would be a tax on everything except essentials. Gas prices would be lower because there would not be layer upon layer of hidden taxes. We would also eliminate the income tax because it penalises industrious people for working. If 1/3 of your paycheque, what you have earned by your own labour, goes to the government before you see it, that is theft. A consumer tax would be paid when you purchase items or services, which means you control how much tax you pay. It is a much simpler form of book keeping. Our present tax laws are understood by extremely few people.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Important to constituents of York Simcoe is also a healthy environment.</hi> It IS possible to decrease pollution without government digging deeper into OUR pockets. The hype around global warming has cooled. People recognise that a healthy environment can be worked on by dealing with the controllable causes of pollution. We dump many toxic chemicals into our atmosphere not just the naturally occurring ones such as Carbon Dioxide and Water. We can and must start controlling these toxic chemicals. We must do the same for our lakes and environment. Reducing the pollution we can control is environmentally friendly. It may not be as glamourous as a global movement but it is much more effective.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">We see a continued deterioration of our infrastructure.</hi> There is no need for government to borrow money from the major banks, basically renting the money supply, to improve infrastructure. The government is entitled to create money. By putting this money is circulation for the purpose of improving our infrastructure and charging municipalities no interest, we are not piling further debt on the backs of our children and grandchildren. As the money is repaid it is withdrawn from circulation thus making it noninflationary. This was done after WW2, when the return of 2 million soldiers seeking employment threatened our economy. This launched the biggest building boom in Canadian history and Canada was left with healthy infrastructure.</item></list>
</text>
