<text id="autogum_interview_doc049" title="part1_Wikinews interviews three figures from Donald Trump&amp;apos;s political past" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-03-12" dateModified="2016-05-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_three_figures_from_Donald_Trump%27s_political_past" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Over a five month period, Wikinews reporter William S. Saturn contacted the three previously involved in Trump's politics to get their thoughts on his current presidential campaign, learn more about Trump's political past including the true nature of his 2000 effort, and obtain details on his personality.</p>
<head id="Roger_Stone">Roger Stone</head>
<figure><caption>Stone in 2014. Image: Lizzie Ochoa.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> first contacted Roger Stone in October.  In addition to his association with Trump, for whom he has worked as a lobbyist and advisor, Stone has a long history as a Republican Party operative, known for "<ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/dirty%20tricks">dirty tricks</ref>".  He worked on the infamous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Committee%20for%20the%20Re-Election%20of%20the%20President">Committee for the Re-Election of the President</ref> for President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard%20Nixon">Richard Nixon</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%201972">1972</ref>, during which he performed such tasks as planting a spy in the campaign of Democratic presidential candidate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hubert%20Humphrey">Hubert Humphrey</ref>, and sending a donation to a potential Republican primary opponent of Nixon under the name of a socialist organization.  After Nixon's resignation, Stone served as Nixon's "man in Washington."  He has a tattoo of Nixon's face on his back.  Among many campaigns, Stone worked on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%201980">1980</ref> presidential campaign of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ronald_Reagan">Ronald Reagan</ref>, for which he purportedly brought a suitcase, presumably filled with cash, to the office of an influential lawyer associated with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liberal%20Party%20of%20New%20York">Liberal Party of New York</ref> in order to secure the party's nomination for Independent presidential candidate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20B.%20Anderson">John B. Anderson</ref>, effectively splitting opposition to Reagan in the state. Stone has also worked for President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_H._W._Bush">George H. W. Bush</ref>, Congressman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%20Kemp">Jack Kemp</ref>, Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Dole">Bob Dole</ref>, and was employed by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20Bush%20presidential%20campaign,%202000">campaign</ref> to organize against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florida%20election%20recount">Florida recount</ref> during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bush%20v.%20Gore">disputed</ref> 2000 presidential election.  In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202004">2004</ref>, Stone volunteered for the presidential campaign of Democrat <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al%20Sharpton">Al Sharpton</ref>. And, ahead of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2008">2008 presidential election</ref>, he founded an anti-<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hillary_Clinton">Hillary Clinton</ref> group with the acronym C.U.N.T.  Recently, Stone joined the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libertarian_Party_(United_States)">Libertarian Party</ref>, and has authored a series of political books including one accusing President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lyndon%20Johnson">Lyndon Johnson</ref> of involvement in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Assassination%20of%20John%20F.%20Kennedy">assassination</ref> of President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20F.%20Kennedy">John F. Kennedy</ref>.  Stone served on Trump's current presidential campaign before a well-publicized split last August. He remains a supporter of the campaign and discusses his association with Trump and thoughts on the current campaign. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Until a few months ago you were a long-time associate of Donald Trump.  When did you first meet him and how would you describe him as a person?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Roger Stone</hi>: I met Donald in 1979 when I was sent to New York to organize Ronald Reagan's campaign for President. He and his father <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fred%20Trump">Fred Trump</ref> were members of the Reagan for President finance committee. We became good friends. I was invited to two of his weddings. He attended my wedding in Washington DC. He is very smart, very tough and can be very very funny. He is also very tall.</item></list></p>
</text>
