<text id="autogum_interview_doc1349" title="part4_G20 protests: Inside a labour march" shortTile="partg-protests-inside" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-04-03" dateModified="2014-05-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/G20_protests%3A_Inside_a_labour_march" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<figure><caption>A march steward calls out a chant</caption></figure><p>At 2:30 the march resumes. Rather than proceeding to the ExCel Centre itself, though, it makes its way to a station of London's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Docklands%20Light%20Railway">Docklands Light Railway</ref>; on the way, several of East London's school-aged youths join the march, and on reaching <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canning%20Town">Canning Town</ref> the group is some 300 strong. Proceeding on foot through the borough, the Youth Fight For Jobs reaches the protest site outside the G-20 meeting.</p>
<figure><caption>Police cover all roads leading into the ExCel Centre. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Killing_Vector">Killing Vector</ref>.</caption></figure><p>It's impossible to legally get too close to the conference itself. Police are guarding every approach, and have formed a double cordon between the protest area and the route that motorcades take into and out of the conference venue. Most are un-armed, in the tradition of London police; only a few even carry <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/police%20baton">truncheons</ref>. Closer to the building, though, a few machine gun-armed riot police are present, standing out sharply in their black uniforms against the high-visibility yellow vests of the Metropolitan Police. The G-20 conference itself, which started a few hours before the march began, is already winding down, and about a thousand protesters are present. </p>
<figure><caption>A speaker demands an end to dictatorship in Ethiopia</caption></figure><p>I see three large groups: the Youth Fight For Jobs avoids going into the center of the protest area, instead staying in their own group at the admonition of the stewards and listening to a series of guest speakers who tell them about current industrial actions and the organization of the Youth Fight's upcoming rally at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20College%20London">UCL</ref>. A second group carries the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ogaden%20National%20Liberation%20Front">Ogaden National Liberation Front</ref>'s flag and is campaigning for recognition of an autonomous homeland in eastern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethiopia">Ethiopia</ref>. Others protesting the Ethiopian government make up the third group; waving old Ethiopian flags, including the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flag%20of%20Ethiopia">Lion of Judah</ref> standard of emperor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haile%20Selassie">Haile Selassie</ref>, they demand that foreign aid to Ethiopia be tied to democratization in that country: "No recovery without democracy".</p><figure><caption>Ogaden Somalis demand an autonomous homeland. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Killing_Vector">Killing Vector</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>A set of abandoned signs tied to bollards indicate that the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Campaign%20for%20Nuclear%20Disarmament">CND</ref> has been here, but has already gone home; they were demanding the abandonment of nuclear weapons. But apart from a handful of individuals with handmade, cardboard signs I see no groups addressing the G-20 meeting itself, other than the Youth Fight For Jobs' slogans concerning the bailout. But when a motorcade passes, catcalls and jeers are heard.</p>
<p>It's now 5pm and, after four hours of driving, five hours marching and one hour at the G-20, Cardiff's Socialists are returning home. I board the bus with them and, navigating slowly through the snarled London traffic, we listen to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC%20Radio%20Four">BBC Radio 4</ref>. The news is reporting on the closure of the G-20 conference; while they take time out to mention that <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canadian</ref> Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen%20Harper">Stephen Harper</ref> delayed the traditional group photograph of the G-20's world leaders because "he was on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/toilet">loo</ref>", no mention is made of today's protests. Those listening in the bus are disappointed by the lack of coverage.</p>
</text>
