<text id="autogum_interview_doc887" title="part12_Author Amy Scobee recounts abuse as Scientology executive" shortTile="partauthor-amy-scobee" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-11" dateModified="2015-12-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_Amy_Scobee_recounts_abuse_as_Scientology_executive" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Shelly Miscavige told you that you were in the "highest ethics condition attainable" in Scientology while holding the executive position of "Watchdog Committee Celebrity Centre" (WDC CC), a condition called "power". How did it feel to attain this status within the Scientology executive leadership? Were you pleased, satisfied, or feel that the work you had done to date was worth it? Did you feel it was appropriate to serve time on the Rehabilitation Project Force, in order to later get to such a status?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: Shelly Miscavige commented that I took the position to a condition of power – which is the highest condition of existence per the Scientology scriptures. But it was just a statement from her. No certificate or anything was issued.</p>
<p>I was awarded PERMANENT POSTING STATUS on two executive positions in Church of Scientology International (CSI – the highest management organization for Scientology). This is a status that can only be verified and authorized by the Religious Technology Center (RTC – the holder of the Scientology trademarks and service marks). I received my Permanent Posting certificate by RTC as the Watchdog Committee member for Celebrity Centres (WDC CC), which I held as a single duty for four years, and as a function with other Scientology sectors for nearly a decade. Amongst the extensive list of requirements one must meet to become Permanently Posted, ones ethics and production record must be verified as excellent and you must be capable of generating on the order of a million dollars a year for the organization.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In 1996, you were transferred to the executive post of Watchdog Committee member for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Association%20for%20Better%20Living%20and%20Education">Association for Better Living and Education</ref> (WDC ABLE). ABLE is an organization operated by Scientology management which oversees groups that promote Scientology techniques. In this executive position, you were responsible for supervising Scientology-associated entities including: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Applied%20Scholastics">Applied Scholastics</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Narconon">Narconon</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Criminon">Criminon</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Way%20to%20Happiness">The Way to Happiness Foundation</ref>. Can you explain a little bit about the function and purpose of each of these groups? Are they actual-practice, separate "secular" functioning organizations, or somehow related to the Scientology organization itself? How specifically were these groups influenced and/or managed by Scientology leadership? How involved was <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_Miscavige">David Miscavige</ref> in the functioning of these groups?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: Association for Better Living and Education (ABLE): ABLE is an umbrella organization which specializes in promoting the use of Scientology technology as a means to solve social problems (drugs, crime, illiteracy and immorality) through Narconon, Criminon, Applied Scholastics and The Way to Happiness.</p>
<p>Narconon: The Narconon program is a drug education and rehabilitation program, founded on Hubbard’s belief that drugs and poisons stored in the body impede spiritual growth. Its "purification program" uses a regimen composed of sauna, physical exercise, vitamins and diet management, combined with auditing and study.</p>
</text>
