<text id="autogum_interview_doc1398" title="part2_Interview with gay marriage movement founder Evan Wolfson" shortTile="partinterview-gay" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-29" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_gay_marriage_movement_founder_Evan_Wolfson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>Third was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loving%20v.%20Virginia">ending race restrictions</ref> on who could marry whom; that only came to a conclusion, legally speaking, forty years ago.  Forty years ago there were people defending with the same ferocity as that with which they oppose gay people’s right to marry, the government’s right to restrict who can marry based upon their race, preaching who was the right kind of person to marry somebody else.  Forty years ago people believed that was okay.</p>
<p>The fourth was ending the legal subordination of women in marriage.  The definition of marriage said it was okay for a husband to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/marital%20rape">rape his wife</ref> because he is entitled to take what belongs to him.  I worked on the case that ended what was called the marital rape exemption.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That was here in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20State">New York</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  That was here in New York when I worked for the Brooklyn D.A.’s office.  This is not ancient history!  This is not the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Civil%20War">Civil War</ref>…this was in our own country in our lifetime in New York State.  Marriage has <hi rend="italic">always</hi> been this battlefield upon which larger questions have been addressed, and there have been many, many changes in the institution that have made it stronger and more reflective of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20values">American values</ref>--love, choice, freedom, equality, commitment, dedication--and reflective of who Americans really are, including men, women and people of diverse religious opinions, and gay people.  Values and exclusion: that’s what this struggle is about.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How did you first become involved in the marriage issue and why was it something you decided to dedicate yourself to?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  The short answer is that I don’t believe now, and I didn’t believe when I started this, that you can say you are for equality but acquiesce in exclusion from the central social and legal institution of this and virtually every other society.  That’s not equality.  You can’t say you are for equality if you accept exclusion from something so important legally and personally.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But why marriage and not immigration, or adoption?  There are many areas where gay people are excluded from participation.  Why do you personally focus on marriage?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  These are not either/ors.  It’s not like you have to pick one thing.  However, the reason I think it is so central to the discussion is because marriage is not just about getting married.</p>
<p>Marriage is a vocabulary, it’s a vehicle, an engine for a larger discussion that moves people’s understanding of who gay people are, why sex discrimination is wrong, why exclusion is wrong in America, that brings up discussion of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Separation%20of%20church%20and%20state%20in%20the%20United%20States">separation of church and state</ref>, that brings up discussion of whether there should be limitations or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gender%20role">roles based on sex</ref>, or whether <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/men%20and%20women%20should%20be%20treated%20equally">w:men and women should be treated equally</ref>.  Whether two women should be considered whole when they form a committed and loving relationship, as opposed to saying they are unwhole and unequal because they don’t have a man in their life.</p>
</text>
