<text id="autogum_interview_doc466" title="part3_Caribou plays the Bowery Ballroom" shortTile="partcaribou-plays" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-06" dateModified="2014-03-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Caribou_plays_the_Bowery_Ballroom" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What would be a bigger turn-off for you in bed, someone who was overly flatulent, or someone who spoke in a baby voice?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  I could get over the baby voice, but the flatulence is a tough one to stomach.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have a favorite curse word?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  Nothing is springing to mind.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Favorite <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/euphemism">euphemism</ref> for breasts?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  Nope.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If you had to choose between the destruction of the entire continent of Africa or the entire continent of Asia, which would you choose?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  Oh, God.  So, population-wise.  It’s tempting…I think that is the only way to choose.  Killing a greater number of people has to be a greater evil.  That’s maybe the bottom line.  I would hate to make that decision.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What are traits you respect in a woman?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  The same traits I look for in anybody else in the world: kindness, thoughtfulness.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It doesn’t differ in men?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  No.  Being a nice human being is what I look for in anybody.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What’s your most treasured possession?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  I have a massive record collection I obsess over, and it would be hard to let that go.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Any favorite films?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  I haven't been able to see any in the last couple of months, but in the last year I went through a complete <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Werner%20Herzog">Herzog</ref> obsession.  I watched all of his films, I read Herzog on Herzog and even read Kinsky’s biography.  Almost all of his films are incredible.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What difficult question in an interview do you anticipate but are never asked?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  I actually don’t anticipate the difficult ones, which is why when you asked me to destroy one continent I didn’t see that one coming.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What question are you tired of answering?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  The ones I get asked the most, and I don’t mind answering them, but I don’t relish answering them: I had to change my name from Manitoba to Caribou a couple years back due a law suit.   I don't mind this one anymore, but at first I got asked that in every interview.  And also, the connection between mathematics and music, which you asked me in a form.  That’s a valid question, though, because it’s a point of interest about the way that I work.  The lawsuit is like reciting a history of facts I’d rather forget.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In the last year, where have you drawn most of your influence, and you can’t have been listening to them beyond a year ago.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  The big thing for me in the last year that is reflected in this album more than in previous ones is songwriting.  I never wrote songs I just built tracks out of loops.  There were melodies in them, but there wasn’t any structure to the songs.  One artist I didn’t’ listen to before a year ago was Ariel Pink who is a lo-fi indie songwriter and producer.  His production is amazing, but it turns people off because it’s so lo-fi; but also, his song-writing is amazing.</p>
</text>
