<text id="autogum_interview_doc1210" title="part1_CanadaVOTES: NDP candidate Don Davies running in Vancouver Kingsway" shortTile="partcanadavotes-ndp" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-25" dateModified="2008-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_NDP_candidate_Don_Davies_running_in_Vancouver_Kingsway" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I'm running for the New Democrats as they are the party that represent my values; the party that works for the rest of us and not just the elite, the party that best protects the most marginalized in our society, and the party that will best protect our healthcare system, our environment, our affordable housing, and the many other things that matter most to us.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Previous to this campaign, have you been politically involved? How will you apply your previous work/volunteer/life experience to serving your constituents?</hi></p>
<p>I first became interested in politics in my university days, where I was heavily involved in student politics. I have been a member of the NDP for over 20 years. I worked in the Alberta legislature as a researcher and then executive assistant to the Leader of the Official Opposition at the Legislative Assembly of Alberta, where I gained essential experience in the legal needs of the business community as well as in government, writing legislation, analyzing budgets and developing sound public policy. I am currently the Chair of the Parent Advisory Council at Mount Pleasant school and a Director of the Meridian Cultural Society, a non-profit group that provides community space for daycare, church and refugee respite services.</p>
<p>My professional career as a labour relations lawyer is directly applicable to serving the needs of the constituents; dealing as it does with human rights, and the safety and security of working people and their families. I have won hundreds of cases, protected thousands of jobs and returned millions of dollars to working people and their families. I have also worked with many businesses to establish positive labour relations and served on many public bodies ranging from transportation policy to regulatory reform. This experience will serve me well as I address constituents' issues such as CPP, EI, visas and other immigration issues, business and community grants, and many others. I am already proven to have the experience and ability to get results for my constituents.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">As you campaign around your riding, it's likely that some issues are mentioned more often by voters, than other issues. What would you say are the three hottest topics this election, in your riding? What would you and your party do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>The three topics that people are raising with me are:</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">affordability</hi>  - the rising costs of living, housing, energy, university tuition, etc coupled with little or no increase in real wages is making it hard for the typical constituent to make ends meet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">healthcare</hi> - particularly around the cost of prescriptions, care of the elderly, increasing privatization, etc</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">childcare, education, environment, transit</hi> - okay that makes more than three issues in total, but theses are all critical and interrelated. If we want to give people the option of not driving their cars for work and shopping we must provide an affordable and usable transit system. And of course there is no point in addressing any of these issues if we have already destroyed our environment.</p>
</text>
