<text id="autogum_interview_doc826" title="part11_Satanism: An interview with Church of Satan High Priest Peter Gilmore" shortTile="partsatanism-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-04" dateModified="2018-10-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Satanism%3A_An_interview_with_Church_of_Satan_High_Priest_Peter_Gilmore" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You see that in all the old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manufacturing%20Belt">Rust Belt</ref> cities.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reading,%20Pennsylvania">Reading</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</ref> was one of the most dangerous cities I’ve ever walked around in, and I thought, “This is what 1982 New York must have felt like.”</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Yeah, I moved down to New York in 1980—that was pretty rough! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  A friend of mine once said if you took someone from 1982 New York and you transplanted them into 2007 New York, the first thing they would say is, “Where did all these people come from?!”  That the streets just used to be barren back then.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  I'm like that too.  Where I live my view of the sunset is gone because two new luxury towers have gone up.  They’re building two additional ones.  I don't know who these people are or where they get all their money because they are charging $6,000 a month for these apartments, and I’m thinking who is spending all this money and wandering around the city like it’s a pedestrian mall that could be in any kind of suburbia.</p>
<head id="Marilyn_Manson">Marilyn Manson</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marilyn%20Manson">Marilyn Manson</ref> is a member?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Yes, he's a member who has been given an honorary priesthood.  When asked about what Satanism is he can be very articulate in explaining it.  But his own music is his own art.  His stage shows are his own, and they don't really exemplify Satanism in particular.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s more of a character.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Yeah, he’s created a character.  We say people forget about past orthodoxies, something that was culturally popular or permeating at one point or another, people forget about that.  What Brian Warner did was he looked at David Bowie and Alice Cooper and re-created and repackaged them, and made a fortune.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is he an active member?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  He’s an honorary priest, but he does his own thing.  If asked about our philosophies he can explain it.  The interesting thing is when his first album came out the two of us met on a panel that we were doing about racism in music that was being sponsored by Seconds Magazine.  Nobody knew who Brian Warner was at that point, and he came up to me and gave me a CD and he was all in costume.  But he said "I heard about you and I wanted to meet you," so we moved aside and talked for a little while and I learned he really did understand Satanism. I told Anton LaVey that this guy was pretty smart and this gimmick is going to do well; it’s clever. He’s using this serial killer and Hollywood star combination, and he’s a smart guy and creating his own persona that is probably going to be successful.   It took off immediately, and when Marilyn Manson was out on tour in California he asked if he could meet Anton LaVey and he was impressed.  He is a really sweet and sincere guy, which has nothing to do with what all of the world sees in just his act and his art.</p>
</text>
