<text id="autogum_interview_doc1011" title="part7_Wikinews interviews Spain's most decorated Paralympian, Teresa Perales" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-01-19" dateModified="2015-11-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Spain%27s_most_decorated_Paralympian%2C_Teresa_Perales" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Is the Spanish Paralympic Committee working to fix this? Is it one of their goals to adjust this problem?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>:  Yes, but the Spanish Paralympic Committee are... Let me count. ((es))Spanish language: ‍ Sí, pero el Comité Paralímpico Español son... Déjame contar.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> They said six...</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>:  Yeah. [Laughs] It is true that the companies who support us, who support the ADO Paralympian Plan, it's been easier to get them to sign again after London than those of the Olympians. But then again, it's because the quantities are smaller! ((es))Spanish language: ‍ Sí. [Risas] Sí que es verdad que las empresas que nos ayudan a nosotros, que patrocinan el Plan ADO paralímpico, ha sido más fácil que volvieran a firmar después de Londres, que las de los Olímpicos. Pero claro, ¡es que la cantidad es mucho menor!</p></p>
<head id="Being_an_elite_female_athlete">Being an elite female athlete</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> In other interviews you talk about your family life. That's interesting, but you are an elite female athlete, and there's other interesting questions. Is there anything...?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>:  As female Paralympians, I think we are one, two, three, four. Four Paralympian mothers. Only. That we go to the Games.  ((es))Spanish langauge: ‍ Como deportista paralímpica, creo que estamos, una, dos, tres, cuatro. Somos cuatro deportistas paralímpicas madres. Solamente. Que vayamos a los Juegos.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> How many women total, then?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>:  Puf, I don't know. It is very difficult, you know, to be a mother, train, compete, be at the stages, take care of the kid... sometimes it's a balancing act. Apart from the physical changes that take place when you become a mother.  ((es))Spanish language: ‍Puf, no lo sé. Es que es muy dificil, eh, ser madre, compaginar los entrenamientos, las concentraciones, las competiciones, atender al niño... a veces es un ejercicio de malabares. Además de los cambios que hay físicos en la mujer cuando eres madre.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Paralympics in some sports have many fewer women than men, especially skiing. Is that something that exists in swimming, and does it hurt the quality of sport? Because the men in the skiing are like, the women, they are so few of them, they embarrass us, is that something that exists on a swimming level?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>:  Yes. But not only in Spain, in the whole world. ((es))Spanish language: ‍ Sí. Pero no solo en España, en todo el mundo. </p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> People say that women don't swim as well as the men, because there's so few?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>: We are very few. In Spain we had a problem before the Games due to the number of spots given to the Spanish women swimmers, which were a third of those offered to the men. And we had female swimmers who made the qualifying time but could not go to the Games. And in Spain qualifiers are hard, there are two kinds: A minimum and B minimum. I'm talking about swimming, athletics... Especially swimming. B minimum is until the eighth position, A minimum is until the third. So, there we women who would have made the finals, and could not go. But this is not a recent problem, it's because of classification, at the World Championships... it's not only a problem in Spain. It's a problem that women do not participate as much as men. I really believe it is a family problem, a cultural problem, and it is a problem that comes from women traditionally doing more things than men and dedicating more time to their families than to training. A man doesn't have to stop to have a child, usually has more support for the house things, and yet however women don't. ((es))Spanish language: ‍ Nosotras somos muy pocas. En España tuvimos un problema antes de los Juegos por el número de plazas que se nos habían dado a las nadadoras españolas, que era una tercera parte de las plazas de los hombres, no llegaba. Y teníamos nadadoras que hicieron mímina y no pudieron ir a los Juegos. Y en España la clasificación es bastante dificil, hay dos clasificaciones: una es la mímina A y otra es la mínima B. Hablo de natación, atletismo... Sobre todo en natación. La mínima B es hasta el octavo puesto, la mínima A es hasta el tercer puesto. O sea, hubo gente que habría entrado en final, y que no pudo ir. Pero esto es un problema que viene de atrás, porque esto es por clasificación, en los Mundiales... que no es sólo un problema en España. Es un problema de que las mujeres no participan tanto como los hombres. Yo creo que de verdad es un problema de familias, es un problema cultural, y es un problema de que la mujer es la que tradicionalmente hace más cosas que los hombres y dedica más tiempo a su familia que a los entrenamientos. Un hombre no tiene que parar para tener un hijo, normalmente suele tener más apoyo para las cosas de la casa, y sin embargo la mujer no.</p></p>
</text>
