<text id="autogum_interview_doc357" title="part3_Creator of website satirizing Glenn Beck on winning domain name case" shortTile="partcreator-website" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-11-09" dateModified="2019-02-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Creator_of_website_satirizing_Glenn_Beck_on_winning_domain_name_case" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Commentators likened the legal conflict between Beck and the site to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Streisand%20effect">Streisand effect</ref>, a phenomenon where an individual's attempt to censor material on the Internet in turn proves to make the material itself more public. <hi rend="italic">Online Media Daily</hi> commented, "The decision appears to mark a significant win for digital rights advocates because a ruling in Beck's favor could have encouraged other subjects of online parodies to take their complaints directly to the WIPO rather than U.S. courts, which are bound by the First Amendment." Citizen Media Law Project's assistant director wrote that the ruling was appropriate, "It's good to see that this WIPO arbitrator had no interest in allowing Beck to circumvent the guarantees of the U.S. Constitution."</p>
<p>Eiland-Hall's website was still operational Monday, at a mirror site www.GB1990.com. At the site, Eiland-Hall announced "WE WON!". He gave Beck well-wishes as the commentator is recovering from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/appendicitis">appendicitis</ref>.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Can you describe a little bit about yourself and your background, and how you came to be interested in the Glenn Beck meme in the first place?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Isaac Eiland-Hall</hi>: I've been a computer geek since 1987, when I was 12. I've been on the internet since 1994. Among other jobs, I've done technical support and web design/hosting. I've gone back to school and I'm working on a degree in Computer Science. If I manage that, I'm thinking of following up with a Master's in Meteorology. If I had more courage, I'd probably try to become a professional storm chaser. </p>
<p>I grew up as a very fundamentalist Southern Baptist. I got better. My political and social outlook has gone from very conservative to very liberal. One nice thing about this is that I understand both sides. A lot of liberals scoff at the concept of Chick tracts, for example; and I do, now. But growing up, I remember believing in all that stuff. I do have to remind myself that most Christians are pretty moderate in their outlook, though, sometimes when I get a little frustrated by some of the more vocal small groups who would like the U.S. to become a Christian Theocracy.</p>
<p>I've also become frustrated with radicals -- liberal and conservative; though, as a liberal, you'll be shocked - shocked, I say - to find out that I see more conservatives that fit the bill -- radicals who I feel are tearing this country apart with their manipulations and lies. These extremists are pushing people toward the extremes, and it's polarizing and ripping our nation apart. It seems like nobody wants to compromise any longer; nobody wants to try and work together; everybody wants their party to win at all costs, because the other party is the spawn of Satan.</p>
</text>
