<text id="autogum_interview_doc158" title="part5_Wikinews interviews Australian Glider Amanda Carter" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-09-26" dateModified="2017-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Glider_Amanda_Carter" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Because you are the more experienced player.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yeah!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  And now you have another silver medal.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yes. Which is great.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  We double-checked, and there was nobody else on the team who had been in Sydney, much less Barcelona or Atlanta.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> I know.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Most of the Gliders seem to have come together in 2004, the current roster.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yes, most since 2004, and some since 2008. And of course there are three newbies for 2012.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Are you still playing? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> I'm having a rest at this particular point. Probably because it's been a long campaign of the training over the four years. I guess more intense over the last eighteen months or so. At the moment I am having a short break just to spend some time with my son. Those sorts of things. ‘Cause he stayed at home rather than come to London.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You would have been isolated from him anyway.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> And that's the thing. We just decided that if he had come, it would have been harder for him, knowing he'd have five minutes a day or twenty minutes or something like that where he could see me versus he spoke to me for an hour on Skype every day. So, I think it would have been harder to say to Alex: "Look, you can't come back to the village. You need to go with my friend now" and stuff like that. So he made the decision that he wanted to stay, and have his normal routine of school activities, and just talk to mum on Skype every day.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Fair enough.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yeah! But I haven't decided where to [go] from here.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> You will continue playing with the club?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> I ‘ll still keep playing women's league, but not sure about some of the international stuff. And who knows? I may well still, but at this point I'm just leaving my options open. It's too early to say which way I'm going to go.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Is there anything else you'd like to say about your record? Which is really impressive. I can count the number of Paralympians who were on Team Australia in London who were at the Sydney games on my fingers.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yes!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   Greg Smith obviously, who was carrying the flag...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libby_Kosmala">Libby Kosmala</ref>... <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liesl%20Tesch">Liesl Tesch</ref>... I've got half my hand already covered!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What I basically wanted to ask was what sort of changes you've seen with the Paralympics over that time — 1992 to 2012.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> I think the biggest change has been professionalism of Paralympic sports. I think way back in '92,  especially in basketball, I guess, was that there weren't that many girls and as long as you trained a couple of times a week, and those sorts of things, you could pretty much make the team.  It wasn't as competitive. This campaign, certainly, we've had a lot more than the twelve girls who were vying for those twelve positions. The ones who certainly didn't make the team still trained as hard and everything as the ones who did. And just the level of training has changed. Like, I remember for 2012 I'd still go and train, say, four, five times a week, and that's mostly shooting and things like that, but now it's not just about the shooting court skills, it's very much all the gym sessions, the strength and conditioning.  Chair skills, ball skills, shooting, those sorts of things to the point where leading in to London, I was doing twelve sessions a week. So it was a bigger time commitment. So the level of commitment and the skill level of the team has improved enormously over that twenty years. I think you see that in other sports where the records are so much, throwing records, the greater distances, people jump further in long jump. Speeds have improved, not just with technology, but dedication to training and other areas. So I think that's the big thing.  I think also the public's view of the Paralympics has changed a lot, in that it was seen more as, "oh, isn't it good that they're participating" in 1992, where I think the general public understands the professionalism of athletes now in the Paralympics. And that's probably the biggest change from a public perspective.</p>
</text>
