<text id="autogum_interview_doc443" title="part1_CanadaVOTES: NDP candidate Michael McMahon running in Prince Edward—Hastings" shortTile="partcanadavotes-ndp" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-22" dateModified="2013-01-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_NDP_candidate_Michael_McMahon_running_in_Prince_Edward%E2%80%94Hastings" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">As you campaign around your riding, it's likely that some issues are mentioned more often by voters, than other issues. What would you say are the three hottest topics this election, in your riding? What would you and your party do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Health Care:</hi></p>
<p>We have too few doctors. Our hospitals are over-crowded. Emergency rooms and clinics require long waits. New Democrats will invest in our health care system. By creating training spaces for doctors and nurses, all of us will have access to proper care, and wait times for treatment will be shortened. By building long term care facilities, hospital overcrowding will be relieved, and we will be able to treat our growing number of seniors with dignity.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Environment:</hi></p>
<p>The New Democrats are not proposing a carbon tax because it will not motivate the person who can afford a Cadillac SUV to use less fuel, but it will impact the ordinary family trying to keep their own car on the road. The NDP transportation strategy will invest in Canadian production of "green" cars. We will provide incentives to those who purchase more efficient vehicles. We will bring in mandatory vehicle emissions standards. And we will increase support for rail and other transport so that dependence on cars can be reduced.</p>
<p>The New Democrats will help large companies audit their energy use, and offer incentives to help them reduce consumption. Allowable emissions by industries will be firmly capped, and this cap will be lowered year by year. Subsidies and tax breaks currently handed out to the petroleum industry will be stopped.</p>
<p>Owners of homes and commercial buildings will be encouraged to improve their efficiency by grants and tax incentives. The building code will be amended to insure lower energy use (as well as fuel bills). The NDP will re-instate the EnerGuide for Houses Retrofit Incentive Program, one of the many programs cut by Harper's Conservatives.</p>
<p>New Democrats will see that an east-west energy grid is built to reliably connect the clean hydro power from Manitoba, Quebec, Newfoundland and Labrador with the areas currently burning coal. We will target 10 000 megawatts of wind generation capacity by 2010, and place a priority on manufacturing wind turbines and solar panels in Canada. There is a big opportunity here for our manufacturing sector, and the good jobs that would result.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">The Economy:</hi></p>
<p>Fuel prices are hurting people. Good jobs are leaving the country. We need to have alternatives to gasoline and fuel oil. The price is only going to increase. Stephen Harper and the Calgary Petroleum Club will do nothing about it, since that's how oil companies make their fat profits.</p>
<p>The New Democrats will stop the tax breaks and subsidies given away to Big Oil and other large corporations. We will use that money to invest in a "green" economy. We should be making our own no-gas cars, wind turbines, solar arrays, energy storage, electric railways... There is plenty of room here for us be world-leaders in the new way of doing things. There are profits to be made, and plenty of good jobs.</p>
</text>
