<text id="autogum_interview_doc538" title="part11_Billy West, voice of Ren and Stimpy, Futurama, on the rough start that shaped his life" shortTile="partbilly-west-voice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2013-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Billy_West%2C_voice_of_Ren_and_Stimpy%2C_Futurama%2C_on_the_rough_start_that_shaped_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  At what point was that for you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  When I stopped drinking, of course. But I couldn’t play music in the way I wanted to play it anymore. I would have been like a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/parody">parody</ref> of myself. So that didn’t seem truthful to me.  Trying to do comedy seemed truthful to me, but then, like I told you before, I didn’t have the discipline to do <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stand-up%20comedy">stand-up</ref>. That term wasn’t popular much before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1970s">seventies</ref>. Then you started hearing these stand-up comics. When I was a kid and when I was a teenager, doing comedy meant you were interrupting somebody’s dinner in a restaurant. There was no comedy clubs <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/per%20se">per se</ref></hi>. But the turning point—it’s called survival. It’s like being a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cockroach">cockroach</ref>. You evolve or die. When I was kid I thought everybody was like me and all these people I hang with are going to be running the country and I couldn’t have been more wrong.</p>
<head id="West_on_politics">West on politics</head>
<p>[<hi rend="italic">continued from previous section</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Well they are. It’s just things have changed.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  I’m way older than a lot of these guys by the way, that are out there. But to me they look like old men with bad breath and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/dandruff">dandruff</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Who are you talking about?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republicans</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Yeah.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  You know, the guys that are running things. They don’t look like people that came from my generation at all. I’m as old as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Karl_Rove">Karl Rove</ref>, or any of those idiots and it’s like, 'Where did you come from?' It’s still the same old geezers that hide behind religion and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/family%20values">family values</ref>, and then <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Larry_Craig">they’re messing with guys in men’s rooms</ref> and scandal prone because that’s sort of what the party is famous for. I hated those guys and I didn’t grow up to be one. But then I watch all these people from my generation just suddenly morph into that and I’m still in a state of shock. Where did these <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donna%20Reed">Donna Reeds</ref> and these little <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breck%20Shampoo">Breck girls</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St.%20Pauli%20Girl">St. Pauli girls</ref> that are filled with Republican ideology come from? It’s like they’re young. What is this, you know.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: It’s confusing because you look at somebody like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dick_Cheney">Dick Cheney</ref>, who has this <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lesbian">lesbian</ref> daughter, who’s in a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_marriage">gay marriage</ref> [<hi rend="italic">Poe and Cheney have not entered into a formal union</hi> - <hi rend="italic">ed</hi>] and now has a baby with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heather%20Poe">her partner</ref>, and you just don’t know how the situation exists. It’s hard to comprehend.  That <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary%20Cheney">Mary Cheney</ref> exists in the Republican party, and that she seems to be fine with that existence and even works for it. </hi></p>
</text>
