<text id="autogum_interview_doc440" title="part1_CanadaVOTES: NDP candidate David Sparrow in Don Valley West" shortTile="partcanadavotes-ndp" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-10" dateModified="2009-03-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_NDP_candidate_David_Sparrow_in_Don_Valley_West" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">As you campaign around your riding, it's likely that some issues are mentioned more often by voters, than other issues. What would you say are the three hottest topics this election, in your riding? What would you and your party do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>In Don Valley West, whether in a challenged area like Flemingdon Park or a more comfortable area like Lawrence Park, people are concerned about the same things. The economy (jobs), keeping a roof over their head and food on the table and the future. Certainly their perspectives are different. The Flemingdon resident wants a national housing strategy that will lower their rent or give them hope of home ownership. The senior in Lawrence Park wants to know that they won't be forced to leave their home simply because their property tax is rising faster than their fixed income. Immigrants want to know they can have hope of professional certification so they can work in the field they've been trained in. The managers and creative workers in the north of the riding want to avoid having to re-invent themselves and seek new employment at age 40 or 50. People are happiest when they can have confidence in theirs and their family's future. Canada has a proud legacy of addressing potential need. Through public healthcare, Canada Pension Plan, Employment Insurance, even social assistance we have created a society that supports its weakest members and offers hope to every resident. Jack Layton and the NDP have practical plans to address these issues and redistribute tax dollars away from subsidies to large foreign companies and the war in Afghanistan to the issues closest to the hearts of hard working families.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Are there any misconceptions about you, your leader, or your party and platform?</hi></p>
<p>The biggest misconception surrounding the NDP is that we can't afford to implement our policies. It couldn't be further from the truth. Right now, the Harper government is spending billions of Canadian tax dollars in Alberta providing tax breaks and subsidies to profitable, multi-national corporations, oil companies, so they can scarify the earth increase Canada's carbon footprint and pollute an entire province. They are also spending billions of tax dollars on a war in Afghanistan that can not be won and in which we are contributing to the death of civilians and supporting US incursions into Pakistan. This money along with the 54 billion dollar EI surplus that they wrote off when the Auditor General said they owed it back to the Canadian people, should be used to meet the social, economic and infrastructure needs of Canadians. The NDP and Jack Layton will redistribute the tax dollars of Canadians to the benefit of all citizens.</p>
</text>
