<text id="autogum_interview_doc962" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Fred Karger, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-04-23" dateModified="2014-03-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Fred_Karger%2C_U.S._Republican_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What did you learn from Ronald Reagan?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Fred Karger</hi>: Well, I learned about his great optimism and his ability to get along with Democrats and Republicans, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conservatism%20in%20the%20United%20States">conservatives</ref> [and] <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liberalism%20in%20the%20United%20States">liberals</ref>. He had an innate ability to work with people of all stripes and get along with them. Good with speaking the language of the time, building alliances to get a lot of things done in the best interest of the country, unlike President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Obama</ref> and the Congress today. Ronald Reagan never took himself too seriously...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">I read on your <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Facebook">Facebook</ref> profile that you supported <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democratic Party</ref> candidate <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hillary_Clinton">Hillary Clinton</ref> during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic%20Party%20presidential%20primaries,%202008">2008 primaries</ref>. Why did you support her?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Fred Karger</hi>: The Republican Party has moved too far to the right for my liking. And that was not the Republican Party that I grew up with. I think there’s room in the party for a broad coalition of thought...</p>
<p>I was very disenchanted with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20Party%20presidential%20candidates,%202008">Republicans running four years ago</ref>, and I liked Hillary Clinton. I liked <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bill_Clinton">her husband</ref>. I thought he was a good centrist and a good president. And I wanted to help out and support her. I didn't work for her, but I did max out. I gave $2300 over a period of time in 2008 to her. And I just thought she would have been a very good president.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Who did you support during the general election?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Fred Karger</hi>: During the general in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2008">2008</ref>, I didn't support either candidate. I had helped <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202000">2000</ref>. We were working an independent expenditure committee that I helped with a gentleman named Charles Francis that was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gay-Straight%20alliance">Gay-Straight alliance</ref> that supported George W. Bush, but then he let us down with his vocal support for a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Marriage%20Amendment">federal Constitutional amendment</ref> banning gay marriage and other anti-gay activities that campaign and he were involved with in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202004">2004</ref>. So I did not help him. I did not vote for him in 2004. I voted for a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third%20party%20(U.S.%20politics)">third party</ref> candidate because then I was not too convinced that Barack Obama was the right man for the job. So I was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ralph%20Nader">Ralph Nader</ref> voter. I didn't do anything with his campaign or more, but I did end up voting for him.</p>
<hi rend="bold">The public doesn't know enough about the Mormon Church, so I wanted to help make them aware because there are some very interesting parts of that religion that I think it’s certainly open for discussion with Mitt Romney as the likely Republican nominee</hi>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You have been very critical of the Mormon Church for its support of Proposition 8, and you created a website titled, "the Top Ten Craziest Mormon beliefs". Some of your followers on Facebook wrote comments that this went too far. What is your response to them?</hi></p>
</text>
