<text id="autogum_interview_doc1082" title="part3_Vanity Fair contributing editor Craig Unger on the Bush family feud, neoconservatives and the Christian right" shortTile="partvanity-fair-contributing" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2015-08-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vanity_Fair_contributing_editor_Craig_Unger_on_the_Bush_family_feud%2C_neoconservatives_and_the_Christian_right" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  I frame it in an almost <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oedipal">oedipal way</ref>—the first chapter is called “Oedipus Tex”—and they have lost.  It was Bush Sr.  and his best friend Scowcroft against Bush Jr.  On the surface there were no words between them; they would play horseshoes and talk nice about their houses and Midland.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Woodward">Bob Woodward</ref> was astonished when Bush Jr. told him he had not spoken to Bush Sr. about the Iraq War at all.  Do you come across what is behind that?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  First, George W. Bush was not the favorite son by a long-shot.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeb%20Bush">Jeb</ref> was, and even <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neil%20Bush">Neil</ref> was ahead of them.  But in 1994 you had George W. and Jeb running for governor of Texas and Florida, respectively, and exactly the reverse happened of what people expected: that George would lose and Jeb would win.  The opposite happened.  In 1998, George wins reelection and suddenly he’s a two-term governor of a very visible state who has positioned himself for the Presidency.  He knows nothing about foreign policy.  He had only left the country one time, which was to visit his daughter in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Italy">Italy</ref>.  He had no curiosity about the world.  Bush Sr. decides they have to educate him about it, so they bring in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prince%20Bandar">Prince Bandar</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Condoleeza%20Rice">Condi Rice</ref> and begin a series of seminars.  They are thinking the old guard—by that I mean <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brent%20Scowcroft">Brent Scowcroft</ref>, Condi Rice, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20H.%20Baker%20IV"> James Baker</ref>,<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colin%20Powell">Colin Powell</ref>—will take charge; that is not what happens <hi rend="italic">at all</hi>.   In late 1998 the neocons quickly move in, and you have <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard%20Perle">Richard Perle</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul%20Wolfowitz">Paul Wolfowitz</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elliot%20Abrams">Elliott Abrams</ref> making semi-secret trips down to Texas.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That was to educate Bush?  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20The%20Daily%20Show"> The Daily Show</ref> did this piece where they did a debate splicing Texas Governor Bush’s views of what he said when he was governor versus what he has said as President, and they are polar opposites.  When he was governor he was saying we can’t go out nation-building.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Right.  If you carefully, carefully examine what is happening, Richard Perle comes back from one of those trips and tells a breakfast meeting in 1999 that Bush is going to carry out their plan to overturn <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saddam%20Hussein">Saddam</ref>.  Bush himself says it in the fall of 1999 and says, “I’m going to take him out.”  Afterwards people call him on it and ask, “You’re going to take out Saddam?” and he gets criticized for it mercilessly.  He backs down and says, ‘No, no, I mean take out the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weapons%20of%20Mass%20Destruction">weapons of mass destruction</ref>.”  He backs off and attacks Gore as you say, and says we are not going to do nation-building instead.  But he’s had these private conversations; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen%20Hadley">Stephen Hadley</ref> tells these private fundraisers that Bush’s first priority is going to be to overthrow Saddam.  This is in early 2000.  I paid a lot of attention to the period just after the election was settled.  Some fascinating things happen—I wrote about this as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salon.com">Salon</ref> expert; it’s a Wolfowitz story—the neocons realize if they want to carry out the Iraq War, they need to control the intelligence apparatus.  The perfect way to do this is to make Paul Wolfowitz the head of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central%20Intelligence%20Agency">CIA</ref>.</p>
</text>
