<text id="autogum_interview_doc697" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Carita Murphy-Marketos, Sudbury" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-04" dateModified="2013-03-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Carita_Murphy-Marketos%2C_Sudbury" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>The FCP Will insist that there be no cover-up of information related to the transmission of viruses, the link between abortion and breast cancer and the inadequacy of condoms against some viruses.</p>
<p>The Family Coalition party would create a responsible free enterprise climate, with government intervention limited to the enforcement of the entrepreneur’s responsibilities in such areas as work safety and protection.</p>
<p>It would reform the school system to prepare young people for assuming the challenge of change and responsibility for innovation, to create a vibrant economy in Ontario. We will help the private sector to create jobs by reducing taxes to stimulate investment and increase the buying power of the average citizen.</p>
<p>People must keep in mind a quote from my own mother when speaking to a grade eight graduating class years ago: The world owes you nothing if you contribute nothing.</p>
<p>The Family Coalition Party will require a person’s juvenile record to be released upon the first adult conviction and will require a person who is convicted of a violent offence for which he/she has been previously convicted to serve the balance of the previous unserved sentence. In addition the maximum sentence for the current conviction will be doubled, without possibility for parole.</p>
<p>We believe that no person living below the poverty line should pay taxes.</p>
<p>The Family Coalition Party will restore freedom of speech of pro-life individuals or groups, including their freedom to demonstrate peacefully in front of hospitals, abortion clinics or any other place of their choice. In addition, The Family Coalition Party will urge the federal government to restore full legal protection to all human beings, from the moment of conception to natural death.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>The first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly should be, in accordance with the wishes of the people from across Canada as demonstrated in a recent pole, to put an end to abortion. The public is also concerned with job loss and crime in our streets.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>The Family Coalition Party would cut taxes by reducing the budgets of all government Agencies, Boards and Commissions by 10% the first year and initiate a review the second year with a view of eliminating as many of them as possible.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>The decision to index support payment programs to inflation was a positive move made by the 38th Legislative Assembly, but left most recipients still short of what they need to live. The health tax was a heavy burden placed on low income members of society.</p>
</text>
