<text id="autogum_interview_doc890" title="part15_Author Amy Scobee recounts abuse as Scientology executive" shortTile="partauthor-amy-scobee" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-11" dateModified="2015-12-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_Amy_Scobee_recounts_abuse_as_Scientology_executive" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: As I was getting on the airplane home, the OSA staff member who escorted me to the airport said that I could not talk to my mother due to the "suppressive person" declare issue that she handed me a few hours before. Of course, after I arrived to my father's house, I realized that I was no longer under Scientology's control and I could contact my mother if I wanted – and I desperately wanted to! I hadn't seen her in years and now I was home for good! Scientology did find out about us seeing each other and took various actions to put pressure on my step-father to enforce their disconnection policy. This was very messy and is one of the key reasons I chose to speak out publicly against Scientology's human rights violations. At one point, my husband and I were followed by Private Investigators anywhere we went. We had to file a police report because one in particular was being very reckless in his attempts to stay on our tail – and flee when we tried to confront him. I finally filed a declaration against Scientology, showing several instances of harassment to myself and my family, which I considered witness tampering since I was named as a witness on an on-going lawsuit against them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Were you concerned that your relationships might be affected due to Scientology declaring you a "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suppressive%20Person">Suppressive Person</ref>", and telling members of the organization never to speak to you again? Has this stopped you, or are you in communication with current and/or former members of the organization?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: Aside from the incident mentioned above with my mother (which is now handled as she, too has left the church along with her husband), the "Suppressive Person" label has not stopped me from communicating to anyone I feel the need to communicate with. Some associates "discovered" (were told by Scientology when they saw them as my friend on facebook or something) that I was declared suppressive and therefore told me they could no longer talk to me. If they want to continue to support a controlling organization and toe the line, they are welcome to. I know what it's like to be in a cult and understand their "reasoning", no matter how much I now see it to be illogical and irrational.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> One month before your book was published, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All%20Headline%20News">All Headline News</ref></hi> reported that you received a legal threat from Tom Cruise's lawyer, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bertram%20Fields">Bertram Fields</ref>, that warned you would face a defamation lawsuit from Cruise if the book was made publicly available. Specific complaints made included your accounts of hearing about a "drug history" involving Cruise, an ultimatum made by the Scientology organization to Cruise to decide between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicole%20Kidman">Nicole Kidman</ref> or the organization, and that Cruise's personal assistants and employees that staff his home are chosen and paid for by the Scientology organization. Can you speak to how you came to have knowledge about these assertions you made, why you believe them to be true and factually accurate, and how you felt when you received the legal threat letter from Cruise's attorney?</hi></p>
</text>
