<text id="autogum_interview_doc1007" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Spain's most decorated Paralympian, Teresa Perales" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-01-19" dateModified="2015-11-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Spain%27s_most_decorated_Paralympian%2C_Teresa_Perales" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> In Atlanta it was really bad...</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>:  Yes, some even were unable to compete because they were not able to get to the place of the event. ((es))Spanish language: ‍ Sí, algunos se perdieron el poder competir porque no tenían comunicación.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Some of the people with the Paralympic movement think understanding classification is key towards moving the Games forward, like how do you convey that to the public, how classification works, so when somebody sees you, an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/S5%20(classification)">S5 swimmer</ref>, they go, 'we got times like this, but the S1 swimmers, this, and I can't see much of a difference'. </p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>:  Yes, that is one of the problems we have. In fact, it is the biggest problem for having in the future an open class system, a system in which all classes were able to compete together. One of the issues that was being evaluated since before London had to do with the events, not the place but the event, for example 50m butterfly, why now yes and before no, or why before yes and now not? One of the systems proposed, to avoid events from having to disappear, is unifying several categories. In other words, to have one class, but open.  ((es))Spanish language: ‍ Sí, ese es uno de los problemas que tenemos. De hecho, es el mayor problema para que en el futuro pudiera hacerse un sistema de clases abierto, un sistema en el que todas las clases pudieramos competir juntas. Una de las cuestiones que se valoraban antes de Londres, relacionada con los eventos, no el lugar sino el evento, la prueba, por ejemplo 50m mariposa, ¿por qué ahora sí y antes no, o por qué antes sí y ahora no? Uno de los sistemas que se plantean es, para evitar que desaparezcan las pruebas, hacer que muchas categorías se unifiquen. Es decir, que haya una clase, pero abierta.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Like skiiing?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>: Yes. It's similar. Yes, yes, similar to that. They are thinking of doing something similar in swimming, athletics, cycling... in sports with many people. This arises because we have a limited number of people who can participate in the Games, which is 4,000. 4,200, total. It's 10,000 Olympians, while we are 4,000. And this is an agreement with the Olympic Committee. The Paralympic Committee makes a deal with the Olympic Committee, and that's why we cannot exceed 4,000, and why some events have to be eliminated. To eliminate events, there is the option to concentrate the classes. But there is a big problem, because the public would not understand me competing against a swimmer who is only missing a hand, because she would obviously beat me. Imagine that I really do beat her not because I arrive before her, but because my time, due to the correction percentages or whatever, is held to be the winner, even if however I came in last position.  ((es))Spanish language: ‍Sí. Es parecido. Sí, sí, es similar. Ellos están pensando en hacer algo parecido en natación, en atletismo, ciclismo... en los deportes que más deportistas hay. Esto surge porque tenemos un número limitado de deportistas que pueden acudir a los Juegos, que son 4,000. 4,200, total. Olímpicos son 10,000, nosotros somos 4,000. Y esto es un acuerdo con el Comité Olímpico. El Comité Paralímpico hace un acuerdo con el Comité Olímpico, y por eso no podemos sobrepasar los 4,000, y por eso hay que eliminar pruebas. Para eliminar pruebas, está la opción de concentrar las clases. Pero hay un gran problema, porque el público no entendería que yo compito con una deportista que sólo le falta la mano, que obviamente me gana. Imagínate que yo realmente le gano no porque llegue antes, si no porque mi tiempo, por los porcentajes de corrección o lo que sea, a mi me conceden que sea la ganadora, pero sin embargo he llegado la última.</p></p>
</text>
