<text id="autogum_interview_doc1432" title="part7_Judging the Courts: Wikinews interviews Prof. Lawrence Douglas" shortTile="partjudging-courts" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-11-20" dateModified="2015-09-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Judging_the_Courts%3A_Wikinews_interviews_Prof._Lawrence_Douglas" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: Does the court's record of events really matter? Don't "Iraqis know Saddam's crimes, trial or no trial"?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: I think a court's record of events can make a difference.  Though many Germans were aware of the "excesses" of the Nazis, the Nuremberg trial made clear to them the extent and depth of atrocity perpetrated by their leaders.  This accounting helped erode whatever residual sympathy the Nazis enjoyed among the German people.  Ideally, the Hussein trial would have achieved a similar end. I doubt though that this has happened.  Unfortunately, in the minds of many Iraqis, the crimes for which Saddam has been sentenced to death pale in comparison to the violence that grips the Iraqi nation on a daily basis.  If anything, a sizeable percentage of the population probably now longs for a strong leader capable of reimposing conditions of security and order.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: Should the trial have been conducted by an international tribunal instead of an Iraqi one?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: Clearly an international tribunal could have avoided some of the more unseemly problems that vexed the Iraqi court.  Still, I believe an international court would have been plagued by other problems.  As the Milosevic trial made clear, the fact that a trial is conducted before an international tribunal does not guarantee that it is perceived as legitimate or independent – the ICTY was dismissed in Serbia as the lapdog of NATO.  And as I mentioned earlier, removing a case to an international court sends the implicit message that the Iraqi legal system is deficient, something guaranteed to breed resentment.  And as the Milosevic trial made clear, there is no reason to believe that Saddam would have been more deferential to his international judges than he was to Iraqi jurists.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: There is a possibility that Saddam may be executed without facing trial over other, far more significant crimes such as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Anfal%20Campaign">Anfal killings</ref>, in which an estimated 100,000 people died. How important is it, for serving justice and for establishing a historical record, for Saddam to face trial for the Anfal killings, the repression of the 1991 Shia uprising, and other alleged acts?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: In August, just as Saddam's first trial was winding down, his second began – this one involving his regime's alleged atrocities committed against Iraqi Kurds during the Anfal military campaign in the late 1980s.  Needless to say, this trial involves far more serious crimes than those at issue in the first trial; in terms of the role of the trial as a tool for clarifying a horrific past, this proceeding promises to do far fuller justice to the abominable crimes of Saddam's regime.  This fact alone creates a strong case for delaying Saddam's execution until at least the completion of this second trial.  Indeed, it would be best to delay his execution until all the crimes of his regime, such as the bloody repression campaign of 1991, can be submitted to legal judgment.  Ideally this would serve the interests of history and justice, as Iraqi prosecutors and judges would grow increasingly familiar with conducting trials according to the rule of law.</p>
</text>
