<text id="autogum_interview_doc1051" title="part3_Past Eurovision contestants give advice to this year's performers, speculate on who will win" shortTile="partpast-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-05-06" dateModified="2015-09-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Past_Eurovision_contestants_give_advice_to_this_year%27s_performers%2C_speculate_on_who_will_win" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What were some of the best memories you have from going to Eurovision? What advice would you give to the singers going to Eurovision for the first time this year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ani Lorak</hi>: Because I participated in the contest only in 2008, I can remember it all: during the promotional tour I visited many countries in which I hadn't been before. I met wonderful people: Dimitris Kontopoulos, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roberto%20Cavalli">Roberto Cavalli</ref>; I made new friends and supporters. <hi rend="italic">[Editor's note: Roberto Cavalli designed the diamond dress Ani Lorak wore during her Eurovision performance.]</hi> I had to work very diligently to get the result [I got]. </p>
<p>In Eurovision I found the heart of this contest. The "Artistic Award", which [they] usually hand to the best artist of the contest, [was given to me]; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raffaella%20Carrà">Raffaella Carrà</ref> invited me to her television program in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Italy">Italy</ref>, and my tours took me further and further away geographically. I really liked the atmosphere of [the] contest. All the contestants were friendly, happy, helped each other, and supported one another. Those weeks were not simple, but very happy in my life. </p>
<p>I wish to all the participants lots of inspiration, tenacity, crazy energy, hard work and belief in yourself and your strength. It is not unachievable; the main thing is to settle for being frank and sincere to the audience.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The music videos for this year are up at <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/eurovision">youtube.com/eurovision</ref>. Which songs are your favorites and which country do you think has the best chance of winning?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ani Lorak</hi>: I can say one thing – Eurovision is a very unpredictable contest, and to do any predictions is very difficult. I know that in Moscow this year there will be many very well-known professional artists: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sakis%20Rouvas">Sakis Rouvas</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patricia%20Kaas">Patricia Kaas</ref>. The main thing in this contest is to enter the scene and present for your country 200%. I wish good luck to all participants, but I'll root, as a patriot, for my country.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What goals have you not achieved yet in your career, but would like to eventually?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ani Lorak</hi>: We have a <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/proverb">proverb</ref>: "If you want God to laugh, then tell Him about your plans." It’s important to have enough strength for my professional accomplishments, for my career, and for my eventual creative achievements. But all this must go together with my personal life. I want to realize my self-worth in all spheres. Maybe I’ll open my own clothing line.</p>
<p>But most importantly for me, every day I will raise the bar with regard to my professional development as a singer and artist. The main point – I have everything ahead of me, and I will go to [any lengths to] achieve my dreams — my <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy%20Award">Oscar</ref> is yet to come!</p>
</text>
