<text id="autogum_interview_doc1351" title="part1_Van Canto's Stefan Schmidt on a capella metal, Wacken, Nightwish, piracy & more" shortTile="partvan-cantos-stefan" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-09" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Van_Canto%27s_Stefan_Schmidt_on_a_capella_metal%2C_Wacken%2C_Nightwish%2C_piracy_%26_more" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<list type="unordered"><item>Before you got your world signing, you changed drummers. Is the previous drummer still involved in any way with the band?</item></list>
<p>Yes, Strilli is still a friend of the band. Van canto first was planned as a studio project among friends. We didn’t expect it to turn out that successful. So Strilli joined the band for recordings and the video shoot although he had I think 4 or 5 bands at that time. When van canto seemed to demand more time, he decided to focus on other projects. It was not a problem for us, because he told us early and still managed to play all shows with us until we had our new drummer</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>How did you select his replacement?</item></list>
<p>Bastian is my long time band mate since 12 years now. We played together in all our bands, only interrupted by the first van canto year, when he lived in China for one year. After he returned he was the first and only choice to follow up Strilli.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>When <hi rend="italic">A Storm to Come</hi> was first released, did you expect the rapid success you subsequently received?</item></list>
<p>To be honest, from time to time we hoped it, but didn’t expect it. If you put that much time in a personal hobby and you notice that the result, the first songs, sound really great, of course you hope that other people like it as well. But the fact that we receive that much positive feedback in shortest time, without any support from a company or management makes us very happy. It shows that metal still works, there are thousands of people out there waiting for new music, fanzine authors working hours and hours on reviews and interviews without getting any money for it. It’s unbelievably great.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>How did you come to be selected for the Nightwish tour at such an early stage in the band's career? How did they discover you?</item></list>
<p>We got in touch with our current record company in April 2007. They managed to get in contact with the booking company of the “on a dark winter’s night”-performances. So we weren’t actually chosen by Nightwish themselves, and it was only for two shows, but nevertheless this was great.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do you feel being associated with them has given or will give your popularity a boost?</item></list>
<p>Of course! We played in front of 15.000 People within 24 hours and every magazine was there to see the first show of the new Nightwish singer in Germany. This was a great experience for us and the audience welcomed us very kindly.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>How easy or hard was it to get your world record deal? Did you see a lot of rejection beforehand, or was it fairly straightforward having by then shown the industry you were serious?</item></list>
</text>
