<text id="autogum_interview_doc353" title="Wikinews interviews Stephen Murphy about the upcoming by-election in the Higgins electorate of the Australian parliament" shortTile="wikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-12-01" dateModified="2014-06-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Stephen_Murphy_about_the_upcoming_by-election_in_the_Higgins_electorate_of_the_Australian_parliament" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Stephen Murphy about the upcoming by-election in the Higgins electorate of the Australian parliament</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 1, 2009</hi></p>
<p>With two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/by-election">by-elections</ref> coming up in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref>, many minor parties and independents will be looking to gain a seat in the House of Representatives. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen%20Murphy">Stephen Murphy</ref> is one of the independents.</p>
<p>Mr Murphy is a computer programmer from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melbourne">Melbourne</ref> suburb of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brunswick,%20Victoria">Brunswick</ref>. </p>
<p>"After growing up in South-East Melbourne I studied Science at Monash with first class Honours, worked in Europe for 10 years and have recently returned to Australia. I work in finance as a computer programmer and speak five languages," Mr Murphy said.</p>
<p>Wikinews reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:RockerballAustralia">Patrick Gillett</ref> held an exclusive email interview with Mr Murphy, candidate for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Division%20of%20Higgins">Division of Higgins</ref>.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why do you want to get into parliament?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Stephen Murphy:</hi> I am standing up for what I believe is the correct course of action on the biggest issue in Australian politics in 100 years - Kevin Rudd's flawed emissions trading scheme (ETS).</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What would the three main policies you are taking into this by-election be?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SM:</hi> I will oppose the emissions trading scheme, ensure that all government policy is based on accurate scientific evidence and return common sense to Canberra</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How would you address these policies?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SM:</hi> By asking for a Royal Commission into climate change so that the facts (such as that global warming stopped in 2001 and the emissions trading scheme will not change the climate one bit) are openly presented to the Australian people.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Sending asylum seekers to Indonesia: good or bad?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SM:</hi> Any government policy that does not properly consider all implications (be it emissions trading, or any other issue) is a bad one.</p>
<figure><caption>File photo: Loy Yang Power Station supplies electricity around the Australian state of Victoria.Image: Marcus Wong.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is the Australian dollar's near parity with the US dollar a sign that the Australian economy is healthy, the US economy in chaos or both?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SM:</hi> It's a sign of both. Many countries around the world look with envy at how well (relatively) Australia is doing, to our credit! It is of concern that the American economy is in such bad shape and that their levels of debt seem unsustainable.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How do you rate the governments economic stimulus package?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SM:</hi> The economic stimulus package was poorly targeted and poorly carried out. When we could have been building roads, dams, railways and hospitals yet instead we were paying for tattoos, PlayStations and overseas holidays.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Should it be wound back?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SM:</hi> The question about levels of stimulus spending is a complicated one and requires expertise in economics, however one could say in general terms that all government spending should be well targeted and spent in the most efficient way.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is Kevin Rudd a better Prime Minister than John Howard?'</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SM:</hi> Australian voters are the best judge of that and we will know in 2019:)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is the Carbon Pollution Reduction Scheme an effective solution to climate change? Why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SM:</hi> Absolutely not. The CPRS will not change the climate by any amount that we can measure - it's just a new tax that will hurt Australians and drive businesses and jobs overseas. Since 2003 there has been mountains of new scientific data which contradicts the popular theory that human carbon dioxide emissions are causing significant global warming. Recently, many of the scientists who wrote the IPCC report (on which the ETS / CPRS is based) have been reported as manipulating scientific data to create scary global warming scenarios. The science is definitely not settled</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is there a better solution?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SM:</hi> We can very easily refocus the momentum and goodwill that has been generated on climate change and channel this energy into other worthwhile environmental projects in Australia that will make a difference.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why should the electorate vote for you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SM:</hi> I will oppose the ETS and support responsible environmental policies instead of radical environmental policies that could end up costing every Australian taxpayer $4550 per year in new taxes.</p>
</text>
