<text id="autogum_interview_doc1071" title="part3_Vivien Goldman: An interview with the Punk Professor" shortTile="partvivien-goldman" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-30" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vivien_Goldman%3A_An_interview_with_the_Punk_Professor" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I felt it was what it was at a certain moment, but it wasn't that anymore.  They were charging eight dollars for a beer.  That's not very punk, and that wasn't attracting the punk crowds.  It was like people who move to the Bowery because they think it's so edgy but it's really a  boulevard of glittering condos. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nostalgie pour la boue</hi>: nostalgia for the mud.  Not all of them, though.  Patti Smith.  Anyway, the spirit had moved on to Williamsburg.</p>
<figure><caption>"They are flushing out the artists.  Manhattan is now a ghetto for the very rich."</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where do you think New York's culture is going?  There are so few places on Earth with such a large concentration of creatives who meet and influence each other, but the city is becoming less affordable and cleansed of any grit.  Is there a place for punk in the Manhattan of the future?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  They are flushing out the artists.  Manhattan is now a ghetto for the very rich.  When punk started it was in weird places, places you broke into and that had never been used for shows.  It was never in regular venues, but now every nook and cranny is a regular venue and it doesn't leave much space for the old punk spirit.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ABC%20No%20Rio">ABC No Rio</ref>, I think they manage to work it in the system.  And there are places like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Stone">The Stone</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Zorn">John Zorn</ref>'s place, which has avant-garde free form jazz.  He subsidizes that place, so it remains a little haven.  There are a few little pockets, but it has a lot do with the rent.  Realistically, there's loads of stuff happening in places like Brooklyn, more than there seems to be in Manhattan.  When I jammed with The Slits, that happened at some after-hours thing in Brooklyn in some warehouse.  I remember loads of things in funny places.  The first time I heard Public Enemy I was on the rooftop of a building.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You're friends with Flava Flav, right?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi> Yes, although I haven't seen him in a very long time.  I remember how I met him.  I was doing this video for <hi rend="italic">I Ain't No Joke</hi> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erik%20B%20and%20Rakim">Erik B and Rakim</ref>, and they weren't very vibey in terms of the stagecraft, as it were.  The projection.  Not to diss anybody, but I needed someone to bring a bit more life into it; it was very low-budget, a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cinéma%20vérité">vérité</ref></hi> kind of shoot. We were in a playground in the projects and there were all these blokes hanging around, and there was one who was super-sprightly, like a live wire.  I didn't know it was Flava Flav and I shouted out, <hi rend="italic">Hey, you, will you come over and be groovy for us?</hi> and he did and a lot of the action in the video is Flava Flav spinning around, doing a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dervish">Dervish</ref> in the middle of the playground.</p>
</text>
