<text id="autogum_interview_doc1341" title="part0_Interview with Anna Mikkola, Finnish Left Alliance candidate for European Parliament" shortTile="partinterview-anna" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-05-28" dateModified="2014-01-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Anna_Mikkola%2C_Finnish_Left_Alliance_candidate_for_European_Parliament" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with Anna Mikkola, Finnish Left Alliance candidate for European Parliament</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 29, 2009</hi>
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Anna_Mikkola.jpg">File:Anna Mikkola.jpg</ref></p><figure><caption>Anna Mikkola<hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Anna_Mikkola.jpg">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=File%3AAnna+Mikkola.jpg">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure><p>Anna Mikkola is running for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finland%20(European%20Parliament%20constituency)">European Parliament in</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Finland">Finland</ref> as a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/eco-socialism">eco-socialist</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Left%20Alliance%20(Finland)">Left Alliance</ref> party. At the age of 28 she's the youngest member of the 14 candidates on the Left Alliance's list for the multi-national body. She spoke to <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> during a break in campaigning. Finland votes in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Parliament">European Parliament</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European%20Parliament%20election,%202009%20(Finland)">election</ref> on June 7.</p>
<figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure><p><hi rend="bold">Thanks for joining us, Anna.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Thanks for asking. I had a convenient break in the campaign this afternoon.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You're the youngest member of your party's list in the Euro elections; but you've also had an extensive career in politics already. How did you first get involved in political activity?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I believe I was 16 or 17 at the time, and I just stopped by at the local party office and asked if there was something I could do. There had just been a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finnish%20parliamentary%20election,%201999">general election in Finland</ref> and the conservatives widely spoke of things I could not accept. Like [how] public financing for culture and sports is unnecessary. One politician even suggested young people could spend their time climbing trees and not expect society to provide them with facilities.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">So from there you went straight into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Left%20Youth%20(Finland)">Left Youth</ref>. How did you choose that party? Did you explore others?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> It was between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%20League">Green party</ref> and the Left Alliance. The Greens I felt concentrated too much on individual life style choices as a method of doing politics, so I chose the Left Alliance. I have always been the sort of person who likes to think of structures and their effects, the big picture in a social sense if you may.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">So what's it like campaigning for a nationally-elected office? Is it like organizing youth locally or does it feel basically different?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Basically different. The whole country is one constituency, which means more traveling than most people do in a year. It's also expensive as in our election system candidates have to buy their way into public knowledge. Luckily I have both an extensive election team covering the whole country and also some financial support from the Left Youth movement.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You mentioned last night waiting for a bus and seeing three with pictures of you on the side pass by...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> It's kind of absurd. I have ads in public transport in the 6 biggest cities in Finland. You are definetely more conscious of yourself when you're traveling on a bus or tram that has your face on it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Now, Finland's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foreign%20relations%20of%20Finland">role in the world</ref> has fundamentally changed in your lifetime: from a neutral state with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finlandization">closer ties to the Soviet Union</ref> than many others in democratic Europe, to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Union">EU</ref> member and now potentially to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NATO">NATO</ref> member. Do you think your youth makes it easier for you to adapt to the changes going on?</hi></p>
</text>
