<text id="autogum_interview_doc415" title="part0_Canada&amp;apos;s Don Valley West (Ward 26) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-don-valley" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Don_Valley_West_%28Ward_26%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Canada's Don Valley West (Ward 26) city council candidates speak</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 3, 2006</hi></p>
<p>On November 13, Torontonians will be heading to the polls to vote for their ward's councillor and for mayor. Among Toronto's ridings is Don Valley West (Ward 26). Four candidates responded to Wikinews' requests for an interview. This ward's candidates include Muhammad Alam, Bahar Aminvaziri, Orhan Aybars, Michele Carroll-Smith, Mohamed Dhanani, Abdul Ingar, <hi rend="bold">Geoff Kettel</hi>, Debbie Lechter, <hi rend="bold">Natalie Maniates</hi>, John Masterson, <hi rend="bold">John Parker</hi>, David Thomas, <hi rend="bold">Csaba Vegh</hi>, and Fred Williams.</p>
<p>For more information on the election, read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto%20municipal%20election,%202006">Toronto municipal election, 2006</ref>.</p>
<head id="Geoff_Kettel"><ref target="http://www.geoffkettel.ca/">Geoff Kettel</ref></head>
<p>58-year-old <hi rend="bold">Geoff Kettel</hi> is a public administrator.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.
<list type="unordered"><item>Development in residential areas in Leaside and Bennington and Wynford/ Concorde</item>
<item>Public safety, tenant issues and property standards in Thorncliffe Park  and Flemingdon Park</item>
<item>Future use of the Leaside industrial area</item></list></p>
<p>For other issues please go to the web site www.geoffkettel.ca</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The need to engage all communities and ensure fair representation of the whole ward.  I will work with the community to build a city that is safe, green and healthy, and  responsibly manage the City's finances</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I want to build a city that is safe, green and healthy and to responsibly manage the city's finances.</p>
<p>The municipal councillor is in a unique position to effect positive change due to working at the order of government that is the closest to the citizens</p>
<p>I am qualified for the job having 25 years of community service in Ward 26 and 30 years of public service in the Ontario government.  My record of community service includes being:</p>
<p>Chair of the East York Board of Health and champion of the East York smoke free bylaws;</p>
<p>Chair of a not for profit housing corporation which created 120 units of seniors housing in Leaside so folks could stay in the community they love;</p>
<p>Chair of the Jenner Jean-Marie community centre in Thorncliffe Park and champion for its recently announced expansion to meet the needs of a growing community.</p>
<p>And in public service my record includes being Chief Financial Officer for Ontairo public health responsible for a $1 billion budget</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> In my view it is essential that the councillor live in the Ward they represent. I have lived in the Ward for 25 years.  As a result of living in and being involved in the community I am very knowledgeable about the Ward, its history, geography and economy etc.</p>
</text>
