<text id="autogum_interview_doc172" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Andy Martin, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-07-28" dateModified="2015-08-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Andy_Martin%2C_U.S._Republican_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Andy Martin, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 8, 2011</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Andy Martin Image: Andy Martin.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">U.S. Republican Party</ref> presidential candidate <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Andy_Martin_(politician)">Andy Martin</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Illinois">Illinois</ref> took some time to answer a few questions from <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter William S. Saturn. </p>
<p>Martin has questioned the validity of the birth certificate released by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States">U.S. President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>, and is best known for his role in the spreading of rumors that Obama is a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islam">Muslim</ref>. According to CNN, Martin has retracted the Muslim claim and now believes that Obama was fathered by journalist and labor activist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank%20Marshall%20Davis">Frank Marshall Davis</ref> rather than <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kenya">Kenyan</ref> economist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barack%20Obama,%20Sr.">Barack Obama, Sr.</ref>. He also believes that the Obama presidency has been a failure and has asked for Obama to resign.</p>
<p>Martin has run for an assortment of public offices in the past and has previously mounted two presidential campaigns. During the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%201988">1988 election</ref>, he vied unsuccessfully for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democratic Party</ref>'s presidential nomination, and in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202000">2000</ref>, he again fell short of winning the nomination of the Republican Party. </p>
<p>In other areas, Martin has filed numerous lawsuits, some reportedly with anti-Jewish language. This has caused some commentators such as former White House Press Secretary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20Gibbs">Robert Gibbs</ref> to label Martin as an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antisemitism">anti-Semite</ref>. Martin vehemently denies the charge. He has also taken legal action against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref>, which he feels is a propaganda arm of the Obama administration.</p>
<p>While focusing his presidential campaign in the first-in-the-nation primary state of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Hampshire">New Hampshire</ref>, Martin has largely emphasized local issues. On national issues, he has taken <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conservatism%20in%20the%20United%20States">conservative</ref> stances, as documented on his campaign website and blog.</p>
<head id="Barack_Obama_and_the_birther_movement">Barack Obama and the birther movement</head>
<p>According to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_New_York_Times">The New York Times</ref></hi>, Martin first spread the 'Obama is a Muslim' rumor via press release following then-Senate candidate Obama's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2004%20Democratic%20National%20Convention%20keynote%20address">2004 keynote address</ref> to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2004%20Democratic%20National%20Convention">Democratic National Convention</ref>. Amid the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2008">2008 presidential election</ref>, Martin traveled to Hawaii to investigate Obama, who was at the time, the Democratic Party nominee for president. In October 2008, he filed a lawsuit against the state to release Obama's birth certificate, but it was dismissed by the courts. After returning from the trip, Martin announced that he believed Frank Marshall Davis was Obama's biological father.</p>
<p>Martin has been a fierce critic of the Obama administration and held a press conference on August 5 to call for the resignation of both Obama and Vice President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Joe_Biden">Joe Biden</ref>. He proposed that a "caretaker administration" be put in place until the 2012 election, with Senate Majority Leader <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Harry_Reid">Harry Reid</ref> as president and a Republican as vice president.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">You have been one of the leading proponents of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barack%20Obama%20citizenship%20conspiracy%20theories">movement questioning the citizenship</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>.  What are your views on the long-form document recently released by the White House?</hi></item></list>
</text>
