<text id="autogum_interview_doc1117" title="part2_Murray Hill on the life and versatility of a New York drag king" shortTile="partmurray-hill-life" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Murray_Hill_on_the_life_and_versatility_of_a_New_York_drag_king" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They say all really great comedians they honed their craft through personal tragedy.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  I agree with most of that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Does that apply to you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  There’s different ways to react to things, and you could be depressed and upset, or you can go another direction.  Comedy got me out of the gutter and got me positive.  It makes people happy.  I think a lot comedians are very negative, angry, bitter people.  I don’t know if you have ever spent any time in the comedy scene.  They can be brutal, on stage and off.  I’m taking a different route than those performers.  It’s important to me that I’m a non-threatening character.  People are more accepting.  Because of that I’ve had a lot of opportunity in my career.  Showbiz!</p>
<head id="Murray_Hill_the_person">Murray Hill the person</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who have you patterned your persona of Murray Hill after?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  It came across naturally.  I was recently at a family funeral—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  As Murray Hill?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  No, half and half.  I have an uncle who I knew growing up.  Dead ringer to Murray!  I’m half Italian.  My grandfather and my father are pretty much the spirit of Murray, this <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriarchal">patriarchal</ref>-yet-warm character.  Roly-poly.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Does your family accept you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  That’s a long story.  I’ll answer it saying I moved out when I was 18 and I have not gone back.  But my Dad died so I did go back for that, and that was the first time in fifteen years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How was the reaction?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  I don’t talk about that much.  It’s still new.  A lot of where my work comes from in a human standpoint is that I came from a very conservative background and intense place.  It’s very important me to have the complete opposite in my shows.  I accept everybody in my shows and I’m very positive.  And—something I look up to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RuPaul">RuPaul</ref> about—is visibility.  It’s so important today to be visible, to be out there, and take up space, to show people they have no reason to have fear.  RuPaul was on TV in the 1990s, and I’ve been trying to get on TV and people are still worried, and it’s been twenty years.  I’ve been the first drag king—if you have to use the word—to do many things.  I performed for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penelope%20Cruz">Penelope Cruz</ref>.  The first to be on television.  I really believe there is a place for us.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you do when you’re not doing show business?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  I got hooked on a new game: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/bowling">bowling</ref>.  There’s a bowling alley near my house.  I’m into this new game called Speedmitton.  I actually exercise.  Then I watch <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean%20Martin">Dean Martin</ref> DVDs.  I have all of his shows on DVD from those late-night commercials.  Have you seen those, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don%20Rickles">Don Rickles</ref>?  I bought them.  I was that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/schmuck">schmuck</ref> at 3:00 in the morning I bought the whole damn set and they are still coming in the mail!</p>
</text>
