<text id="autogum_interview_doc581" title="Wikinews interviews Australian disability standing skier Jonty O&amp;apos;Callaghan" shortTile="wikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-14" dateModified="2017-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_disability_standing_skier_Jonty_O%27Callaghan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Australian disability standing skier Jonty O'Callaghan</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 17, 2012</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Wikinews reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:LauraHale">LauraHale</ref> interviews Australian Paralympic skier Jonty O'Callaghan</caption></figure>
<p>Recently, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> spent time with with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paralympics">Paralympic</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Para-alpine_skiing">skier</ref> Jonty O'Clallaghan who was in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Copper_Mountain_(Colorado)">Copper Mountain</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Colorado">Colorado</ref> for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Paralympic_Committee">IPC</ref> Nor-Am Cup.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I'm interviewing Jonty O'Callaghan, one of the Australian skiers with the IPC [<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Paralympic_Committee">International Paralympic Committee</ref>] Nor-Am Cup, and you're a fifteen-year-old?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jonty O'Callaghan:</hi> Yup. Yeah, I've been skiing since I was about ten and I really enjoy racing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I talked to your father, he said you're <hi rend="italic">kind of</hi> thinking <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2014_Winter_Paralympics">Sochi</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jonty O'Callaghan:</hi> It's the matter of if I qualify by getting enough good races and points.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How do you balance skiing with doing school?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jonty O'Callaghan:</hi> Over the past few years in Australia I've been doing full time in tenth grade in the Australian winter, which means the school at the mountain brings up my work from my home school in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Melbourne">Melbourne</ref> to do up at the mountain when I'm not skiing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Since you're not on the development team, do you get enough support or your parents are supporting this?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jonty O'Callaghan:</hi> Yeah, my parents support me all the way. I've never doubted their support always though the journeys and I [thank them] for their support throughout and continuing through my journeys.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Para-alpine%20skiing%20classification">classification</ref> are you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jonty O'Callaghan:</hi> I am <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LW9">LW9-1</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What does that mean for people who know nothing about classification?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jonty O'Callaghan:</hi> I basically have a disability on the right side of my body.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yep.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jonty O'Callaghan:</hi> which weakens two of my limbs and which means I favor my left side a lot more.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Did you have that from birth?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jonty O'Callaghan:</hi> Yeah, it was caused by premature birth.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you do any other sports anything other than skiing or are you one of those Australian ski bunnies?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jonty O'Callaghan:</hi> I've done a lot of sports doing my journey, I've always played <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cricket">cricket</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australian_football">Australian football</ref>, played a little <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tennis">tennis</ref>, and I like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Golf">golf</ref> too as a hobby.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Are you going to and be one of those dual Paralympians for Winter and Summer? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jonty O'Callaghan:</hi> No, because I don't think any other sports I like are in the Summer Olympics. I think I'll pursue them after I finished my skiing career, because cricket you can do when you're much older.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Is there anything else people should know about you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jonty O'Callaghan:</hi> Yeah, I'm just looking forward to the future and hoping for the best and maybe some medals.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Okay cool, thank you very much.</p>
<figure><caption>Jonty O'Callaghan at Solitude Station on Copper Mountain Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Bidgee">Bidgee</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Jonty O'Callaghan at an awards ceremony IPC Nor-Am Cup Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:LauraHale">LauraHale</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Jonty O'Callaghan competing in the slalom during the last day of the IPC Nor-Am Cup Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Bidgee">Bidgee</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Australian Paralympic skier Jonty O'Callaghan in his first run earlier today Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:LauraHale">LauraHale</ref>.</caption></figure>
</text>
