<text id="autogum_interview_doc450" title="part4_US presidential candidate Duncan Hunter speaks to Wikinews" shortTile="partus-presidential" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-12" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_presidential_candidate_Duncan_Hunter_speaks_to_Wikinews" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Isn’t that just conjecture?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  No, it’s not conjecture at all.  Natanz has been—the arms teams have been there and they have counted the centrifuges and they are operating at full speed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> But there is no evidence that they are making any weapons with them, correct?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  No, they are producing the powder, the explosive material that is used in a nuclear device, which is the most difficult part to obtain.  So they are proceeding at full pace with a part of a nuclear device.  So the question to ask the Iranian is, “Why are you doing this?”  There is no good answer.  I think it is misleading to say they have stopped <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuclear%20program%20of%20Iran">their arms program</ref>.  They haven’t stopped that part of it.</p>
<head id="Terrorism:_the_greatest_threat_to_humanity">Terrorism: the greatest threat to humanity</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What do you think is the greatest threat to humanity?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  The production or the securing of a weapon of mass destruction.  There are several species of threats, but I would say in terms of the war against terrorist—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You think terrorism is the greatest threat to humanity?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  No, I’m going to give you several broad categories, and then I want to give you a sub-category.  But if look at the terrorist threat, which I think right now is perhaps the greatest imminent threat that we have, the securing of a nuclear device or another weapon of mass destruction, and its detonation in a large population center,</p>
<p>I think that’s the greatest—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Are you for nuclear non-proliferation, then?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Well, I’m for nuclear non-proliferation to terrorist groups, and for technology control.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What is technology control?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  It means controlling the subsystems that can be utilized to develop a weapon of mass destruction.  You have technology control with respect to chemical and biological weapons, but also nuclear weapons.  So you have a regime that includes the nuclear suppliers group, you have several international constructs to keep those systems from getting into the wrong hands.  So technology control is a very important aspect of securing and preventing the acquisition of nuclear weapons capability by a terrorist group or a terrorist state.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Do you think we should begin entering into agreements with other countries to disarm the nuclear arsenal worldwide?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  No, I don’t think the United States should eliminate our nuclear arsenal because I think that manifests a deterrent against others who might move aggressively against the United States at some point, or might move aggressively against our allies.  I think there is a deterrent factor to having a nuclear weapons capability for the United States, which I would describe as a responsible nuclear state.  Nor do I worry about Great Britain’s, nor do I worry about France’s.  But what I would do is everything possible to prevent a regime with nuclear technology from falling into the hands of those who would use it irresponsibly, and that would include of course Iran, obvious North Korea, which has some nuclear devices, and other countries.</p>
</text>
