<text id="autogum_interview_doc664" title="part7_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It hasn't affected you then?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I wish it had! It hasn't. It hasn't affected you either. It hasn't affected anybody!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's affected me.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  It's affected you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Every single person I interview I ask about the war because I think it's important and it has affected me.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Then you must have a human spirit unmatched since <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Billy%20Graham">Billy Graham</ref> made his first speech! I mean you have to have a real conscience, social conscience, to care. Where are the protests coming out of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivy%20League">Ivy League</ref> or the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Alabama">University of Alabama</ref>? They're not there because there's no conscription. There should be conscription. There should be a draft. There should be. Everybody should serve.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That's what <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles%20Rangel">Charles Rangel</ref> says.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  He's the only voice in Congress that ever said that and he said it five years ago. I don't know of any other voice. I am not aware of another member of the Congress who said what Rangel said. Not one. Certainly not these candidates, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hillary%20Clinton">Clinton</ref> and the rest of them. Because why? Because they know it would stop the war in an hour. Because then we would have involvement. Right now what's the involvement? The ridiculous stickers, ‘Support Your Troops' on the back of an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SUV">SUV</ref>? The cost of gas matters not at all. Nobody sacrifices.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That's the only thing that does seem to motivate people to be against the war is to be paying more at the gas pump.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  They don't care. Don't care. There's no sacrifice. Americans are unaffected, except those in the military or related to military people, doesn't matter... I go out. I mean, yes you can have conversations at dinner parties about this, but it's very political. It's about whether <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20McCain">McCain</ref> says this or Hillary says this and what's the position of somebody in the defense department. That's all bullshit. Really nobody cares.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Does it bother you that there's a lack of outrage?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Yes it does. It does bother me. And it does bother me that the poor people who need money join the National Guard Reserves because they needed that money or they want to go to college. What most bothers me are the college students – the worst generation is what I call them. These college students are the worst and I've been to a lot of campuses. I taught last year at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Southern%20California">USC</ref>. I always go to USC in the spring in April every year. I go for a week or so. And I hang around. Across from the campus, there's a motel I stay in. College students are always hanging around there. And I was, this year, at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Pennsylvania">University of Pennsylvania</ref> and I was at the University of Alabama, and I've been to a number of campuses this year and nobody cares about this war.</p>
</text>
