<text id="autogum_interview_doc1122" title="part0_Dalai Lama's representative talks about China, Tibet, Shugden and the next Dalai Lama" shortTile="partdalai-lamas-representative" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-13" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dalai_Lama%27s_representative_talks_about_China%2C_Tibet%2C_Shugden_and_the_next_Dalai_Lama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Dalai Lama's representative talks about China, Tibet, Shugden and the next Dalai Lama</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 14, 2007</hi></p>
<p>Kasur <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tashi%20Wangdi">Tashi Wangdi</ref> was appointed Representative of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dalai_Lama">Dalai Lama</ref> to the Americas on April 16, 2005.  He had previously served as His Holiness' representative in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Delhi">New Delhi</ref>.  He has served the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tibet">Tibetan</ref> government-in-exile since 1966, starting as a junior officer and rising to the highest rank of Kalon (Cabinet Minister). As a Kalon, he at one time or another was head of the major ministries, including the Department of Religion and Culture, Department of Home, Department of Education, Department of Information and International Relations, Department of Security, and Department of Health.  He is not a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Buddhism">Buddhist</ref> scholar but describes himself as a civil servant.  He possesses a BA in Political Science and Sociology from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Durham%20University">Durham University</ref>.  </p>
<p>Wikinews reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> recently spoke to him about Chinese-Tibetan relations, the status of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panchen%20Lama">Panchen Lamas</ref>, the awarding of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Congressional%20Gold%20Medal">Congressional Gold Medal</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenzin%20Gyatso,%2014th%20Dalai%20Lama">Tenzin Gyatso</ref>, the 14th and current Dalai Lama, the appointment of Tibetan high monks by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">Chinese</ref> government and some of the Dalai Lama's views on topics on religions and societal topics.  </p>
<head id="The_Office_of_Tibet_and_the_Tibetan_government_in_exile">The Office of Tibet and the Tibetan government in exile</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  What is this office's relationship with the government in exile?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tashi Wangdi:</hi>  I am the Representative of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/14th%20Dalai%20Lama">Dalai Lama</ref>.  We look after Tibetan affairs in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_America">North</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_America">South America</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you essentially an embassy without a country?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Professor%20Venerable%20Samdhong%20Rinpoche">Professor Venerable Samdhong Rinpoche</ref> was elected the head of the Tibetan Administration cabinet--effectively a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/prime%20minister">prime minister</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central%20Tibetan%20Administration">Central Tibetan Administration</ref>, the government-in-exile?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Ever since <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/His%20Holiness">His Holiness</ref> held leadership responsibilities at the age of 16 when he was in Tibet, he wanted to bring about social political reforms.  He started those reforms in Tibet.  Because of the Chinese invasion and the problem thereafter with the occupation, he could not get through the reforms he wanted to implement.  Then in 1959, when the situation went beyond a solution and he had to leave Tibet, as soon as he went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dharamsala">India</ref> he continued with the reform and promulgated a draft Constitution.  A parliament was elected by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tibetan%20diaspora">Tibetans in exile</ref>.  He then brought about gradual changes for the democratization of the system.  The political leadership is now elected.  We have had a parliament in existence since 1961 and seven years ago we elected a Prime Minister.  His Holiness describes himself as semi-retired.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Retired from administrative functions?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes.  The governing responsibility is now carried out by the elected political leadership.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The Dalai Lama exists as a spiritual leader and essentially a figurehead, similar to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Queen_Elizabeth_II">Queen Elizabeth</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  As you know, we are not seeking independence, but it’s more about the future of Tibet.</p>
</text>
