<text id="autogum_interview_doc1451" title="part3_Interview with Jimbo Wales" shortTile="partinterview-jimbo" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-12-05" dateModified="2018-05-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Jimbo_Wales" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Do you think having an open fundraiser will bring in more or less money than having a fundraiser with a definite goal? Why do you think so?</p>
<p>[JWales] I think that having an open fundraiser will bring in more money, for two reasons.</p>
<p>First, I think people have often looked at the pace of the fundraising and the amount being raised, and made a decision not to give based on the fact that we seemed to be meeting our goal.</p>
<p>Second, I just go by the general behavior of other large charities, which often have open fund drives. I assume they do so for a good reason. In any event, we should try it and see.</p>
<p>But is there a reason to call it a "drive" at all if there is no goal?</p>
<p>[JWales] I often think that, as Wikipedians, we project our own ways of thinking onto our audience. We are the sort of people who look closely at budgets and think about goals and achievability. That's great for us. But a lot of people are ready to trust us and will respond better to our big picture vision. They don't care to know in grand detail (though of course we will always stand ready to tell them) where every penny is going. They respond, instead, to an appeal to the aesthetic beauty of our project.</p>
<p>The fundraiser is very low-key, and barely visible. If raising money is so important to the future of the project, why doesn't WMF put it front and center, giving it real space and bandwidth on the main pages and even article pages?</p>
<p>[JWales] Well, we do that during the actual fund drive, but we're hopelessly tasteful of course, so I doubt we will ever be too horribly glaring about it.:-)</p>
<p>The current fundraiser is manually updated, takes place exclusively online, and so on. It's rather like a high school prom fundraiser in the USA. Have you considered developing an integrated campaign with feedback, for example automating a graph of the funds raised and tracking the donations across countries and currencies?</p>
<p>[JWales] Yes, we would love to have a fancier system. It is my feeling that we're going to have to pay for the development of such a system, because volunteer developers are (quite rightly) more interested in more intellectually challenging programming issues. So part of why we need to raise money is so we can be more efficient about raising money in the future.</p>
<p>You have become a cause célèbre, and famous with the rise of the Wikipedia project. Are you using your celebrity to encourage the rich and famous people you’ve come in contact with to make donations?</p>
</text>
