<text id="autogum_interview_doc358" title="part4_Creator of website satirizing Glenn Beck on winning domain name case" shortTile="partcreator-website" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-11-09" dateModified="2019-02-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Creator_of_website_satirizing_Glenn_Beck_on_winning_domain_name_case" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>The sad thing is - the American people are losing in this battle. Republicans are fighting against government interference in business; Democrats are (or should be) fighting against business interference in government. Ultimately, though, special interests are pumping so much money into the political scene that it seems the voice of the People is lost in the noise of business.</p>
<p>It seems that the media - especially the television media - have long ago figured out that the way to make their businesses work (which, being commercial entities, they must, of course, do as well as they can) requires ratings. Ratings require getting people to watch. Getting people to watch requires controversy. And so, people like Glenn Beck - among many others - rise to become stars, because they can get ratings, which ultimately boil down to money. The problem is that truth and compromise are boring, but exaggeration and controversy are exciting.</p>
<p>When I saw the thread on Fark, where one of the posters, in a thread about Sarah Palin announcing her support for Glenn Beck, said, "Why haven't we had an official response to the rumor that Glenn Beck raped and murdered a girl in 1990?" -- I didn't think too much of the post by itself; but in the thread, it immediately took off. A bunch of people ran with it and it became a hit in that thread. It was actually the next day when I saw this thread - and so many people had said so many funny things... it was like a relief
valve had opened up and all this pent up frustration was flowing out.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Why did you decide to create the website "www.glennbeckrapedandmurderedayounggirlin1990.com"?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">E-H</hi>: There was so much energy in the Fark thread where the meme got its start. I felt that it was something worth continuing; that the frustration that was
being expressed in that thread through the expression of the meme might actually become a force for change. And even if it didn't manage to change anything, just the simple act of being a part of the meme might bring about a cathartic release of that frustration at all the stupidity of the pundits out there - of whom I think that Glenn Beck is really the worst of the worst.</p>
<p>The thing about Fark is - it's a great site, but it's all based on these threads. Someone submits a link, and that gives you a thread to talk about it. After something like 30 days, posting is cut off. Also, the site is made up of a lot of links for the public threads, but many times that for the private threads. It can be very hard to keep up with a single thread. So I realized that if this meme were to take off - it needed a home. I knew I needed to create a website, and a forum on that website, to facilitate whatever was going to happen.</p>
</text>
