<text id="autogum_interview_doc802" title="part0_Alex Necochea and Bryn Bennett: the &amp;apos;Guitar Heroes&amp;apos; of Bang Camaro" shortTile="partalex-necochea" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-06" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Alex_Necochea_and_Bryn_Bennett%3A_the_%27Guitar_Heroes%27_of_Bang_Camaro" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Alex Necochea and Bryn Bennett: the 'Guitar Heroes' of Bang Camaro</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 8, 2007</hi></p>
<p>When a fan connects with a band, it's often during moments like a drive down a highway at night reflecting on some aspect of his or her life; sitting at home after a fight with a girlfriend; singing in the shower; or celebrating at a party with her friends.  Music becomes a soundtrack to an individual's life, and a connection with the musician forms when the listener is able to peg a perfect moment or feeling to a song.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston,%20Massachusetts">Boston</ref>-based mega-member rock group <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bang%20Camaro">Bang Camaro</ref>'s fan base claims a different level of interaction: they often have <hi rend="italic">learned</hi> to play their music before they ever had a moment associated with it.  Bang Camaro found fame on the video game <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guitar%20Hero%20II">Guitar Hero II</ref></hi>, where an aspiring rock god uses a guitar-shaped peripheral to play rock music as notes scroll towards him on the screen.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> journeyed to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bowery%20Ballroom">Bowery Ballroom</ref> to talk to the two founding members of Bang Camaro, Alex Necochea and Bryn Bennett.  But when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MTV.com"><hi rend="italic">MTV.com</hi></ref> shows up at the same time as <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> to do an interview, the band must split up.  Below is our conversation with Necochea about touring, influence, politics, throwing his corpse out of a plane and flatulent women.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  How's the tour going?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alex Necochea:</hi>  The tours is going great!  We just played in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poughkeepsie">Poughkeepsie</ref> last night with the OCC house band.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Poughkeepsie, huh?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  Yeah! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Poughkeepsie, it's kind of a dark town.  Not much of a built-in crowd there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What kind of crowd is there?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  From what I could tell, we played for a lot of Guitar Hero fans and people who heard about us through friends of friends, or came across us on MySpace.  That sort of thing.  But for the most part a lot of the kids we meet are anywhere between...well, I guess at a club like that they have to be over 18, but usually they are just much younger kids who are video game fans, who have heard about us through Guitar Hero II.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's that like to have a fan base that comes from primarily video games?  Have you noticed a difference between being known as a local band playing in your city and being known through video games?  How would you compare the audience?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  It's different.  In our hometown it started off as just a big word of mouth thing.  We had twenty guys in the band, so everybody had friends-of-friends.  We started a groundswell that way.  But when we get out of town, not in New York so much, but when we go to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicago">Chicago</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milwaukee">Milwaukee</ref> and places like that they generally tend to be much younger people.  It's a really big thrill for Bryn and I in that we are meeting kids who are just like us: young video game fans, aspiring musicians, usually males who picked up guitars.  They come to us and say, 'Nobody plays guitar anymore like you guys do!' or 'My parents used to listen to music like that!'  It's just a big thrill for us to meet young kids like that who remind us of ourselves when we were kids.</p>
</text>
