<text id="autogum_interview_doc291" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Frank McEnulty, independent candidate for US President" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-15" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Frank_McEnulty%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>The world and the United States would be much better off if we weren't all relying on a small region of the world for the lifeblood of our economies.  The only way to bring the price of oil down is to make it less valuable and the only way to do that is to develop alternative energy sources that can replace oil in everyday life. Not only would this be good for the country and for the future, but it would also go a long ways to reducing Greenhouse gas emissions.</p>
<p>For that reason, I am proposing the following Energy Plan for the United States (and the world) in the following 3 steps.</p>
<p>Short Term - Conservation and Alternative Power</p>
<p>Five to Thirty Years - A Strong Nuclear Program</p>
<p>Long Term - We Need New Technologies – A Manhattan Project for Energy Independence</p>
<p>Please see my website at <ref target="http://frankforpresident.org/FRANKemails.htm#email11">http://frankforpresident.org/FRANKemails.htm#email11</ref> for more details on this and other policies my administration will be following.</p>
<p>Second, the next biggest problem facing us now and for generations to come is our fiscal irresponsibility.</p>
<p>There are fewer topics concerning our current political landscape that get me more upset than the fiscal irresponsibility of our Congress and President. As President, I promise to veto any and all bills that include the barrels of pork as discussed below. If we don't get our country back on a footing of fiscal responsibility soon, we are going to leave a bankrupt, second level economy to our children and grandchildren. The President is our leader and he needs to act like one and do what is right for the country now and in the future.</p>
<p>Under the "fiscal restraint" of the Republicans our deficit has ballooned and spending has increased (even ignoring the war in Iraq) at a greater pace than at almost any time in the history of our country. There was the hope and, as we were promised by the Democrats during the last Congressional elections, that they would show some fiscal restraint and get the country back on a path of fiscal responsibility, but the current Congress has shown they can even outspend the spendthrift Republicans.  Without a truly Independent President our spending will never go down as they will always be trying to buy votes for the parties.</p>
<p>Third, the next biggest problem facing us now is illegal immigration.</p>
<p>The facts are simple.  The President and his administration have conspired with the large business and agricultural interests in our country to artificially depress and hold-down wages.  They have done this at a tremendous cost to all law-abiding, tax-paying American citizens and it needs to stop now!   It is also in the process of bankrupting a large number of our states, counties and cities because of the cost of dealing with illegal immigrants and their families.  If the illegal immigration problem had not occurred most state and local governments would be in a financing surplus situation and wages across the board for entry level jobs would be higher.</p>
</text>
