<text id="autogum_interview_doc120" title="part6_Wikinews interviews specialists on China, Iran, Russia support for al-Assad" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-09-15" dateModified="2015-10-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_China%2C_Iran%2C_Russia_support_for_al-Assad" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>File photo of interviewee Stephen Blank. Image: Stephen Blank.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you believe Russia distrusts US intentions in the region — in the sense of countering the West on regime change?</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Blank</hi>: It is clear that Russia not only does not trust US interests and judgment in the Middle East, it regards Washington as too-ready to use force to unseat regimes it does not like and believes these could lead to wars; more importantly, to the attempt to overthrow the present Russian government. That is critical to understanding Moscow's staunch support for Assad.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Martel</hi>: Russia's policymakers understand that American and Russia interests directly diverge. Russia seeks to undermine US geopolitical influence, and increase its own. It is using its support of the Syrian regime to accomplish that objective. American interests, by contrast, are largely to prevent the spread and use of chemical weapons.</item></list>
<p>Appallingly, Russia is supporting Syria despite the fact that all evidence points to Syria's use of chemical weapons.</p>
<p>One would think that American policymakers would be more critical of Russia; which is directly supporting a regime that used poison gas to slaughter its own men, women, and children.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Farhi</hi>: It is less about trust and more about protection of geopolitical interests and prevention of even more dire consequences if Assad goes. It is true that Russia feels that the United States and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NATO">NATO</ref> went beyond the mandate afforded to them by the UN Security Council in going after regime change in Libya.</item></list>
<p>However, Russia's geopolitical, and economic, interests in Syria are much more important; and, the relationship between the two countries [<hi rend="italic">is</hi>] much deeper.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The Russian Government accepts that chemical weapons have been used in Syria. How does it come to claim that the rebels are behind the attacks even though it is widely accepted that the al-Assad government has stocks of weapons?</p>
<figure><caption>A <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BM-14">BM-14</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/multiple%20rocket%20launcher">multiple rocket launcher</ref>, similar to the type likely to have launched the M-14 munitions found by UN Inspectors on August 26. Image: Vlad.</caption></figure>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Blank</hi>: It [<hi rend="italic">Russia</hi>] simply intends to defend Assad to the hilt; and is hardly unwilling to lie — especially as its intelligence service is notorious for fabricating mendacious and biased threat assessments, and is not under any form of effective democratic control.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Martel</hi>: Russia's claims that Syrian rebels were behind the chemical weapon attacks is, frankly, inexplicable. Worse, Russia's basic credibility is undermined by such statements.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Farhi</hi>: Russia claims Syria has presented it [<hi rend="italic">with</hi>] evidence that the rebels have used chemical weapons; and Russia, in turn, has given the evidence to the UNSC. It has also called the UN report one-sided and biased. The bottom line is — the claim that the opposition to the Assad regime is at least as culpable in the violence being committed in Syria, opens the path for Russia to continue calling for a political solution [which] brings to the table all parties to the conflict in Syria, including Assad and his supporters; something the multi-voiced opposition has so far refused.</item></list></p>
</text>
