<text id="autogum_interview_doc1309" title="part6_Wikinews interviews former Salt Lake City mayor and 2012 presidential candidate Rocky Anderson" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-12-17" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Salt_Lake_City_mayor_and_2012_presidential_candidate_Rocky_Anderson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><p>And at the same time, we’re creating conditions for absolute catastrophe. Hundreds of names of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Environmental%20migrant">environmental refugees</ref>, utter devastation in so many communities, loss of water resources, drought, starvation because of our failure to do what is required to reduce the emission of greenhouse gasses. If there’s any role for government, it’s to provide for, not only for the short term, but long term health, safety, and national security of our people and our approach on climate change has been absolutely counter to that.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Pentagon">Pentagon</ref> studies discuss how oncoming the imminent consequences from climate change are going to create such major national security problems, and that’s going to be the case all over the world. It’s absolutely irresponsible to not be looking out for the future, and doing what’s necessary to prevent the most catastrophic consequences of climate change. And the science is as robust as one could ever expect from science. Every nation’s science academy, every major scientific organization in the United States feels the climate issues are all in agreement: the world is heating up, generally, at a much faster rate than previously predicted. We’re already seeing massive consequences including the melting of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/tundra">tundra</ref>, the melting of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polar%20ice%20packs">arctic ice cap</ref>, melting of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/glacier">glacier</ref>s from which communities for centuries have depended for their water supplies. All of these consequences are happening faster than people believed they would just a few years ago and the future consequences are going to be horrendous. And we know that it’s all because of human’s conduct, either the emission of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse emissions, particularly from the burning of coal, oil, and gas, and from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/deforestation">deforestation</ref> and the failure to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reforestation">reforest</ref>.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">In 2008, you said that you voted for Barack Obama as the “lesser of two evils”, but <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ralph%20Nader">Ralph Nader</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cynthia%20McKinney">Cynthia McKinney</ref> were also on the ballot in Utah. Looking back now as a third party leader, do you regret not voting for a third party candidate in ’08?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Anderson</hi>: In ’08…I actually…I think it was in ’08 but I…or was it <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202004">’04</ref>? Sorry. In one of those years, I swapped my vote with a Nader supporter elsewhere so that Nader would still get a net of one vote, but in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/swing%20state">battleground state</ref>, it wouldn’t take away from the Democrat; it wouldn’t help the Republican get elected. But with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electoral%20College">Electoral College</ref>, the sad fact is my vote doesn’t count in Utah because it’s always so overwhelmingly Republican. The Electoral College is an immensely anti-Democratic part of our electoral system, it needs to be changed, we need to get to the point where we’re all electing the president based on the principle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/One%20man,%20one%20vote">one person, one vote</ref>.</p></p>
</text>
