<text id="autogum_interview_doc1318" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Buddy Roemer, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-10-28" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Buddy_Roemer%2C_U.S._Republican_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Wikinews interviews Buddy Roemer, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, October 30, 2011</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Roemer in June 2011. Image: Gage Skidmore.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican Party</ref> presidential candidate and former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor%20of%20Louisiana">Governor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Buddy_Roemer">Buddy Roemer</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Louisiana">Louisiana</ref> took some time to answer a few questions from <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter William S. Saturn.</p>
<p>Roemer served four terms in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_House_of_Representatives">U.S. House of Representatives</ref> in the 1980s as a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democratic Party</ref>. He was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louisiana%20gubernatorial%20election,%201987">elected</ref> governor as a Democrat in 1987 before switching to the Republican Party ahead of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louisiana%20gubernatorial%20election,%201991">1991 election for governor</ref>. That year, he lost the party's primary to state legislator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Duke">David Duke</ref>. After his governorship, Roemer worked as CEO of Business First Bank in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Baton_Rouge,_Louisiana">Baton Rouge</ref>.</p>
<p>Roemer announced his candidacy for president back in July after exploring a bid for several months.  He has focused his campaign on the issue of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Campaign%20finance%20reform%20in%20the%20United%20States">campaign finance reform</ref>, refusing to accept money from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/political%20action%20committees">political action committees</ref> (PACs) and limiting individual campaign contributions to $100.  He raised a total of $126,500 in the third quarter of 2011, far short of the $14.2 million raised by former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor%20of%20Massachusetts">Governor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</ref>.  </p>
<p>For his campaign, Roemer has adopted the slogan 'Free to Lead'.  He rails against corruption, special interests, and money in politics, and has expressed support for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Occupy%20Wall%20Street">Occupy Wall Street</ref> protests.  Furthermore, he has taken issue positions in favor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fair%20trade">fair trade</ref>, a balanced federal budget, and a strengthened national defense.</p>
<p>Roemer has not been invited to any national presidential debates.  He has focused largely on the first-in-the-nation primary state of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Hampshire">New Hampshire</ref>, and recently signed up to appear on the state's primary ballot.  However, a recent University of New Hampshire Survey Center poll shows him with less than one percent support in the state. Pearson Cross of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Louisiana%20at%20Lafayette">University of Louisiana at Lafayette</ref> commented, "If Buddy can exceed expectations in New Hampshire or even sneak in and steal third — that would give a boost that he could build on".</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why did you decide to run for president at this particular point in time?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Buddy Roemer</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Why run now? The political system has become institutionally corrupt with special interest money in control. I run to reform the system.</p>
<figure><caption>Roemer shakes hands with potential voters. Image: Gage Skidmore.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why are you a better choice for the Republican nomination than any of your opponents?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">BR</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> No other candidate talks about the corruption of the political system as a result of special interest money. No other candidate limits contributions to $100 or less, no PACS, no SUPERPACS, full disclosure. No candidate has even stated a position on campaign reform. Our country is being bought and sold, and they have nothing to say. It is alarming and disgraceful. It is particularly bothersome as our country is in such difficulty with no jobs growth and lack of budgetary control and no solution is possible without exposing and placing broad limits on accepting special interest campaign funds.
Lobbyists and Pacs with DC addresses contributed more money to the two candidates four years ago than 32 States combined.
I will propose to Congress the following reforms:</p>
</text>
