<text id="autogum_interview_doc1152" title="part6_Obesity and the Fat Acceptance Movement: Kira Nerusskaya speaks" shortTile="partobesity-fat-acceptance" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-09" dateModified="2014-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Obesity_and_the_Fat_Acceptance_Movement%3A_Kira_Nerusskaya_speaks" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So your problem with the obesity epidemic and why it corresponds with what you’re saying is that there are large people who are just naturally large for a variety of reasons but the American lifestyle right now is creating obesity based upon reasons that are not particularly related to living slovenly?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  It’s the choices that exist in America. Choices.  Look, David, how many people drink <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/soft%20drinks">soda</ref> in America?  What the hell is soda?  It’s sugar water.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s the only thing that has been proven to be linked with weight gain that you can consume.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Soda, in and of itself, is sugar; water is better for you than sugar water is, correct?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yes.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  So where does it come from?  It comes from the media, and money.  Money behind these companies to advertise to youth.  When you look at school lunches, they’re still heavily <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carbohydrates">carb-based</ref> or poor nutrition.  People want convenience.  People are exhausted.  They work hard, they come home, they want Hamburger Helper: boom! it’s in a pan and done to feed their family of four.  I understand that woman, but I think that if healthier choices are made available to Americans then I they might choose it.  If there’s nothing in the stores but healthy choices or organic choices then that’s what people are going to buy</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  A glass of orange juice every morning is said to put on about four pounds a year.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>Why?  Based on sugar.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are there any heroes of the Fat Acceptance/BBW movement?  Like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camryn%20Manheim">Camryn Manheim</ref>?  Who are some of the people out there that larger people -- fat people -- look to as people who’ve been ground breakers, if you will?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  I would look at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marilyn%20Wann">Marilyn Wann</ref>.  I would look at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul%20Campos">Paul Campos</ref>.  I would look at your average person who’s out there doing it on a daily basis, walking around with a smile, you know.  Anybody who makes it and who makes a difference.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mo'Nique">Mo'Nique</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Yes, to some degree.  I think that anybody that’s making a positive contribution is a positive contribution, simple as that.  But many of the heroes I have within the movement are not known people.</p>
<head id="Fat_women_and_sexuality">Fat women and sexuality</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is there a typical kind of person that is attracted to an overweight woman?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  We fat girls have it hard.  The majority of the pool of men just reject us because we're large, and that's because they were taught fat is bad.  Therefore, the person inside is also bad.  Then we have a portion of men who are fetishists, in that they only receive heightened sexual pleasure from being with a fat girl.  Then you have people who might be '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feederism">Feeders</ref>', they have an interest in making you bigger.  Then you have the guys who want to make you smaller; that's their mission.</p>
</text>
