<text id="autogum_interview_doc1148" title="part2_Obesity and the Fat Acceptance Movement: Kira Nerusskaya speaks" shortTile="partobesity-fat-acceptance" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-09" dateModified="2014-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Obesity_and_the_Fat_Acceptance_Movement%3A_Kira_Nerusskaya_speaks" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is beautiful about being fat?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  The difference in the shape of the body.  The curves.  The softness.  It's difference, which is the opposite of what you see in New York on a Saturday night with the 'Blond Gaggle': they all have straight blond hair, cut the same way, they are all wearing jeans with a little shirt and a little purse over their shoulder.  It's hysterical.  They are all so similar that they are identical.  When you look at fat women, it's so not standard, which is one of the difficulties in finding clothing.  She can be a pear shape, where she carries her weight below the waist.  She can be an apple shape where it's around the middle.  She can be hourglassed where it's big on top, slender in the middle and bigger in the hips.  There's so many different shapes, and when you look at a naked fat woman with the cellulite included, it looks like she was poured into a mold specifically in that shape, like that is the way she was created.  Which is so different compared to straight <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US%20standard%20clothing%20size">Size 2 or Size 4</ref>.</p>
<head id="Fat_and_health">Fat and health</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you respond to the argument that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/obesity">obesity</ref> is unhealthy?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  I can’t say that is 100% wrong.  The one thing that I say about the size acceptance movement is that it’s as vast as we are.  I’m a very practical, logical, reasonable person and this is what I say:  The more weight on your body the harder your heart has to work, period, end of story.  There are factors for heart disease, but you could be skinny and smoke three packs a day, which is just as unhealthy.  There are many factors that come into the equation that determines whether something is unhealthy.  There’s definitely evidence, though.  I’m not a medical expert and it’s probably one of my weakest areas to talk about, because that’s not what I’m here for.  At the same time, I’m 313 pounds, I have excellent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/blood%20pressure">blood pressure</ref> and good <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cholesterol">cholesterol</ref>, and I could walk five flights without getting all huffy puffy so what do you say to that?  You know what I mean?</p>
<p>There are those who believe that you can be fat and that there’s no conclusive evidence in any way, shape or form that was ever put on this Earth by any medical study showing that fat is negative.  They’ll tell you studies are not conclusive, and that fat is beautiful at any cost, in any extreme.  They’re kind of like Fat Nazis.</p>
<p>And then you have people who are members of what <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lynn%20McAfee">Lynn McAfee</ref> calls the Obesity Mafia.  They say we have to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dieting">get those people thin</ref>, man, at any cost.  Ironically, these diet places won’t submit their findings on how people do on their diets.  That’s because <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List%20of%20diets">diets</ref> are 98% ineffective so they don’t want to put it in writing anywhere because people will see that.   It depends on how you feel and where you are.</p>
</text>
