<text id="autogum_interview_doc059" title="part4_Wikinews interviews painter Pricasso on his art and freedom of expression" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-10-10" dateModified="2019-08-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_painter_Pricasso_on_his_art_and_freedom_of_expression" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="italic">[Editor's note:  Accusations of harassment focused on the uploader, rather than the artist; the successive heated discussions, over about six months, that ultimately led to the video's deletion from Commons may be read </hi><ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Commons:Deletion_requests/File:Jimmy%20Wales%20by%20Pricasso%20(the%20making%20of).ogv">here</ref><hi rend="italic">.  Jimmy Wales expressed his position elsewhere and did not directly participate in the discussions themselves.]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> How do you compare the reactions by Mayor of Cape Town Helen Zille who said your portrait painting of her was a product of a "free society" and a reflection of how people "exercise their freedom" with the comment by Jimmy Wales calling the publication of your artwork "harassment" ? Which of these individuals do you feel is correct, Mayor Zille or Wales, and why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: I think Helen got it. They in South Africa are struggling with change from being suppressed to one of freedom as she said "a free society". Jimmy Wales on the other hand although promoting himself as The Free Speech Guy is censoring things he does not agree with and calling it Harassment, not a good look Jimmy!!</p>
<p>I did put the video of Helen Zille being painted on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref>. It was there for a few months but they too delete my work quite regularly so it's probably long gone.</p>
<p>She is an experienced politician and would weigh up the fors and against before she acted, obviously the fors had it.</p>
<p>Mr. Wales on the other hand has probably not seen a lot of my work; if he had he would know I do it for fun and not really to be taken too seriously, it's a comedy performance, but he could not see the unique talent of someone who has cornered the world market of penis portraits painting with no imitators for the past 10 years, so before too many people could have a small chuckle at his expense he had it deleted, I'm sure there would be many others who would like to remove things on Wikipedia but don't have the muscle to do so.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Have you experienced censorship or attempts by others to limit your freedom of expression? How so, and what was your reaction?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pricasso</hi>: As I said before YouTube is always deleting my videos when someone complains, sometimes even when there is no genitals visible. Once one was taken down because the guy I was painting had the word (fuck) on his tee shirt; I mean how many films have this word in the dialogue. Also in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Macau">Macau</ref> at the adult show, the people who make the rules make me perform inside an enclosed area, and people are wary of coming in through the door so is a bit slow there; and the guys that run the show are so polite and passionate trying to change China slowly, making it more open, that I keep on returning year after year.</p>
</text>
