<text id="autogum_interview_doc125" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Scott Lucas, Eyal Zisser, Majid Rafizadeh about risks of US military intervention in Syria" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-09-06" dateModified="2015-10-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Scott_Lucas%2C_Eyal_Zisser%2C_Majid_Rafizadeh_about_risks_of_US_military_intervention_in_Syria" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Scott Lucas, Eyal Zisser, Majid Rafizadeh about risks of US military intervention in Syria</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, September 8, 2013</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Prof._Scott_Lucas_1.jpg">File:Prof. Scott Lucas 1.jpg</ref></p><figure><caption>File photo of Prof. Scott Lucas. Image: Scott Lucas.<hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Prof._Scott_Lucas_1.jpg">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=File%3AProf.+Scott+Lucas+1.jpg">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States">President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> announced last Saturday he was seeking <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Congress">Congressional</ref> authorisation for military intervention in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syria</ref>. </p>
<p>Looking for more-qualified input, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed: professor <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Scott Lucas</hi></hi>, an expert in American Studies, from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">UK</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/University_of_Birmingham">University of Birmingham</ref>; the President of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International%20American%20Council">International American Council</ref> on the Middle East, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Majid%20Rafizadeh"><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Majid Rafizadeh</hi></hi></ref>; and, professor <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Eyal Zisser</hi></hi>, a Syrian expert, from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tel%20Aviv%20University">Tel Aviv University</ref>.</p>
<p>Discussing the risks involved with US military intervention in Syria, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> posed a range of questions to these experts on the region's political climate.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Is it possible for the US to take military action to deter further use of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chemical_weapons">chemical weapons</ref> without getting dragged into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrian%20civil%20war">civil war</ref>?</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Prof. Scott Lucas</hi>:  The US is already involved in the civil war — the question is to what extent.</item></list>
<p>The US has given political support to the opposition and insurgency since late 2011, and from summer 2012, it has pursued covert support to the opposition fighters.</p>
<p>However, the Obama Administration has been hesitant about overt support for insurgents throughout the conflict, and that has affected co-ordination of covert efforts. In June, the Administration finally said it would provide overt military assistance, but then pulled back and failed to deliver any public aid.</p>
<p>Had it not been for the August, 21 chemical weapons attack, that position would have persisted.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Majid Rafizadeh</hi>: It depends on the scope of the military operation. If United States conducts limited military operation, as the adminstration argues, and if US only targets some of the Syrian government's military installments, it is less likely that United States will be drawn into the Syria's civil war. It would be a political suicide for Syria, Iran or Hezbollah to respond.</item></list>
<p>On the other hand, if Assad observes that the balance of power is tilting against him inside the country, he might use chemical weapons in the future despite US limited strikes.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Prof. Eyal Zisser</hi>: Yes, it[sic] the attack is limited. And If the Americans only use missiles. They can cause severe damage, but leave Assad in his palace, and not being dragged into the civil war.</item></list></p>
<figure><caption> The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States">President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian%20President">Russian President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vladimir_Putin">Vladimir Putin</ref> earlier this year. Image: Pete Souza.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Will military intervention from the US affect long term relations between the United States and Russia?</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">SL</hi>: Of course, significant military intervention by Washington will affect relations between the US and Russia, but the long-term effect cannot be predicted.</item></list>
<p>It is dependent on Russia's reaction — so far, Moscow has been able to pressure the US into caution, but a decision for intervention by the US might call Russia's bluff, so to speak, and force some caution by the Russians. Already, Moscow has said it will not join a fight against any US military action.</p>
<p>And, of course, the long-term relationship is dependent on the political and military success of any US intervention.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: Military intervention, in the classic sense of putting troops on the ground, will definitely affect US-Russian long term political relationships.  It might heighten the diplomatic tensions.  However, the limited military operation is less likely [to] change US-Russian long term economic, geopolitical, and political relationships.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">EZ</hi>: No. They need each other in many other places of the world. Russia knows that the US is a super power and will not be interested in a real conflict with Washington.</item></list></p>
</text>
