<text id="autogum_interview_doc1246" title="part9_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You replaced it with writing?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah.  With introspection, reporting on what I find inside.  And it feels very much like a drug, in the sense that it's--I binge.  I don’t write four hours a day, and then do lunch, and then call friends and return emails--I don't have that sense of structure.  I tend to wait too long, and then I tend to work for 15 hours, 18 hours, 48 hours straight.  I tend to do just like I drank.  You know, binging.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you ever had an alcoholic write you and ask you to be their sponsor?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I have not had someone ask me to be their sponsor, no, but I've had some amazing letters.  I had a homeless guy in a big city write me and tell me that he shoplifted my book from a Barnes &amp; Noble.  He only intellectually shoplifted it.  He sat on the sofa and read it.  And he said that he had never read a book about recovery that hit him with the force that Dry hit him.  He realized, "My God! I'm 50.  I'm young."  And he checked into the same treatment program that I myself went to and got sober.  I mean, that to me was just--I--it blew the top of my head off.  So I've had things like that happen, but I've not actually had anybody ask if I would be their sponsor.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When people write to you, and they say they relate to your work, what element do they say they responded to--your upbringing, your relationship with your mother, your contending with alcoholism?  You write on such a variety of topics--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  It so varies, yeah, it’s all so much.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is there a theme that seems to resonate most with people in your life?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Well, certainly being raised in a very untraditional and chaotic childhood.  And addiction; also being single and dating in the city.  I mean, there are so many.  Probably the two are having a crazy childhood or a chaotic childhood or being sort of abandoned by parents; and drug abuse or alcoholism.  I hear from a lot of alcoholics.  It's interesting to me because I've heard from a lot of famous people--whose names you would absolutely know, and politicians, whose names you know, anyone in America would know--soccer moms--and working dads, and--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  [laughs]  And . . . straight and gay, just a whole range of people.  And the thing that is so amazing to me is how absolutely dead similar they all are.  You know?  I mean, it's shocking.</p>
<head id="On_belief_in_a_higher_power">On belief in a higher power</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you believe in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Higher%20power">higher power</ref>?</hi></p>
</text>
