<text id="autogum_interview_doc212" title="part13_BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2008-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Who wouldn’t hurt a fly!</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  They can separate fantasy playing from the harsh reality of domestic dysfunction.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  It’s the same with child pornography.  Just because they have a schoolgirl fetish doesn’t mean they want to actually go out there and prey upon school kids.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is that one that’s common?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I think that’s common with EVERY man! [Laughs]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [Laughs]  Britney Spears didn’t get where she is on her singing talent.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  [Laughs] Exactly!  I think it’s common with every man.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  That goes into another thing, because with some people it feels like you ARE sometimes making it okay for them to have these certain fantasies and some people, they know it is wrong and they would never do that, and feel it is a way to get it out.  You are always walking that line.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I think it comes down to the individual.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  It’s not the majority of people, definitely.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  What it honestly is, is people using this who already have those problems, pedophiles and abusers, who use this as an outlet because they can get away with it.   And that’s really not what we are about, either.  A lot of times we will see people like that and ban them from the dungeons.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are there certain known people who are banned?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Yes, it is usually people who get really obsessive and have created scenes.  Like Ernest.  He has not done anything bad, like try to beat somebody up, but he got into a screaming match with one of the phone girls about some strange detail of his visit.  People who are obviously not together.  I think he has a serious mental illness.</p>
<head id="BDSM_Culture">BDSM Culture</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is some of the literature that is considered classic?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Story%20of%20O">Story of O</ref></hi>.  <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marquis%20de%20Sade">The Crimes of Love</ref></hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Story%20of%20O">Story of O</ref></hi>.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marquis%20de%20Sade">Marquis de Sade</ref>.  There is <hi rend="italic">so</hi> much S&amp;M erotica.  I don’t read much of it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I do.  I’m <hi rend="italic">such</hi> a pervert!</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Perverted, filthy, filthy whore.  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  At the Den of Inequity we had a required reading list that you wouldn’t be considered a Mistress if you didn’t read these books.  <hi rend="italic">Story of O</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Crimes of Love</hi> by Marquis de Sade.  For any Mistress coming in wanting to know more about it, I would recommend <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greenery%20Press">The Mistress Manual</ref></hi>.  <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jay%20Wiseman">S&amp;M 101</ref></hi>, that’s a huge one that really breaks it down for you.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi> <hi rend="italic">Screw the Roses, Send Me the Thorns</hi>.  Midori’s <hi rend="italic">Bondage</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Midori%20(author)">Midori</ref>’s very well known when it comes to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japanese%20bondage">Japanese bondage</ref>.  There’s different bios of people that you don't know if they are real, like <hi rend="italic">I Was a Teenage Dominatrix.</hi></p>
</text>
