<text id="autogum_interview_doc865" title="part5_Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-22" dateModified="2014-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_World_Wide_Web_co-inventor_Robert_Cailliau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: The list is without end.</p>
<p>At the second conference, held by NCSA in Chicago, someone asked if it was not better to use the web for conferences instead of travelling to far places.  Implusively I answered, in front of 1500 programmers in the audience, that there was no such thing as a virtual beer and therefore we preferred to meet in the flesh.  That was 1994.</p>
<p>In 1990, months before there was a shred of code, Tim and I wanted to find a good name for the project.  Sometimes, after a hard day's work in warm offices we drank a beer on the CERN cafeteria terrace before going home.  On one such occasion Tim came up with "World-Wide Web". I would have preferred something shorter, but to find a catching name is not easy.  I agreed to use WWW for the new document that was to go to management and "find a better name later".  WWW stayed:  it summarised well what it was.</p>
<p>Because I'm a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synesthesia">synaesthete</ref> I see characters in colours and I perceive a W as green.  I liked that.  So it remained WWW.  And there was indeed a logo that we used a lot in the beginning.  It was made from three Ws:  white, light green and darker green.</p>
<p>And yes, the hyphen was there for a long time too.  But it confused people who were not so grammatical, and Tim finally cut the knot by stating that he had the right to decide how it was written since he had invented it: without the hyphen.</p>
<p>Some anecdotes were less funny:  at one time I could have made Alexander Totic of NCSA come to CERN to join us.  That was almost arranged when it appeared that Alex had a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Serbia">Serbian</ref> passport and CERN at the time did not admit Serbs.</p>
<p>The most recent and very positive anecdote is from October 2006:  I gave the opening keynote at an Australian conference on e-learning and the internet in education.  I started out by saying I knew nothing about education but would give my keynote anyway.  In a later talk Jean Johnson presented NotSchool (http://www.notschool.net) and mentioned that the project "Web for Schools" of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European%20Commission">European Commission</ref> had been very important for her work.  </p>
<p>Later I asked her whether she meant the project that  ended in a conference in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dublin">Dublin</ref> in 1995.  She said yes and asked if I had been there.  I then had to admit that I had started that project myself and addressed the audience at the closing session of the Dublin conference and therefore maybe I did know a little about internet in education.  It was heartwarming to know that even smaller initiatives had been quite important.</p>
</text>
