<text id="autogum_interview_doc1359" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Finnish 'Rock 'N' Troll' band Kivimetsän Druidi" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-06-07" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Finnish_%27Rock_%27N%27_Troll%27_band_Kivimets%C3%A4n_Druidi" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Joni:</hi> As you might have noticed we went into studio in the beginning of June. That is the main reason why there will be quite many of our previous songs on the album, but also some new material. Personally I prefer it that way because writing  seven new songs in one month wouldn’t give out the picture what we really are at the moment.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Antti:</hi>   There will be new material, of course and also some old songs!</item></list></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>What can we expect from the new album?</item></list>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Joni:</hi> As mentioned before you can expect some new stuff and some old stuff. All of them are – of course – rerecorded and sang by our new vocalist, Leeni-Maria. Some songs are a bit modified too, but if you’re an old fan you can expect the album sound the Kivimetsän Druidi you know. For new fans and listeners then: Well, I think I described our music earlier already, but mention something here, there will be crushing riffs, beautiful and melodic paths, something darker than night and of course lots of fun.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Antti:</hi> Three words: Symphonic, brutal and folkish.</item></list></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>A common complaint is about illegal downloading "killing" the industry. What's your opinion on that?</item></list>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Joni:</hi> I don’t think that way at all. Those people who download a lot, would they buy a CD if they couldn’t download it? I think they wouldn’t. It’s one way of making the band popular and known to more people. We trust that true fans, who really like the music, will buy the CD even if they’ve first downloaded it.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Antti:</hi> It’s two sided thing. Many people download perhaps one album from the band illegally first. Listens it trough and gets exited. Then they buy the original album and tell their friends about it and they may do the same thing. Then there are people who download all their music and never buy albums from the stores. So I wouldn’t immediately say that it kills industry because there are millions of people who want their music with original cd and booklets.</item></list></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>What advice would you give to anyone looking to get into the music industry?</item></list>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Joni:</hi> Always remember to believe in yourself and what you’re doing. If you don’t have faith in yourself, no one will notice you. Keep going after set backs and stay true to your chosen style as long as it feels good for yourself. Use all the possible opportunities you’re given and seek out the ways to make the band known to many. Oh, and always remember to have fun. ☺</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Antti:</hi> Just do the thing you do and believe in and do not rush with it! Patience will be rewarded. Listen to advices, but don’t be blind!</item></list></p>
</text>
