<text id="autogum_interview_doc1378" title="part1_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Did you keep in touch with her throughout her life?  Did she have a presence in yours?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi> Not as closely as James Brown. We would run into each other. She died when I was still very much in my teens. Madame Ernestine Washington, who was the first lady of the church I grew up in, she was a gospel singer. I knew a lot of the gospel greats. James Brown and I got close in my teen years. What happened was when I was around 12 or 13, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin%20Luther%20King,%20Jr.">Martin Luther King</ref> had come to the church and I got totally mesmerized by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adam%20Clayton%20Powell%20Jr.">Adam Clayton Powell</ref>, who was the Congressman in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Harlem,_New_York">Harlem</ref> and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/preacher">preacher</ref>, so I wanted to get involved politically. The church that I was in was Pentecostal; I’m now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baptism">Baptist</ref>. But it was Pentecostal, and it wasn’t that involved in social justice, although Bishop Washington was. Bishop Washington said he didn’t want me to get involved with the more militant groups, because at that time you had the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black%20Panthers">Black Panthers</ref> and a lot of others.  So he brought me to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20Augustus%20Jones%20Jr.">Reverend William Jones</ref>, who was head of Operation Breadbasket, SCLC, in New York, who later became my pastor after Bishop Washington died.  Reverend Jones converted me Baptist from Pentecostal. They knew who I was because of my preaching as a little boy.  I became the youth director in New York of SCLC Operation Breadbasket.  King had just gotten killed; this is 1969 and he had gotten killed the year before. I met King, but I didn’t know him. I was 12, 13 years old.  But I got to know Dr. Abernathy, who succeeded him—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Ralph Abernathy?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ralph%20Abernathy">Ralph Abernathy</ref>. The Director nationally of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation%20Breadbasket">Operation Breadbasket</ref> was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesse%20Jackson">Jesse Jackson</ref>, who was in his late twenties, early thirties. It was interesting, because Jesse Jackson’s age and my age gap was the same as his and King’s. Jackson at that time had a big afro and a medallion. He became a hero to me. Adam Clayton Powell, who had been my hero, had retired and moved so I became a protégé of Reverend Jackson. We became close.</p>
<head id="James_Brown:_a_father_to_Sharpton">James Brown: a father to Sharpton</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Are you still close to Reverend Jackson?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi> Yeah, we talk. In 1971, when Jackson left <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southern%20Christian%20Leadership%20Conference">SCLC</ref> over whatever their problems were with each other—that’s when he left to form Operation Push—I also left the SCLC in protest because I was close to Reverend Jackson. I took my youth division with me and formed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Youth%20Movement">National Youth Movement</ref>, which was my organization. Jesse didn’t have an organization here in New York. When I formed it, maybe about a year, six months later, a young guy joined the organization from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Georgia_(US_state)">Georgia</ref> — he would come up here thinking about going to college — named Teddy.  Teddy’s father was James Brown. Teddy got killed in a car accident in upstate New York. He and I were the same age, sixteen. James Brown came to New York and the disc jockeys here told him about this young preacher his son liked. He decided he’d do a memorial concert for his son for my youth group.  He talked to me, he liked me, and of course this was, like, <hi rend="italic">The Icon</hi>. He became like the father I didn’t have after my parents separated, and I became like Teddy, his ambitious young son.  He had other kids, but they were not as old as Teddy and they didn’t have the ambition, so we started a father-son relationship.</p>
</text>
