<text id="autogum_interview_doc495" title="part0_Asbestos controversy aboard Scientology ship Freewinds" shortTile="partasbestos-controversy" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-05-16" dateModified="2017-06-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Asbestos_controversy_aboard_Scientology_ship_Freewinds" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Asbestos controversy aboard Scientology ship Freewinds</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 16, 2008</hi></p>
<p>Controversy has arisen over the reported presence of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asbestos#Blue">blue asbestos</ref> on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ship%20prefix">MV</ref> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freewinds">Freewinds</ref></hi>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cruise%20ship">cruise ship</ref> owned by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church%20of%20Scientology">Church of Scientology</ref>. According to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint%20Martin">Saint Martin</ref> newspaper <hi rend="italic">The Daily Herald</hi> and the shipping news journal <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lloyd's%20List">Lloyd's List</ref></hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Freewinds</hi> was sealed in April and local public health officials on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caribbean">Caribbean</ref> island of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curaçao">Curaçao</ref> where the ship is docked began an investigation into the presence of asbestos dust on the ship. Former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientology">Scientologist</ref> Lawrence Woodcraft supervised work on the ship in 1987, and attested to the presence of blue asbestos on the <hi rend="italic">Freewinds</hi> in an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Affidavit">affidavit</ref> posted to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Internet">Internet</ref> in 2001. Woodcraft, a licensed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/architect">architect</ref> by profession, gave a statement to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> and commented on the recent events.</p>
<p>According to <hi rend="italic">The Daily Herald</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Freewinds</hi> was in the process of being renovated by the Curaçao Drydock Company. The article states that samples taken from paneling in the ship were sent to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref>, where an analysis revealed that they "contained significant levels of blue asbestos". An employee of the Curaçao Drydock Company told <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radar%20Online">Radar Online</ref></hi> in an April 30 article that the <hi rend="italic">Freewinds</hi> has been docked and sealed, and confirmed that an article about asbestos ran in the local paper. </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Lloyd's List</hi> reported that work on the interior of the <hi rend="italic">Freewinds</hi> was suspended on April 27 after health inspectors found traces of blue asbestos on the ship. According to <hi rend="italic">Lloyd's List</hi>, Frank Esser, Curaçao Drydock Company's interim director, joined Curaçao's head of the department of labor affairs Christiene van der Biezen along with the head of the local health department Tico Ras and two inspectors in an April 25 inspection of the ship. "We are sending someone so that they can tell us what happened, where it came from, since when it has been there," said Panama Maritime Authority's director of merchant marine Alfonso Castillero in a statement to <hi rend="italic">Lloyd's List</hi>.</p>
<p>The Church of Scientology purchased the ship, then known as the <hi rend="italic">Bohème</hi>, in 1987, through an organization called Flag Ship Trust. After being renovated and refitted, it was put into service in June 1988. The ship is used by the Church of Scientology for advanced <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology">Scientology</ref> training in "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operating%20Thetan">Operating Thetan</ref>" levels, as well as for spiritual retreats for its members. Curaçao has been the ship's homeport since it was purchased by the Church of Scientology. </p>
<p>According to his 2001 statement, Lawrence Woodcraft had been an architect in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref> since 1975, and joined Scientology's elite "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sea%20Org">Sea Organization</ref>" (Sea Org) in 1986. He wrote that he was asked by the Sea Org to work on the <hi rend="italic">Freewinds</hi> in 1987, and during his work on the ship "noticed a powdery blue fibrous substance approximately 1 ½" thick between the paint and the steel wall," which he believed to be asbestos. He also discovered what he thought was blue asbestos in other parts of the ship, and reported his findings to Church of Scientology executives. Woodcraft discussed his experiences in a 2001 interview published online by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisa%20McPherson%20Trust">Lisa McPherson Trust</ref>, a now-defunct organization which was critical of the Church of Scientology.</p>
</text>
