<text id="autogum_interview_doc714" title="part4_Canada&amp;apos;s Don Valley East (Ward 33) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-don-valley" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-17" dateModified="2009-04-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Don_Valley_East_%28Ward_33%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Toronto must be a place where police serve and protect everyone, all interest groups, all religions and races, not simply the politicians and lawyers that protect their excessive budgets.</p>
<p>Toronto must be a place where anyone can ride public transit for a small fee to anywhere in the GTA.</p>
<p>Toronto City council must be a place where everyone has a voice, and who's ideas may be shared in resolving the challenges that face this nation in the twenty second century, and not simply a voice for the realty firms and lawyers that charge outrageous service charges. Toronto is this, but can be much more.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> 1) Great to see sheppard subway built to fairview mall, and integration of VIVA tertiary transit system with TTC.</p>
<p>2) I believe building Daniels condominiums along 401 and bayview was more financial than environmental. It would be better to alleviate transit congestion by building along steeles ave east and west, including a steeles subway extension from keele to mccowan. The 401 cannot grow further, and adding more transit chaos to it is not good for environment, nor city planning. Further growth must come from Etobicoke and Scarborough fringes - if not a merger of Toronto and York region for tax revenue purposes.</p>
<p>3) I do not agree with city council that the greatest value in expanding the subway system was from fairview mall to yonge. If this city and province had given the global authroity to the GTA transit authority as I demanded in 2003, we would have a GTA transit system second to Tokyo or New York,</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> If you were elected as a "rookie" councilor, What would you bring to the table beyond the incumbent?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am no rookie in any sense, in fact I have been the advisor and consultant that has not charged Toronto a dime for all of my research and publications the past 5 years. I transformed the University of Toronto into Canada's pre-eminent R+D institution, fully integrated with downtown hospital infrastructure. I am the one that told Ontario to reform gaming laws so hospitals and charities could fund this transformation today. I am the one that has forced the Attorney General to offer NO FEE courts, funds to rebuild Regent Park, VIVA tertiary transit system, and a host of other achievements.</p>
<p>1) 10 years of business, IT, Finance, and Environmental solutions consulting in applying to Toronto's current problems.</p>
<p>2) The knowledge, experience, and innovative ideas that have transformed this city, province, and nation in the past decade.</p>
<p>3) I hold the balance of power against all three levels of government and police service unions. When I choose to use that power, it will result in swift, decisive reforms as those within the past couple of years.</p>
</text>
