<text id="autogum_interview_doc1031" title="part7_Blown for Good author discusses life inside international headquarters of Scientology" shortTile="partblown-good-author" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-11-12" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Blown_for_Good_author_discusses_life_inside_international_headquarters_of_Scientology" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<hi rend="bold">I am sure that it is becoming harder and harder to field and answer questions regarding the criminal activities occurring within the Scientology world. </hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Marc Headley</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Scientology has received quite a bit of attention in the media recently, from allegations of violence levied against David Miscavige by high-ranking former officials, to spokesman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tommy%20Davis%20(Scientology)">Tommy Davis</ref> abruptly leaving an interview with Martin Bashir on ABC News when the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xenu">Xenu</ref> story was mentioned, to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Court_in_France_convicts_Scientology_of_organized_fraud">Scientology's conviction of fraud in France</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Academy_Award-winning_film_director_Paul_Haggis_leaves_Scientology">defection of Academy Award-winning film director Paul Haggis</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Do you think <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Category:Tom_Cruise">Tom Cruise</ref> is aware of these developments? What about other celebrity Scientologists, for example <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Category:John_Travolta">John Travolta</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kirstie%20Alley">Kirstie Alley</ref>? Do you think these issues will affect the perceptions of celebrity Scientologists towards the organization? Why or why not?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: While it is hard to say what these people do or do not know, I am sure that it is becoming harder and harder to field and answer questions regarding the criminal activities occurring within the Scientology world. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In a postcript, "More books by Marc Morgan Headley", you write "Since escaping in 2005, both Marc and his wife Claire have been heavily "fair gamed" by Scientology and many attempts have been made to keep them from speaking out in regards to their experiences at the Int Base." "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fair%20Game%20(Scientology)">Fair Game</ref>" is a Scientology policy written by founder L.Ron Hubbard that states individuals declared "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suppressive%20Person">Suppressive Person</ref>" by the organization, "May be deprived of property or injured by any means by any Scientologist without any discipline of the Scientologist. May be tricked, sued or lied to or destroyed." <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A%20Piece%20of%20Blue%20Sky">A Piece of Blue Sky</ref></hi> author Jon Atack noted that in its appeal of the case <hi rend="italic">Wollersheim v. Church of Scientology of California</hi>, "Scientology asserted that 'fair game' was a 'core practice of Scientology', and therefore protected as 'religious expression'." What do you mean when you write in the book that you and your wife have been "fair gamed" by Scientology"? What actions has the organization taken to attempt to prevent you from speaking about your experiences at Gold Base? How have you and your wife dealt with this?</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Marc Headley at conference on Scientology in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref> (September 4, 2008)</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: I have had private investigators camped outside my place of residence, follow me to the grocery store, follow me when I’m dropping off my kids at school. </p>
<hi rend="bold">I have had private investigators camped outside my place of residence, follow me to the grocery store, follow me when I’m dropping off my kids at school.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Marc Headley</p>
<p>Scientology officials have held meetings with my friends, family and employees and spread lies about me, my wife and our activities. Ex-members have been threatened with disconnection from their immediate family if they had any contact with me. </p>
</text>
