<text id="autogum_interview_doc1096" title="part1_In the land of the open source elves: Interview with "Battle for Wesnoth" creator David White" shortTile="partin-land-open" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-05-29" dateModified="2015-10-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/In_the_land_of_the_open_source_elves%3A_Interview_with_%22Battle_for_Wesnoth%22_creator_David_White" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>Not very well. :) </p>
<p>Version 0.1 of Wesnoth was developed entirely by me, and it was ugly. It had awful graphics, and no sound or music at all.</p>
<p>I think the best way to deal with the problem is to make an early version of the game which showcases the desired gameplay. Then, people with the appropriate skills who like the game will contribute. This worked out well with Wesnoth, anyhow, as I soon attracted a fine artist, Francisco Munoz, and once the graphics were decent, more people started wanting to help.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">I noticed that the forum allows anyone to submit art for the game. How important have contributions from ordinary players been for development?</hi></p>
<p>Well, as with almost any free software project, contributions from users have been very important. In the area of art, this is definitely so, though making a substantial contribution of art generally requires a reasonable amount of skill, so the number of people who can contribute art is somewhat limited.</p>
<p>This has meant that the number of people who contribute art is much smaller than, say, the number of people who contribute bug reports or feature requests. Still, there are plenty of good pixel artists out there, and we have had many good contributions from our community.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Also, within the game itself, it's possible to directly download new campaigns from the Internet, many of which have been created by players. Do you think that, in essence, we are seeing the beginnings of applying "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/wiki">wiki</ref>" principles to game development?</hi></p>
<p>On one hand, I see the ability to directly download new campaigns as a mild convenience — it wouldn't be much more difficult for the user to, for instance, go to a web page and download campaigns.</p>
<p>On the other hand, it does blur the line between 'developer created content' and 'user created content' and so, like a Wiki, makes it much easier for any user to contribute to the game.</p>
<p>I think that for an Open Source game, making it as easy as possible for users to contribute content is a key way to help make the game succeed. We have tried hard to do this in Wesnoth. I don't think that with something dynamic like a game, it's quite as easy to make absolutely anyone be able to edit it or contribute as easily as they can in a Wiki, but we have tried to make it as easy as possible. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How do you moderate user-submitted content? Are there scenarios or graphics you have rejected because they crossed a line — sexual content, excessive violence, etc.?</hi></p>
<p>Well, there are basically three levels of content acceptance:</p>
<list type="ordered"><item>'Official': content can be accepted into the game itself — the  content will reside in our SVN repository, and will be in the tarballs released by developers.</item>
<item>'Campaign Server': Content can be allowed on the campaign server (the server which users can connect to in-game to download more content).</item>
<item>'Disallowed': Finally, content can be disallowed on the campaign server, which means that the creator could only distribute it using their own channels (for instance, having a web site people could download it from).</item></list>
</text>
