<text id="autogum_interview_doc922" title="part7_Scientology protest group celebrates founder's birthday worldwide" shortTile="partscientology-protest" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-03-05" dateModified="2019-02-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology_protest_group_celebrates_founder%27s_birthday_worldwide" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> was earlier accused of being "fake" and Detective 'Tim' refused to give a statement to Wikinews saying "no media. You made that (press badge) from the Internet. I never seen this site before." 'Tim' then refused outright to give his last name and badge number. 'Tim' was quoted only during his time speaking publicly to the protesters.</p>
<p>Shortly after instructing people to remove masks, 'Tim' then accused a member of Anonymous of "portraying an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab">Arabic</ref> terrorist" because of a scarf he was wearing and asked him to remove it.</p>
<p>Shortly after, at least three protesters were detained by police and questioned after taking photographs and video of the Church from across the street. Police approached the three and began to "yell" at them. 'Tim' then told one protester that "the Church want you arrested. Now how am I going to avoid that." The protester then willingly handed over his videotape of the church and asked not to be arrested. Subsequently all three were released without being charged. According to Detective 'Tim', "the tape is now the property of the police." The protesters were not on Church property and were only filming the areas of the Church visible from across the streets.</p>
<p>During the protest, a member of Anonymous read a speech, which according to him, was a worldwide speech to all Churches.</p>
<p>"Today - The Ides of March - is the day Julius Caesar was betrayed by those he trusted. Today we gather together as Anonymous to call attention to another betrayal of trust - that of the Church of Scientology upon its followers. Since is inception, Scientology has traded in false hopes and promises, betrayed the trust of its members, taken their money, their rights, and at times their very lives," said the statement.</p>
<p>"Last month 10,000 people demonstrated in one hundred and seven cities across the world. They came together to make the first breach in the wall of silence," added the statement.</p>
<p>Despite the incident, 'Tim' was friendly to the protesters, even stating that "he might be back later to have a few cupcakes."</p>
<p>According to a member of Anonymous, "we will come again, our numbers ever increasing, in April, May, June and July."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Buffalo Gallery</hi></p>
<list type="unordered">
<item style="width: 155px;">Police detain three members of anonymous videotaping and photographing the Church and pictured here, the officer confiscates the tape.</item>
</list>
<head id="Seattle,_Washington"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Seattle">Seattle</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington">Washington</ref></head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Correspondent: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Roninbk">RoninBK</ref></hi></p>
<p>The Seattle protest was divided into two halves. One group was to assemble at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westlake%20Center">Westlake Center</ref>, and would march from there to the Scientology site. The other group was to meet at the Seattle Center, closer to the site, disseminating fliers to the crowd.</p>
<p>Protesters began to gather in front of Westlake Center at about 9:30 PDT. with about a dozen protesters at first. One of the protesters revealed to me that he was a 30 year former member of the Church of Scientology from the Los Angeles area. He asserted that "this protest is just." He spoke of former members who have been afraid to come out, because of the continuously reinforced teachings of the church. Members are cautioned against looking onto the Internet for alternate information, that they could die if they were to even look at the Internet. The mind is trained not to seek out any information that could contradict the church's teachings. He said that if the Scientologists ever knew what really happens in the church management, they would be terrified, and turn away in droves.</p>
</text>
