<text id="autogum_interview_doc1242" title="part5_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Well, right.  So I don't know why I don't.  I didn't read that, it was just--you know, it was an upsetting thing to have happen; the lawsuit was upsetting, and I think for me it was most upsetting because of the media glomming onto it and thinking, ‘Well of course, it's because of James Frey!’  Just associating with that whole thing…</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you listen to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NPR">NPR</ref> interview with your mom?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I heard about it.  I didn't hear it.  But my mother--I'll tell you something funny.  The first thing my mother said to me-- it was an email.  I haven't been in contact with her now for years.  But right after or before Running with Scissors came out I told her there's a book coming out, and my mother said to me, "What will I tell my media??"  My mother--and so, it's not surprising--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  She's still in that ‘I’m <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anne%20Sexton">Anne Sexton</ref>’ thinking?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Absolutely.  My mother believes that she's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grace%20Paley">Grace Paley</ref>.  My mother believes that she's the most famous woman in the world, or should be--the most famous poet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s ironic that the notoriety she's received has been via you; do you think that in some ways she likes it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Oh, I know she likes it.  Oh, absolutely.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  There's no such thing as bad publicity.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Right.  My mother could get published tomorrow now if she wanted to.  You know?  I love my mother because she's my mother, but I don't like her.  I don’t like the woman.  And I don't want to have anything to do with her, and I don't consider her a mother--she's the woman who gave birth to me, but she's not a mother in the sense of mothering a child.  I was watching <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Annette%20Benning">Annette Benning</ref> on the set of the movie <hi rend="italic">Running with Scissors</hi> with her daughter.  We were sitting around talking and Annette was telling a story to the crew.   I watched her daughter reach up and grab Annette's earlobe, and then Annette just--without stopping, without breaking the conversation, she bent forward so that her daughter could kiss her.  And it was the most natural thing in the world.  When I saw that, I knew--Annette may very well have a staff of twelve for all I know, but she's changed every diaper on that girl.  I knew she had changed every diaper on her daughter.  Because there was an intimacy.  The daughter was not filled with this desperate need.  She had full access to her mother.  And if she happened to want, in the middle of her mother's story, to have a kiss, it was a given that her mother would acknowledge that need.</p>
</text>
