<text id="autogum_interview_doc1335" title="part0_An interview with Paul Campbell, founder of Amazing Radio UK" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-10" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_Paul_Campbell%2C_founder_of_Amazing_Radio_UK" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>An interview with Paul Campbell, founder of Amazing Radio UK</head><figure><caption>Paul Campbell</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 14, 2010</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital%20radio%20in%20the%20United%20Kingdom">Digital radio</ref> listeners in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">UK</ref> may have noticed a new station on their list over the last few months with the beta launch of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazing%20Radio">Amazing Radio</ref>, founded by Paul Campbell as a follow up and companion to Amazing Tunes.  However, unlike the majority of the other stations on both digital and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FM">FM</ref>, Amazing Radio doesn't play normal, mainstream music.  Instead, its playlist consists solely of music from unsigned bands and artists who have signed up and uploaded their music to AmazingTunes.com.  Their music can then be downloaded from the site, for which they get paid.  The more downloads and interest an artist receives, the more likely they are to get played on the national radio station.  Amazing markets itself as an "ethical" download website, on which artists get 70% of the download revenues.  They now have more than 22,000 songs uploaded, with about 100 uploaded every day.  </p>
<hi rend="bold">Blimey, I sound like some corporate twat.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Paul Campbell</p>
<p>Paul Campbell himself has extensive experience in both radio and television production, having worked for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC%20Radio%204">BBC Radio 4</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Channel%204">Channel 4</ref>.  After success with his own production company in the nineties and with support from investors, Campbell launched Amazing Tunes in 2005.</p>
<p>As Amazing Radio introduces a new schedule for the New Year, with presenters rather than solely pre-recorded links, Wikinews reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tristan_Thomas">Tristan Thomas</ref> interviewed Campbell to find out more.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Hi Paul, thanks for doing this interview.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Paul Campbell</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> My pleasure – thanks very much for asking me.  We’re really grateful that Wikinews is interested in us.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">At the end of 2009, you complained to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC%20Trust">BBC Trust</ref> about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC%20Introducing">BBC Introducing</ref>.  Can you explain what this was about and the reasons for it.  Has anything come of it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PC</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Sure: in a nutshell, the complaint was about unfair competition - about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC">BBC</ref> not following its own rules.  It’s still ongoing. It will take, ahem, a while to resolve. </p>
<p>The details are a bit complex, but here goes.  (If you commit suicide out of the boredom at what follows, I apologise). </p>
<p>As British readers will know, the BBC has a guaranteed and very comfortable income derived from the Licence Fee - effectively a tax you have to pay if you want a TV.  According to Wikipedia (so it must be true), this generates an income to the BBC of about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pound%20sterling">stg</ref>4.5bn per annum.  Nice. </p>
<hi rend="bold">BBC people live in an insulated, publicly-funded world</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Paul Campbell</p>
<p>Not really.  In recent years the beeb has increasingly used this gargantuan income - and its incredible audience reach online, on radio &amp; TV - to launch new services that make life impossible for everyone who is not the BBC.  These have ranged from e-learning content (that completely wrecked the market for private publishers), to a new digital radio station (that caused a private speech station to go bust), to an attempt to launch online regional news services (which caused howls of outrage from local newspapers).  The BBC does it for the best of reasons – to provide a public service – but BBC people live in an insulated, publicly-funded world, one where you know with complete certainty you’ll get paid on the 15th of every month. It’s a million miles away from the real world, where entrepreneurial people take risks, and lose their jobs and their houses if it goes wrong.  Here, the BBC’s actions have grave implications.  And not just for private companies: the UK as a whole is very good at creative industries, which are the fastest-growing part of the economy. But it’s kinda hard to grow a global business if your domestic market has been wrecked by a rampaging, publicly-funded, bull in a china shop.  So by accidentally knackering private companies, the BBC is also damaging the British economy.  </p>
</text>
