<text id="autogum_interview_doc1110" title="part1_'Top Model' winner CariDee English on her modeling career and her battle with psoriasis" shortTile="parttop-model-winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-07" dateModified="2014-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/%27Top_Model%27_winner_CariDee_English_on_her_modeling_career_and_her_battle_with_psoriasis" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">CE:</hi> No, I could never move back to North Dakota. What would I do?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Well, you were a fashion photographer, you could have went back there for some work...although I don't know how much you'd be in demand there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CE:</hi> Yeah, it wasn't even an option! Not a thought.</p>
<head id="On_representing_the_National_Psoriasis_Foundation">On representing the National Psoriasis Foundation</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> So you're currently a spokeswoman for the National Psoriasis Foundation. What have you found, in your interactions with others who have had the disease, are their reactions once the disease manifests itself?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CE:</hi> I think a lot of people try to hide away from it, and I want people to be comfortable in their own skin, no pun intended. I just want people to be comfortable with themselves, because I know I hid under clothes for years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> In your experience as ambassador, what story touched you the most?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CE:</hi> It really makes me upset because there are a lot of great medications out there and the government won't fund payments for patients. There was a 9-year-old boy who was on a great medicine and then his insurance dropped him from it. It came back and it's now covered 95% of his body. You know, it's just heartbreaking to be able to be treated for it and then not be able to afford it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Were your reactions to psoriasis and discovering you had it comparable with those of other people?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CE:</hi> No, because I understood what it was when I had it. Other people may be scared of it when they discover they have it, because they might not know what it is.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Did relating with others with the condition give you a personal boost?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CE:</hi> Oh, yeah, absolutely. Seeing a little boy, healing and still living life, that's an inspiration to me. We're all just trying to be here for each other. No one person is above anyone else, we're just trying to support each other and find a cure together.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> As an ambassador for psoriasis awareness, you've become a role model of sorts to young girls and women who are afflicted with the disease. What kind of advice have you given to people coping with the disease?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CE:</hi> "I have psoriasis, I don't let psoriasis have me." Don't live your life through your disease.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Do you think that having had obstacles like your psoriasis and depression have helped you enter the industry more grounded than other girls who may not have had such rough experiences?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CE:</hi> Yeah, I mean, I only know my own experiences, but I didn't take anything for granted. I was grateful for being able to start in such a difficult industry and having that background to be able to overcome things on my own.</p>
</text>
