<text id="autogum_interview_doc636" title="part1_Wikinews holds a follow-up interview with Max Riekse, Constitution Party candidate for the 2008 U.S. presidential election" shortTile="partwikinews-holds" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-25" dateModified="2013-04-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_holds_a_follow-up_interview_with_Max_Riekse%2C_Constitution_Party_candidate_for_the_2008_U.S._presidential_election" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How would you handle foreign relations with Europe, where there are growing anti-American feelings?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Lt. Colonel Riekse:</hi> I fully understand and appreciate the feelings that Europeans have for us, especially in regards to our foreign policy. I've been to Europe, including Iceland, the Netherlands, France, Germany, Russia and some five other European countries, both as part of my military service and as a tourist.  I have found Europeans most friendly and easy to get along with and communicate with.  As president, we will get on very well with all Europeans, especially Russia.  Russia has huge natural gas &amp; oil deposits and it would do well that we be on good, friendly terms with them.  We can be great friends if we try to.  All Europeans will be treated with dignity and respect in my administration.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Gasoline is already $3.50 a gallon and will most likely be $4.00 by summer. As president, how would you control the increasing prices?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Lt. Colonel Riekse:</hi> Gasoline and also diesel fuel which American truckers depend on, is subject largely to the law of supply and demand. Would I would do as president is push the oil companies very hard to build two new oil refiners; one on the east coast and one on the west coast in 1-3 years which will be a great help in keeping the price of gas diesel fuel down. Also, I will push hard for reducing the stress on depending on foreign oil be pushing hard for sun, wind and water power, thus greatly reducing the need for foreign oil which will also help keep the price down. I believe that we can get the price of a gal of gas down to $1.00  We also need to cut the federal gas and diesel fuel tax by 70%. We can save a lot of money for building up our roads and bridges by not sending that money to Washington.</p>
<p>Another way to help bring down gas &amp; diesel fuel cost is to put an end to free &amp; unfair trade which has greatly increased the cost of gas &amp; diesel fuel for truckers in this country. As 'third' world demand for oil raises, especially in China, it pushes up the cost of oil for consumers in this country. Our huge trade imbalance with communist China helps fuel the Chinese economy thus increasing their 'need' and demand &amp; competition for  worldwide oil supply. American consumers buying cheap Chinese goods are not only helping the Chinese build up their economy, but also helping to drive up the cost of oil.  I will slap a stiff tariff on all Chinese imports; and lead a nationwide boycott of all Chinese imports to not only drive down the huge trade deficit with Red China, no real friend of the United States of America, but also to help bring back good paying manufacturing jobs with vested pensions and quality health benefits to working Americans. And finally, to pressure the Chinese to free Tibet from harsh deadly and repressive communist rule. Stop genocide on the Roof of the World.</p>
</text>
