<text id="autogum_interview_doc1060" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Marion Schaffer, Oakville" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-24" dateModified="2013-05-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_candidate_Marion_Schaffer%2C_Oakville" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I am part of local environmental groups fighting to control development and conserve green space. I give financial support to The Sierra Club, The Council of Canadians, Amnesty International, and The David Suzuki Foundation. I support women’s shelters and palliative care centers. I utilize alternative remedies to safeguard my own health. I write letters to politicians at all levels of government to speak against unwise decisions.</p>
<p>But, I am determined to be a less wasteful consumer.</p>
<p>Here are some examples of changes I am making:</p>
<p><list type="ordered"><item>I avoid driving out of Oakville for services of any kind (e.g. dentist, doctor, eye specialist, therapy, auto repair, shopping, beauty salon, rec centre, library, etc.).</item>
<item>I take GO train to attend events in the GTA.</item>
<item>I belong to, and support, local organizations which are striving to achieve similar goals and am striving to become a part of local groups to make new friends here.</item>
<item>In every possible way I am using less and less power in my home (e.g. state-of-the-art furnace and AC system, “green” lights, thermostats, using less water, unplugging appliances and using only energy saving appliances, etc.).</item></list></p>
<p>This list is just a small sample of the many, many things I know I need to do in order to help save our planet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>The first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly should be to declare to the people of Ontario that everyone in the house must pledge to work together to assure a clean environment for all species on our planet and a sustainable future for our children.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>I think Oakville taxes are where they should be; we are served well.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>As far as stimulating new jobs is concerned Ontario should work at creating “green jobs”, that is jobs which will allow our province to manufacture fuel-efficient vehicles, wind turbines, better public transit, sustainable agriculture and forestry, eco-tourism, energy-efficient materials and construction. I think we should pay for what we burn, not what we earn. All these ideas have been put forward in the Green Party of Ontario platform paper.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mixed%20member%20proportional%20representation">mixed member proportional representation</ref> (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>We will have a more participatory democracy if we change the way we vote and adopt Mixed Member Proportional representation. Government of the people, for the people, by the people is the cornerstone of Green Party policy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does “new media” play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
</text>
