<text id="autogum_interview_doc511" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Jim Babka, chair of Libertarian organization Downsize DC" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-02" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jim_Babka%2C_chair_of_Libertarian_organization_Downsize_DC" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>One way we can really address this is through a series of laws, and perhaps, one day, constitutional amendments, which would truly limit Congress in their ability to spend, create and maintain programs, and pass new laws and regulations.</p>
<p>Congress doesn't read their bills and they frequently pass these long un-read bills with little or no time to review them. We have proposed the Read the Bills Act to remedy that problem. The Read the Bills Act has the added benefit of requiring Congress to post their bills online for reporters, watchdog groups, and every day citizens to be able to read for seven days before the final vote.</p>
<p>Because we realized that to get around the Read the Bills Act, Congress might cheat, abbreviate their proposals, and just delegate the nitty-gritty details into the hands of unelected bureaucrats who aren't accountable to the people, we proposed the Write the Laws Act. An elected Congress should sweat the details and then be accountable to their constituents.</p>
<p>Congress also violates the rules of your high school government class, where you were told it took a majority to pass a law. Congress simply combines bad proposals that wouldn't stand on their own, like the Real ID Act (which should be repealed), into bills that are certain to pass, such as a troop appropriation bill. To deal with that problem we presented the One Subject at a Time Act.</p>
<p>And in the future, we'll call for government to follow it's [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] own accounting and reporting rules for the private sector, ala Sarbanes-Oxley, and a sunset provision requiring all taxes and programs to come up for a vote for re-authorization, with the requirement that they too be read, in full.</p>
<p>And it's funny because once I get away from the professional, political culture – "the beltway crowd" – and being talking to the Americans that pay the bills – the people in "flyover country" – I find that it doesn't matter what political party people come from. Nearly everyone I meet thinks Congress should be required to read their bills and post them online for seven days, pass bills one subject at a time, and be required to conduct periodic review so that some government programs that don't work get shut down. These proposals are… transpartisan.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Many people consider organizations like yours to be ultra conservative. Would you agree with this judgement. If not, why not?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JB</hi>: I don't even know what that means. It sounds a bit pejorative. I wouldn't agree with that judgment, but I'd want to know what the definition of conservative is.</p>
<p>In our era, those wearing the appellation "conservative" have, by their actions, if not their rhetoric, defined conservative as… large deficit spending: "monopoly money" policies; corporate welfare alliances; first amendment restrictions; greatly diminished civil liberties in the face of a boogey-man threat; an unconstitutional, unified executive theory; the leap into unconstitutional, pre-emptive wars, also based on boogey-man threats; and an empire. I could go on and on. But if that's all "conservative," then we'd want nothing to do with it.</p>
</text>
