<text id="autogum_interview_doc1024" title="part0_Blown for Good author discusses life inside international headquarters of Scientology" shortTile="partblown-good-author" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-11-12" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Blown_for_Good_author_discusses_life_inside_international_headquarters_of_Scientology" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Blown for Good author discusses life inside international headquarters of Scientology</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 13, 2009</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> interviewed author Marc Headley about his new book <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blown%20for%20Good">Blown for Good</ref></hi>, and asked him about life inside the international headquarters of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology">Scientology</ref> known as "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gold%20Base">Gold Base</ref>", located in Gilman Hot Springs near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hemet,%20California">Hemet, California</ref>. Headley joined the organization at age seven when his mother became a member, and worked at Scientology's international management headquarters for several years before leaving in 2005.</p>
<head id="Background">Background</head>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">Blown for Good</hi> by <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/category:Marc%20Headley">Marc Headley</ref> Image: <ref target="http://blownforgood.com/">blownforgood.com</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Blown for Good</hi> was released November 5, and is available at www.blownforgood.com. Headley worked as an employee of Scientology for 15 years. While an employee of the Scientology headquarters located in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riverside%20County,%20California">Riverside County, California</ref>, Headley had the experience of practicing Scientology counseling services called "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auditing%20(Scientology)">auditing</ref>" with Scientologist <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tom_Cruise">Tom Cruise</ref>, shortly after the actor had completed work on the film <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Days%20of%20Thunder">Days of Thunder</ref></hi>. In 1990, Cruise was training to become proficient in the Scientology auditing techniques, and Headley was selected to become the actor's auditing partner. Cruise and Headley worked together for three weeks, while the actor was practicing his Scientology techniques known as the "Upper Indoctrination Training Routines". Headley says he was chosen to work with Cruise because he was a young staff member who was less likely to leave and discuss the actor's Scientology experiences with the media.</p>
<p>The book provides details of what life was like for the author inside the organization's headquarters. The inner flap of the book includes a map of the "International Headquarters of Scientology; Gilman Hot Springs, California". Headley writes that under the direction of Scientology leader <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_Miscavige">David Miscavige</ref>, employees who signed billion-year contracts routinely put in 100-hour weeks of work for minimal pay. According to Headley, possible discipline faced by the Scientology employees for perceived mistakes included being separated from family as part of the Scientology policy of "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/disconnection">disconnection</ref>", being declared a "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suppressive%20person">suppressive person</ref>", or being sent to the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rehabilitation%20Project%20Force">Rehabilitation Project Force</ref>", a program where Scientologists were assigned harsh labor.</p>
<p>Headley's tasks while working at the Scientology compound Gold Base included dealing with audiovisual equipment used for organization presentations and speeches by Miscavige, and supervising production of thousands of audiotapes of lectures given by Scientology's founder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L.%20Ron%20Hubbard">L. Ron Hubbard</ref>. From 1989 to 2005 Headley worked at the Scientology film production studio on scripts for movies which would be used to instruct new members of the organization on its practices. He faced repercussions from Miscavige if he could not meet production quotas. Headley asserts that he was physically abused by Miscavige, a claim made previously by other former Scientology officials in a series of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/investigative%20journalism">investigative articles</ref> published in the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St.%20Petersburg%20Times">St. Petersburg Times</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>The book gives background on a 9-minute long video of Tom Cruise, leaked to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Internet">Internet</ref> in January 2008, that featured the actor discussing his views on Scientology. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church%20of%20Scientology">Church of Scientology</ref>'s attempts to remove the leaked video from the Internet motivated the group <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anonymous%20(group)">Anonymous</ref> to focus its efforts against the organization. Headley writes that initially the promotional video about Cruise was supposed to feature celebrities including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Will%20Smith">Will Smith</ref> speaking about the actor, but Miscavige instead insisted Cruise should simply talk about himself. According to Headley, Scientology employees were made to watch videos of Cruise which had been spliced together from the actor's appearances in the media. </p>
</text>
