<text id="autogum_interview_doc169" title="part2_Canada&amp;apos;s Don Valley West (Ward 25) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-don-valley" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2007-06-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Don_Valley_West_%28Ward_25%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>•  Greater interaction between councillor and community with a view to engaging the community in decisions that effect the community and ensuring top quality customer service.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Intelligently managing the City's growth with its incumbent challenges relating to real estate development, traffic congestion, and environmental pollution.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> We live in a very exciting time and Toronto is a very exciting place that is growing at a phenomenal rate.  I am a well rounded individual and in the prime of life, energetic and dedicated to civic duty.  I want to use my experience, knowledge,  and intelligence to serve the people of Ward 25 and to engage them more fully in decisions that affect them in their community.  I also want to influence and inspire the direction of the growth of this wonderful city in a positive way.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> It is the ward in which I have lived for the past 17 years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have been involved in charity work with such organizations as Big Brothers, the church to which I belong, and fundraising for other health related causes. I am a avid fan of the arts in Toronto and have volunteered with a number of community groups that provide theatre to seniors and moderate income families. And I am past president of the Upper Canada Tenants Association.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Home Sweet Home, the greatest city in the world.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Most proud of:  The Toronto Green Development Standard.  It is time to put it into effect.</p>
<p>Least proud of: Wasteful spending habits - which impact directly on our property taxes and the City's debt.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> If you were elected as a "rookie" councillor, What would you bring to the table beyond the incumbent?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am a man who prefers to get out into the community and meet the people and I now work very hard to do that.  It amazes me that most people I speak to in the Ward, have no idea who their representative is and have never heard from him - this, to me, is an abrogation of a councillor's duty to her or his electorate.  I want to know their concerns, firsthand, and make every effort to provide the means by which they can communicate their concerns and also hear their suggestions for solutions.  I will forge effective partnerships with the leaders of the residential and business associations as well as representatives of the police, health and environmental bodies, religious groups, and others, in order to have their input and work together to get things done for the benefit of our community. Furthermore, I would be a strong voice at City Council in advocating for those issues at City Hall which directly impact Ward 25: development, taxes, solid wastes issues.  I believe the incumbent has not met the expectations of the community in these regards. Furthermore, I have 18 years' experience in managing a successful business working within strict budgets and tight timelines and would bring that experience to the position of City Councillor.</p>
</text>
