<text id="autogum_interview_doc269" title="part2_US free speech lawyer Marc Randazza discusses Glenn Beck parody" shortTile="partus-free-speech" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-10-19" dateModified="2019-02-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_free_speech_lawyer_Marc_Randazza_discusses_Glenn_Beck_parody" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Prior to your involvement in the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beck%20v.%20Eiland-Hall">Beck v. Eiland-Hall</ref></hi> case, what related legal experience have you had specifically related to the legal concepts of the case?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Marc Randazza</hi>: I am both a First Amendment lawyer and an intellectual property lawyer.  I practice in these areas, write on those areas, and taught them at the law school level.  Given that these are my areas of expertise, this case was directly in my strike zone.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Why did you agree to represent Isaac Eiland-Hall? What interested you about the case?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">When one citizen's constitutional rights are threatened, all of our rights are threatened, and I'm not letting that happen on my watch.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Marc Randazza</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: I took this case because of my sense of patriotism demanded it, as did my feelings about maintaining good karma.  I became a First Amendment lawyer because I believe deeply in the Constitution.  As my career has gone on, I've seen that often wealthy and powerful people are awfully thin skinned about criticism, and they use their money and power to attempt to silence "the little guy." However, when that happens, the guy who gets pushed around suffers, but so do all of us.  When one citizen's constitutional rights are threatened, all of our rights are threatened, and I'm not letting that happen on my watch.</p>
<p>Isaac was being bullied, he was worried, and he couldn't afford a lawyer.  After we spoke, he seemed like the kind of client I would be proud to represent, so I agreed to handle his case.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In your response brief in the <hi rend="italic">Beck v. Eiland-Hall</hi> case, you wrote, "Mr. Beck has all but begged to become the subject of a meme." Are you familiar with the concept of the term the "Streisand effect"? How do you think the Streisand effect applies to this case and to Glenn Beck's situation with regard to the Internet meme, and the website?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">The one thing that breathed life into this meme was Mr. Beck's reaction to it.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Marc Randazza</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: I am familiar with that concept.  This case clearly proved that the effect exists and should be treated as a law of nature.  Had Mr. Beck simply ignored this meme, it likely would have died out.  Most internet memes die quickly.  The one thing that breathed life into this meme was Mr. Beck's reaction to it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You wrote in the conclusion to the Eiland-Hall response brief, "there can be only one purpose to filing this complaint: as an attempt to silence a critic because he doesn't like being criticized." Can you explain your argument that Beck's legal actions are intended only to silence criticism?</hi></p>
</text>
