<text id="autogum_interview_doc903" title="part2_Interview with Reggie Bibbs on his life with neurofibromatosis" shortTile="partinterview-reggie" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2010-04-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Reggie_Bibbs_on_his_life_with_neurofibromatosis" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: You told me one time about a teacher in school who did something. Tell me about that.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: This was in junior-high and I was in special-ed and we would ride the smaller buses. So one day my bus was late and we were there, a group of kids, we were waiting for the bus. By this time some of the teachers were leaving. And there was one particular teacher that was leaving, and as he passed by he told me, "Wow, where did you get that thing from?" And I was shocked. He said, "Oh, never mind, I thought you were wearing a mask." It really hurt me because it was embarrassing and I had some friends with me — and it was a teacher. And I just felt really let down and betrayed because a teacher said this. And after he realized his mistake he never apologized, and that really hurt me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Have you encountered other incidents like this?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: There were a few. One that really springs to mind, was when I was going to an electronics store. My mom and I were walking to the door. We saw one of the managers locked the door and wave us away. I knew they weren't closed, it was in the middle of the afternoon on a Saturday, and there were people walking around, shopping. And he just locked the door and waved me away.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: What about others in your family with NF?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: Well, I'm the youngest of six, I have two sisters that have NF and they have milder cases. They have a few tumors on their body but none that are really disfiguring. And also, I had a brother, one other brother, that had neurofibromatosis. He had some of the tumors. He also developed a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neurinoma">neurosarcoma</ref>, he was about 46-years old and one of his tumors turned to cancer. That was really difficult for all of us because it was unexpected. My mom, she has it and she also has a few of the small tumors. Other than that, there is no one else in the family that have it.</p>
<head id="A_head_to_toe_body_tour">A head to toe body tour</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: If we had a tour of your body, show me from the head to your arms to your leg, how NF has affected you.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: NF has affected me by some of the tumors on my arms, and, I have a few on my back...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Can you show me your arm?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: My arms? Like here, some of the tumors right here...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Okay, you point to, like, the one on your elbow. Does that hurt?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: No this is very soft, and it doesn't hurt. And there's one here, and one here, and there's a few here...</p>
</text>
