<text id="autogum_interview_doc076" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Indiana State Senator Mike Delph" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-26" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Indiana_State_Senator_Mike_Delph" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Behnke: What is your religious affliation?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: We are Christian. We are not <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Roman_Catholicism">Catholic</ref>. That is a falsehood put out on Wikipedia, and I’m not sure where that came from. I think people just assume that if you have a lot of kids that you are Catholic. And there is one nice thing about that, we live right across the street from a very large prominent Catholic Parish called, Our Lady of Mt. Carmel, and they have a fall festival every year and so it's the one place we can go as a family where people don't give us funny looks because of the number of girls that I have, everybody has a large family in that parish.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Hello Senator Delph, I’m Jerrilyn Thompson, and I have a question for you. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sagamore%20of%20the%20Wabash%20Award">Sagamore of the Wabash Award</ref>, you were awarded that in 2005. And this honorary award is awarded by the Governor. And what did you do to get this honor?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: That was something that I was recommended by former Congressman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baron%20Hill">Baron Hill</ref>, who represented the southeastern part of the state.  And I had gotten to know Congressman Hill when I was an executive with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comcast">Comcast Corporation</ref>. We actually brought the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C-SPAN">C-SPAN</ref> school bus throughout his district, especially to his hometown of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seymour,%20Indiana">Seymour</ref>, Indiana. And we had gotten to know each other, and he found out that I had served as an international election observer with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International%20Republican%20Institute">International Republican Institute</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nicaragua">Nicaragua</ref> in 1996 and then in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mongolia">Mongolia</ref> in 2000. And then he had also learned about my service with Congressman Burton and also here in the state of Indiana, and he was gracious to recommend me for that award. And then Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe%20Kernan%20(politician)">Kernan</ref>, before he left office as our governor, was very gracious to award me the Sagamore of the Wabash.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Thompson: Okay, just a few more questions. You had mentioned earlier about the role that Congressman Dan Burton had played in your life, could you please talk a little bit more about that?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: Well certainly. He is somebody that was my boss, I’ve known him for a good chunk of my life. When I was thirteen or fourteen, I served as a page for him. When he was an Indiana state senator. I had volunteered a little bit on his political campaigns but not a great deal. Primarily putting stickers on fire hats in preparation for his parade season.</p>
<p>But I worked for him from — I want to say — 1996 to 2004. Roughly eight years, give or take. I served as a member of his professional staff when he was chairman of the House Committee on Government Reform and Oversight. And then I also served as a member of his professional staff, handling a number of different policy areas, including foreign policy and national security policy. I covered agricultural issues and environmental policy forum, given some of my academic background. But primarily in the national security foreign policy area, primarily focused on anti-narcotics and the drug war. I was able to travel — in addition to traveling when I was an international election observer — I was able to travel as a member of his staff to countries like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Turkey">Turkey</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Colombia">Colombia</ref>.</p>
</text>
