<text id="autogum_interview_doc1227" title="part10_The Onion: An interview with 'America's Finest News Source'" shortTile="partthe-onion-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2013-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Onion%3A_An_interview_with_%27America%27s_Finest_News_Source%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  That was a major launch for us this year with The Onion News Network.  It has been a huge hit.  We get over a million downloads a week, which makes it one of the more successful produced-for-the-Internet videos.  If we’re not the most successful, we’re one of the most.  It is a 24 hour news network.  We have a new show that is part of the platform, but we also have a Sunday morning talk show that’s called “In The Know” and we just launched a morning show this last week called “Today Now.”  It has been really exciting; we’ll have some new shows, show some archive footage and do some more in sports over the next year.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What’s the idea behind the Onion News Network?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  The Onion is a media empire.  We have newspapers and a website, so a 24 hour news network makes a lot of sense.  Creatively, it is very different from other things that are out there.  There are former <hi rend="italic">Onion</hi> writers and editors that have gone on to have big influence on <hi rend="italic">The Daily Show</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Colbert Report</hi>; the Onion News Network is straight, it’s serious.  Those other shows are more like sketch comedy, in a way.  They have a host who is a performer.  There’s a live studio audience.  Everybody is on the joke, there’s voices, there’s faces…it’s very similar to a late-night talk show.  Like a Johnny Carson experience.  The Onion News Network is 24 hour news.  You’re watching what looks like Fox News, CNN and all of our other competitors.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How much do the writers and editors on the print side inform the news network side?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  The primary writers are separate, but there’s a lot of cross-over and creative influence.  The Onion News Network came out of the proud tradition of The Onion and it has been influenced by that.  Our editor-in-chief, Scott Dikkers, is the creative force behind both.  Some of the actual writers on the paper and the Internet site trade off and go over and submit scripts to the News Network; the News Network writers aren’t really writing for the paper.  But there are a lot of people getting in the same room.
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  We have former <hi rend="italic">Onion</hi> editor-in-chief <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carol%20Kolb">Carol Kolb</ref>, who left <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> a few years back, who has since returned to become head writer of The Onion News Network.   So there’s a lot of Onion history there as well.</p></p>
<head id="Relationship_with_other_satirical_news_programs">Relationship with other satirical news programs</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Many of the writers for The Onion have gone on to Daily Show and Colbert.  Is there any collusion that you guys ever do, or a relationship that is fostered?</hi></p>
</text>
