<text id="autogum_interview_doc272" title="part1_Dublin travel agents occupy offices against closure" shortTile="partdublin-travel" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-08-02" dateModified="2012-03-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dublin_travel_agents_occupy_offices_against_closure" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>TSSA headquarters in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref> Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User%20talk:Redvers">Redvers</ref>.</caption></figure><p>A series of TSSA demonstrations against Thomas Cook took place throughout July. Trade union <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unite%20the%20Union">Unite</ref> in Ireland has offered its support for the occupiers and says it will take place in demonstrations scheduled for Monday morning.</p>
<p>Thomas Cook has accused the TSSA of making use of "dirty tactics", according to a statement from Thomas Cook UK &amp; Ireland CEO Pete Constanti. A court order has been delivered to the Grafton Street office requiring the occupiers to turn the keys over to Thomas Cook management. The TSSA, meanwhile, says that Thomas Cook is "riding roughshod over the right to take industrial action by marching staff into a room and telling them they are going to close immediately".</p>
<p>Cullen says that the occupation began spontaneously. "We didn't think it would go so far", she told <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, but when the closure of the office was announced, the staff "opened the windows and started screaming, 'we're not moving, we're not moving'. We haven't moved since."</p>
<figure><caption>Grafton Street, Dublin Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Donaldytong">Donaldytong</ref>.</caption></figure><p>Monday, August 3 is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public%20holidays%20in%20the%20Republic%20of%20Ireland">bank holiday in Ireland</ref>. Both sides in the dispute have delivered ultimata: Thomas Cook management demands that all staff return to work on Tuesday morning as usual or else the offer of five weeks' pay will be reduced to the statutory two weeks' pay, while the TSSA says that if Thomas Cook management do not produce a better redundancy offer by Tuesday then the business will face a boycott by the TSSA's 800,000 members.</p>
<p>Ireland's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialist%20Party%20(Ireland)">Socialist Party</ref> and Dublin <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Member%20of%20the%20European%20Parliament">MEP</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe%20Higgins">Joe Higgins</ref> have declared their support for the Thomas Cook occupiers, with a press release on Higgins' official webpage saying </p>
The High Court order for workers to end their occupation and the threat of Garda action is a disgrace....The trade union movement must mobilise to prevent the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garda%20Síochána">Gardaí</ref> [the Irish police] being used against these workers. Supporters and trade union activists should come to the offices to support the workers’ action and defend the occupation against any attempt to force them out.
<p> Socialist Party members have been leafletting Dublin over the weekend promoting demonstrations in support of the Thomas Cook employees. The smaller <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialist%20Workers%20Party%20(Ireland)">Socialist Workers Party</ref> has also declared its support and conducted demonstrations for the occupiers.</p>
<p>Cullen said that the support of the Dublin community has been "absolutely fantastic". People are bringing the occupiers fresh-baked scones and cakes and donating money, while morale inside the occupied store is "brilliant". In contrast to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Food_packages_to_Vestas_occupiers_cut_off">occupation at Vestas</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref>, where employees have been inside the factory continuously for two weeks, Thomas Cook employees have a chance to go home for a few hours or sleep in one of five rooms at a nearby hotel, although many do sleep in the office overnight. Nearby businesses are providing the occupiers with food at discount prices and, again in contrast to Vestas, the police and security are not interfering with the arrival of food and drink. Thomas Cook management have cut off telephone and internet access to at least some of the affected offices, but employees stay in touch with the outside world via their personal mobile telephones.</p>
</text>
