<text id="autogum_interview_doc1390" title="part13_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you were ten, when you were preaching—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Yeah, exactly.  People say now I’m living by ambition or whatever else they accuse me of, but what was I living by when I was ten years old?  Twelve years old when I joined Breadbasket.  It’s also frightening because it makes you all the more a target for every critic.  There’s not a month that goes by that we don’t have a serious death threat.  Every criminal justice guy is trying to topple you.  So you become a target as much as it is flattering, so I always remember the upside and the downside of it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s interesting that you have become that to other people.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  It is, but I’ll tell you what else is interesting that she said—and I don’t know if she intended to say it this way or not—when she said I’m "Reverend 9-1-1".  What a lot of people don’t understand, particularly in the white community, is I’m projected as an ambulance chaser.  But I’m more the ambulance.  People call me because they know I will come.  If nothing else you write, I have never fought a case where they didn’t ask me to come.  People have this picture like I’m sitting up in bed at night with a walkie-talkie.  “You hear anything?  Oh, let’s run!  It’s Virginia today!”  People call us.  Jena all the way to Florida all the way to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20Byrd,%20Jr.">Jasper, Texas</ref>, all the way to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sean%20Bell">Sean Bell</ref>.  Every victim calls us.  On my syndicated radio show now if we get a case I make the victim get on and say, “Now, you <hi rend="italic">asked</hi> me to get involved in this?”  That’s what I did with Jena.  Now nobody remembers because nobody knew what Jena was then.  We respond to a person coming in, which is why it’s absurd when black conservatives, “Who put Sharpton in charge?”  The victim!  Who put me in charge of Jena?  The people involved with Jena asked me to come.  What gives you the right to tell people not to have who they want to represent them.  Could you imagine?  I’m leading the march on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean%20Six">Jena</ref>, asked to come in by the parents of the kid in jail, and they’re going to sit on MSNBC that night and ask, “Well, why is Al Sharpton leading it?”  Because the parents of the kid asked me to lead it!  Duh!  So at least let’s be straight-up about it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think the criticism is more because you are successful for bringing attention to it?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  If I was not able to bring public attention, they would care less.  And let’s face it: some of them are very cynical and know they can get a lot of play criticizing me.  I was talking about it at the rally this morning—we have rallies here every Saturday.  You have one guy, I can’t think of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jason%20Whitlock">his name</ref>, a sportswriter from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kansas%20City">Kansas City</ref> who made a <hi rend="italic">career</hi> out of criticizing me about Imus.  He did every talk show.  “Sharpton’s wrong!”  Nobody ever said, “Wait a minute, you a sportswriter, what are you speaking for?  What are you talking about it?”  It’s ludicrous.</p>
</text>
