<text id="autogum_interview_doc729" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Brian Moore, Socialist Party USA presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-30" dateModified="2016-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Brian_Moore%2C_Socialist_Party_USA_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">What skills or ideas do or previous positions, you bring from this position that will benefit the Oval Office?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Moore:</hi> Not sure your question is clear.  I have worked in the private and public sector, for-profit and non-profit sectors, domestically and internationally, as an administrator, project director, fundraiser and in sales. I have worked with the poor and solicited funds from corporations and governments as well. I speak <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spanish%20language">Spanish</ref> and some <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portuguese%20language">Portuguese</ref>, and have traveled and lived in South America for almost eight years. I have been involved civically and politically and professionally for forty years, I play sports and attend cultural events, and feel I am well-rounded.  I speak out forthrightly on the issues, take strong and clear stands, take the initiative a lot and leader and/or start causes and projects in a leadership capacity.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Obviously, the next American President and his or her administration will face many diverse issues. But if you were to narrow identify the three most important issues, what would they be? How will you address these issues?</hi></item></list>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Freedom and Privacy Rights:</hi> Abolish the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patriot%20Act">Patriot Act</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military%20Commissions%20Act%20of%202006">Military Tribunal bill</ref>, all executive orders that water down people's rights, and abolish all intelligence agencies overseas and the Homeland Security Agency at home.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Radically Change Economic System:</hi> Transition America's economic system from capitalism to socialism in an efficient, expeditious, non-violent, civil, respectful way in order to eliminate all for-profit corporations and turn full authority and social ownership to the community and control over to workers.  We do not advocate "government ownership" but all decisions will be made from the bottom up, and a redistribution of wealth will begin to take effect.  Workers therefore have, if anything, a GREATER incentive to work hard under socialism than under capitalism because they are able to retain a much greater portion of the value of their own labor.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">End the Iraq and Afghanistan Wars and Bring the American Troops and Corporations Home Immediately:</hi> Immediately end the two wars, and remove our troops and American corporations within a month or two. Assure protection and departure for citizens in danger of retaliation. Turn control of Iraq over to a new coalition or Iraqi tribes to decide on the political outcome of the new country.  Provide generous reparations to Iraq and Afghanistan for the destruction of the infrastructure and culture the United States has caused.  Proceed to make efforts to register any and all war crimes by our political and military leaders, and our allies, and request the Hague and International Law to hold accountable any and all political and military leaders from America, and its allies, responsible for crimes against humanity.</item></list></p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">My grandfather emigrated from Ireland in 1949, some of my relatives lived here illegally, you yourself have Irish immigrant grandparents, what is your opinion on the immigration battle that is occurring today in America?</hi></item></list>
</text>
