<text id="autogum_interview_doc082" title="part9_Wikinews interviews Indiana State Senator Mike Delph" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-26" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Indiana_State_Senator_Mike_Delph" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Tew: But there is also the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Supreme_Court_of_the_United_States">Supreme Court</ref> that the legislature would have to deal with any kind of decision that's made between now and when they act next.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: Certainly, there is a couple of things at play there. Recently, I think in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Michigan">Michigan</ref>, they stuck down and then stayed the decision — the Michigan <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Same-sex%20marriage%20in%20Michigan#Constitutional_amendment">constitutional amendment</ref>. So there is no question that the federal courts are getting involved. There is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourteenth%20Amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution#Equal_Protection_Clause">equal protection ground</ref> litigation that is being filed throughout the country. And specifically in Indiana, I think, there has been four law suits filed challenging the Indiana Statute, which has been on the books since 1986. And so this is a big battle that's going on legally.</p>
<p>Traditionally, the widely held view is that the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Constitution">US Constitution</ref> trumps the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitution%20of%20Indiana">State Constitution</ref> and that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20judiciary%20of%20the%20United%20States">federal decisions</ref> in court trump state constitutional law. And so those are all things that have to be reconciled with the public opinion, and with the will of the people, and what they want, and how they view their government, and how they want society to react and deal with these types of issues.</p>
<p>But there is no question that even if we would have passed the constitutional amendment and even if the public would have adopted it, that that did not prevent a court challenge in federal court.</p>
<p>Let me just make one more comment... To me though we cannot as a legislative body at the state level of government, live in fear of litigation. We have an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Article%20Six%20of%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution#Oaths">Article 6</ref> oath of office that we take to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Constitution">US Constitution</ref> that binds all elected officials to the same <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/rule%20of%20law">rule of law</ref> — except the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States">President of the United States</ref>, who takes a separate oath of office. And that oath of office is to the written Constitution, as written in the Constitution. It has nothing to do with common law, has nothing to do with Supreme Court decisions and <hi rend="italic">stare decisis</hi> [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/precedent">precedent</ref>]. It has to do with the written law, the written constitution. We also take an oath to uphold the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitution%20of%20Indiana">Indiana state constitution</ref>.</p>
<p>And that oath of office is something I take very, very seriously. And that is what should drive us, our own understanding of the Constitution — not any fear of litigation in Federal Court.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Devyn Curry: Can you briefly give us your version of the chronology from the time you made the "tweet heard around the world" to the time when you were punished for the tweet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: I will try to do the best that I can. You know the irony in all of this is that HJR-3 was really not my issue. I had found through interaction with the governor's staff that the governor [<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mike_Pence">Mike Pence</ref>] was pretty displeased with what was going on the legislature, particularly in the House of Representatives. He could not understand how a super majority House and a super majority Senate could not get this issue to the voters. He spoke in favor of HJR-3 and in a "State of the State" address and then in an additional follow-up interview with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WISH-TV">WISH-TV</ref> political reporter Jim Shella — WISH-TV is at channel 8, our <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CBS_News">CBS News</ref> affiliate in Indianapolis. And so I was trying to help them behind the scenes. I worked with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dennis%20Kruse">Senator [Dennis] Kruse</ref>, who had told me that Senator [David] Long had wanted to control that process and have Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/R.%20Michael%20Young">Mike Young</ref> introduce the amendment on the floor that would restore the second sentence so that we could adopt the entire amendment and send it to the voters.</p>
</text>
