<text id="autogum_interview_doc1129" title="part7_Dalai Lama's representative talks about China, Tibet, Shugden and the next Dalai Lama" shortTile="partdalai-lamas-representative" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-13" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dalai_Lama%27s_representative_talks_about_China%2C_Tibet%2C_Shugden_and_the_next_Dalai_Lama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<head id="The_views_of_the_Dalai_Lama">The views of the Dalai Lama</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is His Holiness’ view on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Abortion">abortion</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  He has said many times that as a Buddhist taking a life is wrong.  But on abortion it depends on so many other factors and stages of the development of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fetus">fetus</ref>.  And the circumstances.  It’s a question for the mother and the child, and he did say if there are developmental issues.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  He believes that it should be a personal decision and not a governmental decision?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But that it’s frowned upon as a Buddhist principle?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes.  But he has certainly spoken very often on population control, but that is more on the preventative side.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What are His Holiness’ views on homosexuality?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  He said according to Buddhist practice it is wrong.  In society, it is all right.  I think of it like this.  I am Buddhist.  You are Christian, let’s say.  For me, I have to follow the precepts and principles as a Buddhist.  For me it would be wrong to do that.  But it would be wrong for me to say it is wrong for you because in multicultural, multireligious societies you can’t do that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So if somebody is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homosexuality%20and%20Buddhism">gay they could not be a proper Buddhist</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  I’m sure under certain precepts of Buddhist tradition, a person would not be considered as following ALL the precepts of Buddhist principles.  People don’t follow all the principles.  Very few people can claim they follow all the principles.  For instance, telling a lie.  In any religion, if you ask if telling a lie is a sin—say Christian—they will say yes.  But you find very few people who don’t at some point tell a lie.  Homosexuality is one act, but you can’t say they are not a Buddhist.  Or someone who tells a lie is not a Buddhist.  Or someone who kills an insect is not a Buddhist, because there’s a strong injunction against that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have you ever killed an insect?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  I’m sure, yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is the Dalai Lama planning on visiting Latin America any time soon?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  There’s likelihood that it will be next year.  We are looking at it.  We have so many invitations from countries and every few years we look to see what we can fit in.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s likely next year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  We are thinking of it, yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you know why the Dalai Lama has not explicitly said he is a reincarnation of the Dalai Lama?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  In the broader sense, it is a manifestation, so you can manifest in different ways.  He is talking in that sense.  It’s a broad principle argument.</p>
</text>
