<text id="autogum_interview_doc1157" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Cecile Willert, Ajax—Pickering" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-07" dateModified="2007-12-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_Party_candidate_Cecile_Willert%2C_Ajax%E2%80%94Pickering" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Cecile Willert, Ajax—Pickering</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, October 7, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cecile Willert</hi> is running for the Green Party of Ontario in the Ontario provincial election, in the Ajax—Pickering riding. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref>' Nick Moreau interviewed her regarding her values, her experience, and her campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I decided to get involved because I strongly support the policies of the Green Party of Ontario and want to help ensure that the Green Party is taken seriously, gains in support and wins seats in this election. When the Green Party was seeking a candidate, I knew that I would be a strong candidate and put my name forward. Giving back to my community is important to me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I work closely with the Provincial government as a representative of the Ontario Environmental Industry Association’s Advocacy Committee and Co-chair of the association’s Brownfield Committee and through my professional work, ensuring protection of health and the environment. As a Professional Engineer and business leader, experienced in sound financial management, I offer real answers to solve real issues.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>The Liberal and Conservative candidates will pose the biggest challenge because their party’s are more established and thus have more inertia to carry them forward. The Green Party, on the other hand, is gaining momentum.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>The top issues are funding for religious schools, transportation and poverty; however, preservation of the green belt and farm incomes are also highly important to a large portion of the riding populous.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>The first order of business should be a budget. All actions of the Legislature must be economically sensible and should not be made without a budget in place, just the same as most people don’t go out spending all their pay check before establish what they can afford.</p>
</text>
