<text id="autogum_interview_doc926" title="part1_An interview with gossip columnist Michael Musto on the art of celebrity journalism" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-05" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_gossip_columnist_Michael_Musto_on_the_art_of_celebrity_journalism" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How does that feel when someone acknowledges you achieved an affect you wanted?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  It feels great.  I always was someone who marches to my own drum and I have been vilified for it at times, so it feels nice to be around long enough that people come around and say, 'Hey, maybe you are doing something good.'</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I photographed at the Tribeca Film Festival for Wikipedia, and a lot of the paparazzi photographer would talk in a derogatory way about the celebrities they were photographing, and they gave themselves a lot of credit for making their images.  Recently, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cindy%20Adams">Cindy Adams</ref> wrote in her column a blurb about something <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan%20Greenspan">Alan Greenspan</ref> said, and then she said something to the effect of, 'and I'd mention the name of his book if he had told me that to me first,' as if Greenspan is going to go run to Cindy Adams just to get a book mention in her column.  Is the celebrity press lacking humility because they report on the famous?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  It's a double-edged sword.  Because you are covering the celebrity, some of the celebrity glitter falls on you, and you experience a miniature version of celebrity yourself, especially if like me you go on TV a lot.  So you do develop this lofty idea that you're hot shit.  But then you go to an event, like a movie premiere, and you are reminded of your place in the food chain.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How so?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  You have to go through many hoops just to talk to a major celebrity.  You have to get past three different sets of publicists:  the publicist for the event, the publicist for the movie, and then the celebrity's personal publicist.  They all have to approve you.  Last night I talked to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kenneth%20Branagh">Kenneth Branagh</ref>, who directed <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sleuth%20(film)">Sleuth</ref></hi>, and the publicist had to approve me, talk to him, and then I saw him talk to his publicist and say, "Michael Musto...is that okay?"  And somehow she said yes.  That should actually fuel my ego more that I'm potentially risky enough that I have to get so much approval to even talk to somebody, but what you want in your mind is this fantasy like the Cindy Adams thing, of like, "Oh, let me come to you!"  And that often happens!  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tori%20Spelling">Tori Spelling</ref>'s publicist was like, 'Sorry, she's not talking right now,' but when Tori recognized me from TV she was like, 'Michael, come here, let's talk.'  So that's an ego-enhancing situation, but you are always going to be lower than the celebrity, no matter what.  Even if you think you are a celebrity yourself.</p>
<head id="On_celebrities">On celebrities</head>
</text>
