<text id="autogum_interview_doc463" title="part0_Caribou plays the Bowery Ballroom" shortTile="partcaribou-plays" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-06" dateModified="2014-03-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Caribou_plays_the_Bowery_Ballroom" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Caribou plays the Bowery Ballroom</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 6, 2007</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel%20V.%20Snaith">Daniel Snaith</ref>, better known as Caribou, formerly known as Manitoba until a lawsuit by musician <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard%20Manitoba">Richard "Handsome Dick" Manitoba</ref>, recently played <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20City">New York City</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bowery%20Ballroom">Bowery Ballroom</ref>.  Below is <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>'s conversation with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electronica">electronica</ref> pioneer.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  How is the tour going?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  It’s been really good so far.  We started with a few festivals in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Europe">Europe</ref> and then  did a month around the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">UK</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref>.  Over here we just did <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref> and this is the start of a big tour for us around the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">States</ref>.  Then Europe for another month.  It’s pretty full on, but I love playing shows.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do European and American audiences compare to each other?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  I get asked that all the time and I feel people are expecting some kind of an answer like we are better received in Europe, and I don’t know if people expect that of an electronic musician.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But they are more electronic in Europe than they are here, right?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  Maybe, but my experience is that people are more similar than different in all the shows, and the reaction is more similar than different.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You reach the same fans in each place?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  Yeah people are so connected to the interests that they share with other people around the world.  It’s not like one place is completely different from another anymore.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you play to larger audiences over there or here?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  It’s about the same, again.  When we play in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref> we play about same size venue and size crowd as we do here.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have a favorite venue?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  A few, actually.  Bowery Ballroom is one of my favorites.  It's always awesome.  The sound is so good here, which is really important.  It sounds good on stage, which is important for getting into the show.  We always have really amazing crowds in this place called Richards on Richards in Vancouver.  This venue in Slovenia we played that is this old commune squat that has lots of gigs and art going over there called the Metalkova.  The best ones are the surprises we'll play in a tiny little town in some venue that is like whatever.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What would be a dream venue to play?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  Something along the lines of this place we played in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South%20of%20France">south of France</ref> that was this 1920s arts patron villa where <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean%20Cocteau">Cocteau</ref> and all these people lived and worked, and we played just outside there overlooking the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French%20Riviera">French Riviera</ref> during this tiny little festival, so those ones are always fun when you just end up at some idyllic spot where they have put together a little festival with great bands.  Those tend to be in Europe, to be honest.  The surprise is part of the enjoyment when you arrive and it's like, this is an insane place to play.</p>
</text>
