<text id="autogum_interview_doc1084" title="part5_Vanity Fair contributing editor Craig Unger on the Bush family feud, neoconservatives and the Christian right" shortTile="partvanity-fair-contributing" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2015-08-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vanity_Fair_contributing_editor_Craig_Unger_on_the_Bush_family_feud%2C_neoconservatives_and_the_Christian_right" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why was there a dispute between Rumsfeld and Bush Sr.?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  It was ambition.  Rumsfeld had Presidential ambitions himself.</p>
<head id="Paul_Wolfowitz_and_the_Office_of_Special_Plans">Paul Wolfowitz and the Office of Special Plans</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Coming back to current times, what continues to transpire in the formation of Bush Jr.’s 2000 cabinet?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  They want to appoint Wolfowitz head of the CIA.  Well, there’s a problem: he is dean of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johns%20Hopkins%20University">Johns Hopkins</ref> School of Advanced International Studies, and he is allegedly caught having an affair with a female staff member.  He’s also allegedly having another extramarital relationship with another woman who had become more famous, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shaha%20Ali%20Riza">Shaha Ali Riza</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I believe Riza was called Wolfowitz’s “neoconcubine” by his critics.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Yes.  To him, that relationship was the romantic embodiment of the neocon venture: he’s a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secular%20Jew">secular Jew</ref>; she’s a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secular%20Muslim">secular Muslim</ref>.  He parades her on his arm at all the neocon events that season.  There’s one person who doesn’t like this situation:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clare%20Wolfowitz">Clare Wolfowitz</ref>, his wife of thirty years and mother of his three children.  She’s not happy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What does Mrs. Wolfowitz do about his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extramarital%20affair">extramarital affairs</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  She’s writes a letter to George W. Bush saying, ‘You can’t possibly make my husband head of the CIA because he’s a security risk,’—she has not commented on this, by the way—that ‘he’s a security risk not just because he has undisclosed relationships, but because one of them is with a foreign national, Shaha Ali Riza.’  This alleged letter I’m told was intercepted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scooter%20Libby">Scooter Libby</ref>, who is Wolfowitz’s protégé at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yale">Yale</ref> and is to become Chief of Staff to Dick Cheney.  They are now very wary of putting Wolfowitz up for Congressional hearings; this could be a mess!  Instead, they call in Donald Rumsfeld and they see that if they are going to handle intelligence they are going to do it through the Defense Department.  This is where the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office%20of%20Special%20Plans">Office of Special Plans</ref> gets created.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So they decide to redo the entire intelligence apparatus for Wolfowitz?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  This is an alternative national security apparatus.  We spend $40 billion a year on intelligence and a great power has to have accurate intelligence.  So they put up disinformation pipelines to have the intelligence they want to back up their policies.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What was the CIA’s reaction to this?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  They awaken to it bit by bit by bit.  The people in the CIA who were aware of it became incredibly angry and there were battles and some people who have spoken out about it are former CIA officials and defense intelligence people.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick%20Lang">Patrick Lang</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ray%20McGovern">Ray McGovern</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melvin%20Goodman">Melvin Goodman</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip%20Giraldi">Philip Giraldi</ref>, and so on.  I ended up with around ten people like that on the record.  The Defense Department was going ballistic. Rumsfeld and Cheney, in a stroke of bureaucratic brilliance, devise this way to hijack for the executive branch the whole national security apparatus.  They now can stop the bureaucracy when they want to, grease the wheels when they want to; for example, they put in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josh%20Bolton">Josh Bolton</ref> as under Secretary of State, who acts as a spy watching Colin Powell.</p>
</text>
