<text id="autogum_interview_doc022" title="part0_Wikinews attends ComicCon in Bangalore, India" shortTile="partwikinews-attends" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-12-03" dateModified="2019-08-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_attends_ComicCon_in_Bangalore%2C_India" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews attends ComicCon in Bangalore, India</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 8, 2017</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Cosplayers dressed up like Marvel comic's Loki and Spider-Man; depicting Loki's wish to rule the Earth. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Acagastya">Acagastya</ref>. (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:2017_Bangalore_ComicCon_(media)_IMG_1115.JPG">Reuseterms</ref>.)</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> attended the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bangalore">Bangalore</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comic%20Con">Comic Con</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/comic-book">comic-book</ref> convention on Saturday. Beginning on Saturday morning, it continued through to Sunday. Organised by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comic%20Con%20India">Comic Con India</ref>, who organised Comic Con in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hyderabad,_India">Hyderabad</ref> in October and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mumbai">Mumbai</ref> in November, this event was held at Karnataka Trade Promotion Organisation (KTPO)'s convention hall.  <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> spoke to convention guests Sailesh Gopalan and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Layman">John Layman</ref>.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freelancer">Freelancer</ref> comic book artist and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/illustrator">illustrator</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott%20Hampton">Scott Hampton</ref>, known for sketching <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Batman">Batman</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black%20Widow%20(Natasha%20Romanova)">Black Widow</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandman%20(Vertigo)">Sandman</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hellraiser">Hellraiser</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Star_Trek">Star Trek</ref>, was among the featured guests at the convention. Along with him, professional cosplayer Tabitha Lyons, who dressed up like DC Comics's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wonder%20Woman">Wonder Woman</ref> on Saturday; freelancer comic book writer John Layman, writer of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chew%20(comics)">Chew</ref></hi>, published by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Image%20Comics">Image Comics</ref>; creator of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen%20Pencils">Zen Pencils</ref></hi> Gavin Aung Than; and creator of <hi rend="italic">Brown Paperbag</hi> comics Sailesh Gopalan also attended the event as special guests.</p>
<p>The event started at 11 AM <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian%20Standard%20Time">IST</ref> (0530 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTC">UTC</ref>). Crossing between the genres of science fiction, horror, anime, fantasy and comics, the event sprawled throughout all corners of the facility. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marvel%20Comics">Marvel</ref> Zone, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon%20Video">Amazon Video</ref> zone, AXN Live RED Special Session, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Star_Wars">Star Wars</ref>' Last Jedi</hi> zone and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OnePlus">OnePlus</ref> smartphone zone attracted large number of audience. OnePlus, who were one of the sponsors of the event, had an exclusive launch of their new smartphone OnePlus 5T Star Wars, limited edition at about 5:30 PM. Marvel, <hi rend="italic">Star Wars</hi> and AXN Live RED zones had quizzes about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marvel%20Cinematic%20Universe">Marvel Cinematic Universe</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Star Wars</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">Sherlock Holmes</hi> TV series. Most of the Marvel questions were about the upcoming live action movie <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black%20Panther%20(film)">Black Panther</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>Holy Cow entertainment launched latest issues of their comics <hi rend="italic">Age of Immortals</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Caster</hi>. The Comic Con panel included sessions with Sailesh Gopalan about webcomics, <hi rend="italic">Zen pencils</hi> creator Gavin Aung Than, as well as Scott Hampton. Focusing on Indian mythology, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">Indian</ref> comic book publisher <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amar%20Chitra%20Katha">Amar Chitra Katha</ref> conducted a quiz, and asked questions like, "Who was the mother of Nakul and Sahdev?" from the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahabharat">Mahabharat</ref></hi>. After the quiz, people dressed as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stormtrooper%20(Star%20Wars)">Stormtroopers</ref>, soldiers from Star Wars, took the stage, for the launch of the limited edition of OnePlus 5T Star Wars. </p>
<figure><caption>Stormtroopers taking the stage during OnePlus 5T Star Wars limited edition launch. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Acagastya">Acagastya</ref>. (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:2017_Bangalore_ComicCon_(media)_IMG_0124.JPG">Reuseterms</ref>.)</caption></figure>
<p>Before the cosplay contest, there was a performance by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East%20India%20Comedy">East India Comedy</ref>'s stand-up comedian Sahil Shah. Despite some of the audience being juveniles, Shah cracked some adult jokes, and used cuss words. After a joke about professor Utonium from <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Powepuff%20Girls">The Powepuff Girls</ref></hi> "making girls in his basement with a secret recipe", he asked the audience rhetorically if Indian chef <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sanjeev%20Kapoor">Sanjeev Kapoor</ref> shared the recipe on his show. He said he had presented the same joke in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Delhi">Delhi</ref>, but people did not get it, hinting about the sex ratio. He later added "it was because I said in English", a comment towards Delhi's literacy rate. However, Shah told the Bangalore audience in Hindi. Some other jokes stereotyped certain ethnic groups, and classed of the Indian society, discussing the cussing habits of people in Delhi and comparing it with that of Mumbai. He also made fun of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> president <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref>, saying "the Americans voted for an orange alien".</p>
</text>
