<text id="autogum_interview_doc1386" title="part9_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is getting your message out that you do more than just race-based issues a challenge you have difficulty overcoming?  That’s all that people hear and see you do.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Well, that’s one of the challenges, but part of the problem is guys who are critics won’t tell the truth.  If you were to ask them, they know we’ve marched against record companies.  They won’t cover them, because they know—particularly a lot of black columnists—because that’s the way they can be heard: to be against whoever is out there.  They did it to Jesse before me, and they did it to King before him.  You know, one of the ways you can get covered if you are black in the mainstream media is to attack the guy that is up front.  Make him the boogeyman.  I accepted that going in.</p>
<head id="Al_Sharpton_and_Presidential_Politics">Al Sharpton and Presidential Politics</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Recently a poll came out that showed sixty-one percent of the black Americans surveyed said values between poor and middle-class blacks are moving too far apart to be viewed as a common black experience. Only 41 percent expressed that view in a similar 1986 poll.  Do you think the black experience is no longer defined by race, but by socio-economic status?</hi></p>
<figure><caption>"<hi rend="bold">But do you know what nobody ever talks about?  I’m the only black who ran for President who had to run against another black: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carol%20Mosley%20Braun">Carol Mosley Braun</ref> [<hi rend="italic">above</hi>].  Jesse never had to face a black; Shirley [Chisholm] never had to face a black.  Obama hasn’t had to face a black.  The real question is: why did Sharpton get so many more votes than Carol Mosley-Braun, who on paper was a much better candidate?</hi>"</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  No, I think it was always divided on socio-economic status.  I think that there is a growing socio-economic difference that brings the contrast more to light, but that all comes together around the question of civil rights.  There’s no difference.  There’s any number of polls that show that most blacks, no matter what their class, say that there is still bias in America.  Whether you are a kid in Jena from a poor family, or a college professor at Columbia with nooses hanging on your door, you still have a race problem.  You may have a difference in views about values, but both of you still feel there is bias at whatever class level you are at.  That is why they were shocked when I ran for President and the black elite—the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20L.%20Johnson">Bob Johnsons</ref> who own <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BET">BET</ref> and Earl Grey—were some of the biggest contributors to my campaign.  Because they said we <hi rend="italic">still</hi> have to have somebody out there fighting race.  Let me give you the schizophrenia of the political animal.  When I ran for President, I won every black district in Washington D.C.  I then won the black vote in South Carolina, when I never was from the south.  But do you know what nobody ever talks about?  I’m the only black who ran for President who had to run against another black: Carol Mosley Braun.  Jesse never had to face a black; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shirley%20Chisholm">Shirley [Chisholm]</ref> never had to face a black.  Obama hasn’t had to face a black.  The real question is: why did Sharpton get so many more votes than Carol Mosley Braun, who on paper was a much better candidate?  Former U.S. Senator, former ambassador, and she never got anywhere near my vote.  It shows that blacks vote based on who they think supports their interests.  Now you are talking about Obama has to fight Hillary for the black vote; I had to fight Carol Mosley Braun for the black vote, and beat her everywhere.  I think <hi rend="italic">that</hi> is the analysis they don’t want to give.  They’ll say Sharpton didn’t get the votes that Jesse got, but they never mention there was a black woman—the <hi rend="italic">only</hi> black woman who ever served in the U.S. Senate—running against Sharpton!  They forget that now.</p>
</text>
