<text id="autogum_interview_doc1338" title="part3_An interview with Paul Campbell, founder of Amazing Radio UK" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-10" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_Paul_Campbell%2C_founder_of_Amazing_Radio_UK" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I wrote to the CEO of PRS when we first launched Amazing Radio pointing out these absurdities and asking if we could do a more intelligent deal.  I said that I thought we had identical aims – to make life fair for musicians.  I suggested we could/should be a feeder to them, introducing new members to PRS as they grew in the music industry.  But so far, the PRS head is still firmly in the sand.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">And how would you suggest PRS could improve?  If they did, would you consider allowing artists registered with them? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PC</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> PRS could improve by;  </p>
<p><p>a.  buying some computers (so they could handle our comprehensive data about the tracks we play, and then pay the right people);</p>
<p>b.  accepting that we want to mix PRS and non-PRS artists, and only asking for a share of the artists they actually represent.</p></p>
<p>If they did that, we’d sign up.  This would not necessarily be popular with our audience.  A lot of people – especially charities and small businesses – like the fact that they can listen to Amazing Radio without a PRS licence.  But we’d do it anyway, as it would be a better service for musicians.  </p>
<hi rend="bold">PRS should also stop threatening to murder law-abiding people who want to listen to music at work</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Paul Campbell</p>
<p>My personal view is that the PRS should also stop threatening to murder law-abiding people who want to listen to music at work.  There was a recent case where they threatened someone for singing at work.  They actually did that.  They later apologized, but it revealed the corporate mentality.  I think it’s incredibly counter-productive; it means their members make less money, not more; it’s ruining perceptions of what motivates musicians; it’s causing thousands of people to stop listening to music.  When really, PRS should be encouraging that, shouldn’t it? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">With regard to Amazing Tunes, how many downloads could your most popular artist expect to receive per month and monetary wise, how would this compare to them receiving that number from iTunes?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PC</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Sorry, but we don’t currently release detailed figures – our competitors would love it, but we’d rather be nice to our artists and our investors instead. We do say that we expect amazingtunes.com artists to make ‘anything from a few quid, to a good living, to a small fortune’.  At the moment, because it’s still very early days, people are clustered towards the first two of those options.  As things grow – and there’s been incredible growth even in the past few months – we hope/expect more and more artists will start to make tens of thousands of pounds each month.  We’ll soon register for the official chart, and our guess is that someone will have a major hit before long. Then everything will go really crazy. </p>
</text>
