<text id="autogum_interview_doc1170" title="part3_Lobby groups oppose plans for EU copyright extension" shortTile="partlobby-groups" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-18" dateModified="2014-12-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lobby_groups_oppose_plans_for_EU_copyright_extension" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Eddan Katz</hi>: There's a strategy here that needs to be named, by copyright interests, major entertainment companies that have most to benefit from the extension of copyright without any incentive added; it's a strategy to section it off, to make a story, and pinpoint one segment with that story in trying to justify an overall extension of copyright, which is particularly meant to profit and to remove works from the public domain that were set to be there. And also to really blind the pockets, and change the law in order to be able to raise the rent. It's also being justified under harmonising; harmonising is used to justify a ratcheting up, it generally means more exclusive rights to be granted, and layered on top of existing exclusive rights. It's not meant as harmonisation is intended to be, and as the European project is supposed to be, to find a way to create real markets. It's not to justify the continuing increasing of exclusive rights as one specific theory about incentivising creativity when we see so much evidence that there's a lot of creativity coming out of systems outside of long term exclusive rights.</p>
”
<head id="Perpetual_patents?">Perpetual patents?</head>
<p>We raised the point that many common people also see copyright as a good thing and something that supports artists, while copyright violation has been said to have led to huge financial losses for the music industry.</p>
<hi rend="bold">If the music industry continues to push this side of the bargain, all they do is to serve to grow people's disrespect for the law even more, such that nobody wants to respect copyright any more.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Becky Hogge (Open Rights Group)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Erik Josefsson</hi>: Copyright is like tax: 'Taxes are good, so more taxes are better'. The man in the street would say 'No'. 'Okay, so you don't want any taxes?' 'Oh no, I want taxes', the man in the street is completely aware of its value, you have to have a common financial structure. The tradition of copyright, what is the purpose of copyright, is to strike a balance, to have a thriving cultural life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Becky Hogge</hi>: If you think about what copyright does for the internet culture: if we didn't have copyright, we wouldn't have Creative Commons. Copyright is an incredibly sensible piece of law, and in fact serves to benefit a lot of what goes on online in the way that it's been used in things like free and open software, in things like Creative Commons. These things wouldn't exist without the framework of copyright law. I'm always very careful to say that copyright law is a benefit to society, but I think Erik's comparison to taxes is spot on: it's not about black and white.</p>
</text>
