<text id="autogum_interview_doc349" title="part1_Wikinews discusses H1N1 with the WHO" shortTile="partwikinews-discusses" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-29" dateModified="2019-09-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_discusses_H1N1_with_the_WHO" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><ref target="http://www.who.int/csr/disease/swineflu/guidance/national_authorities/en/index.html">http://www.who.int/csr/disease/swineflu/guidance/national_authorities/en/index.html</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What does the WHO recommend for those individuals affected by H1N1? How does H1N1 affect someone who is infected?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Since the H1N1 pandemic virus is now the dominant influenza virus circulating worldwide, most cases of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/influenza">influenza-like</ref> illness are likely pandemic influenza.</p>
<p>Typical symptoms to watch for include fever, cough, headache, body aches, sore throat and runny nose.</p>
<p>WHO advises health care providers to treat people with influenza-like illness based on their symptoms and the progress of their illness, and not to wait for laboratory confirmation of pandemic influenza. The pandemic H1N1 virus has already spread worldwide.</p>
<p>Regarding laboratory testing of cases, public health authorities and WHO partners continue to do selective testing of samples from patients with influenza-like illness to characterize outbreaks, monitor the virus and identify disease trends.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-viral%20drugs">Anti-viral drugs</ref> (which are medicines that act directly on viruses to stop them from multiplying) should not be taken to prevent H1N1.  There are two antiviral drugs are being used to treat pandemic influenza infections. These are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/oseltamivir">oseltamivir</ref> and zanamivir, which both block the action of an influenza virus protein called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/neuraminidase">neuraminidase</ref>.</p>
<p>For patients with symptoms of severe illness that are probably due to pandemic influenza, WHO recommends that treatment with oseltamivir should start immediately, no matter when the illness started and without waiting for laboratory results to confirm infection.</p>
<p>For patients at higher risk for serious disease from pandemic influenza, including pregnant women, children under age 5 and those with certain underlying medical conditions, WHO recommends treatment with either oseltamivir or zanamivir as soon as possible after the onset of symptoms, and without waiting for the results of laboratory tests.</p>
<p>Otherwise healthy people who are not from a higher risk group but who have persistent or rapidly worsening symptoms should be treated with antivirals. These symptoms include difficulty breathing or a high fever that lasts beyond three days.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How does H1N1 affect someone who is infected?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Pandemic H1N1 virus is spread from person to person in the same way that seasonal influenza viruses are spread. It is transmitted as easily as the normal seasonal flu and can be passed to other people by exposure to infected droplets expelled by coughing or sneezing that can be inhaled, or that can contaminate hands or surfaces.</p>
<p>Signs of the pandemic influenza are flu-like, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/malaise">malaise</ref>, fever, cough, headache, muscle and joint pain, sore throat and runny nose, and sometimes vomiting and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/diarrhoea">diarrhoea</ref>.</p>
<p>The majority of people with pandemic influenza experience mild illness and recover fully without treatment. However, people should seek medical care if they experience shortness of breath or difficulty breathing, or if a fever, and especially high fever, continues more than three days. For parents with a young child who is ill, seek medical care if a child has fast or labored breathing, continuing fever or convulsions (seizures).</p>
</text>
