<text id="autogum_interview_doc1399" title="part3_Interview with gay marriage movement founder Evan Wolfson" shortTile="partinterview-gay" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-29" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_gay_marriage_movement_founder_Evan_Wolfson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>These larger questions are engendered by marriage, are promoted by the discussion around marriage, because marriage is a vocabulary in which non-gay people talk about these things and think about these things.  Marriage has always been a battleground on which questions like this, large defining questions about what kind of country we are going to have and society we are going to have and the proper boundaries between the individual and the government, have been contested throughout American history.  Gay people are not the first people to tackle these questions on the battleground of marriage.  By claiming the battleground and vocabulary, we are not only addressing our exclusion from an important legal institution, to which thousands and thousands of protections, responsibilities and opportunities are connected.  It’s even bigger than that, because we are not just talking about that set of legal protections and responsibilities and the tangible and intangible consequences that flow from that, we are indeed engaging through that vocabulary in a discussion about central and important questions that in a way advances our cause, and a larger causes, more effectively than virtually any other single thing.  That’s why for all the work I have done on many different things, I see the marriage work as important.</p>
<head id="The_gay_community_and_marriage">The gay community and marriage</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It does not appear many gay people are galvanized to fight for the marriage right.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  For what do you see gay people more galvanized?  I would say the opposite.  I’ve seen gay people marching in the streets of California, on Freedom to Marry day all around the country.  But marching in the streets is not the ONLY methodology of social change.  Here in New York we passed a marriage bill this year.  California passed a marriage bill through two consecutive legislatures after unseating anti-gay opponents and electing pro-gay legislators.  That took action, that took planning.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larry%20Kramer">Larry Kramer</ref>, a very prominent gay critic of his own community, has taken it to task for its inaction and focusing on sex and having a good time instead of working to change their place in American society.  But you are saying that there is no case of wider apathy amongst gays nor a relative disengagement with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LGBT%20rights%20in%20the%20United%20States">their issues</ref>?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Absolutely we need to have more people break their silence, find their voice, engage in this discussion with the nongay people around them about who gay people really are, why marriage matters, how the denial of marriage hurts them, their loved ones, their partners.... We need more gay people.  We also need more non-gay people.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you feel disappointment with the level of involvement of the gay community in the marriage issue?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I always want more.  My job is to want more, to help make more happen, and I believe if more people would break their silence, take action, write a check, get involved, talk to their mothers and roommates, we’d go there faster.  What keeps me going is spending less time on disappointment and more time on possibility, and I always believe we can get more.  That leads me to push harder for more.  A few months ago people thought we would never live to see a marriage bill passed in New York, particularly after the cruel blow of the loss in court last year.  Within less than a year we got the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Same-sex%20marriage%20in%20New%20York">New York</ref> assembly to pass a marriage bill.  Just a few years ago people didn’t think we would ever get a legislature to pass a marriage bill.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Same-sex%20marriage%20in%20California">California</ref> broke that impasse, now twice.</p>
</text>
