<text id="autogum_interview_doc1072" title="part4_Vivien Goldman: An interview with the Punk Professor" shortTile="partvivien-goldman" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-30" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vivien_Goldman%3A_An_interview_with_the_Punk_Professor" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  At the time he wasn't known?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  Well, it turned out he was in a group called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public%20Enemy">Public Enemy</ref>.  The first time I heard them was at a rooftop party, and it's one of my great New York memories.  It was a warehouse building that's still there behind Houston and Bowery and I remember it was amazing because you never heard music like that before.  It was blaring.  It was so hot and we were in the middle of the city with graffiti on the walls, people smoking spliffs.  It was very free.  You don't see that anymore.  Everything is more heavily policed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think apathy is a problem today?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  There's less intelligent, critical content in general, and celebrity magazines pay the most and sell the most.  It's the Lowest Common Denominator.  Britney Spears is an unbelievable example. She's so young with no good guidance around her, and she is fodder for them to sell more magazines.  There's a gladiator aspect of it: the worse off she is, the better for that industry.  But I'm still looking for the people who have conscience.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Franti">Michael Franti</ref>, he's one of the only ones I look to now. He had that band Spearhead.  I'm looking around for conscious artists.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G.%20G.%20Allin">G. G. Allin</ref>?  He used to defecate on the stage to make a point.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi> That's quite extreme, and very unhygienic.  I wouldn't need to see that.  I don't think that's necessarily punk, it's just scatological.  Some people might think it's punk, but I personally wouldn't dig it.  It's outrageous, but not in the way I find interesting.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Well, he's dead.  Do you think people are afraid to speak out today?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  I guess in Vietnam you did, but now the culture isn't nearly as organized.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is violence for the cause of social change punk?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  Violence will occur in social change.  Violence has always been associated with punk, although punk wants peace in a way.  When you look at all the bands in punk, like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No%20Future">No Future</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blank%20Generation">Blank Generation</ref>, it has implicit an aspiration to a place where you don't have to be violent.  Often it happens. The punk era was violent.  Very, very violent.  So many people were beaten up during those days.  I'm very much a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pacifist">peacenik</ref>, but violence often happens, one observes, on the road to social change.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandra%20Bernhard">Sandra Bernhard</ref> once did an homage to what she called the <hi rend="italic">Big-Tittied Bitches of Rock n' Roll</hi>:  Heart, Joan Jett, Stevie Nicks.  She mourned that there were no big-tittied bitches left.  Who are the big-tittied bitches of Rock n' Roll today?</hi></p>
</text>
