<text id="autogum_interview_doc503" title="part6_Eric Bogosian on writing and the creative urge" shortTile="parteric-bogosian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-16" dateModified="2014-05-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eric_Bogosian_on_writing_and_the_creative_urge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  I think I agree with that.  And I think that a parallel thing that's going on right now that's invisible to the culture as a whole is that we're moving toward a more medieval way of looking at things.  Narratives are moving toward not only pinwheel narratives, but more tapestry-like narratives.  Like <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Lord%20of%20the%20Rings">The Lord of the Rings</ref></hi>, where you don't really feature a psychological character.  If you look at the movies that were the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1960s%20in%20film">big hits of the sixties</ref>, when I was coming up, you've got these troubled guys that are in the center of the movie.  A guy like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve%20McQueen">Steve McQueen</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dustin%20Hoffman">Dustin Hoffman</ref> in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Midnight%20Cowboy">Midnight Cowboy</ref></hi> or <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Graduate">The Graduate</ref></hi>; <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Easy%20Rider">Easy Rider</ref></hi>, or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%20Nicholson">Jack Nicholson</ref> in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five%20Easy%20Pieces">Five Easy Pieces</ref></hi>.  Then the literature of the time, same thing.  Some central male character who has a lot on his mind and is upset about the ways things are going for him in the world, and he's sort of slogging through.  My kids find stuff like that intensely boring.  They just aren't interested in psychological characters anymore.  Maybe it's because they're kids, but you've got to give them credit.  I was reading <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hermann%20Hesse">Hermann Hesse</ref> when I was their age.  What their taste and what I think the culture as a whole is going toward, is more medieval.  When I say medieval, I mean lots of characters that all have <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/archetype">archetypal</ref> qualities to them; we don't really know what's going on inside their head; they're just kind of all acting and reacting to each other.  You look at the movies that become popular now, even going back to <hi rend="italic">Pulp Fiction</hi> or anything like that, it's, "Who cares about the central, troubled guy?"  No one cares anymore; it's old-fashioned.  Let's look at lots of people doing lots of things to each other over this span of time, and that's why the movie industry runs into all these problems, because the guys that are greenlighting all the caca that run.  They remember the movies that they really liked a lot, and they try and make a movie like that, and they just don't--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But update it.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Nobody cares anymore.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  --that this narrative is currently not popular.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  But those movies don't--they don't swing, you know?  Then <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ocean's%20Eleven">Ocean's Eleven</ref></hi> ends up being the kind of movie that will kick it a little bit better.  That's why there is so much action and comedy: people don't care about the psychological character.  And when you start throwing out that psychological character, which is really what has ruled since Shakespeare.  The 1950s are the ultimate psychological characters; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marlon%20Brando">Brando</ref> and all these really troubled guys.  You know, it's all done.  It's done.  It's finished; it's old-fashioned.</p>
</text>
