<text id="autogum_interview_doc904" title="part3_Interview with Reggie Bibbs on his life with neurofibromatosis" shortTile="partinterview-reggie" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2010-04-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Reggie_Bibbs_on_his_life_with_neurofibromatosis" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: So none of those hurt?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: None of these hurt.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Do any of them hurt, on your face or your leg?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: None of the ones on my face hurt. They're just like extra growths, you know, fatty tissue. Above my left eye there's a lot of itching on the inside, it tingles on the inside above my eye.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Where have you had surgeries?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: I had surgery on my nose, on my lip and on my cheek, and eye.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Can you turn your head to the right? Your left ear seems to be lower. How come?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: Right, it's the fatty tissue and everything, it just hangs, it pulls everything down. I have a small tumor on the optic nerve of my left eye, and it's growing, and it's pushing the eye outwards, and it's out of the eye socket, and that's what makes the eye look lower.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Do you have any vision in the left eye?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: I have very little vision in the left eye.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Can you make out movement?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: Well, the only way I can really see out of it is when I cover the right eye. Then I can see out of it, I can't see really well, but I can count fingers from maybe about 3 feet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Tell me about your leg.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: My leg is... from the knee down, they are tumors and a lot of fatty tissue, and it swells. It's difficult to walk. I have to wear a special sock to hold it together to keep it from expanding. It's a compression sock and it's helped with circulation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: It looks very painful, your leg looks like it's an S.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: That's because on the left side right here it's just a lot of fatty tissue. The bone is not curved it's just, this right here is just a lot of extra tissue. If I take the sock off it won't look like an S. All the fatty tissue would just drop. So, that's how that works.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Okay, tell me about your shoe.</hi></p>
<p>RB: The shoes are specially made, they're custom made. A cast is made and they make the shoes from the mold. Because of the leg, I have to have special support.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: Can you show me the side of your foot... and the other side?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RB</hi>: The shoes they help support the ankle from bending to one side. The right foot is not affected at all, only the left side.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN: It looks like mainly the left side of your body is affected by NF. </hi></p>
</text>
