<text id="autogum_interview_doc974" title="part4_Wikinews interviews Frank McEnulty, New American Independent Party nominee for President of the United States" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-24" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Frank_McEnulty%2C_New_American_Independent_Party_nominee_for_President_of_the_United_States" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>By contrast, in Mississippi, they didn’t try and blame Washington, DC for their problems (the Governor is Republican so no partisan bickering) and they got right to work and have made much greater strides towards getting the state and people’s lives back together.  Now, it will be argued for years as to why this has occurred and while the complete answer is very complex and involves many aspects, I believe a major reason for the lack of progress in Louisiana, and with many governmental initiatives,  can be blamed on the fall-out from partisan politics.</p>
<p>My Administration:</p>
<p>As an independent candidate for President my administration will not be burdened by the fact that we will need to make the proper political appointments or proper political decisions to try and help us keep and maintain power.  My chances of reelection will depend solely on how the American people believe that I am doing as their President.</p>
<p>Every decision that I will make as President of the United States will be based on four very simple questions:</p>
<p>1.       Is it Good for America?  By this I mean good for America as a whole, not for a special interest group, not for a specific industry, not for a specific political party, not for a specific politician’s reelection, but good for America as a whole.</p>
<p>2.        Is this Federal law really necessary?  We have thousands and thousands of Federal laws and way too many people in Congress trying to pass new ones all the time to help themselves get reelected.  Unless a law is absolutely necessary for the American people as a whole, it should not be passed.</p>
<p>3.        Is this a proper use of the citizen’s tax money?  The Republican administration that we have had in this country for the last several years has been on a spending spree unlike that seen in many, many years.  What happened to the theory of fiscal responsibility and smaller government?  We need to stop throwing money at every special project that people in Washington can dream up to buy votes and stop now.</p>
<p>I will not be afraid to veto new laws if I do not believe that they are in the best interest of all Americans.  As an independent President, I will not be under any obligation to pass a law to help a political party or to help get a certain senator or congressman reelected.  I will have the freedom to do what is right for America rather than what is right for a special interest or political party.</p>
 HAVE YOUR SAY 
 Are independent candidates just a distraction? Do you ever see the American public becoming so disillusioned with the mainstream parties to give them a chance?
</text>
