<text id="autogum_interview_doc751" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Jim Reeves, York-Simcoe" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-01" dateModified="2007-11-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_candidate_Jim_Reeves%2C_York-Simcoe" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Jim Reeves, York-Simcoe</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 1, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jim Reeves</hi> is running for the Green Party of Ontario in the Ontario provincial election, in the York-Simcoe riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I have been active for many years in business and environmental organization in York Region and am increasingly concerned about the indiscriminate development, and the lack of effective steps by the major parties to protect the Lake Simcoe watershed. I see in the Green Party policy many ideas which if implemented could greatly improve not only environmental health, but the practical aspects of education, social welfare and health care delivery in our province.</p>
<p>I have lived in Georgina since 1978 and would be proud to represent my home constituency.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insights can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>While I have no specific political experience, I have served on many boards. Business related: Canadian Retail Hardware Association, as director on the committee for legislative affairs. Canadian Tire Dealers Association, at different times, committees on marketing, logistics, and warehousing. Provincial: Workplace Health and Safety, and Social: Association for Community Living, York Environmental Stewardship. As an engineer and having my MBA I have a very practical approach to problems and I believe that I can bring a creative and practical point of view, incorporating new technologies.</p>
<p>Which of you competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable candidate running in the riding?</p>
<p>As a Green Party candidate I recognize that all the major parties pose a big challenge. They all have established riding constituencies and financial support far beyond anything we can realistically expect in this election. However the Green Party represents the grass roots and will be better able to put forward the issues of growth in harmony with the environment, and protection of the Lake Simcoe watershed. They are both issues very important to the riding.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p><list type="ordered"><item>Bad development: The extensive building of single family dwellings, with no centre of shopping, amenities,</item>
<item>No job growth in the developments or nearby. People have to commute, causing more smog, congestion and air pollution.</item>
<item>Degradation of the Lake Simcoe watershed. This degradation is taking place as a result of poor water management, smelter byproducts, dumps and the paving over of large areas of the Oak Ridge’s Moraine.</item></list></p>
</text>
