<text id="autogum_interview_doc971" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Frank McEnulty, New American Independent Party nominee for President of the United States" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-09-24" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Frank_McEnulty%2C_New_American_Independent_Party_nominee_for_President_of_the_United_States" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: How would you handle illegal immigration? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> Enforce the laws on the books and cut out all federal aid to illegal immigrants.  If there are no jobs and no benefits to being here illegally then they will go home and stay there.  This process is working in Arizona and will work nationwide.</p>
<p>I would also push for an amendment to the Constitution which would allow people born here to only be an automatic citizen of the US if their parents are already citizens.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: How would you handle foreign relations with Europe, where there are growing anti-American feelings? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> I would first stop being so unilateral in our policies outside the United States.  If we can’t make a strong enough argument to get the rest of the world on our side in a cause, then maybe we’d better think twice before we go off on our own.</p>
<p>I would also send ambassadors to Europe and the rest of the world that are truly qualified for the jobs and not political appointees who are being repaid for raising lots of money to get me elected.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: How would you handle the War on Drugs? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> I think it is time we started putting more of our resources into drug rehab than prison time.</p>
<p>Until we start to do something concrete and real about the demand for drugs by our people the War on Drugs will never be won.  As long as there is demand, someone will figure out a way to supply that demand.</p>
<p>Look at how successful we have been in cutting down on cigarette use.  Surely an anti-drug program as pervasive as the anti-cigarette programs have been would be successful in cutting drug use.  Combined with a comprehensive program of rehabilitation and we will start to reduce drug use in this country.  Throwing everyone in prison is not the answer.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: It has been over five years since the Iraq War began. As president, how would you handle it? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> The war in Iraq should have never happened.  However, now that we made the mess, we need to see it through or we will create an even bigger mess going forward.  As it appears that the Iraqi government is becoming more and more able to handle its own security and problems every day we must continue to help them grow in the job and then get out of their way as soon as they ask us to.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: For millions of Americans, health care is a major issue. How would you handle it? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> Health care is truly a big concern for a lot of Americans because it is probably the one thing that can ruin them financially quicker than anything else.  However, I do not believe in a Nationalized Health Care system because I’ve never know the federal government to run a program more effectively and cost efficiently.  I also believe that to a certain extent the health care crisis is somewhat of a media and politically created crisis.  People are not dying in the streets due to lack of medical care and, although some people are destroyed by huge medical bills each year, the numbers are not staggering.</p>
</text>
