<text id="autogum_interview_doc761" title="part4_Interview with Innocent Watat, City Council candidate for Wards 3 &amp; 4 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-innocent" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-21" dateModified="2007-06-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Innocent_Watat%2C_City_Council_candidate_for_Wards_3_%26_4_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How could Brampton further itself in attracting corporate investment?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Of course, if the council shows an effective and efficient municipal management, it would be a strong showcase to attract corporate investors in Brampton . This attraction is definitely paramount to ensure the economic development of the city and also the wellbeing of bramptonians who will be providing their expertise to these businesses.</p>
<p>To ensure the efficiency of such attraction, we much encourage corporate investment by providing to these investors a window of tax break for a define period of time; establish competitive municipal tax rate which by itself would lure many investors; organize showcase sessions, invite investors and publicize the millions reasons why their investments are worth being done in Brampton. We must definitely use the fast growth of the city and the strong base of skilled and professional workers present in Brampton as a huge incentive for investment.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I believe I have what it takes to bring hope and energy in Bramptonians life. I do believe I have the vision that would help Brampton to distinguish itself among other municipalities in this twenty first century. I strongly believe that I can turn our diversity into a huge strength and force that would propel Brampton into a respectable level. I think Brampton, as a multi-ethnic and multi cultural city has what it takes to be a Canada model. I do have what Brampton need to achieve it.</p>
<p>I am young, dynamic and resolute to bring the necessary change. Brampton needs change; Brampton council needs new faces. I am involved in this political process because I would be the incarnation of the change and I would bring the energy that Brampton need to solve all pending issues.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Brampton mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> My involvement in this political process is a proof of what Brampton means to me. I have called Brampton home for many years now. In front of the pending issues of our municipality, there is nothing else I could have done but to get involve, to instigate and to bring a new vision.</p>
<p>Instead of complaining or criticizing, there is a better way to make Brampton a better place to live in: it goes through my involvement in this political process, through what I bring to the table as ideas and it shows how much I love and adore this city. I never would have decided to stay aside and wait for the miracle to happen. I am bringing with me the miracle and I am sure that would serve the purpose and the interests of Bramptonians. I am working hard to achieve these goals because Brampton means a lot to me.</p>
</text>
