<text id="autogum_interview_doc947" title="part2_Interview with Sean Semper-Whyte, City Council candidate for Ward 6 in Mississauga, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-sean" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-09-23" dateModified="2008-01-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Sean_Semper-Whyte%2C_City_Council_candidate_for_Ward_6_in_Mississauga%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Of the decisions made by council since the last election, which one would you have changed, and why? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I believe strongly in collaboration and partnerships, in fact this is how big business is being run today all over the world; "we are not an island unto ourselves".  If the City of Mississauga is to be run like a corporation lets be true to the ideals of a corporation.  I believe we need to strengthen our relationships with Brampton and Caledon while also looking out for the best interests of our communities as a priority.  Taking a collaborative approach should always be our first option, as like a corporation we are competing for consumer investment.  Consumers not only favour brands, they favour ease of use and value for their hard earned dollar.  Packaging a well-run Region trumps the struggling city.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have always been an individual who believes in volunteering, this has been how I was able to secure many of my jobs, from my youth.  In my small business Semper-Whyte Solutions – we are a safety and security interest.  We were a sponsor to this year's, Peel Community Police Race Against Racism, an effort I have participated in annually since 2003.  This year I believed in taking the next step in that of being a sponsor.  As a strong proponent of diversity, in this multicultural community, safety and security for all citizens is a major priority.</p>
<p>I have recently submitted for the review of Youth Bureau officers a strategy to not only draw awareness to the issues of Crime, Violence, bullying, and terror, but also solutions to minimizing these incidents within our community.  We can all talk about the problems but we must all also be active in their resolutions.</p>
<p>I have volunteered with the Association of Black Law Enforcers, (A.B.L.E.) representing ABLE at several community functions including 2005's Community Crime Awareness day, organized by the Mississauga Chinese Business Association, and will be doing so again this year.  As a participant in this years Malton Community festival with my local church group, Cathedral of Praise Family Worship Centre, meeting and encouraging, individuals and groups sharing and moving forward the community vision is a priority for me.</p>
<p>This vision shared by organizations like the Argos Foundation, Taking IT Global, (Youth Focused) and the African Canadian Christian Network, are organizations I am currently working with through supporting their efforts or in proposal drafting, though these are only a few.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Many councillors are quite seasoned in the civic political process. What could you bring to the table as a "rookie", above and beyond the current roster of councillors? </p>
</text>
