<text id="autogum_interview_doc934" title="part0_KKE: Interview with the Greek Communist Party" shortTile="partkke-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-05-13" dateModified="2019-09-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/KKE%3A_Interview_with_the_Greek_Communist_Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>KKE: Interview with the Greek Communist Party</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 13, 2010</hi></p>
<p>Wikinews reporter Iain Macdonald has performed an interview with Dr Isabella Margara, a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>-based member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communist%20Party%20of%20Greece">Communist Party of Greece</ref> (KKE). In the interview Margara sets out the communist response to current events in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Greece">Greece</ref> as well as discussing the viability of a communist economy for the nation. She also hit back at Petros Tzomakas, a member of another Greek far-left party which criticised KKE in a previous interview.</p>
<p>The interview comes amid tensions in cash-strapped Greece, where the government is introducing controversial austerity measures to try to ease the nation's debt-problem. An international rescue package has been prepared by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Union">European Union</ref> member states and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Monetary_Fund">International Monetary Fund</ref> – should Greece require a bailout; protests have been held against government attempts to manage the economic situation.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<figure><caption>KKE protestors atop the famous Athens Acropolis</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Iain Macdonald</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Has slavish pursuit of free-market capitalism been the cause of Europe, and particularly Greece's, economic woes?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Dr Isabella Margara</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> What we are experiencing today – not only in Greece, but in all capitalist countries – is a crisis of overproduction. The exploitation of the working class and the other popular <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/strata">strata</ref> is intensified due to the fact that the bourgeoisie has been keeping for itself larger and larger parts of the produced wealth. Behind overproduction lies the over-accumulation of capital. The average profit rate is decreased in the main sectors of the economy.  This leads to destruction of part of productive forces, closing factories, inflation, mass redundancies of superfluous workers as waste – in order to permit a new process of accumulation to begin, when new sectors of the economy will secure the increase of the average profit rate. This has nothing to do with the ‘management’ of the system by social democrats or liberals; it is an inevitable outcome of capitalism.</p>
<p>The national deficits do exist. In fact, behind the debt are the huge tax reliefs for large monopolies, the massive bank bailouts, the inconceivable <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NATO">NATO</ref> military expenses, the subsidies in the name of capitalist development. In Greece at the moment, there is a clear expression of the imperialist rivalries between the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">US</ref> and EU, between EU countries and especially between <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref>. However, it is now becoming clearer every day that the ruling class is using the existing deficits, in Greece and in Europe, in order to promote new anti-labour policies which will secure the profits of the capital. These measures have been pre-decided a long time ago in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maastricht%20Treaty">Maastricht Treaty</ref> and are here to stay. Their aim is not just to exit the crisis, but to ensure stability and high profits for the capital in the next phases of the economic cycle.</p>
</text>
