<text id="autogum_interview_doc607" title="part12_Wikinews interviews John Wolfe, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-19" dateModified="2013-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_John_Wolfe%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">I have one final question. It's on foreign policy. How can the president deal with the nuclear situation in Iran?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: Well, the best thing to do is not to panic. We have a lot of nuclear superiority. Iran is at a stage right now where I think they've only enriched up to the level of 20. There's no proof that they have a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nuclear_weapon">nuclear weapon</ref>. There's no proof even according to our generals that they have a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuclear%20program%20of%20Iran">nuclear weapons program</ref> right now or the intent to build one. You just listen to what people say, the generals and stuff, and even the Israeli generals, the ones that have retired from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mossad">Israeli intelligence</ref>, some of their retired military persons don't think a strike would be good. I don't think it would be either. I mean you'd just radicalize a country of 70 million people. We should have <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iran–United%20States%20relations">diplomatic relations</ref> with Iran. We need to restore those. We need to have an ambassador in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tehran">Tehran</ref>. They need to have an ambassador here.</p>
<p><p>We need to open a dialogue with Iran. We did that with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref>. We did it with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref>. When Russia was a nuclear power, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Soviet_Union">Soviet Union</ref>, we had a hotline between [U.S. President John] <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20F.%20Kennedy">Kennedy</ref> and [Soviet Premier Nikita] <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikita%20Khrushchev">Khrushchev</ref> and then between every American president and Soviet premier after that.  No reason we shouldn't do it here with Iran. They have 79 million people.  We need to have an ambassador in Tehran. They need to have their ambassador in Washington. We need to keep the lines of communication open.  Just talking doesn't calibrate anyone's philosophy but it does us give an opportunity to see what's going on.  It opens things up a little bit and maybe we can learn more by having a channel than just turning the whole <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hull%20classification%20symbol#United_States_Navy">CV</ref> on them.</p>
<p>
<p>| <hi rend="bold">A lot of people are dying in Iran, and the more they know about America, the better it's gonna be for us too.</hi></p>
</p>
<p>There's a lot of things about Iran I don't like. Some of the rantings and things about the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Holocaust">Holocaust</ref>, that it didn't happen and that sort of thing, if that's actually what he said, we don't know if the translations are always right. But anybody that would have a conference to deny that, you know, that's not good. I don't like that. But we have to deal with them as they are and not necessarily what they might be with some of these ridiculous historical interpretations they might make. Despite all that, they're still a power that has to be reckoned with.  They represent a lot of people. Iran has 79 million people. No reason we can't talk to them.</p></p>
</text>
