<text id="autogum_interview_doc1003" title="part2_An interview with Jimbo Wales" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-02-21" dateModified="2014-10-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_Jimbo_Wales" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">WN:</hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Kevin%20Myers">Kevin Myers</ref> asks: "The values reflected in certain Wikipedia policies (anti-censorship, neutral point-of-view) are problematic in cultures where freedom of expression is limited, as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blocking%20of%20Wikipedia%20in%20mainland%20China">blocking of Wikipedia in mainland China</ref> and arguably the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jyllands-Posten%20Muhammad%20cartoons%20controversy">Muhammad cartoons controversy</ref> attest.  As Wikipedia expands internationally, do you foresee Wikipedia becoming increasingly controversial in countries where "Western values" are seen as a potential threat?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JW:</hi>  I don't think that neutrality and objectivity are really controversial among most people of the world. It is true that the leadership in some places does not value these things, and may actually work against these things, but we can not deviate from our goals to accommodate them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN:</hi> <hi rend="italic">On a similar topic, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Vsion">Vsion</ref> asks: "Are there currently any efforts being undertaken by the Foundation to address the People's Republic of China's blocking of Wikipedia or to alleviate its effect?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JW:</hi>  Beijing-area Wikipedians are working to have the block lifted. Our position is that the block is in error, even given China's normal policies. Wikipedia is not propaganda, it is basic information. We expect that the block will be lifted.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN:</hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:David.Monniaux">David.Monniaux</ref> asks: "The Foundation receives daily accusations of libel from semi-well-known people who have an entry on Wikipedia or are mentioned in some Wikipedia entry. What do you propose? Would a strict application of the rule of citing controversial claims suffice, in your opinion?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JW:</hi>  Yes. I think that our current systems do a good job of addressing these sorts of complaints, although it is very time-consuming for us here in the office. What really works wonders is a very strict application of the rule of citing controversial claims particularly relating to biographies of living persons. The new policy on biographies of living persons is a very strong step in the right direction.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN:</hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Tony%20Sidaway">Tony Sidaway</ref> asks: "In the past six weeks the number of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Userboxes">userboxes</ref> on English Wikipedia has risen from 3500 to 6000 and, despite your <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Deletion%20review/Userbox%20debates">appeals for restraint</ref>, the number pertaining to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Userboxes/Beliefs">political beliefs</ref> has risen from 45 to 150. Can the problem of unsuitable userboxes still be resolved by debate?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JW:</hi>  My only comment on the userbox situation is that the current situation is not acceptable.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN:</hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Larsinio">Larsinio</ref> asks: "How can Wikipedia effectively explain to the public its open-contribution model without simultaneously worrying the public about inaccurate information?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JW:</hi>  I think we do a reasonably good job of that. The best thing is to point to our overall quality while at the same time pointing out that we are currently a work in progress. Over time, this answer will change as we move toward '1.0'. At that time, we can point to '1.0' for those who are made nervous by the live editing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN:</hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Robchurch">Rob Church</ref> asks: "Do you consider the encyclopedia to be 'finished'? Do you think it ever can be?"</hi></p>
</text>
