<text id="autogum_interview_doc856" title="part1_Q and A with New Zealand Prime Minister hopeful" shortTile="partq-new-zealand" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-05-17" dateModified="2019-09-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Q_and_A_with_New_Zealand_Prime_Minister_hopeful" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You've said that you will repeal the EFA, will you draft up a replacement Bill? If so, will you take a bipartisan approach when drafting up a possible replacement?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.K.</hi>: That is our intention.  The laws that govern our democratic process are owned by the people, not the group of politicians that happen to occupy the Treasury benches at any one point in time.  The self serving laws that the current Government put in place are an absolute mess.  Anyone who wants to take part in the democratic process is being forced to consult a lawyer, and the confusion has paralysed political and third parties for the first part of the year.  Labour’s intention was to curb its critics, and in this respect, the Electoral Finance Act has done exactly what Helen Clark hoped.  National will repeal this legislation and consult other parties on a set of rules which are fair, transparent and promote free speech and open participation in our democracy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You're relatively politically inexperienced compared to your opponent, Helen Clark. Do you think the voters will take this into consideration at the voting booth? How does your former career in finance help you in a political setting? How about your childhood growing up in a state-house, among other things?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.K.</hi>: I am proud of my achievements since I have been the leader of the National Party. It is true I have not been a career politician, but I believe I bring a fresh approach to politics in this country.  I am not interested in revisiting the arguments of the 80’s and 90’s or subscribing to some arcane ideology. I believe I am a pragmatist.  I am interested in what works – not where it has come from or who is promoting it.  I don’t trust anyone who believes they have all the answers on everything.  They are setting themselves up for a rather large fall.</p>
<p>My career in business taught me a lot about managing people, reaching consensus and taking people with me as we work together for a common purpose.  In my view, good business leaders listen to the people they serve and fight fiercely to protect those interests. In that regard, if I am privileged enough to be elected Prime Minister, I plan to be an unashamed cheerleader for this country on both the national and world stage.</p>
<p>In reference to my upbringing, I believe I was tremendously lucky.  I had a mother who set extremely high standards, who pushed us as children and never once tried to limit our ambition.  Mum taught us that life is what you make it, that there is no dress rehearsal, and unless you make the most of your opportunities you may live to regret that.  I try to give my kids the same sort of freedom and share with them the same sort of values that my mum gave to me.  That is, if you work hard and don’t give up when you hit the hurdles - almost anything is possible.  Believe in yourself.</p>
</text>
