<text id="autogum_interview_doc043" title="part4_Wikinews interviews Rocky De La Fuente, U.S. Democratic Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-03-29" dateModified="2016-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Rocky_De_La_Fuente%2C_U.S._Democratic_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>At least my candidacy is beginning to force some of these practices out in the open. Maybe that's a better result than the one experienced by bigger name candidates who had all the advantages and still failed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">In <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2012">2012</ref>, several primary challengers to President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> including <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Wolfe,_Jr.">John Wolfe, Jr.</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Randall_Terry">Randall Terry</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keith%20Russell%20Judd">Keith Russell Judd</ref> all qualified for delegates, though they ultimately were not seated at the convention due to technicalities.  Given the money you are willing to spend on a campaign and your ability to adhere to the rules, do you regret not running in 2012?</hi></p>
<figure><caption>De La Fuente quotes Einstein: "We cannot solve our problems with the same thinking we used when we created them." Image: Ferdinand Schmutzer.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">De La Fuente</hi>: I found that it isn't a good use of time to second guess a decision you can't change. Did unconventional candidates win delegates in 2012? Yes. That should tell you that the Party changed the rules to prevent that from happening again. That's the real story; not whether I wish I'd run in 2012.</p>
<p>In all honesty, I didn't have any motivation to run in 2012. I only decided to jump into this race late last year because Donald Trump was vilifying entire classes of people and no one seemed willing to confront him. Had there been a Kennedy or even a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ronald_Reagan">Reagan</ref> in the race, I wouldn't have taken this step. I ran because I didn't see anyone in the presidential race who wasn't also part of the problem.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert%20Einstein">Albert Einstein</ref> once said, "We cannot solve our problems with the same thinking we used when we created them." I would suggest that we cannot solve our nation's problems with the same people who created them. We need someone who understands our economy, who understands international relationships and cultural differences, who values education, who has lived and competed in the real world rather than a hypothetical one funded by the taxpayers, and who has experienced the challenges that minorities face in this country and knows how to overcome those barriers. I have personal experience in each of these areas and offer a demonstrated record of success.</p>
<p>I'm not a polished politician; I‘m just like you. I don't make false promises, and I pledge to honor my <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oath%20of%20office%20of%20the%20President%20of%20the%20United%20States">Oath of Office</ref>. I'm a problem solver, and I believe that is exactly what our nation needs. Think about it.</p>
<head id="Issues">Issues</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are your thoughts on the job Obama has done as president? Specifically, what would you have done differently?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">De La Fuente</hi>: I think President Obama is an honorable man who has done the best he could. He took over under difficult economic circumstances, but found a way to help stabilize and reverse the recession. He made significant progress in healthcare and education even in the face of Congressional resistance. I also think his recent steps to normalize relations with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cuba">Cuba</ref> are a step in the right direction.</p>
</text>
