<text id="autogum_interview_doc771" title="part4_Keep your eyes peeled for cosmic debris: Andrew Westphal about Stardust@home" shortTile="partkeep-eyes-peeled" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-05-18" dateModified="2015-10-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Keep_your_eyes_peeled_for_cosmic_debris%3A_Andrew_Westphal_about_Stardust%40home" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">I got to meet one of the stardust directors in March during the Texas Aerospace Scholars program at JSC. She talked about searching for meteors in Antarctica, one that were unblemished by Earth conditions. Is that our best chance of finding new information on comets and asteroids? Or will more Stardust programs be our best solution?</hi></p>
<p>That's a really good question. Much will depend on what we learn during this official "Preliminary Examination" period for the cometary analysis. Aerogel capture is pretty darn good, but it's not perfect and things are altered during capture in ways that we're still understanding. I think that much also depends on what question you're asking. For example, some of the most important science is done by measuring the relative abundances of isotopes in samples, and these are not affected (at least not much) by capture into aerogel. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Also, she talked about how some of the agencies that they gave samples to had lost or destroyed 2-3 samples while trying to analyze them. That one, in fact, had been statically charged, and stuck to the side of the microscope lens and they spent over an hour looking for it. Is that really our biggest danger? Giving out samples as a show of good faith, and not letting NASA example all samples collected?</hi></p>
<p>These will be the first measurements, probably, that we'll make on the interstellar dust There is always a risk of loss. Fortunately for the cometary samples there is quite a lot there, so it's not a disaster. NASA has some analytical capabilities, particularly at JSC, but the vast majority of the analytical capability in the community is not at NASA but is at universities, government labs and other institutions all over the world. I should also point out that practically every analytical technique is destructive at some level. (There are a few exceptions, but not many.) The problem with meteorites is that except in a very few cases, we don't know where they specifically came from. So having a sample that we <hi rend="italic">know</hi> for sure is from the comet is golden! </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">I am currently working on my Bachelor's in computer science, with a minor in astronomy. Do you see successes of programs like Stardust to open up more private space exploration positions for people such as myself. Even though I'm not in the typical "space" fields of education?</hi></p>
<p>Can you elaborate on your question a little — I'm not sure that I understand...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Well, while at JSC I learned that they mostly want Engineers, and a few science grads, and I worry that my computer science degree with not be very valuable, as the NASA rep told me only 1% of the applicants for their work study program are CS majors. I'm just curious as to your thoughts on if CS majors will be more in demand now that projects like Stardust and the Mars missions have been great successes? Have you seen a trend towards more private businesses moving in that direction, especially with President Bush's statement of Man on the Moon in 2015?</hi></p>
</text>
