<text id="autogum_interview_doc986" title="part1_Wikinews holds Reform Party USA presidential candidates forum" shortTile="partwikinews-holds" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-01-02" dateModified="2016-09-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_holds_Reform_Party_USA_presidential_candidates_forum" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benedict%20College">Benedict College</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South%20Carolina%20State%20University">South Carolina State University</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20South%20Carolina">University of South Carolina</ref>. He joined the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Army%20National%20Guard">Army National Guard</ref> in 2006, and has worked as a motivational speaker. He bases his campaign on a platform called the "gameplan".
<head id="Forum">Forum</head>
<head id="Question_1">Question 1</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WIKINEWS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why did you decide to run for president?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Andre Barnett</hi>: Though it may seem a bit selfish, my decision was more of a conviction of heart, mind and spirit after seeing what my own family and friends were enduring during this economic downturn. As I began speaking with my fellow veterans and hearing about the lost jobs, homes, and families many issues came into focus. The time I spent living overseas in different countries allowed me to studying their economies, governments, military capabilities, and learn what other countries really think about the US.</p></p>
<p><p>We can no longer accept the notion we are on a path of no return. Our government has an obligation to the people of this nation to address the needs and concerns they are facing.</p></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Robert Steele</hi>: Multiple reasons.  The economy killed my business, so I've been working on Electoral Reform.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Occupy%20Wall%20Street">Occupy movement</ref> raised my hopes that America was ready to wake up. I had also been sickened by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</ref> clown show. The time seemed right for something better.  While there are politicians I admire, none of them were offering the public a coherent, complete approach to restoring the Republic and the integrity of our government. That's what I'm looking for, and that's why I decided to run.   Some will say I am a long shot but I actually believe that We the People can come together and win this in unconventional ways, and of course I believe very strongly that someone has to say what needs to be said: we live in a two-party tyranny, all three branches of the government have been captured by banks and corporations--hence the US Government no longer represents We the People.  And – this is the big one – we have ONE SHOT, between now and 4 July 2012, to force the issue of Electoral Reform and take our government back.</p></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Robby Wells</hi>: There are several reasons why I chose to run for President. I chose to run after observing the path our elected officials have been taking. It is obvious that the policies of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democratic Party</ref> and the Republican Party are not effective anymore. The 14 million that are unemployed, the 25 million that are underemployed, the 49 million that live in poverty, and the 149 million that are considered low income is proof that our two party system has failed. It is time for America to have strong leadership from someone that has the best interest of the citizens of this country. It is time for our country to move in a different direction. It is time for our country to make a "Real Change". I believe that I am that candidate because I understand the pressures that 99% of our citizens face. Most of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20Party%20presidential%20candidates,%202012">top candidates for the GOP</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">President Obama</ref> are wealthy, and are out of touch with the vast majority of this country. I am just like most Americans. I consider myself middle class, have been unemployed, have been underemployed, and woke up every morning concerned about how I was going to provide for my family. Just like millions of Americans, I felt like the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Dream">American Dream</ref> had been replaced with an Economic Nightmare. Someone had to take a stand. I love my country, and I know that my plan, "The Gameplan," will bring our country back to economic greatness. You can view "The Gameplan" on my campaign web site: www.electrobbywells.com.</p></p>
</text>
