<text id="autogum_interview_doc1250" title="part13_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you make a choice--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I made a deliberate choice with that book, yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why was the choice made?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Because it was the only way I could write that book, and I had to write that book.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you try to write it funny at first?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I was terrified--no.  And I know this may turn a lot of people off.  Because there are going to be people who approach this book with a smile on their face--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  'Oh, another Burroughs!'</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  And as soon as they hear the title, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A%20Wolf%20at%20the%20Table">A Wolf at the Table</ref></hi>, they'll already chuckle.  And then as they read it, they'll think, "Well, my God, he's lost it.  This isn't funny!"  And then the more they read, they'll realize: this is just horrible.  I mean, it's just a devastating, terrifying story.  But I had to write it for me--and, um, I mean, it's, it's definitely scary, because it's--I don't, you know, I don't want to alienate my readers, or my fans, but you know, I can't think about that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  No.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I can't…I can't write books to sell.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But also, too, your fans should realize that you're not one-dimensional.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  With your writing, that you don't have a--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Well, that's the other thing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's like, "Oh, we wanna see Data from 'Star Trek' be Data; we don't want to see him in his full range of emotions," you know--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I don't want to be just funny, or just sarcastic, because you know I am--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Versatile.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I'm very serious--that's the weird thing; in person, I'm very serious.  I'm not so funny.  I'm, like, as funny as your dentist.  So, this book is…is--it's another side of me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why do you think you are so serious in person?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Well, I get a lot of it out in the books.  I used to be funnier, which is funny, ironic.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is it like a purpose-ness? That you're very purpose-driven now, or--?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  It's not that I'm purpose-driven; I've always been serious.  I've always been really, really serious.  I've always been very introspective and introverted, and--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you and Dennis yuk it up at home?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Some, yeah.  He's on the serious side, too.  [Laughs] It's like--whoo! what a fun time--no, we do have fun, we do laugh.  We have a very similar sense of humor, very dark  It's not to say that I'm always deadly serious; it’s that I'm not a person always "on" you know, in that funny way.</p>
</text>
