<text id="autogum_interview_doc706" title="part2_Canada&amp;apos;s Beaches—East York (Ward 32) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-beacheseast" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-21" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Beaches%E2%80%94East_York_%28Ward_32%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which Council decision since the 2003 election do you feel  the city/ward should be most proud of and least proud.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> There are many decisions that I am proud we made both locally and city-wide. For the ward, the development and selection of a citizen team to choose the direction for the future method of disposal of residual waste will be selected; as well as providing recommendations on a potential site is the most important decision made this term. Secondly, the success in receiving significant funding from the city to build the newest and biggest skateboard park in the city together with a private sponsor is a great success for the youth of the ward and city.</p>
<p>The political composition of the Council wherein the majority of the suburban councillors struggle, to support initiatives which reflect the needs of the inner city was a major drawback of this past Council. The art of compromise to receive Council approval  on a series of initiatives like  the City budget for example, led to the reduction in the effectiveness of the Toronto Transit Ridership growth strategy. Recommended spending for the Beautiful City campaign was cut as a result of a "them-and-us" voting attitude.  However, changes to the Council procedural rules for the next term will allow for greater decision-making, in some cases at the local community council level, and by an Executive Committee of Council in order for the Mayor to enact bylaws that reflect the Mayor's Vision for the City.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Toronto is where I live, where I grew up, and where I have raised my family.  It's my home.  I am inspired by the opportunities that present themselves here in our City.  This is a thriving, growing and developing young City.  Recently, growth in the downtown areas has been very strong.  Locally, our communities are stable but in some cases challenged by change.  Making change work positively for the city and local neighbourhoods is an exciting everyday activity for me as a City Councillor.</p>
<head id="William_Gallos"><ref target="http://www.gallosward32.com/">William Gallos</ref></head>
<p>William Gallos candidate city council for Ward 32, Beaches—East York.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Ward 32 is a unique family community within a major city. In order to preserve our quality of life, we must be ever vigilant to ensure we aren't overrun by city by-laws, poor transportation and parking issues,  unsafe environmental issues due to sewage treatment plant drugs/crime and unsafe streets and park management. My aim is to have the community work with me to help economic gross with in the bussinesses, provide safe streets, clean up and maintanence of your parks and boardwalk, establish Sewage Treatment Plan, and much more...</p>
</text>
