<text id="autogum_interview_doc524" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Ruth Bryant White, independent candidate for US President" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-19" dateModified="2008-08-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Ruth_Bryant_White%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I’ve worked in the Corporate world and Government world and I know how both operate. I would run The White House like an up to date corporation that can see monthly reports of where we’re heading financially. We would balance the budget, cut spending and programs that have not worked, and we wouldn’t spend money we don’t have. I am a Public Speaker, and an Expert on Race Relations and I bring communications skills with a Non Profit Organization, “A Place For Us” National www.aplaceforusnational.com,, for over 25 years. The people who have worked with me for over 25 years believe in what this mission and this campaign is about. When they hear me speak they are energized by my message of taking back America and having the essentials of our security handled by our Government as well as empowering people to depend on themselves more and less on Government.</p>
<p>Look me up on votesmart.org.</p>
<p>All of the work positions I’ve held will prepare me for the Oval office.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Obviously, the next American President and his or her administration will face many diverse issues. But if you were to narrow identify the three most important issues, what would they be? How will you address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>I would free the Border Patrol Agents who are imprisoning because they tried to protect our Countrys secure the Northern and Southern Borders, and place A Moratorium on all immigrants from everywhere. Then I’d start the deportation process first for illegal prisoners we take care of everyday, then penalize the employers who knowingly hire illegal’s. Concerning, National Security, we should protect ourselves and Our Military with the best we can give them with the New GI Bill. Should they parish, their families will be taken care of and I believe if a parent is the only heir of a fallen soldier that parent should be able to go to the Commissary to purchase food.</p>
<p>I will protect us by any means necessary without abusing Americans’ Privacy and Free Speech. As far as Education goes, I believe in giving Educators salaries through private entities where they make 200K or the equivalent depending where they live in the Country. I would even include not having to pay rent, because if they don’t teach our children we have a failing country. If they like their job they will go beyond their regular duty. For example, my husband is an Educator and as far as his private clients are concerned (and I concur) he’s the best in the country. He would teach for free if he didn’t have to eat and pay bills; that’s how much he loves seeing children learn and better themselves, but with all of the political correctness I didn’t want him ever teaching in public schools again.</p>
</text>
