<text id="autogum_interview_doc265" title="part4_Wikinews interviews US National Archives Wikipedian in Residence" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-06-11" dateModified="2014-04-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_US_National_Archives_Wikipedian_in_Residence" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>This photo, taken by Ansel Adams at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand%20Teton%20National%20Park">Grand Teton National Park</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wyoming">Wyoming</ref>, was provided by the National Archives as part of its partnership with WikipediaImage: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ansel%20Adams">Ansel Adams</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Having worked in the National Archives for a few weeks now, has your approach to or perception of your work in Wikipedia or the National Archives changed in any way?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DMP</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I really wasn't sure what to expect when I got here. The staff have all been exceedingly welcoming and cooperative which is a major relief. The real work has been figuring out what I can do and where best to spend my time. Most of the National Archives' documents are not digitized, and possibly not even cataloged on the item-level. Those certainly include some items that Wikimedians would like to use for their projects, but it remains to be seen how much I can realistically do in one summer with those documents. I do want to get as much digital content as possible on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikimedia%20Commons">Commons</ref>, but aside from the technological challenges we face at Commons in trying to figure out how to do mass uploads, the situation with the National Archives' scan files is just as much of a barrier. They are often confusingly named, difficult to locate, or incomplete. I hit the ground running with the upload of an important batch of Ansel Adams photographs, but it turns out that that was actually the lowest-possible hanging fruit.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What challenges do you foresee having to face in your work?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DMP</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> The real challenges are about organization, both of documents—as I mentioned—and of people.</p>
<p>One of the biggest challenges is that we need Wikimedians to get on board with the project in a big way. This is an incredible opportunity for us as a project, but it requires a special community effort to take full advantage of it. We need volunteers to tag articles, to categorize media, to help with templates and coding tools, to write related article content, to transcribe and proofread texts, to add new images to articles, to digitally restore images, and so on. I can personally serve as the point of contact between the National Archives and Wikimedia, but it needs to be much more than that to be a successful project. At this point, the project spaces I am creating on-wiki are my attempt to create an inviting and useful infrastructure to serve as a hub for this effort, but they are not organically grown like most Wikimedia projects. I, and various helpers with templates and coding, have magicked them into existence in the last few weeks. They need participants to sign up and adopt them as their own so we can really get the ball rolling.</p>
</text>
