<text id="autogum_interview_doc687" title="part10_Sam Brownback on running for President, gay rights, the Middle East and religion" shortTile="partsam-brownback" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-12" dateModified="2014-12-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sam_Brownback_on_running_for_President%2C_gay_rights%2C_the_Middle_East_and_religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But you've never thought about how--if you could choose how you'd prefer to die?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  No, that's--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It seems like such a basic human thing to contemplate, one's mortality.  I mean, I believe you, but--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  I've contemplated my mortality a lot.  Because I had <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/melanoma">melanoma</ref> eleven years ago, and I thought a long time about my mortality.  But what it did to me, it didn't make me think about how I wanted to die; it made me think about how I was living.  And I just wasn’t happy with how I was living.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What weren't you happy with?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  I was too <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/selfish">selfish</ref>; I was too <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ambition">ambition</ref>-driven.  I was not paying near the attention to my family that I should have been.  I was more interested in climbing the ladder, rather than helping people.  And it really came around to me that if I were to die with this, I wouldn't have been happy with how I'd lived my life.  And it just--it made my faith much stronger; it radically changed me, in looking at that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That was your--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  I still get it wrong a lot.  I am nowhere, anywhere near perfect.  I am a sinful, fallen man, but my faith really drives me much more now, and I do a lot of things that before, I wouldn't have done.  And I'm much happier with my life now than before that episode.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Was that your impetus to run for the Senate?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  No, but it did shape me, because it was just ahead of that run for the Senate that that episode happened.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What trait do you deplore in other people?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  I have too many of my own I deplore; it's hard for me to pick on somebody else.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Oh...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  I get judgmental quickly.  I don't see, as I should, the image of God as much in others as I really want to.  They're not traits in others that I deplore; it's ones in myself.</p>
<head id="On_environmentalism_and_energy">On environmentalism and energy</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you believe that a good Christian should also be a good environmentalist?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How so?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Well, we're given the planet and given dominion over it, and I believe we should be good stewards of that.  Now, the question becomes how do you do that, but I think the admonition to do that is God's creation, and we're the stewards of it.  I think we clearly should be.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And you don’t think that Arctic drilling contradicts that notion?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  I don't think the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ANWR">ANWR</ref> drilling has been proscribed.  We're talking about drilling in an area--I think the size is about ten miles by ten miles in an area that's the size of South Carolina.  We do need resources to be able to continue to run--that our dependency on foreign oil generally favors some people who are--who do a lot of pretty bad things, out of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref>, or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Venezuela">Venezuela</ref>, and that if we were less dependent upon that they would have less chance of doing some of the things they're doing.  To me, I think you've got to look at it in a balance…I'd love to see us using a lot more electricity in our car fleet, reduce our dependence on oil drastically.</p>
</text>
