<text id="autogum_interview_doc439" title="part0_CanadaVOTES: NDP candidate David Sparrow in Don Valley West" shortTile="partcanadavotes-ndp" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-10" dateModified="2009-03-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_NDP_candidate_David_Sparrow_in_Don_Valley_West" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>CanadaVOTES: NDP candidate David Sparrow in Don Valley West</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 10, 2008</hi></p>
<p>In an attempt to speak with as many candidates as possible during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008%20Canadian%20federal%20election">2008 Canadian federal election</ref>, Wikinews has talked via email with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Sparrow">David Sparrow</ref>. Sparrow is a candidate in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario">Ontario</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don%20Valley%20West%20(provincial%20electoral%20district)">Don Valley West</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riding_(country_subdivision)#Canada">riding</ref>, running under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Democratic%20Party">New Democratic Party</ref> (NDP) banner. The riding was set to vote in a by-election on September 22, 2008, following the resignation of John Godfrey, but <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Stephen_Harper">Stephen Harper</ref>'s sudden election call nulled that effort.</p>
<p>Also running in the Toronto riding are Liberal Rob Oliphant, Conservative John Carmichael, Green Georgina Wilcock, and Communist Catherine Holliday.</p>
<p>The following is an interview with Sparrow, conducted via email. The interview is published unedited, as sent to Wikinews.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why are you running for political office, why at the federal level, why this party, and why in this riding?</hi></p>
<p>Canada is at risk of losing its identity, economy and place on the international stage. Through changes to foreign ownership rules, big corporate tax cuts, aggressive changes to foreign policy and diminishing Arts budgets, we are seeing an erosion of Canadian control of our broadcasters, our manufacturing sector, our environment and the level of respect we command on the world over. This is why I am running for the NDP in Don Valley West. We must fight for the Canada we deserve. We must demand that government put all of our residents first before big, foreign controlled business and speculator and shareholder profits. Families are suffering and facing uncertainty over real, daily kitchen table issues and we need a responsive government and vocal, fearless representatives to fight for the issues important to them.</p>
<p>I have lived in and around Don Valley West for 19 years. My family and I lived for three years in Flemingdon Park. My children attended Gateway Public School. We now live in Leaside and I feel that my experience in these diverse communities along with my work in both the public and private sectors as an ambulance attendant and as a self-employed actor, writer and film maker will allow me to identify with the many issues facing different areas within our riding.</p>
<p>Jack Layton and the NDP have practical solutions that will address the kitchen table issues facing the people of Don Valley West. I have always felt that only by addressing the needs of residents at the local daily level of their lives can you properly represent this great country we share. The NDP does that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Previous to this campaign, have you been politically involved? How will you apply your previous work/volunteer/life experience to serving your constituents?</hi></p>
<p>I am currently the Vice President of Member Services for ACTRA Toronto and a national councillor for ACTRA National. I have lobbied on behalf of all cultural workers in Ottawa and at the Ontario Legislature to improve the funding and support of our talented Canadian artists and thereby the projection of Canada's voice to Canadians and the world. I will use this experience to continue our fight for Canada's identity and the reflection of our more established and emerging cultures. And I will use my skills, developed over 18 years in this profession, to fight for the important local issues facing the people of Don Valley West at the national level.</p>
</text>
