<text id="autogum_interview_doc1028" title="part4_Blown for Good author discusses life inside international headquarters of Scientology" shortTile="partblown-good-author" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-11-12" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Blown_for_Good_author_discusses_life_inside_international_headquarters_of_Scientology" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: Well, I think that when I was run off the road by the Scientology Security personnel, I had so much adrenaline pumping that even if I had sustained any minor injuries, I was willing to just do whatever I had to in order to successfully escape their control. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Upon your arrival at the international headquarters of Scientology, you recount how you were given a course where you were instructed that no one was allowed to tell family, friends, or other Scientology staff members that Scientology's "Int Base" was located in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hemet,%20California">Hemet, California</ref> (p. 91). Further, you write that no one outside the facility was to know that Scientology international management was located there. Do you know if this is still the case, or has current practice changed with regard to what outsiders are allowed to know about Gold Base?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: As far as I know, no internal policies have changed since I have left. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Another one of the instructions you write that you received upon arrival at Gold Base was that all outgoing mail would be read by Scientology security staff. Did this apply to incoming mail as well?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: Yes, ALL OUTGOING and INCOMING mail is not only logged, but also opened, checked and read by security personnel. Additionally, bank records or credit card information is culled for account numbers, and personal data or information that would be useful to track the person should they decide to leave the compound is kept on file and regularly updated. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Do you know whether or not this practice is in compliance with United States federal law regarding delivery of mail to its intended recipient?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: As far as I know, it is a federal offense to tamper with a person’s mail. The only place I know that mail can be checked like that is State or Federal prisons. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> According to your account of those that live on Gold Base itself (p. 138), the facility's residents included David Miscavige, three other high-ranking officials in the organization, security guards, and other residents, totaling 14 people excluding the security guards. Are you aware that Scientology requested the since-passed Ordinance 884 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riverside%20County,%20California">Riverside County, California</ref>, specifically to restrict protesters away from residential property - and claimed that Golden Era Productions is such a property? You write in the book that the majority of Gold Base employees actually live offsite in apartments. Do you know how many individuals currently reside on Gold Base itself? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: During the entire 15 years that I was there it was always the plan of Scientology officials to have ALL Int Base staff live on the property in communal housing. As far I know, these buildings have now been built and all employees that work at the Int Base also now live there, limiting not only their contact with the outside world but chances of ever escaping the facility. In fact, one of the reasons construction of these buildings was considered a priority while I was there was just that – keeping the staff housed on the property makes it that much harder for them to escape.</p>
</text>
