<text id="autogum_interview_doc1185" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Libertarian candidate Zork Hun, Parkdale-High Park" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-02" dateModified="2008-11-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Libertarian_candidate_Zork_Hun%2C_Parkdale-High_Park" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>The most important of my experiences is the close observation of the working of a communist country. I was working as a sociological research organizer working on several projects showing us how the benevolent condescension of the state can kill the spirit of civil society.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?</hi></p>
<p>The Libertarian Party advocates a minimal state for several reasons. We believe that a large state apparatus and ambitious government programs are bad for the economy, bad for civil society, bad for individual liberty. The most clearly statist party in Ontario is the NDP, promising anything without any consideration to cost, feasibility or to the potential damage the promised policy can cause. They are by far the most power hungry and the most aggressive in their pursuit of power.</p>
<p>Cheri DiNovo’s attitude exemplifies perfectly both the aggression and the irresponsibility, but it seems to work for her amazingly well.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>I represent the only party with a coherent political philosophy, the only one that derives his policies consistently from moral axioms and well proven economic principles.</p>
<p>We have simple, straightforward answers to every issue raised in this election. We base every one of our policies on:
<list type="unordered"><item>Faith in and respect for people</item>
<item>Trust in the power of the free market</item>
<item>Our commitment to non-coercive measures</item></list></p>
<p>We represent a moral and practical alternative opposed to the policies to all three statist parties.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>My impression from participating in All Candidates' Meetings is that the most important issue is income redistribution. Everybody wants somebody else to pay for what they want and the NDP is more than willing to promise anything to them.</p>
<p>The second issue is Education. People seem to have a problem with the notion of religious education.</p>
<p>The third issue is trust. My impression is that people do not know who to trust and are trying to figure out which of the candidates could be the most trustworthy manager. I don’t think people are looking for sweeping new programs, they just want competent managers.</p>
<p>My top three issues are income transfers, government monopolies (especially in education) and accountability.</p>
<p>The ongoing politics of governments taking money away from successful businesses and hard-working individuals just to hand it to badly managed businesses and special interest groups are causing untold amount of harm to the economy. (Also see my answer below on job creation) These direct money transfers should stop.</p>
</text>
