<text id="autogum_interview_doc643" title="part1_Popular soap opera &amp;apos;The Young and the Restless&amp;apos; celebrates 35 years on the air" shortTile="partpopular-soap" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-25" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Popular_soap_opera_%27The_Young_and_the_Restless%27_celebrates_35_years_on_the_air" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: Our show has always reflected the pertinent issues of the real world, so of course, that is constantly changing. Making the transition from a half hour to an hour was seamless, and that happened in 1980, my second year on the show.  As long as we have riveting character-driven stories, excellent actors and someone at the helm to make sure the look of the show remains unique and mesmerizing, we continue to hold the tradition that Bill Bell created.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michelle Stafford</hi>: Yeah, it's changed a lot but anything that goes on for a long time changes. Nothing stays the same.  I liked it then and I like it now too.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tricia Cast</hi>: Well, to be honest, I don't watch a lot of TV. To be <hi rend="italic">really</hi> honest, I didn't watch it much when I was on it either, and oftentimes didn't know what was going on with the other characters. Is that bad?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: What does being associated with Y&amp;R mean to you? What's the one thing you feel has impacted your life for the better from your association with the show?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: Y&amp;R changed my life in very significant ways. Probably more so than anyone else. It was through the show that I met my husband ([we] will be married for 23 years this October), had my children and given me the beautiful life that I live.  God was and still is smiling down on me!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michelle Stafford</hi>: I made money as an actress and that's always a good thing.  I'm always a fan of making money.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tricia Cast</hi>: Aside from being honored to be part of the best show on daytime, I learned so much in the time I was there. I'm a better technician for having worked there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: In terms of writing and depth of character, do you think your character is stronger now than she was, say, a decade ago?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: Hopefully she has learned more about life, which always makes a person smarter and therefore stronger. However, there are parts of her makeup that never change. For example, thinking with her heart and not her head. She will forever be vulnerable in the romance department and perhaps in the business world as well. I think she probably feels she is smarter than she actually is! But that's one of the things we love her for, isn't it?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michelle Stafford</hi>: You know what, some people would disagree with me but I think she is stronger now.  She's not whacking out every second of the day.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: Out of all the storylines you've been involved in, which one was your favorite?</p>
</text>
