<text id="autogum_interview_doc1307" title="part4_Wikinews interviews former Salt Lake City mayor and 2012 presidential candidate Rocky Anderson" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-12-17" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Salt_Lake_City_mayor_and_2012_presidential_candidate_Rocky_Anderson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><p>So, the American people understand that. They want to see people in elective office that for a change are not going to be sustaining and sustained by the corrupting influence of money in our government. They want to see that the public interest is promoted for a change. So, we have that elevated awareness about what’s going on in our government, about which people are very unhappy as reflected in 9 percent approval rating for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Congress">congress</ref> and a low 40s percent approval rating for our president.</p></p>
<p><p>And at the same time, and this is what’s different than even just a few years ago: we have the democratizing impact on communications from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/social%20media">social media</ref>. We’ve seen revolutions now in different parts of the world, the overthrow of dictators through a combination of courageous, tenacious people working at grassroots organizing and utilizing the tools now provided through social media. That’s why we’re going to be able to run this campaign limiting campaign contributions to $100 per person for the election cycle and maximizing in every way we can, the use of social media. This will be a people’s movement that is already gaining unbelievable traction after just one week since we announced.</p></p>
<head id="The_Justice_Party_and_opposition">The Justice Party and opposition</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Let me ask about the Justice Party. What is it? How large is it? And how can people join?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Rocky Anderson</hi>: People can join in a number of different ways. There’s a website: justicepartyusa.org. There have been hundreds, probably thousands of inquires from people from dozens of states about getting on board, helping out as they can. There’s a steering committee, and we’re building on that steering committee as we speak. These are some great passionate, engaged, brilliant people, who’ve been working on this. But to see this happen in the sense, quite organically over time starting with discussions with people who have been contemplated doing this kind of work, coming together, building coalitions; I see the possibility of alliances or coalitions being built with different organizations around the country. The head of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libertarian_Party_(United_States)">Libertarian Party</ref> in one state came to us and said that he was publicly going to support what we’re doing. I’ve had Republicans contact me, telling us that they’ve had it with the craziness in that party; this extreme right wing approach that that party is now taking since the Tea Party’s had such enormous impact. We’re hearing from people who have been lifetime independents, members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%20Party%20(United%20States)">Green Party</ref>. We’ve got members of the Progressive Democrats that are being threatened to have their charter jerked by the Democratic Party because of their support for what we’re doing. In fact, one gentleman from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressive%20Democrats%20of%20America">Progressive Democrats of America</ref> out of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chicago">Chicago</ref>, is now on our steering committee. So this is an amazingly, cross-partisan representation of people who agree about the fundamentals and that is we need to change, not just the candidates that are playing within the system, but we need to change the system.</p></p>
</text>
