<text id="autogum_interview_doc1342" title="part1_Interview with Anna Mikkola, Finnish Left Alliance candidate for European Parliament" shortTile="partinterview-anna" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-05-28" dateModified="2014-01-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Anna_Mikkola%2C_Finnish_Left_Alliance_candidate_for_European_Parliament" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<hi rend="bold">I think the new political generation are going to change political discourse substantially.</hi>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Well, it makes my relationship with Finland's EU membership definetely easier and less emotional maybe than for many older people. Finland has been in the EU my whole adulthood, so for me membership is not the question. I am more interested in looking at the content. I think the new political generation of around 30 year olds, who are making their breakthrough, are going to change political discourse substantially.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you see green &amp; socialist politics as being the key to this younger generation? In your view can you have environmentalism without socialism?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> We have an interesting Green party in Finland, who have accepted the necessity of additional nuclear power and support market mechanisms as a part of their climate policy without any questions or caveats. So yes, there is an attempt to create a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eco-capitalism">green capitalist system</ref>. The youth as well are divided on this issue. Many people however do see the problems of turning the environment or climate action into products you can buy or sell and speculate with. In that sense I feel environmentalism cannot be separated from socialism, which has a fundamentally different logic.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">The other end, though, to the importance of the youth vote is voter apathy; how do you deal with the situation of "celebrity" candidates, in particular far-right candidates like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timo%20Soini">Timo Soini</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> In European elections the problem is apathy in general, not just youth apathy. But maybe you can separate between two types: many older people do not vote in these elections because they don't like the EU and/or because they feel they cannot change anything by voting since the EU is too big and too far way. These are choices, often resulting from considering the options. Many young people do not vote in elections in general, because they do not really even notice them. Their apathy is not a result of a decision, but genuinely a product of being out of the whle political process. This is something Timo Soini cannot change I think. His candidacy is a big risk for him in any case, since <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/True%20Finns">his party</ref> is a one man show to a great extent. If he buries himself in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brussels">Brussels</ref> it might well be the end of that party.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You've been working in Brussels yourself for over a year now; how did you stay in touch with the situation in Finland before the campaign began?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Mostly by visiting Finland often. It's been two years that I have worked in the European parliament now. Working as a parliamentary assistant to a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esko%20Seppänen">Finnish MEP</ref> kind of means you need to be aware of what is happening in Finland and what the papers are saying about it.</p>
</text>
