<text id="autogum_interview_doc1156" title="part10_Obesity and the Fat Acceptance Movement: Kira Nerusskaya speaks" shortTile="partobesity-fat-acceptance" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-09" dateModified="2014-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Obesity_and_the_Fat_Acceptance_Movement%3A_Kira_Nerusskaya_speaks" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s not speaking a taboo, basically.  To be fat is taboo and to say someone is fat...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  But it doesn’t have to be taboo.  We’ve created the taboo.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you against these euphemisms?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  I don’t know because it’s one of those things.  It’s kind of like...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  People think it’s polite.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  There’s a lot of ways around polite.  I know in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ireland">Ireland</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">England</ref> people can’t use the word “fat.”  That’s extremely offensive.  When I was in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref> interviewing people, they said, “Why do you have to call your movie Under the Fat?  Why do you have to use the word ‘fat’?”  Fat was equal to something negative.  I was like, all right, they haven’t come full circle in the movement yet to understand that fat is just a descriptor.  It’s like, am I curvy?  Yes, I am.  Am I fat?  Yes, I am.  Am I plus size?  Yes, I am.  Am I a big, beautiful woman?  Yes, I am.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do fat people prefer to be called generally?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  I think it depends on each individual.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Generally?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  I don’t know.  A lot of people say, “I’m a fat chick.”  You know, “Are you fat?”  “Yeah, I’m fat.”  Full-figured to me is someone of a certain weight.  After full, then it becomes something else where there are terms like BBW, then we have Super-Sized BBW; it kind of all fits along that umbrella category of plus size.  How people describe themselves depends upon where they are at with their own comfort, so it’s difficult for me to say that it’s one or the other.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is there a terminology that is definitely taboo?  That you hear and it’s not okay.  Aside from the obvious, like you know, ‘fatty’ or something...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Oops, Dave just blew that one out of the water!  She shows Dave Shankbone her pin that says, “Fatty.”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Let me rephrase the question.  For a person trying to be real but not wanting to be offensive, what advice would you give them when they’re trying to use a descriptor or trying to talk about a person who might be large?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  What about a conversation like this: “Yeah, I know this chick.”  “Really?”  “Yeah, I think you might be perfect for each other.”  “Oh, okay.  Well, what does she look like?”  “Well, she’s a big girl.  She’s a large girl,” you know.  Voluptuous and shapely might not be cutting it unless she is voluptuous and shapely.  “Well, she’s a big girl.  She’s a fat girl but she’s really pretty and she’s really nice and she’s this, that and the other.”  Do you know what I mean?</p>
</text>
