<text id="autogum_interview_doc1330" title="part1_Wikinews investigates the reconstruction of Pichilemu, Chile after February earthquake" shortTile="partwikinews-investigates" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-10-23" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_investigates_the_reconstruction_of_Pichilemu%2C_Chile_after_February_earthquake" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agustín%20Ross%20Balcony">Agustín Ross Balcony</ref> after the earthquake and tsunami. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The only radio broadcasting in the area was <hi rend="italic">Entre Olas</hi>, directed by Jorge Nasser, which also helped Pichileminians know what happened in other affected places by the earthquake, as they re-broadcasted the audio of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TVN%20(Chile)">Televisión Nacional de Chile</ref> (National Television of Chile). On the day of the earthquake, the station reported that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pichilemu%20Police">a local police</ref> truck had crashed near La Cruz Hill. There was no tsunami warning, and Mayor Córdova was away on holiday when the earthquake struck.</p>
<p>"Those who live in Pichilemu, and those who were visiting it, were surprised by the giant waves that annihilated its beach and reached the city's square, destroying everything on their way," reported <hi rend="italic">El Morrocotudo</hi> on February 28. "The most tough thing occurred when the firefighters' alarms sounded twice, and the people in the hill began to yell 'tsunami!'," journalist Tania Arce told the newspaper.</p>
<p>The earthquake destroyed one of Pichilemu's oldest and iconic buildings, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pichilemu%20post%20office%20building">the post office</ref>, which was <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pichilemu,_Chile_former_post_office_is_demolished">demolished</ref> in July. The urban centre of Pichilemu was not severely damaged by the earthquake, but its subsequent tsunami caused most of the destruction. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agustín%20Ross">Agustín Ross</ref> architecture in the city (three of his buildings are <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Monuments%20of%20Chile">National Monuments of Chile</ref>) was damaged. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agustín%20Ross%20Balcony">Agustín Ross Balcony</ref> was completely destroyed.</p>
<head id="'It's_something_unforgettable_to_me,_I'm_proud_I_saved_all_of_those_lives'">'It's something unforgettable to me, I'm proud I saved all of those lives'</head>
<figure><caption>The tsunami destroyed most of Pichilemu's coastal street establishments, including kiosks, restaurants and hotels. The picture shows the <hi rend="italic">Donde Esaú Restaurant</hi>, which was severely damaged by both the tsunami and earthquake. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SHOA">SHOA</ref>, the Hydrographic and Oceanographic Service of the Chilean Navy, the tsunami triggered by the earthquake first reached <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pichilemu">Pichilemu</ref>, at 03:48 (06:48 UTC). A second wave came at 04:15 (07:15 UTC).</p>
<p>Policeman José Arévalo was the only person to warn residents that a tsunami was approaching. Arévalo was patrolling the Las Terrazas beach, when the earthquake occurred. He told <hi rend="italic">El Rancahuaso</hi> there were around 25 people in the beach. "Right after the quake, he noticed the sea had shrank around 500 meters inside. He took his megaphone, and shouted people should leave the place instantly." "The sea is coming out! The sea is coming out!," he shouted. "The warning was also preceived by nightclubs and pubs surrounding the <hi rend="italic">costanera</hi>. Then, the tragedy occurred. The sea destroyed everything on its way," <hi rend="italic">El Rancahuaso</hi> reported. "It all was really quick. Everyone is safe, luckily [..] It's something unforgettable to me, I'm proud I saved all of those lives," Arévalo added.</p>
<p>The tsunami destroyed restaurants, hotels, kiosks, the Fishermen Store (Caleta de Pescadores), surf schools, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agustín%20Ross%20Balcony">Agustín Ross Balcony</ref> (located right in front of the Las Terrazas beach) and houses near the <hi rend="italic">costanera</hi> (the nearest street to the beach), and flooded the building of the Government of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardenal%20Caro%20Province">Cardenal Caro Province</ref>, the boarding school of Pichilemu, the city square (Arturo Prat Square), and the Supermarket El 9.</p>
</text>
