<text id="autogum_interview_doc345" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Jim Hedges, U.S. Prohibition Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-01-26" dateModified="2016-11-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jim_Hedges%2C_U.S._Prohibition_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>The rest of that is campaign hyperbole. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why did you choose to run for president and what are your qualifications?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> It’s partly a "finger-in-the-dike" tactic, because I see no one else in the organization who has the free time and the personal background needed to mount a plausible campaign.  Partly, also, it’s the realization that, at age 72, if I’m ever going to do it, I’d better get on with doing it now.</p>
<p>Many times in the past, the Prohibition Party has recruited presidential candidates from outside its own ranks.  The same may happen again this year.   If not, I see myself as being the most  broadly educated and widely experienced person within the core group of the Party.  </p>
<p>I have a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bachelor%20of%20Arts">BA</ref> in musical performance (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Iowa">Iowa</ref>, 1960) and served 20 years in one of our nation’s most elite military units, The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Marine%20Band">United States Marine Band</ref>.  </p>
<p>I have a family-farm background, plus 20 years of life in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington%20Metropolitan%20Area">Washington, DC metropolitan area</ref>.  I understand both rural and urban communities.</p>
<p>I have an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master%20of%20Arts%20(postgraduate)">MA</ref> in Geography (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Maryland,%20College%20Park">Maryland</ref>, 1972),  have published research in refereed journals both here and abroad, and for 11 years edited a journal.  </p>
<p>I have done volunteer work with and served as an officer of community organizations ranging from The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salvation%20Army">Salvation Army</ref> to friends of the library to recycling programs to historical and literary clubs.</p>
<p>I have done newspaper reporting, primarily on local government.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Who are some of your opponents for the nomination and why do you believe you are a better choice for the party?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> To my knowledge, no one else has yet expressed an interest in the Prohibition Party nomination.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">When and where will the party hold their convention, and how will a nominee be decided upon?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cullman,%20Alabama">Cullman, Alabama</ref>, in June.  See the <ref target="http://www.prohibitionparty.org">National Committee's website</ref> for details. </p>
<p>A vote of the  credentialed delegates will determine who is the candidate.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you agree with the decision to allow prominent <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libertarian">Libertarian</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen%20P.%20Gordon">Stephen P. Gordon</ref> to speak at the convention, despite his support for the sale of alcohol?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Yes.  First of all, the Prohibition Party and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Libertarian%20Party">Libertarian Party</ref> share some common interests, such as small government, balanced budgets, and personal freedoms.  Secondly, we should all take time to listen to those who disagree with us, in order to sharpen our debating skills.  Thirdly, we shouldn’t be complacent, because... we might actually be wrong!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">According to the <ref target="http://www.ballot-access.org/2010/02/20/james-hedges-seeks-prohibition-party-presidential-nomination-in-2012/"><hi rend="italic">Ballot Access News</hi></ref>, the Prohibition Party has qualified for the ballot in only Florida. What will you do to gain ballot access in other states?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Most likely, we will be able to meet the ballot requirements in only 2 or 3 states in addition to Florida (which has among the most lenient ballot access regulations today).    Colorado is a likely one, as are Mississippi and Louisiana.  </p>
</text>
