<text id="autogum_interview_doc028" title="part0_Tim Curry, TV premiere screenings, cosplay feature at Fan Expo Canada" shortTile="parttim-curry-tv" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-09-02" dateModified="2019-04-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tim_Curry%2C_TV_premiere_screenings%2C_cosplay_feature_at_Fan_Expo_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tim Curry, TV premiere screenings, cosplay feature at Fan Expo Canada</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 6, 2017</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Toronto">Toronto</ref> pop culture convention <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Fan_Expo_Canada">Fan Expo Canada</ref> has wrapped for another year. It ran from Thursday to Sunday. Major panels included <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim%20Curry">Tim Curry</ref> and the cast of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rocky%20Horror%20Picture%20Show">Rocky Horror Picture Show</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beauty%20and%20the%20Beast%20(1991%20film)">Beauty and the Beast</ref></hi> voices <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robby%20Benson">Robby Benson</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paige%20O'Hara">Paige O'Hara</ref>, actors <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kathleen%20Turner">Kathleen Turner</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard%20Dreyfuss">Richard Dreyfuss</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony%20Daniels">Anthony Daniels</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Felicia%20Day">Felicia Day</ref>, and child leads from <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stranger%20Things">Stranger Things</ref></hi>. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canadian</ref> television channel <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Space%20(TV%20channel)">Space</ref> hosted a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star%20Trek:%20Discovery">Star Trek: Discovery</ref></hi> panel with seven lead cast members. On the heels of sister event Toronto Comic Con's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Degrassi%20Junior%20High">Degrassi</ref></hi> reunion event, the lineup included a twentieth anniversary panel with the stars of another Canadian high school television series, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Student%20Bodies">Student Bodies</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>Heading into its fourth and final season, attendees got a chance to see the season opener of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star%20Wars:%20Rebels">Star Wars: Rebels</ref></hi> on Saturday, followed by a panel. The event has had a continuing relationship with the series, screening other episodes previously. The second season premiere of the sci-fi series <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Travelers%20(TV%20series)">Travelers</ref></hi> was accompanied by a panel including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric%20McCormack">Eric McCormack</ref>. Canadian true-crime drama <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bad%20Blood%20(TV%20series)">Bad Blood</ref></hi> had its world premiere. Other debuts included broadcaster <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City%20(TV%20network)">City</ref> with the Canadian premiere of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghosted%20(TV%20series)">Ghosted</ref></hi>, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Craig%20Robinson%20(actor)">Craig Robinson</ref> in attendance, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teletoon">Teletoon</ref> with the Canadian premiere of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hotel%20Transylvania:%20The%20Series">Hotel Transylvania: The Series</ref></hi>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YTV%20(TV%20channel)">YTV</ref> with the new animated series <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mysticons">Mysticons</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>Anime fans could watch episodes of their favourite shows, including <hi rend="italic">AKB0048</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Otaku No Video</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Hana Yamata</hi>, <hi rend="italic">My Hero Academia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Fairy Tail</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Penguindrum</hi>.</p>
<p>The book <hi rend="italic">Star Wars Made Easy</hi>, targeted to non-fans to get up to speed on the fictional universe's various facts and figures, was ironically launched by DK Canada for a room of fans of the franchise. Author Christian Blauvelt answered questions from the audience on topics like his opinion on Midiclorians — he understands fan contention, but suggested that science and religion can co-exist, like in the real world — quizzed the audience on trivia, and signed copies of his book.</p>
<p>Some panels were quite ahead of the curve: one on <hi rend="italic">Star Wars</hi> costume and prop building discussed building Porgs figures, despite the film <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Last%20Jedi">The Last Jedi</ref></hi> not being released to theatres yet.</p>
<figure><caption>Unity and United, from the York Regional Police. Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Zanimum">Nicholas Moreau</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/York%20Regional%20Police">York Regional Police</ref> were at the event with United and Unity, two brightly lit characters of their own creation. The force received funding in 2014 from the Provincial Anti-Violence Intervention Strategy  to create a short film featuring the character United, receiving positive recognition locally. “Our United superhero program is part of our on-going efforts to connect with our community and show police in a different light,” YRP Constable Andy Pattenden told Wikinews. He explains that the officers who developed the project have a background in film-making, and “serve as an opportunity for us to start a conversation with youth and connect with them at a non-traditional level.”</p>
</text>
