<text id="autogum_interview_doc951" title="part2_Exclusive: 'The Scientology Reformation' author examines Tom Cruise and David Miscavige" shortTile="partexclusive--scientology" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-10-18" dateModified="2012-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Exclusive%3A_%27The_Scientology_Reformation%27_author_examines_Tom_Cruise_and_David_Miscavige" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "No. The tactics are anachronistic. They were conceived during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold%20War">Cold War</ref> to deal with a cold war era attack."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What are your thoughts on the response of the precursor to the Office of Special Affairs (OSA), the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List%20of%20Guardian's%20Office%20operations">Guardian's Office (GO)</ref>, to journalist and author of the book <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Scandal%20of%20Scientology">The Scandal of Scientology</ref></hi>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paulette%20Cooper">Paulette Cooper</ref>? Is there any inside information or backstory you can share with us, regarding what happened to her? Is there anything else that you know, that hasn’t yet been exposed, about what happened to Paulette Cooper?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "Reprehensible. I have no other data to share — it is quite graphically spelled out in the GO's own documents that were put on the public record in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington,_D.C.">D.C.</ref> Federal Court in 1978."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Other high-ranking executives within the Scientology organization have left before you, and tried to form groups which practiced a similar philosophy. For example, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Mayo">David Mayo</ref> formed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advanced%20Ability%20Center">Advanced Ability Center</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa%20Barbara,%20California">Santa Barbara</ref>, California, which (according to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inside%20Scientology:%20The%20Story%20of%20America's%20Most%20Secretive%20Religion"><hi rend="italic">Inside Scientology</hi> by Janet Reitman</ref>) after a few years of operating by 1986 was "bankrupt after several years of litigation and harassment, shut down." Another group was called the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free%20Zone">Free Zone</ref>", similarly formed over disagreements with David Miscavige and the RTC, which was influenced by former Sea Org member William "Captain Bill" Robertson. How and why will the current "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent%20Scientology">Independent Scientology</ref>" movement succeed, where others have failed?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "The main difference is that David Mayo and Bill Robertson tried to become the new L. Ron Hubbard and set up another version of what Hubbard created. That creation — the organization structure served the organization well for its first several decades, but became outdated and obsolete around the time of Hubbard's death, 1986. The current independent movement is predicated on the idea that Scientology was destroyed by being monopolized — and if it survives it will because enough people appreciate that was the core reason for the demise of the original organizations."</p>
<hi rend="bold">[Scientology executives] were long ago overwhelmed with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cognitive%20dissonance">cognitive dissonance</ref> to the point where they have created a bizarre, anachronistic universe that is destined for extinction.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mark_Rathbun">Mark Rathbun</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Since leaving organized Scientology under David Miscavige have you read much about the theory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cognitive%20dissonance">cognitive dissonance</ref>? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "Yes."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> How do you think cognitive dissonance applies to those high-ranking executives still under the authority of David Miscavige? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "They were long ago overwhelmed with cognitive dissonance to the point where they have created a bizarre, anachronistic universe that is destined for extinction. They are clueless and they are so unreal and stuck to literally following outdated policies that it is hardwired for dissolution."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Could you reflect on and describe your own period of mental growth and cognitive dissonance since leaving organized Scientology under David Miscavige?</hi></p>
</text>
