<text id="autogum_interview_doc062" title="part2_Biologist Nick Bos tells Wikinews about &amp;apos;self-medicating&amp;apos; ants" shortTile="partbiologist-nick" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-09-01" dateModified="2015-10-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Biologist_Nick_Bos_tells_Wikinews_about_%27self-medicating%27_ants" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>The Univeristy of Helsinki from file.Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:ElmA">Smaug</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Are there any ethical considerations around exposing ants to toxins and parasites?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NB</hi> Legally, no. Insects do not have any 'rights' as such regarding  ethics. That said, we do take measures to not make them 'suffer  unnecessarily'. For example, dissections are done when the ants are anesthetized (either by CO2 or Ice), and when ants need to be killed,  we do it in alcohol, which kills the ants in a matter of seconds. So while the ants do not have 'rights' as such, we still try to handle them with as much respect as possible (even though the experiment  involves infecting them with a deadly fungus).</p>
<p>But even though the 12,000 ants in our study sounds like a lot (and it is), this is negligible in the 'grand scheme of things'. It has been  calculated that in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Netherlands">the Netherlands</ref> alone, nearly a trillion insects die against just the licence-plates of cars every six months. I don't own a car, so that means I'm excused right? ;)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  This is the first evidence for self-medicating insects. How widespread do you think this phenomenon could be in reality?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NB</hi> It's not actually the first evidence for self-medication in insects. Moths and fruit flies definitely do it, and there's evidence in honey bees and bumble-bees as well. So it seems to be quite wide-spread in  the insect world. I have no doubt that as time goes on, there will be  more and more cases documented. Insects (and animals in general) seem  to be quite good at taking care of themselves.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How might ants locate healing substances in the wild?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NB</hi> Very good question. This is something that's important to know. If they would only do it in the lab, the behaviour wouldn't be very interesting. We have some guesses where they might get it from, but at the moment we don't know yet. That said, I plan to investigate this  question (among others) further [in] the next couple of years.</p>
<figure><caption>Another file photo of <hi rend="italic">Formica fusca</hi>, this time showing foraging workers feeding.Image: Sedeer El-Showk.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  For your PhD you researched ants' scent-based communications. Could healthy ants perhaps tell other ants are infected and encourage this behaviour?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NB</hi> There's not much known about this. There's conflicting evidence about whether sick ants actually smell different from healthy ones or not. At the moment it seems that sick ants mostly take care of the problem themselves. Sick ants stop most interaction with nestmates and especially <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/brood">brood</ref>, and leave the nest to die in isolation. This is probably for reducing chance of infecting nestmates, but of course it  also reduces the work load of their nest-mates, as their corpse  doesn't have to be dragged out etc.</p>
</text>
