<text id="autogum_interview_doc1314" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Darcy Richardson, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-11-24" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Darcy_Richardson%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Darcy Richardson, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 25, 2011</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Democratic Party presidential candidate <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Darcy_Richardson">Darcy Richardson</ref>.Image: Darcy Richardson.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democratic Party</ref> presidential candidate <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Darcy_Richardson">Darcy Richardson</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Florida">Florida</ref> took some time to answer a few questions from <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter William S. Saturn.</p>
<p>Richardson, 55, is a political activist that helped form the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Democrats">New Democrats</ref> in 1989 and founded the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressivism%20in%20the%20United%20States">progressive</ref> <hi rend="italic">Battleground Blog</hi> earlier this year. He is also a political historian, and has authored six books covering <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third%20party%20(United%20States)">third parties</ref> and presidential elections, including <hi rend="italic">A Nation Divided: The 1968 Presidential Campaign</hi> (2002).  His current work, <hi rend="italic">The Spirit of ’76: Eugene McCarthy’s Struggle for Open Politics</hi>, chronicles the late Democratic <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Senate">Senator</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eugene%20McCarthy">Eugene McCarthy</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eugene%20McCarthy%20presidential%20campaign,%201976">1976 presidential campaign</ref> for which he volunteered.  Richardson admires McCarthy, and served as manager for his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%201988">1988 presidential</ref> run. Recently, Richardson advised <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brian%20Moore">Brian Moore</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialist%20Party%20USA">Socialist Party USA</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brian%20Moore%20presidential%20campaign,%202008">presidential campaign</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2008">2008</ref>.</p>
<p>In addition, Richardson himself has sought political office, albeit unsuccessfully. In 1980, he ran for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pennsylvania%20Auditor%20General">Auditor General</ref>, and in 1988, vied for one of Pennsylvania's U.S. Senate seats as a member of the Consumer Party.  Last year, he ran for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lieutenant%20Governor%20of%20Florida">Lieutenant Governor of Florida</ref> as the running mate of gubernatorial candidate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Farid%20Khavari">Farid Khavari</ref>.</p>
<p>Richardson has criticized President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>'s policies for being too similar to those of former President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref>. He hoped to convince several prominent progressives to challenge Obama in the Democratic primaries, but none were available to do so. Last month, Richardson decided to begin a campaign himself and announced through his <hi rend="italic">Battleground Blog</hi> that he would challenge Obama in the Democratic Party primaries as a progressive candidate. So far, he has qualified for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Hampshire">New Hampshire</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Hampshire%20primary">primary</ref> in January and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Missouri">Missouri</ref> primary in February. In an interview with the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent%20Political%20Report">Independent Political Report</ref></hi>, Richardson proclaimed his campaign slogan as "no fourth term for George W. Bush."</p>
<head id="Background">Background</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">When did you first meet Senator Eugene McCarthy, and what attracted you to his campaign?</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eugene%20McCarthy">Eugene McCarthy</ref>.Image: United States Federal Government.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Darcy Richardson</hi>: I first met Senator McCarthy during his independent campaign for the presidency in 1976 when I was about 19 or 20 years old.  I had been an admirer of the former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Minnesota">Minnesota</ref> lawmaker dating back to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eugene%20McCarthy%20presidential%20campaign,%201968">his 1968 campaign</ref> when he courageously challenged <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lyndon%20B.%20Johnson">LBJ</ref> for the Democratic presidential nomination, essentially risking his political career to end the unjust <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vietnam%20War">war</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vietnam">Vietnam</ref>.  It was a candidacy of conscience.  Similarly, I was strongly attracted to Gene's 1976 effort, believing that he was far better qualified than either <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jimmy_Carter">Jimmy Carter</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gerald_Ford">Gerald Ford</ref>.  McCarthy's campaign that year — striking down burdensome and discriminatory <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ballot%20access">ballot access</ref> laws in no fewer than twenty-four states — was an heroic effort to further the cause of open politics in this country.  McCarthy's legal team, headed by young lawyers John C. Armor and Philip L. Marcus, described it as "The Bloodless Revolution of 1976."  McCarthy's candidacy that year had a lasting effect on my own politics.  I knew Gene fairly well and visited him several times in later years in his book-filled home near the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blue%20Ridge%20Mountains">Blue Ridge Mountains</ref>, a rustic and comfortable dwelling lined with pictures of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/W.%20B.%20Yeats">Yeats</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20Joyce">Joyce</ref>.  Gene was an original voice in American politics.  He was also a pretty decent poet.</p>
</text>
