<text id="autogum_interview_doc053" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Steve Burke, U.S. Democratic Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-12-11" dateModified="2019-08-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Steve_Burke%2C_U.S._Democratic_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are some of your achievements as councilman in Macomb, New York?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SB</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I am the only Democrat on the five person board. So the entire board has to take credit of keeping tax increases below 2% a year without going into our fund balance. In fact our fund balance is the best of the other 31 towns and the county of St. Lawrence. We have lowered the cost of health care along with our tax base. Upgraded equipment, put money aside for replacement equipment, made our buildings energy efficient. Then we started at the beginning of each meeting the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pledge%20of%20Allegiance">Pledge of Allegiance</ref> and a short prayer to the Almighty. Best of all we have no debt.</p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St.%20Lawrence%20County,%20New%20York">St. Lawrence County</ref> highlighted in red. Image: David Benbennick.</caption></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are some of your achievements as chairman of the Democratic Party of St. Lawrence County?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SB</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  This was a strong <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</ref> county when I first became chair. I was able to turn the county around to Democrat, but now it has fallen back to Republican. I started the first resource guide that allowed us to raise funds, obtained a house for the first time ever headquarters. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hillary_Clinton">Hillary Clinton</ref> won her first Senate seat with just 10 counties out of 62 in New York. We were one of those 10 counties when I was chair. I served as chair and was called back after several years to be chair again. I left the party in both a happy, strong and good financial condition.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WWNY-TV">WWNY-TV</ref>, you previously ran for president in 1992.  What was the nature of that run and what did you learn from it?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SB</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I am impressed that you did some investigative work. It is rare today. Good for you. You should go far in this field. The country was just starting to feel the impact of a slowdown. I wanted to speak out as to what I saw and speak to the issues of the day. I learned that it was a closed shop then and has gotten worse both in ability to be recognized and the economic situation.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NAFTA">NAFTA</ref> and all free trade policies are detrimental to our economical health, jobs, income and general well being of the country.  When NAFTA was first proposed I was chair and spoke out against it and was given heat for it. But oh well I swim upstream anyway.</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Did you run in any presidential primaries in 1992?</hi></item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SB</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I ran in six states total and did the best [in] <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Louisiana">Louisiana</ref>.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why are you [a] Democrat? What do you like about the party and have you ever considered joining a non-establishment party?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">SB</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  No I will not join any other party. I like the freedom of being a Democrat. This freedom is not found in other parties.</p>
</text>
