<text id="autogum_interview_doc243" title="part1_Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy" shortTile="partdr-joseph-merlino" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-04" dateModified="2013-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dr._Joseph_Merlino_on_sexuality%2C_insanity%2C_Freud%2C_fetishes_and_apathy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/eccentricity">eccentricity</ref> would be a form of insanity in principle, relative to whatever society found it eccentric, since it is a violation of social norms and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/mores">mores</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  It would bring the person to the attention of whoever it is in that society that dictates what is pathology and normality—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  —is '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychopathology">pathological</ref>' better than '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/insane">insane</ref>' as a term?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  Yes, it's a value judgment.  Insanity has a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pejorative">pejorative</ref> connotation as opposed to saying someone is ill.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So a woman who goes walking down the street naked in the middle of Manhattan, but fully cognizant of it and doing it to elicit a reaction, she has a pathology?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  Well, she is going to come to the attention of authorities who are going to question whether she has pathology or not.  Certainly, she is bucking the cultural norm, and chances are the individual is going to be picked up by the police, taken to the station, and then probably be brought to a psychiatric emergency room for an evaluation to determine whether or not she is disordered.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How often are people who are considered to have a mental disorder or pathology aware that their behavior is thought of as problematic by other people?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  It's a challenge for them.  Take the most extreme, say someone who is grossly psychotic.  More often, they are <hi rend="italic">not</hi> aware that their behavior is problematic to society and that is what gets them into difficulties.  Other individuals who <hi rend="italic">are</hi> more aware usually are on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/personality%20disorder">personality disorder</ref> realm of diagnoses.  Even there, people with personality disorders are comfortable with what they are doing; the problem is, what I cause you.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Such as a person who has an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anger%20management">anger management</ref> problem?  The problem isn't that they are brought to anger, it's the external influences.  Even though that they know anger is not a preferable state to be in, they don't see themselves as the problem, even though they know that people get them there is a problem.  In other words, my anger is not good, but the real problem is that you made me angry.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  The challenge is getting them to realize how their own behavior is a problem for other people.  If somebody has an anger management issue that they are not aware of, but they are constantly having fights with their spouse, they are getting fired from jobs, their kids aren't talking to them...this is creating distress if not in the individual, certainly in their family.  The goal there is to get the individual to realize he or she is creating a problem, and get them to identify what that problem is and to take steps to ameliorate it.</p>
</text>
