<text id="autogum_interview_doc795" title="part0_CanadaVOTES: CHP candidate Steven Elgersma running in Haldimand—Norfolk" shortTile="partcanadavotes-chp" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-18" dateModified="2010-06-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_CHP_candidate_Steven_Elgersma_running_in_Haldimand%E2%80%94Norfolk" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>CanadaVOTES: CHP candidate Steven Elgersma running in Haldimand—Norfolk</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 19, 2008</hi></p>
<p>On October 14, 2008, Canadians will be heading to the polls for the federal election. <hi rend="bold">Christian Heritage Party candidate Steven Elgersma</hi> is standing for election in <hi rend="bold">the riding of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haldimand—Norfolk">Haldimand—Norfolk</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>Wikinews contacted Steven Elgersma, to talk about the issues facing Canadians, and what they and their party would do to address them. Wikinews is in the process of contacting every candidate, in every riding across the country, no matter their political stripe. All interviews are conducted over e-mail, and interviews are published unedited, allowing candidates to impart their full message to our readers, uninterrupted.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why are you running for political office, why at the federal level, why this party, and why in this riding?</hi></p>
<p>I am running as a Candidate for the CHP because it is the only Federal Party that is squarely based on Christian principles, the only Party that believes in the Supremacy of God, the only Party that is fully Pro-life from conception to natural death, the only Party that believes abortion is the killing of a life and should not be funded by the government, the only Party that is fully Pro-Family, the only Party that believes that homosexuality is contrary to God's will and commandments, for it has been clearly demonstrated, that homosexuality has no genetic or hormonal cause, but is an addiction much like alcoholism, and the only Party that would deal decisively with the Human Rights Commissions, who have been successful in fining people who say anything against the practice of homosexuality. The Plaintiff is paid by the government, and the Defender has to pay his own expenses. This is Christian persecution.</p>
<p>All other Parties do not figure with the Supremacy of God. They have in effect said to God to keep his nose out of our business and we will decide how to do things. Our Policy Booklet says, "We affirm that the spirit, or moral ethic, behind Canada's laws must be that of the Holy Bible in recognition of the fact hat Canada is founded upon principles that recognize the supremacy of God and the rule of law.’Human Rights' as expressed in the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms can only, therefore, be legitimately interpreted in light of, or in conjunction with, the higher Moral Law of God. We therefore believe that Biblical principles must form the foundation for legislation and judicial interpretation thereof."</p>
<p>Another policy is quite revealing. It states: We believe that anarchy will result from prolonged enforcement of 'human rights' where these are interpreted to mean the freedom to act in violation of Biblical ethics, or where the term 'discrimination' is used as a pretext for the dilution or dissolution of morally-sound activity or conduct. We affirm that the insistence of so-called "Gay-Rights" by homosexuals and lesbians is a threat to our nation's family life and extends civil rights beyond what is appropriate. We affirm that the society that indiscriminately stresses 'rights' is headed for revolution, while the society that stresses 'responsibilities' is headed for revival.</p>
</text>
