<text id="autogum_interview_doc1382" title="part5_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<head id="Tawana_Brawley_to_Megan_Williams">Tawana Brawley to Megan Williams</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you tired of hearing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tawana%20Brawley">Tawana Brawley</ref> always paired with your name?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  No.  You know what happens?  It has been so long—twenty years—that when a lot of people back up on that, others realize how ludicrous it is.  They say, “Wait a minute, you have to go back <hi rend="italic">twenty years</hi> to criticize him?  And He believed in a girl that <hi rend="italic">you</hi> don’t believe in?” So, twenty years later now and the same thing happened to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Megan%20Williams%20case">Megan Williams in West Virginia</ref>.  Was that a hoax?  When you look at the span of my career, from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Griffith%20(manslaughter%20victim)">Howard Beach</ref> before Brawley to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sean%20Bell">Sean Bell</ref> now, if all you can do is go to one case twenty years ago, then most people would say that is a little shaky.  I mean, come on.  Because if I was a hoaxster, then why haven’t we seen other hoaxes in twenty years?  And why didn’t the jury say they thought it was a hoax?  The jury said they didn’t believe <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steven%20Pagones">Pagones</ref> should have been labeled, the same jury that hit us with defamation.  That jury said there was no conspiracy to lie, which is why they only awarded him $65,000 from me.  If they thought it was a hoax, I would have been indicted for conspiracy and I would have been charged with a whole lot more money.  In many ways, I learn to just sit back and laugh, because if you have to go back to 1987 in 2007, that means I have a pretty good record.</p>
<hi rend="bold">I disagreed with the grand jury on Brawley. I believed there was enough evidence to go to trial. Grand jury said there wasn’t. Okay, fine. Do I have a right to disagree with the grand jury? Many Americans believe <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/O.%20J.%20Simpson%20murder%20case">O.J. Simpson</ref> was guilty. A jury said he wasn’t. So I have as much right to question a jury as they do.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right"><hi rend="bold">—Al Sharpton on Tawana Brawley.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How would 2007 Al Sharpton have handled the Tawana Brawley case differently than 1987 Al Sharpton?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  I probably wouldn’t have made it as personal in terms of personal attacks on the Attorney General, but I would still have fought the case.  I would have done the same case, I would have stood up the same way, and I do it the same way now.  When we are approached—phone rings every day here with cases—we are not the investigator.  We are there to make sure there is a fair investigation.  And I would have done the same thing then I do now.  Not long ago a writer said to me, “How can you believe a girl is apprehended by four white men with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nigger">N-word</ref> written on her and all of that?”  I told him, “Let me tell you a story I heard that sounds even worse.  I heard of a guy who was grabbed and brought to a police station and they stuck a pole up his behind, and no cop would stop them and turn them in.”  He said, “That’s ludicrous!”  And I said, “That’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abner%20Louima">Abner Louima</ref>, and it happened!”  I fought that case, and those cops went to jail.  So in my world, who decides what the most bizarre story in the world is?  We hear these every day!  He says, “I never thought about it like that.”  Megan Williams right <hi rend="italic">now</hi> is Tawana Brawley.  What are we talking about?  I’ll give you another example.  Five young black kids were arrested and charged for raping a white female in Central Park.  I defended them.  Thirteen years later we find out that they did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> do it.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA">DNA</ref> cleared them.  One of them works for us now.  So how do you know?  Only by continuing to fight for what you believe in.</p>
</text>
