<text id="autogum_interview_doc1316" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Darcy Richardson, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-11-24" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Darcy_Richardson%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>An architect-turned-enabler of this never-ending economic crisis, Summers later supported the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commodity%20Futures%20Modernization%20Act%20of%202000">Commodity Futures Modernization Act</ref> that, unbelievably as it might seem, mandated that financial derivatives — including the reckless credit default swaps at the heart of the financial crisis — could be traded between financial institutions without any government oversight whatsoever.</p>
<p>It’s little wonder that <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rolling%20Stone">Rolling Stone</ref></hi> writer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20Greider">William Greider</ref>, in a marvelously detailed article in late 2008, pointed out that Obama’s choice of Summers and other key economic advisers, including Treasury Secretary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timothy%20Geithner">Timothy Geithner</ref>, seemed designed to sustain the failed economic policies of the Bush presidency — an administration that never saw the financial crisis coming in the first place.</p>
<p>The Summers appointment told me that the President had no earthly clue how this devastating financial crisis happened or how to reverse it.</p>
<p>Things only got worse after that.  President Obama failed to resurrect the Glass-Steagall Act of 1933.  He failed to include a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public%20health%20insurance%20option">public option in health care</ref>.  He failed to assert his constitutional responsibility during the recent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20debt-ceiling%20crisis">debt limit crisis</ref>.  Unbelievably, he's failed to protect <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social%20Security%20(United%20States)">Social Security</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medicare%20(United%20States)">Medicare</ref>.  He extended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bush%20tax%20cuts">Bush tax cuts</ref> for the wealthy.  He failed to push for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emissions%20trading">cap-and-trade</ref>.  And he failed to close <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Guantanamo_Bay_detention_camp">Gitmo</ref>.  I could go on, but I think you get the point.  If anybody deserves a serious intraparty challenge, it's the current occupant of the White House.</p>
<p>In retrospect, it's really incredible that a Democrat of national stature and credibility hasn't entered this race — at least as of now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you believe Obama has done any good things as president?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Richardson</hi>: Nothing I could write a book about, unless it's a work of fiction.  He's generally been disappointing, allowing the GOP to frame the debate on issue after issue.  Who in their right mind wants the Republicans to dictate fiscal or economic policy in this country?  The folks in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Occupy%20Wall%20Street">Occupy Wall Street</ref> movement have already figured that out.  It's just a matter of the rest of the country coming to the same conclusion...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What necessary freedoms are currently lacking in American society?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Richardson</hi>: Since the beginning of the Bush Administration, most of our personal freedoms have been under constant attack — including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/freedom%20of%20assembly">freedom of assembly</ref>, as many in the Occupy movement can sadly testify.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you disagree with any parts of the current <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Constitution">U.S. Constitution</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Richardson</hi>: Not really, but I'm not particularly crazy about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second%20Amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution">second amendment</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are some of your policy proposals, and if elected, how would you implement these?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Richardson</hi>: First and foremost, I'm advocating a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/capital%20levy">capital levy</ref> on wealth, not unlike the proposal currently being debated in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref> and other European countries.  Much of our current $15 trillion national debt should be recouped from the rich — the pampered and privileged class that hasn't paid its fair share in recent years.</p>
</text>
