<text id="autogum_interview_doc051" title="part3_Wikinews interviews three figures from Donald Trump&amp;apos;s political past" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-03-12" dateModified="2016-05-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_three_figures_from_Donald_Trump%27s_political_past" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why were you specifically selected to co-write <hi rend="italic">The America We Deserve</hi>?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Dave Shiflett</hi>: Got the job through the White House Writer's Group. I don't know if this organization still exists. [As of March 12, 2016, the group has a functioning website at www.whwg.com]</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What was it like to work with Donald Trump?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Shiflett</hi>: Trump was a lot of fun. Didn't seem to take himself too seriously. He was most passionate about his fear of a terrorist attack on New York, which he talks about in the book.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How much input did Roger Stone have in the content of <hi rend="italic">The America We Deserve</hi>?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Shiflett</hi>: I wrote the book without any input from Stone.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Was there any indication that Trump was not serious about the campaign or did not want to run?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Shiflett</hi>: I was under the impression that he was on a lark. As I recall he ended his pursuit of the White House fairly soon after the book came out.</item></list></p>
<head id="Russ_Verney">Russ Verney</head>
<figure><caption>Verney in 2008.Image: Bob Barr.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reached out early this month to Russ Verney, who served as chairman of the Reform Party during Trump's exploratory bid for the party's presidential nomination in 2000.  Verney previously worked on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ross%20Perot%20presidential%20campaign,%201992">1992 presidential campaign</ref> of Ross Perot and became chairman of the Reform Party upon its founding by Perot in 1995.  When Perot ran as the party's presidential nominee in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%201996">1996</ref>, he named Verney as campaign director.  Later, Verney headed the Perot faction of the party when a schism between Perot's supporters and the supporters of Minnesota governor Jesse Ventura threatened to split the party.  With Trump potentially running as a member of the Ventura faction, Verney was initially dismissive of a Trump candidacy.  In a July 1999 interview with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20Daily%20News">New York Daily News</ref></hi>, he said party members were not drafting Trump for president and "never spent one second thinking about him."  Later in the year, Verney commented he had not heard a "compelling reason [...] for [Trump] to seek the presidency." After Trump invited members of the Reform Party, including Verney, to his compound outside <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mar-a-Lago">Mar-a-Lago</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palm%20Beach,%20Florida">Palm Beach</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Florida">Florida</ref> in January 2000, Verney praised Trump, expressing "[t]his is him reaching out to all parts of the Reform Party, and that's good."  However, Trump continued attacks on Pat Buchanan, focusing largely on the support Buchanan garnered from former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ku_Klux_Klan">Ku Klux Klan</ref> leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Duke">David Duke</ref>. These comments received greater attention in 2016 when Trump himself received an endorsement from Duke and the Ku Klux Klan. Trump's seeming inability to disavow the support in an interview with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CNN">CNN</ref> (despite an earlier disavowal) formed part of the basis of the March 2016 speech in which Mitt Romney urged Republicans not to vote for Trump.  After Trump dropped out of the 2000 race, ceasing his attacks on Buchanan, Buchanan received 0.42% of the general election vote, far below Perot's 1996 showing of 8.40%. After the 2000 election, Verney left the party  and began working as a regional director and national adviser for the conservative foundation <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judicial%20Watch">Judicial Watch</ref>. In 2008, he worked as campaign manager for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Barr%20presidential%20campaign,%202008">presidential run</ref> of Libertarian Party nominee <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bob_Barr">Bob Barr</ref>.  Recently, he was hired as executive director for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Project%20Veritas">Project Veritas</ref>, a conservative group known for investigative film journalism. Verney answers questions about his meetings with Trump, responds to the accusation that Trump's 2000 exploratory committee was a "dirty trick" to hurt the Reform Party, and analyzes Trump's rise in the 2016 campaign.</p>
</text>
