<text id="autogum_interview_doc1414" title="part8_John Vanderslice plays New York City: Wikinews interview" shortTile="partjohn-vanderslice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-27" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Vanderslice_plays_New_York_City%3A_Wikinews_interview" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Often people assume an artist makes an achievement, say wins a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony%20award">Tony</ref> or a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grammy%20award">Grammy</ref> or even a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cable%20Ace%20Award">Cable Ace Award</ref> and people think the artist must feel this lasting sense of accomplishment, but it doesn't typically happen that way, does it?  Often there is some time of elation and satisfaction, but almost immediately the artist is being asked, "Okay, what's the next thing?  What's next?" and there is an internal pressure to move beyond that achievement and not focus on it.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  Oh yeah, exactly.  There's a moment of relief when a mastered record gets back, and then I swear to you that ten minutes after that point I feel there are bigger fish to fry.  I grew up listening to classical music, and there is something inside of me that says, Okay, I've made six records.  Whoop-dee-doo.  I grew up listening to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gustav%20Mahler">Gustav Mahler</ref>, and I will never, ever approach what he did.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you try?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  I love Mahler, but no, his music is too expansive and intellectual, and it's realized harmonically and compositionally in a way that is five languages beyond me.  And that's okay.  I'm very happy to do what I do.  How can anyone be so jazzed about making a record when you are up against, shit, five thousand records a week—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  —but a lot of it's crap—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  —a lot of it's crap, but a lot of it is really, really good and doesn't get the attention it deserves.  A lot of it is very good.  I'm shocked at some of the stuff I hear.  I listen to a lot of music and I am mailed a lot of CDs, and I'm on the web all the time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I've done a lot of photography for Wikipedia and the genesis of it was an attempt to pin down reality, to try to understand a world that I felt had fallen out of my grasp of understanding, because I felt I had no sense of what this world was about anymore.  For that, my work is very encyclopedic, and it fit well with Wikipedia.  What was the reason you began investing time and effort into photography?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  It came from trying to making sense of touring.  Touring is incredibly fast and there is so much compressed imagery that comes to you, whether it is the window in the van, or like now, when we are whisking through the Northeast in seven days.  Let me tell you, I see a lot of really close people in those seven days.  We move a lot, and there is a lot of input coming in.  The shows are tremendous and, it is emotionally so overwhelming that you can not log it.  You can not keep a file of it.  It's almost like if I take photos while I am doing this, it slows it down or stops it momentarily and orders it.  It has made touring less of a blur; concretizes these times.  I go back and develop the film, and when I look at the tour I remember things in a very different way.  It coalesces.  Let's say I take on fucking photo in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Athens,%20Georgia">Athens, Georgia</ref>.  That's really intense.  And I tend to take a photo of someone I like, or photos of people I really admire and like.</p>
</text>
