<text id="autogum_interview_doc1271" title="part4_Two-time Eurovision entrant Edsilia Rombley discusses music, love, and her contrasting Contest experiences" shortTile="parttwotime-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-03" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Two-time_Eurovision_entrant_Edsilia_Rombley_discusses_music%2C_love%2C_and_her_contrasting_Contest_experiences" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">ER</hi>: Of course I went in with a positive, winning attitude, so needless to say I was disappointed. For me everything felt perfect, the song, the team I was surrounded by, it all came together perfectly. The reactions in the Netherlands were very positive, so I had that to take with me from the experience. It's the way things go sometimes, I don't dwell on it too much. </p>
<p>I can't really compare the two songs, there was so much time between them, the music industry has changed, as well as the Eurovision. What was different is that at the time of "Hemel en aarde" every country sang in their own language, which was one of the unique things [about] Eurovision.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In the past decade, public interest in Eurovision has dwindled a great deal in the Netherlands, leading a trend that has followed in countries like France and Germany (all three share a common trait in that they haven't won the Contest in decades). Do you feel that's a big reason interest has tapered off, or are there other problems you see that have Dutch people tuning out? Is there anything <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nederlandse%20Omroep%20Stichting">NOS</ref> can do to get Dutch people watching the Contest again, especially in a television landscape populated by reality fare?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">ER</hi>: As I pointed out before, every country sang in their own language before, which was one of the things that separated the Eurovision from other talent shows. With an overflow of talent shows nowadays, the diversity is gone, and you feel the pressure to sing in English more and more. Furthermore, if a professional jury had the upper hand in selecting winners, I believe that would make a big difference as well.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Many fans on esctoday.com have expressed a negative opinion of this year's entrant, De Toppers, saying that their music is out of touch with today's styles. What are your feelings about De Toppers, and do you think they have a good chance of advancing from the semi-finals?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">ER</hi>: De Toppers are very successful in the Netherlands, so from that point of view they have a chance. Whether or not their national success will help them advance at Eurovision, only time can tell.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Do you ever see yourself returning to the Eurovision stage as the representative from the Netherlands?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">ER</hi>: No. As I said, the experiences were great, and the first time I entered was the start of a future in music for me, for that I am very grateful. I have learned never to say never again though, but from where I stand right now, I would not participate again.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Will you be a part of the Dutch delegation going to Moscow this year? </hi></p>
</text>
