<text id="autogum_interview_doc305" title="part11_Shimon Peres discusses the future of Israel" shortTile="partshimon-peres" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-06" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shimon_Peres_discusses_the_future_of_Israel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: You earlier spoke about modernity and the importance of science and how a lot of the terrorists are very scared of modernity and how it will affect their traditions yet one of Israel’s greatest supporters are the evangelicals in America, who are often seen in America as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creation-evolution_controversy#Disputes_relating_to_science">fighters of science</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Biblical%20law%20in%20Christianity">modernity</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Look, I am not going here to make a license office.  [<hi rend="italic">Chuckles</hi>]  I can judge on the general trend but I am not going to make any one remark.  You know, one of the candidates is now <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitt%20Romney">Romney</ref>, who is a Mormon--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Mitt Romney</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Yes, the Mormons too are becoming modern, and the evangelists they participate in all modernity.  They are not terrorists.  I mean, if you have an idea, you have an idea.  The problem begins when you want to shoot when you have a different idea, to kill the future.  You cannot kill it.  Nobody can kill the future.  Nobody can stop it.  The terrorists will discover that they cannot live on their traditions.  They will lose because they are not sustainable.  Take a simple, single item: the attitude towards women.  If they will not give equal rights to women, they will always be inferior because a nation that doesn’t give equality to women is half a nation.  So by definition they are half of modern nations.  You lose a lot.  It’s not that you lose the women; you lose also the children because if the woman is uneducated, she cannot help the children to be educated.  She doesn’t have to make a balance between the number of the children and the state of income of the family.  This contradiction will grow and grow and grow and grow.  It will take time, I don’t know, it will take 5 years or ten years or fifteen years…  But it is so clear that they cannot make a living by killing others or by hanging on tradition.</p>
<head id="Peres_on_his_Presidency_and_learning_from_the_future,_not_the_past">Peres on his Presidency and learning from the future, not the past</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: What do you hope to achieve with your presidency?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: In the long term I would like to help our people to live on two foundations: on the heritage of our spirit and our talent at modernity.  That we should be as old spiritually as the Ten Commandments, and as new economically as the latest model of the Internet.  It’s an educational process.  Here the proportion between authority and freedom is in favor of freedom.  Being free is the greatest, the best administration in life. Administrations are still becoming old, they are becoming bureaucracies.  They represent a world that is disappearing.  The modern economy is based on global companies that don’t have armies, don’t have police; that don’t have laws.  They are based on good will, on inventions. So I don’t see any contradictions.  Since we shall always remain a small land and a small people, we have all time to see how to reach the size that is necessary to exist, to defend ourselves, to offer a future to our children.</p>
</text>
