<text id="autogum_interview_doc193" title="part2_Andrea Muizelaar on fashion, anorexia, and life after &amp;apos;Top Model&amp;apos;" shortTile="partandrea-muizelaar" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Andrea_Muizelaar_on_fashion%2C_anorexia%2C_and_life_after_%27Top_Model%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Yes, definitely, look at CNTM 1 - there was a drinker, a nerd (me), a bitch, etc.</p>
<head id="Experience_on_Canada's_Next_Top_Model">Experience on <hi rend="italic">Canada's Next Top Model</hi></head>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> This question was asked by Steff Groulx, who was on Canada's Next Top Model, Cycle 2. "Do you think the experience you had on the show was what you thought it would be?"</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Yes, the show was as hard as I thought it would be and I can accept that.  It is the "behind the scenes" that went on and is still going on that made me make the decision of "quitting" easier.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> In the third episode, the photographer who was the guest judge that week made a comment that he wanted to take you "to get something to eat," and then criticized fellow contestant Natalie for being "a bit big" for modeling. Did you feel you had the worst criticism, or do you think it was evenly spread out among all the girls?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> It was evenly spread out.  The criticism affected me as much as the others, but because I had a severe eating disorder at this time, I was very afraid of being exploited because of it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Right, you had some big concerns. Ylenia also had self-image concerns while on the show, but we don't know of her full story. Do you still keep in contact with her, and if so, is she in a better state of mind now?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> I've talked to Ylenia maybe once since CNTM and personally I do not know how she is handling herself.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tricia%20Helfer">Tricia Helfer</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canada's_Next_Top_Model,_Cycle_1#Episode_4:_Topping_It_All_Off">hired a personal trainer</ref> for an episode, and he told you to revise your diet and to gain weight in your backside and in your thighs. Were you afraid to listen to him or did you mentally process his tips but were hesitant anyway?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> I knew out of every guest on the show that he was the most sincere in his advice.  I wanted to do what he said, but I knew that it was just for the show and therefore didn't abide.  I have talked to him recently and shared my story and he is so supportive of the way I look now and my true success story.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> He was also the same guest who memorably destroyed a scale with a sledgehammer. Since Tricia Helfer invited him, do you feel that she was sincere about wanting all the contestants to be healthy? Did she know you had an eating disorder?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Tricia Helfer knows the demands of the industry as she lives them herself.  She was not the producer of the show and did not plan the show, so I assume she is doing as she is told, knowing full well that weight was a big issue amongst all of us. They all knew that I had an eating disorder as I barely ate on that show.  If anyone did not know, they were just plain naive.</p>
</text>
