<text id="autogum_interview_doc959" title="part4_Taliban resurgent in Pakistan on enforcement of Sharia law" shortTile="parttaliban-resurgent" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-03-20" dateModified="2019-01-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Taliban_resurgent_in_Pakistan_on_enforcement_of_Sharia_law" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>So as is becoming clear, Qaeda is having trouble replacing people they loose meaning those that were captured or died. They only trust Arabs, and that also a certain type of Arabs, (not all Arabs are the same, not all Arabic is the same - for example they would never trust a Syrian, in fact Qaeda folks consider Syrian brand of Islam an apostasy - but that is another story). </p>
<p>Whatever remains of the Qaeda, are not in a position to set up training camps, since they are in a survival mode. The Taliban resurgence helps them get a little warm and fuzzy in this survival mode, since they feel a little bit more secure with their partners-in-arms doing some evil stuff, blowing up people and causing mayhem.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes the North-West Frontier Province competent to administer money sent as foreign aid?</hi></p>
<p>This is the central question. Much like California has taken a separate initiative on stem cell research – as an analogy – the NWFP is central to the war on terror, not Pakistan. </p>
<p>The NWFP was central to the fight and aid to the Afghans during the Soviet occupation, not Pakistan. </p>
<p>This small distinction is lost on Washington, and it is the main reason, in my opinion, why so much of the Aid was "lost in transit" was because the Punjabi army officers could not bring themselves to dispense such large sums to an ethnic group which it considers anti-Pakistani. </p>
<p>All the FATA is contiguous to the NWFP.  The Taliban and Al-Qaeda are holed up somewhere either in the FATA, or across the Durand Line in Afghanistan; the Durand Line has never been recognized by the locals as an international boundary. Even today, the Pashtun travel from Peshawar to Kabul by road with out a passport or visa, and it has been like that for eons.</p>
<p>The present governor of the NWFP belongs to the Orakzai tribe (he spells his name Aorakzai) and it is my opinion that that he was picked partly because he belongs to one of the FATA as well as he is a retired General of the Pak Army. </p>
<p>The Frontier Constabulary (FC) is a force which primarily recruits from the FATA. All or most of its forces are from the various tribes. In the eyes of the tribes this is a bona fide force and service with the FC is considered an honorable thing. The US has already allocated some funds for increasing recruitment, but far less than what it would take to counter the Taliban and far less than what the economic need is. The US spends a thousand times more on a battalions sent to monitor activity over there. Plus why endanger the lives of our troops and spread our forces thin when a more effective job can be done by the FC. The FC has over history shown that they will attack and use force against the tribes that create trouble. There have been no instances of insubordination or mutiny.</p>
</text>
