<text id="autogum_interview_doc1344" title="part3_Interview with Anna Mikkola, Finnish Left Alliance candidate for European Parliament" shortTile="partinterview-anna" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-05-28" dateModified="2014-01-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Anna_Mikkola%2C_Finnish_Left_Alliance_candidate_for_European_Parliament" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<hi rend="bold">the Lisbon Treaty most probably will not be the last Treaty in the EU</hi>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Close to zero at this point. However the Lisbon Treaty most probably will not be the last Treaty in the EU. And of course the Irish will still vote on it for a second time. Should the result be a no this time too, the chances would increase. What is not widely being talked of is that were are now in a situation where the EU is doing its best to get into effect a Treaty that was negotiated years ago and is founded on an economic logic that has clearly failed. This does not seem to bother most people.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">But given that this process has taken so long, do you think the will for a new Treaty would be present — especially with the current Treaty having passed most national parliaments by solid majorities only a year ago?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Solid majorities...The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parliament%20of%20Finland">Finnish parliament</ref> started its proceedings with it before a translation was available. Then they ratified without any public discussion. I think there would be will, but it is clearly not appropriate to talk about it, since the Lisbon Treaty is presented as the only option. Besides, tax payers pay the politicians to do their job. With that money one would assume they would not say they don't have the energy for a new Treaty.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What place does the organized left have in a post-Lisbon Europe? Would they have to make an uncomfortable alliance with the anti-European right?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I think such an alliance would be impossible in post-Lisbon EU too. The anti-European right tends to combine their act to anti-immigration as well in many cases, and very aggressively. I think with the current economic crisis there is an increased risk that the political right, even <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/neofascism">neofascism</ref>, could gain as people look for some way to express their frustration.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">So to wrap up, then: what's the best thing the next European Parliament can do, and what's the best thing you could do in the next European Parliament?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I think the best thing would be to recognise different opinions. The Parliament is very keen to restrict other voices and likes to pretend were are all one happy family. That is not politics at all.</p>
<p>What I could do and want to do is to speak and try to fix problems with rights; they have not been properly dealt with in the EU, whether they are workers' rights or for example net users' rights. The fundamental problem with for example the telecoms package is that its staring point is not users' rights, defining them and then going into other stuff. Instead, the starting point is the interests of industry, and the limiting of users via different methods in order to protect certain copyright interpretations. The result then for the user is a collection of random and often illogical "rights". The net is something most politicians seem to be unable to handle as a normal and social part of life for millions and millions of people.</p>
</text>
