<text id="autogum_interview_doc155" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Australian Glider Amanda Carter" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-09-26" dateModified="2017-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Glider_Amanda_Carter" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Perth. And then we stayed in Perth the extra few days.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  2000. Sydney. Two Australia wins for the first time against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref>. In the team's 52–50 win against Canada you scored a lay up with sixteen seconds left in the match.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> I did! That was pretty memorable actually, ‘cause Canada had a press on, and what I did was, I went forward and then went back, and they didn't notice me sitting behind. Except Leisl did in my team,  who was inbounding the ball, and Leisl hurled a big pass to almost half way to me, which I ran on to and had an open lay up. And the Canadians, you could just see the look on their faces as Leisl hurled this big pass, thinking "but we thought we had them all trapped", and then they've looked and seen that I'm already over half way waiting for this pass on an open lay up. Scariest lay up I've ever taken, mind you, because when you know there's no one on you, and this is the lay up that could win the game, it's like: "Don't miss this! Don't miss this!" And I just thought: "Just training" Ping!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  That brings us to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2000%20Summer%20Paralympics">2000 Paralympics</ref>. It says you missed the practice game beforehand because of illness, and half the team had some respiratory infection prior to the game.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You scored twelve points against the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref>, the most that you've ever scored in an international match. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Quite likely, yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  At one point you made four baskets in a row.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> I did!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The team beat Japan, and went into the gold medal game. You missed the previous days' training session due to an elbow injury?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> No, I got the elbow injury during the gold medal game.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  During the match, you were knocked onto your right side, and... </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> The arm got trapped underneath the wheelchair.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Someone just bumped you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tracey%20Fergusson">Tracey Fergusson</ref> from Canada.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You were knocked down and you tore the tendons in your elbow, which required an elbow reconstruction...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yes. And multiple surgeries <hi rend="italic">after</hi> that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You spent eleven weeks on a CPM machine – what's a CPM machine?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> It's a continuous passive movement machine. You know what they use for the footballers after they've had a knee reconstruction? It's a machine that moves their knee up and down so it doesn't stiffen. And they start with just a little bit of movement following the surgery and they're supposed to get up to about 90 degrees before they go home.  There was only one or two elbow machines in the country, so they flew one in from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Queensland">Queensland</ref> for me to use, to try and get my arm moving.</p>
</text>
