<text id="autogum_interview_doc374" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Australian Statistician Brian Pink" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-19" dateModified="2008-04-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Statistician_Brian_Pink" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Now, this means collaborating in some cases, it means undertaking statistical activities in others, it means providing advice - methodological, technological, around standards and conceptual frameworks. It's a very broad range of building capability, as well as undertaking ourselves statistical activity, building capability of all those other players, who are important parts and play an important part in what I call the "total portfolio" of official statistics in Australia.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : And of course that change was made before you became Statistician, and in fact you weren't actually in the Bureau at the time - you rose through the ranks here and then went to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Zealand">New Zealand</ref> for a few years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: That's right, I had six years as the Government Statistician in New Zealand, and interestingly there were parallel processes going on in Australia and New Zealand around the national statistical agency in New Zealand, called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Statistics%20New%20Zealand">Statistics New Zealand</ref>, here the Australian Bureau of Statistics, taking stronger leadership in their statistical worlds, inside their own nations, and so when I came back from New Zealand it was not unfamiliar territory that I was coming back to, and some of the changes that had occurred in the period that I'd been away from the ABS were grappling with and dealing with and developing strategies to take that leadership forward, and we'd done similar things in New Zealand so, from my point of view, it was really positive to come back to help play my role in establishing and reinforcing our leadership of statistics in Australia.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : So the two organisations were taking very similar directions. Have you noticed any major differences between the two?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BP</hi>: There's a number of significant differences. Of course, scale's one. Australia, in geography, in population, is a much bigger place, and that has its benefits and challenges. Probably the biggest difference in my role as Australian Statistician and my previous role as Government Statistician in New Zealand is that we're a federal system in Australia, so we have responsibilities not only to the Australian Government but to the states and territories as well. In New Zealand, of course, you have unilateral government, or unimodal government, so there was only one government and there was only one bureaucracy, and so the complexity in a lot of fields of statistics in Australia is made much more complex by the very nature of our government arrangements, and that's a big difference. I think also that the scale means that in some cases in New Zealand we had to try and meet the expectations of society for the quality in the breadth of the statistical services we provided with less resources and less depth of resources in a lot of areas, so that had its challenges as well, but the biggest difference, I think, really was the nature of the government relationships.</p>
</text>
