<text id="autogum_interview_doc1436" title="part2_OpenSync Interview - syncing on the free desktop" shortTile="partopensync-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-05-19" dateModified="2014-01-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/OpenSync_Interview_-_syncing_on_the_free_desktop" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>Armin:</p>
<p>My reason to get involved (or better to start) OpenSync was my involvement with its predecessor Multisync. I am working as a system administrator for a small consulting company and so I saw some problems when trying to find a synchronization solution for Linux.</p>
<p>At that point I joined the Multisync project to implement some plugins that I thought would be nice to have.  After some time I became the maintainer of the project. But I was unhappy with some technical aspects of the project, especially the tight coupling between the syncing logic and the GUI, its dependencies on GNOME libraries and its lack of flexibility.</p>
<p>Tobias:</p>
<p>Well, I have been a KDE PIM developer for several years now, so there was no way around getting in touch with synchronization and KitchenSync. Although I liked the idea of KitchenSync, I hated the code and the user interface [...]. So when we discussed to switch to OpenSync and reimplementing the user interface, I volunteered immediately.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Can you tell us a bit about your further plans and ideas?</hi></p>
<p>Cornelius:</p>
<p>The next thing will be the 1.0 release of OpenSync. We will release KitchenSync as frontend in parallel.</p>
<p>Armin:</p>
<p>There are of course a lot of things on my todo and my wishlist for opensync. For the near future the most important step is the 1.0 release, of course, where we still have some missing features in OpenSync as well as in the plugins.</p>
<p>One thing I would really like to see is a thunderbird plugin for OpenSync. I use thunderbird personally and would really like to keep my contacts up to date with my cellular, but I was not yet able to find the time to implement it.</p>
<p>Tobias:</p>
<p>One thing that would really rock in future versions of OpenSync is an automatic hardware detection mechanism, so when you plugin your Palm or switch on your bluetooth device, OpenSync will create a synchronization group automatically and ask the user to start syncing. To bring OpenSync to the level of _The Syncing Solution [tm]_ we must reduce the necessary configuration to a minimum.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What was the most dire problem you had to face when creating OpenSync and how did you face it?</hi></p>
<p>Cornelius:</p>
<p>Fortunately the problems which I personally would consider to be dire are solved by the implementation of OpenSync which is well hidden from the outside world and [they are] an area I didn't work on ;-)</p>
<p>Armin:</p>
<p>I guess that I am the right person to answer this question then :)</p>
<p>The most complicated part of OpenSync is definitely the format conversion, which is responsible for converting the format of one device to the format that another device understands.</p>
<p>There are a lot of subsystems in this format conversion that make it so complex, like conversion path searching, comparing items, detection of mime types and last but not least the conversion itself. So this was a hard piece of work.</p>
</text>
