<text id="autogum_interview_doc063" title="part3_Biologist Nick Bos tells Wikinews about &amp;apos;self-medicating&amp;apos; ants" shortTile="partbiologist-nick" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-09-01" dateModified="2015-10-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Biologist_Nick_Bos_tells_Wikinews_about_%27self-medicating%27_ants" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>So as an answer to the question, I would find it unlikely that such a  behaviour would evolve, but it's not known yet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Ants generally avoided the peroxide if they were healthy, but in some circumstances might they try to build resistance against infection in advance?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NB</hi> Who knows? Also not known yet unfortunately. That said, there is a very interesting study about resin collection in ants. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wood%20ants">Wood ants</ref> collect tree-resin, which has anti-microbial properties. They collect this even if not infected, and when you infect them, they don't collect more of the resin than normal. So basically it seems like they  collect it in order to keep diseases out of the nest, so they stop the disease before it can actually infect them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Are there plans to follow this research up? Might you research other species? Other substances? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NB</hi> I first want to find out where they get it from in nature. There might  be many sources of medicine (recent evidence suggests that tobacco  plays a similar role for bumble bees). Dalial Freitak, who is also on this paper is currently running tests with Ph.D. student Siiri Fuchs (who is also on the paper) with other substances to see if any have the same effect as H2O2 [hydrogen peroxide].</p>
<p>Once the behaviour has been well described in this species of ant, I might do a comparison with other species. For example, once we find the source of the medicine in nature... would species without access to this source also have evolved the same behaviour in the lab? And if so... where would they get it from?</p>
<p>Also... can ants medicate their friends?:)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What other research are you working on right now?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NB</hi> Phew...lots!:)</p>
<p>I still have some questions left unanswered from my Ph.D. work related to how ants recognize who is a friend and who isn't. I also started  collaborating with Prof. Michael Poulsen from the University of  Copenhagen on immunity in fungus-growing termites, as well as their  chemical recognition abilities. Furthermore we're working on social parasitism in wood-ants (ants have lots of animals exploiting the nest for shelter and resources, which all somehow have to get in to the fortress without getting killed).</p>
Science and Technology
More articles on Science and Technology
<list type="unordered">
<item>25 October 2019: <ref target="/wiki/Wash_your_hands_or_else_spread_superbug_E._coli,_say_scientists">Wash your hands or else spread superbug E. coli, say scientists</ref></item>
<item>12 October 2019: <ref target="/wiki/Scientists_describe_how_%27upside-down_rivers%27_of_warm_water_break_Antarctica%27s_ice_shelf">Scientists describe how 'upside-down rivers' of warm water break Antarctica's ice shelf</ref></item>
<item>10 October 2019: <ref target="/wiki/Swedish_academy_announces_2019_Nobel_Prize_winners_in_physics">Swedish academy announces 2019 Nobel Prize winners in physics</ref></item>
<item>5 October 2019: <ref target="/wiki/Voracious_fish_defend_coral_reefs_against_warming,_say_scientists">Voracious fish defend coral reefs against warming, say scientists</ref></item>
<item>14 September 2019: <ref target="/wiki/Astronomers_find_water_vapour_in_atmosphere_of_exoplanet_K2-18b">Astronomers find water vapour in atmosphere of exoplanet K2-18b</ref></item></list>
...<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Portal:Science_and_technology">More articles here</ref>
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Portal:Science_and_technology">To write, edit, start or view other articles on topics related to Science and Technology, see the Science and Technology Portal</ref>
</text>
