<text id="autogum_interview_doc1200" title="part12_BDSM as business: An interview with the owners of a dungeon" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_An_interview_with_the_owners_of_a_dungeon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  One of them; one of the less pleasant ones, because there are no windows in it.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  But a lot of times they want a room that has nothing to do with S&amp;M.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  This one seems very plain, there's a few things in the corner over there--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  And behind there, there are clothes...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Contrary to what you may think, once again, they don't want that black, dark leathery--they want to look--they--where'd you grow up?  Where did you grow up?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  All over.  I've lived in 17 cities, six states and three countries.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Wow.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  If you grew up in a neighborhood with a cute--did you grow up in a neighborhood?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yeah, I had many, I had neighborhoods.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Yeah, cute neighbors--cute older women--girls that you saw when you were growing up, you were fourteen or whatever--in your mind, you didn't think, "I'd love her to take me to a basement, and"--I'm not saying you're into this, you don't have to--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But some people would, right?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Most would.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Of course.  But those people wouldn't also have a desire to come here, right?  You're meeting a particular need for a particular segment of the population.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  No question about it.  And we have that room, but which is the most popular room?  The Blue Room [see photo]?  Her and I fight all the time because I want to paint it.  I'd like you to see it before you go.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  We cannot figure out why that room is so popular--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  We can't.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Actually, one person has told me, it's because the [seals?]--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's the blue room, first?  Can you describe it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  It's like if you and your wife were into it, and you lived somewhere where you had enough room to make a room like a bondage room.  It's a nice, moderate color; there's not that much stuff in it.  It looks like we took a living room and threw a bondage table in it, and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St.%20Andrew’s%20Cross%20(BDSM)">cross</ref> in there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Got you. Why is it popular?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  They feel very unthreatened.  Assume you came here for a session, okay?  And assume you have a wife and your three kids at home; you finally take the plunge to come to a place.  You wanna know why we do really, really well, and why we're the leader in this industry?  You come here, and you've been calling us, you've been thinking about it, and you're in your mid-thirties and you finally say, ‘You know something? I'm going.  I'm just--I'm going.’  You call your wife and you go, ‘Listen, I'm gonna be stuck in the law library tonight, studying.’  You come here and your heart's pounding away; you're going to get treated with dignity, with kid gloves.  And you're gonna get treated well.  And you're not going to feel like, wow.</p>
</text>
