<text id="autogum_interview_doc705" title="part1_Canada&amp;apos;s Beaches—East York (Ward 32) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-beacheseast" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-21" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Beaches%E2%80%94East_York_%28Ward_32%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>We lived through the long years of incineration at the sewage treatment plant, and know first-hand what the impacts can be on human health and the host community's environment.  We know the struggles that ensue to make change.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I love my community and my city.  I feel I can make a difference and I have the skills and ability to bring citizens together to make positive change.  My professional experience spans assignments as a legislative researcher at Queen's Park for Members of Provincial Parliament, to elected Public School Trustee and City Councillor. Finding funding partners and convincing City Council to approve projects for our ward is my forte. I bring creative problem-solving skills, combined with a sense of vision, toward the determination of the path we should take --this makes me feel that I am contributing to the improvement of the quality of life in our City.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I want to represent Beaches-East York, Ward 32, because it is the community I was raised in and where I have raised my family. I know the people, I know the streets, and I know the neighbourhoods.  It is an honour to be receiving the confidence and trust of the people in my community to represent their interests.  I have a vision of where we should go as a City and a community, and believe I have the skills to achieve results.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am currently the City Councillor and a Deputy Mayor.  I have achieved many successful projects in the Ward, drawing together the right partnerships to make things happen.  Listening to residents, I learn what people want.  For example, improvements to the Beaches Branch Library were suggested.  I was successful in getting this request put on the priority list for the Library Board with the required funding.  The result is glorious!  Today, the Beaches Library is restored to it past splendour and improved with an attractive and fitting expansion.</p>
<p>Every day as the City Councillor, I am at work for my community, taking care of the calls, correspondence and e-mails from the local constituents.  Bringing together citizens to help set the path on local urban planning matters, designing playgrounds or developing local consensus on traffic planning matters are some of the types of activities that I am involved. At the Council level,  I am engaged in the setting of City policy on matters ranging from the way be pick of  solid waste to decisions related to public transit options and the allocations of city-wide budgets.  I am a Deputy Mayor, T.T.C. Commissioner, Chair of the Mayor's Roundtable on a Beautiful City, Member of the Policy and Finance Committee and Budget Advisory Committee, Secretary of the Board of the Toronto Atmospheric Fund, Member on 3 local Business Improvement Areas, among a number of other responsibilities.</p>
</text>
