<text id="autogum_interview_doc754" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Progressive Conservative candidate Jim Chapman, London-Fanshawe" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-25" dateModified="2007-11-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Progressive_Conservative_candidate_Jim_Chapman%2C_London-Fanshawe" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Progressive Conservative candidate Jim Chapman, London-Fanshawe</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 25, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jim Chapman</hi> is running for the Progressive Conservative of Ontario in the Ontario provincial election, in the London-Fanshawe riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I believe Ontario is at a crossroads. We will elect either a Liberal government pledged to continue a high-tax, high-spend policy that has increased taxes by 33% over four years, or a Progressive Conservative government that believes there is generally more to solving a problem than throwing money at it. I was born and raised in London Fanshawe and when the PC Association invited me to stand for nomination, I accepted and was subsequently acclaimed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>As a member of the local news media for fifteen years I have been a keen observer of the political process and have studied and written extensively on provincial politics. I have known both Dalton McGuinty and John Tory personally for years, and have watched and analysed their development as political leaders. I am an effective communicator and a Type A worker, both attributes I believe to be vital to being a successful representative of the people at Queen's Park.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?</hi></p>
<p>The biggest challenge to any candidate is voter apathy, brought on by years of broken promises and political bafflegab.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>My record of public service and advocacy for ordinary people is well-known across the city. I do my homework, I know the issues and I have the ability to speak for those who can't, or won’t speak for themselves. I am not afraid to speak truth to power, I’m not anybody's yes-man and I get things done... And, I believe the proper job of an M.P.P. is to carry the message of the riding to Queen's Park, not the other way around.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
</text>
