<text id="autogum_interview_doc1236" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Australian blind Paralympic skier Melissa Perrine" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-10" dateModified="2017-10-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_blind_Paralympic_skier_Melissa_Perrine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So you liked Vancouver?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> It was just an amazing experience. I came into Vancouver... I had quite a bad accident on a downhill course in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sestriere">Sestriere</ref> about seven weeks out from the games, and I fractured my pelvis. So, I was coming into Vancouver with an injury and I  had only just recovered and was in quite a lot of pain. So it was an amazing experience and I was quite glad I did it, but wish for a different outcome.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So you are more optimistic about Sochi then?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  One of the things about skiing is that it's really expensive to do. How do you afford to ski given how expensive it is? And the fact that you need a guide who's got his own expenses.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> I'm lucky enough to rank quite high in the world at the moment, so due to my ranking I'm awarded a certain amount of funding from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australian%20Sports%20Commission">Australian Sports Commission</ref>, which covers my equipment and expenses, and the team picks up training costs and travel costs. All I've got to pay for is food and my own equipment, which is good, so I've managed to do it a budget.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What do you do outside of skiing, because you look kind of young? And you being not like, 30 or 40?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> I'm 24. I'm a student still.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Which university?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Western%20Sydney">University of Western Sydney</ref>. It's my third university degree. I've completed two others prior to this one that I'm doing now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Which degree? That you're currently pursuing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> Currently, physiotherapy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Because of your experience with sport?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> Not really, except that my experience with sport certainly helped my interest and kind of fueled a direction to take in the physiotherapy field when I'm finished my degree, but more the medical side of injury, rehabilitation that got me interested in physiotherapy to begin with, burns rehabilitation and things like that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You view yourself a full-time student as opposed to a full-time professional skier.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MP:</hi> Not really. I'm a student when uni's on and when uni's finished I'm a skier. The way that the term structure is in Australia it gives me all this time to ski. The uni starts at the end of February and goes to the beginning of June, and then we've got a six or seven week break until beginning or mid-August, and uni starts again then, and we go up to mid way through November, and then we've got a break again. Skiing fits in very nicely to that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What's the route for qualification to Sochi for you. </p>
</text>
