<text id="autogum_interview_doc1304" title="part1_Wikinews interviews former Salt Lake City mayor and 2012 presidential candidate Rocky Anderson" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-12-17" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Salt_Lake_City_mayor_and_2012_presidential_candidate_Rocky_Anderson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I put in place a comprehensive <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/restorative%20justice">restorative justice</ref> program that became a nationwide model. We were one of three finalists for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20Leadership%20Awards">World Leadership Award</ref> by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20Leadership%20Forum">World Leadership Forum</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref> for our restorative justice program, which focuses on solutions rather than simply punishment and retribution.</p>
<p>I worked to provide real and effective drug prevention and education programs filling the completely ineffective <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drug%20Abuse%20Resistance%20Education">D.A.R.E.</ref> program and getting proven effective programs in our schools and providing much better public education on substance abuse issues. We focused not only on the abuse of illicit drugs but also the abuse of prescription and over-the-counter drugs, which is an enormous problem in Utah and throughout the country.</p>
<p>We fought against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Urban%20sprawl">sprawl</ref> development incorporating principles of smart urban growth development with transit orientation development projects and opposition to sprawl-inducing new highways and increased dependence on the automobile.</p>
<p>I started a city-wide youth afterschool and summer program called YouthCity, and always pursued public policy with the understanding that upfront investments in making things better including opportunities for young people was far better for all in our community and far less expensive than ignoring those upfront needs and having to deal with the disasters down the road. We know that if we keep our young people engaged and teach them skills including social skills, we have a lot better shot of building safer healthier and sustainable communities, and at the same time keeping these young people out of trouble.</p>
<figure><caption>Anderson at the 2007 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salt%20Lake%20City%20Marathon">Salt Lake City Marathon</ref>.Image: Jen Wakefield-Dillier.</caption></figure>
<p>I helped change, well, I led for the change in the culture of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salt%20Lake%20City%20Police%20Department">our police department</ref> where there was much more community-oriented policing where police were held accountable for not only excessive force against our residents and visitors but also even for rude behavior. I instituted a crisis intervention team program where officers were trained in recognizing and dealing with people with mental illnesses. Before I was mayor, I noticed that police were getting in confrontations with people with mental illnesses and escalate situations to the point of, in some cases even shooting and killing mentally ill people. We see that happen in communities all over the country and it’s so important that our police be trained to recognize the root causes of some violent behavior and understand when to back off and resolve the situation without further violence.</p>
<p>Our prosecutor’s office and police department were very supportive of our restorative justice program, which took a solution based approach to a wide variety of situations including public sex, drug abuse, prostitution, dealing with both prostitutes and johns. We had a homeless court, we had a mental illness court so that if homelessness or mental illness was at the root of illegal conduct, we could deal with those issues in a constructive way rather than simply running people through the criminal justice revolving door, which is very expensive and in the end destructive to everybody’s interests.</p>
</text>
