<text id="autogum_interview_doc1146" title="part0_Obesity and the Fat Acceptance Movement: Kira Nerusskaya speaks" shortTile="partobesity-fat-acceptance" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-09" dateModified="2014-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Obesity_and_the_Fat_Acceptance_Movement%3A_Kira_Nerusskaya_speaks" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Obesity and the Fat Acceptance Movement: Kira Nerusskaya speaks</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 10, 2007</hi></p>
<p>Opinions rooted in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Racism">racism</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/sexism">sexism</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/homophobia">homophobia</ref> are commonly unacceptable to express in public or in polite company.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Richards">Michael Richards</ref> shouted down a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African%20American">black</ref> heckler by yelling, "Shut up!" followed by "He's a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/nigger">nigger</ref>!" and gave his already dormant career less of a chance of ever reviving.  When <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isiah%20Washington">Isiah Washington</ref> called a co-star on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grey's%20Anatomy">Grey's Anatomy</ref> a "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Faggot%20(epithet)">fag</ref>," his contract was not renewed. </p>
<p>None of this would have happened to either actor if instead of racist or homophobic terminology they had said, "Shut up, fattie!" or "Fat ass!"  It's not an easy time to be fat in America.  A fat person is seen as weak-willed, as suffering from an addiction to food, as unhealthy and deserving of ridicule.  It goes without saying that people who are overweight are, indeed, people with a full range of emotions and feelings that are as easily hurt as a thin person's.  </p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> met Kira Nerusskaya, a documentary filmmaker, at this year's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tribeca%20Film%20Festival">Tribeca Film Festival</ref>.  Her film <hi rend="italic">The BBW World: Under the FAT!</hi> is in production and post-production.  She is a self-described <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big%20Beautiful%20Woman">Big Beautiful Woman</ref> (BBW) and she hosts the website TheBBWWorld.com; she is also one of the leading voices that has recently emerged for fat acceptance.  In researching her film she has traveled to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris">Paris</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ireland">Ireland</ref> and all over the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> to interview fat women about their obesity and their place in their respective societies.  </p>
<p>Below is an interview with Nerusskaya about the health, issues, public reactions to and sexuality of a BBW.</p>
<head id="Fat_Acceptance">Fat Acceptance</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  What is "BBW"?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kira Nerusskaya:</hi>  It's an acronym to describe large women that began in the late 1960's and early 1970's</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is your website about?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  It was originally put up by my producer, Jonn Nubian.  Jonn and I had a long, on-going conversation over five years.  It was always my dream to do a documentary about this subculture that exists in America.  It's a movement that exists.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is the movement?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  It overlaps in a few areas.  Size acceptance, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fat%20acceptance">fat acceptance</ref>, BBW movement.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What exactly does the movement want?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  For people to accept us at the size we are.  I was fortunate enough to be born on January 15th, Martin Luther King Jr.'s birthday.  He felt nobody should be discriminated against because of the color of their skin, and I extend that to nobody should be discriminated against because of the size of their skin.  We are always looked at as sub-human or second-class citizens because of our size.  Ironically enough, we outnumber everyone else.  Over 60% of the population in America is overweight in some capacity.  So there is more of us, and literally, there is more of us.</p>
</text>
