<text id="autogum_interview_doc152" title="Wikinews interviews Spanish para-alpine skier Úrsula Pueyo" shortTile="wikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-02-23" dateModified="2013-03-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Spanish_para-alpine_skier_%C3%9Arsula_Pueyo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Spanish para-alpine skier Úrsula Pueyo</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 23, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Úrsula Pueyo before the start of today's cancelled slalom eventImage: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Raystorm">Raystorm</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Earlier today, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spanish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Para-alpine_skiing">para-alpine</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LW2%20(classification)">LW2 clasffied</ref> skier <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Úrsula_Pueyo">Úrsula Pueyo</ref> during a delay in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slalom%20skiing">slalom</ref> event at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/IPC_Alpine_World_Championships">IPC Alpine World Championships</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/La_Molina_(ski_resort)">La Molina</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>. Pueyo is the only woman on the Spanish 2013 World Championship team, and was the only female Spanish standing skier at the 2010 Winter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paralympics">Paralympics</ref>. Following the interview, event organizers announced the slalom had been cancelled for the day due to high winds and was rescheduled for tomorrow.</p>
<figure><caption>Úrsula Pueyo interview on cancelled slalom ski day.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Hello, we are with Úrsula Pueyo. Today is the slalom race. What are your sensations for the day? ((es))Spanish language: ‍Hola estamos con Úrsula Pueyo en el día del eslalon. ¿Qué tal son tus sensaciones para el día de hoy?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Úrsula Pueyo</hi>: Well, to be honest, my sensations for today are better than ever. I've been feeling really good while skiing, I am looking forward to competing, and I'm liking the slopes. The only thing is, let's see if the weather will allow it. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Bueno, la verdad es que mis sensaciones hoy son mejor que nunca. Me estoy encontrando muy bien esquiando, tengo muchas ganas y me está gustando la pista. Lo único que a ver, porque a ver si el tiempo lo permite.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Right, because the weather today is giving us a surprise... Let's hope you can compete later. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Sí, porque el clima hoy está deparando una sorpresa un poco... esperemos que se pueda competir después.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Úrsula Pueyo</hi>: Yes. Really, the race started, twelve competitors managed to go out and get times, and I had number 19 and I was left at the gate waiting to go. [Laughs] ((es))Spanish language: ‍Sí. La verdad que ha empezado la carrera, doce dorsales ya han salido así que ya están los tiempos marcados, y yo salía con el dorsal 19 y me he quedado en el portillón esperando. [Risas].</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : How do you see yourself for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2014_Winter_Paralympics">Sochi [Winter Paralympics Games of 2014]</ref>, in this last event before it? ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿Cómo te ves de cara a Sochi, en esta última prueba antes de Sochi?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Úrsula Pueyo</hi>: Well, today's the slalom, and on Tuesday and Wednesday the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giant%20Slalom">giant</ref>, so I hope to get other races in before Sochi [Laughs], but yeah, really looking forward to this one. And whatever comes next, will come. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Bueno, hoy es el eslalon, y el martes y el miércoles tenemos el gigante, y espero poder hacer otras carreras antes de Sochi [Risas], pero sí que es verdad que bueno, con muchas ganas de esta. Y luego lo que venga ya vendrá.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : You're the only woman in the Spanish team. Is that an issue ever for you? Is it different, challenging, being the only woman? Is gender an issue in women's skiing? ((es))Spanish language: ‍Es la única mujer en el equipo español. ¿Es diferente, un desafío, ser la única mujer? ¿Importa el género en el esquí femenino?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Úrsula Pueyo</hi>: Yes, I mean it's not a problem in the Spanish team. Four men and a lone woman. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Sí. Quiero decir, no es problema en el eqiupo español. Cuatro hombres y solamente una mujer.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Do you think the level of the women's skiing is the same level as the men's? ((es))¿Piensa que el nivel del esquí femenino es igual que el masculino?: ‍{{{4}}}</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Úrsula Pueyo</hi>: Yes! The same. Maybe the men have more speed, but the technical level is the same. ((es))Spanish language: ‍¡Sí! El mismo. Puede que los hombres tengan más velocidad, pero técnicamente el nivel es el mismo.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Thank you very much! ((es))Spanish language: ‍¡Muchas gracias!</p>
</text>
