<text id="autogum_interview_doc1080" title="part1_Vanity Fair contributing editor Craig Unger on the Bush family feud, neoconservatives and the Christian right" shortTile="partvanity-fair-contributing" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2015-08-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vanity_Fair_contributing_editor_Craig_Unger_on_the_Bush_family_feud%2C_neoconservatives_and_the_Christian_right" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="On_the_likelihood_of_an_attack_on_Iran_before_the_2008_election">On the likelihood of an attack on Iran before the 2008 election</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim%20Wirth">Tim Wirth</ref> sent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20David%20Mixner"> David Mixner</ref> this <ref target="http://www.lrb.co.uk/v29/n20/holt01_.html">article</ref> by Jim Holt in the London Review of Books, and Mixner sent me a link to it.  It posits that the Bush administration has all along planned on having a permanent military presence in Iraq.  Have you seen it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Craig Unger:</hi>  I skimmed this and I know the thirty trillion dollar figure.  What is astonishing about the neocons if you read them, is how little they mention oil.  You can characterize their plans as strategic dominance in the Middle East for the United States and oil is obviously a part of that.  I don’t know if Holt means it ironically or intentionally, but I think it is oversimplifying to say, “Oh, it’s exactly as they intended.”  Although there are people like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20Michael%20Ledeen"> Michael Ledeen</ref> who say “Let’s turn it into a steaming cauldron”—those are his words.</p>
<figure><caption>According to Unger, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron%20Paul">Ron Paul</ref> is the only Republican candidate who would not attack Iran.  "The neocons are in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rudolph%20Giuliani">Giuliani</ref>’s camp, such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman%20Podhoretz">Norman Podhoretz</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel%20Pipes">Daniel Pipes</ref>."</caption></figure>
<p>I would never say things went exactly as planned.  If you go back to the work of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20David%20Wurmser"> David Wurmser</ref>, for example, they really believed that a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shia">Shia</ref> like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20Chalabi">Chalabi</ref> would take over Iraq and be pro-west and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recognition%20of%20Israel">recognize Israel</ref>.  They talk about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hashemite">Hashemite</ref> among the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shia%20in%20Iraq">Shia in Iraq</ref> rising up and they hoped they would overthrow the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mullah">mullahs</ref> in Iran.  Obviously, that hasn’t happened.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You’ve written that Iran is definitely on the agenda for a military strike by the Americans.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Oh, absolutely.  It’s possible it will occur under Bush, but if not and a Republican wins they will do it.  The neocons are in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rudolph%20Giuliani">Giuliani</ref>’s camp, such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman%20Podhoretz">Norman Podhoretz</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel%20Pipes">Daniel Pipes</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If the neconservatives succeed, two years into the future where will we be?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  The biggest single question is Iran.  If we bomb Iran, they will immediately block the Persian Gulf.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strait%20of%20Hormuz">Strait of Hormuz</ref> is only about thirty miles wide and forty percent of the world’s oil goes through there.  Cruise missiles can easily hit Saudi oil facilities.  Oil will shoot to $200, maybe $300 a barrel.  At the pump it’s hard to calculate, but that would mean at $6 a gallon.  We currently have minesweepers in the Gulf, which suggests we are right there for that possibility.  That’s one of the scary things.  But it unleashes uncontrollable forces.  If you have the Saudis attacked by Iran you have the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20Sunni-Shia%20conflict">Sunni-Shia conflict</ref> erupting throughout the entire region.  There’s an inverse correlation between the price of the dollar and oil, so as oil goes up, the dollar goes down.  The dollar is already weak and would plummet accordingly, which would start a global recession.  There would be a global oil war during a period where we may be approaching peak oil—I know that concept is controversial—but its also at a time when China’s energy needs are going through the roof; their imports are going up as much as forty percent a year.  Their energy consumption is going through the roof, and the same with India.  We used to be the lone huge consumer and it didn’t bother anyone, but now there are real rivals out there.  And in geostrategic terms, we are getting in a weaker and weaker position.  If you look at the costs of the Iraq War, 4,000 Americans dead, hundreds of thousand of Iraq dead, four million refugees, hundreds of billions of dollars spent; but in geostrategic terms we are weaker off, Israel is much weaker, and the only beneficiary has been Iran, whose <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gross%20Domestic%20Product">GDP</ref> has gone through the roof because of the price of oil has gone from $22 to $98.</p>
</text>
