<text id="autogum_interview_doc1376" title="part2_Interview: Drupal founder Dries Buytaert balances community and company interests" shortTile="partinterview-drupal" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-01-28" dateModified="2015-10-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview%3A_Drupal_founder_Dries_Buytaert_balances_community_and_company_interests" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : On the other hand, you have to satisfy your investors, they have invested heavily and they will want something in return. How will you generate revenue from your free software product?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DB</hi>: Our business plan is to create Drupal distributions, similar to what <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red%20Hat">Red Hat</ref> did for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux">Linux</ref>. We'll produce distributions that work on the platforms of the client. A second thing will be support. Say you install Drupal, and something goes wrong: who are you gonna call? We want to make Drupal grow and get bigger by bringing it to organisations who don't possess such expertise. Apart from packages and support, a third thing will be network services; services you offer through a network to automate certain things. An upgrade service, for example: if a certain module has been updated, it could be installed automatically. Your website will be easily upgradable: there is a security update, do you want it yes or no?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Some fear that if you focus on wealthy enterprises, NGOs might be disadvantaged.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DB</hi>: I have two answers to that. Answer one: we're just adding extra values. It's not clear that we're going after the big ones, we're still determining our target audience. But we're making contributions, the others will not be worse off, they'll remain status quo. My second answer is a personal vision: I want to make it easy for people, I want to empower them to use Drupal. I want to make web publishing democratic; this is a strong tendency towards a social goal. People often say that we'll focus more on the bigger ones, but I don't believe in that. We're not sure yet if we'll go after the big enterprises, the NGO's or the bloggers. We've just gathered our capital and we've started hiring people. Lately, I've spent about one-third of my time doing interviews, and we're still interviewing more people. One-third of my time has gone to working with the Drupal community, releasing patches and Drupal 6. And about one-third of my time has gone to product definition, to determine what exactly we will do with Acquia.</p>
<head id="The_future,_near_and_far">The future, near and far</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Speaking about Drupal 6, you had a talk about it this morning. I'm not going to ask you to repeat that presentation, but what are the most important new elements in Drupal 6?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DB</hi>: The most important new features are actually a good example of what we're doing for the common user: Drupal 6 has become a lot simpler to use, we've made a lot of usability improvements. But also for enterprises we've implemented a better caching strategy, a better log-infrastructure, etc. These are just some of the features, there are probably 50 to 60. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenID">OpenID</ref> is also integrated in Drupal 6.</p>
</text>
