<text id="autogum_interview_doc1262" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with NDP candidate Sheila White, Scarborough-Rouge River" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-13" dateModified="2007-10-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_NDP_candidate_Sheila_White%2C_Scarborough-Rouge_River" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with NDP candidate Sheila White, Scarborough-Rouge River</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 13, 2007</hi></p>
<p>Having worked as an aide, advisor, and Executive Assistant to municipal and provincial politicians, <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheila%20White%20(politician)">Sheila White</ref></hi> is running for the Ontario New Democratic Party in the Ontario provincial election, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scarborough—Rouge%20River">Scarborough-Rouge River</ref> riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed her regarding her values, her experience, and her campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I've worked in politics for 22 years, first as the senior aide to former mayor Mel Lastman for 13 years and at Queen's Park for the past nine as a special adviser to NDP Leader Howard Hampton, including three years recently as Executive Assistant to MPP Andrea Horwath.  My father William Andrew (Bill) White was the first person of colour to run for federal office in 1949 in the riding of Spadina.  The party to advance him as a candidate was the CCF, forerunner to Ontario's NDP of today.  The great Tommy Douglas was guest speaker at Dad's nomination meeting and history was made. I'm certain this part of my family's legacy has some bearing on my own interest in, passion and facility for politics.  I genuinely care about service to people, so I have been deeply concerned about the impact on working families of Dalton McGuinty's many broken promises.  I chose Scarborough-Rouge River because it is where I was born, lived, attended school, purchased a home and have lived for 40 years. I ran in Scarborough-Rouge River once before in the November 2005 byelection.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>Aside from doing the work of a politician for 22 years, I have been elected to various boards.  I was President of my community association for years and continue to serve on its executive.  I was credited with rejuvenating the organization. I am President of Community Unity Alliance.  I have helped a long list of stakeholders develop programs that bring about positive solutions.  For example, I brought to Toronto the first medication safety inspection program for seniors and the first employment program geared specifically to non-white university students.  I am highly capable.  That's why so many have encouraged me to pursue a political path.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
</text>
