<text id="autogum_interview_doc763" title="part1_Canada&amp;apos;s Parkdale—High Park (Ward 13) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-parkdalehigh" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Parkdale%E2%80%94High_Park_%28Ward_13%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> As far most proud of, there are multiple to choose from in respect to the total City perspective however, the May 2004 Implementation of pesticide bylaw in which Council decided on an implementation schedule for phasing in full enforcement of the bylaw is a decision that our incumbent councilor voted on behalf of the ward 13 constituents behalf in support of the pesticide ban and one that is of great importance on our ward level as citizen engagement in respect to environmental issues is strong within and listening to and supporting the opinions of the local citizenry is, in my belief, one of the key aspects to promoting further and increased citizen engagement in respect to all issues brought forth for discussion to City Council.</p>
<p>As far as least proud of, in respect to the views of our wards constituents, the Council decisions based in respect to financing, in September 2004 in respect to election financing and further tied in to such, in July 2006 in respect to compensation for elected officials.  In July, Council approved a pay increase for members of the Council who will be elected in November, taking effect January 1, 2007 thereby increasing Councillors' current salary of about $87,000 annually to $95,000, a decision that while deemed to be reflective of bring the salaries in line with the average of large Ontario municipalities is not one that I see as being a desirable decision.  Locally within ward 13 our incumbent councillor voted against the ward's constituents in 2004 in respect to a vote taken to restrict election donors to individuals, banning corporations and trade unions from making campaign donations.  My views remain that citizen engagement is of paramount importance within our City and that the wishes of said citizenry should be reflected through individual Council member votes and the collective Council decision/outcome of such.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> If you were elected as a "rookie" councillor, what would you bring to the table beyond the incumbent?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I will bring new age thinking.</p>
<p>I will be productive and resourceful in developing new programs and not flogging dead horses.</p>
<p>I will not be willing to sit in unproductive community partnerships with groups seeking to develop the ward but instead would ask groups to each develop one solid idea for which I would work with them to lobby for full council implementation of such within ward 13.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Toronto, being the largest City in Canada, has the potential to become a world class leader in engaging our diversity thereby prompting our City into becoming the best led, run and operated City in the world.</p>
</text>
