<text id="autogum_interview_doc925" title="part0_An interview with gossip columnist Michael Musto on the art of celebrity journalism" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-05" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_gossip_columnist_Michael_Musto_on_the_art_of_celebrity_journalism" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>An interview with gossip columnist Michael Musto on the art of celebrity journalism</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, October 7, 2007</hi></p>
<p>There are two things one can expect on a trip to see <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Musto">Michael Musto</ref> at the offices of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Village%20Voice">Village Voice</ref></hi>: a 20-minute round-trip wait for the elevator and rapid fire answers from one of the most recognizable gossip columnists in the United States.  Musto, in addition to his appearances on <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Countdown%20with%20Keith%20Olbermann">Countdown with Keith Olbermann</ref></hi> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E!">E!</ref> network, has been writing his column for the <hi rend="italic">Voice</hi> since 1984.  He has recently compiled the best of them in a book released this year titled, <hi rend="italic">La Dolce Musto: Writings by the World's Most Outrageous Columnist</hi>.  He was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carrie%20Bradshaw">Carrie Bradshaw</ref>, replete with a prodigious use of puns, before <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sex%20in%20the%20City">Sex in the City</ref></hi> was a thought.  His column is a romp through his life, spats and opinions on socio-political issues.  As David Thigpen of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicago%20Tribune">Chicago Tribune</ref></hi> wrote, Musto is "a funny and caustic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/satirist">satirist</ref> who masquerades as a gossip and nightlife columnist."</p>
<p>Musto, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbia%20University">Columbia University</ref> graduate, is a rarity in today's celebrity world: he is accessible.  He often corresponds with his readers and his public functions are a mix of parties, nightclubs, academic lectures, university panels and film premieres.  </p>
<p>He is friendly and frank, and he welcomes people to join him in his world ("I just got a message that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Lucas%20(porn%20star)">Michael Lucas</ref> died!" he says staring wide-eyed at his phone; the message turned out to be false).  <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> spoke with Musto about his life and his relationship to the world of celebrity journalism.  And he did not hold back.</p>
<head id="On_writing_a_gossip_column">On writing a gossip column</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you prefer: gossip columnist, journalist or celebrity reporter?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  I always like the sound of gossip columnist.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have a favorite gossip columnist?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Page%20Six">Page Six</ref></hi> is still my bible; they break a lot of stories and it's very readable.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Was it difficult to write a gossip column after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9/11">September 11</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  The weird thing is, in the middle of all that craziness, I decided to just write my usual column.  I put a couple of references to 9/11 in the column, but basically I just put it out there as a run-down of Fashion Week that week.  There was more than enough coverage of 9/11 and I wanted to make my little statement to the world that we have to keep doing whatever it is we are doing, no matter how trivial it seems.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Was there a reaction to that business-as-usual reporting of the column?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  I got a great reaction.  UPI later did a profile of me because I wrote another column about running around <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington%20D.C.">Washington D.C.</ref>, and they said that I was the one who made it okay to be fun and fabulous again.</p>
</text>
