<text id="autogum_interview_doc336" title="part1_Wikinews interviews DuckDuckGo, Opera, Mozilla, Wikimedia about DoNotTrack feature" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-23" dateModified="2019-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_DuckDuckGo%2C_Opera%2C_Mozilla%2C_Wikimedia_about_DoNotTrack_feature" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">GW</hi>: It depends on the Web browser you are using for specifics, but for each major Web browser there are tools you can install (besides DuckDuckGo extensions) to protect you in various scenarios. Some of those that are available in multiple browsers are Ghostery, DoNotTrackMe, and HTTPS Everywhere. Those help protect you while not really changing your browsing experience. Other tools do more, but do impact your browsing experience, like Tor and NoScript.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What is your opinion of ad block tools such as AdBlockPlus and NoScript that ideally aim to block third-party js?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GW</hi>: I think they are effective at doing what they set out to do, and that is great if you are a consumer who wants that experience. However, they are not for everyone because they do degrade browsing ability, especially NoScript.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you think that DoNotTarget option should exist (if consistendly adhered to)?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GW</hi>: Absolutely. My main problem with the DoNotTrack setting right now is it is misleading. If you use a major Web browser, you have this Do Not Track setting within it, but it really does next to nothing. It is a false sense of security.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What do you see the ideal behaviour of companies when it comes to making a user's profile? Would you like to ideally prohibit such activity entirely using legislative regulations in the long run?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GW</hi>: Yes, I think an analogy to the Do Not Call list is apt. Applying that analogy, if you were on a Do Not Track list then companies shouldn't track you unless you explicitly ask them to, e.g. by logging in and consenting to Terms of Service. That will only happen via legislative means, however.</p>
<head id="Opera">Opera</head>
<figure><caption>Flage Bratsberg, Product Counsel, Opera Software ASA</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> also interviewed Haakon Flage Bratsberg, Product Counsel from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opera%20Software">Opera Software</ref>, the corporation behind Opera web browser.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Have you heard of "Do Not Track" feature support in modern browsers? What do you think about it?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Haakon Flage Bratsberg</hi>: Opera browser for desktop computers has built in support for Do Not Track since version 12, and Opera Software participates in the W3C Tracking Protection Working Group.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Given that not all companies respect this setting, do you feel its name misleading? Do you think it could better be named "Do Not Target" instead? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">HFB</hi>: This is our major concern about the DNT functionality: Users can be given a false sense of security.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you think that all websites should respect DNT users' preferences in the long run?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">HFB</hi>: In general we think websites should comply with web standards, including the current proposal for DNT.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Would you ideally see the respect for DNT users' preferences legally enforced?</p>
</text>
