<text id="autogum_interview_doc614" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Joe Schriner, Independent U.S. presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-04-16" dateModified="2019-08-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Joe_Schriner%2C_Independent_U.S._presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">In some sources it says you are running for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%20Party%20(United%20States)">Green Party</ref> nomination, while in others it says you are running as an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent%20(politics)">Independent</ref>. Let's clear this up, are you running for any particular party's nomination, or as an Independent?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I have primarily run as an independent candidate during these four election cycles.  And I am currently running as an independent candidate now.  However, in 2007 I vied for the presidential nomination with the Green Party.   I didn't get their nomination, yet I continued to run in the 2008 election as an independent candidate.  For campaign 2012, I might vie for the Green Party nomination again, once their Primary process starts.  Or, and this is another possibility, there has been some talk over the years of a “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electoral%20alliance">fusion candidacy</ref>” among Third Parties.  That is, say, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitution%20Party%20(United%20States)">Constitution Party</ref>, the Green Party, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libertarian%20Party%20(United%20States)">Libertarian Party</ref>... would all get behind a single presidential candidate to increase the chances of a Third Party candidate winning.  If this evolves, I would consider vying for that kind of candidacy as well.  Running with a Party increases your chances of getting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ballot%20access">ballot access</ref> exponentially.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How large is your campaign?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> In comparison to the size of most major two Party campaigns, I once told a network news show in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indianapolis,%20Indiana">Indianapolis</ref>, in response to a similar question about our size:  “Think the movie <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoosiers">Hoosiers</ref></hi>.”  This, by the way, played well in Indiana.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Has your campaign received any notable endorsements?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Bill Samuels, president of the organization <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consistent%20life%20ethic">Consistent Life</ref>, has personally endorsed us in several campaigns.  (Consistent Life embodies valuing the sanctity of life at all stages from the “womb to the tomb” and is a network uniting organizations and individuals who support a consistent life ethic.  Their issues revolve around improving a spectrum of issues from poverty, to healthcare, to abortion, to global warming... and anything else that has the potential to end life prematurely.)  “[Schriner] is a Christian who is running as a consistent life ethic candidate.  He is right on all the life issues on which Obama is wrong,” Samuel wrote in 2008…    Then there have been the media endorsements.  Some examples:  “...he (Schriner) seems to make a lot more sense than most politicians I try not to listen to.”  Steve Zender, editor, The Progressor-Times newspaper, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carey,%20Ohio">Carey</ref>.  “Isn't our generation ready to truly make our world better?  The first step?  Vote for Joe!”  Leah Beth Bryson, columnist for The Vision student newspaper, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lambuth%20University">Lambuth University</ref>.  “A lot of what Joe says really would come across as good, common sense to many Americans.  They would gladly have someone like him leading the country...”  --editor David Green, The Observer, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morenci,%20Michigan">Morenci</ref>.  Then there have been all the 'average Joe' endorsements – 'notable' to us – from around the U.S.  The following are a smattering of excerpts from a few of these comments (which came in e-mails and letters):   “Just wanted you to know that I'm really impressed with all the research on a variety of local initiatives Mr. Schriner has done.  I was looking for a candidate I could actually support, and I found one here.”  --Iowa.  “I had been searching for a candidate with a consistent life ethic, a commitment to actively working for peace and justice, and concern for the environment... I will happily support you at the voting booth today.” – Washington.  “I was tired of not voting for someone, but rather against the other main candidate.”  --Ohio  “My conscience will be clear when I leave the voting booth... and I approve of this message.” --Georgia.  And from more short media takes on the campaign…  </p>
</text>
