<text id="autogum_interview_doc1362" title="part0_Teräsbetoni frontman J. Ahola on representing Finland at Eurovision 2008 & more" shortTile="partterasbetoni-frontman" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-26" dateModified="2017-05-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ter%C3%A4sbetoni_frontman_J._Ahola_on_representing_Finland_at_Eurovision_2008_%26_more" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Teräsbetoni frontman J. Ahola on representing Finland at Eurovision 2008 &amp; more</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, April 13, 2008</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teräsbetoni">Teräsbetoni</ref> means "steel-reinforced concrete", and is also the name of a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Finland">Finnish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/heavy%20metal">heavy metal</ref> band formed in 2002. Their music, which centres on an honourable warrior lifestyle or on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/metal%20music">metal</ref> itself, quickly became popular in 2003 on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet">Internet</ref>, resulting in a petition by fans being sent to several record labels demanding a recording deal. In late 2004 the band signed to Warner Music Finland, and the following year debut single <hi rend="italic">Taivas lyö tulta</hi> rose to number one in the Finnish charts, and debut album <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metallitotuus">Metallitotuus</ref></hi> hit number two and went <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/platinum%20(Music%20sales)">platinum</ref>, and has now sold about 47,000 copies.</p>
<p>The band, who sing exclusively in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finnish%20language">Finnish</ref>, have just released their third album, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Myrskyntuoja">Myrskyntuoja</ref></hi>. The lead single on this album is <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missä%20miehet%20ratsastaa">Missä miehet ratsastaa</ref></hi>, which Teräsbetoni decided to enter in the Finnish selections for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%202008">2008 edition</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest">Eurovision Song Contest</ref>, where it was selected to go on to the semi-final in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belgrade">Belgrade</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Serbia">Serbia</ref> as Finland's representative this year. Although Finland has seen limited success in the contest, their only victory was with a comparable group. In 2006 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/hard%20rock">hard rock</ref> band <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lordi">Lordi</ref> - whose monster costumes and pyrotechnic displays are famed - achieved a record 292 points in the final with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hard%20Rock%20Hallelujah">Hard Rock Hallelujah</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>Teräsbetoni's frontman, vocalist and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/bass%20guitar">bass guitarist</ref> Jarkko Ahola's fame extends beyond the band he heads. He also features in Finnish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/symphonic%20power%20metal">symphonic power metal</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cover%20band">cover</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/supergroup">supergroup</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northern%20Kings">Northern Kings</ref>, alongside <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco%20Hietala">Marco Hietala</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nightwish">Nightwish</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarot%20(band)">Tarot</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony%20Kakko">Tony Kakko</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonata%20Arctica">Sonata Arctica</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juha-Pekka%20Leppäluoto">Juha-Pekka Leppäluoto</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charon%20(band)">Charon</ref>. </p>
<p>Wikinews was able to conduct an exclusive interview with Jarkko Ahola to discuss these various achievements. This interview is now published below for the first time.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<head id="On_the_early_days">On the early days</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Desite the fact that you focus on a lifestyle set in historic times, your band's name means "steel-reinforced concrete". Why did you choose that name?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> We got together and had a little conversation about the name of our band. Pretty soon V. Rantanen suggested the name “Teräsbetoni”. We all thought it sounded great and it described our music well in a way that made people think “what the hell is this?…” (And here you have to understand that word “Teräsbetoni” sounds and IS much cooler than “steel-reinforced concrete”.) I guess the name was okay, ‘cause we didn’t have a tendency or need to write songs about historic times, those kind of songs just came out. There are also songs that aren’t set in the past, more into this day or this moment.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How did you come up with the concept for the band?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Mostly it just happened. We all must have had some kind of vision about the music and the looks for sure and we all agreed about the leather and skin. That’s how it all began. We wrote songs we thought were good and metallish. We played them as metal should be played: loud’n’proud. There must have been something special about our music and live performances, ‘cause the fan crowds just kept growing and growing. And while the band evolved, the concept evolved on its own.</p>
</text>
