<text id="autogum_interview_doc1233" title="part1_Interview with Dalbir S. Kathuria, Regional Council candidate for Wards 9 & 10 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-dalbir" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-12" dateModified="2009-07-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Dalbir_S._Kathuria%2C_Regional_Council_candidate_for_Wards_9_%26_10_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Well times change and so does the working, a new member (as a rookie) brings in fresh ideas, newer innovations, as they are more alive to changed circumstances, of the city, which they have seen it grow since their childhood. In fact they are more vocal and concerned to today's changed conditions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The Rose Theatre recently launched. What are your thoughts on this facility? Have you had a chance to tour it yet? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I too agree that so far business has been good with the Rose Theatre as local Brampton residents and residents beyond our borders are taking advantage of the entertainment shows. But still some how I feel the money which have been spend for making this theatre is a huge amount, and if it would be spend for the hospitals, which are yet to get ready, then it would have been really awesome.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The province has strongly encouraged the development of high-density residences near the downtown. Do these buildings fit in with your vision of the downtown? How much say should other levels of government have in urban planning? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Well down town means central area of city. My personal opinion is that the development in down town should be restricted. More residences more taller buildings mean more people. It's a strain on the civic amenity. Environmental problems, lead to less of greenery.  It shall cause of course traffic congestion and parking problems. Govt. should have full control on urban planning, with a future vision for next 25 years of residential, markets, playgrounds, &amp; schools so that these people have adequate civic facility.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How do you feel about Brampton's rate of expansion? Council recently capped the annual amount of new development; do you agree completely with this decision, would you have slowed development even further, or not have imposed a cap at all? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I do agree with the council's decision of capping annual amount. The rate at which Brampton is expanding, will lead to chaos. The golf course take over for residential buildings is an example.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What are your opinions on Brampton's congestion and the level of public transit funding?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Yes the congestion levels are high, and more the people more the cars and private transportation. To bring down this we have to increase the level public transport funding to have more buses to make people reach their destination, quicker, faster and reliable, and on time so that they shall avoid their personal cars.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why should businesses be attracted to locating in Brampton?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Brampton is a fast growing city so far in Toronto. Many new immigrant are settling down here. We have a skilled population so I feel any business would find great success for their future prospects.</p>
</text>
