<text id="autogum_interview_doc1101" title="part1_US Nazi leader talks about Barack Obama, the economy and more" shortTile="partus-nazi-leader" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-11-18" dateModified="2015-01-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Nazi_leader_talks_about_Barack_Obama%2C_the_economy_and_more" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If you were in power, how would you deal with the current financial situation?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Commander Schoep:</hi> We would institute a National Socialist Government. We would cut all foreign aid to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israel</ref>, and other unneeded foreign aid. Institute an America First Policy, pull back our troops from oversea's Zionist organized wars, and put them on America's borders to defend against illegal aliens. Halt the 3rd World invasion that is crippling our economy. We would abolish the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Reserve">Federal Reserve</ref>, and ban foreign influence from all aspects of our economy, and seats of Government.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you feel responses so far, both in the US and internationally, by politicians to the financial crisis were adequate, or could more have been done?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Commander Schoep:</hi> More should be done, see above response. Most American Politicians are afraid to take an America first stand, and bow down to the Israelis instead. U.S. politicians need to throw off the shackles, and stand up for the common man NOW, before it's to late. Only through an America First Policy will we regain prosperity and refuel our economy.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you think the economy will be sorted out in, say, four years time?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Commander Schoep:</hi> No, I think it will worsen. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communist%20Party%20USA">Communist Party</ref> openly endorses and supports the new President, if that is a sign of things to come, look out White America. The Winds of Revolution may already be blowing.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is there need for some international financial co-operation, or could America solve its own financial problems entirely on its own?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Commander Schoep:</hi> This would be an easy fix, bring all of our troops home from Overseas, cut off all Foreign aid (starting with Israel), institute an America First Policy across the boards, abolish the Federal Reserve, and remove all Foreign Nationals from any Govn't or banking institutions. That would be a start, and we should concentrate solely on our own Nation.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">The US currently owes a large amount of debt. How would you go about paying this off and preventing the problem repeating itself?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Commander Schoep:</hi> Answer to this is above in the last question, institute those solutions and revive our economy, then we can pay back our debts.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Oil will eventually run out. That may or may not be short-term, but what is clear is that the prices, although back down from the record highs, are set to rise. Would you commit to using alternative sources of fuel and energy to combat this, or have you another energy policy in mind?</hi></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Commander Schoep:</hi> We must look at alternative energy forms, many valiant efforts are being made, such as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tesla%20Roadster">Tesla</ref> electric sports car (can I get one of those for this endorsement, ha ha kidding), and hybrid cars are a step in the right direction. I would favour taking some of the Federal $$$ slated for Foreign Nations and wars to be redirected at finding alternate and greener energy sources, and earmark other funding for cancer research and programs to heal our own sick people here in the U.S.</item></list></p>
</text>
