<text id="autogum_interview_doc276" title="part2_Eurovision &amp;apos;09 competitor Chiara talks about her current song &amp;quot;What If We&amp;quot; and her past accolades" shortTile="parteurovision--competitor" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-05" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2709_competitor_Chiara_talks_about_her_current_song_%22What_If_We%22_and_her_past_accolades" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> After Eurovision, you made a transformation from an unknown singing hopeful to a true recording artist. Tell us a bit about your transformation, and how you felt during this time. Also, around this time you started to perform in concerts and festivals abroad. What was your best memory from this time, when you were performing abroad and people from outside Malta not only knew who you were, but were interested in your life and music.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chiara</hi>: Everything came like rain in my life, from one thing to the other, and before I knew it I became "Chiara of Malta." I loved it, but I didn't have much time to think about it. It came quickly; I went to a lot of places and sang with many people but I think what I will always remember is the concert I did with my band, where Seal was as well in the same event, in Frankfurt. It was incredible.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In 2005, you entered the Contest again, this time with a song you wrote yourself. What is the meaning behind "Angel," and what kind of story do the lyrics tell about your own life and experiences?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chiara</hi>: "Angel" is a love song and it will always have a special place in my heart. It's about the love you give someone without wanting anything back, and the unlimited support too.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You achieved the best placing for Malta in Eurovision history with your performance in 2005. What did you learn from your experiences in 1998 and, in your mind, how did you improve to become more successful in 2005?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chiara</hi>: I think it's the maturity and the experience. [Through] the years, without knowing, you [gather] so many lessons and behave better and take things a bit more serious and so on.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Surely you've read not only supportive comments, but negative ones as well, particularly concerning your weight. At the same time, however, you have become a role model of sorts for fuller-figured women across Europe, who aren't accustomed to seeing "people like them" at Eurovision. How did you deal with the negativity, both in the context of the Contest and in your personal life, and what message do you hope to give to full-figured women who look to you for inspiration?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chiara</hi>: Well, I have always been "full figured," as you put it. I have spent time in my life trying to become as thin as I could, but I could never make it. Through the years I have learnt to accept myself and love me for what I am and how I look. I feel I have nothing less than others and my advice is to be happy with yourself, and love yourself, because you can never get someone to love you if you yourself don't.</p>
</text>
