<text id="autogum_interview_doc760" title="part3_Interview with Innocent Watat, City Council candidate for Wards 3 &amp; 4 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-innocent" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-21" dateModified="2007-06-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Innocent_Watat%2C_City_Council_candidate_for_Wards_3_%26_4_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I strongly believe that the Brampton's rate of expansion is excessive, out of control and way beyond what is acceptable. I have the feeling that is essentially driven by financial gain and the wellbeing of the population is not placed at the center of this abusive development. No doubt the present council has capped the annual amount of new development although this restriction came a little too late.</p>
<p>Looking 10 to 20 years down the road, the development we've witnessed these last years would be a challenge if we do not anticipate and pro-actively prevent its negative effects.</p>
<p>I am a strong advocate of a slow and controlled development while ensuring the population safety and wellbeing.</p>
<p>The brutal development of the last years is the main culprit of the traffic congestions and the blatant need of the extension of 410 or even the construction of a new highway. The cap set at the moment is welcomed however it is not the solution but part of the solution. We must first and foremost control the development, slow it down if necessary or accelerate it if the conditions are ideals.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What are your opinions on Brampton's congestion and the level of public transit funding?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am shocked and ashamed to see a new development area dealing with traffic congestion. It shows that the present council has not done their homework properly and allowed an excessive development without ensure that there was the proper infrastructure around. Who are now paying the price? Bramptonians... They've never been at the center of the preoccupation of the council and financial interest took the power over the population wellbeing. This must be said and must be condemned.</p>
<p>In the same token, the public transit development has not followed the population growth and the new developments within the city. The present council has not push deep enough to secure and increase the necessary funding that would allow Bramptonians to properly move within the city or outside the city while avoiding long waiting hours, if the bus actually show up.</p>
<p>We must look for an immediate remediation of the issues and intensively work to restore the confidence of the population in terms of congestion, regularity and availability of the public transit. To do that, we must increase the funding level and set it at the level which would provide to Bramptonians what they actually need.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why should businesses be attracted to locating in Brampton?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi>We do have in Brampton an increasingly high number of skilled workforces ready to dynamically commit to work 24/7. Brampton is definitely a paradize for various businesses and there is enough place and land to satisfy their need. As for the urban development of the city, the business attraction should be controlled and bramptonians interests must dictate this policy.</p>
</text>
