<text id="autogum_interview_doc1388" title="part11_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Was there a moment that sticks out in your mind during the campaign with anyone in particular?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Not really.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What about during the debates?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  You could see people change.  Remember when I ran in 2004, and when the debates started in 2003, most of the people on the stage, including <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Kerry">Kerry</ref> and Edwards, were pro-war.  I was the first one—even  before <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Howard%20Dean">Dean</ref>—who came out against it.  Then Dean came out and joined the race later.  I saw them go from, “We got to fight terrorism, we got to go to Iraq,” almost to my position in a matter of four or five months, which I considered questionable.  It also validated why you need public pressure.  I remember I went to the first huge anti-war march in Washington, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A.N.S.W.E.R.">A.N.S.W.E.R.</ref> march.  I was the first Presidential candidate that would go.</p>
<head id="On_Barack_Obama">On Barack Obama</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who are you supporting for President?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  No one yet.  The question is, who is going to support a strong social justice agenda?  When I sit and look at the Democratic debates, with all these hangmen nooses, and all these hate crimes, and they don’t even bring it up, how can I support them when they’re not supporting us?  If I was on that stage it would be on the agenda.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The Post reported back in April that you have a conflict with Obama.  What do you think is behind that story?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  I think it’s trying to get a double shot.  Hurt him with people that like me; hurt me with people that like him.  Say that Sharpton has a problem with him so the Obama people say, “Oh, why is Al messing with Obama?”  The people that are in the debates, where he has to contest with Hillary, “Oh, you have a problem with Al Sharpton.”  I don’t have a problem with Obama.  I talk to Obama, I talk to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hillary_Clinton">Hillary</ref>, I talk to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Edwards">John Edwards</ref>.  I have a problem that <hi rend="italic">none</hi> of them are forcefully raising the social justice agenda.  Why?  That’s what I do.  I’m a social justice leader.  That’s what I do.  And I think if you went to a union leader, he’d say, “I like their issues on this, but what about labor?” and I think if you went to a woman leader, “What about gender divided?”  Why do people expect me <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to be concerned about civil rights?  That’s what I do.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why do you think Obama is not dominating the black vote?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  I don’t know.  I think one, they don’t know him as well.  They are just learning him.  I think he’ll do alright, but I think the strategic mistake his handlers made—I don’t think it was him—is they sold him as beyond race.  The antithesis to the civil rights guys.  The problem with that is the blacks say, “Okay, you aren’t standing up for us, then fine.”  So you can’t come back later and say he’s the black candidate when he said no he’s not.   A lady at <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_New_York_Times">The New York Times</ref></hi> called to do a story and I made her change the whole thing.  She said, “I want to do a story on Obama and the civil rights generation and the conflict.”  I said, “You’ve got a problem.  Obama and I are the same generation.  We are only six years apart.  How do you count generations?”  She said she hadn’t thought about that.  You could do that with Jesse, but Obama is 46 and I’m 53; that’s not a different generation.  Why don’t you talk about that <hi rend="italic">every</hi> generation has had blacks on the inside and blacks on the outside.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward%20Brooke">Ed Brooke</ref> was in the Senate like Obama when King was alive.  Ed Brooke was elected and sitting in the Senate when King was alive, and he was a Republican from Massachusetts.  Then we had <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carol%20Mosley-Braun">Carol Mosley-Braun</ref>, then we had Obama.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron%20Brown%20(U.S.%20politician)">Ron Brown</ref> was chairman of the party when Jesse Jackson was the outsider.  This new thing is that you guys don’t do research.  There’s always been blacks inside the system and blacks outside.  That’s not generational, that’s functional.</p>
</text>
