<text id="autogum_interview_doc690" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Communist Party candidate Stuart Ryan, Ottawa Centre" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-09" dateModified="2007-12-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Communist_Party_candidate_Stuart_Ryan%2C_Ottawa_Centre" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Communist Party candidate Stuart Ryan, Ottawa Centre</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 9, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Stuart Ryan</hi> is running for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communist%20Party%20of%20Ontario">Communist Party</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ontario%20general%20election,%202007">Ontario provincial election</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ottawa%20Centre%20(provincial%20electoral%20district)">Ottawa Centre</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref> interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I have been involved in the political process for over 40 years, in terms of organizing over political issues such as opposing the Wars in Vietnam and now the wars in Iraq and Afghanistan. I see the elections, if that is what you mean as the political process, as a way to express our political views to the electorate so that they can pass judgment and see that the various issues we raise are related in that the capitalist system and the neo-liberal agenda take away the rights of workers, woman, aboriginals and people in general.</p>
<p>I run in Ottawa Centre because I have lived in the riding since 1979 and I know the issues that concern the people who live in the riding. It has a progressive history and is open to socialist ideas.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I have run for office in my Steelworker union in Windsor in the 1970s and in my Autoworker union now. I work for a CUPE union at Carleton University in Ottawa. I think I can bring my organizing skills in the labour movement, the anti-war movement and in the Central American solidarity movement to Queen’s Park and in building a base within Ottawa Centre to fight for a people’s agenda.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>I think the biggest challenge to my candidacy is the feeling that people feel they have to vote NDP in order to win the riding, or to prevent a victory by the Liberal or Conservative party. This is a product of the first-past-the-post-voting system.  I have had many people say that our ideas are good, and that I have been a good campaigner, but because they feel voting for the Communist Party might jeopardise the NDP. I think I would be the most desirable candidate because we have the best policies and that I would work very hard to make sure they are pushed for in the legislature.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
</text>
