<text id="autogum_interview_doc1282" title="part7_Edmund White on writing, incest, life and Larry Kramer" shortTile="partedmund-white" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-08" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edmund_White_on_writing%2C_incest%2C_life_and_Larry_Kramer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  A classical <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freud">Freudian</ref> explanation would be suffocating mother and absent father <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sexual%20orientation">makes somebody gay</ref>.  I actually had both of those elements, but I don’t think that’s a universal formula for creating homosexuals.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dr._Joseph_Merlino_on_sexuality,_insanity,_Freud,_fetishes_and_apathy">interviewed an eminent psychoanalyst named Joseph Merlino</ref> and he said it’s a mixture of things—nature, nurture, both.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  You don’t try to explain <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heterosexuality">heterosexuality</ref> and yet it’s extremely difficult to explain.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How so?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  If you get beyond the simple biological fact that we want men to fuck women so we’ll have babies, that doesn’t explain the psychological dynamics of how men come to regard women as so attractive.  I think the way advertising works in our media and movies I think it would be make more sense if all men are heterosexual and all women are lesbians, because women are held up as being so attractive and so much the focus of sexual desire, that I think that would be more logical.  Especially when I was growing up.  You never saw a naked man except Indians in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cowboys%20and%20indians">cowboy and Indian</ref> movies.  You never saw a bare-chested man.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The courting rituals are similar between gays and straights.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Courtship">courting rituals</ref> are very different, because heterosexual men spend a lot of time courting women before they get them; whereas gay men get them instantly if they are going to get them at all.  The most romantic moment with gay men—this is something <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michel%20Foucault">Michel Foucault</ref> said, it’s not an original thought—he said the most romantic moment for a heterosexual man is the build-up to sex, and for gay men the most romantic moment is when you put your trick in a cab and you go back home alone thinking about it all.  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<head id="On_American_politics">On American politics</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who are you supporting for President?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Nobody.  I guess I’ll vote for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hillary%20Clinton">Clinton</ref>, but very reluctantly.  She’s more experienced and has had a lot of time to think about government and how to deal with Congress.  She’s learned from her own mistakes, and from her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill%20Clinton">husband's</ref> mistakes, too.  I think <hi rend="italic">he</hi> learned from his mistakes.  The way they had such a disaster with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1993%20Clinton%20health%20care%20plan">their health proposals</ref>, or their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don't%20ask,%20don't%20tell">gay proposals for the army</ref>, I think they learned from that and she has benefited from all that.  She was a full partner.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Would we benefit from having Bill Clinton back in the White House?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  He’s charismatic and a wonderful mind.  Since he’s been out of office he’s been involved in a lot of public welfare interests, whether it be international poverty or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/AIDS">AIDS</ref>.  The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2004_Indian_Ocean_Tsunami">Tsunami</ref>.  I would say he’s broadened his interests since he was in office.</p>
</text>
