<text id="autogum_interview_doc404" title="CanadaVOTES: CHP candidate Pastor George D. Campbell running in Dartmouth—Cole Harbour" shortTile="canadavotes-chp-candidate" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2008-09-25" dateModified="2009-03-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_CHP_candidate_Pastor_George_D._Campbell_running_in_Dartmouth%E2%80%94Cole_Harbour" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>CanadaVOTES: CHP candidate Pastor George D. Campbell running in Dartmouth—Cole Harbour</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 26, 2008</hi></p>
<p>On October 14, 2008, Canadians will be heading to the polls for the federal election. <hi rend="bold">Christian Heritage Party candidate Pastor George D. Campbell</hi> is standing for election in <hi rend="bold">the riding of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dartmouth—Cole%20Harbour">Dartmouth—Cole Harbour</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>Wikinews contacted John, to talk about the issues facing Canadians, and what they and their party would do to address them. Wikinews is in the process of contacting every candidate, in every riding across the country, no matter their political stripe. All interviews are conducted over e-mail, and interviews are published unedited, allowing candidates to impart their full message to our readers, uninterrupted.</p>
<p>Michael Savage of the Liberal Party won the riding's first election in 2004, and serves as the Liberal critic for Human Resources Development. (Note that the riding, with different names and boundaries, has existed in some form since 1968. Its current size includes the Dartmouth and Cole Harbour areas of the Halifax Regional Municipality.) Along with Campbell, challengers for the riding include Brad Pye (NDP), Paul Shreenan (Green), and Wanda Webber (Conservative).</p>
<p>For more information, visit the campaign's official website, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#External_links">listed below</ref>.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why are you running for political office, why at the federal level, why this party, and why in this riding?</hi></p>
<p>I am running as a candidate because I see the Moral Fibre of Canada slowly deteriorating through poverty, violence, family breakdowns, education system, justice system, environmental issues as well as the moral issues that government refuse to research and put to the people of Canada once and for all. We certainly need to address our Armed Forces and the role they are to play within the nations and that they are well equipped and provided for in their ongoing duties of peace keeping.</p>
<p>I am running at the federal level because I am more familiar with the way the federal government works and as a past employee on many levels I am familiar with its inner workings. I am running in Dartmouth/Cole Harbour because it is where I live and pastor a church and drive a school bus.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Previous to this campaign, have you been politically involved? How will you apply your previous work/volunteer/life experience to serving your constituents?</hi></p>
<p>I have never been politically involved other than being a member of a political party. I believe that my past 45 years wok experience in many professions and areas of volunteering  has given me much wisdom and insight to the struggles and needs of the majority of hard working Canadians. I can also identify with their everyday needs whether at home, at work or in school.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">As you campaign around your riding, it's likely that some issues are mentioned more often by voters, than other issues. What would you say are the three hottest topics this election, in your riding?</hi></p>
<p>The three top issues that I have encountered are:
<list type="ordered"><item>The economy (high prices of basic needs)</item>
<item>Not having any candidate or M.P. meet personally to talk about issues</item>
<item>Our troops in Afghanistan</item></list></p>
<p>I believe our party's platform completely outlines our attack on the economy and the answers to providing a relief from much of the economic pressures suffered by Canadians. One being the change to the income tax structure.</p>
<p>In reference to a one on one with peoples representatives in Ottawa, periodic mail outs are good by does not answer questions and concerns. As a representative of the people in my riding I would hold a quarterly town hall meeting in various locations in the riding to be available to the people.</p>
<p>In regards to our troops, I believe Canada has long been regarded as a peace keeping nation by the world and we need to return to our profile as first and foremost peace keepers but also be ready to defend those who are persecuted due to racial or ethnic origins and who suffer because of war.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Is there any misconceptions about you, your leader, or your party and platform?</hi></p>
<p>I believe that there are no misconceptions about myself, I am who I declare I am and hold dearly to my personal convictions as I also believe our leader does and, our party and platform.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">There are more ways than ever to get your message out, from the traditional campaign fliers and lawn signs, to new media like websites, Facebook, and YouTube. The tried-and-true routes get the message out to the masses much easier, but digital alternatives are much more measurable in how many are seeing or interacting with your campaign. What seems to be the most effective, from your experience?</hi></p>
<p>From my experience, the best way to get the message out is through word of mouth.</p>
</text>
