<text id="autogum_interview_doc465" title="part2_Caribou plays the Bowery Ballroom" shortTile="partcaribou-plays" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-06" dateModified="2014-03-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Caribou_plays_the_Bowery_Ballroom" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Would you consider your music to be mathematical?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  No, not at all.  It's completely aesthetic almost.  It's about tinkering around with ideas in my head and seeing what kind of sound that actually produces.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have a favorite mathematician or unsolved mathematical problem?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  I'm not that kind of person.  I liked doing mathematics and learning about it, but I was never into mathematical history beyond what I was working on.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's a trait you deplore in other people?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apathy">Apathy</ref> or laziness.  I'm the kind of person who is always doing something and get excited about something, and I find it frustrating when people get good ideas that are interesting and don't make the most of that.  Anything I want to do, I'm all about doing it as much as possible.  Meanness, selfishness, obviously.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What’s a trait you deplore in yourself?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  It’s probably twined with my possessiveness and being too controlling of the things I’m doing, which is probably related to the fact I’m so excited to do things.  That’s the flip side of it, I suppose.  Even more so, my self-centeredness.  I spend all my time making this music, and I’m really proud of it and happy with it, but I kind of feel it is indulging my interests.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You think that might be a negative?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  I do, because there are better things I could be doing in this world.  I don’t know, I could be more helpful to humanity than just sitting in my room making music, but I enjoy doing it so much that I make the decision to do it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That's a challenge for any human of whether or not to pursue something you think is a greater good or indulge yourself.  How do you wrestle with that question?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  I guess like most people I avoid it to a certain degree.  I hopefully strike some kind of compromise, but very heavy on doing what I’m excited about.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Well, we need music in this world and if people are responding to it, you’re giving something to them.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  Yeah, I hope so, or maybe you are just trying to make me feel good.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Maybe.  [Laughs]  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hillary_Clinton">Hillary</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  My gut reaction would be Barack, but I’m not really on top of American politics to endorse either.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gordon_Brown">Gordon Brown</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  He's a funny one to pin down.  I can’t figure him out.  The effect of having him in government is probably going to be pretty close to the effect of having <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tony_Blair">Tony Blair</ref> in government, which is a shame.  I’d like to see someone more old Labour and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialist">Socialist</ref>, I guess.  There's always a hint that he is that, but I don’t think it will be reflected in his policies.</p>
</text>
