<text id="autogum_interview_doc1244" title="part7_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>But it's also just the prose; I just find it beautiful, the simplicity of it.  It's just very beautiful.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In the <hi rend="italic">Vanity Fair</hi> article Teresa said that she had come down to New York to visit you with her kids--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Right, right, yep.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And that you were saying that you want to marry her, how great she is, what a kind person she is…</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Right before Running with Scissors was published, I was thinking about her, and I thought, "She is going to love this book.”  I remember feeling really excited because I thought, "She is going to be blown away."  That period of growing up together was a very pivotal and central aspect to both of our lives, hers and mine, and we shared it together.  And I thought, “Man, when she reads this she is”--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  She's really going to be there with you.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yes.  She's going to be like, "Oh, my God, I can't believe you remembered this.  I had forgotten about that.  Oh, my God--"  I thought, she's gonna be so blown away that I remembered so much and brought it all back; I felt like I was giving her our childhood again.  So when the lawsuit occurred, it took me by absolute surprise.  To find out she was involved in it, I was shocked, and then I was disgusted.  I was just blankly disgusted, because it reeked to me of just greed.  It had, you know--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think that's what it was, the motivation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I've learned never to try to put a word on them.  I don't know what the fuck it was about.  Did I say one thing in there that really hurt her?  I didn't mean to, but obviously, I guess I did, you know?  Was it about the money--did they think they could get a lot of money?  I'll never know the answer to that, and I don't even want to know, now.</p>
<p>It's unfortunate, it's unfortunate, but I'm not at all sorry that I wrote it.  And you know, the suit settled-- it settled in my favor.  I didn't change a word of the memoir, not one word of it.  It's still a memoir, it's marketed as a memoir, they've agreed one hundred percent that it is a memoir.  You know, the only thing I--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They got what they wanted apparently from settling with Sony?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah, right.  There you go, exactly I mean, if it was not about money, and it was about, you know--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Setting the record straight?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah.  Then they didn't do a very good job of showing that.  I'm just really glad that it's over, and I know I'm not vindicated.  A lot of people are still like, how did that resolve?  I feel vindicated, because of the way that it settled.  They couldn't have done anything else.  They never could have won.  We had such an incredibly strong case.  I mean, the lawyers worked like hell and got witnesses, and I had my journals--I mean, it's--there were a lot of other people around back then, you know?</p>
</text>
