<text id="autogum_interview_doc837" title="part7_ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush" shortTile="partaclu-president" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-30" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion%2C_drugs%2C_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is it healthy for us to be ringing these alarm bells every time one nuance in the argument gets addressed?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  There’s a difference between predicting something is going to happen that might be an inaccurate prediction and making factual misstatements about what has already happened and what the law is.  There’s a real difference.  So I think the analogy would only be apt if somebody said, “The Supreme Court already <hi rend="italic">has</hi> overturned <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roe%20vs.%20Wade">Roe vs. Wade</ref></hi> and brought back <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Back-alley%20abortion">back-alley abortions</ref>.”  That would be the counterpart to saying, “The Supreme Court <hi rend="italic">has</hi> removed religion from the public schools and the public sphere.”  I have not heard any pro-choice—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But let’s say the Christians give you that, and they say, “This is just the first step and what they ultimately want is not to have the word God said <hi rend="italic">anywhere</hi> in the public square.”</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  But that’s also counter-factual because if they looked at the ACLU’s policy statements and they looked at our briefs, and they looked at our legislative testimony, they would see that we are <hi rend="italic">constantly</hi> defending the rights of people to say God in the public square.  Every day we have cases where we are defending street preachers and people trying to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baptism">baptize</ref> in the rivers…</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Whereas in the abortion argument it is a stated goal to bring about the end of <hi rend="italic">Roe v. Wade</hi>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Yes.  Yes.  But it’s interesting—I think as a responsible advocate you <hi rend="italic">do</hi> have to read between the lines, not only what the Supreme Court says it is doing, but what it actually does, and here you not only have to rely upon those who agree with the result, but those who disagree with the result.  In the so-called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gonzales%20v.%20Carhart">Partial-Birth Abortion Ban Case</ref>, no less an anti-abortion proponent than <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonin%20Scalia">Justice Scalia</ref> joined by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clarence%20Thomas">Justice Thomas</ref>, in his separate opinion, chided the majority for not coming out and explicitly saying that they had overturned not <hi rend="italic">Roe vs. Wade</hi>, but the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stenberg%20v.%20Carhart">prior partial-birth abortion ban case</ref>.  Remember there had been one six years before from Nebraska, and that’s why every lower court to consider this said that based upon that precedent this law is indistinguishable, and that’s why we are striking down this federal law.  The result here got a majority, but there were two separate opinions, one that was written by Kennedy and joined by the new justices; and Scalia and Thomas supported the result.  But they had a separate opinion that said, “You are not being honest, you have effectively overturned that earlier case, why don’t you come out and say so?”  And the campaign finance reform case, same thing.  They said they were not overturning their earlier decision that upheld <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McCain-Feingold">McCain-Feingold</ref>, and Scalia had a very quotable line where he was making the point he made with many earlier decisions, that he supported the result, but <hi rend="italic">he</hi> was saying that they are not being honest about how far-reaching the result is.  This one was quoted a lot in the press; he said, “It is faux judicial restraint, which is really judicial obfuscation.”  So as a responsible analyst and advocate, you have to look behind the lines.  Many are what we now know as landmark decisions, but they didn’t tell us they were landmark decisions, right?  The old Commerce Clause cases.  But when the Supreme Court <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Labor%20Relations%20Board%20v.%20Jones%20&amp;%20Laughlin%20Steel%20Corporation">overturned the narrow view of the Commerce Clause in 1937</ref>, it didn’t say it was making new law.  It paid lip service to the same old tests.  But lo-and-behold, it came out differently.</p>
</text>
