<text id="autogum_interview_doc1347" title="part2_G20 protests: Inside a labour march" shortTile="partg-protests-inside" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-04-03" dateModified="2014-05-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/G20_protests%3A_Inside_a_labour_march" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<figure><caption>The march finds empty streets in the Tower Hamlets Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Killing_Vector">Killing Vector</ref>.</caption></figure><p>The sun has come out, and the spirits of the protesters have remained high. But few people, only occasional faces at windows in the blocks of apartments, are here to see the march and it is in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wapping">Wapping High Street</ref> that I hear my first complaint from the marchers. Peter, a steward, complains that the police have taken the march off its original route and onto back streets where "there's nobody to protest to". I ask how he feels about the possibility of violence, noting the incidents the day before, and he replies that it was "justified aggression". "We don't condone it but people have only got certain limitations."</p>
<hi rend="bold">There's nobody to protest to!</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Peter, march steward</p>
<p>A policeman I ask is very polite but noncommittal about the change in route. "The students are getting the message out", he says, so there's no problem. "Everyone's very well behaved" in his assessment and the atmosphere is "very positive". Another protestor, a sign-carrying university student from Sheffield, half-heartedly returns the compliment: today, she says, "the police have been surprisingly unridiculous."</p>
<figure><caption>Marchers chant labor slogans in Wapping</caption></figure><p>The march pauses just before it enters <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cable%20Street">Cable Street</ref>. Here, in 1936, was the site of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle%20of%20Cable%20Street">Battle of Cable Street</ref>, and the march leader, addressing the protesters through her megaphone, marks the moment. She draws a parallel between the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British%20Union%20of%20Fascists">British Union of Fascists</ref> of the 1930s and the much smaller BNP today, and as the protesters follow the East London street their chant becomes "The BNP tell racist lies/We fight back and organise!"</p>
<figure><caption>Marchers take in lunch in Victoria Park. Speakers from organized labor address the crowd. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Killing_Vector">Killing Vector</ref>.</caption></figure><p>In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victoria%20Park,%20East%20London">Victoria Park</ref> — "The People's Park" as it was sometimes known — the march stops for lunch. The trade unions of East London have organized and paid for a lunch of hamburgers, hot dogs, french fries and tea, and, picnic-style, the marchers enjoy their meals as organized labor veterans give brief speeches about industrial actions from a small raised platform.</p>
<hi rend="bold">A demonstration is always a means to and end.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Neil Cafferky, London organizer of the Youth Fight For Jobs march</p>
<p>During the rally I have the opportunity to speak with Neil Cafferky, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galway">Galway</ref>-born Londoner and the London organizer of the Youth Fight For Jobs march. I ask him first about why, despite being surrounded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red%20flag">red banners</ref> and quotes from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl%20Marx">Karl Marx</ref>, I haven't once heard the word "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communism">communism</ref>" used all day. He explains that, while he considers himself a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marxism">Marxist</ref> and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trotskyism">Trotskyist</ref>, the word communism has negative connotations that would "act as a barrier" to getting people involved: the Socialist Party wants to avoid the discussion of its position on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soviet%20Union">USSR</ref> and disassociate itself from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stalinism">Stalinism</ref>. What the Socialists favor, he says, is "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/democratic%20socialism">democratic</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/planned%20economy">planned production</ref>" with "the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/proletariat">working class</ref>, the youths brought into the heart of decision making."</p>
</text>
