<text id="autogum_interview_doc1368" title="part0_One year on: IFALPA's representative to ICAO, pilot and lawyer on ongoing prosecution of Garuda Indonesia Flight 200 pilot" shortTile="partone-year--ifalpas" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-03-08" dateModified="2014-04-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/One_year_on%3A_IFALPA%27s_representative_to_ICAO%2C_pilot_and_lawyer_on_ongoing_prosecution_of_Garuda_Indonesia_Flight_200_pilot" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>One year on: IFALPA's representative to ICAO, pilot and lawyer on ongoing prosecution of Garuda Indonesia Flight 200 pilot</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 12, 2008</hi></p>
<p>Almost exactly one year ago, on March 7, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garuda%20Indonesia">Garuda Indonesia</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garuda%20Indonesia%20Flight%20200">Flight 200</ref> crashed during landing at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adisucipto%20International%20Airport">Adisucipto International Airport</ref>, near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yogyakarta">Yogyakarta</ref>, after a scheduled domestic <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Indonesia">Indonesian</ref> passenger flight. 21 people - 16 Indonesians and five <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australians</ref> - were killed when the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boeing">Boeing</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boeing%20737">737-400</ref> overshot the runway, crossed a road, struck an embankment and burst into flames in a rice paddy. Overall, the plane had traveled 252m beyond the extreme end of the runway.</p>
<p>The final report, released in October, blamed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pilot%20error">pilot error</ref> for the disaster. The report stated that the aircraft had approached at a speed far exceeding that at which the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/wing%20flaps">wing flaps</ref> could properly operate, and attempted to execute a landing at 408 kph (254 mph), which is 160 kph (100 mph) above the safe speed. It also found that captain Marwoto Komar had ignored fifteen activations of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ground%20Proximity%20Warning%20System">Ground Proximity Warning System</ref> (GPWS) informing Mr Komar that the aircraft was flying at a speed beyond that at which it could safely land, but he failed to abort.</p>
<p>It also commented that he missed one further opportunity for emergency evasive action when the airliner struck the runway and bounced into the air, at which point co-pilot Gagam Rochmana requested a '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/go-around">go-around</ref>' procedure be initiated, but was also ignored. It further criticised Mr Komar for singing during final approach, a direct violation of the Garuda Basic Operations Manual, which calls for activation of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sterile%20Cockpit%20Rule">Sterile Cockpit Rule</ref> at 10,000 feet and below.</p>
<p>Mr Rochmana was also criticised for his failure to take control away from Mr Komar when it became apparent that the aircraft was being operated in an unsafe manner. However, the report did note that Garuda Indonesia had failed to give him any simulator training replicating a situation whereby the co-pilot would take over control duties from the pilot in charge due to unsafe handling of the plane; in fact, training was found to be inadequate for both members of the cockpit crew.</p>
<p>Further criticisms were also leveled at airport and governmental authorities for failures in their respective roles to provide safety features and to enforce regulations.</p>
<p>However, the Indonesian authorities have recently generated intense controversy by deciding to prosecute Mr Komar for his role in the disaster. The move has been pushed for by some, but met with opposition by others.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander%20Downer">Alexander Downer</ref>, Australian foreign minister at the time of the crash, immediately said "...I am very glad that they have reached a point now where they have charged the captain of the aircraft." The unusually high number of Australians amongst the 140 passengers on board was attributable to a visit by Mr Downer. </p>
<p>One of those was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morgan%20Mellish">Morgan Mellish</ref> of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australian%20Financial%20Review">Australian Financial Review</ref></hi>, who died in the crash. His sister, Caroline Mellish, had specifically called for prosecution to be avoided, saying "I think having 21 deaths on your conscience is probably enough. I don't think prosecuting the man is going to make any difference."</p>
</text>
