<text id="autogum_interview_doc1121" title="part6_Murray Hill on the life and versatility of a New York drag king" shortTile="partmurray-hill-life" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Murray_Hill_on_the_life_and_versatility_of_a_New_York_drag_king" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<head id="The_direction_of_New_York_downtown_culture">The direction of New York downtown culture</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why do you think the drag king scene in New York has died down?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  New York is a very different place.  People who do drag have a lot of strong personalities in New York.  There’s a scene, and we all know each other from the scene, but in terms of a group getting together having meetings and a theater company it’s just not part of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Culture%20of%20New%20York%20City">New York culture</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But it used to be?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  Not so much.  I think people are very individual here.  It’s not a group mentality.  It’s more about community building and creating your own community.  Since everything in New York is ‘cool’ here there’s not much of a need to create a community since we are accepted.  Lady Bunny, RuPaul, they are very much who they are and went off on their own.  They were part of the East Village scene—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The Pyramid Club days—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  Yeah, but it wasn’t a group.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where do you think <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Downtown%20Manhattan">downtown Manhattan</ref> culture is going right now?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brooklyn,%20New%20York">Brooklyn</ref>!  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where in Brooklyn?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  There’s a lot of stuff happening in Williamsburg.  There are more queer bars and performance spaces cropping up.  There are more corporate places, too.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clear%20Channel">Clear Channel</ref> just bought a club in Williamsburg.  We are now sitting in a place that still has East Village type performance, and that’s what this wall is about behind me, honoring all the downtown legends.  And now this is closing.  Fez closed, which is where I started, and so did Kiki and Herb.  That place is closed, and now this place is closed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think it’s a permanent change?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  I definitely think that the East Village begin a counter-culture melting pot is definitely over.  Definitely over.  We’re not all in one place anymore but we’re spread out.  Nobody just lives in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East%20Village,%20Manhattan">East Village</ref> anymore; nobody just lives in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Williamsburg,%20Brooklyn">Williamsburg</ref>.  We can’t afford it.  There’s no consolidation.  When I first started in New York—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When was that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  In 1996 I ran for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mayor%20of%20New%20York%20City">Mayor</ref>.  Then you could go to a club every night and the scene would be packed with all kinds of performers like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean%20Johnson">Dean Johnson</ref>, who just passed away.  Mario, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jackie%20Beat">Jackie Beat</ref>, every night!  That’s how I knew everybody, but that’s definitely over.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where did it go?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  It spread out.  It ended and it spread out.  A lot of clubs got raided and a lot of the clubs closed.  Nightlife has really changed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is there not an audience for it anymore?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  There’s always an audience for it!</p>
</text>
