<text id="autogum_interview_doc1419" title="part4_Interview with U.S. Republican Presidential candidate Tom Tancredo" shortTile="partinterview-us" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-25" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_U.S._Republican_Presidential_candidate_Tom_Tancredo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>And the threats!  “You like being Committee Chairman?” Yes I do.  “Do you want to be Chairman tomorrow?”  And that’s how it happens.  I was called into Tom Delay’s office because I was supporting Republican challengers to Republican incumbents.  I had a group called Team America that went out and did that.  He called me and said to me, “You’re jeopardizing your career in this place by doing these things.” And I said, “Tom, out of all the things you can threaten with me that is the least effective because I do not look at this place as a career.”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You have supported proposed constitutional amendments that would ban <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/abortion">abortion</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/same-sex%20marriage">same-sex marriage</ref>. You are also a strong supporter of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second%20Amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution">Second Amendment</ref>. Why do you believe that the U.S. Constitution should regulate medical procedures and personal relationships, but not gun ownership?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  The issue of medical procedures and relationships: I don’t really believe the federal government or any level of government has any business in determining about who I care about, or who anybody cares about, but I do believe they have a legitimate role, and the federal government has a responsibility, because of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reciprocity%20(international%20relations)">reciprocity</ref>.  We are only one federal judge decision away from having gay marriage imposed on all states.  That’s why there is a need for a Constitutional Amendment.  I really believe a family--male, female, rearing children--I believe that is an important structure for the state itself, the way we procreate, which hopefully provides a stable environment for children.  That is important to the state, and that’s why I think it’s legitimate.  The reciprocity clause forces us into thinking about a Constitutional Amendment.  I believe Roe v. Wade should be overturned because I think it’s lousy law, and many liberal jurists think it’s lousy because it read into the Constitution a right to privacy.  I don’t’ see a connection between these things and the 2nd Amendment.  Same-sex marriage and abortion, perhaps, but I don’t see a connection to the Second Amendment question.  I support the 2nd Amendment because it is one of the most important we have.  It’s a right we have to protect a lot of our other rights.  And in our urban centers…and I don’t’ believe as some Second Amendment radicals believe that every single person has that right.  I don’t think so!  If you have committed a felony, or if you are a danger to yourself or someone else, then you shouldn’t be able to obtain a firearm, but law-abiding citizens should because it gives them a sense of security and protection against people who would do you harm.  I don’t believe urban communities are more dangerous because people are allowed to own guns, but because dangerous people have guns.  I would feel more comfortable if in the District of Columbia I could carry a concealed gun.  I have a permit.</p>
</text>
