<text id="autogum_interview_doc1443" title="part2_Interview: Danny O'Brien of the Electronic Frontier Foundation" shortTile="partinterview-danny" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-01-24" dateModified="2012-02-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview%3A_Danny_O%27Brien_of_the_Electronic_Frontier_Foundation" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><p>[Danny O'Brien] Okay, this is where I have to say that I'm a *bit* limited in what I can say. Ah, if only out of blind ignorance in this particular case.</p>
[Wikinews] Do you know if the OpenMG XCP software is mentioned at all in the agreement?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] I don't know about OpenMG: we joined the case representing XCP and SunComm users, so I don't think that was covered. But watch me shine the giant neon IANAL sign above me. If you like, I can ask after the interview, and we can add that to the results.</p>
[ Wikinews] I'd appreciate that.
Can you disclose the terms of the settlement regarding future use of software DRM measures? Have they promised not to alter users machines in the future?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] Again, it's always dangerous to paraphrase legal documents. Ah, we have an FAQ that covers this. Thank goodness: <ref target="http://www.eff.org/IP/DRM/Sony-BMG/settlement_faq.php">http://www.eff.org/IP/DRM/Sony-BMG/settlement_faq.php</ref></p>
[Wikinews] This case also has some connection to copyright infringement: the XCP software included code taken from the VLC media player software, which is released under the GPL. Is EFF involved in any cases regarding this?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] No we didn't cover this. We don't have standing to take on the copyright issue - i.e. we would have to represent a copyright holder.</p>
[Wikinews] Would EFF be involved in such a case if asked?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] It'd be an interesting case, but we try to distribute these cases to where the expertise lies. During the Sony BMG case, we spoke to groups like the FSF and the Software Freedom Law Center.  Generally speaking, they're the people who would be best placed to investigate cases like this.</p>
<p>It's worth saying that we're really pleased that there's now a whole constellation of great organisations that we work with.  FSF, the Berkman Center, Public Knowledge in D.C., the list goes on.</p>
[Wikinews] The Sony BMG case is a content producer attempting to enforce DRM on their clients. The US FCC is trying to do the same thing on the hardware of US citizens with the Broadcast Flag. I know the EFF is involved in the lobbying on this, but I have questions which lead into this. This is a hardware issue. Does it matter on the internet?
<p>[Danny O'Brien] Yes, for a number of reasons.</p>
<p>The point about the broadcast and audio flags is that they set up a kind of ghetto for content. The whole point of both is to *prevent* distribution onto the Internet. But in order to do that, you need to create a hardware world which is fenced off from not just the Net, but from user modification, and open source development.</p>
</text>
