<text id="autogum_interview_doc875" title="part0_Author Amy Scobee recounts abuse as Scientology executive" shortTile="partauthor-amy-scobee" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-11" dateModified="2015-12-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_Amy_Scobee_recounts_abuse_as_Scientology_executive" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Author Amy Scobee recounts abuse as Scientology executive</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 11, 2010</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> interviewed author <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amy%20Scobee">Amy Scobee</ref> about her book <hi rend="italic">Scientology - Abuse at the Top</hi>, and asked her about her experiences working as an executive within the organization. Scobee joined the organization at age 14, and worked at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology">Scientology</ref>'s international management headquarters for several years before leaving in 2005. She served as a Scientology executive in multiple high-ranking positions, working out of the international headquarters of Scientology known as "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gold%20Base">Gold Base</ref>", located in Gilman Hot Springs near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hemet,%20California">Hemet</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref>. </p>
<head id="Background">Background</head>
<figure><caption><hi rend="italic">Scientology - Abuse at the Top</hi> by Amy Scobee Image: <ref target="http://www.scobeepublishing.com/">Amy Scobee</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Scientology was founded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/science%20fiction">science fiction</ref> writer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L.%20Ron%20Hubbard">L. Ron Hubbard</ref> in 1952. Scobee joined Scientology at age 14, and after leaving in 2005 she began to speak out critically about the organization and her views on alleged abuse carried out by management leader <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_Miscavige">David Miscavige</ref> against staff members. </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Scientology - Abuse at the Top</hi> was published in May, and Scobee has subsequently appeared in interviews about her experiences in the Scientology organization – for media including the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St.%20Petersburg%20Times">St. Petersburg Times</ref></hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Florida">Florida</ref> on June 23, and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BBC">BBC</ref> program <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panorama%20(TV%20series)">Panorama</ref></hi> hosted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/investigative%20journalism">investigative journalist</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Sweeney%20(journalist)">John Sweeney</ref>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Secrets%20of%20Scientology">The Secrets of Scientology</ref></hi>, which broadcast on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC%20One">BBC One</ref> on September 28.</p>
<p>Scobee's book is structured chronologically, and she recounts her experiences first joining the Scientology organization, then becoming a staff member in its elite group the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sea%20Org">Sea Org</ref>, and finally rising to serve in multiple different high-ranking roles at the organization's international management headquarters. Periodically throughout her experiences as an executive staff member for Scientology, Scobee was sent to the organization's penal justice system the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rehabilitation%20Project%20Force">Rehabilitation Project Force</ref>" (RPF), for supposed "evil on L. Ron Hubbard" or negative thoughts about the organization. These sentences often occurred after a division of management Scobee had served under experienced downward statistics related to profit margins and financial performance for the organization. In each instance she was sent to the RPF, Scobee was subsequently reinstated to an executive management role, and given supervisory responsibility over other senior Scientology officials. </p>
<p>The author reveals difficult emotional experiences in her book, including an incident where she was <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rape">raped</ref> at age 14 by a Scientology supervisor and subsequently instructed by a "Scientology Ethics Officer" that she was in a "state of treason" and to keep the matter quiet and not report it to the police. Scobee describes difficult experiences she endured as part of her punishment served in Scientology's RPF, including being sent to the RPF at age 16, and subsequently being slapped across the face for refusing to climb into a garbage can and clean it out. </p>
<p>Within Scientology management and the Sea Org, Scobee rose to serve in the Watchdog Committee (WDC) – the highest ecclesiastical body in the organization. After leaving the organization, Scobee was declared a "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suppressive%20Person">Suppressive Person</ref>", and Scientology's <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Intelligence_agency">intelligence agency</ref> the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office%20of%20Special%20Affairs">Office of Special Affairs</ref> attempted to enforce organization regulations preventing her from ever speaking to her family including her mother again. </p>
</text>
