<text id="autogum_interview_doc1139" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Russ Aegard, Thunder Bay-Atikokan" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-24" dateModified="2007-11-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_candidate_Russ_Aegard%2C_Thunder_Bay-Atikokan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>The three most important issues for our riding are the forestry industry, relations between Aboriginal peoples and the government and health care.  All issues are important to me; however, every issue stems from a very important centralizing idea: the environment.  For forestry, I would encourage the development of wood bio-mass electricity, value-added products and local ownership of the forestry industry.  I would encourage the transition for Aboriginal peoples to fulfill their destiny of a right to self-government.</p>
<p>For health, I would lay out our plan that is entirely different than the three major parties stances.  Their solutions usually include the promising of millions and millions of dollars to hire more doctors, more nurses and more drugs.  However, the reason our health care system is burdened right now is due to the poisoning of our environment and lifestyle choices.  We would clean up our air, water and food systems and encourage people to become active again.</p>
<p>We would help working families find more time with their family instead of the constant dredge of working two jobs in order to make ends meet.  Once our society becomes healthier, we will not need the health care system as much.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>Good question.  The environment needs to be fixed up now.  Once we address the problems with our environment, everything else will heal itself.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>In a simple answer, yes.  A tax question always seems to pop up at election time.  Here is an abnormal statement;  I love paying my taxes.  I was born into a life of privilege, being a white, male.  I have had many more opportunities in life than the average Ontarian, and therefore, I have a social responsibility to make sure that ALL Ontarians enjoy a respectable standard of living.  Right now, that is not happening.  The only problem I have is when the government misuse my taxes (pay raises, cricket club donations, etc.)  We live in a society with free health care (although the last two governments are trying their best to privatize our system) and free education.  I do not want to trade that in for anything.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>Be more innovative.  Reform immigration laws that inhibit trained professionals from being able to enter the workplace immediately.  Ensuring that meaningful jobs are created.  Invest in local economies, instead of giving corporate welfare to industries that take our resources and export our money.</p>
</text>
