<text id="autogum_interview_doc920" title="part5_Scientology protest group celebrates founder's birthday worldwide" shortTile="partscientology-protest" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-03-05" dateModified="2019-02-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology_protest_group_celebrates_founder%27s_birthday_worldwide" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Anonymous Member 3</hi>: I honestly can't speak for Anonymous, I can only speak for myself, and I believe that the Church of Scientology's fight against civil liberties in this country is something that has to be protested against. That's why I'm here today.</p>
<p>Reporters also spoke with members of the police:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> How has it been to work with a group like Anonymous?</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Met. Police Officer</hi>: It's been fine, there's been no problems at all.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">London Gallery</hi></p>
<list type="unordered">
<item style="width: 155px;">Anonymous on the left; Scientology on the right, at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tottenham%20Court%20Road">TCR</ref> protest site</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Anonymous signs at the protest</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Yet more signs from Anonymous</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Anonymous protesters</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">More protesters and signs</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Protesters with 'Happy birthday LIAR' balloons and signs</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">The amassed crowd at Tottenham Court Road</item>
<item style="width: 155px;">Anonymous signs near the Dianetics centre</item>
</list>
<head id="Manchester,_England"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Manchester">Manchester</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref></head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Correspondent: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Anonymous101">Anonymous101</ref></hi></p>
<p>The protest started at approximately 11:00 local time with protesters saying that over 100 people have turned up to protest for at least part of the protest. It started at Deansgate, which is the same location as the one for  the start of the February 10 protests. Members of Anonymous have told <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> that their members started arriving at 09:00 local time.</p>
<p>Protesters were holding placards with statements such as “Freedom of religion - A right / Freedom to oppress - A crime.” Placards asking “How do I anger seasoned Amnesty International prize winning journalist, John Sweeney?” were also held as part of the protest. John Sweeney was heavily featured in the UK press after he produced a documentary in which he claimed representatives of the Church of Scientology were constantly following him.</p>
<p>As with the other protests, protesters brought cake, as a result of it being close to the birthday of L. Ron Hubbard, founder of Scientology. </p>
<p>One of the protesters told <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> that “The so-called Church of Scientology's multiple violations of the U.N.'s Universal Declaration on Human Rights have gone unnoticed and unchallenged for far too long.” He continued saying that “the corporation needs to learn that suppression of free speech, institution of forced labour and the more general suppression of its parishioners is both legally and morally wrong. The protests will continue until such a time that major changes are made to the Scientology's organizational structure, or until they meet accusations of wrongdoing head-on and provide evidence that the community's worries are unfounded.” He added that he was “not protesting against the religion of Scientology, but the corporation that delivers it.”
<hi rend="bold">Interview</hi>
This interview was carried out yesterday with two of the Manchester protesters. </p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Why do you consider it important to take part in the protests?</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">Anonymous Member 1</hi>:We consider it important to take part, most of us are regular Internet users who believe in free speech. The CoS [<hi rend="italic">Church of Scientology, ed.</hi>] has on numerous instances suppressed the flow of information regarding any of their criticisms or more esoteric beliefs. Examples include the ARS newsgroup during the 90s, and the recently leaked Tom Cruise video.</p>
</text>
