<text id="autogum_interview_doc1303" title="part0_Wikinews interviews former Salt Lake City mayor and 2012 presidential candidate Rocky Anderson" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-12-17" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Salt_Lake_City_mayor_and_2012_presidential_candidate_Rocky_Anderson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews former Salt Lake City mayor and 2012 presidential candidate Rocky Anderson</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 21, 2011</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Rocky Anderson in 2009Image: Don LaVange.</caption></figure>
<p>Former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salt%20Lake%20City">Salt Lake City</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mayor%20of%20Salt%20Lake%20City">mayor</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Human_rights">human rights</ref> activist <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rocky_Anderson">Rocky Anderson</ref> took some time to discuss his <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2012">2012</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rocky%20Anderson%20presidential%20campaign,%202012">presidential campaign</ref> and the newly-created <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Justice_Party_(United_States)">Justice Party</ref> with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter William S. Saturn.</p>
<p>Anderson served as mayor of Salt Lake City for eight years (2000–2008) as a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic%20Party">Democratic Party</ref>.  During his tenure, he enacted proposals to reduce the city's carbon emissions, reformed its criminal justice system, and positioned it as a leading sanctuary for refugees. After leaving office, Anderson grew critical of the Democratic Party's failure to push for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impeachment%20in%20the%20United%20States">impeachment</ref> against President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref>, and for not reversing policies on torture, taxes, and defense spending. He left the party earlier this year and announced that he would form a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third%20party%20(United%20States)">Third party</ref>.</p>
<p>Anderson officially established the Justice Party last week during a press conference in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington_D.C.">Washington D.C.</ref>. He proclaimed "We the people are powerful enough to end the perverse government-to-the-highest-bidder system sustained by the two dominant parties...We are here today for the sake of justice — social justice, environmental justice and economic justice." The party promotes <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Campaign%20finance%20reform%20in%20the%20United%20States">campaign finance reform</ref> and is attempting to appeal to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Occupy%20Wall%20Street">Occupy Wall Street</ref> movement. It is currently working on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ballot%20access">ballot access</ref> efforts, and will hold a Founding Convention in February 2012 in Salt Lake City.</p>
<p>Among other issues, Anderson discussed climate change, health care, education, and civil liberties. He detailed his successes as mayor of Salt Lake City, stressed the importance of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Executive%20(government)">executive</ref> experience, and expressed his views on President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> and some of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican Party</ref> presidential candidates. He spoke in depth about former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor%20of%20Massachusetts">governor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</ref>, with whom he worked during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2002%20Winter%20Olympics">2002 Winter Olympics</ref>, and fellow Utahan, former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor%20of%20Utah">governor</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Ambassador%20to%20China">U.S. ambassador to China</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jon%20Huntsman,%20Jr.">Jon Huntsman, Jr.</ref>.  </p>
<head id="Background">Background</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Could you list some of your accomplishments as mayor of Salt Lake City?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Rocky Anderson</hi>: I served for eight years and during that time, Salt Lake City became known as the model city for providing leadership on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Climate_change">climate change</ref> solutions. Just before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2002%20Winter%20Olympics">2002 Winter Olympic games</ref>, I declared that we would meet at least the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kyoto%20Protocol">Kyoto Protocol</ref> goals, and we far exceeded those in a very short period of time with 31 percent reductions in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/greenhouse%20gas">greenhouse gas</ref> emissions during the course of three years.</p>
<figure><caption>Downtown Salt Lake City during the 2002 Winter Olympic games.Image: debaird.</caption></figure>
<p>I was a vigorous advocate for mass transit and was able to resurrect a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/light%20rail">light rail</ref> system that was voted down by our city council within days after my election. I was able to turn around the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Politics%20of%20light%20rail%20in%20North%20America">public opposition</ref> and not only received a unanimous vote from the city council but also obtained federal funding.</p>
</text>
