<text id="autogum_interview_doc770" title="part3_Keep your eyes peeled for cosmic debris: Andrew Westphal about Stardust@home" shortTile="partkeep-eyes-peeled" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-05-18" dateModified="2015-10-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Keep_your_eyes_peeled_for_cosmic_debris%3A_Andrew_Westphal_about_Stardust%40home" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Why did NASA decide to take the route of distributed computing? Will they do this again?</hi></p>
<p>I wouldn't say that NASA decided to do this — the idea for Stardust@home originated here at U. C. Berkeley. Part of the idea of course came…</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">If I understand correctly it isn't distributed computing, but distributed eyeballing?</hi></p>
<p>…from the SETI@home people who are just down the hall from us. But as Brian just pointed out. this is not really distributed computing like SETI@home the computers are just platforms for the VM and it is human eyes and brains who are doing the real work which makes it fun (IMHO). </p>
<p>That said… There have been quite a few people who have expressed interested in developing automated algorithms for searching. Just because WE don't know how to write such an algorithm doesn't mean <hi rend="italic">nobody</hi> does. We're delighted at this and are happy to help make it happen </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Isn't there a catch 22 that the data you're going to collect would be a prerequisite to automating the process?</hi></p>
<p>That was the conclusion that we came to early on — that we would need some sort of training set to be able to train an algorithm. Of course you have to train people too, but we're hoping (we'll see!) that people are more flexible in recognizing things that they've never seen before and pointing them out. Our experience is that people who have never seen a track in aerogel can learn to recognize them very quickly, even against a big background of cracks, dust and other sources of confusion... Coming back to the original question — although NASA didn't originate the idea, they are very generously supporting this project. It wouldn't have happened without NASA's financial support (and of course access to the Stardust collector). Did that answer the question? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Will a project like this be done again?</hi></p>
<p>I don't know... There are only a few projects for which this approach makes sense... In fact, I frankly haven't run across another at least in Space Science. But I am totally open to the idea of it. I am not in favor of just doing it as "make-work" — that is just artificially taking this approach when another approach would make more sense. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How did the idea come up to do this kind of project?</hi></p>
<p>Really desperation. When we first thought about this we assumed that we would use some sort of automated image recognition technique. We asked some experts around here in CS and the conclusion was that the problem was somewhere between trivial and impossible, and we wouldn't know until we had some real examples to work with. So we talked with Dan Wertheimer and Dave Anderson (literally down the hall from us) about the idea of a distributed project, and they were quite encouraging. Dave proposed the VM machinery, and Josh Von Korff, a physics grad student, implemented it. (Beautifully, I think. I take no credit!) </p>
</text>
