<text id="autogum_interview_doc1070" title="part2_Vivien Goldman: An interview with the Punk Professor" shortTile="partvivien-goldman" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-30" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vivien_Goldman%3A_An_interview_with_the_Punk_Professor" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Your philosophy is that punk is not just musical, but also an aesthetic.  That it can imbibe anything; that it stands for change and for changing a system.  Let me give you a few names, and you to tell me how you think they are or are not punk.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Britney%20Spears">Britney Spears</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  Oh, no she’s not punk.  Punk is not just about wearing smeary black eyeliner, but some sense of engagement.  That’s it in a nutshell.  She doesn’t have that sense of engagement.  She <hi rend="italic">is</hi> society.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dick%20Cheney">Dick Cheney</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  He is the essence of Babylonian, old structure capitalism, which is about greed and how much one can take for himself.  I could see capitalism that is mutually beneficial, such as ‘I want a bigger customer base,’ but they don't.  Take a place I know well like Jamaica. I don’t know if you have seen that documentary <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Life%20and%20Debt">Life and Debt</ref></hi>, about how the INF squeezed everything out of Jamaica, but that’s a typical thing that happens.  Instead of building these people up and paying them a living wage for their work, where we could sell more <hi rend="italic">to</hi> them, we just want to suck everything out of the place.  Suck the sugar, suck the labor.  And that is not very punk. It’s the opposite of punk.  That’s what Dick Cheney represents to me.  He tries to bring about change, but change that just fattens his pocket.  It's not thinking of the community, and that's what punk is about.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanye%20West">Kanye West</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi> He seems to be a positive force.  In that sense, I would file him slightly under punk.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Osama%20bin%20Laden">Osama bin Laden</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  He thinks he is a punk, but he's too destructive.  If I was sitting in the madrassa in the desert chanting the Koran seven days a week, I'd think, yeah, he's a punk.  But I'm not, so I don't.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is the definition of punk relative, then?  He's a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madrasah">Madrasah</ref> punk but not a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manhattan">Manhattan</ref> punk?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  Having said that, they would loathe punks, so I think we can safely say, <hi rend="italic">not a punk.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pete%20Doherty">Pete Doherty</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  Oh yeah, I think he's a punk.  He's a punk and he engages with the system in terms of how a powerful a presence he's become.  He is the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keith%20Richards">Keith Richards</ref> of his day.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If punk is about change, then why the maudlin sentimentality over the closing of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CBGB">CBGB</ref>'s, which at times turned into demonizing a homeless shelter?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">VG:</hi>  Yeah, and they had not paid their rent, had they?  I sided with the homeless shelter in a way, except I thought the whole thing was ridiculous because somebody should have stepped in and bought it and paid it and fixed it up, in the sense there is no shrine.  They don' think about the tourism, do they?  I expect that of America now.  Los Angeles just destroyed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brown%20Derby">Brown Derby</ref>, and the modernist architecture. That's the thing about America. There seems to be very little regard for legacy.  I think they should have kept CBGBs, but I think that more cynically.  My students had a huge debate about it.</p>
</text>
