<text id="autogum_interview_doc1305" title="part2_Wikinews interviews former Salt Lake City mayor and 2012 presidential candidate Rocky Anderson" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-12-17" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Salt_Lake_City_mayor_and_2012_presidential_candidate_Rocky_Anderson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><p>I was a big proponent and testified before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Senate%20Committee%20on%20Energy%20and%20Natural%20Resources">Senate Energy and Natural Resources committee</ref> regarding the proposal to transport and store high level nuclear waste, first, on a supposedly temporary basis at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goshute">Goshute</ref> Reservation in Utah and ultimately at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yucca%20Mountain">Yucca Mountain</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nevada">Nevada</ref>.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How critical is it for a presidential candidate to have executive experience?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Anderson</hi>: I think it’s extremely important for someone to be able to demonstrate in an executive capacity, he or she can handle the pressure, know how to deal with differing interests, and come to the best solutions. I know some people get in an executive position and they become very dictatorial and dogmatic about what they’re doing.  I’ve always held the view both as a practicing lawyer, as president of my law firm and of course as mayor and then later as executive director of High Road for Human Rights, that you’re going to do a much better job if you learn as much as you can about any topic before you form your views and then still bring in those who have opposing views to hear them out and to learn, try to learn.</p>
<p><figure><caption>Public transit with the skyline of Salt Lake City in the background.Image: CountyLemonade.</caption></figure></p></p>
<hi rend="bold">I think in terms of executive experience, knowing how to bring those opposing forces together, solve problems, being respectful, and always having in mind that just because you’re in that position doesn’t make you any smarter or wiser than you were before. That shared wisdom can mean everything in terms of one’s success.</hi>
<p><p>That’s how we were able to get the light rail project completed right in the beginning of my term. There was a group called Citizens Against Light Rail that formed and they even had their own letterhead and logo, and the leaders of that group will tell you that the first thing I did was brought the opponents all together at my home, went through what caused them to oppose light rail, and we figured out through a really constructive problem solving exercise during the course of several intense weeks, how to resolve most of those issues, and those opponents to light rail were very much in favor of it and are real champions of the community-based problem-solving process that we’ve put into place. That’s also become the national model. We put together a community team of people that was comprised of businesses and residents all along the construction route that would determine whether the contractors would receive bonus payments, and then we set very clear guidelines for those contractors in terms of dust control, noise control, hours of construction, keeping one lane of traffic open at all times so businesses could continue to have access. This system had the contractor very very sensitive to the concerns of those along the construction route and ways we certainly didn’t see during the construction of light rail down Main Street under my predecessor.  And contractors ended up received either 96 or 97 percent of possible bonus payments because of that increased sensitivity, and members of the community felt like they had real power, which of course they did. That’s how it ought to be.</p></p>
</text>
