<text id="autogum_interview_doc1035" title="part2_Wikinews interviews team behind the 2,000th featured Wikipedia article" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-10" dateModified="2009-12-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_team_behind_the_2%2C000th_featured_Wikipedia_article" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I would assume the Wikipedia community was in favour of your project, did anyone outwith that community make notably critical comments about your idea?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">JBM</hi></hi>: No, but then as I say I hardly talked to anyone about it!</item></list>
<p>I should mention, however, that it's not necessarily a given that the Wikipedia community was in favour.  I've noticed that with some other educational projects, the initial reaction from Wikipedians has not always been so favourable.  In part that's because students are encouraged to write a new article on anything they can come up with, and these are swiftly marked for deletion.  In part that's because they write essays offline, then upload them, and naturally enough they are not in Wikipedia format or do not follow Wikipedia conventions (about "original research," for instance).  Those articles are soon laden with tags, and their talk pages filled with warnings or reproaches.  We managed to avoid that on the whole...  mostly by accident!  But we also avoided those problems, I think, because I'd spent a fair amount of time on Wikipedia already and was aware of some (but far from all) the habits of the site.  And more importantly because we had quite definite aims: students weren't editing Wikipedia for the sake of it.</p>
<p>Even so, we did get one "speedy deletion" tag.  It was placed, within less than a minute, on an article that I created in front of all the students, during class time.  For one horrible moment, in front of the whole class, I had a feeling that things might go terribly wrong.  The article tagged for speedy deletion was <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El%20Señor%20Presidente">El Señor Presidente</ref></hi>... which is now, as you know, Wikipedia's Feature Article number 2,000.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How significant a percentage of the mark you were giving for the class came from Wikipedia contributions?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">JBM</hi></hi>: Originally, the Wikipedia assignment was to have represented 30% of the total grade for the course.  Just over half-way through the semester, progress had still been relatively slow, and I was getting worried.  So I proposed to the class that we change the course assessment, and that we scrap the planned final essay or term paper.  This would mean that the other elements (a mid-term, blogs and participation, and Wikipedia) would all come to be worth more.  We talked about the proposal, and I gave them some time to think about it.  We then had a secret ballot, and I said in advance that we would only go ahead with the change if two thirds (66%) were in favour.  In the end, 85% of the class voted for increasing the significance of the Wikipedia project to 40% of the overall course grade.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  As a member of the Wikimedia Foundation's communications committee I (Brian McNeil) frequently see both sides of the conflict over how relevant or reliable Wikipedia is. This ranges from queries coming in from students working on their school paper who want a response to their librarian and teachers effectively banning use of Wikipedia, to the other extreme such as a recent case where a teaching surgeon in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">UK</ref> asking for permission to quote extensively from Wikipedia for a paper on the site's relevance and potential use for undergraduates in medicine. I have a stock answer detailing how to check Wikipedia sources; that Wikipedia is a great starting point for research, and that if you disallow Wikipedia you should disallow Britannica. Is this something you would agree with?</p>
</text>
