<text id="autogum_interview_doc508" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Jeremy Hanke, editor of MicroFilmmaker Magazine" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-11" dateModified="2019-08-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jeremy_Hanke%2C_editor_of_MicroFilmmaker_Magazine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">J.F.</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">MicroFilmmaker Magazine</hi> is free to read on its website. Why did you choose this over the paid subscription route?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mr. Hanke:</hi>  There were so many scams on the internet that were designed to prey on filmmakers, that we didn’t want to make low-budget filmmakers—who had the least money to spend on making their films in the first place—have to pay to get the information to make their films the best they possibly could be.  I and a number of my top writers are believing Christians and we wanted this magazine to be an act of service to the low-budget filmmakers, not a money-making scam.  Clearly our readers have found it to be useful, because many people who have very different beliefs and values than we do regularly frequent our magazine’s pages and have asked for our help with all processes of filmmaking—even on films that are violently anti-Christian.  We don’t turn away anyone that needs help and do our best to help in any way we can.</p>
<p>This is also the reason we chose to make MFM an exclusively online magazine. Because of its online nature, our operating costs are lower than they would be if it were printed, which allows us to survive on online advertising without having to charge our readers a dime.  Additionally, while printed magazines can be more lucrative (even the ones that are paid for by advertising and not by subscription fees), they would not be able to reach the web’s global population of filmmakers that need help.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">J.F.</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Today, most of the films we see in theatres cost millions, sometimes hundreds of millions, to make. Do you think it's really possible to make films that can compete with these on a shoestring budget?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mr. Hanke:</hi> I would say no…yes…and absolutely.  Allow me to explain.</p>
<p>Can you get the same quality of image on a $5,500 Panasonic HVX200 as you can get off a $120,000 Grass Valley Viper?  No, of course not.  There are all sorts of compression and quality differences between the affordable cameras and the ones that Hollywood uses.  (However, this is becoming less and less the case with the extremely popular wild-card camera company, RED.  They’ve made a higher-quality-than-Hollywood camera in the Red One for about 1/10th the cost of a comparable Sony camera that Hollywood use.  Additionally, they’re about to release an even less expensive camera in the Red Scarlet, which will be unveiled at NAB ’08.)</p>
<p>Now moving on to the “yes” part.  When you take out the image quality differences, the amount of leaps in software and compositing abilities that are now available to the shoestring budget filmmaker are amazing.  For example, there is now extremely powerful greenscren software that’s designed to allow you to key DV and HD footage and yields quite nice results.  (I’m actually in the process of working on a book on this subject, and have found the growth in this area really impressive.)  Additionally, a number of special effects programs either have been created for low-budgets, like VisionLab by FXHome, or have dropped their prices for low budget users, like Apple’s Shake, which dropped from $3,000 to $500.  Many of these programs allows you to create everything from blaster fire to lightning and composite them in one place.  And, for folks who want to use Hollywood quality particle effects, the quite impressive particleIllusion is only $300 and was recently used in the new Rambo film, as well as being used in many other Hollywood productions.</p>
</text>
