<text id="autogum_interview_doc451" title="part5_US presidential candidate Duncan Hunter speaks to Wikinews" shortTile="partus-presidential" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-12" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_presidential_candidate_Duncan_Hunter_speaks_to_Wikinews" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> It seems like it is a difficult thing to argue that we have nuclear arms, but other sovereign nations can’t have them.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Yeah, I think that would have to fall under the category of the real world.  You don’t want to have countries which have what I would call non-stable leadership, or anti-American leadership, developing the means to kill large numbers of Americans.  That may not seem fair, that’s not Marquis of Queensbury rules, but it’s in the interest of the United States.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Does it not worry you that governments can change quickly?  You had Shah Pahlavi, who was very pro-Western for a long time, overthrown in Iran.  President Musharraf in Pakistan, which now has nuclear weapons, is also unstable with his hold on power and has nuclear capabilities.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Yes, but I think in both those cases you will see that we did not give nuclear weapons capability to either one of them, and would very much prefer they didn’t have it.  So I agree with you, but I want to remind you that we haven’t given and we have been very much against nuclear proliferation to those states.</p>
<head id="The_United_Nations">The United Nations</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You are a critic of the United Nations and it would seem like out of any foreign body that is positioned to assume global leadership on this issue, it would be the UN.  Do you think it is wise to take an antagonistic view of that body when it seems necessary to have the global cooperation it embodies?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Well, I’m not antagonistic toward the United Nations as much as I am realistic about the United Nations.  I think the United Nations is good, as I have said, for inoculating babies and for operating refugee camps and refugee centers, but they should not be relied upon by the United States for our security, and I think that has been proven time and time again.  So the United States needs to have independently the means for maintaining its security.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> One of the things you said was, “Rest assured no treaty that infringes the sovereignty of the United States…”  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  You said you saw a quote that said ‘a trip to the waste basket’?  That’s not a…</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> That’s not an accurate quote?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  I like what you said, but that’s not a phrase I generally use, but I am not supportive of the United Nations for U.S. security.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> If you’re concerned about infringing on the sovereignty of the United States, but the concern doesn’t extend for the sovereignty of other countries, how do you form a foreign policy principle that doesn’t make it seem the concern is only what is good for us?</hi></p>
</text>
