<text id="autogum_interview_doc271" title="part0_Dublin travel agents occupy offices against closure" shortTile="partdublin-travel" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-08-02" dateModified="2012-03-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dublin_travel_agents_occupy_offices_against_closure" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Dublin travel agents occupy offices against closure</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 3, 2009</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Signs advertising Monday's rally dot Dublin Image: <ref target="http://www.flickr.com/photos/infomatique/3782696008/">informatique</ref>.</caption></figure><p>Employees of two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas%20Cook%20Group">Thomas Cook</ref> travel agency offices in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dublin">Dublin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ireland">Ireland</ref> have occupied their offices in response to management's announcement of earlier closure dates for the sites.  On Friday, July 31, 40 employees at the Thomas Cook store in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grafton%20Street">Grafton Street</ref> began an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/sit-in">occupation protest</ref> after the sudden announcement of the store's immediate closure; workers at the store had previously been told, when the closures were announced on May 12, that the businesses would remain open until September 6.  The day after, employees at the Thomas Cook-owned Direct Holidays store in nearby <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talbot%20Street">Talbot Street</ref> began their own occupation.  A third Thomas Cook store in the capital, in North Earl Street, closed without incident; according to one employee who spoke to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi>, this is because the North Earl Street store was closed up and stripped out while employees were at home, leaving the workers to find an empty space instead of an office when they arrived for work the next morning.</p>
<p>Employees are demanding an improved <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Layoff">redundancy</ref> package from Thomas Cook and allege a string of abuses by management. Thomas Cook management has offered the employees five weeks' redundancy pay for every year worked at the company, in excess of the minimum two weeks' pay per year worked required by Irish employment law, and says that the Grafton Street location had been losing money for five years. Employees, demanding eight weeks' pay, counter that the company realised a profit of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UK%20pound">£</ref>400 million in the past fiscal year, of which <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euro">€</ref>4 million originated from Ireland; and that Thomas Cook's UK &amp; Ireland chief, Manny Fontenla-Novoa, was given a bonus of €7 million earlier this year. 60 jobs would be lost in the closure of the two stores, which constitute all of Thomas Cook's retail operation in the Republic of Ireland; a further 17 jobs were lost in the closure of the North Earl Street store.</p>
<hi rend="bold">There are no jobs out there...We need 8 weeks to live on for the next two years</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Caroline Cullen, TSSA representative</p>
<p>Before the occupations began, workers at Thomas Cook's locations, who are members of trade union the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transport%20Salaried%20Staffs'%20Association">Transport Salaried Staffs' Association</ref> (TSSA) had voted unanimously to strike, alleging that the closures were being done without sufficient consultation of staff by Thomas Cook management. Caroline Cullen, accounts assistant and TSSA staff representative at the Grafton Street location, characterises the behaviour of Thomas Cook management as "intimidation". When the consultation period had finished, she said, Thomas Cook management sent Simon Robinson, an executive director of the company, and a male colleague of his to close the office. The presence of the Thomas Cook executives, two high-ranking, business-suited men, in an office where forty-two of forty-four employees are women is itself intimidating, Cullen asserts; she says that Robinson furthermore attempted to "bully" the employees into accepting the five-week redundancy offer by saying that if they did not accept, they would receive only the statutory minimum. "You cannot live on 5 weeks", says Cullen. "Travel agents are closing every week. There's a hiring freeze at the banks. There are no jobs out there...We need 8 weeks to live on for the next two years while we look for jobs." The extra three weeks' redundancy pay would, she estimates, cost Thomas Cook €400,000. </p>
</text>
