<text id="autogum_interview_doc1426" title="part1_Judging the Courts: Wikinews interviews Prof. Lawrence Douglas" shortTile="partjudging-courts" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-11-20" dateModified="2015-09-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Judging_the_Courts%3A_Wikinews_interviews_Prof._Lawrence_Douglas" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: The magnitude of the crimes should not change our commitment to a fair legal process.  This is not to say that the identical rules of evidence that apply in the trial of a  "common" criminal must be applied to a spectacular trial of a high-level perpetrator.  For example, the Nuremberg and Eichmann trials both permitted hearsay and entertained a more capacious notion of relevance than would have been permitted in a "common" trial.  But these unorthodox evidentiary rules did not erode the fairness of the proceedings.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: Saddam's defense lawyers, rights groups and observers have questioned the fairness and validity of this trial. What do you make of the concerns raised by them?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: The fact that the judge who finally took the reins of control, Raouf Rasheed Abdel-Rahman, frequently got into shouting matches with the defendants and suddenly curtailed the calling of defense witnesses certainly did little to contribute to the image of a neutral, even-handed tribunal.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: Some of the issues raised concern matters that were outside the Court's ambit and control (e.g., the murder of three defense team members, the opposition to the use of the death penalty, the effect of the verdict on the continuing violence in the country). Leaving these aside, what do you make of the concerns raised about the Court's own proceedings, its decisions and actions?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: Clearly the Tribunal made all sorts of missteps and questionable moves.  It's worth bearing in mind, however, that even the best-intentioned court would have faced staggering problems given the tactics of Saddam and the larger political climate outside of the courtroom.  Saddam himself placed the Tribunal in an extremely difficult position.  The first presiding judge, Rizgar Mohammed Amin, was faulted for his failure to restrain the defendant, and this failure arguably made the court look impotent.  His replacement, Judge Abdel-Rahman was faulted for the opposite reason: for dragging the defendant from the courtroom at the slightest provocation, a strategy that undermined the dignity of the court and its appearance of neutrality.  So the court was caught in a difficult position, which was not improved by the periodic news that a member of the defense team had been assassinated.  That said, the fact that one of the accused was acquitted is a good sign.  At the very least, the judges appeared to have learned the Nuremberg lesson that nothing legitimates the death sentence of an architect of atrocity better than the acquittal of a lackey.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: Have the actions of the Iraqi authorities undermined the fairness or independence of the Tribunal?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: The tribunal was subjected to withering political pressure from the Iraqi government, resulting in the resignation of the first presiding judge and in the withdrawal of a possible replacement.  Clearly this kind of political pressure is inappropriate.  At the very least it undermines the perception of the tribunal's independence, and matters of perception play an extremely important role in legitimizing the legal process.</p>
</text>
