<text id="autogum_interview_doc417" title="part2_Canada&amp;apos;s Don Valley West (Ward 26) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-don-valley" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Don_Valley_West_%28Ward_26%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Responsible development for our neighbourhoods</hi>
<list type="unordered"><item>I would advocate for a mandatory architectural peer review council to promote consistent and well planned development.  This would enhance the public realm with respect to green space, size and height, density, and public access ultimately benefiting Toronto's communities.</item>
<item>A thorough and guaranteed public consultation process with local residents for any large scale development proposal.  The recent surge of new buildings in the Bayview Institutional area could bring further development and we must ensure that the confines of any original agreement and framework are adhered to.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Protecting the strong sense of community Ward 26 is the most important issue the must be addressed.   Traffic and development are converging forces in our community that have an impact on the sense of neighbourhood spirit . The city must arrive at well planned decisions through a thoughtful and efficient process that accommodates residents' concerns.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have always had respect for Canada's political process.   The municipal level symbolizes grassroots politics and I enjoy having that direct contact and support of my neighbours.   I decided to involve myself because it is time that younger Canadians entered our political realm to make that difference and encourage our demographic to vote and have their voices heard.  I am confident that I can bring a FIT – Forward, Innovative, Thinking approach to city hall in order to bring sustainable solutions to Toronto over the next twenty years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Growing up and living in our community all my life has shaped my values and given me a sense of pride for where I live. I am proud of how Don Valley West has evolved but still feel that there is more work to be done.  I understand the traditions of my neighbourhood and also identify with the new generation of residents who have chosen Ward 26 as their home. I want the City of Toronto to take responsibility to ensure a safe, healthy, and active community for residents of all ages.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Coaching the Rumsey Rattlers children's basketball at Bloorview Kids Rehab. Fundraising for the Starlight Starbright Children's Foundation and the Toronto Child Abuse Centre over the past three years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Most desirable: The City's commitment of sustained support of the Career Bridge program that helps foreign trained professionals get their first Canadian job experience.  Toronto was responsible for employing new immigrants in the City of Toronto workforce and set an example to employers across our City as to how we can tap in to such valuable expertise that is right at our doorstep.</p>
</text>
