<text id="autogum_interview_doc1151" title="part5_Obesity and the Fat Acceptance Movement: Kira Nerusskaya speaks" shortTile="partobesity-fat-acceptance" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-09" dateModified="2014-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Obesity_and_the_Fat_Acceptance_Movement%3A_Kira_Nerusskaya_speaks" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>One of the reasons why I’m doing this film is to stop the fat-bashing.  We’re fat.  We know it, okay?  You don’t need to tell us or point that out.  It doesn’t mean that we are less than you.  We’re equal.  If God has given us inalienable rights according to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill%20of%20Rights">Bill of Rights</ref> of the Constitution, that all men are created equal here in the United States, well, you know what?  We’re created equal no matter what size we are.</p>
<head id="On_America's_obesity_epidemic">On America's obesity epidemic</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you read stories about an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obesity%20in%20the%20United%20States">obesity epidemic in the United States</ref> what is your reaction to that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  It’s absolutely true.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think should be done about the obesity epidemic?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  And I don’t like it.  One piece of my film will talk about why we are the way we are.  The great conveniences that have been bestowed on America are the things that are hurting us.  When you look at the amount of sugar in an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard%20American%20Diet">average diet</ref>, when you look at the convenience food, when you look at fast food and its availability, when you look at the American lifestyle; we’re rushing around all the time.  We only have two weeks off to enjoy our life yet we have to work more, educate more, achieve a thinner body, a better relationship, a cooler car…we have to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keeping%20up%20with%20the%20Joneses">keep up with the Joneses</ref> and sometimes the Joneses are out of reach.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How would you respond to somebody who said, “You’re a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypocrisy">hypocrite</ref>?”  How could you have a problem with obesity...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  I’m not saying I have a problem with it, what I’m saying is that I see why it exists.  That’s my point.  I see why it exists.  It goes along with diet, with the same thing that we were talking about in regards to breakfast -- I don’t drink soda, I don’t eat sweets or sugar, but a lot of people would automatically think that based upon my size I must eat x, y and z or that I don’t exercise-...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That you’re just there shoveling fries down your face.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Right.  And that’s inaccurate for me and that’s inaccurate for a lot of people.  But there are women who eat ice cream for breakfast and a donut for lunch and a bagel for dinner or whatever.  That’s part of their freedom; that’s their right to do that and if that’s what they want to do, that’s great.  But I would also say to those women: if you’re going to turn around and complain about being fat, shut up or put up.  You can be fat and healthy; at least, healthy to a certain degree.  But no matter the fact that I do have good blood pressure and I do have good cholesterol, people are going to turn around and say, “But you’re fat.”  And you know what?  I am.  I can’t take those 313 pounds away.</p>
</text>
