<text id="autogum_interview_doc404" title="part2_Bat for Lashes plays the Bowery Ballroom: an Interview with Natasha Khan" shortTile="partbat-lashes-plays" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-27" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bat_for_Lashes_plays_the_Bowery_Ballroom%3A_an_Interview_with_Natasha_Khan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You are often compared to Björk and Kate Bush; do those constant comparisons tend to bother you as an artist who is trying to define herself on her own terms?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  No, I mean, I guess that in the past it bothered me, but now I just feel really confident and sure that as time goes on my musical style and my writing is taking a pace of its own, and I think in time the music will speak for itself and people will see that I'm obviously doing something different.  Those women are fantastic, strong, risk-taking artists—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  —as are you—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  —thank you, and that's a great tradition to be part of, and when I look at artists like Björk and Kate Bush, I think of them as being like older sisters that have come before; they are kind of like an amazing support network that comes with me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I'd imagine it's preferable to be considered the next Björk or Kate Bush instead of the next <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Britney%20Spears">Britney</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] Totally!  Exactly! I mean, could you imagine—oh, no I'm not going to try to offend anyone now!  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Let's leave it there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Does music feed your artwork, or does you artwork feed your music more?  Or is the relationship completely symbiotic?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  I think it's pretty back-and-forth. I think when I have blocks in either of those area, I tend to emphasize the other.  If I'm finding it really difficult to write something I know that I need to go investigate it in a more visual way, and I'll start to gather images and take photographs and make notes and make collages and start looking to photographers and filmmakers to give me a more grounded sense of the place that I'm writing about, whether it's in my imagination or in the characters.   Whenever I'm writing music it's a very visual place in my mind.  It has a location full of characters and colors and landscapes, so those two things really compliment each other, and they help the other one to blossom and support the other.  They are like brother and sister.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you are composing music, do you see notes and words as colors and images in your mind, and then you put those down on paper?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  Yes.  When I'm writing songs, especially lately because I think the next album has a fairly strong concept behind it and I'm writing the songs, really imagining them, so I'm very immersed into the concept of the album and the story that is there through the album.  It's the same as when I'm playing live, I will imagine I see a forest of pine trees and sky all around me and the audience, and it really helps me.  Or I'll just imagine <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Midnight%20blue">midnight blue</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emerald%20(color)">emerald green</ref>, those kind of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1980s">Eighties</ref> colors, and they help me.</p>
</text>
