<text id="autogum_interview_doc1219" title="part2_The Onion: An interview with 'America's Finest News Source'" shortTile="partthe-onion-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2013-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Onion%3A_An_interview_with_%27America%27s_Finest_News_Source%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you are going through the headlines, is it just you guys sitting around trying to crack each other up?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  It’s the least amount of fun possible.  Nah, I’m kidding.  It’s actually more businesslike than you’d imagine.  It’s very much like you are trying to make the room laugh, but the room has been a sort of captive audience for many many years now, so it takes a lot to make the room laugh.  
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  The best analogy I’ve heard is when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rob%20Siegel">Rob Siegel</ref>, former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Editor-in-chief">editor-in-chief</ref>, likened it to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wine%20tasting">wine tasting</ref>. It’s this quiet experience where you are trying to soak in what the joke is, have we done anything like this, is it a unique take, what are other people doing.  It’s sort of like, “Hmmm…that’s hilarious.  That’s really really funny” rather than people falling off their chairs.  It’s more subdued than I think what most people would expect.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s more analytical and clinical?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  Not all the time, but it can’t be a laugh a minute.
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  Yeah, what you see on <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Studio%2060">Studio 60</ref></hi> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/30%20Rock">30 Rock</ref></hi>, those are scripted writers rooms.  Everything is funny there.  There's <hi rend="italic">a lot</hi> of unfunny jokes that are told in a back room, that's why they stay and die in that back room and don’t go out in <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi>.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If someone is continually telling unfunny jokes, do you eventually fire them?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  That’s why we are on the 10th floor to make sure they die when they get kicked out.  It can be a real mess on Broadway.
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  By the time you get to be a writer for <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi>, though, the odds are you are going to succeed because we make it pretty challenging.  You go through quite a bit.  You will already have demonstrated a pretty long successful record of writing stuff for us before you will be in that room on a daily basis.  But if somebody wakes up one morning and suddenly no longer is funny, then yeah, head first, out the door as quickly as possible, and as sadistically as possible.</p></p>
<head id="The_features_and_the_columnists">The features and the columnists</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who are the people on the street, the “American Voices”?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  Each one of them has their own magnificent story, but they are mainly people from back in the early days of Madison where <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> started.  One guy’s a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20Parcel%20Service">UPS</ref> driver who came by the office; another one was someone they randomly pulled off the street.  But they go way back in <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi>.  Chet might know more.
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  Way back to the Madison days and they were literally six people on the street that one day, and we have used them ever since.</p></p>
</text>
