<text id="autogum_interview_doc1332" title="part3_Wikinews investigates the reconstruction of Pichilemu, Chile after February earthquake" shortTile="partwikinews-investigates" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-10-23" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_investigates_the_reconstruction_of_Pichilemu%2C_Chile_after_February_earthquake" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<head id="Eight_months_on,_reconstruction_begins">Eight months on, reconstruction begins</head>
<figure><caption>Caleta de Pescadores was destroyed almost completely after the earthquake and tsunami. The fishermen's boats were thrown more than 200 meters away. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>On March 20, in collaboration with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor%20of%20Cardenal%20Caro">Governor of Cardenal Caro</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julio%20Ibarra">Julio Ibarra</ref>, Colonel Raúl Melo, and the Mayor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Litueche">Litueche</ref> Bernardo Cornejo, Mayor of Pichilemu Roberto Córdova announced a "tourism revival campaign" of Pichilemu, promoting the surf practice, whose goal was "to make the city go back to the normality."</p>
<p>On April 4, the first monument was erected in memory of the earthquake and tsunami victims. The monument was created by local artisans, with rocks from several places of the Cardenal Caro Province. "We wanted to create this monument so we don't forget it [the earthquake] [...] This is the beginning of the reconstruction," said Julio Ibarra. The monument was placed in front of the beach, near the building of the Cardenal Caro Government. Mayor Roberto Córdova said that "it definitely will help us reconstruct [ourselves] espiritually, [and that] is essential."</p>
<p>On October 20, with the help of the Government, SERCOTEC (Technical Cooperation Service, <hi rend="italic">Servicio de Cooperación Técnica</hi>) and FOSIS (Solidarity and Social Investment, <hi rend="italic">Fondo de Solidaridad e Inversión Social</hi>), the Fishermen Store (<hi rend="italic">Caleta de Pescadores</hi>) began to be reconstructed. Caleta de Pescadores is administered by the Independent Labour Union of Fishermen of Pichilemu (Sindicato de Trabajo Independientes de Pescadores Artesanales), which has twenty-three members.</p>
<p>"The Government of President Sebastián Piñera has been worried about the fishing area, carrying out several actions in help of them, after all that they've suffered after the earthquake and tsunami that hit them [...] This area is working normally again," Governor Ibarra said.</p>
<head id="New_kiosks;_interview_with_Alejandro_Mella">New kiosks; interview with Alejandro Mella</head>
<figure><caption>Alejandro Mella. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>On October 6, the Municipality of Pichilemu published the design of kiosks that were going to be constructed, as replacement of those destroyed by the earthquake. As of October 23, four kiosks have been constructed in Pichilemu, specifically on Las Terrazas beach, and two more are being constructed. According to Mauricio Grez, a construction engineer, the construction of one kiosk would cost up to US$ 2,500 (CLP 1,000,000).</p>
<p>Alejandro Mella, locally known as "el Rey del Cochayuyo" ("the King of the Cochayuyo"), is a merchant of Pichilemu, who promotes the cochayuyo (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/durvillaea%20antarctica">durvillaea antarctica</ref></hi>), and lost his kiosk after the February earthquake and tsunami. "I was given my [former] kiosk by the Mayor Orlando Cornejo, back in 1993. It was right in front of us [in front of Las Terrazas beach, near "the grotto of the Virgin"], and was made smithereens by the tsunami," he told <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>.</p>
<p>"I have always worked on selling cochayuyo here, and the terrain where my kiosk was located before has been disputed by private people, and the municipality approved that. I talked with the Mayor and he said 'I don't know what's going on the beach'; that left me perplexed. [...] I like the new design of the kiosks, they are larger, and we can do more things with it, but they are way too expensive," he added. Mr. Mella also gave <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> a sample of his work as "the King of the Cochayuyo", an essay called "El cochayuyo es una mina repleta de nutrientes y sales minerales" ("Cochayuyo is a mine full of nutrients and mineral salts", pictured below), which he sells for 200 Chilean pesos (0.41 US$), and that contains "tips and information about the plant, and some recipes."</p>
</text>
