<text id="autogum_interview_doc1145" title="part2_Eurovision '82 winner Nicole talks about 'Ein bißchen Frieden', her success and the Contest today" shortTile="parteurovision--winner" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-02-02" dateModified="2019-09-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eurovision_%2782_winner_Nicole_talks_about_%27Ein_bi%C3%9Fchen_Frieden%27%2C_her_success_and_the_Contest_today" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<head id="Career_today">Career today</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In many European circles, "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/schlager">schlager</ref>" is almost looked upon as if it were a dirty word, synonymous with "uncool" or "out of touch." Do you feel that common threads in schlager songs (namely love and feelings) get stigmatized and mocked, and do you think that's fair?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: That doesn't faze me much. To me, the audience is the most important thing. I did an unplugged tour a few weeks ago with all the songs from the last three decades. It was fantastic to get standing ovations (nearly 20 minutes every evening). </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Where was your favorite place to perform?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: The best place to perform was the "Schmidt's Tivoli" in Hamburg where we also recorded the "Live DVD." </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In your long career, you have released over 30 albums. Do you have any regrets as far as directions your career has taken? If you could do anything over again, would you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: I would do the same all over again, no doubt!</p>
<head id="General_thoughts_about_Eurovision">General thoughts about Eurovision</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> And 27 years later, you remain the only Eurovision winner from Germany. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: In 1982, it was the right song, with the right girl, at the right place. As I said before, it was a three-minute magic moment when I was on stage. An honest girl with an honest authentic song, telling a message everybody understood.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Some of the German performers and entries in recent years had inventive themes, especially Roger Cicero's swing song and Texas Lightning's country performance. How do you feel about these "theme" entries? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: In my opinion, every artist should be authentic, no matter what kind of song.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Do you feel the allegations of "bloc voting," favoring Eastern European countries over Western European countries (of which Germany is a part), are true? Also with the advent of telephone voting, do you feel the Contest has drifted in a direction where Eurovision is no longer "about the song"?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: Yes, it's true. The eastern European countries obviously support each other with the so-called "bloc voting." It's now a political affair and no longer a "song contest."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Do you ever see yourself returning to the Eurovision stage as the German representative?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: No. I can't top being #1.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Will you be a part of the German delegation going to Moscow this year? If no decision has been made yet, would you like to go?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nicole</hi>: I haven't been asked yet, but of course I would like to be a part of the German delegation. Eurovision is still on my mind.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In closing, what would you like to say to all of your fans who have followed your career these past three decades?</hi></p>
</text>
