<text id="autogum_interview_doc973" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Frank McEnulty, New American Independent Party nominee for President of the United States" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-09-24" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Frank_McEnulty%2C_New_American_Independent_Party_nominee_for_President_of_the_United_States" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: Why is it necessary that a third party candidate be voted into the White House this year? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> Because only a third party candidate can bring about the true change that is necessary to get our country back on the right path for all Americans.  Does anyone truly believe that change will come from the two major party candidates when their parties have the greatest vested interests in keeping the status quo?  I don’t think so and never see it happening.</p>
<p>To have true change you need someone in charge who is not a product of the system, who will hire the best people for the job regardless of political affiliation and who is only interested in doing what is best for all Americans.  That person will only come from an source independent of the political machines – from a third party.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: We haven't seen many Frank McEnulty media appearances, billboards or commercials. Will we see these in the weeks ahead? Or are you trying to run more of a grassroots campaign? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> This time around it is a grassroots campaign, but we are building a strong base for the next election that will allow us to have more resources to expend on traditional media while continuing our grassroots appeal.</p>
<p>Every week the campaign gathers more and more notice and that will continue to grow.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford:</hi> How are you currently doing in the polls?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> I rarely am included in any polls.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: Why are you a better candidate than Chuck Baldwin <hi rend="italic">(Constitution Party)</hi>, Bob Barr <hi rend="italic">(Libertarian Party)</hi>, John McCain <hi rend="italic">(Republican Party)</hi>, Cynthia McKinney <hi rend="italic">(Green Party)</hi> or Barack Obama <hi rend="italic">(Democratic Party)</hi>? Why should the American people give you their vote? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> First, they should vote for me because I truly believe that where I stand on most issues is where the vast majority of Americans stand.  We may not agree on everything all the time, but they will know that deep down I am fighting for the same things that they want to see happen.</p>
<p>Also, for the simple reason that I can and will do things differently than all of them would in the same position and below are a few examples of the ways in which my administration would be much different than those of any other President.</p>
<p>Partisan Politics and My Administration:</p>
<p>There will be no partisan politics allowed in my administration because I have seen first- hand how destructive they can be to getting the job done and helping people get back to their lives.</p>
<p>For the last three years I have been involved in developing a project in the New Orleans area.  The project is now underway, but during that time I have had the opportunity to travel to New Orleans several times and have seen first-hand what has and hasn’t been happening in the area since the hurricane in 2005 (over 36 months ago now).  Not nearly enough is getting done.  In Louisiana, they spent way too long blaming the Republicans in Washington, DC for everything that happened to New Orleans and surrounding areas rather than just getting on with the rebuild.  Now, 24 months later, there are still whole neighborhoods where very little has been accomplished and I believe a great deal of the blame for that is because of the initial partisan finger-pointing that is still going on today.</p>
</text>
