<text id="autogum_interview_doc1379" title="part2_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: How did James Brown’s death affect you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi> Oh, I don’t think anything has affected me more.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: He was such an icon, but then to also have had this deeply personal relationship must have had an extraordinary impact on you.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi> James Brown was the father I never had. I traveled with him; he financed my youth group. I met my wife — we’re no longer together — when she was his background singer. He put my kids in private school. I styled my hair after him; <hi rend="italic">he</hi> actually styled my hair after his. What I do functionally is what Dr. King, Reverend Jackson and the movement are all about; but I learned manhood from James Brown. I always say that James Brown taught me how to be a man.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: What was one lesson that he taught you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi> Determination. Don’t be afraid to listen to your inner ear. James Brown changed music; he changed the beat of music. I learned from him to trust your inner ear, go by your own beat. I remember in the 1970’s when disco became popular he refused to water down his music, and it ended up his music became the basis of funk and rap and all that. I watched him deal with adversity and go to jail. When he was in jail I went and saw him every month, and I went and preached for him. He never gave up, he was very determined. He taught me how to take adversity and use it to your advantage.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  There is so much anger at injustice, and that anger can fell a person’s ability to right wrongs, or can steer them down a bad path. You have been able to take your anger and use it productively. When you come across a young person who is angry at the world around them, what kind of advice do you give them?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi> The challenge is to learn that your anger can fuel you in achieving things that can eradicate what you’re angry about; or your anger can consume and defeat you. I’m known for fighting racial bias, police misconduct, and things against poor people. I can either be strategic to say this is Plan A, B and C to get racial profiling off, or hate crime laws passed, or close the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Navy%20in%20Vieques,%20Puerto%20Rico">Navy base in Vieques</ref>, and I’m going to use my <hi rend="italic">anger</hi>, my real, heartfelt anger to fuel me to get up at five o’clock in the morning to do Plan A, B and C; or I can be someone so angry that I never get to a strategy, I never get to Plan A, B and C.  But then the police are not challenged, and the hate crime laws are not written, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vieques">Vieques</ref> is still open.  So the question one has to ask one’s self—I tell young people all the time, and most of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Action%20Network">National Action Network</ref> leadership in our chapters are younger than me—you have to make a choice at some point in your life: are you going to do something about what angers you, or do you want to just be angry?  Because I learned a long time ago that those in power don’t care that you’re angry, they care if you use that anger to do something about it.  You have a choice.  I used to like boxing.  My father was a boxer and I used to watching boxing matches all the time.  If you go into the ring just mad you’ll get knocked out.  Or you can go into the ring and have training, and have a fight plan, and use your natural anger to fuel your fight plan; it’s according to what you want to be.  But the one with the fight plan that uses his anger to <hi rend="italic">drive</hi> the fight plan is the one who ends up champion.  The one without one just ends up angry and laying knocked out.  It’s your choice.  I’m not saying I came to that out of brilliance; I came to that out of trial and error.  I used to be angry with no plan.  Just recklessly angry.</p>
</text>
