<text id="autogum_interview_doc1449" title="part1_Interview with Jimbo Wales" shortTile="partinterview-jimbo" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2005-12-05" dateModified="2018-05-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Jimbo_Wales" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
All Wikimedia Foundation projects currently use the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/free%20software">free</ref> <ref target="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/MediaWiki">MediaWiki</ref> software, which was purposely-designed for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref> project. Which makes it an excellent tool for an online community-developed encyclopedia, but perhaps not so perfect for other forms of knowledge bases like <ref target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Main%20Page">Wikisource</ref> or Wikinews. For Wikinews, an important tool was the creation of <ref target="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/DynamicPageList">Dynamic Page List</ref>, an extension to the software which allows lists of current articles to be built dynamically when they are published so the latest news is on the main page.
When Wikinews was started a year ago, a need for new functions quickly appeared. Dynamic Page Lists are crucial to Wikinews and several other tools should be developed as they are asked for. The situation is similar on other projects (e.g. Wiktionary), maybe a plan for developing a project specific software package should precede the creation of new projects?
<p>I do think we could do a better job of anticipating the software needs of new projects, but it is also important to understand that a lot of needs are not readily apparent a priori. Sometimes we have to try to do things for awhile before we really have an understanding of where the problem points are.</p>
The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Associated%20Press">Associated Press</ref> has changed their copyright notice with articles to include "you may not rewrite this article." Is Wikinews creating an impact on how other news sources release their information?
<p>I think that mainstream news sources are very much paying attention not just to Wikinews but to the entire citizen journalism movement. I think that many thoughtful people in the business understand that a sea change is happening, and are interested in figuring out how to empower more community input while still getting the best out of the old models.</p>
<p>I had dinner with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don%20Graham">Don Graham</ref> last Friday night, and he's an example of someone who isn't reacting to new media with shock and horror, but rather with keen interest in trying to see what the trends will be and how to adapt.</p>
Could you expand on "the best out of the old models."?
<p>Well, to expand on 'best of the old models' -- one thing that often comes up is that you have a reputation mechanism in traditional publishing, a mechanism which sometimes breaks, but which mostly works. Citizen journalism has to find ways to generate the same kind of reputation mechanisms. Blogs are finding that, to some extent.</p>
What is your opinion on Wikinews users gaining <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews:Accreditation_policy">credentials</ref> to be used in the field?
<p>It sounds cool to me, although I'm sensitive to the concerns that people have put forward about it. It's something I plan to study further this month, to see how it is working in practice so far, and to see what users feel about it.</p>
</text>
