<text id="autogum_interview_doc1296" title="part4_David S. Touretzky discusses Scientology, Anonymous and Tom Cruise" shortTile="partdavid-s-touretzky" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-06" dateModified="2012-12-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_S._Touretzky_discusses_Scientology%2C_Anonymous_and_Tom_Cruise" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Indeed, as their PTS/SP [Potential Trouble Source/Suppressive Person] handling tech [technology] needs to be seen to be "working" at least to Scientologists.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: So they sent out their members to counter-picket us as a way to make them feel better, but it didn't work. The members behaved badly, and at some level they must have known they were being jerks. So forget about confronting suppression.  The new tech is "lock doors, douse lights, and whine as loudly as you can!" My suggested picket sign for large Orgs: "Mike Rinder Blew. You Can Too!". Rinder appeared in a tuxedo at past IAS [International Association of Scientologists] events.  They know who he is.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : I would have thought that [Scientologists hiding from critics’ protests] to be "non-confront" [refusing to face up to something] in the Scientologists' own doctrine; although they would see it, I suppose, as "cutting entheta comm" [refusing to engage in negative communication]. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: Yeah, I don't know how they explained the strategy switch to their members, but your suggestion sounds right to me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : In your experience in pickets, has the "Why are you here? Ok, right. So why are you really here? Hehehe, no... why are you *really* here?" bullbaiting [of protesters] been killed off?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: My last picket was in 1999.   I imagine, with so many sites being picketed this time, we'll see a variety of strategies.  But bullbaiting picketers was never very successful. For the 1998 solo picket my sign had two sides.  One side said "Doubt is not a crime.  Freedom is not a stat." The other side said "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religious%20Technology%20Center">RTC</ref>: who crashed gross income?"  That one drove them ape. I didn't fully appreciate why that sign would upset them so much, until some ex-member explained it to me: it was a call for a witch-hunt.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : I think that kind of stratagem is probably going to be the most effective, because the Scientologists themselves can identify with such things; perhaps it may well be that it touches enough of a raw nerve in their own world, as it were, to give them pause for thinking. Is Scientology losing it grip on maintaining its "Wizard of Oz" world whereby its staff consider the tech to be infallible and the orgs to be clearing the planet?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: Yes, the members must be having huge doubts by now. But there remains a hardcore of followers who will not look at critical materials. I'd put them in two categories.   First are the old timers who never got the whole Intertubes thing [the Internet]. The second class is younger folk who are just losers.  Not bright or intellectually curious. Maybe ex-addicts who ended up joining staff. They're not going to go surfing the web for entheta, any more than Tom Cruise would.</p>
</text>
