<text id="autogum_interview_doc1104" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Freedom Party candidate David McGruer, Ottawa-Orleans" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-02" dateModified="2007-12-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Freedom_Party_candidate_David_McGruer%2C_Ottawa-Orleans" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><list type="ordered"><item>Property taxes. A lady long ago bought back her childhood home in Ottawa’s core. Her husband died and her budget tightened but her property taxes ballooned to $12,000 per year. This year she is tearfully selling. What moral code allows a government to force a homeowner to pay taxes for services not of her free choosing and threatens seizure if she does not pay? What is the mental state of people thinking it proper to force individuals to pay for things they neither use nor wish to pay for? Isn’t it time we regained the right to really own our homes and removed the taxation of property from our laws? The Freedom Party would work to eliminate the property tax and rely on consumption tax to fund basic and proper government operations.</item>
<item>Municipal services. Ottawa operates a vast bureaucracy and spends millions on consultants, yet everywhere we look we find waste, inefficiency and interference in business. From social housing to roads, from buses to pollution of our waters, from crime to hockey rinks, there is no end to problems. These are inherent in the nature of government. Because government uses force to implement its plans, it opposes the flexibility and accountability that comes with freedom. To fix your car you have a nearly infinite choice of services and all fully accountable to you. When you want a city service you have no choice or accountability. Efficiency disappears and you are left prisoner to the government monopoly. In the last municipal election my councilor said the city is in over 100 businesses. The City should exit most of these businesses and return them to individual decision making and the province should facilitate this.</item>
<item>Trust in government. This applies to government at all three levels. In past elections some parties and candidates have run on explicit platforms including tax reduction, yet spending at all levels continues to climb to new heights, faster than inflation. Such high spending rates are a tool to control your life more than ever before. The Freedom Party believes government should return to its original role as the protector of individual rights and be dramatically smaller than it is today. That way, politicians would have many fewer promises to make (and keep or break) and you would control your own life and be accountable to yourself. Without control over your life, politicians need not make promises to bribe you with your own money. “No man's life, liberty or property are safe while the legislature is in session.” - Judge Gideon J. Tucker</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>Confirm the rights and freedoms contained in the 1960 Canadian Bill of Rights and then set about dismantling all programs which infringe on the rights of individuals, meaning most of the government programs.</p>
</text>
