<text id="autogum_interview_doc989" title="part4_Wikinews holds Reform Party USA presidential candidates forum" shortTile="partwikinews-holds" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-01-02" dateModified="2016-09-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_holds_Reform_Party_USA_presidential_candidates_forum" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Steele</hi>: BEFORE anyone is elected, I am working hard to present every single politician up for reelection with an Electoral Reform Pledge.  I am the one who presented the original Statement of Demand and Electoral Reform Act to Occupy in NYC. It has since been crowd-sourced and attracted a range of very serious proponents from across the country.  Tomorrow there is an Inter-Occupy telephone conference call to discuss Occupy's morphing toward political activism.  Our goal is simple: to get an Occupy political liaison in each of the 50 states, and to then recruit citizen delegations in each of the Congressional districts.  BEFORE Congress returns to Washington in January, I want a simple table showing where every one of the Representatives and Senators stands on Electoral Reform: red, yellow, or green.  The rest is up to the public.</p>
<p>Ideally, Congress would be forced to pass the Electoral Reform Act in January 2012, in time for the first half of the provisions to apply to November 2012.  I think <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Americans_Elect">Americans Elect</ref>--a good idea corrupted in its implementation--will be litigated into oblivion by the two-party tyranny.  We have to force Congress to be honest.   The documents can be seen online.</p>
<p>AT A MINIMUM and in time for November 2012 I want Congress to mandate that all states be required to put the presidential candidates on the state ballot for each and every party that has achieved national party status.  In addition, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electoral%20College">Electoral College</ref> votes should be apportioned across the party spectrum, not in a winner takes all manner, but that's going to be harder.  Both of these corrections are Constitutional and within the power of Congress to enact.</p>
<p>The corruption of the electoral process at both the state and federal levels has made a mockery of our <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Founding%20Fathers%20of%20the%20United%20States">Founding Fathers</ref>, the concept of a Republic, and all because our elected politicians and their appointees are completely lacking in integrity.  They have sold out their public for a bit of gold.  If I am nominated, I will work with Occupy and others (veterans, young people who should have the vote) to SHUT DOWN any <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election%20debates">Presidential debate</ref> that does not have me and other <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20third%20party%20and%20independent%20presidential%20candidates,%202012">third party candidates</ref> fully integrated into anything televised over public air waves.  Litigation has not worked in the past because the courts--including the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Supreme_Court">Supreme Court</ref>---just go along...  What will work is Occupy.  Organized people will defeat organized money every time.  Now is that time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robby Wells</hi>:  I have friends and business colleagues all over the country. I am relying on them, and volunteers to help us gain access on the ballaots in each state. Every state has different guidelines, and I am relying on the people of our country to take a stand for our future by helping us get on every state's ballot. We will be holding a petition drive to make this a reality. The Reform Party is already on the ballot in five states, and has easy access in another 25 states. That leaves us some hard work to gain access on all 50 states, but I believe the people of America are ready to be heard.</p>
</text>
