<text id="autogum_interview_doc1284" title="part9_Edmund White on writing, incest, life and Larry Kramer" shortTile="partedmund-white" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-08" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edmund_White_on_writing%2C_incest%2C_life_and_Larry_Kramer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You have to choose whether to blow up <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">India</ref>, and if you do not choose then they both go.  They are roughly equal in population according to their last censuses; which do you choose?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I think I would blow up China.  I majored in Chinese in college and I was a great admirer of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four%20Great%20Inventions%20of%20ancient%20China">traditional China</ref>, but I don’t really like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/People's%20Republic%20of%20China">modern China</ref> very much and I’ve never had a desire to go there.  I feel like whatever wisdom or culture or civilization they had they pretty much destroyed through the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cultural%20Revolution">Cultural Revolution</ref>, paradoxically, in the Seventies.  I think that will end up being the worst thing that happened in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twentieth%20Century">Twentieth Century</ref>, worse than the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nazi%20Holocaust">Holocaust</ref>.  It killed more people and it destroyed the fabric of their society more than anything.  India never really had anything comparable.  They had <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colonial%20India">the British</ref>, they had the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British%20Raj">Raj</ref>, and that was pretty damn bad, I guess, but it was an ambiguous thing.  It preserved a lot of things and it destroyed others, but it consolidated power in India.  It had been so many different little kingdoms.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So is China.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Yeah, that’s right, although the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese%20empire">Chinese empire</ref> is very old.  There is nothing comparable in India.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s more cohesive now, but China, once the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese%20Communist%20Party">Communist Party</ref> loses its grip on power, it’s going to fall apart.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I don’t think so.  Maybe <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tibet">Tibet</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You have <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islam%20in%20China">Muslim provinces</ref>, you have Tibet.  You have problems in the south with the north.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hong%20Kong">Hong Kong</ref>.  You don’t think that there will be a domino effect that when one goes, the others will go?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I don’t think so.  You know why?  China has been one country.  Obviously Tibet is a different problem.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manchuria">Manchuria</ref> is a different problem.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inner%20Mongolia">Mongolia</ref> is a different problem.  But if you forget all those problems, and you just talk about the central provinces—which are immense—that’s always been one country for almost 4,000 years with an emperor ruling it. Starting with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Han%20Dynasty">Han Dynasty</ref>, which is about the time of Christ, with an elaborate civil service system.  That’s what <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confucius">Confucius</ref> was about.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So the age of the end of the empire won’t touch China?  It won’t be a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soviet%20Union">Soviet Union</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  If you look at Russia and all those places, like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republic%20of%20Georgia">Georgia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uzebekistan">Uzbekistan</ref>, those are all different little countries and it was the Soviet Union that dragged them all together and when the Soviet Union croaked they all fell apart.  I think China traditionally was unified.</p>
<head id="On_his_intimate_relationships">On his intimate relationships</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you regard as the lowest depth of misery?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I think I felt it about three years ago.  I was dropped by a guy I was really in love with, and it took me back to my late twenties when that had last happened.  I didn’t even think I was capable of that kind of suffering anymore, but I just cried every day for a month and all the time.  I went to a shrink then, and he said, “I can’t even work with you, you’re so depressed.”</p>
</text>
