<text id="autogum_interview_doc1079" title="part0_Vanity Fair contributing editor Craig Unger on the Bush family feud, neoconservatives and the Christian right" shortTile="partvanity-fair-contributing" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2015-08-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vanity_Fair_contributing_editor_Craig_Unger_on_the_Bush_family_feud%2C_neoconservatives_and_the_Christian_right" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Vanity Fair contributing editor Craig Unger on the Bush family feud, neoconservatives and the Christian right</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 12, 2007</hi></p>
<p>In <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dalai_Lama's_representative_talks_about_China,_Tibet,_Shugden_and_the_next_Dalai_Lama">a recent interview</ref> with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/14th%20Dalai%20Lama">Dalai Lama</ref>’s Representative to the Americas, Tashi Wangdi, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> remarked to him that Americans have trouble relating to centuries-long conflicts that exist between peoples around the world, including those in Asia.  Many Asian countries dislike each other tremendously, and the conflict over Tibet is just one enduring multi-national battle.</p>
<p>According to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vanity%20Fair">Vanity Fair</ref></hi> contributing editor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Craig%20Unger">Craig Unger</ref>, it is not that Americans do not have these deep-seeded conflicts; it is that they do not remember them and thus have no context in which to see them as they resurface in our political culture.  </p>
<p>On the same day he spoke to the Dalai Lama’s representative, Shankbone sat down with Unger, author of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20Times%20Best%20Seller%20list"><hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi> best-seller</ref> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House%20of%20Bush,%20House%20of%20Saud">House of Bush, House of Saud</ref></hi>.   In his new book, <hi rend="italic">The Fall of the House of Bush</hi>, Unger attempts to fill in some of the blanks of an epochal narrative in American politics.  Using a mix of painstaking research, interviews with cultural and political leaders and delving into previously classified records to come up with some overview of how America has arrived at this particular political moment.   </p>
<p>To make sense of such complicated history, Unger draws upon three themes:  He illustrates the conflict within the modern Republican Party via the oedipal conflict between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20W.%20Bush">George W. Bush</ref> and his father, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20George%20H.W.%20Bush">George H.W. Bush</ref>.  Things are not well within the House of Bush.  Bush Jr. has not only shut out his father and his allies from his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Administration%20of%20George%20W.%20Bush">administration</ref>—something <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Woodward">Bob Woodward</ref> discovered in his interviews with the President—but he also appointed many of his father’s bitterest enemies to key cabinet positions.</p>
<p>Unger’s second theme draws upon this Bush family feud: many of Bush Sr.’s foes happen to be leaders of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neoconservative">neoconservative movement</ref>, who had been working against the President’s father since the 1970’s.  Back then the neoconservatives did not have a base of political support within the Republican Party, which brings Unger to his third theme: the marriage between the neoconservatives and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian%20right">Christian right</ref> to create a formidable ideological block.</p>
<p>Unger is a Fellow at the Center for Law and Security at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20University%20School%20of%20Law">NYU’s  School of Law</ref>.  In addition to his work at <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vanity%20Fair%20(magazine)">Vanity Fair</ref></hi>, he is a former editor-in-chief of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston%20Magazine">Boston Magazine</ref></hi>, and former Deputy Editor of the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20Observer">New York Observer</ref></hi>.  A journalist of the old school who believes in verifying his sources’ veracity, Unger illuminates the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Republican%20Party">Republican Party</ref>’s ideological struggle between the old and the new and traces its history for those who do know it.</p>
<p>Unger disputes the recent assertion by <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20The%20New%20York%20Times"> The New York Times</ref></hi> that these forces are dead; they are thriving.  Below is <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>’s interview with Craig Unger about his book, <hi rend="italic">The Fall of the House of Bush</hi>.  </p>
</text>
