<text id="autogum_interview_doc899" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Mike Lebowitz, Chairman of the Modern Whig Party" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-12" dateModified="2009-03-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mike_Lebowitz%2C_Chairman_of_the_Modern_Whig_Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Mike Lebowitz, Chairman of the Modern Whig Party</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 13, 2008</hi></p>
<p>In the United States, there are two major political parties; the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Republican%20Party">Republican</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Democratic%20Party">Democratic</ref>. However, there are several other minor - commonly referred to as "third" - parties. One of these is the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modern%20Whig%20Party">Modern Whig Party</ref>, which has been steadily increasing in popularity over recent months. </p>
<p>Last week, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter Joseph Ford was able to speak with MWP Chairman Mike Lebowitz about how his party was formed, what it stands for, and why you should consider joining. The interview can be read below.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> (Joseph Ford): What does The Modern Whig Party stand for?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chairman Lebowitz:</hi> The Modern Whig Party is unique in that it minimizes traditional ideology and instead stands for common sense solutions and rational thought. In fact, this grassroots movement is a non-fringe, mainstream effort designed to cater to those individuals who find themselves cherry-picking between traditional Republican ideals and also traditional Democratic ideals. The fact remains that most people agree with various aspects of both major parties, but one or two issues or reasons ultimately compels them to identify with a specific political party. The Modern Whig Party offers a home for these independent-minded individuals. The general platform of the Modern Whig Party relates to fiscal responsibility, strong national defense and bold social progression.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: How old is your party? How many members does it currently have?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chairman Lebowitz:</hi> The age of the party depends on how one views our organization. The "Whig" name has been associated with American history and tradition since the early 19th Century. The old Whig Party was mainstream and middle-of-the-road during its time. It are those general aspects of rational thinking and common sense that we adopt in terms of the old Whig Party. But at the same time, we do stress that we are the "Modern" Whig Party. We recognize that we live in a different time. In that regard, the Modern Whig Party basic infrastructure was organized in 2007, and ultimately went public in April 2008.</p>
<p>Currently, the Modern Whig Party has well over 10,000 members. We realize this is a modest number in the grand scheme of things, but considering how quickly we have inspired these members to sign on offers evidence that this movement has a chance to catch on and grow. The Modern Whig Party was originally founded by Iraq/Afghanistan veterans as a veterans' advocacy organization and our growth has occurred with minimal funding and can be regarded as a truly grassroots effort. It also is important to note that roughly 6,500 of these members are affiliated with the military. Our membership expanded so quickly based almost exclusively on word-of-mouth through the military ranks. Instead of trying to attract people to our Web site, we decided to come to them. What happened was that military members would send emails to their friends, who in turn would forward these emails to others. These emails described our movement and provided a means of merely contacting the national party, providing some basic information and ultimately becoming a member. Word of mouth among the military eventually caught the Pentagon's attention due to the fact that the military is supposed to be apolitical, and the Modern Whig Party was ultimately featured in the Military Times newspapers. We have since expanded with members coming from all walks of life -- military and non-military alike.</p>
</text>
