<text id="autogum_interview_doc1215" title="part0_Canada's York West (Ward 8) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-york" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-10-19" dateModified="2007-06-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_York_West_%28Ward_8%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Canada's York West (Ward 8) city council candidates speak</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 30, 2006</hi></p>
<p>On November 13, Torontonians will be heading to the polls to vote for their ward's councillor and for mayor. Among Toronto's ridings is York West (Ward 8). One candidate responded to Wikinews' requests for an interview. This ward's candidates include Hau Dang Tan, <hi rend="bold">Garry Green</hi>, Peter Li Preti (incumbent), Abdulhaq Omar, Anthony Perruzza, and Ramnarine Tiwari.</p>
<p>For more information on the election, read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto%20municipal%20election,%202006">Toronto municipal election, 2006</ref>.</p>
<head id="Garry_Green">Garry Green</head>
<p>34-years-old, Garry Green is a Contracted Services Specialist (employment programs), Toronto District School Board.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi></p>
<p>1. Housing: I wish to re-design Edgley Village to make it safer. Former Mayor of Toronto and former head of MTHA (now TCHC) John Sewell proposed the redevelopment 30 years ago and it has died off due to a lack of advocacy. I will get this back on the map and get it done.</p>
<p>I also want to ensure that all people in the ward live in housing that safe, well maintained and that they know they have a champion if they need help. I will be there to listen and act on their behalf. Adequate housing is critical if we wish to raise healthy children and if we want to put people in a position to become employable.</p>
<p>2. Employment</p>
<p>I have worked in the employment field for several years and wish to use this experience to help people in our community. I have helped youth, newcomers and even seniors gain employment and it would be my pleasure to help the residents of ward 8. I will encourage employers to hire locally, I will try my best to build a mega-hospital in our ward and I will have an internship program open for youth and newcomers out of my office.</p>
<p>3. Childcare</p>
<p>The local councillor voted against childcare subsidies in 2003. I have one young child and one on the way in November so I know the importance of getting children off to a healthy start. I will fight for families; not vote against them.</p>
<p>4. Crime</p>
<p>I feel that if we improve the housing, employment and childcare needs of residents, crime will be significantly decreased in coming years. The community will also benefit from far more positive press but we first need to heal on the inside before the external forces (press) are supportive.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?
Housing. How can we ask people to go out and get a job when their home environment is unsuitable?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am also concerned with the growth of development in my ward. We need a councillor free from the strings that come with accepting dollars from developers. I have vowed not to accept dollars from developers or labour because I want to act in the best interests of my community at all times. I live in ward 8, will raise my family in ward 8 and will always look at the impact of all decisions on our community.</p>
</text>
