<text id="autogum_interview_doc102" title="part2_Cold as ice: Wikinews interviews Marymegan Daly on unusual new sea anemone" shortTile="partcold-ice-wikinews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-01-20" dateModified="2015-01-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cold_as_ice%3A_Wikinews_interviews_Marymegan_Daly_on_unusual_new_sea_anemone" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>Daly explained how she obtained these images of the anemone's anatomy. Image: Daly et al.</caption></figure>
<p>Just knowing a whole lot about a single species isn't very useful, even if that animal is as special as these clearly are — we need to know what about them is different and thus related to living in this strange way. The only way to get at what's different is to make comparisons with close relatives.  We can start that side of the work now, anticipating having more beasts in the future.</p>
<p>In terms of their glow, I suspect that it's not theirs — although luminescence is common in anemone relatives, they don't usually make light themselves.  They do make a host of florescent proteins, and these may interact with the light of the ROV to give that gorgeous glow.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What analysis did you perform on the specimens and what equipment was used?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi> I used a dissecting scope to look at the animal's external anatomy and overall body organization (magnification of 60X).  I embedded a few of the animals in wax and then cut them into very thin slices using a <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/microtome">microtome</ref>, mounted the slices on microscope slides, stained the slices to enhance contrast, and then looked at those slides under a <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/compound%20microscope">compound microscope</ref> (that's how I got the pictures of the muscles etc in the paper).  I used that same compound scope to look at squashed bits of tissue to see the stinging capsules (=<ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/nematocyst">nematocysts</ref>).</p>
<p>I compared the things I saw under the 'scopes to what had been published on other species in this group.  This step seems trivial, but it is really the most important part!  By comparing my observations to what my colleagues and predecessors had found, I  figured out what group it belongs to, and was able to determine that within that group, it was a new species.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  It was three years between recovery of specimens and final publication, why did it take so long?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi> You mean, how did we manage to make it all happen so quickly, right?:) It was about two years from when Frank sent me specimens to when we got the paper out.  Some of that time was just lost time — I had other projects in the queue that I needed to finish. Once we figured out what it was, we played a lot of manuscript email tag, which can be challenging and time consuming given the differing schedules that folks keep in terms of travel, field work, etc. Manuscript review and processing took about four months.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What sort of difficulties were posed by the unorthodox preservatives used, and what additional work might be possible on a specimen with intact DNA?</p>
</text>
