<text id="autogum_interview_doc1365" title="part3_Teräsbetoni frontman J. Ahola on representing Finland at Eurovision 2008 & more" shortTile="partterasbetoni-frontman" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-03-26" dateModified="2017-05-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ter%C3%A4sbetoni_frontman_J._Ahola_on_representing_Finland_at_Eurovision_2008_%26_more" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Because what we do is true and pure. We come as we are and play from our hearts.
That seems to be pretty rare in nowadays music, especially in pop genre where glamour and glitter seems to be essential. …And our song is good, too!</p>
<head id="The_new_album">The new album</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How has the reaction to your latest album been?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Well, it reached the position number 1 in Finland’s album chart. Most of our fans have thanked us for the best album so far. I’ve seen few reviews and they weren’t too flattering. On the other hand, they’ve never been ‘cause most of the reviews tend to discuss our looks, image and the lyrics. But it’s all right, that kind of criticism have never affected to our listeners.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What sort of things are the songs on this album about?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> We are still fighting for metal music, so there are traditional songs about playing this music and calling all our brothers and sisters to get together. The other subjects vary from nightmares to galley slavery, from possession to burden of believing in your cause etc.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Talk us through the writing process for the album.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> This time we had much more time to write new songs than we did with our second album “Vaadimme Metallia”. On the other hand the recording process’ schedule was more shattered than it was with V.M. </p>
<p>The cycle of writing must be a bit different with each writer, but for example I might come up with an idea of a title of the song or just a guitar riff . From there I start to develop the song. Mostly it comes out pretty easy. Sometimes there’s just a special mood that evolve to a song. When the rough version of song is in my mind, I record a demo of it. While recording I start hearing how the song should be sang and played. I also arrange the song in the demo phase. I  make the demos ready &amp; polished and send them to band members, A&amp;R and producer. I believe A. Järvinen and V. Rantanen, song writers as well, work pretty much the same way.</p>
<p>At this point we give each other comments and critcism about the songs we’ve written. With the help of the  producer and A &amp; R we choose the songs that should be recorded on the album. Of course the whole process is more complex but basically the it goes like that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Did all the recording, production etc go smoothly?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Yeah it did. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hiili%20Hiilesmaa">Hiili Hiilesmaa</ref>, our producer, and the band knew each other already and we had discussions about the sound and direction of the new album. The working habits  were familiar to us from the Vaadimme Metallia-sessions, so from that point of view things went smoothly. Our guitarists actually did some solos and backing vocals at home! I think that’s a great example of relaxed way of producing.</p>
</text>
