<text id="autogum_interview_doc534" title="part7_Billy West, voice of Ren and Stimpy, Futurama, on the rough start that shaped his life" shortTile="partbilly-west-voice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2013-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Billy_West%2C_voice_of_Ren_and_Stimpy%2C_Futurama%2C_on_the_rough_start_that_shaped_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think that’s had any lasting effect on you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>   Well, I can now get crazy without being angry or raging because I know how to do it. Everything you do has to come from something real. You have to tap into something. Otherwise, there’s nothing to grab hold of if you’re a watcher or a listener or whatever. There’s nothing for you there. It’s no fun for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/audience">audience</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They say that all great comedians typically have extraordinary tragedy in their lives, and they develop their humor as a response to it.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Yes, but I developed mine a lot of the times to comfort my mom. Because she saw the way I was being treated. Not so much my brothers, but I was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/whipping%20boy">whipping boy</ref> and she would just be reduced to tears a lot of times, and I would come in and say stuff, and I would put out little <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stand-up%20comedy">bits</ref> just to pull her out of it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Even though you were hurting, it would hurt you to see her hurting over you.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Yes. And you know, I could take a beating. I finally learned how to just galvanize myself where you just totally like disassociate and your body can sit there and get smacked around and punched or whatever and your mind is a million miles away.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What made you the whipping boy?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Well my dad was very very angry. He was abused as a child and he lived in a matriarchal situation with his mother and her sister and then her mother and there were all these big German ….  I don’t know, like real staunch [people], angry and punishment-inclined. He liked to dish out punishment ….</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What would make you the one that he would unleash that upon as opposed to your brothers?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Because I could do little things that he seemed to be threatened by.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like what?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  I could draw. He was an artist. I could pick up a pen and start drawing immediately. He was a musician, a drummer. Then, I learned to play guitar when I was ten years old. He didn’t sit right with any of these things. Plus, he was very jealous of me because my mother loved me more than him.</p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ren%20Hoek">Ren Hoek</ref> from <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ren%20and%20Stimpy">Ren and Stimpy</ref></hi>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  An <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/oedipal">oedipal</ref> issue?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Well, yeah, but it happened from Day One. He resented eventually the fact that I was born 'cause I took away his mommy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is your relationship with your brothers like? Did they see this going on? Did they feel bad for you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Only my other brother. He's dead now. He bore witness to an awful lot of stuff and he, himself, was the brunt of an awful lot of stuff that I teased him and bothered him, 'cause it trickled down.</p>
</text>
