<text id="autogum_interview_doc251" title="part9_Dr. Joseph Merlino on sexuality, insanity, Freud, fetishes and apathy" shortTile="partdr-joseph-merlino" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-04" dateModified="2013-09-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dr._Joseph_Merlino_on_sexuality%2C_insanity%2C_Freud%2C_fetishes_and_apathy" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  I can't say based upon my practice; I keep a very small <hi rend="italic">talking</hi> practice, because of my other work.  Based on my own personal engagement with the outside world, I think people are very frustrated, annoyed, mistrustful, and non-believing of anything government says, but not to the point of doing anything about it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you mean when you say 'doing anything about it'?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  Being activists about it.  I don't know if it's learned helplessness or what.  There's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/apathy">apathy</ref>.  One of the most energized moments I experienced in years was when there were the large protests of marchers down the east side to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20Nations">U.N.</ref>  I long for the play <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hair%20(play)">Hair</ref></hi> to come back.  It's 40 years old now.  I don't understand why it's not back on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broadway%20theatre">Broadway</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  We have been in this war for four years.  Is it important to discuss it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  I think a lot of us lead more and more isolated existences in the midst of millions of people.  We're on our cell phone.  We're on our Blackberry.  We're on our computer.  It's all disjointed in some kind of a way.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think people are putting their heads in the sand, or do you think it is too much for people to process what is happening?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  I think people feel impotent.  Look, people came out and did <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20general%20elections,%202006">this massive election</ref>, turned over Congress, the House, the Senate, and nothing has changed.  I think people are feeling that if the vote is the thing is going to change society, and it's not even doing that...  Or you have to be a multi-millionaire to run for the office.  With a clean record--who has that?  The jury system, and mistrust of that of whether it is bought off, who gets justice and who doesn't get justice.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But we respond to it.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  Until the Mets lose a game, and then we are on to that.  We are trained to have very short attention spans.  We have become isolated and disjointed from one another, except when we have to mix.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you think that affects personality development, that our interactions today are so two-dimensional?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JM:</hi>  It affects a lot of things.  Relationships, how we get along with each other.  You look at something like 9/11 or a disaster, and how that galvanizes and brings people together and how short-lived that is.  Then it goes back down again.  It's as if we constantly need a jolt of that magnitude to shake us out of our complacency in the ways we live and interact.  I think it's sad, and it's a concern.</p>
</text>
