<text id="autogum_interview_doc1346" title="part1_G20 protests: Inside a labour march" shortTile="partg-protests-inside" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-04-03" dateModified="2014-05-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/G20_protests%3A_Inside_a_labour_march" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>The Youth Fight For Jobs assembles. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Killing_Vector">Killing Vector</ref>.</caption></figure><p>In London around 11am the march assembles on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camberwell%20Green">Camberwell Green</ref>. About 250 people are here, from many parts of Britain; I meet marchers from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newcastle-upon-Tyne">Newcastle</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manchester">Manchester</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leicester">Leicester</ref>, and especially organized-labor stronghold <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheffield">Sheffield</ref>. The sky is grey but the atmosphere is convivial; five members of London's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metropolitan%20Police%20Department">Metropolitan Police</ref> are present, and they're all smiling. Most marchers are young, some as young as high school age, but a few are older; some teachers, including members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lewisham">Lewisham</ref> and Sheffield chapters of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Union%20of%20Teachers">National Union of Teachers</ref>, are carrying banners in support of their students.</p>
<hi rend="bold">Gordon Brown's a Tory/He wears a Tory hat/And when he saw our uni fees/He said 'I'll double that!'</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Youth Fight for Jobs, chant #5</p>
<p>Stewards hand out sheets of paper with the words to call-and-response chants on them. Some are youth-oriented and education-oriented, like the jaunty "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gordon%20Brown">Gordon Brown</ref>'s a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conservative%20Party%20(UK)">Tory</ref>/He wears a Tory hat/And when he saw our <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Higher%20education%20in%20the%20United%20Kingdom">uni</ref> fees/He said 'I'll double that!'" (sung to the tune of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lonnie%20Donegan">Lonnie Donegan</ref> song "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/My%20Old%20Man's%20a%20Dustman">My Old Man's a Dustman</ref>"); but many are standbys of organized labour, including the infamous "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Workers%20of%20the%20world,%20unite!">workers of the world, unite!</ref>". It also outlines the goals of the protest, as "demands": "The right to a decent job for all, with a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/living%20wage">living wage</ref> of at least <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UK%20pound">£</ref>8 and hour. No to cheap labour apprenticeships! for all apprenticeships to pay at least the minimum wage, with a job guaranteed at the end. No to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Top-up%20fees">university fees</ref>. support the campaign to defeat fees." Another steward with a megaphone and a bright red t-shirt talks the assembled protesters through the basics of call-and-response chanting. </p>
<figure><caption>Police escorted the march along the entire length of its route. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Killing_Vector">Killing Vector</ref>.</caption></figure><p>Finally the march gets underway, traveling through the London boroughs of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camberwell">Camberwell</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southwark">Southwark</ref>. Along the route of the march more police follow along, escorting and guiding the march and watching it carefully, while a police van with flashing lights clears the route in front of it. On the surface the atmosphere is enthusiastic, but everyone freezes for a second as a siren is heard behind them; it turns out to be a passing ambulance.</p>
<figure><caption>The march enters the City of London. The top of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/30%20St%20Mary%20Axe">The Gherkin</ref>, a symbol of London's financial center, can be seen in the background. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Killing_Vector">Killing Vector</ref>.</caption></figure><p>Crossing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southwark%20Bridge">Southwark Bridge</ref>, the march enters the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City%20of%20London">City of London</ref>, the comparably small but dense area containing London's financial and economic heart. Although one recipient of the protesters' anger is the Bank of England, the march does not stop in the City, only passing through the streets by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London%20Exchange">London Exchange</ref>. Tourists on buses and businessmen in pinstripe suits record snippets of the march on their mobile phones as it passes them; as it goes past a branch of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HSBC">HSBC</ref> the employees gather at the glass store front and watch nervously. The time in the City is brief; rather than continue into the very centre of London the march turns east and, passing the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tower%20of%20London">Tower of London</ref>, proceeds into the poor, largely immigrant neighbourhoods of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tower%20Hamlets">Tower Hamlets</ref>.</p>
</text>
