<text id="autogum_interview_doc960" title="part5_Taliban resurgent in Pakistan on enforcement of Sharia law" shortTile="parttaliban-resurgent" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-03-20" dateModified="2019-01-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Taliban_resurgent_in_Pakistan_on_enforcement_of_Sharia_law" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Even the US Embassy is protected by a contingent of the FC! That goes to show their trustworthiness and discipline.</p>
<p>The "tribal" Pashtuns in the FATA are not educated or trained and hence not employable right now. I propose that we fund directly the Director of Emigrants, Mr. Azhar Arbab in Islamabad, to set up training facilities in Concrete laying, iron work, pipe work, welding etc, which would then qualify these tribesmen to obtain jobs in the Gulf. As such we would remove them from the scene altogether. They would not be available in the labor pool to the Taliban or anyone else. I might add here, that a number of these individuals have very high innate intelligence, which is one reason they make formidable foes. </p>
<p>Now the central reason why the NWFP ought to do this is because they are themselves most affected by the scourge of Talibanization. They are highly motivated in carrying out these policies because it is to their own benefit. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How many men does the FC field currently?</hi></p>
<p>The FC currently has about 23,000 men in total.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How much do they get paid?</hi></p>
<p>They are paid the equivalent of $60 per month per person -Pak Rupees 3665, where Rs61= $1. 
They do have some fringe benefits but life is very spartan for these soldiers. </p>
<p>What the US could get in return is a huge bang for a buck, no pun intended. </p>
<p>I think we ought to double the number of these soldiers with one proviso that the FC maintains its high standards of recruits.</p>
<p>Compare this with our costs in the War against Terror; just Halliburton’s bills will have you reeling. I think that it would be foolish, NOT to do this. </p>
<p>The Frontier Constabulary is an Institution with a long and glorious history within the Frontier Province.</p>
<p>The recruits come strictly from the tribes of the various FATA and so they are very familiar with the people, the bad guys the terrain.</p>
<p>They speak the Pashto dialect of the locals. The Pashto language has many dialects, and you can tell where someone is from based on which dialect he speaks. So if you do not speak the correct dialect, you are immediately identified as an outsider. This is one reason why these tribes are impossible to penetrate, there are other reasons as well, that are beyond the scope of the current discussion.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the FC help prevent attacks like the suicide bombing attempt on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aftab%20Ahmad%20Khan%20Sherpao">Sherpao</ref> in Charsadda last weekend?</hi></p>
<p>In essence your question is how can <hi rend="italic">anyone</hi> prevent a suicide attack? 
And frankly if I knew the answer to that I think the US military - and several other groups - would be knocking on my door. I think the Israeli Army has had the most experience with this sort of thing. The suicide bombing as a tactical weapon was invented by the Tamil Tigers in Sri Lanka, and even today in terms of statistics they use it in far greater numbers.</p>
</text>
