<text id="autogum_interview_doc542" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Jeff Jacobsen, creator of LisaMcPherson.org" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-12" dateModified="2012-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jeff_Jacobsen%2C_creator_of_LisaMcPherson.org" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Jeff Jacobsen, creator of LisaMcPherson.org</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 19, 2008</hi></p>
<p>On Sunday, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed creator of memorial site LisaMcPherson.org, former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisa%20McPherson%20Trust">Lisa McPherson Trust</ref> employee and long time <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientology">Scientology</ref> critic Jeff Jacobsen. </p>
<p>LisaMcPherson.org is a memorial site created in 1997 containing information on her death and the resulting legal case against the Church of Scientology.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisa%20McPherson">Lisa McPherson</ref> died in 1995 while in the care of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church%20of%20Scientology">Church of Scientology</ref>. After a car accident, she became mentally unstable. Scientologists removed her from the hospital and placed her in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Introspection%20Rundown">Introspection Rundown</ref>, she died 17 days later while still in care of the Church. She was used as an icon during <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Project%20Chanology">Project Chanology</ref>, the protest of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church%20of%20Scientology">Church of Scientology</ref> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anonymous%20(group)">Anonymous</ref>. Protesters were pictured with signs that said "Remember Lisa McPherson" and "Ask Scientology Why Lisa McPherson Died", other protesters had posters with her picture on it.</p>
<head id="The_Interview">The Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Give a short description of yourself and what you do outside of protesting Scientology.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jeff Jacobsen</hi>: I'm a Political Science senior at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arizona%20State%20University">Arizona State</ref> right now.  Full-time student. I'm 52, from South Dakota Was in a cult age 16-22 (not Scientology). Got a BA in Religious Studies in 1984. Worked at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisa%20McPherson%20Trust">Lisa McPherson Trust</ref> until it closed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : What was your job at the trust?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: Librarian, and researcher. So I helped the people "downstairs" when they needed documents or whatever.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : I see from your website that you list your "cult experience" as your once belonging to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20Pentecostal%20Church%20International">United Pentecostal Church</ref>. Do you consider all organized religions as "cults"?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: No.  Not all religions are cults. The word is loaded but I think still useful. A cult is totalitarian, has an us vs. them mentality, and thinks they are the sole keepers of The Truth And uses deception, takes advantage of members.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : How do you finance your activities in this area?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: Myself.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : What happened to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Minton">Bob Minton</ref>, your former chief financial supporter? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: That's a sore point for many, but I'll give my version. I think he wasn't prepared for the backlash he'd get from Scientology. So finally he caved into the pressure that Scientology is so good at applying, and to get out from under them he agreed to certain things, he changed his testimony in court to be helpful to the church, he stopped all anti-scientology activity and he has left the scene.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : How powerful is the Church of Scientology in your opinion?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">J.J.</hi>: Their power now comes from their money. I don't believe they have much recruiting ability, nor that many members (maybe 100,000 worldwide.) Also their ruthlessness gives them power. But I do believe they are on the decline.</p>
</text>
