<text id="autogum_interview_doc605" title="part10_Wikinews interviews John Wolfe, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-19" dateModified="2013-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_John_Wolfe%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>So we need to have work for people and to do that we have to keep capital in the community and we can't do that if we're going to continue to underwrite the speculation. If we're going to use what capital we have to underwrite the speculation right at big banks. I'm talking about JP Morgan, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goldman%20Sachs">Goldman Sachs</ref>. I'm talking about Bank of America, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Citibank">Citibank</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wells%20Fargo">Wells Fargo</ref>, JP Morgan and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morgan%20Stanley">Morgan Stanley</ref>. Everyone of those require billions of dollars in taxpayer bailouts, maybe even more. They got some bailouts from Federal Reserve money ... and what do they do, they hurt the economy. To cover their own losses and stupidity, they take that money at one third of one percent, and turn around and sponsor credit cards, usually with 16 to 24 percent interest rates. I mean, that's backed up by the government, we're actually paying the banks to give us. I mean it's crazy and I don't understand why we're doing that. And we need a president, again this is not Rocket Science, you can spell this out with a chart. I mean, I could sit here with a chart, put all this information up in probably 30 or 40 minutes in a national press conference and I guarantee you 70 percent of the people would approve of what I said, and we'd have a whole new discourse in this country. We'd have a whole new atmosphere. And that's what I'd do if elected. I'd make people see what's going on, open their eyes a little bit.  The president doesn't lead people. Without presidential leadership, the people will flounder.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">At this point, do you believe that the federal budget can be balanced?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: No I don't think it can right now. I think that if you cut spending marginally right now, all you'd do is send the economy into a recession. You eventually got to work toward a balance, but that has to be based on economic growth and not just taking away people's entitlements. People have paid for their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social%20Security%20(United%20States)">Social Security</ref>. People have paid for their <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medicare%20(United%20States)">Medicare</ref>. That's not welfare. It's not even an entitlement. What it is is a repayment.  People who've paid into Social Security, their money goes and they buy bonds, just like foreign creditors buying treasury bonds. They get paid back on principle and interest over time the government guarantees it. It's no different for Social Security recipients. So they're just like any other debtor or any other creditor. They're paid money that they're dued.  We bought our Social Security, it's not welfare, it's not even an entitlement, it's a repayment.</p>
</text>
