<text id="autogum_interview_doc1373" title="part5_One year on: IFALPA's representative to ICAO, pilot and lawyer on ongoing prosecution of Garuda Indonesia Flight 200 pilot" shortTile="partone-year--ifalpas" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-03-08" dateModified="2014-04-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/One_year_on%3A_IFALPA%27s_representative_to_ICAO%2C_pilot_and_lawyer_on_ongoing_prosecution_of_Garuda_Indonesia_Flight_200_pilot" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you believe there ever will be another investigation?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> No.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  If a full investigation into Mr Komar's psychology conclusively found that he was of sound mind at the time, would that change IFALPA's stance on the prosecution?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> No. we are not interested so much in a sound mind as we are the reactions of a professional airman to a certain set of stimuli. Where, as seems to be the case here, the reactions are totally unresponsive, it is not sufficient to give a glib answer, either “tunnel vision” or “psychological problems”. The industry needs to understand the mechanism so that it can be identified and remediated prior to it once again causing an accident.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Does the fact that this prosecution has gone ahead indicate to you that changes in the law may be required?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> Time will tell as the prosecution is continuing.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  To what extent is a pilot protected by law in event of an accident caused by his or her negligent conduct?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> The issue that ICAO, IFALPA, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International%20Air%20Transport%20Association">IATA FSF</ref> and every other serious observer has addressed is the use of the word negligent. Ordinary negligence can be attempting to get it right and not succeeding. The level of negligence that should trigger prosecution would have a component of intent to either do harm or to disregard the high probability that harm would occur. This is variously described as gross negligence or willful and wanton misconduct. To prosecute someone for attempting to deal with a particular situation and getting it wrong adds nothing to the safety mix.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Would you still get into an aircraft that you knew Mr Komar was piloting, assuming he was confirmed to be of sound mind at the time?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> We can assume that a proper training and evaluation program will make certain, to the highest degree possible, that all flight crew members are fully fit to perform their duties. A proper explanation in this instance would have assisted Airline training departments in fulfilling this mission.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How big do you believe the impact would be if Mr Komar were convicted?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> On whom?</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The effect on safety in general.</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Gideon Ewers:</hi> I think I can answer that.</item></list></p>
<p>The important question to ask is “Will the conviction of Capt Komar improve air safety?”  Since in this case there has been no full, independent and complete technical investigation into all the events surrounding the accident the answer to this question would have to be no. All that is known following the report is what happened…not WHY it happened. Furthermore, the prosecution itself is flawed since without a full investigation it is hard to see how willful negligence can be demonstrated but that is a digression from the core issue.</p>
</text>
