<text id="autogum_interview_doc997" title="part0_'Big Brother' contestant Parker Somerville sounds off about the show and his aspirations" shortTile="partbig-brother-contestant" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-25" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/%27Big_Brother%27_contestant_Parker_Somerville_sounds_off_about_the_show_and_his_aspirations" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>'Big Brother' contestant Parker Somerville sounds off about the show and his aspirations</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 25, 2008</hi></p>
<p>In the past two months, Parker Somerville, a videographer for the website TMZ.com, transitioned from an average guy leading an ordinary life, to living in an extraordinary voyeuristic existence, and back again to the beginning. Simply put, it was a transition from reality to reality, with a two-week detour in reality television. Somerville was a former contestant on the CBS <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/reality%20television">reality TV</ref> staple <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big%20Brother%209%20(U.S.)">Big Brother</ref></hi>, currently in its ninth installment. </p>
<p>Evicted on Day 14, Somerville hoped to have another chance to play the game, but came in second in the special "America's Choice" poll to bring back a former HouseGuest (the poll results were eventually not used at all and nobody was brought back). Now freed from a three-week sequester, Somerville was interviewed by <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:TheCustomOfLife">Mike Halterman</ref> and he discussed his thoughts on <hi rend="italic">Big Brother</hi>, how he and his fellow HouseGuests were portrayed and received, and what he plans to do now that his experience is, for the most part, over.</p>
<p>Somerville will return to <hi rend="italic">Big Brother</hi> on finale night in five weeks. Please check your local listings for time and channel. <hi rend="italic">Big Brother</hi> airs on <ref target="http://www.cbs.com/primetime/big_brother_9/">CBS</ref> in the United States, <ref target="http://www.canada.com/globaltv/globalshows/bigbrother/index.html">Global</ref> in Canada, and E4 in the United Kingdom.</p>
<head id="Starting_in_reality">Starting in reality</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: So, you've been billed on the show as a paparazzi for TMZ.com. Tell us exactly what you do at your job. What was your most exciting work-related celebrity sighting?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Parker Somerville</hi>: It's pretty exciting, and also at times it can be pretty boring.  I simply wait outside of major Hollywood hot spots, and get sound bytes and reactions from celebrities and public figures. Sometimes it can be awkward, but for the most part, it's pretty entertaining. My most funny/exciting work-related celebrity encounter was with <ref target="http://www.brightcove.tv/title.jsp?title=1341027097">Wesley Snipes</ref>. He had us running up and down the street for like 5-10 minutes! And he was in a full suit! How random?!  It was exhausting, but funny as hell!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: How much exposure did you have to Big Brother before you were selected to go on the show?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PS</hi>: I was never really an avid watcher of Big Brother before I was selected to become one of the HouseGuests. I knew about the show, but just didn't make time to watch it. I can count on one hand how many times I actually watched the show, and that was just because nothing else was on TV at the moment. Before I went in the house, I did watch Seasons 3 and 6 just to kind of familiarize myself with the game. I must say, it's pretty interesting and I may watch future seasons.</p>
</text>
