<text id="autogum_interview_doc306" title="part12_Shimon Peres discusses the future of Israel" shortTile="partshimon-peres" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-06" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shimon_Peres_discusses_the_future_of_Israel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>The office of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President%20of%20Israel">President of Israel</ref> in JerusalemImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Do you hope to have another term as president?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Oh, maybe next time I shall go and be a shepherd or a poet.  Why go back to government? [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] I think you are already seen as both of those things.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Yes, I’m not orthodox about it and I’m not particular.  You know, once I was free of administration, I discovered the great advantage of being free.  And I feel free.  Most of my life, I was quite controversial.  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  Now I know I am tremendously popular.  I don’t know what is better, to be controversial and fight or to be popular and becoming a little bit…</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: It is unique that when you look at your standing 20 years ago versus now, it’s so different--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: When was better? [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] Well...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: I think 20 years ago when I was fighting.  What do you need popularity?  Popularity is like perfume: nice to smell, dangerous to drink.  You don’t drink it.  Why are people against you?  Because you are against the status quo.  Why was I unpopular?  I didn’t commit any crime in my life.  The only crime I committed was to be a little bit ahead of time.  And if this is the reason for being controversial, maybe the reason is better than the result.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: What do you look at as your greatest legacy in your career?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: I am bored by it.  My greatest legacy...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: What pops into your head right away when I asked that? [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: [Laughs] It is what I’m going to do tomorrow.  What I did yesterday, for me it’s boring and I’m very careful not to talk to my children about it because they will be bored.  So why should I?  My mind is set to see what will happen tomorrow.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: You don’t speak to your children about the things you’ve done in you life or your grandchildren?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: No I learn from them what they are doing.  Why should I bore them?  They know more about the computers and the internet and all; I am taking advantage.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: They probably know <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: My children are my parents because they teach me the future.  Traditionally, I should have taught them, but I think it’s a waste of time.  Why should I?  Why should I load their minds with what I may think are heroic stories?  They have their own heroism which is now giving birth to new possibilities, to a new age.  So my time?  They don’t ask and I don’t bother them.  I imagine they know because [the press writes] about me negatively so much, that they can not escape. [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  But they know one thing:  I don’t complain. I generally never complain.  They know we have an honest life.  So whatever people are writing they do not care, because they know the truth.</p>
</text>
