<text id="autogum_interview_doc1229" title="part0_Interview with John Sanderson, Regional Council candidate for Wards 3 & 4 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-john" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-11-03" dateModified="2007-06-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_John_Sanderson%2C_Regional_Council_candidate_for_Wards_3_%26_4_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Interview with John Sanderson, Regional Council candidate for Wards 3 &amp; 4 in Brampton, Canada</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 3, 2006</hi></p>
<p>The upcoming <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brampton%20municipal%20election,%202006">2006 Brampton municipal election</ref>, to be held November 13, features an array of candidates looking to represent their wards in city council or the council of the Peel Region. The candidates for this region are John Sanderson, Susan DiMarco (this wards incumbent), Tibor Bankuti, Theo Goary and Sukhwant Thethi.</p>
<p>John Sanderson spoke exclusively to Wikinews via questions sent in an email. Mr Sanderson's answers to some of the questions asked are below.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> List the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Safer communities through effective enforcement;</p>
<p>Reduced traffic congestion through effective planning; and</p>
<p>Managed growth through effective plan development.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> My motivation for pursuing pubic office is to ensure that our city has adequate infrastructure to support its rapid growth.  Wards 3 and 4 include Highway 410, Steeles Avenue, Kennedy Rd., Highway 10, McLaughlin Rd. and Chinguacousy Rd, some of the most congested roads in Brampton.  As a life-long resident of Brampton, the severe traffic congestion that we are experiencing today is unprecedented in our history – and is costly to our economy and quality of life.  While canvassing, the common message received from residents in the ward is that we need to better manage traffic and transportation.  As a Regional Councillor, I will be a strong advocate for smart and long-term transportation planning of the City of Brampton and Region of Peel and I will take immediate measures to help alleviate transportation congestion in our city.  This includes the provision of an effective and efficient public transit system that is responsive to users' needs, as well as implementing and promoting carpooling, to help reduce single occupancy vehicles on roadways.  I am also not afraid to speak up about the issues of Brampton. As Past President of The Brampton Board of Trade, I can be a strong voice to the Provincial Government about their need to make transportation infrastructure a priority, particularly as it relates to expanding Highway 410 and better planning and coordination of transportation region wide.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What qualities or experiences do you possess, that make you more desirable than the incumbent?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent your ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> John has been a volunteer his entire life. John understands that "Community" is about service.</p>
<p>From 2001-2002, John Sanderson served as President of The Brampton Board of Trade.  He was first elected as a member of The Brampton Board of Trade Governing Council in 1992, and continued as an active member when he started his own company, J.W.S. Waste Systems Inc., in 1998.  Through his many years as a member of the Board, John served on every Board committee, including 11 years on Governing Council.</p>
</text>
