<text id="autogum_interview_doc117" title="part3_Wikinews interviews specialists on China, Iran, Russia support for al-Assad" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-09-15" dateModified="2015-10-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_China%2C_Iran%2C_Russia_support_for_al-Assad" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurds">Kurdish</ref> supporters of Syria's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic%20Union%20Party%20(Syria">Democratic Union Party</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afrin">Afrin</ref>. Image: Scott Bobb.</caption></figure>
<p><p>Even before the fall of Saddam in 2003, Iran reinterpreted the basically pragmatic cooperation in the field of intelligence and security. Ever since Syria was part of a so called "axis of resistance" consisting of Iran, Syria, Hezbollah, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hamas">Hamas</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamic%20Jihad%20Organization">Islamic Jihad</ref>, the sole common strategic denominator of these different actors is hostility against Israel, which is always depicted as an aggressor against whom the Muslims should resist — hence, the [designation as an] "axis of resistance". Of course, forming an alliance 'officially against Israel' serves another purpose too: to take a stand against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Saudi_Arabia">Saudi Arabia</ref> without naming it. Much of the current crisis in Syria has to do with this scheme.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Farhi</hi>: Syria supported Iran during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iran–Iraq%20war">Iran–Iraq war</ref>; and, that dynamic forged a long-standing relationship between the two countries that includes economic, political, and military cooperation. In more recent years, Iran, Syria and Hezbollah have self-identified as [<hi rend="italic">an</hi>] axis of resistance against Israeli–American involvement in the region. Despite this, Iran initially mostly followed the Russian lead in the Syria. However as other regional players — such as Israel and Saudi Arabia, as well as extra-regional players such as the United States — began to see, and articulate the weakening of, the Assad regime as a first step to the weakening of Iran, this enhanced Iran's threat perception, and gave it [<hi rend="italic">an</hi>] incentive for further involvement in support of Assad.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you think Iranian support for the Syrian government is a way of standing up against UN sanctions imposed on them, and opposing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20imperialism">American imperialism</ref>?</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Kamrava</hi>: No. Iranian–Syrian relations are rooted in common strategic interests rather than in assumptions about US imperialism, or the role of the UN sanctions.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Martel</hi>: Both Iran and Syria share a strategic interest in undermining the influence of the US and the West.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Posch</hi>: Definitely not. The sanctions track is a different one, checking American "imperialism" — as you call it — is, of course. one aim.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Farhi</hi>: As has become evident in the past few weeks, the primary interactive dynamic regarding the Syrian imbroglio is being played out mostly in terms of US–Russian rivalry; and, Iran is following the Russian lead.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The UN has "overwhelmingly" confirmed use of chemical weapons in Syria. Do you think both sides have used chemical weapons?</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of interviewee Mehran Kamrava. Image: Mehran Kamrava.</caption></figure>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Kamrava</hi>: It is undeniable that chemical weapons were used in Syria. But, I have not yet seen conclusive evidence for the responsibility of the use of chemical gas by one side or another. Until valid evidence is made available — proving who used chemical weapons — affixing blame to either the government forces, or to one of the fractious rebel groups, is only a matter of speculation.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Martel</hi>:  I remain skeptical that anyone other than the Syrian government used chemical weapons. It is widely accepted that the Syrian government was behind the use of chemical weapons.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Posch</hi>: I think the Report is quite clear on that.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Farhi</hi>: I —as an academic, with no access to on the ground information — am in no position to know whether both sides have used chemical weapons.</item></list></p>
</text>
