<text id="autogum_interview_doc932" title="part7_An interview with gossip columnist Michael Musto on the art of celebrity journalism" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-05" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_gossip_columnist_Michael_Musto_on_the_art_of_celebrity_journalism" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you miss the old New York?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  I do, and I'm not one of those hypocrites who say, 'Oh, I miss the old Times Square' and were never there.  I was there.  I was running around and enjoying the seediness.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  A friend of mine said that if you transplanted someone from 1983 New York into 2007 New York they would be <hi rend="italic">shocked</hi> by how many people there are walking around; they would be like, 'Where did all these people come from?!'  People don't realize that there were a lot of empty streets back then.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  And there were 'bad neighborhoods.'  There are no bad neighborhoods anymore.  I always used to have to look behind my back.  I was mugged, like, three times.  It's hard to <hi rend="italic">complain</hi> about, 'Oh, gosh, I don't have to worry about getting mugged anymore!'  But, at the same time, some edge is lost.  But when I go to these clubs I hang out with freaky-deaky people who are living on the fringes just as people in the 80's.  I don't know if they live off their parent's money, or if they have day jobs...I'm not sure how they manage.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you define freaky?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  Crazy outfits, insane behavior, swinging from the chandeliers and making for a fun party scene.  They are still out there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think drugs makes for a fun party scene?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  No, I never thought drugs were necessary, and I hate to be like Nancy Reagan and just say no, but my first nightclub was Studio 54 and I was so stimulated by the experience that doing drugs never even entered my mind.  I was so naive that I never even knew that everybody else was on drugs.  I thought, 'why would you need to do that?'</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:'  So the people you are hanging out with who are swinging from the chandeliers, they are just naturally that way?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  No, I think they are on drugs.  But I don't think it's necessary, personally.</p>
<head id="Musto_on_Musto">Musto on Musto</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How would you choose your own death?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  I probably would like to die while RSVPing to a party.  And then I just want to be put into a Hefty bag and leaned against a garbage pail.  I don't want a lot o fuss because I'm not going to be here to enjoy it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's a lesson your father taught you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  He always taught me that all you need is nerve.  We used to watch variety shows on TV and he'd say, "See that, Michael, they have no talent; all you need is nerve." [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's so true, isn't it?</hi></p>
</text>
