<text id="autogum_interview_doc815" title="part0_Satanism: An interview with Church of Satan High Priest Peter Gilmore" shortTile="partsatanism-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-04" dateModified="2018-10-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Satanism%3A_An_interview_with_Church_of_Satan_High_Priest_Peter_Gilmore" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Satanism: An interview with Church of Satan High Priest Peter Gilmore</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 5, 2007</hi></p>
<figure rend="Peter H Gilmore 2 by David Shankbone.jpg"></figure>In the 1980's and the 1990's there were multiple allegations of sexual abuse of children or non-consenting adults in the context of Satanic rituals that has come to be known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Satanic%20Panic">The Satanic Panic</ref>.  In the United States, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kern%20County%20child%20abuse%20cases">Kern County child abuse cases</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McMartin%20preschool%20trial">McMartin preschool trial</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West%20Memphis%203">West Memphis 3</ref> cases garnered worldwide media coverage.  One case took place in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jordan,%20Minnesota">Jordan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Minnesota">Minnesota</ref>, when children made allegations of manufacturing child pornography, ritualistic <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Animal_sacrifice">animal sacrifice</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/coprophagia">coprophagia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/urophagia">urophagia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/infanticide">infanticide</ref>, at which point the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Federal_Bureau_of_Investigation">Federal Bureau of Investigation</ref> was alerted.  Twenty-four adults were arrested and charged with acts of sexual abuse, child pornography and other crimes related to satanic ritual abuse; only three went to trial with two acquittals and one conviction.  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Supreme_Court">Supreme Court</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Antonin_Scalia">Justice Scalia</ref> noted in a discussion of the case, "[t]here is no doubt that some sexual abuse took place in Jordan; but there is no reason to believe it was as widespread as charged," and cited the repeated, coercive techniques used by the investigators as damaging to the investigation.
<p>One of the most visible Satanic organizations—though one that was never a suspect or charged in any of the Satanic Panic cases—is the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church%20of%20Satan">Church of Satan</ref>, founded by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anton%20LaVey">Anton LaVey</ref>.  Members of the Church, such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter%20H.%20Gilmore">Peter H. Gilmore</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peggy%20Nadramia">Peggy Nadramia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boyd%20Rice">Boyd Rice</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adam%20Parfrey">Adam Parfrey</ref>, Diabolos Rex, and musician <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King%20Diamond">King Diamond</ref>, were active in media appearances to refute allegations of criminal activity and the FBI would later issue an official report debunking the criminal conspiracy theories of this time.  </p>
<p>Gilmore feels Satanists are often misunderstood or misrepresented.  LaVey's teachings are based on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/individualism">individualism</ref>, self-indulgence, and "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/an%20eye%20for%20an%20eye">eye for an eye</ref>" morality, with influence from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friedrich%20Nietzsche">Friedrich Nietzsche</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayn%20Rand">Ayn Rand</ref>; while its rituals and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/magick">magic</ref> draw heavily from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/occultism">occultists</ref> such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aleister%20Crowley">Aleister Crowley</ref>. They do not worship—nor believe in—the Devil or a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Devil%20in%20Christianity">Christian notion of Satan</ref>.  The word "Satan" comes from the Hebrew word for "adversary" and originated from the Abrahamic faiths, being traditionally applied to an angel.  Church of Satan adherents see themselves as truth-seekers, adversaries and skeptics of the religious world around them.  </p>
<p>On a windy October day in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central%20Park">Central Park</ref>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> sat down with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High%20Priest">High Priest</ref> of the Church, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter%20H.%20Gilmore">Peter H. Gilmore</ref>, who has led LaVey's congregation of Satanists since his passing in 1997 (he became the High Priest in 2001).  They discussed the beliefs of the Church, current events, LaVey's children and how Satanism applies to life and the world.</p>
<head id="Theistic_Satanism_('devil_worship')">Theistic Satanism ('devil worship')</head>
<hi rend="bold">My real feeling is that anybody who believes in supernatural entities on some level is insane.  Whether they believe in The Devil or God, they are abdicating reason.</hi>
</text>
