<text id="autogum_interview_doc946" title="part1_Interview with Sean Semper-Whyte, City Council candidate for Ward 6 in Mississauga, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-sean" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-09-23" dateModified="2008-01-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Sean_Semper-Whyte%2C_City_Council_candidate_for_Ward_6_in_Mississauga%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>We can only be as strong as our weakest link.  The very idea of the rich getting richer while the poor become more so, negates the very concept of growth.  Growth is about balance which cannot be achieved by hoarding or though preference.  Though it may seem to work for a time eventually all things will comeback into balance by way of natural or structured design.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Building Growth into the community is that very issue.  Reflective of the environment it occupies growth is also about the parks we build and how we maintain them.  The way we build our communities and the freedoms those who live in the community are able to realize.  Be it access to jobs, more family or alone time, what we build into the community is life.  Are our community of individuals, families, neighbours and the like able to grow within the system of government established.  Are taxes too high, can people live with the cost of inflation and community fees, are we working to live, or living to work?  How can we realize a greater balance to these concerns? We do so through unprecedented innovation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What vision do you have, for what you ward should look like?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Should the people of Ward Six (6) choose Sean Semper-Whyte as their next City Councillor, I will become the leader they have hoped for and counted on.  The vision I see is one of being our brothers, and sister's keeper, this can only happen with someone in leadership who has a heart of and for service; it cannot be faked, or imitated.  Ward Six will be the standard for community growth, progress, and prosperity.  We will develop neighbourhood associations, which can tap into the resources of the region to improve community living.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What qualities or experiences do you possess, that make you more desirable than the incumbent?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> As a young adult I reflect the long-term direction of the city.  I have a fresh outlook on the legacy of the city and the stamina of youth to see the vision through, to the next generation of Municipal leadership, as I am the next generation!  As a new face to the city hall scene, I don't hold any political posture or agenda; which could compromise my serving the best interests of my constituents.  There is also no incumbent in Mississauga's Ward Six in 2006.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent your ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I believe Ward Six is a unique place, which represents the core of what Mississauga is about.  We see this in the growth, families, and lives of the entire community, as we work, play and live to the fullest.  We believe in the future, and that the future can be a better place for the whole community.  This is what we are working towards as individuals, families, and neighbours.  I believe this is where we need to focus to create a stronger city, and a focus I will bring to council.</p>
</text>
