<text id="autogum_interview_doc200" title="part1_BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2008-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Does BDSM turn you on?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  The majority of the time I don’t get any sexual pleasure out of it.  There are going to be times in session because of the way I’m dressed…</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Outside of work is it something that is an interest of yours?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi>  A little bit, but definitely not the majority of time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did it start out that it was a turn-on and then you just moved on?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  Yeah, because I’m very experimental by nature.  I love learning about things, and I imagine you are the same way because you do all this research on different topics!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  True; tomorrow I’m talking to a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sam_Brownback_on_running_for_President,_gay_rights,_the_Middle_East_and_religion">Presidential candidate</ref> and the President of the ACLU. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi> <hi rend="italic">Huge</hi> transition!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Maybe not as much as you think! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] I would love for you to <hi rend="italic">combine</hi> these two things and bring <hi rend="italic">in</hi> that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sam%20Brownback">Republican candidate</ref> here, and then perhaps we could…somehow it would be very satisfying.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So BDSM is something that you had a curiosity about, experienced it, you realized you had a talent, and made it into a profession?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  I realized I was good at it and I enjoyed it; I enjoyed the variety and the different people I was hanging out with, people like Jada.  It’s much better than just playing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How did you start, Jada?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I always had an interest in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/S&amp;M">S&amp;M</ref>.  As a teenager it was one of those things that I didn’t know exactly what it was, but I was always into the fetish, the kink, the tying up, the doing all sorts of different things.  Then I was in a relationship where there was no communication. It was going down the toilet [<hi rend="italic">giggles</hi>].</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Was it an S&amp;M relationship?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Just a regular relationship.  There was no communication going on, nothing happening, no intimacy, and after awhile we were literally at the point where we were going to break up.  I was going to break up with him, and then he told me had a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bondage%20(BDSM)">bondage fetish</ref>.  So I was like, “Fine, okay!  That’s perfect, if that’s the only problem that you have, you know, let’s do this!”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is that <hi rend="italic">why</hi> things were going down the toilet, because he had that desire and he wouldn’t express it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Yes, he had expressed it in previous relationships, and because he expressed it he was seen as a freak.  “How dare you!  That’s the equivalent of rape!”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So he learned not to express it and that caused him to not communicate…</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Exactly.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And he just assumed you were somebody who—</hi></p>
</text>
