<text id="autogum_interview_doc1371" title="part3_One year on: IFALPA's representative to ICAO, pilot and lawyer on ongoing prosecution of Garuda Indonesia Flight 200 pilot" shortTile="partone-year--ifalpas" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-03-08" dateModified="2014-04-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/One_year_on%3A_IFALPA%27s_representative_to_ICAO%2C_pilot_and_lawyer_on_ongoing_prosecution_of_Garuda_Indonesia_Flight_200_pilot" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>Mr Komar was released on police bail on February 15, and is currently awaiting trial. He was forced to resign late in February with being fired his only alternative, and his licence has been suspended. He is believed to be the only man ever prosecuted in Indonesian history over an airliner crash.</p>
<p>The issues thrown up by this ongoing case have now been exclusively commented on for <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> by Paul McCarthy. Mr McCarthy is IFALPA's representative to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International%20Civil%20Aviation%20Organisation">International Civil Aviation Organisation</ref> (ICAO). He is both a pilot - as are all of IFALPA's roughly 100,000 members - and a lawyer, and is an acknowledged expert on issues concerning the criminal liability of pilots. Mr McCarthy's comments, obtained by email via IFALPA media representative Gideon Ewers are available below.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure><p> IFALPA's press release expresses difficulty in explaining Mr Komar's behaviour. It has been suggested that it could be caused by a combination of marital problems and sleep deprivation. Do you feel that this alone could explain what happened?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Paul McCarthy:</hi> I have no idea why the Captain acted as he seems to have done. We are recommending that that is the proper job of the accident investigation team. The allegation of “tunnel vision” simply does not answer the issue.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  In your own estimation, without necessary evidence from psychology experts, do you believe Mr Komar's mental condition was such as to render him unfit to stand trial and take responsibility for his actions?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> As above, we do not speculate. The Captain  has a legal team which is charged with such determinations</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The Convention on International Civil Aviation states that various investigative materials cannot be used to establish criminal or civil liability, but makes an exception where the benefit would outweigh the negative effect on aviation investigations. How would such a situation be determined, and is there a serious possibility of this happening here?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> The standard requires, in this case, the court to make the balancing determination. The question becomes, if certain voluntary disclosures made to the investigators are subsequently used in prosecution, what is the probability that such disclosures will no longer be made in future investigations. If they are withheld, will the investigation, and by inference safety suffer?</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What evidence is available to the prosecution? Is a conviction possible even if the authorities are blocked from using evidence from the investigation?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">PM:</hi> The ideal situation is that the police independently investigate and procure their own evidence. Is a conviction possible? I don’t know.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  One official expressed a desire to call in the investigators as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/expert%20witness">expert witnesses</ref> because they cannot use their testimony as investigators. Does this loophole really exist, or can it be prevented?</p>
</text>
