<text id="autogum_interview_doc1196" title="part8_BDSM as business: An interview with the owners of a dungeon" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_An_interview_with_the_owners_of_a_dungeon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  And you're tense.  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So then I go to the bathroom.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  And the first thing I'm going to tell you is, ’Listen.  Meet the girls, find someone you like, it's great!’</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So you'll introduce me to the girls first.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Right.  But first I'm going to tell you, before that--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You're going to talk to me first.  Out there, or in a room?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  No, in a room.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Can I interject --I'll tell you what we won't do:  We won't have some six-foot big girl grab you by the scruff of the neck and throw you into a room, and kick you in the ass--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">laughs</hi>] Sure, sure.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  With a big guy standing outside.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  And make you think, oh, my God.  I'm gonna end up dead in a dumpster with nothing in my wallet, and they're going--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What if  I'm not ready--too much, too soon.  So Rebecca's going to sit down or Alex or whoever's running the place that night is gonna sit down--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Right.  Right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And I'm just-- I'm here, and I'm nervous.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  And we say, 'Listen, people come here all the time, and there's lots of lawyers.'</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And how do they typically react?  How does the conversation usually go?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  I would say, "Hi, how are you?"  I would say, "Look, I know you're nervous.  Relax."  I would say, "Meet them, say hello.  You don't have to tell them anything that you don't want."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is it important to have body contact, touching them on the knee or hand, to form a bond?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  It depends--I don't want them to--I just say, [<hi rend="italic">taking Shankbone's hand</hi>] 'Listen, I know you're nervous.  Relax,"--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What if I shrinked away when you did that?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Then, it's okay, it's all right.  I say, "If you think you meet someone you like, that's fine.  If you don't, that's fine, too.  If you feel that tonight's not the night, that's okay."   I don't know if you noticed, we have cards that look like dungeon cards, which are very pretty and very black, and it looks like what an S&amp;M card should look like.  Which nobody takes, or maybe one or two guys take.</p>
<p>[<hi rend="italic">retrieves two different business cards, see photo</hi>] And then we have cards that are the kind of cards that everybody takes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  A bit more discreet.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So they get to the point where they feel comfortable.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Then they'll say, ’Yeah, but this is what I want--‘ and I say, ‘It's okay, you don't have to say anything to me.  The girls will come in, and you can talk to them, if you feel comfortable.  Or, if you find one that you really like, you can tell her, and then we'll talk about it.’  And usually, they'll say well--okay, I'll come back, and I'll say, ‘That’s fine, come back in.’  And it's really funny because usually it's in order.  I can't figure out why this is--</p>
</text>
