<text id="autogum_interview_doc1164" title="part2_Wikinews interviews journalist Konrad Godlewski, who uncovered BATUTA hoax" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-02-08" dateModified="2010-02-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_journalist_Konrad_Godlewski%2C_who_uncovered_BATUTA_hoax" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold"> Would you reveal your Wikipedia nickname? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Yes, it's actually my high school nickname – conew. Sadly, after some time I stopped. My family got bigger and I didn't have enough time to make all of humanity happier.</p>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold"> When we were talking soon after your publication, you wrote to me you had hoped there would be some positive effects of your story. Do you think you've initiated a landslide change?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I don't think it was a landslide. But still, I do acknowledge the fact that Batuta's case has become something of a milestone in the development of Wikipedia. I had a chance to about it with Jimmy Wales. It was in the time when the German Wikipedia was testing new, stricter editorial guidelines.</p>
<p>However, I think the most important was the impact on the other side – the readers. Even the best editorial system lets some mistakes pass undetected. I know it, I've worked in several newspapers. Batuta's case reminds us the old truth: <hi rend="italic">dubito ergo sum</hi>. There are mistakes in respected encyclopedias and books as well. Sometimes those are "Dawkins-like" mistakes, if you remember the chapter about memes in "The Selfish Gene".</p>
<p>My favorite example is the one about Michał Boym, Polish Jesuit and one of the first sinologists. He had done a great job with his descriptions of Chinese plants and animals. His works were later published in Europe. Sometimes his text were stolen from him and published under other people's names. There was a case of "green-furred turtle". Boym wrote about it because it was extremely bizarre: a turtle with green fur. In fact it was a kind of seaweed growing on the turtle's shell. Boym described it in his Latin text as "viridium". And printers from Vienna made it "vindium" which can be translated as "floating in air". This slight typing mistake made people in the West believe there were flying turtles in China. What's more, there were pictures showing this unusual thing.  </p>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold"> Batuta also started to mutate and it happened at the very beginning. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> That's because Wikipedia's articles are the best example of memetics at work. The articles are like some living organisms transferred to a new environment – with time they evolve, adapting to the requirements such as neutral of point of view, proper language, verifiability and, most importantly, factual truth.   </p>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold"> In the printed edition of "Gazeta Wyborcza" your text was accompanied by a photo, supposedly showing Henryk Batuta. It actually did not appear in the Wikipedia article, but even Jimbo mentioned that photo when he was explaining this situation to the journalists.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Oh yes. The photo was the idea of the editor of that day's edition. It's a petty it is now stuck somewhere in Gazeta'sarchives because it a really great job by the photo editor. Maybe Wikipedia should ask "Gazeta" for permission to use this little masterpiece. </p>
</text>
