<text id="autogum_interview_doc678" title="part1_Sam Brownback on running for President, gay rights, the Middle East and religion" shortTile="partsam-brownback" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-12" dateModified="2014-12-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sam_Brownback_on_running_for_President%2C_gay_rights%2C_the_Middle_East_and_religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: I read that.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Yeah, yeah, I'm pretty excited about that.  Maybe we can get some attention for a prospect that would really work.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Is it pretty gratifying for you to work with people on the other side of the aisle to try and find solutions?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  It is, because I think it defies what the country views Washington as being, which is as so hopelessly polarized that it can't get anything done.  It shows some hope that even on tough issues like Iraq, we can get things done.  So I think it gives some hope to the country, too, when we do things like that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I remember sort of the old days where you'd hear about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ted%20Kennedy">Ted Kennedy</ref> being best friends with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orrin%20Hatch">Orrin Hatch</ref>; do you think that the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tom_DeLay">Tom DeLay</ref> period ushered in an era where people were too opposed to each other on the sides of the aisle?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Oh, I think we too often look for ways to fight, rather than ways to get along.  And that's been a feature in recent years.  Yeah, maybe that time is coming to a bit of an end as people have such low opinions of Congress and of politics, that maybe people will start finding these ways forward, and people will reward folks for doing that.  We'll see.  I don't know that the divisive period is over, but it does strike some interest in people when you do do it.  Maybe we can.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Running for President has to be a grueling experience, and there must be a million things that you see out there when you're on the road that either you had not thought about before or you didn't know existed.  Could you tell me about one?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SB:</hi>  Well, you know, I just heard one.  I was doing a big <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NPR">NPR</ref> interview with a group out of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Boston">Boston</ref>, doing a call-in, and I had a couple of callers coming from the left in the political spectrum talking about their willingness to more engage in a discussion of faith and cut back on abortion.  I thought it was very encouraging--and these are quite sincere people--part of what they're looking for in the Democratic party is more of a way forward on tough issues that have been divisive.  I found that very encouraging.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That's great.  Throughout my life, my father, who is an avid lifelong Republican, he used to tell me--this is a question that <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_U.S._Republican_Presidential_candidate_Tom_Tancredo">I'd asked Tom Tancredo</ref> as well, but I think it really comes down to one of the central issues in this race--he had said, "All we need is a Republican Congress, a Republican Senate, and a Republican White House to get the country on the right track."  And last year, he expressed to me that he was very disappointed with where things have gone with the Republicans running things.  He feels let down; he feels like he was lied to by the Party, either through the rationale for the Iraq war, the sex and bribery scandals, the pork barrel projects, and, as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan%20Greenspan">Alan Greenspan</ref> said, the fiscal irresponsibility.  He feels like there have been many broken promises.  Why should someone like my father vote Republican today?  And I can assure you he will.  But why do you think he should?</hi></p>
</text>
