<text id="autogum_interview_doc1194" title="part6_BDSM as business: An interview with the owners of a dungeon" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_An_interview_with_the_owners_of_a_dungeon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  This is a true story, by the way.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  You could use our bathroom and leave.  Sometimes when I hire girls, I'll ask them if they want to use the bathroom, because I know it's Manhattan.  And I've had to go sometimes really bad, and just can't find a bathroom.  And they look at me like I'm strange, like I have a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/peephole">peephole</ref> or something in there.</p>
<p>We hired a young lady when we first started doing this--I won't mention names—and a guy came in.  He was standing there hopping on both feet, back and forth, because he had to use the bathroom.  She wouldn't let him use the bathroom, because in her mind, he was a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slave%20(BDSM)">slave</ref>.  Now, everybody who comes in here are people first, and then they're--whatever their fetish is.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  And she would let him know when it was appropriate for him to use the bathroom.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And he didn't like that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Well, he was so used to that being the way that it was--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It was acceptable to him.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Right, but that's not the way we are.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And you don’t want that to be a slippery slope.  That's not the kind of clientèle that you really want…</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  We have a very, very good clientèle.  We are upscale--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's your typical client?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Looks like you.  Looks like you.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  For typical client "John."  Who is John?  What is his background, what is he coming here for, what's he looking for?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  There is no typical client.  I know you're looking for generalities.  There is no typical client in terms of what fetish he's looking for.  They're like snowflakes.  I'm not in on the sessions.  I hear from my wife.  I'm always asking questions.  There is no typical role play fetish.  You might want to get dressed up in a red dress.  I might want to get dressed up in a blue dress.  I might want to wear high heels; you might want a pair of pumps.  You might want a whip; everything is different.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So each person that approaches you at first, you don't really know what they're going to look for?  Do you have ideas like, "Mmm--I bet this is this kind of guy"?  Or is it just completely difficult to tell?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  It's completely difficult to tell.  And a lot of times I don't even have them ask me.  I don't even have them tell me.  I wait until they--I just have them come in the room, and I introduce them to the girls; they meet the girls, and then--</p>
</text>
