<text id="autogum_interview_doc1367" title="part5_Teräsbetoni frontman J. Ahola on representing Finland at Eurovision 2008 & more" shortTile="partterasbetoni-frontman" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-03-26" dateModified="2017-05-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ter%C3%A4sbetoni_frontman_J._Ahola_on_representing_Finland_at_Eurovision_2008_%26_more" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is co-ordinating things with the other members hard when they've all got their projects, too?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Well, luckily I didn’t have to do that. That’s producer’s and A&amp;R’s business. But what I’ve seen from aside, it does seem a bit hard to fix up meetings, promo sessions etc. Somebody is always going somewhere!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What do you think personally of the covers you've produced?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I’m very satisfied with the results. We all got to do arrangements and songs that looked like us. I’ve heard few cover albums and they’ve rarely been interesting. I think we managed to reach that point.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What about the work of the others in their bands? Do you like their music as well?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I give all the guys my sincere respect for their work. I think Marco Hietala’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarot%20(band)">Tarot</ref> is one of the Finnish heavy metal legends and it still rocks. I’m not so much into Nightwish, anyway. There’s something that doesn’t quite please my ears. Maybe I should listen to it more. Charon is good on its field and so is Sonata Arctica, while its style is not the style I prefer to listen in metal music. </p>
<head id="The_future_and_final_words">The future and final words</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Except for an apearance at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wacken%20Open%20Air">Wacken Open Air</ref>, you haven't done much international stuff prior to now. Might we see some gigs abroad in 2008, and if not when?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> All I can say is I WISH! There might be few gigs in the summer, but we’ll see. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You said <hi rend="italic">Missä miehet ratsastaa</hi> wouldn't be translated into English simply because it was designed to work in Finnish. Does that mean we could see some songs written specially in English in the future?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> With Teräsbetoni I doubt it. We are pretty much focused on our own language. It would be pretty hard to see us singing in English and still be Teräsbetoni, you know.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What do you expect Eurovision to do for you? Have you seen any changes already?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I hope we can get our music out as widely as possible. Even though it’s just one song, I believe that it evokes interest in watchers and listeners. The local media has been interested in us since we won the finale, but nothing special hasn’t yet happened.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Loads of people in the music industry have been complaining that downloading illegaly is killing the industry. Do you agree?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Jarkko</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I believe it affects the industry and its sales. Still, it’s hard to believe that it’s killing the industry. Of course I also have rights that the illegal downloaders violate. So, even though it’s not killing the industry, it’s totally wrong. The whole system has to change somehow, that’s for sure. </p>
</text>
