<text id="autogum_interview_doc1006" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Spain's most decorated Paralympian, Teresa Perales" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-01-19" dateModified="2015-11-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Spain%27s_most_decorated_Paralympian%2C_Teresa_Perales" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Is there any difference between men and women?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>: Only in the financial support of the clubs. Of course, that doesn't affect us because we do not get money from the clubs. For example, Mireia Belmonte has an ADO sponsorhip, a Federations sponsorship, and well now she has problems with her club because she wanted to get the same amount of money as the men, and so she left the club. But she gets money from three places: ADO, Federation, and club. In our case it's ADO only. ((es))Spanish language: ‍ Solamente en la cantidad económica en los clubes. Claro, eso a nosotros no nos afecta porque no cobramos de los clubes. Por ejemplo, Mireia Belmonte tiene beca ADO, tiene beca de la Federación, y bueno ahora tiene problemas con el club porque quería cobrar lo mismo que los chicos, y entonces por eso dejó el club. Pero ella cobra de tres sitios: beca ADO, Federación, y club. En nuestro caso es beca ADO.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> In the US, the system is, you need sponsorship to get to the elite level. In Australia, the government funds Olympians and Paralympians equally. Like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Goalball">goalball</ref> players got 7,000 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australian%20dollar">dollars</ref> each, so it is interesting to find out how Spain differs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>:  Yes, but then, here in Spain we have to make a disctintion: we have the ADO Paralympic Plan since 2005, and the first time we perceived money, rewards for medals and ADO Plan, was after Beijing. Very recently. ((es))Spanish language: ‍ Sí, pero claro, aquí en España hay que matizar que tenemos el Plan ADO paralímpico desde el año 2005, y la primera vez que recibimos cantidad económica, premio por medallas y Plan ADO, fue después de Pekín. Hace muy poco tiempo.</p>
<head id="Classification">Classification</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> As someone who watched the Paralympics, classification was a huge issue. Mallory Weggemann was an American [Paralympic swimmer] who got reclassified at the Games and the Americans were really upset, and the Australians have said classifiers have won them more medals than the athletes themselves. How important is classification for you and are you happy with the system that exists for swimming?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>:  Well, since I am also a representative of the Athlete's Council at the International Paralympic Committee, this is a topic we have discussed there. We think that it is important than in the Olympic year, especially in the last months, and above all during the Games, there should be no classifications. Exactly to avoid these cases, in which sportspeople go up a category or down a category, and mess up the ranking. There have been many cases, in Spain we've had cases of people losing a medal because of a reclassification. We are worried about that and by the way in which events, the places to hold the competition, are selected during the Paralympic Games.  ((es))Spanish language: ‍Bueno, como además soy representante del Consejo de Atletas del Comité Paralímpico Internacional, este es un tema que hemos tratado ahí. Nosotros creemos que es importante que en el año olímpico, especialmente en los últimos meses, y sobre todo en los mismos Juegos, no haya clasificaciones. Precisamente para evitar estos casos. Casos de deportistas que suben de categoría o que bajan de categoría y que descolocan el ranking. Ha habido muchos casos, en España hemos tenido casos de deportistas que han perdido medalla por tener una reclasificación. Nosotros estamos preocupados por eso y por la manera en que se seleccionan los eventos, específicamente los lugares en los que se hacen las pruebas, en los Juegos Paralímpicos.</p>
</text>
