<text id="autogum_interview_doc952" title="part3_Exclusive: 'The Scientology Reformation' author examines Tom Cruise and David Miscavige" shortTile="partexclusive--scientology" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-10-18" dateModified="2012-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Exclusive%3A_%27The_Scientology_Reformation%27_author_examines_Tom_Cruise_and_David_Miscavige" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "I had a long three years with no contact whatsoever with any semblance of the subject or any Scientologist. I spent three years walking through my own <ref target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Bible%20(King%20James)/Psalms#Psalm_23">valley of the shadow of death</ref> reflecting on my participation in abuses within that were anathema to the philosophy the organization was created to propagate. I studied far and wide outside of Scientology — including from the sources (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern%20thought">Eastern thought</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum%20mechanics">Quantum mechanics</ref>) that Scientology was derived from. Only with that distance and education could I begin to change my thought patterns and evaluate the organization's history and future sanely."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Do you think that public and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sea%20Org">Sea Org</ref> members of the Scientology organization that believed the recent articles in Scientology's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom%20Magazine">Freedom Magazine</ref></hi> which try to explain away criticism of David Miscavige from former executives such as yourself by calling you, a "posse of lunatics", are suffering from a form of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/confirmation%20bias">confirmation bias</ref>? If not, why do you think those who read the 2009 series on the Scientology organization as led by David Miscavige in the newspaper <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St.%20Petersburg%20Times">St. Petersburg Times</ref></hi> (now <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tampa%20Bay%20Times">Tampa Bay Times</ref></hi>) are still actively "in" the Scientology organization?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "Those still in are suffering from heavy cognitive dissonance, and consequent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thought%20Reform%20and%20the%20Psychology%20of%20Totalism">thought stopping</ref>. Dozens of veterans have told me they woke up to what I was saying by first reading Scientology Inc's propaganda on me. It led them to check out my videos (three and one half hours worth) on the <hi rend="italic">Tampa Times</hi> website — and then they really began waking up."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What are your thoughts on the L. Ron Hubbard biography, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bare-faced%20Messiah">Bare-faced Messiah</ref></hi>, by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russell%20Miller">Russell Miller</ref>? Have you read the book? Do you think it is accurate?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "Miller's biography is a cheap propaganda assault on Hubbard. Miller was a hater. Hubbard was no saint, but Miller only put things in the worst possible light."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You wrote the foreword to the book <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blown%20for%20Good">Blown for Good</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Marc_Headley">Marc Headley</ref>, published in 2009. Why did you agree to write the foreword, seeing as how Headley and yourself have differing views about Scientology?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "As covered in the forward itself."</p>
<hi rend="bold">Church of Scientology Inc controls every aspect of Narconon.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mark_Rathbun">Mark Rathbun</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Are you aware of the situation unfolding now with the multiple recent deaths related to the Scientology drug rehab <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Narconon%20Arrowhead">Narconon Arrowhead</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Oklahoma">Oklahoma</ref>? What do you think of the controversy surrounding these four recent deaths? Should David Miscavige change the way <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Narconon">Narconon</ref> is run, or promoted to potential patients?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: "Yes, I gave Narconon Int President Gary Smith the green light to make medical supervised withdrawal policy. I was Inspector General (Number Two) at the time, 2002. The only one with the authority to cross order that was Miscavige. It is quite apparent he did after my 2004 departure."</p>
</text>
