<text id="autogum_interview_doc1319" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Buddy Roemer, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-10-28" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Buddy_Roemer%2C_U.S._Republican_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<list type="ordered"><item>No superpacs</item>
<item>Pacs could contribute only the “individual” amount, whatever the broad limit finally agreed. (currently $2500 for individuals and $5000 for Pacs)</item>
<item>No registered lobbyists would be allowed to host or work in a fundraiser for a Member or the President, nor be allowed to contribute to a Member or the President. Your choice: registered lobbyist or fundraiser. Not both.</item>
<item>Full Disclosure required. Pacs must show members and amounts contributed. No ridiculous $250 threshold.</item>
<item>48-hour reporting. In the age of the internet, we should not have to wait 100 days to see who gave money and how much to the President or Presidential wanabee.</item>
<item>Criminal penalties established for violations.</item>
<item>“Bundlers” must be reported with dollar amount collected.</item>
<item>Seated President must report publically when “bundler” receives a Federal position.</item></list>
<figure><caption>Roemer prepares for a speech. Image: Gage Skidmore.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Which of your fellow 2012 candidates for president do you most admire?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">BR</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ron_Paul">Ron Paul</ref>. Of course, I do not agree with every position, but on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Reserve%20System">Federal Reserve</ref> and its management he has added a great deal to the debate. He has grown in relevance in my thoughts over the past 30 years since we served in Congress together.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If you do not receive the Republican nomination, would you consider running as a third party candidate?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">BR</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I am a Republican and can’t conceive of any other Party or position as a candidate. As President, I will work with both parties and independents to rebuild America.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you believe <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> has done any good things as president?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">BR</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I like his spirit of hope when he first came to DC. But he turned out to be just like the rest of them: money, money, money, money, money.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What necessary freedoms are currently lacking in American society?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">BR</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Fair Trade ought to be a freedom that we can count on. The freedom to compete on a level playing field, but the big boys have bought those in control and have advertised the phrase Free Trade and all our best jobs get shipped overseas with Unfair Trade. A family without work is not happy, not healthy, not free. Our greatest loss of freedom has been loss of jobs. I’d get them back starting with Fair Trade and a level playing field with the biggest economic enemy of our great nation----<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you disagree with any parts of the current <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Constitution">U.S. Constitution</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">BR</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I would like to see a provision relating to money as speech with broad limits, full disclosure, and personal accountability. In that reform I would consider “term limits” and non-political rules for reapportionment.</p>
<figure><caption>Roemer (left) with fellow presidential candidate Christopher Hill. Image: thebudman623.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How have your political views changed in the past twenty years?</hi></p>
</text>
