<text id="autogum_interview_doc536" title="part9_Billy West, voice of Ren and Stimpy, Futurama, on the rough start that shaped his life" shortTile="partbilly-west-voice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2013-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Billy_West%2C_voice_of_Ren_and_Stimpy%2C_Futurama%2C_on_the_rough_start_that_shaped_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right"><hi rend="bold">—West on his wilder days.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Were you at a point where you didn’t necessarily want to die, but you just didn’t care if you lived?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  That’s pretty much it, yeah. You put your finger on it. There is a point that you can reach in your life where you don’t want to live but you haven’t made the decision to die.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Whatever happens happens.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Yeah. You let the wind blow you around. I have a zillion stories. I should write a book.  These are stories that you think, 'No, that couldn’t be true. That couldn’t possibly be true.'  I was in radio around the same time too. I went back to playing music in the early eighties after a hiatus. I started playing again with a couple of people and I was also working radio but I was in a constant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackout%20(alcohol-related%20amnesia)">blackout</ref>. And people said I was good on the radio. I don’t know what I did or said. I just used to come in there and turn the place upside down. I was too good to fire. But they didn’t know what to do with me, you know. I’d come in in the middle of a night—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And that would almost egg you on?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  No, no. It wasn’t that. They wouldn’t just grab me and throw me up against a wall and say, “Listen, you little fuck, you’re going to rehab.” I got away with this kind of behavior and it was awful because I was terrorizing people. Not during the day. At night. And stories. There would always be stories and then it would make the papers. You know, that kind of stuff. I finally cracked up a car and I was in for non-payment of rent and the judge says, 'I don’t care about this non-payment of rent thing, but you’re doing a week in Charles Street Jail for this DWI that you never answered for.'  This was before the advent of computers. Now, they press a button and it spits out everything. But back then, you could screw up in one town and then go to another town and do exactly the same thing and they could never put them together because everything was on paper.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Now it’s all electronic.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  But I wasn’t proud of that. That was the lowest point of my life. But I’ve been sober for longer than I was a user. Twenty-two years.</p>
<head id="Is_West_glad_he_experienced_addiction?">Is West glad he experienced addiction?</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you in some way glad that you went through the drug and alcohol abuse?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  I could ask you the same thing and I don't mean to pull a "<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Rumsfeld">Donald Rumsfeld</ref>," interviewing myself.  But I could ask you the same thing. Are you glad? Because if you are where you are and it seems okay, then you had to have gone through those things for you to be the total sum of your experiences which led you to the very spot and the very phone you’re talking on. You know what I mean?  And so it’s almost like no matter what you did, if you finally get yourself together and you mean well and things are going okay, it’s like, 'Well, it had to be that way.' The universe obviously had to teach me something.</p>
</text>
