<text id="autogum_interview_doc1124" title="part2_Dalai Lama's representative talks about China, Tibet, Shugden and the next Dalai Lama" shortTile="partdalai-lamas-representative" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-13" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dalai_Lama%27s_representative_talks_about_China%2C_Tibet%2C_Shugden_and_the_next_Dalai_Lama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How has the Chinese government’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western%20China%20Development">Western China Development</ref> program affected ordinary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tibetan%20people">Tibetans</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Of course, development <hi rend="italic">per se</hi> is to be welcomed.  One of the reasons why His Holiness has repeatedly stated for wanting to be part of China is the economic benefit.  Tibet is underdeveloped; materially and economically it is backward, in a development sense.  Tibetan people, they need economic development and assistance.  If it is meant for the Tibetan people, it is to be welcomed.</p>
<p>But unfortunately, the development plan they have and the impact—we suspected and we now see—it first doesn’t take into account the fragile environment; secondly, it is not benefiting the local Tibetans.  It is providing facilities for the resettlement of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Han%20Chinese">Han Chinese</ref> in Tibet.  At every point of development, and any casual visitor such as a tourist can see it, all the development is in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese%20settlements%20in%20Tibet">Chinese towns and cities</ref>.  The local people have become more and more marginalized.  There are minor side benefits, of course, but if it continues Tibetans will become a completely insignificant minority increasingly marginalized.  If Tibetans in Tibet were enjoying economic development, there would be no reason for them to be unhappy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The phrase used to describe this by the exiled Tibetan government is “Chinese Apartheid?”</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Effectively it is the segregation of people; the economic benefits are not going to Tibetans, who are second class citizens in Tibet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How are the local people handling this situation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Resentment!  But Tibet should be opened up and we’ve always said you should be able to ask these questions of local Tibetans, and not to me.  It is better to be able to ask people in Tibet openly.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But that's not possible.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  No, journalists are not allowed to go.  Why?  If Tibetan people are happy and free to express their views, then there is no reason why people should not be allowed to meet outside reporters.  Journalists are not allowed to go, though.  About four months back in the international news, it was reported that of the 74 Tibetans in the Tibetan Chinese Communist Party, 54 were dismissed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  For not being loyal to the party.  They were Tibetans who were members of the Chinese Communist Party who are holding posts in the administration.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Have any spoken out as to why they were dismissed?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  No.</p>
<head id="Tibetan_reaction_to_the_Dalai_Lama's_Congressional_Gold_Medal">Tibetan reaction to the Dalai Lama's Congressional Gold Medal</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What happened when the Dalai Lama received the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Congressional%20Gold%20Medal">Congressional Gold Medal</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Restrictions were imposed on people; in spite of that, people expressed their happiness.  Better dresses were worn that day.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Was there a crackdown?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes.  Why should that be if people are happy?  We have always said that if people are happy we have no reason to continue.</p>
</text>
