<text id="autogum_interview_doc955" title="part0_Taliban resurgent in Pakistan on enforcement of Sharia law" shortTile="parttaliban-resurgent" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-03-20" dateModified="2019-01-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Taliban_resurgent_in_Pakistan_on_enforcement_of_Sharia_law" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Taliban resurgent in Pakistan on enforcement of Sharia law</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 4, 2007</hi></p>
<p>"Pakistan was un-affected by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Taliban">Talibans</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al-Qaeda">al-Qaeda</ref> (in my opinion) until the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> flushed them out of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref>. So <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/September%2011,%202001%20attacks">9/11</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International%20Security%20Assistance%20Force">WTC</ref> and the post WTC attacks by the ISAF (read American, for the locals) forces have led to the present condition in NWFP. At least that is the way the people there see it," wrote <ref target="http://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews:Request_an_interview#Riaz_A_Hakeem">Riaz A Hakeem</ref> in one of a series of email exchanges with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>.</p>
<p>Mr. Hakeem, 58, left the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North-West%20Frontier%20Province">North-West Frontier Province</ref> (NWFP) at the age of 25 and became a naturalized citizen of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">U.S.</ref> Now a businessman who is active in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Texas">Texas</ref> politics, he shares some views as a person who is in touch with his family and friends who remain in the region. He travelled throughout portions of Pakistan at the end of last year.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What is the current situation in the NWFP?</hi></p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pashtun%20people">Pashtun people</ref> are or were renowned for their hospitality. Many westerners commented on it. Some with suspicion NOT willing to believe some people so poor could be so generous. It was almost a character flaw. One could travel without fear of personal danger as long as you followed local protocols.</p>
<p>That was the sort of mind set among the people. An ageless paradigm of self satisfaction: this is enshrined in the code of the Pashtuns way of life. </p>
<p>The Islamic radicalism is in reality nothing but the Taliban movement. Not all Pashtuns are Taliban (obviously), but most Taliban are Pashtun. Of these, most belong to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federally%20Administered%20Tribal%20Areas">FATA</ref>. Of these, most were affected by their cousins from Afghanistan coming over. Mingled with them were Arab-Afghans, Uzbeks and some Tajiks and even Chechens. Some of these married within the tribes and formed a bond with the locals. Marriage bonds go back in history. </p>
<p>This Talibanization shows itself in the content of the Friday sermons at the mosque. Now it shows in the popularity of growing beards, especially since the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muttahida%20Majlis-e-Amal">MMA</ref> - the coalition of religious political party's - won power. More recently in their showdown with the Pakistan army in North and South Waziristan - where according to my sources, people prefer going to the Taliban for justice rather than the older system of Maliks and Political Agents. The latter are known as corrupt. In Pakistan, in general, people are sick of the amount of corruption. </p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bannu">Bannu</ref>, from where hails the Chief Minister of the NWFP, Mr. Durrani, is now in Taliban control in the sense that there is a parallel government that they have established which is functioning quite well and is popular among the people.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Has Taliban influence caused a stricter intrepretation of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sharia">Sharia law</ref> in the NWFP?</hi></p>
<p>Yes. The Maliks, or tribal elders, consider themselves quite conservatively religious. Even so, they had a laid back attitude towards enforcement of religious doctrine. </p>
</text>
