<text id="autogum_interview_doc1243" title="part6_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Make that time.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  My mother was not like that.  My mother was absolutely focused on her, on her writing--she shouldn't ever have had kids, she should have probably focused on her writing.  I mean, I'm glad she had children.  It's hard to blame, too, because she was ill.  My mother was ill.  She had mental illness that was not treated correctly; it was exacerbated by the treatment of this ridiculously unqualified doctor.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Intellectually, that’s nice, but I mean, in the end --</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Well, I don't have anything to do with her.  You know, in the end.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  -- it's still your experience too, and what you went through.  It's almost like someone who pleads the insanity defense.  You can't really blame them.  But they still killed your mom, raped your sister or whatever.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Right, but they still did--yeah, exactly.  And she still let a lot of things happen that I find--that I would never let happen to my child.  She still allowed a lot to happen that is terrible.  So when she goes for her publicity, I just have to laugh it off.   You know there's--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  She takes credit for your writing career.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah, you know that's the kind of thing she would do.  You know, when really--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Does that bother you at all?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  It--you know, it doesn't really bother me, no, because what she says doesn't bother me.  My mother has said such outrageous--and this is a woman who used to eat cigarette-butt-and-peanut-butter sandwiches, so she's not the most reliable person.  I can't value her opinions.  My mother's going to say whatever--she's a wild card; she's gonna say whatever she says.</p>
<p>My brother was more of an influence on me in many respects, in terms of being a writer, because he's such a wonderful storyteller.  He would go away and come back with just outlandish stories.  I think I loved watching those stories.</p>
<p>But my mother, to her credit, she always did encourage me to write.  So she did--she definitely played a part, I think, in getting me to write.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth%20Berg%20(author)">Elizabeth Berg</ref> writes a lot about parental and domestic relationships.  Do you think that you're dealing with latent issues with your mom through your love of Berg?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  What I love about Elizabeth Berg is that, if she were a man, she'd be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Cheever">John Cheever</ref>--she'd have that sort of level of critical respect.  She's never written a false word.  I love the humanity and the absolute emotional truth of an Elizabeth Berg book.  I defy the most cynical reader to read an Elizabeth Berg book and not be able to then say that it is emotionally true.  It rings true.  Now, it may not be the world that you're at all interested in, because it's very domestic, and it's often Midwestern, or at least if not Midwestern geographically, emotionally Midwestern.  It's centered around relationships and moms and husbands and wives having problems.  So yeah.  Probably there is an element of finding comfort in that.</p>
</text>
