<text id="autogum_interview_doc314" title="part1_John Reed on Orwell, God, self-destruction and the future of writing" shortTile="partjohn-reed-orwell" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2015-01-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Reed_on_Orwell%2C_God%2C_self-destruction_and_the_future_of_writing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>:  How is that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  It's turned into a much bigger piece of community service than I thought it would be.  It started without major expectations.  At that time I had been drafted into it, there were still places to get literary books covered, it felt like.  There was a VLS; there was a New York Press.  VLS doesn't exist anymore . . . it's a big deal.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  All the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alternative%20media">alternative media</ref> is either becoming a conglomerate, like the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Village%20Voice">Village Voice</ref></hi>, or it's dying, like the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20Press">New York Press</ref></hi>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  The <hi rend="italic">Village Voice</hi> may be dying, too.  It's been bought and resold so many times, I don't really understand what it is anymore.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_gossip_columnist_Michael_Musto_on_the_art_of_celebrity_journalism">I interviewed Michael Musto</ref>, and that was one area that I wanted to touch on, but we got involved in so many other things.   I don't even know how much I could really get out of somebody who's working there, but--</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  I would love to know what he thinks about it.  But the <hi rend="italic">Rail</hi> is doing well--I like covering all those books.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How does the <hi rend="italic">Rail</hi> make its money in order to operate?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  Well, the <hi rend="italic">Rail</hi> is really doing well.  They are getting grants and I'm a little bit astonished at how well they do.  I think the <hi rend="italic">Rail</hi> is in a good position to pull it together and bring itself to the next level.  I'm not over there at the office every day, but that's my impression of it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What about this theory that the drop in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/advertising">advertising</ref> for the print media, even though it's going to go through a period of growing pains, in the end might actually be better for the literary press like the <hi rend="italic">Brooklyn Rail</hi>, because people who have keys to funding will see more of a need to do grants, which will allow them to be more experimental as opposed to worrying about, "Are we going to offend our advertisers?"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JR:</hi>  It may work that way.  There is a gigantic fragmenting because, because the new venues for literary books are not just in print media.  They're on the Internet; there are millions of these <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Small%20press">micropresses</ref> now.  So many I can't keep track of them.  And a lot of them are publishing really good books.  Many are not concerned with getting reviews.  They just don't care.  They're willing to do a very small print run to facilitate their sales through networking sites, and a few literary blogs or literary sites--and there are a lot of them now.  And of course, as these things condense from one thing to the next and grow into larger organisms, there's going to be a fair share of power there filtered down to the small presses.</p>
</text>
