<text id="autogum_interview_doc805" title="part3_Alex Necochea and Bryn Bennett: the &amp;apos;Guitar Heroes&amp;apos; of Bang Camaro" shortTile="partalex-necochea" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-06" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Alex_Necochea_and_Bryn_Bennett%3A_the_%27Guitar_Heroes%27_of_Bang_Camaro" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If you could choose your own death, how would you die?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  I would want to steal what I heard a mutual friend of ours said.  He said when he died--it's not how he died, but this is what I heard--he said when he's dead, he wants his corpse to be dressed up like Superman and thrown out of an airplane.  I thought that would be fitting.  But I'm not ready to think about death, not just yet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You guys have been described as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metal%20rock">Metal</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glam%20rock">Glam rock</ref>.  What would you describe your sound as?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  I would call us anthem rock.  We're really not heavy metal.  I think our focus is more on writing great singles, as best as we can make them.  Pop music.  That's just something Bryn and I grew up on.  We're big fans of melody and big driving hooks, that sort of thing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Would you say anthem rock more in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mötley%20Crüe">Mötley Crüe</ref> vane or more in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T.Rex%20(band)">T. Rex</ref> vane?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  I would say half and half.  Our influences don't just stop with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/hair%20metal">hair metal</ref> and things like that.  We draw on things like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thin%20Lizzy">Thin Lizzy</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston%20(band)">Boston</ref>, bands like that.  Not necessarily virtuosic sort of musicianship, but things that are put together.  We like to spend the time when we are writing our songs that we are taking all the extraneous crap out of it.  We just want to make good, hook-drive pop music.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Does the war in Iraq affect you artistically at all?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  No, not at all.  No, you could say I'm just like everybody else.  I read the paper and blogs, and I'm just as horrified as everybody else.  I'm definitely not a fan of this war.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If you had to fight in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War%20in%20Afghanistan%20(2001–present)">Afghanistan</ref>, where would you fight?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  Oh, the fight was definitely in Afghanistan.  Iraq was a much different animal.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you more inspired by things in nature or things that are man made?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  I would probably have to go with nature.  I'm a student of science.  I have a degree in environmental geology.  When I was 19/20 years old I went through all the regular existential questions people that age go through: why am I here and my place in the universe, that sort of thing.</p>
<figure><caption>"You can typically read anywhere that humanity is a virus, a plague, on Mother Earth.  I really think the greatest threat to humanity is not a meteor or comet hurtling toward the planet, it's us."photo: David Shankbone</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you answer any of them?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  Oh, God!  I play rock guitar in a twenty man band!</p>
</text>
