<text id="autogum_interview_doc781" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Brett McKenzie, London North Centre" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-06" dateModified="2008-10-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_Party_candidate_Brett_McKenzie%2C_London_North_Centre" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>In London, as with most communities in Ontario, the three most important issues to voters will be health care, health care, and health care.  I agree that health care is important, but it can't be addressed in isolation.  We need to make sure we have enough doctors.  We must also provide doctors with support from other health care professionals.  We must address quality of life issues for health care workers, and the populace at large.  We must clean up our air, water and soil.  We must produce our food locally.  We must plan our communities to encourage walking and transit use (more exercise means less obesity, heart disease, diabetes, and more transit means less air pollution and fewer respirator illnesses).  We must discourage sprawl.  We must address poverty.  We must provide shelter.  To look at any one issue in isolation misses the point: our society is interconnected, and our government policy should be, too.</p>
<p>The main issues that concern me are sprawl, climate change, and peak oil.  Once again, these issues are interconnected, they all feed one another, and we must address all of them together: better planned communities means less commuting, lower GHG emissions, and more time before we run out of fossil fuels.  It also means a healthier community, and a closer, healthier food supply, etc.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>Preparing for the coming energy crisis.  Conservation must be our watchword.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>Currently, no, because existing taxpayers must not only pay for services, but must also subsidize new development, expanded infrastructure, and repairing our existing infrastructure, in addition to providing a whole host of services downloaded by the previous government and not yet uploaded.  And since property taxes are really the only way municipalities can raise funds, they must continually increase to cover costs.  However, uploading services in some way only reduces a municipal tax to replace it with a provincial one, so the taxpayer doesn't see it as plainly, but still pays it.  We must allow municipalities to stop subsidizing new development, and develop new revenue streams ot cover costs, while we upload some services to give them a little wiggle room.  Municipalities must be able to choose their destinies.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>What we do currently, propping up failing industries, is a short term solution.  Investing in sustainable industries: green power, green manufacturing, manufacturing based on renewable resources, sustainable farming, will go much farther.  So will encouraging more local economies.  Our global economy is remarkable centralized.  A part is made here, another in Kentucky, and another in Hokkaido.  The whole thing is assembled in Michigan.  This means fewer jobs.  But if things were built locally, and designed locally, and sold locally, and repaired locally, and recycled locally, then we would have a much more vibrant, interesting, sustainable and flexible economy.  That means more jobs.</p>
</text>
