<text id="autogum_interview_doc972" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Frank McEnulty, New American Independent Party nominee for President of the United States" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-24" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Frank_McEnulty%2C_New_American_Independent_Party_nominee_for_President_of_the_United_States" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I’m big on personal responsibility and believe that if a person takes personal responsibility for the little things in life then there should be a program for dealing with the major problems that is the responsibility of the government.  For that reason I have proposed a national, major medical insurance pool for major medical items.  Everyone who wishes to be covered would have to pay in a nominal amount for coverage, then, if a major medical event occurs, they would coverage for those expenses.  However, if you choose not to pay into the system then you have no coverage period and all major medical bills would be your personal problem.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: Homosexual marriage is an extremely controversial subject among Americans. How would you handle it? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> Homosexual marriage will not impact the sanctity of mine nor anyone else’s marriage.  This is truly a non-event in the grand scheme of things.  So I’ll keep it real simple, everyone should have the same rights in all things as everyone else – period.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: How would you handle America's educational system? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> Education and how we educate our children should be a state and local issue.  The best way in which to educate our children is best decided from the bottom up and not from the top down.</p>
<p>The role of the federal government in this issue is to provide the necessary funding to the states to ensure that there is adequate money for the education system to use.  Beyond that, they should stay out of the process.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: How would you handle abortion? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> Having spoken with people who have been faced with the decision of getting an abortion or not, I realize it is probably one of the most difficult decisions most women can ever make in their lives and one rarely forgotten.  My preference would be that no one would ever feel that they have to get or contemplate an abortion for any reason.  However, I also believe that this is a moral issue that is best decided by a woman, her family, friends and religious beliefs.</p>
<p>Abortion should be a state issue decided on the state level although I firmly believe that partial birth abortion is wrong in any and all cases.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: How would you handle the environment? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> I am an outdoorsman. There is nothing I enjoy more than hiking through open spaces, hunting and fishing. I also have children and am worried about what resources they will have as they, and hopefully someday, their children, grow older. Naturally, I am for protecting the environment. However, there is a give and take to everything. As the country continues to grow so will our demands for space and natural resources. I believe that the environment can be protected and nurtured while still being used for the greater good of all Americans. Sometimes that will require a set-aside of certain areas of the country as protected environments and sometimes that will require that we exploit the land and minerals to keep our country going. Will everyone be happy with my decisions? Probably not, but as a President that is independent of the influences of the major parties, I can always make my decisions based on the best information and the best interests of our country, both today and in the future.</p>
</text>
