<text id="autogum_interview_doc1387" title="part10_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What did you learn about national politics from your Presidential run?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  I’ll tell you, I will be completely candid with you.  I learned these guys are not that smart.  I expected them to be a lot smarter, a lot more difficult to debate, and I learned a lot of them only have the value system of win, win, win.  They don’t believe in anything.  Obviously I ran to put forth a political position and to make visible a constituency.  And obviously many of them didn’t; but I thought they had some core beliefs.  Most of them didn’t have core beliefs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is there one moment that sticks out in your mind?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Probably, but let me get back to that.  I also learned that once most Americans and I talked, that we didn’t disagree that much.  When I was campaigning in Iowa and New Hampshire—totally white communities—that the more we talked not only did they get more comfortable with me, I got more comfortable with them.  Because people really don’t disagree on fundamentals as much as the disagree on the stuff we’ve been programmed to disagree on with each other.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The way it’s presented in the media.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Correct.  People would say to me, “Now that I hear you, even if I disagree with you I don’t think you’re as bad as I thought.”  I would say, “Let me ask you a question: what was ‘bad as you thought’?”  And they couldn’t say.  They don’t know why they think you’re bad, they just know you’re supposed to be bad because the right wing tells them you’re bad.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It seems the media—both liberal and conservative—has to follow a narrative.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Exactly.  So even my worse criticism—Brawley—tell me what is wrong with a civil rights leader believing a 15 year old girl who came to him.  I didn’t tell her the story, she told me.  What was wrong about that?  “I guess nothing.  Did you know she was lying?”  A jury didn’t know.  She said that I didn’t know what her story was.  So in your worse scenario, the lack of discourse is what separates most Americans.  I learned that more than anything in the campaign.  When I would meet with a lot of the handlers and DNC officials about the campaign, and everything was geared toward polling and focus groups, and not core beliefs, that’s when I got this thing that took me, as one who is a true believer—I mean, I’ve been prosecuted, stabbed, 9 days in jail in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Navy-Vieques%20protests">Vieques</ref> for what I believe, jail twenty other times—at the end of the day people have to say I believe in what I do.  I don’t know if there are a lot of people in national politics that have core beliefs that they would go to jail for, or even be willing to die for.  I just don’t feel that way about those people.  Ultimately, I only respect people who are willing to put it all on the line.</p>
</text>
