<text id="autogum_interview_doc121" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Dr. Michael Mazilu on creating world&amp;apos;s fastest spinning manmade object" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-09-09" dateModified="2015-01-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Dr._Michael_Mazilu_on_creating_world%27s_fastest_spinning_manmade_object" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Dr. Michael Mazilu on creating world's fastest spinning manmade object</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 13, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption>The equipment used. Description by researcher Michael Mazilu: "The picture shows: in the middle the vacuum chamber with the focussing and collecting microscope objectives. The microscopic gyroscope is levitated by the laser beam coming from below which at the same time is used to apply a torque to the gyroscope. We detect the rotation and oscillation of the gyroscope using the light scattered by it and collected by the top microscope objective." Image: Yoshihiko Arita.</caption></figure>
<p>A study in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nature%20Communications">Nature Communications</ref></hi> last month reported the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/University_of_St_Andrews">University of St Andrews</ref> near <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scotland">Scotland</ref> was briefly home to the world's fastest spinning manmade object. Physicists accelerated a <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/microscopic">microscopic</ref> sphere of atoms to 600 million revolutions per minute; it then, according to press coverage, disintegrated. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> contacted the team to learn more.</p>
<figure><caption>Dr. Yoshiko Arita Image: Supplied by Michael Mazilu.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Dr. Michael Mazilu Image: Supplied by Michael Mazilu.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Prof. Kishan Dholakia Image: Supplied by Michael Mazilu.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>An overlay on a detail of the above image, illustrating where the key parts of the equipment are Image: Yoshihiko Arita.</caption></figure>
<p>The experiment was designed to explore the boundary between conventional physics, which applies to larger objects, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/quantum%20physics">quantum physics</ref>, which applies only to extremely small objects. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subatomic%20particle">Subatomic particles</ref> obey a very different set of rules than the items we see every day, but the behaviour of particles at just above quantum levels remains enigmatic.</p>
<p>The team wanted to expand upon research using single atoms or <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/molecule">molecules</ref>, instead constructing a four-<ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/micrometre">micrometre</ref> thick sphere of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/calcium%20carbonate">calcium carbonate</ref>, in a crystaline form called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/vaterite">vaterite</ref>, in a bid to examine systems containing over a million atoms. The ball was so small it could be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optical%20tweezers">manipulated using lasers</ref>; light beams exert a force called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/radiation%20pressure">radiation pressure</ref>.</p>
<p>With the ball held within a <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/vacuum">vacuum</ref> by a laser trap, the scientists were able to apply a twisting force through the light's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/polarised%20light">polarisation</ref> (orientation) as it passed through the ball. The vacuum eliminated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/air%20resistance">air resistance</ref> so that scientists could look for evidence of quantum friction, a proposed force that slows spinning particles without external assistance.</p>
<p>The spinning sphere turned into a miniature <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/gyroscope">gyroscope</ref>, stabilising itself. The ball <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laser%20cooling">cooled as it span</ref> to −233°C (−387°F, 40 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kelvin">Kelvin</ref>).</p>
<p>The research was carried out by Dr. Yoshihiki Arita, Dr. Michael Mazilu, and Professor Kishan Dholakia. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> was able to ask Mazilu some questions about his research.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What first got you interested in researching quantum friction?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Michael Mazilu</hi>: The fundamental aspect that raised our interest is the mechanism that stops an object [rotating] infinitely fast in absence of friction. Quantum friction is one possible but debatable mechanism that will ultimately limit the rotation rate. One can also imagine other interesting mechanisms and we hope that future experiments will be able to conclusively distinguish between them.</p>
</text>
