<text id="autogum_interview_doc1154" title="part8_Obesity and the Fat Acceptance Movement: Kira Nerusskaya speaks" shortTile="partobesity-fat-acceptance" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-09" dateModified="2014-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Obesity_and_the_Fat_Acceptance_Movement%3A_Kira_Nerusskaya_speaks" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is it accepted when men <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fetish">fetishize</ref> fat women or is that seen as a negative?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  It depends. There are guys who are called an "FAs," which stands for Fat Admirer. He likes women who are big. That's what he likes. Amongst those you have to divide the line again, too. There are those FAs who find that that's just their preference. That's what they like for whatever reason. Why do some men date blonds? Why do some people like vanilla ice cream as opposed to chocolate? Not something you could maybe put in words exactly but you know you like it. Based on my research, it's the same thing for them, from what I understood.</p>
<p>Then there are those for whom it’s kind of a -- it’s a fetish.  For example, one woman I know only wants men who are Fat Admirers because she feels that they accept or enjoy her body at another level than somebody else.  But she’s also dated or been with people in long-term relationships who were not so-called FAs but we were with her for other reasons, and at the end of the relationship they told her they understood why men like the curves, like the softness or whatever the case might be.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you get messages on your MySpace or when you receive e-mails at TheBBWWorld.com that say, “I just love those big <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breast">titties</ref>,” or “I just want to be all over that big ass,” you know, how do you feel when you read things like that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  When I receive something like that I usually just delete it. I understand where they're coming from. They're not coming with an interest to date me. They have an interest to take me to bed, and that's not happening. You find a lot of that. If I had to add up -- I can't even tell you how many calls -- just last week I got a call from somebody who I dated three years ago. The good or bad part or or the interesting part is that I'm still single so it's not like, "Yeah, you know what? I'm married," click. Or, "I'm in a relationship," click. But they come back and you're wondering: why are they coming back? What's the interest? Is it for me personally or is it because...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you ask?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  I do because I’m bold that way.  Often it’s based on personality and it’s a ‘I thought you were really cool, you were really nice to talk to, you know, it wasn’t working out at the time and stuff.’</p>
</text>
