<text id="autogum_interview_doc340" title="part0_Wikinews interviews former Congressman Virgil Goode, Constitution Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-02-27" dateModified="2017-02-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Congressman_Virgil_Goode%2C_Constitution_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews former Congressman Virgil Goode, Constitution Party presidential candidate</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 27, 2012</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Official congressional photo of Goode.</caption></figure>
<p>Former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_House_of_Representatives">Congressman</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Virgil_Goode">Virgil Goode</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Virginia">Virginia</ref> spoke with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter William S. Saturn about his newly announced 2012 presidential campaign.  Goode is currently seeking the nomination of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Constitution_Party_(United_States)">Constitution Party</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third%20party%20(United%20States)">third party</ref>.</p>
<p>Goode served in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virginia%20State%20Senate">Virginia State Senate</ref> for twenty-three years.  In 1996, he was elected to represent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virginia's%205th%20congressional%20district">Virginia's Fifth U.S. congressional district</ref> as a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democrat</ref>, and was re-elected two years later. Goode left the Democratic Party before his second re-election campaign in 2000, and ran as an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent%20(politics)">Independent</ref>. He joined the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican Party</ref> ahead of the 2002 election, and was re-elected three additional times until his defeat in 2008. Since then, Goode has joined the Constitution Party, and has served on its executive committee.  </p>
<p>The Constitution Party was founded in 1991 as the <hi rend="italic">U.S. Taxpayers Party</hi>.  Eight years later, it changed to its current name.  The party advocates <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/states'%20rights">states' rights</ref>, gun rights, limited government, protectionism, and non-interventionism. It strongly opposes abortion and illegal immigration.  In terms of voter registration, it is the third largest U.S. political party with 367,000 members. Pastor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chuck%20Baldwin">Chuck Baldwin</ref> won the party's 2008 presidential nomination, and appeared on 37 state ballots receiving 199,314 votes (0.15%). </p>
<p>Goode had been speculated to make a run for the party's presidential nomination since last year. In fact, the executive committee passed a resolution last spring to convince him to run.  Goode filed paperwork with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Federal_Election_Commission">Federal Election Commission</ref> (FEC) on February 10, and announced his candidacy to the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daily%20Caller">Daily Caller</ref></hi> six days later.   </p>
<p>The 2012 Constitution Party National Convention will be held in April. Other candidates seeking the nomination include former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savannah%20State">Savannah State</ref> football coach <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robby%20Wells">Robby Wells</ref>. National chairman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim%20Clymer">Jim Clymer</ref> described Goode last summer as the frontrunner for the party's nomination.</p>
<p>To <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, Goode affirmed his credentials for the presidency and shared his view on the Obama administration.  Among other issues, he addressed immigration, spending, energy, and foreign policy. </p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">First, I’d like to get some background. What are your proudest political accomplishments?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Virgil Goode</hi>: I served in the Virginia State Senate from December 1973 to January 1997. 23 years. Then I was in the United States House of Representatives from January 1997 to January 2009.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What exactly did you do during those years?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Goode</hi>: Well, in the Virginia Senate, I served on a number of different committees, and became familiar with the operation of the Virginia State government. And then the U.S. House of Representatives where I served twelve years, I became familiar with the operation of the federal government. I was on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Appropriations%20Committee">Appropriations Committee</ref> for several congresses, and that helped with the understanding of the budget and the need that we have to make a serious cut in order to achieve balance.</p>
</text>
