<text id="autogum_interview_doc464" title="part1_Caribou plays the Bowery Ballroom" shortTile="partcaribou-plays" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-06" dateModified="2014-03-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Caribou_plays_the_Bowery_Ballroom" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is there a continent you haven't played where you would like to?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  We have never been to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South%20America">South America</ref>.  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rio%20de%20Janeiro">Rio</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sao%20Paulo">São Paulo</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  I can't remember, I think people—I'd love to go to Rio, but friends who have played in Brazil have said that shows are amazing everywhere.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How has the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq War</ref> affected you as an artist?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  Not too much, directly, to be honest.  The process of recording music, for me, is very insular.  I'm just recording at home and it's very much headspace music.  I'm escaping and I'm not a social commentarian or anything.  It's more about escaping into this world of sound in my head.  I don't think it's affected the business of us touring or anything at all.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Has it affected you as a person?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  I'm an opponent of the war and I live in the UK where I live under a government that has taken troops to the war or whatever.  It hasn't changed my perspective that much where I feel there have been lots of terrible situations like this in the past and you just have to do whatever is in your power.  I was at the big march in London.  Use your vote and protest in whatever ways you can, but I haven't dropped everything in my life and drastically changed my life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you find you're more inspired by manmade things or things in nature?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  I think manmade things, but specifically ideas.  I'm not interested in things in the real world as much as I am interested in mental ideas and mental contexts.  That's why I did a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PhD">PhD</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pure%20maths">Pure Maths</ref>, this elegance of pure ideas and things that are somewhat intangible and about ideas.   Music is very much like that, playing around with ideas and creating this aesthetic of sound.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What sort of ideas inspire you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Caribou:</hi>  In mathematics at the PhD level when I was studying was about constructing these elaborate systems and concepts, playing around with them, and fitting them together.  More than ideas is playing around with the ideas, constructing them, and creating something out of them.  For example, in music I will have an idea to put some different sounds together or a melody that meshes with a chord sequence or a sonic mood, or whatever.  I'm not the type of person who takes physical things apart and plays around with them, but I like taking mental ideas apart and playing around with them.  That's what appeals to me about what I've spent my life doing.</p>
</text>
