<text id="autogum_interview_doc490" title="part6_ACLU, EFF challenging US &amp;apos;secret&amp;apos; court orders seeking Twitter data" shortTile="partaclu-eff-challenging" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-04-06" dateModified="2019-09-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU%2C_EFF_challenging_US_%27secret%27_court_orders_seeking_Twitter_data" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
HAVE YOUR SAY 
 Do you believe the U.S. government should have the right to access data on foreign nationals using services such as Twitter? 
<ref target="//en.wikinews.org/w/index.php?title=Comments:Main_Page&amp;action=edit&amp;preload=Wikinews:Commentary_pages_on_news_events/body&amp;editintro=Template:Editintro_comments&amp;summary=create">Add or view comments</ref>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The same NYT article describes you as a WikiLeaks supporter; is this still the case? What attracts you to their 'radical transparency'?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Jonsdottir:</hi> I support the concept of WikiLeaks. While we don't have a culture of protection for sources and whistleblowers we need sites like WikiLeaks. Plus, I think it is important to give WikiLeaks credit for raising awareness about in how bad shape freedom of information and expression is in our world and it is eroding at an alarming rate because of the fact that legal firms for corporations and corrupt politicians have understood the borderless nature of the legalities of the information flow online – we who feel it is important that people have access to information that should remain in the public domain need to step up our fight for those rights. WikiLeaks has played an important role in that context.I don't support radical transparency – I understand that some things need to remain secret. It is the process of making things secret that needs to be both more transparent and in better consensus with nations.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How do you think the Icelandic government would have reacted if it were tens of thousands of their diplomatic communications being leaked?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Jonsdottir:</hi> I am not sure – A lot of our dirty laundry has been aired via the USA cables – our diplomatic communications with USA were leaked in those cables, so far they have not stirred much debate nor shock. It is unlikely for tens of thousands of cables to leak from Iceland since we dont have the same influence or size as the USA, nor do we have a military.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Your ambassador in the US has spoken to the Obama administration. Can you discuss any feedback from that? Do you have your party's, and government's, backing in challenging the ordered Twitter data release?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Jonsdottir:</hi> I have not had any feedback from that meeting, I did however receive a message from the DOJ via the USA ambassador in Iceland. The message stated three things: 1. I am free to travel to the USA. 2. If I would do so, I would not be a subject of involuntary interrogation. 3. I am not under criminal investigation. If this is indeed the reality I wonder why they are insisting on getting my personal details from Twitter. I want to stress that I understand the reasoning of trying to get to Assange through me, but I find it unacceptable since there is no foundation for criminal investigation against him. If WikiLeaks goes down, all the other media partners should go down at the same time. They all served similar roles. The way I see it is that WikiLeaks acted as the senior editor of material leaked to them. They could not by any means be considered a source. The source is the person that leaks the material to WikiLeaks. I am not sure if the media in our world understands how much is at stake for already shaky industry if WikiLeaks will carry on carrying the brunt of the attacks. I think it would be powerful if all the medias that have had access to WikiLeaks material would band together for their defence.</item></list>
</text>
