<text id="autogum_interview_doc1005" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Spain's most decorated Paralympian, Teresa Perales" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-01-19" dateModified="2015-11-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Spain%27s_most_decorated_Paralympian%2C_Teresa_Perales" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Sponsorship">Sponsorship</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I went to London, and the quality of sport — you didn't go there and say, that's a person in a wheelchair.  You went, fall down guy in a wheelchair, because the sport was so great. There was no embarrassment like the Olympics where they let the people from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lesotho">Lesotho</ref> swim in the pool. [The level of sport] was very equitable [at the Paralympics]. In Australia, there was discussion amongst the Paralympians with the issue of sponsorship because sport is becoming so elite. Do you think Paralympians should be getting sponsorship and on the same level that their able-bodied counterparts are?</p>
<figure><caption>Interior panorama of the London Aquatics Centre, one of the venues of the 2012 Paralympic Games.  Image: <ref target="http://www.flickr.com/people/42892566@N08">Alexander Kachkaev</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>: Of course. Yes, I hope, some day. Here in Spain... I don't know well other countries, how they work, I know the financial recognition they get after the Games, but I don't know the level of sponsorship the sportspeople have.  ((es))Spanish language: ‍ Por supuesto. Espero que un día. Aquí en España... Yo no conozco muy bien otros países, cómo funcionan, conozco el reconocimiento económico que tienen a la vuelta de los Juegos, pero no conozco el nivel de patrocinio que tienen los deportistas.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Yeah I was asking you about Spain, the Australians are why I asked.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>:  Ah, ok. In Spain we have a law, which has to be improved, which is the Law on Patronage ("Ley del Mecenazgo") which regulates the way in which companies sponsor a sportsperson or an event and receive tax deductions in exchange. For example, sponsoring the ADO Paralympian Plan. It's a special plan for Olympians and a plan for Paralympians. The financial support for a Paralympian and for an Olympian is very different. The amount for a Paralympian is a tenth of that of an Olympian. For example, all my medals in London, which were a gold, three silvers and two bronzes, are financially equivalent to one Olympic bronze medal. Very different. Companies prefer to sponsor the event, the plan, before the sportsperson, because they receive more advantages for that. This is in the case of the Paralympians: for Olympians, it is more usual for companies to sponsor sportspeople. For Beijing and London I had a sponsor, Arena, the swimsuit brand, who gave me swimsuits to compete with. For London they gave me three. [Laughs] ((es))Spanish language: ‍ Ah, ok. En España tenemos una ley, que se tiene que mejorar, que es la Ley del Mecenazgo, que regula la manera en que empresas patrocinan a un deportista o un evento y reciben una compensación en impuestos. Por ejemplo, patrocinar el Plan ADO Paralímpico, es un plan especial para deportistas olímpicos y un plan para deportistas paralímpicos. Es muy diferente la cantidad económica de un deportista olímpico y de un deportista paralímpico. La cantidad para un deportista paralímpico es una décima parte de un deportista olímpico. Por ejemplo, todas mis medallas en Londres, que fueron un oro, tres platas y dos bronces, equivalen económicamente a un bronce olímpico. Muy diferente. Las empresas prefieren patrocinar aún así al evento, al plan, mejor que al propio deportista, porque tienen más ventajas. Esto es en el caso de los paralímpicos: en el caso de los olímpicos, sí que es más normal que las empresas patrocinen a los deportistas. Para Londres, bueno, para Pekín y para Londres, yo tuve un patrocinador en especie, que fue Arena, la marca de ropa de bañadores, que me dieron bañadores para competir. Para Londres me dieron tres bañadores. [Risas]</p>
</text>
