<text id="autogum_interview_doc1308" title="part5_Wikinews interviews former Salt Lake City mayor and 2012 presidential candidate Rocky Anderson" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-12-17" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Salt_Lake_City_mayor_and_2012_presidential_candidate_Rocky_Anderson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You mentioned Republicans and Libertarians, what about those that believe, ideologically that the government should not be involved in regulating carbon emissions or providing health care?</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Anderson discusses Global Warming during a 2008 speech.Image: NikiSublime.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Anderson</hi>: Those who believe the government shouldn’t have any involvement in providing essential health care for our citizens are not only on the margins in our country but throughout the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/developed%20country">industrialized world</ref>. The United States is the only country that allows reliance that in fact fosters reliance on for-profit insurance companies for the provision of essential health care for our citizens. It’s simply wrong that people are dying by the tens of thousands throughout this country every year because of inadequate health care services being available to them and you know we oftentimes hear from people like former President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref> that people can go to emergency rooms, well that’s just simply not true. For a lot of the early diagnoses, early diagnostic work that can save lives, there’s not an option for that if you don’t have health care coverage. A lot of people can’t afford those diagnostic tests, and as a result they’re dying because by the time they’re properly diagnosed, the opportunity for saving their lives is gone, and yet the care that then has to be provided to them until they die is going to be extremely expensive. It’s so cost ineffective what we’re doing. We pay in this country more than double per capita health care than the average among the industrialized world, and part of our so-called health care dollars is going toward the profits for the for-profit insurance companies, dividends for their shareholders, huge bonuses, all the marketing for those companies. We are <hi rend="italic">the</hi> most inefficient of nations in the industrialized world in terms of how we pay for health care. Our medical results are mediocre by comparison with other health care systems. And people are paying more money for mediocre results and we still don’t cover all of our citizens. So we come out looking very very badly by comparison with the rest of the industrialized world. If we were running a corporation here, and shareholders were determining how that corporation was doing in comparison to its competitors: higher costs, far less coverage, and mediocre results? I think we’d be replacing our board of directors and the officers and demanding that we catch up with our competitors.</p>
<p>The same thing is happening with education in this country. Our students are not equipped to compete with students from so many other countries. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivy%20League">Ivy League</ref> schools are now putting quotas on the number of Asian students that they can accept because if they accept all of them on the basis of their merits, there would be relatively few <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caucasian%20race">Caucasian Americans</ref> being admitted to those Ivy League Schools. Why is <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Singapore">Singapore</ref> doing so much better? Why are their students doing so much better on their testing than our students? It’s an utter failure of our educational system and it’s going to have an enormous impact in terms of the future. We’re not making the investments in education and innovation and in our nation’s infrastructure, all at the same time we’re wasting trillions of dollars on wars of aggression and continuing tactics in these countries that are creating so much hatred that leads to far less security in the long term for our nation.</p>
</text>
