<text id="autogum_interview_doc1259" title="part2_CanadaVOTES: Christian Heritage Party leader Ron Gray running in Langley" shortTile="partcanadavotes-christian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-09-18" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_Christian_Heritage_Party_leader_Ron_Gray_running_in_Langley" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>The SCJ should also have the authority to accept or reject Supreme Court Justices from nominations prepared by the Justice Committee; and to initiate impeachment proceedings, to be tried by Parliament, on grounds of moral turpitude, bias, corruption or neglect of duty.</p>
<p>5 - Eliminate all present allocations of taxpayer funds to political parties. As Thomas Jefferson wrote, "It is tyrannical to compel a man to pay for the promulgation of ideas with which he does not agree." Instead, the income tax form should include a box with a message somewhat like this: "Two dollars of your taxes will be used to further the democratic political system in Canada. You may designate which registered political party will receive your $2; if no party is designated, your $2 will go into a non-partisan education fund to teach schoolchildren and new immigrants hw Canada's democratic political system works."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Is there any misconceptions about you, your leader, or your party and platform?</hi></p>
<p>Yes, indeed! Many people think the CHP is a "one-issue" party, because of our on-going emphasis on the right to life. This issue is of primary importance, because the right to life is the one right without which no other right has any meaning.</p>
<p>But the CHP has a 56-page policy book (available on our website at www.chp.ca) that covers every aspect of federal government jurisdiction.</p>
<p>Many people also labour under the misapprehension that we aspire to use the power of government to compel others to believe that we believe. This is utterly untrue! Consider this statement from our web-page:</p>
<p>"Our purpose is to place ourselves under the authority and guidance of the principles of the Gospel — principles like justice, honesty, compassion, diligence, thrift and "Do unto others as you would have them do unto you." </p>
<p>Today, the 16% Secularist minority in Canada dominates four powerful institutions that shape all our lives: governments, courts, the public education establishment, and the major news and entertainment media. The best defence of the religious freedom and intellectual liberty of the minority faiths (which at 4% all together total only about 1/3 the 12% who are Secularists) is to make common cause with the 79% of Canadians who identify themselves as Christians. We are thus a bulwark defending religious liberty — for everyone — against a militant Secularist juggernaut that seeks to exclude all faiths from the public square.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">There are more ways than ever to get your message out, from the traditional campaign fliers and lawn signs, to new media like websites, Facebook, and YouTube. The tried-and-true routes get the message out to the masses much easier, but digital alternatives are much more measurable in how many are seeing or interacting with your campaign. What seems to be the most effective, from your experience?</hi></p>
</text>
