<text id="autogum_interview_doc668" title="part11_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Julia Kass wrote a book about a black attorney that I go to see in Selma, his name is JL Cheston Jr.  He's a character in my book <hi rend="italic">A Writer's Life.</hi>  Schools that used to be all white are now all black, so now there's a reverse segregation.  Alabama it used to be kids couldn't get into white schools.  Now there is white flight and they are all black.  That's true of Selma, public schools in New York, too.  They are minority schools, now.  They are either black or hispanic.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think Joel Klein has improved it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Nope.  He might have improved the education because the mayor we have now is a very good mayor, and he chose Klein and he brings a certain articulation and wisdom to an egalitarian education.  But do we have it, really?  Every public school teacher that's in the system in this town is almost like a missionary.  They go off and risk life in the interest of humanism.  But the private schools, the disgusting sight of drivers picking up children, disgusting sight of limousine drivers lining up.  I'm only a block away from one of them here.  All over this city at two and three o'clock, you find dark-skinned women waiting for their young, white blazer-clad private school boy and escorting him either into a car that has a driver or walking the kids to wherever their homes are in the neighborhood.  The public schools and private schools are two different worlds.  Just like our American military.  The people who do not have the resources, and therefore they become dependent on the largess of military life to support their income or because the military affords them opportunity--so they think--because the military provides a life better than the meaningless life they have in private life.  They get out of high school--maybe, maybe not even that-- and what do they have to look forward to, these people?  Particularly the men, the undereducated male.  A life of minimum wage in some shopping mall working for some fast food place or driving a truck.</p>
<head id="State_of_Journalism">State of Journalism</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rupert%20Murdoch">Murdoch</ref> buying <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Wall%20Street%20Journal">The Wall Street Journal</ref></hi>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  It doesn't bother me.  It's not like the wonderful Bancroft family was some noble dynasty!  It's not like we should lament the passing of some noble dynasty  to the corrupt News Corp.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's painted that way.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  He's better than they are!  It doesn't bother me.  Journalism -I think there is some very good stuff.  There's some wonderful writing as well as reporting in The New York Times every day. It's not on the front page, necessarily.  The sections I enjoy reading are The City section, stories about life in the city; and the Real Estate section.  There's stories about neighborhoods at night and neighborhoods at day.  If you are thinking about renting an apartment or moving into a neighborhood, the story says, "look at it at night.  Because at daytime when you usually look at a place you think you might want to rent or buy, it looks a certain way.  Then go at night and it looks a different way.  It might be more isolated at night; it might be the fact there are nightclubs you aren't aware of during the day so it has a lot of noise.  This is the real estate section - very interesting section.  The level of writing is now better at the paper in 2007 than when I was there up until 1965.  Of course, people are better educated now.  The journalist is now far more formally educated than we were.  The journalist today is probably second generation of college education in the family.  In my generation, most of us were probably the first to go to college in our families.  We had more of a sense of being an outsider.  Jews, the Irish and Italians back in the 1950s and 1960s, I do believe we had a sense of being isolated from power and therefore on the outside looking in.</p>
</text>
