<text id="autogum_interview_doc777" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Mr. Orange of IWL in Taiwan about wrestling" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-28" dateModified="2008-12-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mr._Orange_of_IWL_in_Taiwan_about_wrestling" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> In what opportunities did you become a commentator from a wrestling fan?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Orange</hi>: Generally, I'm not a notable person, I just use the media as a promotion tool because we [the public] can't look down the strengths and impacts of public opinions and mass media. At that time, due to some coordination on behalf of broadcasting rights of TV programs, and many serious piracy and copyright issues in Taiwan, furthermore, pirates often used discussion boards to promote piracy. Those badly harmed several companies who do an agent of genuine copies. And accidentally, after a TV broadcaster grasped its opportunities on wrestling TV programs, I finally joined their production for commentary and planning of wrestling programs until now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Undergoing with trendy changes of wrestling?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Orange</hi>: I met those opportunities coincidentally because when no one want to do it, and senior elites from media industry may not spare time to do production. I felt luckily on those undergoing experiences.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Before (its) production, what's your opinion on similar programs especially in Chinese-language?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Orange</hi>: It's difficult or impossible for a broadcaster to produce their own and significant program because the public opinion have their wrong bias on wrestling. If the bias can be corrected, I think the public will not consider it as just a "fighting" or a "violent" sport, or to say: "What are they doing?" I chose the series programs of World Wrestling Entertainment because of its packages rather than a fistfight match which contained several complex rules like points or fouls, or just results rather than its content. Generally, if a significant program can be promoted, I think several wrong bias of wrestling should be corrected.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Generally OK. In your opinion, which pro-wrestling match do you recommend?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Orange</hi>: There were several feature or significant matches in their own years. But I recommended two classic matches like NWA Championship in 1989 - "Ric Flair vs Ricky Steamboat", and a Steel Cage Match in 1981 - "Ric Flair vs Jimmy 'Super Fly' Snuka".</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Back to the topic of wrestling in Taiwan, besides of media, which tool will you use to promote it?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Orange</hi>: The Internet - another media, a better way differ than mass media. By the way, by holding periodical friendship matches, it will work more effective. And of course, we [the IWL] hope the (friendship) matches can be held not only in Taipei but also in several divisions in Central or Southern Taiwan to correct conceptions on wrestling in a simple but relaxed match style.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> If promoted via a portal of "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/citizen%20journalism">citizen journalism</ref>"? Briefly, "citizen journalism" is a commentary, introduction, or a coverage with what incidents he or she witnessed or experienced differ than mass media.</p>
</text>
