<text id="autogum_interview_doc776" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Mr. Orange of IWL in Taiwan about wrestling" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-28" dateModified="2008-12-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mr._Orange_of_IWL_in_Taiwan_about_wrestling" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Mr. Orange of IWL in Taiwan about wrestling</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 29, 2008</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Professional%20wrestling">Pro-wrestling</ref>, a sport derived from Greco-Roman freestyle wrestling, is often connected with the idea of sports-entertainment. Popularized by  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japan">Japanese</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North%20America">American</ref> federations (e.g. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20Wrestling%20Entertainment">World Wrestling Entertainment</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Japan%20Pro%20Wrestling">New Japan Pro Wrestling</ref>, etc.) the ongoing events and news are often discussed on the Internet. As such, television programs and other mass media focused on pro-wrestling are commonplace in Japan, America, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Europe">Europe</ref>.</p>
<p>In <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Taiwan">Taiwan</ref>, fans do not simply watch the TV shows and discuss them via the Internet, but some of them participate in the sport of wrestling through communities from the Internet or colleges. Although a Taiwanese wrestler recently won a world-class pro-wrestling title, due to policies that focused only on promoting key athletic sports like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/baseball">baseball</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/billiards">billiards</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/basketball">basketball</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/taekwondo">taekwondo</ref> (i.e. those with more possibilities to win a gold medal in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asian%20Games">Asian Games</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olympic%20Games">Olympics</ref>), governmental officials lost a great opportunity to promote sports like wrestling, which has many potential participants.</p>
<p>What's the vision of wrestling in Taiwan? How did the communities drive TV spectators and wrestling fans and government officials pay more attention in wrestling? Is wrestling a future key sport in Taiwan? <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> Journalist <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:BrockF5">Rico Shen</ref> visited the "2008 IWL Spring Festival", organised by a fan community and interviewed "Mr. Orange", well-known commentator of WWE TV shows broadcasted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Videoland%20Television%20Network">VideoLand Max TV</ref> in Taiwan, to prospect the future of wrestling.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Opening</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Hello, everyone! In my side is "Mr. Orange", WWE TV show commentator of VideoLand Max TV in Taiwan, I will do a special interview for topics related to wrestling, and he will do an overview of wrestling in Taiwan with his experiences.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Glad to see an unofficial wrestling match in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/zh:台北地下街">Taipei City Mall</ref>. How did you involve in wrestling initially?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mr. Orange</hi>: Since I'm in a childhood, I often watch (wrestling) shows with my neighborhood to a period when going to kindergarten. And then, I progressively understood the meaning of wrestling and finally involved in it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> In what region of a wrestling match did you watch at first?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Orange</hi>: Europe and America. Matches in there are often packaged and refined excellently such as theme music, introduction, momentum of wrestlers better then matches in Japan, which just contained traditional rules.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> On the other way of wrestling in Taiwan, what are the opportunities, possibilities, and threats?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Orange</hi>: It was considered as a bad sport and not well-known in public opinion in Taiwan. As of some unofficial communities like us, we held periodical friendship matches to help the public correct their biased and wrong view of wrestling, especially the quote: "Wrestling played reality not just a fight, scuffle, or violent sport." Because we [the wrestlers] were fully prepared in several professional trainings, we did wrestling without just acting and dishonesty although we player for spectators. For example, as of a famous sport from Korea - taekwondo, it fought without killing the other one but just to did enough with their best. "Since I entered into the ring, I should do my best in a match to respond expectations from spectators rather than its results." That's a theory gained from a stable law of an action movie, its content besides of starting and ending should be rich and not to be hollowed.</p>
</text>
