<text id="autogum_interview_doc577" title="part2_Interview with Brazilian blogger Ricardo Serran Lobo" shortTile="partinterview-brazilian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-01-13" dateModified="2012-05-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Brazilian_blogger_Ricardo_Serran_Lobo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Ricardo Lobo: Yes, sure. The blog "Vizinho do Jefferson" brought many readers to online journalism. Everybody wanted to know what the blog was and what the Vizinho's blog was, since the spread about it in traditional media was big. At present time it is usually only the people reading political blogs and anything else.  Many blogs have appeared since the "Vizinho do Jefferson" blog, every important journalist from the country has a blog today; however they are just starting.</p>
Wikinews: Do you think that Brazilian media has been controlled by Workers Party sympathizers?
<p>Ricardo Lobo:  Very good question. Yes. Several times the Brazilian media has been controlled by Workers Party sympathizers when the party was not in power. At present time, journalists are a littile lost and they are not able to talk about the insanity in Lula's government.</p>
Wikinews:  The Brazilian press have covered the scandal with a lot of detail. Did it redeem itself?
<p>Ricardo Lobo:  But in this case you have the blog influence over the press. How can you not write about it if someone else is talking about the subject?</p>
<head id="Brazilian_politics_in_general">Brazilian politics in general</head>
Wikinews:  What, if any, are your political affiliations, and do they influence the material you choose to include in your blog?
<p>Ricardo Lobo:  Yes, I am from the Green Party. It doesn't influence my work; on the contrary, my work influenced my political life.</p>
Wikinews: Have you run for a political post?
<p>Ricardo Lobo:  The national president of my party asked me to be federal deputy candidate in the next elections. I have been with the national executive of the Green Pary this year—before the blog—asking for a moratorium on the deforestation exploitation. I've always been a very active environmentalist.</p>
Wikinews:   Are Brazilian politicians more corrupt now than before?
<p>Ricardo Lobo:  I think that they are less discreet. Politics and corruption walk together in any country of the world. There are many interests involved in any part of the planet.</p>
<head id="The_scandal">The scandal</head>
Wikinews:  Political scandals like this have happened before in Brazil?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: Not at this proportion. The volume of money involved is huge. The problem is that the 3 Brazilian powers: Legislative, Executive and Judicial were exposed to the population.  Every Ministry had problems of inefficiency and the ruling party, which always represented the ethics and morals, was caught literally with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Worker's_Party_leader_detained_in_Sao_Paulo's_airport_with_$100,000_hidden_in_his_underpants">dollars inside his underwear</ref>. (laughs)</p>
Wikinews:How far does the corruption go? Does it [the crisis] continue?
<p>Ricardo Lobo: The crisis will continue, sure, there are a lot of things that must be explained. The great doubt is if Lula knew or not. Sure, he knew about the existence of the bribery of parliamentarians by the government using the scheme called "mensalão".</p>
</text>
