<text id="autogum_interview_doc1226" title="part9_The Onion: An interview with 'America's Finest News Source'" shortTile="partthe-onion-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2013-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Onion%3A_An_interview_with_%27America%27s_Finest_News_Source%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s more of an instinctual process that you all go through?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  Yeah, it is in some way a responsibility to respond to some of this stuff.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fox%20News">Fox News</ref> is not going to go dark after a big national tragedy and just wait it out until they feel it’s “okay” to respond and report on it.  There is going to be a little more of a delay because we are obviously a weekly newspaper—daily online—we’re not part of the 24 hour news cycle, but it’s just instinct.  Trust your gut to know when is the right time, when is too soon, and is the joke on the right target.
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  And if other fake news sources, like Fox News, are going after it then we have to respond.  It’s just the responsibility we have.</p></p>
<head id="The_Onion_movie_and_Onion_News_Network">The Onion movie and Onion News Network</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is the status of <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> movie?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  Here’s the scoop on that, because I think there is actually a lot of misinformation about it on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref>.  There was a movie that was made seven years ago, it was shot, it was a sketch comedy film.  One of the producers was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Zucker">David Zucker</ref> and it was made with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fox%20New%20Regency">Fox New Regency</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fox%20Searchlight">Fox Searchlight</ref>; they were partners in on it, with some first time directors.  The movie was shot and the original film was viewed and it was determined by the studio and everyone involved that the material just wasn’t working.  They wanted to go out and shoot more, but they needed more money and wanted to start it over.  We worked with them to help make that happen, and it became an on-and-off-again project for years and years.  Basically, it’s a dead project; however the studio might at some point might try to put something out on DVD to try to recoup what happened.  So if it ever comes out, it would come out on home video—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And quietly—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sean:</hi>  Yeah, probably quietly.  Those are the facts of it.  There were lots of creative people involved and lots of different opinions on what worked and what didn’t work, and how to proceed, but rising above that fray: basically, the movie was shot, they didn’t want to redo it, it never got re-shot.  So it has been sitting on a shelf for over six years.  It may or may not make financial sense for the studio, which has the right to put it out on DVD.  They may do it, they may not.
<p><hi rend="bold">Chet:</hi>  We have since redirected our focus from <hi rend="italic">The Onion</hi> video world to The Onion News Network that launched this past year and has been a great success for us, and expanded The Onion news empire.</p></p>
</text>
