<text id="autogum_interview_doc270" title="part3_US free speech lawyer Marc Randazza discusses Glenn Beck parody" shortTile="partus-free-speech" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-10-19" dateModified="2019-02-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_free_speech_lawyer_Marc_Randazza_discusses_Glenn_Beck_parody" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: It seems very clear that this is not about trademark infringement.  Trademark law serves to protect consumers from being confused as to the source or origin of goods.  This isn't a trademark infringement case.  It is an attempt to litigate a defamation case in a forum that might not pay deference to the First Amendment.</p>
<hi rend="bold">This isn't a trademark infringement case.  It is an attempt to litigate a defamation case in a forum that might not pay deference to the First Amendment.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Marc Randazza</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> On September 29, 2009, you requested that Glenn Beck agree to stipulate to the application of the United States Constitution, and also especially to the First Amendment to the U.S. Constitution. Can you explain your rationale for this request? Have you heard back from Beck's attorneys about this request?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: Mr. Beck has publicly stated, many times over, that he is offended at the thought of international law trumping the U.S. constitution.  I presumed that he would not want that to happen in this case.  His attorneys have not responded to my request.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What are the next steps that will occur in the <hi rend="italic">Beck v. Eiland-Hall</hi> case?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: I presume that the arbitration panel will decide this case in my client's favor.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Do you think that Glenn Beck will bring legal actions related to the Eiland-Hall website in the United States? How do you think such legal action would fare, specifically with regard to claims of libel/defamation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: I don't think so, but I've seen many frivolous, stupid, and ultimately disastrous defamation suits filed in my career.  If you look at page 2 of my <ref target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Eiland-Hall%20Request%20to%20Stipulate%20to%20Application%20of%20US%20Constitutional%20Law">request for stipulation letter</ref>, it will articulate our position on that perfectly.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> An article in the UK news magazine The First Post commented that Beck's argument that the domain name of the Eiland-Hall website is itself defamatory "looks like a first in cyber law". Would you agree with this assessment? Have there been other similar cases with regard to this issue in cyber law?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">It is the first time that anyone has claimed that a mere domain name is defamatory.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Marc Randazza</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MR</hi>: It really is not all that novel of an issue.  It is the first time that anyone has claimed that a mere domain name is defamatory, but big corporations have filed many wipo actions to try and get rid of "sucks" sites.  So, while the exact facts are a new one to me, there are well worn grooves in the road that govern the legal concepts in this case.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Are there any other points regarding the <hi rend="italic">Beck v. Eiland-Hall</hi> case that you would like to elaborate or explain?</hi></p>
</text>
