<text id="autogum_interview_doc489" title="part5_ACLU, EFF challenging US &amp;apos;secret&amp;apos; court orders seeking Twitter data" shortTile="partaclu-eff-challenging" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-04-06" dateModified="2019-09-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU%2C_EFF_challenging_US_%27secret%27_court_orders_seeking_Twitter_data" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Twitter via the web, in my experience, tends to use https:// connections. Are you aware of any possibility of the government cracking such connections? (I'm not up to date on the crypto arms race).</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Jeschke:</hi> You don't need to crack https, per se, to compromise its security. See this piece about fraudulent https certificates:</item></list>
<p><ref target="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2011/03/iranian-hackers-obtain-fraudulent-https">Iranian hackers obtain fraudulent https</ref> — <hi rend="italic">EFF website</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  And, do you believe that far, far more websites should - by default - employ https:// connections to protect people's privacy?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Jeschke:</hi> We absolutely think that more websites should employ https! Here is a guide for site operators: (<hi rend="italic">See external links, Ed.</hi>)</item></list>
<head id="Birgitta_Jonsdottir_responds">Birgitta Jonsdottir responds</head>
<p>Finally, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> approached the Icelandic politician, and WikiLeaks supporter, who has made this specific case a landmark in how the U.S. Government handles dealings with – supposedly – friendly governments and their elected representatives. A number of questions were posed, seeking the Icelandic Parliamentarian's views:</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How did you feel when you were notified the US Government wanted your Twitter account, and message, details? Were you shocked?</p>
<figure><caption>Birgitta Jonsdottir's Facebook profile picture.</caption></figure>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Birgitta Jonsdottir:</hi> I felt angry but not shocked. I was expecting something like this to happen because of my involvement with WikiLeaks. My first reaction was to tweet about it.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What do you believe is their reasoning in selecting you as a 'target'?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Jonsdottir:</hi> It is quite clear to me that USA authorities are after Julian Assange and will use any means possible to get even with him. I think I am simply a pawn in a much larger context. I did of course both act as a spokesperson for WikiLeaks in relation to the Apache video and briefly for WikiLeaks, and I put my name to the video as a co-producer. I have not participated in any illegal activity and thus being a target doesn't make me lose any sleep.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Are you concerned that, as a Member of Parliament involved in the Icelandic Modern Media Initiative (IMMI), the US attempt to obtain your Twitter data is interfering with planned Icelandic government policy?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Jonsdottir:</hi> No</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  In an earlier <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York_Times">New York Times</ref> (NYT) article, you're indicating there is nothing they can obtain about you that bothers you; but, how do you react to them wanting to know everyone you talk to?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Jonsdottir:</hi> It bothers me and according to top computer scientists the government should be required to obtain a search warrant to get our IP addresses from Twitter. I am, though, happy I am among the people DOJ is casting their nets around because of my parliamentary immunity; I have a greater protection then many other users and can use that immunity to raise the issue of lack of rights for those that use social media.</item></list>
</text>
