<text id="autogum_interview_doc845" title="part1_Canada&amp;apos;s Etobicoke Centre (Ward 3) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-etobicoke" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-24" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Etobicoke_Centre_%28Ward_3%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have been interested in politics even as a child.  There were often good political discussions at our dinner table.  I have lived most of my life in Etobicoke, graduating from what was then, Royal York Collegiate and after graduation, spent a number of years traveling extensively.  After marrying, I lived in Portugal for five years with my husband and began our family.  During this time of traveling and living abroad, I realized more and more how much I loved my country, Canada, warts and all.  Upon returning, our family moved back to Etobicoke and I gradually became more interested and involved in politics.  Now that our children are old enough to manage themselves I thought the time was right to give back to my community.  I am convinced that politicians can once again be trusted to contribute to society and to think beyond themselves.  Perhaps I am somewhat naïve, but I have good energy and believe that I, one woman, can at least begin to make a difference.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I've lived in Etobicoke most of my life.  I've married and have raised two sons in this community.  We are living in a changing ward and, I understand what work needs to be done in Ward 3 to keep it great.  I also believe that it is time for a change and that Ward 3 deserves better representation at Council than at present.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> A number of years ago, I was involved in what was then called the Youth Line.  The Youth Line phone number was broadly posted and was available to young people wanting to talk about anything from pimples to suicide.  Later, as my sons were growing and attending Eatonville Public School, I became involved in the Eatonville PTA as secretary, organizing Fun Fairs, Pizza Days, Hot Dog Days, and all those events that brought fun and finances to the school.  Presently, I am involved with an organization in South Africa called ‘Mother's Love Foundation'.  This foundation feeds breakfast to children orphaned by AIDS.  As well, this foundation brings women together and provides them work in beading beautiful, colourful South African jewelry and artifacts available for sale, while at the same time providing these women with invaluable information regarding AIDS prevention and the ability to feed their families and become financially independent.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am most proud of the decisions this City Council made towards making our city ‘greener'.  Toronto has received many awards from organizations and cities across North America for environmental achievements brought by this Council, including the pesticide by-law, the private tree by-law, the Deep Lake Water Cooling Project, the purchase of new hybrid diesel-electric buses and the implementation of the green bin.  I would want to continue to make Toronto the 'greenest' city in North America.</p>
</text>
