<text id="autogum_interview_doc211" title="part12_BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2008-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  If you don’t enjoy what you are doing, you shouldn’t be there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What’s the difference between obedience and submission?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Huh, that’s a good question</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  That’s a really good question.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Obedience, I would say, is not as intense as submission.  Submission is they want to serve you and have you be a Goddess to them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  They are doing it willingly, whereas obedience is ‘’you have to’’</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Yeah, a little bit, yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  They have to do it.  Submission is more they want to do it.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  I feel like obedience is completing tasks for somebody—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Yeah, “Go get me a glass of milk!” [Laughs]</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  But submission is, “I am going to put my foot in your face and have you lick the bottom of my boot!”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you know that line between personal and impersonal in such a personal experience?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  First, we don’t get a real chance to talk to them.  They just want a fantasy and a lot of time they don’t want you to know the motivations behind it, because maybe they are a little disturbed by it.  You only have a small window to chat with them at the end, and it’s usually superficial.  You want them to maintain the idea of who you are.  You never ever want to let them know who you are, really, because that would snatch the fantasy of this power woman who is here because she enjoys making men feel like shit!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  “Oh, I love kittens!”</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  [Laughs]  Yeah, let me tell you about my cats!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  That’s true. [laughs]</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  I like Art History and I talk to people about that, about galleries and museums.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think BDSM leads to domestic violence at all?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  No!  Not at all!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  It’s the media that makes that connection, but I honestly have not ever heard of it.  It goes against everything S&amp;M is, which is about consent, about the fact that you have somebody giving themselves to you.  It’s all about trust.  It’s why we even have these safe words here.  It’s for the fact that if anything goes above and beyond anything they want, you can just say, “Now I want you to stop.”</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  You want to give people the level of pain that THEY want, so it’s not about going off on people and beating the crap out of them willy-nilly without consent.  Sometimes if they want to be taken past that level of pain they have experienced before, and they get into deep, deep places, you hurt them more than they are used to.  But I’m not here because I want to take my aggressions out on them, although some of the real serious people ARE sort of vampires like that and really want you to hate them and take aggression out on them.  You can’t really group the clients in one cluster.  Most of them who come in here are really smart, intellectual people—</p>
</text>
