<text id="autogum_interview_doc1450" title="part2_Interview with Jimbo Wales" shortTile="partinterview-jimbo" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2005-12-05" dateModified="2018-05-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Jimbo_Wales" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
Have you had any reports back about it so far? As in experiences that people have had?
<p>None.</p>
<head id="Wikimedia_Foundation_fund_drive">Wikimedia Foundation fund drive</head>
<p>The Wikimedia Foundation has turned to its constituency to cover basic operating costs as well as the ongoing capital expenditures which seem to grow at the same rate as Wikipedia's popularity: exponentially. From the first fundraiser in December/January of 2003/2004 (which raised about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US%20Dollar">$</ref>30,000 after a server catastrophe) to the Fall Quarter fundraiser in 2005 (which raised $244,000), each fund raiser has met the goals laid out for it, usually in a very brief time frame.</p>
<p>"We wish to cover two quarters," said Florence Nibart-Devouard, member of the Wikimedia Foundation Board.</p>
<p>The draft budget for just the first quarter of 2006 is projecting costs of more than $400,000; and projections put the year's expenditures near $3.2 million over all. But beyond the general goal of covering the budgets for two quarters, the foundation has not placed a specific financial goal for their upcoming fund raiser.</p>
<p>This fund drive is open-ended; there is no financial goal. One can find rumours there are estimates of unstated goals which start at a million dollars US and go up from there. How much money does the Wikimedia Foundation need to raise from this drive?</p>
<p><p>[JWales] Rumors sounds strange to me. Rumors? Anyway, our best estimate for the bare minimum needed in the next year just to keep the website running is $1 million to $2 million depending on how long and how fast traffic continues to grow. Traditionally we have been constrained in our growth by the website responding slowly during the time we are waiting for new servers to be purchased and integrated into the system.</p></p>
<p><p>Our _stated_ goal is to create and distribute a freely licensed high quality encyclopedia to every single person on the planet in their own language.</p></p>
<p><p>We know that we are achieving that goal very well in some parts of the world, and not so well in other parts of the world.</p></p>
<p><p>It is my intention that we should experiment with some ways that funding could help with this: for example, hiring co-ordinators for some small languages, to recruit native speakers to work on the project.</p></p>
<p>1-2 million USD is a big jump from the past budgets; is that kind of budget growth sustainable with the fundraiser model?</p>
<p><p>[JWales] Well, that's an open question but I think so. Needs increase with traffic increases, but with traffic increases we have a bigger audience to ask for help. Hopefully those two things scale together reasonably well.</p></p>
<p>Ward Cunningham was discussing a distributed wiki model at wikimania, has this avenue been pursued further?</p>
<p><p>[JWales] I don't know of any serious technical work being done on a distributed wiki model, but I'm personally a skeptic about whether such a model would serve our actual needs. I'm open to ideas though.:-)</p></p>
</text>
