<text id="autogum_interview_doc283" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Eric Saussine, director of the James Bond fan film Shamelady" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-07-16" dateModified="2008-08-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Eric_Saussine%2C_director_of_the_James_Bond_fan_film_Shamelady" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Eric Saussine, director of the James Bond fan film Shamelady</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 16, 2008</hi></p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20Bond%20(film%20series)">James Bond</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/film%20series">film series</ref> is one of the most popular and successful, having grossed over <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20dollar">US$</ref>4 billion worldwide. The suave, sophisticated secret agent has secured his place in popular culture as the definitive action hero that has appeared in twenty-three films between 1954 and 2006.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel%20Craig">Daniel Craig</ref> was announced as the seventh actor to portray 007 in late 2005, making his debut in the 2006 smash hit <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casino%20Royale">Casino Royale</ref></hi>. While fans await Craig's second outing in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum%20of%20Solace">Quantum of Solace</ref></hi>, due later this year, they have been able to watch <hi rend="italic">Shamelady</hi>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fan%20film">fan film</ref> made by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">French</ref> film production company Constellation Studios.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Shamelady</hi> is a tribute to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ian%20Fleming">Ian Fleming</ref>, the author of the James Bond novels on which many of the films are based, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EON%20Productions">EON Productions</ref>, the makers of the official 007 films. The film was first released in 2007 and runs just under an hour long. It can be downloaded from Constellation's website or viewed on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref>.</p>
<p>Legally, the filmmakers cannot profit from <hi rend="italic">Shamelady</hi>, but they didn't make it for the money, rather the thrill of creating an original Bond film. The plot is fairly simple, and reminiscent of <hi rend="italic">Casino Royale</hi>. Bond is sent to a casino to nab a vicious crime lord, but gets betrayed by a fellow agent in the process. Viewer reaction to the film was positive for the most part, and Constellation Studios has now planned a sequel to <hi rend="italic">Shamelady</hi>, which director Eric Saussine speaks of in the interview below.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Although having made several other movies, Constellation Studios is best known for the acclaimed James Bond fan film <hi rend="italic">Shamelady</hi>. Tell us about it.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Saussine:</hi> Shamelady attempts to be a true James Bond adventure, except in length. Our 007 lasts 54 minutes. The story takes place in Iraq, England and France. James Bond is sent to the south of France to buy information about a secret organization that terrorizes Great Britain. During the operation, a couple of killers put a deadly stop to the exchange. Bond escapes, whereas Mangin - who provided the information - is killed. For MI6, it's vivid evidence that S.P.E.C.T.R.E. - the criminal organization to which James Bond was formerly opposed - is back. From this point, Bond goes to the casino of Luc-sur-Mer, Normandy, in search of Descarpes who is suspected of being the number 2 of the organization. Bond challenges Descarpes at the roulette table and seduces Anna Raykova, a mysterious Russian woman working for his adversary. Our favorite spy escapes several murder attempts but, in a nod to Casino Royale, he soon realizes that he is being betrayed. Anyway, the bad guy dies in the end! Some things are eternal. Shamelady is a tribute to the men at the origin of the myth: original author Ian Fleming and James Bond producers Harry Saltzman and Albert Broccoli.</p>
</text>
