<text id="autogum_interview_doc1021" title="Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Miriam Stucky, Peterborough" shortTile="ontario-votes--interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-09" dateModified="2007-12-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_Party_candidate_Miriam_Stucky%2C_Peterborough" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Miriam Stucky, Peterborough</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 9, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Miriam Stucky'</hi> is running for the Green Party of Ontario in the Ontario provincial election, in the Peterborough riding. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref>' Nick Moreau interviewed her regarding her values, her experience, and her campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>As with many (of the best) things in life, I became involved in politics by happenstance, fate. For at least the past 4 elections, I’ve had the pleasure of knowing the Green Party Candidates in our riding. Larry Tylsley, Tim Holland, Brent Wood, and have been inspired by their work. Recently, the federal riding associate was seeking contestants for their nomination, and I was dis-enchanted by the sole contender, thinking “we can do better than that.” If it was to be, it was up to me. So, at the very last minute, I threw my hat in the ring, and sought the nomination. He was much more politically savvy than I (having run for every political party on the ballot); having only two days to sign up new supporters, he won by a nose. As my father said, “if you’d a had another week, you’d-a kicked his ass.”</p>
<p>A few short months later, the provincial nomination came up, and with transportation and energy, two issues close to my heart, being within provincial purvue, I sought the nomination, and now look! Runnin’ runnin’ runnin’ for MPP, here in Peterborough Ontario. My home for the better part of the last 12 years. I couldn’t imagine running anywhere else. My peeps are here.</p>
<p>So, all in all, it stems from the sentiment: “we can do better than that,” and “if it is to be, it’s up to me/us.” True at so many levels when it comes to political leadership and vision, eh?</p>
<p>p.s. I’m learning a lot from my uber-energetic, ever-helpful federal counterpart.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I canvassed for the NDP with my mum before I was old enough to vote (how cute must that have been!). I did a bit of research for our federal Green Party candidate in a past election.</p>
<p>Insight, you ask? I was roommates with/landlord to a friend who’s a (militant) anti-poverty activist and stand-up good woman. She’s honoured me by agreeing to be spiritual/moral advisor to me in this political work/life. I learned a lot from her.</p>
<p>I wildcraft food (pick herbs, berries, etc. for food and medicine). This connects me some with the physical world/our environment.</p>
<p>I ran my own business for a while, delivering local and organic food. From this I learned it’s so much better to have colleagues/workmates/a team.</p>
<p>I’ve worked as a reporter. It’s done nothing to help me keep from getting mis-quoted.</p>
<p>I’ve got a B.A. in cultural studies &amp; native studies. Ergo, I’m a certified good critical thinker (I was born that way), and b) we’re all on Native land. Let’s stop choosing to be blind to what a privilege it is to be here, now, and (re)commit to learning what it is to behave well as humans here, now.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>For part a, I don’t know.</p>
<p>For part b, because, as my kind friend Barb said the other night after an all candidates’ meeting, “you out-classed them all.” I/we are fresh, creative, and fun-loving. I’m the only woman running in our riding, I’m smart, interested, and dam, does our party have some great ideas!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>I’m hearing voters say they’re interested in health care, education, and democratic reform. My friend Gary who’s involved with the Green Party campaign in Quinte west/Northumberland today said he/they are all about water. I would have to add that to the list. If our water’s unhealthy, we’re unhealthy. I’m afraid I’ll have to point here to the party tenet of the interconnectedness of all things: the economic, social and environmental factors of ANY and ALL issues HAVE to be considered simultaneously. THAT is what we would do to address any/all issues close to the heart of voters, is address them simultaneously, holistically.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does “new media” play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</p>
</text>
