<text id="autogum_interview_doc1352" title="part2_Van Canto's Stefan Schmidt on a capella metal, Wacken, Nightwish, piracy & more" shortTile="partvan-cantos-stefan" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-09" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Van_Canto%27s_Stefan_Schmidt_on_a_capella_metal%2C_Wacken%2C_Nightwish%2C_piracy_%26_more" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>Unlike the approach we chose with our former bands, we didn’t contact any record company with our self-produced debut, but managed everything on our own. So this time the record companies contacted us after van Canto was recognized in the internet.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>What about your first video, for <hi rend="italic">The Mission</hi>. How has that gone down with the industry?</item></list>
<p>We did this on our own as well. A friend of ours did all the writing, cutting and effects. We only had to pay a cameraman, a lighting technican  and a make-up artist for 13 hours. It was great to see how many professional people have fun doing their work and not demand thousands of euros of a new formed band.</p>
<head id="On_the_new_album">On the new album</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Are things on track for the recording of the new album?</item></list>
<p>Yes, everything works fine. We recorded drums in November and January and will record all voices in March.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>When do you expect it to be released?</item></list>
<p>That’s up to the record company, I think it will be released in summer, so that the Wacken crowd can sing out the new songs.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Can you give us an idea of what to expect from the new material?</item></list>
<p>If you do something new, you don’t have any references on how to sound. We noticed many things in the year after the recording of “a storm to come”. We now better know which words and syllables sound good in which context of the song.
So I think our bass voice will be “more bass” our guitar voices will be “more guitar” and so on. From the songwriting point of view we are still in the melodic metal genre, what we call hero metal. We will also do some covers.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>What's it like working with Charlie Bauerfeind?</item></list>
<p>Great. He’s a great guy with a very high musical understanding. Having worked with Blind Guardian he definitely knows how to push voices, and many of them, in the right direction.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do you expect to release any singles this time round? Will there be another music video?</item></list>
<p>It’s too early to tell, we will first finish the recordings and then see what we can do around the songs.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do you anticipate comparable success with this album?</item></list>
<p>We wait for nothing but are thankful for everything happened so far and everything that is about to happen. Let’s see.</p>
<head id="On_Wacken_Open_Air">On Wacken Open Air</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>There are a lot of very big names announced for Wacken, as usual. Do you feel daunted by this?</item></list>
<p>Not daunted, but really exited. If we can really manage to shake hand with Iron Maiden I’m sure not being able to speak one comprehensible word, haha. But I guess every band playing on this year’s Wacken will try to shake hands with them so I better not too disappointed if it doesn’t work out.</p>
</text>
