<text id="autogum_interview_doc376" title="Interview with Brodrick Thorpe, City Council candidate for Ward 10 in Mississauga, Canada" shortTile="interview-brodrick" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-02" dateCreated="2006-10-14" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Brodrick_Thorpe%2C_City_Council_candidate_for_Ward_10_in_Mississauga%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with Brodrick Thorpe, City Council candidate for Ward 10 in Mississauga, Canada</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 17, 2006</hi></p>
<p>The upcoming <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mississauga%20municipal%20election,%202006">2006 Mississauga municipal election</ref>, to be held November 13, features an array of candidates looking to represent their wards in city council.</p>
<p>Wikinews contributor Nicholas Moreau has contacted as many candidates as possible, including <hi rend="bold">Brodrick Thorpe</hi>, asking them to answer common questions sent in an email. There is no incumbent in the newly created ward; the sixteen residents competing for the position are Shah Rukh Alam, John Briers, Tony Ciufo, Jamie Dookie, Dale D'Souza, Prag Euclid, Adnan Hashmi, Elias Hazineh, Jack Janiak, Fasal Javaid, Craig Lawrence, Sue M. McFadden, Patrick Mendes, Barbara Polis, Graziano Roti, Ali Tahmourpour, and Scott Wilson.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> List the three most important issues in your campaign, and briefly explain why these are important.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi></p>
<p>THE MOVEMENT OF TRAFFIC WITHIN WARD 10, COMPLETION OF ROADS - This is important to protect the safety of the residents of ward 10 and to ease the traffic congestion in and out of this area. The early morning commute with all the school buses is very slow and congested.</p>
<p>ENVIROMENTAL ISSUES, RECYCLING, POLLUTION - These issues should be important to everyone, the reduction of waste products and the conservation of resources will help us reduce processes that create pollution.</p>
<p>IMPROVED SOCIAL SERVICES LIKE CHILDCARE AND TRANSIT - The children are the future. Many homes now require that both parents work. Our children need to learn skills under the proper guidance to become assets to the community. Expanded transit is a cost effect way to get cars of the street and aid with the traffic movement and pollution.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Of the decisions made by council since the last election, which one would you have changed, and why?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The decision I would have changed is the one concerning store openings on Labour Day. I am a member of an organized union and believe it should be kept a holiday.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The development and completion of roads, parks, schools, and community centres in Ward 10.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What vision do you have, for what you ward should look like?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> My vision is safe neighbourhoods where people look out for one another. It is an area the has several parks and community centres that are easily accessible to all residents, minimal traffic and little congestion.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What service is most lacking in Mississauga?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Transit.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What are your opinions on Mississauga's congestion and public transit funding?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I think more has to be done to relieve the bottlenecks and more funding for public transit would aid in that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The city recently released a study regarding transforming the City Hall and area. How do you feel about these plans?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am in favour of any transformation that continues to offer services to the cities residents. I have no problem with the way it is now, my wedding photos were taken there, but the plans I have heard sound interesting.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How do you feel about Mississauga's rate of expansion?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I don't mind the expansion, but I don't like the high density approach.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why should businesses be attracted to locating in Mississauga?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am in favour of any business as long as it does not create environmental hazards or is a visible eye sore. Mississauga has great highway access and is close to the airport making it a great location for most industries.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How could Mississauga further itself in attracting corporate investment?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I think they just have to continue on the path they are on, maintain and upgrade current projects, and keep offering cost effective solutions to potential investors.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I feel it is time for a younger person that has more in common with the residents to be a leader. Ward 10 is a young ward filled with young couples with young children who will be able to reap the rewards of this vibrant neighbourhood. I fit into that same category.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent your ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I think it is time for someone younger to take over. The decisions being made are for the younger generations future and we should have an input.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am involved with a ministry that mentors young men.  I have also canvassed for ADRA, the cancer society, and the diabetes association.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Many councillors are quite seasoned in the civic political process. What could you bring to the table as a "rookie", above and beyond the current roster of councillors?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I think the councillors are too seasoned, and it is time for new ideas, and new approaches. I would bring youthful excitement and energy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Mississauga mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Mississauga to me is a quiet area away from the big city with fresh air, friendly neighbours, and a world of potential.</p>
</text>
