<text id="autogum_interview_doc1452" title="part4_Interview with Jimbo Wales" shortTile="partinterview-jimbo" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2005-12-05" dateModified="2018-05-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Jimbo_Wales" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><p>[JWales] Yes. I'm now a full-time beggar.:)</p></p>
<p>Many traditional charity programs spend the majority of fundraising dollars on fundraisers. What is the estimate for the cost of this fundraiser, versus what you expect to raise? To qualify this question; some of the fundraising ratios seen are upwards of 80% of funds raised go for fundraising.</p>
<p><p>[JWales] For the exact numbers, it will be best to consult with Mav (our CFO) and Michael (our Treasurer) as well as published results from past efforts. But obviously since the fund raising is done almost exclusively on the website itself (which costs no money), our efficiency is very very high. I don't know the exact numbers, but our costs are mostly just the bank fees and paypal fees.</p></p>
<p><p>I think it's terrible when charities are that inefficient. I think fundraising expenses should be as low as reasonably possible.</p></p>
<p>The current conflict over the Seigenthaler article has raised some ire outside the internet wikimedia community; How do you think this will affect, if at all, corporate or personal donations during this fund drive?</p>
<p><p>[JWales] I don't think it will affect it. It's just news, there's always some news. If anything, I am hopeful that donations will increase just because more people are learning of us.</p></p>
<p>On what do you intend to spend this fundraiser's donations? Do you plan to use some of the funding raised to improve the reliability of Wikipedia? For example, will you hire fact checkers?</p>
<p><p>[JWales] The bulk of the money will go, as usual, to hardware purchases. Some of the money will go to improving the software, which in turn will improve reliability. Hiring fact checkers is not being considered.</p></p>
<p>Fundraisers are not the only source of funding for Wikimedia Foundation. What other revenue streams, such as grants and contracts, does the Foundation currently have? What others are being applied for or worked on?</p>
<p><p>[JWales] We have a small but growing amount of income from partners who pay us for the service of a realtime data stream. For people who reuse our content commercially this is a nice way for them to get a more quickly updated result. We have gotten a few grants in the past, and some grants are being worked on now.</p></p>
<p><p>Danny Wool recently joined the foundation, working in the office as my assistant, but a portion of his time is devoted to grant applications. We anticipate that in the future he will work fulltime on grant applications after training a replacement assistant for me.</p></p>
<p>What companies are paying realtime data streams?</p>
<p><p>[JWales] Answers.com for example.</p></p>
<p>You've mentioned hiring some new employees, like Danny Wool. What's the projection for increasing the budget for employee time?</p>
</text>
