<text id="autogum_interview_doc011" title="part2_Simple animals could live in Martian brines: Wikinews interviews planetary scientist Vlada Stamenković" shortTile="partsimple-animals" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-10-23" dateModified="2019-01-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Simple_animals_could_live_in_Martian_brines%3A_Wikinews_interviews_planetary_scientist_Vlada_Stamenkovi%C4%87" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>When asked about plans for a future model that might include seasonal timescales, Stamenković told Wikinews, "Yes, we are now exploring the kinetics part and want to see what happens on shorter timescales."</p>
<p>Stamenković et al's model also takes account of the tilt of the Mars axis, which varies much more than Earth's does.  </p>
<p>Wikinews asked Stamenković if he had any ideas about whether and how sponges could survive through times when the tilt was higher and less oxygen would be available:</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   I notice from your figure<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#Figure_4">[4] </ref> that there is enough oxygen for sponges only at tilts of about 45 degrees or less. Do you have any thoughts about how sponges could survive periods of time in the distant past when the Mars axial tilt exceeds 45 degrees, for instance, might there be subsurface oxygen-rich oases in caves that recolonize the surface? Also what is the exact figure for the tilt at which oxygen levels sufficient for sponges become possible? (It looks like about 45 degrees from the figure but the paper doesn't seem to give a figure for this.)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Stamenković</hi>: 45 deg is approx. the correct degree. We were also tempted to speculate about this temporal driver but realized that we still know so little about the potential for life on Mars/principles of life that anything related to this question would be pure speculation, unfortunately.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   How quickly would the oxygen get into the brines — did you investigate the timescale?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Stamenković</hi>: No, we did not yet study the dynamics. We first needed to show that the potential is there. We are now studying the timescales and processes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   Could the brines that Nilton Renno and his teams simulated, forming on salt/ice interfaces within minutes in Mars simulation conditions, get oxygenated in the process of formation? If not, how long would it take for them to get oxygenated to levels sufficient for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aerobic%20organism">aerobic</ref> microbes? For instance could the Phoenix leg droplets have taken up enough oxygen for aerobic respiration by microbes?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Stamenković</hi>: Just like the answer above. Dynamics is still to be explored. (But this is a really good question 😉).</p>
<p>Wikinews also asked Stamenković how their research is linked to the recent discovery of possible large subglacial lake below the Martian South Pole found through radar mapping. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   Some news stories coupled your research with the subglacial lakes announcement earlier this year. Could the oxygen get through ice into layers of brines such as the possible subglacial lakes at a depth of 1.5 km?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Stamenković</hi>: There are other ways to create oxygen. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radiolysis">Radiolysis</ref> of water molecules into hydrogen and oxygen can liberate oxygen in the deep and that O2 could be dissolved in deep groundwater. The radiolytic power for this would come from radionuclides naturally contained in rocks, something we observe in diverse regions on Earth.</p>
</text>
