<text id="autogum_interview_doc912" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Donald K. Allen, independent candidate for US presidency" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-02" dateModified="2009-03-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Donald_K._Allen%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_presidency" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Donald K. Allen, independent candidate for US presidency</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 2, 2008</hi></p>
<p>While nearly all mainstream coverage of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202008">2008 Presidential election</ref> has focused on the Democratic and Republican candidates, the race for the White House also includes independents and third-party candidates. These prospects represent a variety of views that may not be acknowledged by the major party platforms.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> has reached out to these candidates throughout the campaign and now presents an interview with Donald K. Allen of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Youngstown,%20Ohio">Youngstown</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ohio">Ohio</ref>, an independent presidential candidate who registered with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Election%20Committee">Federal Election Committee</ref> in January 2007. He says that his three major policies are "1. Take care of America and Americans first. 2. Turn our economy around. 3. Secure our borders."</p>
<p>Allen was previously interviewed by Wikinews, although the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Donald_K._Allen,_independent_candidate_in_US_presidential_elections">previous interview</ref> was only five questions long, and did not go into the candidate's policy in much detail. As a result, Wikinews has decided to do a more in depth interview, which is available below.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">For our readers who did not read the previous interview, could you please explain why you have decided to run for President?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Donald K. Allen</hi>: The vast majority of Americans are furious with their government, disappointed with their elected officials, and afraid of the direction our country has taken.  After 150 years of Republican and Democratic control of Washington, they are looking for someone who will truly bring about a new course and return respect and accountability to our Nation.  With Edmund Burke's "The only thing necessary for the triumph of evil is for good men to do nothing" encouraging me, I chose to challenge the two Goliath political parties and run as an independent, unaffiliated candidate for President of the United States of America.</p>
<head id="On_the_economy">On the economy</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">For many voters, the government's proposed $700 billion dollar bail out of banks is a very important issue. What is your opinion on the bail out?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Donald K. Allen</hi>: If our government decides to bail out a private corporation's failure it will set a precedent for other bailouts, which will surely ruin our economy.  Where will the money come from?  Just print more Federal Reserve Notes that have nothing backing them up, or borrow it from China and the Middle East?  I hope Congress rejects this proposal, because if it is passed our great grandchildren will inherit the debt, and inflation in this country will increase from the dilution of $700 billion into the economy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What do you think is the best way to address the current economic crisis?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Donald K. Allen</hi>: Let the private sector do the rescue, not the government.  There is nothing in the Constitution that allows for or even hints at this action, and national security is not a justification.</p>
</text>
