<text id="autogum_interview_doc1245" title="part8_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yeah.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Who saw.  And who experienced.  So, it was crazy--the whole thing seemed crazy to me to begin with.</p>
<head id="On_his_work">On his work</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you read reviews of your work, and commentary on it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Some of them, not all of them.  Some of them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did it ever bother you if you came across somebody using the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twelve%20Steps">Twelve Steps</ref> in a review of your work?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I don't know if I've seen that.  What do you mean?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I mean comparing the things you did with your writing and comparing them to how they conform to the principles in the Twelve Steps.   It happened with Frey too, where all of a sudden you had these alcoholics coming out and saying, "Oh, this is such a typical alcoholic, doing this or doing that.  It’s not very Step Eight,” or whatever…  You never came across that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  No, I didn't care about that kind of thing.   You know, <hi rend="italic">Dry</hi> is not a terribly structured book.  I mean, it is what it is.  It's what happened when I stopped drinking.  I'm the first to admit that right before it came out, I was horrified.  I thought, you know, my God, what am I doing? The world doesn't need another alcoholic book.  It's already been done by so many authors before me…</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you still feel that way? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Well, no, I think that--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That's the ‘nothing’s original’ thing, isn't it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah, I think everybody is different, and my book's different because it's me.  There are some things about it, I think, that are funny--you know, I'm not the most objective person when it comes to my own work.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you know anyone who is?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Actually, I do.  My friend <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haven%20Kimmel">Haven Kimmel</ref>, the writer, has a mind like a finely tuned laser.  She has perspective.  I don't have that ability to step back like that.</p>
<head id="On_the_response_to_his_work_from_addicts">On the response to his work from addicts</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How does it feel to be a hero to addicts?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  You know what?  I just want addicts to stop.  I want addicts to do whatever it takes.  If it takes thinking of me as a hero, fine.  If it takes thinking I'm a jerk, fine.  If my book makes someone look at themselves, or look at their lives, then that's what I want.  I know that I am absolutely happy in my life.  I'm pretty happy, and I've certainly accomplished a lot, and  I accomplished everything because I don't drink.  That's the only variable.  Nothing else in my life changed except I stopped drinking and taking drugs.  You have to replace alcohol or drugs or sex, or food, whatever the drug is, with something else.  You have to replace it--</p>
</text>
