<text id="autogum_interview_doc116" title="part2_Wikinews interviews specialists on China, Iran, Russia support for al-Assad" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-09-15" dateModified="2015-10-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_China%2C_Iran%2C_Russia_support_for_al-Assad" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you think a political solution is the only realistic means to resolve the Syrian issue?</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of interviewee Kerry Brown. Image: Kerry Brown.</caption></figure>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Roggeveen</hi>: At the moment, both sides [<hi rend="italic">in Syria</hi>] evidently feel they can still obtain their objectives through force. Perhaps one of them will be proved right; or, perhaps there will be a long-term stalemate with Syria split between regime and opposition forces.</item></list>
<p>One important change is the chemical weapons agreement; which now makes it much more difficult for the US or Israel to intervene militarily. The deal also gives the regime some degree of status as a legal authority with which outside powers must negotiate. That weakens the hand of the opposition; but, it could open a door for an international diplomatic intervention to achieve — firstly — a cease fire. and perhaps then something more substantive.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Brown</hi>: There is no appetite for the kinds of expensive and very hard interventions [<hi rend="italic">undertaken</hi>] in Iraq and Afghanistan. And, in any case, the US and its allies don't have the money to fund this, and their publics evidently feel no case has been made yet for getting involved. People are weary of the endless arguments in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Middle-East">Middle-East</ref>, and feel that they should now be left to deal with their own issues. China, in particular, has tried to maintain as strong a [...] network of benign support in the region as possible, while avoiding getting sucked into problems. There is no viable opposition in Syria that would make it easier to justify intervention; and, no easy way of seeing how this tragic civil war is going to be easily ended.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Farhi</hi>: Syria has become the arena for a proxy war among regional and extra-regional players and yes its civil war will not end until all key players and their external supporters develop a political will to end the conflict. For the conflict to end, the bankers feeding the conflict should agree to stop funding it.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Mitter</hi>: Yes. But, it will depend on Russia, China, and the US, being able to come up with a compromise solution. That looks [<hi rend="italic">to be</hi>] a long way off.</item></list></p>
<head id="Iran">Iran</head>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free%20Syrian%20Army">Free Syrian Army</ref> soldiers involved in the civil war. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Voice_of_America">Voice of America</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  For many years, Syria has been considered Iran's "closest ally". What vested interest does the Iranian government have in keeping Bashar al-Assad in power? </p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Kamrava</hi>: These interests are primarily strategic, with both countries sharing common interests in relation to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lebanon">Lebanon</ref> — particularly the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hezbollah">Hezbollah</ref> group — and [as] deterrence against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israel</ref>[<hi rend="italic">i intervention</hi>].</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Martel</hi>: Iran's interests align very closely with that of Russia in supporting Syria and opposing the United States. Further, during this last week, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vladimir_Putin">President Putin</ref> offered to help Iran build a second <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nuclear_power">nuclear reactor</ref>. The policies of Russia, Iran, and Syria align quite closely; thus leading some — such as myself — to argue that we are seeing the rise of an "authoritarian axis" of states, whose policies are coordinated.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Posch</hi>: First, Syria was Iran's only ally against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Saddam_Hussein">Saddam Hussein</ref> and [<hi rend="italic">an</hi>] indispensable partner in Lebanon since the early 1980s.</item></list></p>
</text>
