<text id="autogum_interview_doc176" title="part0_Wikinews interviews 0 A.D. game development team" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-03-22" dateModified="2011-11-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_0_A.D._game_development_team" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews 0 A.D. game development team</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 22, 2011</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/0%20A.D.">0 A.D.</ref></hi> is a historical, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/open%20source">open source</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/real-time%20strategy">strategy</ref> game, published by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wildfire%20Games">Wildfire Games</ref>. It focuses on the period between 500<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anno%20Domini">BC</ref> and 500<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anno%20Domini">AD</ref>. The game will be released in two parts: the first covering the pre-AD period, and the second running to 500AD. With development well underway, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> interviewed the development team.</p>
<figure><caption>Video clip of 0 A.D. Image: Wildfire Games.</caption></figure>
<p>Aviv Sharon, a 24-year-old <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israeli</ref> student responsible for the project's PR, compiled the below Q&amp;A, which the full team approved prior to publication.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Baptiste Domps</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Could you introduce the development team of 0 A.D. ?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Aviv Sharon</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> We are Wildfire Games, a group of approximately 15-20 people from around the world developing 0 A.D., a free, open-source game of ancient warfare. Cumulatively, about 100 different people have contributed to 0 A.D. over time. Our ages have ranged from 15 to &gt;65 and our locations range from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_America">North America</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Europe">Europe</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">India</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Zealand">New Zealand</ref>. The contributions to 0 A.D. are coordinated by a team of department heads led by a lead producer, Erik Johansson (feneur), who is 25 years old from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">BD</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Who are the participants ? Salarieds or benevolents ?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">AS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> All contributions to 0 A.D. so far have been on a voluntary basis only. To speed up development, however, we have decided to raise enough money to support 160 hours of paid development of the 0 A.D. codebase. We have tentatively selected the team member who will receive this compensation, Philip Taylor (Ykkrosh), but decided to hold off for a few months until we start using these funds to wait until he has more time to dedicate to 0 A.D. development. Otherwise, 0 A.D. development will continue to be voluntary, and all funds donated to 0 A.D. will be used for team expenses only, such as website hosting costs.</p>
<figure><caption>A sample fight scene. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Brightgalrs">Robert Schultz de Plainsboro</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">BD</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why did you want to make games?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">AS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> There are several different reasons. Originally, 0 A.D. was born out of a desire to innovate within the RTS genre. We felt, and still feel, that this genre has a lot of potential for innovation and we wish to explore that with some different rules. 0 A.D. started out as a total conversion mod for Age of Empires II: The Age of Kings, until team members at that time ran into the limitations of changing a closed-source game. Hence, as a wish to break free from the limitations of other games' engines, the standalone version of 0 A.D. was conceived and its development continues to this day.</p>
<p>Some other reasons include a deep appreciation of ancient history; the wish to improve our skills and be recognized for our talents; and a determination to prove that a group of volunteers collaborating over the internet can make a game that rivals the commercial, proprietary AAA titles.</p>
</text>
