<text id="autogum_interview_doc1014" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Jon Greenspon, independent candidate for US President" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-03-01" dateModified="2019-08-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Jon_Greenspon%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>Regarding our Economy, let's just say we’re not so good here. Presently we have three choices in dealing with the mounting oil crisis we're under. 1. We can actively, and emphatically, start to look into alternative fuels, energy sources and conservation techniques to reduce the usage and emissions we are generating; 2. We can temporarily stem the costs incurred in our waste by accessing the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arctic%20National%20Wildlife%20Refuge">Alaskan National Wildlife Refuge</ref> (ANWR) and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Colorado">Colorado</ref> oil reserves, buying us both time to develop alternate systems, and reduce our costs from $100+/barrel in crude, as well as giving Americans some breathing room in their wallets; or 3. We can look at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/OPEC">OPEC</ref> and other petroleum regions and say either start a 1970's style rationing system, or bankrupt ourselves by meeting foreign controlled prices. I prefer 1 and 2 over the third option. Similarly, we need to pare down the national deficit. This isn't going to be easy or pretty. Congress has worked extremely hard at wasting taxpayer monies, and they really don't have a clue on how to balance a checkbook, let alone a national bank account.</p>
<p>Lastly, the Congress. When was the last time you could honestly say that Congress was looking out for the interests of the American people? It's hard to believe they aren't working against the common interest when the Congress is dealing with legislation that includes granting amnesty to all illegal immigrants (when 87% of the public is vocally opposed), spending million of taxpayer dollars on a highway between two towns in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Alaska">Alaska</ref> (a highway that will be impassable for more than half the year), or trying to wrangle a million dollars on a museum to a 1960's music event. Personally, I think those monies would have been better spent on trying to balance the budget, or given back to the states for programs that more directly affect the population.</p>
<p>Face it, our federal legislators don't want to fix problems, they are more interested in making the American public afraid of issues and then telling you who's to blame... I’ll come right out and tell you who's to blame. We are. We've left the henhouse unguarded for too long.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Campaigning for the American presidency is one of the most expensive exercises in the world. How do you deal with the cost and fundraising?</hi></p>
<p>Very carefully. As opposed to the major candidates, all of whom have access to vast monetary resources and matching funds, an independent's campaign requires a coordinated effort to even obtain a basic monthly operating fund.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Do you have a running mate yet? Who are they? What are you/were you looking for in a running mate?</hi></p>
<p>I have not selected a running mate for the 2008 election at present. As an independent/third-party candidate, I have aligned myself with a minor party, and we are conducting a party ballot. I will be more then eager to work with a running mate of the party’s selection. If given the open opportunity, my personal selections for a running mate would include either <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill%20Owens%20(Colorado%20politician)">William Owens</ref> (former Governor of the State of Colorado) or Frank McEnulty, who is himself another third-party/independent candidate.</p>
</text>
