<text id="autogum_interview_doc812" title="part5_Frank Messina: An interview with the &amp;apos;Mets Poet&amp;apos;" shortTile="partfrank-messina" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-03" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Frank_Messina%3A_An_interview_with_the_%27Mets_Poet%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  Loving a baseball team is having to put up with the imperfections, the routine of what kind of mood is it going to be today.  It doesn't come down to whether we are going to win or lose, it comes down to: is the player going to perform this way?  Or , is the pitcher going to be ambivalent?  Am I even going to have enough strength to watch this game?  Am I going to wash my hands?  Am  I going to lay in bed all day?  What am I going to do?  The game becomes a reflection of true life in that way.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The difference is that you know what to expect from the players on the Mets.  They have defined roles and there is some certitude.  With women, as the players change you don't know what they are going to do; whereas in baseball the players have roles and you know what to expect of them.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  It's a dangerous proposition being any fan, but particularly a Mets fan, because you are going to have to accept you will fall in love with imperfection.  When you fall in love with a woman, you are accepting them for all their flaws, those elements that make them human, worts and all.  And I accept my team worts and all.  They have given me a great deal of joy, a great deal of entertainment, exhilaration, and a hell of a lot of pain like in any fan.  This isn't the Brady Bunch, this isn't Leave it to Beaver.  Few things are, if anything.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You were the recipient of the 1993 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allen%20Ginsberg">Allen Ginsberg</ref> Poetry Award.  In 1996 I met Ginsberg at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naropa%20Institute">Naropa Institute</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boulder,%20Colorado">Boulder</ref>.  I asked him about NAMBLA, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North%20American%20Man/Boy%20Love%20Association">North American Man/Boy Love Association</ref>.  He told me to follow him into the bathroom.  As I stood there he peed and told me he wasn't for having sex with children, but that he thought that age-of-consent laws were outdated, that he knew what he wanted when he was fifteen and that he thought everyone does at that age.  He said he wasn't for sex with children, but that it should not be illegal to have sex at that age.  When you accepted the Ginsberg award, did you have an issue with some of his political stances?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  I was too young at the time to realize what he thought.  I never knew what went on behind closed doors with Allen, and aside from meeting him a few times, I never knew him on a personal level.  I accepted the nomination, like young people do each year, because of his poetry, not because of his politics.  I was proud.  That is what the award was designed for.  There are laws in this country for a reason, to protect children and to protect people from predators.  Whether Allen was a predator or not, I don't have any idea.</p>
</text>
