<text id="autogum_interview_doc677" title="part0_Sam Brownback on running for President, gay rights, the Middle East and religion" shortTile="partsam-brownback" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-12" dateModified="2014-12-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sam_Brownback_on_running_for_President%2C_gay_rights%2C_the_Middle_East_and_religion" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sam Brownback on running for President, gay rights, the Middle East and religion</head>
 This article mentions the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>, one of its projects, or people related to it. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> is a project of the Wikimedia Foundation.
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 15, 2007</hi></p>
<figure rend="Sam Brownback official portrait 3.jpg"></figure><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sam%20Brownback">Sam Brownback</ref> is perplexed.  The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._Senator">U.S. Senator</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kansas">Kansas</ref> and Presidential candidate is a Republican whose politics—he is against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Same-sex_marriage">marriage for gay people</ref>, he is against abortion, and he has a clean image in a party tainted by scandal—should speak favorably to the party's base.  But it has not.  "I'm baffled by that myself," Senator Brownback told <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>.  "We haven't been able to raise money."  
<p>A recent poll in Iowa has put him in eighth place, with 2% supporting his campaign.  "If we don't finish fourth or better in Iowa...we'll pull out."  </p>
<p>Senator Brownback's relationship with God infuses almost every answer you find below.  Although he doesn't feel "competent" to explain why God would dislike gays, he does feel strongly that allowing two men or two women to enter into the union of marriage will destroy it for heterosexuals.  Pointing to the research of Stanley Kurtz at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoover%20Institution">Hoover Institution</ref>, Brownback asserts that Northern Europeans have "taken the sacredness out of the institution." </p>
<p>In the interview, Senator Brownback discusses the tug-and-pull that befalls him when his constituents show up at his office and say, "Look, I'm a conservative, but we need this bridge, we need this subsidy, we need this hospital.”  Brownback feels this spending system needs to be changed; however, when it comes to energy policy, Brownback is there for his constituents.  David Shankbone asked the Kansas Senator, a supporter of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cellulosic%20ethanol">cellulosic ethanol</ref>, why he doesn't support the lowering of tariffs on sugar since <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/sugar%20ethanol">sugar ethanol</ref> delivers 8 times the energy output of cellulosic ethanol.  Brazil, in particular, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethanol%20fuel%20in%20Brazil">has become energy independent</ref> because of its sugar ethanol program.  It's cheaper to produce, and there is vastly more bang for the buck in sugar fuel than in corn fuel; an entire country no longer needs to import oil because of it.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sucrose#Trade_and_economics">Federal tariffs</ref> currently make sugar ethanol too expensive in the United States.  "You're going to kill the ethanol industry here just as it gets going," was Senator Brownback's response.  However, there is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethanol%20fuel%20in%20the%20United%20States">debate over whether the process</ref> to make corn ethanol uses more energy than the ethanol itself produces.  </p>
<p>Below is David Shankbone's interview with Senator Sam Brownback.</p>
<head id="On_running_in_and_possibly_leaving_the_Presidential_race">On running in and possibly leaving the Presidential race</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  Senator Brownback, how are you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sam Brownback:</hi>  I'm fine; headed into <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iowa">Iowa</ref>.  I’m doing a big event with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Joe_Biden">Joe Biden</ref> tomorrow on a political solution in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq_War">Iraq</ref>.</p>
</text>
