<text id="autogum_interview_doc933" title="part8_An interview with gossip columnist Michael Musto on the art of celebrity journalism" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-05" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_gossip_columnist_Michael_Musto_on_the_art_of_celebrity_journalism" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  I guess...  it helps to have talent too, though, and <hi rend="italic">thankfully</hi> I have it in spades! [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Has the Iraq War affected your writing at all?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  Yeah, it's made me more, you know...whenever there's a Republican President you just bash them every week in between all the celebrity gossip, but then that can become tiresome.  It's changed in the sense that so many more movies are coming out, and have been for the last three years, not only about Iraq, but with this kind of gloomy-doomy worldview.  And most of them are terrible movies.  High aspirations can pave the road to hell, sometimes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Has if affected your world view?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  Yeah.  I grew up with Vietnam, and to see it happening all over again is really disturbing.  When you get out of something like Vietnam and you enter a freer time, you don't expect to go back to something that hideous and pointless.  The pointless bloodshed in the name of spreading democracy is just ludicrous.  Obviously, democracy’s not his goal.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Hillary or Barack?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  Well, it looks like Hillary is going to get the nomination.  I don't know, though; I don't think either one of them can win.  To me, it's devastating that we are being handed a plum.  This is the time in history when, if we set up a viable candidate, we would most have a chance to get in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White%20House">White House</ref>, and we're going to blow it again.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who would be your dream candidate?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  It wouldn't be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al%20Gore">Al Gore</ref> because he's so boring and I don't really care about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/global%20warming">global warming</ref>; I think it's fabulous.  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  I'm wearing my flip flops in October, what's the problem (he said with a joke)!</p>
<p>My ideal candidate?  I guess Gary Coleman.  I mean, whatever...he's as good as the other ones.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  By magic microphone you have to talk to Osama bin Laden, but you can't apprehend him.  What do you say?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  If we ever find you, we're <hi rend="italic">not</hi> going to get Marcia Clarke to prosecute because we really want you to lose.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How would you describe your style of dress?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  It's kind of early <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reign%20of%20Terror">Reign of Terror</ref> [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]].  Which is also my home decorating style!  I shop at thrift shops.  I got this at Webers's, which is next to Jacks 99 Cent Store.  It was US$5.00.  It's my new 'big' buy of the year.  I just don't throw anything out, and I don't buy anything new.  Why bother?  But I do have some fabulous outfits, like if I really need to be 'on.'</p>
</text>
