<text id="autogum_interview_doc1115" title="part0_Murray Hill on the life and versatility of a New York drag king" shortTile="partmurray-hill-life" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Murray_Hill_on_the_life_and_versatility_of_a_New_York_drag_king" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Murray Hill on the life and versatility of a New York drag king</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 19, 2007</hi></p>
<figure rend="Murray Hill by David Shankbone.jpg"></figure>Drag—dressing in the clothing atypical of your born gender—in recent years has found mainstream success.  Films such as <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Adventures%20of%20Priscilla,%20Queen%20of%20the%20Desert">Priscilla, Queen of the Desert</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Midnight%20in%20the%20Garden%20of%20Good%20and%20Evil%20(film)">Midnight in the Garden of Good and Evil</ref></hi> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/To%20Wong%20Foo,%20Thanks%20for%20Everything!%20Julie%20Newmar">To Wong Foo, Thanks for Everything! Julie Newmar</ref></hi> have prominently featured drag performers.  But they have all focused on men in drag as women.
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murray%20Hill%20(performer)">Murray Hill</ref> is a comedian, emcee and performer.  He is also a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drag%20king">drag king</ref>.  Called "The Hardest Working Middle-aged Man in Show Business", <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20New%20York%20Times">The New York Times</ref></hi> christened him "the current reigning patriarch of the downtown performance community."  He is seemingly everywhere, emceeing a bingo night at the now closed, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jimmy%20Fallon">Jimmy Fallon</ref>-backed Mo Pitkins' House of Satisfaction on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avenue%20A">Avenue A</ref>, or hosting the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyamorous">Polyamorous</ref> Pride Day in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central%20Park">Central Park</ref>.  Hill has become a legend in New York's "anything goes" counterculture theater scene who is beginning to find mainstream success; which would be a first for a drag king.  </p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref>'s examination of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20City">New York City</ref>'s culture has brought him to the whip's end of a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business:_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes">BDSM dungeon</ref>, on the phone with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/RuPaul_speaks_about_society_and_the_state_of_drag_as_performance_art">RuPaul</ref>, matching wits with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_gossip_columnist_Michael_Musto_on_the_art_of_celebrity_journalism">Michael Musto</ref>, grilling <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism,_Iraq_and_his_life">Gay Talese</ref>, eating dinner with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction,_writing,_his_family_and_his_new_book">Augusten Burroughs</ref> and quizzing the bands that play the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Music">Bowery Ballroom</ref>.  In this segment he talks to downtown legend <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murray%20Hill%20(performer)">Murray Hill</ref>, former New York City mayoral candidate and comedian, on the last night of Mo Pitkins' House of Satisfaction.</p>
<head id="Murray_Hill_the_performer">Murray Hill the performer</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">David Shankbone:  Where is Murray Hill from?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Murray Hill:</hi>  Murray Hill is from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murray%20Hill%20(Manhattan)">Murray Hill</ref>.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/23rd%20Street%20(Manhattan)">23rd Street</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third%20Avenue">Third Avenue</ref>.  What I like to tell the kids is I was born in the back seat of a cab right there, which is how I got the name.  The cab driver asked my dad, ‘Is it a boy or a girl?’ and my dad said, ‘No.’  I knew right then and there, kid, that I was going to wind up in Showbiz!  And here I am!  Fifty-five years later, lookin’ good!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What does Murray Hill do on a Saturday?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  I’m doing shows.  I am the only entertainer who has the most diverse working schedule, and my nickname is “The Hardest Working Middle-aged Man in Show Business.”  This Saturday I hosted the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polyamory">Polyamorous</ref> Pride Day in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central%20Park,%20New%20York">Central Park</ref>.  That was 106th Street and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central%20Park%20West">Central Park West</ref>.  Then I got into a cab and a half later I was on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canal%20Street%20(Manhattan)">Canal Street</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broadway%20(Manhattan)">West Broadway</ref> to be in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burlesque">burlesque</ref> show I hosted for a completely different audience.  And that’s showbiz!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you ever talk about the Iraq War in your routines?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  I don’t necessarily talk about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">war</ref>, specifically.  I do not speak favorably about our <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20W.%20Bush">President</ref>.</p>
</text>
