<text id="autogum_interview_doc964" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Fred Karger, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-04-23" dateModified="2014-03-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Fred_Karger%2C_U.S._Republican_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><p>So I had asked all the Republican candidates running to have lunch, dinner, coffee with me. I thought it would be a good opportunity for the other Republicans running, and in a friendly manner to meet, to get to know an openly gay candidate for president, which no one has done before. But I think it was just my olive branch. As I was saying earlier, what Ronald Reagan did and what he taught me, which was to reach out to everybody. And certainly there’s some Republicans, who have said some very bad things about my community and I want to help them based on that and come up with the areas we have in common as opposed to the areas where we disagree.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You previously said that one of your goals in your campaign was to participate in a GOP presidential debate, now that no more debates have been scheduled, what are you hoping to achieve by continuing your campaign?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Fred Karger</hi>: Well that had been my primary goal to get in a presidential debate. A big feat for someone who has never run for office before and doesn't have tens of millions of dollars to spend on his campaign. I came very close. I did qualify. I met the criteria for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Fox_News">Fox News</ref> debate last August in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ames,%20Iowa">Ames, Iowa</ref>, but they changed the rules and prohibited me from participating. So I am holding out hope that there still may be another debate. There's talk of a Texas debate. Governor Romney might not do anymore but there may be a situation where there's just a handful of candidates. There's only four of us now that are still actively running that are on state ballots like California and Utah. So I still have hope that there might be a debate. But short of that I will be campaigning vigorously in California. That's the next ballot I am on.</p>
<p>
<p>| <hi rend="bold">The numbers obviously don't add up for me to be the nominee, but I can certainly be a factor and that is one of my goals.</hi></p>
</p>
<p>We are shooting our first California commercial on Saturday. It's an elaborate production, and I'm hoping we'll be running it on television in California. Hopefully it will catch on in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viral%20video">viral</ref> manner like some of our commercials have and maybe be kind of an introduction to California about my campaign years. So I'm going to be spending the next almost eight weeks all up and down my home state. I'm the only Californian on the ballot. And on our California ballot, it doesn't list occupation. It just lists hometown and state. So I will have <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laguna%20Beach,%20California">Laguna Beach, California</ref> as my ballot designation, which none of the other three remaining candidates, of course, are from here. So that's an advantage. And we've got a lot of volunteers. A lot up and down the state. And I hope to register here. I'm going to be targeting three congressional districts, because the delegates are awarded by congressional district here. So I'm hopeful that I can pull out some delegates and be more of a factor in this race. The numbers obviously don't add up for me to be the nominee, but I can certainly be a factor and that is one of my goals.</p></p>
</text>
