<text id="autogum_interview_doc692" title="part0_RuPaul speaks about society and the state of drag as performance art" shortTile="partrupaul-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-06" dateModified="2019-02-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/RuPaul_speaks_about_society_and_the_state_of_drag_as_performance_art" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>RuPaul speaks about society and the state of drag as performance art</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 6, 2007</hi></p>
<p>Few artists ever penetrate the subconscious level of American culture the way <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RuPaul">RuPaul Andre Charles</ref> did with the 1993 album <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supermodel%20of%20the%20World">Supermodel of the World</ref></hi>.  It was groundbreaking not only because in the midst of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grunge">Grunge</ref> phenomenon did Charles have a dance hit on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MTV">MTV</ref>, but because he did it as RuPaul, formerly known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Starbooty">Starbooty</ref>, a supermodel drag queen with a message: love everyone.  A duet with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elton%20John">Elton John</ref>, an endorsement deal with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MAC">MAC cosmetics</ref>, an eponymous talk show on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VH-1">VH-1</ref> and roles in film propelled RuPaul into the new millennium.  </p>
<p>In July, RuPaul's movie <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Starrbooty">Starrbooty </ref></hi> began playing at film festivals and it is set to be released on DVD October 31st.  <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> recently spoke with RuPaul by telephone in Los Angeles, where she is to appear on stage for <hi rend="italic">DIVAS Simply Singing!</hi>, a benefit for HIV-AIDS.  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How are you doing?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  Everything is great.  I just settled into my new hotel room in downtown <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los%20Angeles">Los Angeles</ref>. I have never stayed downtown, so I wanted to try it out.  L.A. is one of those traditional big cities where nobody goes downtown, but they are trying to change that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you like Los Angeles?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  I love L.A.  I’m from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San%20Diego">San Diego</ref>, and I lived here for six years.  It took me four years to fall in love with it and then those last two years I had fallen head over heels in love with it.  Where are you from?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Me?  I’m from all over.  I have lived in 17 cities, six states and three countries.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  Where were you when you were 15?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Georgia, in a small town at the bottom of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fulton%20County,%20Georgia">Fulton County</ref> called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palmetto,%20Georgia">Palmetto</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  When I was in Georgia I went to South Fulton Technical School.  The last high school I ever went to was...actually, I don’t remember the name of it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you miss <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atlanta">Atlanta</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">RP:</hi>  I miss the Atlanta that I lived in.  That Atlanta is long gone.  It’s like a childhood friend who underwent head to toe plastic surgery and who I don’t recognize anymore.  It’s not that I don’t like it; I do like it.   It’s just not the Atlanta that I grew up with.  It looks different because it went through that boomtown phase and so it has been transient.  What made Georgia <hi rend="italic">Georgia</hi> to me is gone.  The last time I stayed in a hotel there my room was overlooking a construction site, and I realized the building that was torn down was a building that I had seen get built.  And it had been torn down to build a new building.  It was something you don’t expect to see in your lifetime.</p>
</text>
