<text id="autogum_interview_doc708" title="part4_Canada&amp;apos;s Beaches—East York (Ward 32) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-beacheseast" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-21" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Beaches%E2%80%94East_York_%28Ward_32%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> This is not only a Ward, but it is my home.  I would be honoured to represent my home and ensure it is looked after to the fullest of my abilities.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Currently I am a volunteer for Community Centre 55, helping with whatever they need and in their Christmas hamper efforts for many years. I have worked with the Lions Club on occasion helping in their Easter Parade work.  I also have helped for many years in trash cleanup of the area, and have been a leader for Girl Guides of Canada for a local unit for over 10 years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I was very happy when have bid for Olympics and the World's Fair.  I have been to other countries and attended such functions.  Toronto needs something like this to help the city financially and promote what a wonderful place Toronto is. I hope in the future we are awarded such an honour.</p>
<p>Least Desirable -  Having the current city council administer themselves an 8% wage increase has to be the worst decision they have made to date. Their wages and increase should be decided by a non-patrician group with council kept out of the process.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> If you were elected as a "rookie" councillor, What would you bring to the table beyond the incumbent?  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I hope that I may bring a regular citizens outlook to city council.   We need a balanced budget, after all everyone else in the general public has to work with the money they have.  Lastly, we have to realize that we are paid by the people, we work for the people and we should all be accountable to the people on a daily basis.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Toronto is my home.  It a city full of diversity, and different cultures.  I have traveled the world and discovered that all that I have purchased is already available to me in Toronto.  I love the mix of cultures, and the many different restaurants I have frequented.  I have friends from all over the world.  I was lucky enough to have a visiting princess meet me in 1979; she wanted to meet the most diversified high school in Toronto, and that was my own.  As a student council member I was formally introduced!  Then later in 1990 I was present when Princess Diana came through my hospital.  Where else in the world could you meet a two princesses but in Toronto!</p>
</text>
