<text id="autogum_interview_doc1434" title="part0_OpenSync Interview - syncing on the free desktop" shortTile="partopensync-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-05-19" dateModified="2014-01-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/OpenSync_Interview_-_syncing_on_the_free_desktop" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>OpenSync Interview - syncing on the free desktop</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 19, 2006</hi></p>
<p>This interview intends to provide some insight into <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenSync">OpenSync</ref>, an upcoming free unified data synchronization solution for free software desktops  such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KDE">KDE</ref>, commonly used as part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU/Linux">GNU/Linux</ref> operating system.</p>
<head id="Basics">Basics</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Hi Cornelius, Armin and Tobias. As you are now getting close to version 1.0 of OpenSync, which is expected to become the new synchronisation framework for KDE and other free desktops, we are quite interested in the merits it can provide for KDE users and for developers, as well as for the Open Source Community as a whole. So there's one key-question before I move deeper into the details of OpenSync:</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What does OpenSync accomplish, that no one did before?</hi></p>
<p>Cornelius:</p>
<p>First of all it does its job of synchronizing data like addressbooks and calendars between desktop applications and mobile devices like PDAs and cell phones.</p>
<p>But the new thing about OpenSync is that it isn't tied to a particular device or a specific platform. It provides an extensible and modular framework that is easy to adopt for application developers and people implementing support for syncing with mobile devices.</p>
<p>OpenSync is also independent of the desktop platform. It will be the common syncing backend for at least KDE and GNOME and other projects are likely to join. That means that the free desktop will have one common syncing solution. This is something really new.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How do the end-users profit from using synching solutions that interface with OpenSync as framework?</hi></p>
<p>Cornelius:</p>
<p>First, the users will be able to actually synchronize all their data. By using one common framework there won't be any "missing links", where one application can sync one set of devices and another application a different one. With OpenSync all applications can sync all devices.</p>
<p>Second, the users will get a consistent and common user interface for syncing across all applications and devices. This will be much simpler to use than the current incoherent collection of syncing programs you need if you have more than the very basic needs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How does OpenSync help developers with coding?</hi></p>
<p>Cornelius:</p>
<p>It's a very flexible and well-designed framework that makes it quite easy for developers to add support for new devices and new types of data. It's also very easy to add support for OpenSync to applications.</p>
<p>The big achievement of OpenSync is that it hides all the gory details of syncing from the developers who work on applications and device support. That makes it possible for the developers to concentrate on their area of expertise without having to care what's going on behind the scenes.</p>
<p>I have written quite a lot of synchronization code in the past. Trust me, it's much better, if someone just takes care of it for you, and that's what OpenSync does.</p>
</text>
