<text id="autogum_interview_doc603" title="part8_Wikinews interviews John Wolfe, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-19" dateModified="2013-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_John_Wolfe%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>And I think also what we need to do is is that we need to ask the oil companies why it is that they're always a little bit short. It could be that they don't refine things like they should.  They always make it to where the demand is a little bit more than supply just to keep that extra pressure on oil. That needs to be investigated too. That needs to be more tightly regulated because energy is like money. The banks are the same way, energy's no different.   One's the veins of the economy and one's the arteries of the economy. And both those things need more federal oversight.  They make plenty of profit, no one's talking about taking them over.  But they need to be regulated. And these artificial shortages and things shouldn't be allowed to happen.  You can't do that. What they got is basically a monopoly.  All this would be doing is just like regulating phone companies. There can only be a few people who do it. There's not going to be that much competition. We know that.  So they actually, when a sector of the economy basically is in oligopolistic or monopolistic hands, that the government's got a right to step in and regulate on behalf of the people, because the more money that goes into energy unnecessarily, just like interest at the bank and things like that, then that hurts other parts of the economy. That means people have less money to spend at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wal-Mart">Wal-Mart</ref>. They have less money to buy furniture. They have less money to buy other goods.</p>
<p>Same with healthcare, that's why you have to regulate that. It's somewhat of a monopoly as well considering that the health care industry, the insurance companies don't have to compete. By law, they've been exempt from competition for about 50 or 60 years, which really hasn't worked out too well. I mean what we have to pay equals six or eight percent of GDP, which is twice what they have to pay in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref> in relation to their GDP. You know Germany out-exports the United States, a country of 70 million, because they don't have to factor all these health care costs for their products. Health care should be something that is individual and not related to the work. It should be paid for through the taxes. People should be afforded so much health care costs, so many health care costs, like take for instance in Germany, exports go up, prices on exports get more competitive, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balance%20of%20trade">trade deficit</ref> narrows and people have more work because you have more exports.</p>
<p>The United States is hurt. We're the only one of our competitors that doesn't have some form of a single payer that controls costs and gives people a choice of doctors. As a result, that has to be built in to the cost of the product and that makes us less competitive, makes the trade balance larger. Germany, again, a nation of 70 million, actual gross dollars, not per capita, gross dollars or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Euro">Euros</ref>, out-exports the United States of America, which has four and a half times the people of Germany, and that's pathetic.</p>
</text>
