<text id="autogum_interview_doc1153" title="part7_Obesity and the Fat Acceptance Movement: Kira Nerusskaya speaks" shortTile="partobesity-fat-acceptance" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-09" dateModified="2014-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Obesity_and_the_Fat_Acceptance_Movement%3A_Kira_Nerusskaya_speaks" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Saviors?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  I don't know if they would be saviors so much as wanting to dominate you, belittle you, into making you smaller.  It's a dominance thing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's not, 'I'm going to help her be normal' but 'I want to have control over her and see a result of that'?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  It may be.  You have to distinguish between all these types of individuals to find somebody you have something in common with, who has similar morals or values, or whatever it is that you want to find in somebody, and it's really hard.  You have some men who think it's going to be so odd and different, and they are interested in trying it.  There are men who like a larger bosom, the larger bottom, and they want more of it.  They see in a BBW that we have more of it, and they want to try it.  They are interested to walk down that road just to see what it's like.  Part fantasy, part interest, part curiosity. Maybe, to them, it's just the freak factor-- in their head we are freaks because we aren't thin. So going through the whole spectrum, it makes the pool increasing smaller to find somebody who appreciate you for just being you.  Likes you as a person and accepts or likes the package it comes in.  And at the same time, there always seems to be someone new popping their head in to  find out who/what we are.  Funny how that is. It could be that he is coming to terms with what he likes, and trying to find it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But doesn't objectify it...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Well, who just accepts it.  Who accepts that this is my friend, this is my girlfriend, this is my lover, this is my wife, as opposed to it being something that is only sexual.  I can't even tell you how many I have met in my experience over the last fourteen years in the BBW world who have skinny girlfriends, wives, lovers, whatever but are out there chasing fat girls because they actually <hi rend="italic">like it</hi>.  They like it in bed, they like the curves, they like the softness.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is there something someone has asked you to do in bed that you find offensive?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  I am open-minded enough that I don't really get offended, but you also find people in those broad categories that would say something like, "I want you to sit on me."  There are people who like to be sqwooshed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What's your reaction?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  It depends!  It depends on what kind of mood you are in, or who the person is, or what your relationship with them is, as to whether or not you would do it.  I think it defines who they are or where they are coming from, certainly.  It might be they have a wonderful relationship with that woman, and that one particular action excites them greatly, and whether you are open to exploring that with them.  Some women might not feel comfortable because they would feel objectified.  It depends on the individual.  It's hard to say.</p>
</text>
