<text id="autogum_interview_doc419" title="part4_Canada&amp;apos;s Don Valley West (Ward 26) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-don-valley" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Don_Valley_West_%28Ward_26%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> If you were elected as a "rookie" councillor, What would you bring to the table beyond the incumbent? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I would bring a determination always to keep an eye on long range goals and needs while focusing on achievable, immediate priorities, and not mortgage the future to finance a response to immediate short term political pressures.</p>
<head id="Csaba_Vegh"><ref target="http://www.csabavegh.ca/">Csaba Vegh</ref></head>
<p>37-year-old <hi rend="bold">Csaba Vegh</hi> is a private investigator.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Property taxes, crime and traffic are three hot topic issues. I believe that homeowners and businesses are being over taxed. Generation of revenue is not a problem for the city, the way we spend taxpayers money needs to be re-evaluated. We need to hire more police officers and we need to give them the resources to do their job effectively. I believe that a city the size of Toronto should have at least one regularly operating police helicopter. We can also address youth crime by giving our youth the opportunity to spend their time in healthful and productive ways. I have suggested that the city should work with the school boards to open high school gyms to their student for after school activities. Currently, a lot of school gyms are closed to students after school due to a lack of qualified supervisors. Finally, infiltration of traffic onto the streets of Leaside have incresed <hi rend="italic">[sic]</hi> drastically over the past few years. I suggest reducing vehicular access to the streets of Leaside during peak hours for non-residents or their visitors. I also support the construction of the Redway Rd. extension to ease traffic flow.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> As I mentioned before, I believe that that property taxes for homeowners and businesses need to be frozen. We are being over taxed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have lived in ward 26 for thirty years. I have also attended school here, worked here, and I have been a volunteer football coach at Leaside High School since 1989. I believe that I can be a strong and effective voice for our community at City Hall without partisan influence because I am not a member of any political party.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have deep roots in the community. Being a long time resident, I share the views and concerns of quite a number of the residents of Ward 26.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have been a volunteer football coach at Leaside High School since 1989. I am also a volunteer with the Scarborough Minor Football Association. And, I have been a volunteer coach for the Leaside Hockey Association.</p>
</text>
