<text id="autogum_interview_doc1008" title="part4_Wikinews interviews Spain's most decorated Paralympian, Teresa Perales" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-01-19" dateModified="2015-11-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Spain%27s_most_decorated_Paralympian%2C_Teresa_Perales" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> That happened in cycling. Set a World Record, did not win a medal.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>: Yes, I know. Yes, but they have, like in ski. In ski what they do is, time goes slower depending in which category you are in, so that at the end it is the same. Then the public really see that the time is going down and they are seeing a timer, seeing the time slowing down, but at the end they are seeing the same time. Then they see who's won because they can see the time. The problem happens in sports in which several of us compete simultaneously, eight lanes. It's difficult to understand. ((es))Spanish language: ‍Sí, lo sé. Sí, pero ellos tienen igual que en ski. En ski lo que hacen es, el tiempo pasa más despacio en función de qué categoría eres, para que al final sea lo mismo. Entonces el público realmente ve que el tiempo está bajando y está viendo un cronómetro, está viendo un tiempo que ve que está yendo más lento, pero al final está viendo el mismo tiempo. Entonces ve que ha ganado porque lo está viendo en el tiempo. El problema es en deportes en los que competimos varios deportistas a la vez, ocho calles. Es dificil de comprender.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Have you ever had any problems with in your career where they've said...?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>: No. At first I was in New Zealand, I was S6, and then in 2000? No, in 1999, in the European Championships, I was reclassified, and now I am S5, SB4, and SM5, because they saw my arm is not very good. ((es))Spanish language: ‍ No. Al principio en Nueva Zelanda era S6, y luego en ¿2000? No, en 1999, en los Campeonatos de Europa, me bajaron, me reclasificaron, y ahora soy S5, SB4 y SM5, porque vieron que mi brazo no era muy bueno.</p>
<head id="Mixing_sport_and_politics">Mixing sport and politics</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> In the US, there is a view that celebrities and sportspeople should stay out of politics because... they're dumb.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>: [Laughs]. Okay, this doesn't happen in Spain. ((es))Spanish language: ‍ [Risas] Vale, esto no pasa en España.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Should sportspeople be involved and do Paralympians especially, should they be more involved because of the nature of the sport they are doing in politics, and is it something in Spain and should be done elsewhere in the world... Should there be a call for more Paralympians in politics? Because you protested in Madrid...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>: Yes! ((es))Spanish language: ‍¡Sí!</p>
<figure><caption> Paralympic swimmer Teresa Perales with Miguel Carballeda; the president of the Spanish Paralympic Committee told IOC inspectors Madrid would stage the "greatest Paralympic Games ever."Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Atr1992">Atr1992</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> And you were a politician.</p>
</text>
