<text id="autogum_interview_doc1118" title="part3_Murray Hill on the life and versatility of a New York drag king" shortTile="partmurray-hill-life" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Murray_Hill_on_the_life_and_versatility_of_a_New_York_drag_king" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you dating anyone?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  Quite a few.  I will say my public girlfriend Is Dirty Martini; my <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hollywood">Hollywood</ref> wife.  My <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beard%20(female%20companion)">Beard</ref>, so to speak.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20New%20York%20Times">The New York Times</ref></hi> article made it seem like you are embodying this character, that you have become him, and have no personality outside of Murray Hill.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  Well, I don’t know about <hi rend="italic">that</hi>.  I think of myself as an entertainer and there are definitely some old school references, and I try to make it a little easier for people and say I am a comedian.   I think people have an easier time understanding what that is.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you consider yourself <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/transgendered">transgendered</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  I really don’t label myself.  It’s a conscious—possibly political—decision and I try not to be labeled by gender.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you consider yourself butch?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  I consider myself a tough guy.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butch">Butch</ref> is another label that doesn’t sit well with me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Because it denies your femininity as well?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  No, just because people like to put narrowing labels on sexuality.  I try to challenge that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you surprise yourself with your sexuality?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  What surprises me is I’m often in a lot of uncomfortable situations as Murray, and it surprises me how accepted I am in certain places.  It’s mind-blowing.  What I do find surprising is when I go to a wedding, and then all the gender-sexuality issues are in a neon shining light, and that’s when I’m like, ‘Whoa!’  I really can say I think of myself as what I am, and I don’t try to put that in a box.  But when I go to a wedding, for example, I’m like, “Agh!” for the way I’m treated, looked at, talked about.</p>
<head id="Drag_as_performance_art_for_women">Drag as performance art for women</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You don’t like the phrase drag king, is that correct?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  No, somebody said that—<hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi> wrote an article about me and they made it seem like I don’t like the phrase ‘drag king’.  What I tried to explain to them is that I don’t like to be labeled as anything that people form a very narrow viewpoint about.  This goes for drag king, this goes for anything else.  When you say ‘<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/drag%20king">drag king</ref>’ it’s a very specific thing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is a drag king?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  A cross-dresser who does some kind of performance, and I think I am much more than that.  I really hammered the press about this and I finally got to a point where I think when people assume that somebody is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queer">queer</ref>, or different, or trans, they always want to put something before their name.  And that is what drag king has been.  Why can’t you just call me a comedian like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerry%20Seinfeld">Jerry Seinfeld</ref> is called a comedian?</p>
</text>
