<text id="autogum_interview_doc072" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Australian wheelchair basketball coach Tom Kyle" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-06-30" dateModified="2015-11-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_wheelchair_basketball_coach_Tom_Kyle" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yes!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tom Kyle:</hi> So that was an amazing experience to go on that tour and to see what a championship team looks like under the competition of that ilk. And I was then the assistant coach basically right through to London. After London, Ben was quite happy for me to continue. I was doing it voluntarily. By this stage, 2011, I'd given up all the Villanova stuff so I concentrated just on the wheelchair and my Queensland group. And I started to build the Queensland junior program, which featured Tom O'Neill-Thorne, Jordon Bartley, Bailey Rowland, all of those sort of players. You probably don't know too many of them, but,</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tom Kyle:</hi>   They're all the up-and-comers. And three of those were in last year's, 2013 under-23s team. So in 2012 obviously we went to Varese then on to London for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2012_Summer_Paralympics">Paras</ref>. Won silver in that. When I came back, Ben asked me to do the under-23s as the head coach, and asked me who I wanted as my assistant, so in the December, we, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Gould">David Gould</ref> and I...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So you selected David as your assistant?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tom Kyle:</hi> Yes! Yes! Yes! I had a lot of dealings with David, seeing him with the Gliders. Liked what I saw. Plus I'd also seen him with the Adelaide Thunder. He was coaching them for a while, and I really liked the way he worked with kids. He'd also done a camp with the under-23s in 2012 because I couldn't attend, himself and Sonia Taylor. What was Sonia's previous name before she married <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nick%20Taylor%20(basketball)">Nick Taylor</ref>? [...] Anyway, they did a development camp in January 2012 with the under-23s group because I couldn't attend. Good feedback coming back from that. In the April, the Rollers had gone off to Verase, and there was an opportunity to go to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dubai">Dubai</ref> with the under-23/25 age group. So David and Sonia took them to Dubai and did a good job with them, a really great job with them. So the job for the 23s came up in November 2012. I applied. Got the job. And then was asked who I would want as my assistants, and Ben told me who the other applicants were and I told him, yep, happy with both of those.  David became my first assistant [...] So we took the under-23s group in December. Had a couple of camps in the first part of 2013, getting ready for the world championships in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Turkey">Turkey</ref> in September. At that stage we got to about June, and the head coach for the Gliders came up as a full time position.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  They hadn't had a full-time coach before.</p>
<figure><caption>Tom Kyle addresses his players at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2014_Women's_World_Wheelchair_Basketball_Championship">2014 Women's World Wheelchair Basketball Championship</ref>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Hawkeye7">Hawkeye7</ref>.</caption></figure>
</text>
