<text id="autogum_interview_doc1136" title="part2_Social networking site lets users run virtual campaign for US president" shortTile="partsocial-networking" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-03-21" dateModified="2012-11-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Social_networking_site_lets_users_run_virtual_campaign_for_US_president" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Many of the top-rated candidates on your site are independent or third party candidates. Why is this the case online but not in real life?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EG: </hi>It has to do with viability. We took a survey several months ago and found that many of the candidates who were professed third party supporters intended to vote for either a Democrat or Republican in the real election.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you think most users take the site’s political aspects seriously, or are they more interested in the social networking aspect?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EG: </hi>It's all about the politics.  I think most of our users have accounts on MySpace and Facebook, and use U4prez strictly for the political dialogue. </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">In your opinion, has the internet has significantly affected the way presidential elections unfold?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EG: </hi>Absolutely.  The support and money raised by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ron_Paul">Ron Paul</ref> ultimately led to the nomination of John McCain. The more traditionally conservative candidates lost millions to Paul.   This was entirely an internet phenomenon.  Because of the communication capabilities of the web, people who have a strong interest in politics naturally migrate to the web.  At u4prez for example, our members aren't likely voters, they are voters.  This is true for just about any politically oriented site.  Some of the candidates are picking up on this and using the web to deliver truly custom messages directly to real voters.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How do you think the internet will affect politics in the 2012 election and beyond?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EG: </hi>The influence of certain websites will grow exponentially.  The big question is what will the impact of the bloggers become? We are rolling out a new feature on the site in the next couple of weeks to allow our members to rate political blogs.  As of now, there is no clearinghouse for political blogs.  We are going to fill a big gap with this feature.  The print media decline will continue and probably accelerate. To help this process along we as members of the web community need a way to vet new content and content creators.</p>
<p>With some of the bigger problems facing our country, a medium is needed for more interactive debate.  Television, radio and newspapers cannot offer any solution to this problem.</p>
<p>The election of 2008 will be the last where the web isn't the driving communication force for any serious candidate.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is there any political issue that you feel has been overlooked by the media?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EG: </hi>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/baby%20boomer">baby-boomers</ref>.  In January of 2008 the first baby-boomer became eligible for social security.  In the next twenty years about 80 million more will follow.  Extrapolating the math is pretty easy.  In about fifteen short years the entire budget (as it stands now) will need to go to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/social%20security%20(United%20States)">social security</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medicare">Medicare</ref> and the prescription drug benefit.  This of course isn't going to happen.  This is a huge issue because 80 million people are going to be voting to protect those programs.</p>
</text>
