<text id="autogum_interview_doc793" title="part0_CanadaVOTES: Liberal Dr. Eric Hoskins running in Haldimand窶年orfolk" shortTile="partcanadavotes-liberal" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-18" dateModified="2019-07-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_Liberal_Dr._Eric_Hoskins_running_in_Haldimand%E2%80%94Norfolk" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>CanadaVOTES: Liberal Dr. Eric Hoskins running in Haldimand窶年orfolk</head>
<p>On October 14, 2008, Canadians will be heading to the polls for the federal election. <hi rend="bold">Liberal candidate Dr. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric%20Hoskins">Eric Hoskins</ref></hi> is standing for election in <hi rend="bold">the riding of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haldimand窶年orfolk">Haldimand窶年orfolk</ref></hi>.</p><p>Wikinews contacted Dr. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric%20Hoskins">Eric Hoskins</ref>, to talk about the issues facing Canadians, and what they and their party would do to address them. Wikinews is in the process of contacting every candidate, in every riding across the country, no matter their political stripe. All interviews are conducted over e-mail, and interviews are published unedited, allowing candidates to impart their full message to our readers, uninterrupted.</p><p>For more information, visit the campaign's official website, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page#External_links">listed below</ref>.
</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why are you running for political office, why at the federal level, why this party, and why in this riding?</hi></p>
<p>I am running for political office because I feel that it is time to change the way we do politics at the federal level. We need a bold, courageous vision for the future of our country, one that rises above party politics and speaks to all Canadians.</p>
<p>I am running in Haldimand-Norfolk because my family's roots in this riding go back five generations and nearly 150 years. I grew up here, and continue to call Simcoe my home. I have spent the last twenty years giving a voice to people, families and communities facing challenges, helping them take hold of opportunities and grow strong.</p>
<p>Now I want to stand up for Haldimand-Norfolk in Ottawa and represent its priorities. We need leadership in Haldimand-Norfolk that works for all citizens, finding common ground and seizing every opportunity for advancement of our families, communities and our economy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Previous to this campaign, have you been politically involved? How will you apply your previous work/volunteer/life experience to serving your constituents?</hi></p>
<p>Political involvement has been an important part of my professional career. After completing my studies at McMaster and Oxford universities I found myself drawn to humanitarian work as a doctor in some of the world's most troubled war zones. Upon returning to Canada I spent three years in federal government as the Senior Advisor to Foreign Minister Lloyd Axworthy. I now practice medicine and serve as President of War Child, a leading Canadian charity helping children in war zones. I have spent the last twenty years advocating for people, families and communities. This experience has prepared me to give a voice to the people of Haldimand-Norfolk in Ottawa.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">As you campaign around your riding, it's likely that some issues are mentioned more often by voters, than other issues. What would you say are the three hottest topics this election, in your riding? What would you and your party do to address these issues?</hi></p>
</text>
