<text id="autogum_interview_doc399" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Vicki Gunn, Glengarry-Prescott-Russell" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-02" dateModified="2010-06-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Vicki_Gunn%2C_Glengarry-Prescott-Russell" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Vicki Gunn, Glengarry-Prescott-Russell</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 2, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Vicki Gunn</hi> is running for the Family Coalition Party in the Ontario provincial election, in the Glengarry-Prescott-Russell riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed her regarding her values, her experience, and her campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>The basic grouping of our society, the family, has been undermined by government for years. Parents are involved in a struggle with the government to raise their families.</p>
<p>Parents are penalised should they wish to educate their children with their values. They must either pay public school taxes and pay the cost of private schooling or pay public school taxes and purchase supplies and home school their children or send their children to public school to have them taught values contrary to their family values.</p>
<p>Our teenagers are encouraged to leave home at 16 years because the government will provide them with student welfare. Our government will not provide the love and direction parents will, they will simply offer our children a way to elude family discipline and live without rules. Then we can all deplore our society where teenagers are violent and out of control.</p>
<p>Our government has undermined the vows of marriage by reducing them to a contract then offering us ways to break the contract. They've redefined the function of marriage to make it simply a sexual contract between any two adults.</p>
<p>It's for this reason that I have entered the political process in Ontario.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I have served twice as a candidate for the federal Christian Heritage Party. I am able offer creative solutions to problems. I am able to work with different people to achieve a common goal. I am willing to stand alone, if I must, against pressure to conform to an idea or course of action. I am thrifty with other people's money, such as tax dollars, as well as my own. I believe in personal responsibility for our actions... not excuses. I am a good listener, I have spent 11 years volunteering at a distress centre.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?</hi></p>
<p>All of them because they all seek a mandate from the people of Glengarry-Prescott-Russell.</p>
</text>
