<text id="autogum_interview_doc1034" title="part1_Wikinews interviews team behind the 2,000th featured Wikipedia article" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-04-10" dateModified="2009-12-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_team_behind_the_2%2C000th_featured_Wikipedia_article" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>And I've always been interested in using technology in teaching: mailing lists, websites, blogs, and so on.  But I've never much liked "educational technology": programs such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebCT">WebCT</ref> that students only ever use as part of a course they are taking.  By creating something of an educational ghetto, educational technology seems to me to miss out on the most interesting and exciting possibilities of the Internet: precisely the fact that it opens up to the world outside the classroom, and can reconfigure or perhaps even break down the rather limited relationship between teacher (supposed to be the expert and source of all authority) and the student (too often treated as the passive recipient of knowledge).</p>
<p>Overall, a Wikipedia assignment offered lots of possibilities, including:</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item>teaching students about Wikipedia, an important site that they use (and too often misuse) often</item>
<item>improving Wikipedia itself, by generating new content on topics where its coverage is lacking</item>
<item>encouraging students to produce something that had relevance outside the classroom, in the public sphere</item>
<item>giving them tangible goals that were measured by something other than my own professorial judgement</item>
<item>changing their views about writing, by stressing the importance of ongoing revision</item>
<item>teaching them about research and about how to use and evaluate sources</item></list></p>
<hi rend="bold">... we did get one "speedy deletion" tag.  It was placed, within less than a minute, on an article that I created in front of all the students, during class time.  For one horrible moment, in front of the whole class, I had a feeling that things might go terribly wrong.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Professor Jon Beasley-Murray</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Did you consult with fellow academics or students prior to launching this project?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">JBM</hi></hi>:  No, not really.  Perhaps I should have!  But off and on last summer I did discuss the idea with a friend who works in educational technology at UBC, who had helped me with the implementation of blogs in my courses.  And this friend, <ref target="http://careo.elearning.ubc.ca/cgi-bin/wiki.pl?Brian_Lamb">Brian Lamb</ref>, was as always very encouraging and supportive of this kind of experimentation.  He looked into the possibility of helping me apply for a grant for the project, but it seems there aren't any for this kind of thing.  I decided to go ahead anyway, essentially on my own.</item></list>
<p>And in January, as the project was getting underway, I signed up with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:School%20and%20university%20projects">Wikipedia:School and university projects</ref>.  There were plenty of other previous and ongoing educational projects listed there, so I presumed I wasn't so alone and that what I was doing wasn't so innovative.  It was only much later that I realized just how different and how ambitious this project was: we were aiming to create featured articles, ideally twelve of them, and no other educational project had ever set out to do that!</p>
</text>
