<text id="autogum_interview_doc863" title="part3_Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-22" dateModified="2014-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_World_Wide_Web_co-inventor_Robert_Cailliau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>The first search engine was built by the "Centre Universitaire d'Informatique" of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Geneva">University of Geneva</ref>.</p>
<p>I predicted that search engines would not cope in the long term.  Maybe the existence of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Google">Google</ref> is only an indication that there is still only little available on the web.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: You were at the inception of the WWW together with Tim Berners-Lee; what aspects are you responsible for exactly? You've convinced CERN to release the basic code library into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/public%20domain">public domain</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: In 1990 I had already left programming for ten years and was doing management.  I'm also 8 years older than Tim, who himself was no longer a young programmer.  It was evident that I could not compete with twenty year old Unix hackers and soon I stopped meddling with the writing of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C%20(programming%20language)">C code</ref>.  Anyway I know only one programming language worse than C and that is Javascript.</p>
<p>I did influence the shapes of the web and the directions of development, but I mainly occupied myself with obtaining the resources necessary to keep the project going.  I had a (meager) budget and so I got computers, offices, and above all people:  young programmers who can spend a year working at CERN in the framework of its Technical Student Programme.  To get all that done I had to plead often with the management.</p>
<p>I also understood that CERN, as a lab for physics, would never devote a division to the web.  Therefore I began to contact true informatics institutes such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Institut%20national%20de%20recherche%20en%20informatique%20et%20en%20automatique">INRIA</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Institut national de recherche en informatique et en automatique, red.</hi>) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fraunhofer%20Society">FhG</ref> (<hi rend="italic">Fraunhofer Society, red.</hi>) , as well as contacting the European Commission.  In this I was fortunately supported by Mike Sendall.  Mike, who was seen as neutral by CERN management, has done more than anyone else to help the development of the web inside CERN.</p>
<p>On the technical side it was not always the best of understanding between me and the team.  For example, I was convinced that we needed to build-in a programming language, but the developers, Tim first, were very much opposed.  It had to remain completely declarative.  Maybe, but the net result is that the programming-vacuum filled itself with the most horrible kluge in the history of computing: Javascript.</p>
<p>I also remember a big resistance against PostScript, but what do we see now?  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portable%20Document%20Format">PDF</ref> everywhere.  Fortunately PDF is an open standard and it's fairly elegant, but it could have turned out much worse. SVG did not make it.</p>
<hi rend="bold">Tim, who had a longer experience with the internet world, convinced me that the web could only survive if all the code was freely available for everyone, [...] put into the public domain. [...] The document was signed on 30 April 1993 that gave the WWW technology to the world.</hi>
</text>
