<text id="autogum_interview_doc118" title="part4_Wikinews interviews specialists on China, Iran, Russia support for al-Assad" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-09-15" dateModified="2015-10-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_China%2C_Iran%2C_Russia_support_for_al-Assad" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Would you agree that part of Iran's vested interest in Syria remaining under al-Assad is bound to two factors: religion and strategy?</p>
<figure><caption>Former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President%20of%20Iran">President of Iran</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mahmoud_Ahmedinejad">Mahmoud Ahmedinejad</ref> who stepped down earlier this year. Image: Russian Presidential Press and Information Office.</caption></figure>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Kamrava</hi>: No, I do not agree. Iran's "vested interest in Syria remaining under al-Assad" is [<hi rend="italic">a</hi>] product only of Iran's strategic calculations.</item></list>
<p>While foreign policies anywhere may be expressed — and justified — through slogans and ideological rhetoric, they are based on strategic considerations and calculations. Despite common, journalistic misconceptions, religion has not played a role in Iranian foreign policy; whether in relation to Syria or anywhere else.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Martel</hi>: Iran's vested interest in Syria is entirely geo-strategic. Iran's support [<hi rend="italic">for</hi>] Syria is designed to undermine US power and influence. For Iran, no policy objective is more important than to possess <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nuclear_proliferation">nuclear weapons</ref>. When the U.S. declared a "redline" if Syria "used or moved" chemical weapons, and then backed away from that redline, it is likely that Iran's leadership drew one principal conclusion:</item></list>
<p>the US redline on Iran's nuclear program is in doubt, the US commitment to preventing Iran from possessing nuclear weapons is in doubt,</p>
<p>and that Iran likely will test US resolve.</p>
<p>In strategic terms, doubts about the credibility of the US redline on Iran dwarfs any concerns about Syria's chemical weapons.</p>
<p>The belief in Iran — that the US may not be willing to prevent Iran from possessing nuclear weapons — could lead to a nuclear arms race in the Middle East. It is difficult to exaggerate just how dangerous a nuclear-armed Iran is for regional and global security.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Posch</hi>: No, it is strategy, and perhaps ideology. Religion doesn't play too much [of] a role, even though the conflict has been thoroughly "sectarianised". This happened a few years back when the Saudis baptised (if that term is appropriate) the "axis of resistance" to "shiite crescent". The domination of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syrian_Baath_Party">Syrian Baath Party</ref> by members of one sect plays no role in Iran's security equation. Attempts to convert Syrian <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alevites">Alevites</ref> to Mainstream Shiites are initiatives of some individual <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayatollahs">Ayatollahs</ref>. I have already mentioned the strategic aspect, [<hi rend="italic">an</hi>] axis of resistance against Israel and Saudi Arabia simultaneously; to this I would add Iranian concern over the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurds">Kurdish</ref> issue.</item>
<item><hi rend="bold">Farhi</hi>: The Assad government is a secular government, and Iran's relationship with it has nothing to do with religion or religious affinities. The relationship is a complex one — and, as mentioned before — forged as a strategic bond during the Iran–Iraq War, when Saddam's regime was deemed aggressively expansionist by both regimes.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   Iran is home to the world's most populous <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shia_Islam">Shiite Muslim</ref> nation. The Syrian rebels are <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sunni_Islam">Sunni</ref>. Could this be a Sunni vs. Shiite alignment in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Middle_East">Middle East</ref>? </p>
</text>
