<text id="autogum_interview_doc948" title="part3_Interview with Sean Semper-Whyte, City Council candidate for Ward 6 in Mississauga, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-sean" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-09-23" dateModified="2008-01-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Sean_Semper-Whyte%2C_City_Council_candidate_for_Ward_6_in_Mississauga%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The challenge of being a rookie is not so great, as the challenge of being in government where it is possible for the infusion of new ideas and perspective to be caramelized by unhealthy friendships or agendas.  As a new – young – fresh – candidate, I bring opportunity to retune the way in which Council interprets the city vision for the *Total Community.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What service is most lacking in Mississauga?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Mississauga needs to be an accessible city.  The recent development of the "Link" at the airport is one way to improve city access.  Not only do we need to plan for access to Toronto, we need to plan for similar access around the city for our community.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The city recently released a study regarding transforming the City Hall and area. How do you feel about these plans?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> As indicated earlier this is a great vision, this vision must not take away from our developing the true core of the city, which is its people.  Buildings will come and go, the legacy of the people who live here is what will live on in generations to come.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How do you feel about Mississauga's rate of expansion?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> This is a natural supply and demand concern, which we must look to with eyes of understanding.  Are we building for the sake of building or to establish a stronger community position for anticipated growth.  As long as we respect and incorporate the need for supportive infrastructure we can meet the demand with a strategic supply methodology.  Mississauga is and will always be a destination of choice as long as we respect the needs of its whole community.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What are your opinions on Mississauga's congestion and public transit funding?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> As indicated earlier these are concerns we must look to resolving now through innovative solutions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why should businesses be attracted to locating in Mississauga? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> This is a moot question!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How could Mississauga further itself in attracting corporate investment?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Mississauga has operated within the standards of general best practices, and in some cases has set the standard to be met by other communities.  Mississauga cannot sit on our past achievements; we must continue to push the boundaries of innovation by empowering the corporations and its citizens, to maximize the numerous resources at hand.  In setting the pace for innovation we become the incubator for the next big ideas and the organizations that will bring them to fruition.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I believe with all my heart that we must all be involved, more than this I believe we can set a greater standard for Total Community service, by demonstrating exceptional service to the community.  This has not been happening as much as it could be.  I believe we need to work towards that standard of greatness others seem to be waning from, at a cost to hard working community members.  It is time we fire-Up City Hall and challenge growth through change.  I want to call my City Councillor and get Him not his secretary or aid, and if not have him or her return my call within a timely manner – this is service and the type of service I will provide as City Councillor for Ward Six.</p>
</text>
