<text id="autogum_interview_doc179" title="part1_Wikinews interviews former Republican U.S. Senator Bob Smith on his latest run for office" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-06-21" dateModified="2014-12-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Republican_U.S._Senator_Bob_Smith_on_his_latest_run_for_office" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>We are in the midst of a violent storm.  I can help lead Florida and the nation through this tempest.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">J.F.</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">For many years, you lived in New Hampshire and represented it in the Senate. Seeing as you moved to Florida relatively recently, many are wondering if you know the state well enough to run for office in it. Do you feel that you are familiar enough with the issues many Floridians are facing such as skyrocketing unemployment, rising taxes and the foreclosure crisis?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Smith</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> :I am no stranger to Florida. My family and I have been enjoying Florida’s beautiful beaches and natural treasures for the last 40 years.  My wife and I have lived in Sarasota for over six years.</p>
<p>Since we made Florida our home, I have worked in the real estate business and served as a founding director of a community bank.  In addition, I spent three years as President of The Everglades Foundation, a non-profit organization headquartered in Miami, whose mission is restore and preserve the Everglades through community awareness and public-private partnerships.</p>
<p>I have enjoyed being a leader on issues affecting Floridians during much of my career.  When I was the Chairman of the Senate Environment and Public Works Committee, I worked with Governor Jeb Bush to restore the Everglades.  I sponsored legislation funding Everglades restoration and guided the bill to passage by the Senate and the House.  In addition, I am a proven advocate for issues about which Floridians feel strongly, including:
<list type="unordered"><item>fiscal prudence,</item>
<item>protecting veterans and strengthening the military,</item>
<item>recognizing the importance of the space industry to the future and security of the country,</item>
<item>healthcare reform, and</item>
<item>protecting our state’s and our nation’s borders.</item></list></p>
<p>I have faced the issues of unemployment, taxes and foreclosures in Congress throughout my career in Congress.  When I was elected to the House of Representatives in 1984, the country was just starting to recover from the recession of the early 1980’s.  I participated in the response to the Savings and Loan crisis, which was similar to the current crisis in cause, if not in scope.  When I became a U.S. Senator in 1990, it was not long before the country was in the midst of another recession and housing crunch.  Though it proved to be the prelude to a much worse crisis, I also was involved with the actions taken by Congress to respond to the bursting of the technology stock bubble earlier this decade.</p>
<p>It is hard for me to sit on the sidelines during these troubling times.  Republican Floridians need a seat at the table while the President and Congress are making decisions that will affect the future of our nation.  As a senior senator, I can provide that seat at the table.</p>
</text>
