<text id="autogum_interview_doc095" title="part22_Wikinews interviews Indiana State Senator Mike Delph" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-26" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Indiana_State_Senator_Mike_Delph" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>When I first got elected to the legislature, my pastor's wife was the executive assistant to the commissioner of the ISHAA, Blake Ress, and she knew how I felt about class basketball. I didn't like it and I wished we'd go back to single class [basketball in Indiana]. But out of unity to my church and not wanting to cause my pastor's wife consternation, I decided I would not do anything or pursue anything. Then she left the IHSAA and then I had an opportunity to interject this multi-facet education proposal. And then I met Bobby Cox, the then commissioner of the IHSAA, and I told him, "I'll table this proposal, but let's see what the public has to say." And he said, "that is a great idea. Let's do some public meetings. Let's go around the state together, let's hold a press conference and tell the world what we are doing, and let's take a vote at every public meeting. We'll give the public a chance that they didn't have at the time when we made this decision.</p>
<p>I think at the time the IHSAA and Commissioner Cox, in particular, thought that the public would be more allow the lines of multi-class basketball. We probably had 50 to 100 people turn out at every one of our meetings. We even went to former historical <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodore%20Roosevelt%20High%20School%20(Gary)">Gary Roosevelt</ref> up in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lake%20County,%20Indiana">Lake County</ref> we went down to several areas in Southern Indiana, we went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pendleton,%20Indiana">Pendleton</ref>. I don't have the list in front of me, so I'm just kind of doing this from memory. I emailed it to Professor Tew. I think the turnout or vote was 68 percent for restoration towards single class basketball.</p>
<p>One of the real joys of that whole process for me was meeting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobby%20Plump">Bobby Plump</ref> and going to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milan,%20Indiana">Milan</ref> and meeting the [19]54 basketball team. They all turned out for that. That was kind of a turning point in our road show. Because up until that point, the turnout was mixed in terms of whether it was single-class or multi-class. But at Milan, it was blowout. Everyone there wants to go back to single class basketball. I toured the Milan high school, and the athletic director tells me to this day he still gets calls from people all over the world wanting to know about Milan and Hoosiers.</p>
<p>He actually had a guy call him once and say how do I get to the high school, I’m flying in to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cincinnati">Cincinnati</ref>, and he gave him directions from the Cincinnati airport to the Milan high school so he could come see the trophies and learn more about the history because he had just seen the movie Hoosiers. To me this is something like, just like the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indianapolis%20Motor%20Speedway">Indianapolis Motor Speedway</ref> puts Indianapolis on the map, we're known as the greatest racing spectacle in world, with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indianapolis%20500">Indianapolis 500</ref>. We are also known internationally for our wonderful single class basketball tournament, which lifts up and extolls the virtues of the underdog and the little guy. When we went to multi-class basketball we lost some of that cultural identity that Indiana was known for. Not only nationally but throughout the world. And I want to try to bring that back.</p>
</text>
