<text id="autogum_interview_doc723" title="Frank McEnulty continues White House run for New American, Reform parties, independently; talks to Wikinews" shortTile="frank-mcenulty-continues" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-04" dateModified="2016-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Frank_McEnulty_continues_White_House_run_for_New_American%2C_Reform_parties%2C_independently%3B_talks_to_Wikinews" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Frank McEnulty continues White House run for New American, Reform parties, independently; talks to Wikinews</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 4, 2008</hi></p>
<p>Throughout the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202008">2008 United States Presidential election campaign</ref>, Wikinews reporters have been talking to candidates of all political stripes, looking for their vision of America and campaign stories. This series continues now with Frank McEnulty.</p>
<p>McEnulty has an interesting campaign. On July 21, he wrote on his site, explaining his multiple campaigns:</p>
At the Reform Party Convention, held recently in Dallas, TX, I was selected to be their Vice Presidential Candidate to run on the ticket with Ted Weill, the Presidential candidate. I am honored to accept this nomination and see this as an important step in uniting the various third party groups around the country into a stronger, more effective voice.
<p>To that end, I am continuing my independent run for president in the other states in which the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reform%20Party%20of%20the%20United%20States%20of%20America">Reform Party</ref> does not have ballot access. I firmly believe the answer for a better America is in a strong, viable third party that will address the views and needs of the Moderate Majority Americans being ignored by the Democrats and Republicans.</p>
<p>I want to reiterate that I am still the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_American_Independent_Party">New American Independent Party</ref> Presidential candidate for the 2008 election and have discussed this strategy at length with Michael Thompson the Chairman of the NAIP. We are continuing our ballot access efforts and hope that this latest development will help our message to be heard in more states. Thank you for your continued support.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Third party candidates: Why should Americans vote for you, your party, and your campaign's platform?</hi>
<hi rend="bold">Independent candidates: Why should Americans vote for you and your campaign's platform?</hi></p>
<p>Since I am running as both an affiliated and non-affiliated candidate, depending on the state, I believe my answer applies to both questions. Americans should vote for me or the campaign platform if and only if, they truly believe that it is the right thing for all Americans and offers the best road map for moving forward.  Very few people will agree with everything that someone has to say, but if there is enough common ground and they truly believe the person will do what he/she says, then that is who they should vote for.</p>
<p>I do not believe that anyone should ever blindly vote for a party. A party does not get elected to office and the fact that parties have been allowed to come to rule politics as they have versus the individual is what is responsible for the terribly bad situation we find our politics in today.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">The election is nearing, and campaigns for all parties are reaching their final leg. What are your plans for the remaining weeks of the campaign? How will you continue to build on the awareness and momentum of your campaign?</hi></p>
<p>I will continue to work on building awareness for the campaign by reaching out through the internet, with email blasts and through radio appearances.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">If you aren't elected President in this election, can we expect to see your return to the ballot in 2012?</hi></p>
<p>That is being explored at this time.  Now that I truly understand what it takes to run a truly effective, nationwide campaign I will be involved when a proper plan can be implemented and developed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">If readers are interested in your campaign, in what ways can they get involved?</hi></p>
<p>Visit my website at www.frankforpresident.org.  If you like what you see, tell everyone you know.  A true independent can only gather the necessary momentum to get a campaign off the ground through word-of-mouth.</p>
</text>
