<text id="autogum_interview_doc673" title="part16_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What are the gay bars like?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  They were just as you would find them in New York where gay men hang around and they have their music and their dancing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are they flamboyant?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  When I first became aware of it, it's like in Iran, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahmoud%20Ahmadinejad">Ahmadinejad</ref> says there's no <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gay%20Rights%20in%20Iran">homosexuals in Iran</ref>...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's because <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Execution_of_two_gay_teens_in_Iran_spurs_controversy">they kill them</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Well whatever it is, but in China I don't hear of any, either boastfully or with reticence, the acknowledgment of homosexuals.  I always stayed in the hotel because I don't have the language so I couldn't stay in a Bed &amp; Breakfast in China or wherever you did in Cuba. You speak Spanish, you said. But I do not speak anything. When I noticed this, I would sometimes have room service, and invariably it was a guy, sometimes two, who were very very <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Effeminacy">effeminate</ref>. They really were. There's just one thing about how free it could be.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How did you get introduced to a gay bar in Beijing?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I got introduced to it because I needed interpreters and in order to get interpreters, I had people who were college students, Americans, sometimes of Chinese origin.  One of them in particular who went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yale%20University">Yale</ref>, who came to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto">Toronto</ref> from Canton as a young boy, and when he graduated from high school in Toronto he went to Yale and after graduating at 21, returned to China and taught English in one of the high schools in Beijing. When I went it was very hard to get interpreters because anybody who could speak English and Chinese was taken by corporations at high paying jobs because all of these multi-national corporations having Chinese partners needed interpreters.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Including the European ones, right? English is the international language.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  Everybody. Everybody. So people like me would have to really scratch around to find somebody. I would get to know journalists very easily because I knew the bureaus. I could go to the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> and they had a five or six man bureau and some of the Chinese workers were there. "Can I get somebody to moonlight for me for a little bit?" "Well no, we can't give you one of our people, but he has got a cousin over here, who's working part-time at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kentucky%20Fried%20Chicken">Kentucky Fried Chicken</ref> and you can see him after". So this is how I met this fellow from Yale. Because he knew the city, he not only served as my interpreter when I had interviews, but he took it upon himself to escort me places, including these bars and sex shops. I'm always interested in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prostitution">prostitution</ref> because that is really something that involves danger. It involves a kind of corruption because everybody abolishes it, but it exists.</p>
</text>
