<text id="autogum_interview_doc967" title="part6_Wikinews interviews Fred Karger, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-04-23" dateModified="2014-03-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Fred_Karger%2C_U.S._Republican_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><p>We need to be much more aware. Think out all of the ways to do it: to speak the language; to offer them the opportunity to participate; to teach them voting at a younger age in high school so that they get in more of a habit once out of high school and off to college or in workforce, and are less likely to become advantageous voters. I think we need to teach voting in high school. Bring candidates like myself, Congressional candidates, their own candidates from city race, into the high school and I think that'll help people become better voters. And I also think it'll also help a certain percentage stay in high school that may not ordinarily, cause we're of course, losing a million high school students a year dropping out, and the 2 or 3 percent love politics and they're learning from politicians. They may be less likely to drop out. It's helping to then lessen that crisis.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Considering the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenth%20amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution">Tenth amendment</ref>, should same sex marriage be a state issue?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Fred Karger</hi>: I am a strong advocate of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/states'%20rights">states' rights</ref>, but not on a civil rights issue like gay marriage. And had we left <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/interracial%20marriage">interracial marriage</ref> to the states, we know that would have been a long time and coming, and the Supreme Court interceded and made that the law of the land. And I think on this issue that the court will ultimately decide that this issue should not be left to the voters. That is a gigantic mistake. A legislature are better. Some have more courage. But it's too hot a political issue. It should be a legal issue. And I'm looking forward to the Nevada case for that to work its way up to federal courts and then for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perry%20v.%20Brown">California <hi rend="italic">Perry</hi> case</ref>. I think those two will be very important in making all the different people equal.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How can high energy costs be reduced?</hi></p>
Karger during the 2012 presidential election.Image: Gage Skidmore.
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodore%20Roosevelt">Theodore Roosevelt</ref> during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%201912">1912 presidential election</ref>.
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Fred Karger</hi>: Well, that's a very complex issue. Talking about certainly making America <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20energy%20independence">energy independent</ref> is number one. Conservation, which no one else is talking about, and that I am beating my chest about is so important. There's so much energy that is wasted in this country. Not just driving, but in our public buildings and homes, where you go into a movie theater in the summer and it's freezing or the airports. There's so many public places where we should not have government mandates, but certainly building owners and managers to take responsibility to really make it comfortable, and to set thermostats at a comfortable temperature. And personal responsibility, there’s so many light-timers that go all night. I grew up with parents who were children of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great%20Depression">depression</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_War_II">World War II</ref>. So I couldn't leave my room without turning the light off. And I think we need to instill those values. We got to stop releasing so much energy. That will be a big contribution toward keeping costs down.</p>
<p>
<p>| <hi rend="bold">I'm more like a Theodore Roosevelt, who took on a lot of corporations and was controversial at those acts he did</hi></p>
</p>
<p>But the oil companies need, and I know there's many factors in the high gas prices, but it's no coincidence that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ExxonMobil">ExxonMobil</ref> makes record profits when gas prices at the pump go up. You can parallel those two. I've taking on ExxonMobil. I'm not afraid to do that. I'm more like a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theodore%20Roosevelt">Theodore Roosevelt</ref>, who took on a lot of corporations and was controversial at those acts he did, very different of course a hundred years ago, monopolies and things like that. But I have no problems with going after big oil, and fine companies that have made a trillion dollars of profit off of the consumers, who are struggling right now with of course the trickle effect of high gasoline prices [which] affects the entire economy, not just at the pump. So there's a lot of ways. I've got some on my website, the issues tab. I talk about ways to bring this down. But those are two areas certainly where we need to pick it up: conservation and making America energy independent.</p></p>
</text>
