<text id="autogum_interview_doc348" title="part0_Wikinews discusses H1N1 with the WHO" shortTile="partwikinews-discusses" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-29" dateModified="2019-09-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_discusses_H1N1_with_the_WHO" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews discusses H1N1 with the WHO</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 31, 2010</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Flag of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20Health%20Organization">World Health Organization</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20Health%20Organization">World Health Organization</ref> (WHO) is a program of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations">United Nations</ref> and a global authority on human health. In an interview with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, the WHO tells about the current <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2009%20flu%20pandemic">H1N1 pandemic</ref>.</p>
<p>The organization's 93rd update as of March 26, 2010 states 213 countries, territories, and other communities have laboratory-confirmed cases and there have been at least 16,931 confirmed deaths, including 4,653 deaths in Europe and 7,673 in the Americas.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:The_New_Mikemoral">Mike Morales</ref> talks with Karen Mah, a media relations representative for the WHO, and asks her several questions.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Morales</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Can you tell us what exactly H1N1 is and how it affects us today?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Karen Mah</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> As of 21 March 2010, worldwide more than 213 countries and overseas territories or communities have reported laboratory confirmed cases of pandemic influenza H1N1 2009, including over 16,931 deaths.  This number is a large underestimation of total deaths with total figures unavailable until a year or two after the pandemic is declared over. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How does the WHO feel the media coverage has been and does the WHO suggest any changes to coverage and if so, what kind?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> WHO does not have any comment with regards to media coverage nor is it in our purview to suggest changes to coverage.  The pandemic is a global event and media coverage can't be characterized with any generalities.   </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Which areas around the world are most affected by the pandemic and why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Current disease activity and epidemiological activity indicates we are seeing the highest levels of activities occurring in Southeast Asia, West Africa, and in the tropical zone of the Americas. After a period of sustained pandemic influenza transmission in Thailand over the past two months, overall activity now appears to be decreasing. In West Africa, limited data suggests that active transmission of pandemic influenza virus persists without clear evidence of a peak in activity. In Central America and in the tropical zone of South America, an increasing trend of respiratory disease activity associated with circulation of pandemic influenza virus has been reported since early March 2010 in an increasing number of countries. </p>
<figure><caption>The H1N1 virus. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Cybercobra">Cybercobra</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What advice does the WHO recommend to any areas affected by H1N1? What does the WHO recommend to governments' health authorities of countries affected?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> This is a very far-reaching question and answer and paraphrasing the pandemic preparedness guidelines is too simplistic.  I will refer you to this page [URL below] to see the whole spectrum of guidance for countries ranging from response, surveillance, reduction of spread, travel, hygiene etc.  From a WHO perspective, we have to offer the broadest range of guidance to cover developing, mid-level and developed countries.</p>
</text>
