<text id="autogum_interview_doc810" title="part3_Frank Messina: An interview with the &amp;apos;Mets Poet&amp;apos;" shortTile="partfrank-messina" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-03" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Frank_Messina%3A_An_interview_with_the_%27Mets_Poet%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  It's opened up a new fan base, so to speak.  For the last year <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SportsNet%20New%20York">SNY</ref> has broadcast footage of me with my poems, so quite a few fans known about the 'Mets Poet'.  I have never called myself that, by the way.  The back of my jersey says 'The Poet' because growing up that was my nickname.  My brother was a runner and they used to call him The Birdman--Birdie--and they called me The Poet.  It was a natural thing, but I never coined myself as 'The Mets Poet.'</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%20Nicholson">Jack Nicholson</ref> once said, "The fuel for the sports fan is the ability to have private theories."  What are some of your private theories?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  The fan is always right.  No matter if he is wrong, he is right.  The fan always has an opinion.  That's why we have talk radio and people call Joe Benigno and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve%20Somers">Steve Somers</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike%20and%20the%20Mad%20Dog">Mike and the Mad Dog</ref> all day long.  That's why we have 24/7 sports-related talk. If you were to come from another planet with only three hours on Earth to find out what human beings are like, to discover how dynamic life is as a human being, you would take them to a baseball game.  A season is like a life, but a game is like one day in that life.  A season has its beginning, its renewal, its innocence and its arch into maturity into the season.  Panic sets in when it hits the middle-age of the season.  Will it we have success, or will we have failure.  At end of season, fans have to accept whether we have failed or whether we have achieved victory.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kansas%20City%20Royals">Kansas City Royals</ref> fans know at the beginning of the season that, more than likely, nothing is going to happen for them.  As Mets fans, we want to win, but we never expect it to be easy.  It's always going to be a fight; it's always going to be hard.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The second-class citizen in a first rate city idea that is found in one of your poems.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">FM:</hi>  Yeah, you're going to get pushed around.  People are going to disagree with you.  It's not going to be easy.  You're going to have to take a lot of pills, take an extra drink, go to the gym an extra day to run off some energy.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You and poet Ron Whitehead embarked on a "War Poets" tour of Europe.  You as a pro-war poet, and Whitehead as a pro-peace poet.  Forgive the crude terminology; I realize there is probably nuance in there.  In the over four years since that tour has your outlook evolved at all?</hi></p>
</text>
