<text id="autogum_interview_doc1394" title="part17_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  I think Lani Guinier did talk about that.  You have to not only have blacks, but you have to have whites and white leadership that want to have that dialogue.  Most of them don’t want to have it.  We have to create that dialogue and hopefully some of the things we are doing creates the climate for that dialogue.  What I have found is that many people in America, particularly the white people, don’t really want peace, they want quiet.  “Just shut up and don’t talk about it.  Fine, there may be a problem, but let’s not talk about it.”   That’s not peace, that’s quiet.  You’ll never have peace until you have real dialogue and look at the difference between the life of a white and life of a non-white in this country, and how we close the gap.  That’s how you get peace.  So people don’t want racial justice; they want racial quiet.  But racial quiet in the absence of racial justice is to allow for things to go forward unfairly.  In the long wrong, that leads to explosions because people hold it in as long as they can and then they explode.  The way to stop the explosions is to deal with the problem.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Would you say what sums up the problem with dialogue as you see it is that white people are too afraid to offend black people by asking questions about their perceptions, but that black people become too offended by white people’s ignorance?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  I think that’s a fair statement.  I think that’s a very fair statement.  I wish I had said it.  That hit it right on the head.  Really.</p>
<head id="Don_Imus,_Michael_Richards_and_Dog_The_Bounty_Hunter"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don%20Imus">Don Imus</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Richards">Michael Richards</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duane%20Chapman">Dog The Bounty Hunter</ref></head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you think about Imus, Michael Richards and Duane Chapman, it’s starting to seem almost like a rehearsed play.  They have these racist explosions, and then they come to you seeking absolution.  How do you feel about playing this?</hi></p>
<figure><caption>"<hi rend="bold">The critics say, “Why do they go to Al Sharpton for absolution?”  What nobody ever asks is, “What did Sharpton do?”  I made Imus go on my radio show and told him he should be fired.  I never talked to the "Bounty man" [<hi rend="italic">above</hi>].  And I told Michael Richards I’m not meeting with him.</hi>" - <hi rend="italic">Sharpton on those seeking absolution from him for racist remarks.</hi></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  That’s a great question, because if you name Don Imus, Richards, Bounty Hunter, they all three came, and none of them got absolution from me.  The critics say, “Why do they go to Al Sharpton for absolution?”  What nobody ever asks is, “What did Sharpton do?”  I made Imus go on my radio show and told him he should be fired.  I never talked to the "Bounty man".  And I told Michael Richards I’m not meeting with him.  So, despite what they <hi rend="italic">designed</hi> to happen with me, I never cooperated with the design.  Imus only went on my show thinking if he did he would get past it; I used it for the basis to get him fired.  He got everything <hi rend="italic">but</hi> absolution.  Why do they come?  Because of my visibility.  Right now, National Action Network is the only civil rights organization in the country that can put tens of thousands of people in the street.  I think we proved that if nothing else this year from Sean Bell to Jena to Washington.  He thought if he did he would get past it; I used it for the basis to get him fired.  You go where you think if you can get this group not to fight me, you get a pass.  If somebody is accused of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antisemitism">anti-Semitism</ref>, they go to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-Defamation%20League">Anti-Defamation League</ref>.  Does that make <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abraham%20Foxman">Abe Foxman</ref> the "President of the Jews"?  No!  That’s what ADL <hi rend="italic">does</hi>.  It’s insulting to us.  They say, “Al Sharpton is not the President of Black America.”  No, I’m like ADL is in the Jewish community.  That’s what he does.  If anybody is going to jump on this, it’s him, so let me go to him.  That doesn’t mean he’s in charge of all blacks.  It means if it’s a civil rights violation—that’s what they have to do—he’s been the guy up front.  It’s very simple.  In gay communities you have the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human%20Rights%20Campaign">Human Rights Campaign</ref>.  With women, you’ve got <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Organization%20for%20Women">NOW</ref>.  In the Jewish community, you’ve got ADL.  Why wouldn’t you have a National Action Network in the black community?  But if sanity is that NOW can have <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kim%20Gandy">Kim Gandy</ref>, and the Jewish community can have Abe Foxman, and the gay community can have Human Rights group, but the black community can’t have an "Al Sharpton", that’s absurd!</p>
</text>
