<text id="autogum_interview_doc713" title="part3_Canada&amp;apos;s Don Valley East (Ward 33) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-don-valley" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-17" dateModified="2009-04-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Don_Valley_East_%28Ward_33%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I live in ward 33, so it was convenient, but also it is next door to my long standing home in scarborough where I grew up the past 30 years. I understand the social, political, economic, and cultural fabric of toronto, ontario, and canadian society. I have lived almost my entire life in East Toronto, so am familiar with all the issues and cultural demands. In short, East Toronto is not a theater for police to terrorize in the media, nor a war games playground, whereby asians are used as an instrument to justify excessive police budgets.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have focused my life's work on understanding and publishing on issues of big picture importance to 3 levels of government to ensure that Canada does not become the social, political, economic, and moral bankruptcy of the United States. And I am content to see the benefits of my hard work the past few years. I am a very charitable time giving person. I committed my time and abilities to the causes I feel will most benefit society, for instance:</p>
<p>-Daily bread food bank, -Ont. Council for Int. Cooperation, -World Vision Refugee Center</p>
<p>-United Way fundraising and CN Tower climb supplier.</p>
<p>-Sueing three levels of government for environmental, transit, education, health, justice reform issues.</p>
<p>-resolving traffic issues at kennedy+steeles, 404/401 ramps, Leslie/401,</p>
<p>-federal funds to rebuild the poorest region in Canada - Regent Park,</p>
<p>-Youth justice system reforms - mitigating 600% Criminal code conviction rate more than adults.</p>
<p>-2004 Canadian police per capita budgeting model to reduce excessive police budgets - ignored by city council todate.</p>
<p>- Environmental groups, researching and publishing papers to local MP, MPPs, and city council that are urgent.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The past decade has been one of stagnation for several reasons: First, fiscal slash and burn policies by Federal Liberals, and Ontario Conservatives. Second, Police and TTC unions rape and extort the tax payers for unending higher wages. Let me be very clear, THE PUBLIC IS NOT A BANK ROLE FOR UNIONS TO MAKE RIDICULOUS WAGE DEMANDS UPON SO THEIR SALARIES KEEP PACE WITH INFLATION - this is the role of banks and financial markets! The result of this is Toronto has become a welfare state that is headed for bankruptcy - if things do not change quickly.</p>
<p>Toronto must be a model mega city in our global village. Toronto must demonstrate leadership in private and public sector innovation to ensure social, political, and economic growth. A homeless man or young child should be able to walk into a court and find justice -with little or no cost, and without fear of persecution.</p>
</text>
