<text id="autogum_interview_doc350" title="part2_Wikinews discusses H1N1 with the WHO" shortTile="partwikinews-discusses" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-29" dateModified="2019-09-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_discusses_H1N1_with_the_WHO" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Supportive care at home with plenty of rest, drinking plenty of fluids and using a pain reliever for aches and pains is adequate for recovery in most cases. A non-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/aspirin">aspirin</ref> pain reliever should be used for children or adolescents under age 18.</p>
<p>The public should be made aware that there are specific groups of people who appear to be at higher risk of more complicated or severe illness which include:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>pregnant women;</item>
<item>infants, and young children particularly under age 2;</item>
<item>people of any age with certain chronic health conditions (including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/asthma">asthma</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/lung%20disease">lung disease</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/heart%20disease">heart disease</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/diabetes">diabetes</ref>, kidney disease or some neurological conditions);</item>
<item>people with severely compromised immune systems.</item></list>
<p>Currently, people age 65 or older are the least likely to be infected with the pandemic influenza, but those who do get sick are also at high risk of developing serious complications, just as they are from seasonal flu.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is it known when the virus will become less virulent and cease becoming a major threat to health and of so when?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> It is impossible to predict when the pandemic H1N1 virus will become less virulent.</p>
<figure><caption>Diagram showing antigenic shift.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is there a significant risk of H1N1 mutating and becoming more deadly?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Influenza viruses constantly change through a process called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/antigenic%20drift">antigenic drift</ref>.  All influenza viruses undergo this process but there is no way to predict if, when and how the pandemic H1N1 virus will shift.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Are the current anti-flu vaccines effective and how sufficient is the current supply? Can you explain how these anti-virus vaccine work and any possible side effects?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> The current H1N1 vaccines are effective and supply is sufficient. The safety profile of H1N1 vaccines is very good.  Outcomes of studies completed to date indicate that pandemic vaccines have a similar safety record as seasonal influenza vaccines. Pandemic influenza vaccines underwent the same production and testing methods as seasonal vaccines.</p>
<p>The safety tracking of the vaccine for adverse events after its distribution and use worldwide has likely been the most thorough and sensitive in history.</p>
<p>Influenza vaccines cause antibodies to develop in the body. These antibodies provide protection against infection with the viruses that are in the vaccine.</p>
<p>Possible side effects can depend on the type of vaccine, how it is administered and the age of the recipient.
There are two main types of vaccines: one is manufactured with inactivated viruses, the other uses live viruses.
Inactivated vaccines, administered by injection, commonly cause local reactions such as soreness, swelling and redness at the injection site, and less often can cause fever, muscle- or joint- aches or headache. These symptoms are generally mild, do not need medical attention, and last 1 to 2 days. Fever, aches and headaches can occur more frequently in children compared to elderly people.</p>
</text>
