<text id="autogum_interview_doc540" title="part13_Billy West, voice of Ren and Stimpy, Futurama, on the rough start that shaped his life" shortTile="partbilly-west-voice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2013-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Billy_West%2C_voice_of_Ren_and_Stimpy%2C_Futurama%2C_on_the_rough_start_that_shaped_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And you think that they are equal?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  No, of course not.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You’re saying in today’s culture they are equal?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Both can be famous. That’s not the kind of fame that I would want and the other kind of fame is a certain flavor of misery too because there’s a trade-off that you lose your personal life. I spent enough time in the fantasy world. I don’t watch <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reality%20television">reality shows</ref>. These are the kind of people I couldn’t wait to get away from in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High%20School">high school</ref> and I’m going to chronicle their stupid adventures, you know? I don’t live there. I don’t watch <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Television">television</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I don’t have cable, so I know how you feel.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Yeah, but even if I had <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cable%20television">cable</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satellite%20television">satellite</ref>, everything, I don’t watch television. I surround myself with things that edify me, not because it’s there. I’m an information freak. I’m a news freak. But it’s got to be truthful news and that’s why I’ll go to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BBC_News">BBC News</ref> on the Internet.  There’s less pressure with the truth teller over there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s amazing when you hear the BBC interview British politicians. We find it shocking that they’ll say things like “Aren’t you essentially lying when you say that?”</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  But that was the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth%20Estate">Fourth Estate</ref>. That was the idea that you owe your readers. You’ve been entrusted to deliver news to them and even if it’s an editorial or an interview, the idea is to get as much true information so people can decide for themselves. I don’t care if the interviewer’s biased. If I get enough information, I have a chance to be biased or not.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That's an argument on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref>: people make the argument, 'let's present the information out there and <hi rend="italic">let the reader decide.</hi></hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BS:</hi>  Yeah, but if a lot of times the information is totally incorrect to begin with.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Exactly,and it can be difficult to decide what to believe when reasonable minds can differ, but I think it's very problematic to ever argue "just let the reader decide."  I don't know if Wikipedia is the place for that fight, but in the news media, that is the place for the fight.  I interviewed Gay Talese, who quoted Norman Mailer who said the media is like a donkey, and you must feed the donkey every day; the donkey will eat anything: garbage, tin cans, slop.  And report on whatever they are fed.</hi></p>
<head id="Billy_West_on_telling_it_like_it_is">Billy West on telling it like it is</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are your voices an attempt to understand reality?</hi></p>
</text>
