<text id="autogum_interview_doc1306" title="part3_Wikinews interviews former Salt Lake City mayor and 2012 presidential candidate Rocky Anderson" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-12-17" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Salt_Lake_City_mayor_and_2012_presidential_candidate_Rocky_Anderson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I think in terms of executive experience, knowing how to bring those opposing forces together, solve problems, being respectful, and always having in mind that just because you’re in that position doesn’t make you any smarter or wiser than you were before. That shared wisdom can mean everything in terms of one’s success.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">According to an article in The Nation publication from 2006, a supporter asked you to run for president, but you told them that a run would require money and the backing of the state machine, which would be virtually impossible in conservative Utah. You added, “If I thought I could win, I would [run].”  How is the atmosphere in 2012 better for you than it was in 2008?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Anderson</hi>: Well first of all, as reflected by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Occupy%20Wall%20Street%20movement">Occupy Movement</ref>, people in this country across the board understand how diseased and corrupt our system is, both our electoral system and the system of governance. We know now that there have been repeated failures in public policy that are a direct result of the corrupting influence of money. We’d have a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/universal%20health%20care">universal health care</ref> system like the rest of the industrialized world were it not for the corrupting influence of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Health%20insurance%20in%20the%20United%20States">medical insurance</ref> money. We wouldn’t be wasting billions, upon billions of dollars for unnecessary weapons programs, where the stranglehold and the corrupting influence of money from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/military-industrial%20complex">military-industrial complex</ref>; we were warned about that by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dwight%20D.%20Eisenhower">President Eisenhower</ref> during <ref target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Eisenhower's%20farewell%20address">his last speech</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>President Dwight Eisenhower warned, "we must guard against the acquisition of unwarranted influence, whether sought or unsought, by the military-industrial complex."</caption></figure>
<p>The deregulation of the financial institutions that led toward this nation’s and the world’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Late-2000s%20recession">economic disaster</ref> from which we’re all still suffering, would never have come about were it not for the corrupting influence of money in the system. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">President Obama</ref> for instance, received more money from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wall%20Street">Wall Street</ref> than any other candidate in our nation’s history, and so they got a really good return on their investment because the Obama administration has not brought one person to justice for the massive financial fraud that took place that helped lead to this economic cataclysm.</p>
<p>The failure of our nation to provide international leadership on climate change and to develop a policy that would result in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20energy%20independence">energy independence</ref> is a direct result of the corrupting influence of money from the coal, oil, and gas industries.  I don’t think President Obama woke up one day and decided it would be a really good public policy to veto the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Environmental_Protection_Agency">EPA</ref>’s position of more strict limits on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ozone">ozone</ref> in our communities. Ozone creates so many illnesses and even death. Rather, his decision was just another example of his kowtowing to polluting industries. Likewise, he could have put an end to any possibility of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keystone%20Pipeline">Keystone Pipeline</ref>, yet he’s just put it off, delayed it until after the election, and by all other signs from how he’s conducted himself as president, it is pretty apparent that he will end up approving that pipeline if he is reelected.</p>
</text>
