<text id="autogum_interview_doc077" title="part4_Wikinews interviews Indiana State Senator Mike Delph" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-26" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Indiana_State_Senator_Mike_Delph" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>When I was in Colombia, I got to watch an eradication mission of coca and poppy fields down in Colombia. I also got to work on other cases. There was a new tribes and missionary case that I worked on where there were three men who were abducted by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FARC">FARC</ref>, and there was no proof of life, and they just basically disappeared. And I was able to work with the families and others in leadership within the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/FBI">FBI</ref> to bring that whole issue to closure. They eventually declared the missionaries as being killed by the FARC. But as you can imagine, it was one of those things where the family was in limbo and they just did not know and nobody was trying to find out for them.</p>
<p>It was a great honor to work as a staff member for Congressman Burton. Probably one of the most thankful points in my time for him was when I helped write, or helped ghost write, the resolution honoring the life of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mother%20Theresa">Mother Theresa</ref>, which was adopted by the Congress. You all probably don't remember, but Mother Theresa died right around the time that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Princess%20Diana">Princess Diana</ref> died and all of the news coverage at the time was dedicated towards Princess Diana. And Mother Theresa is arguably somebody that had lived more of a Christ-like life than anybody, since <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus%20Christ">Jesus Christ</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Thompson: Okay one last question from me. What was your father and mother's relationship with former congressman Dan Burton?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: They went to high school together and knew him from their time in high school. And my mother specifically was involved with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Young%20Republicans">Young Republicans</ref> when Congressman Burton was involved with the Young Republicans. And they all kind of grew up in politics together. And then she later became a volunteer for his campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Jordan Mornout: You ended up losing your first campaign when you sought the nomination for Indiana's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secretary%20of%20State%20of%20Indiana">Secretary of State</ref> in 2002. Of course, your opponents that year were impressive, but can you tell us from your perspective about the dramatic finish to that nomination?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: That is a very sore subject with me, but it's not as sore as it used to be. It's interesting because you guys really... I was kind of surprised with the capturing of the whole flyer deal on the floor, which misled the convention to think that I had willingly dropped out of the race, and my strategy was to win it on the second ballot. I was everybody's second choice. The people that were supporting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Todd%20Rokita">Todd Rokita</ref> were supporting him because of their relationship with Sue Anne Gilroy, and they would support me if Todd was not in the race. The people that were supporting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard%20Mourdock">Richard Mourdock</ref> were supporting him because he was older and had more experience than I had. But they liked me after they got to know me, and I was their second choice.</p>
</text>
