<text id="autogum_interview_doc1216" title="part1_Canada's York West (Ward 8) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-york" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-10-19" dateModified="2007-06-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_York_West_%28Ward_8%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I was very discouraged by the fact that our councillor voted against childcare subsidies and with the rise in influence of local developers. I want the community to have more of a say and as a local resident, I feel that I am in the best position to do something.</p>
<p>I also grew up in a family that did not have any influence politically. I can remember not getting chosen for hockey teams after winning the Most Valuable Player in house league one year and not making the all-star team the next year because people with more connections made it. This was very troubling to me and I always wanted to be someone who could make a difference for people and to treat all people equally.</p>
<p>My dad is a truck driver and my mom worked with developmentally challenged clients and so seeing their strong work ethic was an inspiration to me. I was the first person in my family to gain a post secondary degree (Masters in Public Admin in local government) and vow to use everything I have learned and experienced for the benefit of my chosen community.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I worked with Toronto Youth Job Corps serving Jane and Finch, starting back in 1999 (until 2003) and I just loved the sense of community that existed here. Despite all of the negative press, I couldn't see what all the fuss was about. The clients were great, the agencies were fantastic and I just wanted to be a part of the community. As a result, I bought my house in the area and look forward to raising my family here.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I was a member of the Board of Blacksmith Childcare Centre for 2 years, I am still the President of my former condominium board, a former Big Brother and I have started a youth serving agency entitled Big City Youth Services. While it is just starting out, we have already formed some excellent relationships with other local agencies and look forward to expanding the organization in the coming years.</p>
<p>I am also a resident in ward 8 and will be for my entire time in office.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Toronto, ideally, is a place where anyone from any part of the world can come and feel at home. This is the dream that I have for Toronto. However, there are still many issues that need to be addressed such as systemic biases in hiring, lack of representation by minorities and women and the need to improve housing conditions for our residents throughout the City of Toronto.</p>
</text>
