<text id="autogum_interview_doc1293" title="part1_David S. Touretzky discusses Scientology, Anonymous and Tom Cruise" shortTile="partdavid-s-touretzky" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-06" dateModified="2012-12-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_S._Touretzky_discusses_Scientology%2C_Anonymous_and_Tom_Cruise" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="The_interview">The interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews (Nicholas Turnbull)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : How deep do you think the impact of the Anonymous protests and Internet action will be on Scientology’s cashflow?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Prof. David S. Touretzky</hi>: Anonymous will not have any effect on Scientology gross income. Their stats [statistics] are already in the basement. The only folks left are hardcore true believers who think the Intertubes are full of criminals. What Anonymous might do is increase the pressure on Hollywood celebs to distance themselves from the cult. There was a really good article yesterday about how Anonymous is morphing… changing from hackers or pranksters to a legitimate social protest movement.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Yes, indeed... the movement seems to be taking a different sort of shape from just a load of pranksters to a proper, organised protest. So your basic opinion regarding the impact on Scientology's stats is that they are already too low, and failing, for the damage to be significant?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: That's my view, yes.  But that's only one kind of damage. There are several other kinds of damage that may be significant. One is to warn off Hollywood celebs from cozying up to the cult, like Kimora Lee Simmons was just caught doing. And Will Smith too. A second kind of damage has to do with Scientology's attempts to make inroads into civilized society, specifically government programs and local schools.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Presumably this would be, in part, because the celebs wouldn't want to sully their own PR [public relations] image.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: Yes, the celebs have agents and PR people who will tell them in no uncertain terms to stay away from those crazy Scientologists or risk alienating their fan base. It must be difficult to be a Tom Cruise fan right now. What can you say when your idol publicly steps in dog poo and insists it's spun gold?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Quite... the leaked video was quite possibly worse than the Oprah fiasco for his reputation, I think.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: "Tom Cruise is batshit crazy" has entered the national lexicon, along with "SP", "KSW", and "We are the authorities". Yeah, that line ["We are the authorities"] is priceless.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Yes, indeed; it has now become part of popular culture and the “blogosphere” has gone crazy over it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DT</hi>: There's one more thing I hope Anonymous can accomplish, and that is to shift the focus from Xenu and BTs [“body thetans”, souls said to be attached to a person in Scientology’s secret “OT III” teachings] to disconnection, fair game, fraud, and barratry. Did you know that DM's [David Miscavige, the current leader of Scientology’s] niece is appearing on <hi rend="italic">Inside Edition</hi> tonight?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : I didn't know that she was appearing on <hi rend="italic">Inside Edition</hi>, actually. I must catch that.</p>
</text>
