<text id="autogum_interview_doc1022" title="Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Liberal candidate Kate Holloway, Trinity-Spadina" shortTile="ontario-votes--interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-01" dateModified="2019-07-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Liberal_candidate_Kate_Holloway%2C_Trinity-Spadina" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Liberal candidate Kate Holloway, Trinity-Spadina</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 1, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kathryn%20Holloway">Kate Holloway</ref></hi> is running for the Ontario Liberal Party in the Ontario provincial election, in the Trinity-Spadina riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed her regarding her values, her experience, and her campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>Many of the issues I care about are under the jurisdiction of the provincial government. In Ontario, we're luck to have a young and progressive cabinet. They've done a lot of great things already, and I want to help them do more.</p>
<p>I chose to run in Trinity-Spadina because this is where I've spent most of the last 20 years of my life. It's where I've raised my son and where I feel at home.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I was an organizer for the Green Party of Canada during the 2004 federal election and served on the Federal Council of the Green Party. I bring a wide range of experience from my non-political life, from holding senior executive positions in high-tech and advertising to serving on the Steering Committee of Green Enterprise Toronto to being a founding member of the Women's Environmental Alliance.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?</hi></p>
<p>There's a great field of candidates from other parties as well as a number of independents. Only the voters know who they'll pick on October 10.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>Trinity-Spadina needs an MPP working with and inside the government, fighting for our interests. As a financial professional and renewable energy developer, I have the skills to ensure fiscal health, urban sustainability and appropriate development.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>Many citizens are concerned about our environment in general and climate change in particular. Ontario Liberals have acted decisively by bringing in legislation such as the Clean Water Act and preserving the principle of extended producer responsibility. Liberals protected 1.8 Million acres of arable land from development and urban sprawl through the Greenbelt Plan and also introduced Ontario's new Standard Offer Program for small renewable energy projects. We plan to keep fighting climate change and investing in green technologies.</p>
<p>Another deep concern is ensuring Ontario's publicly funded education system is the best in the world. After years of Conservative cuts and chaos, we're turning things around and we can't afford to go backwards.</p>
<p>Also, healthcare is an issue all over the riding. We are now spending CA$9 billion per year more on healthcare than the previous government, including investing millions into community-based mental health services. Ontario Liberals will continue to fight for a strong, publicly funded health care system for all Ontarians.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>Implementing the Ontario Liberal Party 2007 Platform. <ref target="http://www.ontarioliberal.ca/en/Platformhtml.aspx?id=2">http://www.ontarioliberal.ca/en/Platformhtml.aspx?id=2</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>High property taxes are a big concern for Trinity-Spadina homeowners, especially seniors. The Liberal platform commits to uploading the full cost of both the Ontario Disability Support Program and the Ontario Drug Benefit over four years, relieving over $900 million per year in pressure from local property taxpayers. We will also implement a new homeowners' grant for seniors who have trouble paying their property taxes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>We need to train the best workforce in the world. We need the best educated, most highly skilled workers in order to secure the most investment and the best jobs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What are your views on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mixed%20member%20proportional%20representation">mixed member proportional representation</ref> (MMP) referendum?</hi></p>
<p>I support MMP and <ref target="http://liberals4mmp.blogspot.com">serve as a spokesperson for Liberals for MMP</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What role, if any, does "new media" play in your campaign, and the campaign of your party? (websites, blogs, Facebook, YouTube videos, etc) Do you view it as beneficial, or a challenge?</hi></p>
<p>Websites and YouTube are great tools for voters to access information. The internet is also a great equalizer. Anyone can make a video for YouTube <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c_nsxLUwzos">such as this one</ref>.</p>
<p><ref target="http://www.facebook.com/group.php?gid=4246204068">Facebook groups are also great</ref> for like-minded people to self organize.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Of the decisions made by Ontario's 38th Legislative Assembly, which was the most beneficial to your this electoral district? To the province as a whole? Which was least beneficial, or even harmful, to your this riding? To the province as a whole?</hi></p>
<p>There were many beneficial decisions by the 38th Legislative Assembly. The introduction of a comprehensive, long-term plan to fight child poverty through the Ontario Child Benefit is especially promising. Also, new legislation to strengthen the City of Toronto, giving the city its own Charter, was a huge achievement.</p>
</text>
