<text id="autogum_interview_doc447" title="part1_US presidential candidate Duncan Hunter speaks to Wikinews" shortTile="partus-presidential" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-12" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_presidential_candidate_Duncan_Hunter_speaks_to_Wikinews" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israeli%20West%20Bank%20barrier">fence that was built in Israel</ref> is seen by many as divisive in an area that is far more explosive than the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexican</ref>-U.S. border.  How do you respond to people who say that a fence is more symbolic of divisiveness than a resolution of the issues that cause <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illegal%20immigration%20to%20the%20United%20States">illegal immigration</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Actually, I think the fence has received the approval of people who live on <hi rend="italic">both</hi> sides of the border in my community, because before we built that border fence in San Diego—I don’t know if you read the book <hi rend="italic">Lines and Shadows</hi>, that was a best-selling book by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph%20Wambaugh">Joseph Wambaugh</ref>, who wrote <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Onion%20Field">The Onion Field</ref></hi>—it was about the no-mans land that existed between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San%20Diego-Tijuana%20metropolitan%20area">Tijuana and San Diego</ref> before we built that fence.  You had <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List%20of%20California%20street%20gangs">armed gangs</ref>, some of them with machine guns, that preyed on the illegal aliens, murdered a number of people, robbed people by the hundreds every night, and they preyed on people not only on the northern side, but in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zona%20Río,%20Tijuana">northern Tijuana</ref> neighborhoods.  When we built the double border fence, we took away the mobility of the border gangs, put them out of business, and we actually brought about a much better situation for people on both sides of the border.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Is a fence the remedy for that, or is finding a remedy for the needs and causes of those gangs and for the illegal migration of people a remedy? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi> Let me put it this way:  until we built the border fence, nothing worked.  We had <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Border%20Patrol">law enforcement</ref> operations on both sides of the border, and the gangs ran wild.  They used the border as a safe haven.  If they were pursued in the north, they’d go south; if they were pursued in the south, they’d go north.  So until we built the double fence—it’s two fences with a road between—and we took away the mobility of the border gangs, we weren’t able to handle that.  So actually there wasn’t another remedy.  There’s another reason that we need to have one, and that’s this: today we have 250,000 criminal aliens, mostly people who came across from Mexico, not to look for work or for a better life, but to hurt Americans.  People who created and committed serious crimes against Americans.  250,000 of those folks right now in federal, state and local penitentiaries and jails.  Unless you have—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What were they coming here to do?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DH:</hi>  Well, they came across to hurt people!  Those people didn’t come across to find job, they came across to commit crimes, got convicted, and are presently residing in our penitentiaries and jails.  That’s a quarter of a million criminal aliens.</p>
</text>
