<text id="autogum_interview_doc1098" title="part3_In the land of the open source elves: Interview with "Battle for Wesnoth" creator David White" shortTile="partin-land-open" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-05-29" dateModified="2015-10-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/In_the_land_of_the_open_source_elves%3A_Interview_with_%22Battle_for_Wesnoth%22_creator_David_White" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>Wesnoth was always designed to be a simple game, with simple goals. It has exceeded all the expectations I originally had for it. There is still some 'polishing' work going on, but really I don't think there is too much I would dramatically change.</p>
<p>Probably the largest thing I can name is a much better AI than we currently have. I'm pretty happy with the AI developed for Wesnoth — I think it's much better than AIs for most commercial games — but it could be better. That's the only area of Wesnoth that I think could really be very dramatically improved.</p>
<p>I am pretty happy with our in-game graphics. Some people compare our graphics to modern commercial games, and think our graphics are laughably poor. We often get comments that our graphics are around the same quality as those seen in SNES or Genesis games, or PC games from a decade ago. (These people should try playing a strategy game on the SNES/Genesis/PC from this long ago; Wesnoth's graphics are much better).</p>
<p>I am very happy with our graphics overall. I think our artists have done an excellent job of making the game look attractive without detracting from functionality. Adding 3D graphics, or changing the style of the 2D graphics would only be wasted effort in my mind — I think we've achieved a great balance of making the game easy and clear, while making it look good.</p>
<p>With unlimited resources, I would like some more storyline/cutscene images, and a nice new title screen, but these are relatively small concerns I think.</p>
<p>There are some enhancements to multiplayer I would like added — multiplayer campaigns is a long-time feature request. As are more options and features on the multiplayer server.</p>
<p>Overall though, if I had 'unlimited resources', I'd much rather develop an entirely new game. We don't have enough good Open Source games — it's a waste to pour all the resources we have into one.:) </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wesnoth has dwarves with guns, <hi rend="italic">World of Warcraft</hi> has gnomes and goblins with explosives and flying machines — where do you, personally, define the limits of the fantasy genre? Are there scenarios playing in a steampunk world, or ones with modern technology? Would you allow those?</hi></p>
<p>Actually we have Dwarves with 'Thundersticks':) — mysterious weapons that make a loud sound and do lots of damage, but are clumsy and unreliable. The developers do not comment on whether or not these 'thundersticks' are or are not like 'guns' on earth. We like to keep Wesnoth slightly mysterious, and leave some things up to the player's interpretation, rather than spell it out.</p>
<p>We once used to have dragoons with pistols, and other weapons like that, but we made a very intentional decision to remove them.</p>
</text>
