<text id="autogum_interview_doc1032" title="part8_Blown for Good author discusses life inside international headquarters of Scientology" shortTile="partblown-good-author" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-11-12" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Blown_for_Good_author_discusses_life_inside_international_headquarters_of_Scientology" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>People that I knew that were already declared suppressive were offered to have their declares canceled if they turned over any information that would be helpful with blacklisting me or ruining my credibility or ability to work or make money. </p>
<p>One of my oldest friends (who is also a declared Suppressive Person by Scientology) was offered a “deal” by Tommy Davis to be allowed to speak with his family again if he were to provide any information or details about my current life that could be used against me in my current legal case against Scientology. When they doctored a declaration from him and he refused to sign it, they canceled the deal with him, but still attempted to use the bogus declaration in legal proceedings with me.  </p>
<p>Child Protective Services were given a random phone call “tip” that my two children were being endangered and had to do a mandatory inspection at our house. The agent told us they had investigated the “tip”, that it was clearly false and advised us to be very careful as someone was obviously trying to create trouble for us. </p>
<p>Scientology management has even gone so far as to inform Scientology members that use FaceBook or MySpace social networking sites to spread false information to anyone listed as my friends and instruct them that they should “disconnect” from me. </p>
<p>Private Investigators tracked down and contacted persons that my wife had talked to and the broker she worked under in Real Estate and accused my wife of falsifying loan documents on someone she never did a loan for.</p>
<p>When I traveled to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref> to speak to government officials regarding Scientology’s abuses in the United State and abroad, Private Investigators banged on the door of my house early in the morning when my wife was alone with our children and harassed her, saying they’d [been] sent by Scientology.</p>
<p>During that same trip, private investigators showed up at my company warehouse and gave my employees false propaganda printed up by Scientology regarding me being an “anti-religious extremist”. </p>
<p>If I were to list everything else that I have experienced with Scientology in regards to Fair Game, this site would possibly need to upgrade their storage capacity!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Are there any other points regarding <hi rend="italic">Blown for Good</hi> or your experiences that you would like to elaborate or explain?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">I want to make sure that people know that the more people that speak out, the more that these things will be dealt with.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Marc Headley</p>
<p>I want to make sure that people know that the more people that speak out, the more that these things will be dealt with. The Scientology organization compares itself to other religions all the time. They state that they expect to be treated like other religions. Most mainstream religions in all countries of the world support the living wage or minimum wage for their employees and workers and publicly state this. If organized Scientology wants to be treated like other religions, they should cease the human rights abuses and take a hint from other groups and pay their employees for the work they perform. Maybe then, people would be able to LEAVE if they wanted to and not have the burden of being without family members, resources or the ability to buy a meal should they decide to terminate their employment with Scientology. </p>
</text>
