<text id="autogum_interview_doc1160" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Kristen Monster, Willowdale" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-03" dateModified="2008-10-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Kristen_Monster%2C_Willowdale" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>Of all the candidates running in the riding of Willowdale, I can offer my constituents honesty, integrity, and morality. I am not making campaign promises to be broken later, as others have done. I am not pledging millions of dollars for the sake of buying votes. I am simply presenting principles and reforms for managing government affairs responsibly, efficiently, and fairly, and am offering my services to the people of Willowdale. Whatever this office asks of me, I will seek to do the best for my riding.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>The three most important issues to voters in the riding of Willowdale in this election are transportation, senior care, and education. One or two of these issues are the same as, or related to, the issues that are most important to me (protection of all human life, protection and promotion of the family, and parental choice in education).</p>
<p>For Willowdale's issues, I would propose the following solutions:</p>
<p>Transportation. Recently, Toronto's budget shortfall made funding for the TTC and the quality of transportation in this riding into serious issues. I suggest as a possible solution that the provincial government pursue having the TTC buses (and other public transit systems) privatized, and encourage competing bus companies to become established. This would contribute to lower fare prices and better service, and would most likely attract more consumers and create more jobs. The money that was originally being used for the TTC buses could then be invested in improving and maintaining the subway system (for the present).</p>
<p>Senior Care. Seniors are valuable people, who deserve respect and proper treatment. I believe that, on a general basis, the best care-givers are their family members. I will provide tax breaks for persons who support and properly care for their aged parents, and will create incentives for others to do so. I would rather see seniors at home, being cared for by family members who love them, than in long-term nursing facilities.</p>
<p>Education. The education of a child is not something for the government to decide: parents have an inalienable right and duty to oversee the education of their children, and the provincial government should respect and promote this. The education system should be opened to parental choice and free market competition.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th legislative assembly?</hi></p>
<p>The first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly should be to address the issue of the right of women to be informed. At present, women opting for the elective procedure of abortion are not informed of the risks this procedure poses to their health and the health of the child in the womb. Medical practitioners should be required to make this information available to women patients considering abortion.</p>
</text>
