<text id="autogum_interview_doc1029" title="part5_Blown for Good author discusses life inside international headquarters of Scientology" shortTile="partblown-good-author" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-11-12" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Blown_for_Good_author_discusses_life_inside_international_headquarters_of_Scientology" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Is Scientology's characterization from the Ordinance 884 proceedings, describing Gold Base as residential and containing private homes, appropriate in nature? Ordinance 884 is intended to keep protesters more than 50 feet away from property lines of residences. Are there residential housing buildings within 50 feet inside the property lines of Gold Base?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: I have never measured it out, but most of the housing that exists on the property is located in the “berthing buildings” section of the property. From what I remember these buildings are at least 100 feet or more from the highway. There [are] main production buildings located directly next to the highway all along the property lines. During my 15 years working there I spent many a night sleeping on the floor in my office and witnessed many others doing the same or sleeping under their desks for a few hours each night. Maybe that qualifies those buildings as “housing” based on that. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The book's title is a reference to the Scientology term to "blow", defined in the glossary of the book as "any unauthorized departure from any Scientology organization." What steps are taken once the individual who had decided to leave is located? Has physical force been used in the past to bring individuals back? What other means have been used to attempt to bring people back to the organization?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: I would say that a very large percentage of staff that blow are recovered or at least a recovery is attempted. I know of many other staff that were restrained from leaving, or assaulted when being recovered or thrown into vehicles and brought back to the compound against their will. Stories that corroborate this are all over the internet and many people have spoken out against this abuse. Unfortunately, for most people the fear that they have of the Scientology organization takes years to wear off and by the time people come forward, it is too late, legally, for anything to be done about it by law enforcement.   </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You describe an elaborate scheme to get your wife Claire to join you, after she informed you that she wished to leave Gold Base (p. 322-25). This plan included avoiding use of phones known to Scientology, calling for a taxi under a different name, and calling friends from pay phones. Would it not have simply been easier for her to have contacted the local police for assistance, as they had done previously with you? To put it more simply - why the need for individuals who wish to leave Gold Base to orchestrate an escape to plan how they will "blow"? Could they not simply call the police using a phone, either from the facility itself or elsewhere, and request assistance to leave the organization?</hi></p>
</text>
