<text id="autogum_interview_doc206" title="part7_BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2008-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Just random people who have certain things happen in their life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like what?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Anything really.  Like a trauma from school or problems with a family member.  Things like that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How would you treat that person differently than someone who is coming here for the pleasure or the thrill of it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I would be more aware and pay more attention to where the session is taking them.  You really need to be fully aware of everything that is going on.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What would be a point where you didn’t feel comfortable with the session?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  His reaction, if I see he is starting to fall deeper and deeper into depression, whereas sometimes that has happened in sessions.  Sometimes a guy will cry during the session, or sob uncontrollably.  Sometimes he will get angry and start screaming.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In both of those situations, how would you handle it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  You start to console them.  That’s when you know you are no longer in that session, that It is no longer a role play.  That is where the psychological really comes into it, when the psychology helps, to be there and to listen.  Sometimes they are like, “I killed my pet dog by accident and I’ve kept this inside for me for so long!”  Or, “I had a close family member just pass away and I don’t know how to deal with that right now.”  “My girlfriend just left me—“ I mean, you hear all these stories!  One after the other after the other, and it’s just like, “Wow!”   If one is crying, you console them; if one is angry you try to calm them down.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you give them absolution?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Yeah, “It wasn’t your fault what happened.  You were five years old, how would you know what this would do to the dog, you know?”  A lot of cases you have to help them out with it and at the end of the session they just feel so much better about themselves.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you do when someone gets angry?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Usually just try to bring them down and find out about what it is that gets them so angry.  A lot of times they are not going to come out and say, “This is what is bothering me.”  They are going to veil it so much that you are trying to knock down so many walls they put up, and finally it can be one word, one comment, a simple thing that you might say that might trigger something, and then you realize what happened.  A lot of times you try to keep it within the role play, as well, which is what really makes the session great, but you just calm them down.</p>
</text>
