<text id="autogum_interview_doc617" title="part5_Wikinews interviews Joe Schriner, Independent U.S. presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-04-16" dateModified="2019-08-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Joe_Schriner%2C_Independent_U.S._presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">When you say "<ref target="http://starbeacon.com/obitcorrection/x343696723/In-the-2008-presidential-campaign-it-was-Joe-the-Plumber-In-2012-it-s-going-to-be-Joe-the-Painter">we are left of the Green Party</ref>,” does that mean you view yourself as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialism">socialist</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> No, I'm not a socialist.  In the article you allude to, I made that comment (as I often do) in relationship to being “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Left-wing%20politics">left</ref> of the Green Party” when it comes to the environment.  And that's hard to do.  If fact, I told the Freemont Messenger newspaper in Ohio that when it comes to helping the environment, no Party even comes close to matching the Green Party.  I have merely used the 'left of the Green Party' thing to illustrate how serious we are about the environment.  During a Third Party presidential candidate debate at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Press%20Club%20(USA)">National Press Club</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington,%20D.C.">Washington</ref>, I said that our family had established a “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kyoto%20Protocol">Kyoto Protocol</ref> Home Zone.”  We don't use air conditioning, cut the thermostat back in the winter, dry clothes on the line, recycle practically everything, live simply with few material items, bicycle or walk practically everywhere within a five-mile radius of our home, use lights sparingly...  And at the White House, we'd be doing the same. Not to mention, there would be solar panels and a wind turbine on the White House roof.  Our point being that we can't wait for something more tangible than the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copenhagen%20Accord">Copenhagen Accord</ref> at this point, but rather the time for each American to voluntarily act on this is: now!  Note:  We have traveled extensively looking at things like a wind turbine installation in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mandan,%20North%20Dakota">Mandan</ref>; a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geothermal%20power">geothermal</ref> home installation in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upper%20Peninsula%20of%20Michigan">Upper Peninsula of Michigan</ref> ($17 heating bill in: January); a Southwest Sustainability Project for retrofitting homes with insulation and alternative energy... And our administration would attempt to move America away from being the leading 'Society of Consumers' in the world, to be the leading 'Society of Conservers.'  I mean if we're going to lead, why not lead in the right way – for our kids and for future generations. At the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White%20Earth%20Indian%20Reservation">White Earth Reservation</ref> in Minnesota, I interviewed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winona%20LaDuke">Winona LaDuke</ref>.  Ms. LaDuke is an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ojibwe">Ojibwe Tribe</ref> member who ran for vice-president with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ralph%20Nader">Ralph Nader</ref> in Campaign 2000.  She said her tribe believes they are environmentally responsible for the next: seven generations.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">As a former addictions counselor, would you like to see some prohibitions on the sale of alcohol? Would you consider yourself a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/temperance%20movement">temperance movement</ref>?</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Joe Schriner campaign photo Image: Joe Schriner.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I would, indeed, be an advocate for temperance (more responsible drinking); but not for a return to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/prohibition">prohibition</ref>. At the outset, let me draw some parallels to smoking.  It was determined that smoking was hazardous to one's health.  (Currently more than 160,000 people die of lung cancer each year, as an example.)  Then there are other smoking related respiratory issues (like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/emphysema">emphysema</ref>), and second hand smoke issues, and...  In light of all this, anti-smoking campaigns gained incremental traction over the past 50 years.  These led to eventually getting cigarette smoking ads banned in many media and created a climate favorable for significantly increased taxes on cigarettes.  (President Obama just signed a law increasing federal tax on cigarettes from 32 cents a pack to $1 a pack.) And a wide variety of programs started up to alert youth about the dangers of smoking.  As a result of all this, fewer than 20% of adult Americans still smoke, according to a recent <ref target="http://www.time.com/time/health/article/0,8599,1911796,00.html">Time Magazine article</ref>.  This figure is down significantly from when the campaign started...  Now, while again, I'm not advocating prohibition, common sense says you have to look at the level of drinking in our society at this point – and how destructive it's becoming.  As a former addictions counselor, I did indeed see the destruction alcohol can wreak.  It lubricates things like domestic violence between spouses, child abuse, broken families...  During our cross country research, I also interviewed Mark West, who started a cutting edge two-year treatment model for recovering alcoholics and addicts in prisons nationwide.  He said 80% of prisoners these days have committed crimes under the influence of alcohol or drugs, or were trying to get money for alcohol or drugs when they committed the crime(s).  Then there are all the alcohol related traffic fatalities and maiming.  Then factor in all those alcoholics who have died of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cirrhosis">cirrhosis</ref> of the liver, or have hemorrhaged to death internally from alcohol addiction, or who have committed suicide under the influence.  And add to all this, the number of people in mental institutions with “wet brains” and other mental health complications from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/alcoholism">alcoholism</ref>.  In essence, the numbers with all this are staggering.  And by comparison, because of the tremendously broad ramifications, alcohol abuse has a much more wide sweeping effect on society than smoking...  So, like with cigarettes, our administration would push for things like a significant jump in taxes on alcohol.  The higher costs, like with cigarettes, will curtail some drinking.  Like with what happened with smoking, we would also push for banning drinking ads in the media (There is currently more money spent on ads for alcohol, than on any other product in America.)  Another strategy that we're looking at is proposing: drinking licenses.  Seriously.  A former bartender in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbiana%20County,%20Ohio">Columbiana County</ref>, proposed this to us.  For instance, he said just like with getting a driver's license, there should be a written test for a drinking license.  It would cover such topics as how many drinks it takes approximately to move one's blood alcohol level over the legal limit in a state.  Another set of questions might include identifying the signs and symptoms of alcoholism.  In the event of, say, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DWI">DWI</ref>, or other criminal offense (robbery, domestic violence...) involving alcohol, a person's drinking license could be revoked for a period of time.  And if he/she was caught drinking during this time, more penalties would be levied.</p>
</text>
