<text id="autogum_interview_doc1092" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with independent candidate Charles de Kerckhove, St. Paul's" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-01" dateModified="2014-03-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_independent_candidate_Charles_de_Kerckhove%2C_St._Paul%27s" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with independent candidate Charles de Kerckhove, St. Paul's</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 1, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Charles de Kerckhove</hi> is running as an independent in the Ontario provincial election, in the riding of St. Paul's. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>The purpose of this campaign is to address child sexual abuse, an issue affecting at least 1 out of every 10 Canadians (Health Canada), through the promotion of policies advocated by website www.protect-kids.org.</p>
<p>Every child in Ontario needs to benefit from primary prevention programs addressing all potential sexual offences, accounting for potential offenders either unknown or well-known to a child. While progress has been introduced within our legal system and within our counselling resources to better accommodate child needs, current standards of prevention, support and accountability remain inadequate.</p>
<p>While this campaign is pleased to offer opinions about other issues only as requested, its mandate is limited to public consideration of www.protect-kids.org, with the hopes that mainstream parties will adopt some or all of the proposals.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>My political experience includes participation in a number of campaigns within mainstream parties. Six years of experience within Ontarian industry as an engineer, a manager and as a marketing representative have provided insights with respect to economic development and environmental restoration. With respect to the issues of this campaign however, my insights derive from research within the current status and implementation of child-specific case law, civil litigation in sexual abuse, interviews of organisations working in prevention initiatives, and visits of provincial victim witness programs and of sexual assault support centres.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why? What makes you the most desirable of all candidates running in the riding?</hi></p>
<p>There is no competitor to my candidacy per se, as the purpose of this campaign is to persuade St. Paul’s voters to consider “donating their vote”. While the biggest challenge naturally is outreach towards every potential voter within the riding, our team is encouraged by the many friendly receptions going door to door, as well as the general agreement towards better protecting the dignity and safety of every Ontarian child.</p>
</text>
