<text id="autogum_interview_doc504" title="part7_Eric Bogosian on writing and the creative urge" shortTile="parteric-bogosian" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-16" dateModified="2014-05-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Eric_Bogosian_on_writing_and_the_creative_urge" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Nobody wants to find out why a person's troubled anymore?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They just want to see what the effects are and how things resolve?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Yeah, and tell a good story, and have lots of different things going on between different kinds of armies, like <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/300%20(film)">300</ref></hi> or whoever they are--talk about medieval, <hi rend="italic">300</hi> is <hi rend="italic">before</hi> medieval.  I think you'll see more stuff like that.  It isn't entirely to my taste, but the funny thing is, when I see all that kind of material, and then I go back and I look at the kinds of the things that have always attracted me, I realize that it's really the same story over and over and over again.  Some troubled white male and his dick, and he's trying to figure out what the fuck is going on in this life--I mean, this is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip%20Roth">Philip Roth</ref>.  It gets you to the Philip Roth novels that he's been currently writing, which are--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Which are critically acclaimed but not commercially successful.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Yeah, and they're also complete dead ends.  I mean, they're the most fucking depressing things--I mean if you're a Philip Roth fan like me, and you've been reading them for years, it's okay.  You get it.  This guy is in his seventies, he's wearing a diaper, he can't get it up anymore . . . .</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  You know, but how is it--how would anybody else be into that kind of shit?  It's so uninteresting.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Well, it's been seen so many times that everyone knows where it's going; it gets to the point where you're like, okay, what is this?  "Dejected Man"?  Is this, "World Didn't Turn Out The Way You Thought It Would Man"? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In the end, the stories become uninteresting because you know it's going to be either a, b, c, or d that makes the conflict.   Which is it going to be?  People tend to like to read things because they want their interest grabbed.  They don't want to read a book like when they watch a horror movie, knowing what is right around the corner.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How is that person going to die?  You know they're going to die.  Are they going to be slashed across the throat? are they going to have a sword plunging through their stomach? are they going to be shot in the face?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You know when you watch a horror movie the person's going to die; it's just a question of how.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EB:</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you take that to a literary level, it starts becoming too formulaic, and people don't care how.</hi></p>
</text>
