<text id="autogum_interview_doc1337" title="part2_An interview with Paul Campbell, founder of Amazing Radio UK" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-01-10" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_Paul_Campbell%2C_founder_of_Amazing_Radio_UK" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>When they do, we'll then be able to go back to the BBC Trust to say ‘guess what?  The BBC rejected our complaint. Now will you investigate?’. Yawn. </p>
<hi rend="bold">All this might make me seem a BBC-hater. Actually nothing could be further from the truth. The BBC trained me.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Paul Campbell</p>
<p>All this might make me seem a BBC-hater.  Actually nothing could be further from the truth.  The BBC trained me.  I was once, so I was told by the Head of Appointments, its youngest-ever Producer.  Despite appearances, I firmly believe it's one of the best things about the UK.  I wrote to The Times of London recently in defence of it. But unfortunately it's really, really bad at understanding the damage it does to private companies, the ones like ours that create jobs and try to create wealth, without the benefit of a guaranteed income.  (Or even, any income at all).  </p>
<p>The stakes are high.  The conventional music industry is falling to bits around us. There’s an historic opportunity to re-invent music in a way that's fair to musicians and music-lovers, and also creates jobs and wealth in the real economy. It's vitally important the BBC, with its publicly-funded hobnailed boots, doesn't ruin that opportunity. </p>
<p>So we’ll do our complaint, wait for it to be rejected, complain to the Trust, and keep battering away. Fun fun fun.  (This would never happen in the States). </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You don't accept any <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PRS">PRS</ref> registered artists at all.  Why not? </hi></p>
 HAVE YOUR SAY
 Do you agree with Paul?  Are PRS getting it completely wrong?
<ref target="//en.wikinews.org/w/index.php?title=Comments:Main_Page&amp;action=edit&amp;preload=Wikinews:Commentary_pages_on_news_events/body&amp;editintro=Template:Editintro_comments&amp;summary=create">Add or view comments</ref>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PC</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> We’d love to – after all, we have the same aim as PRS, which is to make it easier for musicians to earn a living from their talent.  But we can’t.  There’s two reasons. </p>
<p><p><p>1. PRS has a barmy standard contract for using their members’ music online.  It requires us to pay them a fixed percentage of ALL revenue from that website – whether or not the revenue is derived from their members’ work. So if we had 100,000 songs from non-PRS artists on amazingtunes.com, and one song from a PRS artist, we’d have to pay them a percentage of the revenue from ALL 100,000 songs.  I.e., we’d have to take money out of the pockets out of non-PRS artists to pay to PRS. That would be immoral.</p></p></p>
<p><p><p>2.  If we played PRS artists on the radio, we’d have to pay PRS for our use of their members’ music.  Sound fair enough? But PRS doesn’t know what to do with the money.  They’d put it into a big bucket, then share it out among ALL their artists - not the members whose songs we played, all their artists, including rich and famous signed ones. The vast majority of PRS payments go to a tiny minority of artists (and big record labels).  So it would be another case of stealing from Peter to pay Paul.  Paul McCartney, that is.</p></p></p>
</text>
