<text id="autogum_interview_doc1009" title="part5_Wikinews interviews Spain's most decorated Paralympian, Teresa Perales" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2013-01-19" dateModified="2015-11-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Spain%27s_most_decorated_Paralympian%2C_Teresa_Perales" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Teresa Perales</hi>: I was, I was. [Laughs] No, I worked in politics, I really wasn't a politician. I believe that when you want things to change, and when you believe that there is something that has to change, you need to be part of the change. And that's why I entered politics. That's why I think that it is important that people get involved in politics. And not only... In my case, I didn't get in for sports politics, I got in for general politics, because I believed there were several things that could be improved or that should be changed, and that's why I got in. And I believe that sportspeople are very qualified, because, let me give an example. Me, that I spend seven days a week, six hours every day training, seeing the floor and walls, I just can do whatever I want in this life.[Laughs] I know I am not going to go down in the dumps if I have a problem, because while training I know that things may not work out the first day, the second, the third, but someday they will, right? And that's what sportspeople contribute to any job, and especially to politics. I defend what sportspeople can contribute, I've given conference talks on what a sportsperson can contribute to a company, and what a sportsperson can contribute to politics is the same because it is also a job and a company, right? It's how to manage resources: I manage my resources every day to get the most out of me. I also manage my emotions, because I am a whole. I am a physical whole, but also an emotional whole. And I know I can make decisions in a matter of seconds. I do it every time I compete. My 50m event takes 35 seconds. It's 35 seconds. Four years, seven days a week, six hours every day for 35 seconds. So I can make decisions and work really well in politics or in whatever I want to.  ((es))Spanish language: ‍ Lo fuí, lo fuí. [Risas] No, yo trabajé en política, no fui realmente una política. Yo creo que cuando quieres que las cosas cambien, y cuando crees que hay algo que tiene que cambiar, tú tienes que formar parte del cambio. Y esto es por lo que yo entré en política. Por eso creo que es importante que la gente se involucre en política. Y no solamente... En mi caso, no me metí en políticas de deporte, me metí en políticas de todo, porque creía que había varias cosas que podían mejorar o que se podían cambiar, y por eso entré. Y creo que los deportistas estamos muy cualificados, porque, vamos a poner un ejemplo. Un deportista. Yo, que me paso siete días a la semana, seis horas entrenando, viendo baldosas, viendo corcheras, es que puedo hacer lo que quiera en esta vida.[Risas] Yo sé que no me voy a venir abajo si tengo un problema, porque entrenando sé que el primer día no sale, el segundo tampoco, el tercero tampoco, pero algún día saldrá, ¿no? Y eso es lo que aportamos los deportistas a cualquier trabajo, y especialmente en política. Yo defiendo lo que puede aportar un deportista, he dado conferencias en las que he hablado de lo que puede aportar un deportista a una empresa, y lo que puede aportar un deportista a la política es lo mismo porque es un trabajo y también es una empresa, ¿no? Es cómo gestionar recursos: yo gestiono mis recursos todos los días para sacar el máximo partido de mi misma. Gestiono también emociones, porque yo soy un todo. Soy un todo físico pero también soy un todo emocional. Y sé que puedo tomar decisiones en cuestión de segundos. Lo hago cada vez que compito. Mi prueba de 50m es 35 segundos. Son 35 segundos. Cuatro años, siete días a la semana, seis horas al día para 35 segundos. Así que puedo tomar decisiones y puedo trabajar muy bien en política o en lo que quiera.</p></p>
</text>
