<text id="autogum_interview_doc1169" title="part2_Lobby groups oppose plans for EU copyright extension" shortTile="partlobby-groups" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-18" dateModified="2014-12-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lobby_groups_oppose_plans_for_EU_copyright_extension" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="italic">Behind all of this info about copyright law, you need to know about the basics</hi>. Copyright law is about a balance, about a trade-off. Artists put a lot in to creating a piece of work, and once that piece has been created, in a sense, it's very easy to replicate. So, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cliff%20Richard">Cliff Richard</ref> sings a song, and it's very easy once he has sung this song, it's laid down to be copied and copied and copied, unlike the making of a table or a shoe where you have to go back to the original creator to get a new pair. Copyright is a kind of monopoly that is granted to the creator so that they may get the revenue that they need, enough to incentivise them to make the initial work. So copyright is a trade-off between the interests of us, the public, the audience, human beings who need culture to survive and thrive, and artists who in order to make this culture need an incentive. In the law it is said that for a certain length of time, you have the rights to exploit this cultural product that has come from your loins and after that, it enters the public domain, and everyone enjoys it without restrictions.</p>
<figure><caption><hi rend="bold">What you've got at the end of the day with copyright term extension is basically ... rent seeking by special interest groups lobbying governments to change the law in order that they may economically gain directly.</hi>-Becky Hogge, Open Rights Group Executive Director (left).</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Extending that term has a lot of implications.</hi> The first question that comes up is, you say: why? Are we going to incentivise Cliff Richards' to record any more tracks in 1958? Clearly not, because it's not 1958 any more. And then you ask yourself the second question: are you going to incentivise artists who are recording tracks now to record more tracks, because they have more incentive, because their monopoly over these neighbouring rights will be knocked up? Economists have looked at this and they say, 'any rational act of making a decision does not look at what's going to happen in 50 years time, let alone 95 years time, we simply don't do this. So what you've got at the end of the day with copyright term extension is basically, and I hope this is not too bold, it's basically rent seeking. It's rent seeking by special interest groups lobbying governments to change the law in order that they may economically gain directly.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">This is were you get to the sort of Cliff Richard argument with pension</hi>. Cliff Richard is a recording artist who didn't write his own songs and will stop receiving <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music%20Royalties">royalty</ref>. You've got Cliff Richard saying 'copyright is a pension for us'. There are artists that are saying 50 years after they've started their career, started recording, they're old, they're pensionable aged, they need their income and this royalty income is stopping. I simply don't like that argument because every other citizen of the E.U. has contributed to their pension during their working life. This argument for me is really designed to do something very clever, which is exact sympathy from the general public for people who are already very rich. If you're still getting royalties after 50 years, you are a very successful artist indeed.</p>
</text>
