<text id="autogum_interview_doc523" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Ruth Bryant White, independent candidate for US President" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-19" dateModified="2008-08-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Ruth_Bryant_White%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Ruth Bryant White, independent candidate for US President</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 19, 2008</hi></p>
<p>While nearly all coverage of the 2008 Presidential election has focused on the Democratic and Republican candidates, the race for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White%20House">White House</ref> also includes independents and third party candidates. These parties represent a variety of views that may not be acknowledged by the major party platforms.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref> has impartially reached out to these candidates, throughout the campaign. We now interview independent Presidential candidate <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruth%20Bryant%20White">Ruth Bryant White</ref></hi>, an ordained Christian minister, author, and homemaker.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why do you want to be President?</hi></p>
<p>I don’t, but I will serve for the betterment of our Country. I love my country I don’t like politics. I seem to be the best qualified candidate besides <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike%20Huckabee">Mike Huckabee</ref>, whom I would gladly work with to run this country. I would love to be Co-President with someone who takes care of business and is not trying to become a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington">Washington</ref> Insider.</p>
<p>I believe we can clean up the mess in Washington. We’re the only two that can in my humble opinion. Nobody knows what’s happening in Middle America. The so-called front-runners can only rely on their advisors. I know what’s happening, because I’m a part of Middle America, I know and see the hurts and the issues first hand.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Have you ever run for political office before?</hi></p>
<p>No, but I’ve worked for the United States Air Force and I’ve worked for the Veteran’s Administration</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Have you ever been a member of a political party, other than the one you're currently in?</hi></p>
<p>No, and I wouldn’t join one now, especially with the cronyism and fundraising a Candidate has to do for a party instead doing the job we pay them to do i.e to run our country.</p>
<p>If this was private Industry most of them would be fired by now fordoing a poor job of making sure our country is never depending on other countries for anything.</p>
<p>However I’m a mother and grandmother and I see first hand how our country is going down the tubes and I want to do everything I can to save it, so I put my Barbeque pit away and my lounge chair and said I Love my Country enough to do whatever I can to save us.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Have you ever campaigned for another political candidate?</hi></p>
<p>No, but I would for Mike Huckabee if he and I were not both running for President.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">What is your current job?</hi></p>
<p>I’m running For President Full Time, I’m a Certificated Christian Counselor, an Ordained Minister, an Author, Public Speaker, and Homemaker.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What skills or ideas do or previous positions, you bring from this position that will benefit the Oval Office?</hi></p>
</text>
