<text id="autogum_interview_doc658" title="part1_Gay Talese on the state of journalism, Iraq and his life" shortTile="partgay-talese-state" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-27" dateModified="2019-01-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gay_Talese_on_the_state_of_journalism%2C_Iraq_and_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  "Sports Gay-zing"?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I don't know when gay revolution or gay rights...I don't know how it happened or when it happened, but it was a parallel movement that happened at the same time I was alive.  What's the difference?  It makes no difference.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is your ancestry Sicilian or Northern?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  No, it's Southern Italian.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Southern, not <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sicily">Sicilian</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calabria">Calabrian</ref>. But it is close enough. It's the total of both. That's my ancestry. My father was born there, in fact. He was the only person from his family that came to the United States and he did so in 1920.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you ever pay any attention to Italian politics and the happenings with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Northern%20League%20(Italy)">Lega Nord</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I pay attention to it when it's in the headlines. I read the papers. But do I pay attention to the point of caring? No. I don't know that the Italians much care about politics. They capitalize on it. They exploit it. I think it's a country of family influences. Families matter so much there. They've had a mistrust of government ever since the fall of Rome. I mean they're really clans. Just a bunch of clans. Little cliquish people, even now. Even now, with transportation and communications pervasive. It used to be they were stuck in the hills and they didn't have any means of getting from one part of the mountain to the other so they were insular. Their dialect was held firm. Now, it's different, but it's still not a country that's a unified country. I mean Italy is called a nation, but ....</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They can't seem to do anything politically. They <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venice#Sinking_of_Venice">can't save Venice</ref> ....</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  They can't do anything. But on the other hand they live damn well. There's a kind of underground economy that's been there, probably for centuries. The surface tells you one thing. The statistics tells you this, this, this. But underneath, there's a core management this kind of internal management of mercenary affairs, or family connections, or ways of gaining what is known on the surface, but underneath there's a whole mysterious way of prosperity in Italy that isn't shown. It's very interesting. You find the news reports or the books that are out saying one thing. I don't exactly ever see it and I've traveled a lot. I haven't traveled very much in the last ten years in Europe.</p>
<head id="On_a_higher_power_and_how_he'd_like_to_die">On a higher power and how he'd like to die</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you believe in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Higher%20power">higher power</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">GT:</hi>  I believe a higher power can exist for inspiring people toward fulfilling a dream.  That's religion.</p>
</text>
