<text id="autogum_interview_doc720" title="part5_Author of My Billion Year Contract reflects on life in elite Scientology group" shortTile="partauthor-billion" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-13" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_of_My_Billion_Year_Contract_reflects_on_life_in_elite_Scientology_group" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I have read all other books about Scientology that were not in a good light.  The one that stands out for me as the best of all time is Helen O'Brien's Book entitled <hi rend="italic">Dianetics In Limbo</hi>.  She was an early Dianeticist and joined during the first wave of Dianetics in the early 50's.  Some things have never changed and that is why that early book is such an important read.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You worked for Scientology's intelligence division the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List%20of%20Guardian's%20Office%20operations">Guardian's Office</ref>" (GO) and then later for the current incarnation of its intelligence department, the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office%20of%20Special%20Affairs">Office of Special Affairs</ref>" (OSA). (pp. 154-155, 289.) From your experiences working for GO and OSA, does the workings of the management of operatives by these groups differ? How so?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: The largest difference in the management of operatives is who those operative are.  In the GO days many were Scientologists and Private investigators rarely used.  Now it is the opposite, the Church has attorneys – with whom they have privilege, and it is the Attorney's who hire the Private Investigators.  Now if a PI gets caught during an operation, it can only go back as far as the Attorney, the church is protected.  There is a deposition on the internet about one of the Churches attorney's who was present when the discussion of breaking into the opposing attorney’s doctor’s office was discussed – by Church Executive, lawyers and PI’s.  That, to me, is no different than what the GO used to do, like break into an enemy’s doctors office and get their files.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You recount in the book how you later felt badly about things you did while in the organization, including "stealing library books that were negative toward Scientology". (p 199) Was this type of action a common practice in the GO? OSA? Sea Org in general?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: Stealing, or taking out an not returning books from libraries that put Scientology in a negative light.  I know it was done for years, I would not be surprised if it is still done, but I have no proof.  The libraries would though.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> How do you think Scientology management can improve the way it conducts its operations? If you were the head of the organization, what would you do differently - what would you change about Scientology practices?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: If I were the head of Scientology Management at this time, I would strip it back to basics.  Stop all Human Abuse and Human Rights abuses, and then have an open forum as to whether it wants to be a "Church" or wants to be a Self Help Group.  Church’s ask for titheing (based on your income)  a Self Help group has fixed prices for it’s counseling and services.</p>
</text>
