<text id="autogum_interview_doc976" title="part1_Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian presidential candidate Wayne Allyn Root" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-03" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Libertarian_presidential_candidate_Wayne_Allyn_Root" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I'm proud to be the FIRST small businessman running for President. Who better to lead a country of small business owners, small investors, entrepreneurs, independent contractors (commissioned salespeople) and the people they employ? Who better than a small businessman to cut the size of government? I've lived my whole adult life on my wits, gut instincts and a small budget. What a perfect business experience as a model to run the U.S. government. Far better to put a small businessman in charge who has always made do with less money…than some out-of-touch, spoiled-brat, big business CEO, used to spending billions of dollars and delegating authority to a staff of thousands. If you agree that it's time for a big change- I'm your guy. I'm the guy George Washington and Thomas Jefferson and Ben Franklin were thinking of when they founded America and created the greatest document ever-the U.S. constitution. I'm a part-time politician who also runs his own small business. I'm the quintessential Citizen Legislator.</p>
<p>As far as how I'd help my fellow Americans, my answer is simple. Get the government out of their lives and out of their business as much as possible. Cut government, cut the bureaucracy, cut the entitlements, and dramatically reduce the tax burden. Get government out of the way and allow small business and small investors to lead the way- to grow, prosper, flourish and thrive. You'll see the greatest economic explosion in world economic history.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">You were a Republican until not too long ago. Why the sudden switch to the Libertarian Party?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mr. Root:</hi> I didn't leave the Republican Party- the GOP left me. The first problem with the GOP is that they talk a great game- smaller government, lower taxes, less spending, reduced bureaucracy. It sounds great. But it's only talk. They only use that talk to get elected. It's just a sales job. However, Republicans are at least slightly better than the Democrats when it comes to fiscal policy. At least Republicans want to cut taxes. But they have no interest in cutting government. They love earmarks, giveaways and spending as much as their Democrat brothers. I call the 2 parties big and bigger, dumb and dumber! Both parties want to make government bigger so they control more power, more money, more spoils to handout to their voters. It's outright bribery- and it's disgraceful.</p>
<p>The second reason for my switch is that I'm a fiscal conservative in the mode of Barry Goldwater, Ronald Reagan and Ron Paul. But when it comes to social issues, I'm a pure Libertarian. Unfortunately the GOP has morphed into Big Brother when it comes to social issues and personal freedoms. They have decided it's okay to use big government to force religion and morality on the American people. I couldn't disagree more strongly.</p>
</text>
