<text id="autogum_interview_doc1174" title="part7_Lobby groups oppose plans for EU copyright extension" shortTile="partlobby-groups" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-18" dateModified="2014-12-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lobby_groups_oppose_plans_for_EU_copyright_extension" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Still, last week when commissioner Charly McCreevy, who is the commissioner of the Directorate General Internal Market, came out and said I propose to do this, that we extend the copyright term of sound recordings from 50 to 95 years. We were surprised that it had come that quickly, and we were also surprised that, well, the commission basically has a mandate up until the beginning of next year and then it's re-elected, so there is very little time for this to become law before the commission gets a new mandate and all that is lost. So we were quite surprised.</p>
<head id="Reclaiming_democratic_processes_in_the_E.U.">Reclaiming democratic processes in the E.U.</head>
<hi rend="bold">Becky Hogge</hi>: One of the reasons I'm in Brussels this week, and specifically this weekend at FOSDEM, there's going to be a lot of people from all over Europe and the world who see different potential for incentivisation models for creativity that aren't based on contributor's rights. It's to start a Europe-wide campaign to show that there is political as well as theoretical and factual opposition to this taking place. Because it's very easy for copyright holders who are concentrated in one place, it's very easy for them to gather their resources, to take those resources to show political support. But the general public and the people who stand to lose out from this move are a very diffuse set of people, and it's much harder for them to get together and oppose something like this. What I'm hoping is that we do spread the word about this issue, and about what it means for not only for creativity and culture, but also in a sense for the way the laws get made in Europe. Because, you know the Gowers review presented compelling economic evidence, the D.G. Internal Market has compelling economic evidence that this isn't right; they got in touch with a place called IVIR in Holland [<hi rend="italic">Institute for Information Law, University of Amsterdam, ed.</hi>], and they came up with an even stronger case against copyright term extension. And yet the evidence is being ignored.
<p><hi rend="bold">Erik Josefsson</hi>: The public interest is to have a proper discussion adapted to problems of democracy, transparency, and that the decisions are taken and prepared in a decent way.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Becky Hogge</hi>: And I think that's even more important when you get to issues that centralise on technology, because often the media and politicians don't have access to independent advice about technological changes. Certainly in the U.K. context, we find that politicians and the media don't often understand the technologies but comment anyway and the result can be poor law and a poorly informed public. There have been instances were the government have only been given technical information and input from private interests.</p>
</text>
