<text id="autogum_interview_doc829" title="part14_Satanism: An interview with Church of Satan High Priest Peter Gilmore" shortTile="partsatanism-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-04" dateModified="2018-10-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Satanism%3A_An_interview_with_Church_of_Satan_High_Priest_Peter_Gilmore" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Yeah, and they’re theists.  They believe that Set exists and that their priests can commune with him and that their founder is the voice of Set.  So, it’s like, good that they left for housecleaning.  But Zeena went and joined them and became High Priestess because Michael Aquino has this Anton LaVey obsession, which is obvious since he wrote a book about him that's about a thousand pages, so he made her the High Priestess of their organization.  Then she left to form an even <hi rend="italic">more</hi> orthodox Setian group called “The Storm”, which to us is just funny.  Such theatrics.  His oldest daughter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karla%20LaVey">Karla</ref> isn't a very bright girl.  She kind of hung around the background and once in a while she would come out to speak in public and support her father.  When Xerxes was born she kind of got miffed because she wasn't the center of attention.  Karla is also jealous type. She withdrew from her father, which hurt him a lot.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How did the legal wrangling surrounding his estate pan out?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  They finally settled.  What ended up happening is he had written a will.  Anton LaVey's idea was that if he acknowledged he is going to die, then he'd be giving in to death, so he didn't want to go to an attorney and make out a will.  He was very feisty and had his own perspective on that.  So he finally wrote a will out and signed it, but it wasn't notarized and there were no witnesses.  So when it came to court they said it wasn't good enough.  They basically split everything up between the three children, so Karla and Zeena and Xerxes all got part of the estate.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who received the copyright to <hi rend="italic">The Satanic Bible</hi>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  The estate.  The money that comes in from that gets split up and goes to the three kids.  Also there is a small percentage that goes to LaVey's companion, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diane%20Hegarty">Diane Hegarty</ref>; she says LaVey.  But they were never married and had a falling out in the early 1980's.  She went off and left Satanism and sued him for palimony and he had to sell his house because of all of that, and he sold it to an old friend and member.  Diane got a pile of money and she got a tiny percentage of the books that had been written up to that point.  Every once in a while she comes creeping in off the periphery to say, “Ah!  I'm Diane LaVey!” and it's like, you were Diane Hegarty and you were kind of involved in it, but before the Satanic Panic happened you left and had nothing to do with it.  She was never someone who wrote or said anything of interest.  She was just the pretty blonde wife of Anton LaVey.  She was a nice figurehead, but wasn't of much use beyond that.</p>
</text>
