<text id="autogum_interview_doc1230" title="part1_Interview with John Sanderson, Regional Council candidate for Wards 3 & 4 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-john" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-11-03" dateModified="2007-06-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_John_Sanderson%2C_Regional_Council_candidate_for_Wards_3_%26_4_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>As a model corporate citizen, John Sanderson and his former company, J.W.S. Waste Systems Inc. contributed extensively to various community initiatives through sponsorship and participation, including: Salvation Army; St. John Ambulance; YMCA Fundraising Committee; Brampton Clean City; Santa Claus Parade; Brampton Excelsiors Major Lacrosse  Club (including 14 years on the Executive and two years as President); Rotary Club of Brampton; Brampton Scouts Leader; and coaching and managing various minor hockey and lacrosse teams.  As a member of the Ontario Waste Management Association, John served as President from 1996-98, in addition to four years on the Executive.</p>
<p>Outside of his business, Sanderson is very well known through his active volunteerism with the Rotary Club of Brampton, where he has been a member for 15 years and on the Board of Directors for six years.  With the Rotary Club, John has participated on: the Easter Seals Fundraising Committee; volunteer at the Rotary owned and operated bingo hall; Membership Committee, where he was recognized with an Membership Award in 2002; and Chair of the Gage Park Enhancement Committee, Brampton's historic park and skating trail, sponsored by the Rotary Club of Brampton.  John's dedicated service to the Rotary Club was honoured in December 2001, when he was presented the prestigious Paul Harris Fellowship Award, the highest award given by Rotary International to recognize community service.</p>
<p>John Sanderson, more important than being a prominent businessperson is a true community leader.  Through his active involvement in The Brampton Board of Trade and Rotary Club of Brampton, along with his many other community initiatives and activities, he has dedicated himself to improving the quality of life in Brampton.  In 2002, The Brampton Salvation Army asked John to be its Kettle Campaign Chair.   John's goal was to surpass the 2001 total.  He dedicated himself so heavily to the campaign, that through his business and community connections, helped raise $233,000 - $118,000 more than the previous year.  This is typical of John Sanderson when he makes a commitment to help.  John, being a modest man, is always quick to thank his dedicated staff at J.W.S. Waste Systems Inc. and caring wife and family, for supporting him as he dedicates, on average, over 50 volunteer hours a month to his various community activities.</p>
<p>Adding to his long list of accolades, in 2002, John was one of two individuals recognized nationally by the Canadian Chamber of Commerce as Volunteer of the Year.  Later that year, he was also the recipient of the prestigious Queen's Jubilee.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The Rose Theatre recently launched. What are your thoughts on this facility? Have you had a chance to tour it yet?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The province has strongly encouraged the development of high-density residences near the downtown. Do these buildings fit in with your vision of the downtown? How much say should other levels of government have in urban planning?</p>
</text>
