<text id="autogum_interview_doc590" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic skiers Jessica Gallagher and Eric Bickerton" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-10" dateModified="2017-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_skiers_Jessica_Gallagher_and_Eric_Bickerton" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you prefer one over the other? Do you say "I'd really rather be out on the slopes than jogging and jumping the same...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> I get asked that a lot. I think I love them for different reasons and I hate them for different reasons so I think at the end of the day I would prefer ski racing mainly because of the lifestyle. I think ski racing is a lot harder than track and field to medal in but I love the fact that I get to come to amazing resorts and get to travel the world. But I think, at the end of the day I get the best of both worlds. By the time my body has had enough of cold weather and of traveling I get to go home and be in the summer and be on a track in such a stable environment, which is something that visually impaired people love because it's familiar and you know what to expect. Whereas in this environment it's not, every racecourse we use is completely different.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I heard you were an average <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/snowboarding">snowboarder</ref>. How disappointed were you when you when they said no to your <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disability%20sport%20classification">classifications</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> Very disappointed! For Sochi you mean?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yes</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> Yeah. I mean we weren't really expecting it. Mainly because they've brought in snowboard cross, and I couldn't imagine four blind athletes and four guides going down the same course together at the same time. That would be a disaster waiting to happen. But I guess having been a snowboarder for... as soon as we found snowboarding had been put in, I rang Steve, the head coach, and said can we do snowboarding? When I rang Steve I said, don't worry, I've already found out that Eric can snowboard. It would have been amazing to have been able to compete in both. Maybe next games.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So you also snowboard?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So she does a lot of sports and you also do a crazy number of sports? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> Uh, yeah?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Summer sports as well as winter sports?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> Me?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yes. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> Through my sporting career.  I've played <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rugby_union">rugby union</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rugby_league">rugby league</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Soccer">soccer</ref>, early days, I played for the Australian Colts, overseas, rugby union. I spend most of my life sailing competitively and socially. Snow skiing. Yeah. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kite%20boarding">Kite boarding</ref> and trying to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Surfing">surf</ref> again.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  That's a lot of sports! Does Jessica need guides for all of them?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> I've played sport all my life. I started with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cricket">cricket</ref>. I've played competition <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/squash%20(sport)">squash</ref>. I raced for Australia in surfing sailing. Played rugby union.</p>
</text>
