<text id="autogum_interview_doc991" title="part6_Wikinews holds Reform Party USA presidential candidates forum" shortTile="partwikinews-holds" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-01-02" dateModified="2016-09-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_holds_Reform_Party_USA_presidential_candidates_forum" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Robert Steele</hi>: I am the only candidate--including the incumbent—who has a concept of operations for modern governance.  I have presented much of this in my chapters in <hi rend="italic">ELECTION 2008: Lipstick on the Pig</hi>, and point to The Substance of Governance as well as Candidates on the Issues, where my populist and centrist views are clearly outlined in the summary section for each issue area.  However, for the purposes of your excellent question, I will summarize my policy proposals at four levels.</p></p>
<p><p>At the highest strategic level, America must restore integrity to its electoral process, its government, and its commercial community.  This integrity demands that we apply True Cost Economics--calculating the cost of all externalities and of now devalued precious elements such as drinkable water--in every transaction.  A Balanced Budget is what sane responsible people do--for the two-party tyranny and its banking and media partners to have sanctioned by omission the FACT that we have been borrowing a third of our federal budget each year for over thirty years shames me for my prolonged ignorance, and angers me as a responsible citizen.  That stops immediately.  Governance with integrity is not possible under a winner take all "do as I say" system.  A Coalition Cabinet that can achieve responsible informed consensus is essential.  I have already selected my Cabinet, and I believe you will find the specifics very revealing about both my competence and my ethics.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Reserve%20System">Federal Reserve</ref> will be turned over to someone like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ron_Paul">Ron Paul</ref>, and as soon as he has done what needs to be done, he will be my nominee for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief%20Justice%20of%20the%20United%20States">Chief Justice of the Supreme Court</ref>--I anticipate at least four justices finding compelling reasons to resign from the court in my first two years in office.  For one third of what we spend on war we can achieve a prosperous world at peace--I am fed up with the corruption in the military, prison, health, and energy complexes.  Our coalition administration will be one that makes decisions based on public intelligence in the public interest.</p></p>
<p><p>At the operational level, we need to eliminate substantial portions of the existing government including the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Department%20of%20Homeland%20Security">Department of Homeland Security</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internal%20Revenue%20Agency">Internal Revenue Agency</ref>, half or more of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Department%20of%20Education">Departments of Education</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Department%20of%20Health%20and%20Human%20Services">Health &amp; Human Services</ref>, and etcetera.  All of it needs to be scrubbed.  The US Government is not a "government," but rather a series of Cabinet Departments and agency stove-pipes that exist to protect "budget share" for their stakeholders--their stakeholders are NOT the public as one might expect, but rather those that receive public funds via a Congress that discounts the Treasury by 95%, earmarking treasure for things we do not need and cannot afford, solely to "earn" their 5% "cut" (bribe).  I have written extensively on how to restructure the government and reallocate our precious funds.  I would start by appointing two Deputies.  The first--and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Michael_Bloomberg">Michael Bloomberg</ref> gets this job if he wants it--will be Deputy for Education, Intelligence, and Research, responsible for stripping two thirds of the money from the ineffective corrupt secret intelligence world, and applying that toward holistic integrative education and research such that we become a Smart Nation, a concept I developed in 1994.  The second will be Deputy for Global Engagement, with oversight of commerce, diplomacy, and the military.  Two thirds of the military budget will be stripped down and away from corporate vapor-ware, with half being pure savings that lower the debt, and the other half funding what we need to be credible and competitive world-wide.  Our infantry, 4% of the force, takes 80% of the casualties and receives 1% of the Pentagon budget.  I will redirect 20% of the surviving military budget to the infantry, sponsor a 450-ship Navy that is truly expeditionary, closes down all of our overseas bases without exception, create a long-haul Air Force, and end our dependence on very vulnerable and costly satellites for all communications.  If should mention that in ending personal and business taxes—in fact most taxes—we will be substituting the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Automated%20payment%20transaction%20tax">Automatic Payment Transaction</ref> (APT) Tax, that yields a much higher revenue stream across a broader base, while drastically reducing the contributions of individuals and small businesses.</p></p>
</text>
