<text id="autogum_interview_doc1340" title="part5_An interview with Paul Campbell, founder of Amazing Radio UK" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-01-10" dateModified="2013-09-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_Paul_Campbell%2C_founder_of_Amazing_Radio_UK" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>So far, we’ve been funded by a very small number of private investors, people of enormous wisdom and insight, natch. They understand that we have a very serious, long-term and audacious ambition to change the music industry for the better, to make radio interesting again, and to turn the word ‘amazing’ into a global challenger brand.   </p>
<p>This year, we expect to do one final fund-raising in the UK, then to raise a lot of money on the West Coast of the USA to make this absolutely massive and global, fast.  They understand this scale of ambition there.   </p>
 HAVE YOUR SAY
 Have you tuned into Amazing Radio?  What did you think?
<ref target="//en.wikinews.org/w/index.php?title=Comments:Main_Page&amp;action=edit&amp;preload=Wikinews:Commentary_pages_on_news_events/body&amp;editintro=Template:Editintro_comments&amp;summary=create">Add or view comments</ref>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are your plans for Amazing Radio in 2010?  Any exciting announcements to come?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PC</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> ‘Fraid so. </p>
<p>In 2010, we hope to make Amazing Radio the default station for everyone who has ever had that incredible experience of hearing a song for the first time, and having to stop what you’re doing to listen to it: a station for everyone who has broad musical tastes, a respect for musical talent and an open mind.  We want it to be constantly surprising, fresh, original, sometimes hilarious, always unexpected.  </p>
<p>Blimey, I sound like some corporate twat.   </p>
<p>Now (obviously) it wouldn’t be massively unexpected if we suddenly started revealing all the unexpected things in advance – but basically, we’d like the message to spread that we’re doing something different, fresh, original and ethical - so we’ll launch more new programmes and more new services – on Amazing Radio and amazingtunes.com.  Things like our virtual radio station Amazing Ambient.   .  There’ll be some video and some TV along soon too.   And other cool stuff.   </p>
<p>It may not be ‘insanely cool’; just cool will do just fine. </p>
<p>We also want to do it in other places.  E.g. America. We’ve already started there. We’ll be unexpected there too. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Finally, your favourite artist on Amazing Tunes/Radio at the moment?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PC</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Now this will sound like a real cop-out, but I never ever say who my favourite artist is.  It’s for a serious reason. I’m not some musical Einstein - I’m merely the bloke who started amazing.  And I’m merely a drummer. My taste doesn’t matter. EVERYBODY’s musical taste does.  One of the many problems of conventional record companies is that they think geezers in suits in big glass buildings have the right to decide what’s good music.  We think the world does. I’ve found hundreds of incredible songs that I love, across loads of styles of music.  You’ll find hundreds of your own.  Enjoy. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Thank you very much for your time Paul.  Good luck for 2010.</hi></p>
</text>
