<text id="autogum_interview_doc416" title="part1_Canada&amp;apos;s Don Valley West (Ward 26) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-don-valley" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Don_Valley_West_%28Ward_26%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have lived in the Ward for 25 years, and with my wife we have raised our 3 children who attended local schools.  In addition to being involved as a parent and community member in such areas as home and school association, school council, and church committees, I have taken on wider community leadership roles.</p>
<p>Most recently I was chair of the Advisory Committee for the Jenner Jean-Marie Community Centre in Thorncliffe Park until September 2006 (chair for 6 years).  I am former Chair of the East York Board of Health for 4 years (and active member for another 8 years) and former Chair of Stay at Home in Leaside (SAHIL) a not for profit community-based organization that built 120 units of seniors housing in Leaside.</p>
<p>In addition I am on a leave of absence from my position with Ontario Public Health effective September 4, 2006. I was formerly senior manager with a budget of $1 billion in health care.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Toronto mean to you?  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Toronto used to be known as "New York built by the Swiss".   I would like to have a role in returning Toronto to being "the city the world wants to visit" because it fulfills its destiny as a diverse city that works for all its residents and visitors.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Which council decision (since the 2003 election) do you feel the city/your ward should be most proud of, and which was least desirable? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The new Official Plan encourages intensification and increasing density, at the same time the plan gives more authority to neighbourhoods to protect and retain their character. Least desirable –  the failure of council to make significant progress on its plan to become a less auto-dependent city (e.g. by approving bicycle lanes – this year only 1 km approved).</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Mr. Kettel abstained from the question "If you were elected as a "rookie" councillor, What would you bring to the table beyond the incumbent?", as incumbent Jane Pitfield is running for mayor, "and as such I believe it is inappropriate to respond to this question".</hi></p>
<head id="Natalie_Maniates"><ref target="http://www.fitfor26.ca/">Natalie Maniates</ref></head>
<p>27-year-old <hi rend="bold">Natalie Maniates</hi> is a Public Affairs and Communications Consultant.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Zero tolerance for urban decay</hi>: 
<list type="unordered"><item>Consistent and efficient services to ensure graffiti eradication, lighting, street cleaning, parks maintenance, and beautification.</item>
<item>The maintenance of Toronto City Housing in Flemingdon Park must be restored to a state of good and safe repair.</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Safe communities that encourage residents to keep active</hi>
<list type="unordered"><item>Toronto must ensure a safe community environment that gives residents peace of mind in their daily life activities.</item>
<item>I propose the city introduce a system of location markers in our ravine and parks to provide residents with a feeling of safety and security as they enjoy our parks.  This will also reduce response time of emergency services responding to 911 calls in our parks and ravines.</item></list></p>
</text>
