<text id="autogum_interview_doc1128" title="part6_Dalai Lama's representative talks about China, Tibet, Shugden and the next Dalai Lama" shortTile="partdalai-lamas-representative" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-13" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dalai_Lama%27s_representative_talks_about_China%2C_Tibet%2C_Shugden_and_the_next_Dalai_Lama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But they are against what he represents.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes.  At the moment it is not against him, but against the Chinese authorities.  Not against him, as a person.  He’s not asserting himself.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  He’s not towing the party line but just keeping quiet.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes, that’s understandable.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So in a sense he is a victim himself?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  I suppose one could say that, yes.</p>
<head id="The_selection_of_the_next_Dalai_Lama">The selection of the next Dalai Lama</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In September the Chinese government has said they must approve all high monks—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes, the state council has promulgated some order.  It’s a religious matter and it’s ridiculous for any government to interfere in religious affairs.  No democratic government would interfere.  Not here in the United States, not in India.  China's   <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religion%20in%20China#Religion_in_the_People.27s_Republic_of_China">government believes in atheism</ref> and doesn’t believe in a religious tradition, which is the Communist government in China.  It believes in religion as an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opium%20of%20the%20People">opiate</ref>, a destructive element; to interfere in that is irrelevant, ridiculous and meaningless.  It is interference in the affairs of followers of traditions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How will it affect the choosing of the next Dalai Lama?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  It will have no effect.  You can’t impose a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope">Pope</ref>.  You can’t impose an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imam">Imam</ref>, an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Archibishop%20of%20Cantebury">Archbishop</ref>, saints, any religion…you can’t politically impose these things on people.  It has to be a decision of the followers of that tradition.  The Chinese can use their political power: force.  Again, it’s meaningless.  Like their Panchen Lama.  And they can’t keep their Panchen Lama in Tibet.  They tried to bring him to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tashilhunpo">his monastery</ref> many times but people would not see him.  How can you have a religious leader like that?  When a Panchen Lama goes to his monastery thousands and thousands of people will come from all over Tibet and outside.  He is an important Buddhist leader.  But when they brought their Panchen Lama, they had to force government officials and the public to attend certain public functions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do they force the public?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  They said if you don’t come you will be punished and each family has to send one person, and so forth.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do they keep track of that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  It’s a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Totalitarianism">totalitarian system</ref>.  Look at the former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Soviet_Union">Soviet Union</ref> and China itself.  They keep track; the civil system is built like that.  It’s run on the basis of fear.  They have developed an effective system of control and monitor.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did the Dalai Lama support <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/India%20and%20weapons%20of%20mass%20destruction">India’s nuclear testing</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  His Holiness has always spoken against violence, arms sales; he has signed with the other Nobel laureates against arms sales and nuclear disarmament.   When India exploded a bomb, he said India is a big country and has its foreign concerns, so it would be unfair with its security concerns to deny of that ability to defend itself.  He also said that in the long run, all the nuclear countries should work towards total disarmament.</p>
</text>
