<text id="autogum_interview_doc1147" title="part1_Obesity and the Fat Acceptance Movement: Kira Nerusskaya speaks" shortTile="partobesity-fat-acceptance" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-09" dateModified="2014-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Obesity_and_the_Fat_Acceptance_Movement%3A_Kira_Nerusskaya_speaks" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How much do you weigh?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  313 pounds and I'm 5'4.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have any desire to lose weight?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Desire?  It depends on the way it's put.  I think I have an interest in being a little bit smaller, but I don't necessarily have an interest in being like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Britney%20Spears">Britney Spears</ref>.  That's considered the ideal beauty in America, even though she's an unfit mother, God knows what else she does in her personal life, on top of the fact the woman has a hard time putting a sentence together beyond a fourth grade level.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Her recent performance was widely criticized because she was seen as out-of-shape.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Out of shape in the sense of not fit, or out of shape in the sense of not having a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rectus_abdominis_muscle">six pack</ref>?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How are they different?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Well, somebody can be fat and fit and somebody can be fat and misshapen.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think the Britney Spears <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MTV">MTV</ref> performance and comments about her physique sent out as a message?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  It was negative.  It said you need to be rail thin in order to be considered beautiful and accepted.  In order to be worthy.  In order to be loved.  Especially in America I find it ironic because we are the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melting%20pot">melting pot</ref>, and there are people from all over the world, different shapes, heights, skin tones, races, religions...you would think we'd see diversity in beauty.  And we lack that.  Isn't it a crime that it took however many years for two African-American actors to win <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy%20Awards">Academy Awards</ref>, and then it's suddenly "The Year of the Black Actor" and it's like, 'No, those were really good performances that year and that's who won.'  I don't consider Britney Spears right, perfect and wonderful.  I feel bad for her, but we should be celebrating everybody.  It is and should be, to take a quote from a great interview I did with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carla%20Drew">Carla Drew</ref> from <hi rend="italic">FAT GIRLS!:  The Musical</hi>...it's the "Everybody Matters Revolution."  That's the underlying feeling in fat acceptance:  everybody matters.  And we are tired of being excluded. Part of that is combating the media that portrays us as terrible, rotten, evil, no good, lazy, slovenly, etc., when that might not be the case.  The stigma attached to fat people is prevalent.  It's hysterical:  do you really think that's what we do, sit around and eat all day?  I remember reading a post from a British news source where women were celebrated for their curves, and there was a woman who posted thinking that they legitimately did nothing else but sit and eat all day.  Ignorance, as they say, is bliss, but only to those it serves.</p>
</text>
