<text id="autogum_interview_doc520" title="part0_Wikinews interviews U.S. Constitution Party presidential candidate Max Riekse" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-01" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Constitution_Party_presidential_candidate_Max_Riekse" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews U.S. Constitution Party presidential candidate Max Riekse</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 1, 2008</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> held an exclusive interview with Max Riekse, one of the candidates for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitution%20Party%20(United%20States)">Constitution Party</ref> nomination for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2008_United_States_presidential_election">2008 United States presidential election</ref>.</p>
<p>Riekse is a retired decorated <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lieutenant%20Colonel%20(United%20States)">Lieutenant Colonel</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Army">United States Army</ref> who served in both the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vietnam%20War">Vietnam War</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq War</ref>. He is also a former public school teacher and Assistant Professor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military%20Science">Military Science</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western%20Michigan%20University">Western Michigan University</ref>. He has a B.A. in Political Science and International Relations from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20South%20Florida">University of South Florida</ref> as well as two M.A.s, one in Political Science and International Relations, the other in Eductaion and History. Both are from Western Michigan University. </p>
<p>We asked him if he thinks he has a good shot at winning the Constitution Party nomination and ultimately the presidency. He replied, "I will give it my best shot because I think I can do better then all previous Constitution Party presidential candidates....As to being in the White House in 2009, realistically, its a long shot; but so was Abe Lincoln in the new Republican Party."</p>
<p>When asked about America's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public%20school#United_States">public school system</ref> he said, "Local school boards and the people they are responsible to are the best judge of what is needed; this with state oversight, will help boost public school quality &amp; education."</p>
<p>Riekse is running for president because he has been "very tired of our Republican and Democratic choices for president for many years. With a population of some 300 million people to draw from, I would think we could do much, much better then we have been doing in regards to having a choice for president."</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">Why do you want to run for president?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Lt. Colonel Riekse:</hi> Why am I running for President:  the ultimate &amp; definitive answer is on my web site; the short answer is that I have been very tired of our Republican and Democratic choices for president for many years. With a population of some 300 million people to draw from, I would think we could do much, much better then we have been doing in regards to having a choice for president. The best presidents we have had were George Washington, truly a great man; a great leader, and a great president.  He lead the way. I'm a member of the Society of the Cincinnati which was formed by former officers who served under him.</p>
<p>Thomas Jefferson was good, but Teddy Theodore Roosevelt was also a great President who really cared about the average person even though he was born to wealth and privilege.  You need to learn what he did with his life prior to becoming President to truly understand and appreciate him.  Lastly, I would like to say that JFK could have been another great president if he had lived.  When you get past his womanizing, he was concerned with taking on the new world order; the Federal Reserve which is not Federal, but a private self-serving banking establishment with over half of its members based in Europe whose interest are not that of the American people and the United States of America, but rather increasing their own wealth, power and influence.</p>
</text>
