<text id="autogum_interview_doc949" title="part0_Exclusive: 'The Scientology Reformation' author examines Tom Cruise and David Miscavige" shortTile="partexclusive--scientology" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-10-18" dateModified="2012-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Exclusive%3A_%27The_Scientology_Reformation%27_author_examines_Tom_Cruise_and_David_Miscavige" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Exclusive: 'The Scientology Reformation' author examines Tom Cruise and David Miscavige</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 19, 2012</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> held an exclusive interview with former high-ranking <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientology">Scientology</ref> executive <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mark_Rathbun">Mark Rathbun</ref> on his new book <hi rend="italic">The Scientology Reformation: What Every Scientologist Should Know</hi>. Rathbun examined the close association between actor <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tom_Cruise">Tom Cruise</ref> and Scientology leader <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_Miscavige">David Miscavige</ref>. Before leaving the organization led by Miscavige, Rathbun served as Inspector General of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religious%20Technology%20Center">Religious Technology Center</ref> within Scientology. He currently practices the teachings of Scientology and its founder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L.%20Ron%20Hubbard">L. Ron Hubbard</ref> independently of the organization managed by David Miscavige.</p>
<head id="Background">Background</head>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mark_Rathbun">Mark Rathbun</ref> in 2010 Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mark_Rathbun">Mark Rathbun</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Mark Rathbun — also known as Marty — left the Scientology organization in 2004 after having been involved for 27 years. Throughout the majority of his tenure as a member of the organization, Rathbun held high-ranking executive posts and was involved with managing multiple litigation issues. </p>
<hi rend="bold">I had the No. 2 position from 1998 until I left.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mark_Rathbun">Mark Rathbun</ref></p>
<p>He was raised in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laguna%20Beach,%20California">Laguna Beach</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref>. He first joined the Scientology organization in 1977 at age 20 after being introduced to a communications course in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Portland,_Oregon">Portland</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Oregon">Oregon</ref>. He subsequently joined the elite Scientology group known as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sea%20Org">Sea Org</ref> and was assigned to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Los_Angeles,_California">Los Angeles</ref>, California. He rose in the ranks and reported to Scientology leader David Miscavige in the 1980s as his lieutenant. </p>
<p>Rathbun attained the high-level position of Inspector General of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religious%20Technology%20Center">Religious Technology Center</ref>, the division which manages trademarks and copyright over works by Scientology founder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L.%20Ron%20Hubbard">L. Ron Hubbard</ref> relating to Scientology and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dianetics">Dianetics</ref>. </p>
<p>He served as director of external legal affairs for the organization. He described his role within the organization to the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San%20Antonio%20Express-News">San Antonio Express-News</ref></hi>, "I had the No. 2 position from 1998 until I left. I answered to no one but David Miscavige, who was chairman of the board. I was the personal counselor for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tom_Cruise">Tom Cruise</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisa%20Marie%20Presley">Lisa Marie Presley</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Travolta">John Travolta</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kirstie%20Alley">Kirstie Alley</ref>."</p>
<hi rend="bold">I was concerned there might be some type of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waco%20siege">Waco</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonestown">Jonestown</ref> event.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mark_Rathbun">Mark Rathbun</ref></p>
<p>He helped manage multiple key hurdles for Scientology, including its 1993 success at attaining tax exemption in the United States, and dealing with the aftermath of the 1995 death of Scientology member <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lisa_McPherson">Lisa McPherson</ref>. He assisted in the Scientology <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/defamation">defamation</ref> claim against <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time%20magazine">Time magazine</ref></hi> over its 1991 article "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Thriving%20Cult%20of%20Greed%20and%20Power">The Thriving Cult of Greed and Power</ref>". </p>
<p>Rathbun left the Scientology organization led by Miscavige on December 12, 2004, leaving on a motorcycle. Rathbun has stated he left due to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/physical%20abuse">physical abuse</ref> witnessed at the Scientology international headquarters known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gold%20Base">Gold Base</ref>, located in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riverside,%20California">Riverside</ref>, California. He later took up residence in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Texas">Texas</ref>.</p>
<p>In 2009, he began speaking out critically about the organization as managed by Miscavige, with coverage from <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CNN">CNN</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20New%20Yorker">The New Yorker</ref></hi>, and the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St.%20Petersburg%20Times">St. Petersburg Times</ref></hi> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Florida">Florida</ref>. Rathbun explained to the <hi rend="italic">San Antonio Express-News</hi> his motivation for coming forward publicly with criticism of the Scientology organization, "I did a lot of soul-searching before going public. I was concerned there might be some type of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waco%20siege">Waco</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonestown">Jonestown</ref> event."</p>
</text>
