<text id="autogum_interview_doc160" title="part0_British TV presenter Rico Daniels tells Wikinews about being &amp;apos;The Salvager&amp;apos;" shortTile="partbritish-tv-presenter" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-14" dateModified="2010-09-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/British_TV_presenter_Rico_Daniels_tells_Wikinews_about_being_%27The_Salvager%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>British TV presenter Rico Daniels tells Wikinews about being 'The Salvager'</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 14, 2009</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Rico Daniels</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rico%20Daniels">Rico Daniels</ref> is a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">British</ref> TV presenter living in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref> who is known for his two television series — <hi rend="italic">The Salvager</hi> — whilst he still lived in the UK and then <hi rend="italic">Le Salvager</hi> after he moved to France. Rico has been in a variety of jobs but his passion is now his profession - he turns unwanted 'junk' into unusual pieces of furniture. Rico's creations and the methods used to fabricate them are the subject of the <hi rend="italic">Salvager</hi> shows.</p>
<p>Rico spoke to <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> in January about his inspiration and early life, future plans, other hobbies and more. Read on for the full exclusive interview, published for the first time:</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How was it you first came to be interested in salvaging?</hi></p>
<p>I grew up in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basildon">Basildon New Town</ref> very close to the enormous spoil heap that later became the green hills of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloucester%20Park">Gloucester Park</ref>. There was all sorts of stuff dumped by developers and local businesses that was pure treasure trove to all the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref> kids that had moved down there. I suppose I was actively seeking play material from as young as 5 I suppose. My dad had big plans for me and tended to buy me "educational" stuff for Xmas. Things like encyclopaedias, microscope, chemistry set. That sort of stuff. Great for the brain but not what you'd call a toy. I ended up playing with my dad's tools and using whatever I could drag off the spoil heap as material.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What makes 'good' rubbish, and how do you tell it apart from other junk?</hi></p>
<p>I dont look at junk as junk. To me its raw material like any other but with added benefits. I like to preserve the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/patina">patina</ref> of age and sometimes decay where it brings an interesting element to a build. Faded paintwork and oxidised metal are dripping with history and add shedloads of character to anything they're included in. Materials obviously have to be sound and usable otherwise you'd just be using crap to make more crap.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What differences are there between salvaging in your home of France and back here in Britain, and what simply doesn't change when you cross the border?</hi></p>
<p>The advantages of France as a source of build material is that there are so many more opportunities to chance on stuff that may be 2 or even 3 centuries old. Hand made hinges and latches, ancient oak boards etc. My favourite hunting places are the ashes of old farmers fires . I pull out astonishingly interesting bits of hand forged ironwork. The thing that stays constant from one country to the other is that people can have amazingly good stuff but see little or no value in it leaving the field wide open for anyone that has a little vision.</p>
</text>
