<text id="autogum_interview_doc1323" title="part0_Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian Party potential presidential candidate R.J. Harris" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-06-16" dateModified="2019-02-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Libertarian_Party_potential_presidential_candidate_R.J._Harris" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian Party potential presidential candidate R.J. Harris</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 17, 2011</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Libertarian presidential candidate R.J. Harris Image: R.J. Harris.</caption></figure>
<p>R.J. Harris, a potential candidate for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libertarian_Party_(United_States)">U.S. Libertarian Party</ref>'s presidential nomination, took some time to speak with Accredited <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> Reporter William Saturn about his campaign and issues positions.</p>
<p>Harris is an officer in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Army%20National%20Guard">United States Army National Guard</ref>, currently serving in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref>.  He is also in his third year as a law student at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Oklahoma%20College%20of%20Law">University of Oklahoma College of Law</ref>.  Harris previously worked as an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air%20Traffic%20Controller">Air Traffic Controller</ref> and small business owner. He plans to enter the race in September after completing his tour in Afghanistan.</p>
<p>Others seeking the nomination include Libertarian activist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/R.%20Lee%20Wrights">R. Lee Wrights</ref>, radio host Jim Duensing, former Nevada Libertarian Party chair Jim Burns, marketing executive Roger Gary and attorney Carl Person. 2008 Vice presidential nominee <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wayne%20Allyn%20Root">Wayne Allyn Root</ref> is also expected to make a run.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p>Ten personal questions were asked followed by ten policy questions.</p>
<head id="Personal">Personal</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are your some of your personal achievements?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">R.J. Harris</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Being chosen by Jennifer R. Friend and her family to be her husband and keeping them happy for the last 20 years. Helping her raise our five children. Serving as a Soldier and Officer of the Republic for the last 20 years at home and on four deployments with honor, award and distinction. </p>
<p>Completing my training and certification as an Air Traffic Controller in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Federal_Aviation_Administration">Federal Aviation Administration</ref>. Continuing my education in Philosophy and Law when time, convenience and the rigors of leading a family easily could have dissuaded me. </p>
<p>Running a principled <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_House_of_Representatives">U.S. Congressional</ref> Campaign which was based upon the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Constitution">Constitution</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liberty#Philosophy">Philosophy of Liberty</ref> and which NEVER personally attacked my opponent but engaged him rigorously on policy and the issues. Getting up, when Life knocks me down.         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are your goals in life?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">RH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> To love and be loved by my family. To reason well. To be Free. To protect the innocent. To defend the Lives, Liberty and Property of my fellow Citizens of the Republic. To restore the Constitution and the Republic. To help ensure <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Founding%20Fathers%20of%20the%20United%20States">our Founders</ref>' vision of Freedom is finally realized by the entire body politic.  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Have you ever been arrested or charged with a crime?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">RH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What historical or contemporary figures do you admire?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">RH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> The Philosophers who argued for the importance of Reason, Freedom and Liberty. The statespersons who were audacious enough to put those philosophies into practice, even at the expense of their own Lives, Liberty or Property. </p>
<p>Every single Soldier, Sailor, Airperson, Marine, Doctor and/or Nurse who has fought with honor to defend the Republic, even if I will never know all their names, as well as their spouses who supported them in that endeavor. Every person -- great and not -- who has struggled for the full equality of the body politic. </p>
</text>
