<text id="autogum_interview_doc994" title="Interview: Wikinewsie Kim Bruning discusses Wikimania" shortTile="interview-wikinewsie" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2005-08-09" dateModified="2012-07-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview%3A_Wikinewsie_Kim_Bruning_discusses_Wikimania" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview: Wikinewsie Kim Bruning discusses Wikimania</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 9, 2005</hi></p>
<p>On Thursday, August 4, 2005, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikimedia">Wikimedia</ref> opened its doors to the first-ever <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikimania">Wikimania Conference</ref>, a five-day event put together by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikimedia">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>.</p>
<p>The event, held in the Haus der Jugend in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frankfurt%20am%20Main">Frankfurt am Main</ref>, Germany, featured discussion and interaction on all Wikimedia projects, including its well-known <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedia</ref> project, an online encyclopedia which touts figures of millions of articles in over 70 languages.</p>
<p>Conference attendee and Wikinews contributor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Kim%20Bruning">Kim Bruning</ref> talked to Wikinews, represented here by contributor <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Cllewr">Jonathan Collwer</ref>, about the event.</p>
<head id="Interview_with_Kim_Bruning">Interview with Kim Bruning</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Cllewr">Jonathan Collwer</ref>: Kim, thanks for taking out some time for a quick interview.  Let's begin with press coverage.  Were any major news organizations present?</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Kim_Bruning">Kim Bruning</ref>: Yes, Wikimania received its fair share of press attention.  According to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikimedia%20Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>, over 100 press representatives were present at the event, as the conference was held in Frankfurt.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Cllewr">Jonathan Collwer</ref>: As many know, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jimbo%20Wales">Jimbo Wales</ref>, the founder of Wikimedia was a featured speaker at the conference.  What was the focus of his speech?</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Kim_Bruning">Kim Bruning</ref>: Jimbo Wales' speech was about a series of blog posts. He's doing a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lawrence%20Lessig">Lawrence Lessig</ref> blog.  It's called <ref target="http://www.lessig.org/blog/">Ten Things That Want to Be Free</ref>.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Cllewr">Jonathan Collwer</ref>: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ward%20Cunningham">Ward Cunningham</ref>, the creator of the wiki, also spoke at Wikimania.  Could you tell us a little bit about what he had to say?</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Kim_Bruning">Kim Bruning</ref>: Cunningham's speech focused on both the history of the wiki and what he envisions the future to hold for wiki software.  Ward Cunningham first described an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypercard">Apple Hypercard</ref> project that eventually developed into the wiki we know today.  Hypercard allows the user to create a "stack" of virtual "cards" that display information.  Cunningham created a work-around for the program that created a stack of cards to display information about certain keywords -- if there wasn't a card about a certain keyword, Hypercard would create one.  While this emulates the gist of today's Wikipedia, Hypercard is not natively a wiki-like program, so Cunningham determined it necessary to write a dedicated program.  He called it the wiki.</p>
<p>After describing the wiki's past, Cunningham described his vision for the future of the wiki.  He hopes to see the wiki become distributed across computers worldwide.  The wikis could drift to and fro between computers and keep a history of where they've been.  Each computer would automatically keep only links to the information that is on that machine.  In all, Cunningham wants to see it embraced that partial data is acceptable.  Why?  Because this would allow people to use Wikipedia (and other Wikimedia projects, for that matter) even if they don't have a connection to the internet, thus extending the reach of public human knowledge.  So that's the inventor of the wiki's take on what the future holds -- a more scalable wiki.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Cllewr">Jonathan Collwer</ref>: So, overall, was the Wikimania conference successful in the eyes of the beholder?</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Kim_Bruning">Kim Bruning</ref>: The Wikimedians I talked with seemed to be quite pleased with how the event turned out. Wikimania allowed people to finally meet each other face to face, without the computer monitors in the way.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Cllewr">Jonathan Collwer</ref>: Lastly -- are there any plans for a future Wikimedia meetup?</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Kim_Bruning">Kim Bruning</ref>: Too early to say. There is a plan floating around for something in 2008, but that's not official yet.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Cllewr">Jonathan Collwer</ref>: Thanks for talking with us, Kim.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Kim_Bruning">Kim Bruning</ref>: Thanks for interviewing.:-)</p>
</text>
