<text id="autogum_interview_doc457" title="part1_Former &amp;apos;Top Model&amp;apos; contestant Whitney Cunningham defends plus size models, celebrates the &amp;quot;regular woman&amp;quot;" shortTile="partformer-top-model" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-03" dateModified="2012-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Former_%27Top_Model%27_contestant_Whitney_Cunningham_defends_plus_size_models%2C_celebrates_the_%22regular_woman%22" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Did you follow <hi rend="italic">America's Next Top Model</hi> before appearing on the show, and if so, who did you like?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> Who didn't [follow <hi rend="italic">Top Model</hi>]! I was a <hi rend="italic">Top Model</hi> fiend in the first couple of cycles it was on the air. I loved <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yaya%20DaCosta">Yaya</ref> because she was the educated chocolate "sista" [who was] much like myself.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> If you could quickly summarize your experience on the show, how would you describe it?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> It was an absolutely memorable experience that I wouldn't change for anything in the world. Not too many people can they say that they've been a participant on a television series that has literally changed the face of popular culture in America and in countries worldwide.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> What do your friends and family think of your stint on reality TV?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> I think everyone was really excited for me. I think their general sentiments are that it's cool to see someone that you know inside and out be put on display for the whole world to see. I know there were times where I would make certain faces or have certain reactions and they would always say, "I know exactly what you were thinking."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> What were some of your specific pros and cons as a result of entering this contest?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> On the pro side, I would have to say that the exposure is incredible. I couldn't imagine how I would have been propelled into the industry so quickly if I hadn't been on the show. On the con side, I'm not exactly sure what the show's impression is on the fashion industry. I try to always remain positive, though. I, personally, have definitely used the show to my advantage as best I know how.</p>
<head id="Impact_Top_Model_has_on_society">Impact <hi rend="italic">Top Model</hi> has on society</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Do you ever fear what negative effect the show will have on girls? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> I said before that ANTM has changed the face of popular culture in America and beyond and I'll say it again. We're living in a "Top Model Era." Every girl, woman, boy and man wants to be a model now. But everyone cannot be a model. Modeling is not just an "easy" way to bring in the big bucks. It takes hard work, dedication, some hustle, and it's not meant for everyone. I kind of feel like ANTM is selling a false dream for a lot of folks out there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Do you think that in some way the show can lead to girls developing an obsession with how they look, their weight, etc?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WC:</hi> I have to say no on this one. I applaud the show for their consistent efforts to try to show their viewers that beauty comes in all shapes, forms, sizes, colors, and creeds. I think that it has actually had a profoundly positive effect on the folks who watch. I can't tell you how many people stop me on the street or e-mail me just to thank me for being a role model and showing the world that very thing.</p>
</text>
