<text id="autogum_interview_doc990" title="part5_Wikinews holds Reform Party USA presidential candidates forum" shortTile="partwikinews-holds" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-01-02" dateModified="2016-09-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_holds_Reform_Party_USA_presidential_candidates_forum" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<head id="Question_5">Question 5</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WIKINEWS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are some of your policy proposals, and how will you implement them as President?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Andre Barnett</hi>: My policy is based around all-encompassing solutions. It is impossible for us to pick out one portion of the larger overshadowing issue and try to fix just that part. The economy is connected to healthcare which is connected to entitlements, which is connected to jobs, which is connected to education, etc… I will provide you with an excerpt of what is on my site.</p></p>
<p><p>Enhancing Health Care</p></p>
<p><p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Health%20care%20in%20the%20United%20States">Healthcare in the US</ref> is so overpriced in comparison to other modern developed nations. Our healthcare system, though we claim it to be the best in the world, is out reach for too many that will never experience its benefits. Insurance companies have been able to drive up cost as well as double dipping billers (doctors and doctor’s groups) have taken advantage of the general public. With this in mind many who cannot afford healthcare have no choice but to take advantage of whatever treatment they can get and the bill is passed to the rest of the tax payers.</p></p>
<p><p>The medical industry justifies the cost by flashing new technology costs and pharmaceutical development cost. Truth be told, that cost is recouped many times over as physicians receive kickbacks from prescribing various drugs in their infancy stages that have not been fully tested. I am aware of this from firsthand experience.  Here is what I support:</p></p>
<p><p><list type="unordered"><item>Healthcare insurance premiums need to be regulated and driven down to affordable levels. This need not be the battle of the federal government as it is one of the major factors in the exploding cost. Intra-business sector checks and balances is one of the best ways to manage any <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/flocculation">flocculation</ref> in cost. Allowing business to bear the burden of the premium cost (not pass it onto the employee) would allow for much lower premiums and also elimination of the government’s role in these negotiation processes. This in turn would allow for the only foreseeable tax deduction for corporations lowering the tax rate to below the 12% threshold.</item></list>
<p>This is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/capitalism">capitalism</ref> in its truest form and the only way to dramatically reduce the size of government. This also permits all family members to be covered and fewer uninsured greatly increasing the pool size driving down cost. To allow small businesses to take part in these savings, they would be placed in the same pools with larger companies to drive down cost even further. What better way to negotiate lower premiums than to have business sectors performing the negotiations of prices they are willing to pay.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Healthcare funded by the government should be subject to the same rules as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General%20Services%20Administration">GSA</ref>, in that the lowest price offered to any customer must be the price made available to the government for provisioning to those not working (for a finite period of time). This would be in the cases where an employee has been laid off and cannot afford healthcare insurance on their own and would last for the duration of unemployment.</item></list></p>
<p>Though this is only a portion of the plan, I am sure you can see where I am going. Reducing the government’s role in this entire process and letting the economy perform as it was meant to, that is what I support. This process should be adapted to all sectors to eliminate the government’s role as a micromanaging resource hog. http://bit.ly/t2th4j</p></p>
</text>
