<text id="autogum_interview_doc214" title="part15_BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2008-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Some of us will have this one bar where it’s like, ‘Hey! We’re all here!’</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  I’m not into the Goth scene, but a lot of women who do this are in the vampire thing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I’m not into the Goth scene, but I do like vampires….</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<head id="Dating_for_Dominatrixes">Dating for Dominatrixes</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you single?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you date, do you tell guys what you do?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Ummm, yes.  Yes, I do.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is that a first date conversation?  A third date conversation?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  The first date.  I like to be very up front with people, because this is what I do, this is what I see myself doing for a long time, so if they are not cool with it, then fuck that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What kind of reaction do you typically get?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  I typically get, “Wow, I’m really turned on by that.”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  I’ve gotten that from a friend.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  And then they’re concerned about, “Well, how much do you do…?” and then it gets into the whole ownership of my body.  IF somebody asks me that, I typically don’t see them anymore.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Because it then becomes about what?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Then you have no control over anything.  It becomes not safe.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Yeah, men a lot of the time, when you are in an industry like this, don’t want you go expose certain parts of yourself because they feel that you are ‘’theirs’’, so when somebody is like that, it really turns me off.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you mean?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Alright, so, if I told certain men that I date that I go topless in session, that would make them feel very uncomfortable because that’s then supposed to be only for ‘’their’’ eyes, right?  Which is ridiculous.  I haven’t been dating men so much lately.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Is that what turned you off?</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  No no, that’s not it at all.  Women are a lot more amenable to that sort of thing.  More sophisticated.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do women you date say about it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  A lot of women I’ve dated have experience with this industry, so it’s not really an issue at all.  SO, I don’t have to formulate an answer to any question because they are already involved.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is that a relief?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Yes!  Yeah, it really is.  To not be judged for it, and not tip toe around what I do.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How long do you think you’ll do this for?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  Probably another five years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Then what do you think you’ll do?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Veronica:</hi></hi>  I’m getting my graduate degree in art history, and I work at a magazine, so I’m expecting that to gel into something.</p>
</text>
