<text id="autogum_interview_doc1255" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Bob Ely, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-05-25" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Bob_Ely%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Have you previously been involved in any political campaigns or issues?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Ely</hi>: No</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If you had been elected in 2008, what would you have done differently than Barack Obama?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Ely</hi>: Cut spending, raised taxes, really made government smaller and more efficient; made it easier for the private sector to function.  Most people don’t realize that the private sector and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref> pays, directly or indirectly. for everything in this country.  It is unclear how long the hard-working savers in China will want to (or be able to) fund our <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/profligate">profligate</ref> ways.  If that changes, everything will fall on the shoulders of the private sector.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Has Obama done any good things as president?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Ely</hi>: Yes.  I give him a "B−."  He was dealt a tough hand and, given he knows little about business or economics, has probably played it as well as he could.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you expect to support the president in November?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Ely</hi>: No.  I will likely vote for whoever is on line 3 or write in for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ron_Paul">Ron Paul</ref>.</p></p>
<head id="Campaign">Campaign</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why did you choose to run for president as a Democrat?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Ely</hi>: I’ve always told people I am a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conservatism%20in%20the%20United%20States">conservative</ref>, not a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</ref>.  I believe the Republican party has lost its soul.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">On your campaign website you admit that you are "inexperienced". What qualifications do you have to be president?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Ely</hi>: I’ve had to meet <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/payroll">payroll</ref>.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What kind of activities do you take part in for the campaign?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Ely</hi>: Writing the website, designing and buying advertising and paying a lawyer to fill out FEC forms.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Does your campaign end after the Texas primary?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Ely</hi>: Yes</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What will constitute a success in this campaign?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Ely</hi>: I am pretty sure it is a complete failure.  I had expected that combining humor, some outrageousness and a cogent "platform" would make me a safe protest vote – pardon the oxymoron.  In a way something like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beppe%20Grillo">Grillo</ref>’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five%20Star%20Movement">5 Star movement</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Italy">Italy</ref>.  I hoped that if I got traction, I would have scared the major candidates into not being <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/petulant">petulant</ref> brats and focus on solutions to the serious issues we face.  Oddly, Keith Judd was much more successful than I will ever be.</p></p>
<head id="Policy">Policy</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">To pass your jobs program, you must receive the consent of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Congress">Congress</ref>, a group of individuals that, as you say, "need to be loved" for their political survival.  Based on this, is it even possible to cut <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/entitlement">entitlement</ref>s or create a "Jobs Bank"?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Ely</hi>: The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Founding%20Fathers%20of%20the%20United%20States">founding fathers</ref>, whose name has been taken in vain by every living politician, so why not me, designed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Constitution">Constitution</ref> to have Congress reign in the King (President).  Now, no one reigns in anything.  But if someone is willing to be despised and to take as a point of pride low single-digit approval ratings, the Constitution gives the President many powers to get things done.  No one is willing to do it because they want to be loved and care about their legacy and how they will be viewed by history.  I am perfectly happy to have a whole new level of presidential ranking just for me, under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warren%20Harding">Warren Harding</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard%20Nixon">Richard Nixon</ref>.</p></p>
</text>
