<text id="autogum_interview_doc804" title="part2_Alex Necochea and Bryn Bennett: the &amp;apos;Guitar Heroes&amp;apos; of Bang Camaro" shortTile="partalex-necochea" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-06" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Alex_Necochea_and_Bryn_Bennett%3A_the_%27Guitar_Heroes%27_of_Bang_Camaro" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you have other areas of your life where you've been able to apply that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  You mean as an ethos?  Don't try?  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]  You know, not really.  I have found the greatest success in the things I have put most of my effort into.  This band has been a complete unique experience in that respect, at least in terms of trying to forge a 'career in music.'  Bryn and I had gotten to the point where we thought maybe this wasn't the way to go.  Bryn was going to go back to his career as a video game programmer and I was just going to find something else to do.  So not really, I don't really apply that in any other portion of my life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What are some dream projects you'd like to work on?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  As a musician, obviously for me it would be to meet and work with some heroes of mine since I was a kid.  Like Mutt Lang; he always made my favorite records.  At the same time, it has also been a dream of mine to meet people like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark%20Linkous">Mark Linkous</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sparklehorse">Sparklehorse</ref>.  Those guys made honest sort of rock n' roll, for lack of a better comparison, the way people like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Lennon">John Lennon</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Dylan">Bob Dylan</ref> would.  To me those are the artists of my generation.  It would be my dream one just to meet those guys and two just to work with them on some level.  I'd also be lying to say that it would just be my dream to take this project with twenty of my best friends and take it as far as we can take it.  So far in my life it's been the most rewarding thing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In the creative process it's so difficult to be original today.  Everything has been done.  Do you ever let that trip you up, the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simpsons%20Already%20Did%20It">Simpsons Did It</ref></hi> problem?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AN:</hi>  No, not really.  I found I would end up falling into that cycle playing in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/indie%20rock">indie rock</ref> bands, just trying to come up with the next thing, like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radiohead">Radiohead</ref> they stopped using guitars and things like that.  Trying to kick the ball forward a little bit instead of kicking it side to side.  With this band we don't get hung up on that.  We originally just started it as a celebration of the things we loved when we were kids.  We're not out here trying to reinvent the wheel.  We're fortunate in that when we were putting the project together we wanted that big vocal sound.  What set us apart was how we went about doing that.  We just invited all of our friends because we didn't want to multi track everything ourselves.  Soon after we had to figure out how to pull it off live, and people would approach and say 'we heard you have this crazy project with all these people.'  The project grew into the live monster it is out of necessity.  We're not rich people, we don't have refrigerators and the big tour bus.  Speaking of dreams, maybe one day we'll have a tour bus.  For now, we travel in two very smelly vans.</p>
</text>
