<text id="autogum_interview_doc479" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic wheelchair basketballer Shelley Chaplin" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-01-03" dateModified="2014-06-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_wheelchair_basketballer_Shelley_Chaplin" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Wow!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yeah, it's really exciting.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  When is that?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> We go in June. But next month we're going to launch a big fund raising campaign to get together all the money to do it all. But yeah, it's pretty cool.  <figure rend="Shelley Chaplin guernsey.jpg"></figure></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Are you still with the basketball? Are you going to continue with that?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yep! I do! So two weeks, no less than two weeks, the fourteenth of January, we go to the AIS for our first training camp of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2016_Summer_Paralympics">Rio</ref> campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So I might be able to catch you guys again there. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> From the fourteenth to the seventeenth.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  It must have been disappointing in London — Let me put it like this: I'm watching the game, and it's "oh no, they're losing" but you don't look like you're losing. You look like you're having the time of your life.  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yeah! Definitely. I mean, what we play for is to play on the world stage and it is a lot of fun.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Did you see how many people were there was?  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yeah, it was insane. In-sane.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I was staring up at the top and I could not see the top rows. They were completely in darkness.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> There was so many people there, and they were all supporting us. It was so much fun. It was the best I've ever done. But yeah, of course it's disappointing, because you don't want to win silver, or lose gold, but...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The silver's pretty good! </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> Yeah, being second in the world's pretty good, definitely, but silver's tough.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  It's just that the Gliders have never won. They've never won the World Championship, they've never won at the Paralympics.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> We've never won. Yeah, so obviously we wanted to change that. So yeah, definitely disappointing. We did what we were capable of. It wasn't like we underperformed. We didn't play badly. We just weren't quite good enough.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> And the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germans</ref> were very good. They worked really hard.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Really good. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> They were very good, so...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You played pretty well. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Shelley Chaplin:</hi> We had patches where we didn't play well, but that's basketball.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The whole team needed to find something and lift, because like... we interviewed one of your team mates, and she we can't expect to win if we're shooting 39 per cent. Then of course you went ahead and won two games shooting 39 per cent, which sort of made a bit of a liar out of her...</p>
</text>
