<text id="autogum_interview_doc1000" title="part3_'Big Brother' contestant Parker Somerville sounds off about the show and his aspirations" shortTile="partbig-brother-contestant" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-25" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/%27Big_Brother%27_contestant_Parker_Somerville_sounds_off_about_the_show_and_his_aspirations" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>What makes me salty at Matt is the fact that he wasn't straightforward with me because I saw what he said in the DR about the situation. Also, I jumped on the live feeds one day, only to see him talking crap about me with Smellsia (Chelsia, I call her "Smellsia" because Allison says her woman parts "down there" aren't too fresh!). I never once said anything bad about Matt inside the house and to see him just diss me like that really didn't sit well with me. I definitely had his back, and for him to talk crap on me, especially when I'm not there to defend myself, shows what kind of person he really is.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: What did you really want to say to Jen after you both got evicted so early in the game? You were very quiet when Julie Chen interviewed both of you...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PS</hi>: [<hi rend="italic">laughs</hi>] You know damn well what I wanted to say to Jen! You saw my face. That was worth more than words.</p>
<head id="Coming_full_circle_back_to_reality">Coming full circle back to reality</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: This season, <hi rend="italic">Big Brother</hi> made the press rather negatively compared to past seasons, specifically with incidents like HouseGuest Adam being fired from his job for a comment about "retards," Amanda being taunted that she should hang herself with a noose "just like her father," and James performing in multiple gay pornography videos. What are your thoughts about all of these these events? When do you think the other HouseGuests will find out about James' past in pornography, if they find out at all? How do you think Chelsia will react?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PS</hi>: I think it's crazy. It's so funny that Adam has no idea what impact his words had to America. The other HouseGuests will find out at the wrap party, I'm sure of it. I think Smellsia won't care about James' past. Being the low-class trash princess that she is, she'll definitely not use protection after finding out the great news! Good luck with that! I wouldn't expect less from her.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: You were kept in sequester for a few weeks, and only recently allowed to return to your normal life. How does it feel being recognized as "that guy from the Big Brother show"?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PS</hi>: I know for a fact that some people are going to come off this show thinking they are the next best thing since ice cream. I still think I'm a nobody. Yeah, the opportunity was great, and the notoriety is cool but I'm still just same ol' Parker.</p>
<p>It's really funny that people come up to me and want to take their picture with me. A few times, when I was filming a star, all of a sudden I hear in the background, "Oh, my God, it's Parker!" I'm really flattered by all the attention and support I'm getting from the fans. I even signed a couple of autographs... Now that was weird. Those autographs are probably in the trash by now anyway. [<hi rend="italic">laughs</hi>] I think I'm gonna keep my night job!</p>
</text>
