<text id="autogum_interview_doc1241" title="part4_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="On_the_Turcottes_and_his_mother">On the Turcottes and his mother</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you read the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vanity%20Fair%20(magazine)">Vanity Fair</ref></hi> interview with the Turcottes?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Believe it or not--I didn't read it, no.  I heard about it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You just don't have an interest?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  How can I explain it so it makes sense?  I don't want to see that family anymore.  I don't need to see--whatever they said, it doesn't matter to me.  Because what I wrote is the truth.  So I don't need to hear them yammering on about whatever it is that--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  A debate that is not a debate.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  It's not.  I mean, you know what, the world is--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It's like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holocaust%20denial">Holocaust denial</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  The world is not flat.  You may not like it.  You don't have to believe it, you don't have to like it, you don't have to think it's polite, but it's true.  You know, I may be an asshole for having written that book because I'm telling family secrets, maybe that makes me an asshole, but I'm not a liar.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think the memoirist has a responsibility to inform people that they're writing about that they're writing about them?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  No.   I changed them in the book.  I changed the house, and I changed the location.  You can't read the book and find the house, and people have tried.  People have tried.  And they're always wrong.  I had people emailing me, maybe about seven, from the area trying to guess.  "I know exactly who this is."  It was funny because they weren't right.  It was not that person that they thought it was--I changed their physical description.  So I think if you're going to write about people on something that's potentially upsetting, you have a moral obligation to at least give them privacy.  Which is what I did.  I changed their name, I mean, we wouldn't have known them if they hadn't announced to the world who they were.  They became public not because--they apparently had said in some magazine that I revealed their name.  But I actually never did.  I've never uttered their name in an interview.  It's been put in my mouth.  But I've never uttered their name.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  So I didn't read that.  I don't read interviews with me, because…I don't know why.  It makes me uncomfortable.  I'm not really sure why.  Partly because if something's wrong, I can't do a thing about it.  So I don't want to have to obsess over it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Although you could with this.</hi></p>
</text>
