<text id="autogum_interview_doc587" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic skiers Jessica Gallagher and Eric Bickerton" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-10" dateModified="2017-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Paralympic_skiers_Jessica_Gallagher_and_Eric_Bickerton" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Australian Paralympic skiers Jessica Gallagher and Eric Bickerton</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 11, 2012</hi></p>
<p>Sunday, Wikinews sat down with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australian</ref> blind <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paralympics">Paralympic</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Para-alpine_skiing">skier</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jessica%20Gallagher">Jessica Gallagher</ref> and her guide <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric%20Bickerton">Eric Bickerton</ref> who are participating in a national team training camp in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vail,%20Colorado">Vail</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Colorado">Colorado</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>Wikinews reporters <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:LauraHale">LauraHale</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Hawkeye7">Hawkeye7</ref> interview Australian Paralympic skier Jessica Gallagher and her guide Eric Bickerton</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Jessica GallagherImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australian_Paralympic_Committee">Australian Paralympic Committee</ref>/<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australian%20Sports%20Commission">Australian Sports Commission</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Eric BickertonImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Bidgee">Bidgee</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  This is Jessica Gallagher. She's competing at the IPC NorAm cup this coming week.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> I'm not competing at Copper Mountain.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You're not competing?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You're just here?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> We're in training. I've got a race at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winner%20Park">Winner Park</ref>, but we aren't racing at Copper.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So.  Your guide is Eric Bickerton, and he did win a medal in women's downhill blind skiing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> Yes!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Despite the fact that he is neither a woman nor blind. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> No, he loves telling people that he was the first Australian female Paralympic woman to win a medal. One of the ironies.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Paralympic_Committee">IPC</ref>'s website doesn't list guides on their medal things. Are they doing that because they don't want — you realise this is not all about you <hi rend="italic">per se</hi> — Is it because they are trying to keep off the able bodied people to make the Paralympics seem more pure for people with disabilities?</p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Jessica Gallagher:</hi> Look, I don't know but I completely disagree if they don't have the guides up there. Because it's pretty plain and simple: I wouldn't be skiing if it wasn't with him. Being legally blind you do have limitations and that's just reality. We're certainly able to overcome most of them. And when it comes to skiing on a mountain the reason I'm able to overcome having 8 per cent vision is that I have a guide. So I think it's pretty poor if they don't have the information up there because he does as much work as I do. He's an athlete as much as I am. If he crashes we're both out. He's drug tested. He's as important as I am on a race course. So I would strongly hope that they would put it up there. Here's Eric!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> Pleased to met you.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  We've been having a great debate about whether or not you've won a medal in women's blind downhill skiing. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Bickerton:</hi> Yes, I won it. I've got it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I found a picture of you on the ABC web site. Both of you were there, holding your medals up. The IPC's web site doesn't credit you. </p>
</text>
