<text id="autogum_interview_doc113" title="part4_Wikinews interviews specialists on South Korea military parade" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-10-02" dateModified="2015-01-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_South_Korea_military_parade" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Chi</hi>: The two Koreas do the military parade almost routinely. South Korea will have a similar parade again when there is a new government in five years. It is unlikely the kind of parade to influence further hostility.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">You</hi>: No, this is just symbolic. As a matter of fact, North Korea is very anxious to escape from the current gridlock and [the] US and South Korea do not give them plenty of reasons to go to the negotiating table.</p>
<figure><caption> File photo of interviewee Sue Mi Terry. Image: Sue Mi Terry.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you think it is likely that North and South Korea may at some point in the near future be engaged in direct military action with each other?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kelly</hi>:  Minor skirmishes are possible, indeed likely, given the border confusion in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Yellow_Sea">Yellow Sea</ref>. But a major conflict is highly unlikely, no matter what bluster comes from NK. The NKs would lose such a war, decisively in fact, and the NK elite would face the hangman in the South afterward. NK is much too far behind to win. So full-scale conflict is very unlikely.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kosal</hi>: I hope not.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ledyard</hi>: No. A year or two ago there was a naval incident that occurred in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Yellow_Sea">West Sea</ref>, but both sides separated quickly, although the North shelled <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Yeonpyeong_Island">an island</ref> claimed by both the DPRK and the ROK.  Neither side has anything to gain from any such incident.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Terry</hi>: The North's latest tactic — to return to diplomacy after provoking Seoul and Washington earlier this year — does not mean that the North has abandoned its timeworn brinkmanship strategy nor that it has shifted its nuclear policy.  The North is likely to pursue more aggressive action down the road, attempting to ratchet up another sense of crisis, if it determines that its current peace ploy is not getting the concessions it seeks from Seoul.   But while the North may provoke Seoul again with border skirmishes, or another missile or nuclear test, I think it will avoid direct military action with Seoul that will escalate to an all-out conflict.  Again, Pyongyang will not risk outright hostilities that will lead to an all-out war.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Chi</hi>: You can never exclude possible exchanges of military actions within a limited range. At the time of North Korean attack on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Yeonpyeong_Island">Yeonpyeong Island</ref> in November 2011, the South Korean Government made an official pledge to retaliate against any future military actions by North Korea. The government will face grave political consequences if it fails to live up to its own words. There is always a possibility of direct military actions but they will be more or less contained to a local level.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">You</hi>: No, I would not think so. North Korea is more desperate to engage in a dialogue with South Korea and [the] US but they look for justification to go to the table. However, [the] Park government and US would not be simply welcoming them to the negotiating table. When they negotiate, they would be not generous or lenient to take all the North Korean offers.</p>
</text>
