<text id="autogum_interview_doc646" title="part4_Popular soap opera &amp;apos;The Young and the Restless&amp;apos; celebrates 35 years on the air" shortTile="partpopular-soap" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-25" dateModified="2014-04-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Popular_soap_opera_%27The_Young_and_the_Restless%27_celebrates_35_years_on_the_air" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Michelle Stafford</hi>: I'd like to think so.  Sure, that would be a huge compliment.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tricia Cast</hi>: I would hope other shows recognize the excellence of Y&amp;R and strive to compete.</p>
<head id="Questions_asked_to_Melody_Thomas_Scott">Questions asked to Melody Thomas Scott</head>
<figure><caption>Melody Thomas Scott describing her character's initial stories: "Nikki went through a lot even before the stripper storyline. In the first few months after I started, she killed her father in self-defense (he had rape on his mind), joined a cult, and was a model for an agency that turned out to be a front for prostitution. Beyond wayward!"(Photo credit: JPI Studios)</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: Twenty-nine years in any job is a long time. What made you stick with it as long as you have?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: Whenever an actor gets a job on a soap, they never know how long it will last. Even though you may be given a three or five year contract, the show has the right to not pick up your option every 13 weeks. So one tends to think of their job in 13 week increments. First, you are nervous that you may be written off after the first several options, so one never feels absolutely confident that it could be a permanent job. Three years go by, then another three or another five, and if you are lucky, you eventually find yourself in double digits! I've been very fortunate to play Nikki all these years as she can get involved in so many variations of stories that it seems like playing many different characters under the guise of one.  No opportunity to ever get bored!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: You remarked in <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soap%20Opera%20Digest">Soap Opera Digest</ref></hi> last year that you get disappointed when your character doesn't get featured regularly in her own story. With that said, did you ever want to just end your involvement with Y&amp;R and do other things?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: I don't recall ever saying that. If it was printed, it had to have been taken out of context because I don't feel that way. Never have. The truth of the matter is that we are an ensemble cast. We all expect to have light storylines as well as heavy. That's the nature of daytime television. Whenever I do have a few light months I take advantage of that by focusing on the everyday things that get lost during heavy storylines.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi>: Nikki and Victor have spent many happy years together, but 2008 has seen the couple divorce for a fourth time. Why so much volatility? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Melody Thomas Scott</hi>: Actually, this is only their third divorce. (With nine marriages under her belt, it is hard to keep it all straight!)  Nikki and Victor are both very passionate people, whether they're madly in love or hating each other with a vengeance.</p>
</text>
