<text id="autogum_interview_doc1322" title="part1_Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian Party presidential candidate R. Lee Wrights" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-06-20" dateModified="2016-11-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Libertarian_Party_presidential_candidate_R._Lee_Wrights" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What do you feel sets you apart from your fellow contenders for the Libertarian Party presidential nomination?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">RW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I've been active in the Libertarian Party and libertarian movement all my adult life. I've never been afraid to passionately champion the unvarnished libertarian message of individual liberty and personal responsibility. Other candidates have tried to refine, revise or remake the libertarian message in order to appeal to voters. That tactic has failed not only the party, but the cause of liberty, as well. Instead, I propose to embrace the principled libertarian message and will not be afraid to speak truth to power.	</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How often do you campaign and how would that change if you won the nomination?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">RW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I am campaigning every day, either in person, online or on the phone and that will not change when I am honored with the Libertarian Party nomination.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If elected, what would you do as president?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">RW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> My first order of business will be to disengage the United States from the tangle of misguided, immoral and unconstitutional military conflicts we are involved in by using the same authority and power as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commander-in-chief">Commander-in-Chief</ref> so many presidents have abused to get us mired in these <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/quagmire">quagmires</ref> in the first place. </p>
<head id="Policy">Policy</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What necessary freedoms are currently lacking in American society?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">RW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> All our freedoms are currently under attack by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democratic</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</ref> politicians who have conjured up myriads of excuses, "imaginary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/hobgoblin">hobgoblin</ref>s" to wage war on American citizens and the world. They have manipulated events to distract, divide and terrorize Americans into willingly sacrificing their liberty before the great false god of Security. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">When is government necessary?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">RW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Government is only necessary to protect individual life, liberty and property. The only just and "necessary" government is one, as James Madison said, "which impartially secures to every man whatever is his own."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">In a market with little or no government regulation, what prevents an entity from seizing the entire means of production and becoming the new main regulator?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">RW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Government regulation is in reality a method by which large businesses with power and influence use government power to benefit themselves at the expense of smaller competitors. In a truly free market, there will always be competition to prevent one entity from seizing the entire means of production. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">In context of government's role, what are your stands on the legality of <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/incest">incest</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/bestiality">bestiality</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Child_pornography">child pornography</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">RW</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> While these practices might be repulsive to most people, as they are to me, government cannot stop them from happening. Libertarians believe people should be free to make choice for themselves about their lifestyle, so long as they do not harm others. In all cases where violations of human rights occur, the proper role of government is to prosecute those who have committed the violation.</p>
</text>
