<text id="autogum_interview_doc1240" title="part3_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That accomplishment is so difficult.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yes, exactly.  I began reading at 24.  I had never read before that.  Once I started reading, I didn't want to do anything else.  But I could never understand how do you keep a whole book in your head.  How does an author do that?  How do you get a book--I mean, it's 250 pages, and yet it resides in your head!  Where?  How?  By writing my book, I saw firsthand how it happens; for me, it was totally subconscious, automatic--it was like watching a movie.  My fingers did the work--I was fully unaware; I didn't think about structure, or characters…I stared at the space between the screen and the keyboard like I was in a trance.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That gives you some amount of respect for people who write a book of crap, but yet write a book.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah.  Any book is an accomplishment.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s like,  you can have the talent, but if you don't have that discipline to actually carry it through, the talent's wasted.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Exactly--I had never had that discipline, and I didn't know where it came from.  But once I did it, I knew I could do it again and again, and by the time I was 40 or 50, or in my 60s, if I kept doing this, if I kept writing a book every--not every seven days, but a month or two months, or even a year, eventually in my 40s or 50s or 60s, I would have written something that was publishable.  And--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How did you get the discipline?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  It was not so much discipline as I realized, this is me.  This is what I'm going to do.  This is it.  It was an epiphany of, "I'm home."  I'm--what am I doing? I've wasted my life.  I need this--writing felt better than anything had ever felt.  It felt better than any drug, and it felt better than any relationship.  So that really changed a lot about me.  Just the experience of having written it made me not care so much what other people thought.  I then went out and tried to get an agent, and I did get an agent, and he did sell the book.  And he sold it for no money, but it was sold.  And that's when everything really changed in my life.  I became much more confident with just--just  being, you know, just me, just myself.  I didn't feel as damaged--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You were sober at the time?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah, I was sober at the time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And you couldn't have probably done all this without being sober.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Never.  Oh no.  No, nothing.  I never wrote a word when I was a drunk.  Never.  Never wrote a word--very few, very few.  And after I sold <hi rend="italic">Sellevision</hi>, I didn't have another idea for a novel, but I did have this journal that I'd written when I got sober.  So I gave it to my agent, who asked, "Why didn't you show me this first?"  And my publisher bought it, and that's <hi rend="italic">Dry</hi>.  And then after they bought <hi rend="italic">Dry</hi>, which was my journal--it was like selling someone my used tissues--I thought my God! well if you guys like that, I should tell you, I had a really fucked-up childhood.  And they said, "Really? What happened?"  And I said, "Well, here."  And I sat down in half an hour and I wrote a proposal for it and emailed it in, and that was <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Running%20with%20Scissors%20(memoir)">Running with Scissors</ref></hi>, and they bought that, and I had to go away and write it.</p>
</text>
