<text id="autogum_interview_doc1430" title="part5_Judging the Courts: Wikinews interviews Prof. Lawrence Douglas" shortTile="partjudging-courts" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-11-20" dateModified="2015-09-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Judging_the_Courts%3A_Wikinews_interviews_Prof._Lawrence_Douglas" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Courts_and_writing_history">Courts and writing history</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: You have suggested in your book, <hi rend="italic"> The Memory of Judgment</hi>, that the Holocaust trials have a pedagogical value - they document events and serve as a historical record, in addition to serving the cause of justice. How well does a criminal trial capture the history of the events underlying the crimes?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: I think it's fair to say that trials are not well equipped at rendering history in its full complexity.  What they can do very effectively is use document and testimony to construct a historical account that reaches a huge audience.  This account may never match the most nuanced renderings of the past that issue from the pen of the professional historian.  But it can establish a baseline of indisputable fact that discredits the apologists of perpetrators and gives the lie to those who would baldly falsify the historical record.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: What does the historical account presented by a judicial process offer that scholarly or journalistic or propagandist accounts don't?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: Certainly trials have the power to galvanize national and international attention in a way that other accounts rarely can.  Prosecutors can often call upon extraordinarily powerful tools of discovery for the purposes of accumulating and organizing vast amounts of evidence.  Survivors are given the opportunity to present stories of victimization in the form of legally potent evidence.  Spectators of the trial – either those present in the courtroom or those who follow the proceeding on television – directly witness the presentation of evidence and testimony.  In this way, they become witnesses to the witnesses.  </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: Is the pedagogical purpose served even when the trials are or are seen as, selective and less than fair?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: One of the central pedagogic aims of these trials is to make visible the workings of the rule of law.  This is a particularly important goal in transitional societies that historically have lacked a robust commitment to the rule of law.  Clearly this aim cannot be realized if the trial is perceived as deeply flawed.  As a further matter, the quality of the justice will inevitably influence the way observers perceive the quality of the history presented in the courtroom.  A biased proceeding will not be viewed as a neutral forum for the presentation of history.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">WN</hi>: Many rights and humanitarian groups document abuses and crimes to serve as a record of events. Do trials offer more?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">LD</hi>: I think of the documentary work of human rights groups and of trials as complementary.  The work compiled by humanitarian groups can make its way into the prosecution's dossier.  Conversely, researchers can further mine the archival trove compiled by prosecutors.  Yet as I've already mentioned, trials enjoy the power to galvanize national and international attention.  One cannot underestimate the drama of seeing a former head of state or a high-level perpetrator standing before his accusers, victims, and judges.</p>
</text>
