<text id="autogum_interview_doc979" title="part4_Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian presidential candidate Wayne Allyn Root" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-03" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Libertarian_presidential_candidate_Wayne_Allyn_Root" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>McCain is another big government conservative. He's been collecting government checks in D.C. for 25 years. Hillary wants Universal Healthcare- so we can bankrupt America and throw Americans in jail for trying to choose the doctor of their choice. Scary. That's what happens in UK and Canada- if you're sick you wait in line for weeks or months to see a doctor- who is forced upon you by the government. You don't like that doctor-too bad.  He's an incompetent doctor- too bad. You're out of luck. You need a hip replaced right away? Too bad- you'll have to sit in a wheelchair for 18 months until it's your turn. Anyone want that system?</p>
<p>Who wants to vote for “the same old, same old.” The D.C. insiders are the ones who have ruined things. Our country is in trouble. It's time for a dramatic change; a non-violent revolution. Who better to lead that revolution than a son of a butcher. I say “THROW THE BUMS OUT.” A perfect example is found in the final 3 contenders for the major party Presidential nominations- Clinton, Obama, and McCain are people that have been agents of big government their whole lives. Always collecting government checks. Always voting against tax cuts (even though it's our money in the first place). Always feeding off taxpayers. Always bribing the voters to stay in office- thereby increasing government spending and running up a huge deficit. But here's the worst thing of all- all 3 are sitting U.S. Senators. They collect a 6-figure income from the taxpayers. Being a Senator is a full-time job, isn't it? But these 3 are spending every waking hour campaigning for President. How are they earning their $175,000 U.S. Senate salaries? They're not even present to vote on important bills. They are cheating the citizens of New York, Illinois and Arizona. It's, in my opinion, fraud to run for higher office while collecting a check for another political office. The rules should be changed- if you want to run for President, you have to step down from your present office. Why should taxpayers pay the cost for absent politicians who ignore the job for which they are being paid?</p>
<p>If what I'm saying strikes a chord- it's time to vote for a complete outsider. A rebel with a pitchfork and musket. A citizen legislator. A small businessman, S.O.B. (son of a butcher) and Las Vegas oddsmaker. I am the perfect “OUT OF THE BOX” candidate. Some people are scared of Vegas. Religious people think it has a negative connotation. You know what the difference is between Las Vegas and Washington D.C.? In Vegas the drunks gamble with their own money! It's time to shake things up in Washington. Put the rebel and maverick small businessman from Las Vegas in charge. I could certainly do a better job than the fools, hypocrites and greedy thieves that have run this country for the past 50 years.</p>
</text>
