<text id="autogum_interview_doc309" title="part2_Interview with Sue Gardner of the Wikimedia Foundation" shortTile="partinterview-sue" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-19" dateModified="2012-01-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Sue_Gardner_of_the_Wikimedia_Foundation" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Mike: The proposal is basically that Turner will give us a venue for the conference and bring in industry people to speak, in addition to more citizen-oriented speakers and our own from Wikinews. I know personally I didn't believe such a media conglomerate would want to partner with free culture, so it was surprising to me. Does it surprise you, or do you see a good working relationship between "free" and "for profit" journalism outlets?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  It doesn't surprise me at all that Turner would want to partner with us. I have had useful conversations with all kinds of people; the head of CNN.com, the head of the BBC online, a head of programming at PBS, etc. And I know many of us are having similar conversations. People want to partner with the Wikimedia Foundation because it is extraordinarily successful and the material it creates is phenomenally relevant and useful.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Brian: we had a reporter with the beeb for a week</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Dodge: And the BBC used some of our content earlier</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Matt: Do you think the fact that they can reuse what we make in partnership with them is one of the reasons for people wanting to partner with us, whereas a lot of traditional media want to retain copyright on work?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  This is great, and it's my opinion that we should partner up with lots of organizations in lots of ways. Probably we will find the most constructive partnerships with the public sector organizations (as Brian and Thunderbird are saying, with the BBC). No, I don't think they understand the GFDL at all. And copyright is a problem for traditional media; it was my single biggest problem at the CBC, since it is so constraining and complex.  I think they are interested in us because a) we are popular, and they strive for relevance/popularity all the time, and b) because we have managed to persuade people to participate in our world and to help us and work with us. Traditional media have been less successful than we have—than you have!—in creating an environment which people enjoy participating in.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Brian: If they don't understand GFDL, is CC-BY (per Wikinews) better for their legal folks?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SG:</hi>  I think traditional media see copyright as a problem, and they do not understand it very well. Basically it just represents cost and complexity to them. I had a meeting with PBS the other day in which we tried to explain the GFDL to them; it makes them quite nervous.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Matt: Do you believe that (at least for non-profit news sources), releasing material into the public domain makes it simpler for them to manage/handle?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Brian: or do they not understand PD?</hi></p>
</text>
