<text id="autogum_interview_doc1213" title="part1_Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian presidential candidate James Burns" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-23" dateModified="2012-05-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Libertarian_presidential_candidate_James_Burns" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>Failure to comply with United States law should, upon conviction, result in deportation at the immigrant's expense. Conviction and deportation will disqualify a person for immigration (green card) for a reasonable period of time (which should be defined).</p>
<p>Then if the immigrant wishes, after a reasonable residency (which should be defined), and good behavior he or she may become a citizen of the United States provided they have the ability to speak English, have an understanding of the operations of the United States Government and the state government of their residency, and they renounce their citizenship and allegiance to any other nation.</p>
<p>"Never in the history of the world has there been a situation so bad that the government can't make it worse." –Unknown</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">How would you help the shrinking middle class?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mr. Burns:</hi> The economic policies of the US government are the cause our troubles. When I am President, the only economic policy I shall pursue is to be frugal with the funds of the United States. The United States government should not have an economic policy and should not impose any economic policy on the people of the United States. We are faced with a choice. We may have a rich government and a poor people or a rich people and a poor government. I choose a rich people.</p>
<p>“Giving money and power to government is like giving whiskey and car keys to teenage boys.” - P.J. O'Rourke</p>
<p>"In proportion as you give the state power to do things for you, you give it power to do things to you." --Albert Jay Nock</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">Do you think you have a good shot at winning the Libertarian nomination? If so, do you think you could be in the White House this time next year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mr. Burns:</hi> My chances of winning are not all in my hands. I shall do my best, but it comes down to what others will do. What will you do?</p>
<p>"It is not the challenge that we face that determine who we are and what we are becoming but the way we meet the challenge." --Richard Bach</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">There are thousands reading this right now. What could you say to convince them to give you their vote?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mr. Burns:</hi> We humans have always found ourselves on what appears to be the horns of a dilemma. On the one hand, the vast majority of us cannot live without others. The food we eat, the clothes we wear, and our very lives depend on the division of labor, that is to say, the actions of others. The world would be a bleak place, indeed, if there were not other people in it. On the other hand, our largest danger does not come from wild beasts or even natural disasters; rather, it comes from other human beings. Humans rob, rape, and kill each other, and these activities are often organized by the greatest threat to human beings: tyrannical governments.</p>
</text>
