<text id="autogum_interview_doc1083" title="part4_Vanity Fair contributing editor Craig Unger on the Bush family feud, neoconservatives and the Christian right" shortTile="partvanity-fair-contributing" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2015-08-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vanity_Fair_contributing_editor_Craig_Unger_on_the_Bush_family_feud%2C_neoconservatives_and_the_Christian_right" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What was the problem with the intelligence apparatus at that time that the neocons needed to take control of it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  If you go back all the way to the mid-1970s, the neocons were distorting intelligence even back then.  They had an operation known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Team%20B">Team B</ref>.  From there I start tracing five neocons who are on the staff of Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry%20Scoop%20Jackson">Henry “Scoop” Jackson</ref>.  He was a muscular Democrat.  He was strong on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Organized%20labor">labor</ref>, but a hard-line <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold%20Warrior">Cold Warrior</ref> who wanted to roll back the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USSR">Soviet Union</ref>.  The neocons grew out of that.  His hero is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert%20Wohlstetter">Albert Wohlstetter</ref>, who was one of the models for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dr.%20Strangelove">Dr. Strangelove</ref>.  1976 is the era of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/détente">détente</ref>, and the neocons hate this; they fear losing their favorite enemy, the Soviet Union.  They are saying the CIA is coming up with much too rosy of predictions and they don’t believe the intelligence.  Who takes over the CIA at this point?  George H.W. Bush.  They decide they have to go to battle against him and they form what is known as Team B, which starts an “alternative intelligence assessment.”  It effectively says the CIA is all wrong and that we have to redo their intelligence.  But Team B’s  estimates were completely inaccurate.  I go into considerable detail of how they vastly, vastly overestimated the power of the Soviet Union.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How did they bring Team B into the present?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  What you see back then are events that prefigure the Iraq War to an enormous extent.  The key operatives in the White House then are the youngest <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief%20of%20Staff">Chief of Staff</ref> in the history of the United States, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dick%20Cheney">Dick Cheney</ref>; and the youngest <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secretary%20of%20Defense">Secretary of Defense</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald%20Rumsfeld">Donald Rumsfeld</ref>.  They are siding with Team B.  Here you have thirty years ago the beginning of this alliance between Rumsfeld, Cheney, Wolfowitz and Richard Perle.</p>
<head id="Bush_appoints_his_father's_enemies_to_his_Cabinet">Bush appoints his father's enemies to his Cabinet</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So Rumsfeld and Cheney are not seen as old Bush Sr. people.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Rumsfeld is probably the bitterest, bitterest enemy of George H.W. Bush <hi rend="italic">ever</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Weren’t they considered part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Realpolitik">realpolitik school</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Cheney was, but not Rumsfeld.  And Cheney was Rumsfeld’s protégé.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What effect did it have on Bush Sr. that some of his bitterest foes were assuming positions in his son’s administration?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  He is famously nonresponsive on this, but James Baker spoke out.  What you see going on in December 2000 is that Bush Jr.’s team had decided on Indiana Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dan%20Coats">Dan Coats</ref> for Secretary of Defense.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I remember that mentioned.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  It was because he was against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gays%20in%20the%20military">gays in the military</ref>.  What better qualification could one possibly have, right?  They first appoint Colin Powell as Secretary of State, and he has a press conference with Bush in which Powell is so dazzling that Cheney freaks out and says, “My God, Dan Coats will never be able to stand up to him!”  They need somebody more powerful.  They call in Donald Rumsfeld and James Baker warns Bush, “You know what this guy did to your father.”  Rumsfeld had sabotaged Bush Sr. again and again and again.  Bush had been considered a likely choice for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vice%20President">Vice President</ref> under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gerald%20Ford">Gerald Ford</ref> instead of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nelson%20Rockefeller">Nelson Rockefeller</ref>, and Rumsfeld kept him off the ticket.</p>
</text>
