<text id="autogum_interview_doc998" title="part1_'Big Brother' contestant Parker Somerville sounds off about the show and his aspirations" shortTile="partbig-brother-contestant" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-03-25" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/%27Big_Brother%27_contestant_Parker_Somerville_sounds_off_about_the_show_and_his_aspirations" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: Who influenced you to audition?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PS</hi>: Nobody really influenced me to audition. I just saw a random ad on craigslist, and was like, "Why the hell not? Meet a few people...possibly win some cash...Ummm...okay..."</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: In a previous interview I conducted with <hi rend="italic">Canada's Next Top Model</hi> winner <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Andrea_Muizelaar_on_fashion,_anorexia,_and_life_after_'Top_Model'">Andrea Muizelaar</ref>, she said that she believed reality shows cast people who are perhaps unstable, to make for better television. Do you feel that's true? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PS</hi>: I don't believe the name of the game is to find the biggest whack-job and stick a mic and camera on them for good TV. I think the producers of these shows carefully look for the best mix of people to create a story around them. They look for who's going to get along with who, who's going to feud, who's going to be the peace keeper, hook-ups, and so on.</p>
<p>Don't get me wrong, everyone loves to watch drama as long as it's not them, so of course they are going to look for people with personal issues but I don't think that's all they cast for. If you think about it, the people with personal issues could grow from their experience and become better people after seeing how they were portrayed. Who knows?</p>
<head id='"The_detour"'>"The detour"</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: You were really not that thrilled when Jen, the "soulmate" the show picked for you, was in a previous outside relationship with fellow HouseGuest Ryan. What were you thinking when Jen revealed the news to you? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PS</hi>: When I first found out about the secret, I was pretty pissed at Jen for not being honest with me from the start. However, I thought it was a pretty good idea to have that "secret alliance" with them because Jen and Ryan definitely didn't look like they were dating so nobody would have suspected it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: Also, Allison, Ryan's partner, was shown on the television broadcasts as being probably more angry than you were. Who do you think was more angry about the developments, you or Allison?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PS</hi>: I think Allison was more angry with the secret than I was, just because she was forced to be in an alliance with Jen, and they didn't like each other.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: You were involved in some of the most dramatic moments we've seen this season, including, but not limited to, you waking up the entire house to find the person who had talked behind your back. Do you think being that direct was a good strategy for your game play? Also, viewers of the show gathered that you were unhappy with the way Jen played the game, but do you believe some of your actions cost you the game as well?</p>
</text>
