<text id="autogum_interview_doc217" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Martin Hyde, Ottawa West-Nepean" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-24" dateModified="2016-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_candidate_Martin_Hyde%2C_Ottawa_West-Nepean" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>In my riding the Liberal MPP Jim Watson poses the biggest challenge. He is the incumbent, and has been a politician for many years.</p>
<p>I'm only the most desirable candidate for those voters who care about creating an economically and environmentally sustainable society in the long term.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>The issues which individuals care about are very diverse. The most important issues for those who are likely to vote Green are likely to be: a taxation plan which does not hit incomes, but directly targets non-renewable resource consumption — and in conjunction with incentives to reduce consumption, initiatives to replace dirty energy with clean, renewable energy sources; a single public school system which has the democratic interests of all Ontarians as its primary concern; and an emphasis on livable communities which promote walking and public transit, decreased levels of pollution, and increased opportunities for healthy activities. It's all about sustainability, economically, politically, and personally.</p>
<p>Our party platform contains specific details on how these issues would be addressed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>The first order of business should be to begin shifting taxes away from personal income, health care, and corporate profit, and onto the consumption of resources. Specifically, our taxes will shift immediately to a 2% tax on oil, natural gas, and coal, as well as an increase in fees on the taking of aggregate (sand and gravel) and water, directly from our income taxes and the tax on health care.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>This is an issue that is probably best addressed by voters at the municipal level. However, the Green Party has a plan to place a moratorium on increases in the assessed market value of residential properties and introduce a Location Value Tax, which will shift the focus from taxing buildings to taxing the land under the buildings. This would be a revenue neutral shift with the purpose of encouraging intensification of land use, while deterring sprawl.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>The tax shift from income to resources will mean that labour will be cheaper for employers without a decrease in wages for employees. It will also provide an incentive to hire people to find more energy efficient ways of making products since non-renewable energy costs will be higher.</p>
<p>To encourage the repair and recycling of products the Green Party of Ontario will establish a Product Stewardship Program that will place the responsibility for the entire life cycle of a product with the manufacturer or importer. This will encourage the creation of jobs focused on designing products that can be repaired and recycled.</p>
</text>
