<text id="autogum_interview_doc281" title="CanadaVOTES: CHP candidate Stefan Jetchick in Louis-Hébert" shortTile="canadavotes-chp-candidate" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-10-10" dateModified="2016-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CanadaVOTES%3A_CHP_candidate_Stefan_Jetchick_in_Louis-H%C3%A9bert" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>CanadaVOTES: CHP candidate Stefan Jetchick in Louis-Hébert</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 10, 2008</hi></p>
<p>In an attempt to speak with as many candidates as possible during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008%20Canadian%20federal%20election">2008 Canadian federal election</ref>, Wikinews has talked via email with Stefan Jetchick, who is a candidate in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Quebec">Quebec</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis-Hébert%20(electoral%20district)">Louis-Hébert riding</ref>, running under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian%20Heritage%20Party%20of%20Canada">Christian Heritage Party of Canada</ref> (CHP) banner. The CHP is a minor, registered political party running a significant number of candidates across the country, looking to earn its first ever seat in the House of Commons. Jetchick is their only candidate running in the province.</p>
<p>The Quebec riding of Louis-Hébert, in the Capitale-Nationale region, has existed in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canadian%20House%20of%20Commons">House of Commons</ref> since 2004. It includes the west section of Quebec City, primarily Sainte-Foy—Sillery and Laurentien's south end. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conservative%20Party%20of%20Canada">Conservative</ref> incumbent in the riding is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luc%20Harvey">Luc Harvey</ref>; also running are Pascal-Pierre Paillé (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloc%20Québécois">Bloc Québécois</ref>), Denis Blanchette (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Democratic%20Party">New Democratic Party</ref>), Jean Beaupré (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liberal%20Party%20of%20Canada">Liberal Party of Canada</ref>), and Michelle Fontaine (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%20Party%20of%20Canada">Green Party of Canada</ref>).</p>
<p>The following is an interview with Mr. Jetchick, conducted via email. The interview is published unedited, as sent to Wikinews; this includes Mr. Jetchick's separation of multipart questions into fragments, and his formatting relating to his applicable experience.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why are you running for political office?</hi></p>
<p>To try to educate voters about one of the most important problems in Canada as we speak. (Sorry, this is going to be a big long.)</p>
<p>A good political party must propose the best solutions to the worst problems. But, what is currently the worst problem in Canada?</p>
<p>To find out, we must think about the nature of all societies. What is one of the corner stones of a civilized society? Human rights! Think about it: What's the use of having well-paved roads, without potholes, if the police can arrest you for no reason? What's the use of eliminating waiting lines in hospital emergency wards, if your neighbors can kidnap your children and steal your car? What's the use of eliminating greenhouse gases, if you have no rights?</p>
<p>Now, given human rights are fundamental, which is the most fundamental human right? The right to life, of course! What's the use of having the right to three warm meals a day, if anybody can kill you anytime? What's the use of having the right to a decent minimum wage, if you're dead?</p>
<p>But currently in Canada, anybody can kill any pre-born child for any reason, from conception to childbirth. That is our worst problem: we live in a barbaric country where the right to life is violated.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why at the federal level?</hi></p>
<p>Ideally, I would run at both the Federal and Provincial levels.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why this party?</hi></p>
<p>See answer to "Why are you running for political office" here above, and add to that the CHP is the only pro-life party in Canada.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">And why in this riding?</hi></p>
<p>Lived here most of my life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Previous to this campaign, have you been politically involved?</hi></p>
<p>Very little. Ran for the same party, same riding, in 2006.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How will you apply your previous work/volunteer/life experience to serving your constituents?</hi></p>
<p>Experience ---&gt; Effect on my political career</p>
<p>------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>Canadian Armed Forces ---&gt; Never back down when intimidated</p>
<p>C++ Programmer ---&gt; Keep citizens informed with my squeeky-clean HTML</p>
<p>BA in Philosophy ---&gt; Drill down into root cause of problems</p>
<p>Conference interpreter ---&gt; Communicate well in English/French</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">As you campaign around your riding, it's likely that some issues are mentioned more often by voters, than other issues. What would you say are the three hottest topics this election, in your riding?</hi>
Actually, I prefer forechecking to backchecking, so I'm trying to control the agenda in my riding. Hence <ref target="http://www.chp-louishebert.ca/en/varia/defi.htm">my Challenge issued to all candidates</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What would you and your party do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>Protect innocent human lives from conception to natural death.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Are there any misconceptions about you, your leader, or your party and platform?</hi></p>
<p>Are there any? A whole truckload! See <ref target="http://www.chp-louishebert.ca/en/faq.htm#polemique">FAQ for Louis-Hébert</ref> for a sampling of the most popular.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">There are more ways than ever to get your message out, from the traditional campaign fliers and lawn signs, to new media like websites, Facebook, and YouTube. The tried-and-true routes get the message out to the masses much easier, but digital alternatives are much more measurable in how many are seeing or interacting with your campaign. What seems to be the most effective, from your experience?</hi></p>
<p>To answer that question, I like the old joke about the business owner who said: "50% of my marketing budget is wasted. Problem is, I don't know which 50%!"</p>
<p>Seriously, I don't know. So far, I'm trying a combination of web site with many detailed explanations, short flyers handed out door-to-door, and welcoming Radio-Canada journalists when they ask for interviews (three in three weeks so far).</p>
</text>
