<text id="autogum_interview_doc987" title="part2_Wikinews holds Reform Party USA presidential candidates forum" shortTile="partwikinews-holds" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2012-01-02" dateModified="2016-09-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_holds_Reform_Party_USA_presidential_candidates_forum" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<head id="Question_2">Question 2</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WIKINEWS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why did you choose the Reform Party?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Andre Barnett</hi>: The Reform Party the party of solutions. This party is ready to propose to America a more excellent debate on the issues, a united and all-encompassing solution to address the issues of this great nation.</p></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Robert Steele</hi>: Of the three excluded parties that are credible in America--<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libertarian_Party_(United_States)">Libertarian</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%20Party%20(United%20States)">Green</ref>, and Reform--only the Reform Party leadership was interested in a "complete" approach to reform.  The others focus on important issues but don't go far enough -- Libertarians focus on civil liberties and the Constitution, and really do not think in strategic holistic terms; Greens have a lot of promise, and I am watching <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jill_Stein">Jill Stein</ref> with interest, but they don't have a coherent approach to governance either.  The Reform Party is aptly named by its founder, Ross Perot, and after overcoming years of internal legal battles is now ready to come out and represent ALL of us, or as they put it, everyone between the two extremes.  The USA <hi rend="italic">needs</hi> the Reform Party <hi rend="italic">now</hi>.</p></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Robby Wells</hi>:  I chose the Reform Party for several reasons. In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%201992">1992</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ross%20Perot%20presidential%20campaign,%201992">Ross Perot ran for President</ref>, and he recieved almost 20% of the vote as an Independent Candidate. In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%201996">1996</ref>, Mr. Perot had formed the Reform Party, and he once again ran on that ticket. I supported Ross Perot, and I believe that he was about 15 years ahead of his time. I truly believe that America is sick and tired of being sick and tired of our elected Republicans and Democrats actions in Washington. We have too many politicians that go to Washington trying to keep their job in lieu of doing their job. The Reform Party believes in balancing the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20federal%20budget">Federal Budget</ref>, spending only what we have, creating jobs in America for Americans, government reform (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Term%20limits%20in%20the%20United%20States">term limits</ref>), and tax reform. Their philosophies are in line with my philosophies, and it seemed like a great fit when the leadership of the Reform Party contacted me and asked me to be a part of their party.</p></p>
<head id="Question_3">Question 3</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WIKINEWS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why would you be a better candidate than your two opponents for the nomination?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Andre Barnett</hi>: I do not intend to engage in "1 upper" politics. I am about the movement this party is moving towards. I am interested in redirecting this conversation towards the solutions we have to offer and working with the other candidates to show a stability this country is longing for.</p></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Robert Steele</hi>: The other two candidates for the Reform Party nomination are good-hearted individuals who share my commitment to reform.  I have the experience to back it up.  I have a deep understanding of how government corruption works and what can be done about it; an understanding of why Occupy matters and how to work with them; and I know how to address patterns of failure, how to recover the substance of governance, how respond to legitimate grievances, and how to begin to roll back much more that is hurting this country.  This is all discussed in my book, <hi rend="italic">ELECTION 2008: Lipstick on the Pig</hi> (Earth Intelligence Network, 2008), on sale at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Amazon.com">Amazon</ref> and also free online.</p></p>
</text>
