<text id="autogum_interview_doc101" title="part1_Cold as ice: Wikinews interviews Marymegan Daly on unusual new sea anemone" shortTile="partcold-ice-wikinews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-01-20" dateModified="2015-01-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cold_as_ice%3A_Wikinews_interviews_Marymegan_Daly_on_unusual_new_sea_anemone" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>The ANDRILL team almost failed to get any samples at all. Designed to examine the seafloor, the ROV had to be inverted to examine the roof of ice. Weather conditions prevented biological sampling equipment being delivered from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/McMurdo_Station">McMurdo Station</ref>, but the scientists retrieved 20–30 anemones by using hot water to stun them before sucking them from their burrows with an improvised device fashioned from a coffee filter and a spare ROV thruster. Preserved on-site in ethanol, they were taken to McMurdo station where some were further preserved with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/formaldehyde">formaldehyde</ref>. </p>
<figure><caption>This map shows the location of the Ross Ice Shelf in the Antarctic, and the two known localities for <hi rend="italic">E. andrillae</hi> relative to McMurdo Station Image: Daly et al.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How did you come to be involved with this discovery?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Marymegan Daly</hi>: Frank Rack got in touch after they returned from Antarctica in hopes that I could help with an identification on the anemone.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What was your first reaction upon learning there was an undiscovered ecosystem under the ice in the Ross Sea?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi> I was amazed and really excited.  I think to say it was unexpected is inaccurate, because it implies that there was a well-founded expectation of something.  The  technology that Frank and his colleagues are using to explore the ice is so important because, given our lack of data, we have no reasonable expectation of what it should be like, or what it shouldn't be like.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  There's a return trip planned hopefully for 2015, with both biologists and ANDRILL geologists. Are you intending to go there yourself?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi> I would love to. But I am also happy to not go, as long as someone collects more animals on my behalf!  What I want to do with the animals requires new material preserved in diverse ways, but it doesn't require me to be there. Although I am sure that being there would enhance my understanding of the animals and the system in which they live, and would help me formulate more and better questions about the anemones, ship time is expensive, especially in Antarctica, and if there are biologists whose contribution is predicated on being there, they should have priority to be there.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  These animals are shrouded in mystery. Some of the most intriguing questions are chemical; do they produce some kind of <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/antifreeze">antifreeze</ref>, and is that orange glow in the ROV lights their own? Talk us through the difficulties encountered when trying to find answers with the specimens on hand.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi> The samples we have are small in terms of numbers and they are all preserved in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/formalin">formalin</ref> (a kind of formaldehyde solution).  The formalin is great for preserving structures, but for anemones, it prevents study of DNA or of the chemistry of the body. This means we can't look at the issue you raise with these animals.  What we could do, however, was to study anatomy and figure out what it is, so that when we have samples preserved for studying e.g., the <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/genome">genome</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/transcriptome">transcriptome</ref>, or <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/metabolome">metabolome</ref>, or conduct tests of the fluid in the burrows or in the animals themselves, we can make precise comparisons, and figure out what these animals have or do (metabolically or chemically) that lets them live where they live.</p>
</text>
