<text id="autogum_interview_doc198" title="part7_Andrea Muizelaar on fashion, anorexia, and life after &amp;apos;Top Model&amp;apos;" shortTile="partandrea-muizelaar" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-25" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Andrea_Muizelaar_on_fashion%2C_anorexia%2C_and_life_after_%27Top_Model%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> She did. This was one of the biggest reasons the industry was cold to me and showed me its true colours. Within days of winning CNTM I gave an interview and said certain words that were easily manipulated to mean harm towards Jeanne Beker versus honest innocent answers. She should have known this when the interview was made known to her but instead she threatened to ruin my career verbally and she did because most people in the business started to turn a cold shoulder to me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> A big criticism of Top Model winners is that they don't go on to do many big fashion-related events, such as runway shows or photoshoots. Do you feel that was the case with you? In the year you did pursue modeling, who did you model for, and what shows did you walk in?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Yes, this was true for me. Because the winner has a pretty big work contract to fulfill, the winner [was] pretty focused on it. You have to make sure you keep your hair and looks the exact same for one year as per contract. There are many jobs to do for the contract therefore the winner cannot just leave Canada and travel abroad to model.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Another question from Steff Groulx from CNTM 2: "Why did you go from wanting to be Canada's Next Top Model to not wanting it at all?"</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> I wanted it because I wanted to make the five years I spent suffering worth the while. I left because of my health and the coldness I learned the fashion industry [had].</p>
<head id='"Happy_and_healthy"'>"Happy and healthy"</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> You're going back to college for business administration. What do you want to do with your degree?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> [I want to] become a very successful businesswoman, preferably working for the bank which I work in presently.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> How do you feel when people tell you that you looked so beautiful in your modeling pictures back when you had anorexia?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Most of the time people are commenting on the glamour and the intrigue of the show's excitement but once they know of my true story and see how beautiful I am now they ALL agree I look way better than ever before. And this is how I feel every day. I don't even watch the past shows of me anymore because I cannot look at this person...she is not me...not at all.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi> Do you feel you've fully grown into your "own skin," so to speak, as far as your self-confidence goes now that you have left modeling?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AM:</hi> Yes I have. I am officially able to hold my own; in fact, I am ready to move out again because I am ready to start my own life and family.</p>
</text>
