<text id="autogum_interview_doc572" title="part1_Wikinews interview with America&amp;apos;s Got Talent finalists Celtic Spring" shortTile="partwikinews-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-08-19" dateModified="2014-02-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interview_with_America%27s_Got_Talent_finalists_Celtic_Spring" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Who was everyone's favorite competitor, at any point in the competition?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> We really liked all the talent who made it to the finals.  They were all good, decent people, who had worked very hard to get where they were at that point in their lives.  We especially enjoyed all the other young people.  Our children travelled to New York City with the cloggers (All That) for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Today%20Show">The Today Show</ref></hi> and had fun getting to know them better.  We liked the Millers, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taylor%20Ware">Taylor</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bianca%20Ryan">Bianca</ref>, and became good friends with David and Dania.  They were very sympathetic when Piers first said to "dump your mum, dad, and little brother."  I think they were shocked when then Piers "attacked" them.  We decided that Piers went after the family acts: the Millers, Celtic Spring, and David and Dania (who were a married couple.)</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Who was your favourite judge?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> We actually liked all three judges.  Until we came before Piers in the semi-finals, we thought his judging was good and we mostly agreed with him.  We were shocked what he said to us, but happy that he could not find something specific to criticise.  He never said why we should "dump" the parents and the little brother. After we had won the semi-finals, he said "You are brilliant!"  We also very much liked David.  During the all the time of filming, we got to know him and we realized that he is different in real life than the show depicted him.  We were really touched and happy, and felt like we had won the million dollars, when at the end of the show, he presented us with a photo of himself that said: To Celtic Spring! Your family values, your talent,your dedication is what me and all of America will remember. See you on the big stage soon!"   We liked Brandy because by the finals we had her appreciating what we do.  I think initially our Celtic music and dance was not a genre she was familiar with. I think she loved our rendition of "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazing%20Grace">Amazing Grace</ref>"!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Celtic Spring has performed across both North America and Europe. Where have audiences been the most responsive?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Wherever we have performed, our audiences have loved Celtic Spring. Music and dance are a universal language and speak to everyone. One of our treasured memories of performing was when we performed in an Italian village for a really enthusiastic crowd with whom we could not speak.  But they loved our show and afterwards showered us with their treasures: a gold painted horseshoe, poems, books, etc... We were so grateful to be able to bring them joy through our music and dance. We also had great fun performing at an all boys boarding school in England.  Afterwards they showed us all around their school, including the haunted corridors (if felt like something our of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harry%20Potter">Harry Potter</ref></hi>) and then shared their music with us: a jazz band and madrigals sung at dawn in the tower in the quad to welcome in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/May%20Day">May Day</ref>.  When we perform we think we are giving something special to our audiences but we are deeply moved by what we get back: happy faces, stories, friendships...</p>
</text>
