<text id="autogum_interview_doc178" title="part0_Wikinews interviews former Republican U.S. Senator Bob Smith on his latest run for office" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-06-21" dateModified="2014-12-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_Republican_U.S._Senator_Bob_Smith_on_his_latest_run_for_office" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews former Republican U.S. Senator Bob Smith on his latest run for office</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, June 21, 2009</hi></p>
<p>Earlier this month, former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Republican%20Party">Republican</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Senator">U.S. Senator</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20C.%20Smith">Bob Smith</ref> announced his candidacy for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Florida">Florida</ref>'s open Senate seat in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Senate%20election%20in%20Florida,%202010">2010 midterm election</ref>. Smith, who was one of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Hampshire">New Hampshire</ref>'s senators for two terms — which amounts to twelve years — said he is running for office in his recently adopted home state due to his disapproval of the direction in which America is headed. He is very optimistic about the conservative change he can potentially bring to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Congress">Congress</ref> which is currently controlled by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/political%20liberal">liberal</ref>-minded members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Democratic%20Party">Democratic Party</ref>.</p>
<p>Smith has, however, some major hurdles to overcome in the Republican primary. He is facing two well known politicians who have been elected to statewide office numerous times. The chief of these is current <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor">Governor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie%20Crist">Charlie Crist</ref>, a moderate-to-liberal who is currently leading in the polls. The second is former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Speaker%20(politics)">Speaker</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florida%20House%20of%20Representatives">Florida House</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marco%20Rubio">Marco Rubio</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/center-right">center-right</ref> 38-year-old who has been criticizing Crist for months on the support he has shown for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20President">President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>'s controversial  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Recovery%20and%20Reinvestment%20Act%20of%202009">economic stimulus package</ref>.</p>
<p>Despite trailing both in recent polls, Smith believes that the polls themselves are irrelevant as the primary is over one year away. He is devoting the remainder of this summer to building up grassroots and financial support for his campaign. </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter Joseph Ford had the opportunity to speak with him about his run this past weekend.</p>
<p>"We must deliver a message that appeals to all members of the Republican Party, and that will appeal to Floridians in the general election," Smith proclaimed. "I am in this race because I want to make my experience as a U.S. Senator available to my fellow Floridians."</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why are you running for the U.S. Senate? What motivated you to do this?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Senator Smith</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> :Like many other Floridians, I have been watching with dismay as the cascade of economic crises</p>
<p>has unfolded over the last couple of years.  The bursting real estate bubble, the credit crunch, the transformation of Wall Street and the failure of American industry have shaken America to its core.  We as a nation are still struggling</p>
<p>to understand the causes of these events and judge whether the hasty actions that our government has undertaken in response to these events will do more harm than good.</p>
<p>In addition, we now face a nuclear threat from North Korea and, soon, Iran.  The Taliban is threatening both Afghanistan and Pakistan.  Terrorism continues to plague the free world.</p>
<p>As our country confronts this period of economic and international turmoil, the Republican Party seems to have lost its way.  Many Republicans feel disenfranchised by the spending orgy and big government approach of the Bush administration.  Republicans are uneasy with the current administration’s approach to these economic and international issues, yet appear to lack the leadership to provide solutions.</p>
</text>
