<text id="autogum_interview_doc1408" title="part2_John Vanderslice plays New York City: Wikinews interview" shortTile="partjohn-vanderslice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-27" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Vanderslice_plays_New_York_City%3A_Wikinews_interview" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  I would say no.  I'm definitely a capitalist, I was an econ major and I have no problem with making money, but I made a pact with myself very early on that I was only going to release music that was true to the voices and harmonic things I heard inside of me—that were honestly inside me—and I have never broken that pact.  We just pulled two new songs from <hi rend="italic">Emerald City</hi> because I didn't feel they were exactly what I wanted to have on a record.  Maybe I'm too stubborn or not capable of it, but I don't think...part of the equation for me: this is a low stakes game, making indie music.  Relative to the world, with the people I grew up with and where they are now and how much money they make.  The money in indie music is a low stakes game from a financial perspective.  So the one thing you can have as an indie artist is credibility, and when you burn your credibility, you are done, man.  You can not recover from that.   These years I have been true to myself, that's all I have.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spoon%20(band)">Spoon</ref> burned their indie credibility for allowing their music to be used in commercials and by making more studio-oriented albums?  They are one of my favorite bands, but they have come a long way from <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A%20Series%20of%20Sneaks">A Series of Sneaks</ref></hi> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Girls%20Can%20Tell">Girls Can Tell</ref></hi>.</hi> </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  They have, but no, I don't think they've lost their credibility at all.  I know those guys so well, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Britt%20Daniel">Brit</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim%20Eno">Jim</ref> are doing <hi rend="italic">exactly</hi> the music they want to do.  Brit owns his own studio, and they completely control their means of production, and they are very insulated by being on Merge, and I think their new album—and I bought <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Telephono">Telephono</ref> when it came out—is as good as anything they have done.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think letting your music be used on commercials does not bring the credibility problem it once did?  That used to be the line of demarcation--the whole Sting thing--that if you did commercials you sold out.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  Five years ago I would have said that it would have bothered me.  It doesn't bother me anymore.  The thing is that bands have shrinking options for revenue streams, and sync deals and licensing, it's like, man, you better be open to that idea.  I remember when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spike%20Lee">Spike Lee</ref> said, 'Yeah, I did these Nike commercials, but it allowed me to do these other films that I wanted to make,' and in some ways there is an article that Of Montreal and Spoon and other bands that have done sync deals have actually insulated themselves further from the difficulties of being a successful independent band, because they have had some income come in that have allowed them to stay put on labels where they are not being pushed around by anyone.</p>
</text>
