<text id="autogum_interview_doc525" title="part2_Wikinews interviews Ruth Bryant White, independent candidate for US President" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-19" dateModified="2008-08-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Ruth_Bryant_White%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I believe in discipline and respect for teachers and administrators, but I believe in school choice. I don’t believe in the Teacher’s Unions taking teachers monies and lobbying in Washington on causes that the Teachers may not believe in. I would enact Child Support Revisions to help good Dads who take care of their children without the government interfering. I would enact a Private Medical CO-OP that pays dividends for those who remain healthily while we pay for whatever health problems the sick may have, with no co-pays and including all dental, vision home care, long term and short term care. This plan may have some government oversight by the Attorney General.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Campaigning for the American presidency is one of the most expensive exercises in the world. How do you deal with the cost and fundraising?</hi></p>
<p>I don’t have an expert to fundraise for me, so I campaign over the internet and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref>. I travel when the funds are available. I'm reaching people in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref> and all over America. They are shocked that I respond to them, when I'm not out physically campaigning or doing interviews. People would support me if I were on the news and was getting support that way.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Do you have a running mate yet? Who are they? What are you looking for in a running mate?</hi></p>
<p>I don’t yet have a running mate. They have to care about our country and not try to be positioning for a powerful position. They have to want to take care of business and carry out my platform and be objective. I don’t like “yes” people. I can deal with constructive criticism, because the things I’m doing are to better our country. The More Than A Woman” Presidential Campaign is not about me. It’s about us “WE The People” and how we can pursue happiness without so much Government Interference.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Can you win the 2008 Presidential election?</hi></p>
<p>Yes, if I had the same media coverage and had been invited to participate in the debates the News Media have and are sponsoring for only Republicans or Democrats and their so-called Front runners, yet excluding the Independent Candidate.</p>
<p>I've proven what I can do on Fox News's <hi rend="italic">The O'Reilly Factor</hi>. Feel free to look at the actual segment on my Presidential Website www.rbwforpres2008.com. Fox received thousands of emails from people who said they liked what I had to say about the issue I was talking about. People want to see me on the news programs, because I have the answers to the problems most can't figure out</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Can any third party or independent candidate ever win?</hi></p>
<p>Yes, especially if the National news would stop being so partisan. At least the voters would know every Candidate running and their platforms. If 57% of the people are Independents that means the voters are being disenfranchised all over the country. The voters have the right and yet have no idea they can vote for any of us 100+ Candidate out there. I will make sure they know. Why not?</p>
</text>
