<text id="autogum_interview_doc1268" title="part1_Two-time Eurovision entrant Edsilia Rombley discusses music, love, and her contrasting Contest experiences" shortTile="parttwotime-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-03" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Two-time_Eurovision_entrant_Edsilia_Rombley_discusses_music%2C_love%2C_and_her_contrasting_Contest_experiences" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">ER</hi>: Because I often work late and seldom sleep before 1 a.m., I usually get up around 11 a.m., check my e-mail, contact my management for day to day business, and depending on the day I might have photoshoots or interviews. I work out at the gym, get groceries and cook some dinner (yes, I really love cooking!). When I've finished eating, it's usually time for me to get ready for my real "workday", although it's more a "worknight" for me. My tour manager picks me up and off I go, performing in every corner of the country with my two backing vocals, and I don't usually arrive back home before 1 a.m.</p>
<head id="Beginnings">Beginnings</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You were originally part of the girl group Dignity. Did you ever feel apprehensive about placing yourself in the public stage at such a young age?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">ER</hi>: The girls and I all knew each other and one time, after a birthday party we decided to form a group. It was performing with that group (remember, I was only fifteen at the time) that I found my love for performing on a stage and really started thinking about a career in music.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Your first international recognition came with winning the European Soundmix Show in Amsterdam in 1997. What was the experience like? What memory sticks out most in your mind even today?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">ER</hi>: That I never thought I would get that far. I remember everyone being nervous and I wasn't really, because I just didn't think it would be such a huge success for me. I was just having fun backstage with everyone, enjoying the experience in general. Only when I won, the reality of having a real long-lasting career in music began to sink in, and that was a great feeling.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Who were your musical influences in the formative years of your career, and are they still influential to you today? You've covered many songs by Oleta Adams; is she someone you've looked up to in your career?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">ER</hi>: I listened a lot to artists like Anita Baker, Betty Wright, Gladys Knight and of course Oleta Adams. In our home we listened to soul and R&amp;B music a lot and we grew up singing their songs while doing our daily household chores, singing together using everything we could find as a microphone, from hairbrushes to broomsticks! I respect all these artists for what they accomplished in their career. They brought me in contact with the kind of music I'm still such a big fan of today.</p>
<head id="Eurovision_'98">Eurovision '98</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You won the Nationaal Songfestival by a wide margin in 1998, and then your song "Hemel en aarde" placed fourth in Birmingham, which was the highest placing the Netherlands had seen since they won 23 years earlier. Did you find the attention and accolades overwhelming? Going into the Eurovision, did you have any insecurities about your song or your performance? Knowing the Netherlands' shaky track record in the Contest, did you expect to receive high marks?</hi></p>
</text>
