<text id="autogum_interview_doc1015" title="part0_Interview with BBC Creative Archive project leader" shortTile="partinterview-bbc" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-06-20" dateModified="2010-07-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_BBC_Creative_Archive_project_leader" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with BBC Creative Archive project leader</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 22, 2006</hi></p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creative%20Archive%20Licence">Creative Archive</ref> project is a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC">BBC</ref> led initiative which aims to make archive audio and video footage available to be freely downloaded, distributed, and ‘remixed’. The project is still in a pilot stage, and is only available to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20Kingdom">UK</ref> residents, but the long-term future of the project could have a major impact on the way audiences interact with BBC content.</p>
<p>The project is partly inspired by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creative%20Commons">Creative Commons</ref> movements, and also by a general move within the BBC to be more open with its assets. Additionally, educational audiences such as schools have expressed an interest in using BBC content within the classroom, both to watch and to create multimedia content from.</p>
<p>So far, clips made available under the licence have included archive news footage, nature documentary footage, and video clips content designed for educational uses. “It’s done very well with the audiences we’ve directed them towards – heavy BBC users,” says Paul Gerhardt, project leader. Users downloading the clips are also prompted to fill in a questionnaire, and so far 10-15% of people seem to be doing something with the material, although the BBC can’t be sure what exactly that is.</p>
<p>One of the biggest limitations within the licence as it currently stands during the pilot scheme is that the material is only available for use by people resident in the UK. The BBC’s Creative Archive sites use ‘geo-IP filtering’ to limit downloads to the UK, but there is some confusion over whether people who create their own content using the material can upload their creations to their own websites. A question within the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FAQ">FAQs</ref> for one of the more recent selections of clips suggests that this isn’t possible, saying “during this pilot phase material released under the terms of the Creative Archive Licence cannot be used outside the UK - therefore, unless a website has its use restricted to the UK only, content from the 'Regions on Film' archive cannot be published on it.”</p>
<p>“We want people to make full use of this content, whether they cut and paste it or whether they share it, and we completely accept that we’ve got a bit of a contradiction at the moment by saying UK-only and yet encouraging people to put it on their sites to share it with others, because you can’t expect people to have geo-IP restriction technology,” admits Mr Gerhardt. “We’re thinking hard about how to deal with this after the pilot – at the moment it’s quite likely that we’re probably going to need to find a distribution partner outside of the UK, so that if you’re outside of the UK you’ve got roughly the same experience as in the UK, but the content could be surrounded by sponsorship messages or advertising or whatever. Once we’ve done that then leakage from one to the other won’t really matter very much.”</p>
</text>
