<text id="autogum_interview_doc533" title="part6_Billy West, voice of Ren and Stimpy, Futurama, on the rough start that shaped his life" shortTile="partbilly-west-voice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2013-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Billy_West%2C_voice_of_Ren_and_Stimpy%2C_Futurama%2C_on_the_rough_start_that_shaped_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Where was your mom during all this?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  She was trying to make a household and trying to keep the place as sane as she possibly could.</p>
<head id="West_moves_to_Boston_after_his_parents_divorce">West moves to Boston after his parents divorce</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It doesn’t sound like she was very successful.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  She had to leave him. She came into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/sixth%20grade">sixth grade</ref> one day.  I saw my mother at school and I was mortified like any other kid would be. She talked to the teacher and they went out in the hall. My mom came and I went with her to the airport. It was like going on a trip. We got out of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Detroit">Detroit</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Michigan">Michigan</ref> and we were on a plane to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Boston">Boston</ref>. Me and my two brothers. One was a baby and the other one was like, gosh, he had to be seven or six because I was about eleven. This was back in 1963.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When did you come to a realization that your voice was something that you wanted to turn into a career?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">I’d go out and kick the shit out of some little cat or something, just like you know, smack it... In a weird way, in a weird permutation of the whole situation, to me that was supposed to be love. Cause why would your parent hit you, hurt you? Why? It never makes sense to a kid. And they all used to say, 'It’s because I care about you.' But I got over that stuff and what I did was start to hurt myself.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right"><hi rend="bold">—West on abusing animals to deal with his own abuse</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  It never was a realization. I started playing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/trumpet">trumpet</ref> in grade school when I was ten years old and I liked the idea of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recital">going on stage and playing</ref>. And I was in a couple of plays in school and I really liked that world. I felt totally at home with it cause you had to be ready for anything and you had to be vigilant and you had to be on your toes, which actors need as skill and survival tools. So it was the perfect place for me to be. It’s not like I was a hollow, empty vessel. I had plenty of things percolating inside and all that, but I needed to be where I to be where I felt good and I never fit in with other kids.  I only had, like, two friends, maybe one, who was, “You like that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/comic%20book">comic book</ref> too?” You know, that kind of stuff. Getting called faygot by any random goon.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you say <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fay">fay</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/faggot">faggot</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  No, it’s <hi rend="italic">faggot</hi>, but they would pronounce it <hi rend="italic">fay</hi>-got, you know, in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Boston">Boston</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Fay</hi>got. What are you, <hi rend="italic">fay</hi>got? What are you, <hi rend="italic">queer</hi>?</p>
</text>
