<text id="autogum_interview_doc097" title="part1_Wikinews interviews specialists on Russian intervention in Ukraine" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-02" dateModified="2016-11-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_specialists_on_Russian_intervention_in_Ukraine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>File photo of interviewee Yanni Kotsonis. Image: Yanni Kotsonis.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Are we going to see a proxy war between the United States and Russia?</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Morris</hi>: No.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Burbank</hi>: I doubt that we will have a real war, but note that the Russians who falsely accused the "West" and the U.S. for instigating the political activism of Ukrainians (denying that Ukrainians themselves wanted to change their corrupt government for a more democratic and inclusive one) now have managed, through provocation, to get the "West" involved in the conflict.  (So far this involvement is only diplomatic and verbal.)  Moreover, the analysis so common in the Western media of a divided Ukraine (East vs West) has played into Russia's hands, setting up a scenario for strife and divisiveness.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Brandist</hi>: I think it unlikely at present. Russia humiliated the US when it entered <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Georgia_(country)">Georgia</ref> to stop it becoming part of NATO, exposing the limits of US power in areas where Russia has an overwhelming superiority in conventional weapons. Russia clearly cannot contest the US on a global basis in the way that the USSR once could, but it remains a great power with a powerful regional presence, while the limits of US power have been graphically illustrated in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Middle_East">Middle East</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caucasus">Caucasus</ref>. This is another illustration of that.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Blank</hi>: It is too soon to know what we are going to see but a proxy war is one  possibility as is a direct confrontation between NATO and Russia (note I did not say war).  In my personal opinion resolute NATO action  combined with  economic and political action of a similarly robust nature would force Russia to back down because it  knows it cannot afford to go up against NATO.  Indeed this operation was undertaken because <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vladimir_Putin">Putin</ref> et al openly and [...] publicly declared their belief that Obama and other Western leaders are weak, irresolute, and afraid to act.  This calculation must be reversed decisively if peace is to hold.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Kotsonis</hi>: I doubt it. The US has used stern language but so far has taken direct intervention off the table. On the other hand Russia has declared publicly that it can intervene militarily and has decided that the US will not. "Proxy" does not capture it because Russia is actually in Ukraine and the US won't be.</item></list></p>
<figure><caption> File photo of interviewee Jane Burbank. Image: Jane Burbank.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  In response to Russia's build-up of its forces in Crimea, Ukraine has ordered a full military mobilisation. To what extent can Ukrainian troops hold back and successfully fight Russian forces?</p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Morris</hi>: Anything is possible, but I think Ukraine lacks the political will to enter large-scale conflict. There may be insurgency-like fighting.</item></list></p>
<p><list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Brandist</hi>: Russia has overwhelming superiority in both the south and east of Ukraine, and the Ukrainian forces are not necessarily reliable in a conflict with Russia given the support for Russia among a substantial part of the Ukrainian population. Ukraine does, however, have substantial assets elsewhere and if Russia was to try to move into the Ukrainian heartland it would be a substantial operation. This is precisely why it is unlikely to do it. Moreover, Russia does not want a division of Ukraine, which could lead NATO to become established within the borders of the ex-USSR, so it is more likely it is seeking to change the facts on the ground so to be able to negotiate from a position of strength. It is difficult to predict how events will unfold on the ground, however, given the informal and extreme nationalist forces who are operating.</item></list></p>
</text>
