<text id="autogum_interview_doc142" title="part2_North Korea&amp;apos;s rising tensions: Wikinews interviews Scott Snyder and Dr Robert Kelly" shortTile="partnorth-koreas" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-04-04" dateModified="2015-09-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_Korea%27s_rising_tensions%3A_Wikinews_interviews_Scott_Snyder_and_Dr_Robert_Kelly" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  There's a lot of talk about <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kim_Jong-un">Kim Jong-un</ref> being an inexperienced leader — do you think he knows where the 'brink' lies?</p>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">RK</hi>: That's actually a really good question. No, I don't, which is why we're having this whole conversation. Kim's father, Kim the second [<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kim_Jong-il">Kim Jong-il</ref>], was actually very good about this, "good" in quotations I suppose. He knew really well how to play this game, he knew really well how to play the South, particularly for aid, rice, assistance, fuel, things like that. The new guy — he's only been in there for a year-and-a-half, right, 14, 15 months — he didn't go through the grooming institutions of the regime, he didn't go through the military or the party. And he certainly has no military training, it's not like he went to some military institute — he went to some boarding school in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Switzerland">Switzerland</ref>, or something like that. So it's not at all clear that this guy knows, sort of how this is done. I have a feeling myself that he's being egged on by the generals at home, and the generals are really doing this because they do not want the military's position to be lowered in the new order. Under the previous Kim, under the second Kim [Kim-Jong-il], the military was raised in the constitution to a very high level of importance, they were sort of the primary pillar of the government, this is called the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Songun">'Military First'</ref> policy. I think people now worry that the new Kim — in order to re-start the economy might downgrade the role of the military, and I think that is where all this is coming from. I don't think they want a war.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  All of these threats, do you think they are just a way of getting more economic aid from the United Nations?</p>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">RK</hi>: I wouldn't say the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations">United Nations</ref> [UN] because the UN role in this is actually pretty minimal. It is true that there are some UN specialized agencies that operate in North Korea — the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20Food%20Programme">World Food Programme</ref> I believe is the big one because North Korea constantly has food problems — and there are western <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-governmental%20organization">NGOs</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/aid">aid groups</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/charities">charities</ref> and stuff like that, also operate in North Korea. I've actually been to North Korea and I've seen these charities operate. I've actually met some of the people who actually live there and do this stuff. But they're actually pretty small, right? I mean, the North Koreans are pretty worried about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westerners">Westerners</ref> running around in North Korea making trouble and saying things and this and that. Any kind of foreign penetration in North Korea is very, very limited. I think the real issue is actually North Korea's neighbors, specifically <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref>, the United States and South Korea. Russia's really sort of a <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/bit%20player">bit player</ref> in this drama. And that's what they really want, the North Koreans now are very dependent on <hi rend="italic">only</hi> the Chinese. They used to be able to play the Chinese off the South Koreans off the Japanese off the Americans and extract aid and concessions from each of those. In the last ten years or so it has become harder to do that — particularly Japan, the United States and South Korea have closed ranks and don't really deal individually with North Korea anymore. This has pushed North Korea to China. North Korea doesn't like being dependent on just one player. And so I think that's what this is an effort to shake up, [...] a very difficult game for the North were they an economic colony of China.</p>
</text>
