<text id="autogum_interview_doc784" title="Interview with Chuck Jeffrey, Regional Council candidate for Wards 2 &amp; 6 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="interview-chuck-jeffrey" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-23" dateModified="2007-06-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Chuck_Jeffrey%2C_Regional_Council_candidate_for_Wards_2_%26_6_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with Chuck Jeffrey, Regional Council candidate for Wards 2 &amp; 6 in Brampton, Canada</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 23, 2006</hi></p>
<p>The upcoming <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brampton%20municipal%20election,%202006">2006 Brampton municipal election</ref>, to be held November 13, features an array of candidates looking to represent their wards in city council or the council of the Peel Region.</p>
<p>Wikinews contributor Nick Moreau contacted many of the candidates, including <hi rend="bold">Chuck Jeffrey</hi>, asking them to answer common questions sent in an email. This ward's incumbent is Paul Palleschi, also challenging Palleschi is <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Vicky_Colbourne,_Regional_Council_candidate_for_Wards_2_&amp;_6_in_Brampton,_Canada">Vicky Colbourne</ref>, David Esho, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Curtis_Grant,_Regional_Council_candidate_for_Wards_2_&amp;_6_in_Brampton,_Canada">Curtis Grant</ref>, and Tejinder Singh.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> List the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ensuring that regional costs are not inappropriately downloaded to Brampton</item>
<item>Ensuring that the voice of Brampton citizens is heard at Regional Council</item>
<item>Ensuring that the citizens of Brampton receive their fair share of regional programs including but not restricted to infrastructure and services</item></list></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Promotion of and protecting of the interests of the citizens of Brampton rather than having decisions affecting the City of Brampton directed by representatives from Mississauga</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What qualities or experiences do you possess, that make you more desirable than the incumbent? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> As a patent agent have developed the skills to assess clearly each issue and do the appropriate research to ensure that the most beneficial outcome is realized from each endeavour.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent your ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Regional Council needs and deserves representation that will both promote and protect their interests and ensure that they receive their fair share.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Of the decisions made by council since the last election, which one would you have changed, and why?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Decision to modify the salary of Councillors.  Believe the salary should represent work effort for the City.  Suggest the recommendation of the review committee could have been more closely followed.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I presently serve as Treasurer for the Rotary Club of Heart Lake and Director of the Brampton Community Service Foundation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Much of Brampton's existing council is quite seasoned in the civic political process. What could you bring to the table as a "rookie", above and beyond the current roster of councillors?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> From time to time new thoughts, ideas and concepts are required to make an enterprise successful; by bringing a fresh perspective to Regional Council I will be able to ensure that decisions are not made because "that's the way we have always done things".</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The Rose Theatre recently launched. What are your thoughts on this facility? Have you had a chance to tour it yet? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The Rose Theatre has added significantly to the stature of Brampton as a progressive community.  The facility represents the history of Brampton yet introduces the latest in theatre construction concepts and beauty. I have attended several events at The Rose Theatre.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> The province has strongly encouraged the development of high-density residences near the downtown. Do these buildings fit in with your vision of the downtown? How much say should other levels of government have in urban planning? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Development of high density residences in the downtown core needs to be carefully considered to ensure that the ambiance that is Brampton is not lost in a metropolitan style environment.  Other levels should restrict their involvement in urban planning to those issues in which direct impact on services provided by the other levels of government would be directly impacted.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How do you feel about Brampton's rate of expansion? Council recently capped the annual amount of new development; do you agree completely with this decision, would you have slowed development even further, or not have imposed a cap at all? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Brampton's rate of expansion has exceeded its ability to develop and support the necessary infrastructure.  Therefore, I support the recent cap on new development.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What are your opinions on Brampton's congestion and the level of public transit funding?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> As mentioned, the lack of a transportation infrastructure necessary to support the growth of Brampton has resulted in a negative impression of our community by both local residents and visitors.  Clearly the issue of funding for public transit needs to be addressed along with the integration of pubic transit with services of neighbouring communities.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What service is most lacking in Brampton?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The service most lacking in Brampton is an adequate transportation infrastructure necessary to sustain the growth in our community.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why should businesses be attracted to locating in Brampton?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Brampton is uniquely positioned to attract business because we are centrally located to major road services, Highway 410, Highway 407, Highway 401, to air transport via Pearson International Airport and via rail.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How could Brampton further itself in attracting corporate investment?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Brampton could further itself in attracting corporate investment by focusing on the immense talent pool available in the community to assume the jobs created through investment in the community.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I have chosen to get involved in the political process because of a deep concern that recent changes in the structure of Regional Council would result in decisions being made by Mississauga yet would have a significant impact on Brampton the impact of which may not have been adequately represented.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Brampton mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Brampton means a safe community where one can raise a family and participate fully in social, sports and cultural events.</p>
</text>
