<text id="autogum_interview_doc1413" title="part7_John Vanderslice plays New York City: Wikinews interview" shortTile="partjohn-vanderslice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-27" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Vanderslice_plays_New_York_City%3A_Wikinews_interview" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_U.S._Republican_Presidential_candidate_Tom_Tancredo">interviewed Congressman Tom Tancredo</ref>, who is running for President, and he feels we should use as a deterrent against Islam the bombing of the Muslim holy cities of Mecca and Medina.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  You would radicalize the very few people who have not been radicalized, yet, by our actions and beliefs.  We know what we've done out there, and we are going to paying for this for a long time.  When <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hezbollah">Hezbollah</ref> was bombing Israel in that border excursion last year, the Hezbollah fighters were writing the names of battles they fought with the Jews in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seventh%20Century">Seventh Century</ref> on their helmets.  This shit is never forgotten.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You read a lot of the stuff that is written about you on blogs and on the Internet.  Do you ever respond?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">JV:</hi>  No, and I would say that I read stuff that tends to be .  I've done interviews that have been solely about film and photography.  For some reason hearing myself talk about music, and maybe because I have been talking about it for so long, it's snoozeville.  Most interviews I do are very regimented and they tend to follow a certain line.  I understand.  If I was them, it's a 200 word piece and I may have never played that town, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Des%20Moines,%20Iowa">Des Moines</ref> or something.  But, in general, it's like...my band mates ask why don't I read the weeklies when I'm in town, and Google my name.  It would be really like looking yourself in the mirror.  When you look at yourself in the mirror you are just error-correcting.  There must be some sort of hall of mirrors thing that happens when you are completely involved in the Internet conversation about your music, and in some ways I think that I'm very innocently making music, because I don't make music in any way that has to do with the response to that music.  I don't believe that the response to the music has anything to do with it.  This is something I got from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Cage">John Cage</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcel%20Duchamp">Marcel Duchamp</ref>, I think the perception of the artwork, in some ways, has nothing to do with the artwork, and I think that is a beautiful, glorious and flattering thing to say to the perceiver, the viewer of that artwork.  I've spent a lot of time looking at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul%20Klee">Paul Klee</ref>'s drawings, lithographs, watercolors and paintings and when I read his diaries I'm not sure how much of a correlation there is between what his color schemes are denoting and what he is saying and what I am getting out of it.  I'm not sure that it matters.  Inland Empire is a great example.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Lynch">Lynch</ref> basically says, I don't want to talk about it because I'm going to close doors for the viewer.  It's up to you.  It's not that it's a riddle or a puzzle.  You know how much of your own experience you are putting into the digestion of your own art.  That's not to say that that guy arranges notes in an interesting way, and sings in an interesting way and arranges words in an interesting way, but often, if someone says they really like my music, what I want to say is, That's cool you focused your attention on that thing, but it does not make me go home and say, <hi rend="italic">Wow, you're great.</hi>  My ego is not involved in it.</p>
</text>
