<text id="autogum_interview_doc219" title="part0_Wikinews interviews former New Mexico governor Gary Johnson, presidential nominee of the Libertarian Party" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-11-05" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_former_New_Mexico_governor_Gary_Johnson%2C_presidential_nominee_of_the_Libertarian_Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews former New Mexico governor Gary Johnson, presidential nominee of the Libertarian Party</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 5, 2012</hi></p>
<p>With the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2012">presidential election</ref> looming, former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Mexico">New Mexico</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor%20of%20New%20Mexico">governor</ref> and current <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libertarian_Party_(United_States)">Libertarian Party</ref> presidential nominee <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gary_Johnson">Gary Johnson</ref> spoke with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reporter William S. Saturn on an assortment of economic, foreign, and social issues. In the interview, Johnson makes his final plea to voters before they cast their ballots on Election Day, November 6.</p>
<figure><caption>Gary Johnson.Image: Gary Johnson.</caption></figure>
<p>Though a member of the Libertarian Party in the early 1990s, Johnson was elected and re-elected governor of New Mexico in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Mexico%20gubernatorial%20election,%201994">1994</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Mexico%20gubernatorial%20election,%201998">1998</ref> as a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</ref>.  During his governorship, he vetoed over 750 bills, more than all other then-governors combined, and left the state with a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">$</ref>1 billion budget surplus. He briefly ran for president as a Republican in 2011 before rejoining the Libertarian Party to seek its 2012 presidential nomination.</p>
<p>After winning the nomination this past May, Johnson has campaigned throughout the nation espousing the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fair%20Tax">Fair Tax</ref>, spending cuts across the board, a repeal of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Obamacare">Obamacare</ref>, an audit of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal%20Reserve">Federal Reserve</ref>, a non-interventionist foreign policy, an end to the Drug War, and legalization of same-sex marriage. He and his running mate, Judge <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20P.%20Gray">Jim Gray</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref>, have attained ballot access in all U.S. states except <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Michigan">Michigan</ref>, where he is a write-in candidate, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Oklahoma">Oklahoma</ref>. Nationally, he has received four percent registered-voter support in the past two CNN/Opinion Research Polls that included him with President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>, Republican presidential nominee <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Green_Party_of_the_United_States">Green Party</ref> nominee <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jill_Stein">Jill Stein</ref>. It is the campaign's goal to reach five percent on Election Day, which will enable the party to receive ballot access and federal funding on par with the two major parties.</p>
<p>With <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, Johnson discusses the federal budget, education, entitlements, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrian%20civil%20war">Syrian uprising</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mexican%20Drug%20War">Mexican Drug War</ref>, same-sex marriage, the Libertarian Party, and his political future.</p>
<head id="Economic_matters">Economic matters</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> :<hi rend="bold">You say that as president, you would propose a balanced budget "not five or ten years down the road" but in 2013. Realistically can that budget pass, especially with a Congress hostile to your proposed spending cuts and tax plan? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Gary Johnson</hi>: I would suggest that if I'm elected president promising to submit a balanced budget to Congress in the year 2013, and also promising to veto any legislation where expenses exceed revenue, even though they would override my veto, I'm going to suggest to you that spending will be lower with those two promises kept than any other scenario you could possibly come up with.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You also propose decreasing federal education spending including decreases in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pell%20Grants">Pell Grants</ref> and loans for college students. Is that correct?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Johnson</hi>: Well the reason being is that because of guaranteed government student loans that is the reason why college tuition is so high. It's an artificial market. It's not a market made up of supply and demand. And it's a market where kids are going to school because they're guaranteed a government student loan and because of that, the vast institutions of higher learning, colleges and universities are immune from pricing much much dramatically lower than they would have to price themselves at if government student loans did not exist. And of course you wouldn't cut students off that are currently receiving student loans. And that isn't to say that government student loans would go away. It's just that you wouldn't make government the guarantor of those student loans.</p>
</text>
