<text id="autogum_interview_doc1159" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Kristen Monster, Willowdale" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-03" dateModified="2008-10-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Family_Coalition_Party_candidate_Kristen_Monster%2C_Willowdale" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Family Coalition Party candidate Kristen Monster, Willowdale</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 3, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Kristen Monster</hi> is running for the Family Coalition Party in the Ontario provincial election, in the Willowdale riding. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref>' Nick Moreau interviewed her regarding her values, her experience, and her campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I chose to involve myself in the political process in order to address the deficiency of integrity and morality in government. This province has suffered from irresponsible leadership and management for too many years. Now is the time to step forward, become involved, and demand accountability. That is why I am running as a candidate in this provincial election.</p>
<p>I chose to run as a candidate in the riding of Willowdale in this election on account of being a student at a university which is situated in the riding (Tyndale University College). In the past four years of study, I have become acquainted with the riding, the people who live there, and the issues they face. With the insights I have gained, I believe I can serve the people of Willowdale.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I grew up with politics. Even from a young age, I can remember discussing events and issues which were affecting the province, the country, and the world. As a teenager, I assisted in grassroots campaigning for the Christian Heritage Party. I have attended a number of political conferences, joined pro-life and pro-marriage rallies in Ottawa, and have participated in Show the Truth demonstrations in both Oshawa and Toronto. In 2006, I was nominated and elected to the position of Secretary of the board for the CHP riding association of Durham.</p>
<p>In addition to this political experience, I have held leadership positions in discussion-based groups, positions that require tact and the ability to mediate controversial topics, as well as organization and communication skills, and also compassion and understanding. I have a strong work ethic: I am competent, thorough, and pursue excellence in my work. Furthermore, attending a university which attracts students of different cultural and religious backgrounds, I have had the unique opportunity to interact with and establish friendships with a wide variety of people, and thus I have confidence that I can relate to and serve all the different people of my riding.</p>
</text>
