<text id="autogum_interview_doc596" title="part1_Wikinews interviews John Wolfe, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-19" dateModified="2013-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_John_Wolfe%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What court will it be filed in?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: It's going to be filed in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Baton_Rouge">Baton Rouge</ref> federal court. That's where the jurisdiction is.</p>
<figure><caption>Louisiana Democratic primary by parish. President Obama won the parishes in black while Wolfe won the parishes in red.Image: William S. Saturn.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">If you qualify for delegates in Arkansas and Texas, in light of what happened in Louisiana, what will you do to avoid having those delegates stripped?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: Well, I don't think we'll have the same problems in those states. The Louisiana people basically are perpetrating a fraud on the vote.  The Democratic Party put me up there. It was a primary. They didn't have to have a primary. There was a new law saying the Democratic primary was mandatory. It's a party function. They put me on their ballot. They accepted my money. And then, after that, what they did was have an election, and 17 percent of the people, and this was the Democratic Primary, this wasn't an open primary, this was just among registered Democratic voters, and I still got 11 or 12 percent. The other guys, there were two other people, together got ten percent: Mr. Ely and Mr. Richardson.</p>
<p>And then despite all that, despite Obama only taking three quarters, the Democratic Party decided to avert, quite flagrantly, the will of the people and assign all the delegates to Mr. Obama, even though their bylaws, the rules themselves say that the results of the primary are binding. Preferential presidential primary results are binding. They forsook their own law in order to make it look like there was unanimous support for Obama. They want a coronation for him instead of just a nomination.  They're treating him again like a king. Who does he think he is? I mean this is ridiculous.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You mentioned open primaries, and Texas and Arkansas have open primaries.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: Yeah pretty much open primaries. Arkansas definitely and Texas is unless you're part of the GOP leadership, then you can't vote in a Democratic primary. But it's pretty much open and I think that we'll do fine in both states.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">So how do you feel about <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</ref> voters that have no interest in their own primary and so vote for you in the Democratic primary to embarrass Obama?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: Well there's been no proof yet that that's happened. People say it will happen. But I mean, Republicans have their own races. And so if they were to vote in the Democratic primary, they would forego the right to vote for local and not only just federal candidates that are Republican, but also local people, because your local primaries in Arkansas are held the same time as the congressional. So they would have to basically decide to not vote for anyone they know or like and switch over, just for the purpose of voting against Obama. Now whether that's going to happen or not, I don't know. We can talk about that after the primary to see if it did happen.</p>
</text>
