<text id="autogum_interview_doc735" title="part2_Randall Munroe, writer of xkcd, talks about the comic, politics and the internet" shortTile="partrandall-munroe" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-09" dateModified="2016-06-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Randall_Munroe%2C_writer_of_xkcd%2C_talks_about_the_comic%2C_politics_and_the_internet" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">That’s related actually to the next question. You have a separate forum for discussion. And the forum not only has discussion on the comic but has, ah serious business and news and sections for math and science and pretty much a lot different things. So how is that? Whats your experience with the forums fora, and related to that what made you decide to add the additional, you know, topical to xkcd but more tangential. If you could comment more directly on what the thought process is there?</hi></p>
<p>RM: I’m less involved in the forums than some other people. Davean is in the business with me is running the forums with me, and my old roommate Belial. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">I hadn’t thought of the IRC readers as potentially different from the forum readers so I’m wondering if other than the obvious connection, aside from the obvious correlation you’re going to get from IRC being more technical, a little more difficult to use obviously. Have you noticed any other differences in the types of people on IRC as opposed to the forum users.</hi></p>
<p>RM: Really I feel they’re pretty similar. I wouldn’t say that it's more difficult or that there is a higher barrier of entry. We get just as many dumb people on IRC as we get on the forums. Just as many trolls or people wandering in. Every community has its trouble causers and the really good people and everyone sort of mixing. I don’t think that the demographics are all that different really. It's just a matter of which medium you’ve had more experience with and are more comfortable in. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You also have your "blag" which is really a blog.(Comic 148 <ref target="http://www.xkcd.com/148/">Mispronouncing</ref>) What about that?</hi></p>
<p>RM. The blag is a fun thing. A project for me. as for the community on the blag, I don’t think there’s much of a community.  There are people who read it, mainly when it gets linked to by something. There are people who are reading it and commenting but they generally are talking back and forth to me, they’re not talking to each other as much  so I feel like that’s just a place to talk about interesting, science technology and funny things. There haven’t been a lot of posts so far. It's sort of a young thing so we’re sort of waiting to see where that goes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What’s your favorite xkcd comic?</hi></p>
<p>RM: There are some, ones where I feel like I got things right. I’ve always liked <ref target="http://www.xkcd.com/150/">the ball-pit one</ref>. Hearing about how people like it and how people respond to it makes me like it even more. There have been a lot of new ones where it would be easier to name, but the ones that have been around long enough people have really responded to way back when the answer to this was the <ref target="http://www.xkcd.com/108/">comic about the MC Hammer slide</ref>, and I liked that one. I feel that one worked out pretty well. There have been a lot in the last year or so, last 6th months that where I felt I got things right. The one with <ref target="http://www.xkcd.com/195/">the internet map</ref>  made it all over the place, and since then there have been a few where they’ve been so well-reviewed that I think of them as high points of the strip. But I don’t know; I have soft spot that’s sort for the silliness of some of them. </p>
</text>
