<text id="autogum_interview_doc891" title="part16_Author Amy Scobee recounts abuse as Scientology executive" shortTile="partauthor-amy-scobee" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-10-11" dateModified="2015-12-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_Amy_Scobee_recounts_abuse_as_Scientology_executive" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<figure><caption>Prior to publication of <hi rend="italic">Scientology - Abuse at the Top</hi> by Amy Scobee, the author was threatened with separate legal actions – by lawyer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bertram%20Fields">Bertram Fields</ref> representing influential Scientology member and celebrity, actor <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tom_Cruise">Tom Cruise</ref>; and Scientology representative <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tommy%20Davis%20(Scientology)">Tommy Davis</ref> on behalf of Scientology management. Image: <ref target="http://www.scobeepublishing.com/">Amy Scobee</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: Bertram Fields made a mistake by issuing that legal threat when he hadn't even read my book to know what I actually said about his client. He made assumptions based on hearsay. When I received the letter, I thought that it was just like Scientology – issue threats to intimidate and back someone off. I wasn't going to back off because what I wrote in my book was true. I am the one who did the project to hire Scientologists for Tom's household. I am the one Shelly Miscavige told what disqualifying drugs Tom took so he could not qualify for the Sea Organization – which he supposedly wanted to join. I didn't say anything in my book about Cruise having to decide between Nicole or the organization. So, I knew that it was an attempt to prevent me from putting out my book as "little 'ol me" could never possibly stand up to the high-powered lawyer of an A-list celebrity who has millions of dollars at his disposal. But the fact is – it didn't phase me as truth is truth and I'm willing to stand up for the truth.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The book was subsequently published and made publicly available. At this point in time, has there been any follow-up from Tom Cruise, his lawyer, or representatives, to you? How do you feel about your legal standing if Cruise were to escalate the matter beyond the initial legal threat letter?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: None, whatsoever and I highly doubt they would follow through with any lawsuit because what I stated in my book is truth. It's what I did myself. It's what I witnessed myself. What I reported in my book can be backed up with evidence and several witnesses – easily.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The month your book was published, the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20Daily%20News">New York Daily News</ref></hi> reported that Scientology organization public representative <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tommy%20Davis%20(Scientology)">Tommy Davis</ref> characterized your accounts as "fiction". With regards to assertions you made that David Miscavige and Scientology officials "snooped" in the confessional folders of Scientology members and particularly celebrities, Davis stated, "Nobody in the church has ever violated the priest-penitent privilege. ... [Confessional files] are held in the strictest confidence." How do you respond to these statements by Davis?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS</hi>: Just like I did to the New York Daily News when they asked me about it: If Scientology does not violate the priest-penitent privilege, what is the Scientology spokesperson doing talking to the press about my sex life?</p>
</text>
