<text id="autogum_interview_doc1326" title="part3_Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian Party potential presidential candidate R.J. Harris" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-06-16" dateModified="2019-02-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Libertarian_Party_potential_presidential_candidate_R.J._Harris" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Policy">Policy</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What necessary freedoms are currently lacking in American society?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">R.J. Harris</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> With the exception of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third%20Amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution">3rd Amendment</ref>, the Natural Rights codified in, and the privileges and immunities established by, the remaining nine amendments of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Bill%20of%20Rights">Bill of Rights</ref>, along with elements of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thirteenth%20Amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution">13th</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourteenth%20Amendment%20to%20the%20United%20States%20Constitution">14th</ref> amendments, are routinely infringed by all <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Separation%20of%20powers">three branches of the federal government</ref> through their collective and Progressive Establishment of Socialism in place of Freedom and Liberty. </p>
<p>These charges are made manifest by appeal to some of the very same made by the Founders of this Republic against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List%20of%20English%20monarchs">King of England</ref> for promulgating some of the same tyrannies which are now being foisted upon We the People by our own federal government. </p>
<p>To enumerate only a few levied by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Declaration%20of%20Independence">Declaration of Independence</ref> our federal government has </p>
<p>1. "…erected a Multitude of new Offices, and sent hither Swarms of Officers to harass our People, and eat out their Substance." </p>
<p>2. "…kept among us, in Times of Peace, [and at our expense] standing Armies…" </p>
<p>3. "…combined with others [<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NATO">NATO</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations">United Nations</ref>] to subject us to a Jurisdiction foreign to our Constitution, and unacknowledged by our Laws; giving [its] Assent to their Acts of pretended Legislation." </p>
<p>4. "…[cut]off our Trade with all Parts of the World [for products or services with which the elected majority finds disfavor]" </p>
<p>5. "…[imposed] taxes upon us without our consent [by way of deficit spending which will have to be repaid by those not yet old enough to vote]" </p>
<p>6. "…suspended <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Habeas%20Corpus">Habeas Corpus</ref> and deprived "…us in many Cases of the Benefits of Trial by Jury [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USA%20PATRIOT%20Act">The Patriot Act</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Guantanamo_Bay_detention_camp">GITMO</ref>]</p>
<p>7. "…[taken] away our Charters, [abolished] our most valuable Laws, and [altered] fundamentally the Forms of our Governments" [this referring to the federal government's many infringements of out states' sovereignty] </p>
<p>8. "…[declared] themselves invested with Power to legislate for us in [nearly] all Cases whatsoever" [by way of gross misuse of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commerce%20Clause">Commerce Clause</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supremacy%20Clause">Supremacy Clauses</ref> as well as many others to pass, sign and uphold onerous legislation which would never be countenanced by a free People] </p>
<p>9. waged the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War%20on%20Drugs">Drug</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War%20on%20Terror">Terror</ref> "…War(s) against us [and in so doing] has plundered our Seas, ravaged our Coasts, burned [or seized] our [property], [invaded our privacy, killed citizens attempting to defend their property, sexually assaulted women and children attempting to travel] and destroyed the Lives of our People."</p>
<p>"In every stage of these Oppressions we have Petitioned for Redress in the most humble Terms [by begging for the cessation of: bailouts (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Troubled%20Asset%20Relief%20Program">TARP</ref>), social welfares (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Patient_Protection_and_Affordable_Care_Act">Obama Care</ref>), undeclared foreign Wars (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Korean%20War">Korea</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vietnam%20War">Vietnam</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation%20Gothic%20Serpent">Somalia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq_War">Iraq</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2011%20military%20intervention%20in%20Libya">Libya</ref>), <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No%20taxation%20without%20representation">taxation without representation</ref> and the devaluation of our Wealth (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/deficit%20spending">deficit spending</ref> and the over-printing of a declining and unconstitutional <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banknote">paper currency</ref>), the theft and destruction of our Property (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eminent%20Domain">Eminent Domain</ref>) along with the killing and incarceration of our People (the Civil War on Drugs), the sexual assault of our Women and Children in the name of security (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transportation%20Security%20Administration">TSA</ref>), the gross infringements of our Privacy (the Patriot Act) ]: </p>
</text>
