<text id="autogum_interview_doc909" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green candidate Bruce Haines, Bramalea-Gore-Malton" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-24" dateModified="2007-11-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_candidate_Bruce_Haines%2C_Bramalea-Gore-Malton" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>Whichever issues are important to the public are important to me. I believe three of the biggest right now are health, education, and climate change. My stance on each issue would be:</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Health</hi> - There are two priorities here. First, we must ensure that no more hospitals are built with private involvement. The citizens of Ontario want a fully public health system, not decades of obligation to private companies. Second, we must focus more on prevention and healthy lifestyles, to prevent diseases before they occur rather than treating them after the fact. Unhealthy lifestyles are placing a huge burden on our health system and are part of the reason the system is under so much financial strain.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Education</hi> - Parents should not have to fundraise for their children's education -- that's not the meaning of "publicly funded". We need to find more money, and we can't take it from other areas that need it either. This is why I support a single public school system. Merging our school boards will save hundreds of millions of dollars, which can be used to restore important school services that have been eroded through years of cost-cutting.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Climate Change</hi> - We need to take immediate action to reduce greenhouse gas emissions. This is not as tough a problem as some people make it out to be, because they are so many different things we can do to make a difference. We need to reduce energy consumption and increase efficiency (Canadians are some of the world's worst energy-wasters) by setting tougher standards on appliances, homes, and technology. We need to reduce our use of cars by encouraging carpooling and transit, as well as making communities walkable.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>The issue that requires the most immediate attention is climate change. The road to sustainability is a long one, so we need to begin immediately. We need to set the tone and show the rest of Canada that Ontario will be leaders in halting and reversing climate change.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>This is a difficult question because there are so many variables. We could be more efficient in how we deliver some services (such as education, where there is so much duplication between the two school boards), while other services are being delivered extremely well. It wouldn't be fair to paint everyone with the same brush.</p>
</text>
