<text id="autogum_interview_doc1345" title="part0_G20 protests: Inside a labour march" shortTile="partg-protests-inside" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-04-03" dateModified="2014-05-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/G20_protests%3A_Inside_a_labour_march" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>G20 protests: Inside a labour march</head><p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews accredited reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Killing_Vector">Killing Vector</ref> traveled to the G-20 2009 summit protests in London with a group of protesters. This is his personal account.</hi></p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, April 3, 2009</hi></p><p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London">London</ref> — "Protest", says Ross Saunders, "is basically theatre".</p>
<p>It's seven a.m. and I'm on a mini-bus heading east on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M4%20motorway">M4 motorway</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardiff">Cardiff</ref> toward <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>. I'm riding with seventeen members of the Cardiff <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialist%20Party%20(England%20and%20Wales)">Socialist Party</ref>, of which Saunders is branch secretary for the Cardiff West branch; they're going to participate in a march that's part of the protests against the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G-20%20major%20economies">G-20 meeting</ref>. </p>
<figure><caption>The South Wales protesters gathered on the steps of the National Museum, Cardiff Image: <ref target="http://www.geograph.org.uk/profile/934">Steve Chapple</ref>.</caption></figure><p>Before we boarded the minibus Saunders made a speech outlining the reasons for the march. He said they were "fighting for jobs for young people, fighting for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free%20education">free education</ref>, fighting for our share of the wealth, which we <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Labor%20theory%20of%20value">create</ref>." His anger is directed at the government's response to the economic downturn: "Now that the recession is underway, they've been trying to shoulder more of the burden onto the people, and onto the young people...they're expecting us to pay for it." He compared the protest to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jarrow%20March">Jarrow March</ref> and to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UK%20miners'%20strike">miners' strikes</ref> which were hugely influential in the history of the British labour movement. The people assembled, though, aren't miners or industrial workers — they're university students or recent graduates, and the march they're going to participate in is the Youth Fight For Jobs.</p>
<p>The Socialist Party was formerly part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Labour%20Party%20(UK)">Labour Party</ref>, which has ruled the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref> since 1997 and remains a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialist%20International">Socialist International</ref>. On the bus, Saunders and some of his cohorts — they occasionally, especially the older members, address each other as "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comrade">comrade</ref>" — explains their view on how the split with Labour came about. As the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third%20Way">Third Way</ref> became the dominant voice in the Labour Party, culminating with the replacement of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neil%20Kinnock">Neil Kinnock</ref> with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony%20Blair">Tony Blair</ref> as party leader, the Socialist cadre became increasingly disaffected. "There used to be democratic structures, political meetings" within the party, they say. The branch meetings still exist but "now, they passed a resolution calling for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privatisation%20of%20British%20Rail">renationalisation of the railways</ref>, and they [the party leadership] just ignored it." They claim that the disaffection with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Labour">New Labour</ref> has caused the party to lose "half its membership" and that people are seeking alternatives. Since the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Category:2008-09_financial_crisis">economic crisis</ref> began, Cardiff West's membership has doubled, to 25 members, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Union%20of%20Rail,%20Maritime%20and%20Transport%20Workers">RMT</ref> has organized itself as a political movement running candidates in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European%20Parliament%20election,%202009">2009 EU Parliament election</ref>. The right-wing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British%20National%20Party">British National Party</ref> or BNP is making gains as well, though.</p>
<p>Talk on the bus is mostly political and the news of yesterday's violence at the G-20 demonstrations, where a bank was stormed by protesters and 87 were arrested, is thick in the air. One member comments on the invasion of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal%20Bank%20of%20Scotland">RBS</ref> building in which phone lines were cut and furniture was destroyed: "It's not very constructive but it does make you smile." Another, reading about developments at the conference which have set <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref> opposing the UK and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>, says sardonically, "we're going to stop all the squabbles — they're going to unite against us. That's what happens." She recounts how, in her native <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref> during <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sweden%20during%20World%20War%20II">the Second World War</ref>, a national unity government was formed among all major parties, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vänsterpartiet#1940s">Swedish communists were interned in camps</ref>, while <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialist_Party_(Sweden,_1929)">Nazi-leaning parties</ref> were left unmolested.</p>
</text>
