<text id="autogum_interview_doc1353" title="part3_Van Canto's Stefan Schmidt on a capella metal, Wacken, Nightwish, piracy & more" shortTile="partvan-cantos-stefan" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-09" dateModified="2014-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Van_Canto%27s_Stefan_Schmidt_on_a_capella_metal%2C_Wacken%2C_Nightwish%2C_piracy_%26_more" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<list type="unordered"><item>What about in terms of style? Wacken is known for the variety, but your music is the most unusual and amongst the lightest at the festival. Is that a worry for you? What sort of reaction do you expect?</item></list>
<p>On every festival we played so far, people were first irritated, then a little bit amused and not later than the third song we played most of the people were enthusiastic about our songs. I hope this will be the way it turns out to be in Wacken.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>What are your opinions on the other acts there? Are there any you want to see yourselves?</item></list>
<p>Iron Maiden of course, Nightwish are there and I’m also looking forward to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avantasia">Avantasia</ref> show.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Have any of you ever been to Wacken before as a fan or fans?</item></list>
<p>Of course. I have been there 1998, 1999, 2002 and 2005.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do you expect Wacken to open up new opertunities for you? Can we expect van Canto at, say, festivals in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">US</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">UK</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref>?</item></list>
<p>Hmm – we hope so. We also have a great fan base in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref> and try to get over there in the summer to do some shows.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>How long is your slot at Wacken?</item></list>
<p>We don’t know yet.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Will we see more new material than anything, or will you perform a mix?</item></list>
<p>This depends on how long our slot is, but I think the focus will be on the second album then.</p>
<head id="On_the_future_of_metal">On the future of metal</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do you expect a capella metal to become a more common genre?</item></list>
<p>I don’t know. I think it would be great if other bands tried out so we can share our experience and do not have to find out everything on our own, haha.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do you expect other bands to be influenced and encouraged by your success?</item></list>
<p>I  hope so. When we get mails from musicians or metalbands influenced by our style of songwriting our by the courage for doing something new we feel really great. I only started playing music because I was inspired by other bands as a teenager, it would be great if we could inspire other musicians, too.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Do you think the industry should be more accepting of fresh or unusual ideas?</item></list>
<p>I think the term “the industry” is too general for that kind of question. I think that today the chances to get heard are better than 10 years ago. Everybody can produce an “ok-sounding” album and put up a video in youtube. And if it’s done well and the idea sticks out, the industry will contact the band, which is their job, actually. </p>
<list type="unordered"><item>One subject that's been in the news a lot recently is bands complaining they feel exploited and/or by their record labels. Have you found this yourself?</item></list>
</text>
