<text id="autogum_interview_doc539" title="part12_Billy West, voice of Ren and Stimpy, Futurama, on the rough start that shaped his life" shortTile="partbilly-west-voice" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-13" dateModified="2013-06-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Billy_West%2C_voice_of_Ren_and_Stimpy%2C_Futurama%2C_on_the_rough_start_that_shaped_his_life" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  I know, it’s almost like it shouldn’t be possible, yet it is. And these guys are thumping their chests about it.  I don’t go for that. It’s like saying you don’t approve of who and what your daughter is by birth. I’ll never understand that. And, again, Cheney is only like six or seven years older than me. You know what I mean?  Like where the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fuck">f</ref> did this <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/shit">shit</ref> come from?</p>
<head id="Billy_West_on_modern_American_society">Billy West on modern American society</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Has the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq_War">Iraq War</ref> affected you much as a person?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Yeah, totally. I watched the whole <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vietnam%20War">Vietnam</ref> thing go down and it’s the exact same thing. You think we would learn, but we don’t because the proof of that is there’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holocaust%20denial">Holocaust deniers</ref> to something that happened a couple years before I was born, that there was <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Holocaust">extermination</ref>. Now there’s people that aren’t sure whether that happened or not, no matter how many shoes are piled up and down in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington,_D.C.">Washington, D.C.</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Teach the controversy. Make it appear there are two sides to every fact.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Yeah, but there ain't two sides to science. And when you start <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Politicization%20of%20science">banning science and real knowledge</ref>, then you’re in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1984%20(book)">George Orwell</ref> land. The pretense of it all really bothers me. I hate sitting there, talking to a guy that’s looking me right in the eye, and he’s lying to me. I hate when adults play pretend. I hate it more than anything. The only time I want to play pretend is when I can play like a child and not make it into an ideology.  I know I go way off the subject, but I have a lot to say and a lot of people say, as far as the animation and the celebrities and all that, you know, I’m not so outspoken. Maybe not everybody talks about it, but what am I going to do? It’s the truth.</p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hubert%20J.%20Farnsworth">Dr. Farnsworth</ref> on <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Futurama">Futurama</ref></hi>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think we live in a fear-based society now?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  It’s no secret to anybody, unless you fell off a potato truck somewhere. Back-street America.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is the reasoning behind questions like, 'Aren’t you afraid of saying such-and-such thing?'</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  Because the person is usually fear-driven himself and totally understands the consequences of telling the truth. You don’t get rewarded for it, let’s put it that way.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you optimistic?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">BW:</hi>  I’m <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optimism">optimistic</ref> about my own life and things changing for the better. I don’t pin my existence on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entertainment%20industry">industry</ref>. I really don’t. Some people, without their fame, they would just roll up into a ball and bounce away and I’m like a reluctant famer, if you know what I mean. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Celebrity">Celebrity</ref> means nothing to me. The word means nothing to me. I don’t know if I said this. I probably already did because I’ve been talking so long. But if you <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fart">fart</ref> the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20National%20Anthem">national anthem</ref> you can be a celebrity. It’s bloodless. It’s artless. It’s <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Atheism">Godless</ref>. But, fuck, that’s what people want. And the idea that the word celebrity and the word diva has been watered down into any girl with a belly button now and some gold chain around her neck can be a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/diva">diva</ref>. It doesn’t matter why they call the great talents divas, you know women in the theater. It’s a pass-fail society. It’s like, in my opinion, the guy that can fart the national anthem and is famous is totally equal to someone else who actually has talent and worked their ass off and became famous for having a gift. But it can be debated. It’s like you’re saying there’s good art and bad art. Then there’s like, well define art. It’s endless. It’s infinite.</p>
</text>
