<text id="autogum_interview_doc1317" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Darcy Richardson, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2011-11-24" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Darcy_Richardson%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><p>Though I'm still developing my platform, I also support a second stimulus package — roughly five or six times the size of Obama's meager $447 billion "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Jobs%20Act">Son of Stimulus</ref>" — to jump-start the U.S. economy; a Medicare-for-All health care plan; and a moratorium on home foreclosures (for primary residences only), not unlike that initiated by Minnesota's radical <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minnesota%20Democratic–Farmer–Labor%20Party">Farmer-Labor Party</ref> during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great%20Depression">Great Depression</ref>.  I also want an immediate end to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/war%20in%20Afghanistan">war in Afghanistan</ref> and am strongly opposed to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keystone%20Pipeline#Keystone_XL">Keystone XL pipeline</ref>.</p></p>
<p><p>The American people are hurting, and they're hurting badly.</p></p>
<head id="Campaign">Campaign</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">You wrote that you had wanted somebody like former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Secretary%20of%20Labor">Labor Secretary</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20Reich">Robert Reich</ref>, economist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeffrey%20Sachs">Jeffrey Sachs</ref>, Senator <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bernie_Sanders">Bernie Sanders</ref> (I-VT), Representative Dennis Kucinich (D-OH), or former Representative <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan%20Grayson">Alan Grayson</ref> (D-FL) to challenge President Obama in the primaries.  You mentioned that you had "encouraged several of them to run".  Which of these individuals did you contact and what were their reasons for declining?</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Secretary%20of%20Labor">Secretary of Labor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20Reich">Robert Reich</ref>.Image: Robert Reich.</caption></figure>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Darcy Richardson</hi>: My personal preference was former Secretary of Labor Robert Reich, whom I had urged to run several months ago.  I never received a response.  In my opinion, Reich's talents are being virtually wasted in academia.  He's a brilliant man and has probably forgotten more than Obama ever knew.  The country desperately needs him.  I also personally encouraged Kucinich to enter the fray, but he was clearly focusing his attention on being re-elected to the U.S. House, a re-election contest complicated by redistricting.  I received a nice reply from Kucinich's congressional staff.  I never got around to contacting Jeffrey Sachs, but the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Columbia%20University">Columbia University</ref> professor, like Bob Reich, would have been an ideal candidate, too.</p></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20Party%20(United%20States)%20presidential%20candidates,%202012">candidates</ref> currently running for the Republican Party nomination, which do you most admire?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Richardson</hi>: Well, I sort of miss <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harold%20Stassen">Harold Stassen</ref>; he was a truly progressive Republican.  But to answer your question it would probably be <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Buddy_Roemer">Buddy Roemer</ref> and gay activist <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Fred_Karger">Fred Karger</ref>.  I also like former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Mexico">New Mexico</ref> Gov. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gary_Johnson">Gary Johnson</ref>.  Roemer, a former congressman and ex-governor, is probably the most principled candidate in the crowded Republican field, but the powers-that-be in both the GOP and the media have denied him a fair hearing.  I wouldn't be surprised if he runs as an independent.  I also admire Congressman <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ron_Paul">Ron Paul</ref>'s tenacity, but I find his politics a little too conservative for my blood.  After all, government isn't the enemy.</p></p>
<p><p>I've never completely agreed with McCarthy's assessment that the Republican Party was like the lowest form of plant and animal life, but the rest of the GOP field — from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Newt_Gingrich">Gingrich</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rick_Santorum">Santorum</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Herman_Cain">Cain</ref> — comes awfully darn close to matching that biting description.</p></p>
</text>
