<text id="autogum_interview_doc1343" title="part2_Interview with Anna Mikkola, Finnish Left Alliance candidate for European Parliament" shortTile="partinterview-anna" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-05-28" dateModified="2014-01-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Anna_Mikkola%2C_Finnish_Left_Alliance_candidate_for_European_Parliament" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Now let's talk policy; on your website you mention numerous issues with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Lisbon">Lisbon treaty</ref> but also say that EU membership isn't an either-or consideration. If you could re-write Lisbon, what would you take out, what would you put in?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Simply put I would take out all the militarisation stuff, and remove the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neoliberalism">neoliberal</ref> economic thinking of no rules for the financial markets, and maybe remove some of the new policy areas. I would put in a social progress clause that would ensure rights (especially worker's rights) inside the EU and add a recognition for e.g. cross border strikes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">On the subject of militarization, what would be the best alternative to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European%20Defence%20Agency">European Defence Agency</ref>? What's the right path, if any, for collective European defense?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Defense is a word that is understood very differently in different European countries. The Finnish tend to understand this term as passive defense, but many — especially old colonial countries — understand it in a more active sense, as including pre-emptive and aggressive operations outside EU borders. I believe the right path to be a firm concentration on non-aggressive <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/peacekeeping">peacekeeping</ref>. As for a common European defense, I am against the idea because of the abovementioned reasons. The European Defence Agency is basically an arms trading operation, when its role would maybe be better in co-ordination of crisis management and peacekeeping.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">So in the long run should the other countries in Europe leave NATO as well?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> That is for them to decide. However any European defence organisation would be based on NATO, and would not respect the status of non-allied countries. I believe the European Union should respect it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">With regard to workers' rights, a number of parties on the left have raised objections to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Posted%20Workers%20Directive">Posted Workers Directive</ref> and the European Court of Justice's positions on the rights of workers from one EU country working in another. Finland both receives foreign workers and sends workers elsewhere; how could the Posted Workers Directive be best fixed, in your view?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Anna Mikkola</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> There is no point in fixing the directive. The ECJ's decisions have been based on the Treaties, and override the directive, which itself is actually not too bad. This is why European trade organisations too have been demanding a social progress clause I mentioned earlier to be put in the Lisbon Treaty, which would be the only way to fix the situation. So that the rights of workers could not be overriden by for example the free movement of services, which has happened in most of the ECJ decisions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">And what are the practical chances that such a clause would be put in?</hi></p>
</text>
