<text id="autogum_interview_doc1135" title="part1_Social networking site lets users run virtual campaign for US president" shortTile="partsocial-networking" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-21" dateModified="2012-11-23" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Social_networking_site_lets_users_run_virtual_campaign_for_US_president" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Have you had any prior experience in politics or political studies?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EG: </hi>No I really haven't. I've never run for office, and never really been a part of a campaign. I read quite a bit and I'm a bit of a polymath when it comes to history and economics.  When I read a book like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom%20from%20Fear">Freedom from Fear</ref>, or Modern Times by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul%20Johnson%20(writer)">Paul Johnson</ref>, I check the footnotes.  When I read an article on-line, for some reason I have an inclination to check up on the author to see if his facts are right.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What goes on in a typical U4Prez candidate’s campaign?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EG: </hi>We have three distinct profiles.  The quick drive by profile with little information, the interested candidate who probably posts once or twice a week, and the die-hards.  The die hards of course drive the site.  These candidates are passionate and amazingly well informed. </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What measures are taken to stop trolling and prevent heated debates from becoming too heated?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EG: </hi>In the first couple of months we had to moderate the site twenty four hours a day.  As the election has heated up this has oddly become less of a concern.  We never censor political thought, but we do put dirty word filters in place.  The dialogue gets heated, but almost never crosses the line.  I've been contacted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ABC%20News">ABC News</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/slate.com">slate.com</ref> and quite a few other news outlets and their first impression is that this is just a bunch of college kids arguing about things they don't understand.  The reality is quite different.  The debate is structured in caucuses, and we occasionally hold moderated debates between specific candidates.  The average age of the candidates is about 35, so this is a much more serious crowd than you would suppose.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How is a candidate’s rating calculated? What specific factors are taken into account?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EG: </hi>Candidates must campaign.  The core score is ratings by other candidates on a scale of 1 to 10.  But this is only about 70% of total score.  After six months of use, we developed a voting algorithm based on how members were using the site.  You could literally have a perfect score of ten from members, and never get in to a runoff.  You have to debate the issues, you have to visit and vote on other candidates platforms.  In other words, you need to campaign. This boosts your candidate rank and overall score.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Were any of the real-life candidates’ profiles created by the candidates themselves?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EG: </hi>Not to my knowledge.  I have seen in the log files that many of the candidates' campaigns have visited the site. Many of the profiles from the real-life candidates were created by us early in the process. We simply pulled the information from their official sites.  That said, many of the third party or independent candidate profiles are created by the candidates themselves, or their staffs.</p>
</text>
