<text id="autogum_interview_doc1053" title="part5_Past Eurovision contestants give advice to this year's performers, speculate on who will win" shortTile="partpast-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-05-06" dateModified="2015-09-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Past_Eurovision_contestants_give_advice_to_this_year%27s_performers%2C_speculate_on_who_will_win" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What projects are you working on? What can your fan base expect to see from you this year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Niels Olsen</hi>: We are working on a new album and we will make a small tour to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Norway">Norway</ref> and Denmark for the rest of the year, so that's what our fans can expect. The album will be released in 2010.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What were some of the best memories you have from going to Eurovision? What advice would you give to the singers going to Eurovision for the first time this year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Niels Olsen</hi>: The best memory...well, it's hard to say...we had a lot of fantastic memories from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stockholm">Stockholm</ref> in 2000. We will never forget the love we received from the public in all the European countries right after Stockholm, and the response from the Swedish people at the event. Apropos, I said to my brother after the first performance, "Well, Jørgen, I think it could be possible for us to have a hit in Sweden!!"</p>
<p>I would say to a "new" artist: Remember that you are not the center of the universe, and in a world perspective, the situation is not that bad if you lose the Eurovision. Stick to the ones you love and try to involve people you believe in, not the ones who promise you everything in life. In our case we have had the same manager for 35 years, we have been working with our friend and producer Stig Kreutzfeldt for 25 years, and so on. We have [made] several hits the last 35 years with these fantastic friends.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The music videos for this year are up at <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/eurovision">youtube.com/eurovision</ref>. Which songs are your favorites and which country do you think has the best chance of winning?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Niels Olsen</hi>: Well, I haven't heard all the songs, but I personally find <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Believe%20Again%20(Niels%20Brinck%20song)">the Danish</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/It's%20My%20Time%20(song)">the English</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La%20voix">the Swedish</ref> songs very nice, but as I [said], I haven't heard all the songs yet.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The Danish version of your winning song implies women "get better with age." Which women in the entertainment industry do you think personify that sentiment, and why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Niels Olsen</hi>: Personally I think my wife is still a beautiful woman, but I think as you said "getting better with age" is not the right word. My wife is still a lively and attractive woman, and we are both in love with life. I also think that a woman like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Annie%20Lennox">Annie Lennox</ref> is a beautiful woman, even though she is past 50. (Sorry, [I know] we don't talk about a woman's age normally. Sorry, Miss Lennox.)</p>
<head id="Hanna_Pakarinen">Hanna Pakarinen </head>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanna%20Pakarinen">Hanna Pakarinen</ref>, from Lappeenranta in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Finland">Finland</ref>, first became well-known in her home country for winning the</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Idols%20(Finland)">Idols</ref> <hi rend="italic">television series in 2004. In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%202007">2007</ref>, she was chosen to represent Finland at Eurovision, placing 17th in the final with the song "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leave%20Me%20Alone%20(Hanna%20Pakarinen%20song)">Leave Me Alone</ref>." Her most recent album went gold this year, and she celebrated her 28th birthday last month, her combined CD sales having risen to over 180,000.</hi></p>
</text>
