<text id="autogum_interview_doc1397" title="part1_Interview with gay marriage movement founder Evan Wolfson" shortTile="partinterview-gay" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-29" dateModified="2016-03-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_gay_marriage_movement_founder_Evan_Wolfson" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>Wolfson's entire career has been at the center of the most explosive legal and cultural issues of the last 30 years in the United States, and his influence has been profound.  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:David_Shankbone">David Shankbone</ref> sat down with him to discuss some of the recent decisions affecting gay marriage, gender in marriage and reactions in the gay community to his fight for their rights.</p>
<head id="Wolfson_and_gay_marriage">Wolfson and gay marriage</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You are one of the leaders, arguably the founder, of the modern gay marriage movement—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  —marriage.  Not gay marriage.  Marriage.  We’re not fighting for gay marriage, or same-sex marriage, or any phrase like that.  We are fighting for an end to exclusion from marriage.  We are fighting for the freedom to marry, the same freedom, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rights%20and%20responsibilities%20of%20marriages%20in%20the%20United%20States">rules, responsibilities</ref> and respect as our non-gay brothers and sisters have.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Same-sex_marriage#Debates_over_terminology">It’s <hi rend="italic">not</hi> just a question of wording.</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The argument is posed that it’s not the same given that marriage has <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traditional%20marriage%20movement">traditionally been a heterosexual institution</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  The defining tradition of marriage has been change.  Throughout its thousands of years of history, across all societies, the most predominant tradition of marriage is that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History%20of%20civil%20marriage%20in%20the%20U.S.">marriage has changed</ref> constantly from place to place, across time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How has marriage changed recently?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  There are four profound battles just within my lifetime that have changed marriage.  First, the battle to end the government’s role in limiting people’s ability to get out of a failed or abusive marriage.  The choice by a couple of whether to marry or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_and_divorce_around_the_world#United_States">divorce</ref>, that it be made by the couple rather than be imposed from without was a legal and cultural battle that took decades, arguably centuries.  We changed that tradition just in my lifetime, and marriage is stronger for it.  Very few people today would turn the clock back, despite all the rhetoric of our opponents who use divorce as an excuse as to assault gay people on marriage.  In fact, they are not seriously working to end divorce because they understand that most people believe rightly that is a decision that belongs to human beings and not one to be imposed from without.</p>
<p>The second important change was ending government interference in personal choices, such as whether or not to engage in sex with a married partner and whether to use contraception [the Supreme Court's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Griswold%20v.%20Connecticut">Griswold</ref></hi> decision].  Many opponents of gay people’s right to marry have never accepted that fundamental principle as a matter of law, even though they exert it in their own life, often hypocritically, behind closed doors.  They profess to want to roll back the clock on the Griswold decision and all the others that established the principle that those decisions rest with individuals.</p>
</text>
