<text id="autogum_interview_doc1266" title="part2_Interview with Derek Begley, Regional Council candidate for Wards 9 & 10 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-derek" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-10" dateModified="2007-06-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Derek_Begley%2C_Regional_Council_candidate_for_Wards_9_%26_10_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What are your opinions on Brampton's congestion and the level of public transit funding?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Traffic congestion in Brampton has spiralled to unimagined levels in recent years. The answer to this problem is two fold. On one hand, we must create a better "live-work" community in Brampton, seeking to develop more high paying sustainable employment within the city borders to reduce overall commute times and travel lengths.</p>
<p>At the same time, we must come up with a GTA wide, multi- governmental tiered plan to deal with this situation before it becomes completely unmanageable. We must create a transit system that is logical enough, efficient enough and economical enough that it becomes a viable first option for work, school and travel anywhere within the GTA. This is not going to be easy and is the greatest challenge facing this and subsequent councils, requiring a council unafraid to make tough decisions that with benefit the long, rather than short term future of our city.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why should businesses be attracted to locating in Brampton?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Brampton is a hub of access for all forms of transport and as our city continues to develop, more and more corporate interests will be attracted by our skilled, driven workforce, excellent family based communities and natural beauty just steps from the heart of the city.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How could Brampton further itself in attracting corporate investment?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Brampton needs to build upon our existing corporate base and seek out educational and support industries to these industries that can help Brampton develop a corporate identity in a core sector. We must identify those skills and attributes that Brampton business and citizens excel at, then work to support and develop  these skills and industries so Brampton can emerge as a world leader in these fields. Innovation and skill are the best assurances of the economic vitality of our community for the future.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Our city has grown in leaps and bounds in the past decade, yet in many ways, the city is still managed like it was 30 years and 300,000 citizens ago. The time has come for a more progressive, transparent system to be implemented so our city can move forward. I believe that I have the knowledge, integrity and conviction to be a intergal part of this process.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What does Brampton mean to you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Brampton means first and foremost to me, home. It means a city bursting with potential. A city waking up to itself and its size, diversity and energy and beginning to understand that with vision and effort, it is a  community capable of forging a limitless future both within Canada and the world.</p>
</text>
