<text id="autogum_interview_doc1205" title="part17_BDSM as business: An interview with the owners of a dungeon" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_An_interview_with_the_owners_of_a_dungeon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Some critics of BDSM say that it encourages domestic violence.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  When they talk about BDSM, they have no idea what the real world of BDSM is all about.  They are maybe the way you were before you came in here.  You researched it a little; I don't know if you watched a few movies; I don't know if you went online to see what you could find out about BDSM.  They get a very, very skewed, incorrect view of what BDSM is.  That's the problem in our world.  If you go to a mainstream, Hollywood movie and they include a minute of it—it’s usually all wrong.</p>
<p>The critics of BDSM--it's not like being a critic of pedophiles.  You pretty much know what pedophiles do.  How does a critic of BDSM learn what BDSM is all about?  And how do they substantiate that it promotes domestic violence?  That's what I would love to know.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And you don't think it does.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  I think on the contrary.  You know what I think?  I think that if somebody comes in here--let's say I want to beat my wife.  My big, fat, two-hundred-and-forty-pound, tub-of-shit, fat-assed wife.  I come in here, and I find somebody that will allow me to spank them to the degree that I--they will allow me.  And maybe I meet in the middle somewhere.  Maybe she's a hundred and twenty pounds and beautiful; I'm willing to say, you know something?  I'll spank you a lot less hard than I'd like to spank my wife.  My feeling is that they're not going to go spank that girl and go home and beat the shit out of his wife.  I think they're going sublimate it that way.  I'd love to see literature somewhere that has any kind of data that will illustrate that people that enter into a BDSM relationship are more likely.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  I think the true pedophile knows he can't do it to little girls, little boys.  I mean isn't it proven that even though they try to make them stop liking it, they can't stop liking it.  If you like ice cream, you like it, and you're just not going to be able to stop liking it, no matter how many drugs, how many things they do to you.  So if they come in here, and a woman is wearing a skirt and maybe a ponytail or pigtails, and he's able to act out his fantasies that way, is that not a healthier release than to go out and maybe--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  --there's different theories in aggression and violence--they're polar opposites.   One of them is you have a child, and you teach the child that when they're angry, you take this plastic bag and beat the living shit out of that dummy outside.  The child's learning at an early age how to associate the violence with the hitting and sublimate his violence.  But how's he sublimating it?  By hitting.  As we get to be adults and we learn how to sublimate it, we're able to draw a conclusion, "Hey, I'm hitting the dummy."  But it feels good to get it out, which is why--</p>
</text>
