<text id="autogum_interview_doc1199" title="part11_BDSM as business: An interview with the owners of a dungeon" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_An_interview_with_the_owners_of_a_dungeon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And that girl's not for you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  I'll tell you why she's not for me, and I'll tell you what I tell the girls who come here.  I don't want anybody--when you get a bruise--if you're involved in this, and you bruise your wife--if you bruise your wife, and you bruise her all up, I don't think that hurts your spirit¬  I think when somebody gets bruised--someone that doesn't love them, doesn't care about them, I think ultimately it tears away at the fabric of their spirit.  That's my theory--</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  The girls here have the complete option to do exactly what they want, and what they don't want.  So--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  If you get in here and say, ‘Listen.  I want to suspend this girl, and I want to spank her until she's black and blue, and I have a girl that wants to do that, I probably--when I met her and interviewed her, I probably would have told her, don't do it.  I don't want you getting black and blue for a number of reasons.  Primarily, if you get too black and blue, you're gonna burn out.  You're not going to want to do this, and you're not going to feel good about yourself.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  But aside from that, there are girls that will do A, B, and C, and there are girls that--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But that probably also attracts a certain clientele that you may not want to have…the bruisers…</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Right.  Right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  Right.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  But the customers that we have--I mean, there are girls that are not comfortable with complete nudity; there are girls that are not comfortable with having their, let's say, breasts touched--and that's okay.  We don't make anybody do anything that they don't feel comfortable with--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  The girls basically can do what they want.  If they get to a point where they don't do anything, then nobody's going to take them.  So there's hopefully a happy balance--</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  And there is.  And there is, usually.</p>
<head id="The_environment">The environment</head>
<figure><caption>Posted cleaning procedures for equipment are found in every room.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are your employees allowed to meet clients outside of the dungeon?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  No.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you control that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Bill:</hi>  I have checkers; people that come in.  So I kind of know.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  But a lot of them don't want to meet people -- they want to keep it in this other situation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  In the workplace.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Rebecca:</hi></hi>  Right.  Right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is this one of the rooms that's typically used [<hi rend="italic">We are seated in the yellow room found in the photographs</hi>]?</hi></p>
</text>
