<text id="autogum_interview_doc835" title="part5_ACLU President Strossen on religion, drugs, guns and impeaching George Bush" shortTile="partaclu-president" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-30" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/ACLU_President_Strossen_on_religion%2C_drugs%2C_guns_and_impeaching_George_Bush" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When does a symbol become historical and when is it intrinsically religious?  For instance, a community that was once a mission and they have had a large cross on a mountaintop that to them is more historical marker.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  That’s the question.  With a lot of legal questions—and since you are a lawyer, or almost a lawyer, right?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Well, two years.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Two-thirds of a lawyer [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Almost a slave.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Oh boy, that was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three-fifths%20compromise">3/5ths</ref>, right? [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Yes, 3/5ths!  [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  It is what a lawyer calls a mixed question of fact and law, but there is an ultimate legal criterion that is really a factual question.  That’s what her question is, and what the Court now asks: “Would a reasonable observer who is familiar with the overall context, history and circumstances, see that as promoting a religious message or not?”  And I don’t know the answer to that; it all depends on the particular facts and circumstances.  The way you describe it, it sounds as if a reasonable observer would <hi rend="italic">not</hi> see it as a promotion of religion.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That’s always the problem in law:  who is that reasonable observer?  Someone from the community, someone who has just moved into the community?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  Exactly!  You get that in a lot of areas of law, David.  I think another one that my students in my free speech class were talking about yesterday is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obscenity#United_States_obscenity_law">obscenity</ref>.  That’s defined according to contemporary community standards.  Is it patently offensive?  Does it appeal to the <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/prurient">prurient</ref> interest in sex?  Does it have serious value?  Reasonable people can disagree about that, and that’s what our jury system and our legal system are for, and there are some cases where reasonable people will disagree, no doubt about it.  But I think the principle is right, if it were up to me I can’t think of a better way to try to maintain fidelity to all of the values—necessarily there’s a tension when the government is trying to walk this neutral line.  It goes on this side and it is supporting religion, which is improper; it goes to that side and it is oppressing religion, which is improper.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Going back to when you have debated religious conservatives and they make the charge that what the ACLU is working toward is no religion in schools, and you can’t have a prayer group, do you think there is a conscious motivation to misrepresent what you have done and want, or is it a misunderstanding?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NS:</hi>  It depends upon about whom you are speaking.  For some people it is a definite distortion, because I know that they know better.  But in some cases it is literally a good faith misunderstanding in part <hi rend="italic">because</hi> of the deliberate distortions that they are hearing, including from top government officials.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ronald%20Reagan">Ronald Reagan</ref> said in speeches that the Supreme Court has told little children that they may not pray.  Many people more recently, including [former] <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernest%20Istook">Congressman Istook</ref>, who regularly introduced an amendment to the Constitution to, as he says,  “Restore prayer and religious freedom.”  Every couple of years he gives a speech—I read the most recent version—in which he says the Supreme Court has “removed religion from the public square!”  Surely you’ve heard that.  It’s ironic when you compare our country to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religion%20in%20Europe">Western European countries</ref>; they think religion—and it is literally true—that religion is <hi rend="italic">thriving</hi> in the public square here in a way that is off the charts compared to other developed industrialized nations.  I think that’s wonderful!  I think religion has been a very positive force in America.  As with everything, there is a good and a bad; but certainly on the issues I care about, religion has been a driving force behind civil rights, the abolition of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20slavery">slavery</ref>, the death penalty.  No matter what the religious group is, including the so-called religious right—which in some contexts will attack the ACLU, and in others work very closely with the ACLU.  Post <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9/11">9/11</ref> we worked very closely with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phyllis%20Schlafly">Phyllis Schlafly</ref>’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eagle%20Forum">Eagle Forum</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Family%20Association">American Family Association</ref>, and others, who are very traditional conservatives and very suspicious of federal government power concentrated in the executive branch.  Very protective of individual privacy.  They are <hi rend="italic">completely</hi> with the ACLU in opposing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/REAL%20ID%20Act">Real ID</ref> and opposing a lot of the post-9/11 dragnet measures.  And let’s not forget that the free exercise of religion, they know the ACLU is in their corner and on the professional level we work together, lobbying.  Years ago, when the Supreme Court gutted the free exercise clause of the First Amendment, I testified in Congress in support of something called the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Religious%20Freedom%20Restoration%20Act">Religious Freedom Restoration Act</ref> that <hi rend="italic">every</hi> single religious denomination under the sun was on our side.  The ACLU was the spearhead of that legislation.  So there’s a difference between what group’s professional staff members are doing when it comes to Supreme Court arguments and Congressional testimony versus what their fund raising letters say, or what their radio programs say.</p>
</text>
