<text id="autogum_interview_doc522" title="part2_Wikinews interviews U.S. Constitution Party presidential candidate Max Riekse" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-03-01" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Constitution_Party_presidential_candidate_Max_Riekse" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Lt. Colonel Riekse:</hi> I will give it my best shot because I think I can do better then all previous Constitution Party presidential candidates.  I urge those that believe in my candidacy and understand what I have said and believe to contact their state party chairman's and go to the convention in April in KS city and lend their hand in supporting me there.</p>
<p>As to being in the White House in 2009, realistically, it's a long shot; but so was Abe Lincoln in the new Republican Party; and this year, we have a Democrat and a Republican who will keep our troops in Iraq for another four years.  This is very true for the Republican and I don't care what the Democrat who will be, both will also keep our troops in Iraq for another four years; along with starting another war with Iran. Enough.  Lets end this madness.  Its time to take back America; send them a message; and change the way we vote and think; for a better America.  To take a line from Ron Paul, who I admire, and give hope to America,  Mad Max for President.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">There are thousands reading this right now. What could you say to convince them to give you their vote?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Lt. Colonel Riekse:</hi> I urge them to go to my web site and read it.  If they agree with me even 80%, i.e. on what I have put on my web site, they will want to consider voting and supporting me. No one will agree with me 100%; that would be strange if they did.  But I think my political philosophy and stands on issues make me stand far apart from the Democrat &amp; Republican that will be nominated;  and also, our party, the Constitution Party is the one closest to the average American and their way of thinking.  By going by the Constitution, we will have a stronger American; a stronger economy for all Americans; and people will live better with a sound health care, pension system and social security system that will take a lot of stress off peoples daily lives.  I know and believe in my heart that I and we, working together, can do it.</p>
<p>The price of gas and diesel fuel is going up for our cars and trucks.  Mexican truckers, as per the new world order types, are right now taking over the jobs of American truckers.  The price of food is going up; the price of oil and natural gas to heat our homes and factories is going up with no end in sight. Our national supply of food stocks has been depleted and is at the lowest level in 50 years.  If you like to eat, thank an American family farmer.  And know this, NO ONE overseas is going to send us food if we run out of food.  We need to take care of ourselves.  We now have very little food in our national reserve to tide us over in years of bad crops, etc.  We have lost millions of good paying jobs to unfair, free trade; the tax on our social security and hard earned pensions continues.  The price of health care keeps going up;  the stock market has gone down, along with it the income of millions of people who depend on that income for their retirement.  The dollar has went down against the Euro; now what part of that do you not understand?  Neither of the two leading Democrats or the leading Republican will give us real change, but more of the same, just more talk, talk and eye wash. Cheap talk don't pay the bills or help families keep up with the price of gas, food, health care,rising taxes, etc.  We need real, substantive change  to turn around &amp; un-stress America and all Americans.</p>
</text>
