<text id="autogum_interview_doc872" title="part12_Wikinews interviews World Wide Web co-inventor Robert Cailliau" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-07-22" dateModified="2014-09-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_World_Wide_Web_co-inventor_Robert_Cailliau" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>"The Wikipedia is full of errors":  maybe, but printed books too and they do not get corrected.  It is also totally unrealistic to compare the Wikipedia with a work like the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Encyclopædia%20Britannica">Britannica</ref> (for which you need a subscription because we have no micropayments).  One should compare the Wikipedia with what people have in their homes (often NOTHING!) or in their heads.  If the Wikipedia is as good as the Brittanica, then hats off!</p>
<p>Are wikis viable in the longer term?  I think so.  They give authors a frame to work in.  Whatever comes later, that frame is important.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: You've edited your own article on Wikipedia, did you find it easy to work with? You probably don't have a lot of experience with it, but what is your impression of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MediaWiki">MediaWiki</ref> software that Wikipedia runs on?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: I find it very good.  Precisely because I do not use it often it is important that it is sufficiently simple and intuitive that I do not need a manual.  The wiki software fulfills this criterion and is therefore very good:  the frame is important.!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: Will it be possible to agree on common standards, with the software companies trying to push their own standards? Are there major obstacles for XML?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: We can apparently agree on common standards:  OS X is full of XML and even Microsoft now uses XML for its Office products.</p>
<p>Proprietary standards are not bad in themselves.  They let one try out new things or be efficient in some ways.  I do not object to them on one condition:  that there is a way to export all data in an XML form, with all the details I could control through the application transmitted to the XML in recognisable form.</p>
<p>The W3 Consortium succeeded in spreading the WWW standards and did even more:  several commercial standards converged under its influence.
That is the good news.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi>: Lawmakers are lagging behind when it comes to computer- and information-technology. On your site, you say: In a society based on technology it is simply dangerous to make policy on the basis of language constructs only. What is the alternative to language-based policy?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Robert Cailliau</hi>: A few years ago I had to speak about www at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European%20Parliament">European Parliament</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brussels">Brussels</ref>.  I was shocked that there was no way to use anything else than spoken language.  No screen, no projector, no whiteboard.  How can one say anything sensible about climate change without showing maps, graphs, videos?  But perhaps we should first work on the scientific literacy of our politicians.  Maybe that won't be necessary if the next form of government grows from web 2.0.  I just discovered Newropeans  (http://www.newropeans.org).  Who knows.  The old technology of the spoken language alone certainly no longer works.</p>
</text>
