<text id="autogum_interview_doc156" title="part3_Wikinews interviews Australian Glider Amanda Carter" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-09-26" dateModified="2017-10-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Australian_Glider_Amanda_Carter" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You're right handed?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So, how's the movement in the right arm today?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> I still don't have full movement in it. And I've had nine surgeries on it to date.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You still can't fully flex the right hand.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> I also in 2006 was readmitted back to hospital with another episode of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/transverse%20myelitis">transverse myelitis</ref>, which is my original disability, which then left me a C5 incomplete <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/quadriplegia">quad</ref>, so it then affected my right arm, in addition to the elbow injury. So, I've now got weakness in my triceps, biceps, and weakness in my hand on my right side. And that was following the birth of my son.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How old is he now?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> He's seven. I had him in July 2005, and then was readmitted to hospital in early 2006 with another episode of transverse myelitis.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So that recurs, does it?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> It can. And it has a higher incidence of recurring post pregnancy. And around the age of forty. And I was both, at the same time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So you gave up wheelchair basketball after the 2000 games?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> I did. I was struggling from... In 2000 I had the first surgery so I literally arrived back in Melbourne and on to an operating table for the ruptured tendons. Spent the next nine months in hospital from that surgery. So I had the surgery and then went to rehab for nine months, inpatient, so it was a big admission, because I also had a complication where I grew <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/heterotopic%20bone">heterotopic bone</ref> into the elbow, so that was also causing some of the sticking and things. And then went back to a camp probably around 2002, and was selected to go overseas. And at that point got a pressure sore, and decided not to travel, because I thought the risk of travelling with the pressure sore was an additional complication, and at that point <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australian_Paralympic_Committee">APC</ref> were also saying that if I was to go overseas, because I had a "pre existing" elbow injury, that they wouldn't cover me insurance-wise. So I though: "hmmm Do I go overseas? Don't I go overseas?"</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Did they cover you from the 2000 injury?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Amanda Carter:</hi> Yes. They covered me for that one. But because that had occurred, they then said that they would not cover if my arm got hurt again.  And given that the tournament was the Roosevelt Cup in the US, and that we don't have reciprocal health care rights, the risk  was that if I fell, or landed on my arm and got injured, I could end up with a huge medical bill from the US and lose my house. So I decided not to play, and at that point I guess then decided to back off from basketball a little bit at that point. But then, after I had my son, and I had the other episode of transverse myelitis, in 2008, I just happened to come across the coach for the women's team...</p>
</text>
