<text id="autogum_interview_doc045" title="part6_Wikinews interviews Rocky De La Fuente, U.S. Democratic Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-03-29" dateModified="2016-12-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Rocky_De_La_Fuente%2C_U.S._Democratic_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>With respect to the environment: We are stewards of our planet, and we bear the responsibility to preserve the environment to the degree that we reasonably can. We cannot ignore science, but we must recognize that it is a two-edged sword. While we cannot deny Man's contribution to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Climate_change">climate change</ref>, we also have to acknowledge that our attempts to mitigate the damage we do is driven by technological realities that we cannot legislate away.</p>
<hi rend="bold">While we need a far more efficient and effective way of vetting potential immigrants and providing them a path toward citizenship, it is astoundingly naive to think that building a wall would solve the problem.</hi>
<p>We cannot impose subjective standards if the science does not exist to provide the solution. What we need to do is establish a rational transition plan that moves away from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fossil%20fuel">fossil fuel</ref>s toward renewable energy and encourages an acceleration of that transition. Today, we impose fines and fees if subjective standards are not met. This damages the economy and negatively impacts job growth. We need to reward the achievement rather than punish failure. We need to take the money we use to create and enforce unattainable regulations and use it to reward accelerated achievement of such goals.</p>
<p>With respect [to] immigration: We need comprehensive immigration reform. <ref target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Constitution%20of%20the%20United%20States%20of%20America#Section_8">Article I, Section 8 of the Constitution</ref> directs us to "provide for the common Defense and general Welfare of the United States," which can have countervailing impacts. We need secure borders to "provide for the common Defense." However, we also need to embrace immigrants to "provide for . . . the general Welfare."</p>
<p><p>As such, we need to assess immigration from a different perspective. Rather than viewing immigrants (documented or undocumented) as a liability, we need to view them as an asset. While we need a far more efficient and effective way of vetting potential immigrants and providing them a path toward citizenship, it is astoundingly naive to think that building a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mexico–United%20States%20barrier">wall</ref> would solve the problem. People enter into the United States from two borders as well as by plane and ship. A wall has little practical value beyond [...] political rhetoric. We need real solutions for this real issue, and we have to remember and honor the values upon which this great nation was built.</p>
<p><figure><caption>De La Fuente at the Veterans Museum in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington_D.C.">Washington D.C.</ref>, October 2015. Image: Claire Cousin.</caption></figure></p>
<p>It is not logical to suggest that we can deport 12 million immigrants just as it is illogical to suggest that we cannot deport the extremely small percentage who have committed felonies in our country. It is also ignorant to punish children, who entered the country illegally with their parents, for the decision of their parents. And it is appalling to deport individuals after we permit them to serve in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Armed%20Forces">United States military</ref>; a practice of which most Americans are unaware.</p></p>
</text>
