<text id="autogum_interview_doc429" title="part1_Dale Ogden, 2010 California gubernatorial candidate, talks with Wikinews" shortTile="partdale-ogden--california" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-04-27" dateModified="2014-04-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dale_Ogden%2C_2010_California_gubernatorial_candidate%2C_talks_with_Wikinews" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Do you believe in the legalization of marijuana and why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DO</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Yes. I believe in the legalization of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/marijuana">marijuana</ref>. The government does not have either the right nor the moral authority to prohibit what substances people put into their bodies for either medicinal or recreational or other purposes. Practically, the war on drugs has been a dismal failure. Just like prohibitions on alcohol, gambling, prostitution, etc., they do not work. They push the activity underground and create opportunities for the criminal element and, likewise, opportunities for the corruption of police and other public officials. Generally, such laws are enforced inconsistently and to the detriment of the most vulnerable individuals in society.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Explain how you think California's immigration laws should work.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DO</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Philosophically, I believe in open borders. People should be able to come and go as they please. However, the government should not take money from one group of individuals (taxpayers) and give it to others. We should not subsidize nor penalize immigrants. If people want to come to the United States and California to work and take care of their families, they should be allowed to do so. However, those who commit crimes against persons or property should be either imprisoned (for serious offenses) or deported. In that regard, the United States government needs to monitor and control its borders.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why should California "permanently roll-back spending to or below the level of 1998... and absolutely limit future spending increases?" </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DO</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Over the past 20-30 years, the state of California has continuously increased the share of the economy that it confiscates through taxes and spends, mostly, on unionized government employees and social welfare. It has reduced the amount of money that benefits the general populace in infrastructure. I chose 1998 because that pre-dates the pension scam perpetrated by Gray Davis, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democrat%20Party">Democrats</ref> in the state legislature, and the government employee unions, in which retirement ages were reduced to absurd levels and benefits were increased by about 50%. Were we to roll back spending to 1998 levels, we could both eliminate the state income tax and have a budget surplus. In my opinion, that process was a fraud perpetrated on the taxpayers of California and should be prosecuted criminally. The politicians took bribes in the form of campaign contributions and support and the leaders of the government employee unions paid bribes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MM</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why is it necessary to repeal the global warming laws?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">DO</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> There is no global warming crisis. The alleged warming trends do not exist and there has actually been a cooling trend over the last ten or so years. The "scientists" who raise the alarm on global warming trends have been discredited as having manipulated their data and destroying data that does not support their beliefs (if they even believe them). Billions of dollars of taxpayer money has been diverted to politically correct scientists and scammers like Al Gore who have gotten rich from this falsehood and who propose to use global warming as an excuse to control mankind's behavior (their real intent). Even if there is some minor global warming (which there has been in some earlier periods in history), there is no reason to believe that it would be harmful to the climate as a whole. Some areas may benefit and some may lose, but that would be true if we had global cooling, too. As an intellectual exercise, ask yourself these questions (originally posed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaclav%20Klaus">Vaclav Klaus</ref>)</p>
</text>
