<text id="autogum_interview_doc329" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Progressive Conservative candidate John O&amp;apos;Toole, Durham" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-09" dateModified="2007-12-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Progressive_Conservative_candidate_John_O%27Toole%2C_Durham" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Healthcare is at the top of the list of provincial and local issues. There are still an estimated one million Ontarians without a doctor, and my riding is no exception. We have also suffered from chronic under-funding for healthcare. A PC government would ensure there is catch-up funding for Durham and other GTA-905 communities as well as any other areas of rapid growth. This will allow local hospitals to continue to provide the outstanding care Durham residents depend upon.</p>
<p>The local economy is foremost in the minds of Durham residents. Ontario has been hit hard by the loss of an estimated 140,000 good jobs in the manufacturing sector.  The Oshawa / Durham area is no exception. All levels of government along with unions, business, education, and individuals citizens must work together to build a strong local economy based on energy, manufacturing and agriculture.</p>
<p>Durham Riding also faces quality of life issues that include gridlock and the need for improved public transit, support for agriculture/rural communities, and protection of our environment.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>Restoring trust and confidence in government. The past four years have been marred by dozens of broken promises from a government that promised not to raise taxes on the campaign trail and then introduced the $2.6 billion-per-year health tax.  Other broken promises range from tackling gridlock on our highways to closing the coal-powered generating stations.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>When property assessment rises suddenly over a few years, it puts pressure on retirees and persons on modest incomes who own a house.  I fully support a five per cent cap on the annual assessment increase for as long as an individual owns his or her home. In addition, the Municipal Property Assessment Corporation should be required to justify higher assessment instead of demanding that homeowners prove why their assessment is too high.</p>
<p>Ontario can do better in forging a new partnership between the provincial government and municipalities.  Local taxes should be used primarily for local needs and not to pay for provincial programs unfairly imposed on a community.  There should be long-term, multi-year funding arrangements for municipalities.  A PC government under John Tory is committed to speed up the municipal review process so that we can start the reforms before the next provincial budget.</p>
<p>How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</p>
<p>By reducing the burden of red tape on small business, reducing inter-provincial trade barriers, helping to create a skilled workforce, lowering taxes for individuals as well as lowering the business capital tax, providing a stable, affordable supply of electricity and by encouraging innovations.</p>
</text>
