<text id="autogum_interview_doc762" title="part0_Canada&amp;apos;s Parkdale—High Park (Ward 13) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-parkdalehigh" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-16" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Parkdale%E2%80%94High_Park_%28Ward_13%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Canada's Parkdale—High Park (Ward 13) city council candidates speak</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 30, 2006</hi></p>
<p>On November 13, Torontoians will be heading to the polls to vote for their ward's councillor and for mayor. Among Toronto's ridings is Parkdale—High Park (Ward 13). Two candidates responded to Wikinews' requests for an interview. This ward's candidates include <hi rend="bold">Linda Coltman</hi>, David Garrick, Greg Hamara, <hi rend="bold">Aleksander Oniszczak</hi>, Bill Saundercook (incumbent), and Frances Wdowczyk.</p>
<p>For more information on the election, read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto%20municipal%20election,%202006">Toronto municipal election, 2006</ref>.</p>
<head id="Linda_Coltman">Linda Coltman</head>
<p>35-year-old <hi rend="bold">Linda Coltman</hi> is a consultant and boards member.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi></p>
<p>Voter specific engagement (locally) leading to the new implementation of something citizen driven on an annual, in ward basis (&amp; an increased citizenry interest in voting and voter engagement in general).</p>
<p>Identifying the social needs of our wards residents and seeking recommendations to such and working towards great new adventurous ways of addressing same.</p>
<p>Being open to inviting corporate development within our ward through the recognition of our strong cultural heritage and respect of such through a means of encouraging positive address of the social needs of the ward 13 constituency.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Unifying the ward and increasing civic engagement throughout (increased participation, heightened voter turnout etc.) Unifying the ward by the institution of a comprehensive website accessible by all the ward's residents is a new, innovative potential means of accomplishing such alongside more tried and true methods of encouraging and fostering participation through regular open community consultation and the like.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> To pay equity to all issues and too to bring a different kind of representation to this ward.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent this particular ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> To represent the multiplicity of its diversity, which differs from that of other wards.</p>
<p>Too, this ward has been my home for 20+ years and I have been actively involved within such throughout, as such I feel well suited to representing the people living and working within and further engaging with them to identify their needs, thoughts, wants etc. and seeking to foster positive interactions and growth within this, my home ward, in keeping and adhering to the diversity of the wards constituents.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> As a leader and a participant within many community groups I currently spend and have spent much of the past two decades alongside the constituency working to address, react to and seek democratic solutions to the ward's needs.  As a member of multiple local Boards, Committees, Executives and community groups, I strive to keep abreast of issues through continual personal interaction with the residents and too through multimedia sources.</p>
</text>
