<text id="autogum_interview_doc716" title="part1_Author of My Billion Year Contract reflects on life in elite Scientology group" shortTile="partauthor-billion" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-13" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_of_My_Billion_Year_Contract_reflects_on_life_in_elite_Scientology_group" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Can you describe a little bit about yourself and your background, and how you came to be interested in Scientology?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Nancy Many</hi>: I was a college student, just starting out in the early 70’s.  It was a time of turmoil, Civil Rights, Women’s Rights, The deaths of JFK, MLK and Bobby Kennedy were still close to our time period.  Viet Nam was polarizing the nation and dividing families.  Woodstock had happened a few years before.  The culture held no real anchors – it seemed everyone was experimenting.  The progam to become a counselor at my college was losing it’s funding, I had just broken up with a long term boyfriend,  and every one I knew was either into drugs or Alcohol.  Never big on alcohol I was growing tired of the drugs.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> When you first started getting involved in Scientology, what attracted you to it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: That they were going to make the world a better place, that they did not do drugs and lived a communal lifestyle.</p>
<figure><caption>Aida Thomas talks with Nancy Many in a separate interview (October 2009) Image: <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/user/AidaThomasFreezone">Aida Thomas</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What positive aspects did you gain from your experiences in Scientology? What benefits does Scientology have to offer people who take its courses?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: I gained more self confidence, I gained an ability to work in sales.  In the first course I gained the ability to quiet my mind and to just exist in the universe.  I think these same benefits are there today for new people, but do I think they are worth the Price Charged, or Years of one’s life given --- No I do not.  Last I checked to do all of Scientology, and make it to the top of the bridge – Operating Thetan 8,  it would cost approximately $250,000.  In the old days you could sign a contract for up to a Billion Years and get those services at no cost, but to my knowledge that is not the type of counseling staff are getting now.  And if you did leave before your particular contract was over, you will receive what is called a “FreeLoader Bill”, a total of all the services that you received in exchange for your working for them.   The current and past food and pay situation for staff members is below the illegal workers in this country.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> If you desired something that Scientology offered - and felt you gain positively from some of your experiences while inside the organization - have you sought out and found such values elsewhere, for example, spirituality or another form of a religious belief system?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: After I left Scientology I did make a list of all the courses, things I learned, personal abilities I had and what I liked from it.  Over the years I have been able to find much of what I liked in other philosophies written years ago by different authors.  L. Ron Hubbard originally acknowledged all those learned men in the beginning of the book Science of Survival, but over the years that list has dwindled, until now it seems that L. Ron Hubbard invented all this material.  What I will give him credit for is that he put it in simple, modern day English, so it was easier to grasp, but of my list of things I have found useful, I was able to find them elsewhere, and for a much less expensive price.</p>
</text>
