<text id="autogum_interview_doc1045" title="part12_Wikinews interviews team behind the 2,000th featured Wikipedia article" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-10" dateModified="2009-12-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_team_behind_the_2%2C000th_featured_Wikipedia_article" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">MF</hi></hi>: I was (and still am) extremely excited. Before this semester started in January, I was not even aware that anyone could edit Wikipedia, let alone create a page and build it from scratch. I honestly did not know if it would make it through FAC but we have had so much help with copy-editing and technical Wikipedia aspects of creating the article that it really would never have been possible to get a feature article if it had not been from the help of a few key other Wikipedians. Unfortunately there was no celebratory drink or party as the work of a student never seems to end but I will admit I have been rather shamelessly bragging about it to family and friends.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">KK</hi></hi>: It was very exciting but to be honest I had gotten used to editing Wikipedia for over 2 months that it was almost a little sad that the entire process was over. Creating a Wikipedia article is such a group process that I did feel a little sad to be leaving after working so intensely with such an amazing group of people. We have not had a celebratory drink, unfortunately it has been overshadowed by all the other work that school entails but I definitely think one is in order once school is done. I also don't think that it has really set in.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">EE</hi></hi>: It was rather a surreal feeling. It's hard to believe an article that was created in January is now deserving of "Featured Article" status less than four months later. Our whole class had a party of sorts to celebrate the end of the class, which I suppose could encompass the wrapping up of Wikipedia editing.</item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Were you disappointed that more of your articles didn't make FA status?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">MF</hi></hi>: I have not been involved with the other articles so I cannot say that I feel strongly one way or another. Perhaps this question would be better suited for Dr. Beasly-Murray, who has indeed been involved in every article.</item></list>
<hi rend="bold">I think FAs [Ed: Featured Articles] deserve more credit in the academic community because they are excellent sources of information.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Katy Konyk</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Was getting the article up to that status harder than you expected?</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">MF</hi></hi>: To be honest, I don't really know what I was expecting. When the project first began I took a good look at other articles on books that achieved Feature Article status and they looked really impressive so I knew from the beginning it was going to be a challenge but I was ready for that challenge and excited to give it a go. Basically, I jumped rather blindly into "editing" and the whole world of Wikipedia.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">KK</hi></hi>: I would not say that it was harder than I expected but perhaps more work. Luckily, we had an amazing group of Wikipedia users and editors on our side who helped make it very clear what was expected for the article. Honestly, without them guiding us I think this whole process would have been a lot more difficult if not impossible. This experience has taught me that if you are willing to put in the work and time than it really is not impossible.</item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">EE</hi></hi>: It required a commitment of considerable time and effort, but I think that's to be expected for a highly recognized article. We were fortunate enough to be guided at every turn by experienced editors, who most likely the reason the article progressed so far, so quickly.</item></list>
</text>
