<text id="autogum_interview_doc1055" title="part7_Past Eurovision contestants give advice to this year's performers, speculate on who will win" shortTile="partpast-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-05-06" dateModified="2015-09-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Past_Eurovision_contestants_give_advice_to_this_year%27s_performers%2C_speculate_on_who_will_win" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Charlotte Perrelli</hi>: The victory in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerusalem">Jerusalem</ref> in '99 was fantastic, of course. My funniest memory was when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dana%20International">Dana [International]</ref> fell on-stage, it was unbelievable and I felt sorry for her. Last year I had a lot of memories. Everything was so different from '99. So much bigger!</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The music videos for this year are up at <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/eurovision">youtube.com/eurovision</ref>. Which songs are your favorites and which country do you think has the best chance of winning?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Charlotte Perrelli</hi>: I like many of the songs this year, but I believe <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fairytale%20(Alexander%20Rybak%20song)">Norway</ref> will win.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Which of the songs you've recorded is your favorite? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Charlotte Perrelli</hi>: Hmm. I have many favorites, but "Black and Blue" from my last CD is a great song; [it was] written by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fredrik%20Kempe">Fredrik Kempe</ref>. I love the lyrics.</p>
<head id="Sirusho">Sirusho </head>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Sirouhi Haroutunyan, nicknamed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sirusho">Sirusho</ref>, has been one of the most popular pop singers in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Armenia">Armenia</ref> since the release of her first album at age 13. In 2008, she represented Armenia at Eurovision, finishing in fourth place with the song "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qélé,%20Qélé">Qélé, Qélé</ref>." Now 22, she is close to finishing her bachelor's degree while still keeping up an active pace of performances and studio sessions.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What projects are you working on? What can your fan base expect to see from you this year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sirusho</hi>: I am currently working on a few big projects, one of them is the new song
"Time to Pray" that I have made with my colleagues from Eurovision, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bo'az%20Ma'uda">Boaz Mauda</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jelena%20Tomašević">Jelena Tomasevic</ref>. The song is a protest against war, and the English lyrics are written by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President%20of%20Israel">President of Israel</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shimon%20Peres">Shimon Peres</ref>. I am also working on my fourth album which will be released in [the] summer. I also premiered my new song in Greek, "Erotas", and it is already number one [on] all the Armenian music charts. My fans are very strong and it's only a pleasure to work hard for them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What were some of the best memories you have from going to Eurovision? What advice would you give to the singers going to Eurovision for the first time this year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sirusho</hi>: Eurovision is a big fun festival. I don't want to call it a competition, because the contestants become friends. I wish for the participants to really enjoy [themselves] and not be scared of it. Eurovision can give and take so much; it took my career to a new level, [and] now I work and have fans all over Europe and it's amazing.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The music videos for this year are up at <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/eurovision">youtube.com/eurovision</ref>. Which songs are your favorites and which country do you think has the best chance of winning?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sirusho</hi>: I have met some of this year's participants in different countries where I was singing as a guest and they were doing their promo tours. I haven't seen all the performances so I can't judge. Also, Eurovision is all about unexpected surprises; that's what makes it interesting.</p>
</text>
