<text id="autogum_interview_doc981" title="part6_Wikinews interviews U.S. Libertarian presidential candidate Wayne Allyn Root" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-02-03" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_U.S._Libertarian_presidential_candidate_Wayne_Allyn_Root" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>Further, I've learned we spend far too much time, effort and money interfering in the business and politics of others. Ron Paul is a bit extreme and he scares a lot of Americans by demanding a complete end to foreign aid and American military bases all over the world. But he's certainly brought up a good point that should lead to a serious discussion. I believe he's on the right track. We need to look at what we're spending and what we're accomplishing. I think it's time to cut foreign aid dramatically. I think it's time to eliminate many U.S. military bases around the world. It's time to let Japan, South Korea and Western Europe defend themselves. It's not our job to pay to protect the entire world. And it's time to cut the waste out of defense spending and the Pentagon- just as we should do with all government spending. If it's okay to criticize entitlements and welfare waste, why is it not okay to seek out waste in the defense budget too? If we can call for an end to welfare, I think we should end corporate welfare and national defense welfare too. I think it's obvious that defense contractors and security firms are ripping off he American taxpayer. Why is that acceptable? Because we're at war? Because Haliburton and Blackwater are close friends with the Bush Administration? Theft is theft. Waste is waste. It doesn't matter if those ripping off the taxpayer wear pinstripe suits or military uniforms. I will root out waste EVERYWHERE.</p>
<p>Perhaps most importantly, I don't think it makes sense to fight for freedom and civil rights in Iraq, while we take away freedom and civil liberties in our own country. No war is worth fighting if it results in reduced freedom and liberties for our own citizens. Those are the lessons I've learned from Iraq.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : <hi rend="bold">Do you believe that it is really possible for you to win the 2008 election, being a third party candidate and all?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mr. Root:</hi> First of all, YES, it is possible. I'll report the findings of two recent polls. The first poll reported that a majority of Americans would consider voting for a third party candidate. The American people are getting screwed by the 2-party system, and they know it. They are desperately looking for a reason to vote for a credible alternative. The second poll found that a large swath of Americans describe themselves as “fiscally conservative and socially liberal” otherwise known as Libertarian. So there is hope. One of my heroes Ronald Reagan took 16 years to be elected President. I'm starting a 16 year campaign to win the Presidency and reduce the size, scope and power of government. It'll be a battle- but who better to win hat battle than a guy named W.A.R. Ron Paul (Republican candidate) is 72 years old right now. I'll still be younger than Ron Paul a quarter of a century from now! I've got time on my side.</p>
</text>
