<text id="autogum_interview_doc1247" title="part10_Augusten Burroughs on addiction, writing, his family and his new book" shortTile="partaugusten-burroughs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-10-11" dateModified="2015-01-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusten_Burroughs_on_addiction%2C_writing%2C_his_family_and_his_new_book" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I wouldn't say that I believe in one.  I don't know.   I don't know if there's an organizing principle to the universe, or if there's  a sentient being that is the architect of everything--you know, everything being the "observable-and-beyond" universe.  I don't know.  I would like to know.  I would like to know--I don't believe in any  God that has been described by man in any way.  I certainly don't believe in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islam">Islamic</ref> or the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judaism">Jewish</ref> or the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christianity">Christian</ref> God.  I don't believe a word of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bible">Bible</ref>, I don't believe a word of any organized religion and I don't have any firm belief whatsoever, other than I don't know.  I can't say that I don't believe, because I really don't know.  I would love to know.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did you ever come close to believing?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah.  Oh, yeah.  Oh, yeah, I have.  As a child, I was very--I would almost say religious, as a child.  I prayed constantly, obsessively even.  So I was very, very, very religious as a child, or spiritual as a child.  And I went through another burst of spirituality, I think, when I got sober.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Through a program?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah, yeah.  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did it feel false to you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  You know, it was funny, because I was able to really go with it and suspend--</p>
<p>[<hi rend="italic">dishes are removed from table</hi>]</p>
<p>I was able to just go with it and just--pretend--I acted as if, and it just totally worked.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Which I think a lot of people do.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Mmm-hmmm.  And that's the thing, I mean if you--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  'Fake it 'til you make it.'</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah, yeah, and I mean, now I'm making it, and I don't really have to fake it.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What was your higher power, then?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I used to visualize--it's ridiculous, it's ridiculous.  But I just visualized a cartoon <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus">Jesus</ref> in the sky with a pet cow --</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">chuckles</hi>]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  The baby Jesus, you know, like--that's what I visualized--just a very cartoon version of Jesus, plucked from the manger with a pet cow.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Sounds like something--that it would be great if one of your fans drew for you.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  Yeah, that would be great.  I wish they would.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [<hi rend="italic">chuckles</hi>]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  And now I'm going to get a stack--</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  A swarm of cows and cartoon Jesuses.  You’ll have to start a collection.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AB:</hi>  I'm going to get a stack of them.</p>
<p>I would like to be a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physics">physicist</ref>.  I would like to find out--because that's the question that physics seeks to answer, ultimately.</p>
</text>
