<text id="autogum_interview_doc1027" title="part3_Blown for Good author discusses life inside international headquarters of Scientology" shortTile="partblown-good-author" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-11-12" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Blown_for_Good_author_discusses_life_inside_international_headquarters_of_Scientology" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<hi rend="bold">As an employee of Scientology for 15 years, we were indoctrinated with the concept that people outside of Scientology were criminals, drug addicts and sexual deviants in need of salvation and rescue by Scientology.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Marc Headley</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: I think that living in the real world, with absolutely no ties or communication with the Scientology world I lived in from the age of 7, was the best thing I could do to decompress and brought me to realize what was actually occurring in the world around me. As an employee of Scientology for 15 years, we were indoctrinated with the concept that people outside of Scientology were criminals, drug addicts and sexual deviants in need of salvation and rescue by Scientology. The overriding goal of ALL Scientologists is to “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clear%20(Scientology)">Clear</ref> the planet and make everyone in the entire world into a Scientologist”. After I left and was interacting with everyday people, I realized that not one single person in the real world treated me as bad as the “nicest” person in Scientology! People in the real world were nice, helpful and supportive of me and were very happy to be my friends and fellow associates. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You also write in the preface that your intention of publishing your experiences was to help readers, "avoid falling prey to any organization that might attempt to perpetrate similar abuses against them or someone they love in the future." What specific types of abuses are you referring to? Do you see commonalities between Scientology and other organizations? If so, which organizations, and what common characteristics do they share?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH</hi>: From what I have read and studied, Scientology is not the only group that uses coercion or heavy handed tactics to convince their members or staff to do things against their will. If people are aware of their rights and that they cannot sign them away, groups or cults that practice this will have less of a chance at succeeding. </p>
<p>When asked to compare what I experienced at the headquarters of Scientology, the only thing that I could liken it to would be what I would imagine that people living behind the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iron%20Curtain">Iron Curtain</ref> felt. No disrespect to anyone who had to go through that experience, but those people had little choice in the matter and escape could be not only dangerous but fatal. That wall was torn down 20 years ago. I can only hope that it does not take 20 years to tear down the iron curtain that exists in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gilman%20Hot%20Springs,%20California">Gilman Hot Springs, California</ref>. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The book begins with an account of your experience leaving Scientology's Gold Base facility on January 5, 2005. Did you suffer any injuries as a result of this ordeal? Have you had any further communications with the police that assisted you that day?</hi></p>
</text>
