<text id="autogum_interview_doc1116" title="part1_Murray Hill on the life and versatility of a New York drag king" shortTile="partmurray-hill-life" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Murray_Hill_on_the_life_and_versatility_of_a_New_York_drag_king" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Has the war affected you at all?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  I think <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9/11">September 11</ref> affected me greatly.  As far as what I do and how I relate to audiences, I don’t know if the war has affected me as much in the last few years other then having pure anger at our government and being ashamed sometimes when I go overseas.  I’m just like, “Ugh!”  I’m against war completely.  I don’t talk about that stuff too much.  I talk a lot about New York <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/gentrification">gentrification</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Would you ever leave New York?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  In my shows I talk a lot about New York and sticking with it.  I’ve seen the changes so drastically.  I would never leave it permanently, but I would go to L.A. for awhile.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  Showbiz!  But I could never do it permanently.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you feel like you are being held back here because it has dwindled so much?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  I have performed in New York for almost ten years and people still come to my show for the first time and are like, “Whoa!”  They had never heard of me and they had never seen me.  I think New York is a place where that can happen over and over.  You can’t really do that in a place like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los%20Angeles">L.A.</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San%20Francisco">San Francisco</ref> because in two years everyone and their mother have seen you twenty times.  I’m a performer who accepts the changes of New York and I perform to that.  I had a closing night here upstairs where there were no <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East%20Village%20(Manhattan)">East Village</ref> people and I couldn’t believe it!  These are all new out-of-towners.  It was almost the gentrified audience that was at my show.  I’m addicted to it.  I’ve never been more electrified by my audience than this year.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How has your show evolved since you started doing it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  It started as something I just did for fun and how it has changed I have put in the time with my craft.  I’m very much an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Improvisation">improv</ref> performer and I think over the years I have developed more of a back-story and honed my craft.  I’m a professional now.  A full-time career, I’m living off of it, I’m doing movies and music videos.  Plays, some TV stuff.  It’s become a full-blown career.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  When you say you have honed your craft, what sort of research do you do?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  A lot of people just see me and think it’s improv, but improv is a skill.  Nobody knows I do a lot of research; I read everything and listen to a lot of records.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Totie%20Fields">Totie Fields</ref> records and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belle%20Barth">Belle Barth</ref>.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frances%20Faye">Frances Faye</ref> records.  All the old guys who are full-bodied entertainers.  I have this extensive knowledge of that 50s, 60s and 70s comedy.  I’m influenced by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bette%20Midler">Bette Midler</ref>—those old concerts are unbelievable!  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justin%20Bond">Justin Bond</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady%20Bunny">Lady Bunny</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan%20Cumming">Alan Cumming</ref>, Jack on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three’s%20Company">Three’s Company</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benny%20Hill">Benny Hill</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jackie%20Gleason">Jackie Gleason</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carol%20Burnett">Carol Burnett</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lily%20Tomlin">Lily Tomlin</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20Jefferson">George Jefferson</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neil%20Diamond">Neil Diamond</ref>, of course.  I do a lot of writing and then develop on stage.  Over the years I’ve learned to write things down and develop a catalog of material.</p>
</text>
