<text id="autogum_interview_doc1418" title="part3_Interview with U.S. Republican Presidential candidate Tom Tancredo" shortTile="partinterview-us" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-25" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_U.S._Republican_Presidential_candidate_Tom_Tancredo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  Yeah, even though he is gone, the President’s feelings about my criticism of him have not changed.  It wasn’t my stand on immigration, it was my criticisms of the President that have made me <hi rend="italic">persona non grata</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Psychologist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20Hare%20(psychologist)">Robert Hare</ref> has discussed in his work the use of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/doublespeak">doublespeak</ref> as a hallmark of psychopaths, and social scientists have pointed out that the use of doublespeak is most prevalent in the fields of law and politics.  Do these two trends alarm you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Laughs</hi>] Yes and no.  Unfortunately doublespeak is all too characteristic of people in my profession.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is the proper <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War%20Powers%20Clause">role of Congress</ref> in the time of war?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  To first declare it, and then to fund it or not.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Politics is dominated by lawyers. What other group of people or professions would you prefer to see dominate the field of politics and why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  I can’t think of a particular profession from which I would be more comfortable drawing politicians from.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think lawyers are better for handling legislation and as politicians?  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  No, they don’t offer anything particularly advantageous to the process.  I don’t think it should be dominated by one profession.  I’ll tell you what this profession is, and it doesn’t matter what field you come out of.  There’s something I noticed here.  I tell every single freshman I come across that there are very few words of wisdom, having only been here for ten years, that I can pass along to you but there is one thing I can tell you: this place is Chinese water torture on your principles.  Every single day there is another drip, and it comes from a call from a colleague asking you to sign on to a bill you wouldn’t have signed on to; but it’s a friend, and it’s not that big a deal.  Or a constituent who comes in and asks you to do something and you think it wouldn’t be such a big deal; or a special interest group that asks you to vote for something you wouldn’t vote for.  After time it erodes the toughest of shells if one isn’t careful doesn’t think about it.  Even if you recognize that these small steps lead to a feeling that remaining here is the ultimate goal; that the acquisition of power or the maintenance of power is the ultimate goal, that really does… it doesn’t matter if you are a lawyer or not, it does seem to have an impact on people.  It’s a malady that is very common in Washington, and you have to think about it, you really do, or you will succumb to it.  I don’t mean to suggest I’ve been impervious to these pressures, but I’ve tried my best to avoid it.  One reason I am persona non grata at the White House is not just because of immigration, but because I refuse to support him on his trade policy, his education policy, Medicare and prescription drugs initiatives.  I remember leaving that debate at 6:30 on a Saturday morning , after having the President call every freshman off the floor of the House to badger them into submission until there were enough votes to pass it.  I remember a  woman, a freshman colleague, walking away in tears saying she had never been through anything like that in her life.  Here was a Republican Congress increasing government to an extent larger than it had been increased since Medicare had come into existence.  Your dad should have been absolutely mortified, because it was against all of our principles.  And I know the leadership was torn, but we had the President pressing us:  we had to do it, we had to stay in power, the President is asking us to do it.  Principles be damned.  There were people who caved in that night who I never in a million years thought would.</p>
</text>
