<text id="autogum_interview_doc088" title="part15_Wikinews interviews Indiana State Senator Mike Delph" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-26" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Indiana_State_Senator_Mike_Delph" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>In terms of the ideology of my constituents. I have some constituents who are socially conservative. I have some constituents who are socially moderate. I have some constituents who are socially liberal. The proof is going to be <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/the%20proof%20is%20in%20the%20pudding">in the pudding</ref> when we run for reelection in November 2014 whether or not this is the driving issue to drive turnout and ultimately render judgement over the totality of my service in the senate.</p>
<p>Last year, I carried three bills into law. I’ve been known widely as somebody who is a leader on Veterans and military issues. Last year, we expanded contracting opportunities for veterans returning from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraqi%20Freedom">Iraqi Freedom</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enduring%20Freedom">Enduring Freedom</ref>. I wrote and carried into law a strong reform in the area of education for high performing schools. I have led efforts in reform for local government reform in Title 36 of Indiana Code. I have been named Legislator of the Year by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disabled%20American%20Veterans">Disabled American Veterans</ref>. And I have been giving the Distinguished Public Service Award twice, once in 2006 and once in 2013 by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American%20Legion">American Legion</ref>. I’ve been awarded the Mr. Clean Award by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common%20Cause">Common Cause</ref> for my efforts to promote lobbying reform, and ethics reform, and redistricting reform. I’ve led an effort to change the law in the area immigration reform. And again that was not a Republican or Democrat issue, it was an American patriotic issue. And a lot of my folks that were not a conservative or Republican because of my leadership on this issue supported me in 2010. We feel very good about where we were politically.</p>
<p>I just actually just had a grassroots campaign committee with my team on Saturday at my house. My 19-year-old daughter Abby, who is a freshman at IUPUI, is going to serve as my campaign manager, and I'm going to teach her how to do this. We have the leader of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/College%20Republicans">College Republicans</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anderson%20University">Anderson University</ref>, as well as IUPUI and other leaders from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butler%20University">Butler University</ref> that will all be involved in my grass roots effort.</p>
<p>Before Thanksgiving, there was some talk that somebody might try to challenge me in a primary. And our grassroots effort, we had <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/home%20school">home school</ref> moms and volunteers make over 7,000 phone calls to base, Republican voters. We shut that down pretty quick. We have the strongest, best grassroots team in the state senate. I welcome competition. We are going to go out and compete. And we are going to let the voters make their decisions. We feel very good where we are politically.</p>
<p>From a campaign finance standpoint. We have the most money that we have ever had. We have <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US$">[US]$</ref>180,000 in cash in the bank. I have a business man, a Christian pastor, who has offered to write a check for $25,000 to support me. Another person is going to write a check for $2500. And I suspect if I really tried to raise more money, I could raise a lot more money.</p>
</text>
