<text id="autogum_interview_doc1354" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Kent Mesplay, Green Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2008-06-29" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Kent_Mesplay%2C_Green_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>Wikinews interviews Kent Mesplay, Green Party presidential candidate</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, June 29, 2008</hi></p>
<p>While nearly all coverage of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202008">2008 Presidential election</ref> has focused on the Democratic and Republican candidates, the race for the White House also includes independents and third-party candidates. These prospects represent a variety of views that may not be acknowledged by the major party platforms.</p>
<p>Wikinews has reached out to these candidates throughout the campaign. We now interview <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green%20Party%20(United%20States)">Green Party</ref> Presidential candidate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kent%20Mesplay">Dr. Kent Mesplay</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why do you want to be President</hi>?</p>
<p>I run for president to help improve society, pointing out that we are more secure when we live in a sustainable manner.  As of this writing our culture is based on the consumption of limited materials such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/petroleum">petroleum</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/coal">coal</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/uranium">uranium</ref> with great emphasis placed on the consumption of "goods" that are produced and purchased with little regard for the well-being of future generations.  Government, ideally, provides an independent, objective forum through which solutions to the needs and wants of our time can be raised, discussed and implemented in a thoughtful, respectful manner.  In contrast to this ideal, our current central, national government exists largely to protect and preserve the status quo of relatively few stake-holders, having undue political influence and acting in a manner not in the best interest of the majority of people.  We cannot blindly consume our way to peace and stability.</p>
<p>A Green presidential administration would put the needs of current and future generations above the rude demands and expectations of the well-heeled political donor class.  It is not important that we have a new president bearing the face of change.  We need vital, core change to our political institutions to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decentralization">decentralize</ref> control, empower rational science-based decision-making and cut the damaging influence of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/corporations">corporate</ref> money on public policy.  This change is unlikely to arise from within the current two political parties that are intrinsically corrupted by the ubiquitous "greased-palm" bribing handshake with corporate entities.  We need to only ask how many corporate media <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/conglomerate">conglomerates</ref> regularly advertize the question, "Should a corporation have the legal status of a super-person?" to realize the extent of the current dilemma. A corporation should never have been considered to have the legal rights of an individual.  The Green Party is independent from business interests.  This political arm of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Environmental%20movement">environmental</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peace%20movement">peace</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global%20Justice%20Movement">justice movements</ref> represents meaningful change to public policy and to our fragile, centralized, short-sighted way of life.</p>
<p>Green solutions are largely local solutions:  more community gardens and small farms, reasonable use of fresh water, grey-water and waste-water, including more water storage and community responsibility for the entire water stream, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Energy%20efficiency">energy-efficient</ref> housing and transportation, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universal%20Health%20Care">health care for all</ref>, protecting besieged <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ecosystems">ecosystems</ref>.  Practically, what this means is a higher base-line of essential services with the costs shared and supported broadly.  To be clear, our basic physical security deserves support, not gaming at the hands of profiteers.  A common wealth for all citizens is possible, with local regional flavors in commerce and culture atop this "baseline" of security.  To be danced out of the way, one finds the current heavy-handed players of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/agribusiness">agribusiness</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pharmaceuticals">pharmaceuticals</ref>, energy, insurance and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military-industrial%20complex">congressional-military-industrial complex</ref> all dependent upon "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/corporate%20socialism">corporate socialism</ref>" for subsidies and protection from real, meaningful, positive change and shielded from probing questions as to why, for example, we so frequently go to war.</p>
</text>
