<text id="autogum_interview_doc1119" title="part4_Murray Hill on the life and versatility of a New York drag king" shortTile="partmurray-hill-life" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-18" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Murray_Hill_on_the_life_and_versatility_of_a_New_York_drag_king" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think people think of when they hear ‘drag king’?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  I’m not really sure.  I think that they immediately think <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/lesbian">lesbian</ref> and sexuality as a show, as a spectacle.  It’s a longer discussion, with drag queen and somebody like Justin Bond and somebody like Lady Bunny.  They are two totally different types of people and perform two different types of ways.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lady%20Bunny">Lady Bunny</ref> is a drag queen—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Who is rarely divorced from that personality—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  Well, who knows.  I’ve known her for ten years and I’ve only known her as Lady.  Justin Bond doesn’t go by drag queen; he says he is a transgendered artist.  It’s much more fluid.  And I think I’m more in that camp.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Then there’s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lypsinka">Lypsinka</ref>, who very much sees it as a character.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  Yes, as an actor playing a character.  I’m more in the Justin vein.  The lines are more blurred.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think it’s less acceptable to be a drag king or a drag queen?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  The differences are unparalleled.  Drag kings have it rough.  I just had a reviewer say some really inappropriate things about me, and I always say to myself, ‘Would they ever say that about Lady Bunny?’  They were questioning genders and names and this, talking about body parts.  Drag queens have been in the culture forever.  They’ve had mainstream visibility and success.  Drag kings are just not comparable.</p>
<head id="The_gay_community_and_drag_artists">The gay community and drag artists</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think you get it worse from the gays or worse from the mainstream?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  I’ve worked very hard, and I still have to work very hard to be recognized by the gay media, because most of it is run by gay men.  They’ve been very supportive, but I’ve had to really push them.  I think mainstream doesn’t ever know what’s going on, but the press has been good to me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_gossip_columnist_Michael_Musto_on_the_art_of_celebrity_journalism">I interviewed Michael Musto</ref> and he spoke about how younger gays are embracing their femininity more and have overcome body fascism; but in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/RuPaul_speaks_about_society_and_the_state_of_drag_as_performance_art">my interview with RuPaul</ref> she said almost the exact opposite.  She felt men using femininity as part of their emotional palate is still considered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anathema">anathema</ref>.  What do you think about how gender is seen today among younger people?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MH:</hi>  It’s definitely different now.  RuPaul does a lot of touring, and it’s very different when you leave New York.  I have noticed the last five years in New York that the lesbian, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butch">butch/femme</ref> thing has eroded.  It’s much more fluid and multi-gendered.  I think the gay guy scene is like that.  If you go to Williamsburg and the East Village gay male scene, it’s completely what Michael said.  RuPaul doesn’t hang out in that scene anymore.  He was here in the 1980s and it was very different.</p>
</text>
