<text id="autogum_interview_doc635" title="part0_Wikinews holds a follow-up interview with Max Riekse, Constitution Party candidate for the 2008 U.S. presidential election" shortTile="partwikinews-holds" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-04-25" dateModified="2013-04-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_holds_a_follow-up_interview_with_Max_Riekse%2C_Constitution_Party_candidate_for_the_2008_U.S._presidential_election" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews holds a follow-up interview with Max Riekse, Constitution Party candidate for the 2008 U.S. presidential election</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, April 25, 2008</hi></p>
<p>In March, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> held an exclusive interview with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20third%20party%20presidential%20candidates,%202008#Constitution_Party">Max Riekse</ref>, one of the candidates for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitution%20Party%20(United%20States)">Constitution Party</ref> nomination for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008%20United%20States%20presidential%20election">2008 United States presidential election</ref>. With the Constitution Party's national convention underway this weekend, we spoke with him one last time before he either becomes his party's candidate or loses.</p>
<p>Riekse is a retired decorated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lieutenant%20Colonel">Lieutenant Colonel</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Army">U.S. Army</ref> who served in both the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vietnam%20War">Vietnam War</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq War</ref>. He is also a former public school teacher and Assistant Professor of Military Science at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Western%20Michigan%20University">Western Michigan University</ref>. He has a B.A. in Political Science and International Relations from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20South%20Florida">University of South Florida</ref> as well as two M.A.s, one in Political Science and International Relations, the other in Education and History. Both are from Western Michigan University.</p>
<p>We asked him if he thinks he has a good shot at winning the Constitution Party nomination and ultimately the presidency. He replied, "I will know Saturday the 26th if I win the nomination of the Constitution Party. As to wining the general election, I'm very sure that I will do far better then we have done in the previous 20 years as a 'third' party.  I'm not only more qualified to be commander in chief then either the Democrat or Republican, but will be far better for the country."</p>
<p>When asked about America's illegal immigration problem he replied, "I will send all 20 to 30 million home. End birth right babies; no social security for them, etc. They are here illegally; now what part of that does anyone not understand?"</p>
<p>Riekse is running for president because "the Republicans and Democrats would not be having candidates that would solve the problems we have in this country and I know that I could do a lot better with my 32 years of military experience and over 20 years in Education, both in the K-12 public school venue and teaching at the University level."</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">In the March interview, you told us why you're running for president. For those who may not have read it, please tell us again.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Lt. Colonel Riekse:</hi> I started to run for President because I know the Republicans and Democrats would not be having candidates that would solve the problems we have in this country and I know that I could do a lot better with my 32 years of military experience and over 20 years in Education, both in the K-12 public school venue and teaching at the University level. Also I did not care for our party focusing on having a Republican lead our party in 2008; I also think we can do better with my heading the Constitution Party ticket this year then we have in the past;  The number of votes we have received in past presidential elections has been pathetic giving our national platform &amp; ideal's.  I think I can do a lot better; and in the process, raise the number of votes our candidates receive for national, state and local offices.</p>
</text>
