<text id="autogum_interview_doc015" title="part3_Wikinews attends 2018 Bangalore ComicCon" shortTile="partwikinews-attends" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-11-21" dateModified="2019-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_attends_2018_Bangalore_ComicCon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Well so, how to you maintain continuity and fluidity of the story across the pages?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">ROS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  By being very diligent before I write it. So if I've, I am a big believer that you should outline everything. So before I write the script I've got it all planned out, I know which character's gonna go where; so that I don't have to make it up and hope I can remember what's all going to happen. If I have got it all laid out, "okay, Issue #1 <hi rend="italic">this</hi> happens. Issue #2 <hi rend="italic">this</hi> happens." I have got a flow chart of all the characters and where they are. That, it might be a bit overkill but for me, it keeps it all. Of course, when I sit down to write, then I just ignore it and do whatever I want. But yeah, outlining is the way to make sure the story flows the way I want it to.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you enjoy movie adaptations of comics?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">ROS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I do, yeah. For different reasons. I like, I really enjoy <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Walking%20Dead">The Walking Dead</ref></hi>. I know it's not a movie, but, actually, no, it is! There a movie coming out. I really enjoy that because, what I find fascinating is it is very different from the comic, but it appeals to the same idea, the same feel. Because in comic, certain characters set stories, and in the show, they put the same stories, but they mix all the characters up, like who is doing what, so you still don't know who's going to die, who is going to be the hero, who is going to be the villain, and I like that unpredictability. I don't like the idea of taking a comic and making it exactly the same in the film. I think that you should translate it to a new medium and use that new medium to its most potential. So, yeah, I really enjoy them a lot. Ah, and yeah, obviously the Marvel films too.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Who were your mentors?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">ROS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  My mentors? Me. I am my mentor. Because a lot of comics is self-learned. But if you would say "Who inspires me?", "Which writers?" I would say, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vladimir%20Nabokov">Vladimir Nabokov</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20Joyce">James Joyce</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herman%20Melville">Herman Melville</ref>. [...] They're probably the writers who, essentially any writer who is angry, and argues a lot in their books, they are the ones I tend to like. I think, okay, I think <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eminem">Eminem</ref></hi> is probably my real, my real influence.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  If you could travel back in time, what advice would you give to your younger self?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">ROS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  [Pauses for a while] "Stop partying so much, go home, and write. Because it takes ages, and you are going to regret [all] this time spent partying. Because ultimately what you want to do with your life, Ryan, isn't party, it's to write. So get on with it." That's what I'ld tell twenty-year-old Ryan. But I'd tell fourteen-year-old Ryan: "Ignore mum and dad. Keep playing video games; it's gonna help in the long run."</p>
</text>
