<text id="autogum_interview_doc048" title="part0_Wikinews interviews three figures from Donald Trump&amp;apos;s political past" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-03-12" dateModified="2016-05-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_three_figures_from_Donald_Trump%27s_political_past" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews three figures from Donald Trump's political past</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, March 13, 2016</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Donald Trump in 2011.Image: Gage Skidmore.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> spoke with three people associated with the early political career of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> businessman <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref>, the front-runner for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_of_the_United_States">Republican Party</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2016">2016 presidential nomination</ref>.  Those interviewed include longtime political operative <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Roger_Stone">Roger Stone</ref>, a close associate of Trump and director of Trump's 2000 presidential exploratory committee; journalist Dave Shiflett, co-writer of Trump's 2000 campaign book <hi rend="italic">The America We Deserve</hi>; and political consultant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russ%20Verney">Russ Verney</ref>, who served as chairman of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Reform_Party_of_the_United_States_of_America">Reform Party of the United States of America</ref> which Trump briefly joined.</p>
<p>In Trump's highly publicized 2016 campaign, he has run under the banner of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Make%20America%20Great%20Again">Make America Great Again</ref>, advocating a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexican</ref>-funded wall along the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mexico–United%20States%20border">U.S.–Mexico border</ref>, renegotiation of trade terms with other nations, and a temporary halt on the immigration of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islam">Muslims</ref> to the United States.  He holds a considerable lead in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2016%20Republican%20National%20Convention">Republican National Convention</ref> delegates over his opponents, winning 15 of the first 24 primary and caucus contests.  Though this is Trump's most visible campaign, it is not his first foray into electoral politics.  He flirted with Republican presidential runs: first in 1987, when he purchased newspaper advertisements on foreign policy and delivered a campaign-like speech in the first-in-the-nation primary state of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Hampshire">New Hampshire</ref>; and then in 2011, when he briefly led <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nationwide%20opinion%20polling%20for%20the%20Republican%20Party%202012%20presidential%20primaries">nationwide opinion polls</ref> for the presidential nomination after questioning the citizenship of President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>.  Trump's most extensive campaign before now came during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%202000">2000 presidential election</ref> when he opened an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/exploratory%20committee">exploratory committee</ref> to consider seeking the presidential nomination of the Reform Party. </p>
<p>For 2000, Trump conducted various speeches and media appearances in support of his potential presidential campaign.  He placed Stone in charge of his exploratory committee and hired Shiflett to work on what would become <hi rend="italic">The America We Deserve</hi>. His chief opponent for the nomination was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/paleoconservative">paleoconservative</ref> icon and eventual nominee <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pat_Buchanan">Pat Buchanan</ref> who entered the race after ending his third unsuccessful campaign for the Republican presidential nomination.  Based on Buchanan's comments against American involvement in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_War_II">World War II</ref>, Trump attacked Buchanan as a "<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Adolf_Hitler">Hitler</ref> lover" and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antisemitism">anti-Semite</ref>.  Trump's campaign received support from then-<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Minnesota">Minnesota</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor%20of%20Minnesota">governor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesse%20Ventura">Jesse Ventura</ref>, the highest ranking elected official in the Reform Party.  This placed Trump at odds with the faction of industrialist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ross%20Perot">Ross Perot</ref>, the party's founder and two time presidential candidate.  Verney, a Perot confidante, was chairman of the party during Trump's exploration.  Though initially dismissive of the campaign, Verney eventually welcomed Trump into the race.  However, the deep divisions within the party precipitated the exit of Ventura, and Trump did not seek the nomination.  Despite leaving the race, Trump still appeared on Reform Party presidential primary ballots in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Michigan">Michigan</ref>, winning both states.</p>
</text>
