<text id="autogum_interview_doc304" title="part10_Shimon Peres discusses the future of Israel" shortTile="partshimon-peres" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-06" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shimon_Peres_discusses_the_future_of_Israel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Do you think it’s hurt the peace process, the Lebanese War?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: I don’t think so.  You know what is promoting the peace prospect more than losing it?  That <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-Iranian%20sentiment">no one in the Middle East</ref> wants to fall under the spell of Iran.  Iran today is a country with an appetite.  An imperial appetite.  They want an Iranian hegemony in the Middle East in the name of god and enriched uranium.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iran-Arab%20relations">And nobody wants it</ref>.  So they <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Annapolis%20Conference">attended Annapolis</ref> for the same reason.  So everything, you know, it’s not a one-sided situation.  It’s very <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dialectic">dialectical</ref>, including Iran.  So they think they won.  What did they win?  They are less accused; they are not less watched, not less disliked and not less suspected.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Do you think there is still a strong peace movement in Israel?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: I think the situation is a peace movement because the more that the Arabs are learning, the more they are becoming peaceful.  Look, we have <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab%20citizens%20of%20Israel">in Israel 50,000 Arab citizens</ref> who are academicians.  Ask where are they.  Some of them are teachers who will remain in the vicinity of their university.  Most of them are doctors.  You won’t find in Israel today a hospital without Arab doctors and Arab nurses.  Now an Israeli that goes to the hospital, maybe he would be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-Arabism#Israel">reluctant to employ an Arab</ref> at his factory but he doesn’t hesitate to come to the hospital, lie on the bed and here comes an Arab doctor with a knife in his hand and operates on him.  And he says thank you.  So if you have healthy relations in hospitals, maybe it’s a cure for the others.  The more people who become professional and modern from both sides, this is the peace movement!  The peace movement is not an attempt to write more songs about peace.  We have enough songs.  What we need is the development and we have to be passionate.</p>
<head id="On_American_politics">On American politics</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: How have you seen America’s role in the peace process change between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foreign%20policy%20of%20the%20Clinton%20Administration">Clinton</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foreign%20policy%20of%20the%20George%20W.%20Bush%20administration">Bush</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Look at America after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20general%20elections,%202006">the elections</ref>.  In my journal, the two parties will come together and try to work up a bipartisan policy.  You know somebody said that the difference between the Republicans and Democrats is the Democrats are reformers and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Republican%20Party">Republicans</ref> are maintainers.  So they put in a little bit the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Democratic%20Party">Democrats</ref> to reform, then they put in the Republican to maintain.  Then they change, but they keep basic on foreign affairs; America is revolutionary in technology, in economy, but very balanced in foreign policy and even when the United States commits mistakes in her foreign policy, a foreign policy without America would be the greatest mistake of our generation.</p>
</text>
