<text id="autogum_interview_doc013" title="part1_Wikinews attends 2018 Bangalore ComicCon" shortTile="partwikinews-attends" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-11-21" dateModified="2019-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_attends_2018_Bangalore_ComicCon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>At 2 PM, there was a session with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AXN">AXN</ref>, and questions about AXN shows. Musician Shrey also played scores of various AXN shows on guitar, which audience had to guess. At 2:30 PM, there was a session with Cuban comic artist Vanesa Del Rey. She said it was her first convention in India, and said, "It is like any major convention in the US". This year, Vanesa Del Rey was nominated for an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eisner%20Award">Eisner Award</ref>. During the discussion, she said she wanted to do sci-fi epic,romance, mystery and thriller comics in future. Regarding romance genre in comics, she said it is "something worth exploring". And regarding her career choice, she said her grandmother was an artist and her "family was very supportive".</p>
<figure><caption>Session with Vanesa Del Rey.Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Acagastya">Agastya</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Later, there was a session with Sony PIX, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minions">Minions</ref> appearing on the stage.</p>
<p>The event finished around 8 PM.</p>
<head id="Interviews">Interviews</head>
<head id="Interview_with_English_comic_book_writer_Ryan_O'Sullivan">Interview with English comic book writer Ryan O'Sullivan</head>
<figure><caption>Comicbook writer Ryan O'Sullivan.Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Acagastya">Agastya</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Wikinews</caption></figure><p> Thank you for agreeing to the interview. So Mr O'Sullian, could you tell us something about yourself?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Ryan O'Sullivan</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  My name is Ryan O' Sullivan. I am a comic book writer from the UK. I have written books such as <hi rend="italic">Void Trip</hi> for Image Comics, <hi rend="italic">Fearscape</hi> for Vault Comics, as well as a lot of video game-based comics, like <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dark%20Souls">Dark Souls</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Evil%20Within">The Evil Within</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warhammer%2040,000">Warhammer 40,000</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic">Eisenhorn</hi>. So that's me in a nutshell.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How old are you, and when did you start writing comics?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">ROS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I am in my 30s, and I started writing comics, ah, well I don't know, I have been writing all my life, but I have done it professionally for, I'll say, two years now. Maybe three.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  How was your first job like?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">ROS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  My first — my <hi rend="italic">first</hi> job? Oh boy! [Laughs] That was um, it was interesting. So the first comic that I did was called <hi rend="italic">Turncoat</hi>, and that was purely online. So that everyday, we'd put another page of the comic out. And that's how I got known because people go online, they'd read the comic, and then after a certain amount of time, we'd collect it all together in a big comic, and they say that the first time you do a comic, you should make it small, you do a few pages just to learn it. But for mine, I did it for a hundred and sixty four pages  And I'm thrown in at the deep end, and somehow I managed to swim. But it was, it was pretty stressful, but was very fun[?].</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Well, so how many companies have you worked with?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">ROS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Oh! Um... I would say around half a dozen, at a guess [...] Image Comics, I have worked with Vault Comics, I've worked with T-Pub: that's a small UK publisher. I've worked with Titan Comics. And what's interesting is with the video game comics, that means I've worked with a lot of other companies as well, like video game companies, so, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bethesda%20Softworks">Bethesda</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SEGA">SEGA</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Relic%20Entertainment">Relic</ref>. I feel I'm missing people out now, just 'cause it's quite a lot. But yeah, it's been a lot of people. But I would say, of them all, if I could talk to fourteen-year-old Ryan, and tell him what his future would be like, the thing that might excite him the most is the fact that I wrote a comic for Warhammer and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Games%20Workshop">Games Workshop</ref>, because that's what was my jam as a kid.</p>
</text>
