<text id="autogum_interview_doc1384" title="part7_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  We could use a little more help from Clarence Page, again.  When I had the campaign against these lyrics—I had the “It’s Not Snitching, It’s Saving” campaign—Clarence was totally silent.  We’ve taken that head on, and had rappers attack us.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Banner">David Banner</ref> said “Al Sharpton can suck my so-and-so.”  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jay-Z">Jay-Z</ref> has a record out, and he's a friend of mine!  He says, “Don’t tell me Al Sharpton not to say '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/bitch">bitch</ref>'!”  They don’t attack Clarence Page they attack me because I’m attacking them.  Just look at the rappers attacking me.  So somebody should ask Clarence Page why they are attacking me if I’m not out there fighting them.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You are saying that black columnists,  whether it be Clarence Page or Juan Williams, who seem to have made their names by attacking a lot of the work done at the grass roots.  How can you change that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  I don’t think you can.  That’s their role.  If you go back to the sixties it was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl%20Rowan">Carl Rowan</ref> who used to attack Martin Luther King.  You have blacks who understand that one of the ways to get a job in the mainstream media is to attack black leaders.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Such as Juan Williams?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Oh, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan%20Williams">Juan Williams</ref> who works at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Fox_News">Fox</ref>?  Juan Williams works for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rupert%20Murdoch">Rupert Murdoch</ref> and wants to ask <hi rend="italic">me</hi> about accountability?  I mean, really.  He works for Rupert Murdoch and wants to ask me about accountability.  I think he was mad because a Republican donated some money to the National Action Network.  And you work for Rupert Murdoch.  Because we are on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Word%20Network">The Word Network</ref> we should have gone to a rally for The Word Network.  It’s ridiculous.  Again, what do they do?  The main thing they write about is criticism of black leaders.  If you read their columns you understand what their job is.  “White leadership is never at fault.  Government is never at fault.  It’s black leaders.”  What’s ironic is the ones they <hi rend="italic">do</hi> praise—<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bill_Cosby">Bill Cosby</ref> does my radio show maybe once a month.  Real close with me.  They praise Cosby, but never talk about the fact that Cosby and I work together on these very issues.  And Cosby supports what I do.  How do they reconcile that?  Because they understand that part of their compact with the right wing is that they’ll beat up on Al Sharpton, or Jackson, or whoever, because they are black.</p>
<head id="Why_the_need_for_an_Al_Sharpton?">Why the need for an Al Sharpton?</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  At Thanksgiving we were talking about the different voices for different communities, and I said that there is no <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hispanic">Latino</ref> "Al Sharpton"—the Cubans used to have <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jorge%20Mas%20Canosa">Jorge Mas Canosa</ref>, but nobody has taken his place—nor is there an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Asia">Asian</ref> "Al Sharpton".  With the black community it seems like Americans are always looking for <hi rend="italic">the</hi> voice.  Do you think that your visibility has been externally imposed?</hi></p>
</text>
