<text id="autogum_interview_doc014" title="part2_Wikinews attends 2018 Bangalore ComicCon" shortTile="partwikinews-attends" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-11-21" dateModified="2019-07-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_attends_2018_Bangalore_ComicCon" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  So, would you classify yourself as a freelancer?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">ROS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I would say so, yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  And do you plan just working for a company, or would you like to carry on freelancing?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">ROS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I enjoy freelancing, because it gives me the freedom to work whenever I want, and do whatever projects I like. And no one person is in-charge of me, and that's really fun.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What does a normal day at work look for you?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">ROS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I wake up. I have coffee. I write all day, until I can't write anymore. Then I have more coffee. Then I read until I can't read anymore. And then I fall asleep. Seven days in the week. That's my life. Sometimes I escape to ComicCons like this.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  What are the changes in the comic book industry that you have noticed?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">ROS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I've noticed that a lot of diverse voices are becoming more prominent recently. And I think that's, it's because I think in society in general, diverse voices from different cultures, different backgrounds, different sort of sects and preferences and whatnot are becoming a lot more prominent in general. And with comics being on the edge, the fringe medium, that tends to accumulate whatever is coming, a lot quicker than say film or other mediums. So I think that new voices is one big thing, one big part of comics. And also, diversification of how it is published. So now it's not just comics in comics stores, you've also got bookstores, you've got online, you've got digital, you've got web-comics like I told you, that I did. So there's a lot more avenues for people to get involved, make their own comics, [...]. I mean, ComicCon India is an exact example of the growing comic market.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Who was your favourite super-hero?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">ROS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  My favourite super-hero is actually a super-villain. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctor%20Doom">Doctor Doom</ref>. Because he is just the biggest badass ever. He's inspired so many villains. He inspired Darth Vader. The guy is just the coolest character ever. So I have not had a chance to write him yet, but if I do, I have got a few stories up my sleeve.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you have some head-cannons regarding that and you will write fan-fiction about it?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">ROS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  I don't write fan-fiction, but I do have a few ideas in my head for how [Doctor] Doom could play.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">A</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Could you brief me about the process from, how an idea comes, and goes to the publication, and it is in the hands of any reader?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">ROS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  You mean like,how does it go from being an idea in my head to a comic in someone's hand? Okay; well, typically, I will come up with an idea and you don't know where you get your ideas from, they appear out of the blue, just jump into your brain, and if they stay around for a while, you can't get rid of them just by ignoring them, that means you have to write them. So what happens usually is I will write on a one-page sheet, of what the comics is about, what my idea for the story would be. And then I find an artist who likes that idea, and I team with them, and I write the script, and the artists will take the scripts off me and draw it, and I will say, "Okay, first page, I want a picture of <hi rend="italic">this</hi>, picture of <hi rend="italic">this</hi>, <hi rend="italic">this</hi> dialogue, and <hi rend="italic">this</hi> dialogue." And then, once we have created the first issue, we'll send that to a publisher, they will proof[read] it, check the spelling mistakes, there's not many of them. And what they do it to print it and send it out to stores. So that would be the "short-and-sweet" way it works.</p>
</text>
