<text id="autogum_interview_doc1163" title="part1_Wikinews interviews journalist Konrad Godlewski, who uncovered BATUTA hoax" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-02-08" dateModified="2010-02-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_journalist_Konrad_Godlewski%2C_who_uncovered_BATUTA_hoax" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p>The second one was the attitude towards streets and generally Poland's communist past. As one could easily guess, Batuta's Army had rather right-wing political views, most probably close to IPN [e.d. note: Instytut Pamięci Narodowej/IPN, English: National Memory Institute is a governmental agency in Poland conducting both criminal investigations and scientific research into the country's communist past], which fights against communist streets' namesakes.    </p>
<p>And there was a third reason. As I'm sure you remember, in the 90s, conspiracy theories concerning Jews were popular in Poland. As some of the people of such origin had changed their names, the conspiracy theory made people see Jews nearly everywhere. Such lists were printed on paper and later they got published on the Internet.</p>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold"> It's a bit strange. Having right-wing views, the Army caused the right-wing websites, which copied the hoax from Wikipedia, to get discredited as an effect of this.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Not all right-wing people are uneducated individuals with antisemitic views. </p>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold"> The same IP number (which is dynamic but from a narrow range) which was used to create the hoax, is still being used today to edit Wikipedia. For example, quite recently someone tried to smuggle in a biography of "Hipolit Pieściuk – sculptor and social activist". Google shows no information on this biography. They've added just text, not an article. Does it mean they have not give up on Wikipedia? Your article in "Gazeta Wyborcza" ended with the words "Batuta's Army is asking for anonymity and claims that Henryk Batuta is not their last word".</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I haven't heard about Hipolit. As far as I know, Batuta's case actually turned up to be their last word. As far as I know those people have made careers and they now have more serious things to care about. </p>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold"> So they don't want to reveal themselves?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I imagine it wouldn't look good in their CVs. There are people who think of such scam as a point of honor. I don't think that's the case with Batuta's Army. Anyway, this case had also had an effect on me. Before the Batuta story I had made a few trial editions in Wikipedia. But later something turned me on. I thought there was a group of idealistic people who want to make humanity happier with their meticulous work. And someone tried to make idiots of them. </p>
<p>((WN))<hi rend="bold"> So you've started to develop articles up to featured article standards.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">KG</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Don't exaggerate. I've written just one such article. But thanks to this, I've realized how important Wikipedia had become. I don't think there is single journalist who doesn't use it.  <figure rend="Konrad godlewski.jpg"></figure></p>
</text>
