<text id="autogum_interview_doc598" title="part3_Wikinews interviews John Wolfe, Democratic Party presidential challenger to Barack Obama" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-05-19" dateModified="2013-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_John_Wolfe%2C_Democratic_Party_presidential_challenger_to_Barack_Obama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How do you feel about the support you received from the conservative publication, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Weekly%20Standard">The Weekly Standard</ref></hi>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: Well, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20Kristol">Mr. Kristol</ref> can publish whatever he wants to. It sure surprised me.  But Mr. Kristol is a very keen observer. I don't always agree with him on what he writes, but he is one of the most articulate spokesmen in American politics.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">In the interview you had with <hi rend="italic">The Weekly Standard</hi>, you said that you are the only Democratic challenger to Obama that is actively campaigning. What kind of activities do you take part in for the campaign?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: Well, what we do is we call people. We make sure we get our message out.  We're on the radio every now and then and we haven't bought any TV or radio ads yet; they're a little bit too expensive, but we're going to try to, here toward the end, to get on the radio to get our message out in a more conventional way. And we have recently bought some inserts, things like that, for the newspaper. And gotten our message out to some of the people in Arkansas. It's a very expensive thing.</p>
<p>This campaign has been something I've wanted to do, but I've had to make a lot of personal sacrifices to do it.</p>
<head id="Challenging_the_incumbent">Challenging the incumbent</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">I mentioned that interview you had with <hi rend="italic">The Weekly Standard</hi>. During that interview, you said that you opposed <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Same-sex_marriage">same-sex marriage</ref> even though you backed the repeal of "<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Don't_ask,_don't_tell">Don't ask, don't tell</ref>". Might this hurt you with Democrats looking for a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressivism%20in%20the%20United%20States">progressive</ref> alternative to Barack Obama?</hi></p>
<p><p><hi rend="bold">Wolfe</hi>: Yeah my record on so much of the issue, on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/LGBT">gay rights</ref>, I mean I have a good record on it. In 1979 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memphis,%20Tennessee">Memphis</ref> when I was part of the student government, I was the adviser and also the so-called attorney general, I mean, there were issues that came up on the campus where they wanted to ban gay meetings. This was back in '79. I stood up there in 1979 and told the people they were wrong for doing it. In 2010, before the most <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conservatism%20in%20the%20United%20States">conservative</ref> audience ever in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cleveland,%20Tennessee">Cleveland, Tennessee</ref>, this is on video tape, I said, no, let's get rid of don't ask, don't tell, it's not right. If someone wants to serve their country, they should. You only want heterosexuals to spill blood for the country? Don't you think the sacrifice ought to be equally borne? I came out against don't ask, don't tell before anybody else around this section of the country. I don't think it was right then, and I don't think it's right now.</p>
<p><figure><caption>Wolfe speaks at a Congressional candidates forum in 2010.Image: millermz.</caption></figure></p>
<p>I am for equality. I just have a little bit of a hard time with accepting gay marriage. I got to look into it a little bit more and see what the ramifications of it are. But I think that the idea of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/hate%20crime">hate crimes</ref> and longer sentences for hate crimes is a good idea because people do commit those. They don't just commit it against the individual. They will tend to be recidivist because they don't just hate an individual, they hate the whole group. And when they do that, of course you have longer sentences because that means their rate of doing it again is going to be higher than somebody that just commits an individual crime against an individual. They're going against the whole race. The same thing would be true for somebody that wanted to beat up <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jews">Jewish people</ref>, or they wanted to assault <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Catholic_Church">Catholics</ref>, or whoever. Sure there should be more time. There should be a special classification for hate crimes. I think the idea of no discrimination by the federal government in hiring based on sexual orientation is the right kind of law to make. I think there should be equality.</p></p>
</text>
