<text id="autogum_interview_doc1416" title="part1_Interview with U.S. Republican Presidential candidate Tom Tancredo" shortTile="partinterview-us" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-09-25" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_U.S._Republican_Presidential_candidate_Tom_Tancredo" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  There are an estimated 12 million illegal aliens in the U.S. To round up and deport millions of people would be a major government undertaking, requiring massive federal spending and invasive enforcement. What level of funding would be necessary for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Department%20for%20Immigration%20and%20Customs">U.S. Immigration and Customs</ref> to achieve the level of enforcement that you'd like to see?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  Only a relatively slight increase because the only thing you have to do, other than building a barrier on the southern border, is go after employers.  We need to go aggressively after the employers, and try to identify some of the more high profile employers who are hiring illegal aliens.  Go after them with fines, and if they are not only hiring them but also conspiring to bring them in, then they could go to jail.  A perp walk would have a chilling effect.  If you break that magnet, most illegal aliens would go home voluntarily.  An article in the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rocky%20Mountain%20News">Rocky Mountain News</ref></hi> stated there has been an employer crackdown in Colorado, and that they are going home or moving on to other states.  If we did it nationally, they will return home, because the jobs are no longer available.  It doesn’t have to happen over time or instantaneously.  The costs to the American public for 12 million illegals are enormous and far more than are paid for by the illegal immigrants themselves in taxes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How long would full enforcement take for you to succeed?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  It would be a couple of years before employers were weaned off illegal immigrants and then a couple more years before you saw a really significant reduction.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Can you explain your remarks about bombing the Islamic holy sites of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mecca">Mecca</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medina">Medina</ref> as a deterrent to terrorists operating against the United States.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  The question I was answering was "What would you do if Islamic terrorists set off on or more nuclear devices in the United States?"  My response was that we would need to come up with a deterrent, and that deterrent may very well be a threat to take out their holy sites if they did something like that in the United States.  I still believe it is something we must consider as a possible deterrent because at the present time there are no negative consequences that would accrue to the people who commit a crime such as a nuclear, chemical or biological attack.  There are no negative consequences; they may die in the attack but that is not a negative consequence for them.  Usually they aren’t going to be state actors.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But wouldn’t an attack on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mecca">Mecca</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medina">Medina</ref> be an attack on a sovereign state?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TT:</hi>  You are not attacking the state, but the religious ideology itself.  Holy sites are not just in Saudi Arabia; there’s a number of them.  In fact, Iran has one of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holiest%20sites%20in%20Islam">holiest cities in Islam</ref>.  And I never used the word nuclear device; I was talking about taking out a physical structure.  The reason I suggested it as a possible deterrent is because it is the only thing that matches the threat itself.  The threat is from a religious ideology.  Not just from Islam, but from a nation whose requirements include jihad against infidels, and we are a threat to their culture, which is why they believe we need to be destroyed.  We must understand what motivates our opponents in order to develop a successful response. I’ve received death threats, enormous criticism, and I’ve been hung in effigy in Pakistan, but nobody has given me an alternative strategy that would be a deterrent to such an event.  I guarantee when you read the national intelligence estimates, you would be hard pressed to not walk away from doing something.</p>
</text>
