<text id="autogum_interview_doc721" title="part6_Author of My Billion Year Contract reflects on life in elite Scientology group" shortTile="partauthor-billion" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-01-13" dateModified="2012-10-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Author_of_My_Billion_Year_Contract_reflects_on_life_in_elite_Scientology_group" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Scientology now has "Fixed Donations" the weirdest oxymoron I have ever heard.</p>
<figure><caption>Scientologists working in the organization's "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rehabilitation%20Project%20Force">Rehabilitation Project Force</ref>" in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los%20Angeles,%20California">Los Angeles</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref> Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Martin%20Ottmann">Martin Ottmann</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Looking back on your experiences in Scientology, you describe several instances in the book where you considered leaving the organization or at least leaving the Sea Org - most notably when you were ordered into the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rehabilitation%20Project%20Force">Rehabilitation Project Force</ref>" while you were pregnant. (pp. 85-94.)  Why did you choose to stay?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: I felt I had no choice but to stay, we had no non-scientology people in our lives to give us safety and help us get on our feet.  I was five months pregnant –who is going to give me a job.  And we literally had no money.  We had been with them as a group and only with them as a group for about a decade, you lose touch with family friends etc who are not scientologists.  If we left we would be put on the “to be shunned list” and none of our public Scientologists who had jobs for us could help us, without severe consequences to them.</p>
<p>The people who had left before us, they become non persons and you have no idea where they went.  I wanted to leave without being put on the shunning list, which we eventually were able to do, that allowed us to get help from other friends who had previously left the Sea Org, but not Scientology.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> In the appendix of the book you reference and discuss <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Lucifer%20Effect">The Lucifer Effect</ref></hi> by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychologist">psychologist</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip%20Zimbardo">Philip Zimbardo</ref>. You cite how "Zimbardo isolated 7 social processes that grease the slippery slope of evil," and acknowledge, "I found myself in all of these seven steps, to a greater or lesser degree. ... In hindsight, I can see each on of these points were present in the apple barrel of Scientology that I lived through." Which of Zimbardo's steps were most applicable to your experiences in Scientology? Knowing what you know now from the knowledge in Zimbardo's book, how would you approach this differently in the future if placed in a similar situation again?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NM</hi>: The step for me was "Mindlessly taking the first step", there was no internet back then.  Books against Scientology had either been removed from the libraries or never been allowed to be printed.  The first class I took when I left Scientology was called "Critical Thinking" – If I had taken that course PRIOR to Scientology, I doubt I would have mindlessly taken that first step.</p>
<p>Today we have the internet, which allows us free speech, and we now have a lot of free speech about Scientology – They still try to "Steal the library books of the internet", but funny, now that just makes more copies.</p>
</text>
