<text id="autogum_interview_doc1056" title="part8_Past Eurovision contestants give advice to this year's performers, speculate on who will win" shortTile="partpast-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-05-06" dateModified="2015-09-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Past_Eurovision_contestants_give_advice_to_this_year%27s_performers%2C_speculate_on_who_will_win" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You pursued a bachelor's degree in international relations. How do you wish to utilize your degree? If you had to stop singing tomorrow, what kind of career would you want to pursue with the degree you hold?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sirusho</hi>: International affairs is something that had interested me. I like to learn. I always tend to learn more but I don't even want to think about stopping my career. I was born with it, it's a big part of who I am, and even if something happens to my vocal cords, I can go on with writing and producing songs for my colleagues...[but] enough about that; I still have so much in me to give to my
audience!</p>
<head id="Tajči">Tajči  </head>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tajči">Tajči</ref>, born Tatjana Matejaš, shot to fame in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yugoslavia">Yugoslavia</ref> at the age of 19, achieving diamond sales with her signature hit "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hajde%20da%20ludujemo">Hajde da ludujemo</ref>"</hi> (Let's Go Crazy). <hi rend="italic">She performed the song at the Eurovision Song Contest in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%201990">1990</ref>, held in her hometown of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zagreb">Zagreb</ref>, and placed seventh. The war in the former Yugoslavia cut her career short, and she moved to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>, where she has lived for the past 17 years. She now tours with her husband across the United States, performing selections of contemporary Christian music. At 38, she is overjoyed to "have it all": a family of her own and the chance to make music on her own terms. Her career is chronicled on her <ref target="http://www.idobelieve.com">website</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What projects are you working on? What can your fans in both America and in Europe expect to see from you this year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tajči</hi>: Apart from my regular tours, which I do four a year, I am working on a show called "Need a Break," which is a bit of a step from my spiritual music and more "everyday." It's more what mothers go through, with marriage and kids. It's a funny show. What I do well is I tell stories. It's how I am. It's who I am. It's why pop music didn't work for me as an artist. This new format is great for me, it's very fulfilling and I'm very excited and looking forward to it, being able to do that and explore musical styles.</p>
<p>I'm also hoping to go to Zagreb this year and bring my new music to them. I think it's time. I've been away for 17 years, and they still play my old music, and occasionally I go there and do radio and television interviews...I don't know, it's time for them to see what I'm doing. Anyone can see my stuff online, but what I do best is live; there's a lot of energy and power there that you can't really see in a recording or in a video. It's different when you're actually in the room. I want to bring it to them and say, "Here, my countrymen, my old fans, this is who I am now. This is how I grew over the last 17 years." Kind of like a reunion.</p>
</text>
