<text id="autogum_interview_doc201" title="part2_BDSM as business: Interviews with Dominatrixes" shortTile="partbdsm-business" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-28" dateModified="2008-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BDSM_as_business%3A_Interviews_with_Dominatrixes" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  —would be that same way.  Someone who wouldn’t be into it and be like, “How could you even think something like that? That’s gross, that’s disgusting!”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  So here you were thinking he hated you, but really he just had—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  —this one little thing, this one little fetish that really isn’t a big deal.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you still with him?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Had you ever done explored BDSM before, or was it a new thing for you when he expressed it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  We played a little bit, because I’m just kind of kinky like that, but he never said anything.  He said nothing.  So I didn’t know what was going on or what the problem was, until he finally told me he has a fetish.  From there we went to a film shop on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/42nd%20Street%20(Manhattan)">42nd Street</ref> where all the porn can be found, and we found some fetish videos on bondage.  It just developed from there, and I started enjoying it more and more, and I wanted to know more about it on a psychological level than anything else.  So I started to become a dom.  I saw an ad on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Craig's%20List">Craig's List</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How long ago was that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  About two years ago.  I decided if I am going to learn more about it I should learn from the pros! [<hi rend="italic">Giggles</hi>]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  And how long have you been doing this, Alex?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  About two years, also.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How long do you see yourself doing this?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  I think I will always do it somewhat.  Professionally?  There’s going to be an end.  For myself, I usually like to do things in blocks of a few years.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I’m very much the same way.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  Yeah!  So I could see…I can’t imagine it anytime soon because I’m actually really happy with the way things are going right now, and I can’t imagine spending less time here.  But I imagine I will probably go down to just one day a week or I will be distracted by something else because I will be traveling or something.  So that’s for me.  I don’t know how much research you’ve done on the sex industry…you can’t really compare it with the sex industry, in places where women…it’s not like that; there’s really not an expiration, which is nice.  I think that might be a misconception.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Jada:</hi>  In that sense, older Doms are actually more respected.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Alex:</hi></hi>  Yeah!  Some are more sought out, they have experience.  It’s across the board; people have different types and they want different things.  That’s really nice.  It’s not really an issue as it is…</p>
</text>
