<text id="autogum_interview_doc938" title="part4_KKE: Interview with the Greek Communist Party" shortTile="partkke-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-05-13" dateModified="2019-09-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/KKE%3A_Interview_with_the_Greek_Communist_Party" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>For us, tourism and holidays are not a trade, they are a social right – for both the Greek workers and the tourists that will choose to visit our country. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Iain</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How do you respond to the assertion that 'democracy is the least-worst of all the political systems tried'? Would the Greek communists accept a multi-party system where some parties would be stridently advocating free-market economics?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Isabella</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Democracy is not synonymous with the number of parties that exist in a country. For example, today in Greece we have dozens of political parties but despite the fact that the vast majority of the population opposes the austerity measures, the Parties that have the majority support them. How is that democratic? Nearly all strikes in Greece over the last decade have been declared illegal by the bourgeois court. In the workplace, there is no other law but the law of the employer.</p>
<p>In the process of building an anti-imperialist anti-monopoly Front, there will be a social coalition of the small farmers, the self employed, or other poor popular strata that will follow the working class since that will be their objective interest. Besides, people’s power is the real democracy, since capitalists and monopolies do not exist: it’s the democracy which is guaranteed by the direct political action of millions of people – in their workplaces, in their industrial units, in their neighbourhoods, in their popular organisations.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Iain</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How would you respond to allegations that the recent protest from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acropolis%20of%20Athens">Acropolis</ref> was not appropriate for a historic monument?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Isabella</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> The Acropolis is more than a touristic attraction. For the Greek people, it is a symbol of hope and dignity. KKE made this symbolic demonstration in order to emphasize that the attack against the Greek working class is a preview of the attack that follows to the other European people. And that the struggle of the Greek working class is indeed at the moment a struggle that gives hope to all the peoples abroad, who suffer the same. From that point of view, our demonstration not only was not inappropriate, but actually highlighted the true meaning of the monument. And judging by the impact this symbolic occupation had, I would think it has been very successful as well!</p>
<p>Those who accuse us of ‘blasphemy’ are those who have been shamelessly privatising most historic and archaeological monuments in Greece during the last decades. In 1992, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Coca_Cola">Coca Cola</ref> used the Acropolis for a commercial, where the monument was built on bottles instead of columns! <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samsung">Samsung</ref> recently filmed its own commercial, let alone the various fashion shows that take place there. They have been selling out our beaches and forests to touristic monopolies and have been offering the monuments in order to promote commercial products – and that is not considered to be inappropriate. They accuse us of undermining tourism – in fact all visitors had free entry to Acropolis on that day!</p>
</text>
