<text id="autogum_interview_doc298" title="part4_Shimon Peres discusses the future of Israel" shortTile="partshimon-peres" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-06" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shimon_Peres_discusses_the_future_of_Israel" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="The_waning_importance_of_history">The waning importance of history</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Isn’t the answer to that question that wise decisions are made with a basis from memory?  Although a computer can have…</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: No, no.  Forget memory.  Look, the new age is unprecedented.  When something is unprecedented, it means it doesn’t have a past, doesn’t have a history.  It’s totally oriented on the future.  And whoever dwells in the past, doesn’t understand the future because the past is full of prejudices, of commitments.  It arrests us.  And then you say you won’t commit a mistake, so you’ll commit new mistakes.  It doesn’t matter.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: What about the adage, “Those who forget history are doomed to repeat it”?</hi></p>
<hi rend="bold">I say brains is the greater producer of wealth, not oil. It’s limitless, and you’ll see that the GNP of Israel is very close to the Saudis’. So they are 3 times larger than us and they have all the oil in the world. We have brains.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right"><hi rend="bold">—Peres, on whether the Arab states' oil wealth will eclipse Israel's prominence in the region.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: So they will make new mistakes.  Mistake is inevitable as long as there are human beings.  But you cannot repeat mistakes because the world is not built on repetition; it’s built on mutation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Don’t you think Darfur is repetition?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: I think Darfur is, again, the last, or among the last battles between old and new.  What are they fighting for?  What are they killing killing killing over?  They don’t carry futures.  It’s not a mistake.  It belongs to a past.  It doesn’t have a moment.  I am sure that the reasons for war are over, even though still there are wars which are an inertia from the past, a continuation that doesn’t make sense.  I’m answering your question.  The problem is how to enable the whole world to enter the new future, including the Arabs.  And there are already Arabs who did it.  Look at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accession%20of%20Turkey%20to%20the%20European%20Union">Turkey, who is knocking on the doors of the united Europe</ref>.  Why?  It’s not a geographic endeavor, it is an intellectual endeavor.  They say you can be <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20Islam%20and%20modernity">Muslim and modern</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS: Like Dubai?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">SP</hi>: Dubai…you must be very careful because Dubai is a small people with a large service sector.  The citizens of Dubai are almost unnoticed.  The rest are hired people.  Turkey is different.  Take Dubai or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qatar">Qatar</ref>; in Qatar you have 180,000 citizens with 700,000 foreign workers.  That also belongs to the past, because you see what’s happening: they live on oil.  Oil is not produced by human beings, the producer of oil is the land.  It takes a million years to produce oil without any human interferences.  The need for oil is growing, so the cost of oil goes up which is forcing people to go to alternative energies to balance it.  Just because oil is discovered doesn’t mean every year more and more and more people will pay for the same discovery.  To hell with you, I shall look for an alternative!  Even for Israel.  If you have to make a choice between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saudi%20Aramco">Saudi Arabia</ref> and the sun, it should go to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solar%20energy">sun</ref>.</p>
</text>
