<text id="autogum_interview_doc1348" title="part3_G20 protests: Inside a labour march" shortTile="partg-protests-inside" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-04-03" dateModified="2014-05-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/G20_protests%3A_Inside_a_labour_march" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>On the subject of the police's re-routing of the march, he says the new route is actually the synthesis of two proposals. Originally the march was to have gone from Camberwell Green to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Houses%20of%20Parliament">Houses of Parliament</ref>, then across the sites of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012%20Olympic%20Games">2012 Olympics</ref> and finally to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ExCel%20Centre">ExCel Centre</ref>. The police, meanwhile, wanted there to be no march at all.</p>
<p>The Metropolitan Police had argued that, with only 650 trained traffic officers on the force and most of those providing security at the ExCel Centre itself, there simply wasn't the manpower available to close main streets, so a route along back streets was necessary if the march was to go ahead at all. Cafferky is sceptical of the police explanation. "It's all very well having concern for health and safety," he responds. "Our concern is using planning to block protest."</p>
<p>He accuses the police and the government of having used legal, bureaucratic and even violent means to block protests. Talking about marches having to defend themselves, he says "if the police set out with the intention of assaulting marches then violence is unavoidable." He says the police have been known to insert "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agent%20provocateur">provocateurs</ref>" into marches, which have to be isolated. He also asserts the right of marches to defend themselves when attacked, although this "must be done in a disciplined manner". </p>
<p>He says he wasn't present at yesterday's demonstrations and so can't comment on the accusations of violence against police. But, he says, there is often provocative behavior on both sides. Rather than reject violence outright, Cafferky argues that there needs to be "clear political understanding of the role of violence" and calls it "counter-productive".</p>
<p>Demonstration overall, though, he says, is always a useful tool, although "a demonstration is always a means to an end" rather than an end in itself. He mentions other ongoing industrial actions such as the occupation of the Visteon plant in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enfield">Enfield</ref>; 200 fired workers at the factory have been occupying the plant since April 1, and states the solidarity between the youth marchers and the industrial workers.</p>
<figure><caption>Members of the International Bolshevik Tendency display signs and sell literature in Victoria Park Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Killing_Vector">Killing Vector</ref>.</caption></figure><p>I also speak briefly with members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International%20Bolshevik%20Tendency">International Bolshevik Tendency</ref>, a small group of left-wing activists who have brought some signs to the rally. The Bolsheviks say that, like the Socialists, they're Trotskyists, but have differences with them on the idea of organization; the International Bolshevik Tendency believes that control of the party representing the working class should be less democratic and instead be in the hands of a team of experts in history and politics. Relations between the two groups are "chilly", says one.</p>
</text>
