<text id="autogum_interview_doc1448" title="part0_Interview with Jimbo Wales" shortTile="partinterview-jimbo" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-12-05" dateModified="2018-05-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Jimbo_Wales" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with Jimbo Wales</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 10, 2005</hi></p>
<p>While this wasn't <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interview%20with%20the%20Vampire">Interview with the Vampire</ref></hi>, getting a live interview with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jimmy%20Wales">Jimmy Wales</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/en:Wikimedia%20Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref> is requiring more work and planning than ever. Four contributors to four different Wikinews language editions (with <ref target="https://sv.wikinews.org/wiki/Intervju%20med%20Jimmy%20Wales">Swedish</ref>, <ref target="https://nl.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview%20met%20Jimbo%20Wales%20op%205%20december%202005">Netherlands</ref>, and <ref target="https://pl.wikinews.org/wiki/Człowiek%20stojący%20za%20Wikipedią%20-%20wywiad%20z%20Jimbo%20Walesem,%20prezesem%20Fundacji%20Wikimedia">Polish</ref>) arranged to interview "Jimbo" in the Wikinews IRC channel, squeezed in before interviews with a periodical and a cable news source.</p>
<head id="Wikinews">Wikinews</head>
<p>The interview was held publically in the <ref target="irc://irc.freenode.net/wikinews">Wikinews IRC channel</ref> because <ref target="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref> was one of the prime topics for the interview. </p>
<p>Wikinews is approximately one year old, with the English and German editions premiering the first week of December 2004. Since then the project has produced more than 13,000 articles in 16 languages, including the recently added Hebrew, Russian, and Japanese.</p>
<p>The project has not been without its detractors, and the questions asked of Mr. Wales reflected some of the most common criticisms.</p>
Wikinews: Wikinews seems primarily dedicated to regurgitating what is already being published on main stream media news sources. Was this the vision for Wikinews?
<p>Jimmy Wales: I would not use the term '<ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/regurgitate">regurgitating</ref>', which sounds rather negative, but rather '<ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/synthesize">synthesis</ref>' which is a more subtle and more important process. This was always a part of the core vision for Wikinews, though of course we want to do a lot more in time.</p>
The wiki movements seem focused on local expertise; people work on things they are interested and expert in. Why is there very little local news on Wikinews, which it seems like it would be best qualified to produce?
<p>Wiki editing thrives on local knowledge, but 'local' in an <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/epistemology">epistemological</ref> sense, not necessarily in a geographical sense. For example, I personally know a lot more about world news on topics that interest me and could synthesize much better in those areas, than I know about local politicians where I live.</p>
Do you believe that Wikinews, or any of the Wiki projects qualify as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/meritocracy">meritocracy</ref>?
<p>I hope so.:-) Although the wiki process sometimes strikes people as being inherently favoring egalitarianism or anarchy, there is a certain sense in which the wiki editing tool is neutral to social structures. As a matter of simple description, it does turn out that users who do quality work end up having a lot more power than users who do bad work. So in that sense, yes, it is a meritocracy, but an informal one.</p>
"Current Events" is not "encyclopedic" enough to reside on Wikipedia! On many Wikipedia projects content have been moved to Wikibooks and Wikisource, shouldn't "Current Events" be transferred to Wikinews in the same way?
<p>I have no very strong opinion about this. Encyclopedia articles about current events are in many ways different from news articles about current events. I suspect we should have some parallel work going on, and Wikinews should be more prominently featured in this way on the Wikipedia homepage. But that's a big internal community discussion that other people know more about than I do.</p>
</text>
