<text id="autogum_interview_doc064" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Mark Everson, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-08-18" dateModified="2015-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Mark_Everson%2C_U.S._Republican_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Mark Everson, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 20, 2015</hi></p>
<figure><caption>File photo of Mark Everson Image: U.S. Government.</caption></figure>
<p>Former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commissioner%20of%20Internal%20Revenue">Commissioner of Internal Revenue</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark%20Everson">Mark Everson</ref>  took some time to talk with <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> about his campaign for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">U.S. Republican Party</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2016">2016 presidential nomination</ref>.</p>
<p>Everson served as Commissioner of Internal Revenue, the administrative head of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internal%20Revenue%20Service">Internal Revenue Service</ref> (IRS) from 2003 to 2007, during the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref> administration. After his departure, he briefly served as CEO of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/American_Red_Cross">American Red Cross</ref>, worked in the cabinet of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Indiana">Indiana</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor%20of%20Indiana">governor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitch%20Daniels">Mitch Daniels</ref>, and worked for the tax consulting firm <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/alliantgroup">alliantgroup</ref>. He announced his candidacy this past March with a sixteen-page open letter in which he outlined the six pillars of his campaign: amnesty for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illegal%20immigration%20in%20the%20United%20States">illegal immigrants</ref>, reinstatement of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/military%20draft">military draft</ref>, a promise to serve only a single presidential term, and calls for tax reform, deficit reduction, and corporate responsibility.</p>
<p>He was excluded from the August 6 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Fox_News">Fox News</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20Party%20presidential%20debates,%202016">Republican presidential debate</ref> and has been excluded from most <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nationwide%20opinion%20polling%20for%20the%20Republican%20Party%202016%20presidential%20primaries">presidential polls</ref>.  However, he is listed on the Republican Party's website as one of 18 candidates and filed a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Federal_Election_Commission">Federal Election Commission</ref> (FEC) complaint against Fox News for his exclusion from the August 6 debate. </p>
<p>With <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:William_S._Saturn">William S. Saturn</ref>‎, Everson discusses his 2016 campaign, the media blackout of his campaign, and his views on the presidency and the possible Everson administration.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<head id="2016_campaign_and_qualifications">2016 campaign and qualifications</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why run for president? Why not run for a lower office that you might be more likely to win and effect change?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mark Everson</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  The electorate is very unsettled. Americans are fed up with politics as usual, so there is a clear path for a nontraditional candidate. I have extensive private sector experience and know the government inside out, but do not carry the political baggage of ties to special interest groups. I have lived in nine states. As a result, I have seen and know America well, but do not have the deep ties to a particular state or community that would traditionally be associated with seeking a different office.</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What qualifications do you have that will assist you in executing the duties of president?</hi></item></list>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Everson</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  While I have not held elective office, my public service credentials meet or exceed those of many of the candidates in the race. My federal executive branch experience (at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Information%20Agency">USIA</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Department%20of%20Justice">DOJ</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office%20of%20Management%20and%20Budget">OMB</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Department%20of%20Treasury">Treasury</ref>) is greater than that of any candidate in the GOP contest. I managed the nation's immigration system under President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ronald_Reagan">Reagan</ref>, and in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Presidency%20of%20George%20W.%20Bush">administration of President George W. Bush</ref> was instrumental in the creation of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Department%20of%20Homeland%20Security">Department of Homeland Security</ref> and directed the nation's tax system as Commissioner of Internal Revenue. Immigration, homeland security and taxes are issues of critical importance to the country and central to the 2016 election.</p>
</text>
