<text id="autogum_interview_doc1269" title="part2_Two-time Eurovision entrant Edsilia Rombley discusses music, love, and her contrasting Contest experiences" shortTile="parttwotime-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-03" dateModified="2012-02-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Two-time_Eurovision_entrant_Edsilia_Rombley_discusses_music%2C_love%2C_and_her_contrasting_Contest_experiences" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">ER</hi>: I really didn't "expect" anything at the time. I was very young and was just very proud that I was given the opportunity to represent the Netherlands in this contest. The attention was a very new experience and I felt fortunate every step along the way that I was experiencing all these amazing things. I kept reminding myself to keep both feet firmly on the ground, because as easy as the success may have come at the time, I realised that it could end as quickly as it began.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You and Ruth Jacott before you are frequently remarked upon as "revitalizing" the "songfestival" with R&amp;B melodies. Do you think that the urban contemporary sound is what Dutch music needed at that time? Would you consider such a move an "Americanization" of Dutch pop music, and if so, do you think that's a good or bad thing?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">ER</hi>: To be honest I didn't really place the whole experience in such a wide perspective at the time. I just did my thing and it turned out great for me, as I still have a great musical career. I think Dutch pop music has always been influenced by America, this was set in long before I entered the Songfestival; on one hand I think this is a great thing, because America has so many great artists. It's just important that we, while embracing foreign influences, don't forget all the talents in the Netherlands, who make great Dutch music.</p>
<head id="Mainstream_record_success">Mainstream record success</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Your next albums after Eurovision were produced by Tjeerd Oosterhuis, who is now your husband. How did you end up in a partnership with him? And perhaps most importantly, how did you two fall in love?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">ER</hi>: I collaborated with his sister Trijntje Oosterhuis, who introduced me to her brother. So we got to know each other, friends at first, but in the end it wasn't only the musical collaboration that worked out great, we fell in love, and we've been together ever since. It's wonderful that I can share my passion for music with my partner.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">MH</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> You've done a fair bit of charity work, dedicating songs and concerts both to situations in Bangladesh and for the victims of the Indian Ocean tsunami. What kind of role do you think charity and giving plays in your life? How do you feel about artists who are more concerned with their own images and song rights than coming together to help others?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">ER</hi>: I always try to do good where I can, as long as the charity is something that touches me and my heart goes out to it. I cannot judge other artists on what they do, especially because I can also understand that you would want to keep those two things (your career as an artist and doing something for charity) separate.</p>
</text>
