<text id="autogum_interview_doc745" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Lloyd Helferty, Thornhill" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-07" dateModified="2013-04-19" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Green_Party_candidate_Lloyd_Helferty%2C_Thornhill" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Green Party candidate Lloyd Helferty, Thornhill</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, October 7, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Lloyd Helferty</hi> is running for the Green Party of Ontario in the Ontario provincial election, in the Thornhill riding. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref>' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>I ran for the Green Party initially for one reason: Peak Oil.  It was and still is an issue that is tremendously serious but is not given enough attention.  I believe it will in fact be the issue of this century.  But I have learned since then that there are many other serious related issues, such as climate change, that need to be tackled in an inventive way using an approach that relies on ingenuity and takes in a different perspective to the problem ~ and approach that looks at the entire system and its relationships to other problems rather than looking at each problem as if it were isolated.  We also need to look at problems using long-range thinking and not simply concentrating on the quick-fixes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I have run twice before in the Federal elections of 2004 and 2006 in Thornhill.  I am also on the board of directors of the Richmond Hill Naturalists, which gives me insight into local issues from the perspective of those working and studying natural systems (ecosystems) and their health and am a member of the Markham Conservation Committee as well, which gives me insight into programs that are being undertaken locally by the town.  I also have a longstanding relationship with some of the local community groups and understand some of the Regional issues affecting the quality of life of Thornhill residents.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Which of your competitors do you expect to pose the biggest challenge to your candidacy? Why?</hi></p>
<p>I believe that my candidacy stands alone.  In fact, I see my biggest “competitor” as the independent candidate, whom I believe will likely be taking a portion of votes that would have probably otherwise come to me [the so-called “protest” votes cast by voters who are fed up with main-steam politics and will vote for anyone except the big parties].  Of course, these are likely only a small number of people, and because I do have some name recognition in this riding, however small, I believe that people who are fed up with mainstream politics will still continue to gravitate toward the Green Party.</p>
</text>
