<text id="autogum_interview_doc1127" title="part5_Dalai Lama's representative talks about China, Tibet, Shugden and the next Dalai Lama" shortTile="partdalai-lamas-representative" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-13" dateModified="2013-08-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dalai_Lama%27s_representative_talks_about_China%2C_Tibet%2C_Shugden_and_the_next_Dalai_Lama" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you think is the thinking on the part of the Chinese government that this six year old boy would be a threat to their power?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  They sense their lack of legitimacy.  It’s weakness.  It’s fear of illegitimacy.  They think everything is going to blow up in their face.  In the long run it’s counterproductive.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It would seem that by the Chinese government installing their own person, they have created their own symbol of illegitimacy as opposed to allowing religious practice to happen whilst keeping their governmental authority intact.  They have created a symbol in the form of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gyancain%20Norbu">Gyancain Norbu</ref> of their illegitimacy and meddling in the cultural affairs.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  That’s right.</p>
<head id="Gyancain_Norbu,_the_boy_selected_by_the_Chinese_government">Gyancain Norbu, the boy selected by the Chinese government</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gyancain%20Norbu">Gyancain Norbu</ref>, the boy the Chinese government selected as the eleventh Panchen Lama, is a victim as well?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  As a good Tibetan, when he comes to his age of making his own decisions, which he is about that age—18 or 19—he will make the right decisions.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What would be the right decision?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  I think if he wants to pursue religious leadership, in Tibetan customs we have more than one reincarnation.  If he proves himself to be a good practitioner and religious leader, people will treat him as a reincarnation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But if he insists on his status as the Panchen Lama?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  If through his own contact and learning he proves himself to be worthy of being a reincarnation—as I said there is more than one reincarnation in our tradition—then people will treat him as a reincarnation.  It’s not a political institution.  Panchen Lama is a religious institution.  So you can have two reincarnations.  I don’t see it as a clash of interests.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But he has no legitimacy now as the Panchen Lama, where as the one the Dalai Lama selected <hi rend="italic">does</hi> have that legitimacy, is that correct?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  Yes, that’s right.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Gyancain Norbu has not made any statements?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  No.  Lately he has not been seen in public.  People are starting to ask questions and there have been speculative reports that he has escaped, or ran away.  There was speculation, but I can’t comment on this.  The fact is that lately has not been seen in public.  About a year or so ago he was prominently shown in public as a propaganda.  For some reason of late he has not been physically seen or made any statements attributed to him.  It raises questions, but I can’t comment on speculation.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do the Tibetan people think about him?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">TW:</hi>  People will respond to him when he comes out on his own.  I don’t think people have any bad feelings against him personally.  It’s not his fault.</p>
</text>
