<text id="autogum_interview_doc928" title="part3_An interview with gossip columnist Michael Musto on the art of celebrity journalism" shortTile="partan-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-05" dateModified="2014-11-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/An_interview_with_gossip_columnist_Michael_Musto_on_the_art_of_celebrity_journalism" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  Well, in the early days of the war when I was going on peace marches, I certainly didn't see any celebrities there.  And then came <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madonna">Madonna</ref> withdrawing that promotional video for <hi rend="italic">American Life</hi> because of some controversial image; even <hi rend="italic">Madonna</hi> didn't want to go there.  And then came, of course, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dixie%20Chicks">Dixie Chicks</ref>, who were crucified for one honest remark.  So, the celebrities held back when they saw your career could be devastated at that point for telling the truth.  And then suddenly it became okay to bash the war, to bash Bush, and everybody jumped on it.  Now it's almost cliche.  Sally Fields saying, 'If mothers ruled the world there'd be no war.'  Excuse me!  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hillary%20Clinton">Hillary Clinton</ref> is a mother and she voted for it.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barbara%20Bush">Barbara Bush</ref> is a mother.  So don't give me that horse shit.  They bleeped her, anyway.</p>
<head id="On_the_gay_community">On the gay community</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you think you play a certain role in the gay community?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  Yes.  I'm kind of the elder statesman, court jester and someone who has been there, knows history and can use that to comment on current situations.  I'm a critic, but I do it with humor, and I'm above all self-deprecating.  I make fun of myself before anybody, so that kind of frees me to lash out at other people.  I'm also <hi rend="italic">out</hi> about everything.  I've written columns about my promiscuity phases, and my seizure disorder...everything!  There's nothing I hold back from my readers and that allows me to go forth without hypocrisy into all kinds of subjects about public figures.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You are a sharp critic of the gay community, almost in the mold of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larry%20Kramer">Larry Kramer</ref>—</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi> —not quite—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  —not completely, but in terms of criticizing apathy and the party lifestyle of the gay community where they do not focus on meaningful issues.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MM:</hi>  I differ from Larry in that I do not think the young generation are a bunch of morons who need to be lectured and told they are stupid and retarded.  I think they are brighter than ever; they just need a little guidance.  But I am a harsh critic of the gay community because I feel that when I first came out I thought I would be entering a world of nonconformity and individuality and, <hi rend="italic">au contraire</hi>, it turned out to be a world of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/gay%20clone">clones</ref> in a certain way.  You are expected to be a certain type of gay to move the community forward, whereas it has always been the fringe-y, crazy people who move it forward.  <hi rend="italic">We're</hi> the ones driving the bus, but we are the ones who are usually told to get in the back of the bus by the gay community.  I also hated the whole body fascism thing that took over the gays for a long time.</p>
</text>
