<text id="autogum_interview_doc748" title="part0_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Libertarian candidate Larry Stevens, Kitchener-Conestoga" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-04" dateModified="2008-11-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_Libertarian_candidate_Larry_Stevens%2C_Kitchener-Conestoga" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with Libertarian candidate Larry Stevens, Kitchener-Conestoga</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 4, 2007</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Larry Stevens</hi> is running for the Libertarian Party in the Ontario provincial election, in the Kitchener-Conestoga riding. Wikinews' Nick Moreau interviewed him regarding his values, his experience, and his campaign.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for further interviews; every candidate from every party is eligible, and will be contacted. Expect interviews from Liberals, Progressive Conservatives, New Democratic Party members, Ontario Greens, as well as members from the Family Coalition, Freedom, Communist, Libertarian, and Confederation of Regions parties, as well as independents.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Why have you chosen to involve yourself in the political process? Why did you choose to run in this constituency?</hi></p>
<p>Over the years, I've watched our politicians: do harm with programs they told us would do good, hurt the people they've told us they were going to help, and break one promise after another. I've also seen them give our tax money and lucrative government contracts to their friends. In the three years since my retirement, I've done a lot of investigation and come to the conclusion that  government regulations and programs are ineffective and many are actually harmful.</p>
<p>I've chosen to become involved in the political process and to run in this election because I think the people of Ontario need to be told about the abuses our government is inflicting on them.</p>
<p>When I retired, I moved from Toronto to South Kitchener. I really like this area and am seriously considering making my home here. What better place to take a stand and run for office.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What prior political experience do you have? What skills and insight can you bring to office, from other non-political positions you may have held?</hi></p>
<p>I've lived in Ontario all my life, have voted in virtually every election since I was eligible to vote, and I was a member of the board of a condominium corporation for several years.</p>
<p>I've worked as both and employee and a contractor for government, and for private industry in both the service sector and manufacturing. I've also owned and run my own small businesses in the service sector and manufacturing. As a result of this experience, I know how things are done in the public and the private sector.</p>
<p>I've developed skill in analysing problems and finding viable solutions through my education as a Mathematical Physicist and my career as a software developer. I've learned how to explain difficult concepts and unconventional or complex ideas through my education as a Secondary School teacher and during my career as a mentor to junior developers and a trainer of programming languages. These are skills I feel I need to get the Libertarian message across.</p>
</text>
