<text id="autogum_interview_doc1263" title="part1_Ontario Votes 2007: Interview with NDP candidate Sheila White, Scarborough-Rouge River" shortTile="partontario-votes" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-13" dateModified="2007-10-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ontario_Votes_2007%3A_Interview_with_NDP_candidate_Sheila_White%2C_Scarborough-Rouge_River" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>This has generally been a Liberal-held riding, but this time people are taking a real look. They don't feel good about supporting Dalton McGuinty because they don't want to condone someone who makes promises and doesn't keep them.</p>
<p>They know he'll say anything to get elected, then let them down after the election like he did last time. The Liberal incumbent has not made the transition well to provincial parliament. No one hears from him.  He doesn't fight on our behalf. He voted himself a 30 per cent pay increase but delivered nothing to the constituents who sent him to Queen's Park. They haven't seen any action on the issues that matter to them and their families nor have they seen any difference over the last four years under Dalton McGuinty. I represent the one party, the NDP, and the one leader, Howard Hampton, who can be counted on to fight for a fair deal for working families. Besides my overall merit, that's my biggest strength in the 2007 election.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What do you feel are the three most important issues to voters in your riding? Are these the same top three issues that are most important to you? What would you do to address these issues?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Health care</hi> (The Scarborough Hospital) (restore democracy and community respect to our local hospital) ; <hi rend="italic">environment and energy</hi> (bold, affordable energy efficiency and conservation strategy, action on greenhouse gases) ; <hi rend="italic">education</hi> (freeze tuition fees, fix education funding formula.)  <hi rend="italic">Transit, housing, property taxes, provincial downloading, child care, pension reform</hi>, there too many important issues to narrow them down to three.  Overall, making life easier and more affordable for the hardworking families of Scarborough-Rouge River.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What should be the first order of business in the 39th Legislative Assembly?</hi></p>
<p>First item of business: Swearing in Howard Hampton as Premier of Ontario.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Are the property taxes in your riding at a fair level for the amount of services received in the municipality?</hi></p>
<p>Property taxpayers are under siege, subjected to volatile upward swings as a result of market value assessment and a host of new fees being contemplated to cover McGuinty's downloading provincial services onto municipalities and not paying his bills. Some areas of Scarborough-Rouge River are particularly hard hit, which is unfair because the level of service hasn't risen proportionately and property tax is a regressive tax that has nothing to do with a person's ability to pay. Ontario's NDP has a plan to address this.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">How can the province lead the way in stimulating job creation?</hi></p>
<p>We can stimulate job creation by doing what worked well in British Columbia and have a Jobs Protection Act and Jobs Protection Commissioner. We can create many jobs with our aggressive energy efficiency and conservation program that enables people to retrofit their homes and businesses with low-interest government loans that can be paid off slowly over time with the savings from their energy bill.  Similarly, the green economy: building retrofits, housing, infrastructure and green power projects.</p>
</text>
