<text id="autogum_interview_doc970" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Frank McEnulty, New American Independent Party nominee for President of the United States" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-09-24" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Frank_McEnulty%2C_New_American_Independent_Party_nominee_for_President_of_the_United_States" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Frank McEnulty, New American Independent Party nominee for President of the United States</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 24, 2008</hi></p>
<p>So far, the news on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008%20U.S.%20presidential%20election">U.S. presidential election</ref> has been dominated by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican">Republican Party</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic">Democratic Party</ref> nominees <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20McCain">John McCain</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barack%20Obama">Barack Obama</ref>. However, recently, some "third party" candidates have begun to gain notoriety, namely <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libertarian">Libertarian Party</ref> nominee <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Barr">Bob Barr</ref> and independent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ralph%20Nader">Ralph Nader</ref>. </p>
<p>Unbeknownst to many, there are several other minor party candidates in the race. One of them is <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_American_Independent_Party">New American Independent Party</ref> nominee <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank%20McEnulty">Frank McEnulty</ref>. McEnulty has been interviewed several times by <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> over the past few months, but in one held earlier this week with reporter <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User_talk:WNewsReporter">Joseph Ford</ref>, he went into detail on why he'd be a good president, why its necessary to support a third party candidate this year, and most importantly, why you should give him your vote.</p>
<p>The interview can be read below.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> (Joseph Ford): Why are you running for president?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> I am running for President because, as the father of two daughters, I am completely and utterly disgusted with both political parties in this country and am very concerned about what type of country we will be leaving for our children and grandchildren.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: You're the nominee of the New American Independent Party. What does your party stand for? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> The New American Independent Party believes in a smaller federal government that is not as wasteful of the people’s money and our country’s resources.  It also believes in a federal government that works for the benefit of all Americans and not predominantly for those Americans who belong to the President’s political party.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Joseph Ford: If elected, how would you handle America's economical crisis? </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Frank McEnulty:</hi> I would handle the current economic crisis by cutting out the cancer as soon as possible and getting the economy back on a sound footing so that Americans can do what they do best, move things forward once again.</p>
<p>Then, to ensure that this did not happen again, I would establish policies that would prevent this from recurring and I would instigate large criminal investigations into fraudulent lending and financial practices.  People would go to jail.  People would lose their financial assets.  People would pay for what they did wrong and allowed to happen.</p>
<p>For example, I would also see to it that the ex-heads of Fannie and Freddie never saw a dime of their deferred compensation even if that meant a prepackaged bankruptcy filing by both entities to void their contracts.</p>
<p>This mess needs to be cleaned up, but someone besides the American people at large needs to help pay for it with their assets and freedom.  This, in and of itself, would go a long way to restoring confidence in our financial system.  No one who almost brought our country to its knees financially should be rewarded when they are fired for doing so.</p>
</text>
