<text id="autogum_interview_doc1088" title="part9_Vanity Fair contributing editor Craig Unger on the Bush family feud, neoconservatives and the Christian right" shortTile="partvanity-fair-contributing" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-11" dateModified="2015-08-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vanity_Fair_contributing_editor_Craig_Unger_on_the_Bush_family_feud%2C_neoconservatives_and_the_Christian_right" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<head id="Orthodox_Jews_and_Fundamentalist_Christians">Orthodox Jews and Fundamentalist Christians</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You have a chapter about the assassination of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yitzak%20Rabin">Yitzak Rabin</ref>; how did that advance the neoconservative agenda?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  It’s one of the least understood events in contemporary history and it is really important in terms of our policy today.  Yes, it was done by this <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yigal%20Amir">one right-wing Israeli</ref>, but it was ordained by Orthodox rabbis because Rabin was backing the land-for-peace process.  It’s parallel to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20Anwar_Sadat#Assassination">Sadat</ref> assassination by Islamic fundamentalists.  Rabin was breaking <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%20Halakha">Halakhic law</ref> by supporting land for peace because it is divinely-ordained land.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are the Israeli orthodox Jews in touch with the Christian right in the United States?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Completely.  And the neocons are a secular version of that, and you see it start coming together, and Netanyahu becomes one of the great backers of an alliance with the Christian right.  Michael Ledeen is going on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat%20Robertson">Pat Roberton</ref>’s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/700%20Club">700 Club</ref></hi> shows.  You start to have this weaving together.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What does the Christian right have to gain from this?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  It’s theological.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/End%20time">End of Days</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Yes, Christ will not return until that land is given back to the Jews.  I try to draw this in the book.  People try to talk about the Culture Wars, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red%20State">Red State/Blue State</ref>.  But no, it’s much deeper than that.  It goes back to the founding of America and the Puritans, really.  I thought I grew up in a country that put a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moon%20landing">man on the moon</ref>, unraveled the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human%20Genome">human genome</ref>, that discovered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA">DNA</ref> and invented the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/iPod">iPod</ref>, but no.  No western country believes so strongly in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creationism">Creationism</ref> and that the world was born 6,000 years ago; that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolution">evolution</ref> is wrong.  This war is deep and profound and what’s happened now is the government is run by people who believe in dictating our policies based upon the Bible.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  This is so much material to be covered in just one book.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Yes, because you can see it in the judiciary.  So many students come from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regent%20University">Pat Robertson’s law school</ref>—</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  They have a model of the Supreme Court for arguing these fights.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  Right.  So many of the people in the White House come from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick%20Henry%20College">Patrick Henry College</ref>.  It used to be you went to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivy%20League">Ivy League</ref>.  Now they have people who are homeschooled by evangelicals because they didn’t want them to be poisoned by the secular public school system.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Our society has always been complicated, but there are so many layers to this complex onion of a social movement that it must have been a challenge to articulate it in your book.  We hold a lot of myths about our history.   </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">CU:</hi>  This book goes from biblical times to English Puritanism to espionage and intelligence battles at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Langley">Langley</ref> to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Likud">Likudniks</ref> in Israel to the assassination of Rabin to the Deep South and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bible%20Belt">Bible Belt</ref> today.  You do see the same themes again and again.  I tried to do a narrative with three narrative lines: The rise of the neocons in the 1970’s; the rise of the Christian right, which goes back to Biblical times through English Puritanism and the founding of America to becoming a powerful force in American politics and taking over the government because they have a leader who is now President of the United States.  It’s important to understand that the Christian right thinks of Bush as a leader, or they have.  Although he certainly has lost credibility, the Christian right is not dead <hi rend="italic">at all</hi>.  I would take issue with The New York Times in their cover story a week or so ago where they proclaim the death of the Christian right, which they do that same story time and again.</p>
</text>
