<text id="autogum_interview_doc290" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Frank McEnulty, independent candidate for US President" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-15" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Frank_McEnulty%2C_independent_candidate_for_US_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Together we will make a difference because:</p>
<p>"ANYTHING IS POSSIBLE IN AMERICA"</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Have you ever run for political office before? (President, senate, congress, city councillor, school trustee... etc.) Have you ever been a member of a political party, other than the one you're currently in?</hi></p>
<p>No [I haven't run for before]. Yes, for years I was a member of the Republican Party back when it believed in fiscal responsibility and smaller government.  For the last 10 years I was registered as an Independent and I recently became a member of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_American_Independent_Party">New American Independent Party</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Have you ever campaigned for another political candidate?</hi></p>
<p>No.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What is your current job?</hi></p>
<p>My current job is President and CFO for a group of small, privately owned companies.  Although I have managed companies that have been involved in a wide cross section of different industries, the vast majority of my work experience has been in various sectors of the real estate industry.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">What skills or ideas do you bring from this position, or previous positions, that will benefit the Oval Office?</hi></p>
<p>During my career I have been called on many times to straighten out problems and get things moving in the right direction.  I am a problem solver who can make the tough decisions to get things done and back on track.  The problem with almost all politicians these days is that they are politicians and only care about what they need to do to win the next election.  What this country needs are statesmen who will look at the big picture and do what is right for all Americans.  You don’t make everyone happy doing that, the same as you can’t always make everyone happy in your business, but if you keep the long-term view it will turn out better for all concerned and make for a stronger more vibrant country that benefits everyone.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Obviously, the next American President and his or her administration will face many diverse issues. But if you were to narrow identify the three most important issues, what would they be?  How will you address these issues?</hi></p>
<p>First, the biggest problem facing us now and for generations to come is our dependence on foreign sources of oil and oil in general.</p>
<p>We need to immediately start a "Manhattan Project" for energy independence. We put a man on the moon back in the "dark ages" of technology and I firmly believe that we have the brain power to come up with solutions to the world's energy problems if only we apply ourselves and our resources to the task. We are quickly on our way towards spending $1,000,000,000,000 (that’s a trillion) of your tax dollars on the war in Iraq. If that money had instead been pointed towards new research and development into fuel cells, hydrogen, solar, wind and other technologies, I believe we would already be well on our way to major break-throughs in renewable and alternative energy solutions.</p>
</text>
