<text id="autogum_interview_doc1279" title="part4_Edmund White on writing, incest, life and Larry Kramer" shortTile="partedmund-white" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-08" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edmund_White_on_writing%2C_incest%2C_life_and_Larry_Kramer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slave%20(BDSM)">slave</ref> or a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master%20(BDSM)">master</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  A slave, but I’m not much of one.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why are you a bad slave?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I’m not into pain and it has to strike me just right or it starts to seem ridiculous.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  At what point does it start to seem ridiculous?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Too much leather, bad grammar on the part of the master! [Laughs]</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  [Laughs]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Like, “Lay down” instead of “Lie down.”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you always <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Top%20and%20bottom%20in%20sex%20and%20BDSM">submissive</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I have dominated, it’s just not as pleasurable.  When I was younger I had slaves, even for a whole year at a time.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You had a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master/slave%20(BDSM)">slave relationship</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Yes, for a year.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What was that like?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  One day we were on acid down in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Key%20West">Key West</ref> and I realized I didn’t even <hi rend="italic">like</hi> him, so I broke up with him.  I thought it was okay to be doing it if I actually like or love him, but if I <hi rend="italic">really</hi> have contempt for him, that’s no good.  It has to be an expression of love.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What psychological issues come out in a relationship like that?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Unrequited feelings for love from your father, often times.   Longings for passivity.  A lot of people have that.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  To give up the feeling they always have to be in control in their waking lives?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I have a good friend who is a European novelist who was willing to literally hand over all of his belongings to this master, just signed over everything he owned to live in a cage the rest of his life.  It turned out to be a fraud to fleece him of his money.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  That must have been disappointing for him.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  It’s a good thing he discovered that in time, didn’t lose his money and didn’t live in a cage the rest of his life, because he’s actually a very interesting person with a very full life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What psychological issues did you work through in your slave-master relationships?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Different ones.  If it’s not an on-going thing then you would get tired of it and drop it all together.  It’s not a very major part of my life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Did it used to be more so?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Yes.  But it was also a fresher scene back then.  Now it feels like a very tired scene and I hate people in leather, I think that’s so stupid.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Like they are wearing Halloween costumes?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Yeah.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  As if the fashion never changes?  It’s always the same chaps, the same harness…</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Yeah…yeah, that’s right.  One of the interesting things about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20Mapplethorpe">Robert Mapplethorpe</ref>—who was a friend of mine and I have quite a few pictures here by him, including two of me—he had leathers made for him in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amsterdam">Amsterdam</ref> with red and blue piping, fitting in an interesting way with different kinds of leather.  A patchwork effect without making it look silly.  He was very elegant.  They were attractive and sexy.</p>
</text>
