<text id="autogum_interview_doc1277" title="part2_Edmund White on writing, incest, life and Larry Kramer" shortTile="partedmund-white" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-11-08" dateModified="2019-10-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edmund_White_on_writing%2C_incest%2C_life_and_Larry_Kramer" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you see a generation that can assume the mantle for the Violet Quill or is there not a necessity for it?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  There’s not a necessity for it now, but there was then.  It’s always been hard to get gay books published, and it’s as hard as ever.  It’s very hard to get gay books published.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  The market is very small.  Only 3% of all people are gay and if you take a diminishing dumbed-down reading public to begin with, and say you are only aiming for 3% of that market, that’s awfully small.  So gay novels if they are successful sell 5,000 copies.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is a gay novel?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  One that is marketed as gay.  Usually a picture of a cute boy on the cover.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Would <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan%20Hollinghurst">Hollinghurst</ref>’s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Swimming%20Pool%20Library">Swimming Pool Library</ref></hi> be one?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  Well, he’s a cross-over writer.  He’s a little different because he did win the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Booker%20Prize">Booker Prize</ref> with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Line%20of%20Beauty">The Line of Beauty</ref></hi>, and he was the editor of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Times%20Literary%20Supplement">The Times Literary Supplement</ref></hi>, which is the most prestigious reviewing organism in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anglosphere">English-speaking world</ref>.  He has a dark brown voice and he went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxford%20College">Oxford</ref> and he knows everybody.  He’s admired by everybody.  London is such a different place because in America writers teach in different universities and they are scattered all across this huge country and they sometimes know each other, but not usually.  Whereas in England they are all journalists , they live in London, and they all know each other.  It’s a very small world, which is good and bad.  One of the good things is that if somebody is really talented like Hollinghurst and has accumulated a bastion of power like the TLS, he’ll have enormous impact, and everybody knows it.  Whereas here somebody like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Leavitt">David Leavitt</ref> is teaching in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gainesville,%20Florida">Gainesville, Florida</ref>.  That’s pretty far off the beaten path even though he’s a wonderful writer.  His last book, <hi rend="italic">The Indian Clerk</hi>, was reviewed on the front page of The New York Times book review very glowingly.  Nevertheless, it doesn’t sell and nobody cares.  It’s very hard.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  You think that’s because of a lack of a community of writers?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">EW:</hi>  I think there’s a number of things.  One of the things that is important for gay writers, gay publishers and gay academics is to try and develop a market.  You can see that with something like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harry%20Potter">Harry Potter</ref> where everybody thought the children’s market had completely vanished and now it’s back in a huge way because of that one book.  I have a friend, Claire Robson who is a lesbian writer that lives in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vancouver,%20Canada">Vancouver</ref>.  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref>, being a semi-welfare state has a lot of money for public things.  She’s trying to develop older lesbian audiences, younger gay male audiences.  She’s organizing reading groups, study groups, autobiography writing groups.  All of this stuff that is paid for by the government.</p>
</text>
