<text id="autogum_interview_doc284" title="part1_Wikinews interviews Eric Saussine, director of the James Bond fan film Shamelady" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-07-16" dateModified="2008-08-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Eric_Saussine%2C_director_of_the_James_Bond_fan_film_Shamelady" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Why did you make this film? Where did the inspiration for <hi rend="italic">Shamelady</hi> come from?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Saussine:</hi> In 1953, Ian Fleming created James Bond and therefore the myth we all know. In 2003, for the fiftieth anniversary of the creation of Ian Fleming's hero, I thought that it was time to pay tribute to this literary and cinema myth . In September 2004, I called his friend Pierre Rodiac, a former president a French James Bond fan club. I talked to him about my idea to adapt Casino Royale, the only Ian Fleming James Bond novel that was not seriously adapted by Eon, holder of the movie rights. Pierre was excited by the project and he started writing a synopsis. We worked alternatively on it. It gave way to a script which I wrote and Pierre corrected, that was a faithful adaptation of the novel, with all the trademarks of the movie franchise. Then I immediately started the search for actors and locations.</p>
<p>On February 3, 2005, Eon Productions announced that Martin Campbell would direct the 21st film of the series. The title was... Casino Royale!</p>
<p>I was happy because I had always wanted to see that. I went back to work on my project. I decided to preserve the general plot, change the names of the villains, the bad guy's plan, a few scenes and re-introduced a well known terrorist organization and its chief from the Bond films and novels : S.P.E.C.T.R.E. and Ernst Stavro Blofeld. I wrote a new script in a couple of months and found its title : Shamelady. Pre-production started in 2004. Filming started in 2005 and went on in 2006. Post-production took place in 2007 and the release date was December 11, 2007.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN (Joseph Ford)</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Last summer, you announced that Constellation Studios is at work on another Bond film, <hi rend="italic">Shatterhand</hi>. Tell us about it.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Eric Saussine:</hi> Well, the team was so happy to do Shamelady. At the end of this movie we were tired but response from the team members themselves that the first of them, Serge Rotelli (Bond) asked that we do another one. Of course I had many ideas going wild in many directions in my mind. So following that wave of enthusiasm I decided to renew the experience and launched the production of a new James Bond 007 adventure. This time, the film will be our way to celebrate Ian Fleming's hundredth birthday.</p>
<p>The plot will stay close to Fleming's literary works and will be derived from the short story Octopussy, the last third of the novel You Only Live Twice, hence the title, Shatterhand, which is Blofeld's pseudonym in that adventure. The new film also includes an original ski chase in the pre-credit sequence and an explosive action finale. Some shots were done for real in Japan. We will probably miss the Fleming centenary in 2008 and will probably release it one year later.</p>
</text>
