<text id="autogum_interview_doc405" title="part3_Bat for Lashes plays the Bowery Ballroom: an Interview with Natasha Khan" shortTile="partbat-lashes-plays" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-09-27" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bat_for_Lashes_plays_the_Bowery_Ballroom%3A_an_Interview_with_Natasha_Khan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Is it always pine trees that you see?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  Yes, pine trees and sky, I guess.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What things in nature inspire you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  I feel drained thematically if I'm in the city too long.  I think that when I'm in nature—for example, I went to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big%20Sur">Big Sur</ref> last year on a road trip and just looking up and seeing dark shadows of trees and starry skies really gets me and makes me feel happy.  I would sit right by the sea, and any time I have been a bit stuck I will go for a long walk along the ocean and it's just really good to see vast horizons, I think, and epic, huge, all-encompassing visions of nature really humble you and give you a good sense of perspective and the fact that you are just a small particle of energy that is vibrating along with everything else.  That really helps.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are there man-made things that inspire you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi>  Things that are more cultural, like open air cinemas, old Peruvian flats and the Chelsea Hotel.  Funny old drag queen karaoke bars...</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  I photographed some of the famous drag queens here in New York.  They are just such great creatures to photograph; they will do just about anything for the camera.  I photographed a famous drag queen named <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miss%20Understood">Miss Understood</ref> who is the emcee at a drag queen restaurant here named Lucky Cheng's.  We were out in front of Lucky Cheng's taking photographs and a bus was coming down <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First%20Avenue%20(Manhattan)">First Avenue</ref>, and I said, "Go out and stop that bus!" and she did!  It's an amazing shot.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi> Oh. My. God.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  If you go on her Wikipedia article it's there.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi> That's so cool.  I'm really getting into that whole psychedelic sixties and seventies <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris%20Is%20Burning%20(film)">Paris Is Burning</ref></hi> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%20Smith%20and%20the%20Destruction%20of%20Atlantis">Jack Smith and the Destruction of Atlantis</ref></hi>.  Things like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Cockettes">The Cockettes</ref>.  There seems to be a bit of a revolution coming through that kind of psychedelic drag queen theater.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  There are just so few areas left where there is natural edge and art that is not contrived.  It's taking a contrived thing like changing your gender, but in the backdrop of how that is still so socially unacceptable.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">NK:</hi> Yeah, the theatrics and creativity that go into that really get me.  I'm thinking about <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Fisher%20King%20(film)">The Fisher King</ref></hi>...do you know that drag queen in <hi rend="italic">The Fisher King</hi>?  There's this really bad and amazing drag queen guy in it who is so vulnerable and sensitive.  He sings these amazing songs but he has this really terrible drug problem, I think, or maybe it's a drink problem.  It's so bordering on the line between fabulous and those people you see who are so in love with the idea of beauty and elevation and the glitz and the glamor of love and beauty, but then there's this really dark, tragic side.  It's presented together in this confusing and bewildering way, and it always just gets to me.  I find it really intriguing.</p>
</text>
