<text id="autogum_interview_doc758" title="part1_Interview with Innocent Watat, City Council candidate for Wards 3 &amp; 4 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-innocent" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-21" dateModified="2007-06-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Innocent_Watat%2C_City_Council_candidate_for_Wards_3_%26_4_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>I am bringing with me a new way to undertake the development of Brampton; a new policy that would see the reduction of the gap between Bramptonians and the council actions; I have with me a new alternative that would make each person living in Brampton really feel at home. I would give to each inhabitant of my wards, the real feeling of being in a city that really fit his desire.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi>I am in many aspects an example within my community and I strive to keep that as effective as possible. I am a leader in my community and I have presided or I am an active member of many non for profit organization working to ameliorate people life and/or to welcome newcomers in our city. I am a dedicate volunteer and always preach by example in an exceptional dedication with the purpose to always have the job well done.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Much of Brampton's existing council is seasoned in the civic political process. What could you bring to the table as a "rookie", above and beyond the current roster of councilors?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> The present council seems to be away of the reality in this fast growing city. They are veterans, with all respect, they are in urgent need of retirement. We're grateful of their effort and commitment for all these years, but we must now realize that they are all running out of ideas. They've been cut off guard by the population growth and they seem to be trailing behind looking desperately for ways to catch up with a train speeding away. The best way to give a better future to our city is to give the chance to "rookies" to come in with fresh mind and fresh ideas that would help our city to cope with this sudden growth. We need to rejuvenate the council chamber and create some sort of positive actions that would consolidate the path of Brampton in this twenty first century. We all appreciate the hard work done by our predecessors, but it is the time to look beyond their path of actions and act accordingly to keep Brampton into the right direction.</p>
<p>Brampton has now a diverse culture and ethnicity that in reality should be our strength. The existing council, despite their talk, is not really walking the talk. There are no actions to really create a sense of belongings to these newcomers in our city. Without a doubt there is need of new energy, a need of rejuvenation.</p>
<p>There are obvious actions that a council should tackle which haven't been done properly. Certainly they've been there so long that they don't see any pressure or obligation. We must work to support our youth, seniors and people with special needs. We must improve on the present infrastructure and develop the public transit within Brampton and beyond. Of course, the safety measures are paramount and it is important to create a great atmosphere of respect and collaboration between Police and the community. We must not forget that the community is important in solving many crimes.</p>
</text>
