<text id="autogum_interview_doc620" title="part8_Wikinews interviews Joe Schriner, Independent U.S. presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-04-16" dateModified="2019-08-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Joe_Schriner%2C_Independent_U.S._presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20Plimpton">George Plimpton</ref>.  He was a rather famous sports journalist who was known for 'walking a mile in an athlete's shoes.'  For instance, he spent a spring training practicing with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Detroit%20Lions">Detroit Lions</ref> and even played quarterback for several downs during an exhibition game.  He then went on to write the book: <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paper%20Lion">Paper Lion</ref></hi> from the experience.  And that's how I've been, to a degree, as a presidential candidate.  That is, I try to live the platform I espouse.  For instance, as part of our urban platform, we exhort some people in suburban and small town America to roll up their sleeves and move into the urban cores of LA, Chicago, Minneapolis... to work on systemically changing things.(Just throwing more money and police presence at the problem is like metaphorically putting a band aid on something that needs major surgery.)  Taking our own advice – in a very 'Plimpton-like' manner – our family moved from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluffton,%20Ohio">Bluffton</ref> (pop. 3,857 and think <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mayberry">Mayberry</ref>) to a hardscrabble part of Cleveland (the poorest big city in the country).  We moved into a block where a group of Catholic Workers were living every 3rd or 4th house down from each other.  There we all helped transform an old asphalt parking lot into an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Urban%20agriculture">urban farm</ref>, volunteered at a drop-in center for the marginalized up the street; coached Rec. Center soccer and baseball teams (many of the kids not having dads at home)   and  ...  Besides participating in the transformation of this area, like George Plimpton again, I wrote a book about the experience titled America's Best Urban Neighborhood...  We also, as another example, promote an agricultural platform that would push for the return of the small <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/family%20farm">family farm</ref>, en mass. And as we traveled the country, not only did we research the various dynamics of the family farm, but our family worked on a number of them as well.  This included chores like chopping wood, bailing hay, weeding by hoe in an organic bean field…  And these were not 20-minute photo-ops, so to speak.  These were long, sweaty days out on the farm.  The essence of my candidacy has been ‘being on the ground’ and working side-by-side with ordinary folks, listening to their thoughts, translating them into positions…  Ours, truly, is an ‘American peoples’ platform.’  Note: While not a bona-fide historical figure (more fiction, but you wish he was real), I also identify with: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rocky%20Balboa">Rocky</ref>.    “Some may feel it’s another Rocky Balboa story about an Ohio man against the millionaires.”  -- Alban Mehling, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Associated%20Content">Associated Content</ref></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Could you take <ref target="http://www.theadvocates.org/quizp/index.html">this test</ref>, and let us know where you stand on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/political%20spectrum">political spectrum</ref>?</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Schriner's results for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World's%20Smallest%20Political%20Quiz">World's Smallest Political Quiz</ref></caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> On the test, I scored as a “<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centrism">centrist</ref>.”  (Surprised me too.)  </p>
</text>
