<text id="autogum_interview_doc961" title="part0_Wikinews interviews Fred Karger, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-04-23" dateModified="2014-03-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Fred_Karger%2C_U.S._Republican_Party_presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Fred Karger, U.S. Republican Party presidential candidate</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 28, 2012</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Fred Karger in 2010.Image: IowaPolitics.com.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> political consultant and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/LGBT">gay rights</ref> (LGBT) activist <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Fred_Karger">Fred Karger</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref> took some time to discuss his <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican Party</ref> presidential campaign with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> reporter William Saturn. Karger holds the distinction as the first openly gay person to seek the presidential nomination of a major U.S. political party. </p>
<p>Before entering electoral politics, Karger worked as an adviser for such prominent Republicans and former U.S. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States">Presidents</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gerald_Ford">Gerald Ford</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ronald_Reagan">Ronald Reagan</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_H._W._Bush">George H. W. Bush</ref>. Since retiring as an adviser in 2004, he has been involved in LGBT issues: opposing <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California_Proposition_8">California Proposition 8</ref>, which banned <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Same-sex_marriage">same-sex marriage</ref> in the state; and leading investigations of such same-sex marriage opponents as the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/National_Organization_for_Marriage">National Organization for Marriage</ref> (NOM) and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Church_of_Jesus_Christ_of_Latter-day_Saints">The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints</ref> (The Mormon Church).</p>
<p>In 2010, Karger first announced his intentions to seek the Republican presidential nomination, but did not officially announce until March 2011. One of his early campaign goals was to participate in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20Party%20presidential%20debates,%202012">GOP presidential debate</ref>, but was never invited due to polling thresholds. However, Karger argued that he did meet the requirement for an August debate, but was still excluded after the organizers deemed polls he cited as inadequate. </p>
<p>So far, Karger has appeared on four Republican primary ballots including <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Puerto_Rico">Puerto Rico</ref>, where he was able to top <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Congress">Congressman</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ron_Paul">Ron Paul</ref>, who, at the time was one of the four major candidates in the race. Karger will next appear on the ballots in California on June 5, and in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Utah">Utah</ref> on June 26. </p>
<p>Karger brands himself as "a different kind of Republican" that wants to open the party to outsiders. He backs gay marriage, is pro-choice on abortion, and wants to lower the voting age. However, he also holds some traditional Republican views: he favors a strengthening of the private sector and believes the U.S. should be steadfast in its support for the nation of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israel</ref>. </p>
<p>In talking to <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, Karger discusses his personal political background and activism, the 2012 presidential election and his GOP campaign, as well as his political views on both domestic and foreign affairs. </p>
<head id="Background">Background</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">I’m going to start with the background. What are some of your proudest accomplishments?</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Karger with former President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_H._W._Bush">George H. W. Bush</ref> in 2006.Image: Fred Karger.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Fred Karger</hi>: Well, I have been involved in politics for 55 years. I am very proud that I first began working on campaigns, and then evolved into a profession. I got to work with some of the great leaders in the country: George H.W. Bush, Gerald Ford, Ronald Reagan. I got to involve myself in a lot of the issues of the time; involved in initiatives, elections all over the country; and then, most recently was a direct activist in discovering a lot of illicit activities by the Mormon Church, involving itself in many of the anti-Gay marriage campaigns from 1995 in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hawaii">Hawaii</ref> to our current election going on now; and then also taking on the National Organization for Marriage, and then investigated in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Maine">Maine</ref>, which resulted in a treasure trove of documents disclosing their illicit activities. So I would think those are certainly some of my highlights in my 62 years, but I got all the fight left in me.</p>
</text>
