<text id="autogum_interview_doc1095" title="part0_In the land of the open source elves: Interview with "Battle for Wesnoth" creator David White" shortTile="partin-land-open" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2006-05-29" dateModified="2015-10-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/In_the_land_of_the_open_source_elves%3A_Interview_with_%22Battle_for_Wesnoth%22_creator_David_White" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text><head>In the land of the open source elves: Interview with "Battle for Wesnoth" creator David White</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 1, 2006</hi></p>
<figure><caption>A simple tutorial helps new players to become familiar with the basics of 'Battle for Wesnoth<hi rend="italic">.</hi></caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Screenshot from the user-created campaign "Under the Burning Suns", showing the German language user interface</caption></figure>
<p>If you've always wanted to live in a world populated by elves, dwarves and wizards, you don't need to pay for a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20of%20Warcraft">World of Warcraft</ref></hi> subscription or buy the Special Extended DVD Trilogy Edition of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Lord%20of%20the%20Rings">The Lord of the Rings</ref></hi> just yet. You could instead give <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle%20for%20Wesnoth">Battle for Wesnoth</ref></hi> a try — an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/open%20source">open source</ref> turn-based strategy game in a fantasy setting. For the practically minded, "open-source" means that the code which the game is made of is available to anyone who wishes to use, redistribute or change it. It was created by volunteers and can be freely shared. Even the multiplayer online part of the game is free (no ads or spyware either).</p>
<p>But <hi rend="italic">Wesnoth</hi>, as it is often abbreviated, is notable not only because it is free. While its graphics are simple by modern standards, the sheer number of units and scenarios that are available for the game is staggering. This is where the "open source" philosophy comes truly into play: anyone can contribute art or new campaigns. As of May 2006, the forum where users can share and discuss their own art contained over 25,000 messages. Most of this art is made available under the same open source terms as the game itself.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Battle for Wesnoth</hi> lets you command armies of units such as archers, swordmen, mages and gryphons during the course of a campaign consisting of multiple missions. Typically, your mission is to defeat an enemy leader, but some scenarios let you liberate a prisoner, find a lost artifact, traverse dangerous territories, and so on. Your best units can be taken from one mission to the next, "levelling up" in the process. Even units of the same type vary in their abilities, making the tactical use of the right unit at the right time very important.</p>
<p>The game is reminiscent of turn-based strategy classics such as <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heroes%20of%20Might%20and%20Magic">Heroes of Might and Magic</ref></hi> or <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warlords%20(game%20series)">Warlords</ref></hi>. Throughout each campaign, the player is informed of the progress of the story. For instance, in the "Heir to the Throne" campaign, the player follows the story of Prince Konrad, who must reclaim the throne of Wesnoth from an evil queen.</p>
<p>The game was originally designed by David White, who is still the project's lead developer. We exchanged e-mails with David about the state of open source gaming, the future of <hi rend="italic">Wesnoth</hi>, and the collaborative aspects of game development.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">David, thanks for taking our questions. Open source games suffer from the problem that very few people have all the abilities needed to make a good game: programming, graphics, story development, sound effects, music, and so on. When you started Battle for Wesnoth, how did you deal with this?</hi></p>
</text>
