<text id="autogum_interview_doc1052" title="part4_Past Eurovision contestants give advice to this year's performers, speculate on who will win" shortTile="partpast-eurovision" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2009-05-06" dateModified="2015-09-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Past_Eurovision_contestants_give_advice_to_this_year%27s_performers%2C_speculate_on_who_will_win" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<head id="Marie_N">Marie N </head>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Marija Naumova, who goes by the stage name <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marie%20N">Marie N</ref>, is best-known to European audiences for winning the Eurovision Song Contest for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Latvia">Latvia</ref> in 2002 with her song "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I%20Wanna">I Wanna</ref>." The next year, she hosted the Contest in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riga">Riga</ref> with past Latvian entrant <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renārs%20Kaupers">Renārs Kaupers</ref>. Now 35, she has moved a lot of her focus to musical theatre and is very serious about honing her talent.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What projects are you working on? What can your fan base expect to see from you this year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Marie N</hi>: At this time I am a student at acting school in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris">Paris</ref>, so now all [my] plans are more about theatre, but I also started to work on my new album and I hope that at the end of the year I [can] present that to [the] audience, but I think that at the moment it's too early to talk about it. <hi rend="italic">[smile]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> What were some of the best memories you have from going to Eurovision? What advice would you give to the singers going to Eurovision for the first time this year?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Marie N</hi>: I liked everything during the week we spent there. We really had a lot of fun. The [atmosphere] was very professional, participants were very friendly...but the most emotional [part] was our trip back home – the way from Tallinn to Riga by bus with the police accompanying us and people waiting for us with flowers along the road...</p>
<p>The only advice is <hi rend="italic">to enjoy</hi> every moment and especially the three minutes of the presentation – it is really something special. <hi rend="italic">[smile]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The music videos for this year are up at <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/eurovision">youtube.com/eurovision</ref>. Which songs are your favorites and which country do you think has the best chance of winning?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Marie N</hi>: I think that there are a lot of songs which have chances to win, but it depends on the energy that [the] singers will bring with them [to] the stage on that special evening.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Mike Halterman</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Which task was more fun for you, winning Eurovision or hosting it the next year? Which one made you more nervous, and why?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Marie N</hi>: Of course singing was more fun than the hosting because you are responsible only for yourself, but hosting brings a responsibility for the whole show. I wish all the best for all the participants; enjoy. <hi rend="italic">[smile]</hi></p>
<head id='Niels_"Noller"_Olsen'>Niels "Noller" Olsen </head>
<figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="italic">Niels Olsen, nicknamed "Noller," (pictured, left) and his older brother Jørgen (right) make up the duo The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olsen%20Brothers">Olsen Brothers</ref>. A well-known act in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Denmark">Denmark</ref> since the early 1970s, the duo successfully staked a new claim to relevance by winning the Eurovision Song Contest in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurovision%20Song%20Contest%202000">2000</ref> with the entry "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fly%20on%20the%20Wings%20of%20Love">Fly on the Wings of Love</ref>." Now 55, Niels Olsen uses every chance possible to let his audience know that age is simply a number, especially in Eurovision which tends to favor younger entrants.</hi></p>
</text>
