<text id="autogum_interview_doc618" title="part6_Wikinews interviews Joe Schriner, Independent U.S. presidential candidate" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-04-16" dateModified="2019-08-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Joe_Schriner%2C_Independent_U.S._presidential_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">Your Pro-Life stance seems to be a big issue in your campaign. What are your thoughts on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott%20Roeder">Scott Roeder</ref>, who assassinated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George%20Tiller">George Tiller</ref>? Was this action justified? How far are you willing to go to end abortion?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> I believe abortion is a form of murder.  And I told the Range News in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wilcox,%20Arizona">Wilcox</ref>, that with abortion American society has “become its own worst terrorist.”  During an abortion, a baby is systematically dismembered in the mother's womb, then suctioned out.  I mean, c'mon!  Yet even with all this (some 4,000 abortions a day in America now), I don't condone the George Tiller killing.  Because, well, it's yet another 'killing.'  As I mentioned earlier, I don't believe in the death penalty in any form – even a pro-life vigilante one.  I give talks all over the country explaining that I believe that if pro-life people really want to end this evil, they need to organize – much better than they are now – and take to the streets en mass, day in and day out, the same as what was mobilized in the South to end the evil of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Segregation">Segregation</ref>.  (We've reached the 50 million abortion mark since 1973.  That's staggering!)) People should regularly be out with protest signs, not just in front of abortion clinics, but in their neighborhoods.  As we've traveled, our family has protested on neighborhood street corners and in front of abortion clinics in California, Michigan, Massachusetts, Ohio, Florida, North Dakota...  And we'd be doing the same as the First Family, I told the Lewiston Argus newspaper in Montana.)  What's more, the newspapers should be flooded with an avalanche of pro-life letters to the editor.  Legislator offices should be deluged with pro-life letters.  A lot of people in the South didn't want Segregation to end, but they wanted the protests to end even more.  So, eventually, Segregation ended. It could well be the same with abortion.  Note:  As I mentioned earlier, I would also work stridently to help end precipitating factors (poverty, dysfunctional family dynamics, relaxed sexual mores, alcohol and drug addiction...) that lead to many abortions.  As I would work to highlight models for the many crisis pregnancy centers we've researched across the country.  Centers that provide food, shelter, clothing, college scholarship money, day care... for moms (and dads) who want to keep their baby. We’ve researched these centers in Minnesota, Indiana, Rhode Island… For more on our stance on abortion, see:     or for a more in-depth paper, see </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">What are your thoughts on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barack%20Obama">President Obama</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">JS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Mixed.  Given, for instance, my stance on abortion (last answer), I find Mr. Obama's strong backing of abortion extremely troubling.  Conversely, I find his efforts toward scaling back <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/nuclear%20weapon">nuclear weapons</ref>, cutting down on greenhouse gases, getting more access to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patient%20Protection%20and%20Affordable%20Care%20Act">healthcare for individuals</ref>... as commendable (and in line with the Consistent Life Ethic I espouse).  I would, however, push for much stronger action on each of these fronts.  (Granted President Obama might have as well in some of these categories, but, as has been the case with healthcare, he has been hamstrung to a degree by Congress.)  I do disagree with the president's troop surge strategy in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War%20in%20Afghanistan%20(2001–present)">Afghanistan</ref>.  I believe this will lead to a situation analogous to what essentially devolved into the '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq%20War">Iraq quagmire</ref>.'  And I believe the stepped up <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/drone%20attack">drone attacks</ref> in the mountain region between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pakistan">Pakistan</ref> and Afghanistan is a mistake, considering all the civilians being killed.  (What we so often refer to as a war's “inevitable collateral damage,” is: children, moms, dads...)  Admittedly however, when it comes to both Afghanistan and Iraq, Mr. Obama inherited tremendous dilemmas, with no easy solutions.  On the environmental/energy front, I strongly disagree with Mr. Obama's plans for more <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Offshore%20drilling%20on%20the%20US%20Atlantic%20coast">drilling offshore in the Atlantic</ref>, and promoting a new generation of nuclear energy plants...  For more on our energy policy, see:   In regard to personal characteristics, I do admire Mr. Obama's tenacity, which was demonstrated graphically in the last election process and with his relentless pursuit of the healthcare bill. An addendum:  There has been much written about Mr. Obama's oratory skills and negotiating skills.  Yet I believe this has to be weighed in the context of:  Is he saying the right stuff?  Is he negotiating for the right stuff?  In my opinion, not always.</p>
</text>
