<text id="autogum_interview_doc078" title="part5_Wikinews interviews Indiana State Senator Mike Delph" shortTile="partwikinews-interviews" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-26" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Indiana_State_Senator_Mike_Delph" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>And so I had literally campaigned in all 92 counties for two years of my life, driving around the state of Indiana in my American-made <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Honda%20Civic">Honda Civic</ref>, which became a political issue for part of the race. During that race, Congressman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luke%20Messer">Luke Messer</ref> was part of the field for a time. Diana Cordray, the clerk treasurer at Carmel, was in part of the field for a time. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kent%20Benson">Kent Benson</ref> was a big part of it. Campaigning against him was like campaigning against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elvis%20Presley">Elvis Presley</ref>. Because we’d go to these southern Indiana counties, and he would autograph basketballs with the starting five in the 1976 Indiana University <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1976%20NCAA%20Men's%20Division%20I%20Basketball%20Tournament">National Championship</ref> team. And that was the time that I said I had to do something because he was killing me politically, and so we started putting our name on peanut butter and passing out peanut butter. We said that if peanuts were the food of elephants, then peanut butter was the food of the grassroots of the Republican party, whose symbol was the elephant.</p>
<p>So we, we ran hard. We ran a strong campaign. And really it was that campaign that created the foundation for my ability to become a senator. But there's no question that that was a hard-fought campaign, and the way that it ended was less than favorable. Literally, the next day I had to get on an airplane to fly to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camp%20Shelby">Camp Shelby</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mississippi">Mississippi</ref> to do my 2 weeks of army training in the middle of nowhere. And I remember being on a rifle range, and a there was misfire happening, and I looked up to the safety officer on the rifle range and I said, "Was that Richard Mourdock over there?" Obviously, they didn't get the joke. But Richard and I are now friends and get along great.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Tew: And, in fact, you were both competing for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard%20Lugar">[Senator Richard] Lugar</ref>'s office.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: Well, you’re talking about the United States Senate, this last go ‘round?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Yes.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">MD</hi>: Yeah, at the time I was finishing up my legal studies and kind of transitioning professionally. I was running my own home-based business called MA Advisory Group, which was based upon my grandfather's name of his company, the MA Delph Company, which I mentioned before.  And I had thought about that for a little bit. I had been approached by some folks out in Washington, D.C., specifically that I have known for years and that had an interest in me considering that. And it really wasn't a good time for me professionally and in the life of my family. And so it wasn't something that I ever formed a committee or raised money or, started campaigning or reaching out to people to build support. But it did get in the press.</p>
</text>
