<text id="autogum_interview_doc1395" title="part18_Al Sharpton speaks out on race, rights and what bothers him about his critics" shortTile="partal-sharpton-speaks" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2007-12-01" dateModified="2014-12-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al_Sharpton_speaks_out_on_race%2C_rights_and_what_bothers_him_about_his_critics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  One of the issues that came up in reference to that at Thanksgiving was <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/political%20correctness">political correctness</ref>.  My brother-in-law brought up the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don%20imus#Rutgers_women's_basketball_controversy">Don Imus ‘nappy-headed hos’ issue</ref> and said it was political correctness.  His brother said that there is a big difference between calling black girls playing basketball <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural%20hair">nappy-headed</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/whore">hos</ref> versus asking a black person why their families are in trouble.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Big difference.  Big difference.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  But those get equated as being politically incorrect.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  I think you’re right.  They equate it, and it’s wrong.  The reason I demanded Imus be fired was because he had a record of making these kinds of derogatory statements.  It’s clear that ‘nappy-headed’ was a racist term.  That’s not questioning social maladies in the community.  What is the social malady or irresponsibility about ‘nappy-headed’?  ‘Ho’ is not only racist, it's misogynist.  People who tried to put that over as he just wasn’t politically correct are ridiculous.  That’s why if I or anybody else said a racist term against anybody else.  That’s not politically incorrect; that’s bias.  And <hi rend="italic">all</hi> of us have made mistakes with language, but you pay for it.  Which is why I don’t object to him getting a job again, but he had to lose that job because he had consistently violated that job.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Are you okay that Don Imus is going back on the air?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  Well, we’ll monitor him; I’m not saying I’m going to throw a banquet for him and say welcome home.  He has the right to make a living, but because he has such a consistent pattern with this we are going to monitor him to make sure he doesn’t do it again.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Do you work with the Hip Hop Action Network?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  On some issues.  They disagree with me at first when I came out hard on the N-word and all, but then they moderated their view.  On some things we work together.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How did they disagree with you?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">AS:</hi>  When I first came out and said the N-word, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bitch">B-word</ref>, should be stopped.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russell%20Simmons">Russell Simmons</ref> came out and said we can’t censor artists.  Then he got such a backlash he said, “We got it to be maybe voluntary, or something.”  Russell kind of slid backwards on that one.  My thing is I’m against the use of the word, and I’ve been against it for a long time.  Even in my book, <hi rend="italic">Al on America</hi> I wrote a whole chapter on the hip hop generation and how to stop that.  On top of it, all of us have used it; I’ve even stopped using it privately, because it’s wrong.  I think the thing that really drove it home to me was the kid who got beat up in Howards Beach last year, and Fat Nick—the white that beat him up saying no niggers in the neighborhood—his defense in court was that he was using a hip hop term.  It’s ridiculous, absolutely ridiculous.  We can’t be the only ones in America in which there is no hate term.</p>
</text>
