<text id="autogum_interview_doc1149" title="part3_Obesity and the Fat Acceptance Movement: Kira Nerusskaya speaks" shortTile="partobesity-fat-acceptance" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-10-09" dateModified="2014-05-04" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Obesity_and_the_Fat_Acceptance_Movement%3A_Kira_Nerusskaya_speaks" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What do you say to people who say you’re a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/gluttony">glutton</ref>?  You’re <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compulsive%20overeating">addicted to food</ref>?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  I would probably tend to disagree.  There are a variety of reasons of why people are fat and I think that’s also part of the stigma and the misconception.  What did you eat for breakfast today, David?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  A bagel with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/bacon">bacon</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cheddar%20cheese">cheddar</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ice%20cream">ice cream</ref>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  And ice cream?  Okay.  I ate one piece of double fiber toast with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olivio">Olivio</ref>, which is like fake butter -- good for you fake butter -- two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egg%20white">egg whites</ref>, and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pear">pear</ref>.  So kind of different, right?  You would say, ‘Gee, here’s this guy who’s 6’0” or whatever and 165 pounds or something and wow, isn’t a tables are turned kind of thing?’  I think a lot of times that’s what people think, that we are gluttons, but if they looked and analyzed my diet they would be pretty shocked.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  How do you keep your weight up then?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Or maybe the question is how do I keep my weight down, how do I keep from getting bigger?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It’s possible but...</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  Right.  I would say that there’s a variety of reasons.  I think the better question would be, “Well, then why are you fat, right?”</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Sure.  </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">KN:</hi>  There are a couple of things.  One, genetics:  one side of my family more than the other have  struggled with the weight issue.  I became fat probably when I was about 5, 6 or 7, somewhere in there.  That’s when my parents noticed my weight gain wasn’t necessarily based on what I ate.  I grew up in a household that only ate dessert if we had company.  We had soda occasionally.  We never had chips or sugar cereal.  If we went to sleep over at a friend’s house it was like, ‘Sugar cereal, wow! this is so cool!’</p>
<p>I was always on a series of diets to some degree.  I was always a fairly active child but perhaps not as active as I could have or should have been.  Increased activity would have been better for me.</p>
<p>I also suffer from something called PCOS, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polycystic%20Ovary%20Syndrome">Polycystic Ovary Syndrome</ref>, which is a documented disease that affects the way insulin is used in your body to store fat.  Look it up on Wikipedia!  Take a look at it.  It’s a pretty serious disease that has a broad spectrum of people suffering from it and it makes it difficult to lose weight.  If affects the chemical reactions in your body.</p>
<p>Now, did I ever overeat in my life?  Yes.  But didn’t you overeat at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thanksgiving">Thanksgiving</ref> last year?  Probably.</p>
<head id="Public_reaction_to_a_fat_woman">Public reaction to a fat woman</head>
</text>
