<text id="autogum_interview_doc1075" title="part0_Canada's Toronto—Danforth (Ward 30) city council candidates speak" shortTile="partcanadas-torontodanforth" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-11-04" dateModified="2013-05-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada%27s_Toronto%E2%80%94Danforth_%28Ward_30%29_city_council_candidates_speak" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Canada's Toronto—Danforth (Ward 30) city council candidates speak</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 4, 2006</hi></p>
<p>On November 13, Toronto residents will be heading to the polls to vote for their ward's councillor and for mayor. Among Toronto's ridings is Toronto Centre (Ward 28). One candidate responded to Wikinews' requests for an interview. This ward's candidates include Edward Chin, Paula Fletcher (incumbent), <hi rend="bold">Patrick Kraemer</hi>, Suzanne McCormick, <hi rend="bold">Daniel Nicastro</hi>, and Michael Zubiak.</p>
<p>For more information on the election, read <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toronto%20municipal%20election,%202006">Toronto municipal election, 2006</ref>.</p>
<head id="Patrick_Kraemer">Patrick Kraemer</head>
<p>41-year-old <hi rend="bold">Patrick Kraemer</hi> is a lawyer.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Describe the three most important issues in your campaign. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Energy, Crime and Poverty are the main planks of my platform and the most serious issues facing Ward 30.</p>
<p>The province is moving ahead with a new gas fired electricity generating plant in the Portlands adjacent to the beaches of Lake Ontario. The provincial Liberals were elected on promises of moving away from our highly polluting coal plants to renewable energies. The Portlands Energy Centre is another broken promise of this provincial government.</p>
<p>And the City could be doing so much more on this front. As Councilor I will fight for a comprehensive and aggressive energy conservation program. Energy conservation will achieve these goals much quicker than the construction of new facilities. Further, I will push for the construction of renewable energy sources such as windmills to fill the energy demands of the City. These proposals will create a competitive and sustainable economy for the City, will reduce pollution and our contribution to green house gases and will prevent the need to create more energy polluting sources such as the provincial plan of the Portlands Energy Centre.</p>
<p>Crime is another important issue for the City of Toronto and of concern for the residents of Ward 30. Many people are concerned about the incidents of guns, violent crimes and physical assaults. We have one of the safest cities in North America yet people still feel vulnerable when these things happen in our own community.</p>
<p>We don't need more police officers, we need to work together to make our communities safe and to feel safe in our communities. I will push to have more police officers out of their cars and to have them walking and biking on the streets in our neighbourhoods. Police also need to be involved in community and business associations, our schools and at neighbourhood functions and facilities. We also need to invest in technology and training to combat the organization and incidents of crime. Finally, we need to create opportunities for citizens to participate more fully in community awareness programs, to become educated about crime in the community and create avenues to report crime and criminal behaviour. We need to take ownership of our neighbourhoods and make them safe.</p>
</text>
