<text id="autogum_interview_doc969" title="part1_Interview: PRS, the UK's music royalty collection society" shortTile="partinterview-prs" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-03" dateCreated="2010-01-25" dateModified="2016-12-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview%3A_PRS%2C_the_UK%27s_music_royalty_collection_society" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
</text>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PRS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Anyone using music in a commercial way – such as a radio station – is required to obtain the permission of those that created the music.  This could be numerous writers, publishers and a record label for each song, possibly in different countries around the world.    By obtaining a PRS for Music and PPL licence in the UK you are ensuring you have those permissions for over 10million musical works. Obviously much of the music used on radio comes from non-UK writers who may not be members of PRS for Music.  Radio and television stations give us almost 100% accurate reports of their music use through their own playlists; this data then enables organisations such as ours to work out who should be paid and how much.  PRS for Music has 144 agreements in place with similar societies around the world, resulting in us representing almost 2 million writers worldwide.   If French, American, Spanish, Australian or any other writer’s music is used we will pay the respective societies so they can pay their members. </p>
 HAVE YOUR SAY
 Is PRS' standard contract "barmy" as Paul Campbell asserts?
<ref target="//en.wikinews.org/w/index.php?title=Comments:Main_Page&amp;action=edit&amp;preload=Wikinews:Commentary_pages_on_news_events/body&amp;editintro=Template:Editintro_comments&amp;summary=create">Add or view comments</ref>
<p>Similarly a writer of musician may be 'unsigned' by that doesn’t mean that they shouldn't earn from their music when it is used by others.   Many bands, writers and performers are currently unsigned but by being members of PRS for Music they ensure that they can begin earning vital royalties that allow them to continue with their musical career.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">How does the PRS ensure that artists outside the UK are properly compensated when their music is used within the UK, such as Thai or Chinese restaurants paying their PRS dues and exclusively using music which is from outside Europe?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PRS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> As mentioned before PRS for Music has agreements in place in over 90 countries around the world to ensure that when music is used the right creators are rewarded.   The system – built up over the last century – works both ways and when UK music is used internationally, PRS for Music receives royalties from foreign societies so we can pay our members.  In 2008 £139.8m was collected from UK music use abroad, with the UK being one of only a few net exporters of music in the world.   </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> <hi rend="bold">There have been a few cases in which PRS have been forced to apologise, exemplified by the threat of prosecution and a fine towards "singing granny" Sandra Burt, a shelf-stacker who sung to herself whilst stacking shelves.  How has PRS moved forward from these incidents in order to ensure they do not happen again?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">PRS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> If we have made mistakes we will of course put our hands up and say so.  For example when we were approached about the Sandra Burt case – by a journalist incidentally and not Sandra – we did give out slightly incorrect advice, although the questions were a little ambiguous.  Once we realised our mistake we contacted Sandra to explain that she wouldn’t need a licence to sing to her customers and offered our sincere apologies.  As an organisation we are very quick to admit where we get things wrong and ensure they are put right.  We’re proud of our record with our customers and currently have 350,000 businesses choosing to use music in the UK.   </p>
</text>
