<text id="autogum_interview_doc827" title="part12_Satanism: An interview with Church of Satan High Priest Peter Gilmore" shortTile="partsatanism-interview" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-04" dateModified="2018-10-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Satanism%3A_An_interview_with_Church_of_Satan_High_Priest_Peter_Gilmore" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head id="On_the_church_after_Anton_LaVey">On the church after Anton LaVey</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Does the Church of Satan have relationships with other churches?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  Not at all.  We’re not ecumenical.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  It would seem there are pagans or humanist religions that follow your general philosophy.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  I wouldn't say that.  Most pagan religions are theistic on one level or another.  They generally think their deities exist in some part.  We don't believe Satan exists as a deity.   I think there are some pagans who may look at their Gods and Goddesses as archetypes only, and in that sense that would be closer to our position because you can look at the symbol of Satan as an archetype.  But, we generally don't feel we have any relation to any kind of religious organization.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is the membership numbers for the Church of Satan?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  We never give out numbers.  The reason for that our founder came up with and I agree with him and keep to his policy:  if people think there are too few of us, they tend to not want to take us seriously.  If they think there are too many of us, they think we’re a threat.  There was even a point back during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satanic%20panic">Satanic Panic</ref> in the late 1980’s and early 1990’s when there was governmental legislation proposed to ban Satanism because they thought there were all these metal heads out there sacrificing babies, doing drugs and making child pornography.  Of course, now we know, it was mostly people who were borderline Christian evangelists pretending, but then accusing their own family members and getting them put in jail, or acting as therapists and most of those people have been sued and properly censured since then.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  Has the church thrived after LaVey’s passing?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  It has.  Partially because we are taking advantage of technology with the Internet and global media; our website gets hundreds of thousands of hits a day and literature keeps getting translated into many different languages the world over.  My own book, The Satanic Scriptures, the hardcover came out in April and the paperback is coming out this month.  I’ve already got five different languages coming out and I’m negotiating for others.  We are thriving, we have many members.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">DS:  What is your book about?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">PG:</hi>  It’s a collection of my essays I’ve written over the past twenty years talking about Satanic philosophy, how it’s applied.  I talk about music since I am by training a composer; I went to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York_University">NYU</ref>.  I have a Bachelor’s and Master’s in music composition, mostly focusing on orchestral work.  One conception in the book I wanted to dispel is the stereotype that Satanism is always associated with Metal and the cookie monster voice. That's Satanism? No.</p>
</text>
