<text id="autogum_interview_doc1232" title="part0_Interview with Dalbir S. Kathuria, Regional Council candidate for Wards 9 & 10 in Brampton, Canada" shortTile="partinterview-dalbir" type="interview" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-12" dateModified="2009-07-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Dalbir_S._Kathuria%2C_Regional_Council_candidate_for_Wards_9_%26_10_in_Brampton%2C_Canada" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Interview with Dalbir S. Kathuria, Regional Council candidate for Wards 9 &amp; 10 in Brampton, Canada</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 19, 2006</hi></p>
<p>The upcoming <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brampton%20municipal%20election,%202006">2006 Brampton municipal election</ref>, to be held November 13, features an array of candidates looking to represent their wards in city council or the council of the Peel Region.</p>
<p>Wikinews contributor Nick Moreau contacted many of the candidates, including <hi rend="bold">Dalbir S. Kathuria</hi>, asking them to answer common questions sent in an email. This ward's incumbent is John Sprovieri; also challenging Sprovieri is <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Interview_with_Derek_Begley,_Regional_Council_candidate_for_Wards_9_&amp;_10_in_Brampton,_Canada">Derek Begley</ref>, Sherdaljit Dhillon, Mahen Gupta, Satpaul Johal, and Vahid Saadati-Khanshir.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> List the three most important issues in your campaign.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi></p>
<p>A) Infastructure - The schools in Brampton are very unorganised. Kids are even send to the portable, which is very depressing.</p>
<p>B) Addressing the increased and unorganised Traffic concerns.</p>
<p>C) Addressing the rissing property taxes and the concerns of our residents, regarding their quality of life.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What one election issue do you feel is most relevant to your ward in this election?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Most important is the infrastructure, which is leading to more unplanned houses, which leading to mismanagement, which is effecting the development.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> What qualities or experiences do you possess, that make you more desirable than the incumbent? </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> Times fly, and lots of water has flowed under the river. I have the ardor, and passion to be in the community development programmes. Community work has been my forte, giving me wisdom, gathered over the years of experience. I am always on the forefront, to complete any assignment allotted to me, never shirking any responsibilities. I am a soft hearted Man, who has given solace to the needy in times of distress. I am a sympathetic listener to people's woes, goes all out of way to help them solving their personal or public related problems.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Why do you want to represent your ward on council?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I would like to see that my ward gets better facilities, better hearing of their local problems, and honest hearing of their difficulties, and a quicker resolution to all of them through a Representative like me.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> How are you currently involved in the community?</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">A:</hi> I am an enterprising Man, having been in the food and hotel business, successfully running a restaurant in Brampton, I am the epitome of humanhood. I have the fervor, the zeal to work for uplifting of the society. I collected CDN$50 000, and donated it to the Hospital for Sick Kids very recently. I am the Vice President of Liberal Riding Assosiation of Brampton.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Q:</hi> Much of Brampton's existing council is quite seasoned in the civic political process. What could you bring to the table as a "rookie", above and beyond the current roster of councillors?</p>
</text>
