<text id="autogum_voyage_doc356" title="Rajkot" shortTile="rajkot" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=29126" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rajkot</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Rajkot</hi> is a city in the state of <ref target="Gujarat">Gujarat</ref> in Western <ref target="India">India</ref>.</p>
<head>Understand</head>

<p>Rajkot is most famous as the place where Mahatma Gandhi pursued his early education. The city is also famous for traditional sweets and dandiya/garba raas dances. Founded in 1620 by a member of Jadeja clan, whose descendants ruled the city until 1947, Rajkot gained economic importance in the early 19th century, under British protectorate. Farmers' and traders' councils were encouraged to grow under British Rule. Later the city plunged into the industrial Age with the first years dominated by casting industries. Even today Rajkot is a wealthy city that ranks the 22nd-fastest-growing city in the world. It's also one of the cleanest cities of India.</p>

<p>Rajkot lies in the middle of Kathiawar peninsula, halfway between <ref target="Ahmedabad">Ahmedabad</ref> and <ref target="Porbandar">Porbandar</ref>. It's well worth one or two days stop although it's not a monumental city. Rajkot rather appeals to spiritual tastes. As in <ref target="Ahmedabad">Ahmedabad</ref>, many ashrams, that offers the teachings of yoga and meditative retreat, are located in the city and its surroundings, amidst forested hills and beautiful lakes. Unfortunately these traditions are not apparent to foreign visitors, especially to those in a hurry.</p>

<p>Gujarati is the main language. Hindi is next most popular. A good number of people will have a working knowledge of English too.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Being one of the major cities of <ref target="Gujarat">Gujarat</ref>, Rajkot is well connected to other cities by air and land transport. For tourists, it's usual to either board a flight from <ref target="Mumbai">Mumbai</ref> (for international arrivals) to Rajkot. For others who are already in India, it's advisable to reach <ref target="Ahmadabad">Ahmadabad</ref> (either by train or by flight), and then take a quick bus ride to Rajkot.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>Rajkot has a ( RAJ ) which has several flights to <ref target="Mumbai">Mumbai</ref> everyday (but no flights to <ref target="Ahmadabad">Ahmadabad</ref>, due to its relative proximity), which in turn is well connected with the rest of the world.</p>
<head>By rail</head>
 is the main railway station. There are several direct trains from all parts of India to Rajkot. Some of them include longer routes trains from Mumbai, Delhi, Kolkata, Bangalore, Jammu, Kochi, Secunderabad, Thiruvananthapuram, Bhopal etc. In common with the rest of India is advisable to book train tickets as early as possible because they are generally not available (ie, in waiting) after the booking slot opens. Booking tickets 2-3 months prior to the journey is recommended. For those who take long distance trains, it is even more advisable.
<head>By bus</head>
<p>Rajkot is quite well connected to the entire region of Saurashtra and rest of Gujarat by buses. <hi rend="bold">GSRTC Bus Station</hi>. is located in Karanpara area, just south of the Town Hall.</p>
<p>If you will be flying out of Ahmedabad, there are some buses that leave from Rajkot and drop you to the Ahmedabad airport. They drop you just outside the airport, so be ready to walk about 10 minutes to get to the entrance, but its paved and many people are walking that way. A lot of private bus companies have a very well established network around the state with comfortable bus options (For e.g. Patel Tours and travels, Eagle travels, Neeta travels, etc..)</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>As Rajkot lies in the middle of the Saurashtra region, it is very easy to visit many famous places from here, whose relatives distances from Rajkot are small.</p>

<p>Commuting inside the city can be done via <ref target="http://rajkotrajpath.com/">BRTS</ref> which covers the roads around the city, but the most favorite is using Auto-richshaws (best to negotiate the rate of travel before sitting inside).</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Watson Museum</hi>, Dhebar Rd, ☏ +91 97241 03824 . The Watson Museum was established in 1888 and was named after the British Political Agent of Kathiwad, Colonel John Watson. The Museum exhibits copies of artifacts from Mohenjodaro, sculptures, costumes of the local tribal people.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Lang Library</hi>, Jawahar Road, Lohana Para (Near by Watson Museum), ☏ +91 281 222 4795, +91 281 2232199 . The library has an extensive collection of old books and a repository of reference material linked to the colonial era.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mohandas Gandhi High School</hi> (formerly known as Alfred High School), Jawahar Rd, Jubilee Chowk. Where Mahatma Gandhi got his primary education. The buildings were built by the Nawab of Junagadh and took the name of the Duke Alfred of Saxe-Coburg and Gotha</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kaba Gandhi No Delo</hi>, Gheekantha &amp; Dharmendra Rds Crossing. Mahatma Gandhi's childhood residence. It has now been converted in to a memorial called "Gandhi Smriti". The museum displays and consists of photographs, objects and the belongings of Mahatma Gandhi.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rotary Dolls Museum</hi>, Yagnik Road, ☏ +91 281 246 4352 . 09:30 – 13:00 &amp; 15:30 – 19:30. Closed Mondays. This unique Museum gives an overview to the culture and traditions of the world at large through a medium of various dolls</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rashtriya Shala</hi>. A centre formpatola weavjng founded in 1921 by Mahatma Gandhi a centre of patola weaving.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Race course</hi>. Where people head for a stroll in the mornings and at nights. The site of major events in the city. Also, Madhavrao Schindia Cricket Stadium is located in the area</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Swaminarayan Temple</hi>, Kalawad Road, ☏ +91 281 245 1000 . A temple of BAPS, a socio-spiritual Hindu organization with its roots in the Vedas. It was revealed by Bhagwan Swaminarayan (1781-1830) in the late 18th century and established in 1907 by Shastriji Maharaj (1865-1951).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shri Ramkrishna Ashram</hi>, Dr. Yagnik Road, ☏ +91 281-2465200 . Has a permanent exhibition showcasing the life of Shri Ramkrishna plus a public library and an Ayurvedic centre</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ishwariya Mahadev</hi>. Located on a hilltop in the outskirts of the city. The surrounding area is a traditional picnic spot.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Panchmukhi Hanuman</hi>, Garediya Kuva Main Road, ☏ +91 99249 21879 . The Temple of Lord Hanuman that is believed to keep the area free of rakshasas (demons). A large number of devotees visit the temple every day to get rid of evil spirits.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shree Ranchoddas Bapu Ashram</hi>, Kuvadva Main Road.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shree Ramnath Mahadev Temple</hi>, Ramnath Para, (Near Aji River).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aji Dam</hi> (8 km from Rajkot). A beautiful dam site constructed during British Raj.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nyari Dam</hi> (13 km from Rajkot). A beautiful dam site. Very good for weekend stay and bird watching</item>
</list>
</text>
