<text id="autogum_voyage_doc311" title="Pays de la Loire" shortTile="pays-de-la-loire" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27057" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pays de la Loire</head>


<p>The <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.enpaysdelaloire.com">Pays de la Loire</ref></hi> is an extensive region of north-western <ref target="France">France</ref> to the west and south-west of <ref target="Paris">Paris</ref>, separated from it by the adjoining region of <ref target="Centre-Val%20de%20Loire">Centre-Val de Loire</ref> with which it shares many affinities. Both regions border on the <ref target="Loire%20Valley">Loire Valley</ref> and host famous châteaux. The Pays de la Loire is somewhat more diverse, however, and has a long coastline along the Atlantic Ocean, forming the northern part of the Bay of Biscay, within the area known as the <hi rend="italic">Vendée</hi>.</p>

<head>Cities</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> is the capital of the Pays de la Loire, though many consider it part of <ref target="Brittany">Brittany</ref>.</item>
<item> is a medium sized city which is the capital of the Maine-et-Loire department.</item>
<item> </item>
<item> is about from <ref target="Nantes">Nantes</ref></item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> a walled city known for locally produced Breton salt in Salt Marshes</item>
<item> or La Baule-Escoublac, is a city in the département of Loire-Atlantique</item>
<item> is best known for its annual 24 Hours automobile race.</item>
<item> is a subprefecture in <ref target="Vendee">Vendee</ref></item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> is a small historical town, known for its <hi rend="italic">château</hi>; the only château of the <ref target="Loire%20Valley">Loire Valley</ref> to have been built in the Loire riverbed, today a museum of contemporary art.</item>
<item> is a port town at the mouth of the Loire, near <ref target="Nantes">Nantes</ref>.</item>
<item> is a small historical town, site of a dramatically situated <hi rend="italic">château</hi> and the heart of its own world-renowned wine district.</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> is a small market town on the river Le Loir in the south of <ref target="Sarthe">Sarthe</ref>.</item>
<item> (more fully, <hi rend="italic">Fontevrault-L'Abbaye</hi>) is an historic town in the <ref target="Loire%20Valley">Loire Valley</ref>.</item>
<item> is a town on the Loire river in the French department of <ref target="Sarthe">Sarthe</ref>.</item>
<item> is an island and commune just off the Vendée coast of western France.</item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Talk</head>
<p>The language here is much the same as the rest of France, with more northern than southern influences due to the influences from Paris, and basic French will be easily understood.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>From <ref target="Paris">Paris</ref>, the A11 autoroute runs to <ref target="Le%20Mans">Le Mans</ref> and onto <ref target="Angers">Angers</ref> and <ref target="Nantes">Nantes</ref>. The A28 runs from <ref target="Normandy">Normandy</ref> from the north and <ref target="Tours">Tours</ref> from the south to Le Mans. Also from Tours, the A85 links to Angers. From the south, the A83 comes from <ref target="Niort">Niort</ref> and runs up through <ref target="Vend%C3%A9e">Vendée</ref> to Nantes. From <ref target="Brittany">Brittany</ref>, there are no autoroutes into the region, however, the N165, N137 and N157 run from <ref target="Morbihan">Morbihan</ref>, <ref target="Rennes">Rennes</ref> (south and west) respectively.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<ref target="Le%20Mans">Le Mans</ref> is in the western branch of the LGV Atlantique line from <ref target="Paris">Paris</ref> Montparnasse (commonly known as the TGV service). Standard mainline track then runs onward to <ref target="Angers">Angers</ref> and <ref target="Nantes">Nantes</ref>. The city also has rail connections to <ref target="Caen">Caen</ref> to the N and to <ref target="Tours">Tours</ref> to the S, to <ref target="Rennes">Rennes</ref> (via <ref target="Laval">Laval</ref>) to the W and to <ref target="Chartres">Chartres</ref> to the E.

<ref target="Nantes">Nantes</ref> has rail connections to the N to <ref target="Rennes">Rennes</ref> and S to <ref target="La%20Rochelle">La Rochelle</ref> as well as to <ref target="Angers">Angers</ref> then <ref target="Le%20Mans">Le Mans</ref> then <ref target="Paris">Paris</ref> by TGV.

<ref target="Angers">Angers</ref> additionally has rail connection to <ref target="Le%20Mans">Le Mans</ref> to <ref target="Tours">Tours</ref> and to <ref target="Nantes">Nantes</ref>.

<ref target="Saumur">Saumur</ref> has rail connections to <ref target="Nantes">Nantes</ref> as well as <ref target="Tours">Tours</ref> and <ref target="Angers">Angers</ref> then <ref target="Paris">Paris</ref> by TGV.

<head>By plane</head>
<p>Pays de la Loire is served by two commercial airports:</p>

<head>Nantes Atlantique</head>
<p>The main airport in the region has good transport links from the center of Nantes and is 10 minuets off of the ring road. If has flights to the <ref target="Caribbean">Caribbean</ref>, <ref target="Africa">Africa</ref>, <ref target="North%20America">North America</ref> and of course, other <ref target="Europe">European</ref> airports.</p>

<head>Angers – Loire</head>
<p>The only commercial flights go to and come from <ref target="London%20City%20Airport">London City Airport</ref> and are run by British Airways. There are three car rental companies operating at the airport: Europcar, Enterprise and Avis. The car park is completely free and has direct access to the terminal.</p>

<p>Also on the airfield is an aviation museum which is worth a visit if you're into that sort of thing.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>The region has a good rail network, with the majority of services operated by <ref target="https://www.ter.sncf.com/pays-de-la-loire">TER Pays de la Loire</ref>.</p>

<head>Loire Valley</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Loire Valley</hi>. The Loire Valley is the 3rd touristic destination in France. It is the largest site in France ever inscribed on UNESCO's World Heritage List under the heading of Living Cultural Landscapes. Kings, artists and famous authors, seduced by the Loire, were many to take up residence on the banks of the "Royal River". You can enjoy Renaissance Chateaux, medieval fortresses, historical gardens or unspoiled landscapes by car, by foot, by bicycle or on board a bareg. Wine, music, litterature, art, sailing, and food are also part of this legacy.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Castle of Angers</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chateau de Montsoreau-Museum of Contemporary Art</hi>, Passage du Marquis de Geoffre, ☏ +33 2 41 67 12 60 . The Château de Montsoreau-Museum of Contemporary Art is the only chateau of the Loire Valley to have been built in the Loire riverbed. Its collection represent the world largest holding of Art &amp; Language works. 9.5 euros.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Castle of Saumur</hi>. Museum of decorative arts.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Castle of Brézé</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Castle of Nantes</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Castle of Brissac</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Abbey of Fontevraud</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cadre Noir</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Castle of Montreuil-Bellay</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Castle of Serrant</hi>.</item>
</list>
<head>Art Museums</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chateau de Montsoreau-Museum of Contemporary Art</hi>, Passage du Marquis de Geoffre, ☏ +33 2 41 67 12 60 . The Château de Montsoreau-Museum of Contemporary Art is the only chateau of the Loire Valley to have been built in the Loire riverbed. Its collection represent the world largest holding of Art &amp; Language works. 9.5 euros.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Castle of Angers</hi>. The castle of Angers shows in its rooms the tapestries of the Apocalypse, which are one of the world largest set of tapestries of the 14th century.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Angers Museum of fine arts</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nantes Museum of arts</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Castle of Saumur</hi>. Museum of decorative arts.</item>
</list>


<head>Other</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bretesche Castle</hi>.</item>
<item> Apremont Chateau</item>
<item> Grand Lieu Lake</item>
<item> Atlantic Coast</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Loir Valley</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Puy du Fou historical theme park</hi>. With over 1,5 million visitors a year, this is one of the most popular attractions in the whole of France. It has 5 main attractions, including a birds of prey show and a Roman style gladiator fight and a number of smaller ones. All spectacles are in French, but for the main ones electronic translators are available. During peak season, there's a regular "Cinescene", a huge show depicting 700 years of history in the region, but you'll need to book separate tickets for it. €31 for adults, kids €22. Booking in advance will give a 3 euro discount..</item>
<item> Airbus <ref target="Saint-Nazaire">Saint-Nazaire</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
