<text id="autogum_voyage_doc375" title="La Fortuna" shortTile="la-fortuna" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11900" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>La Fortuna</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">La Fortuna de San Carlos</hi> is a small town in the north of <ref target="Costa%20Rica">Costa Rica</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>La Fortuna is mostly famous for the nearby Arenal Volcano (1,633 m). The Arenal Volcano is a destination for scientists and tourists. La Fortuna was called "El Borio" before the day of a huge eruption in 1968, when the volcano erupted to the east and destroyed all in its path, including two villages. El Borio (La Fortuna) is located on the west side of the volcano and was untouched. After the eruption of the volcano, El Borio was renamed "La Fortuna", which means "the fortunate", referring to the town's luck during the eruption.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>There are direct buses from <ref target="San%20Jos%C3%A9%20%28Costa%20Rica%29">San José</ref> or with transfer in <ref target="Ciudad%20Quesada">Ciudad Quesada</ref> (San Carlos). Also, buses from <ref target="San%20Ramon%20%28Costa%20Rica%29">San Ramon (Costa Rica)</ref>. There is one local bus per day from <ref target="Tilaran">Tilaran</ref>. From Peñas Blancas (Nicaraguan border) take San Carlos bus (US$8) and alight at Tanque, take bus or taxi to La Fortuna (7 km away).</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">When leaving</hi> La Fortuna, bus schedules seem to be highly arbitrary and unreliable. The more often you ask, the more departure times they will tell you. Some touts will try to exploit this situation. It is best to approximately have a bus departure time, arrive a little earlier and plan for 1 hr waiting or so.</p>

<head>By private shuttle</head>
<p>The cost of a private transportation with a Costa Rican driver is not much if you compare it with the benefit of a direct safe drive to the destination. Available from San Jose to Arenal and other destinations.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>It is a 3½-hour drive from San José, but the junctions are not very well marked, so bring a good map.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>Domestic flights are available with <ref target="https://www.aerobell.com/daily-domestic-flights-to-la-fortuna-arenal-costa-rica/">Aerobell Airlines</ref> or Sansa Airlines. Costs around US$90 for flights to/from San José (SJO) or Quepos (Manuel Antonio National Park). Airport charges US$7/person departure tax.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>The are just one or two buses that go around the volcano. Generally, most tourists rely on taxis or their own cars (everywhere you will have to pay for parking).</p>

<p>Hitch-hiking is actually a reasonable option and quite easy if you are travelling on a tight budget. This way you can reach the park entrance, trails or hot springs time independently and fast.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Arenal Volcano</hi> – The photos at the right of this articles are views from the village of El Castillo, on the southwest side of the Volcano, about 25 km west of La Fortuna and about 4 km up the road from the Arenal National Park entrance. There are great views of Lake Arenal and the Monteverde Cloud Forest from road up above El Castillo. In October 2010, the volcano ceased its activity and the famous flowing lava has been gone since. Seeing some smoke during the day is possible, however, do not expect to see lava/eruptions in the night, regardless of clouds. This could change at any time. Tours to the National Park usually start out in the early afternoon and include walking for about an hour through lava rocks before reaching <hi rend="italic">El Mirador</hi>, the best place to view the eruption of the volcano. There are also possibilities of skipping the lava rock walking and go straight to <hi rend="italic">El Mirador</hi>. Most tours state that they will stay for 1-1½ hours at this place, but if there is nothing to be seen, probably a lot less. It might be chilly, so bring a jacket. The tours come in a variety of options: with buffet dinner and entrance to the Tabacon hot spa $64, with entrance to Baldi hot spa $30, just the tour $25. There is also a possibility of a no-frills tour by mini-bus to <hi rend="italic">El Mirador</hi> and back to Fortuna for $10.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lake Arenal</hi> – just west of the Arenal Volcano and can be seen as you drive over the dam on the main highway to Tilaran. Much better views of the lake and volcano can be seen from the hills above the village of El Castillo, which is located 9 km from the main highway on the Arenal National Park road. Activities on lake include boat tours, fishing, kayaking, and wind surfing.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fortuna Waterfall</hi> (Catarata Río Fortuna), ☏ +506 24799515 , ✉ info@arenaladifort.com . entrance closes 17:00. Stone steps lead to the bottom. Take a swimsuit for the pool in the lovely stream below. The entrance is accessible by road, so a cab works fine too. Once you pay to go in, you are free to stay as long as you'd like. It's about a 10-min hike down to the waterfall and 20 min back up. US$18. </item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">River pool</hi>. Take a dip in the refreshing waters of Río Fortuna and use the El Salto Rope Swing to jump into the water.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Arenal Butterfly Conservatory</hi>, El Castillo Village - Arenal Volcano (20 km west of La Fortuna, turn left at the Arenal Volcano National Park Road and follow the signs. The Butterfly Conservatory is 9 km from main highway.), ☏ +506 2479-1149 . 08:30-16:30. A visit to the Butterfly Conservatory offers a practical educational experience about nature with diversified exhibits of how butterflies, frogs, insects, and plants are reproduced in this natural environment. There are six large atrium habitats that provide representation of the plants, trees, butterflies, and frogs that live within the four micro-climates surrounding Lake Arenal; the lowland habitat, highland habitat, edge of forest habitat, and inside of forest habitat. You will also see laboratories, reproduction greenhouses, the exotic frog habit, host plant gardens and orchid atrium. If you want more adventure, then take the Rainforest River Walk along Quebrada Mariposa, the creek running through the primary forest on the property, where it’s often possible to spot animals such as sloths, tayras and monkeys; or toucans and parrots. Or, just take time to reflect at the Volcano View Gazebo, overlooking the botanical gardens, with views to the Arenal lake and volcano beyond. US$12.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Caño Negro Wild Life Refuge</hi>. Rio Frío are biological humid areas considered to be one of the richest in biological diversity in Costa Rica. Here you can find a great variety of resident and migratory birds plus three different species of monkeys, also iguanas, sloths, turtles and caymans. Along the river you can see many birds, howler monkeys, spider monkeys, white-faced monkeys, also the three-toed sloth and some reptiles like caimans, Jesus Christ lizard and turtles.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Canyoneering (Waterfall-Rappelling)</hi> – In the <hi rend="italic">Lost Canyon</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Horseback ride to Monteverde</hi>– Travel the old fashioned way by horse US$75. This is a gorgeous 2½-hour horseback ride along the beautiful Lake Arenal on wonderful, and hopefully healthy horses.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fishing, kayak, etc. at the lake</hi> – For entertainment a boat navigates around the Arenal lake, so that you can appreciate the unparalleled views. Also, kayaks and other water activities can be done at the lake. Of course the main attraction is the fishing. The lake has many species of fish but the "Guapote" Bass is most prevalent; this fish is a close relative of the peacock bass and is just as strong. Other fish like the Mojara are also prevalent, think 'kin to the piranha but fruit eaters'.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">River cruises</hi> – On the Peña Blancas river, costs around US$45.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">White water rafting</hi> – On the Mighty Río Toro (Class 3-4), with over 45 exciting and continuous rapids that move through 16 km of deep-canyon gorges passing waterfalls in a tropical canyon. Another option is the Beautiful Río Balsa (Class 2-3).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">FlyZone Wakeboard Center on Lake Arenal</hi>, Lake Arenal (Puerto San Luís), ☏ +506 8339-5876 . Lake Arenal is starting to develop into the wakeboard center of Costa Rica. Here you can learn how to wakeboard while the monkeys are watching you from the shore; an unforgettable experience. Always calm water to be found, and year round good air- and water temperatures. For 2018: from one hour for US$140 up to a full day (8 hr) for US$820 per group of 1-4 people.</item>
</list>
</text>
