<text id="autogum_voyage_doc540" title="Višegrad" shortTile="viegrad" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=37939" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Višegrad</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Višegrad</hi> is a city on the banks of the river Drina in <ref target="Sarajevo%20Region">Sarajevo Region</ref>, <ref target="Bosnia%20and%20Herzegovina">Bosnia and Herzegovina</ref>. The town is well known for its <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20site">UNESCO World Heritage site</ref> , Mehmed paša Sokolović Bridge, and the poet Ivo Andrić, nobel prize winner in 1961 for the novel <hi rend="italic">The Bridge over the Drina</hi>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="http://www.visegradturizam.com/">The Višegrad Tourism Bureau</ref> has an English website with many phone numbers and links helping visitors to the area.</item>
<item> Tourist Information Office at the south end of the bridge (opposite Visegrad Hotel) is the best source of reliable information.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>
<p>Daily bus departures from Sarajevo, Banja Luka, Trebinje, Belgrade, Novi Sad, Niš, Užice.</p>

<p>From <ref target="Sarajevo">Sarajevo</ref>, Višegrad can be reached by the M5 road after 120 km. There are a few daily buses from Sarajevo to Višegrad. All buses go from the Eastern Sarajevo-Lukavica station. To get there catch a city trolley from Skenderija centre to Dobrinja and get off at the last station. From there, it is 150 meters to the Istocno Sarajevo bus station. The trolley ticket was €0.90 in summer 2009, and the bus ticket from Sarajevo to Višegrad is around €8.</p>

<p>From <ref target="Belgrade">Belgrade</ref>, Višegrad can be reached by the road M5 via Čačak and <ref target="Uzice">Uzice</ref>, after 280 km in total. Daily buses during the whole day.</p>

<p>Užice to Višegrad 470 Serbian Dinars (€4.70) (2010).</p>

<p>If your bus terminates in Višegrad, try to get off somewhere in the town centre, otherwise you will end up at the terminus on the south edge of town by the sports field, (passing through a tunnel). If this happens it is just a 0.5Km walk downhill to the town, 1km to the old bridge.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>The nearest railway station in BiH is located in Sarajevo, which is 120 km from Višegrad.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>The nearest international airport in BiH is located in Sarajevo 120 km away.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Walk! It is a small-enough, compact town best explored on foot.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mehmed Pasa Sokolovic Bridge</hi> (Na Drini ćuprija). Historic bridge from 1577 over the Drina river, a protected <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20site">UNESCO World Heritage site</ref> .</item>
</list>

 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ivo Andric Monument</hi> (Spomenik Ivi Andriću).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ivo Andric House</hi> (Kuća Ive Andrića). Can be seen only from the outside.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lotus Hotel Building</hi> (Lotikin Hotel). The former Lotus Hotel described in the novel <hi rend="italic">Bridge on the Drina</hi>, can be seen only from the outside.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Marko Kraljevic Tower</hi> (Kula Kraljevića Marka). Old medieval stone tower.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Town Art Gallery</hi> (Gradska Galerija). Exhibition of pictures and sculptures.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ivo Andric Memorial Classroom</hi> (Spomen učionica Ive Andrića).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Virgin Mary Church</hi>, Crkva uspenja presvete Bogorodice. Ortodox church from 1884.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dobrun Monastery</hi> (Manastir Dobrun) (12 kilometers from town). 14th century monastery, with frescoes from 15th century, Art gallery, Museum of the First Serbian Uprising, Museum of the Dabrobosnian Metropolitan. </item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Visegrad spa Višegradska banja Vilina Vlas 5 kilometers from town, old turkish bath from 16th century, one hour rent available, Hotel Vilina vlas with closed swimming pool with warm mineral water, St. Jovan church, summer terrace in spa</item>
<item> Boat ride on Drina river, a few of tourist boats available. Info about boat ride at Hotel Visegrad reception</item>
<item> <ref target="http://www.visegradturizam.com/contact.php">Town tour</ref> , alone or with the local tourist guide.</item>
<item> Cruising the Drina river canyon, additional info here <ref target="http://www.visegradturizam.com/open.php%3Fpage%3D16"></ref></item>
<item> Fishing on Drina river</item>
<item> Swimming, boat drive, kayaking and other water sports (Jaz beach)</item>
<item> Dinner in one of the Višegrad restaurants</item>
<item> Visit of the Visegrad spa description at<ref target="http://www.visegradturizam.com/openfile.php%3Fpage%3D7_38_en.txt"></ref> or info at the official web site of the Hotel Vilina vlas <ref target="http://www.vilinavlas.teol.net/"></ref></item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kruna restaurant</hi>, Kralja Petra bb, ☏ +387 65 626 561 . 07-23. Etno restaurant Kruna, one of the best restaurants in Višegrad, national cuisine</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Višegrad restaurant</hi>, Trg palih boraca bb, ☏ +387 58 631 051 . 07-23. This restaurant has a best position in the town,only 50 meters from the old bridge, it looks directly on the old bridge, it also has summer terrace which is opened during the summer season. Big variety of local food.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>
<p>Night life- live local music on Fridays and Saturdays</p>

<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Višegrad</hi>, south end of the old bridge. Easy to find, bright yellow and pink building! Recently modernised, clean. €43 for double room with breakfast (2010)</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Visit <ref target="Mokra%20Gora">Mokra Gora</ref> in <ref target="Serbia">Serbia</ref>, by bus (take your passport!). It is possible to explore Drvengrad ("Wooden town") - the film set for Kusturica's film "Life is a Miracle" - and take a trip on the Sargan-8 narrow gauge mountain railway, and get back to Visegrad in one day. Catch the <ref target="Uzice">Uzice</ref>-bound bus at approx 09:45, and ask to get off at Mokra Gora station (not the village). The 13:25 train takes you up in the mountains and is due back at 15:48, just in time to miss a bus back to Visegrad! Next bus is approx 18:15-18:30 but check with the owner of the station restaurant, who seems to have the most reliable information.The narrow gauge railway all the way from Visegrad to Mokra Gora is being restored. It was not open June 2010 but was expected to be open by the end of the year. This should be a major tourist attraction when it is fully operational.</item>
</list>
</text>
