<text id="autogum_voyage_doc334" title="Pennine Way" shortTile="pennine-way" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27221" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pennine Way</head>


<p>The <hi rend="bold">Pennine Way</hi> is a designated UK National Trail in the <ref target="United%20Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref> running for 429 km (268 miles) from <ref target="Edale">Edale</ref> in <ref target="Derbyshire">Derbyshire</ref> to <ref target="Kirk%20Yetholm">Kirk Yetholm</ref> in the <ref target="Scottish%20Borders">Scottish Borders</ref>. On its way, the route passes through parts of the <ref target="Peak%20District">Peak District</ref>, the <ref target="Yorkshire%20Dales">Yorkshire Dales</ref> and <ref target="Northumberland%20National%20Park">Northumberland National Park</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The path was the idea of the journalist and rambler Tom Stephenson, inspired by similar trails in the United States of America, particularly the <ref target="Appalachian%20Trail">Appalachian Trail</ref>. Stephenson proposed the concept in an article for the <hi rend="italic">Daily Herald</hi> in 1935, and later lobbied Parliament for the creation of an official trail. The walk was originally planned to end at <ref target="Wooler">Wooler</ref>, but eventually it was decided that Kirk Yetholm would be the finishing point. The final section of the path was declared open in a ceremony held on Malham Moor on 24 April 1965.</p>

<p>Although not the longest of the UK's long-distance paths, it is probably the best known and one of the more demanding routes. It generally follows the higher parts of the Pennines, a chain of moors and hills running north–south along the watershed of northern England. The Pennine Way can be walked in either direction, but is more commonly followed from south to north. This way you tend to have the wind at your back, and most travel guides (including this one) are written in this direction.</p>

<head>Prepare</head>
<p>Although it is waymarked and requires no specialist mountaineering skills, walking the Pennine Way requires a good level of fitness, appropriate equipment and adequate navigation skills. Accommodation is limited along some sections so if you are not camping, you might consider booking accommodation in advance. In particular, the last day normally involves a high-level 25-mile walk across the Cheviots from Byrness to Kirk Yetholm, though off-route accommodation can be used to split the long walk in two.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>The trail officially starts at The Nags Head pub in Edale. Edale is best access by train. <ref target="Sheffield">Sheffield</ref> and <ref target="Manchester">Manchester</ref> are both around a 45-minute train journey away. Bus services to Edale are very limited.</p>

<head>Walk</head>

<p>The route passes through or near the following (landmarks in <hi rend="italic">italic</hi>):</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Edale">Edale</ref></item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Kinder Scout</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Bleaklow</hi></item>
<item> <ref target="Crowden-in-Longdendale">Crowden</ref></item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Black Hill</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Standedge</hi> (near <ref target="Marsden">Marsden</ref>)</item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Blackstone Edge</hi></item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> Mankinholes</item>
<item> <ref target="Hebden%20Bridge">Hebden Bridge</ref></item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Top Withens</hi></item>
<item> Cowling and Lothersdale</item>
<item> Thornton-in-Craven</item>
<item> East Marton</item>
<item> Gargrave</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Malham">Malham</ref> village, <hi rend="italic">Malham Cove</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Malham Tarn</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Fountains Fell</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Pen-y-Ghent</hi></item>
<item> <ref target="Horton-in-Ribblesdale">Horton-in-Ribblesdale</ref></item>
<item> Gayle and <ref target="Hawes">Hawes</ref></item>
<item> Hardraw</item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Great Shunner Fell</hi></item>
<item> Thwaite</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> Keld</item>
<item> Tan Hill Inn (highest public house in England)</item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">God's Bridge</hi> or <ref target="Bowes">Bowes</ref></item>
<item> Baldersdale</item>
<item> Middleton-in-Teesdale</item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Low Force</hi> and <hi rend="italic">High Force</hi> (waterfalls)</item>
<item> Forest-in-Teesdale</item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Cauldron Snout</hi> (waterfall)</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="italic">High Cup Nick</hi></item>
<item> Dufton</item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Knock Fell</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Great Dun Fell</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Little Dun Fell</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Cross Fell</hi> (highest point in the Pennines)</item>
<item> Garrigill</item>
<item> <ref target="Alston">Alston</ref></item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> Slaggyford</item>
<item> Greenhead</item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Thirlwall Castle</hi> and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="Hadrian%27s%20Wall">Hadrian's Wall</ref></hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Wark Forest</hi></item>
<item> Byrness</item>
<item> <hi rend="italic"><ref target="Cheviot%20Hills">Cheviot Hills</ref></hi></item>
<item> <ref target="Kirk%20Yetholm">Kirk Yetholm</ref></item>
</list>


<head>Stay safe</head>
<p>Many parts of the Pennine Way are remote, exposed and prone to sudden changes in the weather. You should be familiar with moorland navigation and be suitably experienced and equipped for mountain walking.</p>

<head>Go next</head>

<p>The trail officially ends at The Border Inn in <ref target="Kirk%20Yetholm">Kirk Yetholm</ref>. From here, a bus service links to <ref target="Jedburgh">Jedburgh</ref> via <ref target="Kelso%20%28Scotland%29">Kelso</ref> where further connections can be taken to <ref target="Newcastle%20upon%20Tyne">Newcastle upon Tyne</ref> (total travel time approx. 2 hours) and <ref target="Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref> (total travel time approx. 1 hour 45 minutes).</p>
</text>
