<text id="autogum_voyage_doc12" title="Erlian" shortTile="erlian" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11068" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Erlian</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Erlian</hi> (二连; <hi rend="italic">Èrlián</hi>) is a city in <ref target="Inner%20Mongolia">Inner Mongolia</ref>. It is also variously known as Ereen or Eriyen in Mongolia, and Erenhot or Erlianhaote (二连浩特; <hi rend="italic">Èrliánhàotè</hi>) in China. It appears as Erlian on Chinese railway timetables, and Ereen on Monglian railway timetables.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>There is a direct flight Beijing-Erlian (Erenhot Shi, code ERL) via Capital Airlines, China.</p>

<p>From Erlian to Hohhot a 40-minute flight was just over ¥170 (Sep 2016).</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>There are trains from <ref target="Beijing">Beijing</ref>. The train station is on the eastern border of the town. Tickets can be purchased at the station 20 days in advance, or from almost any tourist/travel center 5 days in advance. Prices are controlled by the government and there should only be a ¥10 commission on the sale if you buy it from a 3rd party agent. </p>

<p>Train #K23 departs from Beijing at 11:22 arriving in Erlian at 22:30 shared hard berth ¥200 (March 2016).</p>

<p>You can get from Zamiin-Uud in <ref target="Mongolia">Mongolia</ref> to Erlian by train on the international train from Beijing to <ref target="Ulaanbaatar">Ulaanbaatar</ref> as described in <ref target="Zamiin-Uud">Zamiin-Uud</ref>. From <ref target="Moscow">Moscow</ref> and other major Russian cities along the track, you can take the weekly train 43, aka the "<ref target="Trans-Siberian%20Railway">Trans-Mongolian</ref>", to Erlian.</p>

<head>Visa run</head>

<p>Trains to Beijing only run a few days a week. If you are doing a visa run from Beijing, find out when trains will be coming back before going to Erlian. Train tickets can typically be purchased at the train station five days before the train is scheduled to leave, ten days during Chinese New Year (2010). If you are traveling from Beijing to renew a visa, return tickets can not be purchased in Beijing.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>There are sleeper buses from <ref target="Beijing">Beijing</ref>. (¥200, 2011) The long-distance bus station is nearby, about one block west and 2-3 blocks north of the train station.</p>

<p>You can take a bus from <ref target="Hohhot">Hohhot</ref>. There are several buses each day for ¥95 (2017). Depending on the traffic the trip is about 6 hours and 30 minutes. Bus stops for the driver to eat, but there is not much choice so bring some snacks.</p>

<p>You can get from <ref target="Zamiin-Uud">Zamiin-Uud</ref> train center in <ref target="Mongolia">Mongolia</ref> by bus (¥40, July 2009). </p>

<p>The bus station was closed for Chinese New Year until Feb 19 (2010).</p>

<head>By jeep</head>
<p>You can get from <ref target="Zamiin-Uud">Zamiin-Uud</ref> in <ref target="Mongolia">Mongolia</ref> by jeep, which costs around ¥50 per person (July 2009). Russian-made jeeps driven by Mongolian drivers start at the market where Mongolians buy goods to take back to Mongolia. The same jeeps also pick up passengers at the first border checkpoint with Chinese guards if they have room. At the border a jeep will arrive every few minutes. A Chinese taxi can take you to this checkpoint for ¥5-10. The jeeps are allowed to carry 5 passengers; however, some drivers ask the Chinese guards for exceptions and carry up to 7 passengers. If taking a jeep, expect to be very crowded and to either sit on someone's lap or have someone sit on your lap. Get out of the jeep at the Chinese and Mongolian entry points and walk through. Be sure to remember which jeep is yours as they come in only two colors (grey and green) and look nearly identical to each other. Many Mongolians cross the border on a daily basis so they are familiar with the process and can help out. Many speak at least some English.</p>

<p>You are not allowed to walk between the Chinese and Mongolian border posts though they are within walking distance. You will need to pay a ¥5 exit tax. The whole process takes around 1½ hours.</p>

<p>On some holidays (e.g. 1 June, Children's Day), the border is closed and you may be forced to stay a day longer than prepared. It may happen that a driver still offers you a lift, then notices at the border that it isn't possible and still wants to charge you for it.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Taxis, pedicabs and rickshaws are everywhere. A taxi around town costs ¥5 flat rate or ¥10 to the border from town (February 2010). The number one bus also will take you from town to the border for ¥1.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dinosaur Museum</hi> (7 km from the centre of Erlian). This is a cool attraction and outdoor park. There are several exhibits and large outdoor gardens. It takes 2-4 hours to see all the exhibits and gardens. To get to the museum a taxi will cost around ¥40 one way or ¥100 to have the taxi wait for you and take you both ways.</item>
<item> (Konlongmudi). Large replicas of dinosaur skeletons</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sculpture</hi>. There is a giant at the intersection of the main roads - one running east-west from the train station, the other north-south.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dinosaur Plaza</hi> (Towards the center of town). There is a large plaza near the center of town that was under construction (2017). There looks like there is potential for a nice plaza with a dinosaur theme. There is loads of shopping all around. There was a fair in the plaza (July 2017). Several street barbecues set up every night just south of the plaza.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Erlian Grassland Tour Loop</hi>. It is possible to use Erlian as the starting point for the <ref target="Erlian%20Grassland%20Tour%20Loop">Erlian Grassland Tour Loop</ref> itinerary.</item>
</list>

 

<head>Buy</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Antiques</hi> (of suspect age) and touristy knickknacks, at the alleys of gift shops at the north-east corner of 新华街 (mislabeled as Xinghua Street) and 前进路 (Qianjin Road).</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Central Market</hi> (The market can be found directly across the street from the dinosaur square.). There is a large indoor market with many small shops selling all sorts of goods from clothes to power tools. There are also many outdoor stores next to the market. There are many large shopping centers in the area also. There are money changers at the east entrance who will give you a decent exchange rate for Mongolian money if needed.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p>The Mongolian restaurant in the bus station complex (on the left side) has excellent food with reasonable prices and a picture menu. They also have some imported items from Mongolia and ¥1 lockers if you don't want to lug your bag around. Most of the clientele are Mongolians and many of the waitstaff don't speak Mandarin so you know it's authentic!</p>

<p>There are also Muslim restaurants opened by the Hui Muslims of China.</p>

<p>There are many barbecue places on Xilin street that set up outside dinning and start getting busy around 19:30.</p>
</text>
