<text id="autogum_voyage_doc7" title="Cavite City" shortTile="cavite-city" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=154088" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cavite City</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Cavite City</hi> is a city in <ref target="Cavite">Cavite</ref> in the <ref target="Philippines">Philippines</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>This article covers only the city proper; <ref target="Corregidor%20Island">Corregidor Island</ref>, administratively part of Cavite City is practically covered in a separate page.</p>

<p>Cavite City lies at the hook-shaped peninsula that lends Cavite province its name. Until the Spaniards constructed a causeway as a permanent link to the rest of Cavite, most of the peninsula is a sandbar, which becomes flooded during high tide and also pose a risk for ships, and Cavite City, then a town, virtually turns into a an island.</p>

<p>The population is around 103,000, as of 2015.</p>
<head>History</head>
<p>Cavite City has its share of historical charms, and was the capital of <ref target="Cavite">Cavite</ref> until it is transfer to <ref target="Trece%20Martires">Trece Martires</ref>. It is established as a town since its discovery by Miguel López de Legazpi, and at the midst of Spanish colonial rule, Cavite, then called <hi rend="italic">Cavite La Punta</hi>, served as an important point for the Manila-<ref target="Acapulco">Acapulco</ref> galleons, and serves as the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> Port of Manila because of the sandbank that prevents ships from entering the mouth of the Pasig River. As the town grew, Cavite since ceded four independent towns, like San Roque, La Caridad, San Antonio, Santa Cruz, and Dalahican, which remain as barangays. The Spaniards built a causeway over the sandbank to connect the town with mainland Cavite, but erosion reduced this to an isthmus; the causeway remains today as part of Manila-Cavite Road. </p>

<p>During American occupation, Corregidor Island and other smaller islands are added to the city, and the Port of Cavite is converted into a US Navy station, Naval Station Sangley Point. Cavite gained city status in 1940, one year before World War II broke out in the Pacific. Cavite City is devastated by the 1945 Allied bombings; Sangley Point, the walls of Porta Vaga, and the old town is badly destroyed by bombs. Most damaged structures are required to be demolished, and only a few remains of the old Port of Cavite.</p>

<head>Orientation</head>
<p>Cavite City is small, and its street layout has hardly changed since the Spanish colonial era. It is divided into 17 barangays; the most important being <hi rend="bold">San Roque</hi>, which houses the city hall, plaza and Fort San Felipe.</p>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>Cavite City is one of the few places where the Spanish creole language <ref target="Chavacano">Chavacano</ref> is still spoken by most of the population. The variety of Chavacano spoken here is different from what you may encounter at <ref target="Zamboanga%20City">Zamboanga City</ref>, with a different way of indicating verb tense and a distinct set of pronouns. Some local businesses have been promoting Chavacano through signs. </p>

<p>Tagalog is either spoken as a first or second language, and is the lingua franca. English is spoken and understood by many locals, and most signs are in English.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Cavite City lies at the western end of Manila-Cavite Road (Route 62); it is 30 minutes from Manila by car.</p>
<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sangley Point Airport</hi> ( SGL ). <hi rend="bold">Under construction and expected to open by October 2019</hi>, this airport is being built at the present site of Danilo Atienza Air Base and utilizing its current runway, except for some lengthening work to accommodate narrow-body jets. This new airport is expected to receive flights on low-cost carriers, air charters, and general aviation. </item>
</list>


<p>Until the expected opening of Sangley Point Airport, the nearest airport with regular flights is <ref target="Ninoy%20Aquino%20International%20Airport">Ninoy Aquino International Airport</ref> (NAIA), which is about from the city. From NAIA, you can take a taxi, bus or jeepney to the <ref target="Para%C3%B1aque%23By%20bus">bus station</ref> in Parañaque, or just take the taxi. If you arrive on an international flight, they will always touch down at NAIA (the future airport has a runway too short for wide-body jets).</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saint Anthony of Padua Transport</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Saulog Transport</hi> provides service from Manila (Park N' Ride) or Parañaque (PITX) to their terminals in Cavite City. You can also hop onto the colorful but cramped minibuses ("baby buses") from Baclaran in <ref target="Para%C3%B1aque">Parañaque</ref> or <ref target="Bacoor">Bacoor</ref>.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Saint Anthony of Padua Transport</hi>. Most trips depart from PITX, but some still continue to Park N' Ride (or "Lawton" in signs) and Santa Cruz in Manila.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Saulog Transport</hi>, Dra. Salamanca Street. Services leave every 30 minutes from Parañaque Integrated Transport Exchange. Tricycles are available from outside the terminal.</item>
</list>


<head>By ferry</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">MRS Super Shuttle</hi>, ☏ +63 917 827-4669 . Provides ferry boat service between Cavite City and SM Mall of Asia. Boats depart Cavite City M-F at 6:30AM, 9AM, 1:30PM and 5PM, and from Mall of Asia every 7:45AM, 11AM, 3PM, and 6:30PM. Services from Cavite City leave Sa Su and holidays at 8AM, 10:15AM, 1:30PM and 5PM, and from Mall of Asia departs at 9AM, 11:15AM, 3PM and 6:30PM. ₱80 (₱68 for students, ₱64 for seniors).</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Thirteen Martyrs Monument</hi>, intersection of M. Valentin St., Lopez Jaena Rd, Zulueta Rd and the P. Burgos Ave. The thirteen Martyrs of Cavite were Filipino patriots executed by musketry <date when="1896-09-12">on September 12, 1896</date>, for cooperating with the Katipunan during the Philippine Revolution against Spain. The capital city of Trece Martires in Cavite is named after them. In 1906, a monument to the Thirteen Martyrs was erected at the San Roque district of Cavite City, at the head of then San Roque causeway. Their families reinterred the remains of their loved ones at the foot of the monument.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fort San Felipe</hi> (Inside Naval Station Pascual Ledesma). Built in 1609, it served as the fortress for the then town of Cavite, but only half of it remains. As an active naval base, permission is required to visit this fort. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sangley Point</hi>. Former United States Navy station, since turned over to the Philippine Navy and Philippine Air Force. It presently houses the Danilo Atienza Air Base and Naval Base Cavite; visitors must register first before entering. It is also the site of the future Sangley Point Airport (see <ref target="%23Get%20in">#Get in</ref>)</item>
</list>

 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Heroes Arch</hi>. A monumental arch that served as the entrance to the Spanish-era Port of Cavite.</item>
</list>
</text>
