<text id="autogum_voyage_doc219" title="Makassar" shortTile="makassar" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=20917" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Makassar</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Makassar</hi>, formerly called <hi rend="italic">Ujung Pandang</hi>, is the capital of South Sulawesi province. It has the largest population of any city on the island of <ref target="Sulawesi">Sulawesi</ref>, <ref target="Indonesia">Indonesia</ref>, and is the fifth largest city in Indonesia after Jakarta, Surabaya, Bandung and Medan. The city is on the southwest coast of Sulawesi, facing the Makassar strait. It is regarded as the gateway to the eastern part of Indonesia.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Makassar was the traditional capital of the Bugis kingdom (Sultanate of Gowa). The Bugis were known throughout the region as proud, fierce warriors and pirates and highly skilled mariners, and before the Dutch defeated them, they had a formidable empire and sphere of influence in what the Europeans called the "Spice Islands". The Bugis also traded throughout the region, and you can find Bugis people today in many other parts of Indonesia and beyond.</p>

<p>Makassarese cuisine, based as you might expect on seafood, is highly prized throughout the region, so make sure to have some while you are here.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sultan Hasanuddin International Airport</hi> ( UPG ) (is located 20 km from Makassar). Acts as the primary hub for flights to Eastern Indonesia which encompasses the whole Sulawesi island, <ref target="Maluku">Maluku</ref> and <ref target="Papua">Papua</ref>. There are multiple flights from Indonesia's capital, <ref target="Jakarta">Jakarta</ref> as well as smaller cities such as <ref target="Surabaya">Surabaya</ref> and <ref target="Bali">Bali</ref>. The only international flights are from <ref target="Kuala%20Lumpur">Kuala Lumpur</ref> and <ref target="Singapore">Singapore</ref> (not daily though).</item>
</list>

 

<head>Reaching Makassar city center from Sultan Hasanuddin International Airport</head>
<p>Taxi is the most feasible option and should cost around Rp 90,000 to the city (as of 2016). </p>

<p>The Airport Bus (operated by Perum Damri) is operating on the lower ground floor, linking the airport to the city. Ticket costs Rp27,000 (as of March 2019). If there is no one on the counter, you can board the bus and pay after the bus departs. The bus should be departing at a 30-min internal. The journey takes about one hour.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Airport bus (city center)</hi>. 07:00-19:00. Route: Airport (start) - Jl. P. Kemerdekaan - Jl. Urip Sumoharjo - Jl. G. Bawakaraeng - Jl. Kartini - Jl. Kajoalalido - Jl. Arif Rate - Jl. Sultan Hassanudddin - Jl. Pattimura - Jl. Ujung Pandang - Jl. Ribura'ne (end)</item>
</list>


<head>By boat</head>
<p>The main port of Makassar is the <hi rend="bold">Soekarno-Hatta Harbor</hi>. Makassar is a major port for Pelni ships for Central and Eastern Indonesia. It takes about 16 hours to Balikpapan, 24 to Surabaya, and 30 to Tanjung Priok.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Makassar has several bus terminals.</p>
<p>One of the most useful bus terminals is <hi rend="bold">Terminal Daya</hi>, 200 m from the main road from Makassar to <ref target="Pare-Pare">Pare-Pare</ref> (and <ref target="Rantepao">Rantepao</ref>).</p>
<p>The Daya bus terminal is the one that serves <ref target="Tana%20Toraja">Tana Toraja</ref>.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Terminal Daya</hi> (on the main road towards the airport). Rp2000.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Terminal Bintang Prima</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Terminal Litha</hi> (On the main road towards the airport (much closer to the city center than terminal Daya and terminal Bintang Prima)). A pete-pete from the city center to terminal Litha should cost Rp5000.</item>
</list>


<head>By becak</head>
<p>Becak is a trishaw of unique design but minimalist compared to the ones in Java, can accommodate 2 small persons/children, but suitable only for one adult. Fare depends on the distance, usually Rp8,000-15,000 around town.</p>

<head>By taxi</head>
<p>There's a lot of taxi companies, all have the same fare and all use meters.</p>

<head>By petepete (Angkot)</head>
<p>Petepete is the equivalent to other cities' angkot (angkutan kota/city transportation). A trip in town usually costs Rp5000.</p>

<head>By Trans Mamminasata</head>
<p>Trans Mamminasata (Makassar, Sungguminasa and Takalar) operates with Corridor-2 Trans Studio-Mal Panakukkang. Not as TransJakarta which serve only inside Jakarta, Trans Mamminasata serve also to outside Makassar.</p>

<head>By Transportation Sharing Application</head>
<p>On-demand (online) ojek services such as <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.go-jek.com/">Go-Jek</ref></hi> and <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.grab.com/">Grab</ref></hi> are ubiquitous can be booked through their respective smartphone apps, and offer generally cheaper fares which are stated in advance. Payments can be made by cash or using stored value (akin to prepaid mobile phone service). Go-Jek as a pioneer has more widespread availability; those who travel here alongside other Southeast Asian countries may find it useful to keep using Grab. The other more expensive on-demand ojek service is Lady Jek with female drivers. Unlike conventional ojeks, which typically only operate dawn to dusk, they are available 24 hours and relatively safe for both passengers and drivers because they are monitored by GPS. While it seems cheap, those who travel in groups of at least three may be better off taking a taxi for convenience and unnoticeable difference in fares.</p>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>Makassar is a multicultural city, but dominated by ethnic Makassar and Bugis. Therefore, they have a lingua franca language that is, Makassar Malay Language (Logat Makassar) or can be called <ref target="Indonesian%20phrasebook">Indonesian Language</ref> dialect of Makassar.</p>
<p>Macassar Malay is not a creole, but a mixed Malay–Macassarese language, with <ref target="Malay%20phrasebook">Malay lexicon</ref>, Macassarese inflections, and mixed Malay/Macassarese syntax.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Losari Beach</hi> (Pantai Losari). The long stretch of waterfront in the middle of the city. A very nice sunset view. Food stalls set up every night here. This is a hangout place. Do not expect an actual sandy beach.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fort Rotterdam</hi>. An old fortress from Dutch colonial days. Free entrance (they will insist you sign a guestbook). You will be requested to give a small donation, but you do not need to (the money will go to the guards and not to the site). The entrance fee for the Museum (Museum La Galigo) is Rp5000 for Indonesians, Rp10,000 for foreigners (two buildings, but you just need to paid once).If you are a foreigner, you will be the attraction for the locals there, some people may ask you to take photo with them. The friendly attitude makes this experience quite fun, and you can learn a lot about Sulawesi as well from it. Free entrance to main fort.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pulau Khayangan</hi>. A small island about 20 minutes away by boat from central Makassar.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pulau Samalona</hi>. A beautiful white sandy island with good diving. Trip from Makassar takes 30-45 minutes, and costs Rp600,000-800,000 (1 boat can carry 2-8 people).</item>
</list>
</text>
