<text id="autogum_voyage_doc350" title="Gros Morne National Park" shortTile="gros-morne-national" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13473" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gros Morne National Park</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.pc.gc.ca/en/pn-np/nl/grosmorne">Gros Morne National Park</ref></hi> is on the west coast of <ref target="Newfoundland">Newfoundland</ref>, <ref target="Canada">Canada</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>A UNESCO World Heritage site, Gros Morne National Park protects an area of impressive natural beauty, rural Newfoundland culture, and unique geological wonders. The park's namesake mountain, Gros Morne, is the second highest point in Newfoundland at 806 metres. Its French meaning is "large mountain standing alone," or more literally "great sombre." </p>

<p>It covers an area of 1,805 km² (697 sq mi).</p>

<p>Gros Morne is a member of the Long Range Mountains, an outlying range of the Appalachian Mountains, stretching the length of the island's west coast. It is the eroded remnants of a mountain range formed 1.2 billion years ago.</p>

<p>The park's operating season is from mid-May to mid-October: most facilities are open seven days a week, including holidays. This is the high season, so you should book your accommodation well in advance. The park is open in winter with some activities available in winter. All major travel routes are maintained throughout the year, although temporary closures or warnings may come into effect in the event of adverse weather conditions.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Visitor Centre</hi>, Rocky Harbour, ☏ +1 709 458-2417 , ✉ grosmorne.info@pc.gc.ca .</item>
</list>


<head>History</head>

<p>The Gros Morne National Park Reserve was established in 1973 and received <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20Site">UNESCO World Heritage Site</ref> status in 1987. It became a national park on October 1, 2005.</p>

<head>Landscape</head>
<p>The park is in the Long Range mountains, an extension of the Appalachian chain running up the west coast of the island of Newfoundland. The landscape of the park is mountainous and rugged, and has a number of interesting geological features, including a number of fjords and the barren Tablelands.</p>

<p>The park's rock formations include oceanic crust and mantle rock exposed by the obduction process of plate tectonics, as well as sedimentary rock formed during the Ordovician, Precambrian granite and Palaeozoic igneous rocks.</p>

<head>Tablelands</head>

<p>The Tablelands, found between the towns of Trout River and Woody Point in south west of Gros Morne National Park, look more like a barren desert than traditional Newfoundland. This is due to the ultramafic rock—peridotite—which makes up the Tablelands. It is thought to originate in the Earth's mantle and was forced up from the depths during a plate collision several hundred million years ago. Peridotite lacks some of the usual nutrients required to sustain most plant life and has a toxic quality, hence its barren appearance. Peridotite is also high in iron, which accounts for its brownish colour (rusted colour). Underneath this weathered zone, the rock is really a dark green colour.</p>

<head>Fauna</head>
<p>The most notable animal in the park is the moose, part of a booming population that was introduced to Newfoundland around 1900. Other common wildlife in the park include an ecotype of caribou (<hi rend="italic">R.t caribou</hi>), black bears, red foxes, Arctic foxes, snowshoe hares, red squirrels, lynxes, river otters and beavers. Harbour seals are common in St. Pauls inlet, and whales (pilots minkes, humpbacks, fins) may be in the area especially during the capelin season in early summer. Many bird species can be found in the park, from shorebirds along the ocean to birds of the bogs and interior forests.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>The climate in this part of Newfoundland is on the cool side of temperate - daytime highs are around 20°C in the summer and -5°C in the winter. Annual precipitation is just over 1300 mm.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>Most visitors to Gros Morne will probably either fly in to the airport at Deer Lake, about an hour away, and rent a car there (a number of major rental companies have a presence), or take the <ref target="http://www.marine-atlantic.ca">ferry</ref> from <ref target="North%20Sydney%20%28Nova%20Scotia%29">North Sydney</ref> in <ref target="Nova%20Scotia">Nova Scotia</ref> to <ref target="Port%20aux%20Basques">Port aux Basques</ref>. Reservations for the ferry are essential.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Deer Lake Regional Airport</hi> ( YDF ), 1 Airport Road Suite 1, Deer Lake (35 km from the southern park boundary.), ☏ +1 709 635-3601 , ✉ info@deerlakeairport.com . The airport is served by direct daily flights from Montreal (May–October), Toronto, Halifax, and St. John’s. Intra-provincial flights are available between Deer Lake and St. John’s. There are bus services that can also provide transportation from the town of Deer Lake to Gros Morne. </item>
</list>


<head>By car &amp; ferry</head>
<p>If driving from the Canadian mainland, the shortest way to Gros Morne is via the ferry service between North Sydney, Nova Scotia, and Port aux Basques, Newfoundland. It is 300 km from Port aux Basques to the southern park boundary, about a four-hour drive.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Marine Atlantic</hi>, toll-free: +1-800-341-7981 (reservations) , ✉ customer_relations@marineatlantic.ca . Ferries run year-round between North Sydney, Nova Scotia, and Port aux Basques on Newfoundland’s southwest coast. Ferry service between North Sydney and Argentia, on Newfoundland’s east coast, is offered from mid-June to late September. The crossing time from North Sydney to Port aux Basques is approximately 6 hours, and 11 hours from North Sydney to Argentia. Reservations strongly recommended.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Labrador Marine</hi>. Summer. This ferry links northern Newfoundland with southern Labrador.</item>
</list>


<head>Fees and permits</head>
<p>These numbers were updated in 2018.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Daily fees</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> May 16-Oct 31. Adults $9.80, seniors $8.30, families $19.60, children under 18 free.</item>
<item> Nov 1-May 25. Adults $7.80, seniors $6.80, families $15.70, children under 18 free.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Annual passes. Adults $49.00, seniors $41.70, families $98.10, children under 18 free.</item>
<item> Wilderness hiking fees. Long range reservation fee $24.50, Long Range hike $83.40 per person, North Rim hike $68.70 per person, combined Long Range and North Rim hike $122.60 per person.</item>
</list>


<p>Parks Canada Passes</p>

<p>The <ref target="http://www.commandesparcs-parksorders.ca/webapp/wcs/stores/servlet/en/parksb2c/discovery-pass">Discovery Pass</ref> provides unlimited admission for a full year at over 80 Parks Canada places that typically charge a daily entrance fee</p>
<p>It provides faster entry and is valid for 12 months from date of purchase. Prices for 2018 (taxes included):</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Family/group (up to 7 people in a vehicle): $136.40</item>
<item> Children and youth (0-17): free</item>
<item> Adult (18-64): $67.70</item>
<item> Senior (65+): $57.90</item>
</list>


<p>The <ref target="https://www.pc.gc.ca/en/voyage-travel/admission/cultur">Cultural Access Pass</ref>: people who have received their Canadian citizenship in the past year can qualify for free entry to some sites. </p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>A car is probably the most convenient way to get around, because the park is huge, and things are far apart. Biking may also be an option, if you don't mind lots of hills.</p>

<p>Be careful if you drive at night, since moose are often spotted on the roads in Newfoundland, and collisions are common. An adult moose can weigh well over a ton, and hitting one at highway speeds is likely to be fatal. Moose are most active around dawn and dusk, so be vigilant if you're driving at those times.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rocky Harbour</hi> (Inside the park.), ☏ +1 709 458-2376 , ✉ info@rockyharbour.ca . This small town has accommodations, restaurants, shops and services, and is an excellent base for exploring the park.</item>
</list>
</text>
