<text id="autogum_voyage_doc129" title="Western Java" shortTile="western-java" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=39048" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Western Java</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Western Java</hi> is the western third of the island of <ref target="Java">Java</ref>, <ref target="Indonesia">Indonesia</ref>. It covers from west to east the province of <hi rend="bold">Banten</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Jakarta Special Capital Region</hi> (<hi rend="italic">DKI Jakarta</hi>), and the province of <hi rend="bold">West Java</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Jawa Barat</hi>). Western Java is one of the most densely populated regions on earth, but still there are extensive natural areas of impassable rainforest, as well as many active volcanoes and secluded beaches.</p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Jakarta">Jakarta</ref> — the chaotic, congested yet oddly fascinating Indonesian capital.</item>
<item> — the <hi rend="italic">Paris of Java</hi> of Dutch colonial days, now a university city known for shopping and food.</item>
<item> — the former summer capital, known for the world-class botanical gardens.</item>
<item> — once the capital of the powerful Galuh Kingdom.</item>
<item> — nicknamed the 'city of shrimps' at the Java Sea coast, with four sultan palaces.</item>
<item> — mountain town with a cooler climate and many volcanic hot springs.</item>
<item> — Indian Ocean beach town with a nature reserve and a busy fish market.</item>
<item> — city on the foot of the Mount Gede volcano, surrounded by tea, coffee, and rubber plantations.</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Banten%20%28town%29">Banten</ref> — now a small village, but once the centre of the mighty Banten Sultanate.</item>
<item> — archaeological site with (possibly) the oldest remaining temples of Java.</item>
<item> — the blue-water sulphur-smell <hi rend="italic">Kawah Putih</hi> crater lake.</item>
<item> — most-visited national park of Indonesia, centred around two volcanoes.</item>
<item> — very popular weekend getaway among rice fields, tea plantations, rivers, and volcanoes.</item>
<item> — just off the coast of Jakarta, small islands with white sand beaches.</item>
<item> — fishing village on the Indian Ocean, with a turtle sanctuary.</item>
<item> — the last holdout of the Javan rhinoceros and a World Heritage Site.</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
<p>Western Java is very densely populated, with <hi rend="bold">73 million people</hi> living on an area of about 45,000 m (a similar area to the country of <ref target="Estonia">Estonia</ref> or the US state of <ref target="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</ref>), or a population density of on average more than 1,600 people per km². However, the population density is very unevenly divided, with especially many people living in the <ref target="Greater%20Jakarta">Greater Jakarta</ref> area and a few other urban areas, while much of the remainder of the region consists of rainforest and volcanoes where only few people live.</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>For almost 1000 years, from the 7th century to the 16th century, Western Java was under control of the <hi rend="bold">Hindu kingdoms</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Sunda</hi> (centred in <ref target="Bogor%20Raya">Bogor Raya</ref>) and <hi rend="italic">Galuh</hi> (centred in <ref target="East%20Parahyangan">East Parahyangan</ref>). In turn, for many centures these kingdoms were under domination of the Buddhist <hi rend="italic">Srivijaya</hi> Kingdom from <ref target="Sumatra">Sumatra</ref>. In the 16th century, the kingdoms lost their territory quickly to the newly established Islamic sultanates of <ref target="Banten%20%28town%29">Banten</ref> and <ref target="Cirebon">Cirebon</ref>, and Islam spread among most of the population. This is the case until today, although Islam in the region is still influenced by Hindu, Buddhist, and animist beliefs. </p>

<p>Soon after, also the <hi rend="bold">European colonists</hi> (mainly the Portuguese and the Dutch) came to the Indonesian archipelago and to Western Java. The Dutch East India Company (<hi rend="italic">VOC</hi>) established a trading post near the port of <hi rend="italic">Sunda Kelapa</hi> (in present-day <ref target="North%20Jakarta">North Jakarta</ref>) in 1611, and by 1619 a fort was built, named <hi rend="italic">Batavia</hi>. For two centuries, the Dutch administration in Batavia coexisted with the sultanates of Banten and Cirebon, but the power of the colonial power steadily increased. By the early 18th century the entire <ref target="Parahyangan">Parahyangan</ref> mountain region was under control of the Dutch, and by the early 19th century the sultanates were no more than protectorates under Dutch rule.</p>

<p>In 1798 the <hi rend="italic">VOC</hi> was dissolved, and the colony was taken over by the Dutch state to become the <hi rend="bold">Dutch East Indies</hi>. Soon after, the <ref target="Great%20Post%20Road">Great Post Road</ref> was constructed across Java to be able to quickly move troops in case of an attack by the British. The road did not stop the British from invading, and Java was under British rule from 1811 to 1814. Dutch rule was restored thereafter, and the Great Post Road remained important not for military purposes, but for trade, and communication. It became for example much easier to reach the tea, coffee, and rubber plantations of <ref target="Bogor%20Raya">Bogor Raya</ref> and <ref target="Parahyangan">Parahyangan</ref>.</p>

<p>During the Second World War the region was invaded by the Japanese, and immediately after the surrender of Japan, <hi rend="bold">Indonesian independence</hi> was declared in <ref target="Central%20Jakarta">Central Jakarta</ref> in 1945. Then, it took four years of war before the Dutch acknowledged Indonesian independence. Nowadays, Western Java is among the most prosperous parts of the country, although the crowdedness makes that the infrastructure has difficulty to cope, and there are huge economic inequalities.</p>

<head>Culture</head>

<p>The traditional culture of most of Western Java is that of the <hi rend="bold">Sundanese</hi> people. In the <ref target="North%20Coast%20%28West%20Java%29">North Coast</ref> region around the city of <ref target="Cirebon">Cirebon</ref>, the <hi rend="bold">Cirebonese</hi> culture is dominant, which is a mixture of the Sundanese culture with the Javanese culture of <ref target="Central%20Java">Central Java</ref>. Over the centuries, however, the culture of Western Java has been heavily influenced by ethnic groups from other Indonesian islands, and from abroad. The 'native' culture of Jakarta, the <hi rend="bold">Betawi</hi> culture, is in itself an amalgamation of cultures of various ethnic groups that lived in <hi rend="italic">Batavia</hi> (the <ref target="West%20Jakarta">old town of Jakarta</ref>) in the 17th and 18th centuries, including Sundanese and Javanese but also for example <ref target="West%20Sumatra">Minangkabau</ref>, <ref target="Makassar">Makassarese</ref>, <ref target="Bali">Balinese</ref>, Chinese, Indian, and Dutch. Nowadays, Greater Jakarta is a melting pot of cultures from across the Indonesian archipelago.</p>

<p>The art and culture of Sundanese people reflect the influence of prehistoric native animism, the Hindu-Buddhist history, and the current Islamic culture. The story-telling through poetic verses, called <hi rend="italic">Pantun Sunda</hi>, focuses mainly on the history of the Sunda Kingdom, and includes legends such as that of Sangkuriang and the creation of the Tangkuban Perahu volcano near <ref target="Lembang">Lembang</ref>.</p>

<p>A notable example of traditional Sundanese music is <hi rend="italic">angklung</hi> bamboo music, which is a UNESCO Masterpiece of Oral and Intangible Heritage of Humanity. A well-known angklung orchestra is <hi rend="italic">Saung Angklung Udjo</hi>, with an own theater in <ref target="Bandung/East">East Bandung</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Pencak silat</hi> is a collection of Indonesian martial art forms. In Western Java, <hi rend="italic">silat Sunda</hi> (also called <hi rend="italic">silat Bandung</hi>) and <hi rend="italic">silat Betawi</hi> (Jakarta) are specific varities.</p>
</text>
