<text id="autogum_voyage_doc497" title="Belgaum" shortTile="belgaum" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=3268" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Belgaum</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Belgaum</hi> is a city in <ref target="Northwestern%20Karnataka">Northwestern Karnataka</ref>, <ref target="India">India</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Belgaum got its name from Venugrama meaning Bamboo Village. It is the district HQ. The most ancient place in the district is Halsi; and this, once the capital of a dynasty of nine Kadamba kings. In 1776 the country was overrun by Hyder Ali of Mysore, but was retaken by the Peshwa with British assistance. In 1818 it was handed over to the British East India Company part of Bombay presidency and made district of Sangli state.</p>

<p>The Divisional headquarters of seven northern Districts of Karnataka and District Headquarters, Belgaum is a picture of contrasts. On one side is the old town area where the cotton and silk weavers still create magic with their fingers. And on the other the modern, bustling, tree lined Cantonment built by the British.</p>

<p>Kittur in Belgaum district is a place of historical importance. Queen Chennamma of Kittur (1778-1829) is known for her resistance to British rule; another person in the history of Belgaum known for his resistance to British rule is Sangolli Rayanna.</p>

<p>There are several names available for Belgaum city. Marathi people call it as Belgaon, Kannada people call Belgavi, South Karnataka people call it as Belagam.</p>

<p>Belgaum is in the northwestern part of the state of Karnataka, in the southern region of India. It lies near the borders of the Indian states of Maharashtra and Goa. It is <hi rend="bold">502 km from Bangalore</hi>, <hi rend="bold">500 km Southeast of Mumbai (Bombay)</hi> and <hi rend="bold">125 km southeast of Goa</hi>. The town is at the foothills of the Sahyadhri range (Western Ghats) at an altitude of 25,00 feet (779 m) above sea level. The weather of Belgaum is pleasant, owing to its hilly topography. Summers (April–June) are mildly hot and winters are cool (November–February). It experiences heavy southwestern monsoon rains during (July–September). It receives as much as 50 inches of rain annually.</p>

<head>By road</head>

<p>Belgaum is connected by road via the National Highway #4 (connecting Maharashtra[ Now part of the Golden Quadrilateral], Karnataka, Andhra Pradesh and Tamil Nadu) and NH-4A (connecting Karnataka and Goa).</p>

<p>There are a number of Bus operators plying between</p>
<p>a) Mumbai - Belgaum</p>
<p>b) Pune - Belgaum</p>
<p>c) Bangalore - Belgaum</p>
<p>d) Hyderabad - Belgaum</p>

<p>Some of the prominent bus operators are - VRL (Vijayanand Road Lines), Pai Travels, Barde Travels, PVG</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>Belgaum is on the main Indian Railways grid being part of Hubli-Division and is well connected by rail to major destinations such as Bangalore (via Hubli), Mumbai, Pune/Delhi (via Miraj) and Goa.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>Belgaum has excellent city bus connectivity and also for the rural area around Belgaum, the charges are nominal around ₹10 from one end to the other part of the city . Private and Gov't Buses also provide transport for commuting between Hubli, Dharwad, Goa, and other nearby places .</p>

<head>By autorickshaw</head>

<p>This is cheap way of transport between attractions. Though not metered always it would be wise to ask the approximate amount from a local.</p>

<head>By taxi</head>

<p>Normally, Taxis are not needed unless you plan to go way out of the city. If you want to move around in City, Autos and Buses are good enough.</p>

<head>By car</head>

<p>There are many rental companies offering cars with drivers or self-drive.</p>
<p>Hertz : College Road, Belgaum</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>The old stone fort, built in 12th century ad by the local Ratta rulers, is an important spot, though hardly anything of the original structure remains. One can view the splendid Kamal Basti (Jain temple), within the fort's premises. The Fort premises also hosts the Sri Ramakrishna Mission Ashram. This fort was renovated and built on by successive rulers who ruled Belgaum from time to time. Belgaum's Watchtower and Sunset Point should not be missed if one wants to savor the scenic beauty surrounding this small town.</p>

<p>Belgaum is famous for its temples and the religious-minded traveler could find a number of temples here, the main ones being Kamal Basti (in Belgaum Fort) Kapileshwar temple, Shani temple and the Maruti Temple.</p>

<p>A number of religious monuments are located within the cantonment area-the Masjid-Sata mosque, which dates back to the 16th century AD, the Mahadeva temple with its beautiful gardens, the St. Mary's Church of England, St. Xavier's Church, Catholic Cathedral and St. Anthony's Church, all lie within the lush green environs of the Cantonment.</p>

<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Trekking around Jamboti and <ref target="Amboli">Amboli</ref> ghats.</item>
<item> White water Rafting on the Kali Nadi.</item>
<item> Paragliding activities around Belgaum (NCC).</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> The cuisine also has a mixed flavour of central(Marathi)and north Indian flavours. This would be the place to try Chats and other Maharashtrian delicacies in Karnataka.</item>
<item> Ajanta cafe is excellent for its Puri Bhaaji, Dosa's and Spl Chai.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aadinarayan</hi>, Kirloskar Road (Bogar ves). Famous for Fish</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Aadinarayan</hi>, Kirloskar Road (Bogar ves). Famous for Fresh sea food</item>
<item> among the recently opened favorite joints for ice cream is Natural ice cream of juhu scheme. It has its outlet at Nehru Nagar near KLE medical in Belgaum. The shop is open from 10:30AM till late at night and is a delight for all ice cream lovers.</item>
<item> If you are Tea lover then you should visit appolo tea bar near central Bus Stand.</item>
<item> The veg-patty &amp; the cream rolls are amzing here.</item>
<item> Belgaum special sweet, e.g. at Kalyani Sweets in Camp.</item>
<item> Solkadi a drink made from Kokam fruits is also a Goan import goes well with fish.</item>
<item> Pav Bhaji from Shetty Snacks and chat center in front of Aditya Arcade near Ramdev Hotel.</item>
<item> Dhabeli from Sharma hotel on Kirloskar Road.</item>
<item> Tea from Hotel Highway near KLE Dental College and Hospital.</item>
<item> Sugarcane Juice with Aliphak from a shop on congress road near Arun Theatre.</item>
<item> Misal Pav</item>
<item> Kaanda bhajji</item>
<item> Vada Pav</item>
<item> Belgaum's famous sweet-Kunda is available in all major sweet shops.</item>
<item> Butter and toast from Vijay Bakery</item>
<item> Veg Crispi and Gombu Chicken from Hotel Sun N Sand Club Road</item>
<item> Halwa Bun</item>
<item> Hotel Golden Grill near kolhapur circle is good for its flavour.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tatte Idli</hi>, Near Aditya Arcade, Nehru Nagar. Tatte Idli &amp; Masala Dosa with delicious Chutney &amp; Sambar</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aadinarayan</hi>, Kirloskar Road (Bogar ves).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Alurkar Resorts</hi>: This is an Agro-Tourism Resort on Ajra-Amboli Road, near Bugte Alur Village. <ref target="http://www.alurkarresorts.in/"></ref></item>
<item> Hotel Aadarsh Palace : Located opposite Lingraju College</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Adinarayan</hi>, Kirloskar Road (Bogar ves), ☏ +91 831-2424851 . Famous for Fresh sea food in goan style. a rich old heritage of more than 40 years</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Eefa </hi> : The only four star Hotel in North karnataka, Hotel Eefa is located on Club road 5 km from Belgaum city and main bus station (Karnataka, India)and 13 km from Airport. <ref target="http://www.eefabelgaum.com"></ref></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Ramdev</hi>, Nehru Nagar (very near to JNMC campus (KLE Hospital)), ☏ +91 8312470132 . A very good, economical hotel with two good restaurants (veg and non-veg separate).</item>
<item> Hotel Sai Sangam International : Located in Nehru Nagar</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nature And I</hi> : Eco/Home Stay located 10 km from Belgaum (Karnataka, India) City centre. <ref target="http://www.natureni.com"></ref></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pai Resort</hi> : Pai Resort is located at 3 km from Belgaum (Karnataka, India) City Centre and 8 km from Airport. <ref target="http://www.nivalink.com/pairesort/index.html"></ref></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sankam Residency</hi>: The hotel is just a stones throw away from the Pune-Bangalore highway - NH 4. (entry point of Belgaum) and 7 km from Belgaum City Railway station. <ref target="http://www.nivalink.com/sankam/index.html"></ref></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sanman Deluxe</hi>: Hotel Sanman Deluxe is a business hotel located at Belgaum (Karnataka, India) at 1.5 km from Station and Bus Depot and 15 km from Airport.<ref target="http://www.nivalink.com/sanmandeluxe/index.html"></ref></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Surya yatri Nvas</hi> (Kapeel Towers, and located in the heart of city on Kapileshwar road 4 km from Belgaum city and main bus station (Karnataka, India)and 13 km from Airport.).</item>
</list>
</text>
