<text id="autogum_voyage_doc459" title="Lofoten" shortTile="lofoten" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=20009" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Lofoten</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.lofoten.info/">Lofoten</ref></hi> is a group of islands in the northern part of <ref target="Norway">Norway</ref>. With its postcard looking small fishing villages nestled in fjords, dotting a very rugged coast with abrupt peaks rising directly from the ocean, the archipelago is often described as one of the <hi rend="bold">most scenic parts of Norway</hi>.</p>

<head>Towns</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> — a town of 4,500 citizens, and is the largest settlement in the Lofoten archipelago off the coast of <ref target="northern%20Norway">northern Norway</ref>. The town is of little touristic interest. However, it makes a good basis (or at least a transit point) to explore the Lofoten archipelago.</item>
<item> </item>
<item> — a compulsory stopover when traveling by bus in the Lofoten</item>
<item> — pronounced "Oh", this is the southernmost town on the island of Moskenesøya in the <ref target="Lofoten">Lofoten</ref> archipelago of <ref target="Norway">Norway</ref>. The name means simply "river" or "stream", and the town is also known as <hi rend="bold">Å i Lofoten</hi> to distinguish it from other places called Å. A ferry to the Moskenesoya maelstrom (a swirling circular current off the coast of the island), and the fishing museum are the two main attractions of the village, which sits between a picturesque lake and the North Sea, with many of the wooden buildings being built over water on stilts. There are bikes for hire at the <hi rend="bold">Youth Hostel</hi> and at <hi rend="bold">Lofoten Bed and Boat</hi> (150 kr a day) and some hiking paths are dotted around the surrounding area. Nice walks include going around the Ågvatnet lake, crossing the island towards the North-West and the Stokkvikvatnet lake, or going further on the main road (e.g., to Reine). Several ferries a day from the mainland (<ref target="Bod%C3%B8">Bodø</ref>) arrive at Moskenes. From Moskenes, you can either walk following the road (4.8 kilometers, an hour) or take a bus (several times a day, kr 40). It is best to book accommodation well ahead of your travel in Å, as everything may be fully booked during the peak season. (PS: There is no ATM in Å. However, major credit cards are accepted virtually anywhere, including on the bus.)</item>
<item> — this fishing village is known for its incredible scenery.</item>
<item> — a small fishing village on the island, with no tourist information or a supermarket; however, there is a camping location and a car rental option near the ferry terminal.</item>
<item> - a very pleasant village reached by a short bus ride or long painful walk from Svolvær.</item>
<item> - Lofoten's oldest fishing village. Great food and small shops. It lies a little to the south-west of Svolvær, the administrative center of Vågan municipality. The village was founded as Vågan in the early 12th century by King Øystein Magnusson, who built a church and a fishermen's hostel there. According to Heimskringla, there was something resembling a town there several centuries earlier — the first known town in North Norway, known as Vågar. The Lofoten Museum, as well as the Lofoten Aquarium and the Espolin Gallery, are all in Kabelvåg.</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> The <hi rend="bold">Moskstraumen</hi>, popularly known as the <hi rend="bold">Maelstrom</hi> is a very powerful tidal current forming twice a day between Vaeroy and Meskenesoy. It has been featured in many works, usually in a exaggerated form (for instance Edgar Allan Poe's <hi rend="italic">Descent into the Maelstrom</hi>). Captain Ahab in Hermann Melville's famous <hi rend="italic">Moby-Dick</hi> mentions the maelstrom. In Jules Verne's <hi rend="italic">Twenty Thousand Leagues Under the Sea</hi> the submarine encounters the whirlpool. It is unusual because it occurs in open sea. Simply do not go there and expect giant whirlpools...</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Trollfjord</hi> - banned to navigation in spring because of falling rock but otherwise visited on the southbound voyage of the <hi rend="bold">Hurtigruten</hi>. Otherwise take a boat trip from Svolvær. It is so narrow that the Hurtigrute boats, except for the very newest, have to do a three point turn.</item>
</list>


<head>Islands</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Hinnøya (southwestern part)</item>
<item> Austvågøy (southern part)</item>
<item> Gimsøy</item>
<item> Vestvågøy - Vestvågøy is a municipality and island in the county of Nordland in northern Norway. It has a population of 10,764 people, making it the most populated area in the regions of Lofoten and Vesterålen.</item>
<item> Flakstadøy</item>
<item> Moskenesøya</item>
<item> Røst</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="V%C3%A6r%C3%B8y">Værøy</ref></hi> is a small island around six hours from <ref target="Bod%C3%B8">Bodø</ref> by ferry (via Moskenes) and around 2 hours by ferry from Moskenes. The island has a mountainous ridge running through the centre and flat farmland below the mountains. It is famous both for its scenery and the abundance of puffins who nest here over the summer.</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
<p>At 68°N, the Lofoten archipelago is <hi rend="bold">well above the Arctic Circle</hi>, and at the same latitude as Greenland or the northern parts of Alaska. However, it enjoys a relatively mild climate due to the circulation of the Gulf Stream, and temperatures up to 23°C in the summer are not uncommon. Still, it remains a subarctic destination, the weather changes fast, and even in the summer it may get cold. When the sun is not shining a sweater is recommended. </p>

<p>Reciprocally the winter is cold, but remains bearable. Remember, at this extreme latitude - the same as northern Siberia and northern Alaska - winters ought to be very cold, but instead of 40 below, Lofoten temperatures hover around freezing in winter, and starts to climb in April.</p>

<p>The Lofoten, before becoming a popular tourist retreat, was and still is a very important <hi rend="bold">fishing center</hi>, especially for the special type of cod (<hi rend="italic">skrei</hi> in Norwegian), attracted by the rich food brought by the Gulf Stream. At the end of the spring, thousands of tons of cod are hung to dry on wooden racks. For at least a thousand years the very rich Lofoten cod fisheries was a key factors in the Norwegian economy. Thousands gathered from all along the coast to take part in the winter-spring fisheries. Key to Lofoten’s fishery economy was the natural outdoor drying without the use of salt. Low temperatures and constant wind is necessary for this process to be successful, further north it is too cold and further south too warm/humid, while the Lofoten island have the right conditions. This slow drying process creates the characteristic <hi rend="italic">stockfish</hi> (Norwegian: <hi rend="italic">tørrfisk</hi>, literally dry fish). The dry cod was transported to and traded at the <ref target="Bergen">Bergen</ref> harbour thousand kilometers down the coast, the cod trade effectively created Bergen as Norway's (and partly Scandinavia's) largest and most important city. The famous waterfront warehouses in Bergen were mostly used to store dry cod. Still today the stockfish is exported to Italy, Croatia, Nigeria and Sweden (the similar dry-salted cod, the <hi rend="italic">klippfisk</hi>, is particularly exported to Portugal and Spain). </p>

<p>Dry cod is recorded as an important business from the Viking age, but may be older. Long before Tromsø and Bodø existed as towns, Vågar (Kabelvåg) in <hi rend="italic">Lofotr</hi> (today Vestvågøy island) was a major trading post and for centuries the only town north of Trondheim. Bergen, Trondheim and Lofoten were the 3 business centres on Norway's rich coast. For centuries dry cod was Norway's main export, up to 80 % of the trade (as measured in currency) was cod. Vågar may have been Norway's most important town until the Black Death around 1400 and the <hi rend="italic">Hansa</hi> in Bergen seized monopoly in cod export. The original town or trading post was abandoned and turned in to farmland, while nearby Kabelvåg became the new town.</p>

<p>The light varies very much over the seasons. From 24 hours of daylight from May to early August to just a bluish twilight lasting three hours around noon in December and January. In March and September, there is normal daylight hours - 12h day and 12h night.</p>

<p>In 1432 the venetian merchant Pietro Querini and his crew shipwrecked at Røst island after drifting for several weeks from the English Channel. Querini supposedly introduced stockfish to the Italian cuisine. The venetians spent 3 months with the locals and then returned to Venice where Querini produced a report for the senate there. Querini's unique and legendary written report was called <hi rend="italic">The first circuit of paradise</hi>. Despite the cold and dark winter, he described life in Lofoten as paradise ("we spent 3 months in the first circuit of paradise, to the shame and disgrace of Italy").</p>
</text>
