<text id="autogum_voyage_doc381" title="Round the world flights" shortTile="round-world-flights" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=127181" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Round the world flights</head>


<p>Rather than buying separate flights from one destination to another, a flexible and sometimes cheaper way of international travel is via <hi rend="bold">Round the world</hi> (RTW) tickets. A round the world ticket is a plane ticket allowing you to fly around the world, usually over a period of up to a year and with between 3 and 20 stops at different airports. Computerized e-tickets seem to have reduced this to a maximum of 16 segments.</p>

<p>Round the world tickets usually cost far less than the sum of the one-way tickets between each set of individual stops. (One-way tickets generally cost more than round-trip tickets on full service carriers and may be looked at with suspicion by security or border agents.) These tickets are usually slightly more expensive than a return ticket between destinations on opposite sides of the world (<ref target="London">London</ref> and <ref target="Sydney">Sydney</ref> for example), but if you were planning two or more stops then you may find that a round the world ticket is the cheapest option, and allows you at least a side trip. Many travelers plan entire holidays using a round the world itinerary.</p>

<p>As a much more time-consuming alternative, see also <ref target="Round%20the%20world%20overland">Round the world overland</ref>.</p>

<head>Ticket types</head>
<p>There are a number of ways to fly round the world. A "real" round the world ticket is issued as a single ticket, and comes with a host of <ref target="%23conditions">conditions</ref> attached.</p>

<head>Airline alliance round the world deals</head>

<p>Because no individual airlines offer truly global service, round the world tickets are often associated with an <hi rend="bold">airline alliance</hi> and allow you to travel with any airline that is part of the alliance. The specialist travel agents mentioned <ref target="%23Specialist%20travel%20agents">below</ref> can book these flights and provide alternative deals.</p>

<p>The major alliance RTW offerings available worldwide are:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Star Alliance <ref target="http://www.staralliance.com/en/round-the-world">Round the World Fare</ref></hi> With 28 airlines, covering over 193 countries and 1,317 destinations (Nov 2018), this is the champion for sheer number of destinations and easy routing. The pass is available in 29,000-, 34,000- and 39,000-mile versions — in either Economy, Business or First Class — each with up to 15 stopovers. There is also a special "Starlite" Economy-only fare for 26,000 miles, but this is limited to a maximum of 5 stopovers. As in most of these fares, Star's rules require passengers start and end in the same country, but not necessarily in the same city. Some backtracking is allowed, though not over oceans. Backtracking, surface sectors, and transits/connections all count against the mileage total. As for where in the world you can go? Almost anywhere: in addition to the usual suspects, Star has a near-monopoly stranglehold on some regions including Micronesia and the South Pacific. A black spot includes domestic flights within Australia, although there are plenty of international flights to the major cities.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Regions with good coverage:</hi> The entire world, except...</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Weak areas:</hi> Russia, Australia.</item>
</list>




<list type="unordered">
<item> The 15-member <hi rend="bold">Oneworld</hi> alliance offers two types of <ref target="http://www.oneworld.com/flights/round-the-world-fares">RTWs</ref>:</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The unique <hi rend="bold">OneWorld Explorer</hi> is based on the number of continents visited (from three to six) and has no maximum mileage limit. Up to 16 segments, as opposed to stopovers, can be included — in any class of service. However, because of that flight (or "segment") ceiling, this fare can be more limiting than it first seems. (Also, only two stopovers are permitted in the continent of origin.) On the other hand, routings that require major backtracking (i.e., from Europe to Africa) are more easily accommodated here, than they are in mile-centric fares. Travelers are free to change the dates on their ticket at no extra charge.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Global Explorer</hi> is Oneworld's more conventional, mileage-based RTW (26,000-, 29,000- or 39,000-mile tickets in Economy class only; 34,000 in Economy, Business or First class). While the OneWorld Explorer is limited to the full members of Oneworld, several non-Oneworld alliance airlines (including Aer Lingus, <ref target="http://www.fijiairways.com/">Fiji Airways</ref>, Alaska Airlines and its affiliate Horizon Air, Gulf Air and S7 Airlines. Qantas code share flights operated by Air Tahiti Nui, Jetstar, South African Airways and Vietnam Airlines can also be used.) can be used with the Global Explorer. For this reason, travel to certain regions, e.g. many South Pacific islands, is easier with Global Explorer than with Oneworld Explorer. Surface segment rules are particularly rigid and constraining on the Global Explorer, and the 16-segment restriction applies. As with the Star Alliance mileage-based RTWs, all miles are counted, including surface segments. Each surface segment also consumes one of the 16 permitted ticket segments.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Regions with good coverage:</hi> North America, South America (including the Galapagos and Easter Island), the Caribbean, Easter Island, Europe, Middle East, Eastern Asia, parts of the South Pacific (Global Explorer), Australia, India and Russia.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Weak areas:</hi> Intra-Africa, India, the South Pacific (OneWorld Explorer).</item>
</list>





<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="https://www.skyteam.com/en/round-the-world-planner/"><hi rend="bold">Skyteam Round the World</hi></ref>. Long a distant third, Skyteam has gone through a massive growth since 2010 and now bands together almost 20 airlines. Its coverage of China is unparalleled, with four Chinese airlines as members, and Aeroflot ensures that Russia and Central Asia are well-covered. Vietnam Airlines now covers South-East Asia and the Middle East, long a weak spot, now has both Saudia and Lebanon's Middle East Airlines. Mileage and rules are similar to Star Alliance's RTW.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Regions with good coverage:</hi> North America, South America, Europe, central Africa, Russia, China, Central and Eastern Asia.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Weak areas:</hi> India, Australia, Micronesia and the South Pacific</item>
</list>




<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="http://www.thegreatescapade.com/"><hi rend="bold">The Great Escapade</hi></ref>, 29,000 miles and unlimited stops throughout the Virgin Atlantic, Air New Zealand and Singapore Airlines and SilkAir network — great coverage in South-East Asia and the Pacific, but spotty elsewhere. Backtracking allowed. The maximum number of stops within mileage is about 10, e.g. London - Delhi - Bangkok - Bali - Australia Stop - New Zealand Stop - Fiji or Rarotonga - Los Angeles - London. Prices are good value and start from £1025 including tax. For some reason however, this ticket requires that travel must be commenced in either London UK or Manchester UK which effectively prevents North American purchasers from using a westward routing.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Regions with good coverage:</hi> South Pacific, South-East Asia</item>
</list>




<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Four Corners</hi>. Singapore Airlines, Lufthansa, Air New Zealand, Virgin Atlantic. Similar to Great Escapade, but with better coverage in Europe and worse coverage in South-East Asia.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Regions with good coverage:</hi> South Pacific, Europe</item>
</list>




<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Discovery tickets</hi>. Qantas, Cathay Pacific, Fiji Airways, British Airways, and most Qantas codeshares. This is probably the 2nd biggest selling RTW out of the UK, allowing 29,000 miles and 6 stops. However an extra 1,500 miles can be bought for £100, or 3,000 miles for £200. This choice is a lot cheaper than the Global Explorer and the One World, with similar routings, including Africa and South America, and from £765 plus tax.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Regions with good coverage:</hi> Australia, Asia.</item>
</list>




<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">World Walkabout Plus tickets</hi>. Qantas, Cathay Pacific, Fiji Airways, British Airways, and most Qantas codeshares. This is the biggest selling RTW out of the UK, allowing 29,000 miles and 7 stops - 4 can be in Australia including the point of turnaround - within a wide variety of itineraries using the joint Qantas and British Airways route networks. Basically you're allowed 7 stops (including up to 3 in Australia and 3 in New Zealand) and you must travel out and back via Australasia sticking roughly to the routings of the airlines involved.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Regions with good coverage:</hi> Australia, Asia, United Kingdom.</item>
</list>



<p>Discontinued tickets include Big Planet Tour and World Journey (Flying Dutchman).</p>
</text>
