<text id="autogum_voyage_doc239" title="Morgan's Bay" shortTile="morgans-bay" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=23009" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Morgan's Bay</head>


<p>The seaside village of <hi rend="bold">Morgan's Bay</hi> is located on the <ref target="Eastern%20Cape">Eastern Cape</ref> <ref target="Wild%20Coast">Wild Coast</ref> of <ref target="South%20Africa">South Africa</ref> and is about 85 km east of <ref target="East%20London">East London</ref>. Morgan's Bay lies between the famous Morgan's Bay cliffs and a mile-long stretch of unspoilt beach, bordered by the Cape Morgan Nature Reserve.</p>

<p>In the early part of the century, Morgan's Bay was a popular holiday destination for farmers from throughout <ref target="South%20Africa">South Africa</ref>'s <ref target="Eastern%20Cape">Eastern Cape</ref> region. Every year, after the harvest, they packed their families and possessions into wagons for a camping holiday by the sea. These days Morgan's Bay is still a popular camping destination, with families from up country making the yearly trek down to the sea to enjoy the delights of the <ref target="Wild%20Coast">Wild Coast</ref>.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Situated 10 minutes away from the Kei River and the adventures of the <ref target="Wild%20Coast">Wild Coast</ref>, and 45 minutes from the modern amenities of <ref target="East%20London">East London</ref>.</p>

<head>Directions from East London:</head>
<p>Drive North-East along the N2 highway from East London, take the Kei Mouth / Morgan Bay turnoff at Mooiplaas and follow the R349 for 35.5 km. Turn right at Morgan Bay turnoff and follow the road for 7 km until you reach Morgan Bay.</p>

<head>Directions from Durban:</head>
<p>Drive South from Durban along the N2 highway, 31 km past the Kei River Bridge turn left at the Kei Mouth / Morgan Bay turnoff at Mooiplaas and follow the R349 for 35.5 km. Turn right at Morgan Bay turnoff and follow the road for 7 km until you reach Morgan Bay</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>There are no buses or taxis in Morgan's Bay.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>If you're a keen hiker it's worth a ramble over the Morgan's Bay Cliffs. These impressive slabs of dolerite, which drop some 50 m into the pounding surf, are ideal vantage points for watching the sunset. If you're lucky, you may even see the dolphins frolicking in the waves, which crash against the rocks below.</p>

<head>Do</head>
<p>Morgan's Bay is an ideal destination for adventurous family holidays with an excellent swimming beach, patrolled by lifeguards during the festive season, and lagoon in pristine natural surroundings. It's the perfect place to get in some well earned relaxation and breathe in the fresh sea air. During the day you can gaze at passing ships on the horizon or lie on the beach with a book. At night you can lie relaxed in comfortable accommodation while being hypnotised by the dull roar of the sea, glorious stars and the intermittent beam of the Cape Morgan Lighthouse across the bay.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mkulu Kei Horse Trails</hi> (Cheradon), ☏ +27 83 632-7298 . Mkulu Kei Horse Trails Cher-a-Don was established in 1998 and provides guided horse trekking vacations along the Wild Coast of South Africa. Riding tours are available from ~2-hour beach rides, full day rides, as well as 2- to 12-day over-night multi-day riding trails. Multi-day tours are flexible.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Wild Coast Horse Trails</hi>, Sunray Farm Kei Mouth Road Wild Coast, ☏ +27 82 567-0972 . Offers a full holiday experience while giving you the chance to sample the undeveloped beauty of the South African Wild Coast. The beach riding along the Transkei is exhilarating and exciting. Torstone Sport Horses are competitive endurance horses and high quality pleasure riding horses.</item>
</list>
<head>Buy</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Xhosa Crafts</hi>. Xhosa women sell beads and other crafts under the trees near the lagoon.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Craft Markets</hi>, ☏ +27 43 841-1598 . Local Farmers &amp; Craft Markets are held once a month and regularly during holiday periods. They are advertised on the notice board at the Top Shop.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Sandhoppa</hi>, 41 Beach Road (Morgan Bay Hotel), ☏ +27 43 841-1062 . Forgotten your slip slops, sun hat or sun block in the rush to get here? The Sandhoppa offers popular brands including Roxy, Haviannas, Quicksilver and Billabong.</item>
</list>
<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Deck</hi>, 41 Beach Road (Morgan Bay Hotel), ☏ +27 43 841-1062 . Enjoy a choice of breakfast, lunch, tea and dinner menu options. Meals can be enjoyed as a take-away or eat in. Relax and enjoy the 180-degree view of the Indian Ocean while you eat.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Krans Kombuis restaurant and bar</hi>, The Mitford Lodge, Beach Road, ☏ +27 43 841-1510 . Situated on the seafront to provide dining guests with uninterrupted views of the waves and krantzes. Dining at the Mitford Lodge includes sumptuous meals that range from table de hote to an à la carte menu with meals that include seafood platters, deliciously prepared ribs, steak and Italian cuisine.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Mudhutters</hi>, Link Road, Morgan Bay, ☏ +27 43 841-1810 . Open school holidays, long weekends and other times by arrangement for homebakes, homemade jams, pickles, pestos, chilli sauces, etc., Tea, cake and light meals served in our indigenous riverine forest garden. Guided walks with Picnic Lunch.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Shed</hi>, ☏ +27 43 841-1550 . Come and braai, they supply every Friday evening. Had a hectic week? Relax on their deck with an ice cold beer. They can even braai for you. Braai packs, salads and extra goodies supplied. 5 km from Morgan's Bay</item>
</list>


<head>Budget</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cane Castle</hi> (Self Catering), Beach Road, ☏ +27 45 839-4817 . Cane Castle is a double story beach house comprising 2 self-contained units and is located within a 1 minute walk of the beach. Sleeps 6 &amp; 12. From R400 per night.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">DoubleView</hi> (Bed &amp; Breakfast), 127 Yellowwood Place, ☏ +27 43 841-1142 . Newly built, spacious modern home with two large, luxurious bedrooms each with en-suite bathroom. One bedroom has a view of the lagoon and sea, the other the indigenous forest. From R300 pp sharing.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Lower Deck</hi> (Self Catering), 470 Chestnut Place, ☏ +27 43 841-1099 . Situated in a quiet cul de sac, approximately 200 m from the waters edge, The Lower Deck sits a top a hill and is blessed with beautiful sea views. From R400 per night.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Morgan Bay Bed &amp; Breakfast</hi>, Beach Road, ☏ +27 43 841-1125 . A charming old colonial home, situated in a beautiful garden, with the beach and safe swimming lagoon at the bottom of the garden path. From R300pps.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Patty's Place</hi> (Self Catering), Candleberry Place, ☏ +27 43 841-1245 . Patty's Place comprises three self-catering units and is located in a quiet cul-de-sac close to the shop and a short walk from the beach. R500 per night.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tanglewood House</hi> (Self Catering), Tanglewood Drive, ☏ +27 43 841-1031 . Tanglewood House sleeps up to 6 people and is a thatch house set in a lush green belt, a 2 min drive or 10 min walk from the Morgan Bay beach. From R480.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Yellowwood Forest</hi> (Caravan and Camping), Link Road, ☏ +27 43 841-1598 , ✉ info@yellowwoodforest.co.za . Family friendly Caravan Park &amp; Campsite situated in woodland just above the Morgan's Bay Lagoon. We have plenty of shade and are sheltered from the wind. From R85/site plus R10pp.</item>
</list>
</text>
