<text id="autogum_voyage_doc74" title="Prague/East bank of Vltava" shortTile="pragueeast-bank-vltava" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=132700" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Prague/East bank of Vltava</head>


<p>The <hi rend="bold">East</hi> of <ref target="Prague">Prague</ref> is on the east side of the Vlatava River beside the <ref target="Prague/Old%20Town">Old Town</ref> and <ref target="Prague/New%20Town">New Town</ref> districts. It consists of the numbered districts of <hi rend="italic">Praha 3</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Praha 10</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Praha 11</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Praha 12</hi>. Most of the sites listed are in the Casadral district of Žižkov, which roughly corresponds to <hi rend="italic">Praha 3</hi>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
 

<p>Like many districts of the city, Prague 3 is socioeconomically diverse. The western part of Žižkov is known for its high concentration of brothels, strip clubs and cheap bars. Yet only a short distance away are nice apartments and a new shopping mall with expensive stores. Historically, Žižkov was a rough, working-class neighborhood, filled with factories, brothels and gambling bars. Often compared to the Paris neighborhood of Montmartre, Žižkov today is an economically diverse neighborhood filled with Czech families, expats teaching English and working artists. Žižkov is said to have more bars per capita than any other neighborhood in the world.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Praha 10</hi> is an old district in <ref target="Prague">Prague</ref>.</p>

<head>Žižkov</head>
<p>Prague 3 is served by the metro line A|, which stops at Jiřího z Poděbrad, Flora, and Želivského. However, through the heart of Žižkov (oldest part of the quarter with most hotels and restaurants) go trams 9 (it takes just around 10 minitus from "Vodičkova" station on Wenceslas square), 5 and 26 and other areas of Žižkov also trams 1, 10, 11 and 16.</p>

<head>Vinohrady</head>
<p>Stops Náměstí míru  ("Peace Square") or Jiřího z Poděbrad  and trams 4, 10, 11, 16 and 22.</p>

<head>Karlín</head>
<p>Stops Florenc  and Křižíkova  and Invalidovna  . Trams nr. 3 and 8.</p>

<head>Vršovice</head>
<p>Trams 4, 6, 7, 22, 24. No metro connection, but you can go to Náměstí míru  and then use tram 4 or 22.</p>

<head>Trója</head>
<p>The fastest way to get to Troja is to take subway to station Nádraží Holešovice  (you can get there also by several tram or bus lines) and from there continue with <hi rend="italic">bus 112</hi> or the dedicated free <hi rend="italic">ZOO bus</hi> (on weekends in the season) to the station <hi rend="italic">Zoo Praha</hi>. This station is just between the zoo and castle, to get to the botanical garden, follow the marked way uphill (5-10 minutes). Alternatively, from May to October, you can take a steamboat from the city center (Rašínovo nábřeží). If you happen to be in the peninsula area of Praha 7, especially around the Royal Game Preserve or Výstaviště, it can be a nice walk or a bike ride.</p>

<head>North</head>
<p>Northern areas of Prague are accessible via Palmovka  (Praha 8, southern part of Libeň quarter), or via station Nádraží Holešovice  (Praha 7, quarter Holešovice, transit to Pendolino trains), Kobylisy  or Ládví  (Praha 8, quarter Ďáblice - nearly northernmost part of Prague).</p>

<head>Žižkov</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Žižkov Television Tower</hi>, Mahlerovy sady 1, Praha 3, ☏ +42 267 005 778 , ✉ info@tower.cz . 10AM-11PM every day. Built by the communists to jam foreign radio signals, the most hideous building in Prague offers spectacular views of the city. The cafe at the top is a great place to grab a coffee and enjoy the view. Lookout for the giant metallic alien babies that have been added to the tower. Admission is 230Kč (December 2017) for adults.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">National Memorial on the Vítkov Hill</hi> (Národní památník na Vítkově). "Žižkov Monument", located at the top of Vítkov Hill. This immense equestrian statue was erected in 1950 to commemorate Czech national hero Jan Žižkov, who fought his most famous battle on this site and later had the hill and the neighbouring city renamed after himself. The scale of the monument is impressive enough, but the views of Žižkov (and entire Prague) from the top of the hill really make the climb worthwhile.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Military Museum</hi> (Armádní muzeum), U Památníku 2, Praha 3, ☏ +420 973 204 924 . 10AM-6PM. Closed for reconstruction until 2020. Showcases the uniforms, weapons, artifacts, and maps relating to the Czechoslovak armed forces during World Wars I and II. Interactive exhibitions on the World Wars from the Czechoslovakian perspective. Free entrance. Not recommended for young children due to shocking content (war crimes a.o.). Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Church of the Most Sacred Heart of Our Lord</hi> (Kostel Nejsvětějšího Srdce Páně), náměstí Jiřího z Poděbrad (metro line A, station "Jiřího z Poděbrad"). Porbably the most unusual and monumental modern church dominates the big Jiřího z Poděbard Square. Built between 1928 and 1932 and designed by the Slovene architect Jože Plečnik. Candidate to get on UNESCO list. For modern architect lovers, this is definitely a must! After the visit, you can buy something on popular farmer's market nearby.</item>
</list>
<head>Cemeteries</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">New Jewish Cemetery</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Olšany Cemetery</hi>, Vinohradska 153, ☏ +420 267 310 652 , ✉ olsany@hrbitovy.cz . 8:00-19:00. After day in a busy city, walking in calm and big Olšany Cemetery is a great idea! It is the largest graveyard in Prague, remarkable for many art nouveau monuments. The cemetery has calm and mysterious atmosphere, some perts of it are very old. Famous people such as Jan Palach (in protest against apathy of poeple in communism self-immolated student), Klement Gottwald (first communist president of Czechoslovakia), 19th century writer Karel Havlíček Borovský, actors Rudolf Hrušínský and Jan Werich and many others are buried here. free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Old Olšany Jewish Cemetery</hi>, Fibichova (Used since late 18th century, when well-know Old Jewish Cemetery in Old Town stopped to be used. One century later, bigger New Cemetery was built (see above). Located right under the Žižkov TV Tower, more than half of the cementary was destroyed. At least, the oldest part remained), ☏ +420 221 711 511 . Mo, We 11:00-15:00, Fri 9:00-13:00, it's possible to arrange your visit on a different date. 50 Kč.</item>
</list>


<head>Troja</head>
<p>Three of the main attractions of Prague - Troja (the zoo, the botanical garden, and the castle) are close to each other and make a great opportunity for a day trip. To save entrance costs, buy <hi rend="bold">Trojská karta</hi> (Troy Card). The price is 250 Kč for adults, 130 Kč for children and 650 Kč for families (two adults and two children). It also offers free entry to some bonus actions by these attractions. You can buy the Troy Card at ticket offices of these attractions or in the ticket office of Pražská paroplavební (Prague steamship company).</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Prague Zoo</hi> (Zoo Praha), U Trojského zámku 3/120. Founded in 1931, it is well known for its significant contribution to saving many species, most notably the Przewalski horse. In 2008 Forbes Traveler Magazine listed Prague Zoo as the 7th best in the world. The zoo occupies 45 hectares (111 acres) and houses over 5000 animals that represent 674 species from all around the world (as of December 31, 2008). There is also a chairlift in the zoo.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Prague Botanical Garden</hi> (Botanická zahrada Praha). Open air exhibitions including historical vineyard of St. Claire and Japanese garden. Tropical greenhouse Fata morgana. Each year in spring an exhibition of living butterflies.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Troja Palace</hi> (Trojský zámeček). Baroque chateau with garden and art exhibitions. </item>
</list>
</text>
