<text id="autogum_voyage_doc202" title="Lockerbie" shortTile="lockerbie" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=19986" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Lockerbie</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Lockerbie</hi> (<ref target="Scottish%20Gaelic">Scottish Gaelic</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Logarbaidh</hi>) is a small town in <ref target="Dumfries%20and%20Galloway">Dumfries and Galloway</ref>, most famous as the setting for the tragic 1988 crash of Pan Am flight 103, following the detonation of a bomb on board.</p>

<head>By road</head>
<p>Lockerbie is just off the A74(M) which links <ref target="Glasgow">Glasgow</ref> with <ref target="Carlisle">Carlisle</ref> and the south.</p>

<head>By train</head>
 is served primarily by First Transpennine Express trains from <ref target="Manchester%20Airport">Manchester Airport</ref> to <ref target="Glasgow">Glasgow</ref> and <ref target="Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref> via <ref target="Carlisle">Carlisle</ref>. Occasional Virgin trains may be available from <ref target="London%20Euston">London Euston</ref> and <ref target="Birmingham">Birmingham</ref> but trains to these destinations usually require a change at Carlisle.
<p>Lockerbie is about an hour by train from both Glasgow and Edinburgh and about 2 hours 15 minutes from Manchester (another 15 minutes gets you to Manchester Airport)</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dryfesdale Lodge Visitors' Centre</hi>. Mar-Sep 10.00 -16.00, Oct 11.00 - 15.00. An exhibition on the history of Lockerbie, and of Flight 103. The memorial garden is nearby</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hallmuir P.O.W. Chapel</hi> (About 1 mile from Lockerbie). Built by Ukrainians who came to Scotalnd from Italy in 1947.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lockerbie Air Disaster Memorial Window</hi> (Lockerbie Town Hall). office hours.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Eskrigg Reserve</hi> (Lockerbie Wildlife Trust) (Just outside of Lockerbie on the A709, opposite Dryfesdale Lodge Visitors' Centre). Pleasant woodland walks surrounding the site of an old curling pond.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lockerbie Ice Rink</hi>, 14 Glasgow Road, Lockerbie, DG11 2AR, ☏ +44 1576 202197 , ✉ icerink@btconnect.com .</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cobwebs of Lockerbie</hi> (Cobwebs Antiques), 30 Townhead Street, Lockerbie, DG11 2AG, ☏ +44 15762 202554 . 09:00-17:00, Closed Sundays. Antiques, Reproductions, and Curios. Featured on the BBC TV series "Antiques Road Trip".</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Just Be Bistro</hi>, 53 High St, ☏ +44 1576 205715 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Café 91</hi>, 91 High Street, Lockerbie, DG11 2DA, ☏ +44 1576 202379 . 08:30-17:00. Cozy, casual café popular with locals.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Royal Bar</hi>, 6 Station Road, Lockerbie, DG11 2HA, ☏ +44 1576 202374 . 11:00-23:00. Cosy, casual pub, featuring a pool table and darts.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Black Bull</hi>, 13 Station Road, Lockerbie, DG11 2HA, ☏ +44 1576 202647 . 11:00-23:00. Bar with outdoor beer seating area.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Riverside Mill Bed and Breakfast</hi>, Dalton Hook, Lockerbie, DG11 1DG, ☏ +44 1576 510016 . Experience the spectacular sights and sounds of the River Annan cascading through the grounds of the peaceful Riverside Mill B&amp;B whilst still only being 3 miles away from the M74 (M6). £60.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Townhead Hotel</hi>, Townhead Street, Lockerbie, DG11 2AG, ☏ +44 1576 204627 . Check-in: 12pm-10pm, check-out: 11am. Less than 5 minutes walk from Lockerbie Train Station, the Townhead offers well-appointed bed and breakfast accommodation. There is free WiFi and a private car park.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Crown Hotel</hi>, 95 High Street, Lockerbie, DG11 2DA, ☏ +44 01576 203382 . Situated in the centre of town, a short walk from the station, with convenient links to local bus services.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">King's Arms Hotel</hi>, 29 High Street, Lockerbie DG11 2JL, ☏ +44 1576 202410 , ✉ info@kingsarmshotel.co.uk . Pet friendly, Wi-Fi throughout hotel, Complimentary bottled water, Tea &amp; Coffee Making Facilities, Meeting facilities</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Somerton House Hotel</hi> (The Somerton), 35 Carlisle Road, Lockerbie, DG11 2DR, ☏ +44 1576 202583 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Queen's Hotel</hi>, Old Annan Road, Lockerbie, DG11 2RB, ☏ +44 1576 202415 , ✉ info@queenshotellockerbie.co.uk . Check-in: 14:00, check-out: 11:00. A privately run country house hotel standing in over three acres of its own grounds and gardens.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Dumfries">Dumfries</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Annan">Annan</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Gretna">Gretna</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
