<text id="autogum_voyage_doc515" title="County Kerry" shortTile="county-kerry" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=8402" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>County Kerry</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">County Kerry</hi> (<ref target="Irish%20phrasebook">Irish</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Contae Chiarraí</hi>), in <ref target="Southwest%20Ireland">Southwest Ireland</ref>, is regarded as perhaps the most scenic county in <ref target="Ireland">Ireland</ref> and is certainly the most renowned for its scenery. It holds most of Ireland's highest mountains (including the highest, Carrauntuohill) in its most westerly fringes and holds a special place in Irish culture. It became a popular tourist attraction in the 19th century and is still very popular today, despite considerable rainfall. In some places the tourist pressure has arguably had a mixed effect but in general the county is friendly and relaxed as well as beautiful.</p>

<head>Towns</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Cathair Saidhbhín</hi>)</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Oileán Ciarraí</hi>, "people of Ciar's island")</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">An Clochán</hi>)</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">An Daingean</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Daingean Uí Chúis</hi>, "Ó Cúis' fort")</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">An Neidín</hi>, "the little nest")</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Lios Tuathail</hi>, "Tuathal's ringfort") has a 13th C castle.</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Cill Airne</hi>, "church of sloes")</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Cill Orglan</hi>, "Orgla's Church")</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">An Caladh</hi>, "The Harbour")</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Trá Lí</hi>, "strand of the Lee (river)") – county town</item>
</list>


<head>Other Destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Abhainn an Scáil</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Abha na Scáil</hi>)</item>
<item> are six little islands off the Dingle peninsula, inhabited solely by Irish-speakers until 1953 but then evacuated. Boat trips to the largest, Great Blasket, run from <hi rend="bold">Dunquin</hi> on the peninsula, where a visitor centre describes their lives.</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Baile an Bhuinneánaigh</hi>)</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Caisleán Ghriaire</hi>, "Griaire's Castle")</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Corca Dhuibhne</hi>)</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">An Fearann Fuar</hi>, "the cold land")</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Mórchuaird Chiarraí</hi>) – A scenic route around the Iveragh peninsula.</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Sceilig Mhichíl</hi>) – A small island off the coast, granted <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage">UNESCO World Heritage</ref> status in 1996.</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Fionntrá</hi>, "White Strand")</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Páirc Náisiúnta Chill Airne</hi>)</item>
</list>
<head>Talk</head>
<p>English is the most spoken language, however, in certain parts of Kerry such as in Dingle, Irish is the living language spoken by up to 70% of the locals.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>There is the small <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.kerryairport.ie/">Kerry Airport</ref></hi> ( KIR ) at Farranfore, between Tralee and Killarney served by Ryanair and summer charters and this has regularly scheduled flights to <ref target="Dublin">Dublin</ref>, "London"-<ref target="Stansted">Stansted</ref>, "London"-<ref target="Luton">Luton</ref>, <ref target="Manchester">Manchester</ref>, <ref target="Lorient">Lorient</ref> and "Frankfurt"-<ref target="Hahn">Hahn</ref>. However, Kerry is easily connected to <ref target="Cork">Cork</ref> Airport, which serves more destinations, and also <ref target="Shannon">Shannon</ref> Airport near by. (Flights to USA, Canada and the rest of Europe, including Paris CDG.)</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>There is a regular rail service to Killarney, Farranfore and Tralee from Dublin and Cork and there are connections from all stations in Ireland.</p>
<p>See the <ref target="http://www.irishrail.ie">Irish Rail</ref> website for timetables</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>If coming from <ref target="County%20Clare">Clare</ref> or <ref target="Galway">Galway</ref> there is a car ferry across the Shannon estuary between Killimer (Clare) and Tarbert (Kerry) which can save driving and is a scenic route. It departs hourly all year-round and every half hour in Summer from both sides. The ferry crosses the mouth of the river Shannon as it enters the Atlantic and dolphins are commonly seen from the ferry</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Bus Eireann runs regular bus services to and within Kerry.</p>
<p>See the <ref target="http://www.buseireann.ie">Bus Eireann</ref> website</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Options include: </p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Bus Eireann buses</item>
<item> Private bus tours</item>
<item> Rental car</item>
<item> Bicycle rental</item>
<item> Walking - the <ref target="Kerry%20Way">Kerry Way</ref> is a major network of marked trails.</item>
</list>


<head>Car rental</head>
<p>There are numerous major and local car rental companies that have locations in County Kerry. Most will have rental desks in Kerry airport Killarney town or both.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Avis - car rental depot located within Shannon Airport</item>
<item> Budget Car Rental Ireland - desks in both Kerry Airport and Killarney town.</item>
<item> Dan Dooley - Kerry Airport desk</item>
<item> Europcar - Killarney and Kerry Airport</item>
<item> Hertz - Kerry Airport</item>
<item> <ref target="http://www.irishcarrentals.com/carrentalkerryairport.php">Irish Car Rentals</ref> - Kerry Airport</item>
<item> National Car Rental - Kerry Airport</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>
<p>The <ref target="Ring%20of%20Kerry">Ring of Kerry</ref> is the best known area of natural beauty in Ireland. It is a 120 mile circuit around the Iveragh Peninsula in south Kerry passing through Killarney, Killorglin, Glenbeigh, Caherciveen, Waterville, Sneem and Kenmare.</p>

<head>Do</head>
<p>Watch a game of Gaelic football. This is Ireland's national game. It is the dominant sport in Kerry and the county team has won more All-Ireland Senior Football Championships than any other.</p>

<head>Eat</head>
<p>Puffin stew (local speciality)</p>

<head>Sleep</head>
<p>As anywhere else in Ireland, there are many bed and breakfasts (<ref target="B%26amp%3BB">B&amp;B</ref>) in Kerry and around the Ring of Kerry. They are all priced about the same, which is €35 per person during the summer.</p>
</text>
