<text id="autogum_voyage_doc178" title="Sydney" shortTile="sydney" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=34839" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sydney</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.ilovensw.com/">Sydney</ref></hi> is the Harbour City. It is the largest, oldest and most cosmopolitan city in <ref target="Australia">Australia</ref> with an enviable reputation as one of the world's most beautiful and liveable cities. Brimming with history, nature, culture, art, fashion, cuisine and design, it is set next to miles of ocean coastline and sandy surf beaches. The city is also home to the Sydney Opera House and the Sydney Harbour Bridge, two of the most iconic structures on the planet.</p>

<p>Sydney is a major global city and an important finance centre in the Asia-Pacific region. The city is surrounded by nature and national parks, which extend through the suburbs and right to the shores of the harbour.</p>

<head>Districts</head>
<p>Sydney has a compact city core surrounded by sprawling suburbs, forming a vast metropolitan area. The city core, Central Sydney is shaped roughly like a stubby palm-up left hand: the heel of the thumb as City South, the thumb as the district Darling Harbour, the first finger as The Rocks, the palm with the second and third fingers as City Centre and the rest as City East.</p>

<head>Greater Sydney</head>
<p>Greater Sydney, the sprawling suburbs in the vast city metropolitan area surrounding Central Sydney spread for up to 100 km westward from the city centre. The traveller visiting the suburbs will find less crowded beaches, parks, cheaper shopping, commercial centres, cultural festivals and hidden gems.</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>Sydney is the oldest European settlement in <ref target="Australia">Australia</ref>, having been founded as a British penal colony on 26 January 1788 by Arthur Phillip. This day is now celebrated as <hi rend="italic">Australia Day</hi> to mark the establishment of a new nation, although also regarded by many as <hi rend="italic">Invasion Day</hi> that marked the beginning of the British appropriation of Aboriginal land. The settlement was named "Sydney" after Thomas Townshend, 1st Viscount Sydney, who was the British Home Secretary at that time.</p>

<head>People</head>

<p>Sydney is one of the most cosmopolitan cities on the planet, with one third of its population born overseas. European settlement rapidly displaced the Aboriginal people of the Sydney area with colonists largely coming from England, Ireland and Scotland. The Australian goldrush attracted more immigrants, including a significant number of Chinese, with about one in six Australians with convict descent also having some Chinese ancestry. In the early 20th century, Sydney continued to attract immigrants - mostly from the UK and Ireland, with the White Australia Policy preventing non-European peoples (and even Southern Europeans) from settling. Australia's immigration patterns, and consequently, that of Sydney, changed significantly after World War II, when migrants began to arrive from countries as diverse as Italy, Greece, Germany, Holland, China, New Zealand, India, the Philippines, Poland, Lebanon, Iraq, Vietnam, Thailand, South Africa and the Pacific Islands. Sydney's culture, food and general outlook well reflect these contributions to the majority Anglo-Celtic institutions and social establishment.</p>

<p>Sydney is recognised worldwide for its vibrant LGBT community. Every year, the Sydney Gay and Lesbian Mardi Gras is celebrated on the first weekend in March, drawing people from all over Australia and the world for the celebrations.</p>

<p>Sydney was the centre of the world's attention in September 2000 when the city hosted the Summer Olympics - announced by the IOC Chairman at the closing ceremony to be "the best games ever". The Olympics saw a major building and renovation program take hold of Sydney, positioning it as one of the great world cities of the 21st century.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
 
<p>Sydney enjoys over 300 sunny days each year, and it's a year-round destination. Avoid the hottest days for energetic outside activities, and avoid the coolest if you're planning a beach holiday.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Summer</hi> (December to February) is the best time to enjoy Sydney's beachside outdoor lifestyle. Temperatures usually reach around 26°C (about 79°F) but it can be very hot, particularly further inland and to the west, with temperatures climbing to over 40°C (104°F) for a few days each summer. Summer days can be humid, and sometimes have searing dry winds, but hot days frequently end with a "southerly buster", a cold front sweeping up from the south, bringing a clearly noticeable drop in temperature, as well as rain and thunder. Within hours, the storm can pass and the evening continues cooler. Hot, windy days can create a risk of bushfire, and on days of severe risk national parks and walking trails may be closed. Occasionally low pressure systems drift down from the tropics, giving periods of more unstable weather. You won't need to pack much more than T-shirts to visit Sydney in summer, but remember your hat and sunglasses.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Autumn</hi> (March to May) is still warm with mild nights. There can be good days for the beach in March, but you can't count on it. It is a good time for visiting attractions, going to the zoo, catching ferries around the harbour without the summer crowds. You may need a warm top for the evenings, especially for May.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Winter</hi> (June to August) is cool, not cold. Average July maximum temperatures are 17°C, and daytime temperatures rarely drop below 14°C, but night-time temperatures can fall to below 10°C. Most rain falls as a result of a few off-shore low pressure systems, which usually result in two or three rainy weeks during winter. The <hi rend="italic">Bondi Icebergs</hi> will be in the ocean doing their morning laps, but most of Sydney will be well away from the beach. It does not snow in Sydney, and unless you intend spending long periods outside, you can usually get by with just a warm top. Sydney is a year-round city, and only the outdoor water-parks close for the winter. If the beach isn't your scene, and you don't like the heat, winter may be your time to visit.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Spring</hi> (September to November). Spring days are great for exploring Sydney's attractions, bushwalking, cycling, and the outdoors. Beaches are generally patrolled from the end of October, and Sydneysiders start flocking to the beaches in November.</item>
</list>


<p>Sydney's Western Suburbs, which lie away from the coast, tend to be hotter during the day, colder during the night and not receiving as much rain. They miss the afternoon sea breezes and the night-time warming effect of the ocean.</p>

<p>Most public buildings like shopping centres are climate controlled inside. Sydney has a fascination with year-round alfresco dining, where you can find yourself dining mid-winter outdoors with a heater a few tables away. Around 90% of public transport has heating and cooling. For the other 10% climate control consists of an open window. Carry water on a hot day.</p>

<p>Sydney climate and weather information is available online at the <ref target="http://www.bom.gov.au/">Australian Bureau of Meteorology</ref>.</p>
</text>
