<text id="autogum_voyage_doc151" title="Boston/Jamaica Plain-Mission Hill" shortTile="bostonjamaica-plainmission" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=4388" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Boston/Jamaica Plain-Mission Hill</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Jamaica Plain</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Mission Hill</hi> are two distinct neighborhoods within the City of <ref target="Boston">Boston</ref>. They are grouped together here due to their shared border and transit options. Jamaica Plain—or "JP"—is one of the first streetcar suburbs in America and is surrounded by <hi rend="italic">many</hi> parks. JP has undergone significant urban renewal since the turn of the century, with scores of fine shops and restaurants. North of JP, tiny Mission Hill was named quite literally, when a large church was built atop a hill. This small neighborhood is more urban feeling and has a high student population.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Historically, both neighborhoods were simple farming communities within <ref target="Boston/Roxbury">Roxbury</ref>. They became part of <ref target="Boston/Outer_Neighborhoods">West Roxbury</ref> during the mid-19th century for a time, before finally being annexed by Boston in 1874. Around this time a small river, or <hi rend="italic">stony brook</hi>, flowed along what is today the Southwest Corridor. Taking advantage of the available hydropower, several industries sprang up along the route, most notably breweries. Residents have used Centre St and Huntington Ave for almost 200 years to commute between these factories and downtown Boston.</p>

<p>Possessing a wealth of green space and many transit options, <hi rend="bold">Jamaica Plain</hi> is very desirable among Bostonians. The old brewery buildings have been remodeled and updated, while ever fancier shops and restaurants continue to open for business. But JP draws its real strength from the diversity of its residents. A strong character of social awareness and tolerance has mitigated gentrifications worst effects. You can still find traditional bodegas mixed in with the upscale brunch spots.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Mission Hill</hi> came into its own around 1870, after the construction of the eponymous Mission Hill Basilica. Built and paid for by the mostly German congregation, the basilica is striking and can be seen in many views of Boston. The neighborhood has changed drastically over the years. Surrounded by hospitals and universities, it plays host to a frequently rotating cast of young people. And the area affords some great views of the city from its high points.</p>

<head>Neighborhoods</head>

<p>These neighborhoods are listed from north to south. You'll find these larger nodes of activity to be separated by stretches of quieter, more residential areas. Think of the area like a wide slice of residential buildings sandwiched between giant parks on either side.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Brigham Circle:</hi> This is Mission Hill's commercial heart. Most of the neighborhood's shops and restaurants can be found in this area. Named after the nearby Brigham and Women's Hospital, this is a transitional area of the city. Head north or "inbound" to enter the Longwood Medical neighborhood in <ref target="Boston/Fenway-Kenmore">Fenway/Kenmore</ref>. Head south-east on Tremont to continue along Mission Hill, passing the Basilica and eventually entering Roxbury. If you're feeling bold, head up Calumet Street and try to bluff your way into a house party. Your youth and a little red cup camouflage is all you'll need.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hyde Square:</hi> One of Jamaica Plain's commercial districts. Consisting of a tiny rotary and a bunch of fantastic restaurants and bars nearby. Later, head east down Centre Street towards Jackson Square to experience JP's "Latin Quarter". During the 70s and 80s JP was a largely hispanic area, and this section of town still reflects that today.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Monument:</hi> JP's biggest and busiest commercial zone. Heading north from the monument along Center Street affords the opportunity for great people watching and window shopping. If the weather's cooperating, head west to Jamaica Pond, or south-west to witness the amazing Arnold Arboretum. South will take you to Forest Hills and into <ref target="Boston/Outer_Neighborhoods">Roslindale</ref>, and east will take you to Franklin Park in Roxbury.</item>
</list>


<head>By public transit</head>
<p>Taking the Orange Line and walking is the premiere way to access these neighborhoods. <hi rend="bold">Roxbury Crossing</hi> serves Mission Hill, while <hi rend="bold">Jackson Square</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Stony Brook</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Green</hi> serve Jamaica Plain. Green is quite popular, allowing easy access to the main shopping district in one direction, and Franklin Park in the other. Use <hi rend="bold">Forest Hills</hi> when visiting the Arboretum, the entrance is just across the street.</p>

<p>The "E" branch of the Green Line trolley is another great way into Mission Hill. <hi rend="bold">Brigham Circle</hi> is the last stop along its dedicated right of way, while <hi rend="bold">Fenwood Road</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Mission Park</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Back of the Hill</hi> are all street level stops. Watch your step! All trolleys turn around at <hi rend="bold">Heath St</hi>, the terminus of the E branch.</p>

<p>If you'd like to walk a little less, but wait a little more, use the <hi rend="bold">#39</hi> bus. Starting in Copley Square in the <ref target="Boston/Back_Bay-Beacon_Hill">Back Bay</ref>, these big buses run constantly down Huntington Ave following the path of the E trolley. Continuing beyond Heath St and down Centre, they pass in front of every shop and restaurant in JP. Fighting traffic, they eventually make it to Forest Hills station. From Copley to Heath Street, it is arguable faster than the E branch (and a little cheaper), but they come less frequently.</p>

<head>By bicycle</head>
<p>The Southwest Corridor Park, which begins at Back Bay Station, stretches all the way to Forest Hills. It's one of the best bike paths in the city. It's also great for novice cyclists, as the path is completely separated from cars and street traffic at all times. The park runs above and alongside the Orange Line, so consider biking roughly equivalent to taking the T. There are places to lock your bike at all stations, and throughout the neighborhoods. Many locals use bikes here, so you'll never be far from a bike shop if you encounter mechanical issues.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Like most other areas of Boston, driving in these neighborhoods is not a great idea. Only consider driving if you're visiting the Arboretum or Franklin Park, and strongly consider the T even then. Mission Hill borders one of the most congested areas in the city, and traffic is often snarled here at all hours. In Jamaica Plain, the main thoroughfare is called the "Jamaicaway", or Jway. This section borders the Emerald Necklace and can be particularly challenging for out of town drivers. Prepare for high speeds, <hi rend="italic">narrow</hi> winding roads, and a series of busy rotaries along this four-lane undivided boulevard.</p>
</text>
