<text id="autogum_voyage_doc187" title="Derbyshire" shortTile="derbyshire" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=9349" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Derbyshire</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.derbyshire.gov.uk/">Derbyshire</ref></hi> is a county in the <ref target="England">English</ref> Midlands part of the <ref target="United%20Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref>. </p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Towns</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> – county town</item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> – market town and home to the Bakewell Tart</item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Villages</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
<p>The varied landscape of Derbyshire makes it an attractive destination for sightseers, particularly hikers. The south is a low-level clayland area, dominated by the broad, flat, gravel-filled valley of the River Trent. The north and central west of the county is classic limestone hills and valleys. Further north, surrounding these limestone areas, are higher level moorlands, dotted with rock outcrops and gritstone edges, while the lower area are rolling hills and deep valleys with small picturesque villages that a hobbit might feel at home in. The eastern part of the county consists of a rural and urban landscape influence by its industrial, mainly coal-mining, past. </p>

<p>Derbyshire also has many historical attractions from stately homes to early industrial heritage buildings, and includes the Derwent Valley Mills World Heritage Site - a long, wooded corridor running from Derby to Matlock and containing some of the first water-powered mills of the Industrial Revolution. </p>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>Derby people do have a noticeable accent but this is easily understood. You may be greeted by <hi rend="italic">Ey Up Mi Duck</hi>, do not be concerned it is not an insult but a friendly greeting.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> To Derby and Chesterfield: Direct trains from many places including London (St. Pancras station), <ref target="Birmingham">Birmingham</ref>, <ref target="Bristol">Bristol</ref>, <ref target="Oxford">Oxford</ref>, <ref target="Newcastle%20upon%20Tyne">Newcastle</ref>, <ref target="York">York</ref>, <ref target="Leeds">Leeds</ref>, <ref target="Sheffield">Sheffield</ref>, <ref target="Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref> and <ref target="Nottingham">Nottingham</ref></item>
<item> To Buxton and Chapel-en-le-Frith: Trains from <ref target="Manchester">Manchester</ref> (Piccadily station)</item>
<item> To Glossop and Hadfield: Trains from Manchester (Piccadily station)</item>
<item> To Belper and Matlock: Trains from Derby and <ref target="Nottingham">Nottingham</ref></item>
<item> To Edale, Hope and Hathersage: Trains from Sheffield and Manchester</item>
<item> For train times, contact <ref target="http://www.nationalrail.co.uk/">National Rail Enquiries</ref>, telephone 0845 748 4950.</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The nearest airports to Derbyshire are <ref target="Manchester%20Airport">Manchester Airport</ref> and <ref target="East%20Midlands%20Airport">East Midlands Airport</ref>.</item>
</list>


<head>By car</head>
<p>The M1 from London and Leeds runs along the eastern edge of Derbyshire while the A6 crosses from north west to south east of the county.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Coach services are operated by <ref target="http://www.nationalexpress.com">National Express</ref> to Derby from around the country. <ref target="http://www.trentbarton.co.uk/">Trent Barton</ref> connects the Derby to <ref target="Chesterfield">Chesterfield</ref> and <ref target="Nottingham">Nottingham</ref> at very regular intervals on weekdays and weekends. The 'Transpeak' bus service by <ref target="http://www.highpeakbuses.com">High Peak</ref> connects Derby with the <ref target="Peak%20District">Peak District</ref> and <ref target="Manchester">Manchester</ref>.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Local bus services operate between many of the towns in Derbyshire. A number of villages are served by bus services, but many have only a limited frequency. The buses are operated by numerous different companies, including <ref target="http://www.arrivabus.co.uk/">Arriva</ref>, <ref target="http://www.highpeakbuses.com/Pages/Timetables.aspx">High Peak buses</ref> and <ref target="http://www.trentbarton.co.uk/">Trent Barton</ref>.</item>
<item> The Derbyshire Wayfarer rover ticket is good value if travelling on more than one bus or train service. It is valid on nearly all buses and trains within Derbyshire.</item>
<item> The Transpeak bus is the main service for crossing the county. It runs from Nottingham via Derby, Belper, Matlock, Bakewell and Buxton to Manchester.</item>
<item> For timetable information see the <ref target="http://www.derbyshire.gov.uk/transport_roads/public_transport/default.asp">Derbyshire County Council public transport website</ref> or phone <ref target="http://www.traveline.org.uk/">Traveline</ref> on 0870 608 2608.</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Within the county, there are train services between Derby and Matlock and between Derby and Chesterfield.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">East Midlands Trains</hi>. Cheap Train Tickets to and from Derby. <ref target="http://www.eastmidlandstrains.co.uk/EMTrains/YourDestinations/Derby.htm">East Midlands Trains</ref> runs services across Derbyshire plus high speed services to Derby from London, Leicester, Nottingham, Chesterfield and Sheffield.</item>
</list>


<head>Countryside</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Peak%20District">Peak District National Park</ref></hi> - Britain's first ever National Park, set up in 1951. A very large part of Derbyshire is within the Park (though it also extends into parts of neighbouring counties).</item>
<item> Dovedale - a picturesque valley, very popular with visitors and so can be crowded on Summer weekends and Bank Holidays</item>
<item> Ladybower and Derwent reservoirs</item>
<item> High Peak Trail - path for cyclists and walkers along former railway line</item>
<item> Monsal Trail - footpath</item>
<item> <ref target="Pennine%20Way">Pennine Way</ref> - a long distance footpath, which starts in the north of the county</item>
<item> Carsington Water - a reservoir</item>
</list>


<head>Country houses</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Chatsworth House - near <ref target="Bakewell">Bakewell</ref></item>
<item> Haddon Hall - near Bakewell</item>
<item> Kedleston Hall - near <ref target="Derby">Derby</ref></item>
<item> Calke Abbey - near <ref target="Melbourne%20%28Derbyshire%29">Melbourne</ref></item>
<item> Sudbury Hall (also includes The Museum of Childhood) - south of <ref target="Ashbourne">Ashbourne</ref> near <ref target="Uttoxeter">Uttoxeter</ref></item>
</list>


<head>Other historic buildings</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Derwent Valley World Heritage Site</item>
<item> <ref target="Cromford">Cromford</ref> Mill</item>
<item> <ref target="Belper">Belper</ref> North Mill</item>
</list>


<head>Museums</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Derby museums (see <ref target="Derby">Derby</ref> article)</item>
<item> Derbyshire Stone Centre, <ref target="Wirksworth">Wirksworth</ref></item>
</list>


<head>Heritage of transport</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Crich">Crich</ref> Tramway Village (also known as The National Tramway Museum)</item>
<item> Midland Railway Centre, <ref target="Ripley%20%28Derbyshire%29">Ripley</ref></item>
<item> Ecclesbourne Valley Railway in <ref target="Wirksworth">Wirksworth</ref></item>
<item> Peak Rail</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Hiking</item>
<item> Pot holing</item>
<item> Climbing</item>
</list>


<head>Itineraries</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Pennine%20Way">Pennine Way</ref></item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p>There are many great country inns serving English pub food making exploring the villages very rewarding.</p>

<p>The tea rooms serve some excellent cakes. Cream tea (scones, clotted cream and jam) makes a pleasant afternoon break, but also look out for locally made Bakewell pudding and Bakewell tarts.</p>

<p>Also do not miss checking out the local Fish &amp; Chips takeaways, not just for fish and fries but also for the steak and kidney pies, chicken and mushroom, battered sausages and mushy peas.</p>

<p>The city of Derby also has some excellent Indian restaurants.</p>

<head>Drink</head>
<p>The county has a large number of pubs in the towns and in the country serving numerous brands of real ale.</p>
</text>
