<text id="autogum_voyage_doc170" title="Douglas (Arizona)" shortTile="douglas-arizona" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=9969" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Douglas (Arizona)</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Douglas</hi> is a town in Cochise County, <ref target="Arizona">Arizona</ref>. While known primarily as a gateway to Mexico, its small downtown core has a few well-preserved examples of early 20th-century architecture. The town is also noted as the temporary residence of Thornton Wilder, who wrote most of his classic 1967 novel <hi rend="italic">The Eighth Day</hi> while based here.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Douglas Visitor Center</hi>, 345 16th St, ☏ +1 520-417-7344 , fax: +1 520-364-6304 , ✉ info@douglasaz.gov . Offers a helpful <ref target="http://visitdouglas.com/DouglasMap.pdf">map</ref> for walking tours.</item>
</list>


<head>Get in</head>
<p>Douglas is most easily reached by driving Highway 80 or Highway 191 south from I-10.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>The town is pedestrian-friendly, and most sights and restaurants are within easy walking distance. There is no public transportation, so a car is needed to go further afield.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Grand Theatre</hi>, 1139 N G Ave, ☏ +1 520-364-6144 . On the National Register of Historic Places, Ginger Rogers, Anna Pavlova, and John Philip Sousa all performed here. The theatre was closed in 1958, and after decades of neglect is undergoing a complete restoration. It is not yet open to the public, but the ornate facade can be appreciated from the outside. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Douglas Williams House</hi>, 1001 D Ave, ☏ +1 520-364-7370 , ✉ info.doughistsoc@qwestoffice.net . W 10AM-4PM, Sat 12PM-4PM. A small museum displaying historic photographs and memorabilia from the area.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Border Air Museum</hi>, E 10th St and Airport Rd, ☏ +1 520-364-2478 . Summer M-F 12PM-4PM, Sa 11AM-3PM. A small museum dedicated to the history of cross-border aviation in Douglas.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cochise County Fair</hi>, 3677 N Leslie Canyon Rd, ☏ +1 520-364-3819 . all day. Held annually in late September. Attractions include animal exhibits, amusement rides, and rodeo events. $6 (adults).</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<p>As a gateway to Mexico, many visitors walk across the border to <ref target="Agua%20Prieta">Agua Prieta</ref> for the day, which has a number of curio and souvenir shops.</p>

<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Border Taco</hi>, 103 E 5th St, ☏ +1 520-364-6196 . Daily 7:30AM-10PM. A very popular Mexican fast-food restaurant, with good burritos, flautas, and caldos (soups). The service can be a little disorganized, but the food is worth the wait. Burritos $3-6, soups $7.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Casa Segovia</hi> (formerly El Conquistador Restaurant), 1046 G Ave (Gadsden Hotel), ☏ +1 520-364-1169 . Su 7AM-7PM, M-Sa 7AM-9PM. Hotel restaurant operated by the local restaurateur Segovia family. For more details about the Gadsden Hotel, see listing below.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chatitas Mexican Restaurant</hi>, 301 E 10th St (entrance on Pan American Ave), ☏ +1 520-364-1144 . Daily 7:30AM-9PM. One of the most popular Mexican restaurants in town. Mains $8-12.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">El Chef</hi>, 1057 11th St, ☏ +1 520-364-5765 . Su Mo 7AM-3PM, Tu-Sa 7AM-8PM. Good Mexican food, particularly popular for breakfast.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Grand Café</hi>, 1119 G Ave, ☏ +1 520-364-2344 . Serves Sonoran Mexican cuisine. Service can sometimes be a bit spotty, but the food is usually very good.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">La Fiesta Café</hi>, 1844 E 10th St, ☏ +1 520-805-0033 . Daily 10AM-8PM. Excellent Mexican food, very friendly people.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Spice Café</hi>, 1030 19th St (Travelers Motel), ☏ +1 520-364-8434 . Surprisingly authentic Indian food, particularly popular for breakfast and brunches. Can cook up vegetarian meals on request.</item>
</list>


<head>Groceries</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Food City</hi>, 1300 San Antonio Ave, ☏ +1 520-364-3431 . Daily 6AM-11PM. Has a pharmacy and tortilleria.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Saddle &amp; Spur Tavern</hi>, 1046 G Ave (Gadsden Hotel), ☏ +1 520-364-4481 . Known for the assortment of cattle brands displayed on the walls. For a description of the hotel, see listing below.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gadsden Hotel</hi>, 1046 G Ave, ☏ +1 520-364-4481 , fax: +1 520-364-4005 , ✉ robin@hotelgadsden.com . Check-in: 3PM, check-out: 11AM. A National Historic site which in its heyday hosted the likes of John Wayne, Spencer Tracy, and Thornton Wilder. It is widely believed to be haunted by several ghosts, one of them headless. The mezzanine features a 42-foot long Tiffany stained glass mural as well as an Italian marble staircase, and has featured in several films. $60-$150/night. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Travelers Motel</hi>, 1030 E 19th St, ☏ +1 520-364-8434 . Check-in: 12PM, check-out: 11AM. An older but well-maintained motel. Has an outdoor pool and free Wi-Fi, as well as on-site restaurant. $39+.</item>
</list>


<head>Consulates</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Consulate of Mexico</hi>, 1201 F Ave, ☏ +1 520-364-3107 , fax: +1 520-364-1379 .</item>
</list>


<head>News</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Douglas Dispatch</hi>. Also available in print.</item>
</list>


<head>Medical clinic</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Southeast Arizona Medical Center</hi>, 2174 W Oak Ave (corner of N County Hospital Rd), ☏ +1 520-364-7931 .</item>
</list>
</text>
