<text id="autogum_voyage_doc158" title="Arad (Romania)" shortTile="arad-romania" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=1425" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Arad (Romania)</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Arad</hi> is an industrial city of some 160,000 population at the western edge of Romania, close to the border with Hungary. It is a regional transportation hub and a convenient place to stop over on a journey between those countries. There is an intact Vauban-style fortress and an interesting old town with a great number of historic buildings. Most of them date from the <ref target="Austro-Hungarian%20Empire">Habsburg era</ref>, ranging from Baroque to Art Nouveau. While some have been recently renovated, others are left in a state of dilapidation. </p>

<p>The city's cultural life is marked by a Philharmonic Orchestra, several theatres and a museum complex. The latter is particularly interesting for history buffs, as it showcases evidence from various eras of human history that have been discovered in this area. The Arad county <ref target="wine">wine</ref> route starts a few kilometer east of the city.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>The nearest commercial airport is <ref target="Timisoara">Timisoara</ref> (Traian Vuia TSR) 40 km south, with 6 or 7 flights a day to Bucharest, and other European destinations. </p>

<p>Budapest (Ferihegy BUD) airport 230 km north-west has extensive connections.</p>

 <hi rend="bold">Arad Airport</hi> (Aeroportul Internațional Arad ASW) (4 km west of the city). Has only an occasional holiday charter flight.

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Arad is on the main highway E68 between Budapest and Bucharest. There are buses every hour or two to Timisoara (60-90 min); change there for Bucharest. Buses run every 30 min to Budapest, the fastest in only two hours.</p>

<p>For Transylvania, four or five buses run daily to Deva (3 hr), Sibiu (5 hr) and Brasov (8 hr). There are four buses to Cluj Napoca (4-6 hr).</p>

<p>The bus station is in the Atrium Centre on Aurel Vlaicu Bvd, 200 m west of the railway station and 2 km north of city centre.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>There are five direct trains a day to <ref target="Budapest">Budapest</ref> Keleti, taking 4 hr 30 min, fare 100 lei. (This includes an hour waiting at the border; there's also a one-hour time switch between Romania and Hungary.) The last direct train is at 15:30, but there's a 17:00 indirect route taking six hours. The 01:00 train is a through-service to Vienna.</p>

<p>There are only two direct services to <ref target="Bucharest">Bucharest</ref>, both overnight, 11 hr. The best daytime connection is via the midday train to <ref target="Timi%C8%99oara">Timișoara</ref>. </p>

<p>For Transylvania, take the mid-afternoon train running through Deva (3 hr) and <ref target="Sibiu">Sibiu</ref> (6 hr) to <ref target="Brasov">Brasov</ref> (10 hr).</p>

<p>There are two direct trains to <ref target="Ia%C8%99i">Iași</ref> (one daytime 14 hrs, one overnight 17 hr) via <ref target="Cluj%20Napoca">Cluj Napoca</ref>. There's one other direct and two indirect services to Cluj Napoca (5-6 hr).</p>

<p>All passenger trains are run by <hi rend="italic"><ref target="http://www.cfrcalatori.ro/">CFR Calatori</ref></hi>. (<hi rend="italic">Gara Arad</hi>) is 2 km north of the city centre at Piața Gării 8-9. The interior is modernised; few facilities within but lots of fast food places, small supermarkets, currency exchange etc just outside on the main boulevard.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Most sights, eating and accommodation are a short walk from City Hall. Buses and trams run along the main strip here, Bulevard Revolutiei. At its north end this curves west into Calea Aurel Vlaicu, with the bus &amp; railway stations. Taxis and car hire are readily available.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Holy Trinity Orthodox Cathedral</hi> (Catedrala Ortodoxă "Sfânta Treime"), Bulevardul Revolutiei. Built in 1992-2006, the interior was re-plastered &amp; repainted in 2018, with wooden scaffolding filling the northern part near the iconostasis. The murals at the southern part, by the entrance, look very fresh. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lutheran Church</hi> (Biserica Roșie, "Red church"), Bd. Revoluției 61. Built in 1906 from red bricks (hence the nickname), Gothic Revival style. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Administrative Palace</hi> (Palatul Administrativ), Bd. Revoluției 75. Impressive city hall, built in 1876 in Renaissance Revival style. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Neumann Palace</hi> (Palatul Neumann), Bd. Revoluției 78/str. Horia (across the city hall). Representative building created for a very rich industrialist in 1891–92, eclectic style. Today it houses a number of shops as well as the private Vasile Goldiș University. The former ballroom was converted into an auditorium for 200 students. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cultural Palace &amp; Museum</hi> (Palatul Cultural &amp; Complexul Muzeal), Piaţa George Enescu 1 (by City Hall). Museum Tu-Su 09:00-17:00. Imposing cultural complex, dating from 1911-13, in an eclectic style mix of neoclassical, Gothic and Renaissance elements. The museum has three divisions: fine arts, natural sciences, and archaeology/history. The philharmonic orchestra (filarmonia) has regular concerts: the box office is in the Ioan Slavici Theatre. 2 lei. </item>
<item> Just east of the Palace is the Mures river, with a promenade for strolling, and a children's play-park.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Moise Nicoară National College</hi> (Colegiul Național "Moise Nicoară"). Stately school building, built from 1869–1873 with Renaissance and Baroque elements. It was thoroughly refurbished after 2010 and made one of Romania's best equipped schools. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St. Anthony of Padova Church</hi> (Biserica Sf. Anton de Padova). Roman Catholic cathedral built in 1904 in neo-Renaissance style. </item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ioan Slavici Classical Theatre</hi> (Teatrul Clasic „Ioan Slavici”). Elegant neoclassical theatre building, completed in 1874. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Avram Iancu square</hi> (Piața Avram Iancu). The city's main square, with a central green space and monument to the Unknown Soldier. Surrounding buildings include the theatre to the north and the Art-Nouveau Nádasdy House to the west. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">House with locked log</hi> (Casa cu lacăt). One of the oldest secular buildings in the city, built for a Viennese merchant in 1815. The building's distinctive mark, a brass-coated log, was modeled after the famous "Stock-im-Eisen" in central Vienna and used by travelling journeymen to leave a mark of their guild. After being stolen (and recovered) in 1994, the log was moved to the Museum of Art, to protect it from other thieves. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Synagogue</hi>. Reformed synagogue, built from 1828–1834, neoclassical style with Greek and Tuscan elements. </item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Serbian Orthodox Saint Peter and Paul Church</hi> (Biserica Sârbească). Baroque church, built around 1700 (the city's oldest church that has survived in its original form), with a high steeple. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cathedral of the Nativity of John the Baptist</hi> (Catedrala „Nașterea Sf. Ioan Botezătorul”). Old Romanian Orthodox cathedral, built from 1862–65 in Baroque revival style. </item>
<item> Three blocks west of Piața Avram Iancu, <hi rend="bold">Reconciliation Park</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Parcul Reconcilierii</hi>) with the <hi rend="bold">Statue of Liberty</hi> (Statuia Libertății). A monument to the "13 Martyrs of Arad", rebel generals who were executed by Austrian forces after the failed Hungarian Revolution of 1849. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Art Nouveau architecture</hi> (or Secession style, as it was called in Austro-Hungary): several highly decorative examples of this early 20th-century style, similar to those found in <ref target="Budapest">Budapest</ref> or other cities of the former Danube Monarchy, with their elaborate floral or geometric ornamentation. However, most of them are in a rather sad state of preservation. Notable instances include (Str. Goldiș Vasile 1-3), (Str. Horia 3-5/Str. Episcopiei 2), (Str. General Vasile Milea 19).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Trajan Bridge</hi> (Podul Traian). Iron bridge over the Mureș river, dating from 1910–13, carrying road and tramway. Rehabilitated in 2010 for the bridge's 100th anniversary. </item>
<item> East of the river, the is an 18th-century Vauban-style fortification on the site of an earlier Ottoman fort. But it's a military base and closed to the public; you can't even see much of the exterior among the tangled shrubs.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ruins of the Franciscan Church</hi> (Biserica Franciscană). Cannot be visited regularly, as it is in the citadel and therefore part of the restricted military area. </item>
</list>
</text>
