<text id="autogum_voyage_doc524" title="Derry" shortTile="derry" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=9353" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Derry</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Derry</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Londonderry</hi> (<ref target="Irish%20phrasebook">Irish:</ref> 'Doire', meaning 'Oak Grove'), is the second city of <ref target="Northern%20Ireland">Northern Ireland</ref> and the fourth largest city on the island of Ireland after <ref target="Dublin">Dublin</ref>, <ref target="Belfast">Belfast</ref> and <ref target="Cork">Cork</ref>. It is situated on the river Foyle in <ref target="County%20Londonderry">County Londonderry</ref>, close to county <ref target="Donegal">Donegal</ref> in the <ref target="Republic%20of%20Ireland">Republic of Ireland</ref>. It has a population of roughly 100,000.</p>
<p>Note that the name of the city is a point of political dispute, with unionists advocating the longer name, and nationalists advocating the shorter. A common attempt at compromise is to refer to the county as "Londonderry" and the city as "Derry", but this is by no means universally accepted. Because of this, a peculiar situation arises as there is no common consensus either in politics or elsewhere as to which name is preferred; the city council is officially known as "Derry", but the city is officially recognised as "Londonderry" by the Northern Ireland Executive and the UK government. Whilst road signs in the <ref target="Republic%20of%20Ireland">Republic of Ireland</ref> use "Derry", alongside the Irish language translation "Doire", road signs in <ref target="Northern%20Ireland">Northern Ireland</ref> will always read (unless vandalised) "Londonderry".</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Situated on the banks of River Foyle, Derry is the second largest city in Northern Ireland and one of the oldest inhabited places in the whole island of Ireland. As they say there, 'Derry was a city when Belfast was still a swamp'. Derry's history dates back over 1,450 years, a lasting reminder of the early inhabitants of the area is the Iron Age fort, just over the border in <ref target="County%20Donegal">County Donegal</ref>, known as the <ref target="Burt%20%28Republic%20of%20Ireland%29">Grianan of Aileach</ref>.</p>

<p>In the 6th Century St Columba/Colmcille established a monastery in Derry. Shifting ten centuries later to the Plantation of Ulster, King James I of England had the wealthy guilds of London build up the city of Derry (hence the title Londonderry) and surround it by the defensive walls that still ring the city today.</p>

<p>These walls witnessed one of the most prominent events in the history of Derry. In 1688 the city was laid siege by the Earl of Antrim and the Catholic forces of James II, the English king who was deposed in favour of Protestant William of Orange. The settlers of the city who were protestant, barricaded themselves within the walls, when a group of apprentice boys from London on seeing the oncoming forces, locked the city gates and so started the Great Siege of Derry.</p>

<p>The siege was to be the longest in British history, lasting some 105 days, during which an estimated third of the city’s then population of 30,000 died through disease and starvation. When James II himself rode up to the city walls and lay down terms for surrender he was greeted with shouts of ‘No Surrender’. The siege was finally broken when the relief ship Mountjoy broke the boom which was laid across the River Foyle beside the city.</p>

<p>However the legacy of the Great Siege of Derry lasted for centuries with the Catholic and Protestant communities in Derry still largely divided today. During the years of the Troubles, Derry witnessed some of the most prominent and terrible events of those times. It was on Derry's Bogside area that British soldiers shot dead 14 civil rights protesters in what became known as Bloody Sunday. The majority of the Bogside murals commemorate this tragic loss of innocents.</p>

<p>Since the peace process in Northern Ireland, Derry is slowly emerging as an upbeat cosmopolitan city with great potential and huge tourist interest. In July 2010, Derry was awarded City of Culture for 2013. A lot of Derry’s sights are meshed with its history, the 16th Century walls which surround the city are among the oldest and the best preserved citadel walls in Europe.</p>

<p>A huge percentage of Derry’s population fall into the 20 – 30 age group and there are plenty of places to cater for them with lots of clothes shops and boutiques, pubs, bars and clubs and Derry's traditional Irish and folk music scene are well established.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
 <hi rend="bold">City of Derry Airport</hi> ( LDY ) (located 11km north-east of the city centre). An airport serving Derry, <ref target="County%20Tyrone">County Tyrone</ref>, and Donegal in the Republic of Ireland. <ref target="http://www.ryanair.com/">Ryanair</ref> offers flights to <ref target="Alicante">Alicante</ref>, <ref target="Faro">Faro</ref>, <ref target="Glasgow">Glasgow</ref>, <ref target="London">London</ref> (<ref target="London%20Stansted%20Airport">Stansted</ref>), <ref target="Liverpool">Liverpool</ref>.
 

<p><hi rend="bold">Taxis</hi> are available from the airport, with the typical fares to the city centre around £12, with the journey taking roughly 15 minutes. The easiest way to get one is by using the very visible yellow phones by the exit on the left as you come out of arrivals. Although, because there are only ever a few flights a day, many taxi men know when to come to the airport, so when you walk out you should see them by the car park and most are there to pick up any free fares. Don't forget that many won't accept Euros!</p>

<p>There is also a <hi rend="bold">bus</hi> service but given the intermittent timetable, unless you're short of cash, you should just take a taxi. For details of Ulsterbus bus services visit <ref target="http://www.translink.co.uk">Translink</ref>. The typical fare to the city centre is £2.70 and the journey takes approximately 20-30 minutes.</p>

<head>From Belfast</head>

<p>Belfast has two airports, serving a host of destinations. <ref target="Belfast%23By_plane">Belfast International Airport</ref> is situated 100km from Derry, whilst <ref target="Belfast%23By_plane">Belfast City Airport</ref> is located 115km from Derry.</p>
<p>Both Belfast airports are served by a good bus connection to Derry city centre with <ref target="http://www.airporter.co.uk">Airporter</ref>.</p>

<head>From Dublin</head>

<p>It is also possible to get to Derry from <ref target="Dublin%23By_plane">Dublin Airport</ref>, 225km to the south-east.</p>
<p>Dublin Airport is Ireland's international air hub, served by Ryanair, <ref target="http://www.aerlingus.com">Aer Lingus</ref> and many other international carriers, with destinations in Ireland, Europe, Africa, North America and the Middle East.</p>
<ref target="http://www.buseireann.ie/">Buses</ref> link Dublin Airport and the Derry, running throughout the night.

<head>By train</head>

<p>Northern Ireland Railways (a subsidiary of <ref target="http://www.translink.co.uk">Translink</ref>) have trains travelling to and from <ref target="Belfast">Belfast</ref> regularly during the whole day. Trains arrive in Derry's Waterside, with a shuttle bus linking the train station to the (more central) bus station.</p>

<p>The journey between Belfast and Derry takes just over 2 hours and between Coleraine and Derry affords great views along the shores of Lough Foyle, which was described by Michael Palin as<ref target="http://www.belfasttelegraph.co.uk/news/environment/beautiful-rail-journey-from-derry-to-coleraine-is-just-the-ticket-14868466.html">“one of the most beautiful rail journeys in the world”</ref>.</p>
</text>
