<text id="autogum_voyage_doc85" title="Ten Sleep" shortTile="ten-sleep" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=35602" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ten Sleep</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Ten Sleep</hi> is a city in <ref target="Wyoming">Wyoming</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>The name "Ten Sleep" comes from American Indians who marked this location as "ten sleeps" (or ten days' travel) between <ref target="Fort%20Laramie">Fort Laramie</ref> and the government's Indian Agency on the Stillwater River in Montana. </p>

<p>Later, it was known as the location of the Spring Creek Raid, sometimes called the Battle of Ten Sleep, one of the last "Wild West" battles. (You can find a historical marker commemorating this south of town on WY 434.) </p>

<p>Today, Ten Sleep is a common stop for tourists on their way to the Bighorn Mountains, <ref target="Yellowstone%20National%20Park">Yellowstone National Park</ref>, or (in the other direction) <ref target="Sturgis">Sturgis</ref>. The surrounding lands also attract many hunters and fishers.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>Unless you really know the local backroads well, you'll come in on US 16 and you'll leave that way too. From the west, US 16 passes through <ref target="Worland">Worland</ref>, the nearest "big city." From the east, it comes from <ref target="Buffalo%20%28Wyoming%29">Buffalo (Wyoming)</ref> across the Bighorn Mountains and through the Ten Sleep Canyon. </p>

<p>The adventurous might enjoy the drive from Manderson through Hyattville into Ten Sleep on Wyoming Highways 31 and 49, where you can see a variety of farms and ranches squeezing a living out of the "badlands." Between Hyattville and Ten Sleep you will almost certainly have to stop at some point to wait for cattle to cross the road. (Be aware that, should you have any car trouble or anything, it could be an hour or two before you see another car - and that's in the daytime with good weather. Just in case, you might consider whether you're prepared to deal with all problems yourself!) </p>

<p>You could also try to find your way in from Moneta through Lost Cabin. If you are not familiar with the local roads, before trying this, you might want to download the area into your GPS system.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>As long as you're staying in town, you can walk. Heck, there's hardly even room to drive.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ten Sleep Pioneer Museum</hi>, 436 2nd St, ☏ +1 307 366-2759 . 9AM-4PM daily. Exhibits focusing on pioneer life in the area. Free.</item>
<item> Ten Sleep Canyon. To the east of town on US 16, on the way to <ref target="Buffalo%20%28Wyoming%29">Buffalo (Wyoming)</ref>, the canyon is a popular destination for rock climbers and bicyclists.</item>
<item> Ten Sleep Mercantile</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tube the Ten Sleep</hi>. You get yourself an inner tube, you go to Ten Sleep Park, you get in the Ten Sleep Creek, and ride that inner tube as long as you want. Most locals would say that if you hit the confluence with the Nowood River, it's time to get out and walk back to town.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">No Woodstock</hi>. Ten Sleep's own music festival, held every summer. Check online for dates.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">July 4th Rodeo</hi>. Every Independence Day, you can see the finest rodeo in Washakie County just west of town; the rodeo ground is near the RV Park.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dirty Sally's</hi>. Jackalopes galore, rock candy, touristy knickknacks, t-shirts, and the best ice cream and the only malts for literally a hundred miles in any direction.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ten Sleep Saloon and Steakhouse</hi>. 7 AM to 11 PM. Basic American food.</item>
</list>
</text>
