<text id="autogum_voyage_doc275" title="Grover Beach" shortTile="grover-beach" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13498" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Grover Beach</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.grover.org/">Grover Beach</ref></hi> is in <ref target="San%20Luis%20Obispo%20County">San Luis Obispo County</ref> in the <ref target="Central%20Coast%20%28California%29">Central Coast</ref> region of <ref target="California">California</ref>. It is part of the Five Cities Metropolitan Area which also includes <ref target="Oceano">Oceano</ref> to the south, <ref target="Arroyo%20Grande">Arroyo Grande</ref> to the east, and <ref target="Pismo%20Beach">Pismo Beach</ref> and Shell Beach to the north.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Highway 1</hi> runs through Grover Beach. Grover Beach is also the southern terminus of <hi rend="bold">Highway 227</hi>. <hi rend="bold">Highway 101</hi> is a major freeway that goes near Grover Beach. On the 101, you can go south to <ref target="Santa%20Maria%20%28California%29">Santa Maria</ref>, <ref target="Santa%20Barbara">Santa Barbara</ref>, and eventually to <ref target="Los%20Angeles">Los Angeles</ref>, and north to <ref target="San%20Luis%20Obispo">San Luis Obispo</ref>, <ref target="Salinas">Salinas</ref>, and eventually to <ref target="San%20Francisco">San Francisco</ref>. On the 1, you could go south to <ref target="Guadalupe%20%28California%29">Guadalupe</ref> and <ref target="Lompoc">Lompoc</ref>, while you could go north to nearby <ref target="Pismo%20Beach">Pismo Beach</ref> to meet the 101. The 227 goes north to San Luis Obispo.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>The nearest airport with commercial flights is <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.sloairport.com">San Luis Obispo Airport</ref></hi>, approximately 10 miles north of Grover Beach. Scheduled flights are available to Los Angeles and San Francisco on United Express's Skywest Airlines, and <ref target="Phoenix">Phoenix</ref> on American Eagle. <hi rend="bold">Oceano County Airport</hi> is located just south of Grover Beach and it is used mostly for general aviation.</p>

<head>By bus/train</head>

<ref target="http://www.amtrak.com"><hi rend="bold">Amtrak</hi></ref> serves Grover Beach via its <ref target="https://www.amtrak.com/routes/pacific-surfliner-train.html"><hi rend="italic">Pacific Surfliner</hi></ref> train between <ref target="San%20Luis%20Obispo">San Luis Obispo</ref> and <ref target="San%20Diego">San Diego</ref>, there are two daily departures in each direction and several additional Amtrak Thruway buses connecting with trains in <ref target="Santa%20Barbara">Santa Barbara</ref>. is located at 180 W Grand Ave.

<head>By bus</head>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.slorta.org/">SLO South County Transit</ref></hi> provides bus service in Grover Beach, Oceano, Pismo Beach and Shell Beach. The main transit hub is at Ramona Garden Park at 9th Street and Ramona Ave.</p>

<head>Do</head>
<p>Go to <hi rend="bold">Pismo State Beach</hi>, where vehicles are permitted on the beach, by traveling west on Grand Avenue from Highway 1.</p>

<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mongo's Saloon Restaurant</hi>, 359 W Grand Ave, ☏ +1 805 489-3639 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fin's</hi>, 25 W Grand Ave, ☏ +1 805 473-3467 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fatte's Pizza of Grover Beach</hi>, 1741 W Grand Ave, ☏ +1 805 489-5555 . # D,</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Station Grill</hi>, 170 W Grand, ☏ +1 805-489-3030 . 6:30AM - 8PM. Breakfast, Lunch, and Dinner. Sandwiches, burgers, salads, pasta. Casual dining, great for the family. all food $5 - $10.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Holiday Inn Express</hi>, 775 N.Oak Park Blvd., ☏ +1 805 481-4448 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Seaview Inn</hi>, 150 N 5th St, ☏ +1 805 473-1433 .</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Pismo%20Beach">Pismo Beach</ref></hi> - Grover Beach's neighbor to the north is a tourism-focused coastal town that has more than 65 restaurants and 30 lodging options, and draws visitors with its beautiful coastline, annual clam festival, and the thousands of monarch butterflies that gather to spend the winter in a grove at the edge of town.</item>
</list>
</text>
