<text id="autogum_voyage_doc64" title="Kalutara" shortTile="kalutara" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=154115" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kalutara</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Kalutara</hi> is in <ref target="Western%20Province%20%28Sri%20Lanka%29">Western Province (Sri Lanka)</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Kalutara is a coastal city 43 km south of the capital <ref target="Colombo">Colombo</ref> and the administrative capital of Kalutara district. The city holds a unique position for one of the four major rivers in Sri Lanka ( <hi rend="bold">Kalu River</hi> ) joins the sea at the center of the city.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Take the Colombo-Kalutara route No. 400 AC or Non AC bus from Colombo. It'll take around 2 hours to reach depending on the time of the day. Better to travel in the mornings to avoid outbound traffic congestions.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Kalutara has two railway stations (Kalutara North and Kalutara South) and make sure to get off at <hi rend="bold">Kalutara South</hi> station to reach the city. Kalutara South station is a major station on the southern coastal railway and all express trains make a stop here. Pre-booking facility is only available in Rajadhani Express train.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kalutara Vihara</hi> or <hi rend="bold">Gangatilaka Vihara</hi>, built in the 1960s to the south of the Kalutara Bridge, is Kalutara’s most dominant landmark. The white 3-storey-high stupa at Kalutara Vihara is believed to be the only Buddha stupa in the world which is entirely hollow. It contains a smaller dagoba inside. The interior of the stupa is decorated with paintings of the Jataka tales about the life of the Buddha.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kalutara Bodhiya</hi> is one of the most famous sacred and devotional Buddhist sites in Sri Lanka. It is one of the 32 saplings of Anuradhapura Sri Maha Bodiya. Kalutara Bodiya is on Colombo-Galle road.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Richmond Castle</hi> is a two-storey mansion, built in 1896, at Palatota. Richmond Castle is a 42-acre fruit garden estate that wad built for a wealthy regional governor. The architecture is a mix of British and Indian styles, copied from the plans of an Indian Maharaja’s palace designed by a London architect. The entire building is characterized by intricate carvings.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Calido Beach</hi> is a popular beach among tourists due to its natural beauty and scenic views. It is a thin strip of preserved land which runs between the Kalu River and the Indian Ocean.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Asokaramaya Buddhist Temple</hi> is a historic <ref target="Buddhism">Buddhist</ref> temple built in 1873, in Kalutara north.</item>
</list>


<head>Splurge</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Anantara Kalutara Resort</hi>, St Sebastian Road, Katukurunda, ☏ +94 34 222 0222 , ✉ kalutara.resort@anantara.com . 141 rooms, suites and pool villas, equipped with yoga and meditation pavilion, kids' and teens’ centre, gym, library &amp; water sports centre. Starting from US$205.</item>
</list>
</text>
