<text id="autogum_voyage_doc38" title="Glossop" shortTile="glossop" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=12860" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Glossop</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Glossop</hi> is a small town located on the edge of the <ref target="Peak%20District">Peak District</ref>. It lies in the county of <ref target="Derbyshire">Derbyshire</ref>, which is officially part of the <ref target="East%20Midlands">East Midlands</ref> (though most residents would consider themselves part of the Northwest of England).</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Glossop is at the northwestern extremity of Derbyshire and the Peak District, close to the borders with Greater Manchester and Yorkshire. It also lies at the start of two of the most infamous Pennine passes, the Snake and Woodhead passes. Its main development is owed to the 19th-century cotton industry which generated the wealth to build much of the town we see today, although the cotton industry has since declined and almost disappeared from the region. Despite this, the historic mill buildings still dominate the town, such as those at Wren Nest and Howardtown, both of which are undergoing major transformations into new multi-use buildings including retail, leisure and residential.</p>

<p>Glossop is predominantly a commuter town for the nearby conurbation of Greater Manchester, where quite often people have moved to enjoy a more relaxed and laid-back quality of life whilst enjoying the benefits of living near a city. It has a regular market, the usual range of high street chain stores and some independent shops. It attracts tourists mainly due to its good transport links with the surrounding Peak District National Park and its stunning countryside, though the town itself is not without interest and parts (e.g. Manor Park, Old Glossop) are quite attractive. It is not of any administrative significance due to its geographic location and local government structures. The population of the town (2001 Census) is 32,428.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>There are trains to from <ref target="Manchester">Manchester</ref> Piccadilly station every 30 minutes and seven days a week.</p>
<p>The stations on the line are as follows:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Hadfield</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Glossop</hi></item>
<item> Dinting</item>
<item> Broadbottom</item>
<item> Hattersley</item>
<item> Godley</item>
<item> Newton (for Hyde) - Connections: Hyde by bus or a 15-minute walk</item>
<item> Flowery Field</item>
<item> Guide Bridge - Connections: <ref target="Ashton-under-Lyne">Ashton-under-Lyne</ref> by bus</item>
<item> Gorton</item>
<item> Ashburys - Connections: walk or bus to Eastlands/Manchester City FC</item>
<item> Ardwick - only 1 train Mon–Fri stops</item>
<item> <ref target="Manchester">Manchester</ref> Piccadilly</item>
</list>

<p>At peak periods the trains may stop at the following stops in a different order (i.e. Glossop–Hadfield–Dinting).</p>
<p>This rail service is operated by Northern Rail; the journey between Glossop and Manchester Piccadilly is around 30 minutes, but journey times may vary at peak periods. Visit <ref target="http://www.northernrail.org">www.northernrail.org</ref> for timetable or call National Rail Enquiries on 0845 748 4950.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>There is an extensive public transport network across the High Peak, which is unusual for a rural area. Bus services in Glossop are as follows:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">High Peak buses</hi>, ☏ +1 843 523 6036 .</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> 61 Glossop–<ref target="Hayfield">Hayfield</ref>–<ref target="New%20Mills">New Mills</ref>—<ref target="Whaley%20Bridge">Whaley Bridge</ref>–<ref target="Buxton">Buxton</ref></item>
<item> 64 Glossop–Hayfield–New Mills–Whaley Bridge–<ref target="Macclesfield">Macclesfield</ref></item>
<item> 390 Shire Hill Hospital–Glossop–Whitfield</item>
<item> 393 Padfield–Glossop–Shirebrook Park Circular</item>
<item> 394 Glossop–Gamesley–Marple–Stepping Hill Hospital</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="http://www.stagecoachbus.com/pdfs/XJAO236.pdf"><hi rend="bold">Stagecoach</hi></ref></item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> 237 Glossop–Hadfield–Mottram–Stalybridge–Ashton-under-Lyne–Droylsden–Manchester Piccadilly</item>
<item> 358 Glossop–Hayfield–<ref target="Marple%20%28England%29">Marple</ref>–Offerton–<ref target="Stockport">Stockport</ref></item>
</list>



<p>For times, fares and details of these services and how to use them to get to Glossop, call <ref target="http://www.travelineeastmidlands.co.uk">Traveline</ref> on 0871 200 2233. The above services below are correct as <date when="2008-06-01">of 06/01/08</date>; please note that some of them operate only on Sundays, or weekends, or evenings; check before travelling.</p>

<ref target="http://www.nationalexpress.com">National Express</ref> Coaches stop at nearby Hollingworth; here you can pick up their 350 service towards <ref target="Manchester">Manchester</ref> and <ref target="Liverpool">Liverpool</ref>, or in the opposite direction towards <ref target="Sheffield">Sheffield</ref>, <ref target="Nottingham">Nottingham</ref> and <ref target="East%20Anglia">East Anglia</ref>. For times, fares and other service information contact National Express on 0870 580 80 80.

<head>By car</head>

<p>Glossop has connections in all directions to the UK road network; however, the main road (though not a primary route) is the A57. To the West this joins with the A628 Woodhead pass at Hollingworth, to become a primary route and then it is a short distance until it meets the UK motorway network via the M67 to allow quick and easy access into Greater Manchester. To the East is the A57 Snake Pass, an infamous transpennine pass to <ref target="Sheffield">Sheffield</ref>. To the south the main road is the A624 which goes to <ref target="Hayfield">Hayfield</ref>, Chapel-en-le-Frith and eventually <ref target="Buxton">Buxton</ref> via the A6; this is the main route into <ref target="Derbyshire">Derbyshire</ref> and towards the towns and cities of the East Midlands. To the North is the B6105 which links to the A628 Woodhead Pass at Crowden: the A628 is the easiest route to access the M1 from Glossop via Junction 37 at <ref target="Barnsley">Barnsley</ref>. The A628, however, goes through Barnsley and to <ref target="Pontefract">Pontefract</ref> in West Yorkshire.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>The airports easily accessible from Glossop are:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Manchester%20Airport">Manchester Airport</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Liverpool">Liverpool</ref> <ref target="https://www.liverpoolairport.com/">John Lennon</ref></item>
</list>

<p>Both can be reached by train via regular services to Manchester Piccadilly, or by car via the motorway network.</p>
<p>Other airports within 1.5 hours' drive are:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Leeds">Leeds</ref> <ref target="Bradford">Bradford</ref> International</item>
<item> <ref target="http://www.dsaflights.co.uk">Robin Hood Airport</ref> <ref target="http://www.dsaflights.co.uk">Doncaster Sheffield Airport</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="East%20Midlands%20Airport">East Midlands Airport</ref></item>
</list>

<p>However, Manchester, being the largest of nearby airports, can usually offer appropriate services from wherever in the world you wish to travel.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Wren Nest Mill</hi>, High Street West. Remaining building of cotton mill built between 1800 and 1818.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ardotalia</hi> (Melandra Castle), Melandra Castle Rd, Gamesley. Site of Roman fort </item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Walk through Manor Park to Old Glossop and—for the energetic—continue onto the slopes of Bleaklow.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Longdendale Trail</hi>. An all-purpose trail housed on a disused railway line, about 7 miles from Hadfield to Woodhead featuring trails for bicycles, horses and walkers. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Partington Players Theatre</hi>, Henry Street SK13 8BW, ☏ +44 1457 852066 , ✉ partingtonweb@googlemail.com . A 120-seat theatre in the centre of Glossop showing plays for a week 6 times each season. They also have occasional live music, films and visiting productions.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<p>Glossop boasts some of the best shopping in the High Peak. It has a variety of national chain stores and independent stores existing alongside each other in the town centre. The largest supermarket is a Tesco store on the main road through the town. Major retail areas include the nearby High Street West and Wrens Nest Retail Park, which contains shops such as Next, Argos, Wickes (DIY), Brantano and others. The new Howardtown development on the A624 (Victoria St) offers additional retail opportunities.</p>
</text>
