<text id="autogum_voyage_doc4" title="Plympton" shortTile="plympton" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27888" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Plympton</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://town.plympton.ma.us">Plympton</ref></hi> is a small town in <ref target="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref> on the <ref target="South%20Shore%20%28Massachusetts%29">South Shore</ref>. Deborah Sampson was born here in 1760. She dressed as a man and fought in the Revolutionary War. When her leg was injured, she tended to it herself so her gender was not discovered. Later, the leg became infected and she was hospitalized. Her gender was discovered and she was honorably discharged.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Plympton is a small suburb. It is so small that many people fear blinking as they are driving down route 58 because they might miss the town. Deborah Sampson, a woman who dressed as a man and fought in the Revolutionary War, was born in Plympton, but the only other exciting news to come from the town is the addition of their first traffic light in 2008. Overall, Plympton is a great place to raise a family because of their schooling (Silver Lake School District) and the small population.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Routes 106 and 58 both run through Plympton. The new route 44 is the best way in from the highway. Get off at the Plympton-Carver-58 exit (exits are not numbered) and bear right off the exit and continue north on 58 to reach Plympton.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>There is a small, regional airport in Plymouth called Plymouth Municipal Airport (246 South Meadow Road, 508-746-8003). Travellers usually prefer Logan Airport in Boston or T.F. Greene Airport in Warwick, RI.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Plympton is so small that there is no public transportation. There are few sidewalks so walking is not advised.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Llama Farm</hi>, Main Street. People like to look at the llamas from the fence. Don’t get too close because llamas spit and this is trespassing on private property!</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Deborah Sampson House</hi>, Elm Street. The house Deborah Sampson was born in. This is also private property.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Upland Sportsman Club</hi>, 76 Upland Road, ☏ +1 781-582-2896 . Hunting, fishing, and archery, for members only.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Plympton Public Library</hi>, 248 Main Street, ☏ +1 781-585-4551 .</item>
</list>


<head>Annual event</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Old Home Day</hi>. Everyone heads to the Upland Club for games, food, and to get together with the community. Yearly event, usually spread by word of mouth.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Daily Grind Coffee Shoppe</hi>, 286 Main Street, ☏ +1 781-582-0582 .</item>
</list>


<head>Bakery</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Custom Cakes by Paula</hi>, 50 County Road (on Route 106), ☏ +1 781-582-9669 . Fresh cakes specially ordered. By appointment only.</item>
</list>


<head>Farm Stands</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sunrise Garden</hi>, 94 Center Street, ☏ +1 781-585-6035 . A family-owned farm and business that grown their own flowers and chemical free produce. They also sell mulch, pumpkins, mums, firewood and Christmas trees and wreaths. Open year round!</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sauchuk Farm</hi>, 53 Palmer Road (on Route 58), ☏ +1 781-585-1522 . Sells fresh produce and flowers that is grown on their own farm. Open May to October.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Upland Sportsman Club</hi>, 76 Upland Road, ☏ +1 781-582-2896 . Drink with the locals!</item>
</list>
</text>
