<text id="autogum_voyage_doc52" title="Abomey">
<head>Abomey</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.tourismeabomeyetregion.com">Abomey</ref></hi> is a town and former capital of <ref target="Benin">Benin</ref>.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>Nearby <ref target="Bohicon">Bohicon</ref> has a rail link with the capital <ref target="Cotonou">Cotonou</ref> and <ref target="Parakou">Parakou</ref> in the north, there are three departures in each direction every week. Tickets from Cotonou costs CFA 1100 in second class and CFA 1400 in first.</p>

<p>You can take the very good Baobab Express Bus to get to Bohicon. They have quite new buses with air conditioning and Wifi and set a focus on security and punctuality. (2500 CFA per person from Cotonou in Dec. 2018)</p>

<p>Bush taxis from Bohicon cost CFA 300, and CFA 2000 for the 3-hour ride from Cotonou. Cheaper but slower public buses are also available.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Zemi-johns</hi> are a popular, cheap and efficient way to get around. They are simply a scooter-like taxi popular in the country.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>The Royal Palaces of Abomey are a group of earthen structures built by the Fon people of the Dahomey Kingdom between the mid-17th and late 19th Centuries. One of the most famous and historically significant traditional sites in West Africa, the Palaces are on the <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20List">UNESCO World Heritage List</ref>. Each king had a new palace built for himself. They are filled with larger numbers of bas-reliefs and artwork that display everyday life, including war, sacrifices and torture methods. The Dahomey were also notable for being one of the main beneficiaries of the <ref target="Atlantic%20slave%20trade">Atlantic slave trade</ref>, with palaces largely having been built using wealth acquired from capturing slaves from neighbouring ethnic groups to sell to the Europeans. The palaces are:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Akaba Royal Palace</item>
<item> Gbehanzin Royal Palace</item>
<item> Palace of King Glele</item>
<item> Palace of King Agaja</item>
<item> Palace of King Tegbessu</item>
<item> Palace of King Agoli-Agbo</item>
<item> Palace of King Ghezo</item>
<item> Palace of King Angoglo</item>
<item> Palace of King Kpengla</item>
</list>


<p>It is also worth visiting the nearby museum:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Musée Historique d'Abomey</hi> (Historical Museum), ☏ +229 22 50 03 14 . M-F: 8:30am-6pm, Sa-Su: 8:30am-5pm. Houses a number of artefacts and relics from the area. Some of the banners show torture and war tactics of the former Kingdom. The throne of Ghezo is exhibited, which was built on top of human skulls. Admission includes a guided tour, which takes about an hour. CFA 2500.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The <hi rend="bold">Musée Historique d'Abomey</hi> sells souvenirs, including banners and bronze figurines.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chez Yemadje</hi>, Rue du Palais Royal, ☏ +229 9579 0945, +229 9782 3363 . 7am-7pm. Owned and maintained by the family that once embroidered for the previous kings. Sells various craft work.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<head>Drink</head>

<head>Sleep</head>
<p>There are a few motels in town, but none are of particularly good quality.</p>

<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Bohicon">Bohicon</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
