<text id="autogum_voyage_doc145" title="Chaweng" shortTile="chaweng" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=6934" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Chaweng</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Chaweng</hi> is a beach on the east coast of <ref target="Ko%20Samui">Ko Samui</ref>. It has a lovely white beach and vibrant nightlife, especially at its north end.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Chaweng is the largest and most popular of Samui's beaches, and is usually divided into three sections: North Chaweng, Central Chaweng and Chaweng Noi (Little Chaweng) around a headland to the south. Chaweng Beach is the longest beach on Samui's east coast. The beach is beautiful here and local developers are finally cleaning up some of the trashy areas nearby. It attracts many young travellers and families alike, but still remains good value for money.</p>

<p>The beach is approximately 7 km long with powdery white sand. It is bordered by emerald-blue waters and a coral reef where waves break, leaving the bay quite peaceful. Not far from the beach, there are two small islands near the reef. After swimming, you can explore the nearest one by walking through shallow water or go for snorkelling and kayaking at the second island which is further out and larger.</p>
<p>The central part of the beach is a bit more crowded than the quieter north. Many vendors pass by, offering beverages, fruit, ice cream and local Thai food for the more daring. A variety of local crafts and Thai souvenirs are also available.</p>

<p>The beach itself is usually accessed through the hotels, as there are no beach roads to disturb the peacefulness of the area. It is very relaxing but noticeably more touristy during the high season. The water is clean with normal temperatures between 25-28°C.</p>

<p>Parallel to the beach, clustered in the middle of the strip, lies Samui's greatest concentration of restaurants, bars, souvenir shops, and of course, fast food and convenience stores.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Chaweng is a few minutes ride south of the airport. If you book a taxi at the airport's transport desk, it will cost 400 baht. A shared van (usually requiring 5 passengers before it departs) will cost 120 baht per person. Taxi drivers rarely use taxi meters here. If you decide not to use the booking desk, negotiate the fare in advance with the taxi driver. It should cost from 200-400 baht. Or you may book a transfer with your hotel. This service usually costs 300 baht, though some of the higher-end hotels have quoted rates of 400 baht per person.</p>

<p>You may opt to take other, more adventurous forms of transportation like the following:</p>

<p>Motorcycle taxis are ordinary motorbikes and you sit behind the driver during the ride. Depending on the distance, the price ranges from 30-150 baht.</p>

<p>Motorbike rentals are available if riding solo is what you prefer. Most motorbike rentals in Chaweng offer 100-125 cc bikes such as Honda Waves, Honda Clicks, Suzuki Steps, etc. Rentals cost 100-200 baht per day depending on the length of the rental.</p>

<p>Bigger motorbikes like Harley Davidson's and sport bikes like Kawasaki Ninjas and Honda CBRs are also available. Be warned that bike accidents tend to be a regular occurrence in Ko Samui, so drive carefully.</p>

<p>If you are travelling in a large group, you may opt to rent a Jeep. The rental usually costs at least 800 baht per day. A private car will set you back 1,500 baht or more per day. There are many models to choose from: Honda Jazz, Isuzu Hi-Lander, Toyota Camry, Toyota Fortuner, etc. Established rental companies such as Avis and Hertz also offer insurance. It might be a good idea to get the insurance along with the rental as having no insurance and an accident could be expensive.</p>

<head>Do</head>
<p>Almost all activities are on the beach (even parts of the nightlife) and most Samui <hi rend="bold">dive shops</hi> are based in Chaweng. It's also the base to arrange trips to nearby <ref target="Ko%20Tao">Ko Tao</ref> and the <ref target="Ang%20Thong%20National%20Marine%20Park">Ang Thong National Marine Park</ref>.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Calypso Diving Koh Samui</hi>, ☏ +66 77 422437 . Offers all kind of PADI Dive courses from beginner to professional. Calypso also organize individual dive, snorkelling, and island trips to Ko Pha Ngan, Ko Tao and Ang Thong National Marine Park. Two modern high-speed catamarans make the journey very comfortable and safe. At Ko Tao is a tour boat with all the facilities required for a fun-filled day. Maximum 24 passengers per boat. Small groups: maximum 5 divers, 10 snorkellers per professional dive guide.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Magnolia Spa</hi>, ☏ +66 77 601133 . The only spa in Thailand that stocks and uses the complete range of products from Dead Sea Minerals. Next to it is the <hi rend="bold">Magnolia Cafe</hi>, with great breads and cakes, as well as other food.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">100 Degrees East</hi>, ☏ +66 77 245936 , ✉ info@100degreeseast.com . 5 Star PADI Dive Resort and a BSAC Resort Centre. Safe diving in a friendly and supportive environment in which you can relax, have fun and enjoy your time.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Salamander Dive Centre</hi>, ☏ +66 77 413693 . Diving courses and tours, arranging all your travel needs. Stocks all diving equipment needed in your course or tour, for purchase and rental too.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>
<p>There are lots of <hi rend="bold">souvenir shops</hi> around town. It is not uncommon for the shopkeepers to ask 5 times the normal tourist price particularly in the central areas. Bargaining is always acceptable when it comes to souvenirs. Even when a price is indicated a discount up to 50% might be available. As many shops and the often cheaper market stalls sell mostly similar products, ask at several places to get an idea of what is a reasonable price before starting haggling for the product you really want. The clothing sold here can often be found at <ref target="Bangkok/Khao%20San%20Road">Khao San Road</ref> in <ref target="Bangkok">Bangkok</ref> for a lower price.</p>

<p>On the beach, vendors will sell beach clothes, jewelry, beach toys and games, and food (coconuts, sliced fruit, satay, roasted corn, ice cream, water, etc.). Be prepared to bargain. Most food items are generally 50 baht/piece. The vendors will not bother you if you ignore them or say no.</p>

<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chef's Table</hi>, ☏ +66 77 914333 , ✉ rsvn@sareeraya.com . Local dishes, fresh seafood, international cuisine. Fine wines and delicious drinks to match the luxurious tropical atmosphere and outstanding setting.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cloud Restaurant &amp; Bar</hi> (Next to Khun Chaweng Resort and Stars Cabaret). Trendy restaurant and bar in the centre of Chaweng. Ice cold beer, an amazing range of cocktails and a delicious selection of well-presented meals, including Thai food from 100 baht and a variety of Western favourites like pizzas, pastas, and burgers from under 200 baht.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Khao San Road Restaurant</hi> (Near to Soi Green Mango). The breakfast/lunch meeting point for backpackers and a good base camp to select a hostel and meet fellow travellers.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ninja</hi> (Across the street from Baan Samui Resort and Chaweng Buri Resort). A nice family-owned traditional Thai place with very reasonable prices. Don't expect a fancy interior, but very tasty food at cheap prices.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Poppies Samui</hi> (At the lower end of Chaweng Beach). Has an excellent international and Thai restaurant if you are after exquisite surroundings presided over by a great chef.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sea Food Centre</hi> (About half a kilometre inland from Coco Blues Bar). A set of about 5 seafood restaurants. One's called StoneFish, a great place with excellent service. The food is amazing and they will grill/cook/boil/steam it just the way you would like to have it.</item>
</list>
</text>
