<text id="autogum_voyage_doc211" title="Kupang" shortTile="kupang" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=18470" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kupang</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Kupang</hi> is a city in <ref target="West%20Timor">West Timor</ref> and the provincial capital of <ref target="East%20Nusa%20Tenggara">East Nusa Tenggara</ref>.</p>
<head>By plane</head>
 <hi rend="bold">El Tari International Airport</hi> ( KOE Bandar Udara El Tari ), Jl. Adi Sucipto, ☏ +62 274 484261 . Has services to <ref target="Surabaya">Surabaya</ref>, <ref target="Denpasar">Denpasar</ref>, <ref target="Jakarta">Jakarta</ref>, <ref target="Maumere">Maumere</ref>, <ref target="Ende">Ende</ref> and many other remote regions in <ref target="East%20Nusa%20Tenggara">East Nusa Tenggara</ref>. Air Timor has services to Dili three times per week.
 

<p>There is a 'Coco Taxi' operating. A trip from airport to town should be IDR 50,000-80,000. </p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Kupang is a 12-hour bus ride away from <ref target="Dili">Dili</ref>, <ref target="East%20Timor">East Timor</ref>. Soé is a 3 hour bus ride.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>You can use "Microbus" (locally called <hi rend="italic">bemo</hi>). The uniqueness of public transportation in the city of Kupang is due to the appearance filled with accessories, decorations and music blaring. Each bemo is manned by a driver and an assistant who collects the money from passengers. You can tell the assistant your destination / drop-off point in advance. There are multiple routes, so you need to ask your accommodations if any of the bemos are are passing by your destinations. Within Kupang the route number can be seen on top of the bemo, whereas for further destination, it will write the destination name. Each trip is IDR 3,000 (as of Dec 2018).</p>

<p>Ride-hailing app such as <hi rend="bold">Grab</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Go-Jek</hi> is getting more popular here, but you may need to wait a little bit more as the number of drivers are still growing (as of Dec 2018).</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lasiana Beach</hi> (Pantai Lasiana). Famous for its white sand. There aren't many buildings, so you can enjoy the natural beach.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<p>If you like loud music, you can try "Diskotek Berjalan" style of Kupang.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Roslin Orphanage</hi>, Kupang (Timor). If you are in Kupang a visit to the Roslin Orphanage is a definite must. Google and youtube "Roslin Orphanage" for more information. Peggy and Budi Soehardi are CNN heroes and once you read about their story, you will understand why. There were some controversies about their volunteers recently, but just go there and decide for yourself.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Waterpark Kupang</hi>, Jl. WJ Lalamentik. A water-amusement park.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Oeba Market</hi> (Pasar Oeba) (Bemo #6, #10 passing by this market.). A traditional market next to a pier selling daily needs. Tourists will receive a moderate attention here.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Flobamora Mall</hi>, Jl. WJ Lalamentik. The largest mall in area is the Ramayana Department Store which includes shops, food courts, games and other facilities. Flobamora Mall is a family mall concept to provide all the needs of the family in one place.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hypermart Kupang</hi>, Jl. El Tari II Bundaran PU, ☏ +62 380 8585060 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lippo Plaza Fatululi</hi>. two-floor shopping center with Matahari Dept Store and Hypermarket.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Restoran Nelayan</hi>, Jl. Timor Raya 14, ☏ +62 380 823000 . Beachside restaurant with lots of choices including seafood. You can enjoy this dish in huts on the seafront</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Restoran Teluk Kupang</hi>, Jl.Timor Raya, ☏ +62 380 822757 . Also beachside restaurant which served delicious seafood.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Grilled Banana in Lasiana Beach</hi>. Here you can eat grilled banana with a variety of flavors while enjoying the beautiful beach and the sound of waves</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">for Jagung Bose</hi>: along the sidewalk on the Jalan El Tari (in front of the Governor's office).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">for Se'i Babi:</hi> 'Depot Bambu Kuning' and 'Se'i Babi Aroma' (two branches) are the two most popular places to have Se'i Babi.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Night Market (Pasar Malam)</hi>: Every night there is a street food market centred around Jalan Kosasih, not far from the shore. The stalls fry up lots of fresh seafood - fish, lobsters, crabs, etc., while the tahu tempe penyet is a great vegetarian option. Next to the food stalls are drinks stations where the best options are the fresh juice. Juice avokap (avocado juice) and jus naga (dragonfruit juice) are especially common and are blended with ice, sugar, and sweetened condensed milk/chocolate syrup.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kelimutu Hotel</hi>, Jalan Gunung Meja. Check-out: 1pm. A three-storey hotel that has seen better days. However, private rooms with bathrooms and AC are available for a good price. It's not far from the central bus terminal and the night street food market. The staff are friendly though no English is spoken. Free tea and coffee in the morning. Free Wifi is available around the reception area. Standard fan Rp100,000, Standard AC Rp125,000, Deluxe AC Rp150,000.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lavalon Hostel</hi>, ☏ +62 8123770533 . A backpacker spot with a friendly English-speaking staff, who will answer any question about flights, buses and ferries, flyers and maps on other hostels in Roti and <ref target="East%20Timor">East Timor</ref>, and is a good place to meet other backpackers with whom you can talk and share information.</item>
</list>

 Dorm IDR 70,000; Fan IDR 160,000; A/C IDR 260,000. 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">SwissBel Inn Kristal</hi>, Jl. Timor Raya 59, ☏ +62 380 825100 . A three-star international hotel in the heart of Kupang, 20 minutes from El Tari Airport, the hotel allows easy access to the business and government district as well as some of the most noteworthy sites in the vicinity.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">T-More Hotel</hi>, Jl. Piet A. Tallo, ☏ +62 380 881555 . Three-star hotel with the concept of transit and business.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Soe">Soe</ref>:</hi> the highland area to visit traditional village in Boti and None. 3 hours. First take the bemo to 'Noelbakul' destination, and then stop at Oesapa "bus stop". You can find "Travel" shared car for IDR 50,000 or bus for IDR 30,000 (Bus to Kefamenanu will pass by Soe too, ask the bus assistant).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Dili">Dili</ref> (East Timor / Timor Leste):</hi> No ferry from Kupang to Dili is running as of January 22, 2012. The most common way to go to Dili is via land (12 hours). Flight route of Kupang-Dili is available in 2018. (Note: As of May 26, 2015, all EU passport holders (except Ireland or UK) no longer need a visa to East Timor. Otherwise, for all nationalities except Indonesian, a free 'Visa Authorisation Letter' must be obtained from the East Timorese Consulate prior to reaching the land border).</item>
</list>
</text>
