<text id="autogum_voyage_doc448" title="Veszprém" shortTile="veszprm" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=37913" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Veszprém</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"> <ref target="http://www.veszpreminfo.hu/">Veszprém</ref></hi> (German: Weißbrunn, Slovene: Belomost) is one of <ref target="Hungary">Hungary</ref>'s oldest cities, in the <ref target="Transdanubia">Transdanubia</ref> region. In 1009, it became Hungary's first episcopal seat.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>It lies approximately 15 km (9 mi) north of the Lake Balaton. It is the administrative center of the county (comitatus or 'megye') of the same name.</p>

<head>City ​​districts</head>

<p>Belváros, Dózsaváros, Jeruzsálemhegy, Egyetemváros, Füredidomb, Cholnokyváros, Újtelep, Jutasi úti lakótelep, Bakonyalja, Jutaspuszta, Szabadságpuszta, Iparváros, Gyulafirátót, Kádárta.</p>

<p>Further territorial units: Veszprémvölgy, Reptér, Csatár</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bus Station</hi> (Autóbuszállomás Veszprém), Jutasi utca 4 (Center), ☏ +36 88 590751, +36 88 590750 . M-Sa 06:00-18:00; Su 06:00-17:00. <ref target="P%C3%A1pa">Pápa</ref> (hourly, one to one and half hour), <ref target="Budapest">Budapest</ref> (hourly, two hours) via Várpalota, <ref target="Sz%C3%A9kesfeh%C3%A9rv%C3%A1r">Székesfehérvár</ref> (one hour), <ref target="Balatonf%C3%BCred">Balatonfüred</ref> (5 per day, ~1½ hours), <ref target="Sopron">Sopron</ref> (daily), <ref target="Nagykanizsa">Nagykanizsa</ref> (daily five) via <ref target="Si%C3%B3fok">Siófok</ref> and <ref target="Fony%C3%B3d">Fonyód</ref>. Luggage storage: M-Sa 06:00-17:35, Su and public holidays) 06:00-16:35, luggage storage fee: Ft 170 per hour.</item>
</list>



<head>By train</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Train Station</hi> (Veszprém Vasútállomás), Jutasi út (N 2 km from Center). Direct trains to/from <ref target="Sz%C3%A9kesfeh%C3%A9rv%C3%A1r">Székesfehérvár</ref> via Várpalota (East), <ref target="Szombathely">Szombathely</ref> via Ajka, Sárvár (West), <ref target="Gy%C5%91r">Győr</ref> via Zirc, Pannonhalma (north, the Cuha Valley Section is very nice). </item>
</list>


<head>By car</head>
<p>From Budapest take the M7 motorway, to Székesfehérvár then turning to #8 Main road. From Győr take main road #82, from <ref target="Graz">Graz</ref>, Körmend main road #8, from Balatonfüred take main road #73. Tapolca can be approached from a main road #77.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tourinform Veszprém</hi>, Óváros tér 2. (Downtown), ☏ +36 88 404548 , ✉ veszprem@tourinform.hu . May-Sep: daily 10:00-18:00. Infos about transport, sights, programs, events, accommodation, gastronomy. Free brochures, maps, E-Brochures. Gift shop.</item>
</list>


<head>Public transport</head>

<p>Veszprém public transport solved by a dense bus network, <ref target="http://www.vp-menetrend.atw.hu/">details</ref>, <ref target="http://www.balatonvolan.hu/ez/index1.php%23top">Balaton Volan, interactiv map</ref> .</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> 1 Bus Station - Papal Road round (05:10-18:10)</item>
<item> 2 Railway Station - Downtown - Railway Station (05:04-21:35)</item>
<item> 3 Haskovo turns - Csererdő (05:00 to 22:12)</item>
<item> 4 Railway Station-Downtown - Vámosi Road turns (04:00 to 22:05)</item>
<item> 5 Kádártai út – Tüzér u. (05:02–21:56)</item>
<item> 6 Haszkovó turn – Vámosi út (04:58–22:30)</item>
<item> 7 Haszkovó turn–downtown- Cholnokyváros - Haszkovó turn (05:15–22:05)</item>
<item> 8 Haszkovó turn – Pápai út/Csatárhegyi út (05:21–17:53)</item>
<item> 10 Cholnoky turn - Papal út (05:10 to 22:10, only on weekdays, especially in the morning)</item>
<item> 11 Railway Station –Cholnokyváros- Vámosi út (05:15–21:50)</item>
<item> 12 Bus station - Buhim Valley - Bus Station (07:00–16:00, weekdays only)</item>
<item> 13 Kádártai – Dózsaváros - Kádártai út (05:08–20:18)</item>
<item> 22 Bus station - Laci major (Veszprém-Szabadságpuszta) (05:10-22:30)</item>
<item> 23 Bus station - Kádárta-Gyulafirátót, turn (04:35 to 22:25)</item>
<item> 24 Bus station - Kádárta, railway stop (06:50 to 07:25, weekdays only )</item>
<item> 32, 34 Cholnoky turn - Csererdő (05:10 to 22:10, during the holidays Cholnoky - Valeo)</item>
<item> 35 Bus Station - Csererdő (05:15 to 22:10, weekdays only)</item>
</list>

<p>Some other lines runs only on special occasions.</p>

<head>Churches</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">St. Michael's Cathedral</hi> (A veszprémi érsekség főszékesegyháza, Szent Mihály-székesegyház), Vár utca 27 (North end of Catle Hill), ☏ +36 88 328 038 . May-Oct: 10:00-18:00. Masses: Basilica M-Sa 19:00, Su 09:00, 10:30, 19:00. Franciscan daily 07:00, Chapel of St. Anne M-F (during school time) 07:15, Su 10:00; Charles Church M-F 18:00, Sa 18:00, Su 8:00, 18:00, Rosary every day 17:30 (open half hour before mass). The principal cathedral of the Archdiocese of Veszprém. Founded 10th century (Romanesque) origin, Gothic crypt (end of 14th century). The external facade showin medieval details. Today's form of neo-Romanesque, rebuilt in 1907-1910, by architect Sándor Aigner. The church nave with flat paneled ceiling is covered.The column heads are designed model of the Árpád-era (10th-13th centuries) carvings, during the renovation in 1907-1910. Both side naves have two-altars. North side nave have (at the main entrance to the left) the Assumption and the St George's altars. The south nave (the main entrance to the right) have the St. Anne's and the St. Emeric altars. The church wall paintings made by Szirmay Anthony. The wall paintings depict, among other things, Saints of the Árpád dynasty, Great St. Gregory, St. John of Nepomuk and St. Augustine of Hippo, and the four evangelists. The glass windows St. Stephen, St. Margaret, Happy Ilona, Queen Gizella, St. Joseph and St. Gellert shown. There is a special relic: the Queen Gizella right forearm bones- In the main hall of the Gothic crypt placed the headstones of Bánáss Laszlo and Peter Beriszló bishops of Veszprém. A small room opening from here where Bishop Padányi Biró Martin in 1762 Baroque tomb is housed. Donation.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gizella Chapel</hi> (Gizella-kápolna), Vár u. 16 (between the Archbishop's Palace and the High Provost Palace), ☏ +36 88 426088 , ✉ gizellakiralyne@ersekseg.veszprem.hu . Tu -Su 10:00-17:00. The city's oldest medieval building; the 13th-century Gothic. The 13th-century frescoes in Hungary include the oldest. The arch keystones and the dragon's chapters are unique. Ft 300.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St. Stephen's Roman Catholic Franciscan church and monastery</hi> (Szent István római katolikus, ferences templom és rendház), Vár u. 33, ☏ +36 88 426088 . Closed. In addition Bíró-Giczey house. Baroque, 1723 to 1730. The facade is transformed and expanded with a tower in 1909. Inside ceiling painting was made in 1798-1801, a Bucher Xaver creation. Ányos Pál's tomb in the crypt, 1784. The benches carved in the end of the 18th century, copf style.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St. Emeric Roman Catholic Piarist Church</hi> (Piarista templom, Szent Imre-templom), Vár u. 12-14, ☏ +36 88 426-088 . Between May and October: Tu-Su 10:00 -17:00, Monday holiday.. Built in 1823-1833, classicist style. Renewed in 1901. Equipment: five altars (classicist, around 1840)</item>
</list>


<head>Museums</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Salesianum Archbishopric Tourism Centre</hi> (Szaléziánum Érsekségi Turisztikai Központ, Madaras ház), Vár u. 31., ☏ +36 88 580528 , ✉ info@szalezianum.hu . Jan-Feb: Tu-Sa 10:00-17:00; Mar-May: Tu-Su 10:00-17:00; Jun-Aug: daily 09:00-18:00; Sep-Dec: Tu-Su 10:00-17:00. The place got its name from Saint Francis de Sales (the patron saint of writers and journalists). Four levels exhibition area. Here can be seen: exclusive, frescoed halls, Violin Making Workshop. Herbal Garden. There is a cafe. The café offers: Wide selection of tea and coffee, soft drinks and refreshments. Halimba herbal teas. Daily offer fresh cakes. It is possible to taste the special archbishopric communion wine. Try the Pannonhalma Abbey's herbal liqueur and consume other hungaricums. At the interactive tables you get acquainted about housing services, the archdiocese and the city's history and programs. Also there is a Gift and Bookstore. (Holy Scriptures, prayer books, calendars, postcards, greeting cards, candles, CDs and DVDs).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Former Bishop (now Archbishop) Palace</hi> (Püspöki (ma Érseki) palota), Szentháromság tér/Vár u. 16-18.. May-Oct: Tu-Su 10:00-17:00. Only guided tours!. Late Baroque, a Jakab Fellner creation.The Great Hall and Chapel frescoes are baroque from the 18th century. The Picture Hall preserve the paintings made of bishops and archbishop of Veszprém. The image, porcelain and furniture collections are very valuable. The wood-paneling Baroque Library Hall made in the second half of the 18th century. Its library has about 60,000 volumes counted. In the Archives of the Episcopal has got Hungary earliest original remained private document, the Guden's testament of 1079.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Queen Gizella Museum</hi> (Gizella Királyné Múzeum), Vár utca 35, ☏ +36 88 426088 , ✉ gizellakiralyne@ersekseg.veszprem.hu . In Tejfalussy House (Baroque, 1772). The collection include religious artifacts, bishop-prelate bequests, donations to the Queen. In the cellar is a valuable lapidary</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Castle Gate (Heroic Gate) and Castle Museum</hi> (Várkapu (Hősi kapu)), Vár u. 3. (South part of the Castle). Daily 10:00-18:00. 15-17th centuries, rebuilt in memory of the World War I victims, The tower of its include the Castle Museum. Ft 600/400, Combined ticket (Heroes' Gate, and the Tower valid): Adult: Ft 800 Student pensioner: Ft 500.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">House of Arts &amp; the Csikász Gallery</hi> (Csikász Galéria, Művészetek Háza), Vár utca 17, ☏ +36 88 425204 . M-Sa 10:00-18:00. Full price/reduced admission Ft 500/400 (2014), Castle Gallery temporary exhibitions full price/reduced admission Ft 500/400. Granary temporary exhibitions full price/reduced admission Ft 300/200.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Vass Collection</hi> (Modern Képtár- Vass László Gyűjtemény), Vár utca 5-7 (Castle), ☏ +36 88 561-310 , ✉ info@vasscollection.hu . M-Sa 10:00-18:00. In a listed building. Built in neoclassical style, circa 1820 Full price/reduced admission Ft 800/500.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hungarian Construction Industry Museum - Brick Museum</hi> (Magyar Építőipari Múzeum - Téglamúzeum), Vár utca 29-31 (Castle), ☏ +36 88 578310 , fax: +36 88 578310 , ✉ epmuzeum@vnet.hu . Tu-Su 10:00-18:00. Tegularium - collection of the Hungarian 'stamped' bricks. Main unit: 'Stove-house' (Kályhásmester-ház), address=Szent István u. 07., hours=M-F 10:00-18:00, tel:+36 88 578310, fax: +36 88 578310</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dubniczay House, László Károly collection</hi> (Dubniczay-ház, László Károly gyűjtemény), Vár u. 29.. Baroque, 1751. Now offices and an exhibit place. The László collection include 20th century art, paintings, sculptures, graphics (mostly from Hungarin artists). Full price/reduced admission Ft 1000/600.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fire Tower</hi> (Tűztorony, Vigyázó torony), Vár u. 9 (South end of Catle). Daily 10:00-18:00. Former called 'Protector Tower'. The base is medieval, the upper part made in 1814-1817 based on Tumler Henrik plans. From its balcony the whole city can be seen. The clock will ring every quarter hour and at every hour played a recruiting song of composer Anthony Csermák Adult Ft 400,Student pensioner: Ft 300.</item>
</list>
</text>
