<text id="autogum_voyage_doc487" title="Swindon" shortTile="swindon" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=34828" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Swindon</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.visitswindon.co.uk/">Swindon</ref></hi> is a large town in <ref target="Wiltshire">Wiltshire</ref>, in southern England, with a population of approximately 200,000 people. It doesn't have very much to offer from a historical perspective, although it does have a great deal of heritage from the British railway system in which it played a central part during the 19th and 20th centuries.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The town began its existence as a Saxon village, and it is likely that its name is derived from the Saxon words 'swine dun' or 'swines down' meaning 'pig hill'. The small hilltop village subsequently expanded around the site of a quarry, with a 19th-century canal facilitating trade.</p>

<p>During the mid-19th century, the introduction of the Great Western Railway and the associated railway works fully transformed Swindon from a village into a thriving industrial town, which drew workers from across the United Kingdom.</p>

<p>Swindon experienced a population boom after World War II. New housing areas were built due to a shortage of housing in London following the mass destruction caused by the war. This population growth has continued and the town remains one of the fastest growing urban areas in the United Kingdom and Europe.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>Swindon is served by international airports in the south of the United Kingdom. For travellers coming directly to Swindon, the following airports are most convenient:</p>

<p>Arrival points involving greater travel times include <ref target="London%20Gatwick%20Airport">London Gatwick Airport</ref>, <ref target="London%20Stansted%20Airport">London Stansted Airport</ref>, London Luton Airport, Bournemouth Airport, Birmingham Airport and Cardiff Airport.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>Swindon has one railway station, in the centre of the town - . It is on Station Road, immediately north of the town centre, and offers four platforms for arrivals and departures.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">From London and the South East of England</hi> - Swindon has a direct rail connection to <ref target="London%20Paddington">London Paddington</ref>, a major railway terminus in Central London, a short distance north of Hyde Park. Services from Paddington take approximately 1 hour to reach Swindon, travelling via Reading (the halfway point of the journey). Some services also call at Didcot Parkway.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">From South Wales and the West Country</hi> - Services arriving into Swindon from the west originate at a number of stations, such as Swansea, Cardiff Central and Bristol Temple Meads.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">From Gloucestershire and the West Midlands</hi> - Arrivals from Kemble, Cheltenham Spa and Gloucester.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>
<ref target="http://www.nationalexpress.com/">National Express</ref> Coaches are available from the central bus station. Tickets can be purchased from the bus station office for all major cities and airports (bus transfers may apply - visit the website for more information).

<head>By car</head>
<p>Driving along the M4, take junction 15 or 16 into Swindon. There are no direct Park and Ride depots near the junctions, one is available is entering Swindon via Wroughton (traveling from Devises or Avebury) <ref target="http://www.parkandride.net/swindon/swindon_frameset.shtml">National Park and Ride Directory</ref>.</p>

<head>By foot</head>

<p>The town centre is small enough to walk through on foot, as is the shopping areas of Old Town, the Great Western Designer Outlet Village, the Orbital Retail Park and the Shaw Ridge Leisure Park &amp; West Swindon Shopping Centre. Although it is a great way of seeing Swindon, it is not recommended as most attractions are more than 45 minutes walk from the centre of the town - it is advisable to travel by bus. The attractions within 15 minutes walk of the town centre include the Steam Museum, the Railway Village, the Wyvern Theatre, the civic council offices and central Public Library, the Swindon Hydro Centre, the main bus station, the railway station, and some hotels.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Swindon has an extensive local bus network, with the vast majority of routes radiating outward from the town centre (either from the bus station or the Fleming Way bus stands).</p>

<p>The two main bus operators in the town are <ref target="http://www.thamesdown-transport.co.uk/">Thamesdown Transport</ref> and <ref target="http://www.stagecoachbus.com/localdefault.aspx%3FTag%3DSwindon">Stagecoach West</ref>.</p>

<p>A full list of routes can be found at the Swindon Borough Council <ref target="http://www.swindonbus.info/timetables.asp">bus information website</ref></p>

<head>By bicycle</head>
<p>Swindon has extensive support for bikes, with paths following major roads split between pedestrians and cycles.</p>

<p>For more detailed information about cycle routes to and from Swindon, see the <ref target="http://www.swindonweb.com/index.asp%3Fm%3D11%26amp%3Bs%3D1456%26amp%3Bss%3D1464">SwindonWeb Cycle Route website</ref>.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>The road network in Swindon is comprehensively signposted. To get from one side of Swindon to the other, locals have the option of driving through town, or jumping on the motorway from junction 15 to 16. This method of getting across Swindon has been somewhat superseded by the almost unused link between Drove Road/Wroughton and the Rushy Platt junction.</p>
<p>One of the major attractions when driving around Swindon is the <hi rend="italic">Magic Roundabout</hi>, named after the 1960s television show. This sprawling junction contains five mini-roundabouts, each situated around a bigger, but less obvious, central counter-clockwise roundabout (which houses a very bright street light for night driving). Each mini-roundabout has three junctions, two leading on to the next and previous mini-roundabout, and one acting as an entry/exit junction. Many visitors are immediately intimidated by local drivers who use it proficiently, but the local secret is to treat each mini-roundabout as normal, rather than looking at the daunting mass of concrete and cars.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cotswold Water Park</hi>. The United Kingdom's largest water park has over 150 lakes which were formed by filling old gravel quarries. It is about north-west of Swindon and offers many water sports and activities.</item>
</list>


<head>Museums</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Steam: The Great Western Railway Museum</hi> (Steam Museum), Fire Fly Ave, SN2 2EY (Follow directions to the Designer Outlet Village, then pickup signs to Steam), ☏ +44 1793 466637 , ✉ steammuseum@swindon.gov.uk . 10AM-5PM every day except Christmas (check website). The museum is in a restored railway works building. The building is a treat in itself. As well as having a wealth of information about the railways, it also is an invaluable source of social history. There are plenty of events for children, and it is right next to the Great Western Designer Outlet Village and the National Trust Headquarters, so anyone in the family who doesn't want to visit the museum has plenty of other options. Adults £8, Children £6. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Museum of Computing @ Swindon</hi>, 6-7 Theatre Square, SN1 1QN, ☏ +44 7834 375628 . F 10AM-4PM, Sa 9:30AM-5PM. Educational museum with excellent collections of what are now antique computers and games consoles. Guided tours depending on number of visitors. The museum has even been visited by Google Street View: http://goo.gl/maps/bvbyp Adults £2, children £1. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Swindon Museum</hi>, Bath Rd, SN1 4BA. M-Sa 10AM-5PM, Su 2PM-5PM. Interesting displays on local history, geology and archaeology. It is run by the local council. Free. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Wroughton Science Museum</hi>, Red Barn Gate, ☏ +44 1793 846222 . Just outside Swindon on the old RAF Wroughton Airfield, the science museum features display on science and engineering topics. </item>
</list>
</text>
