<text id="autogum_voyage_doc144" title="Fort Pierce" shortTile="fort-pierce" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11888" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fort Pierce</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Fort Pierce</hi> is a small city on the <ref target="Treasure%20Coast">Treasure Coast</ref> of <ref target="Florida">Florida</ref>. The city is most commonly referred to as "The Fort" in reference to the old fort on Indian River Drive.</p>
<head>Understand</head>
<p>Fort Pierce is the oldest incorporated city in St. Lucie County, with a bustling and historic downtown area, close location to beaches on the Indian River Lagoon and the Atlantic Ocean by its extension to Hutchinson Island, and many famous celebrities visiting every summer at the Sunrise Theatre. Ft. Pierce has a population of 43,601 by the 2013 US Census Estimate; Fort Pierce is also a part of the <ref target="Port%20St.%20Lucie">Port St. Lucie</ref> metropolitan area, or the <ref target="Treasure%20Coast">Treasure Coast</ref>, an area populated at almost 600,000.</p>

<p>Fort Pierce is a small railroad city along <ref target="Florida">Florida's</ref> east coast, being the location of a mid-sized rail yard with track rights owned by the Florida East Coast Railroad, with track all the way to Miami and Jacksonville, and South Central Florida Express, with track from the downtown yard to <ref target="Clewiston">Clewiston</ref> and <ref target="Sebring">Sebring</ref>.</p>

<p>FP is becoming more and more modernized, but slowly and steadily. Downtown is considered the hot-spot of the city due to its blossoming commercialism, amazing Spanish-colonial buildings, celebrities performing at the Sunrise Theatre, and an amazing Christmas display yearly at Avenues A and Orange. There's a lot of fun going on with the marina and many interesting shops on the thoroughfares of Orange Avenue and Avenue D.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Fort Pierce, like many cities has many major highways running through the city. Major highways include I-95, US-1, and Florida's Turnpike.</p>

<p>By <hi rend="bold">Interstate 95</hi>, you can access Fort Pierce by:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Exit 126</hi> at Midway Road. Going west will take you to Okeechobee Road, which is what the locals call State Road 70. Going east will take you to the beach.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Exit 129</hi> at Okeechobee Road. There are many hotels and fast food restaurants near by. Going west will take you to Okeechobee and further to Bradenton. Going east will put you closer into the heart of downtown.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Exit 131</hi> at Orange Avenue. Going west will take you out to the "country" area of the city with many ranches. Going east will take you into downtown.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Exit 138</hi> at Indrio Road. Services are east of the exit.</item>
</list>


<p>By <hi rend="bold">Florida's Turnpike</hi>, you can access Fort Pierce by:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Exit 152</hi> at SR 70, or Okeechobee Road.</item>
</list>


<p>One special thing about the Okeechobee Road area between I-95 and the Turnpike is that it is considered to be a crossroads, where two highways are within a driving range of less than a mile. Businesses, from hotels to restaurants, are abundant in this State Road 70 corridor. Businesses along State Road 70 don't just exist at the cross roads, but also run along to US-1.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">US-1</hi> and <hi rend="bold">A1A</hi> run through the heart of downtown, and A1A almost parallels US-1. A1A runs along the barrier islands of the east coast, from Miami to the Jacksonville area. The local name for A1A on Hutchinson Island South crossing onto US-1 is "Seaway Drive".</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>Fort Pierce is home to the St. Lucie County International, the local airport. Here, you can buy a plane to fly from place to place, due to no commercial flights.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">St. Lucie County International Airport</hi>, 3000 Curtis King Blvd., ☏ +1 772-462-1732 . The only airport serving the county. No commercial service yet, so bring your own plane.</item>
</list>


<p>If you want to get in by a commercial flight, your best options are:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Orlando%20International%20Airport">Orlando International Airport</ref> </hi>, 1 Jeff Fuqua Boulevard, Orlando, FL 32827, ☏ +1 407-825-2001 . This airport is outside of the region, but is used to get into the region, serving almost all global US cities.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Melbourne International Airport</hi>, 1 Air Terminal Pkwy, Melbourne, FL 32901, ☏ +1 321-723-6227 . Serves <ref target="Atlanta">Atlanta</ref>, <ref target="Charlotte">Charlotte</ref>, and <ref target="Washington%20DC">Washington DC</ref> at Dulles.</item>
</list>

 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Palm Beach International Airport</hi>, 1000 Palm Beach International Airport, West Palm Beach, FL 33406, ☏ +1 561-471-7400 . Serving major airports from Boston to Dallas.</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>
<p>There has been much talk and controversy about the Florida East Coast Railroad and Amtrak giving the <ref target="Port%20St.%20Lucie">Port St. Lucie</ref> area, possibly Fort Pierce, a train station that serves passengers. If these plans go through, they will be serving the Florida East Coast Railway on rails that have not been touched by the rumbling wheels of passenger trains since the mid-1900s. Also, there has been controversy of a high-speed rail project from <ref target="Miami">Miami</ref> to <ref target="Orlando">Orlando</ref> with a station in <ref target="West%20Palm%20Beach">West Palm Beach</ref>; a station may be placed in the PSL area as well to accommodate. The full plan is rebuilding a passenger line to re-connect the Treasure Coast and the Space Coast with the rest of the country, serving from Martin County to northern Brevard County. The closest stations to date are in <ref target="Okeechobee">Okeechobee</ref> and <ref target="West%20Palm%20Beach">West Palm Beach</ref>.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">West Palm Beach</hi>, 209 South Tamarind Avenue West Palm Beach, FL 33401. Ticket office, waiting room, and two different routes going two ways!</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Okeechobee</hi>, 801 North Parrott Avenue Okeechobee, FL 34972. Platform station with shelter. Only a stopping location, no ticket office yet.</item>
</list>
<head>By bus</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Greyhound Lines</hi>, (bus station) 7150 Okeechobee Rd (Kings Highway and Okeechobee Road, north of the I-95/Florida Turnpike junction.), ☏ +1 775 461-3299 , toll-free: +1 800 231-2222 . M-Sa 7:30AM to 6:30PM and Su 7:30AM to 3:15PM. They also have additional stops at a Shell Station on 1795 SW St Lucie West Rd in Port St Lucie and at a Sunoco Gas Station on 8418 20th St in Vero Beach. The gas stations stops do NOT sell tickets.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jet Set Express</hi>, (bus stop) Port St. Lucie-Fort Pierce Service Plaza (MM 144 of the Florida Turnpike), ☏ +1 407 649-4994 . Venue at stop open 24/7. Bus between Miami-Dade and Orlando</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Red Coach</hi>, (bus stop) Port St. Lucie-Fort Pierce Service Plaza (MM 144 of the Florida Turnpike, north of Crosstown Pkwy Jct), ☏ +1 321 604-7188 , toll-free: +1 877-733-0724 . Venue at stop open 24/7.</item>
</list>
</text>
