<text id="autogum_voyage_doc0" title="Teaneck" shortTile="teaneck" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=35488" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Teaneck</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Teaneck</hi> is a township in <ref target="Bergen%20County">Bergen County</ref>, <ref target="New%20Jersey">New Jersey</ref>. It is the suburb with the second highest population of the 70 towns in the county with 39,776 as of the 2010 United States Census. The town is 11 miles west of New York City.</p>

<p>Teaneck was founded on February 19, 1895. Today, it has a diverse population. Teaneck has many lovely streets for its residents and visitors to stroll, shop, dine, and even enjoy local artwork.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>You will more than likely need a car to get around. If you work in New York City, however, you can easily take a bus ride. Public transportation is fairly easy to figure out and buses run very frequently in and out of the town’s limits.</p>

<p>Just like New York, summers are hot and sticky with temperatures rising into the 90s. The usual summer temperatures range from 69-85 °F (21-29 °C), and the winter months usually range from as high as 38 degrees to as low as . The tri-state area shares a very similar range in temperature and they take pleasure in all four seasons.</p>

<p>The town is known for its major institutions like Holy Name Medical Hospital and the Metropolitan Campus of Farleigh Dickinson University, the largest private university in the state of New Jersey. The Teaneck Armory is home to the New Jersey National Guard’s 50th Main Support Battalion and they host many events for the community, mainly in the summer months. The commercial development of the town is concentrated in four main shopping areas and there is convenient access to many main highways from different points in town.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Teaneck is positioned along a number of major highways, including the New Jersey Turnpike (a portion of I-95) and I-80. Teaneck is the eastern final point of I-80, which stretches around west to downtown San Francisco, California. The town’s main highway is Route 4, running east to west through Teaneck from New York. There is no commercial development along this highway in the town itself due to a decision taken back in the 1940s to create a greenbelt, but there is easy access to the commercial area just a few minutes down Route 4. New Jersey’s other main route is the Garden State Parkway, which can be reached by car just a few miles west of Teaneck.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>The closest commercial airport to Teaneck in New Jersey is <ref target="Newark%20Liberty%20International%20Airport">Newark Liberty International Airport</ref>, away in Newark. New York City’s <ref target="New%20York%20City%23LaGuardia%20Airport">LaGuardia Airport</ref> is miles away in Queens and can be accessed via the George Washington Bridge and is approximately 22 minutes away (in the most ideal traffic conditions). <ref target="John%20F.%20Kennedy%20International%20Airport">John F. Kennedy International Airport</ref> in Queens is (34 minutes) from Teaneck. There is also Teterboro Airport ( TEB ), which offers general aviation service, and is about (10 minutes) away. All of these airports can be accessed by car or by taxi services located in Teaneck that will pick you up any time, day or night.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>New Jersey Transit bus service has very frequent service to Teaneck Road, Route 4, and Cedar Lane. There is less frequent service on other main streets. NJTransit bus services are offered at the Port Authority Bus Terminal in <ref target="Manhattan/Theater%20District">Midtown Manhattan</ref> via the 155, 157, 167, and 168 routes. There is service to and from the George Washington Bridge Bus Terminal in <ref target="Manhattan/Harlem%20and%20Upper%20Manhattan">Upper Manhattan</ref> via the 171, 175, 178, and 186 routes. </p>

<p>A number of jitney services also provide an inexpensive, fast unscheduled service along Route 4 between <ref target="Paterson">Paterson</ref> and the George Washington Bridge Bus Terminal, with stops along the way including several in Teaneck.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>There is no passenger train operation in Teaneck.</p>

<head>See and do</head>

<p>Teaneck has four main shopping areas located on Cedar Lane, Teaneck Road, DeGraw Avenue, West Englewood Avenue, and Queen Anne Road, most commonly known as "The Plaza."</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cedar Lane</hi>. One of the more popular and conveniently located streets is one of the busiest streets in town. There are over 15 restaurants, clothing stores, shoe stores, salons, and the Cedar Lane Cinemas. It is the town’s only movie theater and they occasionally host live performances by local performance groups. Many restaurant on the street are Kosher. A farmers' market is held every week, even into the winter months, and has become one of the most popular events in town. Free dance lessons are also given outdoors in the summer months as a community outreach program to bring people of all ages and backgrounds together.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Teaneck Road</hi>. This is another popular street for residents to shop for the essentials without having to get on any highways. This road stretches all the way through town, connecting Teaneck to its bordering towns. There is also direct access to the highway from many points on this road.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">West Englewood Avenue</hi>. The west portion of this street stretches from the train tracks all the way down to the Hackensack River and is mostly residential, but east of the tracks, the street is part of the Queen Anne Road "Plaza" business district and is lined with restaurants and shops.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Queen Anne Road (“The Plaza”)</hi>. This is the most popular road in town next to Cedar Lane because of its diversity. There is something for every demographic, whether it is a Kosher chain of places to eat, a bank, a pharmacy, and the most popular restaurant in town Mexicali Blues Café. Live bands will come and play at the café once or twice a month and the place will stay open until well passed two in the morning. The younger crowd tends to hang out down there, but up the road is referred to as “The Plaza” where families gather. Several Kosher eateries are found in the area where families can go and have their choice of pizza, falafel, chicken, bagels, pasta, chinese, sushi, Persian, Italian, burgers, salads, and even a Starbucks-like coffee house.</item>
</list>


<head>Parks</head>

<p>For its size, Teaneck has quite a few parks, 7 to be exact. They are mostly small grassy spaces in residential areas with swing sets and basketball courts, but there are a few that hold significance for the entire town.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Andreas Park</hi>. West Englewood Avenue will lead you down the hill to this park that sits on the edge of the Hackensack River. This park has large open space, a jungle gym and free public tennis courts. This park is active year round with a great spot for people to push off in their boats to drift on the Hackensack River.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Votee Park</hi>. The largest completely developed park in Teaneck and is located almost right in the middle of town. The park covers a huge amount of space, covering an area between Queen Anne Road and Palisade Avenue. Facilities include an in-ground swimming pool, a children’s wading pool, restrooms, an amphitheater, three soccer fields, five baseball fields, refreshment stands, a double handball court, four tennis courts, and a lighted, enclosed, two court basketball facility. There are 2 playgrounds (at either end), picnic areas, and paved walking paths. One playground is accessible for disabled children and has special equipment designed for kids with physical disabilities.</item>
</list>
</text>
