<text id="autogum_voyage_doc269" title="County Durham" shortTile="county-durham" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=8399" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>County Durham</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.durham.gov.uk/">County Durham</ref></hi> is a county in <ref target="North%20East%20%28England%29">North East</ref> England with a population of 510,800. It's north of Yorkshire and south of Newcastle, astride the main north-south transport route. The east is mostly farmland, interspersed by former mining towns. <hi rend="bold">Darlington</hi> near its southern edge is the main conurbation, but <hi rend="bold">Durham</hi> is its main visitor attraction. The west is hilly, with sheep farms and remote moorlands. </p>

<head>Cities, towns and villages</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> The <hi rend="bold">City of</hi> , population 29,000, has a well-preserved ancient centre, dominated by its Norman castle and cathedral. It's also home to a large university. The city is well worth a visit of a couple of days.</item>
<item> is the largest settlement in the county, popn 100,000, yet it only counts as a town not a city. Birthplace of the railways and always industrial, but affluent in its leafy west and south west, Darlington doesn't have a university but there's a large college.</item>
</list>


<p>Most of the county's other towns are between Durham and Darlington, in fertile low-lying country along the A1. Beneath them is the Great Northern Coalfield, mined since medieval times, stretching up into Northumbria. Hence the industry, the steam engines to pump those mines, and the railways to haul and consume the coals. The underground mines have all closed, leaving the towns to scratch what living they can from new trades.</p>

<p>The main towns along this stretch are , , which has a railway museum, and . </p>

<p>Other towns in the north of the county are:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> is a small former mining town near the coast. Shotton Colliery is probably the world's only coal mine converted for skydiving.</item>
<item> village has an impressive outdoor museum.</item>
<item> , midway between Durham and Newcastle, has Durham County Cricket Ground, where "Test" ie international cricket matches are also played.</item>
</list>


<p>The western part of County Durham is in the Pennines, the long chain of hills that forms the backbone of England. There are lonely moors, and steep river valleys flowing out eastward, so the main road A68 follows a roller-coaster trajectory. Here are:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> , a market town that's home to the grandiose Bowes Museum.</item>
<item> , former mining town on the northern edge of the county.</item>
<item> in a scenic valley, with High Force waterfall.</item>
<item> in Weardale, an old lead-mining town.</item>
</list>


<p>To the southeast, around the River Tees, is an industrial area which from 1974 to 1996 was a separate county, <hi rend="bold">Cleveland</hi>. Then this was abolished, and its towns south of the Tees were re-assigned to North Yorkshire. (The assignation is notional since these towns are "unitary authorities", not governed by a County Council.) Towns to the north, re-assigned to County Durham, are:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> : a post-industrial port, with an interesting dockyard museum.</item>
<item> actually straddles the Tees. It's very industrial; but there's a southern rural district, <ref target="Yarm">Yarm</ref>, now considered part of North Yorkshire.</item>
</list>


<p>The same 1974 re-organisation also removed Sunderland from County Durham. It's now part of Tyne &amp; Wear.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Within England, only County Durham contains the word "county" in its title (in the way many Irish counties do), because the powerful Norman "Prince Bishops" of Durham ruled it as a palatinate separate from the rest of England's counties. Originally it covered all the territory between the River Tees and the River Tyne, but over the centuries, and especially with modern changes to local government, it's been whittled down and continually re-organised. The name no longer precisely corresponds to a unit of local government, and probably the only two people who can say exactly where County Durham lies are the High Sheriff and Her Majesty's Lord-Lieutenant, whose ceremonial duties relate to an older map of the world.</p>

<p>None of this is of the slightest concern to any traveller not gussied up in alderman's ermine or dress military uniform. For present purposes, "County Durham" on this page includes the post-2009 districts of Durham County (sic), Darlington, Hartlepool and Stockton-on-Tees. It doesn't include Sunderland to the north or Middlesbrough, Redcar or Yarm to the south.</p>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>Listen very carefully to the local language: you'll need to. First, believe it or not, it <hi rend="italic">is</hi> English you're hearing. The minority populations and languages in this area are small: during the 20th C the county was shedding labour from mining and ship-building in an era when others (eg the textile towns) were drawing it in from UK and abroad. The only significant minority language is Polish, spoken by 1%.</p>

<p>The local English dialect is "Geordie", spoken in Durham, Newcastle and Northumbria; the word also means a resident of those areas. "Geordie" probably simply derives from "George", a very common name for a local coal-miner, and there used to be a miners' <hi rend="italic">patois</hi> called "Pitmatic" or "Yakka" but it's almost died out. If you learn only one Geordie word, learn "Howay!", an all-purpose greeting, exclamation or warning.</p>

<p>But what makes Geordie a thing of fascination and wonder is that it is probably very close to English as spoken over thousand years ago, as it evolved from Anglo-Saxon. Read <hi rend="italic">Beowulf</hi> and try to make sense of it - then have a local read it aloud in a heavy Geordie accent for a "Eureka!" moment. And attempts to translate the works of the Venerable Bede (8th C AD), who wrote in Latin, reveal that what he thought and dreamed in was Geordie. Howay, indeed!</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>The closest useful airport is ( NCL ) with direct flights to London, Amsterdam, Paris and Dubai. It's easy to reach, being on the metro. </p>

<p>Manchester Airport is some 150 miles south but has excellent global connections, competitive fares, and an hourly direct train to Darlington, Durham and Newcastle. </p>

<p>The closest airport is ( MME ), near Darlington, but there's little reason to use it. It only has two or three flights a day (to Amsterdam and to Aberdeen), public transport to it is non-existent, and they extort a £6 "facility fee" from departing passengers.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>This county saw the world's first public railway, opened in 1825. The central spine of the county has excellent railway connections, being on the East Coast Main Line. Frequent fast trains come up from London Kings Cross via York to Darlington (2 hrs 30 mins) and Durham. They continue north to Chester-le-Street, Newcastle and Edinburgh. Other trains link Stockton, Middlesbrough and Sunderland. A branch line train runs hourly from Darlington to Newton Aycliffe, Shildon and Bishop Auckland (30 min). </p>
</text>
