<text id="autogum_voyage_doc506" title="West Iceland" shortTile="west-iceland" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=39041" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>West Iceland</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.west.is">West Iceland</ref></hi> (<ref target="Icelandic%20phrasebook">Icelandic</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Vesturland</hi>) is the region of <ref target="Iceland">Iceland</ref> north of <ref target="Reykjav%C3%ADk">the capital</ref>.</p>

<head>Towns</head>

<p>Listed from south to north.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> – a town by Borgarfjörður about an hour and a half from Reykjavík by car. It used to be a service centre for the neighboring farming communities, but has a developed tourist industry and is a good place to stay for those wanting to get out of Reykjavík while remaining close to the southwest corner.</item>
<item> – the largest town on Snæfellsnes and gateway to the islands of Breiðafjörður. Has many houses of Danish influence dating back to the 18th and 19th centuries.</item>
<item> – to the west of Stykkishólmur, on the north coast of Snæfellsnes.</item>
<item> , <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Rif">Rif</ref></hi> and <hi rend="bold"><ref target="%C3%93lafsv%C3%ADk">Ólafsvík</ref></hi> – three villages on the western end of Snæfellsnes, close to Snæfellsjökull and the national park.</item>
<item> – small village in Dalirnir, known for its cheese production.</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> – former home of Snorri Sturluson, medieval poet, author and chieftain.</item>
<item> - on the tip of the Snæfellsnes Peninsula in southern Iceland, this park is home to the ice-covered volcanic crater that was the setting for Jules Verne's book <hi rend="italic">Journey to the Center of the Earth</hi>.</item>
<item> – the largest island in Breiðafjörður, and the only one that is inhabited.</item>
<item> — A shield volcano and former glacier. There is a memorial plaque for the glacier, dated 2019, with the inscription "<hi rend="italic">Ok is the first Icelandic glacier to lose its status as a glacier. In the next 200 years all our glaciers are expected to follow the same path. This monument is to acknowledge that we know what is happening and what needs to be done. Only you know if we did it.</hi>"</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>

<p>West Iceland can be split into four main areas. Furthest north are Dalirnir (The Valleys), a farming area mainly seen by tourists driving through on their way to North Iceland. Dalirnir contain a remarkable natural phenomenon, though: The hills. There are many of them. Very many in fact. And some of the hills have hills on top of them. Icelandic legend has it that the hills are so many that they're uncountable.</p>

<p>A second uncountable phenomenon is found to the west of Dalirnir. Breiðafjörður is a large bay scattered with a supposedly uncountable number of small islands. In earlier times these islands were all used for farming purposes, but today only one of them is inhabited, the island of <ref target="Flatey">Flatey</ref>.</p>

<p>South of Breiðafjörður is a large, long peninsula. Snæfellsnes is one long mountain range with stunning, if barren, beauty. Dotted along the coastline are fishing communities, with farming taking place on the little lowland regions found between the coast and the mountains.</p>

<p>Finally, to the south of Snæfellsnes, there is the farming area surrounding Borgarfjörður. This is an important agricultural area, reaching far inland. Borg, the farm after which both Borgarfjörður and the town of <ref target="Borgarnes">Borgarnes</ref> are named, was the home of Egill Skallagrímsson, the titular character of Egil's Saga. Further inland, <ref target="Reykholt">Reykholt</ref> was home to Snorri Sturluson, one of the most important players in Iceland's 14th-century civil war and chronicler of Norwegian kings. Today the area is home to two universities, the Icelandic University of Agriculture and Bifröst University.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>West Iceland is linked to <ref target="Southwest%20Iceland">Southwest</ref> and <ref target="North%20Iceland">North Iceland</ref> via the ring road. If you are arriving from <ref target="Reykjav%C3%ADk">Reykjavík</ref>, you will most likely go through a tunnel under Hvalfjörður (the fjord marking the start of West Iceland). This is the only toll road in Iceland, and for vehicles shorter than 6 meters each trip costs 1000 kr. If you'll be going back and forth a lot, there's a discount card for ten trips at 6350 kr. Whichever direction you're driving, the toll booths are on the north. An alternative to paying is to drive around Hvalfjörður. It's a scenic drive, and well worth it if you have the time. Since the tunnel was built, the traffic levels are very low and sights include the country's only whaling station in operation as well as innumerable waterfalls, mountains and rivers. However it's a long drive, 59 km, as opposed to the 6-km long tunnel.</p>

<p>If you're arriving from the <ref target="Westfjords">Westfjords</ref>, there are two roads, one on each coast of the peninsula that links the regions. Or you can take a ferry from Brjánslækur, on the south coast of the Westfjords, called <ref target="http://seatours.is/FerryBaldur/">Baldur</ref>. Brjánslækur is only a ferry port and the closest towns are <ref target="B%C3%ADldudalur">Bíldudalur</ref> and <ref target="Patreksfj%C3%B6r%C3%B0ur">Patreksfjörður</ref>, both around 50 km away. The terminal on the West Iceland side of the route is <ref target="Stykkish%C3%B3lmur">Stykkishólmur</ref> on Snæfellsnes, with a stop in <ref target="Flatey">Flatey</ref> on the way.</p>

<p>There are no scheduled flights into West Iceland.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Roads mainly trace the coastline in West Iceland, with a few mountain passes and more inland roads in the rural area northeast of Borgarfjörður. The Ring Road bypasses large sections of the region, including Snæfellsnes and Dalirnir, meaning traffic can be very light. Although most roads are paved, the very tip of the Snæfellsnes peninsula is not, nor are some of the mountain passes. In some places, the road on Snæfellsnes sits on a very narrow ledge, with a long and steep fall to the sea below.</p>

<p>Driving on your own is the most flexible way of getting around, but there are some bus routes operated by <ref target="https://straeto.is/en">Straeto</ref>. Hitch hiking is an option for those travelling by bus who want to reach destinations not served by the bus system.</p>

<p>To get to the islands of Breiðafjörður, a boat is needed. Only Flatey is served by regular ferries from Stykkishólmur, crossing over to Brjánslækur on the south coast of the Westfjords. If you wish to visit other islands you will need to arrange transportation locally, but frankly most of them are small and without much to see.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>Natural beauty is the main attraction of the region, particularly Snæfellsnes and the islands of Breiðafjörður.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Deildartunguhver</hi> – Europe's biggest hot spring, measured in amounts of water. Close to <ref target="Reykholt">Reykholt</ref>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Snæfellsnes</hi> – a magnificent mountain range that forms a peninsula separating the bays of Faxaflói and Breiðafjörður. A trip around the peninsula will allow you to see the ocean and the mountains. Many waterfalls come out of the mountain cliffs and there are a number of beautiful rivers running from the mountains into the ocean.</item>
</list>
</text>
