<text id="autogum_voyage_doc28" title="Tacheddirt" shortTile="tacheddirt" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=35024" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tacheddirt</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Tacheddirt</hi> (also <hi rend="italic">Tachdirt</hi>) is a small village high up (2314m) in the <ref target="Atlas%20Mountains">Atlas Mountains</ref> of <ref target="Morocco">Morocco</ref>. It is the highest settlement in the Rhirhaia valley, about 2.5 miles further up than Ikkiss.</p>

<p>The village is populated by about 200 or 300 people. It has no road or track, but rather a winding footpath.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>From <ref target="Ikkiss">Ikkiss</ref> (see Ikkiss page for how to get there), it is necessary to walk to Tacheddirt, as there is no road or track more than the winding footpath. The footpath is in some places slippery and dangerous for the mules and donkeys that are used.</p>

<p>From Ikkiss it is quite difficult to find the path to Tacheddirt. The path is the one which winds up behind a small concrete water duct (by the school) on the right of the path as you walk down the slope towards the town.</p>

<p>The route is only about 1.5 miles as the crow flies, but is probably 2 or 3 on foot.</p>

<p>From <ref target="Imlil">Imlil</ref> head East up the valley, through Tamatert, and over the pass. Follow the track along the South side of the valley until you reach a ford over the river to Tacheddirt on the other side of the river.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>The only way is by foot, no roads exist. The village isn't very big anyway.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>The village is clustered on the north side of the valley, on the lower slopes of the mountain, Angour. The houses are all mud brick except for the French Refuge that was built here in the 90s(?). </p>
<p>There are only about 100 homes in the village, most are in a clump on the East side of the village by the stream, a line of others extends outwards to the west along the top of a steep slope of scree.</p>
<p>There is a small reservoir in at the top of this slope to the North West of the village, which is used to produce electricity for an hour each day. One of the few electric lights is in the French Refuge, which has a solar panel.</p>

<head>Do</head>
<p>The main reason for being here, for a traveller, is to hike in the surrounding mountains. In all directions rise mighty snow capped ridges. Many people just stay in the village one night, before moving on. However it is often easier to set up a base camp in the village and do day hikes. On the other hand the mountains are so huge, it is hard to get anywhere.</p>

<p>Two day hikes that are available are:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Hike Eastward, up the valley further to Tizi n' Tacheddirt (3230m). This way you'll see locals from the village collecting small bushes for firewood. At the top of the pass you can look over into the next valley, and either continue onwards to the next village, or (if you have time) climb the mountain to the left (called ?), before returning to Tacheddirt. Continuing East from Tizi n'Tacheddirt will bring you down to Iabessene and the Ourika Valley.</item>
<item> Hike northwards to the Tizi n'ou Addi pass. From here there is a (horribly ugly) road for the ski centre in <ref target="Oukaimeden">Oukaimeden</ref>. From the pass it is an exciting unpathed scramble up the ridge to Jebel Oukaimedene's peak (3262m ish).</item>
<item> Tacheddirt is a stop on a reasonably popular long (two week) trekking loop that visits <ref target="Lac%20d%27Ifni">Lac d'Ifni</ref> and <ref target="Jebel%20Toubkal">Jebel Toubkal</ref> before reaching <ref target="Imlil">Imlil</ref>. To continue on this loop head South from Tacheddirt over Tizi Likemt.</item>
</list>


<p>Note: All of this will be covered in snow in winter!!! Weather, in the summer or winter can change very rapidly. A thunder and hail storm can move in on a sunny cloudless day in minutes.</p>

<head>Buy</head>
<p>The French Refuge provides:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Food (the carer makes a really yummy Tagine, just ignore all the ants crawling all over his kitchen!!!)</item>
<item> Bottled Water (Pretty vital up here, unless you've brought a load with you, or have water purification tablets). Note: the water here is far more expensive than you might be expecting. The water has to get all the way from Marrakech to this village across dodgy tracks and up paths on a donkey's back.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p>Either bring your own food or buy some at the French Refuge. He makes yummy tagine and can get you bread from the bakery in Tacheddirt. Food is also available at the new hotel.</p>

<head>Drink</head>
<p>There was a little shop on the way over the pass (Tizi n Tamatert) from <ref target="Imlil">Imlil</ref> which sold coca cola &amp; mint tea. This isn't really in Tacheddirt, but is some 2 hours' walk away.</p>

<head>Sleep</head>
<p>Either in a tent (on a very hard surface remember your mat) by the Refuge, or in the refuge.</p>
<p>A new hotel is being built here by the owner of the last hotel in Aremd, it was still under construction in May 2007, but was open by May 2008. It provides comfortable accommodation and good food. The terrace has first rate views across the valley.</p>

<head>Cope</head>
<p>This village has no roads, no electricity and no running water. Even though there is a French Refuge, you should be prepared to survive on your own, should they run out of bottled water, etc. Some water purification tablets, matches, something to boil water in, etc are all probably a good idea. Also a day or twos worth of emergency food in case you can't get any here.</p>

<head>Go next</head>
<p>Walk back to <ref target="Ikkiss">Ikkiss</ref>, <ref target="Imlil">Imlil</ref> or <ref target="Oukaimeden">Oukaimeden</ref>.</p>
</text>
