<text id="autogum_voyage_doc319" title="West Africa" shortTile="west-africa" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=38843" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>West Africa</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">West Africa</hi> is the western region of <ref target="Africa">Africa</ref>. In the north the region is bounded by the <ref target="Saharan%20Africa">Sahel</ref>, and in the south and west by the <ref target="Islands%20of%20the%20Atlantic%20Ocean">Atlantic Ocean</ref>.</p>

<p>The most densely populated area of Africa, it is many ways both the continent's most difficult place for travel and potentially its most rewarding.</p>

<head>Countries</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Sometimes <ref target="Mauritania">Mauritania</ref>, <ref target="Mali">Mali</ref>, <ref target="Niger">Niger</ref>, and <ref target="Chad">Chad</ref> are also considered as West African states.</hi></p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> — the largest city in <ref target="Cote%20d%27Ivoire">Cote d'Ivoire</ref>, still a West African nightlife hotspot, despite the country's political instability</item>
<item> — the purpose-built government capital of <ref target="Nigeria">Nigeria</ref> is attractive, and remarkably safe!</item>
<item> — an incoherent jumble of a city, the capital of <ref target="Ghana">Ghana</ref>, and one of the most accessible cities in West Africa for travellers</item>
<item> — <ref target="Benin">Benin</ref>'s big non-capital has the feel of a West African, urban version of the Wild West; you can buy anything at a city that is essentially an enormous, lawless (but reasonably safe) market town, and dirt cheap "Rolexes" of questionable origin and voodoo charms remain popular items for travellers</item>
<item> — the capital of <ref target="Senegal">Senegal</ref> and the westernmost city in Africa</item>
<item> — the largest city in <ref target="Nigeria">Nigeria</ref> and the second largest in the whole of Africa is a city bursting with energy. With over 15 million inhabitants, it is considered to be like the New York of Africa where you can find anything you are looking for</item>
<item> — <ref target="Togo">Togo</ref>'s bustling capital, somewhat unfairly disliked by travellers, and possibly the moto-taxi capital of the world.</item>
<item> — the capital of <ref target="Burkina%20Faso">Burkina Faso</ref></item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> — an archipelago of some twenty tropical, beautiful islands in <ref target="Guinea%20Bissau">Guinea Bissau</ref> with French-owned fishing lodges.</item>
<item> — are these paradisiacal-looking beaches, each with an utterly unique appearance and culture, the most beautiful in the world?</item>
<item> — absurdly named the "Venice of Africa," this stilt village, at the centre of a large lake, is more of a stilt city, and offers one of the strangest photo opportunities you'll ever have.</item>
<item> (<hi rend="italic">Fouta Djallon</hi>) — hills and mountains in the interior of <ref target="Guinea">Guinea</ref> with a relatively cool climate, the home of the Pular people and sometimes called the "Switzerland of Africa."</item>
<item> — the largest National Park in <ref target="Senegal">Senegal</ref>.</item>
<item> — the largest remaining intact portion of the once great Upper Guinea Rainforest is home to the world's last viable population of pygmy hippopotami, as well as numerous rare monkeys, chimps, rare forest elephants, and other rare animals.</item>
<item> — <ref target="Togo">Togo</ref>'s somehow completely unknown answer to <ref target="Mali">Mali</ref>'s <ref target="Dogon%20Country">Dogon Country</ref>; an expansive, beautiful, mountainous region filled with surreal villages of improbable mud/clay fortresses, and culture barely touched by modernity.</item>
<item> — a large, trans-border system of national parks, with parts in <ref target="Benin">Benin</ref>, <ref target="Burkina%20Faso">Burkina Faso</ref> and <ref target="Niger">Niger</ref>, which offers the best opportunities for wildlife spotting in West Africa.</item>
<item> — the largest National Park in <ref target="Nigeria">Nigeria</ref>, and the most visited of all the parks in the region.</item>
</list>


<head>Talk</head>
<p>West Africa is home to thousands of languages and dialects native to the region. However, due to the influence of European colonizers, a common language spoken in the region is English, another commonly speaked language is French, and some regions speak Portuguese.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>The African highways connect many cities in West Africa with Nigeria being the main hub.</p>

<p>Flying from other African cities can be dangerous as many airlines have a very poor safety record. Check this first before choosing to fly with an airline.</p>

<p>In order of size here are the main airline hubs.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Lagos Airport - Several flights per day to London. Less frequent flights also to other main cities in Europe</item>
<item> Dakar Airport - Many flights to Milan, Madrid, Brussels and Paris</item>
<item> Accra Airport - Many flights to UK (Manchester, London, Glasgow) as well as Frankfurt.</item>
<item> Abidjan Airport - Flights to Paris, Brussels and Dubai</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>
<p>Generally it takes time - and a whole lot of patience - to move around in West Africa. The roads are not all in great conditions and many roads aren't paved. Always be sure to have an extra day or two in the end if you are going somewhere since planning is very hard when the transport is unreliable.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<ref target="http://www.abctransport.com/"><hi rend="bold">ABC Transport</hi></ref> runs daily coach services between <ref target="Lagos">Lagos</ref> and <ref target="Accra">Accra</ref>, <ref target="Cotonou">Cotonou</ref> and <ref target="Lom%C3%A9">Lomé</ref>.

<head>By train</head>

<p>Railway services are extremely limited in West Africa. The only country with a somewhat functioning railway system is <ref target="Nigeria">Nigeria</ref> where passenger trains connects the largest cities. Outside Nigeria, the only long distance passenger service operates 1-2 times per week between <ref target="Ouagadougou">Ouagadougou</ref>, the capital of <ref target="Burkina%20Faso">Burkina Faso</ref> and <ref target="Abidjan">Abidjan</ref> in <ref target="C%C3%B4te%20d%27Ivoire">Côte d'Ivoire</ref>.</p>

<head>See</head>

<p>Well, there actually isn't too much to see here! Visitors who focus on sightseeing will find themselves experiencing a lot of hardship with pretty small payoffs. A common traveller complaint is of spending the whole trip in miserable bush taxis! The big game animals of the rest of Sub-Saharan Africa are absent; the majestic ruins of North and East Africa likewise are nowhere to be found. Many would argue that time spent searching for "attractions" would be better spent getting to know the people you are visiting, engaging in a real and meaningful cultural exchange: starting to understand their history, religious practice, and way of seeing the world, and sharing a bit of your own.</p>

<p>We're all travellers here, though: it's hard to stay in one place, and chasing down sights is a good way to slake wanderlust.</p>

<head>Historical</head>
<p>Historical monuments dating back past the arrival of Europeans in the region are few and far between. Tropical weather took its toll upon the larger structures built by old kingdoms and empires, and those that survived the weather often were destroyed with some incredible violence by European invaders (the destruction of Benin City in <ref target="Nigeria">Nigeria</ref> being a prominent example). The most notable structures of African past would likely be the enormous collection of ramparts, walls, and ditches at the ancient fortress of Sungbo's Eredo, less than 20 miles from <ref target="Lagos">Lagos</ref> (and the largest pre-colonial monument in the whole of the continent), and the palaces of the Dahomey Empire in <ref target="Abomey">Abomey</ref>, <ref target="Benin">Benin</ref>. Also in Nigeria, <ref target="Kano">Kano</ref> holds much interest (and is generally one of the most pleasant places for a tourist to visit in the country) as the seat of the historical Empire of Kano, with the Emir's palace (in addition to other sixteenth century sites around the city) being fully intact, albeit much renovated throughout the centuries.</p>
<p>Many of the sites of significant historical interest in West Africa are European-built. The terrifying <hi rend="bold">slave castles</hi> of the <ref target="Ghana">Ghana</ref>ian coast (most famously at <ref target="Elmina">Elmina</ref> and <ref target="Cape%20Coast">Cape Coast</ref>) are imposing on their own for their massive size and seaside locations, but their importance to the history of the modern world cannot be overstated, and are a must-see for anyone in the region. Sites of importance to the <ref target="Atlantic%20slave%20trade">slave trade</ref> are hardly limited to the charismatic forts of Ghana, though, with prominent sites near <ref target="Dakar">Dakar</ref>, <ref target="Conakry">Conakry</ref>, <ref target="Ouidah">Ouidah</ref>, aforementioned <ref target="Abomey">Abomey</ref>, <ref target="Porto%20Novo">Porto Novo</ref>, and <ref target="Freetown">Freetown</ref> (with sites especially important to the slave trade to the United States in Freetown).</p>

<p>Modern Africa has ramped up its production of monument-building, epitomized by the colossal <hi rend="bold">African Renaissance Monument</hi> outside <ref target="Dakar">Dakar</ref>, intended to challenge perceived foreign perceptions of African as an inferior backwater. Other monuments, such as the Arch 22 in <ref target="Gambia">Gambia</ref>, the Nkrumah Mausoleum and Independence Square in <ref target="Accra">Accra</ref>, and others throughout the region's national capitals are more concerned with less lofty ideals of good old fashioned national greatness and deification of post-colonial leaders.</p>
</text>
