<text id="autogum_voyage_doc500" title="Fatehpur Sikri" shortTile="fatehpur-sikri" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=132891" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fatehpur Sikri</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Fatehpur Sikri</hi> is in the <ref target="Doab">Doab</ref> region of <ref target="Uttar%20Pradesh">Uttar Pradesh</ref>, <ref target="India">India</ref>. About 40km away from <ref target="Agra">Agra</ref>, it is one of India's UNESCO World Heritage Sites. </p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Literally meaning the <hi rend="italic">city of victory</hi>, Fatehpur Sikri was founded by <ref target="Mughal%20Empire">Mughal</ref> Emperor Akbar in 1571 and served as the capital from its founding to 1585. Often lumped together with <ref target="Agra">Agra</ref> on tourist tours and trails, Fatehpur Sikri is a <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20Site">UNESCO World Heritage Site</ref> in its own right.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>While the closest airport is in Agra, the Fatehpur Sikri has its own railway station, a kilometre from the city centre. By road and in typical traffic, it is a 50-minute drive from Agra.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Buland Darwaza</hi>. This grand gate was built to commemorate the military triumphs of Mughal emperor Akbar in <ref target="Gujarat">Gujarat</ref>.</item>
</list>

 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jama Masjid</hi> (Friday Mosque). </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tomb of Salim Chishti</hi>, Dadupura. Salim Chishti was a Sufi saint, dearly respected by Emperor Akbar. In fact, the emperor held Salim in such great esteem that he named his son Salim (who would later be known as the Mughal emperor Jahangir) in honour of the saint. The mausoleum built for Salim Chishti in 1580 and 1581 is considered to be one of the greatest examples of Mughal architecture. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ibadat Khana</hi>. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Panch Mahal</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Naubat Khana</hi> (Drum House).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Anup Talao</hi> (Peerless pool). The red sandstone architectural symmetry of the walls and bridges that crisscross the artificial lake or pool is beautiful but the water nowadays is polluted and dirty.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Samosa Mahal</hi>. The funny name of the palace (<hi rend="italic">samosa</hi> referring to the pyramidal shaped dumplings in Indian cuisine) is because the it does, in fact, resemble a <hi rend="italic">samosa</hi>! It is clean and well maintained though be wary of the guides in the palace, who can be pushy and touty.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hiran Minar</hi>. A high, circular tower covered in spikes that look like elephant tusks. Akbar is said to have built it in remembrance of his beloved elephant, Hiran.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Birbal Bhawan</hi> (Birbal's Palace), Dadupura. Birbal was a Hindu courtier of Akbar, who ended up becoming one of Akbar's closest and most trusted military advisors. The stone carvings and interior of the palace where Birbal lived are magnificent.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jodha Restaurant</hi>, Hotel Goverdhan, Shahcoolie, Dadupura, ☏ +91 99977 02459 . North Indian vegetarian and vegan food in a casual setting.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sher-e-Punjab</hi>, Fatehpur Sikri Bypass Crossing, ☏ +91 98372 26765 . Punjabi and other North Indian food with non-vegetarian and vegetarian options. The meals are hearty and feel satisfying after a long day of sightseeing.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Vrindavan</hi>, Buland Gate Crossing, ☏ +91 94125 16664 , ✉ contactus@hotelvrindavanfts.com . Hotel with basic amenities. ₹950–₹1450.</item>
</list>
</text>
