<text id="autogum_voyage_doc314" title="Belize City" shortTile="belize-city" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=3288" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Belize City</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Belize City</hi> is the largest city in <ref target="Belize">Belize</ref>. It is on a small peninsula protruding into the <ref target="Caribbean">Caribbean</ref> Sea. It was the capital city until flooding and other damage from a hurricane in 1961 prompted the government to relocated to <ref target="Belmopan">Belmopan</ref>, closer to the geographic center of the country.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
 <hi rend="bold">Philip S. W. Goldson International Airport</hi> ( BZE ), Belize City (about 30 minutes drive (15 km) northwest of Belize City centre in the village of Ladyville), ☏ +501 225-2045 , ✉ bacc@pgiabelize.com . BZE is connected from the U.S. (American, Delta, United, and Southwest); from Central America (Avianca El Salvador, Transportes Aéreos Guatemaltecos and Copa) and from the surrounding regions of Belize, the <ref target="Yucat%C3%A1n%20and%20the%20South">Yucatan Peninsula</ref> and from Flores by <ref target="http://www.mayaislandair.com">Maya Island Air</ref> and <ref target="http://www.tropicair.com">Tropic Air</ref>. There are seasonal flights offered from Canada with <ref target="http://www.aircanada.com">Air Canada Rouge</ref> and <ref target="http://www.westjet.com">Westjet</ref>. The best way to get to and from the city centre is by taxi. If going to San Ignacio see "By shuttle" in the below as there are shuttle companies based in San Ignacio that offer airport transfers to San Ignacio and to the surrounding areas in the Cayo District. Some may connect the airport to other places such as the water taxi terminals in Belize City or Placencia from the airport without going to San Ignacio. Ask. An airport bus service does exist, but it is very infrequent and unreliable.


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sir Barry Bowen Municipal Airport</hi> ( TZA ). Flights from regional airports. </item>
</list>


<head>By water taxis</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ocean Ferry Belize</hi>, 50 N Front St (Along Front Street at the northeast end of the Swing Bridge), ☏ +501 223-0033, +501 233-0033, +501 223-2033 . Connects Belize City to Caye Chapel, Caye Caulker and San Pedro</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">San Pedro Express</hi> (http://www.belizewatertaxi.com), 111 N Front St (behind a marketplace that is 250 m east along Front St from the Swing Bridge &amp; the Ocean Ferry Belize Terminal), ☏ +501 223-2225 . Connects Belize City to <ref target="Caye%20Caulker">Caye Caulker</ref> and <ref target="San%20Pedro%20Town">San Pedro Town</ref>. They have a once daily connection from Caye Caulker and from San Pedro to Chetumal.</item>
</list>



<head>By bus</head>
<p>Buses from Santa Elena/Flores in Guatemala (2-3 hr) arrive at the <hi rend="italic">San Pedro Express</hi> water taxi terminal at 111 N Front St while the ADO bus to Mexico are at the Novelo's bus terminal. See the below:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Atlanta Tour &amp; Express Bus</hi>, 111 N Front St (Inside the San Pedro Belize Express Water Taxi Terminal). Arrange onward transport to Flores with <ref target="http://lineadorada.com.gt/">Linea Dorada</ref> or <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://transportesfuentedelnorte.com/">Fuente Del Norte (FDN)</ref></hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mundo Maya Travels</hi>, Suite #26, Brown Sugar Market Place 90 Front St (250 m east along Front St from the Swing Bridge &amp; the Ocean Ferry Belize Terminal.), ☏ +501 223-1200 . They sell tickets for onward travel to Guatemala by <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://transportesfuentedelnorte.com/">Fuente Del Norte (FDN)</ref></hi> and <hi rend="bold">San Juan Express</hi>. They may also sell tickets for Linea Dorada and ADN as well.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">S &amp; L Travel &amp; Tours</hi>, 91 N Front St (Same building as Image Factory, Next to Spoonaz Coffee), ☏ +501 227-7593 . They offer tours to different places around the region as well shuttle transportation to Tikal, Flores and Cancun</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Grupo ADO</hi>, Novelos Bus Terminal @ W Collett Canal St. Once nightly departure to/from Cancun and Merida.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Various from Novelos Bus Terminal</hi>, Novelos Bus Terminal @ W Collett Canal St (W Collett Canal St and King St). Bus travel is a very common mode of transportation in Belize for going to work, shopping and other errands. Therefore, bus service along the main highways is frequent, usually hourly and sometimes half-hourly during peak travel times. For service to/from small rural towns off the main highway they can be less frequent to as little as 4 times or twice daily and no service on Sundays. Like the famous <ref target="Chicken_bus">chicken buses</ref> in Guatemala, they operate in the recycled U.S. school buses, but they can also be in the older MCI (Motor Coach Industries) buses (intercity buses used by Greyhound and other companies in the U.S., usually for "express" services). They are usually not crowded, but they can be too. The services provided are either "regular" which means they stop anywhere along the road to pick up and let off passengers and "express" with only scheduled stops in major towns.</item>
</list>



<p>The companies and drivers' unions don't have websites or published schedules like they do in Mexico and the "west". If they do, it's usually handwritten on a piece of paper or cardboard and taped to a wall or bus station window for all to see at the bus station. The buses do display the final destination or a list of major destinations served on the windshield.</p>

<head>By shuttle</head>
<p>Shuttles can pick you up at the airport, your hotel or from anywhere, and transfer you much quicker to almost anywhere in the country and with much more ease since they are door to door:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="https://belizegroundshuttle.com"><hi rend="bold">Belize Ground Shuttle</hi></ref> The only shared shuttle service in Belize with daily scheduled airport service. email: belizegroundshuttle@gmail.com</item>
<item> <ref target="https://www.ronsbelizetraveladvisory.com/"><hi rend="bold">Ron's Belize Shuttle</hi></ref>. Specializing in private shuttle service to any destination in Belize. email: belizetraveladvisory@gmail.com</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Elies Guerras Transfer Service</hi> (Belize Shuttle Service), Belize City, ☏ +501 666-9834 , ✉ info@guerratransfers.com . An easy way of getting to and from Belize City, Shuttle can be done on your time. Shuttle is Reliable and on-time for transfer at Any Resort or Hotel.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Teddy Bear Shuttle</hi>, (office) #17 San Ignacio Town, Cayo, ☏ +501 600-2695, +501 667-1441 . Teddy Bear shuttle and taxi service is safe and reliable, you can find him just behind the Belize Bank in the center of San Ignacio Town.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mayan Heart World</hi>, (office) 29 Burns Ave, San Ignacio Town, Cayo District. Offers private shuttle transfers from San Ignacio, Belize western border to Flores or Tikal in Peten, Guatemala. The company even have the ability to transfer you to just about any where from San Ignacio Town.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Belize Shuttle Co</hi>, ☏ +501 666-7268 , toll-free: +1 888 398-1914 (US) . It has an outstanding record of transporting you to and from your destination on-time. Your Belize Shuttle Driver is Denfield Gomez, known locally as Denny, maintain an impeccable driving recorder when it comes to shuttling you to or from your destination.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">http://www.sanignacioshuttles.com/</hi>, (office) 22 Burns Ave, San Ignacio City, ☏ +501-628-7037 . Operated by Sergio Paiz, runs to all major shuttle destination in Belize, Located on Burns Ave, San Ignacio Town.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Williams Belize Shuttle</hi>, ☏ +501 620-3055 . A door to door shuttle.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">BASS</hi>, ☏ +501 662-7225 . Airport shuttle service to Belize City, San Ignacio and any other destination in Belize.</item>
</list>


<p>Most of them are based in San Ignacio Town, east of Belize City in the Cayo District and wrote about connecting San Ignacio to the airport and other places in Belize. Therefore, you must ask them if they provide transportation originating in Belize City and going somewhere else if you don't plan to go to San Ignacio.</p>
</text>
