<text id="autogum_voyage_doc511" title="Eastern Anatolia" shortTile="eastern-anatolia" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=10351" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Eastern Anatolia</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Eastern Anatolia</hi> (Turkish: <hi rend="italic">Doğu Anadolu</hi>) is a region in <ref target="Turkey">Turkey</ref>. It occupies the mountainous east of the country and has the harshest winters.</p>

<head>Cities</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> — town in the north, on the road to Georgia and the Turkish Black Sea coast</item>
<item> — old town close to Malatya</item>
<item> — historic town with artifacts dating back to Ottomans and to Hittites of distant past</item>
<item> — town on <ref target="Iran">Iran</ref>ian border, hub for visiting fascinating Ishak Pasa Palace nearby, as well as climbing up Mt Ararat</item>
<item> — city in northwest, surrounded by mountains and lakes, and the hub for visiting wonderful old city of <hi rend="bold">Harput</hi></item>
<item> </item>
<item> — biggest city of the region, near Palandöken Ski Centre</item>
<item> — the most remote city of the country, in the far southeastern reaches</item>
<item> — city in northeast, with interesting Russian architecture</item>
<item> — locally known as Eğin, this is a beautiful old town on the Karasu River, and is the base town for the adventure sports hotspot of the Karanlık Kanyon ("Dark Canyon")</item>
<item> — the largest city in western part of Eastern Anatolia; a city featuring lots of parks</item>
<item> — town on the railroad to Tatvan/Lake Van</item>
<item> — on the western coast of Lake Van, eastern terminus of railway from <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref>, with ferry connections to Van and then on to Iran.</item>
<item> </item>
<item> — city on the eastern coast of Lake Van, with some remnants from Urartu civilization and some Armenian monasteries, too.</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> — the old Armenian capital</item>
<item> Mountain — a <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20List">UNESCO World Heritage site</ref>, with statues on its summit</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
<p>Covering an area in which you can fit in <hi rend="bold">four</hi> <ref target="Switzerland">Switzerland</ref>s with still some more room, but with a population of just over 6 million, Eastern Anatolia is all about lonely and vast landscapes of mountainous terrain, with occasional flat-ish plateau inflitrated inbetween.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>While the daytime temperatures of around 30<ref target="Metric%20and%20Imperial%20equivalents">°C</ref>—yet it can easily hit 40°C or more in relatively lower western parts of the region around <ref target="Malatya">Malatya</ref>, though—in <hi rend="bold">summer</hi> make travelling in Eastern Anatolia a breeze (especially if you have arrived from the much hotter regions of <ref target="Mediterranean%20Turkey">Southern</ref> and <ref target="Southeastern%20Anatolia">Southeastern Turkey</ref>), the nights are fairly chilly and it's common for temperatures to go down as low as +12°C in late evenings, even in the hottest month of August, so pack along at least a cardigan or sweater.</p>

<p>Eastern Anatolia is constantly under snowcover during <hi rend="bold">winter</hi>, which even shuts some non-major roads for days on end, and temperature can drop as low as a whopping <hi rend="italic">-40°C</hi> — warm clothing is more essential than ever.</p>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>In the eastern and southeastern areas (near <ref target="Iran">Iran</ref>ian border and around <ref target="Van">Lake Van</ref>) of the region, the mother tongue of most locals is <ref target="Kurdish%20phrasebook">Kurdish</ref>. However most locals, especially younger ones, are also bilingual in <ref target="Turkish%20phrasebook">Turkish</ref>, although heavily accented in most cases.</p>

<p>Local Turkish dialect spoken in northeastern section of the region (around <ref target="Erzurum">Erzurum</ref>, and <ref target="Kars">Kars</ref>) is far from the standard Turkish based on <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref> dialect and is very close to <ref target="Azerbaijani%20phrasebook">Azerbaijani</ref> spoken in the <ref target="Azerbaijan">neighbouring country</ref> (to the point of being virtually identical in the easternmost parts of the region, around <ref target="I%C4%9Fd%C4%B1r">Iğdır</ref> close to the border with <ref target="Nakhchivan%20%28region%29">Nakhchivan</ref>), although the written word always uses standard Turkish orthography as is usual.</p>

<ref target="Zazaisch%20Phrasebook">Zaza</ref>, another Indo-Iranian language closely related to Kurdish, may also be heard in certain locales, especially in the central parts of the region around <ref target="Tunceli">Tunceli</ref> and <ref target="Bing%C3%B6l">Bingöl</ref>.

<p>As in <ref target="Southeastern%20Anatolia">Southeastern Anatolia</ref>, it is important to be cautious with whom you are smattering Kurdish or Zaza. Trying to strike up a conversation in those languages with a Turkish official, especially one from military, can have dire consequences.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<ref target="Erzurum">Erzurum</ref> is the main gateway to the region with fairly frequent air, bus, and rail connections with the rest of the country. Other secondary-major cities with airports include <ref target="Malatya">Malatya</ref>, and <ref target="Van">Van</ref>, both of which also has rail links with the rest of the country, and with <ref target="Iran">Iran</ref> in the case of Van. Occasionally potholed (but getting better and wider day by day) highways connect the region to other Turkish regions in <ref target="Eastern%20Karadeniz">north</ref>, <ref target="Southeastern%20Anatolia">south</ref>, and <ref target="Central%20Anatolia">west</ref>; and to Iran to east.

<head>See</head>
<p>At the borderlands of various empires that existed in the vicinity during the last millenia, <hi rend="bold">Northeastern Anatolia</hi> is rich in medieval and early modern sites. The local hub is <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Erzurum">Erzurum</ref></hi>. The modern city is not especially historic or beautiful, but it's the site of a <hi rend="bold">citadel</hi> and two <hi rend="bold">madrasahs</hi> (Islamic academies), one of them built in the 13th century by the Seljuk Sultanate of Rum, decorated with turquoise tiles typical of the Seljuks, and the other dating back to the 14th century, when the area was ruled by the Ilkhanids, an offshoot of <ref target="Mongol%20Empire">Genghis's Mongolians</ref> who later converted to Islam.</p>

<p>North of Erzurum, a major highway follows the <hi rend="bold">Çoruh River</hi> towards the <ref target="Eastern%20Karadeniz">Black Sea coast</ref>. The local mountains are dotted by the ruins of numerous <hi rend="bold">castles and churches</hi> built by the <hi rend="bold">medieval <ref target="Georgia%20%28country%29">Georgian</ref> kingdom</hi>. The most impressive site is perhaps the <hi rend="bold">Öşkvank Monastery</hi> in the village of Çamlıyamaç, about 100 km (60 mi) from Erzurum.</p>

<p>Northeast from Erzurum, you will arrive at the national park covering the <hi rend="bold">Allahuekber Mountains</hi>. This was the scene of the 1914–15 <hi rend="bold">Battle of Sarikamish</hi>, fought between <ref target="Ottoman%20Empire">Ottoman Turkey</ref> and the <ref target="Russian%20Empire">Russian Empire</ref> as part of the Caucasus Campaign during <ref target="World%20War%20I">World War I</ref>. Ill-prepared for the harsh winters of the area, up to 60,000 Turkish soldiers froze to death there; annual commemorations take place in the national park, which is also known for its extensive <hi rend="bold">Scots pine forests</hi> and healthy populations of <hi rend="bold">wolves and bears</hi>, which are rather few in the country.</p>

<p>The area east of the Allahuekber Mountains was ruled by the Russian Empire for four decades before its collapse. A notable local town is <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Sar%C4%B1kam%C4%B1%C5%9F">Sarıkamış</ref></hi>, where a derelict <hi rend="bold">hunting lodge</hi> built by the last czar, Nicholas II (r. 1894–1917), is one of the main attractions. Nearby <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Kars">Kars</ref></hi> is much more famous for its Russian heritage—stately <hi rend="bold">Russian mansions</hi> line its street grid, as do beautiful mosques that had been built as Russian Orthodox or Armenian Apostolic churches. Further east, on the high steppes over a river gorge is the evocative ruins of <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Ani">Ani</ref></hi>, the <hi rend="bold">medieval Armenian capital</hi>.</p>

<p>Southwards, at the foothills of the <hi rend="bold">Mount Ararat</hi>, Turkey's highest at 5,137 m (16,854 ft), is the town of <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Do%C4%9Fubeyaz%C4%B1t">Doğubeyazıt</ref></hi>, near the main border crossing to <ref target="Iran">Iran</ref>. <hi rend="bold">İshak Pasha Palace</hi>, an amazing 17th-century palace and citadel complex on a hillside high above the town, is the main sight. Also nearby, off the highway to <ref target="Van">Van</ref>, is the scenic <hi rend="bold">Muradiye Waterfalls</hi>, which gets frozen every winter.</p>

<p>The rim of <hi rend="bold">Lake Van</hi>, the largest lake in Turkey, is known for its <hi rend="bold">ancient sites</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Armenian heritage</hi>. This is the land of the <hi rend="bold">Urartu</hi>—a name that will be easily recalled the visitors of <ref target="Ankara">Ankara</ref>'s Museum of Anatolian Civilizations, which has a large exhibition of fine Urartian ironwork. The main city of the area is <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Van">Van</ref></hi>, at the eastern end of the lake. As <hi rend="bold">Tushpa</hi>, the city was the capital of the Urartu kingdom, formed by an Iron Age people. Its <hi rend="bold">castle</hi>, on a striking rocky outcrop above the lake, is not to be missed, as are numerous Urartian <hi rend="bold">cuneiform inscriptions</hi> in the surrounding area. Except for a few centuries-old buildings, <hi rend="bold">Old Van</hi>, in the lakeside plains just below the castle, was heavily damaged and abandoned during World War I.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">countryside <ref target="Van%23Nearby">to the southeast of Van</ref></hi> features <hi rend="bold">ancient and medieval citadels</hi>, and other isolated historic and natural attractions but far more travellers head west along the southern coast of the lake to <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Geva%C5%9F">Gevaş</ref></hi>, from where boats to the <hi rend="bold">Akdamar Island</hi> can be taken. The island is topped by one of the jewels of the region, the 10th century <hi rend="bold">Cathedral of the Holy Cross</hi>, which has extensive bas reliefs of Biblical scenes.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="Tatvan">Tatvan</ref></hi> is the hub for travelling around the western half of Lake Van. Just above the town is the <hi rend="bold">Mount Nemrut</hi>, a dormant volcano with a summit nearing 3,000 m (9,700 ft)—higher than the mountain of the same name near <ref target="Kahta">Kahta</ref> to the west, better known for the statues of the ancient gods on its summit. The caldera has freshwater <hi rend="bold">lakes</hi> inside, one of which is comfortably warm regardless the season thanks to a <ref target="hot%20springs">hot spring</ref> flowing into it, all surrounded by a <hi rend="bold">birch forest</hi>. The <hi rend="bold">views over Lake Van</hi> and the surrounding area from the caldera rim are simply phenomenal.</p>

<p>Northeast from Tatvan, the medieval <ref target="cemeteries">cemetery</ref> at <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Ahlat">Ahlat</ref></hi> is known for its <hi rend="bold">massive, highly elaborate headstones</hi> cut from dark volcanic rocks, in a similar fashion with the Armenian khachkars. </p>

<p>Many towns around the lake, including Gevaş, Ahlat, and <ref target="Erci%C5%9F">Erciş</ref>, feature <hi rend="bold">Seljuk <hi rend="italic">kümbet</hi>s</hi>, cylindrical or often octogonal mausolea topped by a cone, seemingly influenced by local Armenian and Georgian architectural styles, with much stonework.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">Upper Euphrates Valley</hi> at the western half of the region is full of <hi rend="bold"><ref target="old%20towns">old towns</ref></hi>. <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Malatya">Malatya</ref></hi> is a reasonable hub for travelling around this part of Eastern Anatolia. While Malatya is a relatively new city by Turkish standards, there is a <hi rend="bold">19th-century mosque</hi> in downtown, as well as (the ruins of) a contemporary <hi rend="bold">Armenian church</hi>. A small <hi rend="bold">hydropower plant</hi>, one of the oldest in the country, is also an attraction of the city, as is the <hi rend="bold">park with many water features</hi> surrounding it. </p>

<p>Nearby <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Orduzu">Orduzu</ref></hi> is a village of pretty single- or two-floored <hi rend="bold">adobe houses</hi> with timber frames. Far more archaeologically important, though, is the nearby <hi rend="bold">Aslantepe Mound</hi>, an eastern outpost of the <hi rend="bold">Hittites</hi>, a Bronze Age people often associated with <ref target="Central%20Anatolia">Central Anatolia</ref> to the west. A number of <hi rend="bold">detailed sculptures</hi> with typically Hittite designs were excavated in the site and have been exhibited there.</p>

<p>West from Malatya, <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Darende">Darende</ref></hi> is the site of the <hi rend="bold">Somuncu Baba shrine</hi>. Imagine a tomb of a local saint and a small adjoining mosque in a <hi rend="bold">very beautifully landscaped garden</hi>, all stucked into a <hi rend="bold">narrow ravine</hi>, clinging to the cliffs.</p>

<p>Just north of Malatya, <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Battalgazi">Battalgazi</ref></hi> is locally known as "Old Malatya", as it was the original site of that city. A major centre during the centuries past, it features a <hi rend="bold">Seljuk-built mosque</hi>, with beautiful, if a bit worn, turquoise tiles and unique in Turkey for having an inner courtyard. The other attractions in the town include a <hi rend="bold">caravanserai</hi> and <ref target="Roman%20Empire">Roman</ref>-built <hi rend="bold">city walls</hi>.</p>

<p>Across the <hi rend="bold">Karakaya Dam Lake</hi>, kind of a very low-key local resort, you will arrive in <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Elaz%C4%B1%C4%9F">Elazığ</ref></hi>. As with Malatya, the city was moved to its current location only in the 19th century (so you won't see anything older), and its original site, <hi rend="bold">Harput</hi> is up the hills. Topped by a <hi rend="bold">castle</hi>, the streets of Harput are lined by <hi rend="bold">historic houses</hi> with stone-built ground floors and wooden upper floors.</p>

<p>Upriver along the Euphrates, you will arrive in <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Kemaliye">Kemaliye</ref></hi>, locally <hi rend="bold">Eğin</hi>, which sits in a particularly <hi rend="bold">lush valley bottom</hi>. It is a beautiful town with many <hi rend="bold">mansions</hi>, sharing a similar architectural style with those of Harput. In the outskirts, a series of <hi rend="bold">tight tunnels and passes</hi> negotiate a formidable and barren terrain high above a <hi rend="bold">deep gorge</hi>. If anywhere could be called "the beaten path" in this part of the world, that would be the trio of Harput, Kemaliye, and nearby <ref target="Divri%C4%9Fi">Divriği</ref> (in Central Anatolia), but that doesn't mean much.</p>
</text>
