<text id="autogum_voyage_doc48" title="Abita Springs">
<head>Abita Springs</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.townofabitasprings.com/">Abita Springs</ref></hi> is a town in <ref target="Louisiana">Louisiana</ref>, in the Piney Woods of <ref target="St.%20Tammany%20Parish">St. Tammany Parish</ref>, part of the Lake Pontchartrain North Shore area. It's about an hour east of <ref target="Baton%20Rouge">Baton Rouge</ref>, and an hour north of <ref target="New%20Orleans">New Orleans</ref>, about 15 minutes east of <ref target="Covington%20%28Louisiana%29">Covington</ref>.</p>
<head>Get in</head>
<p>Access is almost exclusively by private vehicle. From I-12, head north on US-190 to Covington. Then take SR-36 east to Abita Springs.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Abita Springs Brewery</hi>, 166 Barbee Rd, toll-free: +1-800-737-2311 ext 2 . Sa 1PM and 2:30PM, Su 1PM. The brewery tours include free samples of the brewery's local beers. On Highway 36, just west of town towards Covington. free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Abita Springs Tourist Park</hi>. The park features the Abita Springs Pavilion, a large, two-story pavilion once sheltering a spring, built in 1884. It is at the west end of Main St. The park remains open and has a playground and picnic areas. The Abita River runs through it. It is the sight of the Abita Spring Water Festival each October. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">UCM Museum / Mystery House</hi>, 22275 Hwy 36. A uniquely weird collection of folk-art, curiosities, and (let's face it) old junk, entertainingly arranged and displayed.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<head>Buy</head>

<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Abita Brew Pub</hi>, 72011 Holly Street. Tu-Su lunch & dinner.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Abita Springs Brewpub</hi>, ☏ +1 985-892-5837 . Daily 11AM-10PM. A full restaurant and pub, it offers samples of Abita brews (including their non-alcoholic root beer) and has a gift shop.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rosie's Tavern</hi>, 22067 Hwy 59 (right by the Pavilion park), ☏ +1 985-809-0454 .</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Blue Willow Bed and Breakfast</hi>, 505 E. Rutland St., Covington, ☏ +1 985-892-0011 , ✉ bluewillowbandb@earthlink.net . Check-in: 3PM, check-out: 11AM. $125-250.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Artesia's Longbranch Cottage</hi>, 21516 Hwy 36, ☏ +1 985-892-1662 . Call to confirm availability.</item>
</list>


<head>Connect</head>

<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Covington%20%28Louisiana%29">Covington</ref> is just a few minutes drive west</item>
<item> <ref target="Baton%20Rouge">Baton Rouge</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Biloxi">Biloxi</ref>, just under two hours to the east, along I-10.</item>
<item> <ref target="New%20Orleans">New Orleans</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
