<text id="autogum_voyage_doc502" title="Cullera" shortTile="cullera" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=148594" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Cullera</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Cullera</hi> is a coastal city in <ref target="Valencia%20%28region%29">Valencia</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Cullera has been inhabited since Neolithic times, as attested by a large number of remains and archaeological sites in the area. In modern times the city is known for its gastronomy and for its burgeoning tourism sector, and serves as a popular getaway for both domestic and foreign visitors.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tourist Info Cullera Centro</hi>, C/ del Mar, 93, ☏ +34 961 720 974 , fax: +34 961 738 062 , ✉ cullera@touristinfo.net . Winter: M-F 09:30-14:00, 17:00-19:30. Cullera's primary tourist office.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tourist Info Cullera Playa</hi>, Plaza Constitución, s/n (Playa San Antonio), ☏ +34 961 731 586 , ✉ culleraplaya@touristinfo.net . Winter: M-F 09:30-14:00 17:00-19:30, Sa 10:00-13:30 17:30-19:30, Su and holidays 10:30-13:30; Summer: M-Sa 09:00-14:00 16:00-21:00, Su 10:30-13:30.</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>
<p>Valencia has the closest airport, at 40 km away.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Estación de Tren de Cullera</hi> (Cullera Train Station), Carretera Sueca, s/n, ☏ +34 902 240 202 . From <ref target="Valencia">Valencia</ref>, Renfe regional train line <ref target="http://www.renfe.com/viajeros/cercanias/valencia/index.html"><hi rend="bold">C1</hi></ref> connects Cullera with <ref target="Valencia%23By_train">Estació de València Nord</ref> and <ref target="Gand%C3%ADa">Gandía</ref>. Trains depart hourly and the journey from Valencia lasts 34 minutes.</item>
</list>

 

<head>By bus</head>
<ref target="https://www.alsa.com/en/web/bus/our-destinations/regional/valencia-murcia"><hi rend="bold">Alsa</hi></ref> operates a route connecting all major coastal settlements between <ref target="Valencia">Valencia</ref> and <ref target="Alicante">Alicante</ref>, including Cullera, <ref target="Gand%C3%ADa">Gandía</ref>, Oliva, <ref target="D%C3%A9nia">Dénia</ref>, <ref target="Calpe">Calpe</ref>, <ref target="Altea">Altea</ref>, <ref target="Benidorm">Benidorm</ref>, and Villajoyosa. Buses stop at .

<head>Get around</head>
<ref target="http://autocaresribera.wixsite.com/autocaresribera/paradas"><hi rend="bold">Autocares Ribera</hi></ref> (tel. +34 961 721 012) operates a circular bus route between the city and beaches; a schedule is available <ref target="http://autocaresribera.wixsite.com/autocaresribera/quienes-somos">here</ref>.

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Castell de Cullera</hi> (Castillo de Cullera / Cullera Castle), ☏ +34 961 732 643 , ✉ guia_museus@cullera.es . Built by the Moors in the 10th century, the castle was taken in 1239 by King Jaime I of Aragon. In the 16th century it played an important role in the defense of the city against Barbary pirates, and saw action again in the 19th century during the Spanish War of Independence and the Carlist Wars. The castle has been fully restored, and offers great views of the bay, the mouth of the Júcar River, and the region.The castle can be accessed by the <hi rend="italic">Camino del Calvario</hi> ('Way of the Calvary'), a steep footpath which zigzags up the side of the mountain and has 14 stations of the cross. </item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Santuario de la Virgen del Castillo</hi> (Sanctuary of the Virgin of the Castle) (immediately adjacent to the Castell). This neo-Byzantine chapel was built at the end of the 19th century, and is dedicated to Cullera’s patron saint, the ‘Mare de Deu del Castell’. Especially noteworthy inside is a 14th-century Gothic painting of the Madonna.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Torre de Santa Ana</hi> (Tower of Santa Ana). Feb-Jun: Th-Su and holidays 10:00-13:30; Jul-Sep: Tu-Su 10:30-13:00 18:30-20:30; Oct-Jan: Sa Su and holidays 10:00-13:30. Also known as <hi rend="italic">Torre de la Reina Mora</hi> ('Tower of the Moorish Queen'), this 13th-century tower was originally part of the defensive perimeter for the Moorish castle and served as part of the main gate. It was heavily modified in the 16th century to defend against Barbary pirates, but the structure has since been restored to its original design. Inside there is now an exhibit devoted to the history of the tower and the castle. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">El Fort</hi> (Fuerte Carlista / Carlist Fortress), Pla dels Pics (accessed by footpath from the castle). Two ruined fortifications from the first Carlist War, which were built atop a Moorish citadel. At 210m above sea level, great views can be had from this spot. Free.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Museu Cova del Dragut</hi> (Museo Cueva de Dragut / Cave-Museum of Dragut), Plaça Doctor Fleming, s/n (Faro de Cullera), ☏ +34 961 746 700 , ✉ contacto@cuevadeldragut.com . Oct-May daily 11:00-14:30 16:00-21:00; Jun-Sep daily 09:00-14:00. In 1550, Dragut, a close associate of the dreaded pirate Barbarossa, attacked and laid waste to Cullera, after which the town was virtually abandoned for several decades. According to legend this cave was the site of a prisoner exchange during the siege, and is now used as a museum devoted to Mediterranean piracy in the 16th century. €5 (adults), €3 (children).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Torre del Marenyet</hi> (Marenyet Tower), ☏ +34 961 732 643 . Oct-Jan: Sa Su and holidays 10:00-13:30; Feb-Jun: Tu-Su and holidays 10:00-13:30, Jun-Sep: Tu-Su 10:30-13:00 18:30-20:30. This watchtower was built in 1577 as part of a coastal network of watchtowers used to defend against Barbary pirates, following the devastation brought on Cullera by Dragut in 1550. It now has a number of displays demonstrating the use of the watchtower and illustrating the problem of piracy in the 16th century. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Refugio Museo de la Guerra Civil</hi>, Plaça de la Verge, s/n (beneath the Mercado Municipal), ☏ +34 961 732 643 . Guided tours on Th Sa Su 10:00-14:00. This bomb shelter was built by Republicans during the Spanish Civil War. It was never completed or used, but has been fully restored and has displays on life during the war. It is open to the public by guided tours which last between 20-30 minutes. €1.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Barri del Pou</hi> (Barrio del Pozo) (E of the Mercado Municipal and S of the Torre de Santa Ana). This charming neighbourhood with whitewashed houses marks the location of the original Arab settlement of <hi rend="italic">Qulayra</hi>, and the layout of narrow streets remains practically unchanged since that time.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Botánic Cullera</hi> (Jardin Botánico / Botanic Gardens), Crta Nazaret-Oliva, km 27, ☏ +34 637 482 548 , fax: +34 961 118 629 , ✉ botanic.cullera@gmail.com . M-Sa 09:00-14:00 15:30-19:30, Su 09:00-14:00. The gardens have more than 2,500 plant species. Also on the grounds is a restored 19th-century farmhouse, now used for a small ethnological museum to display traditional farming tools. €2 (adults).</item>
</list>


<head>Beaches</head>

<p>Cullera has over 15km of sandy beaches. (<hi rend="italic">Playa de San Antonio</hi>) is the most urban beach, while (<hi rend="italic">Playa del Racó</hi>) is somewhat more sedate; both beaches have loungers for rent as well as snack bars and restaurants. (<hi rend="italic">Playa Cap Blanc</hi>) is well-suited for wind-surfing, while (<hi rend="italic">Playa de los Olivos</hi>) is good for families. The small cove of (<hi rend="italic">Playa del Faro / Lighthouse Beach</hi>) is good for diving, while dogs are permitted at the more isolated (<hi rend="italic">Playa de la Escollera / Breakwater Beach</hi>). In July and August these beaches all have disabled access with lifeguards, toilets and foot-washing stations, and first-aid stations, except for Platja de l'Escullera which has no disabled access.</p>
</text>
