<text id="autogum_voyage_doc147" title="Kununurra" shortTile="kununurra" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=18467" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kununurra</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Kununurra</hi> is a small town built on big dreams. In a remote corner of the vast <ref target="Kimberley%20%28Western%20Australia%29">Kimberley</ref> region of <ref target="Western%20Australia">Western Australia</ref>, its unaffected pastoral feel makes a comfortable base from which to explore the majestic natural attractions in the rugged surrounding landscape.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Kununurra's existence is due entirely to a grand engineering scheme to harness the Ord River, and establish an agriculture industry in the area. The town itself came into existence in the late 1950s as a support centre for the Ord Irrigation scheme. A few vanguard families slowly spread their multi-thousand acre properties across the fertile plain. In recent years, it has unceasingly shaken off its pragmatic origins to develop infrastructure for the growing number of visitors to this previously difficult-to-visit part of the Kimberley. From the initial handful of pioneering farmers, the permanent population has now grown to around 7,000. The town was officially gazetted as recently as 1961.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>As early as 1882, fortune seeking pastoralists and farmers have been drawn to pin their hopes on the Ord River and the wide open plains around it. The Ords potential was first identified by explorer Alexander Forrest in 1879. He encouraged graziers in search of new land to the area and subsequently built his empire on leases of 51 million acres. The most well known of these pastoralists was the Durack family, who in 1882 drove 7,250 head of cattle and 200 horses overland from <ref target="Queensland">Queensland</ref> to establish the Lissadell, Argyle, Rosewood and Ivanhoe stations. At Ivanhoe station, north of the present Kununurra townsite, the potential of growing crops on the rich alluvial soils of the Ord Valley became apparent and after early experiments literally bore fruit, many acres of cattle country were turned over to agriculture. It was soon realised that the full potential of the Ord to grow thirsty crops could only be achieved with more water.</p>

<p>Begun in 1958, the <hi rend="bold">Ord Irrigation Scheme</hi> was an ambitious idea to capture the huge volume of water flowing down the Ord during the monsoon for irrigation of the fertile plains along the river's lower reaches and to develop a productive agriculture industry and create a food bowl for Western Australia.</p>

<p>The first stage was completed in 1963 with the construction of the Diversion Dam, creating Lake Kununurra and feeding a network of canals that supported 31 farms by 1966. Spurred on by this success, the second stage saw the building of the Ord River Dam further upstream, subsequently creating Lake Argyle, Australia's second largest artificial Lake. Construction of the 335-metre-long, earth wall dam was completed in 1971 and ceremoniously opened a year later. The reservoir's initial capacity of a hefty 5,641 gigilitres (equivalent to 11 Sydney Harbours by some peoples estimate) was increased in the early 1990s, when the wall was raised by 6 metres to double its current capacity to an oceanic 10,763 giglitres. The extra capacity enabled a hydroelectric power station to keep spinning and provide the towns power.</p>

<p>In the early days, farmers experimented with a range of crops and had variable results. Crops such as cotton and rice were dismal failures as pests and birds ate them quicker than they could grow. But sugar cane, bananas, melons and mangos became very successful cash crops. In recent years, sandalwood plantations became more abundant. A trial of commercial hemp proved to be viable and production is tipped to be expanded once the states draconian laws can be modernised.</p>

<head>Culture</head>
<p>There are a few explanations for the etymology of the town's name, the most popular being a mangled English pronunciation of <hi rend="italic">Gunanurang</hi> - "Big River" in the local Miriwoong people's language.</p>

<p>Many scenes from the movie <hi rend="italic">Australia</hi> were filmed in the area surrounding Kununurra.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>Kununurra has a tropical climate with two distinct seasons; the monsoonal ‘wet’ season and the touristy ‘dry’ season. The wet season starts around October, typified by heavy rain, 40°C days and uncomfortable humid nights, and ends in April. The rest of the year is the milder, dry season, bringing 30°C highs, blue skies and the bulk of tourists.</p>

<head>When to visit</head>
<p>Though the dry is typically the peak tourist season, the wet is arguably the best time to see Kununurra. The monsoonal weather brews up billowing thunderclouds flashing with electrical storms that make for some beautiful sunsets. The ensuing downpours create rushing cascades to usually dry waterholes and bring a flush of new green growth to the landscape. If you can endure the humidity and incessant rain, you will see a Kununurra that many miss.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kununurra Visitor Centre</hi>, 75 Coolibah Dr, ☏ +61 8 9168 1177 , fax: +61 8 9168 2598 , ✉ info@visitkununurra.com . Your best source for free pamphlets about services in Kununurra, maps and Kimberley themed knick-knacks. Staff can be quite helpful in answering your questions, even more so if you look interested in booking a tour.</item>
</list>


<head>By car</head>
<p>Kununurra is a mere 30 km from the <ref target="Northern%20Territory">Northern Territory</ref> border, but a long way from anywhere else. The drive over vast distances, through some very isolated country to get there should not be taken lightly, though with a bit of forward planning the getting there can be a great trip in itself.</p>

<head>From Broome</head>
<p>The easy way is on the <hi rend="bold">Great Northern Highway</hi>, taking about two days to cover the 1,044 km if you push it. The good sealed road passes through a few small towns and sights. The more interesting, but harder way, is via the <ref target="Gibb%20River%20Road">Gibb River Road</ref>, taking at least seven days to trundle over its 650 km length. The Gibb is an unsealed 4WD only track across the Kimberleys northern parts, passing many gorges, waterfalls and generally beautiful country. It is prone to flooding in the wet season and may be closed entirely. It's best to check with the tourist bureau before setting out.</p>

<head>From Darwin</head>
<p>The sealed Stuart Highway runs 324 km south from <ref target="Darwin">Darwin</ref> to <ref target="Katherine">Katherine</ref>. From Katherine, you can turn right and drive the final 524 km stretch on the Victoria Highway to Kununurra.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kununurra airport</hi> ( KNX East Kimberley Regional Airport ) (is 4 km outside of town). has flights to regional centres as well as some charter and scenic flights. The airport is small but modern and the runway has one of the most scenic approaches you are likely to find. <hi rend="bold">Taxis</hi> wait for every arriving flight and cost around $10 to town. Some hostels/hotels offer a <hi rend="bold">free courtesy bus</hi> if you are staying with them. There isn’t a local bus or airport bus service into town. </item>
</list>
</text>
