<text id="autogum_voyage_doc364" title="Gothenburg" shortTile="gothenburg" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13069" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gothenburg</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.goteborg.com">Gothenburg</ref></hi> (Swedish: <hi rend="italic">Göteborg</hi>) is <ref target="Sweden">Sweden</ref>'s second largest city with 570,000 inhabitants, and about 1 million in the metropolitan area. The city lies on Sweden's west coast, at the outlet of the Göta river. Gothenburg is Sweden's largest industrial city with companies such as the Volvo Group and Volvo Cars, as well as Scandinavia's largest port. While the port and factories employ fewer people, the city prides itself in hosting numerous national and international sporting and music events such as Gothia Cup, Partille Cup and Way out West. Gothenburg also has the Sweden's largest amusement park, Liseberg.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Gothenburg is a fairly green city with parks and a large river bisecting the city. Built after being founded by royal decree in 1621 it was modeled after Dutch city style, with plenty of canals. Gothenburg has many humorous nicknames that allude to its canals such as "little London", "little Amsterdam", and "little Venice". Early on Gothenburg was famous for its port and trade and has prominently hosted the Swedish East-India Company. Due to its historically industrial character Gothenburg has had strong working class associations, being known for its friendly yet brusque "<hi rend="italic">goa gubbar</hi>". This together with its large port has given rise to the moniker "Marseille of the North".</p>

<p>Today, with over 50,000 students in the city and two major universities it has a young side with plenty of bars and night-clubs. Gothenburg has a reputation for being very friendly place, and more welcoming than <ref target="Stockholm">Stockholm</ref>, the Swedish capital.</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>Gothenburg is at the mouth of the river Göta älv. <ref target="G%C3%B6ta%20%C3%84lvdal">Lödöse</ref>, some upstream from Gothenburg was one of the largest cities in Sweden during the middle ages, and is considered a precursor of Gothenburg. During the middle ages the mouth of Göta älv was controlled by Sweden, while <ref target="Bohusl%C3%A4n">Bohuslän</ref> immediately north of it was <ref target="Norway">Norwegian</ref> and <ref target="Halland">Halland</ref> to its immediate south was <ref target="Denmark">Danish</ref>. The area thus became a tripoint of the three kingdoms. In order to consolidate Swedish control of the area, Älvsborgs fortress was constructed near modern day Gothenburg. Several failed attempts were also made to build a city in the area.</p>

<p>The modern city of Gothenburg was built in 1621 by the Swedish king Gustav II Adolf. During the 17th century Sweden conquered Bohuslän and Halland, thus making Gothenburg the center of an expanded western Sweden. During this era the older Danish Älvsborg fortress was demolished. It was replaced by a new castle, ingeniously called New Älvsborg fortress, on an island in the mouth of the river. Gothenburg eventually became a major gateway into Sweden, and one of the busiest ports in the Nordic countries. As the largest port in Sweden Gothenburg became the seat of the Swedish East India Company in the 18th century, and a hub for American emigration in the 19th century. During this era the city also became heavily industrialized, particularly as a center for the Swedish shipbuilding industry. Its large port, strong trade community and proximity to <ref target="Marstrand">Marstrand</ref> meant the city had a large Jewish and international community, with the first Jewish association forming before that of Stockholm.</p>

<p>With rising competition from foreign ship yards in the 1900s, many of the dry docks closed down in the 1970s. Much of the inner harbor area has changed from industrial ship building to high technology and education, representative of the general change in the city. Today Gothenburg has international sporting events, concerts, and conventions. Being an industrial center, Gothenburg has been politically dominated by the left-wing Social Democrats for many years.</p>

<p>In the 1960s with Sweden investing heavily in affordable housing with <hi rend="italic">Miljonprogrammet</hi> large parts of the working class town was demolished. Much like parts of Södermalm in Stockholm, Masthugget was an entire district comprised nearly exclusively of small red-painted wooden houses, some of which had stone-laid ground floors, so called <hi rend="italic">Landhövdingehus</hi>. Today such houses can only be found at <hi rend="italic">Gathenhielmska kulturreservatet</hi> by Stigbergstorget in Majorna, as well as on some of the islands in the <ref target="Gothenburg%20Archipelago">Gothenburg archipelago</ref>. Gothenburg is famous for its Landshövdingehus of which more upscale housing remains in Haga, Gårda and Majorna.</p>

<head>People</head>
<p>The working-class history is easily visible, for example in the harbor area, especially on the northern riverfront of Hisingen and north of the city center on the southern riverfront in Gullbergsvass. Before the 1970s there were few fashion houses or posher cafeterias, but that has changed.</p>

<p>The Gothenburg dialect is associated with cheerfulness and witty, if pun-laden humour, with many humorists classically from Gothenburg, often of the "<hi rend="italic">goa gubbar</hi>" (lit. "good guys") stereotype, working class and somewhat fat. The connection to Britain has been said to be behind the high frequency of the male given name Glenn.</p>

<p>Like <ref target="Marseille">Marseille</ref> in <ref target="France">France</ref> there is some animosity towards the capital, with those who move there sometimes being called "traitors".</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>Like most of southern and coastal Sweden, the city is best visited during springtime as well as in the summer. The climate is temperate with mild winters and warm, but not hot summers. Because it is located on the west coast by the sea the climate is milder and rainier in the winter than Stockholm, but comparable to Copenhagen. Snow is not a given in winter, for <ref target="Winter%20in%20the%20Nordic%20countries">real Scandinavian winter</ref>, visit <ref target="Dalarna">Dalarna</ref> or <ref target="Norrland">Norrland</ref>.</p>

<p>In other words, May to September tend to have the most comfortable weather. From Midsummer to the end of July, many inhabitants leave the city, and some venues close for summer, making the city more dominated by tourists.</p>

<head>Tourist information</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kungsportsplatsen Tourist Office</hi>, Kungsportsplatsen 2 (About ten minutes walk from Nordstan), ☏ +46313684200 , ✉ turistinfo@goteborg.com . M–F 09:30–18:00 Sa 10:00–15:00.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nordstan Tourist Office</hi>, Nordstadstorget (Next to the central train station), ☏ +46313684200 , ✉ turistinfo@goteborg.com . M–F 10:00–20:00 Sa, Su 10:00–18:00.</item>
</list>


<p>Gothenburg offers the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.goteborg.com/en/Do/Gothenburg-City-Card/">Gothenburg City Card</ref></hi>, which allows entry into many tourist attractions, grand houses, museums as well as offering free travel on trams and buses and free parking. Among attractions covered are Ringlinien vintage train, admission to Liseberg, Universeum, free travel with Paddan boat, boat trip to New Älvsborg Fortress, guided tour by bus, Museum of World Culture, Gothenburg Natural History Museum, Gothenburg City Museum, Gothenburg Art Museum, Röhsska Museum, Maritime Museum Aquarium, Medical History Museum, the Sports Museum, Maritiman, Casino Cosmopol, Gothenburgs utkiken, Guided tour of Gunnebo House, the Garden Society of Gothenburg, Greenhouses in the Botanical Garden, Röda Sten, Stinsen Sightseeing, Aeroseum, Volvo Museum, Mölndals Museum. This card is available to people's mobile phones, making it not only cost-effective and convenient.</p>

<p>In case official tourist information is unavailable, Gothenburgers are usually more than willing to help.</p>
</text>
