<text id="autogum_voyage_doc501" title="Tepoztlan" shortTile="tepoztlan" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=35618" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tepoztlan</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Tepoztlan</hi> is a popular tourist destination an hour south of <ref target="Mexico%20City">Mexico City</ref>. It's famous for the El Tepezteco pyramid, which is on the summit of the nearby Tepezteco Mountain. It's also known for its spas, meditation, alternative medicine clinics and a very traditional city center. It is a small town so you don't need a car to travel within the city.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>From Mexico City, you may take the metro to the Tasqueña station and follow the "autobuses" signs to the southern bus depot next door. The various bus companies display their destinations and times. Pullman de Morelos offers bus service every 30 minutes and a one-way ticket cost M$134 (<ref target="Mexico%23Currency">pesos</ref>) in 2018. The bus ride is comfortable, scenic and takes about an hour and a half (depending on traffic). Upon arrival in Tepoztlan, the bus may drop you at a depot on the edge of town. Taxis will be waiting to take you to the main square for M$40. Walking to the center will take 20-30 minutes or so. The path to walk downtown is marked by a red metal guard rail across from the bus station.</p>

<p>Frequent buses run to and from the Adolfo Lopez Mateos market in Cuernavaca and pick up passengers along the way to the center of Tepoztlan. About MX$20.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Tepoztlan is a small quaint town and is easily walkable. Most of the activity is centered around its main square and along the main avenue, Avenida 5 de mayo. There is local bus service to surrounding towns.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>There is an archeological site at the top of an easy-hikeable mountain (assuming you are in decent shape -- there are 400m of stairs) that is also famous for its "good vibrations". The hike can take up to 2 hours depending on your fitness level. The pyramid, <hi rend="bold">El Tepozteco</hi>, offers wonderful views of the surrounding area. The site may be reached by walking down Avenida 5 de mayo (in the direction away from where you entered the town). Continue until the street ends to the steps which mark the beginning of the trail. Make sure to bring water with you. The hike to the top is free but it will cost M$37 (in 2010) to access the pyramid. At the top you will also encounter coati, also known as a tejón. These animals, members of the raccoon family, are curious and will attempt to open backpacks to find food.</p>

<p>There is also a beautiful former convent called <hi rend="bold">Dominico de la Navidad</hi>. It has been restored and entrance is free. It is located right off the main square.</p>

<p>If you are curious about it, the locals claim UFO sightings are common, which mostly just adds to the "new age" vibe of the town. Ask about the "ovni" to hear strange tales.</p>

<head>Do</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Temazcal</hi> is an ancient Mexican therapy that consists of a little igloo-shape room in which a group of people enter and medicinal plants are burned inside it and the place gets really warm. A guide asks people to sing ancient songs to make the experience more complete. Many hotels have this option either in groups or individual.</p>

<p>The Mexican Association of Scouts runs a large campground called <hi rend="italic">Meztitla</hi> just outside of town. The camp offers warm showers, tent camping, hiking, rock climbing, and rappel. It is open to the public 365 days (except for occasional closings due to special Scout events). First-aid service is available. There is an area for campfires. Food services must be arranged in advance.<ref target="http://morelosturistico.com/espanol/pagina/z_252_Campamento_Meztitla.php">Mextitla (in Spanish)</ref></p>

<p>No visit to Tepoztlan would be complete without climbing <hi rend="bold">Tepozteco</hi> to see the pyramid.</p>

<p>The Dominican monastery and museum is another must-see. The building was damaged during the 2017 earthquake and may be closed at this time. There is a small fee (MX$10) to enter the monastery/museum. The <hi rend="bold">Pellicer Museum</hi> behind the monastery has an extensive collection of archaeological pieces.</p>

<p>The market is colorful and offers delicious local dishes. It spreads out to cover an entire street on Sundays and is an excellent place to buy souvenirs.</p>

<head>Buy</head>
<p>There are many handicrafts sold in the market and nearby shops, as well as imported knickknacks from around the world. Mezcal and quartz rocks are produced locally.</p>

<head>Eat</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tepoznieves</hi> has multiple locations around town (Av. 5 de mayo, 21) and their ice cream is famous. They may have up to 200 flavors available ranging from the pedestrian chocolate to more exotic rose petal, figs &amp; mescal or carrot with chili.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">La Posada de Tepoztec</hi> is located two blocks above the main square. In addition to offering beautiful (though pricey) lodging, the restaurant serves delicious local cuisine. Sit on the serene patio to enjoy the mountain and town views. Their Chicken Mole is delicious.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cuatecomate</hi> is a prehispanic restaurant. It is located on Av Revolucion #10, interior of Plaza las Flores.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">El Ciruelo</hi> at Zaragoza #10 is a moderately-priced restaurant that features local food. It is apt for vegetarians and vegans. Tel. 52-739-395-1203.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">La Sombra del Sabino</hi> is a moderately-priced cafe near the toll booth at Revolucion #45, Barrio San Jose. Tel. 52-739-395=0369. It offers Mexican food for breakfast or afternoon dinner.</item>
<item> Many visitors choose to eat tacos, gorditas, and quesadillas in the market. <hi rend="italic">Flor de calabaza</hi> is quite popular. Dried grasshoppers (<hi rend="italic">chapulines</hi>) are also popular.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">Tepoztēcatl</hi> was the god who invented pulque in Tepoztlan.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pulques El Nectar Tepozteco</hi>, 62520, Revolución de 1910 36, San Miguel, Tepoztlán, ☏ +52 739 395 0212 . Fri, Sat, Sun 10AM to 8 PM. pulqueria MX$20 for 200 mL.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pulques El Rey Tepozteco</hi>, Santisima Trinidad, 62520 Tepoztlán. pulqueria</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lagartija Club Mezcal</hi>, Isabel La Católica 12, San Miguel, 62520 Tepoztlán, ☏ +52 739 395 0196 . Daily 12:30-19:30 (Fri, Sat to 20:00). mezcal bar</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mezcalería La Cueva</hi>, Av. Revolución 2, Santo Domingo, 62520 Tepoztlán. Fri noon to midnight, Sat noon to 2AM, Sun noon to 11 PM. mezcal bar with live music</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>
<p>Sleeping in Tepoztlan can be noisy at times (in December 2010, the church bells seemed to ring on the half hour all night).</p>

<p>There are two campgrounds nearby: <hi rend="bold">Camhomila</hi> (YMCA camp; accepts trailers and has cabins) and <hi rend="bold">Meztitla</hi> (Scouts of Mexico, tents only; hiking, rock climbing, rappel. ) Both nice, safe, and open to the public.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Posada Ali</hi> is nice place with a good view of the cliffs. It costs around M$500 on weekdays (prices seem to vary).</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Amomoxtli</hi>, Calle Netzahualcóyotl 115, Valle de Atongo, 62520 Tepoztlán (4 m from tollway, 3 km from ruins), ☏ +52 739 395 0012 . Check-in: 3PM, check-out: 12 noon. large gardens, suites, cabins, bar, swimming pool, wi-fi, spa MX$3,924.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Boutique Casa Fernanda</hi>, De Niño Artillero 20, San Jose, 62520 Tepoztlán, ☏ +52 739 395 0522 . Check-in: 3 PM, check-out: 1 PM. couples, wi-fi, air conditioning, cable TV, spa, swimming pool, three gardens, view of mountains MX$2,898.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hostal de la Luz Spa Holistic Resort</hi>, Carretera Federal Tepoztlan Amatlan s/n Km4, ☏ +52 739 395 3374 . Hostal de la Luz Spa Holistic Resort provides suites 2 twin beds, junior suite queen bed, junior suite nicho 2 double beds, junior suite balcony king bed, master suite king bed, master suite 2 double beds and gran master suite with complimentary buffet breakfast, private bathroom and telephone. Its facilities and services include swimming pool, Shambhala restaurant, Sirio Holistic Spa and Feng Shui bioenergetic design.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hospedaje San Antonio</hi>, Calle Netzahualcóyotl 5, Santisima Trinidad, 62520 Tepoztlán, Mor, ☏ +52 739 395 7478 . Good location, swimming pool mx$898.</item>
</list>
</text>
