<text id="autogum_voyage_doc344" title="Plymouth (Massachusetts)" shortTile="plymouth-massachusetts" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27882" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Plymouth (Massachusetts)</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.visit-plymouth.com">Plymouth</ref></hi>, <ref target="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref> is located on the <ref target="South%20Shore%20%28Massachusetts%29">South Shore</ref>. Known as "American's Hometown," Plymouth is most famous for being the final landing place of the Pilgrims who arrived on board the Mayflower in 1620. The settlement they established, Plimouth Colony, was one of the earliest successful settlements of Europeans in North America. In addition to its obvious historical draws, modern-day Plymouth is a picturesque seaside town with a bustling summer resident population who come back year after year to enjoy its beaches, ponds, and forests. Although summer is Plymouth's peak tourist season, spring (before Memorial Day) and fall (after Labor Day) can be excellent times to visit. These bumper seasons are less crowded and certainly more comfortable temperature-wise. Spring has mild temperatures and flowers in bloom, and fall has beautiful New England foliage, warm days with cool nights, and different events to explore, such as observing a cranberry harvest.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>In area, Plymouth is the largest town in the state of Massachusetts, covering about 100 square miles (259 km²). Although the center of tourist activity is in Plymouth's historic downtown and waterfront areas, the rest of the town is divided into many smaller villages such as Chiltonville, Manomet, Cedarville, North Plymouth, and West Plymouth. Although somewhat homogeneous on the surface, each village has its own unique characteristics which makes it worth venturing outside the harbor-side to visit. North Plymouth, for example, was once home to the Cordage Company, the largest rope-maker in the world. Cordage employed many Italian and Portuguese immigrants who settled in company housing in this part of town, which many of their descendants still proudly call home. The Holy Ghost Festa, a major holiday for Portuguese of Azorean descent, is still widely celebrated in North Plymouth each summer.</p>

<p>Plymouth still has many residents who can trace their ancestry to the original Mayflower passengers and/or Native American tribes. Plymouth receives many visitors who are interested in researching their own colonial ancestry, and provides several key resources for doing so. The <ref target="https://www.themayflowersociety.org/visit/gsmd-library"><hi rend="bold">General Society of Mayflower Descendants Library</hi></ref> is the recognized authority on Pilgrim ancestry and has plenty of resources to assist you. <ref target="http://www.plymouthpubliclibrary.org/historygenealogy/"><hi rend="bold">Plymouth Public Library</hi></ref> also maintains a large room dedicated to genealogy.</p>
<p>It should go without saying that Plymouth residents feel <hi rend="bold">Thanksgiving Day</hi> belongs to them; after all, the holiday commemorates a feast shared by the surviving Mayflower passengers and local Native Americans following the Pilgrims' first harvest in 1621. That said, Thanksgiving in Plymouth isn't celebrated that much differently than in most places; local activities include a morning parade through town and a local high school football game between cross-town rivals Plymouth North and Plymouth South. For tourists, Plimouth Plantation offers a Thanksgiving Dinner on location at their site with the opportunity to learn more about the facts and fictions surrounding the historical event. Since 1970, the United American Indians of New England (UAINE) have observed the <ref target="http://www.uaine.org/"><hi rend="bold">National Day of Mourning</hi></ref> on Thanksgiving Day. Observance takes place annually at noon on Cole's Hill, acknowledging European settlement as the beginning of the genocide and forcible relocation of millions of Native Americans.</p>

<p>As a final note, "Plimoth", the old English spelling, is sometimes used to denote a historic site (e.g. Plimoth Plantation), while town sites will be spelled with the modern spelling, "Plymouth" (e.g. Plymouth Town Hall). Keep this in mind to avoid confusion if you notice signage such as the exit maker on Route 3 that helpfully reads, "Plymouth / Plimoth Plantation."</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Plymouth makes an excellent day trip (or several days' trip) when exploring the <ref target="Boston">Boston</ref>, <ref target="Providence">Providence</ref>, or <ref target="Cape%20Cod">Cape Cod</ref> areas.</p>
<head>By car</head>
<p>Plymouth covers the entire southern end of Route 3, extending from Exit 7 along Route 44 to Exit 2 approaching <ref target="Sagamore">Sagamore</ref> and the Cape Cod Canal. The historic section of Downtown Plymouth is accessed via Exit 6A. Metered parking is available downtown at both public lots and on street. The lots often have ticketing machines while street spots have individual meters. All parking fills up quickly during summer tourist season and during events such as festivals and parades. Get an early start or plan to do a lot of circling to find a spot.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">From Boston and points north</hi>: Plymouth is about an hour south of Boston, Massachusetts via Interstate 93 South to Route 3 South. Traffic is notorious during weekday rush hours, especially in the summer months where Route 3 is congested with vacationers heading south past Plymouth towards Cape Cod. Travel in off-peak hours is strongly advised for an enjoyable and timely trip. Route 3A, a two-lane back road which runs parallel to Route 3 from Boston down through the <ref target="South_Shore_%28Massachusetts%29">South Shore</ref> and directly through Plymouth, was the original road from Plymouth to Boston prior to the national highway system being built in the 1950s. Although quite scenic, it is a lengthy drive and not typically worth traveling the entire route.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">From Providence, Rhode Island and points west:</hi> Plymouth is connected to the west via Route 44, which runs into the western part of Plymouth through <ref target="Carver">Carver</ref>. Major interstates to the west such as Interstate 95 connect somewhat haphazardly with Plymouth via I93/Route 3 on the more northern part of I95, and I495/Route 44 on the more southern end.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">From Cape Cod and points south:</hi> Plymouth connects to the Cape via Route 6 over the Sagamore Bridge, which turns into Route 3 North. It is also accessible via Route 28 on the Cape, which goes over the Bourne Bridge. From <ref target="Bourne">Bourne</ref>, you can take Route 6 to connect to Route 3 North, or continue north on I495 to Route 44.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Plymouth Municipal Airport</hi> ( PYM ), 246 South Meadow Road. This airport is home to over 170 aircraft, most of which are one to ten seat, single or twin engine planes. Although the airport mainly serves pilot hobbyists and Cessna-style aircraft, Boston Med Flight, the State Police Air Wing, and the Plymouth County Fire Plane are also based there. </item>
</list>


<p>For those who don't wish to pilot themselves into town, travelers arriving by plane usually land at Boston's <ref target="https://www.massport.com/logan-airport/"><hi rend="bold">Logan International Airport</hi></ref> ( BOS ). Coach bus and MBTA rail connections can be made from Boston Logan to the Plymouth area. Other travelers may elect to arrive at Rhode Island's <ref target="http://www.pvdairport.com/"><hi rend="bold">T.F. Green Airport</hi></ref> ( PVD ) as flights are often cheaper, but there are no direct public transit options to Plymouth from <ref target="Warwick_%28Rhode_Island%29">Warwick</ref>.</p>
</text>
