<text id="autogum_voyage_doc429" title="Santa Cruz (Galapagos)" shortTile="santa-cruz-galapagos" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=31371" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Santa Cruz (Galapagos)</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Santa Cruz</hi> is the most important (although not the largest) island in the <ref target="Galapagos%20Islands">Galapagos Islands</ref> archipelago, in <ref target="Ecuador">Ecuador</ref>. It contains the largest town in the Galapagos Islands, <hi rend="bold">Puerto Ayora</hi>, which is the only location on the island with tourist infrastructure, on the southern side of the island, and is connected by road and ferry to the airport on <ref target="Baltra">Baltra</ref> Island. It is also home to the Galapagos National Park administration, the Darwin Foundation, and the Charles Darwin Research Station.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Due to the central location of Santa Cruz in the archipelago, Puerto Ayora makes the best base for those wishing to visit the Galapagos while staying onshore. Although it is a small town, it has the best infrastructure in the Galapagos with the largest number of hotels and restaurants, as well as shopping and supplies. Services include include grocery stores, pharmacies, hardware stores, boat supplies, a small hospital and a hyperbaric chamber.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>European and American interest in the Galapagos was stimulated by the publication of William Beebe's book Galapagos: World's End in 1924. This book inspired the beginnings of the eco-tourism that today dominates the Galapagos economy. Tourism began, however, as only a trickle (one of those early tourists was U.S. President Franklin D. Roosevelt, who visited the islands in 1938). There was also a trickle of Europeans immigration to the Galapagos around this time. The largest group was 60 Norwegians, persuaded to settle on Floreana in 1927 by several young journalists and a whaler who had written about the Galapagos. Floreana turned out to be anything but the paradise the promoters promised, as the colonists came to realize after the promoters left. Most managed to survive for a difficult year or two there. Some of the survivors eventually returned to Norway, others moved to the settlement on <ref target="San%20Cristobal%20%28Galapagos%29">San Cristobal</ref>, and others settled on Academy Bay on Santa Cruz, joining another group of Norwegians that had set up a cannery there the year before. Within a few years, most of the colonists left as well, but a few remained. A few years later, other Norwegians came to Santa Cruz, as well as a sprinkling of others from Europe, America, and Ecuador, all seeking a simpler life. Among them were the four Angermeyer brothers from Germany, who settled on Santa Cruz in 1935. Their descendants still live there and operate touring yachts and a hotel in Puerto Ayora.</p>

<head>Towns</head>
<p>The island is administrated as a single municipality, but contains several towns:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> - largest town in on the island and the only one with major tourist accommodation</item>
<item> - at the center of the island</item>
<item> - near Puerto Ayora</item>
<item> - very small</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>
<p>Access to Santa Cruz is almost exclusively by air, with planes landing at the on the small nearby island of Baltra.</p>

<p>Inter-island flights are available from <ref target="http://www.emetebe.com.ec/">EMETEBE Airlines</ref>, which operates nine seater aircraft to transport passengers and their luggage from San Cristobal Airport to Isabela, Santa Cruz and Baltra islands. Bookings can be done directly through EMETEBE's website or a travel agent.</p>

<p>As of Nov 2018, upon exiting the Baltra airport, board a bus to the Itabaca channel for $5. Proceed on a ferry/a smaller water taxi for $1. At the other end of the canal you can ride the bus into town ($5) or take a taxi ($25).</p>

<p>For the reverse direction, buses from Puerto Ayora to the channel only leave in the morning. Times may vary. Check locally at the time (at least a day before your flight). If you have an afternoon flight, you'll have to take a taxi ($25) or find alternative transport.</p>

<head>By boat</head>
<p>There is public transportation via local speed boats to both <ref target="San%20Cristobal%20%28Galapagos%29">San Cristobal</ref> and <ref target="Puerto%20Villamil">Puerto Villamil</ref> on <ref target="Isabela%20%28Ecuador%29">Isabela</ref> daily. They leave at 2PM and the 2-hour, and tend to be rough and noisy (US$25-35). There are no bathrooms or other services available on these boats and passengers should carry their own water or snacks.</p>

<head>Private Yacht</head>
<p>Many people arrive annually by private yacht as part of a trip around the world. Puerto Ayora and Puerto Baquerizo Moreno are the main ports of entry in the Galapagos - however most sail boats will enter at Puerto Villamil. Boating in the Galapagos is restricted. A non-Ecuadorian vessel arriving from a non-Ecuadorian port may stay up to 20 days in a single port. Arrival fees are approximately $130 plus $3 per tonne for the vessel, plus $110 per person for the Park's pass and island immigration. National Immigration and Customs are about another $50.</p>

<p>A permit to visit the five ports in the Galapagos (Puerto Ayora, Baltra, Puerto Baquerizo Moreno, Puerto Villamil and Puerto Velasco Ibarra) can be obtained by applying in advance with a ship's agent. These permits cost $300 for the vessel, in addition to the fees above. This permit is the only way for an Ecuadorian vessel or a vessel arriving from mainland Ecuador to visit the Galapagos. Licensed Yacht Handling Agencies can assist private vessels secure cruise permits.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>The only paved road on the island is between the Itabaca channel and Puerto Ayora. Busses will transport airport passengers from the ferry to Puerto Ayora and back. There are also white pick-up trucks functioning as collectivo, just wait at one of the <hi rend="italic">parades</hi> but they usually won't go further than Santa Rosa. They also double as taxi</p>

<p>Puerto Ayora itself is small enough to explore by foot. Most tourism is concentrated along the waterfront. White pickup truck taxis operate and can provide transportation around town, into the highlands, or across the island. Water taxis are available at the main dock and can take you to either a waiting boat or the dock on the other side.</p>

<head>In/around Puerto Ayora</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Charles Darwin Research Station</hi>, Avenida Charles Darwin (Located at the end of the road on the eastern edge of town). 6AM to 6PM M-Sa. 1.5 km west of the centre of Puerto Ayora. It has a turtle breeding area and interesting information about the conservation of the unique biosphere of the Galapagos, and extensive exhibits on the natural history of the islands. The breeding programs at the station allow visitors to see many iguanas, tortoises, and other animals in various stages of their lives. Until his death in 2012 the station was also home to <hi rend="italic">Lonesome George</hi>, a tortoise found on <ref target="Pinta">Pinta</ref> island who was believed to be the last of his sub-species. George became a symbol of the park and for many years was known as the rarest creature in the world.</item>
</list>

 Free. 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tortuga Bay</hi>. 6AM-6:30PM daily. a 2.5 kilometer long trail from Puerto Ayora leads to this beautiful beach with a strong undertow. If you walk about 1 km further down the beach you reach a calm bay known as Playa Mansa. The visibility in the water isn't perfect, but close to the mangroves white tip sharks can be seen. Marine turtles, pelicans, and Blue Heron sightings are also common. Visitors must register at a at the beginning of the trail. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Punta Estrada beach/German beach</hi>. small beach good for snorkeling especially with high tide. Take a watertaxi ($0.60) from Puerto Ayora to the Hotel Finch dock. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Las Grietas</hi>. further up the trail from Punta Estrada beach following the green and white posts. A spectacular canyon filled with crystal clear water. Good for snorkeling. A local swimming hole made from a large crevice between volcanic rock. The water is clear and emerald green. You can snorkel here but there isn't much to see besides a few large fish, probably as the water is a mix of the sea water and filtered rain water. Taking a snorkel is worth it as there is a series of tunnels created by fallen rocks. There are three swimming pools. In the furthest you can climb up the rocks and jump down into the water. Getting here. From Puerto Ayora pier, hail over a yellow water taxi and tell them you want to go to Las Grietas. $0.80 (Nov 2018) will get you a one way trip and drop you off at Angermeyer Waterfront Inn. Follow the well marked path through the iguanas, German's beach, the salt pans, and the lava rock path to Las Grietas. Along the path is a detour to the left. Well worth the short walk to look down at the crystal clear water and the length of Las Grietas. Closes at 5pm. Getting away. Back at the pier hail over a water taxi that's waiting not to far from the pier. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Laguna Las Ninfas</hi>. A pretty lagune with a footpath. Free.</item>
</list>
</text>
