<text id="autogum_voyage_doc172" title="Swedish phrasebook" shortTile="swedish-phrasebook" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=34816" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Swedish phrasebook</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Swedish</hi> (<hi rend="italic">svenska</hi>) is a North Germanic language, closely related to <ref target="Norwegian%20phrasebook">Norwegian</ref> and <ref target="Danish%20phrasebook">Danish</ref> (and through them, related to <ref target="Icelandic%20phrasebook">Icelandic</ref> and <ref target="Faroese%20phrasebook">Faroese</ref>) and strongly influenced by <ref target="Low%20German%20phrasebook">Low German</ref>. Spoken by over 9 million people, Swedish is the national language of <ref target="Sweden">Sweden</ref> and the official language of the <ref target="%C3%85land">Åland</ref> Islands. It is also an official language of <ref target="Finland">Finland</ref> (along with <ref target="Finnish%20phrasebook">Finnish</ref>), though only the mother tongue for about 6 percent of Finns, mostly concentrated in some coastal areas.</p>

<p>Like for instance British and American English, there are differences between Swedish spoken in Sweden (<hi rend="italic">rikssvenska</hi>) and Swedish spoken in Finland (<hi rend="italic">finlandssvenska</hi>), in pronunciation, grammar and vocabulary, partly due to influence from <ref target="Finnish">Finnish</ref> in the latter, but also due to it retaining some archaic features.</p>

<p>Finland-Swedish is less tonal, slightly more phonetic and like in Finnish the 'r' is always trilled. There are dialectal differences inside Finland and Sweden too, most notably the Swedish spoken in <ref target="Scania">Scania</ref> reminds of Danish to some extent, but Swedish speakers with different dialects seldom have difficulties understanding each other. Some archaic dialects of rural <ref target="Ostrobothnia">Ostrobothnia</ref> are incomprehensible, but the speakers will switch to normal Swedish when talking to non-locals.</p>

<p>As Swedish is a Germanic language, speakers of other Germanic languages like <ref target="German%20phrasebook">German</ref>, <ref target="Dutch%20phrasebook">Dutch</ref> or even English will be able to recognise many cognates.</p>

<p>While practically everyone in Sweden under the age of 70 can speak some English, most younger people fluently, trying out some words of Swedish is always appreciated. The same is true about the Swedish speaking in Finland – but you should probably stick to English or <ref target="Finnish%20phrasebook">Finnish</ref> with people whose first language is Finnish.</p>

<head>Vowels</head>
<p>Swedish is notorious for its extra vowel sounds, giving Swedish nine (!) different vowels. Most are pronounced differently than English, and some don't even have a true English equivalent; some may be close, but sound like a combination of two vowel sounds. This can be very confusing, but you probably won't hear enough Swedish to know the difference, as they can be very slight. If you don't get it exactly, you may still be understood. All vowels can be pronounced short or long which means that Swedish has 17 different vowel sounds (short e and short ä is the same).</p>

<p>Please note: in Swedish 'Y' is a vowel and not a consonant. Å, Ä and Ö are letters in their own right, in the end of the alphabet past Z.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> a : like 'a' in "father."</item>
<item> e : short: like 'e' in "bed" or "pen." long: like 'ey' in "hey," but longer. Can sometimes sound slightly like "Ay-uh;" because the Swedish pronunciation is longer. E's are usually pronounced at the end of a word, such as in "<hi rend="italic">kaffe</hi>" (pronounced kaff-eh, meaning coffee), unlike English where e's at the end of a word are usually silent.</item>
<item> i : short: like 'i' in "India" long: like 'i' in "machine." Fairly straightforward.</item>
<item> o : like 'u' in "put," but not exactly. It's somewhere between that and the 'o' in "broken" in actuality.</item>
<item> u : like 'ou' in "you."</item>
<item> y : like 'y' in "Nitroglycerin." This is one of the harder ones to learn. Easiest way is to round your lips (important) and say "bee." It may sound closer to an English short 'i' sound to some people.</item>
<item> å : like 'au' in "Paul" generally speaking. Similar to <hi rend="italic">å</hi> in Danish.</item>
<item> ä : identical to the <hi rend="italic">ä</hi> in German (sounds like an "e" as in "bet". Pronounced with more bass if preceding r. Corresponds to <hi rend="italic">æ</hi> in Danish and Norwegian.</item>
<item> ö : Same as in German. Pronounced with more bass if preceding r. Corresponds to <hi rend="italic">ø</hi> in Danish and Norwegian.</item>
</list>


<p>The pronunciation of u and y varies quite a lot between regions; all native speakers make a clear distinction, although the u of somebody may be close to y of somebody else.</p>

<head>Consonants</head>
<p>Consonants are closer to English, but some combinations can be downright tricky, i.e. 'sj' in "sjutton." Some pronunciations depend on the vowel following it, and so the vowels are divided into "soft" and "hard" vowels. A, o, u, and å are the hard vowels, and e, i, y, ä, and ö are the soft vowels. There are also some combinations of letters treated as a group for the purpose of pronunciation (e.g. ch, ng, sch, sj, tj).</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> b : like 'b' in "bed"</item>
<item> c : like 'c' in "cat", sometimes 's' like the first c in circus; a 'ch' combination is sometimes pronounced like English 'sh', but pronounced like a 'k' in the word <hi rend="italic">och</hi>.</item>
<item> d : like 'd' in "dog"</item>
<item> f : like 'f' in "for"</item>
<item> g : like 'g' in "go", when preceding a hard vowel, like 'y' in "yellow" when preceding a soft vowel. A 'gn' pronunciation is pronounced like an English 'g', except for when it follows a vowel, in which case it is pronounced 'ng+n.'</item>
<item> h : like 'h' in "help". A superfluous silent 'h' is common in names (e.g. Elisabet and Elisabeth are pronounced the same).</item>
<item> j : like 'y' in "yell," and if there is a d, g, or h before a 'j' then that letter is silent.</item>
<item> k : like 'k' in "king" before a hard vowel, like 'sh' before a soft one. 'Kj' is pronounced 'sh' as well</item>
<item> l : like 'l' in "love," but 'lj' is pronounced like a 'y'</item>
<item> m : like 'm' in "mother"</item>
<item> n : like 'n' in "nice", like 'ng' in "song" when preceding k</item>
<item> ng: not a letter; like 'ng' in "song"</item>
<item> p : like 'p' in "pig"</item>
<item> q : like 'q' in "quest" (with "u", almost always)</item>
<item> r : like 'r' in "row", and like 'r' in "feather." Swedes tend to roll their r's in certain words (not comparable to an English 'r', more like a Spanish one). 'Rs' is pronounced 'sh'.</item>
<item> s : like 'ss' in "hiss," but 'skj' and 'stj' are pronounced 'sh.' 'Sj' is hard for non-native speakers – try rounding your lips and saying "hwoo" to get the gist of it. 'Sk' is also pronounced this way before soft vowels.</item>
<item> t : like 't' in "top," but 'tj' is pronounced 'sh'</item>
<item> v : like 'v' in "victory"</item>
<item> w : like 'v' in "victor," but w's in Swedish are uncommon.</item>
<item> x : like 'cks' in "kicks", like 'ehcks' at beginning of a word.</item>
<item> z : like 's' in "saw"</item>
</list>
</text>
