<text id="autogum_voyage_doc33" title="Aberdyfi">
<head>Aberdyfi</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.aberdovey.com/">Aberdyfi</ref></hi> (sometimes spelt <hi rend="bold">Aberdovey</hi>) is a village in <ref target="Gwynedd">Gwynedd</ref>. It lies at the mouth of the river Dyfi, from which it derives its name. Aberdyfi is a holiday resort, traditionally popular with golfers and sailors but also with more adrenaline-driven sportspeople, and is home to <hi rend="italic">Britain's Best Beach Donkey</hi>. The village marks the southern edge of the <ref target="Snowdonia%20National%20Park">Snowdonia National Park</ref>. It is set by the mouth of the river Dyfi which is a UNESCO world biosphere reserve.</p>
<head>Get in</head>

<head>By rail</head>
<p>Aberdyfi is served by the Cambrian Line, operated by <ref target="http://www.arrivatrainswales.co.uk/home.aspx">Arriva Trains Wales</ref>. There are 2 stations, the request only at the eastern end of the village, and (<hi rend="italic">Aberdovey station</hi>), at the western end of the village.</p>

<head>By road</head>
<p>Aberdyfi is on the A493 <ref target="Machynlleth">Machynlleth</ref> to <ref target="Tywyn">Tywyn</ref> road</p>

<head>By sea</head>
<p>Aberdyfi Harbour has facilities for visiting yachts. The Harbour Master can be contacted on +44 1654 767626.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Aberdyfi is easy to get around on foot, though some streets away from the harbour front can be quite steep.</p>

<head>Cycle Hire</head>
<p>is available in nearby <ref target="Tywyn">Tywyn</ref></p>

<head>Taxis</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dyfi Cabs</hi>, ☏ +44 7831 551538, +44 7773 385335 .</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Artworks</hi>, 16 Chapel Square, ☏ +44 1654 767127 . Gallery of local professional artists</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aberdyfi Outward Bound Center</hi> (Aberdyfi Outward Bound Centre), ☏ +44 1654 767464 . The golf course is the 3rd best course in Wales and is in the new Top 100 Golf Courses of the World listings for Wales (2014), after the two Royals – Royal Porthcawl and Royal St Davids.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aberdovey Golf Club</hi>, ☏ +44 1654 767493 . A popular Championship links course.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dovey Yacht Club</hi>, ☏ +44 1654 767607 .</item>
<item> Walk up to the <hi rend="bold">Bandstand</hi> on the hill above the village centre, for great views acrosss the village and the estuary.</item>
<item> For a more strenuous walk, but one which will reward you with even better views, follow <hi rend="italic">Copperhill St</hi> uphill from the village and keep on walking as it turns into a steep country lane. Eventually this leads to the mythical <hi rend="bold">Bearded Lake</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Llyn Barfog</hi>), scene of a battle between King Arthur and a monster called the <hi rend="italic">Afanc</hi>. Arthur's horse left its hoofprint in a nearby rock known as <hi rend="italic">Carn March Arthur</hi>. The lake is also the scene of another well-known legend regarding a local farmer and his herd of magic fairy cows. Follow signs to the nearby <hi rend="bold">Echo</hi> which is mildly entertaining. If you have a car you can drive up the hill until the tarmac runs out, and leave the car. From here it's only a short walk to the lake.</item>
<item> Fish for <hi rend="bold">crabs</hi> off the jetty. Hooks, Lines and bait can be bought from shops around the harbour, including Dyfi Marine (see "Buy").</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dyfi Donkeys</hi>, Next to the Children's playground by the beach, ☏ +44 7717 020344 . Every weekend May-Sep, daily during school holidays including Easter. Donkey rides for children along the beach. Aberdyfi beach had been without the traditional donkeys for many years, but they returned in 2005. Note there is a maximum weight limit of 8 stone (51 kg). In 2008 <hi rend="italic">Del-Boy</hi> was named Britain's best beach donkey by <ref target="http://drupal.thedonkeysanctuary.org.uk/">The Donkey Sanctuary</ref> at their annual awards.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Outward Bound Aberdyfi</hi> (Outdoor Activity Centre), ☏ +44 1654 767464 . Also have centres in <ref target="Cumbria">Cumbria</ref> and <ref target="Scotland">Scotland</ref>. They offer courses for companies, schools, families and individuals.</item>
</list>

 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kitesurfing</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aberdovey Language Teachers & Aberdovey Language Tuition</hi>. Learn Welsh. 30% of the population speak Welsh.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Gallery</hi>, 11 New Street, ☏ +44 1654 767319 . Aberdyfi has long been popular with artists and The Gallery always has a good selection of works on sale</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dyfi Marine</hi> (Yacht Chandler. Also sells some fishing tackle and bait), Copperhill St, ☏ +44 1654 767581 .</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Y Bwtri Blasus</hi> (Tasty Pantry), Sea View Terrace, Aberdyfi, ☏ +44 1654 767470 . Open 7 days per week from 09:00, and 10:00 on Sundays. Cafe and delicatessen serving morning coffee, light lunches and afternoon teas. Their homemade puddings are a highlight.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Penhelig Arms</hi>, ☏ +44 1654 767215 . Awarded UK Seafood Pub of the Year in 2005. Not just for fish-lovers though. You can eat in the bar or the adjacent restaurant (booking recommended).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Britannia Inn</hi>, ☏ +44 1654 767426 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Sea Breeze Restaurant</hi>, ☏ +44 1654 767449 .</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Penhelig Arms</hi>, ☏ +44 1654 767215 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Dovey Inn</hi>, ☏ +44 1654 767332 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Britannia Inn</hi>, ☏ +44 1654 767426 . Lovely terrace overlooking the harbour - arrive early for a seat here if the weather's good.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<p>There's a wide choice of B&B and self-catering accommodation. Campers may need to head north towards <ref target="Tywyn">Tywyn</ref>.</p>

<head>B&B and Guest Houses</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sea Breeze</hi>, 6 Bodfor Terrace, Aberdyfi, ☏ +44 1654 767449 . Check-in: from 14:30, check-out: 10:00. 8 rooms (all en-suite, 5 have sea-views) in a seafront townhouse close to the village centre. Double sea view room: £75 per night inc breakfasts.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cartref</hi> (On the Tywyn road, close to Aberdyfi station), ☏ +44 1654 767273 . 4 guest rooms (all en-suite) in a recently (2008) refurbished Edwardian house just a few minutes walk from the beach and village centre. Double room: £75 per night inc breakfasts.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Brig-Y-Don</hi>, Balkan Hill, Aberdyfi, LL35 0NH (Just up Church Street), ☏ +44 1654 767301 , ✉ contact@aberdoveyaccommodation.co.uk . Stunning views, beautiful gardens, secure car parking and modern facilities. Double En-suite & Sea View Room from £65 inc breakfasts.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Smugglers Cove</hi>, Smugglers Cove, Frongoch Boatyard, ☏ +44061 3205024 , ✉ cottages@csholidays.fsnet.co.uk . Self catering holiday cottage with 7 bedrooms</item>
</list>


<head>Hotels</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Penhelig Arms</hi>, 27-29 Terrace Road, ☏ +44 1654 767215 . Acclaimed 18th-Century Inn overlooking the estuary at the eastern end of the village.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Trefeddian Hotel</hi>, ☏ +44 1654 767213 . Half a mile or so out of town, on a hillside above the main coast road heading towards <ref target="Tywyn">Tywyn</ref>. The largest hotel in the area with 59 rooms, overlooking the golf course. Heated swimming pool, tennis courts, 9-hole putting green, snooker room, beauty salon. WTB 3-star.</item>
</list>

 


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aberdovey Hillside Village</hi>, Church St (Turn right in square, past front of chapel and continue straight up Church St for approximately 200 metres, ignoring left dog-leg and continue to metal gates.), ☏ +44 1654 767522 , ✉ info@hillsidevillage.co.uk . "The Village" is a cluster of specially designed houses and apartments which blend naturally into a south-facing hillside with views. Pet friendly, with landscaped grounds which lead into the open countryside. The shops and beaches are within 300 m.</item>
</list>


<head>Connect</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tourist Information Centre</hi>, Wharf Gardens. +44 1654 767321.</item>
</list>


<head>Area Code</head>

<p>The area dialling code is 01654. To call from overseas, dial +44 1654 XXXXXX</p>

<head>Internet</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tywyn Library</hi>, Neptune Road, Tywyn. (In Tywyn, 4 miles to the north). Opens 10:00-17:30 (Mo/Th/Fr), 10:00-19:00 (Tu), 10:00-12.30 (Sa). Closed for 13:00-14:00.. 4 PCs with free broadband internet access..</item>
</list>


<head>Post Office</head>

<p>Aberdyfi's Post Office is at Penrhos Service Station, close to Aberdyfi train station. +44 1654 767530.</p>

<head>Media</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cambrian News</hi>. Local English-language newspaper, published weekly. Covers Ceredigion, North Powys, South Gwynedd. Renowned for its occasionally bizarre headlines.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dail Dysynni</hi>. Welsh-language monthly newspaper, dedicated to the Bro Dysynni area.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Radio Ceredigion</hi> 96.6-97.4 FM. Bilingual community radio station, broadcasting from Aberystwyth to the Cardigan Bay area.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">BBC Radio Wales</hi> 882 and 657 AM.</item>
</list>


<head>Stay safe</head>

<head>Healthcare</head>
<p>♡❤♡In an emergency, dial <hi rend="italic">999</hi> or <hi rend="italic">112</hi> (<hi rend="italic">ideally from a landline</hi>) and request ambulance, police or fire service.<hi rend="bold"></p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> </hi>Bronglais District General Hospital<hi rend="bold">, <ref target="Aberystwyth">Aberystwyth</ref>. +44 1970 623131. The nearest Accident & Emergency unit. Open 24 hours.</item>
<item> </hi>Tywyn Memorial Hospital<hi rend="bold">, Aberdyfi Road, <ref target="Tywyn">Tywyn</ref>. +44 1654 710411/0845 8501362(Out of Hours). Local Cottage Hospital. Medical cover is provided by the local GP surgery during the hours of 08:30 to 18:30 hours. The care is then taken over by the Out of Hours Service. The Minor Injuries Unit is open from 09:00 to 24:00 hours and is manned by a Clinical Practitioner.</item>
<item> </hi>Neptune Dental Surgery<hi rend="bold"> Neptune Road, <ref target="Tywyn">Tywyn</ref>. +44 1654 710607. NHS and Private dentist. Has an attached dental laboratory for any denture repair work.</item>
<item> </hi>Medical Hall Aberdyfi<hi rend="bold"> Glandyfi Terrace, Aberdyfi. +44 1654 767227. The friendly and helpful pharmacy, right on the sea front in the village.</item>
</list>


<head>Beaches and Coast</head>

<p>Due to the fact that is part of a tidal river estuary, the beach at the village itself can be subject to strong and unpredictable currents, so care should be exercised in the water. Better to head half a mile or so north, away from the river mouth. The beach stretches all the way to <ref target="Tywyn">Tywyn</ref> and has a safe reputation due to its gently-shelving nature, though of course sensible precautions should still be taken.</p>

<p></hi>General advice for safe swimming<hi rend="bold">:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> A red flag means danger. Do not enter the water if the red flag is flying</item>
<item> Consider bathing at a beach that's under lifeguard protection</item>
<item> Don't swim alone at a deserted beach</item>
<item> Don't use inflatables. They are easily swept away by strong currents</item>
<item> If you see someone in trouble, call 999 and ask for </hi>Coastguard♡❤♡</item>
<item> Inquire about swimming conditions at local tourist offices prior to venturing to a beach without lifeguard cover</item>
<item> Read warning notices posted near beach access sites</item>
</list>


<head>Mountains</head>

<p>Snowdonia's mountains claim lives every year. The weather can change very quickly in this part of the World, and this is especially true in the mountains. Make sure you are wearing suitable clothing and footwear, and always carry a suitable map. Ordnance Survey 1:25000 scale Explorer Map OL23 <hi rend="italic">Cadair Idris and Bala Lake</hi> is ideal, alternatively the 1:50000 scale Landranger series sheets 124 <hi rend="italic">Dolgellau and Porthmadog</hi> and 135 <hi rend="italic">Aberystwyth and Machynlleth</hi>.</p>

<p>Follow the <hi rend="bold">Mountain Safety Code:</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Before You Go</hi></p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Learn the use of map and compass</item>
<item> Know the weather signs and local forecast</item>
<item> Plan within your capabilities</item>
<item> Know simple first aid and the symptoms of exposure</item>
<item> Know the mountain distress signals</item>
<item> Know the country code</item>
</list>


<p><hi rend="bold">When You Go</hi></p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Never go alone</item>
<item> Leave written word of your route and report your return</item>
<item> Take windproofs, woollens and survival bag</item>
<item> Take map and compass, torch and food</item>
<item> Wear climbing boots</item>
<item> Keep alert all day</item>
<item> Avoid disturbance to farming, forestry and field sports</item>
</list>


<p><hi rend="bold">If There is Snow On The Hills</hi></p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Always have an ice axe for each person</item>
<item> Carry a climbing rope and know the correct use of rope and ice axe</item>
<item> Learn to recognise dangerous snow slope</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Machynlleth">Machynlleth</ref></hi> is a pleasant market town with an "alternative" feel, 11 miles to the east. It hosts a regular street market every Wednesday, as well as being home to the Museum of Modern Art (MOMA). The Centre for Alternative Technology, a few miles north of the town, is well worth a visit. Just a short distance further north lies the village of Corris, with a number of craft shops.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Tywyn">Tywyn</ref></hi>, just 4 miles to the north by train or the main A493 road (possible to walk there along the beach) is home to the World-famous Talyllyn Railway.</item>
</list>
</text>
