<text id="autogum_voyage_doc382" title="Montreal/Downtown" shortTile="montrealdowntown" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=22875" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Montreal/Downtown</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Downtown</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Centre-ville</hi>) is a district of <ref target="Montreal">Montreal</ref>.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Street parking costs $3/hour from 8AM-9PM and ticketing is common. There are a number of large, commercial parking structures and by-the-day lots. Driving can be very slow and frustrating along rue Sainte-Catherine, with large numbers of pedestrians and heavy traffic. Sherbrooke often comes to a standstill during rush hour.</p>

<head>By metro</head>
<p>Downtown Montreal is served by the Orange and Green Lines. The Green Line follows boulevard de Maisonneuve, while the Orange line runs parallel five blocks to the south (i.e. towards the river). In many cases, you can use the "Underground City" to walk from one station to another — even between lines — without surfacing (useful in winter or rain!)</p>

<p>Useful stops include:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">McGill</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Peel</hi> on the Green Line for McGill University and downtown shopping district.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bonaventure</hi> for Gare Centrale (<hi rend="italic">Central Train Station</hi>) and AMT Downtown Bus Station.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>
<p>Dozens of bus lines run through the downtown area.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">24 Sherbrooke</hi> runs on rue Sherbrooke, a good way to get out to <ref target="Montreal/Westmount">Westmount</ref> or the <ref target="Montreal/Plateau">Plateau</ref>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">15 Sainte-Catherine</hi> covers rue Sainte-Catherine from rue Atwater to the <ref target="Montreal/Gay%20Village">Village</ref>.</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>
<p>Downtown is walkable, weather permitting, but watch for frustrated drivers trying to cut through throngs of pedestrians crossing the street. The new bike lane on Blvd. de Mainsonneuve provides easy and relatively safe bike access in and out of downtown.</p>

<p>Many blocks are connected by 30 km of underground pedestrian tunnels, arcades and malls. You can walk and shop in comfort when the weather above is foul.</p>

<head>See</head>
 <hi rend="bold">McGill University Campus</hi>, 805 rue Sherbrooke ouest at ave McGill College, ☏ +1 514 398-4455 , ✉ servicepoint@mcgill.ca . The lower section of McGill's campus is composed mainly of 19th-century neoclassical buildings and is definitely worth a ten-minute stroll. 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Underground City</hi> (Montréal souterrain). Throughout the downtown area. This network of underground malls and passageways is a very convenient way to walk around during the winter months. It encompasses six metro stations on the green and orange lines and all of the major downtown shopping malls, including food courts, cinemas, innumerable boutiques, and services.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Christ Church Cathedral</hi>, 1444 ave Union (entrance on rue Sainte-Catherine; metro McGill), ☏ +1 514 843-6577 . It is a small, but colourful church, the mother church of the region's Anglican (Episcopalian) denomination. Of special interest is the organ with additional remote-controlled organ pipes in the front of the church. If you have the opportunity to listen to an organ concert there, you should go. The concert will probably be by donation only. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mary Queen of the World Cathedral</hi> (Cathédrale Marie-Reine-du-Monde), 1065 rue de la Cathédrale (main entrance on boul René-Lévesque; metro Bonaventure), ☏ +1 514 866-1661 . 7:30AM-6PM daily. A 1/4 scale copy of St. Peter's in Rome. Impressive interior. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Canadian Centre for Architecture</hi> (Centre canadien d'architecture), 1920 rue Baile (between rue Saint-Marc and rue du Fort; metro Guy-Concordia or Georges-Vanier), ☏ +1 514 939-7026 . W F 11AM-6PM, Th 11AM-9PM, Sa Su 11AM-5PM. Architecture museum and research institute that incorporates the <hi rend="bold">Shaughnessy House</hi>, an 1876 Second Empire-style manison. Across boulevard René-Lévesque from the CCA is a sculpture garden with works designed around the theme of architecture. Guided tours available. $10 adults, $7 seniors, free for students and children.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Montreal Museum of Fine Arts</hi> (Musée des beaux-arts de Montréal), 1380 rue Sherbrooke ouest (at ave du Musée; metro Guy-Concordia), ☏ +1 514 285-2000 , toll-free: +1-800-899-6873 . Tu-F 11AM-5PM, Sa Su 10AM-5PM. Permanent exhibitions free for under 30s. Many prominent travelling exhibits. There is a fee for over 30s, and for special exhibitions. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">McCord Museum</hi> (Musée McCord), 690 rue Sherbrooke ouest (at rue Victoria; metro McGill). M Tu Th Fr 10AM-6PM, W 10AM-9PM, Sa-Su 10AM-5PM. Museum dedicated to Canadian history, next to McGill University. $15 adult, $12 senior (65+), $8 student (13-17), $9 student (18-30), free for children, $30 family. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Musée d'art contemporain de Montréal</hi>, 185 rue Sainte-Catherine ouest (at rue Jeanne-Mance; metro Place-des-Arts), ☏ +1 514 847-6226 . Tu 11AM-6PM, W-F 11AM-9PM, Sa Su 10AM-6PM. Contemporary art museum at the Place-des-Arts complex. $15 adult, $12 senior (60+), $10 students (18+ with ID), free for children (0-12), $5 youth (13-17), $30 family, children free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Redpath Museum</hi> (Musée Redpath), 859 rue Sherbrooke ouest (between rue McTavish and ave McGill College, behind the Roddick Gates from rue Sherbrooke; metro McGill), ☏ +1 514 398-4086 . M-F 9AM-5PM, Su noon-5PM, Sa closed. A museum of natural history on the McGill campus. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Windsor Station</hi> (Gare Windsor), 1160 rue de la Gauchetière ouest (at rue Peel), ☏ +1 514 287-8726 . This Romanesque Revival building served as one of the city's main railway stations until it was cut off from the rail network by the construction of the Bell Centre nearby. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pont de Victoria</hi> (French; translation: Victoria Bridge) is the one of the oldest crossings of the Saint Lawrence Seaway and definitely the oldest bridge in Montreal that is still standing. While there is no pedestrian access on the bridge, it is still a must-see, especially for those interested in architecture.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Habitat 67</hi>, 2600 avenue Pierre-Dupuy (take Chemin du Moulins exit from Hwy 10 south), ☏ +1 514-866-5971 . This visually striking residential building was created by architect Moshe Safdie for Expo 67. The result was an amazingly modern dwelling that challenged the way architects created urban homes. Compared alternately to a beehive, a Taos pueblo, and a crystalline growth, the complex's 154 units are composed of prefabricated concrete cubes assembled on site. The apartments here are highly prized and a number of prominent Montrealers make Habitat 67 their home. </item>
</list>


<head>Chinatown</head>
<p>Montreal's <hi rend="bold">Chinatown</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Le quartier chinois</hi>) mostly runs along rue de la Gauchetière between rue Jeanne-Mance and rue Saint-Dominique (this section is mostly pedestrianized), and also along rue Saint-Urbain and boulevard Saint-Laurent between rue Viger and boulevard René-Lévesque. It is the third largest Chinatown in Canada, behind those in Vancouver and Toronto, and is known best for its many restaurants and gift shops.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Place Sun-Yat-Sen</hi>, rue de la Gauchetière and rue Clark (metro Place-d'Armes). A small public square in the middle of Chinatown. There are murals made of grey slate along the north and east side of the square; also at the square is a pavilion selling typical Chinatown tourist souvenirs.</item>
</list>
</text>
