<text id="autogum_voyage_doc220" title="Santa Cruz (California)" shortTile="santa-cruz-california" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=31367" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Santa Cruz (California)</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.santacruz.org/">Santa Cruz</ref></hi> is a small coastal city (population about 55,000) in <ref target="Santa%20Cruz%20County%20%28California%29">Santa Cruz County</ref>, at the north end of <ref target="Monterey%20Bay">Monterey Bay</ref> in <ref target="California">California</ref>, about 40 miles (64 km) south of <ref target="San%20Jose%20%28California%29">San Jose</ref> and 75 miles (120 km) south of <ref target="San%20Francisco">San Francisco</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Santa Cruz is best known as a countercultural hub, with a bohemian feel and youthful vibe, and fun weekend tourist attractions like the <hi rend="bold">Santa Cruz Beach Boardwalk</hi> and the dubious <hi rend="bold">Mystery Spot</hi>. The rather relaxed beach lifestyle is supplemented by some remaining high tech industry and a vibrant university culture. The University of California Santa Cruz (UCSC) is regarded as one of the premier centers of higher learning in the region and was once well known for its strong emphasis on the arts and humanities.</p>

<p>The beaches north and south of Santa Cruz are considered some of the more pristine areas of natural beauty in central California. A variety of conditions prevail, depending on the beach, few are suited for swimming due to temperature and current, several are considered an expert surfer's cold cold paradise. Don't expect a beach culture like Southern California, with bikini babes and children swimming in the surf; for much of the year it's considered perfectly normal to wear a sweater and long pants to the beach. The beautiful beaches and the rather mild climate play a central role in local culture. Most visitors leave Santa Cruz amazed by the city's beauty and ambiance.</p>

<head>Get in</head>


<p>Highway 17 south from <ref target="San%20Jose%20%28California%29">San Jose</ref> is the most direct route when driving from the more populated parts of the <ref target="Bay%20Area">Bay Area</ref>. It is a winding and very dangerous road over the mountains, arguably the most hazardous in the state shared during the week with heavy gravel trucks, so heed the speed limits take it easy and arrive alive. Accidents are very common, but the road is a bit safer since the addition of concrete barriers some years ago. Beware of fog, as well as "hurried" drivers, and drive with caution, especially when roads are wet.</p>

<p>To merge from Highway 17 to Highway 1 in Santa Cruz to continue south, you must merge three times on the dreaded "fish hook". This causes the beginning of the dreaded commute from "over the hill" to the coast for many. Congestion usually lasts M-F 3PM until 6PM, from just south of 41st Ave. on Highway 1, spilling back onto Highway 17 going south.</p>

<p>Highway 9 is a a slower, longer, and more scenic route over the mountains, but it can get congested, and is often subject to extended periods of closure due to landslide damage during the winter. It's also very popular with both bicyclists and motorcyclists, so if driving a car over it be sure to be vigilant.</p>

<p>A much more beautiful, but slower, approach to Santa Cruz is on <ref target="Pacific%20Coast%20Highway">Highway 1</ref>, either from the north, <ref target="San%20Francisco">San Francisco</ref> and <ref target="Pacifica">Pacifica</ref> (about 65 miles), or from the south, <ref target="Monterey%20%28California%29">Monterey</ref> and <ref target="Big%20Sur">Big Sur</ref> (about 35 miles). During stormy seasons, check for rare, but often long-term road closures, although Devil's Slide, the most notorious location for landslides, was bypassed by a tunnel several years ago.</p>

<p>To take public transportation there is a commuter shuttle, the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.scmtd.com/en/routes/schedules/systemschedule/17">Highway 17 Express</ref></hi> (Santa Cruz route 17; VTA route 970; Amtrak Thruway Motorcoach Rt 17), that runs from <ref target="San%20Jose_%28California%29%23By%20train">Diridon Station</ref>, in San Jose 7 days a week with connections to <ref target="https://www.capitolcorridor.org/">Amtrak Capitol Corridor</ref>, <ref target="http://www.caltrain.com">CalTrain</ref>, <ref target="http://www.acerail.com">Altmont Corridor Express</ref> and other <ref target="http://www.amtrak.com">Amtrak</ref> trains serving San Jose. There are also multiple lines that go south to <ref target="Watsonville">Watsonville</ref> 7 days a week. Greyhound also runs buses to the city. All these lines go to, or near to, the Santa Cruz Metro Center, which is in the downtown area.</p>

<p>The nearest major airport is in San Jose ( SJC ), but <ref target="San%20Francisco%20International%20Airport">San Francisco International Airport</ref> ( SFO ) and even <ref target="Oakland">Oakland</ref> ( OAK ) aren't much farther away, and sometimes have cheaper flights. The small regional airport in Monterey ( MRY ) has flights to major hubs (<ref target="Los%20Angeles">Los Angeles</ref>, San Francisco, <ref target="Sacramento">Sacramento</ref>), but in most cases San Jose is the best choice because of the greater choice of airlines and destinations. Scheduled airport shuttles provide service every few hours to San Jose, and less often to San Francisco. Caltrain also provides a route to the San Francisco airport, through a transfer with BART in <ref target="Millbrae">Millbrae</ref>. For private aircraft, there'a 2,000 ft. runway about 10 miles northwest of downtown, near Henry Cowell Redwoods State Park.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>The main downtown strip is pedestrian friendly, and it's a 20-minute stroll from there to the beach. Walking to the University of California Santa Cruz from downtown is a little more difficult, with bad or non-existent sidewalks and a very steep climb.</p>

<p>While driving is certainly an option (parking is tight, careful to not get ticketed), <ref target="http://www.scmtd.com">Santa Cruz Metro</ref> provides bus service.</p>

<p>Santa Cruz can be a wonderful town for town for cycling, but be careful because drivers are no better here than in many other places. Around town and along Highway 1 is easy, but roads in the Santa Cruz Mountains are steep, winding and challenging for many cyclists. Be careful. Collisions between bicycles and cars are often reported. A number of pedestrian and car collisions have also happened in the downtown area.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mission Santa Cruz</hi>, 126 High St, ☏ +1 831 425-5849 . Th-Sa 10AM to 4PM (&amp; Su during the summer); closed holidays. The original Mission Santa Cruz was dedicated by Fermin Lasuen in 1791 as the 12th <ref target="El%20Camino%20Real">California mission</ref>. In its early years, the mission suffered due to violence among the Indians. The original mission buildings (save one) fell down in an 1857 earthquake, and it is place was built a Catholic Church with the anglicized name Holy Cross Church. However, a replica of the old mission was constructed nearby at half-scale in the 1930s by a wealthy benefactor. This exists today as Santa Cruz Mission State Historic Park.</item>
</list>

 Free.


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Beach Boardwalk</hi>, 400 Beach St. 11AM to 10 or 11PM. Founded in 1907, it is the only original boardwalk amusement park still operating on the West Coast. It features one of the oldest wooden rollercoasters still in use in the US as well as numerous modern attractions. Entrance is free, rides cost between $2–4 each (but less than $1 on selected summer evenings). Day, month, and yearly passes available.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Municipal Wharf</hi>, 21 Municipal Wharf. Restaurants, gift shops, sea lions and pelicans, and great views.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mystery Spot</hi>, 465 Mystery Spot Rd (3 miles north of town; take Water St, then Market St, then Branciforte Drive). The famous ('as seen on TV') tourist trap, complete with anti-gravity cabin and amazing hillside of illusion. $6; $5 at the door. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Surfing Museum</hi>, 701 W Cliff Dr (in the lighthouse at Lighthouse Point). Th-M noon-4PM. Memorabilia from the introduction of surfing to California by Hawaiians in 1885 to the present day. A statue of an early surfer is a few yards from the museum. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Seymour Marine Discovery Center</hi>, 100 Shaffer Rd. End of Delaware Ave. Tu-Sa 10AM-5PM, Su noon-5PM. Has exhibits focusing on ocean conservation and marine science, big tanks full of native species, a guided tour with a dolphin overlook area, and amazing views of Monterey Bay at sunset. $6.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">University of California at Santa Cruz</hi> (UCSC) (On the hill at the north end of town). This UC campus has a smaller student population (except for the brand new campus in <ref target="Merced">Merced</ref>), with about 15,000 students. The main part of campus is spread over half of 2001 acres (8.1 km²), mostly covered with redwood forests with the occasional stunning view of the bay. There is an <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www2.ucsc.edu/arboretum/">UCSC Arboretum</ref></hi> specializing in native plants and plants from <ref target="Australia">Australia</ref>. Mountain bike and hiking trails criss-cross the upper part of campus, connecting <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.santacruzstateparks.org/parks/wilder/">Wilder Ranch State Park</ref> </hi> to <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.santacruzstateparks.org/parks/henrycowell/">Henry Cowell Redwoods State Park</ref> </hi> (<hi rend="italic">get a trail map and a parking permit from the kiosk as you enter campus</hi>). The <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://slugstore.ucsc.edu/">Bay Tree Bookstore</ref></hi> sells clothes with the UCSC mascot – the banana slug. The critters themselves are fairly common in the surrounding redwood forest - their bright yellow color tells would-be predators that their skin secretes a foul-tasting poison. Keep your eyes open for mountain lions seen (but rarely) in undeveloped parts of the campus.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Downtown Santa Cruz</hi>. Lots to see and do here all day and night; "SantaCruz" character mixed with some great restaurants and lots of cool shops. Mostly it's a great people watching center. The nightlife is worth sticking around for. Pacific Ave is the main street downtown.</item>
</list>
</text>
