<text id="autogum_voyage_doc484" title="Iraqi Kurdistan" shortTile="iraqi-kurdistan" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=15719" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Iraqi Kurdistan</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Kurdistan</hi> (<ref target="Kurdish">Kurdish</ref>: کوردستان) refers to portions of Turkey, Iraq, Iran and Syria, however only the Iraqi region of Kurdistan is discussed here. See the articles on <ref target="Turkey">Turkey</ref>, <ref target="Western%20Iran">Western Iran</ref> and <ref target="Syria">Syria</ref> for information regarding the other regions of Kurdistan.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Having been spared the war of 2003, Kurdistan-Iraq is a very different place from middle and southern Iraq. With a minimal level of terrorist activity and massive economic development, Kurdistan is fast becoming a "gateway to Iraq" with high levels of foreign investment and development of infrastructure and tourism.</p>

<p>Be careful when discussing nationalist issues which many Kurds feel strongly about. Also read up on the Al-Anfal campaign and chemical attack on the Kurds by Saddam Hussein to exterminate droves of Kurds in the late 1980s, an event which has colored the last few decades of Kurdish history. There are several powerful reminders of it, such as the Amna Suraka prison in Sulaymaniya.</p>

<p>And be careful about calling a Kurd Iraqi because they don't count themselves as Iraqi: even though they are Iraqi citizens by record, they say Kurds are from Kurdistan - 'the land of the Kurds' or from Mesopotamia - 'the land between the rivers'. Not Iraq, and recently the president of Kurdistan was claiming to announce the Kurdish State, which is a serious debate in the region. Many Kurds also consider it unjust that there is no independent Kurdistan.</p>

<p>The Kurdish society consists of a variety of religions and beliefs (such as Muslims, Christians, Jewish, Yazidis, Kakayis, Zoroastrians, Yarsanis, Hawaris, Ahli Haqs, etc.) all of which normally coexist peacefully.</p>

<p>In general, Kurdish people are very friendly and hospitable, you can make friends with anybody and start talking to anyone on the street, so be open to new experiences.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>Spring and fall are the best months to visit Iraqi Kurdistan, because temperatures are mild. Winters can be cold, whereas summers are likely too hot for most outdoor activities. The weather rarely gets extreme though, making Iraqi Kurdistan an attractive year round travel destination.</p>

<head>Orientation</head>

<p>Iraqi Kurdistan refers to the four northern Iraqi Provinces, which are autonomous of the central Iraqi government and ruled by the Kurdistan Regional Government (KRG). These provinces achieved de facto independence after an uprising in 1991 and their autonomy has now been enshrined into the Iraqi federal constitution. The three Kurdish Provinces are Duhok, Erbil, and Sulaymaniya. The KRG has applied for creating a fourth region around the city of Halabja.</p>

<p>Although the city Kirkuk is largely inhabited and controlled by Kurdish armed forces, <hi rend="italic">the Peshmenga</hi>, it is still not under official administration of the KRG. Kirkuk and parts of the Ninaveh and Diyala provinces are disputed. The Kurds claim that these places are originally Kurdish, but were subjected to harsh Arabisation by the ousted Ba'ath Party. The Kurds want these areas returned to Kurdish autonomy, something that has largely been realized during the ISIL rebellion in June 2014 after which the Kurdish armed forced took full control over the areas. However, in October 2017, Iraqi government forces pushed into these disputed areas and retook Kirkuk.</p>

<head>Cities</head>
<p>The major cities controlled by the Kurdish Regional Government (KRG) are</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> — the capital city of Kurdistan, its citadel Hawler is a <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20site">UNESCO World Heritage site</ref> .</item>
<item> — the town that was the scene for Saddam Hussein's gruesome gas attack that killed 5000 people in 1988 now holds a number of memorials, monuments and cemeteries commemorating the event.</item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> — is the centre of education and culture in Iraqi Kurdistan. The city features the best museums - the Amna Suraka and Slemani Museum, and a number of pleasant parks.</item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> – a tranquil, 2500-year-old Christian village.</item>
<item> – a 4000 year old town perched on the peak of a mountain, rumoured home of Biblical Magi, and confirmed home to Assyrian ruins.</item>
<item> — the famous caves in which the earliest human ceremonial burial site.</item>
<item> — a large man-made lake lying at an altitude of 900m. Great for Friday picnicking.</item>
<item> – beautiful mountain road between as a shortcut between Erbil and Iran.</item>
<item> – site of ancient cave paintings.</item>
<item> — valley. The "Holy See" of Yazidi faith.</item>
<item> – 4th century Syrian Orthodox Monastery, the oldest of its kind, overlooking Mosul in its horizon.</item>
<item> — the biggest national park in the Middle East, located in North Erbil, on the Zagros mountains.</item>
<item> — The only ski resort which is open in the region is accessible by a 4 km long Teleferic (cable car) from <ref target="Bekhal">Bekhal</ref>. Has a resort and activities park at 2,127 m above sea level.</item>
<item> — the largest astronomical observatory in Iraq with a 30 m telescope, staring into the night sky from Mount Korek.</item>
</list>


<head>Get in</head>
<p>Citizens of the <ref target="European%20Union">EU</ref>, <ref target="Australia">Australia</ref>, <ref target="Brazil">Brazil</ref>, <ref target="Canada">Canada</ref>, <ref target="Iceland">Iceland</ref>, <ref target="Japan">Japan</ref>, <ref target="Kuwait">Kuwait</ref>, <ref target="Lebanon">Lebanon</ref>, <ref target="Monaco">Monaco</ref>, <ref target="New%20Zealand">New Zealand</ref>, <ref target="Norway">Norway</ref>, <ref target="Qatar">Qatar</ref>, <ref target="San%20Marino">San Marino</ref>, <ref target="South%20Korea">South Korea</ref>, <ref target="Switzerland">Switzerland</ref>, the <ref target="United%20Arab%20Emirates">UAE</ref>, and <ref target="Vatican%20City">Vatican City</ref> are given a free stamp on arrival. This is valid for 30 days after arrival, which can be extended by reporting to the Residency Office within 30 days of arrival. This involves many forms to fill out, around $30 USD in fees as well as a compulsory blood test to check for hepatitis C and HIV. Be prepared to wait for around 2–3 hours throughout this whole process. Citizens of <ref target="Iran">Iran</ref> and <ref target="Turkey">Turkey</ref> are given a free stamp with a validity of 15 days after arrival.</p>
<p>Most other nationalities must produce a valid "Iraq – Kurdistan Region" visa upon arrival.</p>

<p>Border control at land borders is fairly strict. If you have a contact in Kurdistan, come armed with their name and address. If you don't, make sure you have a very good idea of what exactly you will be doing and where you will be staying. You are also more likely to get in if travelling with someone else, and if you are well-dressed.</p>

<p>A visa for Iraqi Kurdistan <hi rend="bold">can not</hi> be used to travel to other areas in Iraq, which includes <ref target="Mosul">Mosul</ref> as of 2019. When attempting to cross the Iraqi Kurdistan border, you will be sent back at the first military checkpoint encountered.</p>
</text>
