<text id="autogum_voyage_doc193" title="Montreal/Parc Jean-Drapeau" shortTile="montrealparc-jeandrapeau" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=22890" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Montreal/Parc Jean-Drapeau</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Parc Jean-Drapeau</hi> is a district in <ref target="Montreal">Montreal</ref>. It is comprised of the islands <hi rend="italic">Île Sainte-Helene</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Île Notre-Dame</hi> in the Saint Lawrence river. </p>

<head>By metro</head>
<p>The Yellow Line runs from Berri-UQAM in <ref target="Montreal/Downtown">Downtown</ref> to metro Jean-Drapeau, on Ile Notre Dame, just next to the Biosphere. </p>

<head>By ferry</head>
<p>Seasonal ferries run from the <ref target="Montreal/Old%20City">Old Port</ref>.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>The seasonal <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.stm.info/en/info/networks/bus/shuttle/line-769-south">769 La Ronde</ref></hi> shuttle connects Papineau metro station to La Ronde amusement park</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Access the island from Pont Jacques-Cartier at the north end of Île Sainte-Helene or pass by Habitat 67 and use Pont Condorde to the south. Parking is limited and expensive, running $10-15 flat rate depending on the season and events. Note that car access to and around the islands is cut off during Formula One races (obviously, since the road around Ile Notre Dame doubles as the race track) and other events.</p>

<head>By foot</head>
<p>There are a number of footpaths throughout the park, on both islands.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Two bus routes run from main terminal a few meters from the metro station: <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.stm.info/en/info/networks/bus/shuttle/line-767-east">767 La Ronde / La Plage</ref></hi> to La Ronde amusement park and the beach, and <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.stm.info/en/info/networks/bus/shuttle/line-777-west">777 Le Casino</ref></hi> to the casino.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Montreal Biosphère</hi>, 160 Chemin Tour-de-l'Isle, ☏ +1 514 283-5000 , toll-free: +1-855-773-8200 , ✉ info.biosphere@ec.gc.ca . Jun 1-Sep 6 10AM-5PM daily, Sep 7-May 31 Th-Su 10AM-5PM. The former United States pavilion from Expo 67, a geodesic dome designed by R. Buckminster Fuller. It now houses an Environment Canada museum dedicated to water and the environment. $15 adult / $12 senior / $10 student (18+) / free for youth (0-17). </item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Habitat 67</hi>, 2600 avenue Pierre-Dupuy (take Chemin du Moulins exit from Hwy 10 south), ☏ +1 514-866-5971 . This visually striking residential building was created by architect Moshe Safdie for Expo 67. The result was an amazingly modern dwelling that challenged the way architects created urban homes. Compared alternately to a beehive, a Taos pueblo, and a crystalline growth, the complex's 154 units are composed of prefabricated concrete cubes assembled on site. The apartments here are highly prized and a number of prominent Montrealers make Habitat 67 their home. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Formula 1 Grand Prix</hi> (Circuit Gilles Villeneuve), 2170 Pierre-Dupuy Avenue, office 100, ☏ +1 514-350-0000 , fax: +1 514-350-0007 , ✉ dfauteux@octanemanagement.ca . The Canadian Grand Prix is a must-see for any petrolhead or sports fan. The annual event, taking place on Île Notre-Dame, attracts up to 100,000 people, and spans an entire weekend, with practice and qualifying on Friday and Saturday and the race on Sunday. Weekend admission is $126, and grandstand seats are upwards of $267. Wheelchair accessible seats are available at a lower price.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Musée Stewart</hi> (Stewart Museum), 20 Chemin du Tour de l'isle Montréal, ☏ +1 514 861-6701 . Tu-Su 10AM-5PM. $10 general admission, $8 senior/student, free for children.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Montreal Casino</hi> (Casino de Montréal), 1 Avenue du Casino, ☏ +1 514-392-2746 . 24 hours daily. Opened in 1993, this is the largest <ref target="Gambling">casino</ref> in Canada. Open to visitors aged 18 or older.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Public pool</hi> (Complexe aquatique de l'île Sainte-Hélène). Open daily 16 Jun-24 Aug 11AM-4PM, Weekends 25 Aug-14 Sep. Ages 6-13 $2.50, adult $5, 65+ $4.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Beach park</hi>, ☏ +1 514 872-6120 . 20 Jun-24 Aug, 10AM-7PM.. Clean water and sand attracts families to this small, man-made beach at the south tip of Ile Notre Dame. Activities include a playground, volleyball, and watercraft rentals. There are bathrooms, changing rooms, and a snack bar. Ages 14 and up $<date when="2013-08-06">8, 6-13</date> $4, 65+ $7, Family $20. Season passes available.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dragon Boats</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rowing</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Waterskiing and wakeboarding</hi> (L'école provinciale de ski nautique).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Île Notre-Dame lake and at the Olympic Basin.</hi>, ☏ +1 514-592-6552 . Summer. $35/hr. Reservations required.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">La Ronde</hi>.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p>Picnicking is the most common form of dining on the islands, but there are a few snack bars scattered around (open Jun-Sep). For sit-down dining, head to the Casino on Ile Ste-Helen.</p>

<head>Budget</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Snack Bar Espace-Bouffe</hi> (métro Île Ste-Hélène, just outside Jean-Drapeau metro). 8AM-8PM. Basic chips-and-hot-dog snack bar. $1 and up.</item>
</list>


<head>Mid-range</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">La Bonne Carte</hi>, 1 avenue du Casino (located in the Casino, third floor). Lunch Mon-Fri 11AM-2:30PM, Dinner Sun-Thu 4:30PM-closing, Brunch Sat 11AM-2:30PM Sun 11AM-3:30PM. Lunch, dinner, and weekend brunch are offered at the Casino buffet. Brunch $19.95, Lunch $15.95, Dinner $25.95.</item>
</list>


<head>Splurge</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nuances</hi>, 1 avenue du Casino (located in the Casino, top floor), ☏ +1 514-392-2708 . Open Sun-Thu 5:30PM-11PM, Fri-Sat 5:30PM-11:30PM. French haute cuisine with a Quebec edge served far removed from the noise of the casino. Choose between lobster, Quebec lamb, loin of deer, and other season specialties or try the chefs "discovery menu". Note, no exceptions are made to the Casinos: strict 18 &amp; up policy. Mains $40-$45.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Festin du Gouverneur</hi> (in the Stewart Museum), ☏ +1 514-879-1141 . Apr-Oct 6PM and 8:30PM; 1 Nov-31 Mar, 6PM; Dec Sun-Thu 7PM and Fri-Sat 6:30PM and 8:30PM. Set menu (meat, fish, and veggie options) with historical reenactment show. $50 adults/$25 under 12.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>
<p>There are no hotels on the islands, and you will therefore have to cross the Saint Lawrence river to find somewhere to sleep. The closest place to look would be <ref target="Montreal/Old%20Montreal">Old Montreal</ref> or <ref target="Montreal/South%20West">South West Montreal</ref> west of the islands, or Saint-Lambert east of the islands. But given the fact that Montreal Casino is open 24 hours daily, why would you want to sleep?</p>
</text>
