<text id="autogum_voyage_doc46" title="Bengbu" shortTile="bengbu" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=3398" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bengbu</head>

<p>Bengbu (蚌埠; Bèngbù; literally "Clam Wharf" or "Oyster Quay") is a prefecture-level city with a populati<date when="469-03-01">on of 3,469,700</date> (including rural area) in northern <ref target="Anhui">Anhui</ref> Province.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>The city is on the Jinghu Railway, with hourly direct trains from Beijing, Shanghai and other large cities.</p>
<p>Bengbu South Station is in the south of Donghai Avenue, Beijing-Shanghai high-speed rail to the first station, east China Central Station, one of the Beijing-Shanghai high-speed rail seven central hub station, while the high-speed railway linking Beijing and Taiwanco mussels passenger line. The early stages of the Beijing-Shanghai high-speed rail operating speed of 300 km, the initial operation Bengbu to Nanjing can be reached in about 35 minutes.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Taxis start at ¥5 for 2.5 km, and ¥1.2 per km after that.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>Bengbu is the birthplace of the Huagudeng Sizhou drama, has been declared the country and the world intangible cultural heritage.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bengbu Museum</hi> (蚌埠市博物馆), Civic Plaza, Donghai Avenue (东海大道市民广场), ☏ +86 552 2042312 . 9AM-5PM Tu-Sun (Closed on Mondays and Public Holidays). Free.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<p>Bengbu is the provenance of the House of Flying Daggers, Farewell My Concubine story Gaixia ancient battlefield Gaixia, to pay homage; contains white Ruquan, Bian and Tung Kai Mother Stone, Yu Temple Jing Tu Lanwins; Huaihe River culture Square, and the musical fountain Metro night; covered by the Long Lake and the awl mountain Scenic Area, including the soup and the tomb of the pearl bridge, Long Lake bridge, the Longhu style garden, and martyrs' cemetery, including Longhu scenery; city River, Huaihe RiverLiu view of the scenery on both sides Huai River; the center of the Pearl Garden dawn; According to legend, Yu Yu dukes princes Tu Yu Kuaihuai ancient executive instruments of peace, the nations "; Wang Huai tower, public lake Zhang Gong foothills; the Tuohu crab and mussels mountain sunset.</p>

<head>Buy</head>
<p>Antique jade, wine and Anhui, the arrival of tobacco, a product of Huangshan smoke, the Guzhen peanut, Huaiyuan asparagus, peppermint oil, pomegranate. Five river crabs.</p>

<head>Eat</head>
<p>A local specialty is river crayfish cooked with lots of spices. There is a whole block near the center of town that consists mainly of restaurants serving this and other dishes. Turn right at the end of that block, there is a nice small trendy restaurant on the right. Specialties are ice cream and Japanese/Taiwan style light meals. The jiaozi are excellent.</p>

<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Guest House</hi>, ☏ +86 15921173717 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Guest House</hi>, ☏ +86 15014035894 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Guest House</hi>, ☏ +86 13430742672 .</item>
</list>
</text>
