<text id="autogum_voyage_doc128" title="Montreal/Old Montreal" shortTile="montrealold-montreal" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=22886" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Montreal/Old Montreal</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Old Montreal</hi> (French: <hi rend="italic">Vieux-Montréal</hi>) is what many visitors come to <ref target="Montreal">Montreal</ref> for: old cobblestoned streets lined with buildings dating from the 17th through 19th centuries, grand old French restaurants, history museums, and the riverfront Old Port. That's not to say that Old Montreal is completely removed from the rest of Montreal — back a few blocks from the mimes and steakhouses, you'll find warehouses converted to boutique shops and loft apartments.</p>

<p>During the summer, Place Jacques-Cartier is packed with street performers and restaurant terraces overflowing with tourists. Winter presents a much more subdued scene, with bundled figures hurrying from gallery to restaurant to hotel in the cold and snow.</p>

<p>It is a mistake to call Old Montreal the "Old City" or "Old Town". Locals do not call it this, only guide books do.</p>

<head>By metro</head>
<p>Old Montreal is served by three metro stations — <hi rend="bold">Square-Victoria</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Champ-de-Mars</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Place-d'Armes</hi>. They are a short walk into the heart of things, but there's a bit of a hill.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Street parking</hi> is scarce and runs $3 per hour. <hi rend="bold">Parking complexes</hi> run $6/1hr, $15 max, $20 for 12-24 hours.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Clock Tower Quay</hi>, enter from rue Berri or rue de la Commune est.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Montréal Science Centre</hi>, take boulevard Saint-Laurent or rue de la Commune.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Alexandra Quay</hi>, either rue de la Callière or rue de la Commune ouest.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Complexe Chaussegros-de-Léry</hi>, next to Champ-de-Mars metro, has over a thousand spots.</item>
</list>


<p>A few small commercial lots operate around City Hall for $20/day. Note that the streets are small and one-way, and thronged with pedestrians in the summer. Plans are in the works to turn rue Saint-Paul into a pedestrian walk, further complicating things.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Buses don't run in Old Montreal itself, but they can get you within a few blocks.</p>

<p>From the <ref target="Montreal/Plateau">Plateau</ref>, the 55 runs down Saint-Laurent to Saint-Jacques and up St. Urbain and the 30 runs down rue Berri (1 block east of Saint-Denis). From downtown, take the 75 de la Commune, get off at McGill/Wellington: it's then a four block walk to the edge of the cobblestone.</p>

<head>By boat</head>
<p>Ferries (<hi rend="italic">navettes</hi>) run to and from <ref target="Montreal/Parc%20Jean-Drapeau">Île Sainte-Hélène</ref> May to October and to the suburb of <ref target="Longueuil">Longueuil</ref> on the south shore.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Old Montreal is small enough that walking is usually the best way to get around. Sidewalks are narrow and the streets cobblestone, making slow going for wheelchairs and strollers.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Horse drawn carriages</hi> (Calèche). Carriage tours departed from Place d’Armes and the top and bottom of Place Jacques-Cartier. Operation was suspended for a year in 2016 and is expected to end permanently at the end of 2019. $45 for 30 min, $75 for 1 hour.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Segway Tours</hi>, ☏ +1 514 613-3300 , ✉ info@ecorecreo.ca . Guided tours on a Segway upright scooter, which is a novelty in itself.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Old Montréal: The Official Walking Tour</hi>, 110 rue Notre-Dame ouest (in front of Notre-Dame Basilica). May-Oct 11AM and 1PM. This 90 minute tour will get you oriented. $17.50 adult / $15.50 student and senior / $8.50 child.</item>
</list>


<head>Bike rentals</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Vélo Aventure</hi>, quai des Convoyeurs, ☏ +1 514 288-8356 . Summer bike and roller blade rentals.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Montréal On Wheels</hi>, ☏ +1 514 866-0633 . Bikes, tandem bikes, roller blades, and accessories such as baby seats. Bike tours also offered. Weekdays $8/hr; weekends $9/hr..</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Vieux-Port</hi> (Old Port), South of rue Saint-Antoine between rue McGill and rue Berri (metro Champ-de-Mars or Place-d'Armes). The Old Port is a large waterfront green space with attractions such as Cirque du Soleil, the Montreal Science Center, the Labyrinth, the Clock Tower, and a large outdoor audio-visual stage which is the site for the Canada Day fireworks.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Place Jacques-Cartier</hi>. Pedestrian street filled with street artists and musicians, and there are numerous fine restaurants and private art galleries nearby. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bonsecours Market</hi> (Marché Bonsecours), 350 rue Saint-Paul est (between rue Bonsecours and rue Saint-Claude; metro Champ-de-Mars). 10AM-6PM daily.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Notre-Dame Basilica</hi> (Basilique Notre-Dame), 116 rue Notre-Dame ouest (at place d'Armes/rue Saint-Sulpice; metro Place-d'Armes), ☏ +1 514 842-2925 . Visitor hours M-F 8AM-4:30PM, Sa 8AM-4PM, Su 12:30PM-4PM. Probably the city's most spectacular church, a gem of Victorian Gothic. Service is at 5PM daily and on Sunday morning. Entrance is free for worship, but donations are suggested. During service, the organ music is not to be missed. While it shouldn't have to be mentioned, tourists should be respectful during services. Note that photography is not allowed during services. 20 minute guided tours offered in French or English. Adults $5, children 7-17 $4, children under 7 free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Montreal Clock Tower</hi> (Tour de l'Horloge de Montréal), Quai de l'Horloge (metro Champ-de-Mars), ☏ +1 514 496-7678 . Early May and September (after Labour Day): Sa-Su 10AM-7PM; mid May-mid June and mid August-Labour Day: M-Th 10AM-7PM, F-Su 10AM-9PM; mid June-mid August: 10AM-9PM daily. Also known as the <hi rend="bold">Sailors' Memorial Clock</hi>, the clock tower was built between 1919-1922 as a memorial to sailors lost at sea. Its clock mechanism is similar to <ref target="Big%20Ben">Big Ben</ref>'s and was known for its accuracy; sailors would often set their watches by it. From May to September, visitors can climb the 192 steps to the top of the tower for a good view of Old Montreal and the St. Lawrence River.</item>
</list>

 Free. 

<head>Museums</head>
<p>Old Montreal has the largest concentration of historical homes and museums — plus the ultra-modern Montréal Science Centre.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Marguerite-Bourgeoys Museum and Notre-Dame-de-Bon-Secours Chapel</hi> (Musée Marguerite-Bourgeoys et Chapelle Notre-Dame-de-Bon-Secours), 400 rue Saint-Paul est (at rue Bonsecours; metro Champ-de-Mars), ☏ +1 514 282-8670 , fax: +1 514 282-8672 , ✉ info@marguerite-bourgeoys.com . May-Oct: Tu-Su 10AM-5:30PM; Oct-Apr: Tu-Su 11AM—3:30PM. Built in 1655, Notre-Dame-de-Bon-Secours, is the oldest stone church in Montreal. The museum houses artifacts from the church's history and pays tribute to Marguerite Bourgeoys, Montreal's first teacher. $3 child / $4 student / $6 adult / $4 senior / $12 family.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pointe-à-Callière</hi> (Montréal Museum of Archeology and History), 350 place Royale (at place d'Youville/rue de la Commune; metro Champ-de-Mars), ☏ +1 514 872-9150 . Labour Day to 24 June: Tu-F 10AM-5PM, Sa-Su 11AM-5PM; 25 June to Labour Day: M-F 10AM-6PM, Sa-Su 11AM-6PM. A modern museum built over the ruins of Montreal's first settlement, Pointe à Callière. This museum uses audiovisual technology as well as surrounding archaeological remains to tell the story of Montreal from the first natives to the present day. $20 adult / $16 seniors (65+) / $12 student (13-30 with ID) / $7 youth (6-12) / free for children (0-5) / $42 family.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sir George-Étienne Cartier National Historic Site</hi> (Lieu historique national de Sir-George-Étienne-Cartier), 458 rue Notre-Dame est (at rue Berri; metro Champ-de-Mars), ☏ +1 514 283-2282 . 6 Apr-19 June and 7 Sep-23 Dec: W-Su 10AM-5PM; 20 June-4 Sep: 10AM-5:30PM daily. Reconstruction of two 19th century Victorian homes. $3.90 adults, $3.40 seniors (65+), $1.90 youth (6-16), $9.80 families/groups (up to seven people with a maximum of two adults).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Montréal Science Centre</hi> (Centre des sciences de Montréal), 333 rue de la Commune ouest (at boul Saint-Laurent on Quai King-Edward; metro Place-d'Armes, bus 55 or 515), ☏ +1 514 496-4724 , toll-free: +1-877-496-4724 . 10AM-5PM daily; check listings for IMAX movie times. Interactive science museum and IMAX theater. IMAX screenings $8.50 child / $10.50 teen / $11.50 adult / $10.50 senior; exhibitions $8.50 child / $13 teen / $15 adult / $13 senior / $40 family; see website for details.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Centre d'histoire de Montréal</hi>, 335 place d'Youville (at rue Saint-Pierre; metro Square-Victoria), ☏ +1 514 872-3207 , fax: +1 514 872-9645 , ✉ chm@ville.montreal.qc.ca . W-Su 10AM-5PM. Covering the history of Montreal from its founding in 1535. The museum is housed in a former fire station that dates from 1903. $6 adults, $5 seniors, $4 children (6-17) and students, $15 families, free for children under 6. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bank of Montréal Museum</hi>, 129 rue Saint-Jacques ouest (at place d'Armes; metro Place-d'Armes), ☏ +1 514 877-6810 . M-F 10AM-4PM. Hands-on museum focusing on the history of banking in Montreal. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Château Ramezay Museum</hi>, 280 rue Notre-Dame est (at rue Saint-Claude; metro Champ-de-Mars), ☏ +1 514 861-3708 . Jun-Oct 10AM-6PM daily. 18th century Governor's residence and gardens full of historical artifacts from daily life. $4 child / $5 student / $8 adults / $6 senior / $16.50 families. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">DHC/ART</hi>, 451 rue Saint-Jean (at rue du Saint-Sacrement; metro Square-Victoria), ☏ +1 514 286-6626 . W-F noon-7PM, Sa-Su 11AM-6PM. A privately endowed foundation, DHC/ART is a permanent location for exciting and relevant temporary visual arts exhibitions and projects. Free.</item>
</list>
</text>
