<text id="autogum_voyage_doc464" title="Diving in East Timor" shortTile="diving-east-timor" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=9597" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Diving in East Timor</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://timor-leste.gov.tl/%3Fp%3D547%26amp%3Blang%3Den">Timor-Leste</ref></hi> has some of the best <ref target="dive%20sites">dive sites</ref> in the world due to its location, warm waters, minimal tourist trade and lack of commercial fishing or heavy industry. Situated in the <ref target="Coral%20Triangle">Coral Triangle</ref>, Timor is surrounded by deep water (about 2,500 m between <ref target="Liqui%C3%A7%C3%A1">Liquiçá</ref> and <ref target="Alor%20Island">Alor Island</ref>, <ref target="Indonesia">Indonesia</ref>) that gives home to an abundance of coral and fish life, including the annual migration of whales through the Ombai Strait and Wetar Strait according to a <ref target="http://www.cdu.edu.au/sites/default/files/research/docs/project3.pdf">Marine Megafauna Survey</ref> in Timor Leste of June 2009. However, those same deep waters can cause strong currents at even the most protected sites so check the <ref target="http://easytide.ukho.gov.uk/easytide/EasyTide/SelectPrediction.aspx%3FPortID%3D5418">Tidal Predictions</ref> beforehand. High tide and days of smaller variation are usually better. Always have a good look at the water before entering.</p>

<p>While many of the dive sites can be reached by land, some of these entry points require a long walk over coral, a long surface swim or a boat.</p>

<p>Listed below are some of the popular dive sites in <ref target="Timor-Leste">Timor-Leste</ref>, but there are plenty more if you are adventurous or have a boat to get to those hard to reach places.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Remember, always dive safely</hi> and in accordance with current dive regulations and procedures. Note <ref target="Dive_Sites_of_Timor-Leste%23Security">security precautions</ref> topside, cultural sensitivities such as the sacred trees at K41 and private property issues. </p>

<head>Nun's Tree</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">General.</hi> (This information is unconfirmed and maybe out of date).</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Location.</hi> Coordinates: 8°37'1"S 125°10'48"E see <ref target="http://wikimapia.org/%23lat%3D-8.6169444%26amp%3Blon%3D125.18%26amp%3Bz%3D17%26amp%3Bl%3D0%26amp%3Bm%3Db%26amp%3Btag%3D570">Wikimapia Satellite Map</ref>. Near Nun's clinic.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Entry.</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Profile.</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Points of interest.</hi> Large giant clam (~1 meter), black tipped reef sharks, turtles.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Topside.</hi></p>

<head>Seal Rock Maubara</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">General.</hi> This is a nice dive, easily found, but <hi rend="bold">dangerous currents</hi> in all directions have been encountered, including a strong downward/northerly one. Until more data is collected, this is considered an <hi rend="bold">advanced adventure dive for experienced divers</hi>. Safety marker buoys and gloves in particular are essential. Tight buddy teams and conservative diving well within no-deco and minimum air limits are also recommended given the potential for sudden changes in the situation. A stand-by boat would be optimal. Have a good look at the water's surface before entering.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Location.</hi> Coordinates: 8°36'41"S 125°11'33"E see <ref target="http://wikimapia.org/%23lat%3D-8.6117254%26amp%3Blon%3D125.1930785%26amp%3Bz%3D16%26amp%3Bl%3D0%26amp%3Bm%3Db%26amp%3Btag%3D570">Wikimapia Satellite Map</ref>. From Maubara Fort, drive 1.2 km west and look for the large seal shaped rock on the right. Park on the road.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Entry.</hi> Gear up at the car, negotiate a low wall, and go straight in on either side of the rock. Although an easy entry initially, at low tide the coral is very close to the surface, so fin-up early or dive on high tide.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Profile.</hi> The slope dips away slowly at first, then drops off quickly to 30 m or more. Follow the shoreline and enjoy nice coral gardens with lots of "bombies" and creatures to see including bat fish, nudibranchs, flute fish, lobsters and others. On the west side of Seal Rock there is plenty to see both at depth and in the shallows, but note safety issues above. As of June 2012 the east side is yet to be explored.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Top Side.</hi> There is plenty of parking beside the road, but no shade. However, <ref target="Maubara">Maubara</ref>, its shade and amenities are close by.</p>

<head>Maubara Church aka Kindergarten</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">General.</hi> Although getting mixed reviews, there is still plenty to see on this coral slope with some good gardens and lots of creatures to be seen. In close proximity to <ref target="Maubara">Maubara</ref> (see “topside”, below) and with plenty of shady parking, this is a great place for a picnic, sun-baking, snorkelling and diving.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Location.</hi> Coordinates: 8°36'36"S 125°12'7"E, see <ref target="http://wikimapia.org/%23lat%3D-8.6106821%26amp%3Blon%3D125.2021158%26amp%3Bz%3D17%26amp%3Bl%3D0%26amp%3Bm%3Db%26amp%3Btag%3D570">Wikimapia Satellite Map</ref>. From <ref target="Liqui%C3%A7%C3%A1">Liquiçá</ref>, drive through <ref target="Maubara">Maubara</ref> past the fort, cross the small river, past the Church and an old, disused, chalet style building on the right. Immediately after that building, turn right onto the track leading to the beach and large shady trees, about 150 m west of the Church.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Entry.</hi> Easy entry straight out from the car parking area (NNW), although better to walk west for 50 m before entering, over sand and small rocks.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Profile.</hi> Enter, swim out 50 – 100 m then turn west along the lovely coral slope, sprinkled with sandy patches, plenty of bombies (coral outcrops) and an abundance of sea life. Beware of currents on this semi-exposed site. Average depth 15 m, max 28 m.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Points of interest.</hi> Bat fish, lion fish, assorted nudibranchs, crabs, the occasional spotted ray or shark, and dolphins and whales (November to January).</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Topside.</hi> At Maubara there are local products on sale at the road side stalls. The historic Dutch fort is usually open for inspection and the restaurant within it serves a good meal or coffee quickly and at reasonable prices, under the shade of some magnificent trees. Be prepared for local spectators and curious children whilst on the beach!</p>

<head>Maubara Fort</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">General.</hi> This infrequently dived location has some good coral on a sloping, sandy bottom, although parts of it have been washed away.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Location.</hi> Coordinates: 8°36'34"S 125°12'15"E, see <ref target="http://wikimapia.org/%23lat%3D-8.6098653%26amp%3Blon%3D125.2046478%26amp%3Bz%3D17%26amp%3Bl%3D0%26amp%3Bm%3Db%26amp%3Btag%3D570">Wikimapia Satellite Map</ref>.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Entry.</hi> Entry in front of the fort, down the steep steps of the sea wall and out over the easy entry sandy bottom.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Profile.</hi> The usual profile is to head straight out (NW) over the gradual sandy slope, then turn right and follow the slope roughly east/SE until ready to turn around. Average depth 8 m, max 18 m.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Points of interest.</hi> Large nudibranchs, some “spanish dancing worms”, some unusual soft corals, big shrimps, eels, clams and some larger fish.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Topside.</hi> As per Maubara Church, however there is no shade close to the entry point.</p>

<head>Bubble Beach</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">General.</hi> Although difficult to find underwater, this is worth the effort. Like most dive sites around Timor-Leste, the currents can vary from calm to hazardous and visibility can vary from stunning to poor. A fence effectively denies access to the beach, although a number of dives have been undertaken when the fence has collapsed or divers have walked from the road to the beach.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Location.</hi> Coordinates: 8°34'30"S 125°22'7"E, see <ref target="http://wikimapia.org/%23lat%3D-8.5761942%26amp%3Blon%3D125.3690565%26amp%3Bz%3D17%26amp%3Bl%3D0%26amp%3Bm%3Db%26amp%3Btag%3D570">Wikimapia Satellite Map</ref>, about 30 km from Dili and about 4 km before Liquica. After coming over a headland with a religious station on it, the dive site is in front of an old, walled Indonesian memorial.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Entry.</hi> Nice sandy slope.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Profile.</hi> Head straight out (NNW) from the old Indonesian memorial on a bearing of (needs information)° for about (needs information) m to find the bombies and, possibly, the sharks at about 30 m depth. Alternatively, head NW until the slope drops away to a maximum of about 18 m and turn due west. The NE profile drops to about 27 m and is mostly sand.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Points of interest.</hi> Large, picturesque bombies and soft corals on a sandy bottom at about 30 m (straight out) or 15 to 5 m (half left). In places, the sand is warm and bubbles leak from the sea bed (needs information). Sharks, barracuda, lobster, nudibranchs, garden eels, blue spotted rays, triggers, puffers, morays, lizards, squirrels, parrots, angels and butterfly fish.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Topside.</hi> No shade close to the entry point – fence</p>
</text>
