<text id="autogum_voyage_doc50" title="Tabriz" shortTile="tabriz" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=35017" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tabriz</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Tabriz</hi> (<ref target="Persian%20phrasebook">Persian</ref>: تبریز, <ref target="Azerbaijani%20phrasebook">Azerbaijani</ref>: Təbriz) is the capital of East Azerbaijan province, in the <ref target="Iranian%20Azerbaijan">Azerbaijan region</ref> of <ref target="Iran">Iran</ref>. It is a modern industrialized Iranian city with signs of civilization dating back 2,500 years. Having some of most famous museums, holding some of the cultural events, and harboring a couple of the most prestigious Iranian universities, the city is considered a major hub for science and culture in Iran. Tabriz was named by the Organization of Islamic Conference as the "city of the Islamic world tourism" for 2018.</p>

<head>People</head>
<p>The majority of the city's population are Iranian Azerbaijanis, followed by Persians, Armenians, Assyrians, and other people of the Caucasus.</p>

<head>Geography</head>
<p>Situated at an altitude of 1,340 meters above sea level, 619 km northwest of <ref target="Tehran">Tehran</ref>, it was the second largest city in Iran until the late 1960s. It is a former capital of Persia, and had a population of 1,400,000 according to 1992 census. Tabriz is in a valley to the north of the long ridge of Mount Sahand. The valley opens out into a plain that slopes down gently to the northern end of Lake Orumieh, 60 km to the west. The 160-km long Aji ,Chai or Talkheh River is the major river of the city, formed by merging of three smaller rivers, namely the Ab Nahand, Quri Chai, and Ojan Chai, all of which originate from the Sabalan Mountain and the heights in the southeastern part of the town. The river and streams join the Orumieh Lake after passing through the valleys between the Sorkhband and Yekkeh Chin mountain north of Tabriz and Osku district. Mehran River or Maidan Chai, also called Liqvan River, originates from the peaks between Karim and Sultan mountains overlooking the Liqvan village (a major center of cheese production in Iran) near Esparakhoun and Qeshlaq. Its worst natural disadvantage, however, is its vulnerability to earthquakes, one of which utterly destroyed the city in 858. Rebuilt in a minor key, it was again devastated in 1041, when more than 40,000 people lost their lives.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>By virtue of its situation, Tabriz has a continental climate with low humidity (average annual rain fall is 288 mm). It has a modestly warm summer climate and a severely cold winter.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>The town has a long and checkered history. Although the early history of Tabriz is shrouded in legend and mystery, the town's origins are believed to date back to distant antiquity, perhaps even before the Sassanian era (224-651 AD). The oldest stone tablet with a reference to Tabriz is that of Sargon II, the Assyrian king. The tablet refers to a place called Tauri Castle and Tarmkis. The historians believe that this castle was situated on the site of the present Tabriz. It was the capital of Azarbin the 3rd century AD and again under the Mongol Ilkhanid dynasty (1256-13 53), although for some time Maragheh supplanted it. During the reign of Aqa Khan of the Ilkhanids, as well as under the reign of Ghazan Khan, Tabriz reached the peak of its glory and importance. Many great artists and philosophers from all over the world traveled to Tabriz. During this same period, Khajeh Rashid od-Din Fazlollah, the learned historian and Minister of Ghazan Khan, built the famous Rob'e Rashidi center.</p>

<p>In 1392, after the end of Mongol rule, the town was sacked by Tamerlane. It was soon restored under the Turkman tribe of the Qara Qoyunlu, who established a short-lived local dynasty. Under the Safavids it rose from regional to national capital for a short period, but the second of the Safavid kings, Shah Tahmasb, moved the capital to Qazvin because of the vulnerability of Tabriz to Ottoman attacks. The town then went into a period of decline, fought over by the Iranians, Ottomans and Russians and struck by earthquake and disease.</p>

<p>Tabriz was the residence of the crown prince under the Qajar kings, themselves of Turkish stock, but the town did not return to prosperity until the second half of the 19th century. The greatest boost to Tabriz came with the opening up of Persia to the West at the turn of this century, when it became the main staging post between the interior of Iran and the Black Sea and, for a short time, the economic capital. In 1908 it was the center of a revolt against Mohammad Ali Shah, which was only put down with the brutal intervention of the Russians.</p>

<p>In the second Irano-Russian War the city was occupied by the Tsar's troops. However, it was returned to Iran following the signing of the Turkmanchai Treaty, a peace and trade settlement that ended the Irano-Russian War of 1826-1828. The Iranian Constitutional Revolution originated in Tabriz and culminated during the reign of Mohammad Ali Shah of Qajar dynasty (1779-1925). Sattar Khan and Baqer Khan were the two most prominent leading figures behind the movement. Tabriz was occupied by Russians several times in the first half of the 20th century, including most of both world wars. A railway line to the border at Jolfa, built by the expansionist Russians, has been of little importance, but it increased in significance in the 1990s as a result of Iran's friendlier relations with its northern neighbors.</p>

<head>Talk</head>
<ref target="Azerbaijani">Azerbaijani</ref>, a Turkic language, is the primary language spoken by most Tabrizis, although many people, especially the younger generation, can communicate in <ref target="Persian">Persian</ref> and moderate to advanced <ref target="English">English</ref>.

<head>Get in</head>

<p>Tabriz is 310 km southeast of <ref target="Bazargan">Bazargan</ref> (at the Iran — <ref target="Turkey">Turkey</ref> frontier), 159 km south of <ref target="Jolfa">Jolfa</ref> on the Iran — <ref target="Azerbaijan">Azerbaijan</ref> Republic border, and can be reached by road, rail (742 km from <ref target="Tehran">Tehran</ref>, with connections to Europe and <ref target="Moscow">Moscow</ref>), air from Tehran, <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref> and other major cities in the region, and highway (Highway number 1 connects Tabriz to Tehran).</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tabriz International Airport</hi> ( TBZ ), Bolvar-e-Shahid Khalaban Babayi (10 km from the city center), ☏ +98 411 523 4705 . This is a hub airport for Ata Airlines. </item>
</list>

<p>Airport bus #136 goes to airport from Motahhari St. every 30-40 minutes. Another option is getting a taxi.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Ahwaz">Ahwaz</ref> operated by <ref target="http://www.iranair.com/">Iran Air</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Bandar%20Abbas">Bandar Abbas</ref> operated by <ref target="http://www.iranair.com/">Iran Air</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Isfahan">Isfahan</ref> operated by <ref target="http://www.iranair.com/">Iran Air</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Mashhad">Mashhad</ref> operated by <ref target="http://www.ataair.ir/">ATA air</ref>, Iran Air Tours, <ref target="http://iaa.ir/en/">Iran Aseman</ref> and Zagros Airlines</item>
<item> <ref target="Shiraz">Shiraz</ref> - Mon and Fri, operated by <ref target="http://iaa.ir/en/">Iran Aseman</ref> . Fare is 2,200,000 rials for 1-way.</item>
<item> Daily direct flights to <ref target="Tehran">Tehran</ref> (Mehrabad Airport) by <ref target="http://www.iranair.com/">Iran Air</ref>, <ref target="http://iaa.ir/en/">Iran Aseman</ref> and other companies. Fare is 490,000 rials for 1-way.</item>
</list>


<p><hi rend="bold">International direct</hi> flights to the following destinations exist:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Baghdad">Baghdad</ref> - F and M, operated by <ref target="http://www.ataair.ir/">ATA air</ref>.</item>
<item> <ref target="Baku">Baku</ref> - Tu and Sa, operated by Kish Air.</item>
<item> <ref target="Damascus">Damascus</ref>.</item>
<item> <ref target="Dubai">Dubai</ref> - Tu and Sa, operated by Kish Air (around 200 USD for round trip).</item>
<item> <ref target="Gaziantep">Gaziantep</ref> - Tu, operated by Sky Airlines.</item>
<item> <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref> 13 flights per week, operated by Turkish airlines (7 flights), <ref target="http://www.iranair.com/">Iran Air</ref> (2 flights) and <ref target="http://www.ataair.ir/">ATA air</ref> (4 flights). Fare is around 250 USD for a round trip.</item>
<item> <ref target="Tbilisi">Tbilisi</ref> 2 flights per week, operated by <ref target="http://www.ataair.ir/">ATA air</ref>.</item>
</list>
</text>
