<text id="autogum_voyage_doc379" title="Rugby football" shortTile="rugby-football" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=139519" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rugby football</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Rugby football</hi> is a game named for the school in the English town of <ref target="Rugby%20%28England%29">Rugby</ref>. There are two main versions: <hi rend="bold">rugby union</hi> with 15 players a side (with a 7-a-side variant), and <hi rend="bold">rugby league</hi> with 13 players a side (with 7-a-side and 9-a-side variants). Rugby union is played in many countries, whereas rugby league is little played beyond Australia, Papua New Guinea, the south of France and the north of England.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>Many towns in Britain had traditional ball games, but the rules were entirely local and unwritten, and games were mob affairs akin to pitched battles. In the early 19th century, it still wasn't agreed whether you were meant to kick or throw the ball. The legend goes that during a match at Rugby School in 1823, young William Webb Ellis opted to pick up the ball and run with it. Whether or not he did so, it was that school that first wrote rules for the game we now call rugby. Most clubs preferred the non-handling game and founded The Football Association (hence "Association football", or "soccer" in short) in 1863, but 21 clubs led by Blackheath split away, and formed the Rugby Football Union (RFU) in 1871. The schism with soccer was made permanent by accident, when changes in the making of balls caused the rugby ball to become elongated. This was crucial: you can kick a spherical ball with accuracy over distance, at close quarters dribble it round your opponents, and head it, flick it and all sorts of tricks. You can't do so with an ellipsoid ball as the kicker's contact is too variable, the bounce is unpredictable and the ball bobbles not rolls; it's better to carry and pass it. It's also more snug to hold than a spherical ball. </p>

<p>The RFU required players to be amateurs, which was alright for the nobility and a growing middle class with money and leisure time. But working-class men lost wages if they took time off for games and training, and clubs from the industrial north of England sought to refund them with "broken time payments". The RFU wouldn't accept this so in 1895 those northern clubs broke away, forming the Rugby Football League (RFL). This second schism was very bitter: the RFU banned not only payment but any taint of association with rugby league, even in an unpaid or non-playing capacity. It took human rights legislation in the 1990s and a string of lawsuits to bring the RFU to its senses. Both games are now professional at their higher levels, and there is some cross-over of players, but the geographical distribution of fans for both codes still bears the scars of the split; in England, support for rugby union is still largely concentrated in the south, while support for rugby league is still largely concentrated in the north.</p>

<p>Britain exported rugby to its colonies, who swiftly learned to beat the mother country at her own game - New Zealand became pre-eminent, and remains so over a century later. Rugby also became popular in France, Argentina and Italy, and to a lesser extent elsewhere. Large countries where it never took hold include India, the United States, Russia and China (except Hong Kong).</p>

<p>In the 21st century women's rugby union has greatly developed.</p>

<head>Going to a match</head>
<p>The top matches are the internationals. These sell out weeks in advance - check the host nation union's official website for ticket sales, and be wary of online scalpers. (Plane and hotel prices will also be hiked.) These matches are usually on TV, and watched in pubs on widescreen. At the level below, of professional clubs, you should have little difficulty getting tickets, or getting into the stadium on the day, yet you'll see top-ranked players doing their stuff with skill and verve. Games lower down the pyramid are thinly attended, the skill and athleticism are not so fine, but the impact and intensity are all there. See the Wikivoyage travel pages for the relevant cities for practicalities. </p>

<p>You will always be welcome. Rugby union rival fans mingle amicably inside and outside the stadium, and abhor the hostilities and hooliganism that too often mar soccer games. Keep the violence on the pitch, where it's controlled by the rules and the referee's whistle. "Hard luck today guys, you were unlucky with some of the decisions and the bounce of the ball, what are you having to drink?" After a drink or three however, an argument is likely to boil over, with punches thrown - but it won't be country versus country unless it's about Brexit. It'll soon come to order and everyone pals again and more drinks, until the next brawl starts. The drinking culture is both traditional and silly and is best avoided, especially in a strange city where unfriendly denizens lie in wait for drunks.</p>

<head>Rules</head>
<p>Accept from the outset that you'll never fully understand these. It's like <hi rend="italic">Tao</hi>, where that which can be written is not the true <hi rend="italic">Tao</hi>. The reason it's baffling is that there are several different passages of play, with different rules on handling the ball and on contact with other players. And the game can switch between passages at high speed, with the ball hidden in a pile of furious bodies. Even the players can't always tell, so the referee maintains a running commentary to guide them. "Tackler roll away! That's a ruck - hands off Number Six! Blue Five, step back." The referee has two assistants or "touch judges" on the sidelines, and big games have a fourth video referee or TMO: "Television Match Official".</p>

<p>The game is played with 15 a side, players 1 to 8 being "forwards", 9 to 15 being "backs" ie defensive, and up to eight substitutes, 16 to 23. They play on a pitch 100 m long by 70 m wide with an H-shaped goal at each end. Players seek to advance the ball across any part of their opponents' goal line (not just the H) to score a <hi rend="bold">try</hi>, worth 5 points. Players may run with or kick the ball in any direction, but may only pass the ball backwards or horizontally. A player carrying the ball may be tackled, no small matter if that player weighs 120 kilo and is running hard. The tackled player must release the ball, whereupon there is a struggle to regain it, usually in the form of a "ruck". There are two halves of 40 min, with teams switching ends; there is no added time because the referee stops the clock at interruptions to play. However play doesn't stop on the 40 min, but whenever the ball next goes dead: there are thrilling examples of teams keeping play alive in "red-clock" time to snatch a victory. </p>

<p>To score a try, the ball must be securely grounded in the opponent's "in-goal area" - dropping it doesn't count, and the defenders may contrive to get under the ball and hold it up. The try-scoring team is also awarded a <hi rend="bold">conversion</hi>, earning two more points if it's kicked over the crossbar of the H-shaped goal. These names came about because before 1886 the try didn't score points; it just provided an opportunity to "try" to kick a goal unimpeded by the opponents, and a successful kick would "convert" the try into a goal. The kick is taken in line from where the ball was grounded, so try-scorers attempt to go central to give their kicker a better angle. </p>

<p>Players may also drop kick the ball over the goal crossbar during open play, for a <hi rend="bold">drop goal</hi> worth 3 points. It's a tricky manoeuvre and not often attempted. Most scores come from <hi rend="bold">penalty kicks</hi> awarded for serious infringements. Teams have a choice of how to play from a penalty, but often opt for a place kick at goal, worth 3 points if it clears the crossbar. Hustling your opponents into mistakes that incur a penalty is an important part of attack. </p>

<p>There are several set plays. A <hi rend="bold">lineout</hi> is awarded if the ball goes over the sidelines "into touch". The lines themselves are in touch, so a ball or player carrying the ball and setting foot on the line is out of play (likewise a ball grounded on the goal line itself is a try.) Normally the other side then has a throw-in to the two lines of opposing players, but if the ball has gone out from a penalty kick, that side gets the throw-in. This is a common attacking ploy: you kick for touch close to the goal line, hoping to win the line-out and charge over for a try. A <hi rend="bold">scrum</hi> is awarded for a minor infringement: the forwards crouch into a 3-4-1 set, while the "scrum-half" feeds the ball in. The ball may not be handled within the scrum. Messy, collapsing scrums are the game's least attractive feature, and carry risk of injury.</p>

<p>What counts as a minor or major infringement often depends on the game situation, eg did it thwart a promising attack, was it deliberate or repeated offending, was it physically dangerous? Common offences usually deemed minor are forward passes, knock-on (i.e. ball forward from hand to ground), and tackled player not releasing the ball. It's usually a penalty for collapsing a scrum or being offside, ie competing for the ball from in front of it. For an offence that thwarts a probable try the referee may award a <hi rend="bold">penalty try</hi>, 5 instant points and a conversion kick for two more. For serious misconduct such as a dangerous tackle, a player could be sent off for 10 minutes ("yellow card"), or for the rest of the game ("red card"). In a game that's all about weight and numbers, that hands a big advantage to the other team. Referees are martinets from a bygone era, and visible dissent from their decisions is punished more rigorously than in other sports. </p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Rugby sevens</hi> is a variant of rugby union with only 7 players, but using the same sized field, so play is fast and open, a real test of fitness. A few rules and set-plays are adapted, eg scrums are of three players, and penalty goals and conversions are from drop kicks not place kicks. The game is two halves of 7 or 10 minutes; this lends itself to tournaments with all the games played over a single weekend, or sometimes even a single day. Drop goals and penalty goals are extremely rare in rugby sevens, and the vast majority of points are scored from tries.</p>
</text>
