<text id="autogum_voyage_doc42" title="Abijatta Shalla Lakes National Park">
<head>Abijatta Shalla Lakes National Park</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Abijatta-Shalla Lakes National Park</hi> is in the <ref target="Southern%20Ethiopia">southern</ref> Oromia region of <ref target="Ethiopia">Ethiopia</ref>, about 200 km south of the capital of <ref target="Addis%20Ababa">Addis Ababa</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<head>History</head>

<head>Landscape</head>
<p>Thousands of flamingoes create pink carpets in the blue bays of the lake; great white pelicans soar in from Lake Shala to enjoy the fishing and execute their fantastic ballet; pied kingfishers hover and dive; fish eagles protect their territory with their eerie cry; cormorants and darters fill the dead acacia trees silhouetting strange and beautiful shapes against the sunset. Here are tall marabou stalks and sacred ibis. Snipe, stilt, avocet dwell sometimes in the hundreds of thousands, the black heron searches the shallow water in the shadow created by his black umbrella.</p>

<head>Flora and fauna</head>
<p>Warthogs, ostriches and flamingoes are common.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>The National Park and this part of Ethiopia as a whole can be visited during the rainy season: dirt roads in the area not that slippery, even at the end of July or the beginning of September.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<head>By car</head>
<p>From <ref target="Addis%20Ababa">Addis Ababa</ref>, Abijatta Shalla Lakes National Park is 210 km via <ref target="Modjo">Modjo</ref>, using the Addis Ababa–Adama Expressway (3 hours 15 minutes drive), or it's 228 km via <ref target="Butajira">Butajira</ref> (3 hours 45 minutes drive).</p>

<p>The is in between the two lakes, on national Highway 6, 47 km south from <ref target="Ziway">Ziway</ref> and 41 km north from <ref target="Shashemene">Shashemene</ref>.</p>

<head>Fees and permits</head>

<head>Get around</head>

<head>See</head>

<head>Do</head>

<head>Buy</head>

<head>Eat</head>

<head>Drink</head>

<head>Sleep</head>

<head>Lodging</head>
<p>No lodge exists inside the park. The possibilities within less than 1 hour's drive are to find hotels in <ref target="Ziway%23Sleep">Ziway</ref> or <ref target="Shashemene%23Sleep">Shashemene</ref> or to go to one of the expensive resorts of Lake Langano. The closest town, Bulbula, doesn't seem to have any hotel.</p>

<head>Camping</head>

<head>Backcountry</head>

<head>Stay safe</head>

<head>Go next</head>
</text>
