<text id="autogum_voyage_doc215" title="Bend" shortTile="bend" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=3386" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bend</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.visitbend.com/">Bend</ref></hi> is the county seat of Deschutes County in <ref target="Central%20Oregon">Central Oregon</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The city of Bend, which is nestled between the Cascade Range and the Maury Mountains, is a tourist destination in summer and winter.</p>

<head>Visitor information</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bend Visitor Center</hi>, 750 NW Lava Rd, Suite 160 (At Oregon Ave), ☏ +1 541-382-8048 , toll-free: +1-877-245-8484 . M-F 9AM-5PM, Sa-Su 10AM-4PM.</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Redmond Municipal Airport</hi> (Roberts Field RDM ) (Terminal Bldg is on the west side of the airport runways. It is accessed via SE Airport way.). It is the major airport for commercial flights serving Redmond, Bend, Sunriver, Prineville and the surrounding communities in <ref target="Central%20Oregon">Central Oregon</ref>. The airport is north of town along US Hwy 97 in the southeastern part of Redmond. It is served by:</item>
</list>



<head>By car</head>
<p>Bend is served by <hi rend="bold">U.S. Routes 20</hi> and <hi rend="bold">97</hi>. From the west, U.S. 20 carries traffic from Santiam Pass and the Willamette Valley, and from Burns and southeastern Oregon. U.S. 97 passes north-south through the city, carrying traffic from Klamath Falls to the south and the Columbia River Gorge and Yakima to the north.</p>

<p>To get to Bend from <ref target="Portland%20%28Oregon%29">Portland</ref>, you can take U.S. 26 east from Gresham over Mount Hood to Madras where it meets up with U.S. 97 south, and follow U.S. 97 south through Redmond to Bend. Or you can take I-5 south to Albany, then U.S. 20 east through Santiam Pass and Sisters. Either way will take about three hours, not counting rest stops. Both routes cross the Cascade Range and may receive heavy snow during the winter.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>The main bus station for local public transportation and intercity buses is at the on NE 4th &amp; Hawthorne (334 NE Hawthorne). Bus stops for Cascades East Transit are lined up along NE Hawthorne and along NE 4th while the long distance buses are along NE 4th:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cascade East Transit</hi>, ☏ +1 541 385-8680 , toll-free: +1-866-385-8680 . Operates local public transportation and intercity buses to the surrounding cities/towns of Culver, Redmond, Madras, Metolius, Prineville, Sisters and Warm Springs from Hawthorne Station</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">CoBreeze</hi>, (bus stops) Circle 'K' @ 3405 N Hwy 97; Redmond Airport and Redmond Transit Hub, ☏ +1 541 389-7469 . Comes from <ref target="Portland_%28Oregon%29%23By%20bus">Portland</ref>, <ref target="Portland_%28Oregon%29%23By%20plane">Portland International Airport</ref> and <ref target="Gresham">Gresham</ref> via Sandy, Welches, Government Camp (Mt Hood), <ref target="Madras_%28Oregon%29">Madras</ref> and Prineville P&amp;R along US Hwy 26. Buses may not make all the above stops regularly but on request in advance of travel. Check with them.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Grant County People Mover</hi>, ☏ +1 541 575-2370 . Goes east towards Prairie City through Redmond Airport, Redmond Transit Hub, Prineville, John Day, Mitchell and Dayville. There's another route that goes towards Monument from Dayville. Check schedules.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mt Hood Teleporter</hi>, (Bus stop) Hawthorne Station, ☏ +1 541 903-0724 . Goes up to Portland through Sisters and Salem via US Hwy 20/SR-22 and I-5. Passengers can transfer to Greyhound, Amtrak and other bus lines in <ref target="Portland_%28Oregon%29%23By%20bus">Portland</ref> and <ref target="Salem_%28Oregon%29%23By%20bus">Salem</ref></item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Oregon Point</hi> (Operated by MTR Western and Pacific Crest Bus Lines), (bus stop) Hawthorne Transit Center, ☏ +1 888 846-4183 . Tickets can be purchased through their website or through <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.greyhound.com">Greyhound.com</ref></hi> :</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pacific Crest Bus Lines</hi>, ☏ +1 541 923-1732 . Connects Bend to Eugene and Coos Bay. Passengers connect to <ref target="http://www.amtrak.com">Amtrak</ref> and Greyhound (Seattle-Portland-Sacramento route) in <ref target="Eugene%23By%20bus">Eugene</ref></item>
</list>



<head>Get around</head>

<p>To fully enjoy the city of Bend, your best mode of transportation is the bicycle. Bend has extensive bike paths and lanes and walking paths. When visiting downtown Bend, you can park for free for the first two hours during business hours and unlimited hours after 5PM. Downtown is best explored by foot. Parking can be difficult at times but a spacious parking garage is located at the corner of Bond and Oregon Streets.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<ref target="http://www.cascadeseasttransit.com/"><hi rend="bold">Cascade East Transit</hi></ref> provides limited bus service in and around Bend. Phone number: +1-866-385-8680, +1 541 385-8680. All buses stop at Hawthorne Station at fourth street and Northeast Hawthorne Ave.

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">High Desert Museum</hi>, ☏ +1 541-382-4754 ext 271 (weekday business hours) . Daily: May 1-Oct 31: 9AM-5PM; Nov 1-Apr 30: 10 AM-4 PM. The High Desert Museum is just south of Bend on Highway 97. The High Desert Museum is a great way to gain educational experience about some of the animals and habitat that go along with Central Oregon. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Historic Tower Theatre</hi>, 835 NW Wall St (Along NW Wall St between Minnesota &amp; Franklin, downtown), ☏ +1 541 317-0700 . </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Smith Rock</hi>, ☏ +1 541-548-7501 . Smith Rock State Park encompasses 651 acres on the Oregon high desert plateau which hovers around 3000 feet in elevation. The park and campground are open year-round. A $5 day use permit or a current state park camp receipt is needed for each vehicle. A yearly permit is available for $30. Hiking trails offer spectacular views of the surrounding area. You can spend 30 minutes walking along the river or a half day making a loop on the entire trail system that extends outside of the park. The major rock faces are composed of welded tuff (compressed volcanic ash) reaching a height of up to 550 feet. The picnic and campground areas sit on top of the rimrock which is made up of columnar basalt. There are over 1400 climbing routes in and around the park ranging from some of the best sport climbs in the world to. “Why would anyone want to climb that pile of choss”. People climb year-round, but summer temperatures can reach over , and in the dead of winter the thermometer stays close to the freezing mark () during the day. Spring and fall are the most popular climbing months. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Deschutes River</hi>. The Deschutes features ruggedly beautiful scenery, outstanding whitewater boating, and a renowned sport fishery for steelhead, brown trout, and native rainbow trout. The Upper Deschutes features primarily flatwater boating with limited whitewater and excellent trout fishing opportunities. The Middle Deschutes has excellent hiking opportunities with spectacular geologic formations and waterfalls, but boating is limited. The Lower Deschutes offers the greatest opportunities for whitewater rafting and is one of Oregon's premier steelhead and trout fisheries</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Newberry National Volcanic Monument</hi>, ☏ +1 541 593-2421 . South of Bend, See lava flows, explore lava caves and ice caves, fishing for trophy rainbow and brown trout in the two alpine lakes at the Newberry caldera (East Lake &amp; Paulina Lake) and explore the massive Obsidian Flow. There are hiking trails, camping and resorts. Also snow parks, winter cross-country skiing and snowmobiling. Visit the Lava Lands Visitor Center for information. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cascade lakes and Mountains</hi>. These areas are spectacular. Take a drive on the Cascade Lakes Highway and you can go to Sparks Lake, which is ideal for canoeing and kayaking, the Twin Lakes, Elk Lake and more while taking in some beautiful mountain scenery at the same time. Many of these lakes offer fishing, camping, and trailheads for hiking up into the mountains. Along the Cascade Lakes Highway, you can access trailheads as well as snow parks for snowmobiling in the winter.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cultus Lake</hi>. About 45 minutes outside of Bend, Oregon, on the cascades lake highway. At the lake there are a number of activities and facilities available for tourists, all centered around the crystal clear waters of the lake. At Cultus Lake there are a number of activities available. The resort's main attraction is its water sports. One can rent a number of watercrafts including jet skis, motorboats, canoes, kayaks, paddleboats and party boats. Gas and oil can be purchased on site. Another popular activity at Cultus is the fishing. The lake is filled with Rainbows, Bass, Mackinaws and Browns. There are also beaches where people can swim and enjoy the water from another perspective. At the lodge there is a restaurant open to the public. They serve a wide variety of food here and it is reasonably priced. One can also purchase groceries, although the selection is limited and prices higher than a supermarket. Cabins are available to rent at Cultus Lake. The cabins are near the lake, and have fireplaces, kitchens and appliances. There are a number of campsites available on and near the lake. They are operated by the National Forest Service, and have a small per night fee. There is running water, toilets and parking available to campers, however there are no R.V. hook ups. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Elk Lake</hi>. About 11 miles past Mount Bachelor and just a short drive out of Bend, Oregon. It is known for its mountain scenery and relaxed atmosphere. It has clear water, making it popular to people seeking water activities. The Lake is 405 acres in size, with a depths ranging from 25'-75. The elevation of the resort is about 4884'. At Elk lake fishing is a popular activity. The lake is filled with Kokanee and brook trout. In the summer months the lake is planted with brook trout. Popular fishing techniques include: still-fishing, trolling and fly fishing. Boating is also permitted at Elk Lake. At the resort there are paddle boat, canoes, and sail boats available to rent. Prices for these boats are fairly reasonable and can be checked out by the hour or by the day. Larger motor boats are not allowed to help maintain the peacefulness on the lake. There are a number of boat docks that surround the lake to make launching a boat relatively easy. Swimming is easily accessible at the sunset and beach areas of the lake. If hiking is your choice there are miles of trails that circle the lake. At the resort there is a restaurant open to the public. It serves a wide variety of food, specializing in their hamburgers. For dessert they have a small ice cream parlor with about a dozen different flavors. There is also a small store where groceries can be purchased. Cabins are available to rent, and can be checked out at the main resort. They vary in size and location. Camping can be done at a number of different sites in the area. The different sites include: Little Fawn Campground, Little Fawn Group Camp, Point Campground, and Elk Lake Campground. There are also areas reserved specifically for day use. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tumalo State Park</hi>, ☏ +1 541 388-6055 . Day use $5/ vehicle, Tent site $21, Yurt $46. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pilot Butte State Scenic Viewpoint</hi>, ☏ +1 541 388-6055 . Free. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Deschutes Historical Museum</hi>, 129 NW Idaho Ave, ☏ +1 541-389-1813 . </item>
</list>
</text>
