<text id="autogum_voyage_doc258" title="Makrinitsa" shortTile="makrinitsa" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=20933" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Makrinitsa</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Makrinitsa</hi> (Greek: Μακρινίτσα), called the 'balcony' of Mt. <ref target="Pelion">Pelion</ref>, <ref target="Magnesia">Magnesia</ref>, <ref target="Greece">Greece</ref>, for it's amazing views.</p>
<p>Located only birth-flight, or by winding mountain road, north-east of <ref target="Volos">Volos</ref> it is one of the most easily accessed of Pelions 24 villages.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>One of the most characteristic traditional settlements on mount Pelion. It is filled with mansions and houses from the <ref target="Ottoman%20Empire">Ottoman era</ref> that look like hanging ornaments on the green mountain side and are colorful (but not as <ref target="Portaria">Portaria</ref>). Many of these have been restored into restaurants and guesthouses. It sits on a slope of the Pelion range and another mountaintop to the east with forests, at a height of about above sea level. The square with age-old trees lends a panoramic view of Volos and the Pagasetic Gulf. In one of the traditional coffee houses there is a big fresco by the 20th century naïve folkloristic artist <hi rend="italic">Theofilos</hi>. The picturesque cobbled paths of Makrinitsa are scattered with traditional water fountains. Makrynitsa, with a population of about 900 people, has a school, a lyceum, a church, a post office and a square (plateia) with tall trees.</p>

<p>Orientation in Makrinitsa is made more difficult by the fact that village streets are not named. Every place has got the address "Makrinitsa 370 11". Fortunately Makrinitsa is not very large, and you can easily orient yourself by the pedestrian main street, on which you will find the town square and the village church.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>By bus from <ref target="Volos">Volos</ref> Interurban Bus Terminal ("Yperastiko KTEL") (<ref target="http://www.ktelvolou.gr/">KTEL Volou</ref>), Details on buses, <ref target="http://ktelvolou.gr/en/routes/map/%26amp%3Bmap%3Dmagnesia">can be found online here</ref></p>

<p>A taxi from Volos city centre will cost approximately €20, although do ask before you get in.</p>

<p>There is some parking in the village, in the main carpark at the foot of the village and on the approach roads. It does get very busy in the carpark, and the approach roads are on a fairly steep gradient. Park with your front wheels turned to point into the kerb and either in park or in first gear!</p>

<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pelion Museum of Folklore and History</hi> (Signposted from the main square.). Saturday 11:00-14:30, Sunday 11:00-14:30. Adults €2, children free, groups €1 pp.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<p>There is a main street lined with shops leading from the carpark to the main square. These shops sell all kinds of touristy trinkets, as well as jarred fruits in syrup, local herbs and pasta.</p>

<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">To Kentrikon</hi> (Κέντρικο), Main square. Good food, much of which is from local recipes. The highlight is the fantastic view from the tables on the square. 7-9€ for a large dish.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cardamom Oinomageireio</hi> (Καρδαμο Οινομαγειρειον), ☏ +30 2428 090131 . A cosy restaurant with a large outdoors seating area.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>
<p>The tap water is drinkable and restaurants will serve glasses of ice water upon request. Local drinks include Mythos (beer) and Ouzo.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Art Cafe</hi>, ☏ +30 697 438 4488 . A café and bar. As anywhere else in Makrinitsa, it has a large outdoor seating which offer a great view of Volos. Indoors you will find a welcoming fire and a large number of paintings by local artists.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Archontika Karamarlis Boutique Hotel &amp; Guesthouse</hi> (Has got a main entrance towards the car road climbing mount Pelion and a back-entrance towards the village main street), ☏ +30 2428 099570 . An old mansion turned hotel with a breakfast buffet and a great view of Volos. They often host larger celebrations such as weddings.</item>
</list>
</text>
