<text id="autogum_voyage_doc45" title="Abington Township">
<head>Abington Township</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Abington</hi> is in <ref target="Montgomery%20County%20%28Pennsylvania%29">Montgomery County</ref>, <ref target="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Abington Township named one the 100 best communities to live in America according to Money Magazine is a township in <ref target="Montgomery%20County%20%28Pennsylvania%29">Montgomery County</ref>, <ref target="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</ref>, <ref target="United%20States">United States</ref>. Just outside <ref target="Philadelphia">Philadelphia</ref>.</p>
<p>Abington Township is one of Montgomery County’s oldest communities dating back to before 1700</p>
<p>and being incorporated in 1704. It is home to some of the county’s oldest transportation routes,</p>
<p>industries and churches. Many of these older business and transportation centers were the forerunners</p>
<p>of modern Abington. Today, Abington Township is a highly desirable residential area that contains a major shopping center, several small businesses, and a few of Montgomery County's largest employers. With easy access to <ref target="Philadelphia">Philadelphia</ref> and such destinations as King of Prussia Mall, Sesame Place, Philadelphia Premium outlets, Abington is a great place to visit.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Philadelphia%20International%20Airport">Philadelphia International Airport</ref></hi> ( PHL ) - Just a thirty minute drive with trains to and from the airport to Abington.</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">SEPTA</hi> - Northeast regional rail is an easy way to access Abington with many train stations throughout the town.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>
<p>Buses from the city of Philadelphia travel in and around Abington as well.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>You can reach Abington by car by route 611 or the Pennsylvania turnpike exiting at Willow Grove/Abington.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Alverthorpe Manor Art Museum</hi>. This small non profit community art center is a contemporary art museum located in the heart of Abington. In its historic, 27-acre campus in suburban Philadelphia, Abington Art Center is dedicated to providing opportunities for its many audiences to experience, appreciate and participate in the arts at whatever level they choose. From preschool to lifelong learners, casual observers to art enthusiasts, AAC engages visitors, artists and students with its sculpture park and gallery exhibitions of today’s artists, studio art classes, and public programs.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bryn Athen Cathedral</hi>. The Episcopal seat of the General Church of the New Jerusalem, an international Swedenborgian Church. The cathedral is renowned for its stained glass collection and for its unusual architecture. It was built in the early 20th century, following the Gothic revivalist emergence.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Keswick Theater</hi>. Catch a show or concert at the Keswick Theater. Nationally recognized by audiences and performing artists as the most comfortable, friendly, acoustically-perfect listening room in the Philadelphia area. It presents a broad range of internationally acclaimed performers geared to virtually every entertainment taste and interest housed right in Glenside. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Alverthorpe Park</hi>. Equipped with a golf course, mini golf course, children's pool, playground and fishing lake, outdoor picnic areas and bike trails, Alverthorpe is the perfect place to take your family for an outdoor day of fun. </item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Willow Grove Park Mall</hi>, 2500 Moreland Road, ☏ +1 215 657-6000 . M-Sa 10AM-9PM, Su 11AM-6PM. This shopping mall consists of over 130 stores on three floors and is anchored by Bloomingdale's, Sears, Primark, Macy's, and Nordstrom Rack. The mall offers a food court and sit-down dining options including The Cheesecake Factory and TGI Fridays. The mall has a carousel located on the third floor near the food court. </item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Levis Hot Dogs</hi>, 966 Old York Rd (Between the Library and The Fairway), ☏ +1 215-572-1895 , ✉ levishotdogs@verizon.net . 11am-5pm. Hot Dogs and Sandwiches including home made South Philly roast beef and pork. Iconic Champ Cherry soda. Formerly located in Philadelphia for almost 100 years. Original recipe all beef hot dogs and fishcake sandwiches. $.</item>
</list>
<head>Budget</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Kitchen Bar</hi>, on 611 about three miles from the Pennsylvania turnpike. Kitchen bar is open for breakfast, lunch, dinner and late night drinks. The huge menu includes everything from appetizers, sandwiches, salads and pizza to full course dinners of meat, chicken, fish and more. Kitchen Bar provides a wholesome and delicious meal to satisfy any appetite at any meal.Kitchen bar also features a brand new bar and lounge with live entertainment every weekend. In addition, they offer a newly renovated private banquet room that will accommodate from 20 to 70 people for parties and meetings.</item>
</list>


<head>Mid-range</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ookaa</hi> - Authentic Hibachi-style Japanese cooking. Be sure to ask for the flaming volcano.</item>
</list>


<head>Splurge</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Stefano's Ristorante Italiano</hi>, Huntingdon Pike. This BYOB has authentic Italian food. It is owned and operated by three generations of the Terra Family and is in Huntingdon Valley. Over 60 years of experience in preserving the time-honored tradition of preparing superlative food with only the freshest and finest ingredients.</item>
</list>


<head>Dessert</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sprinkles</hi>, in Elkins Park on Township line on the edge of Abington. This mom-and-pop ice cream parlor serves homemade ice cream.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Days Inn</hi>, 245 Easton Rd (in nearby Horsham), ☏ +1 215-674-2500 .</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>
</text>
