<text id="autogum_voyage_doc11" title="Santa Cruz (city, Bolivia)" shortTile="santa-cruz-city-bolivia" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=31368" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Santa Cruz (city, Bolivia)</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Santa Cruz</hi> (or <hi rend="bold">Santa Cruz de la Sierra</hi>) is the capital of the department of <ref target="Santa%20Cruz%20%28department%2C%20Bolivia%29">Santa Cruz</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Santa Cruz is the most populous city and heart of the second most populous metropolitan area in <ref target="Bolivia">Bolivia</ref>, and it is considered the most economically prosperous city in the country.</p>

<p>Santa Cruz is a boomtown whose population has increased tenfold in the last 25 years, it is almost in the center of Bolivia and is the capital city of the department of Santa Cruz. It lies at one end of the Death Train's line.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>For its first 400 years Santa Cruz was very poor and far from potential markets to be able to grow at all. It shares this with the rest of eastern, northern and south eastern Bolivia for most of its history, up until some 50 years ago when a paved road was opened and the possibility of markets opened which summed with some royalties from oil production they also started receiving served as seed to one of the fastest growing cities and economies in the continent. Growth was slow to start but after some 20 years it was spectacular. Today it is difficult to imagine this city and provincial towns of the department for what they really were some 25 or 50 years ago.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>In contrast to <ref target="La%20Paz%20%28Bolivia%29">La Paz</ref> and the other major Bolivian cities located high in the Andes, Santa Cruz lies at an altitude of 416 meters, and its climate is distinctly tropical. Santa Cruz is furrowed by drainage ditches.</p>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>Although, the country´s official language and main language is Spanish, most places (stores specially) will be able to understand Portuguese and English. If they do not speak those languages, they will probably get someone that does. The people are <hi rend="italic">really</hi> friendly, they will try their truly best to talk to you if you are a foreigner.</p>
<head>Get in</head>

<p>If you arrive during carnival (during February, sometimes March) it is almost impossible to change money as everything except markets, restaurants and internet cafes are closed. Traders will accept U.S. dollars but at half the going rate. Also be prepared to be pelted with ink filled water balloons, soaked with water bombs and covered in string spray. Wear clothes you don`t mind having permanently stained.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>There are many bus companies from another cities, like <ref target="Cochabamba">Cochabamba</ref>, <ref target="La%20Paz%20%28Bolivia%29">La Paz</ref>, <ref target="Sucre">Sucre</ref>, Trinidad, that go to Santa Cruz de la Sierra. You can arrive from <ref target="La%20Paz%20%28Bolivia%29">La Paz</ref> in about 18 hours, and it takes about 10 hours from <ref target="Cochabamba">Cochabamba</ref>.</p>

<p>To and from the Brazilian border in <ref target="Corumba">Corumba</ref>/<ref target="Puerto%20Quijarro">Puerto Quijarro</ref> is cheaper and faster (10 hr and tickets from Bs. 40) than the famous <hi rend="italic">death train</hi>.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="Asunci%C3%B3n">Asunción</ref> (Paraguay)</hi> – The bus is extremely slow (the Transchaco Highway is only paved as far as the Bolivian border), buses generally travel only at night - meaning that you miss out on any views of the Chaco, and roadblocks on the Bolivian side of the border can cause your journey time to double. There is at least one bus daily. The trip takes 21-24 hr, costs US$40-60 (bargain if you can), and flights might actually only be marginally more expensive, depending on the time of booking. Any intermediate exit or boarding (like <ref target="Filadelfia">Filadelfia</ref> or <ref target="Villamontes">Villamontes</ref>) will likely cost the same as the complete trip. But if your nerves are strong, you will get the price down bargaining directly with the bus driver.</p>

<p>A taxi from the bus terminal to the center will cost about Bs. 12.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>The "death train" (so named because of its history in transporting Yellow Fever victims) runs on bumpy tracks from <ref target="Puerto%20Quijarro">Puerto Quijarro</ref>, close to <ref target="Corumb%C3%A1">Corumbá</ref> on the Brazilian side. There is a variety of different trains offering different classes and prices. The journey takes 13-17 hr. The most comfortable option, with cama seats, is the "Ferrobus" (Tu Th Sa) which costs Bs. 235 per person (Jul 2019). Expreso Oriental needs longer, but only costs Bs. 70. Tickets can be purchased days in advance at the station (Terminal Bimodal) or online (<ref target="https://www.ticketsbolivia.com">ticktsBolivia.com</ref>, plus a US$7 fee). Biting insects are plentiful, so get repellent before you go. It's also a good idea to have blankets or a sleeping bag with you in the colder months of June-August.</p>

<p>The railway between Santa Cruz and <ref target="Puerto%20Quijarro">Puerto Quijarro</ref> is operated by <ref target="http://www.ferroviariaoriental.com">Ferroviaria Oriental S.A.</ref>.</p>

<p>For crossing the border see <ref target="Puerto%20Quijarro">Puerto Quijarro</ref>.</p>

<p>From <ref target="Corumb%C3%A1">Corumbá</ref> the bus-ride to Sao Paulo takes about another 24 hr.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Viru Viru International Airport</hi> ( VVI ). Bolivia's largest and most modern airport, and a hub for BoA. International flights on BoA travel to Madrid, São Paulo, and Buenos Aires with other destinations on the horizon. AeroSur is no longer operational. American Airlines flies direct to Miami. Other options include a variety of destinations via Panama, and LATAM and Avianca also fly to Santa Cruz. Gol Airlines and Aerolineas Argentinas also offer flights to São Paulo and Buenos Aires, respectively. Air Europa also flies direct to Madrid. </item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">El Trompillo Airport</hi> ( SRZ ). The city's older airport, and is used by military operated Transporte Aéreo Militar (TAM) airlines for internal flights (to Cochabamba and Sucre, for example) and Aerocon (to Tarija and Trinidad for example). Major airlines have daily flights to Santa Cruz de la Sierra, mainly from La Paz (about 4 flights per day: early in the morning, in the afternoon, early in the evening and late in the night). From Cochabamba (about 2 flights per day). Flights to international cities is also daily, (Sao Paulo, Brasil - Buenos Aires, Argentina - Lima, Peru - there are daily flights). American Airlines has daily service to and from Miami. </item>
</list>


<p>About Bolivian airlines and flying within Bolivia: <ref target="Bolivia%23Get_around">Bolivia#Get_around</ref></p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Micros 17 and 18 travel the first ring, Micros 72 and 73 travel the second ring. To get to the center from Parque Urbano take Micro 69 or 100. You can pick up a map of all the bus routes from many "librerias" or bookstores downtown. There is also a great mobile app called <hi rend="bold">Cruzero</hi> (both for <ref target="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/cruzero/id1158164502">iOS</ref> and <ref target="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details%3Fid%3Dcom.mos%26amp%3Bhl%3Den">Android</ref>) which contains route maps of all micros. It can also find you an optimal route if you just select the source and the destination on the city map. There is a website with the same content as well: http://cruzero.net/.</p>

<p>The fare for most micros is Bs. 2, but some of the ones that go further charge more, and the one that goes to the airport charges Bs. 6.</p>

<p>Shared taxis circulate the rings as well, they are called "trufis". Look for the signs on the roof. Faster than Micros and more comfortable because you can actually sit down. The fare for most trufis is Bs. 2.</p>
</text>
