<text id="autogum_voyage_doc95" title="Watertown (New York)" shortTile="watertown-new-york" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=38676" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Watertown (New York)</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://ny-watertown.civicplus.com/index.asp%3FNID%3D82">Watertown</ref></hi> is a small city in <ref target="New%20York%20%28state%29">New York</ref>'s <ref target="North%20Country">North Country</ref>, and the seat of Jefferson County.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Settlers came here in the early 1800s to use the power from the Black River for industry. <date when="1852-04-13">On April 13, 1852</date> Frank Winfield Woolworth was born in the tiny village of Rodman, ten miles south of Watertown; he attended business college in the city and worked as a stockboy in a general store on Watertown's Public Square in 1873 before attempting to launch his own "five-cent store" in <ref target="Utica">Utica</ref> in 1878. That short-lived effort fared poorly, but a Woolworth "five and dime" in <ref target="Lancaster%20%28Pennsylvania%29">Lancaster (Pennsylvania)</ref> in 1879 succeeded.</p>

<p>Watertown is only a few miles from <ref target="http://www.drum.army.mil/sites/local">Fort Drum</ref>, home of the US Army 10th Mountain Division, the region's largest employer. It is home to various manufacturing industries (the "Car Freshener" scented air freshener is a local invention) and to Jefferson Community College.</p>

<p>Today. Watertown has a beautiful, historic downtown center.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Watertown is about 75 miles north of <ref target="Syracuse%20%28New%20York%29">Syracuse</ref> on US 11 or Interstate 81 (exits 45, 46, and 47). Adirondack Trailways Service and Greyhound provide bus service, while the closest Amtrak stations are in <ref target="Rome%20%28New%20York%29">Rome</ref> or in Syracuse.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Adirondack Trailways</hi>, 540 State St., toll-free: +1-800-776-7548 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Greyhound</hi>, 540 State St. (North Dr Inn Theatre, NY Route 3E), toll-free: +1-800-858-8555 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Watertown International Airport</hi> ( ART ), Dexter NY 13624, ☏ +1 315 639-6247 . Twice-daily service to <ref target="Philadelphia">Philadelphia</ref>; airport otherwise primarily serves general aviation and charters. </item>
</list>


<p>The closest major airport is Syracuse Hancock International ( SYR ) a little over 70 miles to the south.</p>

<p>There is no direct scheduled transportation from Watertown to <ref target="Canada">Canada</ref>, despite its proximity (<ref target="Kingston%20%28Ontario%29">Kingston</ref> and <ref target="Brockville">Brockville</ref> are each an hour away by road).</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">CitiBus</hi>. Provides a limited local bus service on three daytime routes.</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">New York State Zoo at Thompson Park</hi>, ☏ +1 315 755-0894 . 10AM-5PM daily (Apr-Oct). 32-acre Thompson Park Zoo exhibits species that are or were native to New York State, including wolverines, black bears, eagles, mountain lions, Canada lynx and grey wolves. $9/adult.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Washington Street Arboretum</hi>, 200 block of Washington Street. Over 30 different varieties and species of trees.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Black River</hi>. Kayaking and whitewater rafting. Three rafting companies (Adirondack, Bob's, Hudson), seven miles of whitewater, fourteen sets of class III and IV rapids. Riverfront walking trails at the Veteran's Memorial Riverwalk, Waterworks and Marble Street Park; bike, hike or fish along the shoreline.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dry Hill Ski Area</hi>, 18160 Alpine Ridge Rd, ☏ +1 315 782-8584 , toll-free: +1-800-379-8584 , fax: +1 315 782-1741 . Wintertime tubing, snowboarding and downhill skiing.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Thompson Park</hi>, entrances off Gotham St, Academy St and Franklin St. 7AM-9PM. A historic Olmsted Creation with scenic views, children's playground, pool, golf course, zoo, picnic area. On or near the 4th of July, the <ref target="Potsdam%20%28New%20York%29">Potsdam</ref>-based Orchestra of Northern New York presents the 1812 overture with cannons as a concert in the park, followed by fireworks.</item>
</list>



<head>Events</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Snowtown USA</hi>. Two weeks of indoor and outdoor activities and exhibitions, mid-February. <ref target="http://www.snowtownfilmfestival.com">Snowtown Film Festival</ref> in late January.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Farmers' Market</hi>, Washington Street (by City Hall). Open Wednesdays; everything from fresh fruit &amp; vegetables to arts &amp; crafts,</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Salmon Run Mall</hi>, 21182 Salmon Run Mall Loop West, ☏ +1 315 788-9210 . 9:30AM-9PM daily, 11AM-6PM Sunday. Mall with stores including Target, Lowe's, near I-81, popular with Canadian cross-border shoppers.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Art's Jug</hi>, 820 Huntington St., ☏ +1 315 788-9513 . 4pm-9:30pm. Italian.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Black River Coffee Co</hi>, 4 Paddock Arc, ☏ +1 315 955-6972 . Café, wi-fi.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Church Street Diner</hi>, 107 Church St, Carthage 13619, ☏ +1 315 493-0997 . 6am-2pm. Burgers, sandwiches, chicken, breakfast foods.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jreck Subs</hi>, 1201 Arsenal St., ☏ +1 315 782-3529 . Watertown-based submarine sandwich chain, over forty locations in <ref target="North%20Country">northern New York</ref>.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Stefanos Pizza and Restaurant</hi>, 258 State St, Carthage 13619, ☏ +1 315 493-0400 . Italian/Sicilian.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Maggie's on the River</hi>, 500 Newell St, Watertown 13601, ☏ +1 315 405-4239 . Sports bar and restaurant, casual.</item>
<item> Water is plentiful in the region.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Best Western Carriage House Motor Inn</hi>, 300 Washington Street, ☏ +1 315 782-8000 , fax: +1 315 786-2097 . Wi-fi.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Econo Lodge Watertown</hi>, 1030 Arsenal St, ☏ +1 315 782-5500 . Wi-fi.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Holiday Inn Express Hotel &amp; Suites</hi>, 1290 Arsenal St, ☏ +1 315 779-1234 . Wi-fi.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ramada Watertown</hi>, 6300 Arsenal St, ☏ +1 315 788-0700 .</item>
</list>


<head>Connect</head>
<p>Postal service is available from USPS at 232 Commerce Park Drive 13601-9900 (phone +1 315-786-5900); commercial parcel receiving service is available from the <ref target="https://watertown-ny-6889.theupsstorelocal.com/about-our-store/contact-us">UPS store</ref> at 968 Bradley Street (phone +1 315 755-2028, fax 755-2030).</p>

<p>Wi-fi is available at most <ref target="Fast%20food%20in%20the%20United%20States%20and%20Canada">fast food</ref> and coffee shop chains, or at the public library:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Flower Memorial Library</hi>, 229 Washington St., ☏ +1 315-785-7705 , fax: +1 315-788-2584 . Mo-Th 9AM-8PM, Fr-Sa 9AM-5PM, Su Noon-5PM. </item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Thousand%20Islands">Thousand Islands</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Sackets%20Harbor">Sackets Harbor</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Adirondacks">Adirondacks</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
