<text id="autogum_voyage_doc20" title="Abbottabad">
<head>Abbottabad</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Abbottabad</hi> is a city in <ref target="Khyber%20Pakhtunkhwa">Khyber Pakhtunkhwa</ref> of <ref target="Pakistan">Pakistan</ref>, north of <ref target="Islamabad">Islamabad</ref> on the <ref target="Karakoram%20Highway">Karakoram Highway</ref>. The town is at an altitude of 1250 m (4150 feet) and gets quite a lot of Pakistani tourism, mainly people escaping the hot season in nearby <ref target="Islamabad">Islamabad</ref>, <ref target="Rawalpindi">Rawalpindi</ref> or <ref target="Peshawar">Peshawar</ref>.</p>

<p>Abroad, the city has gained fame as the place where Osama Bin Laden, leader of Al Qaeda, was shot and killed.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>The town was founded as a British district headquarters and military base in the 1850s. It was named for the founder, Major James Abbott (later General Sir James Abbott).</p>

<p>At one time, the city was quite important as a transport hub, a stop on the main route north toward <ref target="Gilgit">Gilgit</ref> and <ref target="China">China</ref>. Its importance in this role has been somewhat diminished by the completion of the Karakoram Highway.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>From <ref target="Rawalpindi">Rawalpindi</ref> or <ref target="Islamabad">Islamabad</ref> you can reach Abbottabad by road in less than 3 hours. Daewoo bus service operates more than three services daily for under Rs. 500 per passenger. It is an hour's drive from Nathia Gali which is about 34 km dropping steeply through the beautiful valleys with few trees to the river bed.</p>

<p>Abbottabad is the junction from where you can go to places like <ref target="Hunza">Hunza</ref>, <ref target="Gilgit">Gilgit</ref>, <ref target="Skardu">Skardu</ref> and Indus Kohistan, of the Karakoram Range. You can reach Swat, Swati Kohistan, Dir and Chitral of the <ref target="Hindu%20Kush">Hindu Kush</ref>. And approach Naran, Saif-ul-Muluk, Shogran and Babusar Pass of the Himalayan Range. Neelum, Lipa and Jhelum Valley of beautiful <ref target="Azad%20Kashmir">Azad Kashmir</ref> are also connected through Abbottabad.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Mukeshpuri 9800 feet and Miranjani 9750 feet are its highest peaks.</item>
<item> Ilysi Mosque, Shimla Pahari hill)</item>
<item> Takaya</item>
<item> Dodheyal</item>
<item> Nawansheher Bazaar stairs</item>
<item> Harno (tourist area with open water)</item>
<item> Thandiani (~25 km)</item>
<item> Dhamtoor</item>
<item> Swinging Bridge near Harno</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<p>Trekking, Hiking, Camping, Photography, Golf, Picnic</p>

<p>Abbottabad in addition to being a hill station has some of Pakistan's best educational institutions (e.g. Army Burn Hall School & College, Abbottabad Public School, International Public School, Ayub Medical College, Frontier Medical College, Hazara University). It has therefore become a leading learning seat in Pakistan.</p>

<head>Buy</head>

<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Pakoras and fish at Ilyasi Masjid. A lot of people gather there to enjoy those tasty pakoras.</item>
<item> Kebab of Qalandarabad.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<head>Sleep</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sarban Hotel</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jan's Continental Guest House</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pearl Continental Motel</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pine Inn Guest House</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shelton Inn Guest House</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Snow Land Guest House</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Alaf Laila Guest House kaghan colony, opp usmania restaurant, 03459566871</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Devgru Resort & Spa</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel One</hi>, Mansehra Road, Near Mirpur Police station.</item>
</list>


<head>Connect</head>

<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Nathiagali</item>
</list>
</text>
