<text id="autogum_voyage_doc360" title="Finnish phrasebook" shortTile="finnish-phrasebook" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11621" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Finnish phrasebook</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Finnish</hi> (<hi rend="italic">suomen kieli</hi>, <hi rend="italic">suomi</hi>) is spoken in <ref target="Finland">Finland</ref> and by Finns elsewhere, predominantly in Scandinavia. Whether travellers to Finland <hi rend="italic">need</hi> to learn Finnish is doubtful, since most Finns — including virtually all under 50 — speak at least some English. However, since so few people make the effort, you're guaranteed to get delighted reactions if you try.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Finnish is a <hi rend="bold">Finno-Ugric language</hi> and hence completely unrelated to most other languages. In particular, Finnish has grammatically nothing at all in common with the Nordic languages, English or Russian. Although there are many old loan words especially from <ref target="Swedish%20phrasebook">Swedish</ref> but also from other European languages, they are not necessarily recognizable due to the very different phonology. The use of modern neologisms instead of borrowing is common, but there may be a less used loan word in addition to the neologism: a polygon may be called <hi rend="italic">polygoni</hi>, although the common word is <hi rend="italic">monikulmio</hi> (a direct translation from the Greek).</p>

<p>The origin of Finnish and its relatives traces back over 5000 years to nomadic peoples of the Ural mountains in Russia that migrated westward. The details of the migration and the relations between languages are still topics of scientific debate. The closest major modern relative, <ref target="Estonian%20phrasebook">Estonian</ref>, is spoken across the Gulf of Finland. The <ref target="Saami%20phrasebook">Sámi</ref> languages of Lapland and the Murmansk Peninsula are also related, as are a host of small languages in Russia. While <ref target="Hungarian%20phrasebook">Hungarian</ref> is not by any means close, Hungary and Finland have a special relationship as Finnish for a long time was the only other Finno-Ugric language that was a main language of a sovereign country. Except for Kven in Northern Norway, Meänkieli in northern Sweden, Karelian, spoken by a minority across the eastern border, some other minority languages in Russia, and arguably Estonian, Finnish is not close to mutual intelligibility with any of its relatives.</p>

<p>Finnish is an agglunative language, and suffixes express what English expresses mostly with prepositions. For instance, <hi rend="italic">junalippu Helsinki<hi rend="bold">in</hi></hi> means "train ticket <hi rend="bold">to</hi> Helsinki", while <hi rend="italic">junalippu Helsinki</hi> is hard (but possible) to understand.</p>

<p>Also new words are often formed from the same root by endings: kirjain, kirjasin, kirjuri, kirjoitin, kirje, kirjelmä, kirjasto and kirjaamo are all substantives related to <hi rend="italic">kirja</hi>, "book" (letter, font, bookkeeper, printer, ...), and then there are related verbs and adjectives.</p>

<p>Reading signboards can be difficult as use of loan words is uncommon, and those used are not necessarily recognized. Using a dictionary, especially for longer texts, is complicated by the word inflection; also the stem of many words varies somewhat (such as <hi rend="italic">lippu</hi>, <hi rend="italic">lipun</hi> for ticket).</p>

<p>Colloquial speech differs significantly from what is described here: <hi rend="italic">(minä) olen</hi> → <hi rend="italic">mä oon</hi> ("I am"). The formal pronunciation is still more or less what you will hear in the news, what is taught in school and what is easiest for others to understand.</p>

<head>Pronunciation</head>
<p>The Finnish language is fairly easy to pronounce: it has one of the most phonetic writing systems in the world, with only a small number of simple consonants and relatively few vowel sounds.</p>

<p>Native English speakers tend to have the most problems with <hi rend="bold">vowel length</hi> and the distinction between the <hi rend="bold">front vowels</hi> (ä, ö, y) and <hi rend="bold">back vowels</hi> (a, o, u). English <hi rend="italic">does</hi> make similar distinctions – consider the "a" sounds of <hi rend="italic">father</hi> (back) and <hi rend="italic">cat</hi> (front), or the difference in the "i" sound for <hi rend="italic">bit</hi> (short) and <hi rend="italic">beat</hi> (long) – but you will need to pay extra attention to it in Finnish.</p>

<p>In Finnish, all vowels are single sounds (or "pure" vowels). Doubled letters are simply pronounced longer, but it's important to differentiate between short and long sounds. Example:</p>

<p>The basic Finnish alphabet consists of the following letters:</p>

<p>Additionally the letters <hi rend="bold">š</hi> and <hi rend="bold">ž</hi> appear in a small number of loanwords and are pronounced like English <hi rend="bold">sh</hi> and as <hi rend="bold">s</hi> in <hi rend="italic">trea<hi rend="bold">s</hi>ure</hi>, respectively. The letter <hi rend="bold">w</hi> also occurs infrequently in proper names and is treated identically to <hi rend="bold">v</hi>. Lastly, the letter <hi rend="bold">å</hi> occurs in some Swedish proper names and is pronounced like a Finnish "oo" (similar to English "aw" as in "law"). The beginning learner needs not worry about these minutiae.</p>

<head>Vowels</head>

<p>Long vowels are indicated simply by doubling the vowel in question.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> a : like <hi rend="bold">a</hi> in <hi rend="italic">f<hi rend="bold">a</hi>ther</hi>, but short and clipped</item>
<item> aa : like <hi rend="bold">a</hi> in <hi rend="italic">f<hi rend="bold">a</hi>ther</hi></item>
<item> e : like <hi rend="bold">e</hi> in <hi rend="italic">g<hi rend="bold">e</hi>t</hi></item>
<item> ee : not found in English, but just stretch out the <hi rend="italic">e</hi> sound</item>
<item> i : like <hi rend="bold">i</hi> in <hi rend="italic">b<hi rend="bold">i</hi>t</hi></item>
<item> ii : like <hi rend="bold">ee</hi> in <hi rend="italic">b<hi rend="bold">ee</hi>t</hi></item>
<item> o : like <hi rend="bold">o</hi> in <hi rend="italic">n<hi rend="bold">o</hi>r</hi></item>
<item> oo : stretch out the <hi rend="italic">o</hi> sound</item>
<item> u : like <hi rend="bold">u</hi> in <hi rend="italic">r<hi rend="bold">u</hi>le</hi> — that's the same u as in German, Italian or Spanish</item>
<item> uu : stretch out the <hi rend="italic">u</hi> sound</item>
<item> y : like German <hi rend="bold">ü</hi>, similar to <hi rend="bold">ew</hi> in <hi rend="italic">f<hi rend="bold">ew</hi> </hi> but with lips rounded (<hi rend="italic">transcribed <hi rend="bold">uu</hi> </hi>)</item>
<item> yy : not found in English, but just stretch out the <hi rend="italic">y</hi> sound</item>
<item> ä : like <hi rend="bold">a</hi> in <hi rend="italic">c<hi rend="bold">a</hi>t</hi></item>
<item> ää : like <hi rend="bold">a</hi> in <hi rend="italic">b<hi rend="bold">a</hi>d</hi></item>
<item> ö : like German <hi rend="bold">ö</hi>, similar to <hi rend="bold">e</hi> in <hi rend="italic">h<hi rend="bold">e</hi>r</hi> (<hi rend="italic">transcribed <hi rend="bold">eu</hi> </hi>)</item>
<item> öö : not found in English, but just stretch out the "ö" sound</item>
</list>


<p>Diphthongs (vowel sequences) like the <hi rend="italic">uo</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Suomi</hi> (Finland) are common. They retain the individual sounds of their vowels, but are slightly blended together to be pronounced in one "beat".</p>

<head>Consonants</head>

<p>If a Finnish consonant is <hi rend="bold">doubled</hi>, it should be pronounced lengthened. For plosives like p, t, k, this means getting your mouth ready to say it, but pausing for a moment. Hence <hi rend="italic">mato</hi> (worm) is "MA-to", but <hi rend="italic">matto</hi> (carpet) is "MAT-to".</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> b : as in English or approximated as p (rarely if ever used in native Finnish words)</item>
<item> c : only in loanwords, pronunciation approximated as s or k</item>
<item> d : as in English or as t (in native words only in conjugated words, with big variations between dialects)</item>
<item> f : as in English or approximated as v (rarely if ever used in native Finnish words)</item>
<item> g : like <hi rend="bold">g</hi> in <hi rend="italic"> <hi rend="bold">g</hi>et</hi> or approximated as k (rarely if ever used in native Finnish words, except in ng, see below)</item>
<item> h : like <hi rend="bold">h</hi> in <hi rend="italic"> <hi rend="bold">h</hi>otel</hi>, pronounced more strongly before a consonant</item>
<item> j : like <hi rend="bold">y</hi> in <hi rend="italic"> <hi rend="bold">y</hi>es</hi></item>
<item> k : similar to English <hi rend="bold">k</hi>, but unaspirated and slightly voiced</item>
<item> ks : like English <hi rend="bold">x</hi></item>
<item> l m n : as in English</item>
<item> ng : like <hi rend="bold">ng</hi> in <hi rend="italic">si<hi rend="bold">ng</hi></hi></item>
<item> nk : as ng + k</item>
<item> p : similar to English <hi rend="bold">p</hi>, but unaspirated and slightly voiced</item>
<item> r : trilled, as in Spanish pe<hi rend="bold">rr</hi>o</item>
<item> s : like <hi rend="bold">ss</hi> in <hi rend="italic">hi<hi rend="bold">ss</hi> </hi></item>
<item> t : as in English</item>
<item> v w : like <hi rend="bold">v</hi> in <hi rend="italic"> <hi rend="bold">v</hi>ine</hi></item>
<item> z : like <hi rend="bold">ts</hi> in <hi rend="italic">ca<hi rend="bold">ts</hi> </hi> (not used in native Finnish words)</item>
</list>
</text>
