<text id="autogum_voyage_doc277" title="Huaihua" shortTile="huaihua" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=132860" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Huaihua</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Huaihua</hi> (怀化, Huáihuà) is in western <ref target="Hunan">Hunan</ref>, southwestern China. It is a prefecture-level city in a mountainous area with some rural poverty problems. The city itself has a population around 400,000, the prefecture as a whole 5 million.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The prefecture encompasses several autonomous ethnic counties, towns and villages.</p>
<p>Major ethnic groups found here are the Dòng or Kam (侗族), Miáo or Hmong (苗族), Tǔjiā (土家族), and Yáo (瑶族).</p>
<p>It was long inhabited by these ethnic group before the arrival of the Han Chinese more then a thousand years ago. They are known to be indigenous to these mountainous areas. They also inhabit neighboring <ref target="Guizhou">Guizhou province</ref>.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Huaihua is located on the <ref target="Shanghai">Shanghai</ref>-<ref target="Kunming">Kunming</ref> railway line, which now host both fast and regular trains.</p>
<p>1 hour and a half by fast train and 5 to 9 hours on regular trains from <ref target="Changsha">Changsha</ref>.</p>
<p>1 hour and 15 minutes by fast train and 3 to 5 hours on regular trains to <ref target="Kaili">Kaili</ref> in <ref target="Guizhou">Guizhou</ref> province.</p>

<p>Regular trains also go northwest towards <ref target="Chongqing">Chongqing</ref> and it takes between 8 to 18 hours. Check out schedules and journey time on 12306.com, because it can vary in an exaggerated way.</p>

<p>There are trains to <ref target="Zhangjiajie">Zhangjiajie</ref> as well.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Huaihua Zhijiang Airport</hi> ( HJJ ). Has flights from several cities in China. </item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>
<p>The two train stations in the north and south of the city are connected via bus number 12 (~30 minutes).</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>Huaihua City itself has nothing to offer a tourist. All the main attractions and ethnic towns are out of the city, in Huaihua Prefecture, and can be reached by bus.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tongdao Dong autonomous county</hi> (通道侗族自治县). Visit Kam people, whose language is a branch of the Tai-Kadai linguistic family. A distant relative of the Thai people.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jingzhou Miao and Dong Autonomous County</hi> (靖州苗族侗族自治县). Visit Hmong people, whose language is a branch of the Hmong-Mien linguistic family.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hongjiang old commercial town</hi> (洪江古商城). A Ming dynasty town that flourished back in the old days. Has a ancient brothel with waxwork figures and it explains a lot about the local lives back in imperial China.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Qianyang old town</hi> (黔阳古镇).</item>
<item> The airport is of some historic importance—back in World War II it was known as <hi rend="bold">Chihkiang Airfield</hi> and used by the U.S. air force. Nowadays there's a museum about the airport's history.</item>
<item> World War II general Su Yu (粟裕) was born in Huitong County, and it's possible to visit historic sites related to his life.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Wanfu Mountain</hi> (万福山 Wànfúshān).</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Pao Cai</hi> (泡菜) or pickled vegetables are found everywhere around the city. It's a must try if you are in this dusty city.</p>

<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Fenghuang">Fenghuang</ref> – well-preserved ancient town</item>
</list>


<p>Go east to <ref target="Changsha">Changsha</ref>, the provincial capital, west to Tongren(not to be confused with the one in Qinghai province) or <ref target="Kaili">Kaili</ref> in <ref target="Guizhou">Guizhou</ref> province, south to <ref target="Guangxi">Guangxi</ref> Province or northwest to <ref target="Chongqing">Chongqing</ref>.</p>

<p>From Chongqing or Changsha there are <ref target="High-speed%20rail%20in%20China">fast trains</ref> all over China. A route popular with tourists is from Changsha to <ref target="Guiyang">Guiyang</ref> and on to <ref target="Kunming">Kunming</ref>.</p>
</text>
