<text id="autogum_voyage_doc159" title="Nordkalottleden" shortTile="nordkalottleden" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=162759" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Nordkalottleden</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.nationalparks.fi/en/nordkalottledentrail">Nordkalottleden</ref></hi> (Swedish), <hi rend="bold">Nordkalottruta</hi> (Norwegian), <hi rend="bold">Kalottireitti</hi> (Finnish) or the <hi rend="bold">Arctic trail</hi> is a long-distance hiking trail in <ref target="Finnish%20Lapland">Finnish Lapland</ref> (70 km), <ref target="Northern%20Norway">Northern Norway</ref> (380 km) and <ref target="Norrland">Swedish Norrland</ref> (350 km), crossing borders many times. It features varying Arctic fell landscapes, including high fells, fell heaths, lakes and fell birch forests. Much of the trail is above the treeline, on two legs for several days.</p>

<p>Most of the trail is through wilderness, often with roads or dwellings not seen for days. The only town close to the trail is the small Kautokeino at the northern trailhead. In season you will meet people, but not every day, and even on the most busy stretches not all the time. Much of the trail, perhaps half of it, is through national parks and other protected areas. The area is used as reindeer pasture and for fishing, berry picking and similar, so there are locals, but population is very sparse.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>The trail goes through Arctic wilderness, including some rough terrain at quite high altitudes, with long distances between huts on some legs. You should be reasonably fit and at least somebody in the company should have enough hiking experience and experience of handling <ref target="cold%20weather">cold weather</ref>. You should also have equipment that you can trust in adverse conditions. The trail is in no way extreme, but you should be able to handle also unlikely nasty surprises, as in finding an alternative route if the spring floods took your bridge, or as in waiting out a snow storm in summer. Some legs are suitable also for a less experienced company.</p>

<p>Distance between huts varies from 10 to 50 km, depending partly on popularity of the specific leg. Also standards vary considerably, from the Spartan open wilderness huts in Finland (and a few minimal turf huts and emergency huts you can choose to use) through the <hi rend="italic">obetjent</hi> variety of Norwegian huts and manned Swedish huts with some service but with the expectation of guests taking care of themselves, to the fjällstation with restaurant and at least hostel like accommodation. As you will probably be carrying your own tent, hiking mattresses, sleeping bags and cutlery anyhow, the standard of individual huts is not necessarily that important, but some extra service may feel good after days in the wilderness.</p>

<p>You can follow marked trails all the way in normal conditions, but the markings, the terrain and the condition of the trail vary quite a lot. Although you may find your way easily on some legs, using your map is necessary on others. Fog is common on some legs, and reduced sight can be a major problem in open areas. Much of the time you walk on rolling fell heaths and through sparse fell birch forest, where walking is easy, but there are quite a lot of legs with steep grades, and there are passages where the terrain is mostly boulders and good boots are needed. There are many fords, some of which can be difficult or even impossible at high waters, and quite some wetlands on some legs. You may see several glaciers, but you do not have to cross any. No climbing either – unless you choose such a sidetrip.</p>

<p>The trail was opened in 1993, mostly combining existing shorter trails. It coincides with other trails on a number of legs, notably with the newer <ref target="Long%20distance%20walking%20in%20Europe">European long distance path E1</ref> from Kautokeino to the tripoint after Kilpisjärvi and perhaps elsewhere, with <ref target="Grenses%C3%B8mmen">Grensesømmen</ref> from the tripoint to the Ny Sulitjelma hut, with <ref target="Nordlandsruta">Nordlandsruta</ref> (part of?) the distance from Gautelihytta to Ny-Sulitjelma, and with the <ref target="Padjelantaleden">Padjelantaleden</ref> and <ref target="Kungsleden">Kungsleden</ref> on some legs. Some of these other trails are much more busy than the Nordkalottleden, so you may walk for days hardly meeting anybody and then find more people on the trail and huts crowded the next few days. Huts close to trailheads are also likely to be more busy, but as trailheads usually are on the end of a long dirt road, often a day's hike from Nordkalottleden, day hikers are not a common sight.</p>

<p>The <ref target="right%20to%20access">right to access</ref> allows you to deviate from the trail if you like, also when there is no alternative marked route. The trail may be flooded by a river, a bridge may be absent, or you might want to climb a nearby peak or pick berries on a bog, or just prefer another route. In some areas the right is however restricted, mostly in nature reserves. Check the rules for such areas and be cautious in any unfamiliar type of terrain (as there sometimes is a serious reason for the trail to avoid a seemingly nice route).</p>

<p>Mosquitos, black flies and their friends (known collectively as <hi rend="italic">räkkä</hi> in Finnish) are a nuisance in the Nordic summer, here in the north more or less from Midsummer to August. The Nordkalottleden trail is above the treeline for much of the distance, where the wind keeps most of them away, but in valleys they may be plentiful, and on still and moist days there may be quite some räkkä also on higher ground. Long sleeves, insect repellent and a mosquito hat – and a mosquito-proof tent – may be necessary to keep you sane (the räkkä is not otherwise dangerous: they carry no diseases and you need to get hundreds of bites for them to affect you other than having the itch). Keep the door closed when using huts. You could also time your trek for August–September, when most are gone (although exact dates vary by year and location).</p>

<p>There is plenty of good water along the trail, so you need to carry water only for some hours' need. In warm weather you might want to boil it for a few minutes to be safe, but few hikers bother to. Streams coming directly from glaciers (you will notice the strange colour) has lots of particles and should not be used for drinking or cooking.</p>

<p>You are allowed to make campfires on most of the trail, unless there is risk for wildfire (announced or otherwise). In Norway open fire is also disallowed in or near forests in summertime, except at designated camp fire sites, in Finland you always need landowner permission, but you have it in the Käsivarsi Wilderness Area. In Sweden campfires are generally allowed, but restricted in Abisko National Park. There are long distances with little firewood. There are cooking facilities in the huts, but some huts may be crowded. A <ref target="Outdoor%20cooking">portable stove</ref> is more or less necessary.</p>

<p>The trail is described from north to south. That way you gain in mountain height but lose in latitude. The other way round could be equally good.</p>
</text>
