<text id="autogum_voyage_doc213" title="Kurashiki" shortTile="kurashiki" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=18477" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kurashiki</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://world.kankou-kurashiki.jp/eng/">Kurashiki</ref></hi> (倉敷) is one of Japan's great old merchant towns, with around half a million citizens today. Sitting along a scenic canal at the foot of Mt. Tsurugata, Kurashiki's white-walled storehouses are beautifully preserved and open for exploration.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>During the Edo period, Kurashiki did heavy trade with <ref target="Tokyo">the capital</ref> in rice, sugar, and other goods. Later, during the Meiji Restoration (i.e. after 1868), the city became known for textiles. Kurashiki escaped <ref target="Pacific%20War">World War II</ref> largely unscathed, and as a result, many of the original storehouses, mills, and shops remain in beautiful condition, open to visitors in the <hi rend="bold">Bikan Historic Area</hi>.</p>

<p>The effect is delightful — storehouses (倉 <hi rend="italic">kura</hi>) with lattice windows share space with weeping willows along the banks of the old canal, which is illuminated at night. The canal has led some overly optimistic tourist associations to call Kurashiki "the Venice of Japan". If not that — the city surrounding the Bikan area is as much a concrete jumble as any other in the country — Kurashiki is still a rare piece of old Japan, one that gives a sense of where people lived and worked, not merely the temples at which they worshipped.</p>

<head>Tourist information</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">JR Kurashiki Station</hi>, ☏ +81 86-424-1220 . 09:00-17:00. Exit the train station to the south (left from JR ticket collection), overlooking the bus depot. Stay on the upper level, and you'll find the office among the shops to the right (west).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bikan Historic Area</hi>, 1-4-8 Chuo-dori, ☏ +81 86-422-0542 . 09:00-17:00.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">JR Shin-Kurashiki Station</hi>, ☏ +81 86-526-8446 . 09:00-17:00.</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>
<p>A shuttle bus will take you from the <ref target="Okayama">Okayama</ref> airport to JR Kurashiki Station in approximately 45 minutes (¥1130). Tickets can be purchased from a vending machine outside of the airport. Large luggage is okay; the driver will stow it underneath the seats. Staff at the information booth just beyond baggage claim are very helpful, and will go outside with you to purchase the ticket and get you on the appropriate bus.</p>

<p>Connections can also be made with the <ref target="Hiroshima">Hiroshima</ref> airport, via shuttle bus to Okayama (2 hours, ¥2100).</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Kurashiki is on the San'yo Main Line between Okayama and <ref target="Fukuyama">Fukuyama</ref>.</p>

<p>The best way to reach Kurashiki from the San'yo Shinkansen is to transfer to a local train at Okayama; the ride takes about 15 minutes (¥320). The few express trains between Okayama and Kurashiki are more than twice as expensive, and will only save you a couple of minutes. However, if you have a Japan Rail Pass, you can take either a local or a limited express; on the latter, hop onto any non-reserved car and simply flash your rail pass to the conductor, declaring Kurashiki as your destination.</p>

<p>The Shinkansen stops at <hi rend="bold">Shin-Kurashiki</hi> Station (新倉敷), another 10 minutes down the San'yo Main Line, but only with the all-stops <hi rend="italic">Kodama</hi> trains. It's about 10 minutes on the local train from JR Kurashiki Station to Shin-Kurashiki Station.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>Several companies run daytime and overnight bus routes from <ref target="Tokyo">Tokyo</ref>, <ref target="Osaka">Osaka</ref>, <ref target="Kobe">Kobe</ref>, <ref target="Matsuyama">Matsuyama</ref>, <ref target="Tokushima">Tokushima</ref>, <ref target="Kochi%20%28Shikoku%29">Kochi</ref>, <ref target="Fukuoka">Fukuoka</ref>, and elsewhere. Operators include <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.chugoku-jrbus.co.jp/">Chugoku JR Bus Company</ref></hi> (+81 86-236-1123). Buses arrive and depart outside the north exit of JR Kurashiki Station.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Most of the sights in Kurashiki are in and around the Bikan area, which is easily reached on foot from the south exit of JR Kurashiki Station — about a ten-minute walk down Chuo-dori or the Ebisu-dori covered arcade.</p>

<head>Bikan Historic Area</head>

<p>Even if you're not interested in the subject of a certain museum, the chance to explore inside these old warehouses and mills might be worth the price of admission. Virtually all of the museums (and many of the stores) are closed on Mondays, which does at least mean fewer crowds and photo hounds competing for that perfect shot at the foot of a bridge.</p>

<p>For a terrific view of the entire Bikan area, head up the granite stairs on <hi rend="bold">Mt. Tsurugata</hi> to the <hi rend="bold">Achi Shrine</hi>, and have a wander around the park at the top.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ohara Museum of Art</hi> (大原美術館, ōhara bijutsukan), 1-1-15 Chuo-dori, ☏ +81 86-422-0005 . Tu-Su 09:00-17:00. Houses a deservedly renowned collection of classic European and American art, including major works by Picasso, Renoir, Monet, Matisse, and many others. There's another building for exhibitions by modern Japanese artists, which tend to be very good. Set aside some time to wander the grounds as well, with Rodin statues out front, a small sculpture garden out back, and neoclassical columns beatifically out of character with the rest of the area. ¥1300 adults (includes Kojima Torajiro Memorial Hall admission). English audio guide for main hall ¥500.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kojima Torajiro Memorial Hall</hi> (児島虎次郎記念館), 7-1 Hon-machi (Ivy Square), ☏ +81 86-422-0005 . Tu-Su 09:00-17:00. Dedicated to the work of the Japanese artist who directed the acquisition of most of the Ohara Museum's collection. ¥1300 adults (includes Ohara Museum admission).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Archaeological Museum</hi> (倉敷考古館), 1-3-13 Chuo-dori, ☏ +81 86-422-1542 . W-Su 09:00-17:00. Housed in a particularly lovely old rice warehouse, this museum has Japanese, Chinese, and even Incan artifacts on display. ¥400 adults, ¥250 students.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Japan Rural Toy Museum</hi> (日本郷土玩具館), 1-4-16 Chuo-dori, ☏ +81 86-422-8058 . Tu-Su 09:00-17:00. Has a collection of over 40,000 toys, although only 5,000 or so are generally on display. Most are show-pieces (and occasionally eerie ones at that), but there are some that kids can play with hands-on. ¥300 adults, ¥200 teenagers, ¥100 kids.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Museum of Folkcraft</hi> (倉敷民藝館), 1-4-11 Chuo-dori, ☏ +81 86-422-1637 . Tu-Su 09:00-17:00 (Dec-Feb to 16:15). Hosts excellent seasonal and permanent exhibitions of Japanese folk crafts. Even if you're not captivated by the subject matter, the space in which it's housed — three vintage structures connected by narrow corridors and old stairwells — is worth checking out. ¥700 adults, ¥400 students.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Senichi Hoshino Museum</hi> (星野仙一記念館, hoshino sen'ichi kinenkan), 1-10-11 Chuo-dori, ☏ +81 86-430-0001 . Apr-Sep: 09:30-18:00, Oct-Mar: 09:30-17:00. Kurashiki native Sen'ichi Hoshino was a long-time pitcher and manager for the Chunichi Dragons of Japanese pro baseball; now, as manager and director of the Hanshin Tigers, his open hatred of the Yomiuri Giants has renewed focus. This recently-opened museum collects some of his memorabilia and career highlights. Adults ¥500, students ¥200.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shogi Master Oyama Memorial Museum</hi> (大山名人記念館), 1-18-1 Chuo-dori, ☏ +81 86-434-0003 . Th-Tu 09:00-17:15, F to 21:00. Yasuharu Oyama (1923-1992), also a Kurashiki native, was an eighteen time world champion of <hi rend="italic">shogi</hi>; upon his retirement, he was crowned the 15th Lifetime <hi rend="italic">Meijin</hi> (Grand Master) of the game. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Momotaro Museum</hi> (桃太郎のからくり博物館), 5-11 Hon-machi, ☏ +81 86-423-2008 . Tu-Su 10:00-17:00. With the figure of Momotaro outside and souvenirs sold inside, it is often mistaken by foreign tourists as just another shop and a cute photo-op, but this building is actually a "museum of mystery" dedicated to Momotaro, the Peach Boy. The museum features a variety of fun and interactive mind tricks that bear no real connection to the tale but are quite fun, especially for children. From there, prepare yourself for a walk through the dark lair of the ogres that Momotaro defeated before ascending the stairs to see some historical depictions of the tale and other items of nostalgia. Adults ¥600, young students ¥400, children ¥100.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Yumiko Igarashi Museum</hi> (いがらしゆみこ美術館), 9-3 Hon-machi, ☏ +81 86-426-1919 . 09:00-18:00. Memorabilia and artwork from <hi rend="italic">Candy Candy</hi>, one of the most popular <hi rend="italic">manga</hi> among Japanese girls and a cult favorite overseas. (There is, however, no actual candy here.) ¥600 adults, ¥400 students.</item>
</list>
</text>
