<text id="autogum_voyage_doc14" title="Abancay">
<head>Abancay</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Abancay</hi> is in the department of <ref target="Apurimac%20%28department%29">Apurimac</ref>, <ref target="Peru">Peru</ref> in a valley over the <ref target="Pachachaca%20%28river%29">Pachachaca</ref> river. The population is 58,000, and with an altitude of 2,378 m.</p>

<p>Abancay is part of Peru's <ref target="Southern%20Sierra%20%28Peru%29">Southern Sierra</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">Tourist Office</hi> is next to the Plaza de Armas.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>All buses on the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Lima">Lima</ref>-<ref target="Nasca">Nasca</ref>-<ref target="Cusco">Cusco</ref></hi> Interoceánica Sur line pass through Abancay. The</p>
<p>road is well paved.</p>

<p>There are daily <hi rend="bold">buses</hi> from and to <ref target="Andahuaylas">Andahuaylas</ref>, one of the closest <hi rend="bold">airports </hi>. This journey takes 5 to 6 hours on an unpaved road. The closest airport is in <ref target="Cusco">Cusco</ref>, a 4½-5 hour drive on a bus or a 3½-4 hour drive in a "colectivo" (taxi car)</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Distances are short, so walking is your best options for getting around. If you need a taxi, don't pay more than S/3 (<ref target="Peru%23Money">soles</ref>) in the city.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">AMPAY</hi> (mountain and tree species) protected area (sanctuary). Get the collectivo 2 (70 centimos) to Sawanay. From there ask for "camino del ampay". You'll reach the park's house. If somebody is at the hut at the entrance the fee would be S/30 to enter, it`s better to go because the way begin in this place, and they´ll give you informations if you're going by yourself (you can also pay a guide in the municipalidad, S/30 for the day). The way is hard, 3 km for the first laguna, 4 more to the second and you'll see the Nevada Ampay. Possible to make a loop but long (more than 20 km). Better in dry season.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Swimming in natural water pool</item>
<item> Cock fights</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Take a hike</hi>. Mountains (foothills) rise abruptly from the North and South end of town, allowing you to be in a beautiful setting with stunning views very quickly. From the center of town, walk downhill and cross the river. Head for the radio tower up on the hill (south). From here, a large wide trail that's cut into the side of the mountains proceeds west along the side of the folded ridges. A lovely walk that goes on for miles. Nice at sunset. Bring a flashlight in case it gets dark as you're coming back - it's a steep drop-off the side of the trail.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<p>Avenida Arenas, which turns into Arequipa, is the main drag through town. You can find all manner of restaurants and bars along this strip. Also a market for picking up fruits and vegetables. There are also a couple of supermarkets along this street. Paralleling this street one block further uphill is another avenue with a fair amount of shops and restaurants, including a vegetarian one.</p>

<head>Sleep</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">El Dorado</hi>, Av. Arenas, good and safe, ca. US$5.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Turistas (old hacienda)</hi>,splurge with hot water and dining-room.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Paraiso</hi>, across from the bus terminal. S/30 for a matrimonial with bano privado. Nice place, television, but lacked hot water despite the claims.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Saywa Hotel</hi>, 302 Av. Arenas, ☏ +51 83 32-4876 . A good value for the price. Nice rooms with real, strong hot water showers, cable TV, and a fast connection of WiFi. Rooms on the front have fantastic views overlooking the park and mountains behind. Price includes breakfast. Price for a single room is normally S/50 per night, but can be talked down to S/40.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<p>You can visit the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Canyon%20of%20Apurimac">Canyon of Apurimac</ref> (Cañon de Apurimac)</hi> and cross it on a hanging bridge. Take a bus towards Cusco and exit after ca. 1h at the village of <ref target="Curuahuasi">Curuahuasi</ref>. Then go to Cachora - you can rent mules,horses and guides (canyon depth approx. 1000 m - one of the deepest in the world)</p>

<p>If you have 3 days, you can climb the canyon at the other side and</p>
<p>visit the recently discovered and only 30% excavated ruins of an Inca</p>
<p>city (Choquequirao). Guides are easily found via the tourist office in Abancay.</p>

<p>From Abancay to Puquio the bus costs S/40 and the first one of the day leaves at 12:00 (Palamino). The views and country along this route are great, but it is windy.</p>
</text>
