<text id="autogum_voyage_doc460" title="Loch Lomond and The Trossachs National Park" shortTile="loch-lomond-trossachs" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=19981" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Loch Lomond and The Trossachs National Park</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.lochlomond-trossachs.org/">Loch Lomond and The Trossachs National Park</ref></hi> straddles the two regions of the <ref target="Scottish%20Highlands">Scottish Highlands</ref> and the <ref target="Central%20Belt">Central Belt</ref> of <ref target="Scotland">Scotland</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Scotland's first national park is located north-west of <ref target="Glasgow">Glasgow</ref> with train access at <ref target="Balloch">Balloch</ref>, Arrochar/<ref target="Tarbet">Tarbet</ref>, <ref target="Ardlui">Ardlui</ref> and Crainlarich. It is divided into four distinct areas:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Loch Lomond</hi> is the largest loch in Scotland, the largest body of fresh water in Britain and probably the most famous after <ref target="Loch%20Ness">Loch Ness</ref>. The southern end of the loch is quite flat, but the scenery soon becomes more mountainous and distinctly wild by the time you reach the north end.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.trossachs.co.uk/">The Trossachs</ref></hi>, Loch Katrine and Loch Array are in the north-east</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://scotland.forestry.gov.uk/forest-parks/argyll-forest-park">Argyll Forest</ref></hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.breadalbane.org/">The Breadalbane</ref></hi></item>
</list>


<head>Visitor centres</head>
<p>There is one national park visitor centre:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">National Park Visitor Centre Balmaha</hi>, <ref target="Balmaha">Balmaha</ref>, G63 OJQ (in the pretty village of Balmaha, East Loch Lomond), ☏ +44 1389 722100 . A stop-off point for walkers on the West Highland Way, local produce and top-up supplies.</item>
</list>


<head>Towns and villages</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Arrochar">Arrochar</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Callander">Callander</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Crianlarich">Crianlarich</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Ardlui">Ardlui</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Inverbeg">Inverbeg</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Balloch">Balloch</ref> — located at the southern end of Loch Lomond, it is the main town on the loch, and can get busy. The <hi rend="italic">Loch Lomond Shores</hi> TIC/visitors centre can help you plan your stay and provide you with close-area maps. Has a railway station.</item>
<item> <ref target="Luss">Luss</ref> — a town without any attractions other than its beautiful appearance and cottages, which are still worth a visit.</item>
<item> <ref target="Rowardennan">Rowardennan</ref> — this village makes a great base to explore Ben Lomond.</item>
<item> <ref target="Drymen">Drymen</ref> — good base for the Conic Hill, also a nice pub (claimed to be the oldest in Scotland) and Buchanan castle.</item>
<item> <ref target="Tarbet">Tarbet</ref> — a large village near the centre of the west shore with railway station</item>
</list>


<p><hi rend="bold">Islands</hi></p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.lochlomond-trossachs.org/things-to-see/inchcailloch/">Inchcailloch</ref></hi> — the largest island in the loch</item>
</list>


<head>History</head>
<p>The Loch Lomond and the Trossachs National Park was the first national park established in Scotland. It became fully operational on 19 July 2002 and was officially opened by Princess Anne on 24 July 2002.</p>

<head>Landscape</head>
<p>The National Park encompasses around 720 sq miles (1,865 km) of land including the Loch Lomond area and The Trossachs region.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<ref target="http://www.scotrail.co.uk/">ScotRail</ref> local trains run frequently from <ref target="Glasgow">Glasgow</ref>'s Queen Street Station low level to <ref target="Balloch">Balloch</ref> which is at the end of the line, taking about 50 minutes, with generally two trains per hour. The station in Balloch is easy to find.

<p>Several trains run daily between <ref target="Glasgow">Glasgow</ref> and <ref target="Oban">Oban</ref>, <ref target="Fort%20William">Fort William</ref> and <ref target="Mallaig">Mallaig</ref> which stop at <ref target="Tarbet">Tarbet</ref> and <ref target="Ardlui">Ardlui</ref> on the north-west shore and at Crainlarich in the northern part of the park. These leave from the upper level of Glasgow's Queen Street station.</p>

<p>The <ref target="https://www.sleeper.scot/">Caledonian Sleeper</ref> from <ref target="London">London</ref> also runs up here.</p>

<ref target="Garelochhead">Garelochhead</ref>, <ref target="Arrochar">Arrochar</ref>/<ref target="Tarbet">Tarbet</ref>, <ref target="Ardlui">Ardlui</ref>, <ref target="Crianlarich">Crianlarich</ref>, <ref target="Tyndrum">Tyndrum</ref> are all on the <ref target="West%20Highland%20Railway">West Highland Railway</ref>, which has around three trains per day from <ref target="Glasgow">Glasgow</ref> Queen Street main level to <ref target="Oban">Oban</ref> and <ref target="Fort%20William">Fort William</ref>.

<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The A82 road up the shore of Loch Lomond is used by the Citylink buses (3 per day) from <ref target="Glasgow">Glasgow</ref> to <ref target="Fort%20William">Fort William</ref>.</item>
<item> Citylink buses from <ref target="Glasgow">Glasgow</ref> to <ref target="Campbeltown">Campbeltown</ref> go up Loch Lomond as far as Tarbet and then pass <ref target="Arrochar">Arrochar</ref> and <ref target="Cairndow">Cairndow</ref> on the way to <ref target="Inveraray">Inveraray</ref>.</item>
<item> Citylink buses from <ref target="Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref> via <ref target="Stirling">Stirling</ref> to <ref target="Fort%20William">Fort William</ref> pass <ref target="Callander">Callander</ref> and <ref target="Crianlarich">Crianlarich</ref>.</item>
</list>

<p>Buses run frequently between <ref target="Balloch">Balloch</ref> and <ref target="Glasgow">Glasgow</ref>.</p>

<head>By car</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> From <ref target="Oban">Oban</ref> follow the A85, which runs parallel to the train line, and you will enter the park from its north-western boundary. On this route you also pass by Kilchurn Castle at Lake Awe.</item>
<item> From <ref target="Stirling">Stirling</ref> follow the A84 and you will enter the park from its eastern boundary at <ref target="Callander">Callander</ref>.</item>
</list>


<head>Fees and permits</head>
<p>No permit is required to enter the park or explore on foot, by bicycle or by road. Permits may be required for fishing, or some boat use.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>An excellent reference tool for planning your journey is the <ref target="http://www.travelinescotland.com/">travelinescotland website and journey planner</ref> for all bus, rail, coach, air and ferry services in Scotland. Also open 24 hours by phone on 0871 200 22 33.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Buses run along Loch Lomand, but not that frequently. You should check the departure-times first, as timetable are not usually available at the stops. The National Park Authority publishes a timetable of all the <ref target="http://www.lochlomond-trossachs.org">buses and ferries</ref> which may be available as a booklet locally.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>If you're driving, mind that the road along the northern part of Loch Lomond is pretty narrow for the traffic it has.</p>

<head>By boat</head>
<p>Sightseeing trips by boat on Loch Lomond run from <hi rend="italic">Loch Lomond Shores</hi> near Balloch.</p>

<p>There is also a useful passenger ferry between <hi rend="bold">Inverbeg</hi> (served by Citylink buses) and <hi rend="bold">Rowardennan</hi> (at the foot of Ben Lomond mountain).</p>

<p>The steamship <hi rend="bold">SS Sir Walter Scott</hi> offers cruises on Loch Katrine in the Trossachs. There are connecting buses from <ref target="Callander">Callander</ref> and <ref target="Stirling">Stirling</ref> for some services.</p>

<head>By bike</head>
<p>To enjoy the nature, it is best to go by bike. There's a (relatively!) well-maintained and -signposted cycleway from Glasgow to Balloch called National Route 7. A good place to join it is Bells Bridge over the Clyde by the SECC (Scottish Exhibition and Conference Center). It's a fairly flat 20–25 miles.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Queen Elizabeth Forest Park</hi> (From Glasgow follow signs on M8 for Aberfoyle. From Stirling/Callander follow A81 to Aberfoyle via Dukes Pass).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Breadalbane Folklore Centre</hi>, Killin (Easily reached from Aberfeldy and Kenmore (via the A827 along the shores of Loch Tay), and from Crianlarich and Lochearnhead (via the A85 and A827)). April to October 10AM - 5PM. Overlooks The Falls of Dochart at the western end of Killin. Discover the story of Scotland's 'High Country'. Adult £2.75, Child (5-16) £1.80.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Falls of Dochart</hi>, Killin.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Glen Ogle Viaduct</hi> (Between Lochearnhead and Killin). A hiking trail starting in Lochearnhead is described on <ref target="http://www.walkhighlands.co.uk/lochlomond/glen-ogle.shtml">walkhighlands</ref>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Inchmahome Priory</hi>, Lake of Menteith (along the A81), ☏ +44 1877 385294 . Nov-Mar closed. An Augustinian monastery on an island, where Mary Stuart once hid from Henry VIII. A ferry runs to the island, but is only operated in summer. Lake of Menteith is one of the very few lakes in Scotland referred to as "lake" and not as "loch".</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Falls of Falloch</hi> (North of Loch Lommond on the A82 and the <ref target="West%20Highland%20Way">West Highland Way</ref></item>
</list>

 ).

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Benmore Botanic Gardens</hi>. See <ref target="Dunoon">Dunoon</ref>.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kilmun Arboretum</hi>.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Loch Lomond Shores</hi>, Balloch. See <ref target="Balloch">Balloch</ref>.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Balloch Castle Country Park</hi>, Balloch. See <ref target="Balloch">Balloch</ref>.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Luss Village Paths</hi>, Luss (along the A82). A beautiful town with four walks around town and a sandy <hi rend="bold">beach</hi>. A map can be picked up at Balloch TIC or at the Luss Visitor Information.</item>
</list>
</text>
