<text id="autogum_voyage_doc384" title="Botswana" shortTile="botswana" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=4409" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Botswana</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.botswana-tourism.gov.bw/">Botswana</ref></hi> is a land-locked country located in <ref target="Southern%20Africa">Southern Africa</ref> and bordering on <ref target="Namibia">Namibia</ref>, <ref target="South%20Africa">South Africa</ref>, <ref target="Zimbabwe">Zimbabwe</ref> and <ref target="Zambia">Zambia</ref>. Formerly the British protectorate of Bechuanaland, Botswana adopted its new name upon independence in 1966. Its economy, one of the most robust on the continent, is dominated by diamond mining and tourism.</p>

<p>Botswana is famous for its wildlife, and areas like <ref target="Chobe%20National%20Park">Chobe National Park</ref>, <ref target="Moremi%20Game%20Reserve">Moremi Game Reserve</ref> in the <ref target="Okavango%20Delta">Okavango Delta</ref>, and the <ref target="Central%20Kalahari%20Game%20Reserve">Central Kalahari Game Reserve</ref> have a very high concentration of game. The bulk of the Kalahari desert falls within Botswana's borders and Botswana is home to most of the world's San (Bushman) population.</p>
<head>Cities</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> or <hi rend="italic">Gabs</hi> – a neat and tidy little capital, but with rapidly growing shantytowns on its periphery</item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> - A unique geological formation where a delta is formed by a river (the Okavango) flowing into the Kalahari desert instead of the ocean. Part of the Delta is designated as <ref target="Moremi%20Game%20Reserve">Moremi Game Reserve</ref></item>
<item> </item>
<item> - a great place to see wildlife, and a good point from which to move on to <ref target="Victoria%20Falls">Victoria Falls</ref>.</item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> - a unique corner of Africa where nature &amp; culture combine in spectacular wildlife, stunning scenery and fascinating history</item>
</list>


<p>See also <ref target="African%20National%20Parks">African National Parks</ref></p>

<head>History</head>
<p>Botswana was never colonized by Europeans. Instead, the Three Chiefs went to the Queen of England to ask for protection from Boers to the south and Ndebele tribes from the north-east. The Boers were (to them) the white people that had invaded and were taking over South Africa. The Queen obliged. In 1964 the Three Chiefs went back to England and told the Queen that they did not need the protection any more. The Queen did away with the protection, and the Chiefs went back to Botswana. Botswana discovered diamonds in 1965. They produce 65% of the world diamonds today. In 1969 DeBeers created a partnership with the Botswana government to create the company Debswana.</p>

<head>Government</head>

<p>Botswana has been a stable representative democracy since independence and has been largely devoid of the racial and ethnic conflict some of its neighbours have suffered from — perhaps due in part to the relative dominance of its majority Tswana ethnic group. Since the turn of the century, thousands of Zimbabweans have sought sanctuary and economic betterment.</p>

<p>One of the poorest countries at independence, Botswana transformed itself into one of the fastest-growing economies in the world with a GDP (purchasing power parity) per capita of about USD14,000 <hi rend="italic">per annum</hi>. In contrast to the sad situation of its eastern neighbour, Zimbabwe, kleptocracy has been absent and Botswana now also has the second highest Human Development Index of all continental Sub-Saharan African countries.</p>

<head>Public holidays</head>
<p>The public holidays in Botswana are:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">1 January</hi>. New Year's Day</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Easter weekend</hi>. ("Good Friday", "Easter Saturday", "Easter Sunday" and "Easter Monday"): a four day long weekend in March or April set according to the Western Christian dates.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">1 May</hi>. Workers Day</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">1 July</hi>. Sir Seretse Khama Day</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mid July</hi>. President's Day</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">30 September</hi>. Botswana Day</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">25 December</hi>. Christmas Day</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">26 December</hi>. Day of Goodwill</item>
</list>


<p>The first Monday after Christmas is also a Public Holiday.</p>

<head>People</head>
<p>The <hi rend="bold">Tswana</hi>, for whom Botswana is named, comprise 79% of the population.</p>

<head>Entry requirements</head>
<p>Unlike more stiff necked administrations such as India, Pakistan, Nigeria and China, the Botswana government has not erected high bureaucratic barriers to enrichment from tourism.</p>

<p>Citizens of <hi rend="bold">Commonwealth</hi> countries do <hi rend="bold">not</hi> need a visa to visit <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">except</hi></hi> those from <ref target="Bangladesh">Bangladesh</ref>, <ref target="Cameroon">Cameroon</ref>, <ref target="Ghana">Ghana</ref>, <ref target="India">India</ref>, <ref target="Nigeria">Nigeria</ref>, <ref target="Pakistan">Pakistan</ref>, and <ref target="Sri%20Lanka">Sri Lanka</ref>.</p>

<p>Citizens of <hi rend="bold"><ref target="European%20Union">European Union</ref></hi> countries, Norway, Iceland, Liechtenstein and <ref target="Switzerland">Switzerland</ref> do <hi rend="bold">not</hi> require a visa to visit.</p>

<p>Citizens of <ref target="Argentina">Argentina</ref>, <ref target="Angola">Angola</ref>, <ref target="Bahrain">Bahrain</ref>, <ref target="Brazil">Brazil</ref>, <ref target="Chile">Chile</ref>, <ref target="Costa%20Rica">Costa Rica</ref>, <ref target="Cuba">Cuba</ref>, <ref target="Dominican%20Republic">Dominican Republic</ref>, <ref target="Israel">Israel</ref>, <ref target="Japan">Japan</ref>, <ref target="Kuwait">Kuwait</ref>, <ref target="Mexico">Mexico</ref>, <ref target="Oman">Oman</ref>, <ref target="Paraguay">Paraguay</ref>, <ref target="Peru">Peru</ref>, <ref target="Qatar">Qatar</ref>, <ref target="Russia">Russia</ref>, <ref target="Saudi%20Arabia">Saudi Arabia</ref>, <ref target="South%20Korea">South Korea</ref>, <ref target="South%20Sudan">South Sudan</ref>, <ref target="Turkey">Turkey</ref>, <ref target="United%20Arab%20Emirates">United Arab Emirates</ref>, <ref target="United%20States%20of%20America">United States of America</ref>, <ref target="Uruguay">Uruguay</ref>, <ref target="Venezuela">Venezuela</ref>, <ref target="Zimbabwe">Zimbabwe</ref> do <hi rend="bold">not</hi> require a visa to visit.</p>

<p>For citizens of <ref target="http://www.gov.bw/Ministries__Authorities/Ministries/Ministry-of-Labour__Home-Affairs-MLHA/Tools__Services/Services__Forms/Requirements-for-VISA-application/">other nations</ref>, a visa must be obtained prior to arrival and this usually takes about a week to process.</p>

<p>Visas can be applied for at a Botswana embassy in <ref target="Australia">Australia</ref>, <ref target="Belgium">Belgium</ref>, <ref target="Brazil">Brazil</ref>, <ref target="China">China</ref>, <ref target="Ethiopia">Ethiopia</ref>, <ref target="India">India</ref>, <ref target="Japan">Japan</ref>, <ref target="Kenya">Kenya</ref>, <ref target="Namibia">Namibia</ref>, <ref target="Nigeria">Nigeria</ref>, <ref target="South%20Africa">South Africa</ref>, <ref target="Sweden">Sweden</ref>, <ref target="Switzerland">Switzerland</ref>, the <ref target="United%20Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref>, <ref target="Zambia">Zambia</ref>, <ref target="Zimbabwe">Zimbabwe</ref> and at the <ref target="United%20Nations">United Nations</ref> in <ref target="NYC">New York</ref>, <ref target="USA">USA</ref>.</p>

<p>If you require a visa to enter Botswana, you might be able to apply for one at a British embassy, high commission or consulate in the country where you legally reside if there is no Botswana diplomatic post. The <ref target="https://www.gov.uk/government/collections/apply-for-a-commonwealth-visa-at-a-uk-visa-application-centre-or-embassy">UK Government website</ref> lists UK embassies around the world where Commonwealth visas can be issued. British diplomatic posts charge £50 to process a Botswana visa application and an extra £70 if the authorities in Botswana require the visa application to be referred to them. The authorities in Botswana can also decide to charge an additional fee if they correspond with you directly.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>Botswana's main airport is Sir Seretse Khama in Gaborone. International flights are to <ref target="Zimbabwe">Zimbabwe</ref>, <ref target="South%20Africa">South Africa</ref>, <ref target="Namibia">Namibia</ref>, <ref target="Kenya">Kenya</ref> and Ethiopia. The airport in Maun can also be reached via Johannesburg, Cape Town, or Gaborone and, once a day (in summer 2009), from Windhoek, Namibia. The distance between Gaborone and Maun is more than 1,000 km. Maun is very much a tourist attraction spot.</p>

<p>Airlines that fly to Gaborone are.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Air Botswana. Harare, Victoria Falls, Lusaka, Johannesburg, Cape Town.</item>
<item> Airlink. Johannesburg.</item>
<item> Ethiopian airlines. via Addis Ababa. to Europe, Asia, Africa.</item>
<item> Kenya airways. Via Nairobi to Europe. Asia, Africa.</item>
<item> TAAG Angola airlines. Luanda.</item>
<item> South African express. Johannesburg.</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>
<p>Trains to/from <ref target="South%20Africa">South Africa</ref> have been withdrawn since 1999. For domestic train service, see <ref target="%23Get%20around">#Get around</ref>.</p>
</text>
