<text id="autogum_voyage_doc363" title="Camotes Islands" shortTile="camotes-islands" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=140322" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Camotes Islands</head>


<p>The <hi rend="bold">Camotes</hi> are a small island group in the <ref target="Philippines">Philippines</ref>. Administratively, they are part of <ref target="Cebu%20Province">Cebu Province</ref> but they are some distance east of Cebu Island (63 km from Cebu City), actually closer to <ref target="Leyte">Leyte</ref>.</p>

<p>Until recently these islands did not get many tourists, though they have some fine beaches and dive sites. Now there is considerable development with several resorts and quite a few resident foreigners. </p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The group includes three main islands and one small islet. The islands of <hi rend="bold">Pacijan</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Poro</hi> are joined by a causeway; <hi rend="bold">Ponson</hi> is separate, a bit to the north.</p>
<p>There are several ports around the islands:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Poro is the main port, where the ferry from <ref target="Cebu%20City">Cebu City</ref> arrives.</item>
<item> Consuelo, for the service to/from <ref target="Danao">Danao</ref></item>
<item> Pilar, for <ref target="Ormoc">Ormoc</ref> on Leyte</item>
</list>

<p>In addition, at some other places, such as Kawit, the pumpboat is just pulled up onto the beach.</p>
<head>Talk</head>
<ref target="Cebuano">Cebuano</ref> (also called Bisayan) is the main language of the islands. English is also widely spoken.

<head>Get in</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Oceanjet</hi>. fast ferry two times a day to/from <ref target="Cebu%20City">Cebu City</ref>. Departure to Cebu: 6AM/3PM (from Poro Port), ₱500 + ₱25 port tax. Scheduled travel time is 90 minutes.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jomalia Shipping lines</hi> fast ferry Mactan to/from Consuelo port. depart Mactan at 8am-12 noon. depart Consuelo port at 10am/4pm. travel time is 80 minutes. fare is ₱500</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jomalia Shipping lines</hi> roro ferry to/from <ref target="Danao">Danao</ref> to Consuelo port (five times a day). with a fare of ₱220</item>
<item> there is also a ferry going to/from <ref target="Ormoc">Ormoc</ref> from Pilar port Camotes.</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>

<p>Rent a scooter for ₱300 a day or get a driver with a <ref target="multicab">multicab</ref>.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Lake Danao (small entrance and parking fee; restaurants available)</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> Timobo Cave (₱30 )</item>
<item> Santiago Beach (restaurants available)</item>
<item> Bukilat cave</item>
<item> View point and calvary near Timobo cave</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Walk around Poro town. Enjoy the beaches. Have a swim in the sea.</item>
<item> Rent a scooter (₱300 /day + gas) and explore the island.</item>
</list>


<head>ATM</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Development Bank</hi>. near the market in Poro town has a 24-hour ATM.</item>
</list>

<p>Only VISA cards accepted. No MasterCard withdrawal. </p>

<head>Eat</head>
<p>If you are looking for midrange restaurants, choice will be limited to the resort restaurants. Cheap eateries with lower prices and hygiene standards can be found around the island, especially at the beaches (e.g. Santiago beach) and in Poro (market area).</p>

<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Big Z Pension House</hi>. Poro Town. near the port. big fan double rooms with shared bathroom. ₱350 a night.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sea View Pension House</hi>. Poro Town. Phone 099057552398. fan double rooms with shared bathroom ₱300 a night.</item>
<item> <ref target="http://www.facebook.com/RMS-travellers-inn-Lodging-house-263343664139322%E2%99%A1%E2%9D%A4%E2%99%A1RMS"><hi rend="bold">Travelers Inn</hi></ref>. Pamatasan (400m from San francisco town Public market) . dorm bed for 290 per person. fan double room with own bathroom from 388. free wifi. a good clean low-cost place for backpackers to stay.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Seaside Guest house</hi>, 10 min walk from San francisco town. fan double room, outside bathroom, free wifi 400.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Cebu%20City">Cebu City</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Danao">Danao</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Ormoc">Ormoc</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
