<text id="autogum_voyage_doc29" title="Diving inland in South Africa/Wondergat" shortTile="diving-inland-south" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=9619" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Diving inland in South Africa/Wondergat</head>

<p>The dive site <hi rend="bold">Wondergat</hi> is an inland fresh water sinkhole and cavern near <ref target="Mafikeng">Mafikeng</ref> in the <ref target="North%20West%20Province">North West Province</ref> of <ref target="South%20Africa">South Africa</ref>. The altitude is approximately 1,450m </p>

<head>Position</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Approximately 60km from Lichtenburg and 30km from Mafikeng</item>
</list>



<p>This site is not in a Marine Protected Area. A permit is not required.</p>

<head>Name</head>
<p>The name "Wondergat" is Afrikaans for Amazing hole.</p>

<head>Depth</head>
<p>Maximum depth is about 58m. </p>

<head>Visibility</head>
<p>About 6m above 20m, and about 15m below 20m. Visibility of over 30m has been known in the cave.</p>
<head>Topography</head>

<p>Wondergat is a collapsed cavern filled with water. The hole is about 75 x 100m at the surface and the sides are near vertical to the bottom at about 36m. There are caverns extending from the main shaft to the north and south at the bottom. The bottom of these caverns slopes downward away from the main shaft. There is an overhang to the north about half wat up, and a narrow cave on the south wall, quite shallow, known as Leopards cave.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Geology:</hi> Dolomite sinkhole.</p>

<head>Conditions</head>
<p>Water temperature will be between 14 and 21°C </p>

<p>This is a summer rainfall region. Temperatures vary from 35’C in the summer to as low as -4’C at night in the winter.</p>

<p>Visibility is often better during winter because there are fewer divers kicking up a mess, and less rain runoff bringing in silt </p>

<head>Facilities</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Two permanent shotlines with grids at the bottom</item>
<item> Large capacity Air (to 300 bar) and Nitrox filling station on site.</item>
<item> Oxygen cleaning of cylinders.</item>
<item> Trimix is available on request and by prior arrangement.</item>
<item> Rental of BCs, DVs and cylinders.</item>
<item> Accommodation at Wondergat is at campsites with braai areas, and includes ablution facilities with hot and cold water.</item>
<item> Electricity is available to campsites.</item>
<item> There is a canteen, which stocks most of the basics for those who have forgotten something at home. Take-away meals can be arranged in advance.</item>
<item> Emergency oxygen provision is on site if needed</item>
<item> All South African cellular networks cover the dive site</item>
<item> The nearest medical facility is the hospital at Mafikeng, 30km away and Lightenburg Provincial hospital, 60km away.</item>
</list>

<p>Wondergat manager: Willie Halgrijn: 082 484 7887 (2012)</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>This is a shore entry site. Access is by 35 irregular steps. The walk down the steps fully kitted up requires good balance, and the return after the dive can be strenuous.</p>

<p>Public access. An entry fee is payable.</p>
<p>Adequate parking is provided and included in the entry fee.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> From Johannesburg and other places to the south and east:</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> From Pretoria and other places to the north and west:</item>
</list>


<p>Wondergat may occasionally be closed to visitors for maintenance. Phone before planning the trip to ensure it will be open when you wish to visit. </p>

<head>Aquatic life</head>

<p>The Banded Tilapia (Tilapia sparrmanii) is endemic to Wondergat. Other fish include the Sharptooth Catfish (Clarias garipinus), Southern Moutbrooder (Pseudocrenilabrus philander)</p>
<p>There are also fresh water shrimps and crabs.</p>

<head>Features</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> The south and north caverns</item>
<item> The Leopard's cave</item>
<item> A bell chamber at the bottom</item>
<item> The memorial stones and task force noticeboard at the mouth to the south cavern</item>
</list>


<head>Suggested Routes</head>
<p>Suggested routes include:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item>1. Cavern certified divers can dive from the south grid to the back of the cave</item>
<item>2. From the north grid to south grid or vice versa along the guide ropes.</item>
<item>3. From either of the grids to the Bell.</item>
<item>4. From the south grid to the Memorial stones and the Taskforce noticeboard.</item>
</list>
<head>Equipment</head>

<p>Dry suits or semi dry suits are recommend for the winter months.</p>
</text>
