<text id="autogum_voyage_doc53" title="Abra">
<head>Abra</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Abra</hi> is a province in the <ref target="Cordillera%20Administrative%20Region">Cordillera Administrative Region</ref> of the <ref target="Philippines">Philippines</ref>. With <ref target="Bangued">Bangued</ref> as its capital, it is composed of 27 municipalities and 303 barangays.</p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Get in</head>
<p>Abra is accessible to its neighboring provinces through a network of highways and roads. A typical bus trip from the country's capital, Manila, lasts about 8 to 9 hours and is quite scenic. Bus lines going to and fro the province include the Philippine Rabbit and the Partas Trans.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pinaing</hi> or Sacred Stones in Dumayco - these stones are placed in the hollow of a huge Balete tree and symbolize the spirits of village ancestors</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Don Teodoro Brillantes Family Museum</hi> - displays Spanish artifacts and personal mementos of the Brillantes family</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tugot ni Angalo</hi> - huge footprints believed to be made by a real giant in San Quintin. The prints are 15 meters long, 5 meters wide, and 10 feet deep.</item>
<item> Natural bodies of water found in the province, like the <hi rend="bold">Abra River</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Boliney Hot Springs</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Kimkimay Lake</hi>, and the <hi rend="bold">Limbo Lake</hi>.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Explore the stalagmites at the <hi rend="bold">Libtec Underground River</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Sibud-Sibud Cave</hi></item>
<item> Participate in the <hi rend="bold">Arya Abra Festival</hi>, celebrating the creation of the province, and the <hi rend="bold">Tingguian Festival</hi>, which features songs and dances of the Tingguian ethnic tribe.</item>
</list>
<head>Buy</head>

<head>Eat</head>

<head>Drink</head>

<head>Sleep</head>

<head>Connect</head>

<head>Go next</head>
</text>
