<text id="autogum_voyage_doc317" title="Sharjah" shortTile="sharjah" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=32387" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sharjah</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.sharjahtourism.ae">Sharjah</ref></hi>(Arabic: الشارقة) is the third largest city in the <ref target="United%20Arab%20Emirates">United Arab Emirates</ref> and the capital of <ref target="Sharjah%20%28emirate%29">Sharjah emirate</ref>. Sharjah is known for its Arabic and Islamic architecture as well as its libraries, Islamic museums, and cultural centers. The city is known as the cultural and literature hub of the United Arab Emirates. The city is rooted in its Arabic and Islamic heritage with many Ummayyad and Abbasid-styled buildings and offers a glimpse of Arabic and Islamic environment in an otherwise largely westernized country. It is a major hub for family friendly environment and activities and has a more conservative atmosphere. The city has many green parks, apartment complexes, and a large community of Arabs from all the Arab world making the city an effective cultural meeting point for many different communities of Arabs.</p>

<p>In contrast to <ref target="Abu%20Dhabi">Abu Dhabi</ref> and <ref target="Dubai">Dubai</ref>, Sharjah offers visitors a vastly larger view into Arabic and Islamic art, literature, and architecture. Its a usual destination for visitors who are looking for a cultural and a more local experience of Arabia and Islamic atmosphere compared to Abu Dhabi and Dubai.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Sharjah is very closely connected to <ref target="Dubai">Dubai</ref> through the Dubai-Sharjah-Ajman metropolitan area, with commuter traffic creating rush hour traffic jams. Many people live in Sharjah but work in Dubai, hence traffic from Sharjah to Dubai and Dubai to Sharjah is largely expected in rush hours.</p>

<p>The emirate is considerably larger than Dubai, with coastline on both west and east coasts of the peninsula, and with exclaves of Kalba, Khor Fakkan, and Dibba Al Hisn. The road to the east coast goes through rugged Al Hajar mountains. Public buildings in the Emirate are all in Umayyad and Abbasid architecture, and were all designed by the present Shaikh (a qualified architect). Therefore the city offers a nice visual change and a more cultural atmosphere from the usual fare of skyscrapers in other Emirates.</p>

<p>The <ref target="http://www.sharjah-welcome.com/en/home">Sharjah Commerce and Tourism website</ref> has sections on business, heritage, leisure, education, and coast.</p>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>As in the rest of the UAE, Arabic is the official language, although most residents speak other languages - particularly Hindi, Urdu and Tagalog. English is widely spoken in shops, souqs, and hotels.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>For visa requirements to visit Sharjah, see the <ref target="United%20Arab%20Emirates">United Arab Emirates</ref> page.</p>
<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sharjah International Airport</hi> ( SHJ ) (is around 15 kilometres from Sharjah city). It is the home of the low-cost carrier Air Arabia which has connections with various Middle East and Indian Subcontinent cities. </item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> Getting to/from the airport:</item>
</list>

<p>There is a shuttle bus connecting the airport with Sharjah centre (Rolla) running every 30 min (5 dirham).</p>
<p>Public bus route 111 (10 dirham) runs hourly from the airport via Al Qusais Bus station to the Metro's Rashidiya station in Dubai.</p>

<p>Dubai International Airport ( DXB ), in the neighbouring emirate of Dubai, has many more international connections and will be the more popular gateway to Sharjah.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Getting to/from the airport:</item>
</list>

<p>To go to Dubai International Airport by taxi will set you back at around 100 dirham.</p>
<p>You can travel by public bus to or from Dubai International Airport by using Dubai's local bus service and the inter-Emirate bus service.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>Bus travel to Dubai is possible via an inter-emirate bus service run by the Government of Dubai Road and Transport Authority. Most buses arrive at , next to the Sharjah Fish market and the Sharjah Fruit and Vegetable market, nearby to the Central Souk. A bus from Sharjah to Dubai can take about 1 hr and costs 5 dirham. Timetables can be found at the RTA website.</p>

<head>By taxi</head>
<p>Taxis are widely available. Taxis can travel from other emirates such as from Dubai to Sharjah or from Ajman to Sharjah and vice versa without any restrictions. Traveling from farther emirates such as Abu Dhabi or Ras Al Khaimah is also an option, but taxi fares may be costly. Ride-share applications such as Uber and Careem are also an option and can be used to travel across emirates. You may also call the government sponsored <ref target="https://www.sharjah.ae/registration-locations.aspx%3FVal%3D137">Sharjah taxi service</ref> to request a taxis to come right to your location.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Public buses are by Sharjah Transport,<ref target="http://www.stc.gov.ae/en"></ref> There are seven local and three express routes. Dubai's RTA also offers express commuter bus service. Licensed taxi companies are Sharjah, Emirates, Citi, Union, and Advantage. Taxi plates are reflective green, which helps to spot them at night. Flag fall is 3.50 dirham, then 1 dirham every 650 m, and the minimum fare is 11.50 dirham. There is a surcharge of 20 dirham to go into Dubai.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Heritage Area</hi> - Good overview available here including a few restoration of old houses. The Heritage is situated near the Corniche between Burj Avenue &amp; Al-Maraija Road. Many historic buildings have been reconstructed with traditional materials. The most interesting sites are Al Hisn Fort, Literature Square with House of Poetry, Sharjah Museum of Islamic Civilization, Sharjah Heritage Museum and Souq al-Arsa. Most sites in the Heritage Area have opening times set aside solely for women. Visitors of both genders should make certain of these on arrival in the city.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Al Hisn Fort</hi>, Al-Hosn Avenue, ☏ +971 6 5685500 . Sa-Th 8AM-2PM, F closed. The Sharjah Fort Museum dominates the Heritage District. The fort itself has been lovingly restored by the present Sheikh and the museum provides something of a glimpse at social history of the Emirate. Many exhibit signs, however, are solely in Arabic, with those in English often being rife with errors. Adult 5 dirham, family 10 dirham, children free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sharjah Museum of Islamic Civilization</hi>, ☏ +971 6 5655455 . Sa-Th 8AM-8PM, F 4-8PM. Sharjah Museum of Islamic Civilization is a fascinating place for any visitors with an interest in the faith, as there are handwritten Qur'ans, letters from the Prophet Muhammad to other leaders and various artifacts from Mecca. Also a comprehensive display of Arab handicrafts. Adult 5 dirham, family 10 dirham, children free. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bait al-Naboodah</hi>, Heritage Area, ☏ +971 6 5685500 . Sa-Th 8AM-8PM, F 4-8PM. Adult 5 dirham, family 10 dirham, children free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Souq al-Arsah</hi>, Heritage Area. Sa-Th 9AM-1PM, 4-9PM, F 4-9PM only. Another souq worth a visit. It is considered to be the oldest souq in the country. Stop at the traditional <hi rend="italic">coffehouse</hi> for a mint tea and a plate of dates.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sharjah Calligraphy Museum</hi> (Heritage Area), ☏ +971 6 5694561 . Sa-Th 8AM-8PM, F 4-8PM. A small museum with magnificent calligraphic works of art by Persian, Arabic and Turkish artists with a workshop where students are trained in the art of calligraphy Adult 5 dirham, family 10 dirham, children free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sharjah Heritage Museum</hi> (Heritage Area), ☏ +971 6 5680006 . Sa-Th 8AM-8PM, F 4-8PM. A small museum about the history and habits of the emirate Adult 10 dirham, children 5 dirham.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Art Area</hi> - Includes Sharjah's Art Museum which covers regional and international art exhibits, with the oriental collection being its highlights. The Arts Area is situated opposite the Heritage Area on the other side of Burj Avenue.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sharjah Art Museum</hi>, ☏ +971 6 5688222 . Sa-Th 8AM-8PM, F 4-8PM. The Sharjah Art Museum shows contemporary art by local and foreign artists. It is also the home of the <ref target="http://www.sharjahart.org/biennial/sharjah-biennial-10/welcome">Sharjah International Art Biennale</ref>, a bi-yearly exhibition of international contemporary art and performance. Free.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sharjah Archeology Museum</hi>, Sheikh Rashid bin Saqr alQassimi Rd, ☏ +971 6 5665466 . Sa-Th 9AM-1PM, 5-8PM; F 5-8PM. The museum explore the changing environments experienced by the region's inhabitants from the Stone Age to the present day through displays of artefacts, coins, jewellery, pottery and ancient weapons. Investigate a dig in progress, explore models of burials, houses and tombs and see the first forms of writing in this area. Adult 10 dirham, children 5 dirham.</item>
<item> Other museums also covers marine, natural history, aviation, and other valuable aspects http://www.sharjahmuseums.ae/.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Blue Souq (Souq Al Markazi or Central Souq)</hi>. An interesting, if slightly chaotic, shopping centre hosting around 600 shops in two wings. The ground floor shops tend to stock gold and expensive designer clothes, with the upper level containing shops stocking carpets and curios from as far afield as Afghanistan and Tibet. Haggling over prices in the upper-level shops will frequently attract massive discounts. A great place to buy gifts and traditional goods. Considered superior to Dubai for carpets by Western expatriates.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sharjah Desert Park</hi> (28 km from Sharjah on the road to Al Dhaid). Su-Th 9AM–5:30PM, F 2PM-5:30PM, Sa 11AM–5:30PM. It has three components spread over 1 km²: the Natural History Museum, Arabian Wildlife Centre and the Children’s Farm. The museum provides people of all ages with an opportunity to learn about the flora and fauna of the Arabian Desert and has five main exhibition halls: A Journey through Sharjah, Man and the Environment, A Journey through Time, The Living Desert and The Living Sea. The Arabian Wildlife Centre showcases the rich diversity of fauna in the Arabian Peninsula as well as teaching about species which have become, and are becoming, extinct. It contains more than 100 species of animals, and is divided into a reptile and insect house, aviary, nocturnal houses, viewing area and a section for large predators and monkeys. The children’s farm gives children a chance to come into close contact with farm animals, such as donkeys, goats, sheep and chickens. Adult 15 dirham, child (12–16 years) 5 dirham, child (under 12) free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fish Market</hi>, Corniche Road (opposite Blue Suq). Daily 5AM-1PM.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">King Faisal Mosque</hi>, Al-Ittahid Square. This magnificent mosque was a gift of the Saudi Arabian King Faisal. It was opened in 1987 and has space for 15,000 people. There are separate prayer rooms for men and women and the mosque has an Islamic library with more than 7,000 books. Admission for Muslims only.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Al-Qasba Waterfront and Eye of the Emirates</hi>, Al-Taiwoon Road, Al-Khan Lagoon, ☏ +971 6 5560777 . Sa-Th 10AM-11PM, F 4-11PM. Here you can enjoy culture, entertainment and leisure attractions representing the very best from the Arab world and beyond.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Al-Mahattah-Museum</hi>, Estiqlal Square, ☏ +971 6 5733079 . Sa-Th 8AM-8PM, F 4-8PM. Al Mahatta was the first airport in the Gulf region. It opened in 1932 as a staging post for commercial flights from Britain to India. There is an interesting film about the daily life at the airport and Sharjah town in the 1930s and four original propeller planes stand in the hangar. Adult 5 dirham, family 10 dirham, child free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sharjah Aquarium</hi>, Al Meena Street,Al Khan Area,Near Sharjah Maritime Museum, ☏ +971 6 528 5288 . The Sharjah Aquarium first opened its doors on June 16, 2008. It features deep-sea creatures. Sharjah Maritime Museum gives you a close-up look at the local fishes and lets you learn about Sharjah's historic coasts and ports. 35AED per adult (Age 13+ yrs), 25AED per child (age 2-12 yrs), below 2 yrs free. 90 AED Family (2 Adults + 3 Children).</item>
</list>
</text>
