<text id="autogum_voyage_doc155" title="Marrakech" shortTile="marrakech" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=21485" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Marrakech</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Marrakech</hi> (Arabic: مراكش, Berber: ⴰⵎⵓⵔⴰⴽⵓⵛ), also spelt <hi rend="bold">Marrakesh</hi>, is one of the imperial cities of <ref target="Morocco">Morocco</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The name Marrakech originates from the Amazigh (Berber) words <hi rend="bold">mur (n) wakush</hi>, which means "Land of God". It is the third largest city in Morocco after Casablanca and Rabat, and lies near the foothills of the snow-capped Atlas Mountains and a few hours away from the foot of the Sahara Desert. Its location and contrasting landscape has made it an enviable destination in Morocco.</p>

<p>The city is divided into two parts: the Medina, the historical city, and the new European modern district called Gueliz or Ville Nouvelle. The Medina is full of intertwining narrow passageways and local shops full of character; it also contains the large square Djemaa El-Fna, where many hotels are located and tourists, locals and vendors congregate. In contrast, Gueliz plays host to modern restaurants, fast food chains and big brand stores.</p>

<p>Marrakech is the main tourist destination in Morocco and thus it is also a place where many Moroccans try to become rich fast by ripping off tourists. This mentality is so widespread that even Moroccans are now ripped off whenever possible so that they call the city "Marrakech, Arnakech" - which rhymes in Arabic and translates to "Marrakech, Mafia". See the <ref target="Marrakech%23Scams">Scam</ref> section for more information.</p>

<p>For further information, you may also visit the <hi rend="bold">Marrakech Tourist Information</hi> (at a small square at the intersection of Avenue Mohammed V and Rue de Yugoslavie). </p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Marrakech-Menara Airport</hi> ( RAK ), ☏ +212 4444 7910 . The airport has two terminals housed in one complex. Both terminals have money exchange offices, and there is an ATM in the arrivals hall of Terminal 2. On ATMs, check for the Maestro, Cirrus or Plus logos to be sure that the machine accepts foreign credit cards. Some ATMs work only in French. If your card is taken at the ATM, tell airport security and they can help you get it back. There are no potable water dispensers after the security check and the small shops only see overpriced 0.5L water bottles. However the tap water from the WC tastes slightly of chlorine and is drinkable for tourists.For some airlines (e.g. Ryanair in 2018) can only use the smartphone or mobile app for check-in but have to arrive at the airport with a print-out of your ticket. You also need to queue at the check-in counter before entering the security check (even if you do not have drop-off luggage), to get your tickets stamped by the airline, so better arrive earlier than usual. </item>
</list>


<p>Marrakech has an international airport with direct scheduled flights from many major European centres, including flights operated by a number of low cost carriers. Connections via <ref target="Casablanca">Casablanca</ref> (45-min flight) are also possible.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="http://www.easyjet.com">Easyjet</ref> flies to Marrakech from Manchester, Stansted and Gatwick Airport (and also from <ref target="Madrid">Madrid</ref>, from <ref target="Lyon">Lyon</ref>, <ref target="Amsterdam">Amsterdam</ref> and from <ref target="Basel">Basel</ref>)</item>
<item> <ref target="http://www.ryanair.com">Ryanair</ref> - direct flights from <ref target="Oporto">Oporto</ref> (Portugal), <ref target="London">London</ref> Luton, and <ref target="London">London</ref> Stansted to Marrakech. They also fly from <ref target="Hahn">Hahn</ref> (Germany), Alicante (Spain), Girona (Spain), Eindhoven (the Netherlands), Bergamo (Italy), Madrid and Reus (Spain), Dublin (Ireland) to Marrakech.</item>
<item> Thomson Airways travels from London Gatwick and <ref target="Manchester">Manchester</ref>.</item>
<item> <ref target="http://www.ba.com">British Airways</ref> flies from London Gatwick.</item>
<item> TUIfly flies from Cologne and several other European destinations.</item>
<item> <ref target="http://www.Transavia.com">Transavia</ref> a low-cost airline from Air France-KLM group coming to Marrakech from several cities in Europe, including Paris.</item>
<item> <ref target="http://www.norwegian.no/">Norwegian</ref> offers direct flights from <ref target="Copenhagen">Copenhagen</ref>, <ref target="Oslo">Oslo</ref> and <ref target="Stockholm">Stockholm</ref>.</item>
<item> Iberia offers two non stop flights from Madrid.</item>
<item> TAP Portugal offers direct flights from <ref target="Lisbon">Lisbon</ref></item>
<item> Domestic flights operated by <ref target="http://www.royalairmaroc.com">Royal Air Morocco</ref>, with flights from <ref target="Agadir">Agadir</ref>, <ref target="Casablanca">Casablanca</ref> (daily), <ref target="Fez">Fez</ref> (daily), <ref target="Ouarzazate">Ouarzazate</ref>, <ref target="Al%20Hoceima">Al Hoceima</ref>, and <ref target="Tangier">Tangier</ref>.</item>
</list>


<head>Getting there</head>
<p>The airport is about 9 km south-west of the city center (Medina), and 6.6 km from the Djemaa El-Fna square.</p>

<p>The L19 Airport express <hi rend="bold">bus</hi> is 30 dirham for a round trip (if the return trip is within 2 weeks of purchase). It serves all the major hotels and is a great way to go from the airport to the Median area. The is right out of the terminal according to the bus' route. (If not, exit the arrivals hall at Terminal 2, to your left you will see the parking area, walk into it and continue across all the taxis, at the end, close to the exit, there's an empty area with a black BUS sign without signs or maps, nor a place to sit or shadow.) The bus leaves the airport every twenty minutes between 07:00 and 21:30. This bus line terminates at Jeema El Fna and it only has a couple of stops along the way, most notably the Menara Mall. The whole trip takes 15-20 minutes. You can see the whole route and departure times in Google Maps. <hi rend="bold">Beware</hi>, some taxi drivers will approach and try to convince you to go with them, sometimes even resorting to lies ("The bus is not running today" or "It comes only once an hour")—don't listen to them. </p>

<p>You can also catch No 11 city bus which runs from M'Hamid district to the long distance bus station at Bab Doukkala, stopping also at Jeema El Fna. It stops on Avenue Gnassa - main road near airport, 500 m from terminal. This is an option only for people with convenient luggage, but it is the cheapest one—the bus costs 3.50 dirham.</p>

<p>The airport is about a 10-15 min ride by <hi rend="bold">petit taxi</hi> from the city center. Prices directly from the airport are fixed, insanely inflated and displayed prominently just outside the airport (just like at every airport in Morocco). Walking the 200 m across the parking lot to the road and hailing a taxi there will get you a much, much better price per vehicle (about 20-40 dirham compared to the official 200 dirham).</p>

<p>Many hotels and riads offer a <hi rend="bold">shuttle service</hi> for about €15 per person. The advantage is that you avoid the hassle, and they will lead you all the way to you lodging, even if the car cannot drive there. However, you might have to wait a while for all your fellow passengers to get out of the airport.</p>

<p>Several international <hi rend="bold"><ref target="renting%20a%20car">rental car</ref></hi> companies are based at the airport as well.</p>

<p>If you do not have too much luggage then it is possible to <hi rend="bold">walk</hi> from the airport to the Medina even though it would take you from an hour and half to two hours. There is a footpath alongside the road all the way and the minaret of the Koutoubia mosque provides an excellent landmark to head towards. If you have enough time you can break the trip with a visit to the Menara gardens, which are between the airport and the city.</p>
</text>
