<text id="autogum_voyage_doc112" title="Belgium" shortTile="belgium" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=3273" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Belgium</head>


<p>A low-lying country in the <ref target="Benelux">Benelux</ref>, <ref target="http://www.visitbelgium.com"><hi rend="bold">Belgium</hi></ref> (<ref target="Dutch%20phrasebook">Dutch</ref>: <hi rend="italic">België</hi>, <ref target="French%20phrasebook">French</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Belgique</hi>, <ref target="German%20phrasebook">German</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Belgien</hi>) sits at the crossroads of Western Europe. It marries the historical landmarks for which the continent is famous with spectacular modern architecture and rural idylls. Its capital, <ref target="Brussels">Brussels</ref>, is home to the headquarters of the <ref target="European%20Union">European Union</ref>.</p>

<p>Despite this, Belgium is not without its divisions. On the contrary, Flanders, the northern part of the country that speaks Dutch, and Wallonia, the southern French-speaking area, are frequently at loggerheads and it sometimes seems that their quarrels will split the country in two. Yet, despite this apparent incompatibility, the two halves of Belgium come together to form a country that contains some of Europe's most attractive and historical cities and is a true 'must-see' for any visitor to the continent.</p>

<p>Lying on the North Sea coast, Belgium's immediate neighbours are <ref target="France">France</ref> to the south-west, <ref target="Luxembourg">Luxembourg</ref> to the south-east, <ref target="Germany">Germany</ref> to the east and the <ref target="Netherlands">Netherlands</ref> to the north.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Belgium is a densely populated country trying to balance the conflicting demands of urbanization, transportation, industry, and commercial and intensive agriculture. It imports large quantities of raw materials and exports a large volume of manufactured goods, mostly to the EU.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>Belgium is the heir of several former Medieval powers, and you will see traces of these everywhere during your trip in this country.</p>

<p>After the collapse of the Carolingian Empire in the 9th century, the territory that is nowadays Belgium, Netherlands, and Luxembourg, was part of Lotharingia, an ephemeral kingdom soon to be absorbed into the Germanic Empire; however, the special character of "Lower Lotharingia" remained intact in the feudal Empire : this is the origin of the Low Countries, a general term that encompasses present-day Belgium, Netherlands, and Luxembourg.</p>

<p>The widely autonomous fiefdoms of the Low Countries were among the richest places in Medieval Europe and you will see traces of this past wealth in the rich buildings of Bruges, Brussels, Antwerp, Ghent, Leuven, Tournai, Mons, etc. These cities progressively fell under the control of a powerful and ambitious family : the Dukes of Burgundy. The whole realm of the dukes extended from the Low Countries to the borders of Switzerland. Using wealth, strategy, and alliances, the Dukes of Burgundy aimed at reconstituting Lotharingia. The death of the last Duke, Charles the Bold, put an end to this dream. However, the treasures of the Dukes of Burgundy remains as a testimony of their rules in Belgian museums and landmarks.</p>

<p>The powerful Habsburg family then inherited from the Low Countries. <ref target="Protestant%20Reformation">Reformation</ref> is the reason that Belgium and Netherlands were first put apart: the northern half of the Low Countries embraced Protestantism and rebelled against the Habsburg rule, while the southern half remained faithful to both its ruler and the Catholic faith. These two halves roughly corresponds to present-day Belgium and Netherlands.</p>

<p>Belgium was called Austrian Netherlands, then Spanish Netherlands, depending on which branch of the Habsburg ruled it. The powerful German emperor and Spanish king, Charles V, was born in the Belgian city of Ghent and ruled from Brussels. Many places in Belgium are named after him, including the city of Charleroi and even a brand of beer. Every year, the Brusselers emulates his first parade in their city in what is called the Ommegang.</p>

<p>Belgium was briefly a part of the Napoleonic Empire. After Napoleon's defeat, a large Kingdom of the Netherlands was created, comprising the whole of the Low Countries. However, the religious opposition still remained and the split was aggravated by political differences between Belgian liberals and Dutch aristocrats. Belgium became independent from the Netherlands in 1830 after a short revolution and a war against the Netherlands.</p>

<p>It was occupied by Germany during World Wars I and II and has many war graves near the battle zones, most of them are around Ieper (in English, archaically rendered as <ref target="Ypres">Ypres</ref>, with Yperite another name for mustard gas due to intensive use there in WWI). It has prospered in the past half century as a modern, technologically advanced European state and member of NATO and the EU. Tensions between the Dutch-speaking Flemings of the north and the French-speaking Walloons of the south have led to constitutional amendments granting these regions formal recognition and autonomy.</p>

<head>Terrain</head>
<p>Flat coastal plains in northwest, central rolling hills, wooded hills and valleys of Ardennes Forest in southeast.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>Temperate; mild winters with cool summers. Generally rather rainy, humid and cloudy. Belgium's average annual temperature in the decade between 1976 and 2006 was 10 °C - a somewhat meaningless measure for non-meteorologists.</p>

<head>Electricity</head>
<p>Electricity is supplied at 220 to 230 V and 50 Hz. Outlets are CEE7/5 (protruding male earth pin) and accept either CEE 7/5 (Grounded), CEE 7/7 (Grounded) or CEE 7/16 (non-grounded) plugs. Older German-type CEE 7/4 plugs are not compatible as they do not accommodate the earth pin found on this type of outlet. However, most modern European appliances are fitted with the hybrid CEE 7/7 plug which fits both CEE 7/5 (Belgium &amp; France) and CEE 7/4 (Germany, Netherlands, Spain and most of Europe) outlets.</p>

<p>Travellers from the UK, Ireland, Australia, New Zealand, Denmark, Italy, Switzerland and all the other countries using 230 V and 50 Hz, which use different plugs, simply require a plug adaptor to use their appliances in Belgium.</p>

<p>Travellers from the US, Canada, Japan and other countries using 110 V 60 Hz may need a voltage converter.</p>
<p>However, some laptops, mobile phone chargers and other devices can accept either 110 V or 230 V so only require a simple plug adaptor. Check the voltage rating plates on your appliances before connecting them.</p>

<head>Regions</head>
<p>Belgium consists of three regions, listed from north to south:</p>

<head>Cities</head>
<p>Belgium has a very high rate of urbanization and has an astonishing number of cities for such a small territory</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> — Belgium's capital and the unofficial capital of the EU. Nice historic centre and several museums of interest. One of the most multicultural cities in Europe.</item>
<item> — Belgium's second largest city, with a giant cathedral, medieval streets and artistic heritage, and a great place for fashion.</item>
<item> — one of Europe's wealthiest cities in the 14th century, it is touristy yet still very authentic, medieval and quiet at night, with small guest houses and family businesses greatly outnumbering chain hotels.</item>
<item> — once one of Europe's largest cities, now a perfect mixture of Antwerp and Bruges: a cosy city with canals, yet with rich history and lively student population.</item>
<item> — a small city dominated by one of Europe's oldest universities. Beautiful historic centre and a lively nightlife.</item>
<item> — second largest city of Wallonia, along a wide river, industrial cityscape with hiking and resorts in the nearby hills, it has a very strong, independent character and an exciting night-life.</item>
<item> — a small medieval city with a nice historic district around the cathedral.</item>
<item> — has had the extraordinary privilege of having two sites inscribed on the <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20site">UNESCO World Heritage site</ref> List and one event on the Representative List of the Intangible Cultural Heritage of Humanity.</item>
<item> — capital of <ref target="Wallonia">Wallonia</ref>, at the confluence of Sambre and Meuse with the Citadel.</item>
</list>
</text>
