<text id="autogum_voyage_doc35" title="Abergavenny">
<head>Abergavenny</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Abergavenny</hi> (<ref target="Welsh%20phrasebook">Welsh</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Y Fenni</hi>) is a town in <ref target="Monmouthshire">Monmouthshire</ref> in southeast <ref target="Wales">Wales</ref>.</p>
<head>Understand</head>
<p>A thriving town, <hi rend="bold">Abergavenny</hi> prides itself as a gateway to South Wales and the eastern gateway to the <ref target="Brecon%20Beacons%20National%20Park">Brecon Beacons National Park</ref> where you can enjoy a relaxing short break or longer holiday amidst beautiful countryside. The town itself nestles within the beautiful Usk Valley at the point where the river emerges from amongst the mountains to flow through lowland Monmouthshire. The mass of the <hi rend="bold">Black Mountains</hi> and their highly individual outliers of <hi rend="bold">Sugar Loaf</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Skirrid</hi> (Welsh: Ysgyryd Fawr) form a spectacular northern backdrop to the town. Along with <hi rend="bold">Blorenge</hi> to the south, the opportunities for walkers are hugely varied.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>On the A465 <ref target="Hereford">Hereford</ref> - <ref target="Neath">Neath</ref> and A40 London-<ref target="Fishguard">Fishguard</ref> road between <ref target="Monmouth%20%28Wales%29">Monmouth</ref> and <ref target="Brecon">Brecon</ref></p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Abergavenny railway station</hi>. on the Welsh Marches Line: <ref target="Newport%20%28Monmouthshire%29">Newport</ref> - <ref target="Hereford">Hereford</ref>.</item>
</list>

 

<head>Get around</head>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Abergavenny Castle</hi>. Dates back to 1087 and makes for a fascinating visit. </item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Abergavenny Museum</hi>. Set in the grounds of the Norman Castle. If it’s a nice day, take a picnic, otherwise simply learn about the history of this historic market town. </item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sugar Loaf</hi>. heigh mountain </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Grosmont Castle</hi>, Grosmont. ruined castle </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Llanthony Priory</hi>. ruined former Augustinian priory </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">White Castle</hi>. medieval castle </item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<head>Events</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Abergavenny Food Festival</hi>. it stands to reason that the number of eateries on offer is more than adequate. From fancy restaurants to old-fashioned pubs, from bars and cafes to takeways, there is something offer to suit every taste. </item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>
<p>One of the most well-known markets in Wales, <hi rend="bold">Abergavenny’s Tuesday market</hi> has more than 200 stalls offering a huge array of goods. In addition there is a Friday and Saturday market and the occasional craft fair, flea market and antique fair.</p>

<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Greyhound Vaults</hi>, Market St, ☏ +44 1873 858549 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Walnut Tree</hi>, Llanddewi Skirrid, ☏ +44 1873 852797 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fig Tree Espresso</hi>, 15 Nevill Street, ☏ +44 7702 580071 (mobile) , ✉ figtree@abergavennycoffee.co.uk . 9AM-4PM Tue-Sa. Established in 2013 by a young couple and set in a Grade 2 Listed Georgian Townhouse, this small cafe has quickly become the place to go to get your caffeine fix in Abergavenny. Using coffee beans that have been roasted less than half an hour away and making all of the cakes and savouries themselves, this place is definitely local. Also, there is a rear courtyard to sit and enjoy your drink.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>
<p>Abergavenny has a thriving nightlife of pubs and bars</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Kings Arms</hi>. Great social spot in the town centre. Generally quite quiet during the week but much busier on a Friday and Saturday night, often with live entertainment. Home to the Tudor Microbrewery serving a selection of local ales.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Skirrid Mountain Inn</hi> (few miles north of Abergavenny), ☏ +44 1873 890 258 . claimed to be the oldest pub in Wales </item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Old Pandy Inn & Black Mountain bunkhouse</hi>, Hereford Road, Pandy, ☏ +44 1873 890208 . The Black Mountain Lodge is sited at the Old Pandy Inn, a 17th Century Country Inn some 4 miles north of Abergavenny, 15 miles south of Hereford at the foot of the Black Mountains. The Offa's Dyke Path is some 400 yards away.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Angel Hotel</hi>, 15 Cross St., ☏ +44 1873 857121 .</item>
</list>


<head>Connect</head>

<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Monmouth%20%28Wales%29">Monmouth (Wales)</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Crickhowell">Crickhowell</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Usk">Usk</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
