<text id="autogum_voyage_doc472" title="Melbourne/St Kilda" shortTile="melbournest-kilda" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=21944" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Melbourne/St Kilda</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">St Kilda</hi> is a vibrant beachside suburb of Port Phillip, in south-eastern inner <ref target="Melbourne">Melbourne</ref>, <ref target="Australia">Australia</ref>. St. Kilda is famous for its beach life and the bar and restaurant scene along Fitzroy Street.</p>
<p>Formally known to be seedy and run down, there has been a revival in the 21st century as young professionals and travellers have increased in numbers.</p>

<head>Get in</head>


<p>St Kilda can be reached from the City Centre by public transport; a map of St Kilda and the surrounding area's public transport network is available on the <ref target="http://ptv.vic.gov.au/assets/Maps/Localities/PDFs/45_Port_Phillip_LAM.pdf">PTV website</ref>.</p>

<head>By tram</head>
<p>The best way to reach St Kilda from the <ref target="Melbourne/City%20Centre">city centre</ref> is by tram. The journey takes approximately 25 minutes.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.yarratrams.com.au/using-trams/route-guides/route-96/">Route 96</ref></hi> from along Bourke Street or Southern Cross Station (towards St Kilda Beach) - the fastest of the three, it functions as a light rail travelling along the former railway, taking about 20 minutes with a 6-10 minute frequency. It operates exclusively with high-capacity, low-floor trams but can be very crowded. Within St Kilda, it travels along Fitzroy Street, the Esplanade and terminates at Acland Street.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.yarratrams.com.au/using-trams/route-guides/route-16/">Route 16</ref></hi> (also <hi rend="italic">3a</hi> on weekends) from along Swanston Street or Flinders Street Station (towards Kew) - passes along Fitzroy Street, the Esplanade and Carlisle Street. It then travels into the neighbouring suburbs of <hi rend="italic">Balaclava</hi> and <hi rend="italic">St Kilda East</hi>, before heading onwards to Kew in <ref target="Melbourne/Boroondara">Boroondara</ref>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.yarratrams.com.au/using-trams/route-guides/route-12/">Route 12</ref></hi> from along Collins Street (towards St Kilda) - passes through the residential streets of the <ref target="Melbourne/Inner%20south">inner south</ref> and <hi rend="italic">St Kilda West</hi> before terminating at Fitzroy Street.</item>
</list>


<p>The eastern periphery of St Kilda, including St Kilda East, can be reached by <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.yarratrams.com.au/using-trams/route-guides/route-67/">Route 67</ref></hi> (towards Carnegie), or by <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.yarratrams.com.au/using-trams/route-guides/route-3/">Route 3</ref> or <ref target="http://www.yarratrams.com.au/using-trams/route-guides/route-3a/">Route 3A</ref></hi> (towards East Malvern).</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>St Kilda does not have a railway station, with the former railway converted to the Route 96 light rail tram. St Kilda East is served by <hi rend="italic">Balaclava Station</hi> on the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://ptv.vic.gov.au/route/view/12">Sandringham Line</ref></hi>.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Buses are useful for accessing the more residential areas of St Kilda and its surrounds that lack tram services. High-frequency <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://ptv.vic.gov.au/route/view/8074">Route 246</ref></hi> operates along Punt Road and connects St Kilda East to Melbourne's <ref target="Melbourne/Inner%20east">inner east</ref>. Bus routes 600, 606, 922 and 923 run via Mitford St and Broadway in Elwood, south of St Kilda.</p>

<head>By bike</head>
<p>Melbourne's Blue Bike docked bike scheme extends down as far as St Kilda - and the ride between here and the city centre is very pleasant cycling. Of course, Obikes (dockless) are ubiquitous if you care to pick one up and go for a ride along the beach.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>From the City Centre, St Kilda is best reached via <hi rend="bold">St Kilda Road</hi>, the continuation of Swanston Street in the CBD. At St Kilda Junction, follow the signage for Fitzroy St. The journey takes approximately 25 minutes, depending on traffic.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jewish Museum of Australia</hi>, 26 Alma Rd (Trams 3 or 67: Stop 32, Alma Rd and walk east along Alma Rd), ☏ +61 3 8534 3600 , ✉ info@jewishmuseum.com.au . Tu-Th 10AM—4PM, Su 10AM—5PM. An engaging museum that depicts the story of the Jewish community in Melbourne and Australia, in addition to the history of the strong local congregation within St Kilda and Caulfield. Houses a number of artefacts from around the world. Guided tours available on request. Adult $10, child/concession $5.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St Kilda Beach</hi>, 43 Jacka Blvd (Trams 3a, 16 or 96: Stop 136, The Esplanade). One of Melbourne's most famous and popular beaches, it is an enjoyable place to spend an afternoon. Apart from the omnipresent swimming, popular activities include sunbathing, sailing, beach volleyball, sandcastle-building, jetskiing and kitesurfing. The beach is regularly patrolled in the Summer by surf lifesavers.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St Kilda Botanical Gardens</hi>, Cnr Herbert &amp; Blessington St (Tram 96: Stop 140, Barkly St terminus and walk along Blessington St; or tram 67: Stop 36, St Kilda Primary School and walk along Mozart St), ☏ +61 3 9209 6777 , ✉ ospace@portphillip.vic.gov.au . Gardens: sunrise–sunset, conservatory: M–F 10:30AM–3:30PM, Sa Su sunrise–sunset. St Kilda's own botanical gardens were established in the 1800s and are an oasis of tranquility amongst the area's bustling surrounds. A short five minute walk down a side street from St Kilda's main hub, its features include a large conservatory, glasshouses, a gazebo, playground, a giant chess board and an ornamental lake. Detailed information about the plants and wildlife are available on the council's website.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St Kilda Pier, Breakwater and Kiosk</hi> (Home of St Kilda's Little Penguin colony), Pier Rd (Trams 3a, 16 or 96: Stop 135, Jacka Blvd), ☏ +61 131 963 , ✉ info@parks.vic.gov.au . The long, wooden pier is a popular spot for walking and fishing. Many of the fishermen along the pier will be happy to show you their catch if politely asked. At the end of the pier sits the historic kiosk, now a restaurant, which was rebuilt to the original plans in 2006 after an earlier arson attack. At the far end of the pier is the St Kilda breakwater, which is home to native water rats and the popular <hi rend="italic">little penguins</hi>. The colony has existed since the 1950s, nestled amongst the rocks of the breakwater. As it's not an official tourist development, you can see the penguins for free most days at sunset in the publicly accessible area of the breakwater. Respect the penguins by not touching them, feeding them or using flash photography. Alternatively, boat tours are available through Parks Victoria via their website.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Luna Park</hi>, 18 Lower Esplanade (Trams 3a, 16 or 96: Stop 138, Luna Park), ☏ +61 3 9525 5033 , ✉ justforfun@lunapark.com.au . Opening hours vary, although generally open 11AM-6PM weekends and 11AM-8PM weekdays during school holidays; closed weekdays during school term. This St Kilda icon's famous mouth entrance continues to grace Melbourne's postcards and for good reason. Built in 1912, the historic amusement park is free to enter, with a number of rides to keep the young and young at heart entertained. The fabled Scenic Railway is the oldest continually operating wooden-framed rollercoaster in the world, and gives panoramic views over the nearby bay. Other rides include all the usual favourites, such as a Ferris wheel, dodgem cars and a ghost train. A great day out for kids and families. In poor weather, some rides may close, including the historic rollercoaster. Single ride: adult (13+) $11, child (4-12) $9, infant $5; unlimited ticket: adult $49.50, child $39.50, infant $16.50. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St Kilda Sea Baths</hi>, 10/18 Jacka Blvd (Trams 3a, 16 and 96: Stop 136, The Esplanade). An old Melbourne institution perched on the St Kilda foreshore, the Sea Baths building now has a variety of different functions, including a gymnasium, a spa, a sea water pool and countless restaurants, bars and cafés.</item>
</list>
</text>
