<text id="autogum_voyage_doc8" title="Aba (prefecture)">
<head>Aba (prefecture)</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Aba Tibetan & Qiang Autonomous Prefecture</hi> (Mandarin Chinese: 阿坝藏族羌族自治州; <hi rend="italic">Ābà Zàngzú Qiāngzú Zìzhìzhōu</hi>, or Ngawa Tibetan and Qiang Autonomous Prefecture (Tibetan: རྔ་བ་བོད་རིགས་དང་ཆང་རིགས་རང་སྐྱོང་ཁུལ་), is located in north-western <ref target="Sichuan">Sichuan province</ref>.</p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>
<p>Aba Prefecture contains 3 of the 6 World Natural Heritage Sites in the all of China, making Aba the premier destination in China for nature-based and ecotourism. There is also great cultural diversity, with a majority Tibetan population, elaborate Tibetan Buddhist temples (e.g. Langmusi on the border with Gansu), picturesque grasslands and beautiful mountain scenery. There is also a significant Qiang minority population (particularly in Maoxian county).</p>

<p>The 3 UNESCO World Natural Heritage Sites are:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Jiuzhaigou%20Nature%20Reserve">Jiuzhaigou Nature Reserve</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Huanglongsi%20National%20Park">Huanglongsi National Park</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Siguniangshan%20National%20Parks">Siguniangshan National Parks</ref></item>
</list>


<p>Other national parks include:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Muni Valley national park</item>
<item> Baihe Golden Monkey Reserve</item>
<item> Wanglang National Park</item>
<item> Wolong Nature Reserve - sanctuary for endangered pandas</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
<p>Aba Tibetan and Qiang Autonomous Prefecture is located in the north-west of Sichuan Province, at the upper reaches of the Chang jiang River and the Yellow River, with an area of 84,200 square kilometers. Under its jurisdiction, there are 13 counties. The prefecture lies in the historic northern Tibetan region of Amdo. Besides the obvious Han Chinese and Tibetan influences you may encounter Hui and Qiang minorities as well. The further you get from Songpan and Chengdu the stronger the minority influences get.</p>

<p>Within Aba, there is a diversity of ethnic groups, including Tibetan (52.3%), Han (26.7%), Qiang (17.7%) and Chinese Muslim (Hui). (3.2%).</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Jiuzhai Huanglong Airport ( JZH )</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<head>See</head>

<head>Do</head>
<p>The Zang Mii Tibetan Opera cultural performance hall, located in Zhang Zha township of Jiuzhaigou county, hosts nightly (outside of winter) spectacular and elaborate performances which tell a story of a pilgrim's journey in an intimate and entertaining, colourful and exciting way. The theme of the opera has deep cultural meaning and significance and conveys a proud sense of the Tibetan people and their beliefs.</p>

<head>Eat</head>
<p>Try the Tibetan round baked walnut bread ('hetao da bing') or the delicious round-baked cake-like bread baked by the Hui Muslim minorities in Songpan and Wenchuan</p>

<head>Drink</head>

<head>Stay safe</head>

<head>Go next</head>
</text>
