<text id="autogum_voyage_doc434" title="Tegucigalpa" shortTile="tegucigalpa" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=35502" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tegucigalpa</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Tegucigalpa</hi> is the capital of and largest city in <ref target="Honduras">Honduras</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Tegucigalpa (Hondurans in general, and people familiar with the city, shorten it to "Tegus", while most locals actually use the full name...) is a great example Central America of urban sprawl gone amok, spread out across very hilly terrain.</p>

<p>Of course, the city, a 400 year-old mining center, has a depth that is there for those with time and nerve to find it. It has a plethora of interesting, if decaying, old colonial buildings, and many old stone streets winding intriguingly up steep hills to hidden parks, stone steps, and old houses.</p>

<p>The defining event in recent Honduran history, and that of Tegucigalpa also, is Hurricane Mitch, which devastated the country in 1998. Mitch reportedly set the country back 50 years. Tegus is still recovering from the massive flooding of the river, and equally massive landslides, both triggered by the rampant deforestation of the hills surrounding the city. Indeed, signs of whole colonias (neighbourhoods) having slid off steep hills are still evident. Workers continue to toil daily in the river, removing silt deposited by the flooding. Many or most people lost friends and relatives during the crisis.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>There are a number of bus international bus lines running to Tegus from other Central American capitals. These offer first class, very comfortable service at a reasonable price. A trip from <ref target="Managua">Managua</ref>, <ref target="San%20Salvador">San Salvador</ref>, or <ref target="Guatemala%20City">Guatemala City</ref> would cost between US$20-40. <hi rend="italic">Ticabus</hi>, is the most affordable and frequented by backpackers. Hedman Alas <ref target="http://www.hedmanalas.com"></ref>, Nicabus, and King Quality, are other first class, reliable bus companies. Of course, it is also possible to travel on less comfortable, less expensive lines, but this is difficult or impossible to plan from afar. Internal travel in Honduras is easy enough, and made more easy thanks to the excellent transportation guide published by the Honduran tourism magazine called Honduras Tips, and available online at their website. Travel from <ref target="La%20Ceiba">La Ceiba</ref>, on the north coast, Empresa de Bus Cristina provides good service, at around US$10 for the 7-8h trip.</p>

<p>95% of buses coming to Tegus arrive into <hi rend="bold">Comayagüela</hi>, the sister city of Tegucigalpa. It is also reputedly one of the more dangerous parts of the city. If arriving to Comayagüela after dark, <hi rend="bold">do not walk around</hi> looking for a place to stay. Even in the day, walking from bus stations in Comayagüela to a hotel or hostel any distance away would be a bit risky.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Toncontín International Airport</hi> ( TGU ). TGU isn't necessarily the best port of entry to the country though there are a bunch of flights to various US cities and throughout <ref target="Central%20America">Central America</ref>. San Pedro Sula is the other big airport and may sometimes be better value. Unfortunately the airlines in Central America are still able to keep prices high and competition hasn't yet gained much of a foothold, so flights inside the region can be pretty expensive.</item>
</list>

 

<head>Get around</head>
<p>The football (soccer) stadium is a great central point for learning your bearings map-wise of the city. Several of the larger roads meet in a round-about that uses the stadium as its hub.</p>

<head>By taxi</head>
<p>As of June 2009, taxis (<hi rend="italic">directos</hi>) will cost ~L80 for a 20 minute cross-town trip. Negotiating for the price (<hi rend="bold">before</hi> getting in) is expected. Taxi drivers are a bit wild, so buckle up (oops, they don't have seatbelts). Prices increase with number of passengers and late at night. Don't be afraid to walk away from an expensive offer - taxis are everywhere and you'll likely win the negotiation by walking away.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Colectivos</hi>, like the city buses, run set routes from one point to another. If you see a long line of people weaving down a side walk, this is most likely a collectivo line. As of June 2009, <hi rend="italic">colectivos</hi> cost L11/person.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>As of March 2007, buses were L3 (US$0.16) but run set routes that most visitors won't know.</p>

<p>There are common bus stops throughout the town, but are unlabeled. Find a large group of people standing on the sidewalks for the largest selection of bus routes. To know the main destinations of the buses, look on the front of the bus above the windshield. Most buses operate to distinct neighborhoods and link to El Centro or the market in Comayaguela. In the market in Comayaguela you can also find many inter-city buses with various prices and various levels of comfort, ranging from the most common chicken-bus to double decker luxury buses.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Parque La <ref target="https%3A//www.google.com/maps/place/La%2BLeona%2C%2BTegucigalpa/%4014.1112907%2C-87.2094175%2C16z/data%3D%213m1%214b1%214m5%213m4%211s0x8f6fa2945c636e3b:0x2d0c5bfa6e58488a%218m2%213d14.1115986%214d-87.2058346">Leona</ref></hi>, is an old neighbourhood in the center of Tegus, overlooking the central park. It is a bit of a labyrinth to make your way up the old steep windy streets to arrive at parque La Leona, but it is a nice park, with a beautiful view, and a relaxed atmosphere. If walking, if you start facing the front door of the basilica in the central park, head to your left, and just keep walking up hill, and you will almost certainly hit the park as long as you continue upwards. Or ask someone in the area. In the park there is a little store/restaurant that sells typical Honduran food and has a patio overhanging from the park, with a spectacular view of the city, the valley, and the hills.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Parque el <ref target="https%3A//www.google.com/maps/place/Naciones%2BUnidas%2BEl%2BPicacho%2BPark/%4014.1191299%2C-87.2000452%2C16.5z/data%3D%214m5%213m4%211s0x8f6fa2f06717791d:0x874feba81d02ad7b%218m2%213d14.1189985%214d-87.1981809">Picacho</ref></hi>, is a park overlooking the city which takes its name from the huge statue of Jesus Christ, also called "Cristo el Picacho", which is visible from almost any point in the city. Free parking is available at the entrance of the park, and entrance to the park is a nominal fee (around 5 USD). The views from the park are gorgeous. The park is well maintained, clean, and seemingly not very busy (though likely busier on weekends). To get to the park if you don't have a car, you can take the rapidito bus that passes the park on the way to El Hatillo. The bus leaves from a few blocks north of the central park. If you walk to the end of the Calle Peotanal that begins in front of the basilica, and follow it to the end, through the black gates, past the Museo de Identidad Nacional, all the way to the Bonillo Theatre, take a left there on the far side of the theatre, walk up one block and the bus leaves on the right. Or just ask someone in this area. On the rapidito ask the fare-taker to tell you when to get off for Picacho (about a 5-10 minute walk in to the park gate, then a further 15 to the big Jesus). The bus ride takes around 15 to 20 minutes.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">National <ref target="https%3A//www.google.com/maps/place/Naciones%2BUnidas%2BEl%2BPicacho%2BPark/%4014.1206979%2C-87.1962884%2C17z/data%3D%214m8%211m2%212m1%211szoo%2Bnear%2BCristo%2Bdel%2BPicacho%2C%2BTegucigalpa%213m4%211s0x8f6fa2f06717791d:0x874feba81d02ad7b%218m2%213d14.1189985%214d-87.1981809">Zoo</ref></hi>, on the same hill as the Picacho statue, with tropical animals such as monkeys, bright-colored parrots, and others. There is a separate entrance fee to enter the zoo. While not a horrible zoo, and worth seeing if you don't mind dropping a few dollars on the entrance fee, the zoo features mostly lethargic animals, the larger ones often noticeably insane as a result of their encagement. The zoo has a variety of monkeys, crocodiles, a jaguar, tapirs (anteaters), snakes, a collection of various raptors, and others.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Museo para la Identidad Nacional</hi> (National Identity Museum), Calle El Telegrafo. Museum of Honduran history and art. Gets good reviews on other sites.</item>
<item> <ref target="https%3A//www.google.com/maps/place/Museo%2BArqueologico/%4014.461864%2C-87.6438065%2C17z/data%3D%213m1%214b1%214m5%213m4%211s0x8f658f61c6430635:0x35ff9bf65f723488%218m2%213d14.4618588%214d-87.6416178"></ref> <hi rend="bold">Museo Arqueologico</hi> (Archaeology Museum).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Centro de <ref target="https%3A//www.google.com/maps/place/Tegucigalpa/%4014.0839962%2C-87.2399923%2C13z/data%3D%213m1%214b1%214m5%213m4%211s0x8f6fa2babf743d51:0x68cf2238206ac9d3%218m2%213d14.065049%214d-87.1715002">tegucigalpa</ref></hi> Tegucigalpa is the capital city of Honduras. Set in a central valley surrounded by mountains, it’s known for its well-preserved Spanish colonial architecture. The main Plaza Morazán is dominated by the 18th-century Cathedral of St. Michael the Archangel, with its baroque interior. The Museum of National Identity traces the country’s history. It includes a virtual tour of the Copán Mayan ruins of western Honduras.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https%3A//www.google.com/maps/place/Parque%2BNacional%2BLa%2BTigra/%4014.2456033%2C-87.1245249%2C17z/data%3D%213m1%214b1%214m5%213m4%211s0x8f6fa76aaaaaaaa7:0xf07fdf8520a84467%218m2%213d14.2455981%214d-87.1223362">Parque Nacional La Tigra</ref> </hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https%3A//www.google.com/maps/place/Basilica%2Bde%2BNuestra%2BSe%25C3%25B1ora%2BDe%2BSuyapa/%4014.0803969%2C-87.1595935%2C17z/data%3D%213m1%214b1%214m5%213m4%211s0x8f6fbcb46189a67b:0x3ea25a43ce2571e5%218m2%213d14.0803917%214d-87.1574048">Our Lady of Suyapa</ref> .</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https%3A//www.google.com/maps/place/Cathedral%2Bof%2BTegucigalpa/%4014.1055099%2C-87.206389%2C17z/data%3D%213m1%214b1%214m5%213m4%211s0x8f6fa2bfb6ac9f9f:0xe68924f7201cddbf%218m2%213d14.1055047%214d-87.2042003">St. Michael the Archangel Cathedral, Tegucigalpa</ref> </hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https%3A//www.google.com/maps/place/Iglesia%2Bde%2BLos%2BDolores/%4014.1080765%2C-87.2087448%2C17z/data%3D%213m1%214b1%214m5%213m4%211s0x8f6fa295e8ca6507:0x35f0bcaed1dd4686%218m2%213d14.1080713%214d-87.2065561">Iglesia de Los Dolores</ref> </hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https%3A//www.google.com/maps/place/Galeria%2BNacional%2Bde%2BArte/%4014.1072462%2C-87.2095441%2C17z/data%3D%214m8%211m2%212m1%211sIglesia%2Bde%2BLos%2BDolores%2C%2BTegucigalpa%2Bgaleria%2Bnacional%2Bde%2Barte%213m4%211s0x8f6fa2bf03f6a595:0x8aa2a2bf7772276d%218m2%213d14.1064108%214d-87.2081547">Galeria Nacional de Arte</ref></hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https%3A//www.google.com/maps/place/Chiminike/%4014.0718604%2C-87.205066%2C17z/data%3D%213m1%214b1%214m5%213m4%211s0x8f6fbd37f8f3a641:0x267e487d421ef979%218m2%213d14.0718552%214d-87.2028773">Chiminike</ref></hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https%3A//www.google.com/maps/place/Museo%2Bde%2BHistoria%2BNatural/%4014.0862866%2C-87.1685878%2C17z/data%3D%213m1%214b1%214m5%213m4%211s0x8f6fa32cca0c0227:0xaa18f7c39ebef594%218m2%213d14.0862814%214d-87.1663991">Museo de Historia Natural</ref></hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https%3A//www.google.com/maps/place/Museo%2Bde%2BHistoria%2BRepublicana%2BVilla%2BRoy/%4014.1123514%2C-87.2085567%2C17z/data%3D%213m1%214b1%214m5%213m4%211s0x8f6fa2941e904e99:0x9fa85b9a47d1d284%218m2%213d14.1123462%214d-87.206368">Museo de Historia Republicana Villa Roy</ref></hi></item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Movies</hi> The Mall-Multiplaza has a <ref target="https://www.cinemarkca.com/es/theatres/honduras-multiplaza-tegucigalpa">Cinemark theater</ref> on the third floor. Showtimes for popular movies frequently are half English with Spanish subtitles, and half dubbed in Spanish. As of 2009, tickets are L63/person.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Karaoke</hi>. There's a karaoke bar a few blocks west of Parque Central. There's no song list, so you just need to think of songs and hope they have them. They seem to have a good number of the more popular English karaoke songs (aka Beatles), otherwise you can sing Spanish songs. They also have cheap beer and they serve you small snacks (crackers with tuna on them) at no extra charge while you're sitting down.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Parque de la Paz</hi>, Just south of the Estadio Nacionál. From the top you can see great panoramic views of Tegucigalpa, and the Peace Monument itself is also worth the trip up to see. However, see below for VERY important safety instructions.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St. Michael's Cathedral, Los Dolores Church, and San Francisco Church</hi>. These are all old Catholic churches well worth visiting, and La Merced and the Basilica de Suyapa are really good, too. While not up to the level of a place like Cartagena, Colombia, such older churches are a nice surprise to the tourist who isn't aware that Tegucigalpa has older, Colonial-era attractions as well.</item>
</list>
</text>
