<text id="autogum_voyage_doc205" title="Shawnee" shortTile="shawnee" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=32408" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Shawnee</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Shawnee</hi> is in the <ref target="Frontier%20Country">Frontier Country</ref> region of <ref target="Oklahoma">Oklahoma</ref>.</p>

<p>While normally not on the sight-seeing itinerary of those who do not know someone already living there, Shawnee could prove to be an interesting day trip.</p>

<p>In recent days, Shawnee has become increasingly known for its numerous Native American casinos.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Practically the only method of getting in or out of Shawnee is on the highway. Taxi cabs can be hired by calling a taxi service to have them pick you up, although doing so from another city could prove expensive.</p>

<p>There is an Enterprise rent a car in Shawnee and Shawnee Airport, so car rentals must be made before hand. Many times this is done at Will Rogers World Airport in <ref target="Oklahoma%20City">Oklahoma City</ref>.</p>

<p>Most traffic enters and exits Shawnee via <hi rend="bold">Interstate Highway I-40</hi>, although <hi rend="bold">State Highway 3</hi> and <hi rend="bold">US Highway 177</hi> pass through Shawnee as well.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Greyhound</hi> buses make daily stops in front of the American Colony motel on the far north side of Shawnee.</p>

<p>From there you will have to either call a taxi or arrange another form of pickup.</p>
<head>By train</head>
<p>Originally established as a railroad hub, Shawnee still has many infrequently used rail tracks. While logistically difficult as well as illegal, it could be feasible to stow aboard a freight car inbound to Shawnee. Not recommended.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>Chartered flights can be acquired to fly you in to Shawnee airport, most likely originating from <ref target="Oklahoma%20City">Oklahoma City</ref> or <ref target="Tulsa">Tulsa</ref>. There are no commercial flight charter services based in Shawnee, so arrangements for your eventual pickup would have to be made as well.</p>

<head>On foot</head>
<p>While towns in Oklahoma are quite spread out, some have been known to hitchhike especially along I-40. Not preferred.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>If you are a tourist, getting around in Shawnee means either calling a taxi cab service to pick you up or using a rental car.</p>

<p>Shawnee is very, very spread out and you will quickly abandon any thoughts of walking if you ever want to get where you're going.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Heart of Oklahoma Shawnee Expo Center</hi> (fairgrounds and outdoor arena), 1700 W. Independence, ☏ +1 405 275-7020 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Log Cabin</hi>. 19th century log cabin built by early settlers. Has been moved from original location. Partially demolished.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Burial Plot of Brewster Higley</hi>, 1500 North Center Ave, ☏ +1 405 878-1529 . The now deceased author of the western epic "Home on the Range" has his final resting place in Fairview Cemetery located next to McDonalds on Harrison Street.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Downtown Shawnee</hi>. Many old buildings from Shawnee's early years still remain, although most have changed facade and/or fallen into disrepair.</item>
</list>
<head>Notable Downtown Shawnee Buildings</head>

<p>In recent years, Shawnee has spent over a million dollars revitalizing a three block section of <hi rend="bold">Bell Street</hi>, one of Shawnee's oldest roads and site of the Aldrige Hotel and former Round House Building.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aldrige Hotel</hi>, 20 East 9th St, ☏ +1 405 275-9500 (Apartments), +1 405 273-3030 (Barber Shop) . Once renowned hotel tower that has been internally restored by federal funding as housing for the indigent elderly.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Round House</hi>. Three story manufacturing site of Round House bib overalls for over 80 years. (Business moved outside city limits in 1995 when city code enforcement precluded expansion.) Round House slogan still visible on side of building.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Santa Fe Depot</hi>, East Main St, ☏ +1 405 275-8412 . Old railroad station turned museum. Has working railroad tracks.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cinema Center 8</hi>, 3031 North Harrison, ☏ +1 405 275-7511 . Movie theater, Jones Theaters</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hornbeck and Penthouse</hi>, 125 North Bell Ave, ☏ +1 405 275-0963, +1 405 275-0964 (Office) . Movie theater (Still commonly, and now incorrectly, referred to as the "Dollar Movie", despite a recent price increase to .50).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mabee-Gerrer Museum of Art</hi>, 1900 W MacArthur Dr, ☏ +1 405 878-5300 , ✉ dfpollei@mgmoa.org .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Movies 6</hi>, 4901 North Kickapoo (Shawnee Mall), ☏ +1 405 275-6666 . Recently bought and renovated by Jones Theatres and reopened in the spring of 2010. It is now equal to the Cinema Center 8 in quality and price.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Noah's Ark Petting Zoo</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Oklahoma Baptist University Sporting Events</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Oklahoma Baptist University Theater</hi>, ☏ +1 405 878-2347 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shawnee Airport Jogging Trail</hi>, 2202 Airport Dr, ☏ +1 405 878-1625 (Airport Manager) . 4-mile track built in mid 1990s courtesy federal grant,</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shawnee Bowl Family Fun Center</hi> (formerly Tri-County-Bowl; colloquially "Ghetto Bowl" although recent facility upgrades may have rendered this pejorative a misnomer), 701 North Harrison St, ☏ +1 405 275-4064 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shawnee Little Theater</hi>, 1829 Airport Dr, ☏ +1 405 275-2805 . Theater</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shawnee Public Library</hi>, 101 North Philadelphia Ave, ☏ +1 405 275-6353, +1 405 273-3334 (Administrative Services) .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St. Gregory's University Sporting Events</hi>, 1900 West Macarthur, ☏ +1 405 878-5100 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Star Skate</hi>, 37303 45th St, ☏ +1 405 273-2030 . Roller skating rink.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Veterans of Foreign Wars (VFW) Headquarters</hi>, 811 East Macarthur St, ☏ +1 405 273-7098 . Weekend concerts and annual Super Bowl parties.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA)</hi> (Saratoga &amp; Hornet Street), ☏ +1 405 273-4386 . Gyms, fitness facilities, youth sports.</item>
</list>


<head>Golfing</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shawnee Golf and Country Club</hi>, 2501 Augusta, ☏ +1 405 273-4076, +1 405 273-2764 (Golf Shop), +1 405 273-0784 (Greens Keeper), +1 405 273-1763 (Office) . Collared shirt and appropriate golf attire required. 18 hole course, Pro Store, and Club House dining available.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fire Lake Golf Course</hi>, 1901 South Gordon Cooper Dr, ☏ +1 405 275-4471 . 18 hole course; usually considered to Shawnee's budget golfing: "Golfing for the price of a gordita", Miniature Golf located nearby.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Elk's Golf Course</hi> (Shawnee Lodge 657), ☏ +1 405 275-1060 . Driving range and batting cages also available.</item>
</list>


<head>Public Parks</head>
<p>Since Shawnee's many public parks are used infrequently by locals, a quiet and serene environment can usually be expected.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">KidSpace</hi>. Children's outdoor play equipment (adult supervision strongly recommended)</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lions Club Park</hi>. (has baseball field)</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Briscoe Rotary Boy Scout Park</hi>. (lighted public tennis courts, great place for pick-up style basketball games) (<hi rend="bold">not recommended after dark</hi>)</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Weigant Park</hi>. Aka "Slide Park" (<hi rend="bold">not recommended after dark</hi>)</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Woodland Park</hi>. (public swimming pool available in Summer months) (lighted public tennis courts)</item>
</list>
</text>
