<text id="autogum_voyage_doc18" title="Château-d'Œx" shortTile="chteaudx" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=6938" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Château-d'Œx</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.chateau-doex.ch/en/">Château d'Œx</ref></hi> is a ski station in <ref target="Switzerland">Switzerland</ref> near <ref target="Gstaad">Gstaad</ref> and <ref target="Montreux">Montreux</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Château-d'Œx is a small village of approximately 3,500 inhabitants in the <ref target="French%20phrasebook">French</ref>-speaking part of Switzerland. In recent years, Château-d'Œx has become increasingly popular among travelers primarily for the village's incredibly authentic Swiss alpine feel, stunning natural surroundings, and quiet atmosphere. </p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>The of Château-d'Œx has hourly trains to <ref target="Montreux">Montreux</ref> (1h) and Zweisimmen (50min) via <ref target="Gstaad">Gstaad</ref> (30min) in the <ref target="Bernese%20Highlands">Bernese Highlands</ref>. The trip will take a bit longer if you happen to take a regional slow train. The train is operated by GoldenPass Montreux-Bernese Oberland (MOB) Railway. Some of the connections are panorama trains or old style 'classic' trains which do not cost extra and are part of the regular timetable.</p>

<p>There is a bus to Col-des-Mosse from where it is possible to join Aigle via another bus to Le Sépey and a train to Aigle, however it is much easier and faster to take the longer route via train passing through Montreux.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Château-d'Œx is approximately a 2 hour drive from Geneva and a 1 hour and 15 minute drive to Bern. While not directly accessible by a motorway, driving into Château-d'Œx is not difficult. It can be accessed from three different directions. The main road comes in from <ref target="Spiez">Spiez</ref> (with access to the A6 motorway) and Zweisimmen in the <ref target="Bernese%20Highlands">Bernese Highlands</ref> and goes on to Aigle (with access to the A9 motorway) near the border to <ref target="Valais">Valais</ref>. Another smaller road leads into the canton of Fribourg, to <ref target="Gruy%C3%A8res">Gruyères</ref> and Bulle, where you can join the A12 motorway.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Château-d'Œx is small enough that walking is the easiest and most efficient method of transportation to get anywhere in the village. Château-d'Œx is hilly, however, so any walk may involve a steep hike at one point or another.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Museum of the Pays-d’Enhaut</hi>, Grand Rue 107, ☏ +41 26 924 65 20 . Tu-Su 14:00-17:00, closed in November. Has permanent exhibits on the life in the village in past times, but also on local art, notably paintings and paper cuts. Fr. 8/4. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Balloon Museum</hi>, Chemin des Ballons 2, ☏ +41 78 723 78 33 , ✉ info@espace-ballon.ch . Tu-Su 14:00-17:00. This museum showcases the history of hot-air balloons. A highlight is the capsule Breitling Orbiter used by Bertrand Piccard to circumnavigate the globe in 1999. Fr. 8/5. </item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hot-air balloon flights</hi> (Ballon Château d'Œx), ☏ +41 26 924 22 20 , ✉ info@ballonchateaudoex.ch . See the Alps from a new perspective - from the basket of a hot-air balloon! Available year-round, weather permitting. Fr. 390/195.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Paraglide.</hi> There are numerous take-off points and numerous pilots in the area, allowing you to ride the winds no matter their direction.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Horseback Riding.</hi> Numerous bridle paths wind between <ref target="Rougemont">Rougemont</ref> through Château dŒx to <ref target="Rossini%C3%A8re">Rossinière</ref>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Climbing wall.</hi> Meet at the Les Moulins to take a climb rain or shine. Tel 924 56 53.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bowling.</hi>, Parc des Sports, ☏ +41 26 924 24 54 . Head to Bowling du Parc for a good time on the lanes. The centre also offers tennis and ice skating. Fr. 8/7.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hiking.</hi> With over 300km of marked paths, this regions offers some great opportunities to experience the great outdoors. A walking map with 15 suggested itineraries, labelled with length and difficult, is available around town.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Watersports</hi></item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hydrospeed.</hi> A wild adventure on the river Sarine. Strap on your flippers and float down the river with your head bobbing on the water's surface.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Canyoning.</hi> Suited into an isothermal outfit, you can walk and swim into some of the wildest gorges in the region.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Canoe or kayak.</hi> Paddle around on the lake.</item>
<item> <hi rend="italic">Contact</hi>:</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rivières et Aventures</hi>, ☏ +41 79 434 70 89 , fax: +41 26 924 34 23 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">H2O Experience</hi>, ☏ +41 79 438 74 51 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Swiss Raft</hi>, ☏ +41 26 924 43 50 .</item>
</list>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Biking.</hi> Marked mountain biking tracks can be found all around the region.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Swim.</hi> The heated, olympic sized swimming pool at au Berceau is open from mid-May to early September.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ski.</hi> There are plenty of opportunities for downhill and cross country skiing, even tobogganing.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">La Braye</hi> (29 km in winter, 7 lifts). A rather small ski area right in the village Day pass Fr. 42/32.</item>
</list>



<head>Eat</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Le Chalet</hi>, Route de la gare 2, ☏ +41 26 924 66 77 , ✉ lechalet-fromagerie@bluewin.ch . Sa-Th 08:30–18:00, F 08:30–00:00. Local cuisine in an old house. Has a cheese-making demonstration on some days from 10:30–12:30.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">le Castel</hi>, ☏ +41 26 924 74 77 . A pub.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Irish Tavern</hi>, ☏ +41 26 924 74 23 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">le Poulailler</hi>, ☏ +41 26 924 57 04 . Cabaret.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">La Bamba</hi>, ☏ +41 26 924 52 52 . Discotheque.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Le Zenith</hi>.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>
<p>Château-d'Œx has various hotels and traditional Swiss châlets for rent. </p>
<head>Budget</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Camping - Au Berceau</hi>, Route des Mosses 18, ☏ +41 26 924 62 34 , fax: +41 26 924 25 26 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Youth hostel</hi> (Auberge de Jeunesse), Route des Monnaires 67, ☏ +41 26 924 64 04 , fax: +41 26 924 58 43 , ✉ chateau.d.oex@youthhostel.ch . €20 - 27, Fr. 29-40.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chalet Perce-Neige</hi>, 1660 Château d'Oex, ☏ +41 26 924 69 81 . €26 - 43, Fr. 39-65.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Restoski</hi>, Route des Mosses 104, 1660 La Lécherette, ☏ +41 26 924 62 59 , fax: +41 26 924 41 63 . €27 - 53, Fr. 40-80.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Beau-Sejour</hi>, 1660 Château d'Oex, ☏ +41 26 924 74 23 , fax: +41 26 924 58 06 . A 2-star hotel. €30 - 100, Fr. 45-150.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pension le Vieux Chalet</hi>, Route de la Frasse 57, 1660 Château d'Oex, ☏ +41 26 924 68 79 , fax: +41 26 924 43 11 . €33 - 73, Fr. 50-110.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Valrose</hi>, Place de la Gare, Rougemont, ☏ +41 26 923 77 77 , ✉ welcome@hotelvalrose.ch . A 3-star hotel. €40 - 100, Fr. 65-150.</item>
</list>
</text>
