<text id="autogum_voyage_doc253" title="Melk" shortTile="melk" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=21959" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Melk</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Melk</hi> is a small riverside town (pop. ~5,000) on south bank of the Danube River in the <ref target="Wachau">Wachau</ref> Valley of <ref target="Lower%20Austria">Lower Austria</ref>. Melk marks the western terminus of the Wachau (86km west of Vienna) and lies upstream (40km west) from <ref target="Krems">Krems</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Stadtgemeinde Melk Tourismusbüro</hi>, Linzer Straße 5 (temporary location; original site damaged during flooding), ☏ +43 2752-511 60 , ✉ melk@donau.com . Apr-Oct. Free town map with a self-guided walking tour, a list of Melk hotels and rooms, latest info on nearby castles, bike rentals, and bike rides along the river.</item>
</list>


<head>By rail</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bahnhof Melk</hi>, Bahnhofplatz 1, ☏ +43 2752 52321 . Ticket office: M-F 05:50-11:40, 12:10-16:05, Sa 06:40-12:25; Su and holidays 08:20-11:40, 12:10-18:35; automats: 24hrs. Trains leave frequently from Vienna's Westbahnhof to Melk, with two brief stops en route (about 1 hr. trip time). Use ÖBB's <ref target="http://fahrplan.oebb.at/bin/query.exe/en%3F"><hi rend="bold">SCOTTY</hi></ref> to look up train information online.</item>
</list>


<head>By car</head>
<p>Use the <hi rend="bold">A1</hi> Westautobahn motorway and take the exit <hi rend="italic">Melk</hi>. Melk-Wien: 85 km.</p>

<head>By boat</head>
<p>From mid-April through October Dürnstein can be reached by river boats which ply the route between Melk, Emmersdorf, Spitz, <ref target="D%C3%BCrnstein">Dürnstein</ref>, and <ref target="Krems">Krems</ref>/Stein.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">DDSG Blue Danube Schiffahrt GmbH</hi>, ☏ +43 1 588 80 , fax: +43 1 588 80 440 , ✉ info@ddsg-blue-danube.at . Operates several times daily; timetables and fares (listed at the bottom of the page) can be found <ref target="http://www.ddsg-blue-danube.at/linie-wachau/linie-wachau-wachauschifffahrt/">here</ref>. Tickets can be purchased at any of the docking points, in Vienna, or <ref target="https://shop.ddsg-blue-danube.at">online</ref>. Bicycles (€2) and dogs (free) permitted on board.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Brandner</hi>, Pionierstrasse, ☏ +43 7433 2590 21 , ✉ schiffahrt@brandner.at . Operates twice daily, also making a stop in Weißenkirchen. Timetables and fares can bee seen <ref target="https://www.brandner.at/en/liner-cruises/timetable-fares/">here</ref>. Tickets can be purchased <ref target="https://www.brandner.at/en/shop/ticket/60968/%23/trip">online</ref>. Bicycles (€2) and dogs (free, muzzle and leash required) permitted on board.</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>
<p>Walking the small historic town center (of mainly 16th-17th century buildings) is easy; takes about 10 minutes to traverse it. The famous and huge 18th century Benetictine Abbey on top of a bluff forms a northern Baroque backdrop for the older town center and is accessed on its eastern side.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nextbike</hi> (bicycle rental), ☏ +43 2742 22 99 01 (hotline) . After registration (online or by mobile), pick up a bicycle at any Nextbike location, and drop the bicycle off at the same or any other Nextbike spot. A map of pickup and drop-off points can be found <ref target="http://www.nextbike.at/1384.html%3F%26amp%3BL%3Den">here</ref> (click 'Wachau' for Melk); a brochure with map is available for <ref target="http://www.nextbike.at/fileadmin/austria/Karten//2016/nextbike_Folder_Wachau_2016.pdf">download</ref>. €1/hr, €10/day.</item>
</list>


<head>Taxi</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Taxi Gugler</hi>, ☏ +43 2752-52358 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Taxifunk Stumpfer</hi>, ☏ +43 2752-22022 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Taxi-Funk-Türke</hi>, ☏ +43 2752-52316 .</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Melk Benedictine Abbey</hi> (Benediktinerstift Melk), Abt-Berthold-Dietmayr-Straße 1 (ticket booth on the south side, entrance at the east), ☏ +43 2752-555-232 , ✉ tours@stiftmelk.at . May-Sep daily 09:00-17:30 (last entrance at 17:00); Mar-Apr, Oct daily 09:00-16:30 (last entrance at 16:00); Nov-Mar: guided tours only at 11:00, 14:00, (German and English). The must-see in Melk. The abbey is built on a bluff overlooking the Danube River to the northwest and the town center to the south. Most of the design of the present abbey (a reconstruction started in 1702) was by the architect Jakob Prandtauer. The 200m-long <hi rend="italic">Kaisergang</hi> (Imperial Corridor and Abbey Museum) is decorated with portraits of Austrian rulers. The <hi rend="italic">Marmorsaal</hi> (Marble Hall) contains pilasters coated in red marble; a richly painted allegorical picture on the ceiling is the work of Paul Troger. The <hi rend="italic">Bibliothek</hi> (Library), rising two floors, again with a Troger ceiling, contains some 80,000 volumes. The <hi rend="italic">Stiftskirche</hi> (Abbey Church), with its 200-ft dome and symmetrical twin towers, dominates the abbey complex and emphasizes its sacred purpose. Damaged by fire in 1947, the church is now almost completely restored, even to the gold-bullion gilding of statues and altars. With/without guided tour: €11/13 (adults), €6/8 (concessions). </item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Abbey Park and Baroque Garden Pavilion</hi> (Stiftspark). May-Oct daily 09:00-18:00. Originally designed as a Baroque park in 1750, and replanted in 1822 as an English garden. €4 (adults), €3 (students), €1 (children 6-16); free with abbey admission.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Stadtmuseum Melk</hi> (Alte Post / Altes Posthaus), Linzer Straße 3-5, ☏ +43 2752 52307-112 . Open only for special exhibits: Th-F 09:30-13:00, Sa-Su 15:00-19:00. Built in 1792 by the Viennese architect Franz Wipplinger, the building now houses a collection of prehistoric artifacts from the region, as well as a photographic archive and library. Special exhibits change annually. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Town Hall</hi> (Rathaus), Rathaus Platz 11 (in the center of town). Built in 1575.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Haus am Stein</hi>, Kremser Straße 2. Built in the 15th century, this is the oldest building in Melk. The building is a private residence but can be appreciated from the outside.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Accordion Museum</hi> (Akkordeon Museum), Sterngasse 19, ☏ +43 2752 514 89, +43 664 431 70 25 , ✉ akkordeonmuseum@aon.at . Summer: T-Su 10:00-18:00. The accordion was invented in Vienna in 1829, and since then became popular around the world. This private museum has 250 accordions, including some very rare and eccentric pieces, with the oldest dating from 1860. Free, but donations appreciated.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">KZ-Gedenkstätte Melk</hi> (Concentration Camp Memorial), Schießstattweg 8, ☏ +43 2752 51 888 . May-Jun: T-Su 10:00-14:00 and by appt.. From April 1944 until liberation in April 1945 this site was a concentration camp, operated as a branch of the main camp in Mauthausen. Approximately 5,000 Jews lost their lives here. The former crematorium has been preserved as a memorial. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Schallaburg Castle</hi> (Renaissanceschloss Schallaburg), Schallaburg 1 (5km south of Melk), ☏ +43 2754 6317-0 . Apr-Oct M-F 09:00-17:00, Sa Su and holidays 09:00-18:00. A well-preserved German Renaissance castle, on a site occupied since the Roman occupation; the foundation dates to the Romanesque period. Special architectural features include the courtyard with terracotta figures and the Renaissance garden. The building is now a museum with specially-themed, annually rotating exhibits. €10 (adults), €9 (concessions), €3.50 (children). </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gugler Forum Melk</hi>, gugler print &amp; media, Auf der Schön 2, Pielach, ☏ +43 2752 50050 0 , ✉ office@gugler.at . M-Th 07:30-17:30, F 07:30-15:00. This graphic design agency hosts special solo artist exhibits three times a year from the contemporary Austrian art world. Artists are selected by an independent jury. A restaurant and café are onsite. Free.</item>
</list>
</text>
