<text id="autogum_voyage_doc482" title="Newark Liberty International Airport" shortTile="newark-liberty-international" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=123857" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Newark Liberty International Airport</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.panynj.gov/airports/newark-liberty.html">Newark Liberty International Airport</ref></hi>, 1-800-EWR-INFO, ( EWR ), is west of <ref target="New%20York%20City">New York City</ref> in <ref target="Newark%20%28New%20Jersey%29">Newark</ref> and <ref target="Elizabeth">Elizabeth</ref>, <ref target="New%20Jersey">New Jersey</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Newark opened in 1928 as the only airport in <ref target="Metro%20New%20York">Metro New York</ref>, but became pretty deserted when LaGuardia Airport opened in <ref target="Queens">Queens, New York</ref>. After World War II, commercial activity returned to the airport. Gradually, it grew to the massive international hub it is today. </p>

<p>Before 9/11, the airport was called "Newark International Airport". The word "liberty" was added to the airport's name after 9/11 to honor the victims, as one of the four hijacked planes that day, United Airlines Flight 93, took off from this airport. Additionally, the word "liberty" is also a reference to the Statue of Liberty not very far from the airport.</p>

<p>Terminal A, especially the small section that serves American Airlines and Virgin America has <hi rend="bold">insufficient security capacity</hi> at peak times, most notably Monday afternoons. You should plan to arrive <hi rend="bold">at least 2 hours before</hi> your flight during these periods.</p>

<head>Flights</head>
<p>The airport has three sprawling terminals, labeled A, B, and C, arranged in a semicircle around a central roadway. Terminal C is the home of United Airlines' major East Coast hub. As a rule of thumb, most international airlines use Terminal B while most domestic airlines use Terminal A.</p>

<p>Note 1: Flights arriving from international destinations will arrive in Terminal B.</p>

<p>Note 2: Check your departure or arrival terminal. International United flights arrive at Terminals B or C while United Mainline and Express flights can either depart from or arrive at Terminals A or C.</p>

<p>Singapore Airlines' flight from Newark to Singapore is the longest nonstop commercial flight in the world, taking around 19 hours to cover a distance of 9,521 miles (15,323 km).</p>

<head>Ground transportation</head>

<p>Newark Liberty is well connected to New York City by both train and bus. NJ Transit train tickets bring you to New York Penn Station in <ref target="Manhattan/Theater%20District">western Midtown Manhattan</ref> for $13. If you are with a few people, you could consider a taxi, which will set you back around $60 plus tip.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.njtransit.com/pdf/bus/T0062.pdf">New Jersey Transit Bus #62</ref></hi> - The most inexpensive option, New Jersey Transit bus #62 runs from in front of the airport terminals to Newark Penn Station (one-way fare $1.60; exact change only; 25 minutes). From there, you may take a PATH subway train ($2.75) either to World Trade Center station in lower Manhattan (25 minutes), or, to Journal Square, where you can transfer to the Journal Square-33rd Street train across the platform, which runs to the following stops along 6th Avenue: Christopher St in Greenwich Village, 9th St, 14th St, 23rd St, and 33rd St. Plan on 90 minutes including waiting times. As a word of caution, note that this is not a well-publicized option; you may well find yourself to be the only tourist on the bus, so don't expect much help or companionship in finding your way. The bus runs 24 hours a day, 7 days a week, but be careful at night, as this bus travels through some rough areas.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.njtransit.com/var/var_servlet.srv%3FhdnPageAction%3DGoBus28To">GoBus 28</ref></hi> - a limited stop service that also travels to downtown, with continuing service to North Newark.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.coachusa.com/olympia/ss.newarkairport.asp">Newark Airport Express Bus</ref></hi> - ($16 one way, $28 round-trip) runs every 15 minutes to 42nd street in Manhattan. It stops in the Port Authority, outside of Bryant Park, and outside of Grand Central. The trip takes about 40 minutes depending on traffic. At peak times (afternoons in particular), the bus to the airport can fill up at the first stop, so allow extra time for mishaps, and try to catch it at Grand Central.</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Newark Liberty International Airport Station</hi> - The station can be accessed directly by New Jersey Transit's Northeast Corridor and North Jersey Coast Lines, as well as Amtrak's Northeast Regional and (some) Keystone services. At the station, you can disembark and board the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.panynj.gov/airports/ewr-airtrain.html">AirTrain Newark</ref></hi> monorail to get any of the three terminals, as well as airport parking lots. There is a $5.50 fee for passing to or from AirTrain and NJT/Amtrak (children 11 and under are exempt). The fee is included in the ticket price when you buy an NJT/Amtrak ticket starting or ending at this station, so be sure to keep your ticket (and the magnetic strip embedded in it) so that you can pass through the gates (you can also use a ticket or monthly pass for a station beyond here to get to the station, but you will need to pay the fee separately to get to AirTrain). From this station, NJ Transit trains run north to Newark Penn Station (about 6 minutes) and New York Penn Station (about 25-30 minutes); for other North Jersey destinations served by NJ Transit, change at Secaucus Junction. NJ Transit trains also run south along the Jersey Shore as far as Bayhead (2 hours or more to get this far, though) and Trenton (30-50 minutes depending on the time of day); from the latter you can change for a SEPTA train to Philadelphia 30th Street (about an additional 30 minutes, not including wait time). Amtrak trains also run north to New York Penn Station and south to Trenton and Philadelphia before moving on to points all along the East Coast, though they will be more expensive. Two things to note if you're taking the train to New York:</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> First, NJ Transit tickets are <hi rend="italic">not</hi> valid on Amtrak trains.</item>
<item> Second, NJ Transit trains stop at both Penn Station in Newark and at Penn Station in New York, so if your destination is Manhattan stay on until the second Penn Station (past Secaucus Junction). The platforms in the Manhattan station are below street-level following a stretch of underground travel through the tunnels under the Hudson River while the platforms in the Newark station are above street level -- if you're seeing most of the disembarking passengers walking <hi rend="italic">down</hi> stairs, get back on the train as soon as possible because you're still in Newark (the stairs at the New York station lead <hi rend="italic">up</hi>.)</item>
</list>
</text>
