<text id="autogum_voyage_doc84" title="Marmara (region)" shortTile="marmara-region" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=21450" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Marmara (region)</head>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">Marmara Region</hi> in northwestern <ref target="Turkey">Turkey</ref> is the country's bridge and connection to Europe, with Turkey's largest city, Istanbul, at its heart. </p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The region is named after the sea it surrounds: the Sea of Marmara, connected to the Aegean Sea by the Straits Dardanelles, and to the Black Sea by the Bosporus. The Sea of Marmara is considered the geographical border between Europe and Asia: the coastline to the north of the sea is European, while its southern and eastern coasts are in Asia. In addition to the Sea of Marmara, the region has coastlines on the Black Sea to the northeast and the Aegean Sea to the southwest.</p>

<p>The <ref target="Eastern%20Thrace">northwestern/European part</ref> of the region is one of few wide lowlands in the country, with the occasional gently sloping hill, except southwestern and northeastern coasts which are dominated by hilly areas. <ref target="Southern%20Marmara">South</ref> and <ref target="Eastern%20Marmara">east</ref> parts of the region is more mountainous, or hilly at least. While the Marmara Region is the second smallest Turkish region in size (with only <ref target="Southeastern%20Anatolia">Southeastern Anatolia</ref> being smaller), it is only a bit smaller than <ref target="Ireland">Ireland</ref> or the <ref target="Netherlands">Netherlands</ref> and <ref target="Belgium">Belgium</ref> combined.</p>

<p>This region is Turkey’s most populous and most heavily industrialized part, with the residential and industrial suburbs and exurbs of Istanbul going on for <hi rend="italic">hundreds</hi> of kilometres towards any direction the geography permits, although you can still find primordial forests hardly seen by human eyes here and there.</p>

<p>Travellers often overlook Marmara Region except for <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref> and a few sites in the southwest and southeast of the region, but there is not really a reason why they should—in addition to quite friendly and open locals, fairly good transportation links throughout and temperate climate which make travelling in the region a breeze, you will certainly find something to catch your glimpse in any part of this region, where empires have made their debut and have seen their fall, and where dense urban areas and farmlands interact with untouched wilderness beautifully.</p>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>While it is possible to come upon a village founded by immigrants from the <ref target="Balkans">Balkans</ref> in the early 1900s where old people speak the Pomak dialect of <ref target="Bulgarian%20phrasebook">Bulgarian</ref> or some other Balkan language in the region, <ref target="Turkish%20phrasebook">Turkish</ref> is by far the most common and the most useful language, as is in most of Turkey.</p>

<head>By air</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Istanbul Airport IST </hi>, in Arnavutköy 40 km northwest of city centre, is nowadays the main international port of entry into Turkey. The city's former main airport "Atatürk" closed in April 2019.</p>

<p>The other international airport in this region is <hi rend="bold">Sabiha Gökçen SAW </hi> in <ref target="Istanbul/Asian%20Side">Asia-side Istanbul</ref>, much used by low-cost airlines. </p>

<p>There are regional airports with domestic flights at <ref target="%C3%87orlu">Çorlu</ref> TEQ , <ref target="Bursa">Bursa</ref> YEI and <ref target="%C3%87anakkale">Çanakkale</ref> CKZ .</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>There are trains to</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref> from <ref target="Bulgaria">Bulgaria</ref>, <ref target="Greece">Greece</ref>, and a number of other <ref target="Balkans">Balkan</ref> countries via <ref target="Edirne">Edirne</ref>.</item>
<item> Istanbul from various <ref target="Central%20Anatolia">central</ref> and <ref target="Eastern%20Anatolia">eastern</ref> Turkey locations via <ref target="Izmit">Izmit</ref> and <ref target="Eski%C5%9Fehir">Eskişehir</ref>, and from <ref target="Tehran">Tehran</ref>, <ref target="Iran">Iran</ref>.</item>
<item> <ref target="Bandirma">Bandirma</ref> on the southern coast of Marmara from <ref target="Izmir">Izmir</ref>.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>
<p>All cities and many towns in Turkey has direct daily bus services to <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref>. Many cities neighboring <ref target="Balkans">Balkan</ref> countries also has bus links to the city. <ref target="Bursa">Bursa</ref>, by virtue of being a big city, is also served from a large number of cities and towns throughout Turkey.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>The Marmara Region is well linked to neighboring regions and countries by a motorway and highway network.</p>

<head>By boat</head>
<p>There is a weekly ferry service to <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref> from <ref target="Izmir">Izmir</ref> during summer months.</p>

<head>By air</head>
<p>While there are more than one airport in the region, given the region's relative small size and the relative short distance between the airports make transportation by plane practically impossible. The only feasible (and, operating) air service totally within the region is between <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref> and <ref target="%C3%87anakkale">Çanakkale</ref>.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>There is an extensive bus network between towns and cities of the region, and any town with a considerable population (over 10,000), has a direct bus service to <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref>.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>As in the rest of Turkey, the rail network in the region consists of linear lines rather than a spider web-like system. The lines with passenger services are between <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref> and <ref target="Edirne">Edirne</ref> (via <ref target="Corlu">Corlu</ref> and a number of other towns on the way), continuing on to <ref target="Bulgaria">Bulgaria</ref> and <ref target="Greece">Greece</ref>; Istanbul and <ref target="Boz%C3%BCy%C3%BCk">Bozüyük</ref> (via <ref target="Izmit">Izmit</ref>, <ref target="Adapazar%C4%B1">Adapazarı</ref>, <ref target="Osmaneli">Osmaneli</ref>, <ref target="Bilecik">Bilecik</ref>, and a number of other towns on the way), continuing on to <ref target="Eski%C5%9Fehir">Eskişehir</ref>/<ref target="Ankara">Ankara</ref> in <ref target="Central%20Anatolia">Central Anatolia</ref>; and between <ref target="Bandirma">Bandirma</ref> and <ref target="Balikesir">Balikesir</ref>, continuing on to <ref target="Aegean%20Turkey">Aegean Region</ref>.</p>

<head>By boat</head>
<p>There is an extensive network of ferry and fast ferry lines connecting northern and southern coast of the Sea of Marmara, cutting travel time dramatically. Most fast ferry lines fan out of <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref> towards towns and cities on the <ref target="Southern%20Marmara">southern coast</ref>, while conventional ferries can be found between almost any town on the northern and southern coasts (such as <ref target="Tekirda%C4%9F">Tekirdağ</ref>-<ref target="Gemlik">Gemlik</ref> line, which traverses almost the whole sea northwest to southeast).</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>As both the Byzantine and <ref target="Ottoman%20Empire">Ottoman Empire</ref>s were centred here, the Marmara Region has quite a lot of imperial monuments from each. While the Byzantine monuments are mostly in <ref target="Istanbul">Istanbul</ref> with a number of intact artifacts in historically important, but nowadays provincial towns such as <ref target="Iznik">İznik</ref>, <ref target="Tirilye">Tirilye</ref> and <ref target="Vize">Vize</ref>. The Ottoman monuments, on the other hand, while can be found almost anywhere in the region, are best seen in <ref target="Bursa">Bursa</ref>, <ref target="Edirne">Edirne</ref>, and Istanbul—the three consecutive capitals of the empire.</p>

<head>Drink</head>
<p>The main <hi rend="bold">wine areas</hi> of the region are the <ref target="%C5%9Eark%C3%B6y%20District">Şarköy District</ref> on the Marmara coast of <ref target="Eastern%20Thrace">Eastern Thrace</ref> which produces wine out of many varieties, the Marmara island of <ref target="Av%C5%9Fa">Avşa</ref> where the local wine is of varying quality but is often strong, and the Aegean island of <ref target="Bozcaada">Bozcaada</ref> which has a wine tradition dating back millenia ago.</p>

<p>The town of <ref target="Susurluk">Susurluk</ref> in the south is renowned nationwide for its local foamy <hi rend="bold">ayran</hi>, which is available in (and apparently advertised by) many rest areas along the main Istanbul–Izmir highway.</p>
</text>
