<text id="autogum_voyage_doc222" title="Signs" shortTile="signs" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=144702" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Signs</head>


<p>Different <hi rend="bold">signs</hi> are today a part of the surroundings in built-up areas and along roads. Especially in the developed world you can expect to find <hi rend="italic">some</hi> kind of signs in pretty much all public areas, both indoors and outdoors. </p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>While probably most travelers visit destinations for other attractions than signs (and they are often not even considered attractions), they are still frequently objects of photography and part of the environment. Few foreign travelers would abstain from taking photos of the painted tile street name signs in <ref target="Spain">Spain</ref>, iconic pub signs in <ref target="Britain">Britain</ref>, kangaroo signs along <ref target="Driving%20in%20Australia">Australia’s highways</ref> and the neon signs of <ref target="Las%20Vegas">Las Vegas</ref> and Chinatowns around the world.</p>

<p>The very first time you travel to a country where another alphabet is used, being surrounded by signs in a script you probably cannot make any sense of is likely one of the major factors that make the place feel exotic and even intimidating.</p>

<head>Road and street signs</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Route signs</hi> along the former <ref target="Route%2066">Route 66</ref> are the obvious example of iconic road signs. Other famous routes, roads and hiking trails, also often have a special recognizable type of sign.</p>

<p>When <hi rend="bold"><ref target="border%20crossings">crossing into another country</ref></hi>, province or other area there may be a remarkable “welcome” sign or even kind of gate or "arch of triumph". Note that it may not be OK to take photos of or near border crossings, as these are regarded as sensitive security areas.</p>

<p>Abroad you may see not only <hi rend="bold">traffic signs</hi> you haven’t seen before but new variants of familiar signs. For instance outside Europe and the US chances are that the text on the eight-sided red stop sign will be something else than “STOP”. Even in Latin America you will encounter “PARE” or “ALTO”.</p>

<p>Signs notifying of <hi rend="bold">dangers</hi> that are not commonly found around the world like the polar bear signs on <ref target="Svalbard">Svalbard</ref> are also worth a photo. Relatively unique <hi rend="bold">prohibitive signs</hi> also belong in this category, like the crossed-out maté gourd on <ref target="Uruguay">Uruguay</ref>an intercity buses or durian fruit in the <ref target="Singapore">Singapore</ref> MRT system (though photography is not allowed in the latter).</p>

<p>Cities and towns often have street signs that are aesthetically beautiful like the ones in the <ref target="Vienna/Innere%20Stadt">Vienna Old town</ref> or otherwise iconic. Moreover some streets and squares like <ref target="Manhattan">Broadway</ref> or the <ref target="Central%20Moscow">Red Square</ref> are world famous, so while there don't forget to take a pic of the sign as well! Some famous streets (Champs Elysée in Paris, <hi rend="italic">Unter den Linden</hi> in Berlin) are also marked by street signs that in some cases have become famous in their own right if only as "proof" that you actually were there, so take pictures.</p>

<p>Streets, squares and roads are often named after important historical persons, events or places. Interestingly, they may be named after persons still alive (countries with authoritarian regimes are almost guaranteed to have these). And rock fans will probably find AC/DC Lane in <ref target="Melbourne">Melbourne</ref> and the Calle AC/DC in Leganés outside <ref target="Madrid">Madrid</ref> worth a visit.</p>

<head>Places</head>
<p>Whether it be <ref target="places%20with%20funny%20names">places with funny names</ref> like <ref target="Fucking">Fucking</ref> or places famous for one reason or another like <ref target="Wacken">Wacken</ref> or <ref target="Schengen">Schengen</ref>, the entrance sign to the town has often become a common motive for photography. Signs for <ref target="Hollywood">Hollywood</ref> and <ref target="Las%20Vegas">Las Vegas</ref> (see image) have even become attractions in their own right.</p>

<p>If a destination is rather small but has a <ref target="Places%20with%20unusual%20names">funny or unusual name</ref>, road and street signs that include the place’s name are often among the main attractions. This also includes corresponding signs of businesses if such exist. Of course some destinations may have names that businesses prefer not to use.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Mountain peaks</hi>, particularly high or low locations, extreme points of countries, continents and such often have a sign informing people that they are at such a location. Also, places where important historical people have been born or events have taken place are often marked by a <hi rend="bold">commemorative plaque</hi>.</p>

<head>Rail systems</head>

<p>Some major <hi rend="bold"><ref target="urban%20rail">urban rail</ref> systems</hi> have very distinctive signs and logos, the best known probably being the Underground signs at the entrance to and inside the London Tube and the “Metropolitain” signs of Paris. Also, stations that are remarkably decorated often also feature remarkable station name signs.</p>

<p>If you travel on <hi rend="bold">named train services</hi>, there are often signs on the stations or at least on and inside the wagons themselves. In addition, before and after an extraordinary train journey like the <ref target="Trans-Siberian">Trans-Siberian</ref>, do take photos of the station signs too.</p>
<p>Most modern <ref target="high%20speed%20rail">high speed rail</ref> systems have some display showing travel speed. If you are fortunate enough to catch the speedometer (in practice, unless you're allowed into the driver's compartment, info screen) when it shows 300 km/h, 200mph or even more, do take a picture. For some this may even be a factor or at least a contributing factor to chose a certain train in the first place.</p>

<head>Business signs</head>

<ref target="Old%20town">Old town</ref>s may have <hi rend="bold">signs for businesses</hi> from the time where electrical light didn’t exist. Sometimes the establishment the sign marks may not be there any longer, sometimes it is, and otherwise the establishment isn't actually that old but just has an old-looking sign to better fit into the environment. These can be painted on the walls like murals or signboards mounted on or hanging out of the wall. In particular the <ref target="British%20Isles">British Isles</ref> are famous for their beautiful pub signs. Painted signboards such as the ones seen in Western movies can be seen in the <ref target="ghost%20towns">ghost towns</ref> of the <ref target="old%20west">old west</ref>.

<p>"Guild signs" (or modern replicas made to look like them) are another favorite. Often, they protrude into the street at a right angle to be better visible. Examples include a distinctive striped "barber pole" (or a pair of scissors) for barbers, a pretzel for bakers, animals for butchers or restaurants. They are often used to invoke (real or proclaimed) tradition going back centuries and a "down home" feeling of the "good old days".</p>

<p>The modern version of these are <hi rend="bold">neon signs</hi>, that have been around for about a century. Invented in <ref target="France">France</ref>, they are probably more often associated with the <ref target="United%20States">United States</ref> and subsequently <ref target="East%20Asia">East Asia</ref> and East Asian communities around the world. Actual neon signs used to be more common, but have partially been replaced by LED signs and screens.</p>

<p>Billboards and street advertisements can also be considered part of this category, however they are not as permanent as the other forms of signage.</p>

<p>In some cites (notably the <ref target="City%20of%20London">City of London</ref>) you may also find older signs typically cast in metal with heraldic elements accompanied by numbers or letters These were originally signs to private fire brigades (run by insurance companies) that a particular building had paid its insurance premium and was thus under that brigade's protection.</p>
</text>
