<text id="autogum_voyage_doc440" title="Zalalövő" shortTile="zalalv" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=168783" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Zalalövő</head>

<ref target="http://www.zalalovo.hu/"><hi rend="bold">Zalalövő</hi></ref> is a town in <ref target="Zala%20County">Zala County</ref> in the valley of Zala river. 

<head>Understand</head>
 
<p>The Roman legions created a military camp on the northern shore of the Zala river at the beginning of the 1st century. Around the camp a village-like settlement founded. In 124, Emperor Hadrian gave town status for the settlement, and called as Municipium Aelium Salla. However, in the middle of the 2nd century the invading Germanic tribes destroyed the settlement.</p>

<p>According to a 13th-century document, royal archers lived here. Zalalövő was elevated to town status in 2000.</p>

<p>This article includes travel-related information not only for Zalalövő, but also for the surrounding rural areas.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Direct trains are available once a day from <ref target="Budapest">Budapest</ref>-Déli pályaudvar via <ref target="Sz%C3%A9kesfeh%C3%A9rv%C3%A1r">Székesfehérvár</ref>, <ref target="Veszpr%C3%A9m">Veszprém</ref> and <ref target="Zalaegerszeg">Zalaegerszeg</ref>. The journey takes 4 hours and costs 4840 Ft.</p>

<p>Other direct connections are:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Toward east: <ref target="Zalaegerszeg">Zalaegerszeg</ref> seven times a day. The journey takes about 30 minutes and costs 465 Ft.</item>
<item> Toward west: <ref target="%C5%90riszentp%C3%A9ter">Őriszentpéter</ref> seven times a day. The journey takes about 15 minutes and costs 310 Ft. There are direct international trains via Bajánsenye to Hodoš (<ref target="Slovenia">Slovenia</ref>) four times a day, and to <ref target="Ljubljana">Ljubljana</ref> once a day.</item>
</list>


 <hi rend="bold">Zalalövő Train Station</hi>, Táncsics Mihály utca 10, ☏ +36 1 349-4949 , ✉ informacio@mav-start.hu . There is no ticket office, tickets can be purchased on the train. The train station is just 700 m away from the center. 

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Frequent buses are available from <ref target="Zalaegerszeg">Zalaegerszeg</ref>. The journey takes about 30 minutes and costs 465 Ft. From <ref target="Budapest">Budapest</ref>-Népliget, you have to transfer in Zalaegerszeg. The whole journey from Budapest takes 4 hours and costs 4770 Ft.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>There is no local public transport or taxi service. You can use the regional buses operated by <ref target="http://www.enykk.hu/">ÉNYKK</ref>.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>In Zalalövő:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">All Saints Roman Catholic Chapel</hi> (Mindenszentek római katolikus kápolna), Petőfi Sándor utca 100. Built in 1743 in Baroque style.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Borosán Valley and Holy Well</hi> (Borosán-völgy és Szentkút).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">John of Nepomuk Sculpture</hi> (Nepomuki Szent János-szobor), Kolozsvári utca 4. Built in 1810 in late Baroque style.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Saint Anne Roman Catholic Church</hi> (Szent Anna római katolikus templom), Kossuth Lajos utca 66, Zalapataka. Built in 1753 in Baroque style.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Saint Ladislaus Roman Catholic Church</hi> (Szent László király római katolikus templom), Szabadság tér. Built in 1925.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Salla Museum</hi> (Salla Múzeum), Kossuth Lajos utca 3, ☏ +36 92 371-004 . May–Oct Tu–F Su 09:00–12:00 13:00–16:00 on appointment. Archaeological site and exhibition about the Roman age of Zala County. Adult: 500 Ft; senior, student: 250 Ft.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Zalalövő Heritage Museum</hi> (Zalalövői tájház), Petőfi Sándor utca 35, ☏ +36 92 371-004 . May–Oct Tu–F Su 09:00–12:00 13:00–16:00 on appointment. Peasant house with thatched roof. Built in the middle of the 19th century. Adult: 300 Ft; senior, student: 150 Ft.</item>
</list>


<p>In Bagod:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Saint Paul Chapel</hi> (Szent Pál-kápolna), Rákóczi Ferenc utca, Szentpál, Bagod. Built around 1260 as round church, rebuilt and extended with a nave and a tower in 1755.</item>
</list>


<p>In Böde:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Saint Michael Archangel Roman Catholic Church</hi> (Szent Mihály arkangyal római katolikus templom), Zalaszentmihályfa, Böde. Interior fittings: 1970s. The church was founded around 1220, destroyed churches have been restored around 1750, the shrine was rebuilt. Sacristy was built in the 19th century. In 1923 it was improved and redesigned. </item>
</list>


<p>In Kávás:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kávás Heritage Museum</hi> (Kávási tájházak), Temető utca 11–13, Kávás. Built in the 19th century.</item>
</list>


<p>In Vaspör:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Roman Catholic Church</hi> (római katolikus templom), Pusztacsatár, Vaspör. Built in 1736 in Baroque style. It's a place of pilgrimage.</item>
</list>


<p>In Zalaháshágy:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Trinity Roman Catholic Church</hi> (Szentháromság római katolikus templom), Petőfi Sándor utca 7, Zalaháshágy. Built in the 12th century, and rebuilt in 1860 in Baroque style.</item>
</list>


<p>In Zalaszentgyörgy:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Saint George Roman Catholic Church</hi> (Szent György római katolikus templom), Zalaszentgyörgy. Built in Romanesque style in the 13th century, and rebuilt in the 14th century in gothic style, and rebuilt again in 1756 in Baroque style.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lake Borostyán</hi> (Borostyán-tó). Lake with beach and sports, fishing possibilities.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Salla Community Center</hi>, Szabadság tér 2, ☏ +36 92 371-004 , ✉ mkk@zalalovo.hu . M W Th 08:00-12:00 13:00-19:00, Tu 08:00-12:00 13:00-16:00, F 08:00-12:00 13:00-21:00.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lake Kustánszeg</hi> (Kustánszegi-tó), Kustánszeg. Artifical lake with beach and sports, fishing possibilities.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pro Equus Horse Park</hi> (Pro Equus Lovaspark), Szent Erzsébet utca 61, Bagod, ☏ +36 20 988-9863 , fax: +36 92 460-626 , ✉ info@bagodilovaspark.hu . Lunge, riding training, trail riding, jump training, riding-tour. Riding training: 4500 Ft, single room: 7000 Ft, double room: 9500 Ft.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Zabolázó Horse Yard</hi> (Zabolázó Lovasudvar), Fő utca 40, Hottó, ☏ +36 30 208-4445 , ✉ jani@zabolazo.hu . Lunge, riding training, trail riding. Riding training: 3000 Ft.</item>
</list>


<head>Events</head>
<ref target="http://www.sallamkk.hu/eves-programtervezetek/">Official events</ref>:

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Day of Zalalövő Town</hi> (Zalalövő város napja). In July.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Days of Zala Cultural and Equestrian Festival</hi> (Zala Menti Napok Kulturális és Lovas Fesztivál). In August.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Farewell of Pataka Hill</hi> (Pataka hegyi búcsú). On August 20.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Stum Festival of Zala</hi> (Zalai Murcifesztivál). In September.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Coop ABC</hi>, Kossuth Lajos utca 6, ☏ +36 92 571-035 . M 05:45–18:00, Tu–Th 05:45–18:30, F 05:45–19:00, Sa 05:45–16:00.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fezo ABC</hi>, Szabadság tér 8. M–F 05:30–19:00, Sa 06:00–13:00, Su 07:00–12:00.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jóár</hi>, Kossuth Lajos utca 8, ☏ +36 92 310-426 , ✉ joar2@fezo.hu . M–Sa 07:00–18:00, Su 07:00–12:00.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p>In Zalalövő:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Alapozó Food Bar</hi>, Kossuth Lajos utca 1, ☏ +36 30 881-8587 , ✉ kruerd2013@gmail.com . M–Th 06:00–20:00, F 06:00–21:00, Sa 07:00–21:00, Su 08:00–19:00. Food bar. 900 Ft, hamburger: 650 Ft.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gold Pub and Restaurant</hi>, Szabadság tér 12, ☏ +36 30 334-7977 . M–Sa 07:00–21:00, Su 07:00–12:00. Traditional restaurant with local cuisine. Lunch menu: 895 Ft.</item>
</list>


<p>In the surroundings:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Alsó Club and Pizzeria</hi>, Kossuth utca 76, Gellénháza, ☏ +36 30 214-8284 . M–Th Su 11:00–22:00, F–Sa 11:00–23:00. Pizzeria and fast food bar. 1350 Ft, pizza: 1500 Ft, hamburger: 650 Ft.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fakopács Pizzeria</hi>, Petőfi Sándor utca 40, Teskánd, ☏ +36 30 523-3277 . M–Th 11:00–22:00, F–Sa 11:00–23:00, Su 15:00–22:00. Pizzeria and fast food bar with some traditional food. 1400 Ft, pizza: 1230 Ft, hamburger: 650 Ft.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Három Fenyő Restaurant</hi>, Olajbányász körút 2, Gellénháza, ☏ +36 70 424-1913 . M–Sa 06:00–22:00, Su 07:00–22:00. Traditional restaurant with local cuisine. Lunch menu: 700 Ft.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Silvestro Pizzeria</hi>, Kossuth Lajos utca 28, Gutorfölde, ☏ +36 30 992 0439 . M–Th 15:00–22:00, F–Sa 12:00–22:00, Su 13:00–21:00. Pizzeria. Pizza: 1300 Ft.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Válicka Restaurant</hi>, Válicka utca 2, Bak, ✉ valickavendeglo@freemail.hu . M–Th 07:00–21:00, F 07:00–22:00, Sa 09:00–22:00, Su 09:00–21:00. Traditional restaurant and pizzeria with local cuisine and with specialties like prósza and deer stew with dödölle. 1450 Ft, pizza: 1250 Ft, hamburger: 600 Ft.</item>
</list>
</text>
