<text id="autogum_voyage_doc539" title="Montreal" shortTile="montreal" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=22870" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Montreal</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.tourisme-montreal.org/">Montreal</ref></hi> (<ref target="French">French</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Montréal</hi>) is the largest city in the Canadian province of <ref target="Quebec">Quebec</ref>. While Quebec City is the capital, Montreal is the cultural and economic centre, and the main entry point to the province. With 1.7 million citizens in the city and 4 million in the urban area, Montreal is Canada's second largest city, and the largest francophone city in the Americas. Montreal is the second-largest French-speaking (as a mother language) city in the world, behind Paris. Still, around 12% of the population speak English as a mother language, and most Francophones are conversant in English to varying degrees of fluency. <ref target="Montreal/Old%20Montreal">Old Montreal</ref> has a heritage of colonial times. Though a large city, Montreal gives opportunities for <ref target="outdoor%20life">outdoor life</ref>, and for watching the legendary Montréal Canadiens ice hockey team.</p>

<head>Ville-Marie borough</head>
<p>Neighbourhoods from west to east:</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>On an island in the St. Lawrence River at the historically highest navigable point, Montreal has been a strategic location since before the arrival of Europeans in Canada. A thriving Iroquoian town called Hochelaga was on the site of present-day Montreal when explorer Jacques Cartier first visited in 1535. In 1642, the tiny town of Ville-Marie was founded as a Catholic mission by Paul Chomedey, sieur de Maisonneuve. It soon became a centre of the fur trade. After its capture by the English in 1762, Montreal remained (until the 1970s) the most important city in Canada and was briefly capital of the province in the 1840s.</p>

<p>Prohibition on sales of alcohol in the United States during the 1920s and 1930s made Montreal a Mecca for cross-border fun seekers from nearby New England and New York. The city built up a seedy, yet playful, industry in alcohol, burlesque, and other vices. In the 1960s, an urban renewal drive centred on Expo 67. The World's Fair in Montreal brought a subway system (the métro) and attractive urban parks and is considered to be one of the most successful World Fairs. Over 50 million visitors gathered in Montreal during this memorable summer. The 1976 Olympics left a strikingly idiosyncratic stadium and many other urban improvements.</p>

<p>The opening of the Saint Lawrence Seaway in 1959, though much-lauded as an economic boom, spelled the beginning of the end for Montreal's economic dominance in Canada. Once the transition point between western railways and eastern sea carriers, Montreal watched helplessly as some of this business moved farther west, up the now navigable seaway, to ports in Ontario and on Lake Superior. The Quebec sovereignty movement, which began to pick up steam in the 1960s, further chilled the atmosphere for Canada-wide businesses, many of which moved their headquarters to Toronto.</p>

<p>Following an economic depression in the 1980s and 1990s, Montreal became more secure in its place in North America and the world. It remains a centre of culture, arts, computer technology, aerospace, the biotech industry, and media for all of Canada.</p>

<head>Orientation</head>

<p><hi rend="italic">It has been said that Montréal is the only city in the world where the sun "rises in the south"</hi>.</p>

<p>Montrealers use an unconventional compass, using the river and the mountain as cardinal points. When you are downtown, the St Lawrence River is “south” and Mount Royal is “north”; making the West Island and the East End correct in both their names and orientations. This tends to confuse visitors because the “East” End is really north and the “South” Shore is east, and the St Lawrence River runs almost north-south at this location.</p>

<p>Most local maps use this convention as do the highways around the city. For example, Autoroute 15 north actually runs northwest and Autoroute 40 east runs northeast.</p>

<p>To underscore this fact, a Montreal map will show that the "south end" of Victoria Bridge is in fact further north than the "north end".</p>

<head>Gay Montreal</head>
<p>Montreal is an extremely inviting destination for gay and lesbian tourists. Canada's contributions to gay rights have become widely known, but Quebec was the first province in Canada to pass a non-discrimination law for sexual orientation and to provide same-sex civil unions (although <ref target="Toronto">Toronto</ref> was the first municipality in Canada to do so). Same-sex marriage is legal in Quebec (neither residency nor citizenship are required for a marriage licence, but there is a three-week waiting period after you receive the licence) as it is in the rest of Canada. Canadian and Quebec immigration law allow residents to sponsor their same-sex partners or spouses.</p>

<p>Montreal is a very safe, open, and inviting city. The métro station in the Gay Village, Beaudry, is marked with rainbow pillars. <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.diverscite.org">Divers/Cité Montreal's pride celebration</ref></hi> (last week of July, first week of August) is the second-largest in Canada after <ref target="Toronto">Toronto</ref>'s.</p>

<head>Climate</head>



<p>The climate of Montreal is a true humid continental climate with 4 distinct seasons. The city has warm—and occasionally hot &amp; humid—summers, generally mild spring and autumn, and often very cold &amp; snowy winters. Montreal gets over 2,000 hours of sunshine annually. Precipitation is moderate throughout the year, with around 2 metres of snow per season.</p>

<head>Visitor information</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Centre Infotouriste de Montréal</hi>, 1255 rue Peel, bureau 100 (At rue Sainte-Catherine; metro Peel), ☏ +1 514 873-2015 , toll-free: +1-877-266-5687 , ✉ info@bonjourquebec.com . Apr 1-May 7: 09:09-17:00; May 8-Oct 4: 09:00-18:00; Oct 5-Mar 31: 09:00-17:00; Closed: Dec 25 &amp; Jan 1.</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>

<p>Montreal's ( YUL ) (also known to locals as Dorval Airport) is west of the city centre on Expressway (<hi rend="italic">Autoroute</hi>) 20. Travel time to the airport from the city centre can be as much as an hour, depending on traffic. The airport is served by all major Canadian and U.S. airlines and is a major hub for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="http://www.aircanada.ca">Air Canada</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="http://www.airtransat.ca">Air Transat</ref></hi>, and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="http://www.westjet.ca">WestJet</ref></hi>. There are daily trans-Atlantic flights to and from (among others) London, Amsterdam, Paris, Geneva, Zurich, Athens, Doha, Frankfurt, Rome, Madrid, Lisbon, Munich, and Casablanca. Trans-Pacific flights are more limited but growing. Air China has service to Beijing, and Air Canada offers services to Shanghai and Tokyo.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">taxi</hi> fare to and from downtown is a fixed price of $40 (a sticker on the window behind the driver gives the boundaries of the zone where the flat fare applies; if you are going from or to places outside this zone, you will have to pay a metered fare with a minimum rate of $17).</p>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.stm.info/en/info/networks/bus/shuttle/747-aeroport-p-e-trudeau-centre-ville-shuttle">STM Airport Express bus 747</ref></hi> offers service between the airport and Montreal 24 hours a day. A single fare will cost $10 (exact change in coins only when paid in the bus) and includes unlimited use of the STM bus and metro network for the following 24 hours. There's a machine that takes credit cards inside the arrivals area where you can purchase fares (including a three-day pass for $18). To get to the bus stop leave the arrivals area and go to the right. There is an area to line up for the 747 buses. The bus will stop at Lionel-Groulx metro station, and some buses continue to various downtown stops (the bus's marquee will state which).</p>

<p>It is possible to go downtown by the cheaper regular <hi rend="bold">public transit system</hi>. Late at night, it is all right, but during peak hours, you will need to complete several transfers with potentially crowded vehicles, so it is really only best to do so only if you are on a very low budget and/or have very light baggage.</p>

<p>Between 05:00 and 01:00, take <ref target="http://www.stm.info/English/a-somm.htm">STM</ref> bus 204 east (<hi rend="italic">est</hi>) which leaves from outside arrivals every 30 min to <hi rend="italic">Gare Dorval</hi> (Dorval Train Station). Check that the driver is not going west (<hi rend="italic">ouest</hi>) as both ways are served from almost the same place, and the sign does not say. You can also use the 209 on weekdays to get to Gare Dorval. Also, be sure to keep the ticket that the driver will give you as it is a transfer which you will need later. From Gare Dorval, use your transfer ticket to catch any one of buses 211, 411, 405, 425, or 485 to Lionel-Groulx metro station. Also make sure it is going east as the same routes go west too. Your transfer will then let you into the metro. Take the Montmorency-bound orange line or the Honoré-Beaugrand-bound green line into downtown on the metro. This costs only $3.25, but exact change in coins only must be provided to the first driver.</p>

<p>Between 05:00 and 01:00, for the same price ($3.25, exact change in coins only), take bus 356 (again, check that the driver is going east, not west) directly into downtown via Sherbrooke. This bus runs relatively close to most downtown hotels. However, if needed, a transfer can be completed to access the rest of the city. See the STM's trip planner or Google Maps for more details.</p>

<p>At <hi rend="italic">Gare Dorval</hi> it is also possible to catch the <ref target="https://exo.quebec/en/trip-planner/train/vaudreuil%25E2%2580%2593hudson">Exo</ref> commuter rail to downtown (Direction Lucien L'Allier), during the day from 06:00 to 20:00 for a single one-way fare of $6, leading to the downtown station of <hi rend="italic">Lucien L'Allier</hi> which is also atop the Lucien L'Allier metro station.</p>

<ref target="Plattsburgh%23By%20plane"><hi rend="bold">Plattsburgh International Airport</hi></ref> and <ref target="Burlington%20%28Vermont%29%23By%20plane"><hi rend="bold">Burlington International Airport</hi></ref>, in the United States, are 1 hr 20 min and 1 hr 50 min, respectively, by car from Montreal. Adirondack Trailways offers a bus service between Plattsburgh International Airport and Montreal. Greyhound offers a bus service from Burlington International Airport and Montreal. For travellers from the US, these airports may offer a significant cost savings compared to Trudeau but at the added inconvenience of arranging ground transportation between the US and Canada.
</text>
