<text id="autogum_voyage_doc368" title="Aqaba" shortTile="aqaba" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=1407" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Aqaba</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.aqaba.jo">Aqaba</ref></hi> (العقبة <hi rend="italic">al-ʿAqabah</hi>) is <ref target="Jordan">Jordan</ref>'s only port city. It is on the Gulf of Aqaba in the extreme south of the country.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Aqaba is Jordan's window on the <ref target="Red%20Sea">Red Sea</ref>. Historically the same city as <ref target="Eilat">Eilat</ref> on the <ref target="Israel">Israel</ref>i side of the border, plans for a shared international airport and other forms of cooperation have cooled down in the past few years during a period of political tension. Aqaba has seen a lot of development. This has improved the infrastructure and facilities. Be prepared for road maps to be incorrect or out of date.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>The Desert Highway terminates in Aqaba. The is about 300 m east of the mosque. There are frequent buses to <ref target="Amman">Amman</ref> and other points along the highway. The fare is 7 JD each way. </p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Amman to Aqaba is about 350 km using the Desert Highway. It will take about 4 hr to travel this distance at a reasonable speed. Service/fuel stops are not very frequent on this road.</p>

<head>By taxi</head>
<p>Minibus rental with driver from <ref target="Petra">Petra</ref> costs 45 JD and it takes about 2 hr to get from Petra to Aqaba.</p>

<p>Coming from the Israeli border, you will probably want to take the border taxi into town and switch to another taxi to continue on, especially if your hotel is in the South Beach resort area. From Aqaba city, taxi prices are lower than from the border.</p>

<p>Also see the note on the <ref target="%23Stay%20safe">Aqaba border taxi Mafia below</ref>.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">King Hussein International Airport</hi> ( AQJ ) (north of Aqaba, about 20 min to drive). Royal Jordanian operates twice daily between Amman and Aqaba, one in the morning and one in the evening. Duration of the flight is approximately one hour and costs 37 JD + tax one-way. <ref target="https://www.easyjet.com/">Easyjet</ref> flies twice weekly to London and Berlin during the winter months, whilst <ref target="https://www.ryanair.com/">Ryanair</ref> operates twice weekly to Cologne, Athens and Sofia, also on a winter schedule. Turkish Airlines flies year-round to <ref target="Istanbul%20Airport">Istanbul Airport</ref>. Various smaller European airlines operate seasonal holiday charter flights as well. Most larger hotels and dive operators can arrange airport transfers, and hire-cars and taxis are available. Note there is no public transport to and from the airport. An Israeli company offers a so-called "Aqaba airport shuttle" service through its website, which appears to be a scam, according to numerous online reviews on a number of different websites.Given the relatively painless (for the area at least) border crossing process and the closeness of <ref target="Eilat">Eilat</ref>, it is also feasible to fly into Ramon Airport ETM , which is served by the likes of <ref target="http://www.ryanair.com">Ryanair</ref>. The former Ovda and Eilat city airports have both closed.</item>
</list>



<head>From other countries</head>
 for details on getting in from other countries and the associated visa requirements.

<head>Israel</head>
<p>If you are coming from <ref target="Eilat">Eilat</ref>, Israel, you will cross through the Yitzhak Rabin Terminal. It is open Sunday-Thursday from 06:30–20:00 and Friday-Saturday from 08:00–20:00, except for Yom Kippur and the Moslem New Year (Id il Hajira). Taxi from Eilat centre to the border is <ref target="Israel%23Money">₪</ref>35 (Feb 2014). The fee to exit Israel is ₪101 plus a processing fee of ₪5 – you can pay with credit card.</p>

<p>If you are planning to come to Aqaba directly from northern Israel (e.g. from Tel Aviv, Jerusalem, or Be'er Sheva) by catching an Egged bus to Eilat, you should ask the driver to let you off at the "Eil<hi rend="bold">o</hi>t stop to Jordan", which is the last stop before the Egged station in Eilat, and then walk to the border checkpoint (less than 1 km).</p>

<p>After crossing the border, take a taxi from the taxi mafia (see <ref target="%23Stay%20safe">below</ref>) for 11 JD, or just walk out. If the bird observatory to the right is open, walk straight through until the road with the fence and continue through the treatment plant further on another deserted road until you reach the housing area. From here, taxis are very cheap. If the bird observatory is closed, go through the sandy desert area to the right after it around the treatment plant until the road north of the new golf course, resort and oasis. It is best to have a map or GPS. If you get bothered by the taxi mafia, just keep walking, don't talk. The other way around is easier: either you walk through the treatment plant or cross through the sandy desert area straight north just before the treatment plant. If you get a taxi from the city for 5 JD, it is fine. 13 JD is way too much. In any case, if you feel you have been bothered, complain to the <ref target="http://www.mota.gov.jo/Contents/Contact_Us.aspx">Ministry of Tourism &amp; Antiquities</ref>.</p>

<head>Egypt</head>
<p>Ferries run regularly from Aqaba across to <ref target="Nuweiba">Nuweiba</ref> on <ref target="Egypt">Egypt</ref>'s <ref target="Sinai">Sinai</ref> peninsula, bypassing <ref target="Israel">Israel</ref> and the sometimes complicated border arrangements. Generally, there is no visa fee for entering Jordan through Aqaba since it is a part of the free trade zone. The line to Nuweiba is operated by <ref target="http://www.abmaritime.com.jo/">ABMaritime</ref>, see their website for the timetable and current prices.</p>

<p>Also ferries from <ref target="Taba">Taba</ref> and <ref target="Sharm%20el-Sheikh">Sharm el-Sheikh</ref> are available. There is more information about the boat crossing in the itinerary <ref target="Ferries%20in%20The%20Red%20Sea">Ferries in The Red Sea</ref></p>

<head>By taxi</head>
<p>Taxis are easily available in the city. A ride within town should cost no more than 2 JD. A ride outside town (to a beach near by or to any border crossings) costs around 5 JD. However, if your hotel calls you a taxi, you may end up paying double for it as they receive a kickback (this is especially true if you are staying on the South Beach).</p>

<p>While taxis are yellow all around Jordan, Aqaba taxis have been painted green and blue: the logo colours of Aqaba Special Economic Zone (ASEZ).</p>

<p>When negotiating the price of a taxi, make sure to determine whether the final cost is the total or "per-person" price, as you may otherwise receive a surprise at the end of the ride.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Local minibuses connect residential areas with downtown. The fare is 17 piasters (0.17 JD) regardless of the length of the journey. Passengers can get on and off at any point of the route.</p>

<p>The central bus station is in front of the police station in King Talal street, less than 10 min walk from city centre (Ayla Square, Al-Hussein Bin Ali Mosque).</p>
</text>
