<text id="autogum_voyage_doc254" title="Tomioka" shortTile="tomioka" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=139580" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tomioka</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.city.tomioka.lg.jp/www/toppage/0000000000000/APM03000.html">Tomioka</ref></hi> (富岡) is a city in southwestern <ref target="Gunma">Gunma Prefecture</ref>, Japan.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Tomioka is served by the non-JR <hi rend="bold">Jōshin Line</hi>, which runs from the nearby railway hub at <ref target="Takasaki">Takasaki</ref>. The line has 8 stations in the city, but the main one is Jōshū-Tomioka. There are usually one or two trains an hour from Takasaki to Jōshū-Tomioka, taking 40 minutes and ¥790.</p>

<p>Jōshin Railway sells a combination ticket, which covers a return journey between Takasaki and Jōshū-Tomioka and admission to the Silk Mill, for ¥2140 (a saving of ¥440). They also sell a one-day free ticket (which allows unlimited travel on the line) for ¥2220.</p>

<p>The Jōshin Line is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> covered by the Japan Rail Pass or the JR East Passes, but it is covered by the <ref target="https://www.jreast.co.jp/e/tokyowidepass/">JR TOKYO Wide Pass</ref>, which is available to holders of non-Japanese passports. Note also that the Jōshin Line does <hi rend="italic">not</hi> accept IC Cards (Suica, Pasmo, Icoca etc.)</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tomioka Interchange</hi> on the Jōshin-etsu Expressway (about 2.5km south of the Silk Mill) is served by a fairly frequent direct bus service towards Tokyo:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="http://www.seibubus.co.jp/kousoku/line/line_chikuma.html">Seibu Bus</ref> and <ref target="http://www.chikuma-bus.com/home/modules/expres_bus/index.php%3Fcontent_id%3D1">Chikuma Bus</ref> run 16 buses a day from <ref target="Tokyo/Toshima">Ikebukuro</ref> Station East Exit, Shimo-Ochiai Station, <ref target="Tokyo/North">Nerima</ref> Ward Office, and <ref target="Kawagoe">Kawagoe</ref>-Matoba Bus Stop, taking 2 hours 5 minutes (and continuing on to Karuizawa, Komoro or Ueda). Two buses a day start back from <ref target="Tokyo/Shinjuku">Shinjuku</ref>.</item>
<item> Chikuma Bus also runs 2 buses a day from <ref target="Tachikawa">Tachikawa</ref> Station North Exit and Tamagawa-Jōsui Station, taking 2 hours 10 minutes (and continuing on to Komoro or Ueda).</item>
</list>


<p>All of these buses cost ¥2100. You can buy two tickets for ¥3700, or 4 tickets for ¥7200.</p>

<ref target="http://www.ncbbus.co.jp/hbus/time2.htm">Nippon Chūō Bus</ref> runs an overnight service from <ref target="Osaka">Osaka</ref> <ref target="Osaka/Minami">Namba</ref> (OCAT) and <ref target="Kyoto">Kyoto</ref> Station Hachijō Exit to <hi rend="bold">Nippon Chūō Taxi Tomioka Eigyōsho</hi> (on the main road 350m south of Nishi-Tomioka Station and 500m northwest of the Silk Mill), taking 8 hours 15 minutes and ¥9200 (¥16,560 return, valid for 10 days). Note that this bus leaves Tomioka for <ref target="Kansai">Kansai</ref> after 11:45pm, and arrives at Tomioka before 4:45am.

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Jōshin Railway offers free bike rentals from 5 of its stations, including Jōshū-Tomioka and Jōshū-Ichinomiya.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tomioka Silk Mill</hi> (富岡製糸場), 1-1 Tomioka (15 minutes walk southwest of Jōshū-Tomioka Station). 9:00-17:00 (last admission 16:30). Japan's oldest modern silk mill, which was in operation between 1872 and 1987. It was designated a Historic Site in 2005, an Important Cultural Property in 2006, and both a National Treasure and a <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20site">UNESCO World Heritage site</ref> in 2014.</item>
</list>

 ¥1000. 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nukisaki Shrine</hi> (貫前神社), 1535 Ichinomiya (15 minutes walk northwest of Jōshū-Ichinomiya Station, 3 stops beyond Jōshū-Tomioka on the Jōshin Line). The Ichinomiya for Kōzuke Province (most of Gunma Prefecture). Much of the shrine is an Important Cultural Property.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gunma Safari Park</hi> (群馬サファリパーク), 1 Okamoto (15 minutes drive south of Jōshū-Tomioka Station, or 10 minutes drive south of Tomioka Interchange). 9:30-16:30 (last admission 15:30) November-February, 9:30-17:00 (last admission 16:00) March-October, closed Wednesdays. This is the type of zoo where you either drive through in your own car (in which case you must pay ¥500 for a guide radio, which is available in Japanese or English) or are driven around (¥500 for the safari bus, or ¥1300 for either the feed-the-animals bus or the off-road ranger tour in a four wheel drive). The most interesting animals are the white tigers and Japan's only Sumatran elephants; animals native to Japan include the snow monkeys (Japanese macaques), black bears, sika deer, and Japanese squirrels. There is also a rather child-centred amusement park with individually priced rides (¥200-¥400). ¥2700.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gunma Museum of Natural History</hi> (群馬県立自然史博物館), 1674-1 Kamikuroiwa (10 minutes drive from Jōshū-Tomioka Station, 5 minutes drive from Jōshū-Ichinomiya Station, or 25 minutes walk from Jōshū-Nanokaichi Station). 9:30am-5pm (last admission 4:30pm), closed Mondays. ¥510.</item>
</list>
</text>
