<text id="autogum_voyage_doc0" title="'s-Hertogenbosch">
<head>'s-Hertogenbosch</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">'s-Hertogenbosch</hi>, commonly known as <hi rend="bold">Den Bosch</hi>, is a city in the south of the <ref target="Netherlands">Netherlands</ref> and the capital of the province of <ref target="North%20Brabant">North Brabant</ref>. Once a stronghold, vital in the protection of the young Dutch nation, Den Bosch has a charming and well-preserved medieval centre. Wander through the winding streets to see Saint John's Cathedral and then pick out a street terrace on the market square to relax with a chilling beer. Take a boat to see part of the unique Binnendieze, a subterranean network of canals under the city, or head to the south part of town where the ancient ramparts still mark the border of the city and the beginning of a natural reserve area. In short: what Den Bosch lacks in fame, it makes up for in charm. A place well worth visiting.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>The population of Den Bosch is approximately 151,000 and with that it is reaching its limits, because almost all the ground available for building has been used. This does not mean that the whole area is one big city, as there are several (big) parks. Likewise, the southern edge of city is totally green as this is a protected natural reserve.</p>
<p>Den Bosch can be seen in 9 regions (<hi rend="italic">note: these regions are built up of several neighborhoods</hi>):</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Center</hi> includes the whole area inside the city walls. Most sights and places to visit can be found in this area.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">North</hi> is the area between the city center and the A59, which includes the neighborhoods <hi rend="italic">de Rompert</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Orthen</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Herven</hi> and the area around the <hi rend="italic">Prins Hendrik Park</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Maaspoort</hi> is the area north of the A59. Mostly a residential area with some industry.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hintham</hi> is the area around the FC Den Bosch football stadium.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">South</hi> is the area between the city center and the A2 highway to the south. Residential, but with also a large amount of office buildings.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">West</hi> is the area west of the central station. High presence of industry, as wel as the residential neighborhoods <hi rend="italic">Kruiskamp</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Helftheuvel</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">Brabanthallen</hi> can be found here.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Engelen</hi> is the village of <hi rend="italic">Engelen</hi> which is going through the development of <hi rend="italic">Haverleij</hi>, a combined residential complex on a golf course.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rosmalen</hi>, a town to the east of the A2.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Empel</hi>, small village to the north of <hi rend="italic">Rosmalen</hi>.</item>
</list>


<p>Most visitor attractions are found in the center, except for the footballstadium and the <hi rend="italic">Sportiom</hi>.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Amsterdam%20Airport%20Schiphol">Amsterdam Airport Schiphol</ref></hi>, the largest airport in the Netherlands and of Europe's most important intercontinental hubs, is roughly 1½ hr away from Den Bosch by train. One needs to change on the way, as there are no direct trains - the most convenient changes are in <ref target="Utrecht">Utrecht</ref> or <ref target="Breda">Breda</ref>. Either way, the cost is €16.20 for the complete journey. There are multiple times an hour allowing such connections. Consult e.g. <ref target="http://9292.nl">9292.nl</ref> for the most convenient option.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Eindhoven%23Eindhoven%20Airport">Eindhoven Airport</ref></hi>, the country's second largest, is in Brabant and is mainly served by low-fare carriers from many European cities, with special emphasis on Eastern Europe and the Mediterranean. Getting to Den Bosch from Eindhoven is as simple as taking one of the many trains shuttling every hour between the cities, taking less than 20 minutes to connect them, but you must get a bus ride from the airport to Eindhoven station first, adding another 20 minutes to the travel time. With some walking and waiting factored it, the total journey time should not be over 50 minutes and will only cost you €6.30 in total.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Rotterdam%23By%20plane">Rotterdam The Hague Airport</ref></hi> is a smaller, business-focused airport in the city of Rotterdam, which can be used as an alternative to Schiphol from some destinations. The airport also does not have a direct train connection - you need to take the bus to Rotterdam Centraal (20 min) and then a direct Intercity train to 's Hertogenbosch. Total journey time is under two hours and cost is less than €18 .</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>

<p>Den Bosch has a good location within the railway system of the "<ref target="http://www.ns.nl">Nederlandse Spoorwegen</ref>" (Dutch Railroads) and almost every city has a direct connection or with a single stopover. Trains depart from Den Bosch main station in city center, which is located at the 'Stationsweg', towards Utrecht-Amsterdam-Haarlem and Utrecht-Schiphol in the north, in the direction of Nijmegen-Arnhem-Zwolle in the east, towards Eindhoven-Maastricht in the south and Tilburg-Breda-Roosendaal in the west.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Den Bosch is accessible via the A2 highway, which was improved in 2016, alleviating the previously chronic traffic jams.</p>

<p>The major highway that passes Den Bosch is the A2, generally seen from Amsterdam to Maastricht. This one of the busiest highways of The Netherlands, and the part along Den Bosch, known as "knooppunt Hintham" and "knooppunt Empel" (intersection Hintham and Rosmalen), is in the top 5 of busiest traffic points in The Netherlands.</p>

<p>The other, less busy, highway passing Den Bosch is the A59, coming from Roosendaal (and the A16) towards Nijmegen. This highway is less busy than the A2, although traffic jams might occur when there is a jam on the A2 as the A59 merges into the A2 for a short part.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, if staying outside the peak hours, which are roughly from 07:00-09:00 and from 16:30–19:30, Den Bosch is easily accessible by car.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>The regional buses, operated by the BBA, link Den Bosch with Tilburg and Eindhoven. As these are the regional buses, they do not go directly between these city but stop at several small villages. Therefore, the fastest and advisable way is using the train.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<head>On foot</head>
<p>Everything within the city center is reachable by foot. Everywhere in the city, so also in the suburbs, are sidewalks. In the city center, most areas are accessible by foot and bicycle only, and traffic within the city is restricted.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>There is a free electric citybus that can take you from the central railroad station to the city centre and back.</p>
<p>If you want to go to the suburbs (where there is no reason to, as all points of interest are within the city center), Arriva operates a network of buses throughout the city and places in the vicinity. All buses arrive and depart from the central station, although for some lines it is not a terminus. Travelling on these buses is around €1.20 per zone, and you have to purchase at least 2 zones. You can either pay cash at the driver, or buy a 'strippenkaart', a sort of multiple journey card, for this. The last one should only be considered of you intend a lot of traveling, or travel with multiple persons.</p>
<head>By car</head>
<p>The city council is trying to get the city center car free, so it is bringing up all kind of measures to deter people from taking the car into the city. Cars can still be parked in the city center, but on Saturdays and Thursday evening these garages are packed. Parking is also available just outside the city center and from there buses are available every 15 minutes for only a few euros including bus trip.</p>

<head>By bike</head>
<p>The best means of transportation is, just as in the rest of the Netherlands, by bicycle. The city is rather flat and bike friendly </p>

<head>Taxi</head>
<p>While taxis are relatively expensive in the Netherlands, they are typically reliable and can be good value if you're a small group. Taxis can be found in front of the train station and are available on call. Companies include <hi rend="bold">Taxi TCO</hi>, ☏ +31 412 484 41 . and <hi rend="bold">Taxi de Hart</hi>, ☏ +31 73 5112733 . . They will also offer transportation services to other cities or towns in the region. While they will work by meter for trips inside the city, fixed prices are available for longer trips, e.g. to Eindhoven Airport (around €45 ) or Schiphol (around €90 ).</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>'s-Hertogenbosch is a medieval city and among the oldest cities in the Netherlands. As the city center is historically protected there are still a lot of medieval buildings to be found. Wander around and see the traditional building style.</p>

<p>When the Netherlands were still young it was a <hi rend="bold">fortified city</hi> that served for the protection of the Netherlands. Especially on the south side of the city, a lot of these fortifications have been saved and over time restored. Start at <hi rend="italic">Bastion Vught</hi> and walk northwards via the <hi rend="italic">Parklaan</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Spinhuiswal</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Zuidwal</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Bastion Oranje</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Hekellaan</hi> until you reach the bridge over the <hi rend="italic">Zuid Willemsvaart</hi>. This way you cover the best part of the old fortifications. In 2004, the city was awarded <hi rend="italic">European Fortress of the year</hi>.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Saint John's Cathedral</hi> (Sint Jans Kathedraal). One of the most prominent landmarks of Den Bosch. Building started in 1380, in Gothic style. The exterior of the building had been deteriorating fast due to acid rain and restoration works started in 1960. It has taken many years to restore the full church, but the works are completed and the church can be seen in all its glory. The restoration also included the interior. Of course some minor maintenance takes place constantly.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Moriaan</hi> (on the market square). The oldest brick building in The Netherlands, built in the 13th century. It houses the Tourist Center (VVV), and in the basement, the rock cafe Plein79.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Town Hall</hi> (Stadhuis), Markt 1 (south side of the market square). The facade was built in the 17th century and reflects Dutch <hi rend="italic">classicism</hi>. The cellars are from about 1200, with a restaurant for coffee, tea, lunch, etc.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The North Brabant Museum</hi> (NoordBrabants Museum). It houses a collection of art and historical artifacts, from pre-roman times to the 20th century. Special exibitions are a must to see, the 'Hyeronimus Bosch Exhibition' with his original work from museums all over the world.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">City Museum 's-Hertogenbosch</hi> (Stedelijk Museum 's-Hertogenbosch (SMS)) (next to, and connected to, the North Brabant Museum). A museum for modern art. Together they form one of the biggest museums of the Netherlands. The ground floor can be visited freely, and it's up to you to decide to see more.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jhyeronimus Bosch Art Center</hi>, Hinthamerstraat (in a former church). It displays all the works of the famous painter. All in live sized copies. Combined with 3D models of his monsters and objects. Because the paintings are copies, you can get very close to them and the guide will open or close the panels to get the full picture. Visitors, young and old, can enjoy this permanent exhibition.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Citadel</hi> (In the north of the city center, outside the boundaries of the northern fortifications). This fortress was added to the city later and is not directly included in the fortifications but sort of pasted on. It held the garrison to protect the city or, if necessary, to counter an uprising in the city. It is now part of the national archive.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kruithuis</hi> (powder arsenal) (Opposite the Citadel). It is an hexagonal building and one of the last of its kind. It is used as a museum for art.</item>
</list>


<p>Hidden below the old city is a canal network called the <hi rend="bold">Binnendieze</hi> that once stretched 22 km. It started out as a regular river, the Dommel, running through the city in medieval times but due to lack of space in the city, people started building their houses and roads over the river. In later times it functioned as a sewer and fell into disrepair. The remaining sixth of the old waterway system has been renovated, and it is possible to take several guided subterranean boat trips through it.</p>

<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Take a boat on the Binnendieze, a river that goes below the houses of the center of town, which was used historically as an open sewer, but is now quite a special tour. There are several tours avaiable. It is a popular tour so be aware when booking a time. Tickets can be bought at the Bolwerk which also have a beautiful café and a restroom free of charge.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>
<p>Den Bosch is a popular place for shopping, combining a charming historic atmosphere with a wide variety of stores. In the city centre you'll find all the major chains and department stores. For more characteristic speciality stores or small boutiques try the <hi rend="bold">Snellestraat</hi> or the so-called <hi rend="bold">Bossche Kwartier</hi>, meaning the small streets around the Fonteinstraat. The <hi rend="bold">Verwerstraat</hi>, with its large monumental buildings, is the place to go for antiques, fashion and design. The <hi rend="bold">Vughterstraat</hi> is another excellent pick, with clothing shops as well as some fine home decoration and furniture places.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Markets</hi> are frequently held on the large market square. The main market is on Saturdays (09:00-17:00) and has a wide selection of food and non-food products. On Wednesday the selection is similar, but the market somewhat smaller. On Fridays, there's a biological market (09:00-14:00) with a good selection of high-quality, mostly regional products. There's another regular market on every first Sunday of the month, but it's a lot smaller than the one on Saturday.</p>
<head>Eat</head>
<p>The city is famous for a local pastry called "Bossche Bol" or "moorkop", a must-try for any visitor. It's a chocolate ball filled with cream, the size of a tennis ball, typically eaten with a cup of coffee in the afternoon but also for dessert. It makes for a fine sweet treat when you kick back and relax at one of the many cafés, after a day of walking through town.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jan de Groot</hi>, Stationsweg 24. This bakery is particularly well-known for its Bossche bollen and caters to many of the cafés in town. They also have a lunchroom of their own. €2.05 for one pastry.</item>
</list>


<head>Restaurants</head>
<p>The city centre is packed with small and large restaurants that serve all kinds of crowds. The <hi rend="bold">Korte Putstraat</hi> and the <hi rend="bold">Lange Putstraat</hi> are your best bet if you're looking for a meal, as they have a particularly broad selection of places with nice outdoor terraces in summer. Typically you'll have no problems finding a table somewhere, but if you have a particular establishment in mind or if you want a good table on the terrace it's definitely wise to reserve ahead, as the best places are often full.</p>

<head>Budget</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Eetcafé 't Keershuys</hi>, Lepelstraat 45, ☏ +31 73 612 80 87 , ✉ info@keershuys.nl . Cosy place in a 14th-century building, once a small cheese factory. Today it's a restaurant serving simple, good value for money food. It's also a popular place for lunch and High Tea. Lunch breads start at around €5 and in the evening you can have the dish of the day for €10.50 . Pasta dishes around €12 and other mains from €15 .</item>
</list>


<head>Mid-range</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">In Den Zevenden Hemel</hi>, Korte Putstraat 13-17, ☏ +31 73 6901451 . Popular with locals, this place gets good reviews and is often crowded. Mains start around €20 and there's several vegetarian options too. The staff is friendly; ask them for the English menu. €34.95 for a set 3-course menu.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bistro Puik</hi>, Hinthamerstraat 80, ☏ +31 73 6 100 900 . Cosy little restaurant with good food, right next to the cathedral. On the menu you'll find a range of small dishes which allows you to get a good idea of the cuisine. Most visitors opt for the chef's menu, called the "Wandeling door de kaart" (walk through the menu).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Binnenhof -eten & drinken-</hi>, Guardianenhof 26, ☏ +31 73 6145010 , ✉ info@binnen-hof.nl . Modern, nicely decorated restaurant with good food. From €34.95 for a 3-course menu.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">FF Swanjee</hi>, Hinthamerstraat 76-78, ☏ +31 73 - 614 78 32 . Daily from 12:00. This popular and informal place serves a range of small "wappaz", an internation take on tapas, available in small and large portions. The menu also has some excellent grill dishes, lots of cocktails and tasty desserts. Sharing is encouraged.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Brasserie Top</hi>, Markt 42, 5211 JX 's-Hertogenbosch,, ☏ +31 73 613 7616 .</item>
</list>


<head>Splurge</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Restaurant Sense</hi>, Verwersstraat 58, ☏ +31 73 614 42 08 , ✉ info@restaurantsense.nl . Tu-Sa. Sense has a number of small, high quality dishes on the menu; the idea is that you order them more or less in a random order, as you like. They start at around €16 ; count on 4 dishes for an average eater. If you're not very picky, the surprise menu is a good option. From €43.50 for 4 courses.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fabuleux</hi>, Verwerstraat 23, ☏ +31 73 741 00 11 . W-Sa. Proper French cuisine in a historic house. This place also has some excellent wines on the menu. From €37.50 for a 3-course surprise.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>
<p>Nightlife in Den Bosch is as you might expect from a city of its size: not as extravagant as Amsterdam or Rotterdam, but nice, with a friendly crowd attending and a nice atmosphere. The places most worth visiting:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">De Drie Gezusters</hi> (One of the most popular places in Den Bosch, it has 3 areas: Pub, Apres Ski and Club with different music and appearance. Can't miss it on Friday and Saturday as there will be a line outside.), Karrenstraat. Opens at 21:00, but the scene starts at around 23:00. Open until 04:00. Entrance €4 , coatcheck €1.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cinq</hi> (formerly known as the <hi rend="italic">Cuba Libre</hi>, it turns into a nightlife scene after 23:00. On busy nights hard to get in.), Parade, ☏ +31 73 6900768 . Entrance depends on attendance. Busy nights require around €2 entrance to be paid.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">De Carrousel</hi> (Place to attracts a crowd of mainly 25+. Is sometimes open slightly longer than the other places.), Karrrenstraat, ☏ +31 73 6900311 . Starts at around 22:00 until 04:00, sometimes later.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Silva Ducis</hi> (Next to Cinq, same attendance.), Parade, ☏ +31 73 6130405 . 10:00-16:00.</item>
</list>
<head>Sleep</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Golden Tulip Hotel Central</hi>, Burg. Loeffplein 98 (the hotel is on the north side of the Markt, easily recognized as a white building), ☏ +31 73 6926926 , fax: +31 73 6145699 . It's in the city center, and is one of the best hotels to visit the city if you are willing to pay a little more. around €140.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mövenpick Hotel 's-Hertogenbosch</hi> (Moevenpick), Pettelaarpark 90 (near the highway A2. Take exit 22, where signage will guide you to the hotel.), ☏ +31 73 6874674 , fax: +31 73 6874635 , ✉ hotel.s-hertogenbosch@moevenpick.com . Check-in: 15:00, check-out: 12:00. This 4-star hotel offers clean, cosy rooms with good showers and 100% organic, fair trade linen. There's a spacious (no-swimming suit) sauna and infra-red room and the hotel restaurant offers a diverse menu with healthy and vegetarian options. This hotel is located in a business area but lies next to a small lake, which gives it its charm. It's about a 20-minute walk from the city centre and easily accessible by car. The large parking has electric car charging options. Bicycle rent is also available and there's a bus stop 200 meters away, with connections to the city centre. around €140.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Best Western Euro Hotel</hi> (/ in the city center), Kerkstraat 56 (near the St. Jans Cathedral opposite the main post office.), ☏ +31 73 6137777 , fax: +31 73 6128795 . Check-in: 14:00, check-out: 11:00. €95.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Campanile Hotel 's-Hertogenbosh</hi> (Cheap hotel located in the northern suburb 'Maasport' and adjacent industrial area), Goudsbloemvallei 21-25, ☏ +31 73 6422525 , fax: +31 73 6410048 , ✉ denbosch@campanile.com . €59.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bark Hotel 's-Hertogenbosch</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fletcher Hotel Rosmalen</hi> (Located outside the city center along the A2 highway), Burg. Burgerslaan 50, ☏ +31 73 5219159 , fax: +31 73 5216215 , ✉ info@fletcherhotelshertogenbosch.nl .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">van der Valk Hotel Vught</hi> (Large hotel located in the town of Vught, about 10 minutes by bus to 's-Hertogenbosch.), Bosscheweg 2, ☏ +31 73 6587777 , fax: +31 73 6587700 , ✉ vught@valk.com . €80-100.</item>
</list>


<head>Connect</head>
<p>Den Bosch uses the area code 073.</p>

<head>Stay safe</head>
<p>Den Bosch is in general a safe city. Even the neighborhoods considered dangerous by the locals are still quite safe during daylight (<hi rend="italic">Hambaken</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Graafsewijk</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Kruiskamp</hi>). If a traveler uses his common sense he will be alright, also during night. The only time the crowd can get a bit rough is during Thursday, Friday and Saturday night. These are the general party nights, so people sometimes drink too much. Watch out to the drunk people that might easily start brawls (especially during the carnival).</p>

<head>Go next</head>
<p>Well connected and at a fairly central location, there are endless options for next destinations when leaving 'sHertogenbosch. Some of the more prominent nearby places are <ref target="Utrecht">Utrecht</ref>, <ref target="Tilburg">Tilburg</ref>, <ref target="Eindhoven">Eindhoven</ref>, <ref target="Breda">Breda</ref> and <ref target="Nijmegen">Nijmegen</ref>. Families will find fun all year round at the <ref target="Efteling">Efteling</ref>, the country's largest theme park. The Loonse en Drunense Duinen National Park is also a short ride away.</p>
</text>
