<text id="autogum_voyage_doc10" title="West Bengal" shortTile="west-bengal" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=38857" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>West Bengal</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.wbtourism.com">West Bengal</ref></hi> is a state in <ref target="India">India</ref>'s <ref target="East%20%28India%29">East</ref> region.</p>

<head>Cities</head>
<p>Here are 10 of the most notable cities.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> — centre of Bengali culture, the largest city in the state, current capital of West Bengal and former capital of British India until 1911, is known as the "City of Palaces"</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> — a fortified British cantonment with Dutch, French, Mughal and Portuguese architecture and remniscences</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> — a major agricultural town</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> — a former French colony</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> — a beautiful hill station and centre of a major tea growing area</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> — an industrial metropolis</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> — Kolkata's twin city, the second-largest in the state, with the largest railway complex in India</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> — former capital of Bengal under the Mughals</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> — a major business and shopping centre and gateway for travellers to Sikkim</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> — business capital of birbhum district, major tourist destination and gateway for travelers to North Bengal.</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> — a low lying hill in Purulia district</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> (Parmaden Forest) —</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> — a forested area located in Buxa Hills is habitat for tigers, Asian elephants and other mammals plus a variety of birds, amphibians and reptiles</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> — famous for the Hindu temple of Goddess Kali known as Bhavatarini, an aspect of Kali, meaning, 'She who liberates Her devotees from the ocean of existence i.e Saṃsāra'. Situated on the eastern bank of the Hooghly River, near Kolkata the temple was built by Rani Rashmoni, a philanthropist and a devotee of Kali in 1855. The temple is famous for its association with Ramakrishna a mystic of 19th century Bengal</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> —</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> , <ref target="West%20Bengal">West Bengal</ref> — rolling grasslands and forest is rich with herbivores such as the Indian rhinoceros and elephants birds, reptiles and amphibians</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> — deltaic island on the mouth of river Hoogly, a major pilgrimage site</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> (Sandakphu) — at 3,636 metres (11,929 ft) is the highest point in West Bengal. Kanchenjunga and Mount Everest are visible from here</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> — town of Rabindranath Tagore's university Viswa Bharathi and known for exotic handmade goods</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> — a wildlife sanctuary with Royal Bengal Tigers and deer found in forests and mangrove swamps <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20site">UNESCO World Heritage site</ref></item>
</list>


<head>History</head>

<p>West Bengal's history dates back before 20,000 years. The region was a part of the Vanga Kingdom, the kingdom of <ref target="Magadha">Magadha</ref>. Bengal had ancient trade relations with Burma (<ref target="Myanmar">Myanmar</ref>), <ref target="Thailand">Thailand</ref> and <ref target="Sumatra">Sumatra</ref>. She was invaded by Rajendra Chola I of Chola Dynasty between 1021 and 1023. During the 12th century Sufi missionaries arrived in Bengal, bringing along with them the message of Islam. Bakhtiar Khilji, a military commander from the <ref target="Delhi">Delhi</ref> Sultanate, overran Bengal between 1202 and 1206. Bengal was conquered by the Mughals in 1576. There were several independent Hindu states established in Bengal during the Mughal period like those of Maharaja Pratap Aditya of <ref target="Jessore">Jessore</ref> and Raja Sitaram Ray of Burdwan. Koch Bihar Kingdom in the northern Bengal flourished during the 16th and 17th centuries. European traders arrived late in the 15th century. The Battle of Plassey in 1757 saw the defeat of Siraj ud-Daulah, the last independent Nawab of Bengal. Presidency was established by 1765, eventually including all British territories north of the Central Provinces (now <ref target="Madhya%20Pradesh">Madhya Pradesh</ref>), from the mouths of the Ganges and the Brahmaputra to the Himalayas and the <ref target="Punjab">Punjab</ref>. Calcutta was named the capital of British India in 1772. The Bengal Renaissance and Brahmo Samaj movement had great impact on the cultural and economic life of Bengal. There was a failed uprising against British rule in 1857 known as the "Sepoy Mutiny". Between 1905 and 1911, attempts were made to divide the province of Bengal into two zones, to curb nationalism, but widespread protest forced the British to call it off. Bengal played a major role in the Indian independence movement, producing some of Indian's greatest revolutionaries including Netaji Subhash Chandra Bose. When India gained independence in 1947, Bengal was partitioned along religious lines. The western part went to India (and was named West Bengal) while the eastern part joined <ref target="Pakistan">Pakistan</ref> as a province called East Bengal (later renamed East Pakistan, giving rise to independent <ref target="Bangladesh">Bangladesh</ref> in 1971). In 1950, the Princely State of <ref target="Cooch%20Behar">Cooch Behar</ref> merged with West Bengal. In 1955, the former French enclave of <ref target="Chandannagar">Chandannagar</ref> was integrated into West Bengal. The 1970s saw the rise of Left-Radicals in the name of Maoism, with a significant portion of the youth refusing to recognize the independence of 1947. Incidents surrounding the Bangladesh Liberation War of 1971 caused millions of refugees to influx into West Bengal, most of them Hindus. The Left Front, led by the Communist Party of India (Marxist), governed the state for the subsequent three decades, making it the longest serving democratically elected communist party in the world. Although they were defeated in the 2011 elections, the Communists' imprint remains powerful on the state, with many streets named after Marx and other local and foreign revolutionary figures.</p>

<head>Geography</head>
<p>West Bengal is diverse in terms of geography and is distinctively unique for being the only state in India with mountains in the north and sea in the south, with vast stretches of plains, plateaus and deltas between them.</p>

<p>The Eastern Himalaya range starts abruptly up from the Terai region near <ref target="Siliguri">Siliguri</ref>. The region is further divided into two parts: the Singalila and Darjeeling ranges. The Singalila range is located along the border of <ref target="Darjeeling">Darjeeling</ref> and <ref target="Nepal">Nepal</ref>. <ref target="Sandakfu">Sandakfu</ref> at 3,636 metres (11,929 ft) is the highest point of West Bengal. Remnants of the Siwaliks can be seen in the Jalpaiguri district, where they are known as the Buxa-Jayanti Hills. The Terai is a belt of marshy grasslands, savannas and forests at the base of the Himalaya range. The Dooar region stretching across the middle of the Terai belt are a conglomerate of tall grasslands, savannas and evergreen and deciduous forests. South of Terai region the plain of North Bengal starts and continues up to the left bank of the Ganges. It gets fed by rivers and rivulets originating in the Eastern Himalaya. The Rarh lies south of the Ganges and east of the Chotanagpur plateau, eastern part of which is in West Bengal. Part of the Sunderbans is located in the vast deltaic region, South-East of the state.</p>

<head>Climate</head>

<p>Bengal experiences 5 seasons: Spring, Summer, Monsoon, Autmn and Winter.</p>

<p>Spring is short and more dominant in the northern region. Summer commemces from the first week of March and continues till June. The weather remains hot and humid during the day, accompanied by cool breezes at night. The western highlands will experience a hot dry climate. Thunderstorms locally called <hi rend="italic">Kalbaishakhi</hi> occurs late summer. Monsoon starts from July and ends late September, when torrential rainfall gives rise to severe floods in the south. Autmn is short, between October and mid-November. The retreating monsoon at this time may give rise to storms. Winter sets by late November and continues till Spring arrives in February, January being the coldest. The Himalayan region in the north experiences snowfall during winter, usually after mid-December.</p>
</text>
