<text id="autogum_voyage_doc73" title="Chattanooga" shortTile="chattanooga" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=6916" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Chattanooga</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.chattanoogafun.com/">Chattanooga</ref></hi> is the 4th largest city in <ref target="Tennessee">Tennessee</ref>. It is the seat of <ref target="Hamilton%20County%20%28Tennessee%29">Hamilton County</ref>. It is in Southeast Tennessee on the Tennessee River and near the border of <ref target="Georgia%20%28state%29">Georgia</ref>. It is famous for being immortalized in the popular 1941 song Chattanooga Choo Choo, made famous by Glenn Miller.</p>
<head>Understand</head>
<p>Chattanooga played an important role during the American Civil War, when it was a major railroad hub and one of the most industrialized parts of the Confederacy along with the nearby city of Atlanta, resulting in Chattanooga and being at the center of numerous pitched battles. Many of the tourist attractions center around Civil War history such as numerous battlefield parks in and around the city. It is less prominent today because of the decline of its famed railroad, immortalized in the popular song Chattanooga Choo Choo, which is also commemorated in numerous tourist attractions and the popular Chattanooga Choo Choo hotel. As of the census of 2000, there are 155,554 people, 65,499 households, and 39,626 families residing in the city. There are 72,108 housing units at an average density of 205.9/km² (533.3/mi²). The racial makeup of the city is 59.71% White, 36.06% African American, 0.29% Native American, 1.54% Asian. 2.11% of the population are Hispanic or Latino of any race.</p>

<p>Despite its economic loss and a small population, the city has become notably modernized, urbanized, and economically revitalized, receiving nationally recognition for the renaissance of its once-dilapidated, post-Industrial downtown and redevelopment of its riverfront. Within the last ten years the city has won three national awards for outstanding "livability", and nine Gunther Blue Ribbon Awards for excellence in housing and consolidated planning. An early cornerstone of this project was the restoration of the historic Walnut Street Bridge, which is now the world's longest pedestrian bridge. Chattanooga is the corporate headquarters and home of Blue Cross &amp; Blue Shield of Tennessee, Rock Creek Outfitters, Krystal, Chattem, Unum, The Chattanooga Bakery (home of the Moon Pie), and Miller Industries, and the largest tow truck manufacturer in the world (Chattanooga is the birthplace of the tow truck, so you'll also find tourist attractions such as the tow truck museum to commemorate this). Chattanooga is also home to the Tennessee Valley Authority, a self-funding government agency which operates numerous power plants in the South. Following the city's industrial decline, many businesses in the banking and insurance industries also set up operations in Chattanooga; the city is home to large branch offices of Cigna, AT&amp;T and UBS.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>I-75 (<hi rend="italic">North-South</hi>) and I-24 (<hi rend="italic">East-West</hi>) intersect in Chattanooga.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">I-75</hi> - Easy access from <ref target="Atlanta">Atlanta</ref> and <ref target="Knoxville">Knoxville</ref>. Begins in <ref target="Hialeah">Hialeah</ref>, <ref target="Florida">Florida</ref> and ends in <ref target="Sault%20Ste.%20Marie%20%28Michigan%29">Sault Ste. Marie</ref>, <ref target="Michigan">Michigan</ref> at the Canadian border.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">I-24</hi> - Easy access from <ref target="Murfreesboro">Murfreesboro</ref>, <ref target="Nashville">Nashville</ref> and <ref target="Kentucky">Kentucky</ref>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">I-59</hi> - Connects to I-24 just Southwest of Chattanooga, gives access to <ref target="Birmingham%20%28Alabama%29">Birmingham</ref>, <ref target="Alabama">Alabama</ref>, Southeast <ref target="Mississippi">Mississippi</ref> and ends near <ref target="New%20Orleans">New Orleans</ref>.</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chattanooga Metropolitan Airport</hi> ( CHA )) (The airport is located east of downtown Chattanooga and you can easily get transportation from the airport to local hotels). It is serviced by: <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.aa.com">American Eagle</ref></hi>; <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.delta.com">Delta Connection Carriers</ref></hi>; <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.allegiantair.com">Allegiant Air</ref></hi> (Nonstop service only to Orlando, Tampa, and Fort Lauderdale; no onestops or connections).</item>
<item> There are non-stop flights to/from Chattanooga:</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Atlanta">Atlanta</ref>, GA</item>
<item> <ref target="Charlotte">Charlotte</ref>, NC</item>
<item> <ref target="Chicago">Chicago</ref>, IL (Service to O'Hare International Airport)</item>
<item> <ref target="Dallas">Dallas</ref>, TX (Service to Dallas-Ft. Worth International Airport)</item>
<item> <ref target="Detroit">Detroit</ref>, MI (Service to Detroit Wayne County International Airport)</item>
<item> <ref target="New%20York%20City">New York City</ref>, NY (Service to LaGuardia Airport)</item>
<item> <ref target="Orlando">Orlando</ref>, FL (Service to Orlando Sanford Airport)</item>
<item> <ref target="Philadelphia">Philadelphia</ref>, PA</item>
<item> <ref target="Tampa%20Bay">Tampa Bay</ref>, FL (Service to St. Petersburg/Clearwater Airport)</item>
<item> <ref target="Washington%2C%20D.C.">Washington, D.C.</ref> (Service to Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport, otherwise known as National Airport, and Dulles Airport)</item>
</list>



<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Greyhound</hi>, 960 Airport Rd, ☏ +1-800-231-2222 . Service to Chattanooga begins and ends at their station found near the airport. To get downtown from Greyhound walk a couple blocks to Van Ness Rd &amp; Lee Hwy and catch the inbound CARTA route 4 bus to downtown. Last stop is at Market St. &amp; W 4th Ave.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Megabus</hi> (The bus stop is located on Market Street at West 14th Street, next to the Chattanooga Choo Choo.). Service from <ref target="Atlanta">Atlanta</ref>, <ref target="Nashville">Nashville</ref>, <ref target="Knoxville">Knoxville</ref>, <ref target="Lexington%20%28Kentucky%29">Lexington</ref>, <ref target="Louisville">Louisville</ref>, <ref target="Cincinnati">Cincinnati</ref>, <ref target="Columbus">Columbus</ref>, <ref target="Cleveland">Cleveland</ref>, <ref target="Indianapolis">Indianapolis</ref>, and <ref target="Chicago">Chicago</ref></item>
</list>


<head>By boat</head>
<p>Chattanooga is accessible by way of the Tennessee River by personal water craft.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ross's Landing</hi> (downtown Chattanooga). There are 11 mooring posts with electrical and water hookups.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chickamauga Marina</hi>, Chickamauga Lake at the Chickamauga Dam, Kings Point Rd, ☏ +1 423 622-1978 . Summer, May 1 - Sept 30, Su-Th 8:30AM–6:30PM and F-Sa 8:30AM-7PM; Winter, Oct 1 - Apr 30, M-Su 8:30AM–5:30PM. Full service marina, complete with laundry/bath house. Fuel Dock/Ships Store open 7 days year round accepting all major credit cards.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gold Point Yacht Harbor</hi> (just off the Tennessee River at mile marker 472), ☏ +1 423 622-1978 . Constructed in 2001 and nestled into a picturesque cove. All business for Gold Point Yacht Harbor is conducted from the marina office located at the Chickamauga Marina.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Shady Grove Harbor</hi>, 1805 Clift Eldridge Rd, Soddy Daisy (To get to the harbor, enter the Soddy Creek Channel at Mile Marker 487, then travel 1.3 miles up Soddy Creek.), ☏ +1 423 332-5613 . Summer (Apr 1 - Labor Day) open 7 days 8AM-8PM; Winter, F-Tu 10AM-6PM.. The Ship Store is equipped to satisfy all boating needs.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Island Cove Marina and Resort</hi>, Mile marker 477.5 on the Tennessee River, 6701 Highway 58, Harrison, ☏ +1 423 344-8331 , fax: +1 423 344-6275 . Ship Store hours: Summer, M-Sa 8AM-6PM, Su 9AM-6PM; Winter, M-Sa 8AM-5PM, Su 10AM-5PM.. Featuring a full stocked ship store, transient dockage, bath house, laundry and a 24 hour fuel dock. They were awarded a 5 Anchor Rating by Quimby's Cruise Guide. Sydney's On the River restaurant also on site.</item>
</list>
</text>
