<text id="autogum_voyage_doc154" title="Budapest/Hegyvidék" shortTile="budapesthegyvidk" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=132759" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Budapest/Hegyvidék</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Hegyvidék</hi> is a district in <ref target="Budapest">Budapest</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Hegyvidék</hi> (The Mount area) comprises all of the <ref target="http://www.hegyvidek.hu/">12th</ref> &amp; <ref target="http://www.masodikkerulet.hu/">2nd districts</ref>. It is the most exclusive area, with villas, embassies and foreign residences. This is the 'greenest' part of the city. Here is the city highest hill János hegy (527 m above sea level). It is situated in Buda the northwestern part. In north and northeast the III. district called <ref target="Budapest/%C3%93buda">Óbuda</ref> (Old Buda), in the east the Danube river by XIII. and V. district, <ref target="Budapest/Belv%C3%A1ros">Belváros</ref> Downtown or "Inner city". To the southeast is the I. district called <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Belbuda">Belbuda</ref></hi> (Inner Buda). To the south is the XI. district <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Budapest/%C3%9Ajbuda%20and%20T%C3%A9t%C3%A9ny">Újbuda and Tétény</ref></hi> (New Buda and Teteny). The neighboring communities are Budakeszi and Budaörs.</p>

<p>Because a significant part of the district is covered by forest, the area is very popular for local hikers, and as a residence for wealthy people. Countless luxurious villas, flashy cars and upscale quarter are located here, as are diplomatic offices.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>The major transport hubs: <hi rend="bold">Szell Kalman Square</hi> (former Moszkva Square) and</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hűvösvölgy Transport Hub</hi>, II. Hűvösvölgyi út ~213 ( : Széll Kálmán tér further take tram 61 to end stop). Tram 61, bus 29, 57, 63, 64, 64A, 157, 157A, 164, 257, 264, 956, 963, 964 terminated here. Also a hundred meters away is the end station of the Széchenyi Hill Children's Railways</item>
</list>


<head>Metro</head>
<p>Two stations are located here:</p>

<head>Buses</head>
<p>Bus 16, 16A and 116 go to Buda castle from : Széll Kálmán tér.</p>
<p>Bus 21 very useful exploring Jan Mountain or Secheni Mountain (János-hegy or Széchenyi-hegy), these are part of the Buda Protected Landscape Area.</p>

<head>Trams</head>
<p>The district is the most important tram is No.61 between Hűvösvölgy and Móricz Square, the former is a transport hub for the northern part of district, to transport hub to New Buda (Újbuda). You can catch it at : Szell Kalman tér or : Deli Pályaudvar</p>

<head>Other transport modes</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cogwheel tram</hi> (Fogaskerekű). Using in the Buda Hills is a great escape from the city. The cogwheel tram, which is tram 61, leaves from Varosmajor, accessible by tram: 59 or 61 from Szell Kalman Square. It climbs through the wooded Buda Hills and at the top.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> To take M2 Szell Kalman Square further bus 56 or tram: 59, 61. From station : Szell Kalman Square take bus 21 to stop 'Ordas út' and walk 500m, near the Children's Railway terminal, to the </item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Children's Railway</hi> (Gyermekvasút), Hűvösvölgy ( : Széll Kálmán tér further tram: 61 to stop Hűvösvölgy 5 min walk to Lower Terminal - - To Upper station (Széchenyi-hegyi állomás) take Cogwheel tram (see above) to the Upper station and 200m walk ), ☏ +36 1 397 5392 , fax: +36 1 397 5396 , ✉ info@gyermekvasut.hu . May-Sep all day, other only T-Su. Using in the Buda Hills is a great escape from the city. If you feel like doing it, take the Children's Railway through the hills to Hüvösvölgy and take tram 61 back down to Széll Kálmán tér. <ref target="http://www.gyermekvasut.hu/english/page.php%3F7">The cogwheel tram accepts local travelcards, but the Gyermekvasút does not, and fares can be found here</ref>. Also if you have an old map, you're supposed to find Pioneers' Railway (Úttörővasút) instead of Children's Railway in it, which is the former name of the railway from the soviet era. More info: <ref target="Budapest%23Get%20around">Budapest#Get around</ref></item>
</list>

 OW/RW HUF700/1400, student half price.

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Zugliget Chair-lift</hi> (Libegő), XII. Zugligeti út, 97 (Lower station) ( : 'Széll Kálmán' take a bus), ☏ +36 1 3255-255, +36 1 394 3764 , ✉ bkk@bkk.hu . Daily 10:00-18:00. This is a chair lift what taking you from "Zugliget" to Jan Mountain ("János hegy"). Ft900. BKK tickets and passes are not valid..</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Adyliget St. Stephen's Church</hi> (Adyligeti Szent István templom), II. Feketerigó u. 28. (From Huvosvolgy take bus 63 to stop Ady lepcso). Masses Tu 18:00, F 18:00, Sa 18:00, Su 08:00.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Béla Bartók Memorial House</hi> (Bartók Béla Emlékház), Csalán út 29 (5-minute walk on the Csévi street, coming from the bus terminal (no. 5), at Pasaréti square, 1st bus 5 take at : Széll Kálmán tér ), ☏ +36 1 394-4472 , ✉ bartok-1981@t-online.hu . Tu-Sa 10:00-17:00. The final home of one of the greatest Hungarian composers. Located at a very beautiful place and has a big garden. - Bartók's sheet music, books, CDs, DVDs, postcards are available in the Museum Music Shop. Evening concerts: at 18:00. extraphone=+36 1 394-2100 Adult €4, student €2.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tomb of Gül Baba and Rosegarden</hi> (Gül Baba Türbe és rózsakert), II. Mecset utca 14. (entrance: Türbe tér 1.) (tram: 17 from Margit híd, Buda side to Szent Lukács Gyógyfürdő stop), ☏ +36 1 237-4400 , ✉ info@mnv.hu . 10:00-18:00. Built around 1548 by the Turkish occupants of the city. It is the northernmost place of Muslim pilgrimage. The beautiful view and the peacefulness of the place makes a visit worth. Free.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Millenaris Park</hi> (Millennium Park, Millenáris Park), II. Kis Rókus u. 16–20 ( : Széll Kálmán tér further walk 500m or take tram: 4, 6 one stop</item>
</list>

 ), ☏ +36 1 336 4000 , fax: +36 1 336 4012 , ✉ millenaris@millenaris.hu . This is a cultural center for showing the Hungarian capital and Europe significant cultural and lifestyle values. It is developed from an iron foundry, what founded Abraham Ganz in the 'Field of Pest roller mill' (Pesti Hengermalom) company area. There is the <hi rend="bold">House of the Future</hi> exhibition hall (Jövő Háza kiállítás) with themes as genome research, spacecraft (include the Hungarian Mars rover), astronomy or the lives of people with disabilities durable presentation 'Ability Park'. Located in the Great Hall (Building B), this is a huge multi-level building. The <hi rend="bold">Pixel Gallery</hi> (Building C) has a similar spiral arrangement as the New York's Guggenheim Museum, used for media arts and visual art exhibitions. <hi rend="bold">Theater</hi> (Teátrum) is a nearly 0.7ha of assembly hall converted building, a kind of studio. Used for TV studio, theaters and concert halls. <hi rend="bold">The Host</hi> or Building G (Fogadó) was built in 1930s, former machine repair, plating plant. Used for concerts, child and family programs, studio theater performances, Chamber of Commerce exhibitions. The <hi rend="bold">Worm Gallery</hi> (Csiga Galéria) is a separate gallery space for contemporary art exhibitions. The Loft (Padlás), a theater space, with mobile auditorium for 150 to 200 people. And also the <hi rend="bold">park</hi>, a big green area (3.5ha). Vary.

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Foundry Museum</hi> (Öntődei Múzeum), II. Bem József u. 20 (TTram 4, 6 to 'Mechwart liget', 2nd stop From : 'Szell Kalman square' ). Th 10AM-4PM, F 10AM-2PM, Sa 10AM-4PM. This is the one-time factory of Abraham Ganz, where the foundry existed even in 1960s. Ft800.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ruins of Pauline Monastery</hi> (Pálos kolostor romjai), Budaszentlőrinc, over 'Szépjuhászné' (By Children's Railway to train stop 'Szépjuhászné' or From : 'Szell Kalman square' take bus 22 to stop 'Szépjuhászné, Gyermekvasút'</item>
</list>

 ). Built in 13-14th centuries.

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Elizabeth Lookout</hi> (Erzsébet kilátó), Janos-hill (János-hegy) ( Take the chair lift.<ref target="Budapest%23Get%20around">Budapest#Get around</ref>'Libegő' or From : 'Szell Kalman square' take bus 90A to stop Normafa and strolling in wood 15 min, or take Children's Railway to stop Janos-hill or Virágvolgy station and short woodland walk to lookout ). Daily 08:00-20:00. is Budapest's highest peak with its 527 meters.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bajor Gizi Actors’ Museum</hi> (Bajor Gizi Színészmúzeum), Stromfeld Aurél út, 16 (From : 'Deák tér' take Bus 105 to Németvölgyi út stop ), ☏ +36 1 225 3161 , ✉ bgm@ella.hu . W-Su 14:00-18:00. The museum covers decisive participants and events of almost 200 years of Hungarian theatre, from the strolling players of the 1820s up to the present moment. Placed in a neo-baroque, early 20th century villa and its compelling garden and park.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hegyvidék Region History Collection</hi> (Hegyvidéki Helytörténeti Gyűjtemény), Beethoven utca 1/b (tram: 59 from : Déli p.u.</item>
</list>

 ), ☏ +36 1 457-0501 , fax: +36 1 457-0500 , ✉ hegyvideki.budapest@museum.hu . Tu,Th,F: 10:00-18:00..

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hegyvidék Region Contemporary Art Gallery, Barabás Villa</hi> (Hegyvidéki Kortárs Galéria, Barabás Villa Galéria), Városmajor u. 16 &amp; 44 ( : Déli p.u.</item>
</list>

 ), ☏ +36 1 201-6607 , ✉ info@hegyvidekgaleria.hu . M-F 10:00-18:00, Sa 10:00-12:00. In two buildings

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Farkasret Cemetery</hi> (Farkasréti temető), Németvölgyi út 99 ( : Széll Kálmán tér further tram: 59</item>
</list>

 ), ☏ +36 1 248 3520 , ✉ farkasretitemeto@btirt.hu . This is the largest and most beautiful located cemetery in Buda. Opened 1894. At the west side of Denevér street is the Jewish Cemetery section. Car entry fee Ft280.

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jokai Club</hi> (Jókai Klub), XII. Hollós út 5. (From : Széll Kálmán take tram: 61 to 'Városmajor' further "red 60" (Cog Wheel train) to stop 'Svábhegy' to Svábhegy ), ☏ +36 70 334 4468 , fax: +36 1 395 8284 , ✉ jokaiklub@jokaiklub.hu . Built in 1883.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">MOM Cultural Center</hi> (MOM Kulturális Központ), XII. Csörsz u. 18. ( : Széll Kálmán tér or Déli Pályaudvar further tram: 61 to 'Csörsz utca' ), ☏ +36 1 319-9854 , fax: +36 1 248-1756 , ✉ info@momkult.hu .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Virányos Community Center</hi>, XII. Szarvas Gábor út 8/c ( : Széll Kálmán further Bus 156 or tram: 61 to stop 'Budagyöngye' ), ☏ +36 70 33 44472 , fax: +36 1 200 8713 , ✉ viranyosikh@gmail.com . Built in 1989. This is a family house type, three-storey building.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ybl Villa</hi>, XII. Budakeszi út 36/B ( : Széll Kálmán tér + bus 22, 22A, 222 to 'Labanc út' ), ☏ +36 1 354 3833 , ✉ info@yblvilla.hu . One of the most beautiful villas of Buda built in the 1850s.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">'Városmajori' Heart of Jesus Parish</hi> (Városmajori Jézus Szíve Plébánia), XII. Csaba u. 5. ( : 'Széll Kálmán tér' and walk ), ☏ +36 1 212-4656 . Roman Catholic.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Baptist St. John Church of Upper 'Krisztinaváros'</hi> (Felső-krisztinavárosi Keresztelő Szent János Plébánia), XII. Apor Vilmos tér 9-11. ( : Széll Kálmán or Déli Pályaudvar further tram: 59 to 'Zólyomi lépcső' ), ☏ +36 1 356-0089 . Roman Catholic. Krisztinaváros means Kristinatown.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Holy Family Parish of Zugligeti</hi> (Zugligeti Szent Család Plébánia), XII. Zalai út 1/C. (Zugliget quarter : Széll Kálmán further bus 222, 229 to 'Zalai út'</item>
</list>

 ), ☏ +36 20-823-4598 , ✉ zugligetiszentcsalad@gmail.com . Roman Catholic

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">All Saints Church of Farkasrét</hi> (Farkasréti Mindenszentek Plébánia), XII. Hegyalja út 139. (Farkasrét quarter, - : Széll Kálmán or Déli Pályaudvar further tram: 59 to 'Farkasréti temető' - or - : Ferenciek tere further bus 8 to stop 'Farkasréti temető' ), ☏ +36 1 319-3105 , fax: +36 1 319-3104 , ✉ farkasreti.plebania@axelero.hu . Roman Catholic</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St. Ladislaus Parish of Istenhegy</hi> (Istenhegyi Szent László Plébánia), XII. Diana u. 15/A. (Istenhegy quarter, : 'Széll Kálmán tér' take tram: 61 to 'Városmajor' further "red 60" (Cog Wheel train) to stop 'Városkút' ), ☏ +36 1 398-1591 , fax: +36 1 395-8343 , ✉ sztlaszlo@t-online.hu . Roman Catholic. Built in 1975-78.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mary's Chapel of Atonement of Kútvölgyi</hi> (Kútvölgyi Mária Engesztelő Kápolna), XII. Galgóczy u. 49 (Kútvölgyi quarter. - : 'Széll Kálmán tér' + bus 128 to last stop 'Városkúti út' ). Roman Catholic. In 1990, next to the original 18th-century chapel built a larger chapel named Mary's Chapel of Atonement. In 1998, extended with "Camp Hill" pilgrim house. Next to the chapel stand the Mary Fountain with a small cloister</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Greek Catholic University Church</hi> (Szinaxis Diákotthon és Budapesti Görögkatolikus Egyetemi Lelkészség), XII. Hegyalja út 113. ( : Ferenciek tere further bus 8 to 'Korompai utca' ). Greek Catholic.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Reformed Church of Buda Mountain</hi> (Budahegyvidéki Református Egyházközség), XII. Böszörményi út 28 ( : 'Széll Kálmán tér' or Déli Pályaudvar further tram: 59 or bus 102 to stop 'Királyhágó tér'</item>
</list>

 ), ☏ +36 1 355 4482 101 , ✉ ref.bhv@t-online.hu .

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Reformed Mission Church of Svábhegy</hi>, XII., Felhő u. 10 ( : 'Széll Kálmán tér' take tram: 61 to 'Városmajor' further "red 60" (Cog Wheel train) to stop 'Svábhegy' ), ✉ bertadorogi@citromail.hu .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lutheran Church of Buda Mountain</hi> (Budahegyvidéki Evangélikus Egyházközség), XII. Kékgolyó u. 17. ( : 'Déli Pályaudvar' further tram: and 10min walk uphill ), ☏ +36 1 224-0640 , ✉ pal.keczko@lutheran.hu . Lutheran church.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Former Post Palace</hi>, Krisztina körút, 8 ( : 'Széll Kálmán tér' ). Protected Monument Building. A landmark of Szell Kalman square hilly side.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Villas on Bela Kiraly street</hi> (Villák a), Bela Kiraly street, 27, 29, 33, 34 (multiple) (Cog wheel or bus 21, 21A to stop 'Adonis utca' take the rail underpass at 'Költő' street and there start the Bela Kiraly street). Just outside. Strolling between hundred or more years old buildings. - Frivaldszky–villa, Mauthner–villa, Pálffy-villa.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Újlak Visitation of Our Lady Parish</hi> (Újlak Sarlós Boldogasszony plébánia), III. Bécsi út 32. (Bus 9, 29, 65, 65A, 109, 111, 165, tram: 17, 19, 41, : Szépvölgyi út. ), ☏ +36 1 335-3573 , ✉ iroda@ujlakitemplom.hu . Masses M-Sa 6:30 and 18:00, Su 9:00, 10:30 and 18:00. - St. Stephen's Chapel Masses Weekdays 17:30, Su 9:00 &amp; 11:00. Above the main entrance of the church in Latin inscription (1705 Creature Creator) marks the year of founding of the parish. For builders, mostly German-speaking Újlaki (Neustift) little more than fifty yearsfaithful took to build and furnish this church. The building Christopher Hamon Nepauer Matthew was raised in 1746-1766. The main altar was designed by Christopher Hickisch in 1799. The tower formed hard: The first, which began to build above the center of the front facade had to be demolished before its have fallen. Place it on the south side of the connector tower can still be seen. Instead made ​​on the south side another tower, this can still be seen nowadays. Top of the tower, "helmet" part, due to natural disasters, should be renewed twice. Present form of the tower was completed according to the plans of Ybl Miklós in 1877.The "Water level" indicator plaque located in the little church, a memory for 1875 rainstorm that causes serious damage. The frescoes made in 1920s.</item>
</list>
</text>
