<text id="autogum_voyage_doc41" title="Boston Harbor Islands" shortTile="boston-harbor-islands" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=4401" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Boston Harbor Islands</head>

<p>The <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.nps.gov/boha/">Boston Harbor Islands</ref></hi> are a group of thirty-four islands in <ref target="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref> that are a unit of the <ref target="United%20States%20National%20Park%20System">United States National Park System</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The Boston Harbor Islands national park area is managed by a unique 13-member partnership called the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.BostonIslands.com">Boston Harbor Islands Partnership</ref></hi>, 617-223-8666, which includes the National Park Service and other public and private organizations. Massachusetts claims 17 of the islands within <ref target="http://www.mass.gov/eea/agencies/dcr/massparks/region-south/boston-harbor-islands-generic.html">Boston Harbor Island State Park.</ref></item>
<item> During the <hi rend="bold">summer season</hi>, the islands are open daily from 9AM until sunset. During spring and fall the islands are open on an abbreviated schedule. Special arrangements for school groups are possible for weekdays in spring, summer, and fall seasons. Some sites have additional hours.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pets are not allowed</hi> on the islands.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bicycle riding and rollerblading are not permitted.</hi></item>
<item> Georges and Peddocks islands have paved walkways suitable for strollers.</item>
<item> Day-use permits are required for groups of 25 or more.</item>
</list>


<head>History</head>
<p>The islands have great historical significance in a number of ways. Archeological sites on 21 of the islands have been placed on the National Register of Historic Places and all the islands are considered likely to have significant sites. Evidence indicates that Native American peoples lived on the islands as early as 1000 BC and perhaps before they separated from the mainland sometime in the 2000 years previous to that. The highly alkaline shell-fragmented soils which preserve artifacts better than typical New England soils, and the relatively low-intensity use by Euro-Americans, make the islands an archeological treasure.</p>

<p>The islands have undergone many various uses over the years: agriculture, cemetery, fishing colony, fortifications, hospital, hotel or resort, industrial, poorhouse, prison, prisoner-of-war camp, quarantine, sewage treatment, lighthouses, and dumps.</p>

<p>Deer Island has particular significance to Native Americans as a place of imprisonment and interment during King Philip's War in the 1670s. Contemporary Native Americans return each October to commemorate their ancestors' suffering in this tragic slaughter. Indications are that 1000 or more American Indians were forced onto Deer and other islands, often to die of starvation. Later Deer Island also served as a quarantine hospital in 1847 to treat the many sick, impoverished Irish immigrants fleeing the potato famine.</p>

<p>In 1970 the Commonwealth of Massachusetts began acquiring islands for the benefit of the public. In 1985 Boston Harbor was named the most polluted harbor in the nation. After investment of $4 billion and extensive wastewater treatment efforts by the Massachusetts Water Resources Authority, improved water quality contributed to widespread support for establishing a national park area.</p>

<p>The Boston Harbor Islands National Recreation Area was established by act of Congress in 1996. The Partnership which governs it is made up of thirteen members appointed by the Secretary of the Interior to represent various Federal, State, City of Boston, and non-profit interests. The Partnership subsequently adopted the name "Boston Harbor Islands, a national park area" in response to Native Americans' objections to the term "recreation" being used for an area they consider sacred.</p>

<head>Landscape</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The land area changes from 3100 acres to 1600 acres as the tide rises from low to high. The typical island, and even the peninsulas, consist of drumlins (rounded hills of till that form under glaciers). Some of the smaller islands are based on rocky outcroppings. The larger islands have a variety of landscapes—deciduous trees and thickets of bushes, salt marshes, bluffs, cliffs and, of course, beaches and waterscapes, including lighthouses.</item>
</list>


<head>Flora and fauna</head>
<p>Many of the islands have trees, with some having been planted for shade in recent years. Native plants such as bayberry and beach plum are abundant. Decorative flowers are in raised plantings so as not to disturb possible archeological sites. Many marine and migrating birds are found on the islands. Lovell Island has a large population of European hares put here in the 1940s and 1950s. Gallops Island also has a large population of rabbits.</p>

<head>Climate</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Weather is variable, from clear, crisp days to stormy, chilly days. Water breezes make for cooler ferry rides, requiring jackets or windbreakers. Walking shoes, hats, sunscreen are essential.</item>
</list>


<head>By boat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ferries</hi> run from four mainland locations to George's Island. <hi rend="bold">Shuttles run a loop between George's and Hull to Lovells, Peddocks, Bumpkin, and Grape Islands</hi>. Daily ferry service is available from Long Wharf, Boston to Spectacle Island, and on Sundays only a loop runs from EDIC Pier in South Boston to Thompson and Spectacle Islands.<ref target="http://www.bostonislands.com/ferry-schedule"></ref></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mainland ferry terminals</hi>, Phone: +1 617-223-8666, Schedules: <ref target="http://www.nps.gov/boha/parkdocs/boatschedule.pdf"></ref>.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Boston">Boston</ref>, 66 Long Wharf, at Christopher Columbus Park <hi rend="italic">North of the Long Wharf Marriott</hi>. MBTA Blue Line to Aquarium stop.</item>
<item> <ref target="Boston/South%20Boston">South Boston</ref>, Dock #10, Drydock Av., off Summer Street, at EDIC Pier. Taxi or bus from South Station.</item>
<item> <ref target="Hull%20%28Massachusetts%29">Hull</ref>, 180 Main Street, at Pemberton Point.</item>
<item> <ref target="Quincy%20%28Massachusetts%29">Quincy</ref>, 703 Washington Street, at Fore River Shipyard.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://bostonislands.com/trip_moorings.html">Moorings</ref></hi>: Limited docking space is available for private boats at Georges Island on a first-come, first-served basis. On all other islands, docks are available for off-loading only. Small prams are available for anchoring off-shore. For information on moorings for private boats at Bumpkin, Georges, Peddocks and other Boston Harbor Islands, phone: +1 617-223-8666. For reservations and technical information, phone: +1 617-241-9640, email: moorings@basport.com. $10 day use, $25 overnight (2006).</item>
</list>


<head>By land</head>
<p>Even though some of the "islands" are really peninsulas, car travel is discouraged. Limited parking is available at Deer Island, Nut Island, Webb Memorial, and World's End.</p>

<p>Long and Moon Islands are accessible by land, but are not open to the public. Access is restricted by a police guard station at the mainland end of the causeway connecting them to the Quincy neighborhood of Squantum.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Deer Island</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">William Webb Memorial Park</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Worlds End Reservation</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nut Island</hi></item>
</list>


<head>Fees and permits</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> No entrance fee (but without your own boat, you will need to get ferry tickets to reach the islands.)</item>
<item> <ref target="http://www.bostonharborislands.org/directions-fees">Round-trip passenger fare</ref>, including the ferry to Georges Island and water shuttle to five other islands. Adults: $17, seniors (65+): $12, college students &amp; active military with ID: $12, children 3-12: $10, under 3: free, family four pack: $43 (2 adults &amp; 2 children), ten-ticket pack: $140 (2016).</item>
</list>
</text>
