<text id="autogum_voyage_doc135" title="Melbourne" shortTile="melbourne" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=21920" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Melbourne</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.visitmelbourne.com/">Melbourne</ref></hi> is the second largest city and the cultural capital of <ref target="Australia">Australia</ref>, with Victorian-era architecture, extensive shopping, museums, galleries, theatres, and large parks and gardens. Many of its 5 million residents are both multicultural and sports-mad. The capital of the south-eastern state of <ref target="Victoria%20%28state%29">Victoria</ref>, and located at the head of Port Phillip Bay, Melbourne is a magnet for migrants from all over the world, and consistently ranks as one of the world's most liveable cities.</p>

<p>Visitors come to attend major sporting events, and to use it as a base for exploring nearby places such as <ref target="Grampians%20National%20Park">Grampians National Park</ref>, the <ref target="Great%20Ocean%20Road">Great Ocean Road</ref>, and <ref target="Phillip%20Island">Phillip Island</ref> and its penguin parade. Many UK visitors come for tours of filming locations of the soap opera <hi rend="italic">Neighbours</hi>.</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>The British settlement of Melbourne commenced in 1835 when settlers from <ref target="Tasmania">Tasmania</ref> "purchased" land on Port Phillip Bay and the Yarra River from the local Aboriginal people. The streets of central Melbourne were carefully laid out in 1837, with some streets 30 metres wide. The settlement was named "Melbourne" after William Lamb, 2nd Viscount Melbourne, the British Prime Minister at that time. The first British lieutenant-governor, Charles La Trobe, arrived in 1839 – his Cottage still stands and can be visited in the Kings Domain. </p>

<p>1851 was a landmark for Melbourne — the colony of Victoria was separated from <ref target="New%20South%20Wales">New South Wales</ref> and very soon after, gold was discovered in Victoria, sparking a huge gold rush. The gold rush history can be seen at the Gold Treasury Museum, housed in the Treasury Building built in 1858. Gold was the catalyst for several decades of prosperity lasting through to the late 1880s and examples of the ornate Victorian-era structures built during this time still stand. Throughout the gold and building booms, Melbourne managed to retain its many spacious parks and gardens that remain to this day.</p>

<p>In 1888, the boom collapsed and Victoria suffered through the depression of the 1890s. </p>

<p>In 1901, the British colonies of Australia federated and Melbourne became the temporary capital of Australia, with the Federal Parliament meeting in the Parliament House of Victoria until 1927 when the new Federal capital of <ref target="Canberra">Canberra</ref> was founded. After World War II, Melbourne grew rapidly, with its mainly Anglo-Celtic population boosted by immigration from Europe, particularly from Greece and Italy. Today Melbourne has the biggest Greek population (over 800,000) of any city outside Greece and the biggest Italian population (over 230,000) of any city outside Italy. The significant pre-war Jewish population was also boosted after the war. From the mid-1970s, many immigrants came from Southeast Asia, particularly Vietnam and Cambodia. Melbourne has had a Chinese population since the gold rush of the 1850s. Chinatown has existed from that time but the population of Chinese and other East Asians has also been boosted by immigration.</p>

<p>New highrise buildings replaced many of Melbourne’s interesting old structures in the construction boom of the 1970s and 80s. Melbournians belatedly recognised the loss of their architectural heritage and steps were taken to protect what was left. Construction of the huge Crown Casino (briefly the largest casino in the world) in the 1990s introduced glitz and gambling to the city centre. Melbourne’s development continues in the 2000s with the opening of the Melbourne Museum, Federation Square and the Docklands precinct.</p>

<head>Culture</head>

<p>Melbourne is the cultural capital of Australia, with its many art galleries, film festivals, orchestras, choral and opera productions, vibrant live music scene, and a strong food, wine and coffee culture. People in Melbourne tend to dress up more than the northern states - partly due to the colder climate. Many bars and clubs have strict dress regulations, such as requiring collars and dress shoes for men.</p>

<p>Particular cultural events to note include the Melbourne International Film Festival in August, the International Art Festival in October, and the Melbourne Comedy Festival in April. There are also many concerts and exhibitions throughout the year. In addition to the Melbourne Museum, there are special museums dedicated to subjects such as science, immigration, Chinese history, Jewish history, sport, racing, film and moving image, railways, police, fire brigades and banking.</p>

<head>Sport</head>

<p>Melbournians are sports enthusiasts and particularly passionate about <ref target="Australian%20rules%20football">Australian rules football</ref>, a sport invented in Melbourne. In fact the <ref target="http://afl.com.au/">Australian Football League (AFL)</ref> is not so much a sport as a religion in Melbourne, with 9 of the 10 Victorian teams being based in Melbourne. As a guide, the entire national competition only has 18 teams, meaning half the league is based in Melbourne alone. The AFL culminates in the AFL Grand Final in the spring, which is played every year at the Melbourne Cricket Ground. Horse racing is another passion, and the majority of the state has a public holiday on the first Tuesday of November for the racing of the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.melbournecup.com/">Melbourne Cup</ref></hi>, one of the world’s famous horse races. Cricket is the big summer sport and the <ref target="http://www.mcg.org.au/">Melbourne Cricket Ground</ref> (the 'MCG') is one of the world's leading grounds. The <hi rend="bold">National Sports Museum</hi> (NSM) (including the Racing Museum) Australia’s only truly dedicated multi-sports museum is also located at the MCG.</p>

<p>Each January, Melbourne hosts tennis' <ref target="http://www.ausopen.org/">Australian Open</ref>, one of the world’s four Grand Slam championships. In March, Melbourne hosts the first race of the <ref target="Formula%20One">Formula One</ref> season, the <ref target="http://www.grandprix.com.au/">Formula One Grand Prix</ref>. The race is held in Albert Park in South Melbourne. Two professional Association Football teams are based in Melbourne, Melbourne Victory and Melbourne City FC; the two teams now share the new Melbourne Rectangular Stadium, commercially known as AAMI Park also playing at Etihad Stadium. The city also boasts one professional team in each <ref target="Rugby%20football">rugby code</ref>, with both also playing at AAMI Park. The Melbourne Storm play rugby league in the National Rugby League, with teams throughout Australia plus one in New Zealand. The Melbourne Rebels play rugby union in Super Rugby, which features four other Australian sides and five each in New Zealand and South Africa. Melbourne is the unquestioned sporting capital of Australia with the largest arenas and two of the major sporting administrations basing their operation in Melbourne: Cricket Australia is a stone's throw from the MCG, and the AFL games are played at both the MCG and Etihad Stadium.</p>
</text>
