<text id="autogum_voyage_doc318" title="Budapest/Várkerület" shortTile="budapestvrkerlet" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=132758" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Budapest/Várkerület</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.budavar.hu/">Várkerület</ref></hi> <hi rend="italic">(Castle District)</hi> is a district in <ref target="Budapest">Budapest</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Bel-Buda is officially known as 'Várkerület' (lit. Castle district). It includes Watertown (Vízíváros, Fő utca), Castle Hill (Budai Várnegyed), Taban (Tabán) and Kristinatown (Krisztinaváros). The borders of the district are Gellért Hill, South (Déli) Railway Station and, at its northernmost point, the Margaret Bridge's bridgehead on its Buda side. Administratively this is First district (abbrev. <hi rend="bold">I.</hi>) which is bounded in the northwest II. and XII. district, the Mount area (<hi rend="bold"><ref target="Budapest/Hegyvid%C3%A9k">Hegyvidék</ref></hi>), in south the XI. district (<hi rend="bold"><ref target="Budapest/%C3%9Ajbuda%20and%20T%C3%A9t%C3%A9ny">Újbuda</ref></hi>) while in the east the Danube, by the V. district the Downtown</p>
<p>(<hi rend="bold"><ref target="Budapest/Belv%C3%A1ros">Belváros</ref></hi>).</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Castle Hill</hi>, known as <hi rend="italic">Várhegy</hi> in Hungarian, was first settled in the thirteenth century, after a Mongol attack led Buda's citizens to seek a more easily defended area. The royal Hungarian court also decided to move, to the southern end of the hill. By the fourteenth century, there were an estimated 8,000 residents in Buda. After a long (1541–1686) period of Turkish rule, a 75-day siege left Buda in ruins, and Austrian authorities counted a mere 300 people left. This would not be the last heavy attack on Castle Hill. In 1849 and 1945 the Baroquified area once more came under attack. A completely surrounded German force held out for almost a month in January 1945, in the thirty-first siege of the city. Since 1987 part of the <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20List">UNESCO World Heritage List</ref>. The three main part of the Castle district (Várnegyed) are: the Buda Castle Palace, the area of St George's Square (Szent György tér) and the historical residential area.</p>

<head>Tourist information point</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tourinform - Buda Castle</hi>, I. Tárnok u. 15 (From : 'Deák Ferenc tér' take bus 16 to Szentháromság tér</item>
</list>

<p>). Daily 09:00 – 18:00. stocks a comprehensive range of free leaflets, maps and listings magazines and free guidebooks which offer lots of ideas about sights and sounds, gastronomy, shopping, by night and lifestyle. You can also book shows, concerts and sightseeing tickets. </p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>Metro lines M2 (red) and M4 (green) cross the Danube from <ref target="Budapest/Pest">Pest</ref> to the Buda side. M2 stops at three major transport hubs: <hi rend="bold">Batthyány Square</hi> (gaze at the view to the Parliament before changing to the <hi rend="italic">HÉV</hi> suburban train for <ref target="Szentendre">Szentendre</ref>), <hi rend="bold">Széll Kálmán Square</hi> (former Moszkva Square, gateway to the Castle Hill in fact this is on the I. and II. districts perimeter) and <hi rend="bold">Southern Railway Station (Déli pályaudvar)</hi> (southern railway station).</p>

<p>You can take trams tram: no. 19, 41, 56, 56A. at west limits of the district useful the tram: 59, 59A, 59B. tram: 4 &amp; 6 also serve district needs.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The zero statue on the Clark Ádám Square</hi> („0” kilométerkő), Clark Ádám Square (Bus 16, 105, tram: 19, 41). This is at the western end of the <hi rend="bold">Сhain Bridge</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Széchenyi Lánchíd</hi>), which is considered to be the most beautiful of the bridges over the Danube. The square is also home to the zero statue that signifies the start (or end) point of journeys from the capital as shown on the roadsigns on major roads. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">South Railwaystation</hi> (Déli pályaudvar) ( : 'Déli pályaudvar', tram: 17, 56, 56A, 59, 59A, 59B, 61. Bus 21, 21A, 39, 102, 139, 140, 140A, 142 ). Bel-Buda railway station is the terminus of metro line M2 (red). </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Batthyany Square transport hub</hi> (Batthyány tér), Batthyany square. This is a combined transport hub there is station, the end terminal - only this HÉV-station is underground, in all Budapest, - for north direction to <hi rend="bold">Óbuda</hi>, to suburbs, to <ref target="Szentendre">Szentendre</ref> where is the southern end of the very nice Danube Bend. A couple of citybus and two tram lines stop also here. This port will affect the following boat services D11 and D12.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Széll Kálmán Square</hi> (Széll Kálmán tér) ( : 'Széll Kálmán tér'; tram 4, 6, 17, 56, 56A, 59, 59A, 59B, 61; bus 5, 16, 16A, 21, 21A, 22, 22A, 39, 91, 102, 116, 128, 129, 139, 140, 140A, 142, 149, 155, 156, 222. Nightbus 956, 960</item>
</list>

<p>). One of the main transport hub of Buda, makes the most convenient entry point to the Castle District. You can walk upon the hill (it takes about 20 minutes) or take the bus 16 or 16A. When you come up from the subway station look for the outdoor stairway leading to a pedestrian bridge over the trolley tracks. Up the steps, over the tracks, cross the street to the mid-block bus stop. </p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Széna tér bus station</hi> (Széna tér buszpályaudvar), II. Széna tér ( : 'Széll Kálmán tér '</item>
</list>

<p>), ☏ +36 1 2013688 . Cash desk M-F 06:00-18:00; Sa-Su 06:00-16:00 - public toilets M-F 08:00-18:00, Sa, Su 08:00-14:00, Buffet daily 06:00-18:00, Newspaper sales 06:00-18:00. Buses depart from here to the northwestern suburb, Zsámbék village and neighbouring areas. There is a ticket vending machine. Timetable and list of destinations: <ref target="http://budapestcity.org/11-egyeb/kozlekedes/volanbusz/szena-ter-hu.htm">here</ref> </p>

<p>It's also pleasant to walk by Chain Bridge (Széchenyi lánchíd) from Pest and walk up by the narrow streets or paths (as Király lépcső or Kemál Atatürk sétány). Walking from Pest is likely to be faster than public transport or taxi on peak hours.</p>

<head>Get around</head>


<p>This district is small enough to discover it on foot. However, if you get tired, you can jump on bus 5 or 11 86 which has several stops inside the Bel-Buda District, or two convenient trams: 19 and 41 go along the Buda bank of the river. There is also a bicycle route in parallel to it. Tram 56 and 56A could be useful to explore Taban (Tabán) and Kristinatown (Krisztinaváros) on Krisztina boulevard.</p>

<p>In Buda Castle area you can use bus 16 (formerly known as <hi rend="italic">Várbusz</hi>) which has several stops inside the Castle District. Pricey horse carriages are also waiting for taking you on a tour.</p>

<p>As private cars are not allowed to enter the Castle Hill zone, your only options remain public transport, walking or taxi.</p>

<head>Other transport modes</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cable car, Lower station</hi> (Budavári Sikló, alsó állomás), Clark Adam Square (From Deák square take bus 105, from Batthyány square take tram 19, 41). The spectacular but very touristy and pricey cable car (funicular) called <hi rend="bold">Budavári Sikló</hi> climbs up Castle Hill from Chain Bridge's Buda side to <hi rend="bold">Fisherman's Bastion</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Halászbástya</hi>). As the cable car is rising up the hill you get a beautiful view of Pest across the river. Alternatively you can check the view from one of the two small pedestrian bridges over the cable car way - for free. Ft 1000/1400 one way/return, children Ft 400/750.</item>
</list>
</text>
