<text id="autogum_voyage_doc259" title="Australian rules football" shortTile="australian-rules" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=148736" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Australian rules football</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Australian rules football</hi> is a sport that originated in the state of <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Victoria%20%28state%29">Victoria</ref></hi>, <ref target="Australia">Australia</ref>. Today it is the most popular spectator sport throughout Australia with the exception of the states of Queensland and New South Wales, where <ref target="Rugby%20football%23Rugby%20league">rugby league</ref> dominates, as well as the Australian Capital Territory, where <ref target="Rugby%20football%23Rugby%20union">rugby union</ref> and rugby league vie for supremacy.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>The origins of Australian rules football are unclear, though at first glance it appears to be a cross between <ref target="rugby%20football">rugby football</ref> and <ref target="association%20football">association football</ref> (soccer). A game called "football" was known to have been played in the state of Victoria as early as 1841, though the precise rules of this game have been lost to history. Some contend that it can trace its origin to 1858, when a <ref target="cricket">cricket</ref>er attempted to develop of new code of football to keep cricketers fit during the off-season in the winter. In any case, the first set of rules for a uniquely Australian code of football were written down in 1859 at the Melbourne Football Club, and a copy of these rules still survives to this day. Modern Australian rules football likely evolved from this set of rules over the years.</p>

<head>Rules</head>

<p>Australian rules football is played on an elliptical field 135-185 metres long, and 110-155 metres wide, known as an <hi rend="bold">oval</hi>. This makes the playing field of Australian rules football one of the largest of any spectator sport, far larger than that of rugby football, association football or <ref target="American%20football">American football</ref>. Games are played between teams of 18 players with four <hi rend="bold">interchanges</hi> (substitutes); one exception is AFL Women's, in which each side has 16 players and five interchanges.</p>

<p>Similar to rugby football and American football, Australian rules football is a full contact sport, meaning that it is perfectly legal for players to be tackled to the ground, though tackles have to be made between the shoulders and the knees. If the tackle is legal, players are required to pass the ball immediately when they are tackled. Players typically run while carrying the ball, but are required to bounce the ball every 15 metres. Players may pass the ball to another player by hitting it with a clenched fist in any direction, but may not throw the ball. Alternatively, players may also kick the ball to another player, and if the ball travels at least 50 metres and the receiving player catches the ball cleanly without it touching the ground or any other player, the receiving player is said to have taken a <hi rend="bold">mark</hi>, and may kick the ball unimpeded by the opposition from the spot where he was marked.</p>

<p>The ends of the oval consist of two tall posts called the <hi rend="bold">goal posts</hi>, and two shorter posts flanking them called the <hi rend="bold">behind posts</hi>. Kicking the ball between the two goal posts results in a <hi rend="bold">goal</hi> which is worth six points. Failing which, kicking the ball between the goal post and the behind post, or having the ball touch the goal post or another player on the way in results in a <hi rend="bold">behind</hi>, which is worth one point. If the defending team puts the ball in between its own goal posts, or between its goal post and behind post, this results in a behind being scored by the attacking team.</p>

<p>For any rule infringement, a <hi rend="bold">free kick</hi> is typically awarded by an umpire to the opposing team, during which a player may kick the ball unimpeded by the opposition. For more serious infringements, the umpire may award a <hi rend="bold">50-metre penalty</hi>, which is a free kick taken 50 metres closer to the goal posts from the spot the infringement was committed.</p>

<p>Australian rules has aspects of both free and limited substitution. Interchanges may be made at any time during the game, even during open play; however, players must enter and exit through the "interchange area", a 15-metre stretch of the field between the two benches at the centre of the field (with exceptions in cases of serious injury), and the new player cannot enter the field of play until the player being replaced has left the field. Players are free to return to the game after being interchanged, but each team is limited to a set number of player rotations. In the AFL, the limit of player rotations is 90 per match; state and local leagues may have different limits on the number of interchange players and rotations. AFL Women's has no limit on player rotations; the AFL chose not to enforce a rotation limit in its women's league because that league plays during the main AFL's offseason in the southern summer.</p>

<head>Australian Football League</head>
<p>The <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.afl.com.au/">Australian Football League</ref></hi> (AFL) is the premier professional competition in the sport. The competition originated in Victoria, and was originally called the Victorian Football League (VFL). Though the competition is still dominated by Victorian teams, it has since expanded and now features teams from all the states of Australia except Tasmania. Tickets to most games are reasonably priced, especially when compared to ticket prices at soccer matches in Europe, or basketball or American football games in the United States. However, tickets to some games, and most finals matches, especially the Grand Final, are more expensive. Some games may not have tickets available to the public, as club, ground or league members normally have priority access to tickets. Australian rules football fans are generally well behaved, and crowd violence is extremely rare, even when the fans of two bitter rivals are sitting together. As such, unlike at soccer matches in Europe, there are no separate sections for the fans of opposing teams at AFL games.</p>

<p>Traditionally, games were only played on Saturday afternoons, but night football now is played most Friday and Saturday nights, with the occasional Thursday or Monday night game. The AFL season normally starts at the end of March and concludes with the <hi rend="bold">AFL Grand Final</hi>, which is held at the Melbourne Cricket Ground on the last Saturday in September or first Saturday in October. The AFL Grand Final is a major part of Australian culture and the most important game on the Australian sporting calendar, with the largest attendance and television audience of any Australian sporting event.</p>

<p>Preseason games are played throughout February and March, and are often played at smaller venues in regional cities.</p>

<p>The league is kept competitive through the use of a draft system and salary caps. As part of the draft system, teams that finish lower on the table are typically allowed to pick their drafts first, which ensures that the top teams do not monopolise the top players.</p>
</text>
