<text id="autogum_voyage_doc13" title="Abakan">
<head>Abakan</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Abakan</hi> (<ref target="Russian%20phrasebook">Russian</ref>: Абака́н <hi rend="italic">uh-buh-KAHN</hi>) is a city in <ref target="Khakassia">Khakassia</ref>, <ref target="Russia">Russia</ref>.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<head>By plane</head>

<head>By rail</head>
<p>The principal rail route is from Moscow with the fast <hi rend="italic">Sayany</hi> train, journey time is 75 hours. The train departs <hi rend="italic">Moskva Yaroslavsky</hi> station at 10:55PM and arrives 6PM three nights later. The train makes stop-overs in <ref target="Yekaterinburg">Yekaterinburg</ref> (45 h), <ref target="Omsk">Omsk</ref> (31 h) and <ref target="Novosibirsk">Novosibirsk</ref> (22 h) along its way. Take care as the train does not start daily.</p>

<head>By Bus</head>
<p>You may come or go to <ref target="Kyzyl">Kyzyl</ref> by bus. There are several buses daily, and two stops in Abakan: one is at the "Railway" station and the other one the bus station.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>There is a reliable bus system and locals may help you with the directions. You may use it to go from the train station to the Holy transfiguration Cathedral. Remember to have pictures to show, because almost no one will speak russian.</p>
<p>There are also taxis available.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Holy Transfiguration Cathedral</hi>. free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Good Angel of Peace sculpture</hi>. free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Park of Topiary Art</hi>. Do not miss also the nearby heartlock artwork: a big metallic heart where lovers can append their little lovelock. free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sitting Lenin Statue</hi>. Near to the Railway station there is a sitting Lenin all paint with a metallic color. free.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<p>You can walk aroud but there isn't so much to see. Remember not to loose your onward connection, as Abakan is not served so often by onward transport, especially train.</p>

<head>Buy</head>

<p>There are some supermarkets with fresh fruits.</p>

<head>Eat</head>

<head>Drink</head>

<head>Sleep</head>

<head>Go next</head>
</text>
