<text id="autogum_voyage_doc520" title="Plitvice Lakes National Park" shortTile="plitvice-lakes-national" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27864" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Plitvice Lakes National Park</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Plitvice Lakes National Park</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Nacionalni park Plitvička jezera</hi>) in <ref target="Croatia">Croatia</ref> is one of the most beautiful natural sights in <ref target="Europe">Europe</ref>. Due to its beauty and significance, this system of 16 interlinked lakes and a large forest complex around it were set aside as a national park in 1949. In 1979 the park was inscribed on the <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20site">UNESCO World Heritage site</ref> List. Many Germans will recognize features of the park, as many of the Karl May Westerns were shot here. </p>

<head>History</head>
<p>Humans have inhabited the Plitvice Lakes area for thousands of years. It was settled in turn by Illyrians, Thracians, Celts, Japods, Romans, Avars, Slavs and Turks. The area fell to the Ottomans in 1528, and was retaken by the Austrian Empire 150 years later. The Austrians incorporated it into their Military Frontier and, in addition to the native Croats who already inhabited the region, Serbs who had fled Ottoman repression settled there.</p>

<p>The Plitvice Lakes became a major tourist attraction in the late 19th century. The first hotel was built in 1896, and as early as 1893 it had a conservation committee – the predecessor of today's national park authority. In 1949 the communist government of Yugoslavia nationalized the lakes and made them a national park. The park was inscribed on the <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20site">UNESCO World Heritage site</ref> List in 1979 in recognition of its "outstanding natural beauty, and the undisturbed production of travertine (tuff) through chemical and biological action".</p>

<p>The park soon became one of <ref target="Yugoslavia">Yugoslavia</ref>'s most popular tourist attractions. In March 1991 it became the scene of the Plitvice Lakes incident - the first armed confrontation of the <ref target="Croatia">Croatian War of Independence</ref> that resulted in fatalities. The park was held by forces of the Republic of Serbian Krajina during the conflict and suffered some damage in the process, with hotels and other facilities being used as barracks. A massacre of three children by the Yugoslav Army occurred around Grabovac in September of 1991. It was retaken by the Croatian Army in August 1995 during Operation Storm, which ended the Croatian war.</p>

<p>The war led UNESCO to add the park to its List of World Heritage in Danger. Due to the economic importance of the park, the Croatian government made it a priority for its de-mining efforts, and in December 1998 UNESCO recognized the parks new mine-free status by removing it from the list of endangered sites. The surrounding municipalities outside the park boundaries still have minor problems with mine contamination.</p>

<head>Landscape</head>
<p>The lakes are on the Plitvice plateau, between the mountains of Lička Plješevica (Gornja Plješevica peak 1,640 m), Mala Kapela (Seliški Vrh peak at 1,280 m) and Medveđak (884 m). The 26 lakes are separated into an upper and lower cluster formed by runoff from the mountains, descending from an altitude of 636 m to 503 m over a distance of some 8 km, aligned in a south-north direction. The lakes collectively cover an area of about 2 km², with the water exiting from the lowest lake to form the Korana River.</p>

<p>The Plitvice Lakes lie in a basin of karstic rock, mainly dolomite and limestone, which has given rise to their most distinctive feature. The lakes are separated by natural dams of travertine, which is deposited by the action of moss, algae and bacteria. The encrusted plants and bacteria accumulate on top of each other, forming travertine barriers which grow at the rate of about 1 cm per year.</p>

<p>The lakes are renowned for their distinctive colours, ranging from azure to green, grey or blue. The colours change constantly depending on the quantity of minerals or organisms in the water and the angle of sunlight.</p>

<p>The lakes are divided into the 12 Upper Lakes (Gornja jezera) and the four Lower Lakes.</p>

<head>Flora and fauna</head>
<p>The Plitvice Lakes national park is heavily forested, mainly with beech, spruce, and fir trees, and features a mixture of Alpine and Mediterranean vegetation. It has a notably wide variety of plant communities, due to its range of microclimates, differing soils and varying levels of altitude.</p>

<p>The area is also home to an extremely wide variety of animal and bird species. Rare fauna such as the European brown bear, wolf, eagle, owl, lynx, wild cat and capercaillie can be found there, along with many more common species. At least 126 species of birds have been recorded there, of which 70 have been recorded as breeding there.</p>

<head>Climate</head>

<p>The area knows a mountainous land climate, with hot summers and cold winters. Although generally cooler than coastal Croatia because of its altitude, sunny days in summer get very hot with temperatures up to 35°C. As there are few opportunities to buy refreshments in the park, visitors should bring plenty of water along for rehydration. In the evening, occasional thunderstorms can unleash large amounts of rain in a short time, so make sure to keep an eye on the weather forecast to avoid being surprised by heavy rain in the absence of shelter. The many calm streams in the park may quickly transform into wild water torrents, so stay away from the water in case of heavy rain.</p>

<p>In winter, heavy snowfall can be expected, enabling the Mukinje Ski Resort to operate from December to early March. Fog is common in the morning and can occur very locally, making driving up and down the often narrow roads in the park hazardous.</p>

<head>Tourist information</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nacionalni park Plitvička jezera</hi> (Plitvice Lakes National Park), Josipa Jovića 19, Znanstveno - stručni centar "Dr. Ivo Pevalek", HR 53231 Plitvička jezera, ☏ +385 53 751 015 , ✉ info@np-plitvicka-jezera.hr . 07:00-20:00. Aug: 180 kn; Apr-Jun, Sep-Oct: 110 kn; Nov-Mar: 55 kn; 2-day cards 280, 180, 90 kn respectively; discounts for students (an ISIC student card is required) and children; tickets sold at the entrances and they are also valid for park's internal buses and ferries. <ref target="https://np-plitvicka-jezera.hr/en/plan-your-visit/price-list/">Tickets</ref> often sell out leaving people disappointed at the park gate. To avoid this, buy your tickets online a minimum of two days in advance. If you plan on purchasing tickets at the entrance do arrive early, especially on weekends..</item>
</list>
</text>
