<text id="autogum_voyage_doc79" title="Calatafimi Segesta" shortTile="calatafimi-segesta" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=148642" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Calatafimi Segesta</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Calatafimi Segesta</hi> is in <ref target="Sicily">Sicily</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The town takes its name from the Arab "Qal’at Fimi" (that is Rock of Eufemio): he was an officer of <ref target="Byzantium">Byzantium</ref> who, according to an old tradition, favoured the conquest of Sicily by the Saracens. Some scholars link the name Calatafimi with Acesta, a little town contemporary of <ref target="Segesta">Segesta</ref>, or with Castrum Phimes, from the name of a noble landowner of Segesta, named also by Cicero. The present town originated around the “Castle of Phimes”, and its oldest part stands here. Calatafimi, with the Castle of Eufemio and its churches, is characterised also by its lanes and small streets of Arab derivation. At about 10 km from this town there is the archaeological site of <ref target="Segesta">Segesta</ref>, with the Greek temple and the ancient theatre, where they hold classical performances.</p>
<head>Tourist Information</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ufficio Turistico</hi>, piazza Cangemi,1, ☏ +39 0924 9505507 , fax: +39 0924 9505515 , ✉ affarigenerali@comune.calatafimisegesta.tp.it .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pro Loco</hi>, Corso Vittorio Emanuele,16, ☏ +39 333 9245687 , ✉ prolococalatafimisegesta@gmail.com .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">U.R.P.</hi> (Public Relations Office), Piazza Francesco Cangemi,1, ☏ +39 0924 9505240 , ✉ urp@pec.comune.calatafimisegesta.tp.it .</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>
<p>Calatafimi is about 60 km from Aeroporto "Falcone e Borsellino" of Palermo-Punta Raisi and 50 km from Aeroporto "Vincenzo Florio" of Trapani-Birgi (phone: +39 0923 842502).</p>

<p>From Airport Palermo-Punta Raisi, you can get the train from Punta Raisi to Alcamo Diramazione railway station (one every 30 minutes) and take a taxi from there.</p>

<head>By car</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> From <ref target="Palermo">Palermo</ref> — Through the A29 Motorway Palermo-Trapani, at Segesta exit, after passing the archaelogical area, you enter the National Road 113 (S.S.113) towards Trapani. The junction for Calatafimi is at about 3 Km.</item>
<item> From <ref target="Trapani">Trapani</ref> — Through the A29 Motorway, towards Palermo, at Segesta exit; otherwise you can go along the National Road 113 and take the junction after those for Vita and Pianto Romano.</item>
</list>


<head>By ship</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Linea Tirrenia</hi> (Cagliari-Trapani), ☏ +39 0923 545433 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Linea Grimaldi</hi> (Tunisi-Trapani), ☏ +39 0923 542470 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Linea Ustica Lines</hi> (Livorno-Trapani), ☏ +39 0923 873813 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Siremar</hi> (Isole Egadi e Pantelleria), ☏ +39 0923 24968 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Traghetti delle Isole</hi>, via Ammiraglio Staiti, 23 (<ref target="Trapani">Trapani</ref></item>
</list>

<p>). </p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ustica Lines</hi> (Aliscafo per Isole Egadi, Pantelleria, Ustica e Napoli), ☏ +39 0923 873813 .</item>
</list>


<head>By rail</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Railway Station of Alcamo Diramazione</hi> (At about 9 km from the town, near the junction Alcamo Ovest A29 Motorway). It is on the railway line Palermo-Trapani.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">AST</hi> (Azienda Siciliana Trasporti), via Virgilio, 20 Trapani (<ref target="Palermo">Palermo</ref></item>
</list>

<p>), ☏ +39 0923 21021 , fax: +39 0923 872939 . </p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Autoservizi Lumia</hi> (Agrigento-Trapani) (<ref target="Palermo">Palermo</ref></item>
</list>

<p>), ☏ +39 0922 20414 . </p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Autoservizi Salemi</hi> (Roma - Trapani) (<ref target="Palermo">Palermo</ref></item>
</list>

<p>), ☏ +39 0923 981120 . </p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Segesta autolinee</hi> (Palermo - Trapani), Via Libertà, 171 (<ref target="Palermo">Palermo</ref></item>
</list>

<p>), ☏ +39 0923 2006, +39 091 304106 , ✉ info@segesta.it . </p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Segesta autolinee</hi> (Roma - Trapani), Via Libertà, 171 (<ref target="Palermo">Palermo</ref></item>
</list>

<p>), ☏ +39 091 300556,+39 091 304106 , ✉ info@segesta.it . </p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tarantola bus</hi>, Via Marina Petrolo, 16 (Castellammare del Golfo), ☏ +39 0924 31020 , ✉ info@tarantolabus.it .</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>
<p>Owing to the particular geographical position of Calatafimi, many streets have a steep slope. Moreover, Eufemio Castle and the Church of Santissimo Crocifisso are two perfect points of reference as they are visible from different places. After going uphill for Via Segesta (take the <hi rend="italic">ingresso della cittadina</hi> if you are coming from the National Road 113), you get to largo Duca degli Abruzzi which is the right starting point for any exploration. On the left there is Via Alcide de Gasperi (an almost new area), while the main road link is corso Garibaldi, on the right. From via Marconi, an important main road which continues to Corso Vittorio Emanuele, you will arrive at piazza Plebiscito and can start an artistic tour of the town. Here you can admire the Church of Madonna di Giubino, built by Giovan Biagio Amico from Trapani, close to the 16th-century small church of the Benedictine nunnery of Santa Caterina, and, on the other side of the square, the Church of San Michele, with the Civic Library on its right. Further on, along via Marconi, you will meet the Town Hall (Palazzo Comunale), between palazzo Pampalone, where the hero of the Risorgimento (19th-century struggle for Italian unification), Garibaldi rested after the battle of Pianto Romano, and the 16th-century church of San Giuliano. From via Marconi you will arrive at piazza Nocito and, behind it, piazza Nullo. At the end of the slope, there is the mother Church of San Silvestro Papa, and, if you go on climbing, you get to the hill’s peak (338 metres high) where Eufemio Castle rises. Coming down viale Oberdan you will find the medieval quarter of Borgo (the old village), that keeps integral its environmental features inside the small streets and courtyards.</p>

<head>Taxi service</head>
<p>As the town centre of Calatafimi is quite small and its streets are narrow, there is no bus service, so you can walk, or for long distances, you can use your car or get a taxi.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="italic">Nstonline Transfer &amp; Taxi</hi>, Via Segesta, 34, ☎ +39 366 8710222.</item>
</list>


<head>Segesta archaeological site</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.regione.sicilia.it/beniculturali/SoprinTP/arche/Segesta_parco_IT.htm">Segesta</ref></hi> is the site of an ancient <ref target="Ancient%20Greece">Graeco</ref>-<ref target="Roman%20Empire">Roman</ref> city.</p>

<p>The site is immediately off the main A29 road, straight after a long tunnel if travelling from Palermo. Onsite there is free parking.</p>

<p>Tarantola Bus goes between Palermo and Calatafimi (aka Calatafimi-Segesta) a few times daily, stopping at Segesta en route. You may have a long wait for a return bus. (Perhaps confusingly, Segesta Bus does not go to Segesta.)</p>

<p>Entry to the temple is on foot - about a 5-minute uphill walk. A bus (€1.50) is available every 30 minutes to the site of the Amphitheatre at the top of the hill. It's a brisk, uphill, 20-minute walk otherwise (no entrance fee). Coffee and pizza are well deserved at the cafe near the car park if you walked to the amphitheatre.</p>

<p>There are 3 major sights at this location, and there are other remains from the Roman and medieval periods which are documented by signs in five languages across the site.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Doric temple</hi>, Archaelogical area of Segesta. Built between 430-420 BCE, 61 m (190 feet) long, 26 m wide, built upon a platform of 4 steps, it has 36 Doric columns supporting the stone roof-frame of the structure (14 columns along the lengths of the building, 6 columns across front and back). They are of a "rough" finish as the temple has never been completed. The temple seems also to have lacked a roof over the cella (main chamber) in antiquity, rather uniquely - scholars are in disagreement as to whether the temple was planned this way, or just never completed. Entry is charged.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Greek Amphitheatre</hi>. It is on a hilltop and was built by the Greeks at about 400 BC. It was discovered in the 19th century. They play classical comedies and tragedies in July and August.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Greek sanctuary</hi>, contrada Mango (on the Provincial Road leading to Segesta). In the archaeological area of Segesta there are the remains of an ancient sanctuary, dating back perhaps to the 6th century BC and built outside the town centre of Segesta.</item>
</list>
</text>
