<text id="autogum_voyage_doc22" title="Pensacola Beach" shortTile="pensacola-beach" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27238" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pensacola Beach</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.visitpensacolabeach.com/">Pensacola Beach</ref></hi> is a city in <ref target="West%20Florida">West Florida</ref> on Santa Rosa Island, a 40-mile barrier island.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Pensacola Beach is an independent community from its neighbor, <ref target="Pensacola">Pensacola</ref>. It is unincorporated and administered by Escambia County. The eight and one-quarter square miles of land that comprise Pensacola Beach was originally owned by the United States Department of the Interior, but was deeded to Escambia County in 1947, on the condition that the land would never be sold. As a result, there are no property owners in the community, only long-term leaseholders. There is some antipathy between mainland residents and Pensacola Beach leaseholders over tax issues related to the unique situation.</p>

<p>During the city of Pensacola's early history, Indian attacks forced the fledgling settlement to relocate from the mainland to Pensacola Beach, near modern day Fort Pickens, in 1722. Although this protected the settlers from attack, it left them highly exposed to hurricanes, which eventually forced them back to the mainland in 1752.</p>

<p>Most of Pensacola Beach and Santa Rosa Island's modern history began with Fort Pickens, completed in 1834 and used continually until after World War II. In 1971, the coastal land east and west of the community, still owned by the United States government, was designated part of the <ref target="Gulf%20Islands%20National%20Seashore">Gulf Islands National Seashore</ref>.</p>

<head>Visitor information</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pensacola Beach Visitor Information Center</hi>, 7 Casino Beach Boardwalk, ☏ + 1 850 932-1500 .</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>
<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.flypensacola.com">Pensacola International Airport</ref></hi> is 10 miles north of Pensacola Beach and is served by six airlines.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>From Pensacola, take the Pensacola Bay Bridge to Gulf Breeze, and turn right at the giant Pensacola Beach swordfish sign, seen in the photo above. There's a small toll of $1 to enter the community.</p>

<p>From <ref target="Navarre">Navarre Beach</ref> and points east, follow Hwy 98 to Gulf Breeze, then take the onramp to Pensacola Beach Rd.</p>

<p>J. Earle Bowden Way is a scenic beach road that connects Pensacola Beach with Navarre Beach. It's a backdoor route into Pensacola Beach, with no toll. The speed limit is restricted to 35 mph, and the road quality is poor.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
 <hi rend="bold">ECAT</hi>, 1515 W Fairfield Dr, ☏ +1 850 595-3228 . M-Sa 7:55AM-5:15PM, Su closed, exact times depend on route. Based in Pensacola, ECAT sends one bus to Pensacola Beach, twice a day. From Pensacola, you can board the bus either at the main transfer center, on Fairfield Dr, or from the Park -n- Trolley parking lot downtown, underneath the I-110 overpass, across from the Pensacola Civic Center. The bus to Pensacola Beach leaves the transfer center at 7:55AM, and leaves the Park -n- Trolley at 8AM; it arrives at the Pensacola Beach visitor center at 8:20AM. The bus back to Pensacola leaves the Visitor Center at 4:30PM, and arrives at 5:10PM. $2.35 one-way.. 
<head>By bicycle</head>
<p>Some hotels on the island offer bicycle rentals for their guests, but if you're not staying on the island, you'll have to bring your own bike. If you're taking the ECAT bus to the island, you can bring your bike on one of their bicycle racks. A bicycle is a great way to get around the island quickly while still taking time to see the sights and enjoy the sun. And if you get tired of cycling around, the free beach trolleys on the island are equipped with bike racks, so you can give your legs a rest. For visitors to Fort Pickens, a bicycle is the next-best option to renting a boat; you can ride most of the seven miles to the fort along the broken road, although there is a half-mile of sand you'll have to walk across.</p>

<head>By boat</head>
<p>Pensacola Beach is easy to explore by boat. <hi rend="bold">Boat rentals</hi> are available on the island, or from Pensacola and Gulf Breeze, and you have a wide variety of craft to choose from. Kayaks, parasails, motorboats, sailboats, yachts, pontoon boats and waverunners are all available for rent. If you own your own boat, there are plenty of marinas and docks around the island, which offer short-term, overnight, and long-term mooring. Your hotel, if you're staying at the island, might even pick up the tab. From Pensacola Beach, it's just a short boat ride to the cities of Pensacola, Gulf Breeze, or Navarre. Just remember, the Escambia County Sheriff's Office does have <hi rend="bold">police boats</hi> patrolling the water, and they won't hesitate to pull you over for unsafe boating. Drinking while boating is a big no-no here, and there is a zero tolerance policy for violators.</p>

<p>If you don't have the skill or the will to captain your own boat, you can <hi rend="bold">charter a boat.</hi> This can be expensive, running up to $200 an hour, but it's a great way to deep sea fish or scuba dive. Due to the closing of Fort Pickens Road, many boat captains are offering reduced rates for visitors to Fort Pickens; these usually start around $25 a person. Some of the more expensive resorts on the island offer <hi rend="bold">complimentary boat taxis,</hi> which will take you to the popular beaches, the boardwalk, or across Santa Rosa Sound to golf resorts in Gulf Breeze.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Santa Rosa Island is a narrow, elongated island. The two main roads, which run along the island's length, are Fort Pickens Road and Via de Luna Drive.</p>

<p>Parking lots are available all over the island, and parking is free and plentiful. However, on exceptionally busy weekends, the main parking lot for the Portofino Boardwalk and Casino Beach may fill up. There's usually alternate parking available at the hotels or restaurants. Resist the urge to park along the side of the road; the fine sand on the beaches can easily ensnare cars. There is <hi rend="italic">no vehicle access to Fort Pickens or Opal Beach.</hi> There's a parking lot just outside the entrance gates, but if you want to any further, you'll have to hoof it, or find another way.</p>

<head>By foot</head>
<p>Most of the attractions of Pensacola Beach can be visited by foot, and Casino Beach is conveniently close to all the major restaurants, shopping, hotels, and the Portofino Boardwalk. Sidewalks are available on most (but because of storm damage, not <hi rend="italic">all</hi>) of the island.</p>
</text>
