<text id="autogum_voyage_doc499" title="Aragua" shortTile="aragua" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=1433" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Aragua</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Aragua</hi> is a state in north central <ref target="Venezuela">Venezuela</ref>. It is famous for its fertile valleys and beautiful beaches, and is within easy reach of Caracas</p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> (<hi rend="bold">Capital</hi>)</item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> - a fascinating town hidden in the mountains outside Caracas, still populated by descendents of a colony of German settlers who built the town from scratch in the 19th century. Today, the town is a popular weekend escape for Caraqueños who enjoy its cool climate, restaurants serving traditional German food and locally brewed beer. Locally grown produce such as strawberries and raspberries are also sold.</item>
<item> - probably Venezuela's most popular beach destination for foreign travellers with a great after dark atmosphere, plenty of restaurants and <hi rend="italic">posadas</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cata</hi> - together with neighbouring Catica, this is another good Aragua beach resort in a beautiful bay, albeit somewhat spoiled by the construction of two tall apartment buildings just behind the beach.</item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Henri Pittier National Park</hi> - Venezuela's first national park, covering the mountains that separate Maracay from the coast. Cloudforest and plenty of wildlife.</item>
</list>


<head>Get in</head>
<p>Buses from the Caracas La Bandera bus terminal go to Maracay (1.5 hours) and La Victoria (1 hour). Change at Maracay for buses to Choroni (2 hours).</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>A railway linking Aragua with Caracas is under construction but all travel at present is by road. A fast highway runs the length of the state.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Santa Teresa Rum</hi> (</item>
</list>

<p>It is located in the village of El Consejo, close to <ref target="La%20Victoria">La Victoria</ref> ). This excellent family owned rum plantation is open to the public at weekends, with tours and a tasting session. It is the home of arguably Venezuela's best rum, the "1796" brand, which is carefully aged in oak barrels. </p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rancho Grande Biological Station</hi> (From <ref target="Maracay">Maracay</ref>, take the road to Ocumare-Limon and the station is about 45 minutes outside the city, on the right hand side just after the Rancho Grande Restaurant (which only usually opens at weekends). Buses to Ocumare leave from Maracay's bus terminal, and ask the driver to drop you off at Rancho Grande.</item>
</list>

 ), ☏ +58 243 5507085 . This ecological research post is run by Venezuela's prestigious Central University, hidden in the <ref target="Henri%20Pittier%20National%20Park">Henri Pittier National Park</ref>.

<head>Do</head>
<p>Hang gliding is offered close to La Colonia Tovar, on the road down towards La Victoria.</p>

<head>Eat</head>

<p>The Hacienda Santa Teresa's <hi rend="bold">Zafra</hi> restaurant, in El Consejo, is open weekends until sundown, offering interesting variations of traditional Venezuelan dishes with a rum theme, as well as international dishes.</p>

<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel El Recreo</hi>, ☏ +58 244 3210244 . Av Intercomunal, La Victoria. A converted colonial era farm, this pleasant hotel is a lovely retreat with a good terrace restaurant and swimming pool. Certainly the best option in La Victoria.</item>
</list>
</text>
