<text id="autogum_voyage_doc126" title="Sharm el-Sheikh" shortTile="sharm-elsheikh" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=32394" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sharm el-Sheikh</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Sharm el-Sheikh</hi> (<ref target="Arabic%20phrasebook">Arabic</ref>: شرم الشيخ, also transliterated as <hi rend="italic">Sharm ash Shaykh</hi> and popularly known simply as "Sharm") is a well-known port and resort town at the southern tip of the <ref target="Sinai">Sinai</ref> Peninsula in <ref target="Egypt">Egypt</ref>, popular with package holiday makers and divers. </p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Sharm el-Sheikh is one of the most popular tourist destinations in the Arab world. But there are also some very good reasons to visit it if you are not the common tourist, who likes to lie on the beach all day. It is one of the <hi rend="bold">finest diving spots</hi> in the world and a trip into the desert is an unforgettable adventure.</p>

<p>The Sinai Peninsula is a remote desert mountain range. The rocky mountains are parted from the deep-blue sea by a flat desert strip. This combination of desert and sea is an incredible sight and makes you believe you are on a different planet.</p>

<p>Sharm el-Sheikh used to be nothing but a small fishing village with about 100 Bedouin citizens. When Sinai was occupied by Israel in 1967, Sharm el-Sheikh started to develop as a tourist destination (like the rest of the peninsula). The Israelis evacuated Sinai between 1979 and 1982 following the signing of a peace agreement between the two countries. Since the 1980s, the Egyptians have been continuing the development of Sharm where the Israelis left off. Sharm's 100 grew into a bustling 10,000 population. There is now a nice promenade, a Hard Rock Cafe, one of the most modern hospitals in Egypt and so on.</p>

<head>Climate</head>



<p>The climate is very dry. Rainfall is very rare. The weather is very hot in summer days and moderately hot at summer nights. In winter, it is warm at days and has one of the warmest night temperatures in Egypt.</p>

<p>The most comfortable time to visit Sharm El-Sheikh are late summer and beginning of the fall. For example in September the air temperature is about 34 °C and water is about 29 °C.</p>

<head>Orientation</head>
<p>The Na'ama Bay part of the city is the center of nightlife and dining: most of Sharm's clubs, cafes, restaurants and shops are here. Na'ama Bay lies midway between Sharm Airport and Old City, nearly 10 minutes driving from each. </p>

<p>Microbuses can take you from downtown, but to reach Na’ama Bay from the airport, you will have to take a cab.</p>

<p>Sharm el Sheikh has grown into three distinct areas now, Nabq is a new area to the north of Na'ama, Old Market and Hadaba to the south of Na'amaa Bay.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>See <ref target="Sinai">Sinai</ref> for information on the Sinai visit pass, which allows visa-free travel for up to 14 days.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sharm el-Sheikh Airport</hi> ( SSH ). The largest airport in the Sinai, it receives plane-loads of charter tourists daily in the winter high season. The principal airline for local flights is <ref target="http://www.egyptair.com.eg/">EgyptAir</ref>. There are 2 terminals that are next to each other. Terminal 1 is the new one with Egypt Air and Easy Jet. You will need a visa only if you plan to go out of the Sharm area (such as Ras Mohammed bus or boat, Cairo, St Catherine's). It can be bought on arrival (price seems to vary day to day, make sure you have £15, US$15, or €15 handy. </item>
</list>


<p>For departures: timetable shows only nearest 1-2 hours, makes you watch over the row of check-in desks for your flight number.</p>

<head>Airport cafes</head>

<p>Cafes after security check are: <hi rend="bold">Sbarro</hi> (overcrowded), <hi rend="bold">Cafe Europa</hi> (on the back of the lounge, less crowded): sandwiches, coffee, Egyptian sweets; outlet of <hi rend="bold">Caffè Ritazza</hi> international chain coming soon (also in Athens, Budapest, Madrid, Milan, London, Paris, New York, Stockholm, Zurich, Vienna).</p>

<head>Shops in the airport</head>
<p>After security check: <hi rend="bold">Patisserie</hi> offers lucums, khalva and other Egyptian sweets.</p>

<head>By boat</head>

<p>Ferry services between <ref target="Hurghada">Hurghada</ref> on the mainland <ref target="Red%20Sea%20Coast">Red Sea Coast</ref> and Sharm were suspended in 2018. The high-speed catamarans used to be run by <ref target="http://www.lapespes.com/">La Pespes</ref>. </p>

 is along the southern entry road, about 1 km southeast of the old market.

<head>By car or bus</head>

<p>Sharm el-Sheikh can be reached by driving down the eastern coast from <ref target="Eilat">Eilat</ref> (<ref target="Israel">Israel</ref>) via <ref target="Nuweiba">Nuweiba</ref> and <ref target="Dahab">Dahab</ref>, or via the western coast from <ref target="Cairo">Cairo</ref>. There are daily buses for both routes. From Cairo, East Delta buses take approximately 8 hr (LE80) while Superjet buses take 6 hr. When taking the bus from Cairo, keep your bus ticket and passport handy, as you will pass through a number of checkpoints, which require passengers to present identification and ticket. The drive is interesting with beautiful scenery, throughout the route.</p>

 is removed, by about a kilometer, from the Peace road. If you should arrive during the evening hours your only option may be to take a taxi, as micro-bus service can be spotty. Since Sharm is a tourist-driven economy, you should be prepared to do some bargaining. If you are of the hiking type, the main road is, roughly, 20 minutes from main road. Just ask anyone to point you in the direction of Peace road. Once at Peace road you should have no problem hailing down a micro-bus.

<p>When heading to the bus station via micro-bus along Peace Road, tell the driver that you are going to the bus station, and want to be left off at the gas station. This may take some work, given the limited English skills of the drivers. Once at the gas station, you should see micro-buses, which will take you on the final leg. Remember, transfers are not issued, you must pay another fee for the final leg.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">About micro-bus fees</hi> If your journey is within a kilometer or two, the cost should be about (LE3-5). If your stop is further out, or if you are traveling during the late night hours, be prepared to get a demand for more money, in some cases drivers may demand up to (LE10-20). Demands for higher fees can also take place, if the driver feels he you have money! So, be prepared to negotiate. If the driver's fee is unreasonable, get out — this will often bring down the cost. When arriving, ask a local how much the bus costs before hailing one down. The information provided will give you a base-line price, from which you can bargain with.</p>
</text>
