<text id="autogum_voyage_doc5" title="Fionnphort" shortTile="fionnphort" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11626" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fionnphort</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Fionnphort</hi> is a small port at the far west of the Ross of <ref target="Mull">Mull</ref>, where the ferry crosses to <ref target="Iona">Iona</ref>. It lacks accommodation - this can be found in <hi rend="bold">Bunessan</hi> five miles east, so facilities there are also described on this page.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>A849 runs west from <ref target="Craignure">Craignure</ref> which has a ferry from Oban on the mainland; and Oban has buses and trains from Glasgow. The road follows the shore of Loch Scridain to Bunessan (30 miles) and Fionnphort (another 5 miles). </p>

<p>Bus 96 / 496 meets the ferries at Craignure and runs four times M-Sat and once on Sunday to , taking 70 mins. Here it connects with the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.calmac.co.uk">ferry to Iona</ref></hi> which sails roughly hourly 08:30-18:15, but on demand in summer, taking 10 mins. Adult single ferry fare is £1.75, bikes are free, visitors' cars are not permitted. Fionnphort ferry terminal has toilets and a small waiting room and snack bar. </p>

<p>Buses and ferries are held to make these connections but in bad weather, Fionnphort is exposed to the Atlantic and ferries may be cancelled for days on end. Ferry staff will advise non-residents against crossing to Iona if the forecast is bad.</p>

<p>There are two car parks in Fionnphort. There's a pay &amp; display car park by the ferry pier; current charges unknown but the Council are proposing £9 / day for summer 2019. A quarter mile further back in the village, turn into the lane south for the Columba Centre car park, free, but it's small and fills up quickly in summer.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>You'll want your own wheels between Bunessan and Fionnphort, since the bus is infrequent.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Iona">Iona</ref></hi> can easily be done as a day trip but deserves longer.</item>
<item> is a tiny village 2 miles north of Fionnphort. It has a nice sheltered beach when the tide drops, suitable for children's bathing, but at high tide the beach is completely covered.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ardalanish Isle of Mull Weavers</hi>, Bunessan PA67 6DR, ☏ +44 1681 700265 . Apr-mid Oct daily 10:00-17:00, mid Oct-mid Dec &amp; mid Jan-March M-F 10:00-16:00. Farm, knitwear and gift shop, and you can tour the weaving mill. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ross Of Mull Historical Centre</hi> (Ionad Echdraidh an Rois Mhuilich), Millbrae Cottage, Bunessan PA67 6DG, ☏ +44 1681 700659 . Apr-Oct M-F 10:00-16:00. It's really a local history archive and research centre rather than a museum. Free.</item>
<item> Boat trips to on the island of Staffa, and the , may pick up from Fionnphort and Iona.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The best beach is on the south coast at Ardalanish: follow lane from village.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Become a Monk or Nun</hi>. There are two religious retreats here, not open for casual visits:</item>
<item> <ref target="Bird%20watching">Bird watching</ref> both on land and on the boat trips.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Spar</hi> (Convenience Store), Post Office Stores, Bunessan PA67 6DG, ☏ +44 1681 700395 . M-Sa 08:00-18:00, Su 10:00-16:00. The only proper store in the Ross of Mull, and the last chance to stock up before crossing to Iona. Good selection of food and other essentials, with off-license. More expensive than the mainland but decent value for such a remote spot. Also incorporates the local Post Office.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ninth Wave</hi>, Bruach Mhor (Half a mile east of Fionnphort, watch for sign, turn north into lane), ☏ +44 1681 700757 . May-Jun &amp; mid-July-Oct W-Su 19:00-23:00. Seafood dinners, licensed, booking essential.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Keel Row</hi>, ☏ +44 1681 700458 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Creel Seafood Bar</hi>, Fionnphort Pier, PA66 6BL, ☏ +44 1681700312 . It's a seafood takeaway in a cabin by the pier.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>
<p>Argyll Arms has the only public bar.</p>

<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> is 2 miles south of Fionnphort. It's open May-Sept, with basic pitches by the shore and portacabin showers &amp; toilets, tel +44 1681 700427.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Seaview Bed and Breakfast</hi>, ☏ +44 1681 700235 . Comfy friendly place close to the ferry pier. They also let The Bothy for self-catering by the week. B&amp;B double from £100.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://www.holidayisleofmull.co.uk">Caol-Ithe</ref></hi> does B&amp;B and self-catering lets.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://catcheancaravans.co.uk">Catchean Caravans</ref></hi> are static for self-catering let by the week, Sat-Sat; they don't have tourer pitches.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Staffa House</hi>, ☏ +44 1681 700677 . B&amp;B with four bedrooms en suite. B&amp;B double £90.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ardachy House</hi>, Ardalanish, Bunessan PA67 6DS (1.5 miles south of Bunressan on Ardalanish Bay), ☏ +44 1681 700505 , ✉ info@ardachy.co.uk . Check-in: 16:00, check-out: 10:00. New owners in 2019 but still in business, 3-star B&amp;B in modern building. B&amp;B double £90.</item>
<item> There's also B&amp;B at <ref target="https://www.mull-holidays-iona.co.uk">Newcrofts</ref> south of Fionnphort and <ref target="http://www.isleofmullholidays.com">Ardness House</ref> a couple of miles west.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Argyll Arms Hotel</hi>, Bunessan PA67 6DP, ☏ +44 1681 700240 , ✉ argyllarmshotel@isleofmull.co.uk . Hotel open Apr-Sept, restaurant and bar open all year daily. B&amp;B double from £80.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Beach House Self Catering</hi>, Lower Ardtun, Bunessan, ☏ +44 131 669-3082 . Check-in: 16:00, check-out: 11:00. Beach House is a restored farmhouse looking over Loch Scridain, half way between Bunessan and Pennyghael. (The name is Gaelic <hi rend="italic">be-ach</hi>, bees, not beach which would be <hi rend="italic">traigh</hi>.) The holiday home sleeps 8, let Sunday to Sunday. No availability however during 2019. £1000 / week.</item>
<item> Plus a couple of self-catering cottages in Bunessan.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Take the short ferry crossing to <ref target="Iona">Iona</ref>.</item>
<item> Reaching the rest of Mull is usually via <ref target="Craignure">Craignure</ref>, but there's a lane along the coast via Dhiseig and Gruline to <ref target="Salen">Salen</ref>.</item>
</list>
</text>
