<text id="autogum_voyage_doc122" title="Halberstadt" shortTile="halberstadt" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13900" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Halberstadt</head>


<p>A town in the northern foothills of the <ref target="Harz%20Mountains">Harz Mountains</ref> of central Germany, <ref target="http://www.halberstadt.de/en/"><hi rend="bold">Halberstadt</hi></ref> is known as <hi rend="italic">The Gateway to the Harz Mountains</hi> and retains many important historic buildings.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Halberstadt, a town of about 50,000 people, is only a few minutes by car from the mountains and travellers are welcomed from afar by the impressive towers of the 1200-year old Bishop`s Seat. The town was severely damaged in World War II, but retains many important historic buildings and much of its ancient townscape. Notable places in Halberstadt include the Liebfrauenkirche and St. Stephen Cathedral, churches built in the 12th and 13th centuries, respectively. Halberstadt is the site of the first documented large, permanent pipe organ installation in 1361. The cathedral is notable among those in northern European towns in having retained its medieval treasury in virtually complete condition. Among its treasures are the oldest surviving tapestries in Europe, dating from the 12th century.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>The closest airports with international flights are Leipzig/Halle ( LEJ ) near <hi rend="italic">Schkeuditz</hi> and <ref target="Hanover%23By%20plane">Hanover Airport</ref> ( HAJ ) both airports are connected to their respective towns by S-Bahn and from there you can take regional trains to Halberstadt; for Hanover change in <ref target="Goslar">Goslar</ref> and for Leipzig/Halle change in <ref target="Halle">Halle</ref>. Leipzig Halle Airport is also served by some long distance trains, enabling a change in <ref target="Magdeburg">Magdeburg</ref></p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>There are frequent daily direct connections to <hi rend="bold">Magdeburg</hi> <hi rend="italic">approximately 40 minutes</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Halle</hi> <hi rend="italic">approximately 1 hour 30 minutes</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Hanover</hi> <hi rend="italic">approximately 2 hours</hi>. Trains can be booked via <ref target="http://www.bahn.de">the DB website</ref>.</p>

<head>By road</head>
<p>Halberstadt is served by both the <hi rend="bold">B79</hi> and the <hi rend="bold">B81</hi> which provide access from all directions and lead to the main regional road <hi rend="bold">B6</hi> to the south. The B6 in turn, leads north west to the <hi rend="bold">A395</hi> and Braunschweig, or east to the <hi rend="bold">A14</hi> which goes north towards Magdeburg or south to Halle and Leipzig.</p>

<head>By tram</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Halberstadt has around 9.5km of tram track which form two tram routes around town. These trams can be accessed from any one of around 30 tram stops and used to travel around the area for a small charge.<ref target="http://www.stadtverkehr-halberstadt.de/">Timetables</ref>.</item>
</list>


<p><hi rend="bold">TIP:</hi> The <ref target="http://www.nasa.de/index.php%3Fid%3D66">www.insa.de <hi rend="italic">HarzTourCard</hi></ref> enables you to travel by bus, train and narrow gauge train (only Schierke–Brocken) as much as you like within three days. It costs €18, family: €34,50 from the local tourist information or website.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Halberstadt has 5 bus routes which cover the whole area and are available for use by visitors and locals alike for a small charge. Timetable and prices also at the above website.</item>
</list>


<head>By historical tram</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Historische Straßenbahnen</hi>, Hinter dem Rathause 6, ☏ +49 3941 551815 , fax: +49 3941 551089 . A 1939 Tram with 40 seats can be booked for a 1 hour tour of the town for €129. This must be pre booked on the website.</item>
</list>


<head>Museums</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Berend Lehmann Museum</hi>, Bakenstraße 57, ☏ +49 3941 583238 . Tu-Th 12:00-18:00, F-Sa 12:00-22:00, Su 12:00-17:00. Established in 2001, on the 300th Anniversary of the Prussian state, this museum is concerned with German-Jewish history and in particular the difficult periods of Prussian-Jewish history. There is also a café on site for refreshments.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gleimhaus Halberstad</hi>, Domplatz 31, ☏ +49 3941 68710 . May-Oct Tu-F 09:00-17:00, Nov-Apr 09:00-16:00, All year Sa-Su 10:00-16:00. This Literature Museum displays the collection put together in 1862 by the poet "Johan Ludwig Wilhelm Gleim" and is a must for fans of German Poetry and Literature €3. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">DDR Museum</hi>, Karl-Liebknecht-Straße 1, ☏ +49 3084 7123731 . Su–F 10:00-20:00, Sa 10:00-22:00. Not technically part of Museum Island, but immediately adjacent, the hands-on DDR Museum, gives an upbeat look at daily life in the GDR – achieved partly by glossing over gloomy issues like censorship and repression. €6 or €4.</item>
</list>


<head>Places of Worship</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Der Halberstädter Dom St. Stephanus und St. Sixtus</hi>. M-F 10:00- 17:30, Sa-Su 11:00-17:30. The cathedral was built 1236-1491 and is considered a jewel of Gothic architecture. The two mighty towers typify renaissance and baroque building skills. It had 2 predecessors: one was the 859 Carolingian structure and the other, the 922 Otto creation. The 600 Artefacts and treasures in the cathedral's collection make up the largest and most important collection of art from the middle ages in any German church. It was severely damaged in 1945 and was restored by Halberstadt architect Walter Bolze. €8. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St. Burchardi church</hi> (Sankt-Burchardi-Kirche), Am Kloster 1. This little church has been playing a John Cage piece called <hi rend="italic">Organ²/ASLSP</hi> (<hi rend="bold">A</hi>s <hi rend="bold">SL</hi>ow a<hi rend="bold">S</hi> <hi rend="bold">P</hi>ossible) since 5 Sep 2001. The note played changes, on average, only once a year and is reckoned to be both the slowest and longest duration performance in the world since the concert is scheduled to end on 5 Sep <hi rend="bold">2640</hi>. The next date when something "exciting" happens will be 5 Sep 2020. </item>
</list>


<head>Places of Interest</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cave dwellings of langenstein</hi>, Langenstein, at the southern rim of the Harz. No Restrictions. Occupied as dwellings until 1916 these dwellings are unique within Germany. (Bring a torch) Free. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Giant Wine Barrel</hi>, In den Spiegelsbergen 6, ☏ +49 3941 583995 . Open daily from 11:00 clock Monday - Closed. Located in Jagdschloss is Halberstadts entry in the Guinness book of records, namely the oldest and largest wine barrel in the world. Holding 140,000 litres it was built 400 years ago by Michael Werner from Landau, and was entered in the Guinness book of records on 6 June 2008. The barrel can be accessed via the Spiegelsberge Jagdschloss restaurant which opens daily from 1100 hrs</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nordharzer Stadtebundtheater</hi>, Spiegelstr. 20a, ☏ +49 3941 696549 . As Per Theatre Guide. For visitors who wish to experience German Theatre. There are details on the website of a frequent and varied programme of productions and tickets can also be ordered on the website or purchased directly in the theatre As Per Theatre Guide.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sport and Freizeitzentrum</hi>, Gebrüder-Rehse-Str. 12, ☏ +49 3941 68780 . The many facilities have different timings, the website gives a full list. Halberstadt has a large sports centre which consists of a sports and fitness area, a comprehensive water park, and a large wellness and beauty centre. Sports includes squash, tennis, badminton and a climbing wall as well as a comprehensive keep fit and weight training area. Sealand has 4700 square metres of water park facilities such as pools and slides etc. Sauna land offers a range of sauna experiences and beautyland completes the set with wellness facilities on offer</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tiergarten Halberstadt</hi>, Spiegelsberge 4, ☏ +49 3941 24132 . May - Sept. Mo - So 9 - 19hrs Oct. - Apr Mo - So 9 - 17 hrs. A Family friendly park which will provide a few hours entertainment for children and animal lovers. Open all year round, its occupants include camels, raccoons, wolves, dingos, lynxes as well as domestic animals and an area where visitors can touch the tame animals and feed them. There is also an amusing animal school show for visitors</item>
</list>
</text>
