<text id="autogum_voyage_doc165" title="American football" shortTile="american-football" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=139517" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>American football</head>


<p>Although <hi rend="bold">American football</hi> (the term "football" in this article will mean American football unless otherwise noted) is played throughout the world, it is still mostly seen as "America's sport" and is the most popular sport in the <ref target="United%20States%20of%20America">United States</ref>. By far the best talent plays in the United States' National Football League (NFL), so football enthusiasts worldwide will most likely have to travel to the USA to see their idols play live, even with the occasional NFL or college football match held outside of North America. Additionally, in many areas of the country (especially those that lack top-level pro teams), there is a huge following for collegiate and even high school football—millions of adults and youth play the game so no matter where you are in North America, you aren't far from football for several months out of the year.</p>

<p>For the purposes of this article the <ref target="Canada">Canadian</ref> variety of the game—mostly played in the Canadian Football League (CFL)—will be considered the same sport, even though the differences in rules and gameplay are more than trivial.</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>Football finds its origins in <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Rugby%20football">rugby</ref></hi>, which bears some general similarities to gridiron-style football. (<ref target="Association%20football">Association football</ref>—or "soccer"—also split from rugby around the same time, albeit in a very different direction.) The first football games were played by the colleges of the Northeastern United States, with the first recognized football game taking place in 1869, soon followed by the establishment of a standard set of rules and intercollegiate play. The game closely resembled rugby, but as it evolved through the 1870s and 80s football began to break from its rugby roots, particularly with the innovation of the "line of scrimmage" and the "snap" (passing the ball backwards at the start of play). <hi rend="bold">Walter Camp</hi>, then-captain of Yale's football team and now considered the "Father of American Football", was instrumental in securing rule changes that effectively created the modern sport of football.</p>

<p>Further innovations followed in the early decades of the 20th century, such as the establishment of the forward pass and the current point system and field dimensions. During this time, the collegiate leagues established a governing body, the National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA), and the tradition of annual postseason <hi rend="bold">bowl games</hi>. The era also saw the rise of <hi rend="bold">professional football</hi>, with the 1920 creation of the National Football League, which quickly established itself as the premier professional league, but nonetheless had to fight off rival claimants to major league status during almost all of its first five decades of existence. Eventually, the NFL would come to surpass the collegiate leagues in popularity, and by the late 1960s football was the most popular sport in the United States. 1960 saw the establishment of the American Football League, a rival professional league which soon proved fierce competition for playing talent with the NFL, though the rivalry quickly came to an end when the two leagues agreed to a merger in 1966, which instituted a championship game to be played between the champions of each league: the <hi rend="bold">Super Bowl</hi>. The AFL–NFL rivalry arguably helped football surpass <ref target="Baseball%20in%20the%20United%20States">baseball</ref> in popularity and grow as a sport as the game went from 12 teams in 1959, only two of which played south of <ref target="Washington%2C%20D.C.">Washington, D.C.</ref> or west of <ref target="Chicago">Chicago</ref> (both in California), to 26 in 1970 upon completion of the merger. Both game attendance and TV ratings also grew very fast during that period of time.</p>

<p>Today, the NFL and the NCAA remain far and away the most popular football leagues in the world, with both having made attempts since the 1990s to promote football abroad, the most notable of which is the yearly NFL international series in London. The Super Bowl is the single most important game on the American sporting calendar, and perennially one of the most-watched television events every year, with hundreds of millions tuning in from around the world for the only football game they will watch until the following February.</p>

<p>Due to a number of rules that ensure competitiveness, such as the <hi rend="bold">draft</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">salary cap</hi>, or revenue sharing for TV revenue, the NFL is one of the most balanced professional sports leagues in the world and many teams have gone from championship contender to the bottom of their division or the other way round in just a few years. This makes "<hi rend="bold">dynasties</hi>" of teams appearing in and winning multiple Super Bowls in a short span of time all the more impressive, as unlike in other sports, simply outspending opponents to get the best players is not a feasible tactic.</p>

<head>Rules</head>
<p>The following is a brief overview of the basics of American football, as played in the NFL (there are some small differences in the NCAA or high school matches):</p>

<p>Football is played by two teams of <hi rend="bold">11 players</hi> on the field who face off trying to advance an elongated ellipsoid ball (often described as looking like an egg) towards the <hi rend="bold">end zone</hi> and its tall yellow <hi rend="bold">goalpost</hi>, where points can be scored. The offense has <hi rend="bold">four</hi> opportunities (called <hi rend="bold">downs</hi>) to advance the ball <hi rend="bold">10 yards</hi> ( ). Each new down begins where the preceding down ended (i.e. where the ball carrying player was "marked down" or—in the case of an incomplete pass—at the previous spot). If the 10 yards have been achieved, a new set of four downs starts. If a net distance of 10 yards has not been achieved after four downs, the offense must turn the ball over to the other team. Oftentimes, a down is synonymous with a play but if a penalty is called on the defensive, the offensive may be given extra opportunities or even an all-new first down to start over after a particularly egregious defensive infraction.</p>

<p>In very few cases will the offense risk turning the ball over on downs when they are in a disadvantageous field position; instead, they almost always elect to <hi rend="bold">punt</hi> on fourth down. Punting means kicking the ball away out of the hand towards the opposing team (much like a goalkeeper does in soccer). However, if the field position is good enough (usually within 35 yards of the end zone) a field goal will be attempted (see below).</p>
<p>Each play starts with a <hi rend="bold">snap</hi>, in which the ball is passed backwards to the <hi rend="bold">quarterback</hi>, away from the line of scrimmage. The ball may then be advanced through <hi rend="bold">passing</hi> with one forward pass (subject to some other preconditions as well) and unlimited backward passes (which are rarely used) permitted per play. Passing is almost exclusively the domain of the quarterback, who is usually the best paid and most prestigious player on the field. He is the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> team captain and guides the other offensive players. If a forward pass is not caught before it hits the ground, the referee signals an incomplete pass, the play ends ("is blown dead") and the next play begins at the spot where the previous one started. The ball may also be advanced by <hi rend="bold">running</hi> (carrying it forward) which is usually done by a <hi rend="bold">running back</hi>. The other positions on the offense are the <hi rend="bold">wide receivers</hi>, who catch forward passes; the <hi rend="bold">offensive linemen</hi>, who try to clear a space for the running back to run through and are also responsible for protecting the quarterback; and the <hi rend="bold">tight end</hi> (not always present), a larger receiver who may be called on to either catch passes or block, depending on the play call.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">defense</hi> tries to stop the offense's advance by <hi rend="bold">tackling</hi> the player that carries the ball. There are three basic defensive positions. The <hi rend="bold">defensive linemen</hi> try to prevent the offense from pushing the defense back and will try to reach the quarterback on passing plays. <hi rend="bold">Linebackers</hi>, who play behind the defensive linemen, have perhaps the broadest role. Depending on what the offense does, they may rush the passer, cover a running back or tight end on a pass pattern, or try to chase down a running back. <hi rend="bold">Defensive backs</hi>, divided into <hi rend="bold">cornerbacks</hi> who play at the edges of the defense and <hi rend="bold">safeties</hi> who play in the middle of the field, are usually assigned to a specific receiver or area and try to prevent the receivers from catching the ball or catch it themselves. If they catch it themselves, it is called an <hi rend="bold">interception</hi> and possession of the football changes to the other team. If a player who had control of the ball drops the ball, or a backwards pass or snap is not caught, it is called a <hi rend="bold">fumble</hi>. When the ball is fumbled, any player of either team may take the ball and advance it (for an exception to <hi rend="italic">that</hi> rule, found only in the NFL, see Wikipedia's article on the <ref target="w:Holy%20Roller%20%28American%20football%29%23Reaction">"Holy Roller" play</ref>). Lost fumbles and interceptions are collectively referred to as <hi rend="bold">turnovers</hi>, and one of the most important aspects in winning the game is to turn the ball over less than the opponent does. Typically a team that turns the ball over three or more times loses the game.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Scoring</hi> is done through one of three means. The most common and coveted is a <hi rend="bold">touchdown</hi>: when a player enters the opponent's end zone with the ball, or catches the ball inside the opponent's end zone. Unlike in rugby, and despite its name, touching the ball to the ground is not required. A touchdown is worth six points, and further points may be earned by either a two-point conversion (another touchdown from the two-yard line) or a single point by touchdown kick (which is similar to a field goal). As the touchdown kick is by far the preferred option and has a success rate well over 90% (in the NFL at least; in youth and amateur leagues that rate may be considerably lower), touchdowns are often perceived to be worth seven points. <hi rend="bold">Field goals</hi> are scored by kicking the ball through the yellow goalpost from a place kick, and are worth three points. A very rare drop kick can also be attempted instead of the place kick when attempting a field gold or one-point conversion, whereby the ball is dropped and immediately kicked through the goalposts on hitting the ground—only one has been successfully converted in NFL football since 1941. Least commonly, the defense can score a two-point <hi rend="bold">safety</hi> if the opposing offense is brought down within their own end zone.</p>

<p>Fouls, or <hi rend="bold">penalties</hi>, are signaled through yellow <hi rend="bold">flags</hi> which are thrown onto the field by an official. Enforcing the penalty involves placing the ball some distance forward or back, to the detriment of the offending side. Common penalties include unnecessary roughness, any type of illegal motion prior to the snap (such as a false start or crossing the line of scrimmage) and holding (grabbing a player who doesn't have the ball).</p>

<p>Each game lasts for four <hi rend="bold">quarters</hi> of 15 minutes each, although each team is allowed a limited number of <hi rend="bold">timeouts</hi> to briefly stop the clock. As the clock stops or keeps running depending on what happened in the previous play, "clock management" is one of the most crucial and complicated aspects of tactics at the highest level, particularly in the last few minutes of a half. After the first two quarters, an extended break called <hi rend="bold">half-time</hi> occurs where the two teams return to their locker rooms to recover. During this intermission, <hi rend="bold">entertainment</hi> is provided for the fans, such as a cheerleading or a marching band performance, or a pop music concert in the case of major events. When the teams return from the break, the end zones are swapped for the second half of the game.</p>

<p>As American football allows an unlimited number of substitutions, players tend to specialize in either offense or defense, and the entire team is usually substituted whenever there is a stoppage during or after a turnover. This means that touchdowns by defensive players are a rare event, and typically only occur if a pass by the offensive team is intercepted, or if a fumble by the offensive team is recovered by the defensive team in a good position. While even the NFL has a few players that play "both ways" (J. J. Watt is a commonly cited example), this is more common in youth or developmental leagues or outside North America, as some players so far outrank others in talent that the additional strain and less rest is not a deciding factor. It is more common for an otherwise defensive or offensive player to play on special teams, often in a role broadly similar to his role on scrimmage downs.</p>
</text>
