<text id="autogum_voyage_doc47" title="Abisko and Björkliden">
<head>Abisko and Björkliden</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Abisko</hi> is a village in <ref target="Norrbotten%20County">Norrbotten County</ref> and the <hi rend="italic">Lappland</hi> province in northern <ref target="Sweden">Sweden</ref>.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Abisko nationalpark</hi> is a national park around Abisko, .</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Björkliden</hi> is a resort village 7 km northwest of Abisko.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Abisko is a popular outdoor destination due to its proximity to nature and relatively easy accessibility. Abisko is near many great national parks and hosts a trailhead on the spectacular <ref target="Kungsleden">Kungsleden</ref> hiking trail; at the same time, it is on the <hi rend="italic">malmbanan</hi> railway between <ref target="Narvik">Narvik</ref> in <ref target="Norway">Norway</ref> and <ref target="Lule%C3%A5">Luleå</ref>, which means it can be reached by an overnight train from <ref target="Stockholm">Stockholm</ref> quite easily. Abisko village is around the train station "Abisko Östra". The large and well equipped hostel/hotel "Abisko turiststation" lies at the train station of the same name, 2 km further west.</p>

<p>Torneträsk, on the shore of which Abisko is located, is the sixth largest and second deepest lake of Sweden, and the largest fell lake in Scandinavia.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<head>By car</head>
<p>Abisko is 80 km east of <ref target="Narvik">Narvik</ref> and 100 km north-west of <ref target="Kiruna">Kiruna</ref>. It is easily accessible by car by the <ref target="E10%20through%20Sweden%20and%20Norway">European route E10</ref> between the two. Cars can be rented at the Tourist Office in <ref target="Kiruna">Kiruna</ref> (closed from Friday 18:00 to Monday morning).</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>There are two main airports serving Abisko:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item>1. <ref target="Narvik">Narvik</ref>/Harstad Airport in Norway, 120 km west of <ref target="Abisko">Abisko</ref>, has direct flights to/from Oslo Gardermoen (operated by SAS, Norwegian), Trondheim Værnes (operated by Norwegian, Widerøe) and Bodø (Widerøe) Airports.</item>
<item>2. Kiruna Airport, 100 km south-east of Abisko, has daily direct flights to <ref target="Stockholm%20Arlanda%20Airport">Stockholm Arlanda Airport</ref> (operated by Norwegian and SAS). It is connected to Abisko by train and buses run by "<ref target="http://www.ltnbd.se/">Länstrafiken Norbotten</ref>".</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>
<p>The two nightly trains from <ref target="Stockholm">Stockholm</ref> to <ref target="Narvik">Narvik</ref> stop in Abisko, both in the village itself (Abisko Östra) and outside the mountain station (Abisko Turiststation). One is direct, whereas the other has a change in <ref target="Boden">Boden</ref>. There are also two daily trains from <ref target="Lule%C3%A5">Luleå</ref> or <ref target="Narvik">Narvik</ref>. Timetables can be found through <ref target="http://www.samtrafiken.se/tjanster/tidtabeller/tagtidtabeller/">Samtrafiken</ref> (look for Nr. 30, Narvik-Kiruna-Boden-Luleå).</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>There is a chair lift up Nuolja mountain operating in the summer from the tourist station.</p>
<p>It also runs from 08:00 to 00:00 during the aurora season and is operated by the nearby STF hostel.</p>

<p>For moving around outside the villages, foot and ski (in season) are the main options. Roads are limited to the area along E10.</p>

<p>The Abiskojåkka delta is off limits in summer, to protect the nesting of birds.</p>

<p>There is a snowmobile route to Abiskojaure and onwards, turning back towards <ref target="Riksgr%C3%A4nsen">Riksgränsen</ref> along the border to Norway.</p>

<head>See</head>
<p>Abisko is a great place to observe <ref target="Northern%20lights">Northern lights</ref> thanks to the location within the Auroral belt and its relatively dry climate and low cloudiness. Aurora Sky Station (a part of STF Abisko Mountain Station) is located on the top of the mountain Nuolja and can be reached by a 10 min walk from STF Mountain Station and from there by a chair-lift.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aurora Sky Station</hi>, STF Abisko Mountain Station, Sweden, ☏ +46 980 402 00 , ✉ lapplandsbokning@stfturist.se . In 2013/2014 winter season: Sep 5 - Sep 28 and Nov 1 - Nov 30: Th-Sa 21:00-1:00; Guided tour: 22:00, 22:30, 23:00 and 23:30. Dec 1-Mar 30 Mon - Sun (except Dec 24 and Dec 31): 21:00-01:00; Guided tour 22:00, 22:30, 23:00 and 23:30. The night visit to the station includes return ticket by chair-lift, guided tour and an aurora watchers overall. Alternatively, an aurora photo tour with professional photographers can be arranged. Sep, Nov 625 kr, STF member: 525 kr; Dec-Mar 695 kr, STF member: 595 kr.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<p>The tourist station organises various activities throughout the year, but the real attraction is hiking on the many trails, out in the spectacular wilderness of the national parks of the area. Winter offers cross country skiing and even some alpine skiing. There is a chair lift on Nuolja and two more alpine areas nearby at Björkliden and <ref target="Riksgr%C3%A4nsen">Riksgränsen</ref>.</p>

<p>There are three (partly coinciding) long distance hiking trails from or passing Abisko. They can be used also for shorter hikes, especially Kungsleden has good infrastructure.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Kungsleden">Kungsleden</ref> (440 km), probably the best-known hiking trail is Sweden, to the south.</item>
<item> <ref target="Nordkalottleden">Nordkalottleden</ref> (800 km), the southern part of which partly coincides with Kungsleden and <ref target="Padjelantaleden">Padjelantaleden</ref> but also meanders among the Norwegian fells. To the north the trail continues via Norway, northernmost Sweden, the tripoint Sweden/Norway/Finland and <ref target="Kilpisj%C3%A4rvi">Kilpisjärvi</ref> (190 km) to <ref target="Kautokeino">Kautokeino</ref> in Norwegian <ref target="Finnmark">Finnmark</ref> (190 km more).</item>
<item> <ref target="Long%20distance%20walking%20in%20Europe">European long distance path</ref> <ref target="http://www.era-ewv-ferp.com/index.php%3Ftopmenu_id%3D29%26amp%3Bid%3D29%26amp%3Bpage_id%3D99%26amp%3Bmodule%3Dtext">E1</ref> from Italy, north of Abisko mostly coinciding with Nordkalottleden.</item>
</list>


<p>Kebnekaise, the highest mountain in Sweden, can be reached from Abisko by Kungsleden, although Nikkaluokta is closer (see <ref target="Kebnekaise%20and%20Nikkaluokta">Kebnekaise and Nikkaluokta</ref>). Kebnekaise fjällstation at the root of the mountain is the most common base for expeditions (also guided tours in season). The Singi mountain cabins (Singistugorna) at Kungsleden are another option for independent expeditions.</p>

<p>There are also other mountains in the 2,000 m (6,000 feet) range in the area.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Björkliden</hi>. A <ref target="downhill%20snowsport">downhill snowsport</ref> system.</item>
</list>

 

<head>Buy</head>
<p>There is a shop at the tourist station which caters for hikers' daily needs and also carries a selection of outdoor equipment, and some other shops:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">MakoMat</hi>, Kalle Jons Väg 1, 98107 Abisko (connected with the petrol station), ☏ +46 980-669 30 , ✉ info@abiskomackomat.se . M-Sa 10:00-17:00, Su 11:00-17:00. A shop with a petrol station and a restaurant/bar.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tjuonavagge</hi>, Abisko Östra (Inside the tourist station). Serves up great organic food, buffet style, taking inspiration from the nature around it - reindeer meat with cloudberry jam anyone?</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">MakoMat</hi>, Kalle Jons Väg 1, 98107 Abisko, ☏ +46 980-402 55 , ✉ info@abiskomackomat.se . M-Th 10:00-17:00, F-Sa 10:00-21:00, Su 11:00-19:00. The restaurant offers à la carte food and a lunch menu.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>
<p>The <hi rend="italic">Storstugan</hi> pub inside the tourist station is the friendliest place in town to go for a drink. Rather fortunate, since it's also the only place.</p>

<head>Sleep</head>
<p>There's a bed and breakfast in Abisko village, as well as some summer cottages. The tourist station has hostel, hotel and cottage accommodation available. It is run by STF, Svenska Turistföreningen; as accommodation is considerably cheaper for members it may be advisable to sign up for membership before booking. Membership is also available at the reception. There is also a camping ground – although the <ref target="right%20to%20roam">right to roam</ref> basically entitles you to sleep anywhere except in the Abisko national park or by private houses, as there are not really any cultivated lands. In the national park camping is allowed at the tourist station, at Nissonjohka and at the Abiskojaure cabins.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">STF Mountain Station Abisko</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Abisko Fjällturer</hi>, ☏ +46 980-401 03 . Lonely Planet describes it as a "backpackers delight", and few would disagree. Good-value accommodation in twin and dormitory-styles rooms. 250 kr.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Abisko Mountain Lodge</hi>, Lapportsvägen 35, ☏ +46 980 401 00 . A small hotel surrounded by cosy cabins that offers a relaxation only possible in a rustic setting. 990 kr.</item>
</list>


<p>There is a quite good network of cabins, day huts and shelters along Kungsleden, other trails and commonly used routes. Mostly there is a moderate fee for lodging (470/150 kr per person for non-members). Also camping by cabins is usually subject to a fee (giving access to the facilities, such as possibly a <ref target="sauna">sauna</ref>).</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Abiskojaure fjällstuga</hi> (13 km from Abisko along Kungsleden). Closest mountain cabins, in the other end of Abisko national park. Accommodation in dormitories. Sauna and shop.</item>
</list>


<head>Connect</head>
<p>STF Abisko (Abisko Tourist station) +46 980-402 00, <ref target="mailto:info%40abisko.nu">info@abisko.nu</ref>.</p>

<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Laponia">Laponia</ref>, several national parks and nature reserves forming a UNESCO World Heritage site, some 100 km southward</item>
<item> <ref target="Kiruna">Kiruna</ref>, the nearest city</item>
<item> <ref target="Narvik">Narvik</ref>, Norway, a port town at the end of the railway; the Narvik mountains are an important <ref target="Hiking%20destinations%20in%20Norway">hiking destination</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
