<text id="autogum_voyage_doc168" title="Santa Clarita Valley" shortTile="santa-clarita-valley" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=31359" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Santa Clarita Valley</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Santa Clarita Valley</hi> in <ref target="Southern%20California">Southern California</ref> is a region of <ref target="Los%20Angeles">Los Angeles County</ref> far to the north of Los Angeles proper.</p>

<head>Cities</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Agua Dulce</item>
<item> - A suburban community at the northern end of the valley, home to recreational Castaic Lake.</item>
<item> - The primary city of the valley, home to most of its dining and lodging options as well as the shopping of the upscale Valencia Town Center mall.</item>
<item> Stevenson Ranch</item>
<item> - A district of Santa Clarita home to Six Flags Magic Mountain, orange groves, and the CalArts university.</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> - By far the most well-known attraction in the Santa Clarita Valley, famed for its numerous roller coasters which are among the tallest and fastest in the world.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Vasquez Rocks</hi> - A unique rock formation outside Agua Dulce where many movies and television shows have been filmed, including <hi rend="italic">The Flintstones</hi>, <hi rend="italic">24</hi>, and several episodes of the original <hi rend="italic">Star Trek</hi> television series.</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>

<p>The Santa Clarita Valley rests between the Golden State Freeway (<ref target="Interstate%205">Interstate 5</ref>) and the Antelope Valley Freeway (State Hwy 14), with new growth swelling beyond these borders. The valley is home to a lot of recent suburban development amidst some fairly rural landscape, enough so that the valley's farmland and surrounding hills have frequently stood in for rural and Old West locations in Hollywood films. The hills above the valley are wild enough to be home to bears, mountain lions, coyotes and other wild animals. The <ref target="Pacific%20Crest%20Trail">Pacific Crest Trail</ref> runs right through the Santa Clarita Valley.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>The closest major airport is located in <ref target="Burbank">Burbank</ref>, south of the Santa Clarita Valley in the <ref target="San%20Fernando%20Valley">San Fernando Valley</ref>, with the more distant <ref target="Los%20Angeles%20International%20Airport">LAX</ref> serving as a major international hub. </p>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="Interstate%205">Interstate 5</ref></hi> is the primary route in and out, traversing the length of the valley from Los Angeles and the San Fernando Valley to the south and continuing north through <ref target="The%20Grapevine">The Grapevine</ref> and on into the <ref target="San%20Joaquin%20Valley">San Joaquin Valley</ref>. CA-14, the Antelope Valley Freeway, traverses the Soledad Pass between Santa Clarita and the <ref target="Antelope%20Valley">Antelope Valley</ref> to the east.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.metrolinktrains.com/">Metrolink</ref></hi> Antelope Valley Line passes through the Santa Clarita Valley on its way to the Antelope Valley, making three stops in Santa Clarita (Newhall, Santa Clarita, and Via Princessa) and offering a direct rail connection to Burbank, Glendale, and Union Station in <ref target="Los%20Angeles/Downtown">Downtown Los Angeles</ref>. The service is geared towards weekday commuters, although there is some evening and weekend service.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Driving is the primary means of getting around, seeing as this is a very suburban and rural region. <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.santaclaritatransit.com/">Santa Clarita Transit</ref></hi> offers a limited degree of public transit around the developed portion of the valley, with several routes spurring out of the McBean Regional Transit Center at Valencia Blvd and McBean Parkway, across from the Valencia Town Center. Routes 5/6 and 4/14 link the transit center to the Newhall Metrolink station, while Routes 3/7 link the transit center to Six Flags Magic Mountain.</p>

<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The <hi rend="bold"><ref target="San%20Fernando%20Valley">San Fernando Valley</ref></hi> lies to the south and is famed as the home of many of the largest Hollywood film studios, including Disney, Warner Brothers, and Universal with its associated Universal Studios theme park.</item>
<item> The arid landscape of the <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Antelope%20Valley">Antelope Valley</ref></hi> lies to the northeast on the other side of the mountains, via CA-14.</item>
</list>
</text>
