<text id="autogum_voyage_doc414" title="Irish phrasebook" shortTile="irish-phrasebook" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=15734" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Irish phrasebook</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Irish</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Gaeilge</hi>) is one of the three Goidelic languages, the others being <ref target="Scottish%20Gaelic%20phrasebook">Scottish Gaelic</ref> and <ref target="Manx%20Gaelic%20phrasebook">Manx</ref>. This Goidelic branch together with the Brythonic branch (Welsh, Cornish and Breton) form the Celtic language family. These are spoken in parts of <ref target="Ireland">Ireland</ref>, the <ref target="United%20Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref> and <ref target="France">France</ref>. Irish is compulsory in schools in the <ref target="Ireland">Republic of Ireland</ref>, but spoken as a first language only by a minority of the Irish population. It is also taught in Catholic schools in <ref target="Northern%20Ireland">Northern Ireland</ref>, but is in general much rarer than in the Republic. Practically all native Irish speakers are also able to speak English, so learning Irish is not necessary to communicate. That said, many place names and personal names are in Irish, so at the very least, knowledge of Irish pronunciation is useful for getting around and meeting people.</p>

<p>Some common features of the Celtic languages which strike learners as odd are:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> 'mutations': sounds change, often at the beginning of words, as part of the grammar, e.g. <hi rend="italic">cat</hi> 'cat', but <hi rend="italic">mo chat</hi> 'my cat'</item>
<item> the verb is usually at the beginning of the sentence</item>
<item> prepositional pronouns that are conjugated, e.g. <hi rend="italic">agam</hi> 'at me', <hi rend="italic">agat</hi> 'at you', etc.</item>
</list>


<head>Pronunciation guide</head>

<p>There are three major dialects in Irish, named for the three provinces in the north (Ulster, major cities Derry and Belfast), west (Connacht, major city Galway) and south (Munster, major cities Cork, Limerick, Waterford) of the island. The eastern province, (Leinster, major cities Dublin, Kilkenny), no longer has its own distinct dialect. The Caighdeán Oifigiúl (kaigh-DAWN iffig-OOL, official standard) has been in place since the mid-20th century after spelling was 'regularised' (to an extent). This is the official Irish that appears in phrasebooks and in Government publications. It is largely the same as the Munster dialect, with a very few exceptions. There are great differences in pronunciation between the dialects, with Munster differing the most from the other two. For example 'tá go maith', 'yes indeed' is pronounced 'TAY guh MAIGH' in Ulster but 'TAW guh MAH' in Connacht and Munster. There are also differences in the phrases used in everyday speech. In the phrasebook below, the Munster phrase has been used except where indicated. The conjugation of verbs, too, differs from dialect to dialect. Munster uses a contracted form in the past and present first person and in the third person of all three tenses. For example 'tá mé' ('TAW MAY', I am) is 'táim' ('TAW'm') in Munster, and 'bhí mé' (VEE MAY, I was) is 'bhíos' (VEE-us) in Munster. </p>

<head>Vowels</head>
<p>These are the pronunciations of the vowels when stressed (stress with word-initial). Unstressed short vowels (not marked with an accent) are generally pronounced like an 'uh' sound.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> a : like 'o' in "cod"</item>
<item> á : like 'aw' in "flaw"</item>
<item> e : like 'e' in "peg"</item>
<item> é : like 'ay' in "hay"</item>
<item> i : like 'i' in "tin"</item>
<item> í : like 'ee' in "heel"</item>
<item> o : like 'u' in "bud"</item>
<item> ó : like 'o' in "home"</item>
<item> u : like 'u' in "bud"</item>
<item> ú : like 'oo' in "cool"</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> note: vowel combinations/diphthongs in Irish (e.g. 'G<hi rend="bold">aei</hi>lge, 's<hi rend="bold">ea</hi>cht<hi rend="bold">ai</hi>n) are slightly rounded and pronounced in the back of the mouth without using the lips at all. (e.g. 'Gaeilge' should not, strictly speaking, be pronounced with a w after the g.) Thus, correct pronunciation can be obtained only from imitating spoken Irish, but the pronunciation guide given here is an adequate enough approximation in that by using it, you will be perfectly understood by any Irish speaker.</item>
</list>


<head>Consonants</head>
<p>Consonant combinations with <hi rend="italic">h</hi> are sometimes written with a dot (séimhiú, shay-VOO) on the letter instead of the <hi rend="italic">h</hi> and are sometimes silent. All consonants have two versions called <hi rend="italic">caol</hi> (narrow, palatalized) and <hi rend="italic">leathan</hi> (wide, velarized) (except for h, which is neither palatalized or velarized); this is indicated in writing by adjacent vowels.</p>

<p>As a rule, if the nearest vowel is <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, <hi rend="italic">o</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">u</hi>, the consonant is broad. If the nearest vowel is <hi rend="italic">e</hi> or <hi rend="italic">i</hi>, it is slender. </p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> b : like <hi rend="bold">b</hi>ed</item>
<item> bh : like W sound when broad; like a V sound when slender</item>
<item> c : like <hi rend="bold">k</hi>id when broad; like the <hi rend="italic">ty</hi> in Hungarian when slender (does not occur in English)</item>
<item> ch : as is Scottish 'loch' when broad; like <hi rend="bold">h</hi>igh or German <hi rend="italic">ich</hi> when slender</item>
<item> d : like <hi rend="bold">d</hi>og but sometimes slightly softer, like the Icelandic ð or <hi rend="bold">th</hi> in <hi rend="bold">th</hi>em, often like the English 'j' when followed by an 'e' or 'i'</item>
<item> dh : voiced <hi rend="italic">h</hi> sound when broad, <hi rend="italic">y</hi> when slender; sometimes vague <hi rend="italic">gh</hi> sound (Munster dialect especially), always silent after long vowels</item>
<item> f : like <hi rend="bold">f</hi>un</item>
<item> fh : silent (except in Ulster, where it's said like an <hi rend="italic">h</hi>)</item>
<item> g : like <hi rend="bold">g</hi>o when broad; like the <hi rend="italic">gy</hi> in Hungarian when slender (does not occur in English, with the closest approximation probably being the <hi rend="italic">d</hi> in the French <hi rend="bold">d</hi>ure)</item>
<item> gh : see <hi rend="italic">dh</hi></item>
<item> h : like <hi rend="bold">h</hi>elp</item>
<item> l : like <hi rend="bold">l</hi>ean</item>
<item> m : like <hi rend="bold">m</hi>other</item>
<item> mh : same as <hi rend="italic">bh</hi> but slightly softer</item>
<item> n : like <hi rend="bold">n</hi>ice</item>
<item> ng : like si<hi rend="bold">ng</hi> when broad and word initial (follow with a broad <hi rend="italic">g</hi> otherwise); like o<hi rend="bold">ni</hi>on when slender and word initial (follow with a slender <hi rend="italic">g</hi> otherwise)</item>
<item> p : like <hi rend="bold">p</hi>ig</item>
<item> ph : like <hi rend="bold">ph</hi>one or <hi rend="bold">wh</hi>om</item>
<item> r : like <hi rend="bold">r</hi>at when broad; like <hi rend="bold">zh</hi> sound in vi<hi rend="bold">s</hi>ion when slender</item>
<item> s : like <hi rend="bold">s</hi>oon when broad; like <hi rend="italic">sheen</hi> when slender</item>
<item> sh : like <hi rend="bold">h</hi>ear</item>
<item> t : like <hi rend="bold">th</hi> in 'the', or occasionally like <hi rend="bold">t</hi> in 'tin', depending on its placement in the word; sometimes pronounced as the English 'ch' in China when slender</item>
<item> th : like <hi rend="bold">h</hi>ear</item>
</list>


<head>Common diphthongs</head>

<p>Diphthongs are generally irregular and can be learned only by experience. For example, 'ai' in "Corcaigh" (the city and county of Cork) is pronounced like the 'i' in "dig" but the 'ai' in "faic" (nothing) is pronounced like the 'a' in "hack", and the 'ai' in "haigh!" (hi!, transliteration of a loan-word) is pronounced like the 'i' in "high".</p>
</text>
