<text id="autogum_voyage_doc108" title="Dongji Islands" shortTile="dongji-islands" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=140364" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Dongji Islands</head>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">Dongji Islands</hi> are a chain of islands in the far eastern region of <ref target="Zhoushan">Zhoushan</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>The Dongji Islands are a few small islands in the far east of the Zhoushan archipelago. The small communities on these islands have recently experienced an upsurge in tourism because a movie called "The Continent" was filmed there. Still remote, the islands are far enough out to sea that the silt of the Yangtze River Delta doesn't reach the sea around them, giving them nice blue water, a rarity in this region of China.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>Take a ferry from Shenjiamen, in Zhoushan. Tickets cannot be purchased in advance. It's best to stay overnight near the ferry terminal in Shenjiamen (if facing the rows of seafood restaurants along the harbor, go left, the ferry terminal is just beyond them,) and get up early in order to get tickets during any particularly busy season. </p>

<p>Ferries will take you to Miaozihu (庙子湖). From there, you can transfer to another boat (rafted directly to the one you took to Miaozihu) to Qingbang and Dongfushan Islands. Dongfushan is the most scenic. When arriving at Miaozihu, going to shore will put you on Miaozihu island, getting on the boat attached to your own boat will take you to Qingbang and Dongfushan. The second ferry will cost an additional 40 yuan.</p>

<p>To leave Dongfushan, ask around as to when tomorrow's ferry tickets will be on sale. They generally go on sale between 6:00 and 8:00PM at the small convenience store at the "lowest" end of town, on the road back to the ferry dock. If tickets are unavailable for the ferry from Miaozihu back to Shenjiamen, get in line anyway: The ticket checkers sometimes have a wad of their own tickets which they will sell to you.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Miaozihu has taxis. </p>

<p>Dongfushan has no automobiles save a few military and construction vehicles. There is only one road, and most of the paths along the island are steep and include stone stairs, so you'll be on foot.</p>

<head>See</head>

<p>Dongfushan Island can be hiked in its entirety over about four hours, and allows great views of the surrounding ocean, as well as an abandoned village.</p>

<head>Eat</head>

<p>The various guesthouses on Dongfushan Island can prepare food for you, even if you're not staying there. Generally you can walk into the kitchen, select the seafood or vegetables you want them to cook for you, and they'll give you a price.</p>

<head>Sleep</head>

<p>The village on Dongfushan Island has numerous guesthouses which offer reasonable rates (though they increase on the weekends) and can also cook food for you for a modest price. There is also one hostel with a very relaxed atmosphere.</p>
</text>
