<text id="autogum_voyage_doc406" title="Morelia" shortTile="morelia" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=22997" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Morelia</head>

<p>With a consistent colonial-style throughout, <hi rend="bold">Morelia</hi> is one of the most beautiful cities in Mexico. It is not really on the well-trodden path of the leisure tourists and so you can walk around in comfort without fear of the bermuda shorts crowds. Morelia is the capital of the state of <ref target="Michoacan">Michoacan</ref> in <ref target="Mexico">Mexico</ref> and it is a registered UNESCO World Heritage site. There are at least two "information" booths in the area of the square. They are staffed with multilingual students who are very helpful.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Morelia is the capital city of <ref target="Michoacan">Michoacan</ref>. It serves government and many students attending school there. The central business district is very clean with plenty of places to eat and shop. Tourists are not as common here as some other areas of Mexico. You may want to load up on pesos before ordering food or trying to make a purchase, as foreign currency is not widely accepted. There are money changer stalls on the side streets off of the square.</p>

<p>It has a decent climate, nice parks to relax in, lots of places to get stuff, and very nice place over all. If you stay downtown, most of the attractions like the Cathedral, the square, museums, and shopping, are all pretty much within walking distance. Due to Morelia's location, being a college town and center of State Government, tourist are not as common as some other areas of Mexico. The People are very friendly. In the central business district, drivers use their horns 24 hours a day to excess, prodding other drivers and to give notice at the numerous blind intersections. You will get used to it, but request a room away from the street.</p>

<p>Morelia is more than just the downtown. Its outlying areas feature modern housing developments, shopping centers and parks. Tres Marias and Altozano are ultra-modern newest residential areas.</p>
<head>By bus</head>

<p>Deluxe buses serve Morelia from all parts of the Republic, and Morelia's state-of-the-art bus station, located in the northern part of the city. The bus station consists of separate terminals for first-class and second-class buses. Cost of taxi going to downtown from bus station is about 60 pesos (Jan 2018), you can buy a ticket from the kiosk inside the station and then give it to the taxi driver. It is easy to reach Morelia from either Mexico City or Guadalajara. The bus trip from Guadalajara is about <date when="2002-04-01">4 1/2</date> hours and from Mexico City is 4 hours, depending on the company. You can also reach Morelia from the United States by way of Greyhound.</p>

<head>By car</head>

<p>Morelia is accessible by a modern toll road, and is located equidistant from Guadalajara and Mexico City, is about <date when="2002-03-01">3 1/2</date> hours driving. There are plenty of gas stations along the way with restrooms and food. Be prepared with change/pesos to pay tolls the cost may vary depending of the route you take, from Mexico City is about M$500 (<ref target="Mexico%23Currency">pesos</ref>) one way. It is a very scenic trip, to say the least.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Morelia International Airport</hi> ( MLM General Francisco Mujica International Airport ). Relatively new, modern airport at the edge of town. There are daily international flights from LAX , IAH and ORD and scheduled flights from SFO , SJC , as well as commuter flights from GDL , MEX , BJX and TIJ .</item>
</list>

 

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Buses, combis and taxis form Morelia’s public transport.</p>

<p>Combis are a good way to see the smaller roads and backstreets of the city. Various destinations are usually indicated on the windshield of these mini-vans. As of November 2011, a ride within the city costs 6 pesos. Get in, grab a handle and sit down before the driver speeds off, and then give your money directly to the driver, or to someone else to pass to the driver for you (you can ask the person “Si no le molesta, por favor”, basically, “thanks, if you don’t mind”). Above your head you will find a buzzer to get out at the next corner, or you can simply ask “en la próxima ezquina, por favor” (next corner please). It is very common for people to greet other passengers when boarding, according to the time of day (“Buenos días”, “buenas tardes” or “buenas noches”).</p>

<p>Taxis are also plentiful and inexpensive, operating on zone fares. As elsewhere in Mexico, make sure to determine the price before getting into the taxi.</p>

<p>Driving in the city is not easy, but with patience you can. Drivers use their horns to excess, to prod others and at the numerous blind intersections. The Centro Histórico is plagued by lack of parking. Driving in and around Morelia differs little from driving in any urban area. However, there is an “uno y uno” protocol in place. Drivers are actually quite respectful and obey this “one and one” rule, where — in stark contrast to Mexico City — at an intersection, you do not simply charge into any space larger than 5 cm, but fall into line, with one vehicle at a time from each direction driving through the intersection.</p>

<head>See</head>

<p>There are a lot of interesting and beautiful colonial buildings to see in <hi rend="bold">Morelia</hi>, most of them are open to the public for at least part of the day. Highlights of a Morelia city tour will include:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cathedral</hi>: One of the downtown highlights is the baroque cathedral with its surrounding gardens and parks. The cathedral is enormous, covering more than 2 city blocks in area. Architectural details like the flying buttresses and tiled cupolas give it a distinctive look. The Cathedral is the site for the local “<ref target="Day%20of%20the%20Dead">Day of the Dead</ref>” celebration in early November. It is more of an experience than can be described here. Most of the activities take place after dark, make sure you have a good seat around the square at dark for the outside performance of the choir and the fireworks each night.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Casa Natal de Morelos</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Casa de Morelos</hi>: Hero of the Mexican War for Independence, native son Jose Maria Morelos y Pavon, was born, raised, and lived his life in Morelia. There are two Morelos homes in the city, and both are historical museums that chronicle Morelos and his role in shaping Mexico.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aqueduct</hi>: Running down the center of Avenida Acueducto is an enormous aqueduct built in the 17th century to bring water into the budding young city.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Santuario de Guadalupe</hi>: One of the most serenely beautiful churches in Mexico, adorned in soft pink and white with gold trim, the church is a work of art in itself. It also houses a series of 17th century oil paintings that ideologically depict the Spanish missionaries’ conquest over the “barbaric” religious traditions of the Aztecs.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Benito Juarez Zoological Park</hi> is a 250-ha (620-acre) urban oasis that is home to a 30-m (75-acre) lake and a large and diverse collection of animals, including everything from polar bears to monkeys. Kids love it! Admission costs M$12 for adults and $6 for kids. Open 7 days a week. <ref target="http://www.mexconnect.com/articles/207-morelia-land-of-adventures-for-children"></ref></item>
</list>
</text>
