<text id="autogum_voyage_doc167" title="Makati" shortTile="makati" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=20918" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Makati</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.makati.gov.ph/portal/index.jsp">Makati City</ref></hi>, also known as <hi rend="bold">Makati</hi>, lies in the heart of the vast <ref target="Metro%20Manila">Metropolis of Manila</ref>. The city is known for its upscale shopping malls with high fashion brands, restaurants, hotels and is home to many affluent Filipinos. Makati is considered to be the center of financial, commercial and economic hubs and home to the "Philippine Stock Exchange" (PSE).</p>

<head>Cost of living</head>

<p>Makati City's cost of living is significantly higher than its neighboring Filipino cities, owing primarily to its skyrocketing real estate value and relatively upscale commercial and residential selections. However, compared to other major cities of the world, Makati offers service, accommodations, and value that is not that expensive compared to other upscale cities in the world. Furthermore, bargains comparable to other Philippine cities may be found in certain areas in Makati, such as in the Makati Cinema Square, The Landmark, Cash &amp; Carry, and Guadalupe Mall, that will make a stay in Makati even for the most jaded backpackers more than economical.</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>The area of Makati City was first dismissed as worthless swampland by the Spanish conquistador Juan Miguel de Legazpi in 1571. Yet over the centuries, this small community would leave large imprints in social, economic and cultural history of the country. In 1670 it was established as a visita of Sta. Ana de Sapa under the jurisdiction of the Franciscans. The friars established two of the earliest churches in the Philippines, the Nuestra Señora de Gracia in Guadalupe and the Church of Sts. Peter and Paul in Makati, drawing pilgrims from all over the country. At the opening of the 20th century, the Americans established Fort McKinley in Makati, and in 1901, San Pedro de Makati, with a population of 2,500, was incorporated into the province of Rizal. On February 28, 1914, the Philippine Legislature passed Act 2390, shortening the name San Pedro Makati to Makati in the 1930s, the first airport, Nielson Airport, opened in what is now the Ayala Triangle. The first centrally planned community was established in the 1950s, and since the 1970s, Makati has been the undisputed financial and commercial capital, the once worthless swampland becoming prime real property. Makati has also figured prominently in the political history of the Filipino. The community was one of the cradles of the revolt against Spanish colonial rule, and following the assassination of Ninoy Aquino in 1983, the epicenter of the protest movement against the dictatorial rule of Ferdinand Marcos. On January 2, 1995, Makati became an independent city by virtue of Republic Act 7854.</p>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>The main language choice for communication in this affluent city is English, making the stays here of international travelers and businessmen a relatively enjoyable experience. A knowledge of <ref target="Filipino%20phrasebook">Filipino</ref>, the local language, will benefit any traveler.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>Makati has some of the strictest traffic rules in Metro Manila. Traffic marshals actively enforce rules. This means that you can't tell your bus to let you on or off anywhere within its route except at designated stops. Moreover, the color coding scheme is active all day unlike in other neighboring cities when they are only enforced during rush hour.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>The Line 3 elevated train has four stations along EDSA. These are the Guadalupe, Buendia, Ayala and Magallanes stations. Getting off at the Ayala Station will set you in the middle of the Ayala Centre, a complex of shopping malls and restaurants.</p>

<p>Line 3 is a quick and inexpensive way to get into the city. The cost of a ticket ranges from ₱11-14 .</p>

<head>By car</head>

<p>Two of Metro Manila's main arteries pass through Makati. The <hi rend="bold">Epifanio De los Santos Avenue</hi> (EDSA) passes along the southeast part of Makati and connects the city with Mandaluyong City and Pasay City. The <hi rend="bold">South Luzon Expressway</hi> (SLEX) runs through the western part of Makati and connects the city with Manila to the north and with southern Metro Manila. The <hi rend="bold">Skyway</hi>, an elevated highway built on top of SLEX, provides residents coming from southern Metro Manila a fast way to reach Makati. SLEX and EDSA intersect at the Magallanes Interchange, which is the most complex system of elevated roadways in Metro Manila.</p>

<p>Other major roads in Makati include <hi rend="bold">Buendia Avenue</hi> (Sen. Gil Puyat Avenue), which connects EDSA and SLEX in the north; <hi rend="bold">Ayala Avenue</hi>, an important street that runs through the Central Business District; and Makati Avenue, which connects Ayala Avenue with Buendia Avenue and also extends north to cross the Pasig River to Mandaluyong City.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<p>Buses plying the Epifanio De los Santos Avenue (EDSA) route from Baclaran in Paranaque to Quezon City and Caloocan City pass through the Central Business District daily. As mentioned above, you can't load or unload just anywhere, you have to wait or go to the designated stops. There are separate loading and unloading zones which you must observe.</p>

<head>By premium bus</head>
<p>Most of Metro Manila's expanding <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Metro%20Manila%23Premium%20point-to-point%20buses">Point-to-Point</ref></hi> (P2P) bus network terminate at Makati; common termini are <hi rend="bold">Greenbelt</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Glorietta</hi>, <hi rend="bold">The Circuit</hi>, and <hi rend="bold">Trasierra</hi>.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">RRCG Transport</hi> runs Alabang Town Center–Greenbelt 1, Ayala Malls South Park–Greenbelt 5, Robinsons Cainta–Trasierra, SM Cherry <ref target="Antipolo">Antipolo</ref>–Greenbelt 5, SM City Masinag–Greenbelt 5</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">DNS Transport</hi> (Delta Neosolutions) runs from <ref target="Quezon%20City/Southeast">Eastwood City</ref>–Makati CBD, Sucat Exit—Greenbelt 5, and UP Town Center–Glorietta 3.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">San Agustin</hi> runs Noveleta—Trasierra and SM Southmall—Circuit Lane.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">HM Transport</hi> runs Robinsons Galleria—Glorietta 3.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">MetroExpress Connect</hi> runs Camella Homes <ref target="Dasmari%C3%B1as">Dasmariñas</ref>—San Lorenzo Place, Robinsons Place <ref target="Dasmari%C3%B1as">Dasmariñas</ref>—Trasierra, <ref target="Bacoor">Vista Mall Daang Hari</ref>—Trasierra, and Vista Mall Daang Hari—San Lorenzo Place.</item>
</list>


<head>By taxi</head>
<p>Taxis come form across the metro, including the airport. A single costs ₱200-300 from Ninoy Aquino International Airport or ₱200-250 from Ermita.</p>

<head>By ferry</head>

<p>The <ref target="http://www.prrc.com.ph/index.php%3Fpage%3Dthe-pasig-river-ferry-boat">Pasig River Ferry</ref> stops at two stations in Makati: <hi rend="bold">Valenzuela</hi> (near the city government complex) and <hi rend="bold">Guadalupe</hi> (near Guadalupe Bridge). Although neither station is in a convenient spot for tourists, which makes this option far less convenient than hailing a taxi. It may be worth keeping the ferry service in mind as another means of getting into Makati from other riverside districts such as <ref target="Manila/Intramuros">Intramuros</ref> in <ref target="Manila">Manila</ref>.</p>
</text>
