<text id="autogum_voyage_doc333" title="Melbourne (Florida)" shortTile="melbourne-florida" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=21922" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Melbourne (Florida)</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.melbourneflorida.org/">Melbourne</ref></hi> is on <ref target="East%20Central%20Florida">East Central Florida's</ref> Space Coast in Brevard County.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>While most of Melbourne is on the mainland, a small portion is located on a barrier island. The <ref target="http://www.indianriverlagoon.org/">Indian River Lagoon</ref> separates the mainland from the island. The island is a narrow strip of land that separates the Lagoon from the Atlantic Ocean.</p>

<p>Spanning the Indian River Lagoon to connect the mainland to the barrier island are a pair of four-lane, high-rise bridges -- the Melbourne Causeway and the Eau Gallie Causeway.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Melbourne International Airport</hi> ( MLB ), ☏ +1 321 723-6227 (ext. 222) . Serves Florida's Space and Treasure Coasts with domestic and international passenger and air freight service. Utilizing convenient, state-of-the-art facilities, the Melbourne International Airport is served by Delta and American Airlines as well as regional carriers. The Airport also provides services including charter passenger flights, private aviation, and air freight flights. </item>
</list>


<p>Other nearby airports include:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Orlando%20International%20Airport">Orlando International Airport</ref> ( MCO ) 64 miles NW of Melbourne.</item>
<item> Orlando-Sanford International Airport ( SFB ) 84 miles NW of Melbourne.</item>
<item> <ref target="Daytona%20Beach">Daytona Beach</ref> International Airport ( DAB ) 90 miles N of Melbourne.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://321transit.com/">Space Coast Area Transit</ref></hi> is the name of the local Brevard County bus service. It is a cheap way to get around and is handicap accessible. The website provides maps and timetables. Buses travel to most sites and places of interest. $1.25 per ride, or $35 for a monthly pass.</item>
</list>
<head>By car</head>
<p>The best way to get around Melbourne is by car. Major Roads include:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="U.S.%20Highway%201">U.S. Highway 1</ref></hi>. Harbor City Boulevard is the local street name, and it runs parallel to the Indian River on the eastern side of the city. This road allows easy access to the beaches over 3 causeways: the Pineda Causeway (Florida State Road 404), Eau Gallie Causeway, and Melbourne Causeway.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">U.S. Highway 192</hi>. Locally named New Haven Avenue or Strawbridge Avenue (historic downtown), US 192 is one of the major commercial, entertainment, and retail areas of Melbourne. Many businesses, large and small, are located on this busy avenue. It serves as a route to <ref target="Kissimmee">Kissimmee</ref> and the tourist corridor of <ref target="Orlando">Orlando</ref> to the west, and the town of <ref target="Indialantic">Indialantic</ref> to the east via the Melbourne Causeway.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Interstate 95</hi>. This 6 lane interstate highway passes through the city limits, 4 exit ramps located in the Melbourne Vicinity. It serves as the main north-south route in the metropolitan area.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Florida State Road A1A</hi>. This road runs along the beaches and provides easy access to other areas of Brevard County.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">County Road 509 (Wickham\Minton)</hi>. Wickham serves as a second north to south route in the Melbourne area.</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Henegar Center for the Arts</hi>, 625 East New Haven Av, ☏ +1 321-723-8698 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Honor America's Liberty Bell Museum</hi>, 1601 Oak St, ☏ +1 321-727-1776 . M-F 10AM-4PM.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">King Center for Performing Arts</hi>, 3865 N. Wickham Road, ☏ +1 321-242-2219 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Melbourne Arts Festival</hi>, ☏ +1 26-27 2008 . April.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Melbourne Community Orchestra</hi>, ☏ +1 321-952-9949 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Melbourne Civic Theatre</hi>, ☏ +1 321-723-6935 .</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Florida EcoSafaris at Forever Florida (Zipline Safari)</hi>, ☏ +1 407 957-9794 , ✉ info@floridaecosafaris.com . Journey deep into Forever Florida, a 4700 acre eco-ranch and wildlife conservation area, preserved just as nature intended. This beautiful site boasts 9 distinct Florida ecosystems and an endless array of natural flora and fauna including alligators, black bears, nearly two hundred species of birds and the endangered Florida panther. Choose your own fully-guided adventure: Coach Safari, Horseback Safari, soar through the treetops on the NEW Zipline Safari. Reservations Required.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Andretti's Thrill Park</hi>. Go Kart's, Mini Golf.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Brevard Zoo</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Galaxy Skateway</hi>, ☏ +1 321 259-3366 . Roller Skating Rink.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Brevard Symphony Orchestra</hi>, 1500 Highland Ave (offices are in the historic Winchester Symphony House in the Eau Gallie Arts District), ☏ +1 321-242-2024 . Founded in 1954, the orchestra-in-residence at the King Center for the performing arts. Brevard's only professional orchestra.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">CrossFit Rise Above</hi>, 1973 Guava Ave (Gym is located in the Eau Gallie Arts District), ☏ +1 321-254-0002 . Founded in 2011, CrossFit affiliate located in Melbourne.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Melbourne Square Mall, 1700 W New Haven Ave, +1 321 956-3393.</item>
<item> Longboard House, 101 Fifth Ave, Indialantic, +1 321 951-8001.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Squid Lips</hi>, 1477 Pineapple Avenue. "Where the locals eat &amp; drink." $5-$15 per person. Located on the Indian River.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Siam Orchid</hi> Best Sushi in town!</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Makotos</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cedar's Cafe</hi>. Authentic Lebanese food wonderful! Best Tabouli in town!</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Wagon Wheel</hi>, 3082 Lake Washington Rd, ☏ +1 321-254-7411 . In business for over 40 years, known for Pizza and Stromboli.</item>
</list>
<head>Historic Downtown Dining</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Continental Flambe</hi>, 936 E New Haven Ave, ☏ +1 321 768-2445 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Island Pasta Company</hi>, 820 E New Haven Ave, ☏ +1 321 723-1584 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Meg O'Malley's Irish Pub &amp; Restaurant</hi>, 810 E New Haven Av, ☏ +1 321 952-5510 .</item>
</list>


<head>Beachside Dining</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Longdoggers</hi> Great local food for $5-$10 per person</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Coasters Pub</hi>, ☏ +1 321 779-2739 . 971A E Eau Gallie Blvd (Wal-Mart Plaza). 100+ Awesome Beers and Great Food</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Meg O'Malley's Irish Pub &amp; Restaurant</hi>, 810 E New Haven Ave, ☏ +1 321 952-5510 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Club 702</hi>, 702 E New Haven Ave, ☏ +1 321 953-6050 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Coasters Pub</hi>, ☏ +1 321 779-2739 . Beachside at 971A E Eau Gallie Blvd (Wal-Mart Plaza). 100+ Awesome Beers and Great Food</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hilton Melbourne Rialto Place</hi>. Is located within minutes of the Melbourne International Airport.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Suburban Extended Stay</hi>, 1125 Airport Blvd., ☏ +1 321 768-9777 . Check-in: 3pm, check-out: 12pm. This hotel offers free wireless high-speed Internet access in all rooms and an on-site fitness room.</item>
</list>
<head>Bed &amp; Breakfast</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Crane Creek Inn Waterfront Bed &amp; Breakfast</hi>. Located in Historic Downtown Melbourne.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kennedy Space Center</hi> is about an hour's drive north, in <ref target="Cape%20Canaveral">Cape Canaveral</ref>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Disney%20World">Disney World</ref></hi> is <date when="2002-01-01">1-1/2</date> hours by car due west in <ref target="Lake%20Buena%20Vista">Lake Buena Vista</ref>.</item>
</list>
</text>
