<text id="autogum_voyage_doc345" title="Easter Island" shortTile="easter-island" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=10347" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Easter Island</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://chile.travel/en/where-to-go/islands/easter-island/">Easter Island</ref></hi> (<ref target="Spanish%20phrasebook">Spanish</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Isla de Pascua</hi>, Rapa Nui: <hi rend="italic">Rapa Nui</hi>) is one of the most isolated islands on Earth. Early settlers called the island "Te Pito O Te Henua" (The Navel of the World). It is a territory of <ref target="Chile">Chile</ref> that lies far off in the Pacific Ocean, roughly halfway to <ref target="Tahiti">Tahiti</ref>. Known as one of the world's sacred sites, it is most famous for its enigmatic giant stone statues or <hi rend="italic">moai</hi> whose oversized heads, carved centuries ago, reflect the history of the dramatic rise and fall of the most isolated Polynesian culture.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>The English name of the island commemorates its European discovery by a Dutch exploration vessel on Easter Sunday in 1722.</p>

<p>After Thor Heyerdahl and a small party of adventurers sailed their raft from <ref target="South%20America">South America</ref> to the Tuamotu islands, far to the north of Easter Island, a controversy raged over the origin of the islanders. DNA testing has proved conclusively that the Polynesians arrived from the west rather than the east, and that the people of Easter Island are descendants of intrepid voyagers who set out from another island thousands of years ago. Legend says that the people left for Easter Island because their own island was slowly being swallowed by the sea.</p>

<p>In brief, the prehistory of Easter Island is one of supreme accomplishment, flourishing and civilization, followed by environmental devastation and decline. Although it is not agreed when people first arrived on Easter Island (with estimates ranging from 300 to 1200 CE), consensus seems to be that the first peoples arrived from Polynesia. Rather than being inhabited by mistake or chance, evidence has suggested that Easter Island was colonized deliberately by large boats with many settlers—a remarkable feat given the distance of Easter Island from any other land in the Pacific Ocean (4,231 km to Tahiti).</p>

<p>The first islanders found a land of undoubted paradise—archaeological evidence shows that the island was covered in trees of various sorts, including the largest palm tree species in the world, whose bark and wood furnished the natives with cloth, rope, and canoes. Birds were abundant as well, and provided food for them. A mild climate favored an easy life, and abundant waters yielded fish and oysters.</p>

<p>The islanders prospered due to these advantages, and a reflection of this is the religion which sprouted in their leisure, which had at its centerpiece the giant moai statues, that are the island's most distinctive feature today. These moai, which the island is littered with, are supposed to have been depictions of ancestors, whose presence likely was considered a blessing or watchful safekeeping eye over each small village. The ruins of Rano Raraku crater, the stone quarry where most of the moai were carved and outside which many still sit today, is a testament to how central these figures were to the islanders, and how their life revolved around these creations. It has been suggested that their isolation from all other peoples fueled this outlet of trade and creativity—lacking any other significant way to direct their skills and resources. The bird-man culture (seen in petroglyphs), is an obvious testament to the islanders' fascination with the ability to leave their island for distant lands.</p>

<p>However, as the population grew, so did pressures on the island's environment. Deforestation of the island's trees gradually increased, and as this main resource was depleted, the islanders would find it hard to continue making rope, canoes, and all the necessities to hunt and fish, and ultimately, support the culture that produced the giant stone figureheads. Apparently, disagreements began to break out (with some violence) as confidence in the old religion was lost, and this is reflected partly in the ruins of moai which were deliberately toppled by human hands. By the end of the glory of the Easter Island culture, the population had crashed in numbers, and the residents—with little food or other ways to obtain sustenance—resorted sometimes to cannibalism and a bare subsistence. Subsequent slave raids by countries such as Peru and Bolivia devastated the population even more, as did epidemics of western diseases, until barely a hundred native Rapa Nui were left by the late nineteenth century.</p>

<p>Today, Rapa Nui National Park is on the <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20List">UNESCO World Heritage List</ref>. Its residents rely much on the tourism and economic links to Chile and daily flights to Santiago. As with many native peoples, the Rapa Nui seek a link to their past and ways to integrate their culture with the political, economic, and social realities of today.</p>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>As the island is part of <ref target="Chile">Chile</ref>, the government language is <ref target="Spanish%20phrasebook">Spanish</ref>. The indigenous people speak the Rapa Nui language, a Polynesian language closely related to Māori and Tahitian.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>Easter Island had the same <ref target="visa">visa</ref> requirements as the rest of <ref target="Chile">Chile</ref>. This was tightened in 2018 in an attempt to protect the natural environment and island heritage from an influx of voyagers. Maximum stay was limited to 30 days (instead of 90) with requirements that visitors fill out a special form, show return tickets and provide a copy of a hotel reservation or letter of invitation from an islander.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mataveri International Airport</hi> ( IPC ) (at Hanga Roa in the southwest of the island). The primary passenger airport, with non-stop service to <ref target="Santiago%20de%20Chile">Santiago</ref>, Chile and <ref target="Tahiti">Tahiti</ref>.</item>
</list>

 

<p>Still, the Island <hi rend="italic">is</hi> rather "out of the way" for most people, requiring at least 5½ hours in the air from the nearest continent, and there are very limited routes to get there. The <ref target="https://flights.latam.com/en_us/flights-to-easter-island">only regular flights</ref> are via <ref target="http://www.latam.com">LATAM Airlines</ref>, daily to <ref target="Santiago%20de%20Chile">Santiago de Chile</ref>, and once per week to <ref target="Tahiti">Tahiti</ref>. With no competition for fares on a lengthy flight, fares range between US$300-1200 for a round trip from Santiago.</p>

<p>About the only scenario in which Easter Island is "conveniently located" is on a <ref target="Round%20the%20world%20flights">round-the-world</ref> voyage, in which it provides an interesting stop on the way between Polynesia and <ref target="South%20America">South America</ref>, and will help bolster others' perception that you went "everywhere".</p>

<p>Coming from Santiago, it is a good choice to reserve seats on the left side of the airplane. Easter Island's runway has a west-east orientation. Even though the plane comes from Chile (to the east), it is likely it will circle the north portion of the island and land from the west, so seating at the left side (both landing and taking off) will give you a great view of the island.</p>

<p>If you want to take the intrepid route Tallship Soren Larsen sails to Easter Island from New Zealand once a year. The voyage takes 35 days, crossing the point on earth furthest from land.</p>
</text>
