<text id="autogum_voyage_doc430" title="Gloucester (Massachusetts)" shortTile="gloucester-massachusetts" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=12864" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gloucester (Massachusetts)</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Gloucester</hi> is a city in <ref target="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref>. One of the country's oldest settlements, established in 1623, it serves as America's oldest seaport. Although the sea is contributing less to the city's economy, Gloucester is still a true New England fishing center as immortalized in the movie <hi rend="italic">The Perfect Storm</hi>. Rocky Neck, the longest continually operating art colony in North America, is also in Gloucester.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>Gloucester is America's oldest seaport. Established in 1623, the city's roots are tied to the sea. Even with the decline of fishing due to heavy federal regulations, the city has an active waterfront. It also hosts great museums and sites. The Cape Ann Museum has the largest collection of Fitz Henry Lane paintings in the country, Hammond Castle, built by John Hayes Hammond, the father of remote control, Beauport, built by Henry Sleeper and a National Historic Landmark, the Sargent House, home of Judith Singer Sargent, one of the country's first feminists and the Gloucester Maritime Heritage Center, telling the story of the fishing industry and featuring the oldest continuously working railways in the country. Gloucester's City Hall was built in 1871 and has examples of the finest WPA murals in Massachusetts. Gloucester also features a diverse selection of fine restaurants and a delightful downtown.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>From <ref target="Boston">Boston</ref> take I-93 or Route 1 to Route 128. It's about 35 mi (56 km).</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>The <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.mbta.com">MBTA</ref></hi> commuter rail runs from North Station in <ref target="Boston">Boston</ref> to Gloucester via the <hi rend="bold">Newburyport/Rockport</hi> line. The trip takes about an hour and costs $7.25 one-way.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Cape Ann Transportation Authority, (CATA)</hi>, phone: <hi rend="italic">+1</hi> 978-283-7916, <ref target="http://www.canntran.com"></ref>, runs buses on Cape Ann including special routes during the summer.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gloucester Visitor Information Center</hi>, off Rt. 127 at <hi rend="bold">Stage Fort Park</hi>, Phone: <hi rend="italic">+1</hi> 978-281-8865. Seasonal. Get a free brochure on the <hi rend="bold">Gloucester Maritime Trail</hi> which describes four self-guided walks.</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fisherman's Memorial Statue</hi>, Stacy Blvd. Iconic statue of a typical storm-dressed "Old Salt" at the wheel commemorating the over ten thousand Gloucester fishermen who have been lost at sea.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rocky Neck Art Colony</hi>, Rocky Neck Av. <hi rend="italic">off East Main</hi>. The oldest art colony in America, with galleries of local artists, bars and restaurants.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<p>Gloucester was voted "Top 5 <ref target="whale%20watching">whale watching</ref> destinations in the World" by the World Wildlife Fund as several species of whales migrate to the shores of Gloucester every year to feed on the abundant natural resources. Whale watching enthusiasts can expect to potentially see humpback whales, northern right whales, minke whales, blue whales, fin whales, sperm whales, pilot whales among other whale species.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cape Ann Whale Watch</hi>, 415 Main St, ☏ +1 978 283-5110 , toll-free: +1 800 877-5110 , ✉ whale.watch@verizon.net . 7AM-7PM daily. Offering guaranteed whale sightings on all tours. Departing twice daily for over 35 years, Cape Ann Whale Watch sails aboard "The Hurricane II", made famous in the 1991 movie <hi rend="italic">The Perfect Storm</hi>. $48.00.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hammond Castle</hi>, 80 Hesperus Ave, ☏ +1 978 283-2080 . Castle overlooking the Atlantic Ocean since 1929, now a museum open to the public, once served as John Hayes Hammond, Jr's laboratory and home, inventor and pioneer of remote control. Hammond held over 400 patents and built a weather chamber in his home where he tried to control rain, snow, sleet and wind inside his lab. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Stage Fort Park</hi> The site of the city's first establishment, with giant bronze plaque to prove it, the fort retains the original cannons used for defense pointing towards Gloucester Harbor. A good place to enjoy a picnic, have a swim at two of the parks beaches, or wander through the maze of stone step remains of the original fort. Gloucester's Visitor and Welcoming Center is also found here.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Coastal Fishing Charters</hi>, 417 Main St, ☏ +1 508 284-2909 , toll-free: +1 800 877-5110 . 7AM-7PM daily. In business since the 1980s offering bluefin tuna fishing charters aboard a classic 35-ft (11-m) boat. Featured in reality TV series <hi rend="italic">Wicked Tuna</hi>.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<p>The main downtown area of Gloucester holds a number of local shops and restaurants for many tastes. Although the downtown area has lost the department stores it used to have, many new shops and eateries have opened. The area is a pleasant walk around, and it's easy to drop in and visit shops for Souvenirs, such as the Weathervane and the House of the Raven. The area is changing daily, into a more tourist friendly venue for visitors attracted to a still operational fishing port. Although the city has suffered from the loss of the fishing industry, residents have moved towards recognizing other avenues that the city can survive economically, including tourism, while still maintaining the active fishing community. The main street area has begun sprouting condos downtown, and a new retail spot has arisen in the former Browns Mall, where the Green Life Natural Living Store, and a kitchen specialty store are new additions to the retail scene. There is a sporting goods store called Palazolas, as well as a few bookshops, and antiques stores.</p>

<p>For more typical needs beyond souvenirs and an enjoyable downtown section, there are two main plazas in town, one on Eastern Avenue, and one on Bass Avenue which hold supermarkets and drug stores, along with other outlets.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">House of the Raven</hi> (House of Raven), 141 Main St., ☏ +1 978-281-1624 . M-F 10:10AM-5:30PM, Sa till 5PM. Custom picture framing on-site. Master framer with 30 years experience. Fine gold, sterling silver jewelry, gifts, cards, and souvenirs.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Latitude 43</hi>, 25 Rogers St, ☏ +1 978-281-0223 . 11:30 AM- 1 AM. Coastal cuisine with a modern twist. Award-winning sushi in a sunken in sushi pit.</item>
</list>
<head>Breakfast</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sugar Magnolias</hi>, 112 Main Street (downtown), ☏ +1 978 281-5310 . This is one of the most popular places for breakfast in town, fresh, interesting takes on breakfast foods.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Morning Glory</hi>, 25 Western Ave, ☏ +1 978 281-1851 . Has an outdoor deck overlooking the harbor on Stacy's Boulevard.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Charlie's Place</hi>, 83 Bass Avenue, ☏ +1 978 281-5002 . Serves a nice breakfast, inexpensive.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Two Sisters Coffee Shop</hi>, 27 Washington Street, ☏ +1 978 281-3378 . Have some nice Swedish Nisu bread.</item>
</list>
</text>
