<text id="autogum_voyage_doc470" title="Pawtucket" shortTile="pawtucket" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27043" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pawtucket</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Pawtucket</hi> is a <ref target="Rhode%20Island">Rhode Island</ref> city founded in 1671. It was home to the father of the American Industrial Revolution, Samuel Slater. The construction of his historic textile mill, called Slater Mill, marked the beginning of said revolution in 1793. Since then Pawtucket has shifted out of textiles (with only a few specialty manufacturers remaining) and has grown to hold 300 diversified industries with the most prominent being jewelry, silverware, and metalworking.</p>

<p>Pawtucket has more than 71,000 residents (as of the 2010 census). It is a diverse city home to many cultures resulting in a spectrum of sights, sounds, and flavors. Its neighborhoods have all improved greatly over the last decade as the city's developmental policies focus on improving the quality of residential areas and expanding emplyoment. With an emerging interest and concentration on the arts, Pawtucket has introduced performing arts and visual arts into the community.</p>

<head>By plane</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">T.F. Green Airport</hi> ( PVD ) is about a 20-minute drive from Pawtucket. PVD is a national airport with connecting international flights.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Logan International Airport</hi> ( BOS ) is an hour away in Boston, Massachusetts and is an international airport.</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> RIPTA bus Route 99, from Kennedy Plaza in Providence, converts into Route 76 which goes to Central Avenue and Newport Avenue. It also converts to Route 71 to Broad Street.</item>
</list>


<head>By car</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Route 95 runs right through Pawtucket. Exit 29 (from 95N) will bring you to Central Avenue, from which you can easily get downtown.</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> The Providence/Stoughton Rail line runs through Pawtucket. The closest passenger train stop is the one in downtown Providence, about a 10 minute drive from Pawtucket.</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="http://www.ripta.com">RIPTA</ref> lines run everyday all throughout the city.</item>
<item> The easiest way to get around Downtown Pawtucket is by bus, since traffic tends to make driving very frustrating. Schedules can be found online at the RIPTA website.</item>
<item> If driving is your preferred means of transportation, traffic or not, beware of the one ways around the RIPTA Station and the Pawtucket Public Library.</item>
<item> <ref target="http://expresstaxi.us/">Express Cab</ref> . 98 Larch St, +1 401 286-5515</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>
<p>Downtown Pawtucket has received federal recognition for its contributions to community planning, industry and architecture. The Historic District has been added to the National Register of Historic Places by the National Park Service.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pawtucket Red Sox at McCoy Stadium</hi> (Pawsox), 1 Ben Mondor Way, ☏ +1 401-724-7300 . Built in 1942 the Thomas P. McCoy Stadium is the home of the Triple-A Pawtucket Red Sox, a minor league affiliate of the Boston Red Sox. McCoy Stadium was host to the longest game in <ref target="baseball">baseball</ref> history, which lasted 33 innings played for 8 hours over the course of two days in 1981. After major renovations in 1999, the ballpark is beautiful with it’s hand-painted murals of past Pawsox turned baseball greats and left field berm. Photo posters with biographies of players, information about the stadium, and the longest game, hung about the concourses and around the clubhouses make for a good reason as to why McCoy Stadium is one of the most visited minor league ballparks in the country. At McCoy, fans enjoy promotional giveaways, such as “bat night” and “bobble-head night” and after choice games, especially <date when="2003-07-02">on July 2nd, 3rd</date> and 4th, get the opportunity to watch a fireworks display, which, packing the streets outside, draws citizens from all over Pawtucket.</item>
</list>

 Tickets for games are $10 for Box Seats and $6 for General Admission.. 


<list type="unordered">
<item> The Pawtucket Redsox host concerts in conjunction with the Pawtucket Arts Festival, in which past acts included The Dropkick Murphys, The Counting Crows and Bob Dylan. The show at McCoy kicks off the festival in July.</item>
<item> As the Triple-A affiliate of Boston, fans can watch Red Sox players rehabbing injuries with the Pawsox and view possible Red Sox athletes of the future.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Slater Memorial Park</hi>, Entrances at Rt.15 Armistice Blvd. or Rt. 1A Newport Ave, ☏ +1 401-728-0500 ext 257 . Park hours from Memorial Day until Labor Day are 8AM-9PM. From Labor Day until Memorial Day 8AM-dusk.. In the heart of the park is a small lake with ducks and swans, the Daggett House, the oldest house in Pawtucket, Daggett Farm, the Loof Carousel which opens in April and closes in, the oldest of its kind, and the Rhode Island Watercolor Society headquarters and Gallery. Ten tennis courts, baseball diamonds, basketball courts and open fields allow for sport recreation all year round. Picnic areas are available for rent and throughout the year, the City of Pawtucket holds Slater Park as a host for seasonal fun for the public.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Fall events are Pumpkins in the Park, a display of hundreds of carved and lighted jack-o-lanterns, and The Haunted Tunnel, which occur from late September until Halloween. Winter Wonderland occurs in December, and includes the opening of the carousel for that special event, decorated Christmas trees, and concerts. The Pawtucket Arts Festival holds concerts and other events in the park during the summer, the most popular being the free concert performed by The Boston Pops and a finale of fireworks, which acts as the closing to the festival</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Slater Mill Historic Landmark</hi>, 175 Main St, ☏ +1 401-724-2200 . On the Blackstone River, a museum complex dedicated to the preservation and interpretation of the American industrial heritage at the birthplace of the American Industrial Revolution. This serves as a Blackstone Valley National Corridor Visitor Center as well. Slater Mill was the first water powered cotton mill in North America and was built in 1793. The Mill holds a number of events regularly, including workshops and ghost tours. Tours are $9 for adults, $8 for seniors and $7 for children aged 7-12.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">St. Cecelia's Church</hi>, 1253 Newport Avenue, ☏ +1 401 722-1101 . At the corner of Newport and Central, it's one of the biggest churches in Rhode Island. Named after the patron saint of music.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dagget Athletic Fields</hi>, Dagget Ave. A wonderful athletic complex with a variety of field types and plenty of room. The best slopes in Pawtucket for sledding/snowboarding. There are woods in back, perfect for nice secluded walks. The trail leads right into Slater Park, where it turns into a bike path, so bring some rollerblades or something.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lee's Pond</hi>, Broadway, near Leedham Hardware. A nice area and a skate park. The main reason to go there (only reason) is because it's the perfect place to go ice skating when it's below freezing. Loads of fun and chances are you'll make a friend or two.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hasbro Company</hi>, Newport Ave. The Hasbro company is one of the leading toy companies in the world.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Blackstone River</hi>. The Blackstone runs through Pawtucket and into Worcester, Ma. Its power runs Slater Mill and, therefore, helped to began the nation's transformation from farm to factory.</item>
</list>
</text>
