<text id="autogum_voyage_doc166" title="Watsonville" shortTile="watsonville" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=38688" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Watsonville</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://cityofwatsonville.org">Watsonville</ref></hi> is a city in <ref target="Santa%20Cruz%20County%20%28California%29">Santa Cruz County</ref> in <ref target="California">California</ref> in the <ref target="Monterey%20Bay">Monterey Bay Area</ref>.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<ref target="http://www.scmtd.com/">Santa Cruz Metro</ref> provides service from <ref target="Santa%20Cruz%20%28California%29">Santa Cruz</ref> and other towns around it, and <ref target="https://mst.org/">Monterey-Salinas Transit</ref> provides service from destinations including <ref target="Monterey%20%28California%29">Monterey</ref> and <ref target="Salinas">Salinas</ref>.

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Downtown is pedestrian friendly. There are some bicycle and pedestrian paths along the creeks, rivers, and sloughs around Watsonville as well and some limited bus service. Taxi's are available throughout the area by phone. Watsonville airport also provides small craft access.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Mountains</item>
<item> Pajaro River</item>
<item> Mount Madonna</item>
<item> Auto races at <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://oceanspeedway.com/">Ocean Speedway</ref></hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sunset State Beach</hi>, 201 Sunset Beach Rd (The beach is 16 miles south of Santa Cruz. Take Highway 1, exit on San Andreas Road, and follow signs south.), ☏ +1 831 763-7062 , toll-free: +1-800-444-7275 (Reservations) . Day use open daily 8AM to 1/2 hour after sunset. Campground open year-round (reservations recommended).. The beach features pine trees, mountainous sand dunes, and ocean side picnic spots. Bordered by large agricultural fields west of the city of Watsonville, the beach is a year-round destination for thousands of visitors. Amenities include: Picnic tables, Camping areas (including large group camping), Restrooms, and Showers (Camping showers are 25 cents; bring quarters.). Food, lodging and supplies are available nearby. The campground is open year-round. There are 91 camping sites, one bicycle site and one group site. Cost is $35 per night. Call 800-444-7275 for reservations. Campsites in the Dunes and Pine Hollow loops are first-come, first-serve during the winter (Nov. 1 to the end of February). Nature walks on the dunes and family programs are offered; call the park for more information. More information: More information: http://www.parks.ca.gov/pages/544/files/Sunset-ManresaWebBrochure2012.pdf </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Manresa State Beach</hi>, 1445 San Andreas Rd (From Highway 1, south of Aptos, take San Andreas Road southwest and continue for three miles to Manresa State Beach. It is the first beach access you will reach on the coast.), ☏ +1 831-724-3750 . Open daily sunrise to sunset, year round.. Manresa State Beach features a beautiful expanse of sea and sand, with surf, fishing, surfing, and recreation. Amenities include: Restrooms, Outdoor shower, Food Dogs are allowed on the beach on leash. Fire rings are available for beach fires. More information: More information: http://www.parks.ca.gov/pages/544/files/Sunset-ManresaWebBrochure2012.pdf $10 day use parking fee. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pinto Lake County Park</hi>, 757 Green Valley Rd (From Highway 1 south, exit onto Airport Boulevard, on Green Valley Road make a left. From Highway 1 north, take the Airport Boulevard exit, turn left onto Airport Blvd to Green Valley Road, go left. You will go past Pinto Lake City Park and will see Pinto Lake County Park. Make a left turn into the park.), ☏ +1 831-454-7956 , ✉ reservations@scparks.com . Reservation hours are available daily from 10AM to 7PM during summer months. Reservation end time varies according to season. Drop in park use is open daily from dawn to dusk.. A 183 acre regional park, which features a scenic lake with a fishing pier and surrounding nature trails, playground, two family picnic areas, and wheelchair accessible restrooms. Turtle Dove, a public art project by artist Roberto Castro and youth from the JTPA program, can be found at the park; trail markers highlight the wildlife which can be viewed along the nature trail. Soccer fields and two pavilions with BBQs are available for rent. There is also a small baseball field. See the location where locals believe the Virgin Mary appeared. A disc golf course is the newest attraction to Pinto Lake Park. Reservable picnic areas: Reservable Picnic Areas Pavillions A and B are perfect outdoor locations for family and company picnics. Available by reservation only. They offer privacy for your group and a comfortable, scenic oasis for your enjoyment. Capacity is 100. 1 Large Barbecue and picnic tables are included. Pavillion A is the first covered picnic area upon entering the park. It is closest to the playground and near public restrooms. Pavillion B is the second covered picnic area located at the far end of the park. Public restrooms are nearby. It offers privacy for your group. Reservations can be made up to one year in advance. Walk-in reservations can be made at the Simpkins Family Swim Center at 979 17th Avenue, Santa Cruz. Office hours are Monday through Friday from 9AM- 4PM. Please allow one month before event date for phone reservations, and 3 days for walk-in. Cash, check or Visa/Mastercard accepted. For more information, call (831)454-7956.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pinto Lake Park</hi>, 451 Green Valley Rd (Traveling North on HWY 1 from Monterey: Take Green Valley Road exit and follow for 3 Miles. Traveling South on HWY 1 from Santa Cruz: Take HWY 152 Watsonville/Gilroy exit, Then IMMEDIATELY left onto Green Valley Rd. and travel 2.6 Miles inland.), ☏ +1 831 722-8129 , ✉ pintolakepark@gmail.com . Pinto Lake City Park is owned by the City of Watsonville and offers RV camping. Amenities: Back-in Sites 50' x 15' On grass Electricity (30 amp) City water Sewer Wi-fi (Strong, reliable signal) Locked gate at night (You get a key.) Fire rings allowed in picnic area adjacent to campground Showers, laundry Rates: Two adults in one RV or trailer: $35.00 One tow vehicle: Free Children 16 and under: Free Extra adults: $2.00 each Dogs: $2.00 each Extra vehicles: $2.00 each</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Wetlands of Watsonville</hi>, 30 Harkins Slough Rd, ☏ +1 831 768-1622 . The City of Watsonville's nature trails provide easy public access to this 800 acre freshwater wetland. More than six miles of paved trails and 29 trail entrances in Watsonville neighborhoods offer new opportunities to enjoy the natural beauty of our special wetlands for recreation and relaxation. The Wetlands of Watsonville Nature Center offers trail maps and other information about the animals and habitats of the area. City wetland trails are free to use and open every day in every season. Joggers, hikers, cyclists and birders are welcome to access any of the trails. Several trails are wheelchair accessible; please see trail maps for appropriate entrances. Recommended Trail Walks &amp; Entrances Watsonville Slough Trail Trail Head: Park at the Wetlands of Watsonville Nature Center – 30 Harkins Slough Road, Watsonville, CA.(831)768-1622. Trail map available outside Nature Center. Trail entrance behind center. Approximate walk: 1.5 miles Ohlone Loop Trail Trail Head: Park in the back of the West Marine parking lot by trail head – 500 Westridge Drive, Watsonville, CA. Approximate walk: 1.5 miles Upper Struve Slough Trail Trail Head: Park in Body Zone parking lot by trail head – 1810 Main Street, Watsonville, CA. Approximate walk: 1.5 miles Nearby Areas: Food and shopping center on Main Street.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Santa Cruz County Fairgrounds &amp; Event Center</hi>, 2601 E. Lake Ave (From Highway 1, take Airport Blvd to East Lake Blvd; turn left on East Lake and the Fairgrounds will be on your left-hand side.), ☏ +1 831-724-5671 . Home of the Santa Cruz County Fair held each September and the races at the Ocean Speedway, Agricultural History Project and Museum and the historic Rogers House.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Henry J. Mello Center for Performing Arts</hi>, 250 East Beach St (From Highway 1, take the CA-152 E/Main Street exit toward Watsonville/Gilroy; turn left on East Beach Street.), ☏ +1 831-763-4047 , ✉ mellocenter@charter.net . This premier concert performance hall boasts the best acoustics in the county.</item>
</list>
</text>
