<text id="autogum_voyage_doc348" title="Rameswaram" shortTile="rameswaram" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=29154" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rameswaram</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Rameswaram</hi> is a town on Pamban Island, in the southeast Indian state of <ref target="Tamil%20Nadu">Tamil Nadu</ref>. It's known for Ramanathaswamy Temple, a Hindu pilgrimage site with ornate corridors, huge sculpted pillars and sacred water tanks. It is separated from mainland India by the Pamban channel and is about 40 km from <ref target="Mannar">Mannar Island</ref> in <ref target="Sri%20Lanka">Sri Lanka</ref>. It is in the Gulf of Mannar, at the tip of the Indian peninsula. Pamban Island, also known as Rameswaram Island, is connected to mainland India by the Pamban Bridge. Together with <ref target="Varanasi">Varanasi</ref>, it is considered to be one of the holiest places in India to Hindus, and part of the Char Dham pilgrimage.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
<p>Nearest airport in <ref target="Madurai">Madurai</ref> - 174 km from Rameswaram. Most of the major Indian cities have daily flights here.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Being a significant pilgrimage site, Rameswaram (<ref target="https://etrain.info/in%3FSTATION%3DRMM">RMM</ref>) is connected to all major south Indian cities like Kochi, Chennai, Hyderabad and Bengaluru. But you might find it difficult to find a direct train till here from north Indian cities.</p>

<head>By road</head>
<p>Connected with all important towns of Tamil Nadu, City Buses are available including night services. Point to Point services, Tourist taxi, auto / cycle rickshaws and horse carts are also available.The taxi charges for a small car (Indica) is around ₹5 per km. It costs around ₹1800 for return trip from Madurai to Rameswaram. Andhra Pradesh State Road Transport corporation ( APSRTC ) operates Rameswaram – Tirupathi daily service.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sri Ramanathaswamy Temple</hi> (near the sea on the eastern side of the island). Renowned for its magnificent prakaras or corridors with massive sculptured pillars on either side. The longest corridor in the world is here, long and wide. The temple has a Gopuram tall. Different rulers built the temple as it stands today, at different periods from the 12th century AD. There many guides who will attack as soon as you enter the temple premises; negotiate the deal of how much to pay them if you need their services. The history of the temple is linked with "Ramayan" and it is believed that the deity was installed by Lord Rama after the war with Ravana at the instance of the great saints to get rid of the "Brahma Dosham".</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Agnitheertham</hi>. Sri Ramanathaswamy temple faces east. The seashore, about from the main entrance of the temple, is very calm and therefore ideal for bathing. The water at this place is considered sacred and known as Agni theertham. Pilgrims perform poojas in honour of their ancestors at this seashore.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Annai Indira Gandhi Road Bridge</hi> (Pamban Bridge) (12 km). Connects the Rameswaram island with the mainland. It is the longest sea bridge in India, nearly long, and stands as a fine example of Indian architecture. The islands near by and parallel rail bridge below can be viewed from this bridge.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Badrakaliamman Temple</hi> (2 km from the main temple on the way to the Gandamadana Parvatham.). A temple for Devi Durga</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Dhanushkodi</hi> (18 km). the southern tip of the island, Dhanushkodi was completely washed away by the 1964 cyclone. This is a strip of land about wide and long on the eastern end of Rameswaram island. On one side are the waters of the Indian Ocean and on the other is the Bay of Bengal. The two seas, otherwise known as Ratnakaran and Mahodadhi, with their confluence is shaped like a bow while the strip of land resemble an arrow poised for release. Devout Hindus consider the Adi Sethu, or the arrowhead, a sacred place to perform religious rites. It is also a place worth visiting for its scenic beauty and bird life.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Five-faced Hanuman Temple</hi> (2 km from the main temple). the deity of Hanuman drawn withsenthooram. Idols of Lord Ram, Sita and Hanuman brought from Dhanushkodi during the 1964 cyclone were placed here. The floating stone, used to build the SethuBandanamor, the bridge between India and Lanka, can be found in this temple.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gandamadana Parvatham</hi>. is a hillock situated 3 km away and is the highest point in the island. Here one can see the imprint of Lord Rama’s feet on a chakra. The entire island of Rameswaram is visible from this point.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jada Theertham</hi> (about 3.5 km from Rameswaram on the Dhanushkodi road). legend has it that Lord Rama, on his way back after killing Ravana, Worshipped SriRamalinga (believed to be installed by him). Before doing so, he washed his hair in this theertham to purify himself.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kalam House</hi>, Mosque Street. The former President A.P.J. Abdul Kalam House is an interesting place to visit. At present, his residence has been converted into a museum that stocks his childhood memoirs. The place is ideal to get a glimpse into the extraordinary life of this simple man, right from childhood to his research days. Several pictures and awards of Dr. Kalam are kept on display in this two-story building, which is maintained by his elder brother. Moreover, a section of the house has been turned into a store that sells a variety of merchandise.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kalam Memorial</hi> (on the main approach road to the island). A very beautiful and grand building. It was inaugurated on the second death anniversary of Dr Kalam. A must-visit. No photography is allowed inside the main halls. No entry fee.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kothanda RamaSwamy Temple</hi> (12 km away from Rameswaram). A popular belief is that Vibishana, brother of Ravana, surrendered before Rama here.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nambu Nayagiamman Temple</hi> (8 km from the main temple in Rameswaram on the way to Dhanushkodi.). Greatly venerated by the people of Ramnad District.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Satchi Hanuman Temple</hi> (3 km from the main temple, on the way to the Gandamadana Parvatham.). A very small roadside temple. It is considered to be the place where Hanuman delivered the good news of finding Sita to Rama with satchi or evidence, Choodamani or the jewel that belonged to Sita</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sugreevar Temple/Theertham</hi> (on the way to Gandamadana Parvatham near the Doordarshan Kendra.).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Villoondi Theertham</hi> (7 km from the main temple on the way to Pamban). It is found inside the sea like a well where freshwater is available.</item>
</list>
</text>
