<text id="autogum_voyage_doc313" title="West Antarctica" shortTile="west-antarctica" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=38845" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>West Antarctica</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">West Antarctica</hi> is the region of <ref target="Antarctica">Antarctica</ref> that falls in the Western Hemisphere.</p>

<head>Regions</head>

<p>There are many regions of Antarctica, some of which are mountains and some of which are flatter areas. However, these regions do not have their own articles because they offer few points of interest, let alone places to eat and sleep.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ross Dependency</hi> is the portion of Antarctica claimed by <ref target="New%20Zealand">New Zealand</ref>. Home to the largest Antarctic research station, <ref target="McMurdo%20Station">McMurdo Station</ref>, and the world's southernmost active volcano, Mount Erebus.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Marie Byrd Land</hi> is the largest area in the world that isn't claimed by any country. This area is very empty even by Antarctic standards.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chilean Antarctic Territory</hi> contains the entire <ref target="Antarctic%20Peninsula">Antarctic Peninsula</ref> and overlaps with Queen Elizabeth Land and Argentine Antarctica. It contains the Union Glacier Camp, which is a stopping point for most trips to the South Pole.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Queen Elizabeth Land</hi> is the <ref target="United%20Kingdom">U.K.</ref>'s claim to Antarctica. It also contains the entire Antarctic Peninsula and overlaps with the Chilean Antarctic Territory and Argentine Antarctica.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Argentine Antarctica</hi> is another Antarctic claim that overlaps with the Chilean Antarctic Territory and Queen Elizabeth Land.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Coats Land</hi> is closer to the Antarctic Peninsula than Marie Byrd Land.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ellsworth Land</hi> is close to Vinson Massif.</item>
</list>


<head>Bases</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">(Excluding bases in the <ref target="Antarctic%20Peninsula">Antarctic Peninsula</ref> region)</hi></p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> (<ref target="Argentina">Argentina</ref>) The world's southernmost research station built on solid rock (not on ice) and is home to the world's southernmost church.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> (<ref target="United%20Kingdom">U.K.</ref>) A research station that had been rebuilt 5 times and consists of 8 stringed modules. There are retractable gigantic skis on the bottom of the station, allowing it to be moved.</item>
<item> (<ref target="Germany">Germany</ref>) A German research station on the Ekström Ice Shelf.</item>
<item> (<ref target="South%20Africa">South Africa</ref>) A South African research station consisting of 3 double-storied modules.</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> is home to Antarctica's highest point, Vinson Massif, at 4,892 m (16,050 ft).</item>
<item> is part of the Transantarctic Mountains. An aircraft fueling station for planes flying between the Union Glacier Camp and the <ref target="South%20Pole">Amundsen-Scott South Pole Station</ref> is nearby.</item>
<item> is a long range of mountains and is part of the Transantarctic Mountains.</item>
<item> is another part of the Transantarctic Mountains.</item>
<item> is also part of the Transantarctic Mountains and is in Marie Byrd Land.</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>

<p>The mainland of Antarctica is divided into two sides: the east and the west. While the Peninsula section of Antarctica is in the western portion of the continent, the Peninsula is not considered to be part of West Antarctica because it's a more popular tourist destination and has a climate not quite as extreme due to its location off the Antarctic Plateau, which East and West Antarctica sit on.</p>

<p>West Antarctica is the emptiest region of Antarctica, as there are only 4 permanent research stations here, compared to 17 in East Antarctica. </p>

<head>Weather</head>

<p>Due to West Antarctica's location on the Antarctic Plateau, most of this region lies at a high elevation, with ice miles deep. This means that what would already be a very cold area if it was at a low elevation is even colder. The high altitude, of course, brings health-related problems as well.</p>

<head>Landscape</head>

<p>West Antarctica is mostly on the Antarctic Plateau, and the Transantarctic Mountains is mostly in West Antarctica. West Antarctica has a high altitude, which gets even higher when getting closer to the Transantarctic Mountains. However, the terrain is generally flat on most parts of the Antarctic Plateau.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>This region is extremely difficult to get into, like <ref target="East%20Antarctica">East Antarctica</ref>. Unlike the Peninsula to the north, expedition ships generally avoid going to West Antarctica; the only exception to this would probably be the Ross Sea. However, a blue ice runway exists on Union Glacier Camp. This camp is privately owned and operated by Antarctic Logistics &amp; Expeditions LLC (ALE). Chartered flights from <ref target="Punta%20Arenas">Punta Arenas</ref> fly tourists to the camp and run trips to the interior of Antarctica including the <ref target="South%20Pole">South Pole</ref>, Vinson Massif and Hercules Inlet.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>Like the rest of Antarctica, transportation within bases can be done on feet, and transportation out of bases should be done on skis and/or base transport.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bentley Subglacial Trench</hi>. The lowest point in the world not covered by oceans at 2,555 m (8,382 ft), although it is covered by ice.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mount Sidley</hi>. Antarctica's highest volcano (extinct), at a whopping 4,181 m (13,717 ft).</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Vinson Massif</hi>. The highest point in Antarctica, Vinson Massif (<hi rend="italic">Mount Vinson</hi>) stands at 4,892 m (16,050 ft); climbs can be arranged by international travel agencies such as <ref target="https://www.rmiguides.com/vinson-massif">RMI</ref> and <ref target="https://www.adventureconsultants.com/expeditions/seven-summits/vinson-massif/">Adventure Consultants</ref> for some tens of thousands of dollars (US) per person, and take at least 14 days round trip from <ref target="Punta%20Arenas">Punta Arenas</ref>. Aside from the weather and the absurd difficulties involved in transport there, the climb is supposed to be pretty easy, especially by "<ref target="seven%20summits">seven summits</ref>" standards.</item>
</list>

 RMI: $43,600 Adventure Consultants: $43,000.


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mount Tyree</hi>. This is one of the second seven summits; in other words, it's the second highest mountain peak in Antarctica. As of 2017, only 15 people had climbed to the top of Mount Tyree, so there are probably no tours to Mount Tyree.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Antarctic Ice Marathon</hi>, ✉ rd@icemarathon.com . The annual <hi rend="bold">Antarctic Ice Marathon</hi> is the start of the <hi rend="bold">World Marathon Challenge</hi> (7 Marathons on 7 continents in 7 days). Racers will run 2 laps starting at the Union Glacier Camp. There is also a half-marathon option. $18900 for 2019 and 2020.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p>Like anywhere else in Antarctica, food will be served in bases, and must be carried when outside bases.</p>

<head>Drink</head>
<p>At most places in West Antarctica, there is ice covering the ground, so those with the ability to melt ice should not worry about water. </p>

<head>Sleep</head>
<p>Unless someone at a base is willing for you to lodge, you will need to camp. Some excursions use Union Glacier Camp, a privately owned camp, as a base for their tourists.</p>

<head>Stay safe</head>
<p>Like the rest of Antarctica, West Antarctica is extremely cold and medical care is very limited. Medical insurances are strongly recommended and sometimes required.</p>
</text>
