<text id="autogum_voyage_doc398" title="Groton (Connecticut)" shortTile="groton-connecticut" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13488" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Groton (Connecticut)</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Groton</hi> is a city in <ref target="Connecticut">Connecticut</ref>. The tourist village of <ref target="Mystic%20%28Connecticut%29">Mystic</ref> lies in the eastern part of Groton.</p>

<head>By car</head>

<p>From either <ref target="New%20Haven">New Haven</ref> or <ref target="Providence">Providence</ref>, take Interstate 95 to exit 30, or U.S. Route 1. From <ref target="Worcester%20%28Massachusetts%29">Worcester</ref>, take Interstate 395 to CT Route 85, to Interstate 95/U.S. Route 1.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.amtrak.com">AMTRAK</ref></hi> services southern Connecticut to <ref target="New%20York%20City">New York</ref> and points south; and <ref target="Providence">Providence</ref>, <ref target="Boston">Boston</ref> and points north.</p>

<head>Major airports</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bradley International Airport</hi>, <ref target="Windsor%20Locks">Windsor Locks</ref>, Phone: +1 860-292-2000.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">T.F. Green Airport</hi>, <ref target="Warwick%20%28Rhode%20Island%29">Warwick (Rhode Island)</ref>.</item>
</list>


<head>Small, regional airports</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Groton–New London Airport</hi>, 155 Tower Ave., Phone: +1-860-445-8549.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Westerly Airport</hi>, 56 Airport Road, <ref target="Westerly">Westerly</ref>, Phone: +1-401-596-2357.</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fort Griswold Battlefield State Park</hi>, ☏ +1 860 449-6877 . </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">U.S. Navy Submarine Force Museum</hi>, 1 Crystal Lake Rd, toll-free: +1-800-343-0079 . Mid May-mid Oct Daily 9AM-5PM. Winter: W-M 9AM-4PM. Tues. 1PM-5PM. I-95, Exit 86. World's finest collection of submarine artifacts and home of the USS Nautilus, the first nuclear sub. Traces development of subs from Revolutionary War times. Admission, including self-guided tour of USS Nautilus, is free, but donations invited. </item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<p>Holiday Bowl-</p>

<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Koto Japanese Steak House</hi>, 527 Long Hill Road. Although the name implies a steak house it is similar to Benihana in the Teppenyaki side of the house. But, where the place really shines is their sushi. The chef is a Japanese national who is very skilled and quite innovative at making sushi. They regularly import fish from Japan and it is fantastic. It rivals some of the best NY sushi restaurants and by far exceeds anything in the area.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ninety Nine Restaurant</hi>, 117 Long Hill Road, ☏ +1 860 449-9900 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Wokery</hi>, 507 Route 184, ☏ +1 860 448-3336 . Chinese/Japanese.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hampton Inn, Groton</hi>, 300 Long Hill Road, ☏ +1 860 405-1585 , fax: +1 860 446-8456 . The Hampton Inn Groton hotel is a gateway to downtown Groton and minutes away from <ref target="Mystic%20%28Connecticut%29">Mystic</ref>. Nearby are numerous restaurants. Easily accessible from I-95 North and South and centrally located near major businesses. Features four stories with 80 rooms, including 4 king suites, a complimentary deluxe continental breakfast, indoor heated pool, meeting room for 65 people, exercise room and business center with complimentary high-speed internet and ATM.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Groton Inn &amp; Suites</hi>, 99 Gold Star Highway, toll-free: +1-800-452-2191 . (Route 184). Great for business travel since it is close to General Dynamics-Electric Boat Corporation, Dow Chemical, USS Submarine Base New London/Groton, Connecticut College, US Coast Guard Academy, Mitchell College, The Day Paper, Lawrence and Memorial Hospital, Sonalysts Studios Inc. and Pfizer.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Best Western Olympic Inn</hi>, ☏ +1 860 445-8000 , toll-free: +1-800-622-7766 , fax: +1 860 449-9173 . 360 Route 12.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mystic Marriott Hotel and Spa</hi>, 625 North Road, ☏ +1 860 446-2600 , toll-free: +1-866-449-7390 , fax: +1 860 446-2601 . (Route 117).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Super 8 Motel Groton</hi>, 173 Route 12, Groton, CT 06340 (I-95 Exit 86), ☏ +1 860 448-2818 . Check-in: 15:00, check-out: 11:00. A cheap place to crash very near New London and just across the street from the Groton Inn and Suites. The place is no nonsense and simple but it is clean and well maintained and an excellent bargain. ~$50.</item>
</list>
</text>
