<text id="autogum_voyage_doc119" title="Chicago/Bronzeville" shortTile="chicagobronzeville" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=7123" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Chicago/Bronzeville</head>


<p><hi rend="bold">Bronzeville</hi>, the <hi rend="bold">Black Metropolis</hi>, is a mecca of <ref target="Chicago%23African-American%20history">African-American History</ref> on Chicago's South Side, just miles south of downtown. Gwendolyn Brooks published poetry in the Chicago Defender, Andrew Rube Foster created Negro League Baseball, and Louis Armstrong kept his trumpet singing at the Sunset Cafe to keep Al Capone off his back. Long in disrepair, the neighborhood is coming back, with new residents refurbishing historic homes, and with new dining and nightlife scenes beginning to take root.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Bronzeville was the site of Chicago's version of the Harlem Renaissance, and was home to many famous African-Americans, including Gwendolyn Brooks, Richard Wright, Louis Armstrong, Bessie Coleman, Ida B Wells, Andrew Foster, and many more. The neighborhood was from the 1920s to the 1940s one of the premiere centers of African-American culture and was fairly affluent and middle class. The Great Depression hit the area hard, bankrupting black-owned businesses, but the neighborhood's worst enemy proved to be the neglectful and segregationist city government. Because black Chicagoans were restricted (unofficially) from renting and buying property outside of the "Black Belt," rents were actually higher in the district's run-down, ill-maintained buildings, owned by white absentee landlords, than in the adjacent, wealthy, white neighborhoods. In 1941, the city built the infamous and gigantic Ida B Wells housing projects in Bronzeville, which produced devastating and unintended results. Because of segregation, many low-income African-Americans were unable to find housing anywhere else and the projects quickly became overcrowded, while crime and urban blight expanded throughout the neighborhood.</p>

<p>Today, the neighborhood is seeing major community-driven revitalization efforts, mostly by wealthy and entrepreneurial African-Americans who value the neighborhood's historic importance. Historic clubs are reopening, and there are a handful of nice coffee shops and restaurants. More so than the present, however, the principal attraction remains the neighborhood's rich history. As a rule, the revitalization efforts have not extended below 47th Street or west of the Dan Ryan Expressway into the Washington Park and Fuller Park neighborhoods, which remain very blighted, with an extraordinary amount of vacant lots and the highest violent crime levels in the city. Unfortunately, this means that 47th Street, which has some major draws, can be a little edgy after dark. But don't worry about Washington Park the park (as opposed to the neighborhood) — it's perfectly safe during the day.</p>

<head>Tourist information</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bronzeville Visitor Information Center</hi>, 3501 S Martin Luther King Jr Dr, Ste 1 (in the old Supreme Life Building), ☏ +1-773-373-2842 , ✉ visitbronzeville@aol.com . M-F 10AM-5PM, Sa 10AM-2PM, and by appointment. The Bronzeville Visitor Information Center seeks to provide visitors with orientation and offers tours, exhibits, and a small gift shop. </item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>
<p>The best way to reach Bronzeville by public transport is definitely the CTA <hi rend="bold">Green Line</hi>, which runs along State and Indiana, with key stops at 35-Bronzeville-IIT, 43rd St, 47th St (Jackson), and Garfield (Jackson). The <hi rend="bold">Red Line</hi> runs along Bronzeville's western border by the Dan Ryan Espressway — a bit further away from most Bronzeville attractions, but convenient nonetheless.</p>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">Metra Main Line</hi> has a stop at 27th St, which is near the "Walk of Fame" and Michael Reese Hospital, but not near much else.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Many CTA bus lines travel throughout Bronzeville. A few key routes are the #4 and #3, which run north-south along Michigan Ave and Martin Luther King Jr Dr respectively and will take you to Bronzeville from <ref target="Chicago/Loop">the Loop</ref>. The #55 Garfield route is useful for travel between Bronzeville and <ref target="Chicago/Southwest%20Side%23By%20plane">Midway Airport</ref>, in the <ref target="Chicago/Southwest%20Side">Southwest Side</ref>.</p>
<head>By car</head>
<p>Bronzeville is one of the few neighborhoods close to the Chicago center that is actually best seen by car. Free on-street parking is in ample supply pretty much everywhere throughout the neighborhood — owing to the relatively low population density of the district. There are many exits leading into Bronzeville from the <hi rend="bold">Dan Ryan Expressway</hi>, although you might enjoy the ride better if you take a more northerly exit (like 35th or 31st Streets) and then explore the area from Martin Luther King Drive — some of the areas further south around the expressway are a bit run down. If coming from the <ref target="Chicago/Loop">Loop</ref>, the best way is probably to just head south on Martin Luther King Drive, which serves as the main drag for most of the district.</p>

<head>Black Metropolis landmarks</head>
<p>The following buildings are the city-designated, remaining landmarks from Bronzeville's golden age, from the "Black Metropolis" city within a city where blacks could find employment serving their own community.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chicago Bee Building</hi>, 3647-3655 S State St, ☏ +1-312-747-6872 . M-Th 9AM-8PM, F Sa 9AM-5PM. The home of the <hi rend="italic">Chicago Bee</hi> newspaper, which was founded by Anthony Overton to promote black businesses and issues. The art deco building has an elegant terra cotta façade and today houses the Chicago Bee Branch Library. Free. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chicago Defender Building</hi>, 3435 S Indiana Ave. Built in 1899 as a Jewish synagogue, this building housed the <hi rend="italic">Chicago Defender</hi> (the nation's foremost African-American newspaper through World War I) from 1920-1960. The <hi rend="italic">Chicago Defender</hi> published works by Langston Hughes and Gwendolyn Brooks, and is largely credited for starting the Great Migration in its exhortations to southern blacks to move to the North for greater economic opportunities and freedom. The building is oddly vacant and neglected at present and may be available for sale. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Eighth Regiment Armory</hi> (Bronzeville Military Academy), 3533 S Giles Ave, ☏ +1-773-534-9750 . This was the first armory for an African-American regiment, serving the "Fighting 8th," which fought in the Spanish-American War and served with distinction in World War I. After years of disuse, this grandiose building has been restored and now houses the nation's first public college-prep military school, which is unfortunately not open for visitors. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Overton Hygienic Building</hi>, 3619-27 S State St. Built by the wildly successful African-American entrepreneur Anthony Overton to house the headquarters of his nation-wide cosmetics franchise. The building housed several of his other businesses, including Victory Life Insurance Company and Douglass National Bank, America's first national African-American bank. The building is now owned by the Mid-South Planning and Development Commission. Just across the street from the now demolished, notorious Robert Taylor Homes, the formerly beautiful art-deco building is in a sad state of disrepair. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sunset Cafe</hi> (Ace Meyers Hardware Store), 315 E 35th St, ☏ +1-312-225-5687 . M-Sa 9AM-6PM, Su 11AM-2PM. Countless jazz legends played at this legendary jazz club, including: Bix Beiderbecke, Jimmy Dorsey, Benny Goodman, Earl Hines, Fletcher Henderson, Count Basie, and of course, Louis Armstrong. The club was run by unsavory mafia types and the musicians often had no choice but to keep playing here! Disjointed as it may be, the legendary club no longer exists and the building houses a hardware store. Nonetheless, the Sunset Cafe is Chicago's <hi rend="bold">number one jazz history site</hi> and should not be missed by anyone traveling along <ref target="The%20Jazz%20Track">The Jazz Track</ref>. There has been talk of resurrecting the club, but plans remain embryonic. Feel free to stop in if you'd like — the owner is used to all sorts of foreign jazz aficionados wandering in.</item>
</list>

 

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Supreme Life Building</hi>, 3501 S Martin Luther King Jr Dr. Built to house the first African-American insurance company, which was one of the few Black Metropolis businesses to survive the Great Depression. The building houses the Bronzeville Visitor Information Center (see below) and is finally undergoing a proper restoration which will restore the 1920 classical façade. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Unity Hall</hi>, 3140 S Indiana Ave. Built in 1887 to house a Jewish social organization, this building became famous as the headquarters of the Peoples Movement Club, founded by Oscar Stanton De Priest (1871-1951), the first African-American on Chicago's City Council and the first northern black delegate to the U.S. House of Representatives. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Victory Monument</hi>, E 35th St and S Martin Luther King Jr Dr. This monument was built in 1928 to honor the service of the African-American Eighth Regiment of the Illinois National Guard in France during World War I. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Wabash Avenue YMCA</hi>, 3763 S Wabash Ave, ☏ +1-773-285-0020 . Bronzeville's YMCA, housed in a huge 1913 brown-pressed brick building, was a major social and cultural center for the neighborhood in its heyday, providing job training and housing for recent arrivals in addition to its more common functions. A painstaking restoration was completed in 2000 and the YMCA is again open to the community. Free. </item>
</list>
</text>
