<text id="autogum_voyage_doc241" title="Santa Coloma de Cervelló" shortTile="santa-coloma-de-cervello" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=31361" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Santa Coloma de Cervelló</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="w:Santa%20Coloma%20de%20Cervell%C3%B3">Santa Coloma de Cervelló</ref></hi> is a small minicipality near <ref target="Barcelona">Barcelona</ref> in <ref target="Spain">Spain</ref>.</p>
<head>Understand</head>
<p>It’s a nice village in the region of the Baix Llobregat, where there are many pine forests to walk around. It has the tranquillity of a small town and it is near the big city. There are many streets with home gardens. </p>

<p>In Santa Coloma de Cervelló municipality is located <hi rend="italic">Colònia Güell</hi> — a famous and one of the most important modernist sites in the province of Barcelona. </p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Visitor Service Centre</hi>, c/ Claudi Güell, s/n, Colònia Güell, ☏ +34 93 630 58 07 , ✉ coloniaguell@adleisure.com . Nov-Apr M-F 10:00-17:00, Sa-Su 10:00-15:00; May-Oct M-F 10:00-19:00, Sa-Su 10:00-15:00.</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>
<p>For Colonia Güell take <ref target="http://www.gaudicoloniaguell.org/en/practical-info/how-arrive">FGC trains S4, S8 and S33</ref> from <hi rend="italic">Plaça d'Espanya</hi>, Barcelona, get off at <hi rend="italic">Colonia Güell</hi> stop, then follow blue footprints painted on the pavement.</p>

<p>Santa Coloma de Cervelló is the next stop.</p>

<p>If, by chance, you are heading to Colonia Güell right from the <ref target="Barcelona%20El%20Prat%20Airport">airport</ref> by R2 Nord train, then you don't need to go to Plaça d'Espanya to get a FGC train. Instead you can make a change at <hi rend="italic">Bellvitge</hi> RENFE stop (the 2nd from the airport) to <hi rend="italic">Gormal</hi> FGC station (just cross a square) and save half an hour.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>By foot — that's a small place.</p>

<head>Colònia Güell</head>
 <hi rend="bold">Colònia Güell</hi>. It is a tiny settlement built on-purpose around a textile factory. The works began in 1890 and a number of renowned Catalan architects participated in this project: Antoni Gaudí, Francesc Berenguer, Joan Rubio. 
<p>Without a doubt the most important object there is:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">La cripta de la Colònia Güell</hi> (The crypt of the Church of Colònia Güell). see Visitor Service Centre hours. Albeit unfinished and one of the most forgotten of his works, the crypt is a highlight in the creative work of Gaudí. €7. </item>
</list>


<p>A <ref target="http://virtualcoloniaguell.com/"><hi rend="italic">virtual tour</hi></ref> to the crypt is available on the Internet.</p>

<p>Among the other notable buildings are:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ca l’Ordal</hi>. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ca L’Espinal</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">L’Escola i casa del mestre</hi> (The School and the Teacher’s House).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Can Soler de la Torre</hi>. An old Catalan mansion dating back to 1622.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<p>Every May there’s a festival to honor the cherries , there is an exhibition of different kinds of cherries.</p>

<head>Buy</head>
<p>The people come to live here to be quiet . There aren’t many stores because it’s very small but it’s safe and friendly. </p>
<p>There is a tiny supermarket and a Tobacco shop at the street behind the Visitors center. </p>
<p>It has a square where every Sunday, many people take their children out to play.</p>

<p>There is a farmer's market on Saturday mornings in Colonia Guell.</p>

<head>Eat</head>
<p>At the Colonia Guel there is a couple of restaurants and a cafe. Also in the lobby of the public toilet facility there is a couple of vending machines with drinks and snacks.</p>

<head>Drink</head>
<p>It looks like there is no nightlife in this place.</p>

<head>Sleep</head>
<p>There are no hotels here, but Barcelona is only 20 minutes away by train. Perhaps you'd be able find an apartment to rent here.</p>

<head>Connect</head>
<p>Free WiFi at the Visitor's Centre.</p>

<head>Cope</head>
<p>There a free public toilet just across the street of the Visitor's Centre.</p>

<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Montserrat_%28Spain%29">Montserrat</ref> — <hi rend="italic">Santa Coloma de Cervelló</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Colonia Guell</hi> stations are located on the railroad connecting Montserrat with Barcelona.</item>
</list>
</text>
