<text id="autogum_voyage_doc347" title="West Kilbride" shortTile="west-kilbride" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=39052" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>West Kilbride</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">West Kilbride</hi> is a historic small town in North <ref target="Ayrshire">Ayrshire</ref>, <ref target="Scotland">Scotland</ref>.</p>

<p>In September 2006, West Kilbride won First Prize in the "Enterprising Britain 2006" award, for its "Craft Town Scotland" initiative.</p>
<head>By car</head>
<p>The A78 - picturesque coastal route, wending through North Ayrshire.</p>

<head>By bus</head>
<p>Stagecoach and Shuttle Buses both provide a regular service;</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Regular passenger trains from <ref target="Largs">Largs</ref> to Glasgow Central Station; </p>

<head>By plane</head>
<ref target="Prestwick">Prestwick</ref> Airport and <ref target="Glasgow">Glasgow</ref> Airport are convenient.

<head>Get around</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Eddie's Taxis</hi>, ☏ +44 1294 822812 .</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">West Kilbride Museum</hi>, West Kilbride Village Hall, 1 Arthur Street. Tue, Thu, Sat:10:30am – 12:30pm, 2:00pm – 4:00pm. free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Portencross Castle</hi>. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Law Castle</hi>. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Seamill Beach</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ardneil Bay</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hunterston B nuclear power station</hi>. Visitor centre, and tours of the power station are available if UK citizens book 3 weeks in advance, (4+ weeks for foreigners). The AGR (Advanced Gas cooled Reactor) power station has been generating since 1976, and is scheduled to operate until 2023. The older Magnox Hunterston A next door operated from 1957 to 1990. </item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">West Kilbride Golf Club</hi>, Fullarton Drive, Seamill. This well-respected 18-hole links course offers many challenges to test even the seasoned golfer. The fabulous view of Arran makes a wonderful backdrop to your game - and you may find it hard not to take your eye off the ball! Relax in the clubhouse afterwards. from £30 (winter round).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kirktonhall Glen</hi>. is a woodland walkway leading from West Kilbride to Seamill, gifted to West Kilbride in 1924 by Robert Barr. Through it flows the Kilbride Burn which enters the Firth of Clyde at Seamill.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Craft Town Scotland art gallery and museum</hi>, The Barony Centre, 50 Main Street, ☏ +44 1294 829179 .</item>
</list>
<head>Buy</head>
<p>West Kibride has recently been dubbed "The UK's Capital of Enterprise" because of its pioneering Craft Town Scotland initiative. Its growing colony of top-class craftspeople and retail shops deserves your support. Now is the time to invest in original and stylish works of art - for example, from <ref target="http://www.marionsilversmith.com">Silversmith Marion Kane</ref>; Nicola Beattie, candle-maker; and many others. </p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">A Gift Tae Gie</hi>, 45 Main Street, ☏ +44 1294 829509 . offers a fantastic array of gifts, toys, cards and interior accessories for all ages.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Glenbryde</hi>, 31 Ritchie Street, ☏ +44 1294 829839 . specialises in the sale of quality clocks and barometers.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>
<p>Various Indian and Chinese take-aways in the centre of town</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Cherry Orchard</hi>, 2C Orchard St, ☏ +44 1294 824880 . delightful coffee-shop in the heart of West Kilbride</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Seamill Hydro Hotel and Resort</hi>, 39 Ardrossan Rd, Seamill, ☏ +44 1294 822217 . beautiful restaurant with a la carte and table d'hote menus.</item>
</list>

<p>Further afield</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Catch At Fins Restaurant</hi>, Fencefoot Farm, Fairlie, KA29 0EG. Thu - Sat: noon - 3PM, 6PM - 9PM; Sun: 12PM - 3PM. award-winning seafood restaurant mains from £12.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Braidwoods</hi>, Dalry. Michelin star restaurant dinner from £50.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>
<p>The Kilbride Tavern and the King's Arms are typical Scottish pubs, located in the heart of West Kilbride.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Wee Deli</hi>, 2 Ritchie Street, ☏ +44 1294 822015 . A tardis of food delights. Best known for the wee deli pate &amp; soups.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Carlton Seamill Bed &amp; Breakfast</hi>, 53 Ardrossan Road, Seamill, ☏ +44 1294 822075 , ✉ carlton@westkilbride.net . Impressive Scottish Victorian house and garden. Generous Traditional Scottish Breakfast. Rooms from £65 per couple per night..</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Waterside</hi>, Ardrossan Rd., ☏ +44 1294 824414 .</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<p>Major tourist attractions near here are: </p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Isle%20of%20Arran">Isle of Arran</ref> (Brodick);</item>
<item> Isle of <ref target="Great%20Cumbrae">Great Cumbrae</ref> (Millport)</item>
<item> <ref target="Isle%20of%20Bute">Isle of Bute</ref> (Rothesay and Mount Stuart)</item>
<item> <ref target="Loch%20Lomond%20and%20The%20Trossachs%20National%20Park">Loch Lomond and The Trossachs National Park</ref></item>
<item> Clyde Muirshiel Regional Park; City of <ref target="Glasgow">Glasgow</ref></item>
<item> Robert Burns Heritage Trail; Kelburn Castle and Country Estate</item>
<item> Important golf courses within easy reach - for example, Royal <ref target="Troon">Troon</ref> and <ref target="Prestwick">Prestwick</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
