<text id="autogum_voyage_doc402" title="Sierre" shortTile="sierre" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=154119" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sierre</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.sierretourisme.ch/">Sierre</ref></hi> (German: <hi rend="italic">Siders</hi>) is a city in Central <ref target="Valais">Valais</ref>. While the city is in the French part of Valais, there is a large German-speaking population and you will encounter many people being fluent in both languages. Sierre has a a rich cultural heritage but is also known for its wine. </p>

<head>Understand</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tourist Information</hi>, Place de la Gare 10, ☏ +41 27 455 85 35 , ✉ info@sierretourisme.ch . M–F 08:30–18:00, Sa 09:00–17:00, Su 09:00–13:00.</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>

<p>The is in the city centre. There are half-hourly trains from <ref target="Brig">Brig</ref> and <ref target="Visp">Visp</ref>, as well as from <ref target="Sion">Sion</ref>. <ref target="Lausanne">Lausanne</ref> and <ref target="Geneva">Geneva</ref>. Half hourly regional trains connect to the smaller towns.</p>

<p>The is around 500 metres from the main station and links to <ref target="Crans%20Montana">Crans Montana</ref>.</p>

<head>By car</head>

<p>From the <hi rend="bold">A9 motorway</hi> north of the city, either exit Sierre-Ouest or Sierre-Est can be taken to access Sierre.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>The city centre is quite compact and it is possible to walk to most places.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hôtel de Ville</hi> (Right outside the main entrance to the train station). This building which serves today as town hall was built during the 17th century by Jean-François de Courten as a residence. It served as a hotel for a long time, where a lot of famous people stayed for long periods.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Château des Vidômes</hi>. Not accessible to the public. A castle from the 15th century and Sierre's oldest building.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Church Sainte-Catherine</hi>. Baroque style church from the 17th century.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Notre-Dame des Marais</hi>. The old church of Sierre, built in the 14th century.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Wine Museum in Sierre-Salgesch</hi>, Rue Ste-Catherine 6, ☏ +41 27 456 35 25 , ✉ contact@museeduvin-valais.ch . March-October W-F 14:00–18:00, Sa-Su 11:00–18:00. This museum about all things wine is spread out over two villages, with one exposition in Sierre and a different one in nearby . Both museums are linked by a 6 km long trail through vineyards. Fr. 6 for both museums.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Foire de Ste-Catherine</hi>. Monday and Tuesday of the last or second last week of November.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">VINEA wine fair</hi> (Around the Hôtel de Ville), ☏ +41 27 456 31 44 , ✉ info@vinea.ch . Two days in early September. Wine fair showcasing wines from around Switzerland. Fr. 30 per day.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fondation Rilke</hi>, Rue du Bourg 30, ☏ +41 27 456 26 46 , ✉ info@fondationrilke.ch . Tu-Su 14:00-18:00. A museum dedicated to the work of the poet Rainer Maria Rilke. It is situated in the 18th century Maison Pancrace de Courten.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Didier de Courten</hi>, Rue du Bourg 1, ☏ +41 27 455 13 51 , ✉ info@hotel-terminus.ch . Tu-Sa 12:00–13:00, 19:00–21:00. This two-Michelin star restaurant is owned and operated by a renowned Swiss chef. Offers special menus for vegetarians and other dietary restrictions. Mains from Fr. 80, set meal from Fr. 180.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>
<p>Sierre is known for its wine.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Œnothèque Château de Villa</hi>, Rue de Sainte-Catherine 4, ☏ +41 27 456 24 29 , ✉ info@chateaudevilla.ch . M-F 10:30–13:00, 16:30–20:30, Sa-Su 10:30–20:30. This wine-bar has a huge collection of wines from all over the Valais.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hôtel de la Poste</hi>, Rue du Bourg 2, ☏ +41 27 456 57 60 , ✉ info@hotel-sierre.ch . Fr. 140.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Take the funiculaire up to <ref target="Crans%20Montana">Crans Montana</ref>.</item>
<item> <ref target="Sion">Sion</ref>, the capital of the canton, is only 10 minutes away by train.</item>
</list>
</text>
