<text id="autogum_voyage_doc132" title="Sweden" shortTile="sweden" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=34810" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sweden</head>

<ref target="http://www.visitsweden.com/sweden/"><hi rend="bold">Sweden</hi></ref> (<ref target="Swedish%20phrasebook">Swedish</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Sverige</hi>) is the largest of the <ref target="Nordic%20countries">Nordic countries</ref> by size and population, with about 10 million inhabitants. It borders <ref target="Norway">Norway</ref> and <ref target="Finland">Finland</ref> and is connected to <ref target="Denmark">Denmark</ref> via a bridge-tunnel across Öresund.

<p>Visitors can experience deep forests and many lakes, the heritage from the <ref target="Viking%20Age">Viking Age</ref> and the 17th-century Swedish Empire, the glamour of the Nobel Prize, and the country's successful pop music scene.</p>

<head>Regions</head>
<p>The three traditional lands of Sweden, <hi rend="bold">Götaland</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Svealand</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Norrland</hi>, are further divided into 25 provinces (<hi rend="italic">landskap</hi>), which largely define Swedish people's cultural identity.</p>

<p>The provinces mostly coincide with the 21 counties (<hi rend="italic">län</hi>), the mid-level political entities. The 290 municipalities (<hi rend="italic">kommun</hi>), are the bottom-level political entities, typically consisting of a town or a city, and the surrounding countryside, including small villages. Some municipalities used to hold city (<hi rend="italic">stad</hi>) privileges, and still style themselves as such, though there is no legal distinction. Most municipalities have their own visitor centre.</p>

<p>Though Swedish people rarely have strong feelings for their country, most of them are patriotic for their province or hometown, and appreciate anything good that a traveller can say about them.</p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> is Sweden's capital and largest city, spread out over several islands.</item>
<item> (Swedish: <hi rend="italic">Göteborg</hi>) is Sweden's largest port and industrial centre, second in population.</item>
<item> is a <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20Site">UNESCO World Heritage Site</ref>, as the base for Sweden's navy since the 17th century.</item>
<item> has a large university, and is the birthplace of Sweden's aviation industry.</item>
<item> is a lively pretty university city with a Viking Age heritage.</item>
<item> , with a quarter million inhabitants, is connected to the Danish capital Copenhagen by the Öresund Bridge.</item>
<item> is the largest city in Norrland, known for its silver birches and university.</item>
<item> , once the centre of Viking era Sweden, is home to the largest cathedral and oldest university in the Nordic countries.</item>
<item> is the only city on the <ref target="Gotland">Gotland</ref> island, a <ref target="Hanseatic%20League">Hanseatic League</ref> centre of commerce with an impressive city wall.</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> is the traditional heartland of Swedish metallurgy and mining.</item>
<item> is a freshwater archipelago with the Royal family's residence Drottningholm, and Viking Age settlement Birka.</item>
<item> (Swedish: <hi rend="italic">Höga kusten</hi>) is the most scenic area along the Norrland coast.</item>
<item> (<ref target="Sami%20phrasebook">Sami</ref>: <hi rend="italic">Giron</hi>) at Sweden's northernmost edge is known for a large mine, a space flight centre, the <ref target="Jukkasj%C3%A4rvi">Jukkasjärvi</ref> ice hotel and <ref target="Abisko">Abisko</ref> national park.</item>
<item> is Western Europe's largest wilderness, in the Arctic.</item>
<item> is an archetype of Swedish folk culture in central <ref target="Dalarna">Dalarna</ref>.</item>
<item> (Swedish: <hi rend="italic">Stockholms skärgård</hi>) consists of islands all shapes and sizes.</item>
<item> is one of Sweden's largest ski resorts, with 44 lifts.</item>
<item> is Sweden's second largest island, with long beaches.</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
<p>The "Nordic model" of economics and social policy was largely developed by Swedish social democrats and liberals during the early 20th century. The foundation is a strong welfare state, combined with market economics. Swedish society, as it has become through this policy, is often described as "folkhemmet", comparing solidarity in the society with that in a family:</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>In ancient times, Sweden was inhabited by the Suiones (<hi rend="italic">svear</hi>) in <ref target="Svealand">Svealand</ref> and the Geats (<hi rend="italic">götar</hi>) in Götaland. Some of these participated in Viking expeditions (see <ref target="Vikings%20and%20the%20Old%20Norse">Vikings and the Old Norse</ref>), and are said to have founded the first kingdoms in <ref target="Russia">Russia</ref>. Written sources from the Viking Age are few and short.</p>

<p>Around AD 1000, Christianity replaced Norse paganism, Suiones and Geats united under one king (probably Olof Skötkonung), and the first cities were founded; among them <ref target="Sigtuna">Sigtuna</ref>, <ref target="Uppsala">Uppsala</ref> and <ref target="Skara">Skara</ref>. With Christianity came written chronicles and stone architecture, which have provided the afterworld with better historical detail than earlier remnants. Swedish kings christianized and annexed <ref target="Finland">Finland</ref>. During the 14th and 15th century, Sweden was a subject of the Kalmar Union with Norway and Denmark. Gustav Vasa liberated Sweden from Danish rule, was elected as king in 1523, and is regarded as the founder of modern Sweden. He also reformed the church to Lutheran-Protestant. Today's Sweden is a secular state with very few church-goers.</p>

<p>During the 17th century Sweden rose as a Great Power, through several successful wars (such as the <ref target="Thirty%20Years%27%20War">Thirty Years' War</ref>), where kings such as Gustavus Adolphus and Charles X annexed <ref target="Scania">Scania</ref>, <ref target="Halland">Halland</ref> and <ref target="Bohusl%C3%A4n">Bohuslän</ref> from <ref target="Denmark">Denmark</ref>, as well as temporary possessions in the <ref target="Baltic%20countries">Baltic countries</ref> and <ref target="northern%20Germany">northern Germany</ref>. In the early 18th century, an alliance of Denmark, Poland and the <ref target="Russian%20Empire">Russian Empire</ref> defeated Swedish king Charles XII, marking the end of the Swedish Empire. In 1809, Sweden was again defeated by Russia, which annexed Finland. The country has been at peace since 1814; the country has a high peace profile, with internationally renowned names such as Raoul Wallenberg, Dag Hammarskjöld, Olof Palme and Hans Blix. Sweden is a monarchy by constitution, but King Carl XVI Gustaf has no executive power.</p>

<p>Sweden is a developed post-industrial society with an advanced welfare state. The standard of living and life expectancy rank among the highest in the world. Sweden joined the European Union in 1995, but decided by a referendum in 2003 not to commit to the European Monetary Union and the euro currency. Leadership of Sweden has for the larger part of the 20th century been dominated by the Social Democratic Party, which started out at the end of the 19th century as a labor movement (coalitions of centre-right liberal/conservative parties held the power 1976–1982 and 2006–2014).</p>

<p>Sweden has a strong tradition of being an open, yet discreet country. Citizens sometimes appear to be quite reserved at first, but once they get to know who they are dealing with, they'll be as warm and friendly as you'd wish. Privacy is regarded as a key item and many visitors, for example mega-stars in various lines of trade, have many times realized that they mostly can walk the streets of the cities virtually undisturbed.</p>

<p>Sweden houses the Nobel Prize committee for all the prizes except the peace prize, which is hosted in Oslo, a memento of the Swedish-Norwegian union that was dissolved in 1905.</p>
</text>
