<text id="autogum_voyage_doc179" title="Fire Island" shortTile="fire-island" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11631" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fire Island</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Fire Island</hi> is a 32-mile (51.5-km) barrier island off the coast of <ref target="Long%20Island">Long Island</ref> in <ref target="Suffolk%20County%20%28New%20York%29">Suffolk County</ref>, <ref target="New%20York%20%28state%29">New York</ref>. Most of <ref target="Fire%20Island%20National%20Seashore">Fire Island National Seashore</ref> is on the island.</p>

<head>Communities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Kismet - The westernmost village, a haven for singles and partiers that is now becoming more family-oriented.</item>
<item> Saltaire - A family-oriented village featuring Clam Cove harbor. During the summer, the village has many youth sport programs. Larger houses than most of the island</item>
<item> Fair Harbor - Another family-oriented community that appeals to creative artists as well. Small house on small lots that are very close to each other.</item>
<item> Dunewood - A totally planned and residential community. Group houses are banned in order to preserve the family oriented atmosphere.</item>
<item> Lonelyville - No longer a lonely place, but with some solitude.</item>
<item> Atlantique - A very small community with no commercial services.</item>
<item> Robbins Rest - Another small and relatively isolated place.</item>
<item> Corneille Estates - A small place to the west of Ocean Beach that hosts the island's school.</item>
<item> Ocean Beach Village - The main tourist destination and cultural center. Formerly known as "the Land of No" because of many rules to discourage tourism, the local rules have become more visitor friendly, designed to keep the village as a quality of life destination.</item>
<item> Seaview - A beautiful and residential area with the tallest trees and great walks. Also known as the suburb of Ocean Beach.</item>
<item> Ocean Bay Park - One of the livelier villages thanks to Flynn's.</item>
<item> Point O'Woods - A private and gated community. Residents must have children, and have 99-year leases rather than ownership. Visitors not permitted.</item>
<item> Cherry Grove - Once the gay "capital" of Fire Island, now a haven for lesbians, older gay men and those with an artistic flair.</item>
<item> Fire Island Pines - For urbane gay men. A retreat from the real world, with "rolling boardwalks" and natural beauty and late-night discos.</item>
<item> Water Island - Small, quiet community on the narrowest part of the island.</item>
<item> Davis Park - The most remote, most self-sufficient, birthplace of the "sixish". Tourism is allowed, there is a Town of Brookhaven beach in the middle of the community</item>
<item> Watch Hill - The largest National Seashore complex with 3 mi (4.8 km) of boardwalks and a campsite. Tourists welcome.</item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Sunken Forest at Sailor's Haven - A primordial holly forest crisscrossed with wooden walkways administered by the national park service</item>
<item> <ref target="Fire%20Island%20National%20Seashore">Fire Island National Seashore</ref> —</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
<p>There are no paved roads going to most of the island and vehicle traffic is not permitted in summer. A plan to create a paved road across the island resulted in such resistance that it was abandoned. Over the years each of the island's seventeen communities has developed its own unique personality. Several of the villages restrict access by tourists or do all they can to be unwelcoming of tourists. If you are visiting Fire Island, make sure you find the appropriate community to visit. In some cases, visiting the state parks, instead of the towns, might be a better solution. In addition to the state parks at either end of the island, public bathrooms and snack bars are in the National Seashore facilities at Atlantique, Sailor's Haven, and Watch Hill. Restrooms can also be found in Ocean Beach and Fair Harbor but may be hard to find.</p>

<p>Fire Island is home to many vacation communities on the western part of the island (Ocean Beach being the most populous, with the most restaurants and bars that make for an excellent day trip). The eastern part of the island is home to the largely gay communities of Cherry Grove and Fire Island Pines.</p>

<p>Bring cash with you on your trip to Fire Island as most businesses will only accept cash payment. (This includes parking, transportation fees to and from the island, on many of the small on island shops.)</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>Most of these methods of getting in must be used in combination. For example, to reach Fair Harbor from Manhattan, you could take the LIRR, then a taxi from the train to the ferry, and then the ferry to the Island. The car methods mentioned are usually only good for day trips, and there is no way to get from the parking lots to the main parts of the island other than walking.</p>

<head>By air</head>
<p>The island is about 60 miles from <ref target="Manhattan">Manhattan</ref> (the drive can range anywhere from 1-4 hr based on traffic. It averages about 1½ hr). You can fly into LaGuardia or Kennedy Airports in <ref target="New%20York%20City">New York City</ref> or Islip MacArthur Airport on <ref target="Long%20Island">Long Island</ref>, then use a rental car, taxi, or train to your destination.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>There are only two bridges to Fire Island. The Robert Moses Causeway on the western end of Fire Island leads to parking lots at Robert Moses State Park. The <hi rend="bold">William Floyd Parkway</hi> leads to Smith Point County Park on the eastern end of Fire Island, where there are also parking lots (fees charged). Fire Island has no public roads.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tommy's Taxis</hi>, <ref target="tel:%2B16316654800">+1 631-665-4800</ref>, also goes direct from Manhattan. $18 (or $21 Sundays and holidays)</item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.sct-bus.org/">Suffolk County Transit</ref></hi>, <ref target="tel:%2B16318525200">+1 631-852-5200</ref>. Operates bus routes to provide access to the island's gateway communities, but you'll have to walk or take a taxi to get to your destination.</item>
</list>


<head>By train</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.mta.info/lirr">Long Island Rail Road</ref></hi>, <ref target="tel:%2B16312315477">+1 631-231-5477</ref>. Has stations are near three ferry terminals: Patchogue, Sayville, and Bay Shore. All have taxi service to the ferry terminals.</item>
</list>


<head>By boat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Ferries to Fire Island depart from the following locations: Sayville and Bay Shore (villages of <ref target="Islip">Islip</ref>) and Patchogue (a village of <ref target="Brookhaven%20%28New%20York%29">Brookhaven</ref>). Water taxis are available if you miss the ferry.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fire Island Ferries</hi>, 99 Maple St, ☏ +1 631-665-3600 . Bay Shore. Year round to Ocean Beach, Fair Harbor, Dunewood, Atlantique, Kismet, Saltaire, Ocean Bay Park and Seaview.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://sayvilleferry.com/">Sayville Ferries</ref></hi>, 41 River Road. Year round to Cherry Grove, Fire Island Pines, Sunken Forest and Water Island.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.pagelinx.com/dpferry/">Patchogue Ferries</ref></hi>, <ref target="tel:%2B16314751665">+1 631-475-1665</ref>. Mid-March to November from two ferry terminals in Patchogue. Leaves from County Road 83 to Davis Park; and from County Road 19 to Watch Hill in the Fire Island National Seashore park.</item>
<item> Many Fire Island sites can be reached by private boat from the Great South Bay, with marinas at Watch Hill, Sailors Haven and most island communities. The bay is shallow, and boaters occasionally moor offshore. When on Fire Island, water taxis can shuttle you from point to point.</item>
</list>


<p>Western Fire Island is reachable by ferry from Bay Shore on Long Island. Bay Shore is about an hour train ride on the Long Island Railroad from Manhattan, and the ferry ride from Bay Shore is another 30 minutes. Ferries to Ocean Beach from Bay Shore run about once every hour during the summer. Cherry Grove and the Fire Island Pines are reachable by ferry from Sayville. The easternmost community, Davis Park, is reachable by ferry from Patchogue.</p>
</text>
