<text id="autogum_voyage_doc182" title="Fort Ross" shortTile="fort-ross" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11890" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Fort Ross</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.parks.ca.gov/%3Fpage_id%3D449">Fort Ross</ref></hi> is a State Historical Park in the <ref target="North%20Coast%20%28California%29">North Coast</ref> of <ref target="California">California</ref>. Although fairly remote, it is well worth a visit as you will become one of the few people who know about the <ref target="Russia">Russia</ref>n contribution to the colonizing of California.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>The fort is in a remote area with little food or services. There is no cell phone service in this region.</p>
<head>History</head>
<p>Fort Ross was a Russian fur trade outpost in what is now <ref target="Sonoma%20County">Sonoma County</ref>, California. It was established by the Russian-American Company in 1812 and sold to John Sutter in 1841, owing to the depletion of the local population of fur-bearing marine mammals, and to the decreased strategic importance of a supply base for Russia's Alaskan colonies following the Conventi<date when="1825-02-28">on of February 28, 1825</date> with the British. It was the southernmost outpost of a Russian presence in the Pacific Northwest and Alaska. The fort and the surrounding settlement was home to Russians, Aleut hunters in their employment, and native Kashia Pomo. This unique site has been the subject of intensive archaeological investigation. It is designated a National Historic Landmark.</p>

<head>Landscape</head>
<p>The fort is on a small peninsula that juts out into the pacific ocean. The edge of the peninsula forms a large bluff (20 m) that can make it somewhat difficult to gain access to the beaches. Large coastal mountains covered in a thick forest tower over the park.</p>

<head>Flora and fauna</head>
<p>There is a wealth of wildlife activity in the region, particularly on the isolated beaches that run below the bluff. Sea otters, sea lions and many impressive sea birds are abundant in the area. Whales are also known to migrate along the coast.</p>

<p>Much of the beaches are covered in large piles of kelp (seaweed) with the occasional tide pool near by. It makes for a great place to explore for wildlife but not great for beach swimming.</p>
<head>Climate</head>
<p>Warm in summer, rainy and foggy (and occasionally sunny) in winter. Dress in layers, and if you are planning on swimming, expect the Pacific Ocean to be cold.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>The most scenic way to get to Fort Ross from <ref target="San%20Francisco">San Francisco</ref> is by driving up the <ref target="Pacific%20Coast%20Highway">Pacific Coast Highway</ref> (Highway 1).</p>

<head>Fees and permits</head>
<p>A day-use vehicle permit costs $8.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Expect a bit of a walk. From the visitor center and parking lot down to the fort proper it is a quarter mile walk. To get down to the beaches expect about a 20- to 30-minute hike.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> Old Russian Fort</item>
<item> Russian Burial Grounds</item>
<item> Russian Orthodox Church</item>
<item> Visitor Center (nicely done)</item>
<item> Whales</item>
<item> Sea Otters</item>
<item> Sea Lions</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<p>Hike along the beach</p>

<p>Cultural Heritage Day - last Saturday in July every year, 10AM-5PM. </p>
<p>The fort comes alive with costumed reenactors, this is a fun way to see the fort as it was in its heyday.</p>

<head>Buy</head>
<p>There is a souvenir shop at the visitor center where you can get some great Russian memorabilia such as post cards with a historical California/Russia post card.</p>

<head>Eat</head>
<p>The fort does not offer much in the way of food so be sure and pack a lunch or expect to drive out of the park to a restaurant or local store to get some food.</p>

<head>Sleep</head>
<p>There are motels located about a half mile drive further up Highway 1. You can also just camp in your car, although it is not recommended that you do this in the Fort Ross parking lot.</p>

<head>Camping</head>
<p>Basic camping facilities are available to the south about a 2-min drive at The Reef Campground. (Pit toilets, camp sites, dirt road, pay phone. Cell phones don't work here.) Open most of the year. Other camp grounds are to the north, 10-20 miles.</p>

<head>Back country</head>
<p>The coastal mountains that tower over the fort have some great hiking trails. Just ask at the visitors center. there are also hiking trails along the bluffs to the north and south of the fort.</p>
</text>
