<text id="autogum_voyage_doc427" title="West Chester (Pennsylvania)" shortTile="west-chester-pennsylvania" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=38871" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>West Chester (Pennsylvania)</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">West Chester</hi> is a borough in <ref target="Chester%20County">Chester County</ref> in the <ref target="Philadelphia%20Region">Philadelphia Region</ref> of <ref target="Pennsylvania">Pennsylvania</ref>. It is the county seat.</p>

<head>By bus</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="http://www.septa.com/index.html">SEPTA</ref> Route 104, follows West Chester Pike into Downtown West Chester, ending in a stop on the campus of West Chester University.</item>
</list>


<head>By air</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Brandywine Airport</hi>, 1205 Ward Ave., ☏ +1 610 692-6100 , fax: +1 610 692-6213 , ✉ airportmanager@n99.com . Small, private airport for corporate or personal flights.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Philadelphia International Airport</hi>. About 45 minutes away from West Chester, the Philadelphia International Airport is much bigger than the Brandywine Airport. It has many commercial airlines that fly in from all over the world.</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>
<p>No taxi services run steadily through downtown West Chester, but the downtown area is an easy walk from one end to another. Walking around downtown is nice because of the historic atmosphere and brick sidewalks with a mixture of shops, bars, restaurants, and local offices.</p>

<head>See</head>

<p>The entire town is rich with history. The cobblestone streets were put in the 1700s. The soldiers of the Revolutionary War walked through West Chester on those very cobblestones. Visitors along with residents marvel at the building where Abraham Lincoln started his journey towards the presidency. West Chester has more than 3,000 structures built before the colonial time which puts the entire downtown on the list of National Registered Historic Places. The town was home for the legendary African-American folk artist, Horace Pippin, Pulitzer Prize winning composer Samuel O. Barber (1910-1981) along with many other aspiring and proven artists.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Chester County Historical Society</hi> (Museum &amp; Library), 225 N. High Street, ☏ +1 610 692-4800 . The Museum &amp; Library are open Tue-Sat, 10 am to 5 pm, The Museum Shop is open Monday-Saturday, 10 am to 5 pm. Definitely bigger and fancier than your average Historical Society Museum. One of the buildings was originally an opera house designed by the same architect who designed the capital dome in Washington, DC. Not as good as a Smithsonian or something, but if you're into history at all and you're in the area, it's definitely worth seeing. Genealogical and newspaper records at the library are very comprehensive. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Court House</hi>, 2 N High street. is a sight to see. It is one of the most historic buildings in the town. William Penn established Chester County as a member of the three first counties of the Colonial Pennsylvania in 1682. In 1724 a courthouse was built near the Delaware River in Chester. Because of population growth the courthouse moved inland into West Chester. A court house was constructed between 1784 and 1786 on High street in the middle of West Chester. This establishment is listed on the National Register of Historic Places.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<p>There are so many exciting things to do in West Chester. With all of the restaurants, bars and shopping there is an activity for everyone.</p>

<p>West Chester University is a major attraction to the area. Many families visit the campus in hopes of sending their children to a highly accredited university. Because the school is located in the heart of the town it is mainly seen as a college town, which means the nightlife is always active and exciting. For those who enjoy golf there are more than five golf courses in West Chester.</p>

<p>Parking is free all weekend in the Parking Garages &amp; Lots and on-street meters. And you never have to feed the meters after 5 pm everyday.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> Televised home shopping channel <hi rend="bold">QVC</hi>'s headquarters and main broadcast studios are just north of town. Studio tours, which are $7.50 ($6 for children), run several times daily, and tickets to special live-audience events are available in advance via the website. A company store selling fan ware with the QVC logo as well as a small selection of popular items is on the premises. <ref target="http://www.qvctours.com"></ref></item>
</list>


<p>For those interested in the arts, downtown West Chester is home to more than 15 shops containing art gallery work.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">American Helicopter Museum</hi>, 1220 American Boulevard, ☏ +1 610-436-9600 . Wed-Sat 10am-5pm; Sun 12n-5pm; Mon-Tue (prescheduled groups only). The American Helicopter Museum and Education Center is an aviation museum devoted exclusively to helicopters. They collect, restore and display historic aircraft and chronicle the origin and development of rotary wing aircraft. This museum can be interesting to actual pilots down to people who know nothing about helicopters. Adults $6; Seniors $5; Students (with ID) &amp; Children (2-12) $4, (under 2) free with paying adult.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Northbrook Canoe Company</hi>, 1810 Beagle Road, toll-free: +1-800-898-2279 . may-sept 9am-4pm. Offers canoeing, kayaking, tubing and splash boat trips.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">West Chester Railroad Heritage Association</hi>, 250 E. Market St., ☏ +1 610 430-2233 . Call for rentals and charters. The purpose of the West Chester Railroad Heritage Association is to collect, preserve, and exhibit railroad equipment and artifacts relating to railroading with emphasis on the southeastern Pennsylvania region; to operate a demonstration railroad for the education and enjoyment of the public.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">West Chester Growers Market</hi>, Church St &amp; Chestnut St. May-Dec: Sa 9AM-1PM. The first producer-only market in southeastern Pennsylvania, in their 17th year. Wide variety of locally grown produce in season along with baked goods, cheese, meat and other farm-market staples.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<p>West Chester is known for its quaint boutiques and trendy shops. Gay street is a central area for shopping. Malena's Vintage boutique, Plane Janea and Niche are just some of the fashionable shops located on Gay Street. The unique finds in Malena's Boutique range from 50s cocktail dresses to Gucci bags. This little store has everything a fashionista would want. Plain Jane sells any type of beauty product a girl could need. This affordable store has jeans and nice button-downs for men along with beautifully, colorful dresses for women. These are just a few of the shopping experiences West Chester has to offer.</p>

<p>One place that is frequented by the local kids during the summertime is the Brandywine River. There are plenty of rope swings and little spots to hang out. The rope swings aren't really a tourist spot, they are more like a hangout spot for residents of West Chester. <ref target="The%20Brandywine%20River%20Park">The Brandywine River Park</ref> is also a popular place for companies and large groups to spend the day. There are also canoe and kayak tours during the spring and summer seasons.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Malena's Boutique</hi>, 145 West Gay Street, ☏ +1 610 738-9952 . M-Sat:12-7; Sun:12-4. The unique finds in Malena's Boutique range from 50s cocktail dresses to Gucci bags</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fairman's Skate Shop</hi>, 43 West Gay Street, ☏ +1 610-344-9959 . Established in 1977, FAIRMAN’S is one of the East Coast's oldest Skate, Snow and Surf shops.</item>
</list>
</text>
