<text id="autogum_voyage_doc401" title="Tacloban" shortTile="tacloban" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=35029" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Tacloban</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Tacloban</hi> is a city in <ref target="Eastern%20Visayas">Eastern Visayas</ref> and the capital of the province of Leyte. It's the home of the Pintados Festival, a cultural event in Leyte commemorating the life and culture of the early settlers of Tacloban.</p>

<head>Tourist Information Centers</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">City Tourism Operations Office</hi>, Tacloban City Hall.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">City Tourism Information and Assistance Counter</hi>, Arrival Area, DZR Airport, San Jose.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Provincial Tourism Office</hi>, Leyte Academic Center, Pawing, Palo, Leyte.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Department of Tourism Regional Office No. 8</hi>, Magsaysay Blvd, ☏ +63 53 3212048 . M-F 9AM-5PM. free city map.</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Daniel Z. Romualdez Airport</hi> (Tacloban Airport, DZR Airport, TAC ). Formerly a US air base during World War II, it is the main entry point to Leyte (and Eastern Visayas in general) by plane. Tacloban Airport has one runway which can accommodate small passenger jets like the Airbus A320 family. This is badly damaged by Typhoon Haiyan (Yolanda) in 2013, but has been rebuilt, and in 2015, the airport is the venue of an open-air Mass during Pope Francis' visit to the Philippines. </item>
</list>


<p><hi rend="bold">Cebu Pacific</hi> flies from <ref target="Ninoy%20Aquino%20International%20Airport">Manila</ref> using an Airbus A320 jet, while its regional carrier <hi rend="bold">Cebgo</hi> flies from <ref target="Mactan%E2%80%93Cebu%20International%20Airport">Cebu</ref> using turboprop aircraft. <hi rend="bold">PAL Express</hi> flies from Manila and Cebu using jets and turboprops, respectively. <hi rend="bold">Philippines AirAsia</hi> has flights from Manila or <ref target="Clark%20International%20Airport">Clark</ref> using jets.</p>

<head>By ferry</head>

<p>There are no passenger ferries to or from Tacloban, but you can take a bus or van to <ref target="Ormoc">Ormoc</ref> port, <ref target="Baybay">Baybay</ref> port or <ref target="Naval">Naval</ref> port then get a ferry to <ref target="Cebu%20City">Cebu City</ref> from there.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> There are buses going to <ref target="Manila">Manila</ref> via <ref target="Catbalogan">Catbalogan</ref>, <ref target="Calbayog">Calbayog</ref>, <ref target="Sorsogon">Sorsogon</ref>, <ref target="Legazpi%20City">Legazpi City</ref>, <ref target="Naga">Naga</ref>, <ref target="Lucena">Lucena</ref>, and to <ref target="Davao">Davao</ref> and <ref target="Cagayan%20de%20Oro">Cagayan de Oro</ref> via <ref target="Surigao">Surigao</ref> and <ref target="Butuan">Butuan</ref>.</item>
<item> There are small buses going from Tacloban to <ref target="Naval">Naval</ref>, <ref target="Sogod">Sogod</ref>, <ref target="Maasin">Maasin</ref>, <ref target="Baybay">Baybay</ref>, and <ref target="Ormoc">Ormoc</ref>.</item>
<item> Long-distance buses arrive at the Tacloban Bus Terminal, 2 km from downtown.</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> There are many ways to get from the airport to all over Tacloban City, especially downtown, which is where most of the fun and excitement happens.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Jeepneys are the cheapest way to get from the airport to downtown and cost an average of ₱10 </hi> for a one way trip downtown, for a taxi or pedicab you are looking at ₱50-100 ; if asked for more, then you are being ripped off.</item>
<item> For visitors not familiar with the city, you hire a tricycle to get to your destination. It costs around ₱8 per ride.</item>
<item> Taxis operate from the airport to any part of the city. MLHuillier Taxi have the most cars. Taxi service is now available from the hotel to fetch you to the airport or any destination within the city and sub-urban towns around Tacloban at a higher price. For pick-up from downtown hotels in Tacloban to the airport, the standard price is ₱250 . More than this amount is above the norm. Be prepared with the exact amount as drivers may not always have loose change. When wanting taxi service at your hotel, ask the front desk, they have contacts with taxi operators and drivers. For out-of-city points, prices are negotiable.</item>
<item> Jeepneys are the cheapest way to travel all around the city. Although confusing at first, it may take you a while to adjust to the directions and the naming of the different sections of the city, if in doubt ask a local since everyone is very willing to help.</item>
<item> When walking around the city, crossing the streets, intersections, observe traffic rules as the city imposes its <hi rend="bold">anti-jaywalking ordinance</hi>. Some tourists and visitors who are used to the indifference of pedestrians in other cities in the Philippines, Tacloban could be a different place for them. The feel of the city is not as urbanized as in other highly urbanized cities in the Philippines. So every visitor and locals alike who come from rural towns may mistakenly take for granted traffic rules. There is a tendency to disregard the local ordinances.</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Price Mansion</hi>, Justice Romualdez Street. CAP Building served as the residence and headquarters of General Douglas MacArthur for three months.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Redona Residence</hi>, T. Claudio Street. Official residence of President Sergio Osmena Sr. during the liberation period.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Leyte Provincial Capitol</hi>, Senator Enage St. The seat of Philippine Commonwealth in 1944.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Philippine-Japan Commemorative Peace Park</hi>, Magsaysay Boulevard. Stone's throw away from city hall. It was donated by the Tokyo Survivors Associations in honor of soldiers and paramilitary personnel who perished in the area.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Maria Kanon Madonna of Peace Shrine</hi>, Magsaysay Boulevard. Near the city hall. Carved out of a rare Miyagi rock and fashioned by Japanese sculptor Shiniche Tani.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tacloban City Convention Center</hi>, Real Street, Sagkahan District. Popularly known as the Astrodome.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Calvary Hill</hi>. Larger than life statues of Jesus Christ and other personages, in tableaux, depict Christ's sacrifice and sufferings.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Crucified Christ and the Map of Leyte Pilgrim Monument</hi>, Magsaysay Boulevard.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Santo Niño Shrine and Heritage Museum</hi>, Real Street.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Balyuan Amphitheater</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Boy Scout Monument</hi>, Fatima Village.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">World War II Japanese Pillboxes</hi>, Baluarte, San Jose.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Indoor climbing at Bukid Outdoor Shop</hi>, P. Burgos Street.</item>
</list>



<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">San Juanico Bridge</hi>. It is the longest bridge in the Philippines. It connects the city to the third biggest island of the Philippines, Samar. The bridge spans 2.14 km and is one of the major tourist spots in the city.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">San Juanico Golf Park and Courtry Club</hi>, Cabalawan Hills.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The People's Center and Library</hi>, Real Street. It houses volumes of books from the US and Europe and other countries.</item>
</list>
<head>Events</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Grand Santacruzan</hi>. May 30</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tacloban City Charter Day</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Balyu-an Rites</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Subiran Regatta</hi>. It is a race of one-man native sailboats with outriggers locally called "subiran" along scenic and historic Leyte Gulf. The race is done without using a paddle but only skills and techniques to manuever the sail.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pintados-Kasadyaan Festival</hi>.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sangyaw Festival</hi>. June 29</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Barrio Fiesta</hi>. Leyte Landing Anniversary, October 20.</item>
</list>
</text>
