<text id="autogum_voyage_doc227" title="Bengkulu" shortTile="bengkulu" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=3400" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bengkulu</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Bengkulu</hi> is the capital of <ref target="Bengkulu%20province">Bengkulu province</ref>, which is named after the city, on the island of <ref target="Sumatra">Sumatra</ref>, <ref target="Indonesia">Indonesia</ref>. With a population of 329,000 (latest estimate for 2014), Bengkulu is the largest city of Bengkulu province. It was founded by the British as their main source of pepper for almost two hundred years, before being exchanged for <ref target="Malacca">Malacca</ref> in 1824. The city offers slow-paced and quiet coastal life - locals hang out on the beach in the late afternoon buying freshly caught fish and waiting for the sun to set.</p>

<head>History</head>

<p>Several small chiefdoms ruled what is nowadays the Bengkulu area. These chiefdoms were under the loose suzerainty of the Inderapura Sultanate from southern West Sumatra. They didn’t flourish as much as the settlements in the eastern part of Sumatra that enjoyed the bustling traffic of Malacca Strait; they were far from major population centres, lacked natural harbours, and were swarmed with diseases. Inderapura became a vassal of the Banten Sultanate after its ruler married the daughter of Inderapura’s sultan circa 1560. </p>

<p>In 1682, the Dutch attacked Banten and expelled all other Europeans including the British from that town. The British thereupon signed a treaty with some chiefs, so as to maintain a presence in Sumatra. After a failed attempt by Banten-Dutch forces to knock the British out, the British established a trading post under the East Indian Company, named the area Bencoolen, and secured a safe anchorage spot for their ships. Their first fort (Fort York) didn’t last very long, leading them to built Fort Marlborough in 1714, which still robustly stands today.</p>

<p>This trading post brought the British only trouble, as it was never profitable, quarrels constantly broke out with the locals, and the local climate was deemed highly unpleasant; yet in spite of all of this, the British remained for another century. In 1807, a rebellion broke out to end the rule of Thomas Parr, the Resident of Bencoolen at that time. He was killed and decapitated in his home during the uprising.</p>

<p>Founder of modern Singapore, Thomas Stamford Raffles landed in Bencoolen on 19 March 1818 to assume the rule of the colony’s Governor General. He managed to abolish slavery, sent in convict labourers from India, and limited cockfighting and similar games among locals. During his time, the tug-of-war between the British and the Dutch concerning the archipelago once again took place. Somehow it was resolved in the Anglo-Dutch Treaty in 1824, in which British Bencoolen was ceded in exchange for Dutch Malacca. Bencoolen (which became Bengkoelen and Bengkulu later) remained part of the Dutch East Indies until the Japanese occupation in World War II.</p>

<p>During Sukarno's imprisonment by the Dutch in the early 1930s, the future first president of Indonesia lived briefly in Bengkulu where he met his wife, Fatmawati. After independence, the city became part of Sumatra Province, then South Sumatra Province, and finally was made capital of the newly-formed Bengkulu Province. </p>

<p>Bengkulu lies near the Sunda Fault and is prone to earthquakes and tsunamis. In June 2000, an earthquake killed at least 100 people. A series of earthquakes struck Bengkulu later during September 2007, killing 13 people. A recent report predicts that Bengkulu is at risk of inundation over the next few decades from undersea earthquakes predicted along the coast of Sumatra.</p>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>Indonesian is widely used in the city for official business, education, commerce, and service purposes. Locals also speak Bengkulunese Malay, lingua franca of the province, especially when conversing among themselves. Both are mutually intelligible, with little adaptation required</p>

<p>Foreign languages are rarely heard in the city. Basic Indonesian knowledge helps a lot during your stay here. Youths should be able to hold conversation in basic English, although most of them will be quite shy about engaging in conversation in a foreign tongue. Despite that, locals are very happy to help and try their best.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Fatmawati Soekarno Airport</hi> ( BKS ). Serves Bengkulu, the city and the province. As of 2016, there are eight, daily direct flights from <ref target="Jakarta">Jakarta</ref> (both <ref target="Soekarno-Hatta%20International%20Airport">Soekarno-Hatta International Airport</ref> and Halim Perdanakusuma Airport in <ref target="East%20Jakarta">East Jakarta</ref>), as well as direct flights from <ref target="Palembang">Palembang</ref>, <ref target="Batam">Batam</ref>, and <ref target="Bandar%20Lampung">Bandar Lampung</ref>. The airport also connects the city to several small towns inland. There is no direct international flight to Bengkulu, and domestic flights are few and tend to be rather expensive. The airport itself consists of two terminals, one is used for high-ranking government service. You can find airlines ticket counters and ATM gallery on the landside of two-storey main terminal, as well as restaurant, gift shop, and lounge on the airside.</item>
</list>

 

<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Siliwangi Antar Nusa</hi> (SAN), ☏ +62 21 4705502 . SAN buses to Bengkulu would take Trans-Sumatran Highway East Route that passes through towns. In turn, the road is in better condition and safer to travel. Jakarta-Bengkulu Rp350.000 (25 hours), Padang-Bengkulu Rp200.000 (12 hours).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Putra Rafflesia</hi>, ☏ +62 21 4892717 . Putra Rafflesia buses to Bengkulu takes Trans-Sumatera West Route which cuts the travel time but the road is not as good as its eastern counterpart as it passes some jungles and hills (Bukit Barisan Selatan National Park). Jakarta-Bengkulu Rp.340.000 (22 hours), Pekanbaru-Bengkulu Rp220.000.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">CSH 88</hi>, ☏ +62 736 23088 . Jakarta-Bengkulu (Rp280.000).</item>
</list>


<p>There are also several van travel services that ply the route between <ref target="Padang">Padang</ref> and Palembang toward Bengkulu. Journey from/to Padang may pass Muara Bungo and Sarolangun in Jambi province (Trans-Sumatran Highway East Route) or the coastal road that go through Mukomuko and Painan (Trans-Sumatran Highway West Route). The latter offers less winding roads, although at some spots, there are potholes and damaged section due to its proximity to the beach. You should ask the travel counter before booking any ticket.</p>

<head>By minivan</head>
<p>Minivan (<hi rend="italic">angkot</hi>) acts as the city's sole public transport system. Riding the minivan will also give you insight into the daily life in the city, since its service covers most of Bengkulu, including traditional markets, business districts, and residential areas. There are neither fixed timetables nor proper stops. You can hail and alight from anywhere along the streets. State your destination before you board and pay when you alight. As of 2016, it costs Rp4.000 per trip regardless of distance. Operating hour is 06AM-06PM. </p>

<p>The drivers usually wait for their van to be filled, which may prolong your waiting time. They are not likely to speak English, so you'll need basic knowledge of Indonesian to ask for information or anything else. Words you need to know are "<hi rend="italic">kiri</hi>" (kee-ree) or "<hi rend="italic">minggir</hi>" (meeng-gear) which indicates you want to alight.</p>

<p>The minivan is colour- and alphabet-coded, based on which line it's operated in. Each alphabet actually has suffix to indicate certain route it takes, but in practice only Green and Red minivan follow the convention.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Yellow minivan/A line</hi> (angkot kuning).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Green minivan/B line</hi> (angkot hijau).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Red minivan/C line</hi> (angkot merah).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Blue minivan/D line</hi> (angkot biru).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">White minivan/E line</hi> (angkot putih).</item>
</list>
</text>
