<text id="autogum_voyage_doc24" title="Aberaeron">
<head>Aberaeron</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Aberaeron</hi> is a coastal town in <ref target="Ceredigion">Ceredigion</ref>, <ref target="Wales">Wales</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Aberaeron is a Welsh-speaking seaside town, with multicoloured houses, a harbour and many small independent shops.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<p>There is no train station. The nearest is in Aberystwyth, from where there are buses. By road, the main A487 runs through the town.</p>

<head>Get around</head>

<p>It's about a 20 minute drive to <ref target="Aberystwyth">Aberystwyth</ref>. To the south there are good beaches at Llangrannog and Cwmtydu.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> The town and harbour. Aberaeron is well known for its multicoloured houses and buildings. Take a stroll down the High Street and around the harbour. Look out for the local family of Bottle-nosed Dolphins out to sea.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Llanerchaeron</hi>, Ciliau Aeron, SA48 8DG (2.5 miles southeast), ☏ +44 1545 570200 , ✉ llanerchaeron@nationaltrust.org.uk . 18th-century Welsh gentry estate - with house, walled gardens and home farm </item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Ceredigion%20Coast%20Path">Ceredigion Coast Path</ref> </hi>. Aberaeron and Aberarth are on the path. Walk along the cliff tops as far as you please.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cegin Cymru</hi> (Welsh Kitchen), 18 Market Street. Lovely little shop selling locally-produced delicacies. The farmhouse cheeses are a particular favourite.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Aeron Sports</hi>, 2 Alban Square. Fishing tackle and other sports gear</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Book Worm</hi> (Gwisgo Bookworm), 8 Sgwar Alban, SA46 0AD, ☏ +44 1545 238282 , ✉ info@gwisgo.co.uk . A good selection of Welsh and English books. Plenty at the more intellectual end of the spectrum. Free parking nearby.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Harbourmaster Hotel</hi> (Gwesty'r Harbwr), 2 Quay Parade, ☏ +44 1545 570755 . has a superb restaurant, specialising in seafood</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">New Celtic</hi>, 8 Market Street, ☏ +44 1545 570369 . fish-and-chips and more restaurant (eat in or take away), tasty and substantial meal</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Hive on the Quay</hi>, Cadwgan Pl (exactly where the name implies), ☏ +44 1545 570445 . The Famous Holgate's <hi rend="bold">Honey Ice Cream</hi>. Also holds a cafe/restaurant serving more substantial meals.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Friends Coffee Shop</hi>, 5 Alban Square, ☏ +44 1545 571122 . A great cafe/takeaway specialising in baguettes and Segafredo coffee. Great quality food at very reasonable prices with a warm and friendly atmosphere.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">La Cuccina</hi>, 35 Alban Square, ☏ +44 1545 571012 . little bakery.</item>
</list>
<head>Drink</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Cadwgan Arms</hi>, 10 Market Street, ☏ +44 1545 570149 .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Royal Oak</hi>, 30 North Road, ☏ +44 1545 570233 .</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">The Harbourmaster Hotel</hi> (Gwesty'r Harbwr), Pen Cei (1 Quay Parade), ☏ +44 1545 570755 . A cobalt blue small hotel with views of the sea and harbour. £80-£120 per night for bed and breakfast.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nant Meigan</hi> (Holiday Home), 9 Water Street, ☏ +44 7971 282007 . A Grade 2 listed Georgian terrace holiday let, in the centre of the town. A five minute walk to the pebble beach, and backing onto the river Aeron, the property enjoys a walled garden.</item>
</list>


<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="New%20Quay">New Quay</ref></item>
<item> <ref target="Aberystwyth">Aberystwyth</ref></item>
</list>
</text>
