<text id="autogum_voyage_doc124" title="Pocatello" shortTile="pocatello" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27900" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pocatello</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.pocatellocvb.com">Pocatello</ref></hi> is a college town in <ref target="Southeastern%20Idaho">Southeastern Idaho</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Named after a noted 19th-century Shoshoni chief, Pocatello is a working-class town with a strong railroad and trade union heritage. As such it has more of a blue-collar feel to it than the other major Idaho cities. At one time the city boasted the largest rail yard west of the Mississippi River. The city has a reputation for being a (slightly) more progressive enclave in otherwise conservative, Mormon-dominated Eastern Idaho.</p>

<p>Although the presence of <hi rend="bold">Idaho State University</hi> in Pocatello unquestionably makes it a college town as well, student life is somewhat more sedate than in other college towns in the region such as <ref target="Moscow%20%28Idaho%29">Moscow</ref>, Idaho, or <ref target="Missoula">Missoula</ref>, <ref target="Montana">Montana</ref>. The bar scene can be lively on the weekends, but don't expect to find too many raging frat house keggers here.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Pocatello Regional Airport</hi> ( PIH ), 1950 Airport Way. Is served by regular flights from <ref target="Salt%20Lake%20City">Salt Lake City</ref> on <hi rend="bold">SkyWest Airlines</hi>. There are no scheduled commercial flights to or from other locations in Idaho. The airport in <ref target="Idaho%20Falls">Idaho Falls</ref>, 45 minutes away, offers a more robust schedule.</item>
</list>

 

<list type="unordered">
<item> Pocatello can be accessed by car via <hi rend="bold">Interstate 15</hi> from <ref target="Idaho%20Falls">Idaho Falls</ref> in the north and <ref target="Salt%20Lake%20City">Salt Lake City</ref> in the south. Pocatello is the eastern terminus of <hi rend="bold">Interstate 86</hi>, which connects the city to the <ref target="Twin%20Falls">Twin Falls</ref> area in the west.</item>
<item> Despite its railroad heritage, Pocatello now has no passenger rail service. For decades the railroad tracks have been used only for freight trains.</item>
</list>


<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Idaho Museum of Natural History</hi>, ☏ +1 208 282-3168 . </item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Deleta</hi> - A rollerskating rink open at nights and during the day on non school days. Also has laser tag, a play area, video games, and a food court.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Outer Limits</hi> - Video games, small indoor roller coaster, laser tag, food and a play area.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">McKee's</hi> - A pet store that also has an outdoor petting zoo. One can pet goats, sheep, pigs, llamas, donkeys, turtles, see ostriches, emus, miniature horses, and even a deer along with lots of chickens.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.shobangaming.com/">Fort Hall Casino</ref></hi> - Owned and operated by the Shoshone-Bannock Tribes, and located on the Fort Hall Indian Reservation north of Pocatello, Fort Hall Casino is the only legal gaming facility in southern Idaho. Unlike in many <ref target="Nevada">Nevada</ref> casinos, where a minimum age of 21 is strictly enforced, 18-year-olds are allowed to gamble (but not drink) here.</p>

<head>Learn</head>
<p>Idaho State University is an important part of Pocatello.</p>

<head>Drink</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">First National Bar</hi>, ☏ +1 208 233-1516 . The in downtown Pocatello is a perennial favorite among ISU students and locals alike. Known locally as simply the "First Nash," the bar often features live blues music on the weekends.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Goody's</hi>, 5th Avenue (directly across from the ISU campus), ☏ +1 208 233-9210 . Doubles as a deli in the front and the bar in the back, both student favorites. If someone says they're going to the "Hindenburg," (the bar's former name), they certainly mean here.</item>
</list>


<head>Camping</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">KOA-Pocatello</hi>, 9815 W Pocatello Creek Rd, ☏ +1 208-233-6851 . Easy access to interstate. Only 30 amp service available; otherwise full hookups. Cook-to-order breakfast for purchase by the park staff, very good food.</item>
</list>


<head>Stay safe</head>

<p>Pocatello tends to have more snow and more severe snowstorms than the other major cities in Idaho (although not as severe as places like <ref target="Stanley%20%28Idaho%29">Stanley</ref>). Given that and the city's hilly landscape, driving can be a challenge in the winter.</p>

<p>The Pocatello area is also subject to inversions in the winter months. This, combined with the output of nearby fertilizer plants, can make air quality an issue.</p>
</text>
