<text id="autogum_voyage_doc201" title="Penzance" shortTile="penzance" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=27245" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Penzance</head>


<ref target="https://www.visitcornwall.com/things-to-do/penzance"><hi rend="bold">Penzance</hi></ref> (Cornish: <hi rend="italic">Pennsans</hi>) is the most south-westerly town in <ref target="Cornwall">Cornwall</ref>. Famous for its association with the Gilbert and Sullivan opera (now often played as a <ref target="musical">musical</ref>) <hi rend="italic">The Pirates of Penzance</hi>, the town is an ideal base for exploring the Penwith area of Cornwall. It is increasingly attracting those interested in cultural tourism due to its long association with the arts.

<p>Penzance is the main link with the <ref target="Isles%20of%20Scilly">Isles of Scilly</ref> via the spring and summer-only ferry.</p>

<head>By plane</head>
 ( NQY ) has flights from London (Gatwick &amp; Stanstead), Dublin, Leeds Bradford, Bristol, Manchester and Cardiff. It's about 30 miles (48 km) away from Penzance by A3075 and A30, reckon 45 min by car. Its two disadvantages are (i) most flights are summer only; (ii) public transport is tricky as first you have to get the bus into <ref target="Newquay">Newquay</ref> (last bus around 6:30PM), then rely on an infrequent bus or branch-line train for connections to Penzance.

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="Exeter">Exeter</ref> Airport</hi> ( EXT ) is further but may be a simpler option. It has more flights year-round, the airport bus runs until 10PM, and mainline trains run hourly from Exeter to Penzance.</p>

<p>There are flights to the <ref target="Isles%20of%20Scilly">Isles of Scilly</ref> from ( LEQ ) at St Just TR19 7RL, 6 miles (10 km) west of Penzance. Flights operate year-round M-Sa and in summer are every 30 min; flight time is just 15 min so day-trips are feasible. The "Skybus" aircraft are small fixed-wing twin-props (e.g. Twin Otter or BNF Islander) so your total baggage limit is only 15 kg, and flights can be grounded by weather that wouldn't bother an Airbus or 737. There's also a helicopter service, using a 10-seater AW169. Adult fare is from £80 each way, day-trip £120 by "Skybus" and from £120 each way, day-trip £220 by helicopter. (For other transport routes, see <ref target="Isles%20of%20Scilly">Isles of Scilly</ref> "Get in".) A bus runs hourly between Penzance railway station and the airport to connect with flights: 20 min, £6 each way, book it along with your flight. By car follow A30 then B3306, long-stay parking is available.</p>

<p>There are plans for a new helipad just outside Penzance, to run helicopters year-round to St Mary's and Tresco in the Isles of Scilly, including on Sundays. This is intended to start service in 2019 but at present is not confirmed.</p>

<head>By train</head>

<p>Direct trains run to Penzance from <ref target="London%20Paddington">London Paddington</ref> (8 daily, 5 hours), <ref target="Exeter">Exeter</ref> (8 daily, 2 hours) and <ref target="Plymouth%20%28England%29">Plymouth</ref> (15 daily, 2 hours). There are frequent connections to Bristol (4 hours), Birmingham (5 hours) and the north, with one direct service to Sheffield, York, Newcastle, Edinburgh and Glasgow.</p>

<p>There is also an overnight sleeper train, <hi rend="italic">The Night Riviera</hi>. This runs Sunday to Friday from London Paddington around 11:30PM, reaching Penzance by 8AM (on Su by M 9AM). The return train leaves Penzance Su-F around 9:30PM to reach Paddington at 5AM; you can stay aboard until 7AM. Book via Great Western (www.gwr.com), with airline seats, or single or double sleeper cabins available.</p>

<p>Other nearby destinations along the main line, served by hourly trains between Penzance and Plymouth, are St Erth (for St Ives), St Austell (for Eden Project), Par (for Newquay), and Bodmin. See <ref target="http://www.nationalrail.co.uk">National Rail</ref> for times and fares; advance booking is usually much cheaper. A <ref target="http://www.nationalrail.co.uk/times_fares/pra3e4df0a040002005aaf3aa9d4ac43.aspx"><hi rend="italic">Ride Cornwall Ranger</hi></ref> is good value for local travel. It allows unlimited off-peak travel within Cornwall, and between Cornwall and Plymouth, by all trains and most buses. "Off-peak" means M-F after 9AM, and all day Sa Su &amp; holidays. An adult day-ticket is £13, children and concessions around £10.</p>

 is at the bottom end of town by the bus station, and a short walk from the ferry terminal. There's not much within the station, but cafes and other facilities in town nearby.

<head>By coach</head>

<p>National Express coach NX404 runs overnight from London Victoria (8 hr) via Heathrow Airport, Bath, Bristol Airport, Exeter, Torquay and Plymouth. NX315 runs daily along the south coast from Eastbourne via Brighton, Portsmouth, Southampton, Eastbourne, Exeter and Plymouth.</p>

<p>First Kernow bus T1 runs every 30 min between Penzance and Truro (1 hr 45 min), via St Erth, Hayle, Camborne, and Redruth. Change at Truro for Newquay, St Austell and Bodmin. Reaching Plymouth and Exeter by bus is not worth the bother, take the train.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>Penzance is a 5- to 6-hour drive from London via M4, M5, and A30. It's a long way and at some point you'll need to refuel. Don't be paying motorway prices, there's supermarket petrol at (amongst others) M5 jcn 28 (Cullompton Tesco), A30 Bodmin (Asda, Launceston Rd Bodmin) and A30 Penzance (Tesco).</p>

<head>By boat</head>
<p>A ferry plies between Penzance and the Isles of Scilly, daily from mid-March to October. The ferry (<ref target="http://www.islesofscilly-travel.co.uk/travel-information/scillonian/">Scillonian III</ref>) leaves Penzance around 9AM to reach the main island of St Mary's at noon; it returns at 4:30PM for 7:15PM. Only foot passengers are carried. Day-trips allow enough time to visit Tresco, where the Abbey Gardens are the islands' main draw. Booking strongly recommended, and see <ref target="Isles%20of%20Scilly">Isles of Scilly</ref>: "Get in" for other ferry practicalities.</p>

<p>For long-stay parking in Penzance while you visit the islands, check Islesofscilly-travel for options, which include:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> For a day-trip, the Council-run long-stay car parks at the Harbour and St Anthony's Gardens charge £8 for 24 hours. They're pay &amp; display so you can't use them for longer stays.</item>
<item> IOS Parking and Scilly Parking are two firms offering secure long-stay parking, both near the harbour and off-site with shuttle transfer. They're about £5 per day.</item>
</list>


<head>Get around</head>

<p>Walking is the best way to get around town in Penzance. <ref target="Newlyn">Newlyn</ref>, <ref target="Mousehole">Mousehole</ref> and St Michael's Mount are within hiking distance for healthy adults, but use the bus for those places if there are children, luggage, or dodgy knees or hips involved. Take the bus for:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Land%27s%20End">Land's End</ref>:</hi> bus A1 hourly via <ref target="Newlyn">Newlyn</ref>, Lamorna and Porthcurno, one hour, from 7AM to 6PM.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="St%20Ives">St Ives</ref>:</hi> bus A2 hourly via Marazion, St Erth and Lelant, 45 min, from 9AM to 10PM.</item>
</list>



<p>These "A"-buses, operated by First Kernow, are blue open-top double-deckers in summer. For bus travel plus rail, a good deal is the <hi rend="italic">Ride Cornwall Ranger</hi> (adult £13) described above. For bus only, buy a <hi rend="italic">Day Rider</hi> for £12 (child £6) from the Bus Station or from the driver on boarding - contactless bank cards accepted. Bus drivers also issue Ride Cornwall Rangers, but only for full price, go to the station for concessions.</p>
</text>
