<text id="autogum_voyage_doc44" title="Niue" shortTile="niue" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=24665" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Niue</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.niueisland.com">Niue</ref></hi> (<ref target="Niuean%20phrasebook">Niuean</ref>: Niuē, <hi rend="italic">NYOO-ay</hi>) is an island in <ref target="Oceania">Oceania</ref> located approximately halfway between <ref target="Tonga">Tonga</ref> and the <ref target="Cook%20Islands">Cook Islands</ref>.</p>

<head>Villages</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Alofi</hi> - the administrative centre and, therefore, possibly the smallest "capital city" on earth with 434 souls at the last census</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Avatele</hi> - formerly known as <hi rend="italic">Oneonepata, Matavaihala</hi>, it's got a population of 150 and the largest and best coarse sand beach on Niue</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hikutavake</hi> - the home of two of Niue's great attractions: the Matapa Chasm and Talava Arches</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Liku</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lakepa</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mutalau</hi> - where Christianity started on Niue</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Makefu</hi> - home to the Avaiki Cave</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hakupu</hi> - gateway to the Huvalu Forest Conservation Area</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Namukulu</hi> - has a small motel</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tamakautoga</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Toi</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tuapa</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Vaiea</hi></item>
</list>


<head>Other destinations</head>
<p>Niue is full of natural wonders, including the following:</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Anapala Chasm</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Avaiki Cave</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Huvalu Forest Conservation Area</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Liku Sea Track and Cave</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Matapa Chasm</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Talava Arches</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Togo Chasm</hi></item>
</list>


<p>These destinations are all covered in more detail in the "See" section below, and several of them are also pictured in this article.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>Niue's remoteness, as well as cultural and linguistic differences between its Polynesian inhabitants and those of the <ref target="Cook%20Islands">Cook Islands</ref>, have led to it being separately administered. It is self-governing in free association with New Zealand since 1974, with Niue fully responsible for domestic affairs, and New Zealand asked to retain responsibility for foreign affairs and defence.</p>

<p>The population of the island continues to drop (from a peak of 5,200 in 1966 to 1,611 at the <ref target="http://www.spc.int/prism/niue/">last census in 2011</ref>) with substantial emigration to <ref target="New%20Zealand">New Zealand</ref> and <ref target="Australia">Australia</ref>.</p>

<p>The economy suffers from the typical Pacific island problems of geographic isolation, few resources, and a small population. Government expenditures used to exceed revenues, with the shortfall made up by critically needed grants from New Zealand that were used to pay wages to public employees. However in 2016, Niue paid off all of its national debt. The agricultural sector consists mainly of subsistence gardening, although some cash crops are grown for export. The sale of postage stamps and coins to foreign collectors is an important source of revenue. Tourism has been identified as the main economic driver for Niue moving forward.</p>

<p>Niue's time zone is GMT-11 while New Zealand's is GMT+12 (GMT+13 during Daylight Saving Time). Therefore Niue is <hi rend="italic">one day behind</hi> New Zealand when New Zealand has Daylight Saving Time, and <hi rend="italic">23 hours behind</hi> New Zealand at other times of the year.</p>

<head>Climate</head>
<p>Tropical; modified by southeast trade winds. The average daytime temperature is 27°C from May to October and 30°C from November to April. December to March is the cyclone season</p>

<head>Landscape</head>
<p>From the sea, the approaches to Niue are flat with its cliff faces resembling a large ‘Swiss cheese’ composed of coral limestone rock peppered with caves. There are hidden caverns and chasms, buried grottoes and other subterranean natural fissures are yet to be discovered and developed into tourist attractions.</p>

<p>The island is approximately 73 km in circumference with two distinct terraces. The upper terrace, 60m high at its highest point, slopes steeply to a 0.5 m coastal terrace ending with high cliffs, some over 20m above sea level. A rugged fringing reef, which in places over 100 m wide, surrounds the island.</p>
<p>Steep limestone cliffs along coast, central plateau. Unlike most Pacific islands, there are no long, white sandy beaches, only tiny, secluded, white sand beaches that might be yours for the whole day.</p>

<head>History</head>
<p>Niue was first settled by Polynesians from Samoa in around 900 AD. Further settlers from Tonga arrived in the sixteenth century.</p>

<p>The first european to spot Niue was Captain James Cook in 1774. He made three attempts to land but was refused permission to do so by the inhabitants.</p>

<p>Mutalau, in the northern end of Niue was where on 26 October 1846 some of the people decided to accept Pastor Peniamina to introduce and teach the gospel to its people before it spread to the four corners of Niue. The Uluvehi landing is the landing place of Christianity.</p>

<head>Time difference from New Zealand</head>
<p>You need to cross the International Date Line (west to east) while travelling from New Zealand to Niue, so Niue is 23 hours behind the mainland (winter) and 24 hours (the whole day) behind in summer. So be careful about the date when you communicate between Niue and New Zealand, because Auckland is one day ahead of Niue.</p>

<head>Visa</head>
<p>Other than New Zealand nationals who are Niueians or descendents of Niueians, everyone will require visa unless they are visiting for less than 30 days. Visitors will require sufficient funds, confirmed reservation for accommodation and return/onward plane ticket.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Niue International Airport</hi> ( IUE also known as Hanan International Airport ) (is about 2 km south-east of Alofi). There is no public transport or taxis to meet the flight though almost all accommodation options include free transfers. If you don't have accommodation booked, just about anyone will give you a lift. </item>
</list>


<ref target="http://www.airnewzealand.co.nz">Air New Zealand</ref> has scheduled flights from <ref target="Auckland">Auckland</ref> twice a week on Wednesdays and Saturdays (arriving in Niue on Tuesday and Friday) and is the only airline that flies to Niue. Huge crowds gather at the airport to meet every flight. Everyone (including New Zealanders) must have a return ticket. There is a $34 (cash only) departure tax upon leaving (not included in price of plane ticket). You might want to avoid flying in around religious holidays such as Easter or Christmas, or the October Constitution celebrations, as seats are often at a premium, since many Niueans return home at these times.

<head>By boat</head>

<p>There are no ferries from foreign ports. Outside of the cyclone season you can sail your own yacht to Niue. Niue Yacht Club has <ref target="http://www.niueyachtclub.com">information on-line</ref>. Harbour fees are $15 per day. If you fly in during sailing season it's possible to hitch on a yacht out of Niue</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Alofi and all the other villages are small enough to walk around. There's no harm in walking around the villages and in town as it is perfectly safe and a good way to catch and interact with the Niuean culture.</p>

<p>Hire a motor vehicle or bicycle on arrival if you don't want to walk. There is no public transport system.</p>
</text>
