<text id="autogum_voyage_doc156" title="Gotland" shortTile="gotland" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13070" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Gotland</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.gotland.info/eng/">Gotland</ref></hi> is <ref target="Sweden">Sweden</ref>'s largest island, in the middle of the Baltic Sea. Some 50,000 people live here all year. Together with some minor islands it forms the <hi rend="italic">Gotland province</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Gotland Municipality</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gotland County</hi>.</p>

<p>With a peculiar dialect, a glorious history and a scenery very different from mainland Sweden, the island has a spirit of independence.</p>

<head>Cities</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> — the only city, around 20,000 inhabitants, crowded during summers. Is on UNESCO's World Heritage list as an "<hi rend="italic">outstanding example of a Northern European walled Hanseatic town which has in a unique way preserved its townscape and its extremely valuable buildings, which in form and function clearly reflect this significant human settlement</hi>".</item>
</list>


<head>Regions and minor islands</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Northern%20Gotland">Northern Gotland</ref></hi> including <hi rend="bold">Slite</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Fårösund</hi> as well as the Lummelunda cave.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Central%20Gotland">Central Gotland</ref></hi> including <hi rend="bold">Roma</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Klintehamn</hi></item>
<item> <hi rend="bold"><ref target="Southern%20Gotland">Southern Gotland</ref></hi> including <hi rend="bold">Ljugarn</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Burgsvik</hi></item>
<item> — A smaller island just off the northern coast of the main island. Known for its high concentration of rauks and sand beaches.</item>
<item> — A national park island north of Gotland.</item>
<item> — The islands of Stora Karlsö and Lilla Karlsö are definitely worth a day's visit, Stora Karlsö is one of the world's oldest nature preserves, second only to <ref target="Yellowstone%20National%20Park">Yellowstone National Park</ref>. Situated outside of Klintehamn.</item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>
<p>Gotland is said to be the homeland of the legendary Goths, who migrated through Central Europe sacked the <ref target="Roman%20Empire">Roman Empire</ref> during the 5th century AD. Medieval Gotland language has many similarities with the Gothic language, though there are no first-hand historical records that the Goths really came from Gotland. In its early history, Gotland was an independent kingdom and still today, the older generations do not regard themselves as Swedes - they are nothing but Gotlanders.</p>

<p>Gotland was a central location of the <ref target="Vikings%20and%20the%20Old%20Norse">Viking Age</ref> of the 8th to 11th centuries. While the true Vikings (pirates or mercenaries) were not from Gotland, many people on the island were sailing merchants; <hi rend="italic">farmaðr</hi>. During the <ref target="Hanseatic%20League">Hanseatic period</ref> in the Middle Ages, <ref target="Visby">Visby</ref> and Gotland was an important stop on the trade routes on the Baltic Sea. The island lost its role after a Danish war in the 14th century. One of the best-known events of the island's history was Danish king Valdemar Atterdag's ransom for Visby, where he demanded large amounts of gold and silver to spare the city from being burnt down. The written records are unreliable, though.</p>

<p>As the Hanseatic League lost importance, the Danes took control over the island for 300 years, ending Gotland's golden age. The Dano-Swedish wars of the 16th and 17th centuries gave Sweden the dominant power of the Baltic Sea, including Gotland. The island was a poor backwater until the late 19th century, as cement manufacturing, tourism and military presence gave the island a renaissance.</p>

<p>Swedish filmmaker Ingmar Bergman recorded many films on Gotland and the surrounding smaller islands, especially <ref target="F%C3%A5r%C3%B6">Fårö</ref>.</p>

<p>The island holds many medieval memories; old farmlands and more than 90 churches, all with different architecture.</p>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>The Gotland dialect is remarkable and is easy to recognize. Still, the islanders understand standard Swedish, and virtually everyone but the oldest speaks English.</p>

<head>By plane</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Visby Airport</hi> ( VBY ) (just north of Visby). The easiest way to get to the city centre is by taxi. There is a special reduced price for travelling the airport-city centre. Approx. 10 minutes. </item>
</list>


<p>There are flights all year to <ref target="Visby">Visby</ref> from <ref target="Stockholm">Stockholm</ref>, <ref target="Gothenburg">Gothenburg</ref> and <ref target="Link%C3%B6ping">Linköping</ref>. During summer, there's also flights from <ref target="Oslo">Oslo</ref> and <ref target="%C3%84ngelholm">Ängelholm</ref>. A flight from Stockholm takes about 25 minutes, from Gothenburg about 50 minutes.</p>

<head>By boat</head>
<ref target="http://www.destinationgotland.se/">Destination Gotland</ref> runs ferries from <ref target="Nyn%C3%A4shamn">Nynäshamn</ref> and <ref target="Oskarshamn">Oskarshamn</ref> to Visby all year. You can also bring your car. This is the cheapest way to get to the island. The ferry takes about three hours. The harbour is in the very centre of Visby.

<p>Gotland is a natural destination for <ref target="boating%20on%20the%20Baltic%20Sea">boating on the Baltic Sea</ref>. Safe natural harbours are few if any, but there is an adequate number of guest harbours spread along the coasts, the most busy in Visby centre.</p>

<p>Several <ref target="cruising%20the%20Baltic%20Sea">international cruise lines</ref> call at Gotland.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>The easiest way to see the island is by car. There are several <ref target="car%20rentals">car rentals</ref> in Visby.</p>

<p>There are also bus services from Visby to all parts of the island, but be sure to bring a timetable before you leave Visby, since many bus stops are served only a few times per day. See <ref target="http://www.gotland.se/kollektivtrafiken">Kollektivtrafiken</ref> and <ref target="http://resrobot.se">Resrobot</ref> (a search engine for all public transport inside Sweden).</p>

<p>Gotland is Sweden's largest island, but still only about 120 km from north to south and 50 km across, and with relatively short distances between different sites of interest. Most roads are paved and the hills are few. Therefore, <ref target="cycling">cycling</ref> is an alternative to driving. Bikes can be brought from mainland on the ferry, or rented at arrival to the island (or later, if you go to a suitable location).</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> There are over 90 <hi rend="bold">medieval churches</hi> on the island. Most of them haven't been modernised since the 15th century.</item>
</list>


<head>Rauks</head>

<p>Fantastic rock formations (<hi rend="italic">Raukar</hi>) are found along the island's coast. These natural sculptures are made out of lime stone and created as surrounding "softer" minerals have been eroded by the sea.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Asunden rauk field</hi> (By Slite in the north-eastern of Gotland). A barren island, connected to the Gotland mainland by a bridge, with a large rauk field.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bjärge rauk field</hi> (Located on Fårö). The largest rauk field on Gotland.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gamle hamn rauk field</hi> (Located on Fårö). Also contains a viking era burial field.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hammarshage hällar and Holmshällars rauk fields</hi> (In the southern part of Gotland). Two nearby rauk fields.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hoburgsgubben</hi> (On the southernmost tip of Gotland). The rauk is said to resemble a human face in profile from the right angle.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Kyllaj rauk field</hi> (In north-eastern Gotland).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Langhammars rauk field</hi> (Located on Fårö).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lergrav and Husken rauk fields</hi> (On the north-eastern shore of Gotland). Two nearby rauk fields.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Lickershamn rauk field and "Jungfrun"</hi>, Lickershamn (Approx. 25 km north of Visby). There is a minor rauk-field by the village Lickershamn. However, the rauk "Jungfrun", located some 500 meters from Lickershamn, is the largest rauk on Gotland.</item>
</list>
</text>
