<text id="autogum_voyage_doc113" title="Hajar Mountains" shortTile="hajar-mountains" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=13886" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Hajar Mountains</head>


<p>The <hi rend="bold">Hajar Mountains</hi> are a range in <ref target="Northern%20Oman">Northern Oman</ref> stretching along the northern coast of Oman, from southwest of Muscat to the United Arab Emirates.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>This dramatic mountain range has a wealth of attractions for the adventurous traveler, including trekking, rock climbing, canyoning, and off-road exploration. In addition to outdoor activities, there are numerous sights of historic, cultural, and geological interest.</p>

<p>Temperatures in the higher elevations tend to be on average 10-15°C cooler than Muscat, and snow, although very rare, is not unknown. In summer the mountains offer a retreat for those looking to escape the heat baking the rest of Oman and the Arabian peninsula.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>From <ref target="Muscat">Muscat</ref>, Highways 15 and 21 skirt the southern reaches of the range, and Highways 13 and 11 provide access from the north. Travelers from the <ref target="UAE">UAE</ref> will arrive via Highway 21.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>It is possible to get a glimpse of some of the mountains' spectacular scenery with just a 2WD, but to really explore a 4WD is essential, as many highlights are otherwise simply inaccessible.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Archaeological Sites of Bat, Al-Khutm and Al-Ayn</hi> (from Hwy 21, turn north at the petrol station between Nizwa and Ibri, following signs for Amla, Al Ayn, Damm/Dham, and Sint). Three sites of prehistoric settlements and beehive tombs dating from the 3rd millennium BCE, collectively inscribed on the <ref target="UNESCO">UNESCO</ref> World Heritage list.</item>
</list>

 Free. 


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Bat</hi>. This site was excavated in 1976 and includes communal graves, ruins of tower forts, and beehive tombs. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Al-Khutm</hi> (2 km west of Bat). This site contains the ruins of a stone tower 20 m in diameter. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Al Ayn</hi> (Al Ain). These unexcavated beehive tombs here are in much better condition than those at Bat, with the added dramatic backdrop of Jebel Misht and its 1000m-high cliffs. To access them, take the graded road to the left (just past the junction), and turn right and drive 100 m down the wadi. From here a footpath leads to the tombs. </item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Wadi Tanuf</hi> (Wadi Tanoof) (access from Hwy 21). At the mouth of the wadi are the photogenic ruins of Old Tanuf, which was bombed extensively by the British Royal Air Force during the Jebel Rebellion of 1954-1955. A 4WD track proceeds up the wadi past a recharge dam to the trailheads for <hi rend="bold">W19</hi> and <hi rend="bold">W19a</hi> (not waymarked), two excellent hikes through and above neighboring Wadi Qashah. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Al Hoota Cave</hi> (Al Hutah, Al Hotta, Al Fallah, Al Falahi), Al Hoota Cave Rd (turn off of Hwy 21 enroute to Al Hamra), ☏ +968 24 498258 (reservations required) , ✉ reserve@alhootacave.com . Sa-Th 09:00-13:00, 14:00-18:00; F 09:00-12:00, 14:00-18:00. A 2.7-km-long living cave network with a large chamber of stalactites and stalagmites, as well as a 800-m-long lake, home to a species of blind fish. There is also a geological museum onsite, as well as a cafe and gift shop. RO 6.5/3 (non-Omani adults/children 6-12), RO 3/1 (Omani adults/children 6-12), free (children under 6). </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Misfat al Abriyyin</hi> (Misfah) (5km north of Al Hamra). One of the few mountain villages accessible by 2WD on a paved road. The ancient village is in a beautiful setting, with terraced gardens and a falaj irrigation system. The ruined fort of <hi rend="italic">Al Rogan</hi> overlooks the village, which is the starting point for the challenging <hi rend="bold">W9</hi> trekking path, connecting with trails <hi rend="bold">W8</hi> and <hi rend="bold">W10h</hi>. Donkeys and guides are available for hire here as well.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Misfah Old House</hi>, ☏ +968 99 338491 , ✉ bandb.misfah@gmail.com . One of only a couple of accommodation options available in the village, in a traditional Omani house with Omani cuisine cooked by local families. Arrangements for guides can be made here. No internet. RO 25 / singles, RO 50 /doubles, including half-board; cash only.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Al Hamra</hi>. Set right at the base of the mountains, this town is notable for a number of Yemeni-style mud-brick buildings, some of which are among the oldest houses in Oman. They are in an older section of the town overlooking the newer town; in recent years many of the older houses have been abandoned as the inhabitants have chosen to move into more modern buildings. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Rustaq Fort</hi>. Sa-Th 09:00-16:00; F 08:00-11:00, 14:00-16:00. This restored fortress in the northern foothills has four watch towers and dates to the 13th century. The complex includes a mosque, a former prison and a falaj system. It has been nominated for listing as a UNESCO World Heritage site.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nakhal Fort</hi>, ☏ +968 26 781384 . Sa-Th 09:00-16:00; F 08:00-11:00. A restored fortress with a history dating to the pre-Islamic era, scenically situated on a rocky outcropping at the base of the northern Hajar Mountains. The fort houses a museum of historic guns. 500 Bzs (adults). </item>
</list>


<head>Jebel Akhdar</head>
<p>Jebel Akhdar ('Green Mountain') is topped by the vast <hi rend="bold">Sayq Plateau</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Saiq Plateau</hi>), home to traditional mountain villages, fruit orchards, and terraced gardens. Oman's most highly-prized rosewater is produced here, and springtime is particularly beautiful when the fruit trees and rose gardens are all in bloom. This is a cool destination even during the height of summer, and in winter temperatures drop below freezing. It is possible to visit as a very ambitious day trip, but to really appreciate it is best to allow a couple of days. The road is newly paved and in excellent condition but a 4WD is mandatory; travelers without a suitable car will be turned back at the police checkpoint.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> From Highway 15, take the turnoff for <hi rend="bold">Birkat al Mawz</hi>. Turn left at the T-junction (following signs for 'Nizwa'), and then follow the signs for 'Al Jabal al Akhdar'. On the right you'll pass , a thousand-year-old fortress, now fully restored and open to the public.</item>
<item> A 4WD is required to pass the , where you must show your driver's license and car registration. From here you'll need to use low gear.</item>
<item> 500 m after passing (tel. +968 25 429009), turn left for <hi rend="bold">Sayh Qutnah</hi>.</item>
<item> After 3 km the road forks; take the road to the left and proceed 700 m to (tel. +968 25 429288). A little way further is the scenic , so named after the Princess of Wales visited in 1990 via helicopter. Some good campsites are nearby, as is the (tel. +968 2521 8000, doubles RO 132+).</item>
<item> The trailhead for (<hi rend="italic">Village Walk</hi>) begins in the village below the Sahab Hotel. This 2-hour hike passes through the cliff-hugging terraced gardens of <hi rend="italic">Al Ayn</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ash Shirayjah</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Sayq</hi> and offers outstanding views of the deep wadis below. If you like you can continue for another 1.5-2 hours along <hi rend="bold">W18a</hi> to . A short path near the public toilets leads to an abandoned village of mudbrick houses overlooking photogenic plantations.</item>
</list>
</text>
