<text id="autogum_voyage_doc346" title="Chicago" shortTile="chicago" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=7106" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Chicago</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://choosechicago.com/">Chicago</ref></hi> is the home of the blues and the truth of <ref target="jazz">jazz</ref>, the heart of comedy and the idea of the skyscraper. Here, the age of railroads found its center, and airplanes followed suit. "Stormy, Husky, Brawling / City of Big Shoulders," Chicago is a Heartland boomtown, its ethos defined by urban planner Daniel Burnham's immortal vision: "Make no little plans; they have no magic to stir men's blood." It is one of the world's great cities, and yet the metropolitan luxuries of theater, shopping, and fine dining have barely put a dent in real Midwestern friendliness. It's a city with swagger, but without the surliness or even the fake smiles found in other cities of its size.</p>

<p>As the hub of the <ref target="Midwest">Midwest</ref>, Chicago is easy to find — its picturesque <ref target="Chicago%20skyline%20guide">skyline</ref> calls across the waters of Lake Michigan, a first impression that soon reveals world-class museums of art and science, miles of sandy beaches, huge parks and <ref target="Loop%20Art%20Tour">public art</ref>, and perhaps the finest downtown collection of modern architecture in the world.</p>

<p>With a wealth of iconic sights and neighborhoods to explore, there's enough to fill a visit of days, weeks, or even months without ever seeing the end. Dress warm in the winter, and prepare to cover a lot of ground; the meaning of Chicago is only found in movement, through subways and archaic elevated tracks, in the pride of tired feet and eyes raised once more to the sky.</p>

<head>Districts</head>
<p>Many visitors never make it past the attractions downtown, but you haven't truly seen Chicago until you have ventured out into the neighborhoods. Chicagoans split their city into large "sides" to the north, west, and south of the central business district (the Loop). Chicagoans also tend to identify strongly with their neighborhood, reflecting real differences in culture and place throughout the city. Rivalries between the North and South Sides run particularly deep, while people from the West Side are free agents in critical issues like baseball loyalty.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<p>Chicago was known as a fine place to find a <hi rend="bold">wild onion</hi> if you were a member of the Potawatomi tribe, who lived in this area of <ref target="Illinois">Illinois</ref> before European settlers arrived. It was mostly swamps, prairie and mud long past the establishment of Fort Dearborn in 1803 and incorporation as a town in 1833. It could be argued that nature never intended for there to be a city here; brutal winters aside, it took civil engineering projects of unprecedented scale to establish working sewers, reverse the flow of the river to keep it out of the city's drinking supply, and stop buildings from sinking back into the swamps — and that was just the first three decades.</p>

<p>Chicago became a waypoint between the Great Lakes and the <ref target="Old%20West">Wild West</ref>, where boats came to drop off settlers, and load crops and other goods from the <ref target="Great%20Plains">Great Plains</ref> and the <ref target="Rocky%20Mountains%20%28United%20States%20of%20America%29">Rocky Mountains</ref>.</p>

<p>By 1871, the reckless growth of the city was a sight to behold, full of noise, Gothic lunacy, and bustling commerce. But on October 8, Mrs. O'Leary's cow supposedly knocked over a lantern in the crowded immigrant quarters in the West Side, starting a roaring fire. Most likely the cow story is fiction, but whatever the real reason, the <hi rend="bold">Great Chicago Fire</hi> quickly spread through the dry prairie, killing 300 and destroying virtually the entire city. The stone Water Tower in the <ref target="Chicago/Near%20North">Near North</ref> is the most famous surviving structure. But the city seized this destruction as an opportunity to rebuild bigger than before, giving canvas for several architects and urban planners who would go on to become legends of modern architecture.</p>

<p>At the pinnacle of its rebirth and the height of its newfound powers, Chicago was known as <hi rend="bold">The White City</hi>. Cultures from around the world were summoned to the 1893 World's Columbian Exposition, to bear witness to the work of Louis Sullivan, Daniel Burnham, and the future itself. Cream of Wheat, soft drinks, street lights and safe electricity, the fax machine, and the Ferris Wheel bespoke the colossus now resident on the shores of Lake Michigan.</p>

<p>As every road had once led to Rome, every train led to Chicago. Carl Sandburg called Chicago the <hi rend="bold">Hog Butcher for the World</hi> for its cattle stockyards and place on the nation's dinner plate. Sandburg also called it the <hi rend="bold">City of the Big Shoulders</hi>, noting the tall buildings in the birthplace of the skyscraper — and the city's "lifted head singing so proud to be alive and coarse and strong and cunning." But Chicago is a city in no short supply of nicknames. Fred Fisher's 1922 song (best known in Frank Sinatra's rendition) calls it <hi rend="bold">That Toddlin' Town</hi>, where "on State Street, that great street, they do things they don't do on Broadway." It's also referenced by countless blues standards like <hi rend="bold">Sweet Home Chicago</hi>.</p>

<p>Chicago is also known as <hi rend="bold">The Second City</hi>, which refers to its rebuilding after the fire — the current city is literally the second Chicago, after the one that disappeared in 1871. The moniker has stuck, in no small part due to its popular association with the city's long-held former position as the United States' second largest city. And many know the nickname from Chicago's great comedy theater in <ref target="Chicago/Lincoln%20Park-Old%20Town">Old Town</ref>.</p>

<p>Chicago's history of corruption is legendary. During the Prohibition era, Chicago's criminal world, emblemized by names like Al Capone, Baby Face Nelson, and later Sam Giancana, practically ran the city. The local political world had scarcely more legitimacy in a town where voter turnout was highest among the dead and their pets, and precinct captains spread the word to "vote early, vote often." Even Sandburg acknowledged the relentless current of vice that ran under the surface of the optimistic city.</p>

<p>Today, Chicago is known as <hi rend="bold">The Windy City</hi>. Walking around town, you might suspect that Chicago got this nickname from the winds off Lake Michigan, which shove through the downtown corridors with intense force. But the true origin of the saying comes from politics. Some say it may have been coined by rivals like <ref target="Cincinnati">Cincinnati</ref> and <ref target="New%20York%20City">New York</ref> as a derogatory reference to the Chicagoan habit of rabid boosterism and endless political conventions. Others say that the term originated from the fact that Chicago politicians change their minds "as often as the wind." Yet another saying is that the name came about because of Chicago's long-winded politicians.</p>

<p>Finally, the city is known as <hi rend="bold">The City That Works</hi>, as promoted by longtime Mayor Richard M. Daley, which refers to Chicago's labor tradition, the long hours worked by its residents, and its willingness to tackle grand civic projects. Daley and his father, former Mayor Richard J. Daley, ruled the city for decades in what can only be described as a benevolent dictatorship; as other Midwestern manufacturing cities like <ref target="Cleveland">Cleveland</ref> and <ref target="Detroit">Detroit</ref> went into decline, Chicago thrived, transforming from a city of stockyards and factories to a financial giant at the forefront of modern urban design. Former White House Chief of Staff Rahm Emanuel became mayor of Chicago in 2011.</p>

<p>While the city has many great attractions downtown, most Chicagoans live and play outside of the central business district. To understand Chicago, travelers must venture away from the Loop and Michigan Avenue and out into the vibrant neighborhoods, to soak up the local nightlife, sample the wide range of fantastic dining, and see the sights Chicagoans alone know and love — thanks to the city's massive public transit system, every part of Chicago is only slightly off the most beaten path. The good public transport, as well as its historical (and current) role as a major rail hub make Chicago one of the places best suited for visiting the <ref target="United%20States%20without%20a%20car">United States without a car</ref>.</p>

<p>Today, Chicago is one of the most ethnically diverse cities in the United States, with the population almost evenly divided among whites, blacks and Hispanics. Chicago is also home to smaller communities of other origins, with the only Chinatown in the Midwest, as well as a Vietnamese community in Argyle, South Asians in Devon, and a Jewish community in the northern suburb of Skokie and surrounding neighbourhoods. However, decades of racist housing policies have also made Chicago a very racially segregated city; whites tend to be concentrated in the more affluent North Side, while blacks and Hispanics tend to be concentrated in the poorer South and West Sides. An exception to this rule is the neighbourhood of Hyde Park, where the University of Chicago is located, which stands out as an ethnically-diverse middle class neighbourhood in an otherwise black-dominated, poverty-stricken South Side.</p>
</text>
