<text id="autogum_voyage_doc327" title="Ben Gurion International Airport" shortTile="ben-gurion-international" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=3405" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ben Gurion International Airport</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.iaa.gov.il/Rashat/en-US/Airports/BenGurion/">Ben Gurion International Airport</ref></hi> ( TLV ) is <ref target="Israel">Israel</ref>'s primary airport. Named after Israel's first prime minister, it is near the town of <ref target="Lod">Lod</ref> (hence its previous name - Lod/Lydda Airport), on the outskirts of the <ref target="Tel%20Aviv">Tel Aviv</ref> metropolitan area.</p>

<head>Security</head>
<p>The airport is one of the most secure airports in the world, especially given its location. It's advisable to budget at least an additional two hours on top of your pre-flight check-in time to ensure timely arrival and completion of security procedures (though most of the time it will go much faster). </p>

<p>Airport security is especially suspicious of travellers with Muslim names or visas from Islamic countries in their passports. Expect to be stopped and questioned for several hours if this is the case, both on the way in and on the way out. It would be wise to have some phone numbers of local contacts for security officials to call to verify your reasons for visiting. </p>

<p>The most evident security check is pre-check-in. Bag inspection, both by machine and hand, is routine and should be expected, in addition to repeated interviews about your time in Israel. (Optional; should you go through it, you will be escorted to skip regular security check.) If travelling as part of a group, they will usually question you separately before cross-checking your accounts.</p>

<p>On joining the queue for this security check, a security official will ask you several questions. Based on these and a brief inspection of your passport, you will be assigned a number from 1 to 6. 1 signifies the lowest security concern and 6 the highest. Foreigners will typically get between a 3 and a 6. Age, appearance, stamps from Arab countries, evidence of visits to Palestinian areas, and other factors will be taken into account. Depending on the number you get (stuck on your passport and luggage), the security check is more or less thorough. Travellers who have visited Palestinian areas will almost certainly receive a 5 or 6 (but you can also get a 5 if you have never been to Israel before, and are of European descent). With a 5 or a 6, you can expect every single item of luggage to be taken from your bag and inspected in detail. Security officials have been known to check individual bank-notes. With a 6 (but sometimes even 5 if they have time), you can also expect to be taken to a cubicle and asked to remove your belt and shoes and have a personal inspection. If your clothes contain any metal that would set off a detector (such as studs in your jeans or a zip) even if plainly visible on the outside, you will be asked to remove the item of clothing. Travellers are regularly prevented from taking mobile phones, laptops, and even shoes in their hand-luggage, although there is no consistency, with reports of one policy one week and another the next week. </p>

<p>Arguing about such invasive checks is almost always fruitless and security reasons are the only ones that are ever cited. Though encouraging tourism, Israeli authorities would answer to criticism by angry travellers that Israel is a prime target of many international terrorist groups, and that people who are looking for sun with no security checks should rather head to Canary Islands. The security check process can be very irritating, but it is one of the factors which makes TLV one of the safest airports in the world.</p>

<p>Unlike in many other countries, airport security staff is quite intelligent. They will be looking at how you answer questions as much as what you say. Also, over-careful procedures like removing shoes and throwing out liquids, which are standard in Western airports, tend to be lessened at Ben Gurion.</p>

<p>In addition, when driving to the airport, there is a security checkpoint on the road several minutes before you arrive. Expect your taxi to be stopped, and have your passports, tickets, and answers for some questions (how long have you been in Israel, where are you going) ready.</p>

<head>Airlines</head>
<p>Ben Gurion acts as a hub for Israel's three main international airlines:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">El Al</hi>, ☏ +972(3)9771111 . Israel's largest airline and flag carrier offering flights around the globe. El Al generally does not operate flights on the Jewish Sabbath or major holidays. Similarly, they have never served a non-kosher meal on any of their flights. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Arkia Israel Airlines</hi>, ☏ +972-3-6902255 , ✉ incoming@arkia.co.il . Israel's largest domestic airline. It also serves European destinations. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Israir</hi>, ☏ +972-3-5109589 . Su-Th 10:00-14:00 (excluding Festivals). serves many European destinations </item>
</list>


<p>Around 50 international airlines fly to Ben Gurion airport from around the world, including Delta, United Airlines, American Airlines, Air Canada, Turkish Airlines, Pegasus, Aegean Airlines, Ukraine International, British Airways, Air France, Lufthansa, Alitalia, Iberia, LOT, Austrian Airlines, Swiss, KLM, Czech Airlines, Royal Jordanian, Egypt Air (via Air Sinai), Ethiopian Airlines, Korean Air, and Cathay Pacific. </p>

<p>A notable flight is Air India 139, a flight to <ref target="Delhi">Delhi</ref>'s <ref target="Indira%20Gandhi%20International%20Airport">Indira Gandhi International Airport</ref> which is unique is that it is the only flight not affected by a ban on using Saudi airspace for flights to Israel. For travelers in a hurry, this is two hours faster than a flight around Saudi Arabia and definitely quicker and easier compared to a connection.</p>

<p>Low cost airlines also fly to Ben Gurion airport from European destinations, including Ryanair, EasyJet, Wizz Air, Jet2 and more.</p>

<p>Some low cost airlines fly to Ovda airport ( VDA ) near Eilat, which has become Israel's second airport since the 2010s. A new "Ramon Airport" named after the first Israeli in space and his son - both of whom died tragically in aerospace accidents - is scheduled to open early in 2019 eventually replacing the civilian functions of Ovda Airport and also take over for Eilat's domestic airport ( ETH )</p>

<head>Terminals</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Terminal 3</hi> (טרמינל 3). This is nowadays the main terminal, used by most international airlines. The airport train station is here, and minibus transfers (and on a free trial basis, trains) to Jerusalem.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Terminal 1</hi> (טרמינל 1). Many low-cost airlines and domestic flights depart from Terminal 1, though they often bus passengers to T3 for arrivals. A few domestic flights to Eilat also fly from here, though there's much more from Sde Dov city airport. If you're gasping for a cuppa before check-in and security, use the cafe near the domestic check-in area, Door 2. The airport exchange desks have only a 5% buy-spread on major currencies so this is very good value.</item>
</list>


<p>A <hi rend="bold">free shuttle bus</hi> runs between T1 and T3 every 15 mins, taking 8 mins. Terminal 2 has been demolished and Terminal 4 is not in routine use. Check with your carrier which terminal to use, and your inbound and outbound terminals may often differ. Don't ask your taxi driver, he hasn't a clue and will drop you off wherever is more convenient for him.</p>
</text>
