<text id="autogum_voyage_doc521" title="Escaldes-Engordany" shortTile="escaldesengordany" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=11089" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Escaldes-Engordany</head>

<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://visitandorra.com/en/the-country/some-of-our-history/escaldes-engordany/">Escaldes-Engordany</ref></hi> is a parish (administrative division) mainly to the east of <ref target="Andorra%20La%20Vella">Andorra La Vella</ref> but with main village of the same name 1.6 km N of the capital of <ref target="Andorra">Andorra</ref> on the road to <ref target="La%20Massana">La Massana</ref> and <ref target="Ordino">Ordino</ref>.</p>

<head>Understand</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Escaldes-Engordany Tourist Office</hi>, Plaça Santa Anna, ☏ +376 890 881 , ✉ oficinaturisme@e-e.ad .</item>
</list>


<head>Get in</head>
<p>By car, take the CG2 direction <ref target="Pas%20de%20la%20Casa">Pas de la Casa</ref> and <ref target="France">France</ref> and turn north into Ave der Pessebre. Route map at <ref target="http://www.viamichelin.co.uk/viamichelin/gbr/dyn/controller/Driving_directions%23startLocid%3D31MzM1ZzEwY05ESXVOVEEzTlE9PThNUzQxTWpFNA__%26amp%3BdestLocid%3D31NTExY3hlMTBjTkRJdU5URXpNems9Y01TNDFNelUyTWc9PQ__%26amp%3Bstep1Locid%3D%26amp%3Bstep2Locid%3D%26amp%3Bvh%3DCAR%26amp%3Bdistance%3Dkm%26amp%3BstrVehicle%3D0%26amp%3BintItineraryType%3D1%26amp%3Bdevise%3D1.0%7CEUR%26amp%3BisAvoidFrontiers%3Dfalse%26amp%3BisFavoriseAutoroute%3Dfalse%26amp%3BisAvoidPeage%3Dfalse%26amp%3BisAvoidVignette%3Dfalse%26amp%3BisAvoidLNR%3Dfalse%26amp%3BcarTypeHidden%3DCitadine%26amp%3BcaravaneHidden%3Dfalse%26amp%3BtypeCarbHidden%3Dessence%26amp%3BautoConso%3D6.8%26amp%3BvilleConso%3D6%26amp%3BrouteConso%3D5.6%26amp%3BcarbCost%3D1.3%26amp%3BdtmDeparture%3D19/08/2007">ViaMichelin</ref> - Andorra La Vella to Escaldes-Engordany. Parking is available at Carrer del Prat Gran.</p>

<p>By bus, with the exception of e (express) bus to Sant Julia de Loria, all of the Andorra's local bus routes (L1 through L6) have stops in Escaldes-Endogrdany. International bus line between Toulouse and Andorra la Vella also stops here.</p>

<p>If you are in Andorra la Vella, simply walk east. Once you passed Carrer del Valria, you are in Escaldes-Engordany.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>The entire tourist area can be explored on foot. Av. Carlemany is pedestrian street and closed off to traffic from 12:00 to midnight daily.</p>

<p>The greater part of Escaldes-Engordany stretches towards Spain and the east. Some wonderful walks are to be had up the <hi rend="bold">Riu Madriu</hi> direction <hi rend="bold">Pics del Pessons</hi>, the "lakes" and the <hi rend="bold">Coll de Vall Civera</hi>.</p>

<head>See</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Sant Miquel d’Engolasters</hi>, ☏ +376 844 141 . From July to August: daily 10:00-13:00 and 15:00-18:00. The rest of the year only at mass hours. Romanesque style, dated from 12th century and restored on 20th century. It is notable the disproportion between the nave and the 17-m bell tower. It is obligatory to reserve beforehand. Free-guided tours. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Casa Creu</hi>, 67 Carlemany Street. Modernist style, designed by the architect Josep Puig i Cadafalch. It is no possible to visit because it is a home address. From the 1930s.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Roc del Metge</hi>. A hot spa, considered one of the hottest in Europe (70ºC).</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Museu del Perfum</hi> (Perfume Museum), Av. Meritxell.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Museu Carmen Thyssen of Andorra</hi>, Av. Carlemany, 37, ☏ +376 800 800 . Art museum</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Centre d'Art d'Escaldes-Engordany (CAEE)</hi>, Av. de les Escoles, 2, ☏ +376 802 255 . Art gallery which is formerly a cinema. It has sculptures by Josep Viladomat, Romanesque models of Andorra buildings and temporary exhibitions. First floor is a library with washroom facilities. Free.</item>
</list>


<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Caldea</hi>, Parc de la Mola, 10, ☏ +376 800 999 . The spa/sauna/swimming complex Caldea is located at the top of the town in the large glass spire structure. </item>
</list>


<head>Madriu-Perafita-Claror Valley</head>

<p>The cultural landscape of <ref target="http://www.madriu-perafita-claror.com">Madriu-Perafita-Claror Valley</ref>, which was inscribed in the <ref target="UNESCO">World heritage list</ref> in 2006, can only be accessed on foot. It offers great hiking and climbing possibilities in summer and in winter ski mountaineering or walking with snowshoes is an option.</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item> One entrance to the valley is a short bus ride or just over an hour walk from the oldest part of Andorra la Vella.</item>
<item> Start at gas station</item>
<item> Take <hi rend="italic">Cami de la Muntanya</hi> (mountain path) until it crosses a road (Ctra de la Comella i de la Plana) which takes about 20min</item>
<item> At this point you will be in the valley and can continue hiking on the mountain path for hours</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>
<p>Similar to Andorra la Vella, Av. Carlemany has plenty of brand name fashion, electronics and jewellery. It is worth shopping around to find the best deals.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Illa</hi>, Av. Carlemany, 70. A large commercial centre with several floors of shops, many of which are clothing and fashion stores. There is a food court on the 3rd floor and a supermarket at the basement level.</item>
</list>


<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Marisqueria Don Denis</hi>, Carrer Isabelle Sandy, ☏ +376 820 692 . A Mediterranean restaurant with local cuisine. The restaurant also has a wall of photos of "who's who" celebrities, politicians and dignitaries eating at the restaurant.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>
<p>A number of restaurant pubs can be found along Av. Carlemany or its side streets.</p>

<head>Budget</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Oriol</hi>, Plaça Co-Princeps 4, ☏ +376 821 105 . Check-in: 13:00, check-out: 09:00. Near Andorra la Vella €39.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Residencia Nuria</hi>, Carrer Santa Anna, 11, ☏ +376 821 572 , ✉ info@residencia-nuria.com .</item>
</list>


<head>Mid-range</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Eureka</hi>, Avinguda Carlemany 36, ☏ +376 880 666 . A four-star hotel just beside the Av. Carlemany pedestrian street.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Golden Tulip Hotel</hi>, Carrer del Prat Gran, ☏ +376 760 760 . A hotel with underground parking. Located adjacent to Av. Carlemany pedestrian street.</item>
</list>


<head>Splurge</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Hotel Spa Termes SERHS Carlemany Andorra</hi> (Hotel Carlemany), Av. Carlemany, 4, ☏ +376 870 050 , ✉ info.carlemany@serhs.com .</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">A Casa Canut Hotel Gastronòmic</hi> (Casa Canut), Av. Carlemany, 107, ☏ +376 739 900 , ✉ reserves@acasacanut.com .</item>
</list>


<head>Connect</head>
<p>The stretch of Avinguda Carlemany in Escaldes-Endogrdany that continues west on the same street as Avinguda Meritxell in downtown Andorra la Vella has free public WiFi.</p>

<head>Go next</head>
<p>Andorra la Vella is the obvious choice as it is right beside Escaldes-Engordany. You may have cross the Carrer de la Valira street without realizing that it is the boundary between Andorra la Vella and Escaldes-Engordany.</p>

<p>You can also head to <ref target="La%20Massana">La Massana</ref> and <ref target="Ordino">Ordino</ref> in the north and <ref target="Encamp">Encamp</ref>, <ref target="Canillo">Canillo</ref>, <ref target="Soledu">Soledu</ref> and <ref target="Pas%20de%20la%20Casa">Pas de la Casa</ref> in the east.</p>
</text>
