<text id="autogum_voyage_doc9" title="Abacos">
<head>Abacos</head>

<p>The <hi rend="bold">Abacos</hi> are a group of islands in the <ref target="Bahamas">Bahamas</ref> east of <ref target="Grand%20Bahama">Grand Bahama</ref>. Great Abaco and Little Abaco are the primary islands. Disney's privately-owned "Castaway Cay" is here.</p>

<head>Towns</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> &mdash; island with small population</item>
<item> &mdash; island with small population</item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
<item> </item>
</list>


<head>Understand</head>

<head>Talk</head>
<p>You should not have problems speaking for they speak English and most employees speak Spanish.</p>

<head>Get in</head>

<head>Get around</head>

<head>See</head>
<p>The outer reefs are great to go to see sharks.</p>

<head>Do</head>

<head>Eat</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Curly Tails</hi>, ☏ +1 242 367-4444 . Despite a very fun, touristy air to the place, Curly Tails features great gourmet food breakfast through dinner. $$$.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Magnolia Cafe</hi>. Maybe the best restaurant in the Abaco Islands. Situated in Man 'O War key, run entirely by a local man and wife.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Baker's Bay</hi>. World class dining in the brand new Baker's Bay marina on the north end of Great Guana Cay.</item>
</list>


<head>Drink</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Nipper's</hi>. Three story bar overlooking the ocean with a famous Nipper's cocktail and a pig roast every Sunday afternoon.</item>
</list>


<head>Sleep</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Ocean Frontier</hi>. Great Guana Cay, Abacos, Bahamas, 1.888.828.6745, Well equipped cottages on the Atlantic beach of Great Guana Cay with private decks and well landscaped property provide privacy as well as direct access to the beach. All cottages are air conditioned and include a full kitchen and grill, a three piece bath, two private bedrooms and a loft with additional sleeping quarters.</item>
</list>


<head>Stay safe</head>

<head>Go next</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="Elbow%20Cay">Elbow Cay</ref> is several miles east of Great Abaco Island. This six-mile stretch of land is less than an hour-long ferry ride from Great Abaco's Marsh Harbor.</item>
</list>
</text>
