<text id="autogum_voyage_doc541" title="Elche" shortTile="elche" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=139632" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Elche</head>


<p><hi rend="bold"><ref target="http://www.visitelche.com/en/">Elche</ref></hi> is in the <ref target="Valencia%20%28region%29">Valencia region</ref>, southeastern <ref target="Spain">Spain</ref>. Elche is the Spanish name of the city, and it is also known by its Valencian name Elx.</p>

<head>Understand</head>
<p>A city of 225,000 inhabitants, Elche is located just outside <ref target="Alicante">Alicante</ref> and is the capital of the Baix Vinalopó region. The Vinalopó River divides the city in two. Elche has a history as an industrial city (especially known for its shoe industries). Today the industries are still present, but the city also offers different attractions and services for visitors — among them the huge <ref target="world%20heritage">world heritage</ref> listed palm grove.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Tourist Info Elx</hi> (Main Office), Plaça del Parc, 3, ☏ +52 966 658 196 , ✉ elx@touristinfo.net . Apr-Oct: M-F 09:00-19:00, Sa 10:00-19:00, Su/holidays 10:00-14:00; Nov-Mar: M-F 09:00-18:00, Sa 10:00-18:00, Su/holidays 10:00-14.</item>
</list>


<head>By plane</head>
 <hi rend="bold">Aeropuerto de Alicante-Elche</hi> ( ALC L'Altet Airport) (from Elche). This airport has flights to over 50 destinations at least weekly. One terminal is in service, known as Terminal N or the new terminal. Terminals T1 and T2 that were used before the construction of the new terminal are no longer in service. 

<head>By boat</head>
<p>The port of <ref target="Alicante">Alicante</ref> is 20km away, and you can get there by ferry from the <ref target="Balearic%20Islands">Balearic Islands</ref> and <ref target="Oran">Oran</ref> in <ref target="Algeria">Algeria</ref>.</p>

<head>By train</head>
<p>Elche is on the <ref target="Alicante">Alicante</ref>-<ref target="Murcia%20%28city%29">Murcia</ref> line. From either of those cities you can connect to most major cities in Spain. The train line passes the city through an underground tunnel, and there are two railway stations in the city. Renfe regional train (<hi rend="italic">cercanía</hi>) line <ref target="http://www.renfe.com/viajeros/cercanias/murciaalicante/index.html"><hi rend="bold">C1</hi></ref> can get you from <ref target="Alicante">Alicante</ref> to Elche in half an hour, and from <ref target="Murcia%20%28city%29">Murcia</ref> in under one hour.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Estación de Tren de Elx Parc</hi> (Elx Parc Train Station), Avda del Ferrocarril Este, 10, ☏ +34 902 432 343 . The primary train station, conveniently located next to the bus station. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Estación de Tren de Elx-Carrús</hi> (Elx-Carrús Train Station), Avda Llibertad, s/n, ☏ +34 902 432 343 . </item>
</list>


<head>By bus</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Estació Autobusos Elx</hi> (Elche Bus Station), Avda del Alcalde Vicente Quiles, 8 (near the rail station), ☏ +34 966 615 050 , ✉ info@pimesa.es . The modern bus station has connection both to Spanish and international destinations. Facilities at the station include a restaurant and 24-hr convenience shop.</item>
</list>


<head>Bus companies</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <ref target="https://www.alsa.com/en/web/bus/our-destinations/regional/valencia-murcia"><hi rend="bold">Alsa</hi></ref>, tel +34 902 422 242.</item>
<item> <ref target="http://www.autocaresmelillense.com/"><hi rend="bold">Autocares Melillense</hi></ref>, tel +34 965 456 947.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mollá</hi> (Grupo subús), tel +34 965 424 242.</item>
<item> <ref target="http://www.autocaresserrano.com/sitio/"><hi rend="bold">Serrano</hi></ref>, tel +34 965 456 146.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Autobuses Urbanos de Elche</hi>, tel +34 965 420 392.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Vegabús</hi>, tel +34 966 613 222.</item>
</list>


<head>By car</head>
<p>A-7 (European route E15) stretches along the Mediterranean coast and connects the city to the French border in the north and <ref target="Algeciras">Algeciras</ref> and beyond in the south. Another main route is A-31 connecting Elche to <ref target="Central%20Spain">Central Spain</ref>. Regional roads connects Elche to places like Alicante and Murcia.</p>

<head>By bus</head>

<ref target="http://www.auesa.es/eng/"><hi rend="bold">Autobusos Urbans d'Elx</hi></ref> (AUESA) operates a fairly extensive network of bus routes. A single journey costs €1.35, payable to the driver on entry; night journeys cost €1.45. If you plan to use the bus frequently, it may be worth purchasing a <hi rend="italic">Bus Bono</hi> card, which will give you ten journeys for €8.40.

<p>A route map can be downloaded <ref target="http://www.auesa.es/infomovil.pdf">here</ref>, and detailed route maps with schedules can be downloaded <ref target="http://www.auesa.es/eng/descargas.html">here</ref>. For travelers with smart phones, <hi rend="italic">BusElche</hi> is a useful Android app with a route planner and estimated travel times.</p>

<head>By car</head>
<p>At certain times of the day it might be impossible to find a parking space downtown, therefore you're better off going by bus or foot.</p>

<head>Palmeral of Elche</head>
<p>One of the world's largest palm groves and the only one in Europe, this was established by the Phoenicians and expanded by the Arabs in the 8th and 9th centuries. The palmeral consists of several parts spreading across downtown. It was inscribed on the <ref target="UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20List">UNESCO World Heritage List</ref> in 2000.</p>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">L'Hort del Cura</hi> (Huerto del Cura), C/ Porta de la Morera, 49, ☏ +34 965 451 936 , ✉ jardin@huertodelcura.com . Daily; hrs vary, see details <ref target="http://jardin.huertodelcura.com/en/horarios/">here</ref>. In addition to well-maintained palm trees, this private botanical garden features lovely water fountains and cactus gardens. €5 (adults), €3 (concessions), €2.50 (children/residents). </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Parc Rei Jaume I</hi> (Parque Rey Jaime I). This municipal park was created by combining two semi-abandoned palm groves, and has been transformed by the planting of new date palms as well as fruit and ornamental trees and native grasses. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Parc Municipal</hi> (Parque Municipal), Paseo de la Estación, s/n. Nov-Mar daily 07:00-21:00, Apr-Oct daily 07:00-23:00, Aug daily 07:00-23:45. Comprised of several individual palm groves, the largest of which was granted to the city in the 17th century by a wealthy landowner. Free.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Molí del Real</hi>. An 18th-century water wheel, which once was powered by a channel of the Vinalopo River.</item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Parc del Filet de Fora</hi> (Parque del Filet de Fora). The second largest park in the city after the Municipal Park, it was created in the 1990s by combining five individual palm groves. Free.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Museu del Palmerar</hi> (Museo del Palmeral), C/ Porta de la Morera, 12, ☏ +34 965 422 240 . Tu-Sa 10:00-14:00 15:00-18:00, Su/holidays 10:00-14:00. Housed in a 19th-century farmhouse, this museum is devoted to date palms and the fronds used for Palm Sunday rites. Admission includes entry to the nearby palm grove and garden. €1 (adults), €.50 (concessions); free on Su. </item>
</list>


<head>Monuments and museums</head>


<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Palau d'Altamira</hi> (Palacio de Altamira / Alcázar de la Señoría), C/ Diagonal del Palau, 7, ☏ +34 966 658 203 . M-Sa 10:00-18:00, Su/holidays 10:00-15:00. First built by the Moors between the 11th and 13th centuries; the large southern tower dates from this period. The palace was expanded during the 15th and 16th centuries, and again in the 18th century. In the 20th century the building was used as a prison, and finally restored at the end of the century. It now houses a portion of the Archaeological Museum and is occasionally serves as a venue for cultural events. Admission combined with Museu Arqueològic: €3 (adults), €1 (concessions); free on Su. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Museu Arqueològic i d'Història d'Elx</hi> (Museo Arqueológico y de Historia de Elche (MAHE)), C/ Diagonal del Palau, 7, ☏ +34 966 658 203 . M-Sa 10:00-18:00, Su/holidays 10:00-15:00. Housed in a refurbished former textile factory, the museum presents artifacts dating from the Neolithic period to the 15th century CE. Part of the exhibition area incorporates a portion of the Alcazar. Admission combined with Palau d'Altamira: €3 (adults), €1 (concessions); free on Su. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Banys Àrabs</hi> (Baños Árabes / Arab Baths), Paseo de les Eres de Santa Llúcia, 14 (beneath the Convent de la Merced), ☏ +34 965 452 887 . Tu-Sa 10:00-14:00 15:00-18:00, Su/holidays 10:00-14:00. Moorish baths built in the mid-12th century, restored in 1998. An audiovisual presentation is available in English. €1 (adults), free (students/seniors/disabled); free on Su.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Basílica de Santa Maria</hi> (Basílica de Santa María), Plaça del Eucharistic, ☏ +34 615 337 821 , ✉ elcampanari@hotmail.com . Tower: Oct-May daily 10:30-15:00, Jun-Sep daily 11:00-19:00. The church was built in the late 17th to early 18th centuries in the Spanish Baroque style, on the site of an earlier mosque, and is the venue for the annual <hi rend="italic">Misteri d'Elx</hi>. Good views of palm groves and the city of Elche can be had from the top of the church tower, with 170 steps to the top. Inside the tower itself are three rooms, formerly inhabited by the bell-ringer with his family, with photographic displays on the church facade and the <hi rend="italic">Misteri d'Elx</hi>. €2 (adults), €1 (children under 10), free (children under 5). </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Yacimiento Arqueológico L'Alcúdia</hi> (L'Alcúdia Archaeological Park), Carretera de Dolores, km 1.5 (on the CV-855 motorway to Dolores), ☏ +34 966 611 506 , ✉ web.alcudia@ua.es . Archaeological site and interpretation centre: Tu-Su 10:00-20:00 (ticket ofc closes at 18:00); Museum: Tu-Sa 10:00-18:00. This archaeological site extends over 10 hectares, and was inhabited from the Bronze Age to the Islamic period. The most famous discovery made here is the Iberian sculpture <hi rend="italic">Dama de Elche</hi>, now located in the National Archaeological Museum in Madrid. Also onsite are an interpretation centre and a museum showcasing many artifacts discovered during excavations. €5 (adults), €2 (students/children), free (children under 6). </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Torre de la Calaforra</hi> (Torre de la Calahorra / Calahorra Tower), C/ Uberna, 14, ☏ +34 966 658 243 . Tu-Sa 10:00-14:00 15:00-18:00, Su/holidays 10:00-14:00. Formerly part of the city wall (now no longer extant), this tower was originally Muslim and built from the late 12th to early 13th centuries. Originally a full ten metres higher than now, neglect and an earthquake took their toll and the upper two floors had to be dismantled. From the 15th to 20th centuries it was used as an aristocratic residence and can now be visited. €2 (adults), €1 (concessions), free on Su. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Torre Vaillo de Llanos</hi> (Vaillo de Llanos Tower), Hort de la Torre (Municipal Park). Su 11:00-14:00. This watchtower was built in the late 15th and early 16th centuries as part of a defensive network. Now owned by the city, it has been fully restored and is used for temporary exhibits. Visitors can climb to the top for a good view of the surrounding palm groves. Free. </item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Museo de Arte Contemporáneo</hi> (Museum of Contemporary Art), Plaça del Raval, s/n, ☏ +34 965 421 534 , ✉ maheadmon@ayto-elche.es . Tu-Sa 10:00-14:00 15:00-18:00, Su and holidays 10:00-14:00. Initially established as a gallery for a local artists' cooperative, the museum now showcases a range of modern and contemporary art from the region and from across Spain. €2 (adults), €1 (concessions), free on Su. </item>
</list>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Centre d'Exposicions</hi> (Exhibition Centre), Plaça de San Juan. A venue for temporary art exhibits organised by the Museum of Contemporary Art.</item>
</list>
</text>
