<text id="autogum_voyage_doc308" title="Iringa" shortTile="iringa" author="Wikivoyage community (see URL)" type="voyage" dateCollected="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikivoyage.org/wiki?curid=15730" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Iringa</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Iringa</hi> is a town in the <ref target="Southern%20Highlands%20%28Tanzania%29">Southern Highlands</ref>, <ref target="Tanzania">Tanzania</ref>.</p>

<head>Get in</head>
<p>You can get to Iringa by bus from Dar, Dodoma, and Mbeya. There are many bus companies but some are dangerous. The best are Sumry, Sutco, and Hood.</p>

<p>The road from Dar is being upgraded into a very decent road so once the roadworks have gone the ride will be very good. The journey passes through beautiful scenery and a national park.</p>

<head>Get around</head>
<p>Iringa is a great stop-over point on the way down through the Southern Highlands or if you are off to visit <ref target="Malawi">Malawi</ref> and <ref target="Zambia">Zambia</ref>. If you are going back the other way towards <ref target="Dar%20es-Salaam">Dar es-Salaam</ref> it is definitely a much nicer place to stop than <ref target="Morogoro">Morogoro</ref>. It would be all too easy to just see Iringa as a blur as you hurtle past in a Sutco coach sipping your complimentary soda, but is definitely worth breaking your journey for a day or so to take in the sights, sounds, and smells of this bustling little town. It is also the gateway to the jewel in the crown of Tanzania's game parks: Ruaha. Ask at Iringa Info opposite Hasty Tasty for top of the market tours or at Neema Crafts for the smaller companies to arrange your trip. Get a bus or taxi to Tungamalenga village near the park gate and stay at Chogela campsite, where they can arrange a cheaper vehicle hire (this is the cheapest way to do the park). Ask at Neema Crafts for Chogella campsite details.</p>

<head>See</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Gangilonga Rock</hi> (talking stone). This large rock gives you great views over Iringa. To get to it you have to walk out past Lulu's/bakery/Ruaha Club way through the well-off suburb where all the rich NGO and government workers houses are. The rock is covered in graffiti from local youth. Reports have indicated that criminals may lurk here.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Neema Crafts Centre</hi> is a great place to visit with cafe with great cake and fresh ground coffee, a tour of the workshops is great to see all the different crafts being made, especially paper from elephant dung!</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Isimila Stone Age Site</hi>. About 15 km from town towards Mafinga, easily accessible by daladala or taxi. This is one of the most interesting stone age sites in East Africa and is well worth a visit.</item>
</list>


<p>At Kalenga, you can go and see Chief Mkwawa’s skull which was returned by the Germans after many decades.</p>

<head>Do</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Iringa Swahili School</hi>. Take Swahili courses with Iringa Swahili School. Classes are at Rivervalley Campsite (formerly Riverside Campsite). This Swahili school is used by many NGOs, humanitarian and missionary organizations. It is considered one of the best Swahili courses in Tanzania. Visit <ref target="http://www.swahilitanzania.com">Iringa Swahili School</ref> for more information.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Mkwawa Golf Course</hi>. Brown greens and more caddies offering unwanted advice and mirth than you can shake a stick at... hilarious... watch out for the donkey- and goat-based green keeping team.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Learn about the AIDS pandemic first hand</hi>. Iringa region has the highest infection rates in the country. The <ref target="http://www.mbigili.de/">Amani Orphanage in Mbigili</ref> (around 25 km from Iringa, in Mbigili 2 km away from the Dar es Salaam Highway) is run by a German-Tanzanian NGO and offers a nice round guesthouse in traditional style with 2 double rooms for a small donation - very lovely, an ideal spot for hikes through the surrounding area or visits in the very beautiful Ruaha National Park, 100 km away. Trips can be organised by the helpful staff. The food there is awesome and the kids are also always very happy to see new playmates! Bookings through ingolenz@gmx.net or facebook: Amani Orphans Home Mbigili.</item>
</list>


<head>Buy</head>

<list type="unordered">
<item> <hi rend="bold">Masai Market</hi> – Go and visit Sengai (the unofficial leader of the Iringa Masai) in the Masai market between the Posta and Sokoni. All manner of beaded things, katenge bags, herbal medicines, and second hand shoes available. You will also get lots of souvenir traders bothering you outside of Hasty Tasty – They are selling cards, carved wood items, and musical instruments. One of them has a nasty habit of playing his terrible violin-type device. Shouting <hi rend="italic">Inatosha</hi> (<hi rend="italic">that's enough</hi>) stops him for a few minutes and eases the headache but it does make sitting on the outside tables a bit annoying and not the best place to relax.</item>
<item> <hi rend="bold">Neema Crafts</hi>. The workshop employs deaf people who produce elephant dung paper products (cards, albums, etc.), beaded bits and bobs (bracelets, earrings, flip flops) including stuff from their beads they make from recycling glass bottles (ask to go and see their cool mud kiln), cushions, vitenge patchwork blankets, lamps and lamp shades, and more recently have employed disabled folks who are weaving rugs, hammocks, and various other interesting textiles. Their projects include micro solar panels for lighting, radios and charging phones, very useful if you are camping, and a physiotherapy unit for disabled children. You can help the physiotherapy unit by having a fantastic hour long massage for Tsh 25,000 from their bubbly physio Beatrice and you can lie there and relax in your pampering knowing the money you are paying is going to allow more disabled children to get treated for free! Along with the obvious benefits of providing employment to people that Tanzanian society has rejected, the products are excellent and make great presents! Haruna, a hilarious character, will be happy to give you a guided tour, and they have a café selling proper coffee and homemade cakes, ice cream and sorbets if that tickles your fancy; Their panini bacon and avocado sandwiches and the carrot cake draw expat volunteers from all over the south of Tanzania who also stock up on their reading materials at the book exchange in the cafe. Also they are the center for a great project to bring safe drinking water to rural villages using the sun, (SODIS.ch) so drop off any empty 1½-liter drinking water bottles you may have and they can make use of them.</item>
</list>


<p>There are dozens of shops selling vitenge and kanga. The best are located around the Dala Dala stand near the market and down “Indian” street. Expect to pay TSh 2,500 for kanga and TSh 4,000 for vitenge. Real Wax vitenge comes in at about TSh 10,000 if you are a purist. Always demand a punguza for multiple purchases though they are tough negotiators but don't worry too much about going as low as you can as these guys are the middle men not the producers whatever they may claim!</p>

<p>The duka opposite the Posta selling batiques, carvings, paintings and painted tins have now all been moved on (they were illegally there in the first place). You can now find them scattered about town.</p>

<p>In the corner of the main market you’ll find the basket market - several stalls selling straw mats, baskets, kitchen bits and pieces. The hand woven baskets are a signature of Iringa and well worth getting for keeping your mchele and maharage in. You will pay Tsh 10,000 for four medium sized baskets – an absolute bargain for the Iringa style they will bring to your bare, soulless volunteer accommodation.</p>

<p>For postcards try the post office for the usual Tanzanian variety, or try Neema Crafts. They have their own postcards, cheaper than the post office and much more local. They sell stamps there as well and have a post box outside.</p>

<p>For food retail therapy, take a walk to Premji’s and/or Raju’s on “Indian” street, two mini-supermarkets heavily stocked with wazungu luxuries; wine, Marmite, Coco Pops, olives, etc. Not what you would describe as cheap but when you are desperately in need of a yeast extract based hit, beggars can’t be choosers. (also Neema Crafts does take away giant chocolate chip cookies and fudge, which are great when you need a lift).</p>

<p>The Consollata Fathers and Sisters live on two sites up in the Gangilonga suburb. The fathers sell their own cheese (well, that of their cows...) including mozzarella (amazing), the sisters sell excellent homemade pasta, great pasta sauce and various pork products which are from pigs they have raised themselves.</p>
</text>
