<text id="autogum_news_doc565" title="Two dead in storms with no sign of floods letting up in Britain" shortTile="two-dead-storms-sign" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-02-15" dateModified="2019-08-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Two_dead_in_storms_with_no_sign_of_floods_letting_up_in_Britain" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Two dead in storms with no sign of floods letting up in Britain</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 15, 2014</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Flooding in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Staines-upon-Thames">Staines-upon-Thames</ref>. Image: Marcin Cajzer.</caption></figure>
<p>Two people have died in incidents related to storms that battered the southern coast of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref> last night while many across the country continue to struggle with flooding, property damage, and closure of road and railway routes.</p>
<p>In central <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, masonry from a building near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holborn%20tube%20station">Holborn tube station</ref> fell on top of a car in the street outside, killing a woman and injuring a man in the car. The woman was pronounced dead on the scene; the man is recovering in hospital and is reported to be in a stable condition. A third, female passenger in the car escaped before emergency responders arrived.</p>
<figure><caption>The MS <hi rend="italic">Marco Polo</hi>. Image: Luca Riva.</caption></figure>
<p>In the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/English_Channel">English Channel</ref>, an 85-year-old man and a woman in her 70s were airlifted from the cruise ship <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MS%20Marco%20Polo">MS <hi rend="italic">Marco Polo</hi></ref> which was hit by a large storm wave on its way back to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tilbury">Tilbury</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Essex">Essex</ref>. The man subsequently died. Other passengers aboard the ship suffered minor injuries.</p>
<p>The cruise line operator, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cruise%20&amp;%20Maritime%20Voyages">Cruise &amp; Maritime Voyages</ref> (CMV), said in a statement: "CMV regrets to advise that earlier today their cruise ship <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MS%20Marco%20Polo">MS Marco Polo</ref>, en-route to her home port of Tilbury from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Azores">Azores</ref>, was hit by a freak wave during adverse sea conditions in the south western approaches of the English Channel. One elderly passenger has died and a further passenger has been airlifted for further shore-side medical assistance. The vessel sailed from Tilbury on January 5 and is carrying 735 mainly British passengers and 349 crew. Our thoughts are very much with these passengers and their families during this difficult time."</p>
<p>In addition to the two deaths from yesterday's storms, a 77-year-old man died yesterday from injuries sustained Wednesday in the town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caernarfon">Caernarfon</ref>, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gwynedd">Gwynedd</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wales">Wales</ref>. Bob Thomas was hospitalised after being hit by a falling tree in his garden.</p>
<figure><caption>Flooding in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bury%20St%20Edmunds">Bury St Edmunds</ref>. Image: Martin Pettitt.</caption></figure>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Met%20Office">Met Office</ref> said that after storms this weekend, weather in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">UK</ref> should return to "normal winter weather" next week. In contrast to the predictions of the Met Office, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Environment%20Agency">Environment Agency</ref> have said that floods could remain in some areas of England until March, and that up to 3,000 homes in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thames%20Valley">Thames Valley</ref> could be flooded over the weekend. On Friday, they raised the number of "danger to life" level flood warnings from 17 to 24.</p>
<p>Flooding across England and Wales has led to thousands being without electricity. In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North%20Wales">North Wales</ref>, as of Friday 17,000 people had no electricity supply, while 7,000 homes in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cornwall">Cornwall</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Devon">Devon</ref> had their electricity supply cut off by Friday's storms.</p>
<p>Trains operated by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southeastern%20(train%20operating%20company)">Southeastern</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Southern%20Railway%20(UK)">Southern</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South%20West%20Trains">South West Trains</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CrossCountry">CrossCountry</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First%20Great%20Western">First Great Western</ref> have been affected. Train services to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Staines-upon-Thames">Staines-upon-Thames</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windsor,%20Berkshire">Windsor</ref> have been replaced by buses.</p>
<p>Trains on the London to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hastings">Hastings</ref> service have been affected by land-slips between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wadhurst">Wadhurst</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle,%20East%20Sussex">Battle</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/East_Sussex">East Sussex</ref> while trains to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East%20Grinstead">East Grinstead</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uckfield">Uckfield</ref> have been affected by a land-slip at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxted">Oxted</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surrey">Surrey</ref>.</p>
<p>Services in the south-west have been affected by damage to railway lines in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dawlish">Dawlish</ref>. Service is not expected to restart for at least six weeks. In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Devon">Devon</ref>, buses have replaced trains between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exeter">Exeter</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newton%20Abbot">Newton Abbot</ref>.</p>
<p>The damage to the railway line at Dawlish has been the subject of criticism by passenger group TravelWatch SouthWest who said <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Network_Rail">Network Rail</ref> — the company charged with maintaining the British railway network — had been "in complete denial" about the vulnerability of the sea wall. The group pointed to a 2004 report they produced arguing for re-routing of railway services on a disused railway in the area. "Had the recommendation in that 2004 report been heeded, the studies would already have been completed, and a clear preferred diversionary route might now be available", they said.</p>
<p>In <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wales">Wales</ref>, there have been delays on the railway between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porth">Porth</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pontypridd">Pontypridd</ref>, and replacement bus services between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hereford">Hereford</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newport">Newport</ref> due to flooding in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abergavenny">Abergavenny</ref>. Trains going between <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Manchester">Manchester</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cardiff">Cardiff</ref> have also been affected by the floods.</p>
<p>Streets have closed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Purley">Purley</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxford">Oxford</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Worcester">Worcester</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wrexham">Wrexham</ref>. Journeys for drivers using the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A29%20road%20(England)">A29</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A32%20road%20(England)">A32</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A4113%20road">A4113</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A54%20road%20(England)">A54</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A57%20road%20(England)">A57</ref> roads have all been affected. A 50-foot-hole appeared in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M2%20motorway%20(Great%20Britain)">M2</ref> motorway in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kent">Kent</ref> which led to the closure of a ten mile section of the road.</p>
</text>
