<text id="autogum_news_doc552" title="Conservatives win Newark by-election" shortTile="conservatives-win" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-06-06" dateModified="2019-10-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Conservatives_win_Newark_by-election" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Conservatives win Newark by-election</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 6, 2014</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Robert Jenrick, the new Conservative MP for Newark. Image: altogetherfool.</caption></figure>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Conservative_Party_(UK)">Conservative Party</ref> has won the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newark%20(UK%20Parliament%20constituency)">Newark</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref> <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/by-election">by-election</ref> but with a reduced majority. Voters gave 45.03% of the vote to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20Jenrick">Robert Jenrick</ref>, while the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK_Independence_Party">UK Independence Party</ref> candidate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger%20Helmer">Roger Helmer</ref> came second with 25.91% of the vote. The turnout was 38,707, 52.67% of the electorate of 73,486.</p>
<p>The by-election was called following the resignation of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick%20Mercer">Patrick Mercer</ref> after it was revealed he was paid to lobby and ask questions in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK_House_of_Commons">Parliament</ref> on behalf of the country of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Fiji">Fiji</ref> in an investigation by the BBC <hi rend="italic">Panorama</hi> programme.</p>
<p>Jenrick is a 32-year-old who works as managing director of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christie's">Christie's</ref> auction house. After the election result was announced, he said: "I want to thank the prime minister for his personal support to my campaign and I want to thank the government for its commitment to re-building Britain. I hope now that I can repay the faith and trust that the people of Newark have put in me as your new member of parliament — and in the months and years to come I can build a reputation as a strong and effective MP."</p>
<p>UKIP's candidate, Roger Helmer, attracted controversy during the election campaign due to past public statements about the acceptability of homosexuality. In remarks to <hi rend="italic">The Sun</hi> newspaper, he compared considering homosexuality "distasteful if not viscerally repugnant" to tea preferences. He explained: "Different people may have different tastes. You may tell me that you don’t like Earl Grey tea. That may be a minority view but you are entitled not to like it if you don't like it." Helmer later stated the manner in which his comments were reported showed "the mainstream media are engaged in a feeding frenzy against UKIP, and are prepared to twist the facts to suit their agenda".</p>
<p>UKIP leader <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nigel_Farage">Nigel Farage</ref> said the party had run a "stunning campaign": "We've been up against probably the biggest ever Conservative machine, defending about their 40th safest seat in the country. If the indications are right, we'll be celebrating a massive advance for our party."</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Liberal_Democrats_(UK)">Liberal Democrat</ref> candidate, David Watts, said coming in sixth place "wasn't a good result, but smaller parties often get squeezed in by-elections and that's what's happened to us here". He said the independent campaign by Paul Baggaley had got a lot of support, and "a lot of our voters had transferred to vote against UKIP to make sure UKIP didn't get elected".</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grant%20Shapps">Grant Shapps</ref> from the Conservative Party said the surge of support for UKIP after the European elections was now "going backwards", while Nigel Farage said Conservative MPs in more marginal seats would be filled with "sheer horror" at UKIP's success.</p>
<caption>Newark by-election results</caption>
Position
Candidate
Party
Votes
Percentage
1
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20Jenrick">Robert Jenrick</ref>
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Conservative_Party_(UK)">Conservative Party</ref>
17,431
45.03%
2
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger%20Helmer">Roger Helmer</ref>
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK_Independence_Party">UK Independence Party</ref>
10,028
25.91%
3
Michael Payne
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Labour_Party_(UK)">Labour Party</ref>
6,842
17.68%
4
Paul Baggaley
Independent
1,891
4.89%
5
David Kirwan
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Green_Party_(UK)">Green Party</ref>
1,057
2.73%
6
David Watts
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Liberal_Democrats_(UK)">Liberal Democrats</ref>
1,004
2.59%
7
Nick The Flying Brick
Loony
168
0.43%
8
Andy Hayes
Independent
117
0.30%
9
David Bishop
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bus%20Pass%20Elvis%20Party">Bus Pass Elvis Party</ref>
87
0.22%
10
Dick Rodgers
Stop Banks
64
0.17%
11
Lee Woods
Patriotic Socialist Party
18
0.05%
</text>
