<text id="autogum_news_doc760" title="Earthquake, tsunami combo caused devastation in Pichilemu, Chile" shortTile="earthquake-tsunami" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-03-04" dateModified="2018-01-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Earthquake%2C_tsunami_combo_caused_devastation_in_Pichilemu%2C_Chile" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Earthquake, tsunami combo caused devastation in Pichilemu, Chile</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 4, 2010</hi></p><p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pichilemu">Pichilemu</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chile">Chile</ref> — Last Saturday, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chile">Chile</ref> was hit by a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2010%20Chile%20earthquake">8.8 earthquake</ref>. Many coastal towns were also hit by a tsunami, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pichilemu">Pichilemu</ref> was one of them. Its inhabitants were surprised by the giant waves that destroyed the most of the <hi rend="italic">costanera</hi> and that reached the city square.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pichilemu">Pichilemu</ref>, that means in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mapudungun">Mapudungun language</ref> <hi rend="italic">small forest</hi>, is one of the most famous Chilean resort towns in the central zone of Chile. It is recurrently visited by surfers from all the world, because the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Punta%20de%20Lobos">Punta de Lobos beach</ref> is considered one of the best for surf practice worldwide.</p>
<p>Central Pichilemu was not severely damaged by the earthquake, but the tsunami caused significant destruction. The Fishermen Creek, located in front of the beach, was completely destroyed, and its machines are now unusable. Most of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ross%20Casino">Agustín Ross architecture</ref> that characterized the city, three of them being <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Monuments%20of%20Chile">National Monuments of Chile</ref>, were damaged. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agustín%20Ross%20Balcony">Agustín Ross Mirador</ref>, a famous location in front of the beach, located less than 200 meters from the Fisherman Creek, was completely destroyed. Its famous <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baluster">balustrades</ref> were washed away or thrown asunder. Many restaurants, kiosks and a circus were affected by the tsunami.</p>
<p>The rural parts of Pichilemu, like Ciruelos, Rodeillo and Espinillo feature houses constructed from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/adobe">adobe</ref>. Many were more than 100-years old, and were destroyed or are now uninhabitable.</p>
<p>The most powerful aftershock was produced almost 40 kilometers in front of the coast of Pichilemu, at the 03:10 local time (07:10 UTC) in March 2, with an intensity of 5.5 in the Richter scale, according to the USGS.</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intendant">Intendant</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/O'Higgins%20Region">O'Higgins Region</ref>, Juan Núñez, had a meeting with the Governor of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardenal%20Caro%20Province">Cardenal Caro Province</ref>, Loreto Puebla, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mayor">Mayor</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pichilemu">Pichilemu</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Roberto_Córdova">Roberto Córdova</ref>, and naval and military authorities, <hi rend="italic">juntas de vecinos</hi> representatives. They decided to leave the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/es:Carabineros">Carabineros police force</ref> to maintain the security of the city.</p>
<figure><caption>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arturo%20Prat">Arturo Prat</ref> square was severely damaged by the earthquake and later by the tsunami. In the left picture, can be seen some kiosks, all of them were destroyed, as can be seen on the right picture. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.</caption></figure>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arturo%20Prat">Arturo Prat</ref> square was severely damaged by the earthquake and later by the tsunami. In the left picture, can be seen some kiosks, all of them were destroyed, as can be seen on the right picture. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.
<figure><caption>A boat that was originally in front of the Fisherman Creek of Pichilemu, was thrown almost a block away by the powerful tsunami that hit Chile last Saturday. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.</caption></figure>A boat that was originally in front of the Fisherman Creek of Pichilemu, was thrown almost a block away by the powerful tsunami that hit Chile last Saturday. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.
 <figure><caption>A fair was located in front of the beach, called Feria Internacional Artesanal, where Peruvian and Chilean craftsmans were selling their crafts. All of their premises were destroyed, and later looted by the people that were passing by the <hi rend="italic">costanera</hi>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.</caption></figure>A fair was located in front of the beach, called Feria Internacional Artesanal, where Peruvian and Chilean craftsman were selling their crafts. All of their premises were destroyed, and later looted by the people that were passing by the <hi rend="italic">costanera</hi>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.
 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Augustin-balcony-before.jpg">File:Augustin-balcony-before.jpg</ref>The Famous Agustín Ross balcony (<hi rend="italic">mirador</hi>), before and after the earthquake and tsunami. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.
 <figure><caption>A strong aftershock was originated around Pichilemu, in March 5, 2010, 12:34:32 AM at epicenter (03:34:32 AM UTC). Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Geological%20Survey">USGS</ref>.</caption></figure>A strong aftershock was originated around Pichilemu, in March 5, 2010, at 12:34:32 AM at epicenter (03:34:32 AM UTC). Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Geological%20Survey">USGS</ref>.
</text>
