<text id="autogum_news_doc443" title="Massive flooding in China; over 550 thousand evacuated" shortTile="massive-flooding" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-06-17" dateModified="2015-02-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Massive_flooding_in_China%3B_over_550_thousand_evacuated" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Massive flooding in China; over 550 thousand evacuated</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 18, 2011</hi></p>
<figure><caption>The course of the Yangtze River, China's largest, from north to south. Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%20Upload%20Bot%20(Magnus%20Manske)">File Upload Bot (Magnus Manske).</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Heavy June rainfall has forced <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref> to  evacuate more than 550,000 people from their homes. Massive floods have devastated the central and  southern parts of the country,  causing rivers to overflow their banks and triggering mudslides.  The rains follow the worst <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/drought">drought</ref> in China in over 50 years, which has decimated  crop yields.  </p>
<hi rend="bold">Since June 13, the damage caused by the rainstorms has led to ... the emergency evacuation of 671,200 people to safety.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—China's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ministry%20of%20Civil%20Affairs">Ministry of Civil Affairs</ref></p>
<p>Overall, 40 rivers have risen above safe limits, stressing  dykes and dams including those on China's largest waterway, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yangtze">Yangtze River</ref>, which is flooding downstream while experiencing a severe drought near its source in the north. </p>
<p>China's disaster level has been raised to four, the highest on the scale. In a statement on its website on Friday, China's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ministry%20of%20Civil%20Affairs">Ministry of Civil Affairs</ref> said, "Since June 13, the damage caused by the rainstorms has led to ... the emergency evacuation of 671,200 people to safety."</p>
<p>The current round of heavy rains began in early June. Since then, more than a million and a half people have been displaced in  the central and southern regions of the country and at least 168 deaths have been reported. Meteorologists in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Beijing">Beijing</ref> are predicting more heavy rain in  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sichuan">Sichuan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guizhou">Guizhou</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zhejiang">Zhejiang</ref> this weekend.</p>
<hi rend="bold">[R]escue boats cannot go through those narrow lanes inside the village. A lot of them depend on their relatives rowing small wooden boats to get to them... It is hard to help these people inside there.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Chinese villager</p>
<p>The government has mobilized its forces to aid in the massive evacuations. According to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Reuters">Reuters</ref>, local authorities are distributing a box of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/instant%20noodles">instant noodles</ref> and a carton of bottled water to those affected by the flood. But villagers have reported that survival is difficult, especially for those still trapped by the flood waters in small villages, and distribution of aid is slow, with some not receiving any. </p>
<p>A villager was quoted by Reuters: "To be frank, those rescue boats cannot go through those narrow lanes inside the village. A lot of them depend on their relatives rowing small wooden boats to get to them... It is hard to help these people inside there." Another villager, Shou Pengfei  said, "Some did not even get any relief items. There is no electricity and you get bitten by mosquitoes all the time." </p>
<hi rend="bold">Some did not even get any relief items. There is no electricity and you get bitten by mosquitoes all the time.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Shou Pengfei, A Chinese villager</p>
<p>According to  the Beijing Climate Centre, weather trends have shifted drastically. Currently the  rain is coming in shorter but fiercer bursts, with  protracted periods of drought in between the torrential rain. </p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three%20Gorges%20Dam">Three Gorges Dam</ref> on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yangtze">Yangtze</ref> in 2009. Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Rehman">Rehman</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The heavy  rainfall is not likely to reduce the crop failure caused by months of drought, especially in the north, the heart of China's grain-growing bread basket, where many rivers have dried up. According to reports, the northern countryside  has been left devastated by the droughts. Huge dams hundreds of meters wide are now small, muddy pools. Large cities such as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Beijing">Beijing</ref> are draining the underground water sources and China is facing a long-term water crisis.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, China is engaged in  a huge multi-year engineering project designed to move water to the parched north and away from the flooded south. The North-South water project is a massive series of canals and pipes designed to carry water from the Yangtze and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yellow%20River">Yellow</ref> rivers to Beijing.</p>
<p>It is likely, analysts predict, that Chinese crop shortages will increase food prices worldwide. Even before the latest flooding, the severe drought in the north caused a  shortfall in China's crop yields that will likely  affect the price of wheat and may propel a price increase in global markets.</p>
</text>
