<text id="autogum_news_doc499" title="Emmanuel Macron wins French presidential election race" shortTile="emmanuel-macron-wins" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-05-08" dateModified="2019-08-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Emmanuel_Macron_wins_French_presidential_election_race" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Emmanuel Macron wins French presidential election race</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 9, 2017</hi></p>
<p>On Sunday, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/En%20Marche!">En Marche!</ref></hi> candidate <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Emmanuel_Macron">Emmanuel Macron</ref> won the second round of the 2017 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">French</ref> Presidential election, winning about 66.1 percent of the votes, defeating <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Front%20national">Front national</ref>'</hi>s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marine%20Le%20Pen">Marine Le Pen</ref> with the final result declared yesterday. Winning the race with a significant vote difference, Marcon tweeted, "Everyone told us that it was impossible. But they did not know France!" ((fr))French language: ‍Tout le monde nous disait que c’était impossible. Mais ils ne connaissaient pas la France !</p>
<figure><caption>Distribution of votes. Yellow represents <hi rend="italic">En Marche!</hi> and blue represents <hi rend="italic">Front national</hi>Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Mélencron">Mélencron</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>With this victory, winning almost twice as many votes as Le Pen, 39-year-old Emmanuel Macron became the youngest President-elect of the Republic of France. In the first round of the election, held on April 23, no candidate won the absolute majority. The abstention rate increased from 22.23% to 25.44% in the second round, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/AFP">AFP</ref> reported, the first such second-round increase since 1969. He won the presidential race in the continuing state of emergency which was announced after the November 2015 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paris">Paris</ref> attack.</p>
<p>Known for her anti-<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Union">European</ref> and anti-globalisation programme, far-right leader Le Pen managed to win about twice as many votes as her father and founder of the <hi rend="italic">Front national</hi> party <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean-Marie%20Le%20Pen">Jean-Marie Le Pen</ref> who lost to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jacques_Chirac">Jacques Chirac</ref> in 2002. <hi rend="italic">Front national</hi> won the highest number of votes in their history.</p>
<p>In his speech in front of the glass pyramid near the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louvre%20Museum">Louvre Museum</ref>, Macron said, "I understand the divisions of our country that have led some to vote for extremists. I understand the anger, the anxiety, the doubts that a great part among us have also expressed." ((fr))French language: ‍Je sais les divisions de notre nation qui ont conduit certains à un vote extrême. Je sais les colères, les doutes, l'anxiété que certains ont exprimé. He also added, "I will defend France, its vital interests, its image, I promise you in front of you. I will defend Europe, our civilisation is at stake, our way of being free. I will work to re-establish the bonds between Europe and the citizens. I address to the nations of the world, the salvation of fraternal France." ((fr))French language: ‍Je défendrai la France, ses intérêts vitaux, son image. J'en prends l'engagement devant vous. Je défendrai l'Europe, c'est notre civilisation qui est en jeu, notre manière d'être libre. J'oeuvrerai à retisser les liens entre l'Europe et les citoyens. J'adresse aux nations du monde, le salut de la France fraternelle. Macron said he would serve as per the motto of France — <hi rend="italic">Liberté, égalité, fraternité</hi>((fr))French language: ‍Liberty, equality and fraternity. Acknowledging the "immense" awaiting task, he said, "I will do everything I can in the coming five years to make sure you never have a reason to vote for extremism again".</p>
<p>"Congratulations Emmanuel Macron! Let's meet soon, and keep working to grow and strengthen the deep ties between Canada and France" ((fr))French language: ‍Félicitations Emmanuel Macron! Rencontrons-nous rapidement et continuons à renforcer les liens de fraternité entre le Canada et la France, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canadian</ref> Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Justin_Trudeau">Justin Trudeau</ref> tweeted. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">German</ref> chancellor <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Angela_Merkel">Angela Merkel</ref> congratulated Macron via a telephone call.</p>
<p>French parliamentary elections are to be held in June, and Emmanuel Macron, who describes himself as "neither left nor right" does not have a party in the parliament. <hi rend="italic">En Marche!</hi> was formed last year. Marine Le Pen tweeted that <hi rend="italic">Front national</hi> "must renew itself to live up to this historic opportunity and expectations of France" ((fr))French language: ‍doit se renouveler pour être à la hauteur de cette opportunité historique et des attentes des Français.</p>
<p>Current president, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/François_Hollande">François Hollande</ref> announced he would not run for re-election in December.</p>
"Everyone told us that it was impossible. But they did not know France!" ((fr))French language: ‍Tout le monde nous disait que c’était impossible. Mais ils ne connaissaient pas la France !—Emmanuel Macron
20,753,798
10,644,118
Emmanuel Macron– <hi rend="italic">En Marche!</hi>
Marine Le Pen– <hi rend="italic">Front national</hi>
Data from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interior%20Ministry%20(France)">Ministère de l'Intérieu</ref>.
</text>
