<text id="autogum_news_doc449" title="Japanese nuclear plant operators ordered to compensate affected families amid calls for prime minister to resign" shortTile="japanese-nuclear" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-04-14" dateModified="2019-10-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japanese_nuclear_plant_operators_ordered_to_compensate_affected_families_amid_calls_for_prime_minister_to_resign" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Japanese nuclear plant operators ordered to compensate affected families amid calls for prime minister to resign</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 16, 2011</hi></p>
<figure><caption>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fukushima%20I%20nuclear%20accidents">crisis</ref> at the flooded <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fukushima%20I%20nuclear%20power%20plant">Fukushima I nuclear power plant</ref> has now been designated on par with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chernobyl%20disaster">Chernobyl disaster</ref> in 1986. Image: kawamoto takuo.</caption></figure><figure><caption>File photograph of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Akihito">Akihito</ref>, who visited northeast Japan this week to meet survivors of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2011_Sendai_earthquake_and_tsunami">the tsunami which devastated the area</ref>. Image: Shawnc.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Thousands of people were left dead and many more are missing after the disaster. This image shows the flooding which devastated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sendai%20airport">Sendai airport</ref>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._Air_Force">U.S. Air Force</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The operators of the stricken <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fukushima%20I%20nuclear%20power%20plant">Fukushima I nuclear power plant</ref> in northeast <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref> have been ordered to pay compensation to families affected by the ongoing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fukushima%20I%20nuclear%20accidents">crisis</ref> at the site, amid calls for the resignation of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/prime%20minister%20of%20Japan">Japanese prime minister</ref> over how he is handling the crisis, which has now been designated on par with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chernobyl%20disaster">Chernobyl disaster</ref> in 1986.</p>
<p>Japanese officials ordered <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/TEPCO">TEPCO</ref> to pay <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japanese%20yen">¥</ref>1million (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>12thousand,
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pound%20sterling">£</ref>7.35thousand) to each household affected by the crisis, which the company says will add up to approximately <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japanese%20yen">¥</ref>50billion (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>599million,
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pound%20sterling">£</ref>367million). Earlier this week, officials announced plans to expand the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/nuclear%20exclusion%20zone">nuclear exclusion zone</ref> around the plant to include five more communities as radiation continues to leak from the plant. Pressure is now mounting for the resignation of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Naoto_Kan">Naoto Kan</ref>, the Japanese prime minister, for his handling of the nuclear crisis in Fukushima; some of his opponents have called for an independent inquiry into how he reacted to the disaster. </p>
<p>TEPCO has this week announced plans to move equipment to higher ground after a series of strong <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/aftershock">aftershocks</ref> that have hampered efforts to repair the crippled facility. Officials have warned some of the nuclear rods in the reactors at the plant may have been damaged, but likely remain intact. Workers at the plant are still fighting a desperate battle to stop radiation leaking from the plant, but have been hit by constant setbacks. </p>
<p>Earlier this week officials of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nuclear_and_Industrial_Safety_Agency">NISA</ref>, the Japanese government nuclear authority, said officials had upgraded the crisis to a level seven on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International%20Nuclear%20Event%20Scale">International Nuclear Event Scale</ref>—the same applied to the Chernobyl disaster—designating the crisis as a "major accident" with "wider consequences" than previously thought. "We have upgraded the severity level to seven as the impact of radiation leaks has been widespread from the air, vegetables, tap water and the ocean," he said. </p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Akihito">Akihito</ref>, the emperor of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref>, travelled to the northeast of the country on Wednesday to visit survivors of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2011_Sendai_earthquake_and_tsunami">the tsunami which devastated the area</ref> last month against a backdrop of mounting anger over the  at a nuclear plant, where technicians are continuing to battle to cool the reactors as radiation continues to leak from the site. Akihito and his wife, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Empress%20Michiko">Michiko</ref>, met people displaced by the tragedy at two emergency shelters in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asahi,%20Chiba">Asahi</ref>, near the northeast coast where the tsunami struck. 140,000 people are now living in emergency shelters across Japan after their homes were destroyed in the disaster.</p>
<p>Emergency workers, dressed in protective white suits, gloves and goggles, have began searching for bodies within the exclusion zone around the stricken nuclear plant, much of which was left muddied and destroyed by the tsunami. Officials fear up to 1,000 bodies may be among the wreckage in the area. Search efforts in the area have been put off because of high radiation levels, but authorities want to recover bodies before they deteriorate to the point where they become a health hazard and impossible to identify.</p>
<hi rend="bold">I am physically and mentally worn out by the nuclear crisis. They [the government] have done nothing so far to help us.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Yoshihisa Kato, businessman in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fukushima%20prefecture">Fukushima</ref></p>
<p>Japanese television reported radiation levels in the ocean off the plant have fallen but remain high. Health officials have found radiation 25 times the legal limit in fish caught south of the nuclear plant, and radioactivity had been detected in 11 different vegetables in Fukushima earlier this week.  The death toll from the disaster is continuing to rise; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/law%20enforcement%20in%20Japan">Japanese police</ref> have reported 13,300 people have been confirmed dead and more than 15,000 are still missing.</p>
<p>Another aftershock, with a magnitude of 6.1, struck on Thursday morning, following a more powerful one, measuring magnitude 6.6, on Monday. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List%20of%20foreshocks%20and%20aftershocks%20of%20the%202011%20Tōhoku%20earthquake%20and%20tsunami">Hundreds of aftershocks</ref> have rattled northeast Japan in the month since the initial earthquake. Before the aftershock on Monday, people across Japan marked the one month anniversary of the earthquake with a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/moment%20of%20silence">moment of silence</ref>, and Kan paid tribute to countries who had sent aid to the stricken country. However, Kan has been criticised for his handling of the nuclear crisis. An entrepreneur in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fukushima%20prefecture">Fukushima</ref>, Yoshihisa Kato, complained about how he had been left abandoned by the government. "I am physically and mentally worn out by the nuclear crisis," he said. "They have done nothing so far to help us."</p>
<head id="Related_articles">Related articles</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>"<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Crisis_at_stricken_Japan_nuclear_plant_escalates_to_level_of_Chernobyl;_six_killed_in_aftershock">Crisis at stricken Japan nuclear plant escalates to level of Chernobyl; six killed in aftershock</ref>" — <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page">Wikinews</ref></hi>, April 12, 2011</item>
<item>"<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japanese_nuclear_officials_race_to_avoid_disaster_as_radiation_levels_in_sea_rocket">Japanese nuclear officials race to avoid disaster as radiation levels in sea rocket</ref>" — <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page">Wikinews</ref></hi>, March 31, 2011</item>
<item>"<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Situation_at_damaged_nuclear_power_plant_remains_'very_grave',_says_Japanese_Prime_Minister">Situation at damaged nuclear power plant remains 'very grave', says Japanese Prime Minister</ref>" — <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page">Wikinews</ref></hi>, March 25, 2011</item></list>
</text>
