<text id="autogum_news_doc707" title="GWAR frontman Dave Brockie aka Oderus Urungus dies at age 50" shortTile="gwar-frontman-dave" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-25" dateModified="2014-04-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/GWAR_frontman_Dave_Brockie_aka_Oderus_Urungus_dies_at_age_50" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>GWAR frontman Dave Brockie aka Oderus Urungus dies at age 50</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 25, 2014</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Brockie as Oderus Urungus onstage in 2010. Image: Stuart Sevastos.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dave_Brockie">Dave Brockie</ref> of rubber-costumed <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Heavy_metal">metal</ref> act <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/GWAR">GWAR</ref>  was found dead in his <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Richmond,_Virginia">Richmond</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Virginia">Virginia</ref> home late on Sunday. Better known by stage name Oderus Urungus, Brockie was 50.</p>
<p>Founder, singer, leader, and occasional bassist of GWAR, Brockie's career stretches back to 1984. He and fellow <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Virginia_Commonwealth_University">Virginia Commonwealth University</ref> art students formed what they dubbed "Earth's only openly extra-terrestrial rock band", growing famous for satirical and obscene lyrical themes, and live shows featuring the defilement of effigies and plenty of fake blood.</p>
<p>Fellow founding member Don Drakulich, who still makes props and costumes for the rockers, said he was "very sad" and "shocked". He said Brockie's roommate found the corpse. GWAR members changed frequently and the band recovered from the sudden death of guitarist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cory%20Smoot">Cory "Flattus Maximus" Smoot</ref> during a 2011 tour, but the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20York%20Daily%20News">New York Daily News</ref></hi> notes "it's hard to envision their saga going further" after Brockie's death.</p>
<p>The band ran with the backstory of crashing to "the most insignificant planet in the universe" 43 million years ago before creating humans by having sex with apes. Becoming encased with ice, the legend ran that upon thawing out in 1984 the members decided to form a band.</p>
<hi rend="bold">I am one of the blessed people that gets to do what I love to do for a living</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Brockie in 2009</p>
<p>Manager Jack Flanagan announced the death via GWAR's website, adding a post-mortem will be conducted. "My main focus right now is to look after my band mates and his family" he said. Flanagan said another GWAR member found the body.</p>
<p>Brockie said in 2009 "I am one of the blessed people that gets to do what I love to do for a living." GWAR received a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grammy%20Award">Grammy</ref> nomination in 1993, with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phallus%20in%20Wonderland">Phallus in Wonderland</ref></hi> up for Best Longform Music Video.</p>
<p>Fellow Virginia rocker <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Randy%20Blythe">Randy Blythe</ref>, vocalist for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lamb_of_God_(band)">Lamb of God</ref>, paid tribute online, writing on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Instagram">Instagram</ref> "When someone dies, a lot of the time people will say 'Oh, he was a unique person, really one of a kind, a true original' [...] I can't think of ANYONE even remotely like him." </p>
<hi rend="bold">He never put much stock in 'limits'</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Lamb of God singer Randy Blythe</p>
<p>Blythe also took to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Facebook">Facebook</ref>. "Right now, if I were to truly honor Dave in the way HE would do it if it were ME that had died, I would make a completely tasteless joke about his death. But I do not have the stomach for that — Dave would, but not me. He never put much stock in 'limits'."</p>
<p>Ex-GWAR guitarist Steve Douglas said on Facebook "I have had a few bad days in my life but this one truly ranks right up there. [...] you are gone and it is hurting very badly!" "I wish it was a joke" said another ex-member, Chris Bopst. "Everyone is in shock."</p>
<p>Former bassist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Bishop%20(bassist)">Mike Bishop</ref> paid tribute in an interview with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Style%20Weekly">Style Weekly</ref></hi>. "Dave was one of the funniest, smartest, most creative and energetic persons I've known," he said. "He was brash sometimes, always crass, irreverent, he was hilarious in every way. But he was also deeply intelligent and interested in life, history, politics and art."</p>
</text>
