<text id="autogum_news_doc677" title="Argentina score in extra-time; beat Mexico, get to quarter-finals" shortTile="argentina-score-extratime" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-06-24" dateModified="2015-07-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Argentina_score_in_extra-time%3B_beat_Mexico%2C_get_to_quarter-finals" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Argentina score in extra-time; beat Mexico, get to quarter-finals</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 24, 2006</hi> <figure rend="World Cup 2006 logo.png"></figure> An epic round sixteen contest between Argentina and Mexico was won by a work of genius from Maxi Rodriguez, Saturday.</p>
<p>
Juan Sorin hit a cross-field pass to the midfield player at the top right edge of the Mexican box. Rodriguez jumped to receive the ball and, in the same moment, chested high the way it had come. He met the descending ball 25 yards out with a perfectly timed left-footed volley and the ball arrowed over Oswaldo Sanchez into the opposite corner of the net.</p>
<p>The evenness and excitement of the match might easily be overshadowed by the winning goal. Though the shot totals were not high - Argentina had five shots on target to Mexico's three -  the action was end to end.</p>
<p>Part of the reason for the excitement was while Mexico tried to keep a fast attacking pace Argentina attempted to slow the game down. There could have been more goals; both Argentina and Mexico defended well and had timely saves from their goalkeepers. </p>
<p>Mexico got off to the best possible start with a goal from a set-piece after five minutes. Pavel Pardo's cross from the right touchline was flicked on by Mario Mendez and Rafael Marquez slid in to score on a half volley at the far post.</p>
<p>For Argentina the equalising goal five minutes later was the best possible response to going behind. A corner kick was swung in low to the near post; Hernan Crespo raised his foot, Jared Borgetti stuck out his neck and between them the ball sped past Sanchez.</p>
<p>The match had its moment of controversy. Just before half time the Argentine goalkeeper rolled a ball to Gabriel Heinze. Somehow his defender let it go past him to Mexican striker Jose Fonseca. Heinze lunged to bring Fonseca down. Massimo Busacca adjudged Roberto Ayala to be the last defender and spared Heinze the red card for the deliberate professional foul. </p>
<p>Goalkeepers at either end made match saving contributions in the second half.  On 53 minutes Roberto Abbondanzieri saved a defensive a clearance that deflected off Borgetti six yards from goal. Five minutes later Javier Saviola was through on goal; he went high and hard with the shot but Sanchez stuck out a strong left palm and batted the ball away for a corner. </p>
<p>Lionel Messi and Carlos Tevez replaced Crespo and Saviola as Argentina sought to break the deadlock. A minute from time Tevez thought he was through on goal but Ricardo Osorio got back just in time and the game was destined for another 30 minutes and that special moment in extra time.</p>
<p>Argentina's win meant they would play their quarter-final match in the Olympiastadion, Berlin, against the host nation Germany on June 30.</p>
<head id="Round_of_sixteen">Round of sixteen</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Match 50</hi></p>
June 24, 200621:00
<hi rend="bold"> Argentina</hi>
<hi rend="bold">2–1</hi>
<hi rend="bold"> Mexico</hi>
Zentralstadion
Crespo 10'  Rodríguez 98'
Márquez 6'
<p>Attendance: 43'000</p>
<head id="Formations">Formations</head>
<head id="Argentina">Argentina</head>
Right wing
Right
Center
Left
Left wing
Roberto Abbondanzieri (GK)
Lionel Scaloni
Roberto Ayala
Gabriel Heinze 46'+
Javier Mascherano
Maxi Rodriguez
Juan Riquelme
Esteban Cambiasso
Juan Sorin (C) 112'
Javier Saviola
Hernan Crespo
<p><hi rend="italic">Substitutes</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>75' Carlos Tevez for Crespo</item>
<item>76' Pablo Aimar for Cambiasso</item>
<item>84' Lionel Messi for Saviola</item></list>
<figure rend="Soccerball.jpg"></figure> <hi rend="italic">denotes one goal scored.</hi>
<head id="Mexico">Mexico</head>
Right wing
Right
Center
Left
Left wing
Oswaldo Sanchez (GK)
Rafael Marquez
<p>(C)  70'</p>
Ricardo Osorio
Carlos Salcido
Jose Antonio
<p>Castro 82'</p>
Mario Mendez
Andreas Guardado
Pavel Pardo
Ramon Morales
Jose Fonseca 119'
Jared Borgetti
<p><hi rend="italic">Substitutes</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>38' Gerardo Torrado 118'</item>
<item>66' Gonzalo Pineda</item>
<item>74' Zinha</item></list>
<figure rend="Soccerball.jpg"></figure> <hi rend="italic">denotes one goal scored.</hi>
<head id="Officials">Officials</head>
<figure rend="Flag of Switzerland.svg"></figure> Referee: Massimo Busacca
<figure rend="Flag of Switzerland.svg"></figure> Assistant referee: Francesco Buragina
<figure rend="Flag of Switzerland.svg"></figure> Assistant referee: Matthias Arnet
<figure rend="Flag of Saudi Arabia.svg"></figure> Fourth referee: Khalil Al Ghamdi
<figure rend="Flag of Jordan.svg"></figure> Fifth referee: Fathi Arabati
</text>
