<text id="autogum_news_doc482" title="Mirror&apos;s exposé prompts call for inquiry into child abuse ring in Telford, England" shortTile="mirrors-expose-prompts" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-03-12" dateModified="2018-03-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mirror%27s_expos%C3%A9_prompts_call_for_inquiry_into_child_abuse_ring_in_Telford%2C_England" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Mirror's exposé prompts call for inquiry into child abuse ring in Telford, England</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 13, 2018</hi></p>
<p>On Monday, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucy%20Allan%20(politician)">Lucy Allan</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/House_of_Commons_of_the_United_Kingdom">MP</ref> (Member of Parliament) called for a public inquiry into an alleged child sexual exploitation ring in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Telford">Telford</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shropshire">Shropshire</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref>, which may have been operating for 40 years and had as many as a thousand girls as victims. This came in direct response to an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/investigative%20journalism">investigative report</ref> by the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sunday%20Mirror">Sunday Mirror</ref></hi> the previous day. Allan wants an independent inquiry, similar that for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotherham%20child%20sexual%20exploitation%20scandal">Rotherham child sexual exploitation scandal</ref>, which came to light in 2012 and had a similar scale and duration.</p>
<figure><caption>Lucy Allan, MP Image: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris%20McAndrew">Chris McAndrew</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The <hi rend="italic">Mirror</hi> alleges that hundreds of girls were raped, beaten, drugged and sold for sex. Victims were as young as 11 and at least three were killed. Details of negligence and outright misconduct by the authorities, including local council staff, the police and social workers, are also contained in the exposé. </p>
<p>"There must now be an independent inquiry into child sexual exploitation in Telford so that our community can have absolute confidence in the authorities," Allan said. "The IICSA will not investigate whether any of the authorities in Telford should be accountable. That is why we must have an independent inquiry into what happened in Telford; such an inquiry is outside the current scope of the IICSA." </p>
<p>IICSA is the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent%20Inquiry%20into%20Child%20Sexual%20Abuse">Independent Inquiry into Child Sexual Abuse</ref>, which plans to look into the Telford situation, according to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BBC">BBC</ref>. In 2013, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Telford%20child%20sex%20abuse%20ring">Operation Chalice</ref> saw the breakup of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/child%20grooming">child sex grooming</ref> ring in Telford with seven men of South Asian origin convicted. However, if the <hi rend="italic">Mirror'</hi>s report is accurate, it was only the tip of the iceberg.</p>
<p>Some of the alleged failings by authorities include social workers being aware of abuse without a police investigation for up to a decade; classifying underage girls as prostitutes instead of victims; not keeping records of alleged perpetrators out of fear it could look like racism; police not investigating despite five reports being filed. The <hi rend="italic">Mirror</hi> also said the authorities actively tried to obstruct their investigation.</p>
<p>"Child sexual exploitation [CSE] is a vile, evil crime. It’s an issue right across the UK and has been for a long time. Telford will be covered by the national CSE review. We welcome this. All agencies continue to work very closely together and this remains our top priority," said a spokesperson for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Telford%20and%20Wrekin%20Council">Telford and Wrekin Council</ref> according to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russia%20Today">Russia Today</ref>. "Our approach to CSE is now very different from 10-20 years ago. We have learned lots of lessons and are constantly on the lookout for indicators of CSE so that we can pass information on to police and bring these evil criminals to justice. Indeed, further cases are now coming to court."</p>
</text>
