<text id="autogum_news_doc668" title="Joey Logano wins his first NASCAR Sprint Cup race of 2016" shortTile="joey-logano-wins" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-06-13" dateModified="2016-11-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Joey_Logano_wins_his_first_NASCAR_Sprint_Cup_race_of_2016" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Joey Logano wins his first NASCAR Sprint Cup race of 2016</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 14, 2016</hi></p>
<p>On Sunday, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Team%20Penske">Team Penske</ref> driver <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joey%20Logano">Joey Logano</ref> claimed his first <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASCAR">NASCAR</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sprint%20Cup%20Series">Sprint Cup Series</ref> win of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2016%20NASCAR%20Sprint%20Cup%20Series">2016 season</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FireKeepers%20Casino%20400">FireKeepers Casino 400</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michigan%20International%20Speedway">Michigan International Speedway</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brooklyn,%20Michigan">Brooklyn</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Michigan">Michigan</ref>. The 200-lap race began with Logano starting from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pole%20position">pole position</ref>, and featured nine cautions and fourteen lead changes between eight different drivers. </p>
<figure><caption>File photo of Joey Logano, 2015. Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Missvain">Sarah Stierch</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Despite starting first, Logano was quickly overtaken on the first lap by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Furniture%20Row%20Racing">Furniture Row Racing</ref> driver <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin%20Truex%20Jr.">Martin Truex Jr</ref>. Truex led the race until Logano reclaimed the first position on lap ten, a position he would keep until the the first cycle of green flag <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pit%20stop">pit stops</ref> around lap 40. Logano's teammate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brad%20Keselowski">Brad Keselowski</ref> took the lead during the pit stop cycle by staying out on the track. Keselowski, low on gasoline, led until a caution came out for a spin by Truex around lap 46. During the caution, Keselowski pitted and returned the lead back to his teammate, who led the race until lap 93. </p>
<p>Two other cautions slowed the race between the first caution and lap 93. The first occurred when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kyle%20Busch">Kyle Busch</ref>'s engine failed around lap 53, forcing the driver to a last-place finish in the race. The other caution was caused by contact between the cars of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris%20Buescher">Chris Buescher</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dale%20Earnhardt%20Jr.">Dale Earnhardt Jr.</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A.%20J.%20Allmendinger">A. J. Allmendinger</ref> ten laps later. Between laps 93 and 103, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kyle%20Larson">Kyle Larson</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ryan%20Newman">Ryan Newman</ref>, Keselowski, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jimmie_Johnson">Jimmie Johnson</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul%20Menard">Paul Menard</ref> led at least one lap. Logano returned to the lead on lap 104, a few laps before a caution when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jeffrey%20Earnhardt">Jeffrey Earnhardt</ref>'s car caught fire. After the caution, Logano remained in first until <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hendrick%20Motorsports">Hendrick Motorsports</ref> driver <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chase%20Elliott">Chase Elliott</ref> passed him on lap 117. </p>
<p>Elliott kept the lead until lap 149, when he was briefly passed by Logano. Elliott retook the lead for three more laps on lap 150 before returning the lead back to Logano, who led until the seventh caution was called around lap 156 for of a collision between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danica%20Patrick">Danica Patrick</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brian%20Scott">Brian Scott</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casey%20Mears">Casey Mears</ref>. Logano held the lead on the ensuing restart and led through two more caution periods that were called in the final 50 laps. The first began around lap 164 because of a collision involving Johnson, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trevor%20Bayne">Trevor Bayne</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ryan%20Blaney">Ryan Blaney</ref>, while the final caution of the race was called with about ten laps remaining after <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denny%20Hamlin">Denny Hamlin</ref> suffered a tire puncture on the front straightaway and collided into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SAFER%20barrier">SAFER barrier</ref>. On the final restart, Logano retained the first position and led the remainder of the race to capture the fifteenth win of his career. </p>
<p>After the race, Logano, who led a race-high of 138 laps, praised his team, saying "Team Penske gave me a great race car. Everyone did a great job figuring out exactly what this car was going to do. This is <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ford%20Motor%20Company">Ford</ref>'s backyard, Roger [<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger%20Penske">Penske</ref>]'s backyard; this is a great win". Elliott, who finished second in the race, expressed disappointment with his result, claiming he "messed up" by not using the correct gear. Larson, Keselowski, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kevin%20Harvick">Kevin Harvick</ref> completed the top-five finishers, while <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl%20Edwards">Carl Edwards</ref> finished in the sixth position. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony%20Stewart">Tony Stewart</ref> finished seventh ahead of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Austin%20Dillon">Austin Dillon</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jamie%20McMurray">Jamie McMurray</ref>, who finished eighth and ninth. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurt%20Busch">Kurt Busch</ref> completed the first ten positions with a tenth-place finish. In post-race inspection, Larson's car did not pass laser inspection, prompting NASCAR to impound his car so it can be further evaluated. Any possible penalties are to be announced in the next week. </p>
<p>In the drivers' championship, Harvick led Kurt Busch and Keselowski with 526 points. Edwards and Logano were fourth and fifth with 472 and 455 points. Elliott was sixth with 453, followed by Johnson with 441. Truex was scored eighth ahead of Kyle Busch and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Matt_Kenseth">Matt Kenseth</ref>, who completed the top-ten. The 2016 season is scheduled to continue on June 26 with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toyota/Save%20Mart%20350">Toyota/Save Mart 350</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonoma%20Raceway">Sonoma Raceway</ref>. </p>
<caption>Unofficial <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2016%20FireKeepers%20Casino%20400">2016 FireKeepers Casino 400</ref> Top-10 Race Results</caption>
Pos
Grid
No.
Driver
Team
Manufacturer
Laps
Led
Pts.
1
122Joey LoganoTeam PenskeFord200
13845
2
1024Chase Elliott <hi rend="bold">(R)</hi>Hendrick Motorsports<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chevrolet">Chevrolet</ref>200
3540
3
742Kyle Larson<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chip%20Ganassi%20Racing">Chip Ganassi Racing</ref>Chevrolet200
139
4
152Brad KeselowskiTeam PenskeFord200
1038
5
294Kevin Harvick<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stewart-Haas%20Racing">Stewart-Haas Racing</ref>Chevrolet200
036
6
1119Carl Edwards<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe%20Gibbs%20Racing">Joe Gibbs Racing</ref><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Toyota">Toyota</ref>200
035
7
314Tony StewartStewart-Haas RacingChevrolet200
034
8
83Austin Dillon<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard%20Childress%20Racing">Richard Childress Racing</ref>Chevrolet200
033
9
141Jamie McMurrayChip Ganassi RacingChevrolet200
032
10
1741Kurt BuschStewart-Haas RacingChevrolet200
031
<hi rend="bold">(R)</hi> – Rookie
</text>
