<text id="autogum_news_doc163" title="U.S. President Trump defends decision to share classified information with Russians" shortTile="us-president-trump" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-05-16" dateModified="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._President_Trump_defends_decision_to_share_classified_information_with_Russians" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>U.S. President Trump defends decision to share classified information with Russians</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 17, 2017</hi></p>
<p>Yesterday morning, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref> defended his disclosure of classified information regarding the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islamic_State_of_Iraq_and_the_Levant">Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant</ref> (ISIL or ISIS) to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russian</ref> foreign minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sergey%20V.%20Lavrov">Sergey V. Lavrov</ref> and ambassador <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sergey%20I.%20Kislyak">Sergey I. Kislyak</ref>, a decision that has drawn a storm of both explanation and criticism from the media and both major U.S. political parties over the past week.</p>
<hi rend="bold">As president, I wanted to share with Russia (at an openly scheduled [White House] meeting) which I have the absolute right to do</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—U.S. President Donald Trump</p>
<p>Trump spoke directly to the public, as is his custom, via <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Twitter</ref>: "As president, I wanted to share with Russia (at an openly scheduled [‍<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/White_House">White House</ref>‍] meeting) which I have the absolute right to do, facts pertaining to terrorism and airline flight safety. Humanitarian reasons, plus I want Russia to greatly step up their fight against Isis and terrorism."</p>
<p>On May 10, President Trump met with Lavrov and Kislyak in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oval%20Office">Oval Office</ref> and, according to reports first from the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington_Post">Washington Post</ref></hi>, told them about an Islamic State plot to sneak explosives onto airplanes by hiding them in laptop computers, which may have placed the anonymous partner who provided it in danger of identification. According to U.S. officials, the information in question was so sensitive that it is not only usually not shared with allies but also extremely restricted even within the U.S. government.</p>
<p>"The Russians have the widest intelligence collection mechanism in the world outside of our own," said <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Sipher">John Sipher</ref>, the former head of the U.S. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Central_Intelligence_Agency">Central Intelligence Agency</ref>'s Russia division. "They can put together a good picture with just a few details[...] They can marry President Trump's comments with their own intelligence, and intelligence from their allies. They can also deploy additional resources to find out details."</p>
<p>While it is not illegal for the sitting U.S. president to share classified information with foreign officials, it may violate the agreement with the person or organization who provided the information in the first place.  There are concerns the Russians may reverse-engineer the process by which the information was gathered and identify the source. Because many of the countries in the Middle East have tribal-level connections to areas controlled by the Islamic State, allowing a source to be identified could place them in political as well as personal danger. An official from one country in Europe told the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Associated_Press">Associated Press</ref></hi> his government might cease to share intelligence with the United States. According to U.S. officials who spoke on condition of anonymity, the information came from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israel</ref>.  None of their Israeli counterparts have seen fit to either confirm or deny this, and Israeli ambassador to the U.S. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron%20Dermer">Ron Dermer</ref> wrote to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_New_York_Times">The New York Times</ref></hi> expressing "full confidence" in the U.S. intelligence process.</p>
<p>Trump's advisors who were present at the meeting were quick to say on Monday, once the disclosure was reported publicly, that Trump did not tell the Russians exactly how the U.S. had come by any information. "At no time — at no time — were intelligence sources or methods discussed, and the president did not disclose any military operations that were not already publicly known," said Trump's National Security Advisor, Lieutenant General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H.R.%20McMaster">H.R. McMaster</ref>, who also told reporters, "I was in the room. It didn't happen." No U.S. newspapers were invited to the meeting.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria%20Zakharova">Maria Zakharova</ref>, a spokesperson for the Russian foreign ministry, said the report of Trump disclosing classified material was "another fake." </p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._Republican_party">Republican</ref> Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Corker">Bob Corker</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tennessee">Tennessee</ref>, noting he was not present at the meeting and did not personally know if President Trump actually compromised the source, said, "To compromise a source is something that you just don't do, and that's why we keep the information that we get from intelligence sources so close as to prevent that from happening."</p>
<p>Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%20Reed%20(politician)">Jack Reed</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rhode_Island">Rhode Island</ref>, who serves on the U.S. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Senate%20Committee%20on%20Armed%20Services">Armed Services Committee</ref>, and fellow <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._Democratic_party">Democrat</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Adam_Schiff">Adam Schiff</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20House%20Intelligence%20Committee">House Intelligence Committee</ref> both raised concerns about Trump's mindfulness.  Reed called it "reckless" and said: "The president of the United States has the power to share classified information with whomever they wish, but the American people expect the president to use that power wisely. I don't believe the president intentionally meant to reveal highly secretive information to the Russians."</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._Republican_party">Republican</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_McCain">John McCain</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Arizona">Arizona</ref> called this "A troubling signal to America's allies and partners around the world and may impair their willingness to share intelligence with us in the future."</p>
<p>Trump's meeting with the Russian ministers took place one day after he fired <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Federal_Bureau_of_Investigation">Federal Bureau of Investigation</ref> director <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/James_Comey">James Comey</ref>, who had been running an investigation into alleged <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russian_involvement_in_the_2016_US_presidential_election">Russian involvement</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2016_U.S._presidential_election">2016 U.S. presidential election</ref>, which raised concerns about obstruction of justice.</p>
</text>
