<text id="autogum_news_doc428" title="Feared toll of Indonesian floods, landslides up to 130; dozens missing as bridge swept away" shortTile="feared-toll-indonesian" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-12-27" dateModified="2014-12-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Feared_toll_of_Indonesian_floods%2C_landslides_up_to_130%3B_dozens_missing_as_bridge_swept_away" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Feared toll of Indonesian floods, landslides up to 130; dozens missing as bridge swept away</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 27, 2007</hi></p>
<p>Heavy rains in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Indonesia">Indonesia</ref> yesterday triggered widespread flooding and landslides across the nation. It has emerged that last night a bridge was swept away by the swollen river it stretched across, leaving around 40 to 50 people missing in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madiun">Madiun</ref>, East <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Java">Java</ref>. Meanwhile, the total toll of those known or feared to be dead has reached 130.</p>
<p>According to local police chief Supardi in a telephone conversation with <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xinhua">Xinhua</ref></hi> the flood waters weakened a foundation, resulting in the collapse. At least twenty motorcyclists, car drivers and passengers are thought to be dead, but as of midnight, no bodies had been recovered. However, three bikes have been retrieved. 100 rescuers have been dispatched to the scene. Continuing heavy rain forced the search to be abandoned temporarily. </p>
<p>Java as a whole is the worst affected island; in addition to the bridge collapse most of the landslides occurred in two Central Java districts. Health ministry official Rustam Pakaya told reporters that at least 28,000 people have been forced to abandon their homes in central Java, although exact figures are not yet available. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red%20Cross">Red Cross</ref> commented that 45,000 East Javanese people have been similarly displaced. Thousands are seeking shelter in mosques and other public buildings.</p>
<p>Landslides buried houses and made roads impassable, while hundreds police officers, military personnel, local officials and volunteers have been digging with farm tools and even their hands to search for survivors. Heavy machinery is available but the road conditions have prevented it arriving at the areas where it is required. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jakarta">Jakarta</ref> has dispatched aid in the form of five tonnes of biscuits and instant meals, ten tonnes of baby food and multiple boats.</p>
<p>Heru Aji Pratomo, head of the disaster management centre in the worst-hit district of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karanganyar">Karanganyar</ref> has confirmed the recovery of twelve more bodies. This brings the total confirmed death toll in the area to 48. He said that most bodies were recovered from three metre deep mud and required heavy digging machinery to retrieve. 28 remain missing.</p>
<p>Local resident Siswo told AFP "Suddenly I felt my house shaking, and I thought it was an earthquake. When I got outside, I saw that the houses next to mine were already covered by earth," and that it struck twelve neighbouring houses.</p>
<p>In the next district, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wonogiri">Wonogiri</ref>, disaster management centre head Sri Mubadi told reporters they had retrieved two more bodies, reaching a total of six, with eleven more missing. He also confirmed that they currently have no access to heavy equipment.</p>
<p>In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tawangmangu">Tawangmangu</ref> about 1,000 rescuers were also searching for bodies and survivors without the aid of heavy machinery. Three more bodies were retrieved today.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islam">Islamic</ref> cleric <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abu%20Bakar%20Bashir">Abu Bakar Bashir</ref> toured a Karanganyar village, at which time he commented that he felt the disaster had been caused as a form of divine revenge, saying "This was likely caused by immoral acts going on here," and "This could be a lesson to be learned." The 69-year-old served two years after being linked to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2002%20Bali%20bombings">2002 Bali bombings</ref>, before having his conviction overturned last year.</p>
<p>Chalid Muhammad, director of Walhi, an Indonesian environmental group, had a different opinion. "For five consecutive years landslides and floods have occurred in Java, claiming many lives. The main trigger is ecological destruction caused by deforestation, forest conversions and chaotic spatial planning," Chalid told <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reuters">Reuters</ref>.</p>
<p>"There have been no adequate efforts by the government to protect the people from disasters. When the landslides happened officials were on holiday and there was no access of heavy equipment to the affected areas."</p>
</text>
