<text id="autogum_news_doc484" title="Irish rock band The Cranberries&apos; lead singer Dolores O&apos;Riordan dies at 46" shortTile="irish-rock-band-cranberries" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-01-17" dateModified="2018-07-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Irish_rock_band_The_Cranberries%27_lead_singer_Dolores_O%27Riordan_dies_at_46" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Irish rock band The Cranberries' lead singer Dolores O'Riordan dies at 46</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 18, 2018</hi></p>
<p>On Monday, 46-year-old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dolores%20O'Riordan">Dolores O'Riordan</ref>, lead singer of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ireland">Irish</ref> rock band <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Cranberries">The Cranberries</ref>, was found dead, her publicist Lindsey Holmes confirmed; reports suggested she was found in her room at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London%20Hilton%20on%20Park%20Lane">London Hilton on Park Lane</ref> hotel. O'Riordan's agent said she was in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref>, for a recording session. According to the police, her death was considered "unexplained" and no cause of death disclosed, though it was to be investigated. </p>
<figure><caption>File photo of Dolores O'Riordan Image: Eva Rinaldi. (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:The_Cranberries_(7003086657).jpg">Reuseterms</ref>.)</caption></figure>
<p>Later one of the richest women of Ireland, O'Riordan joined the rock band, then known as "the Cranberry Saw Us", as a teenager around 1989, after Niall Quinn had left the band. Also featuring <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/drummer">drummer</ref> Fergal Lawler, <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/bassist">bassist</ref> Mike Hogan and his brother <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noel%20Hogan">Noel Hogan</ref>, the lead <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/guitarist">guitarist</ref>, the band released their first album <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Everybody%20Else%20Is%20Doing%20It,%20So%20Why%20Can't%20We%3F">Everybody Else Is Doing It, So Why Can't We?</ref></hi> in 1993. The debut album featuring single <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linger%20(song)">Linger</ref></hi> was an international success. The band went on to release six more albums  featuring O'Riordan's voice, including <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Something%20Else">Something Else</ref></hi>, which was released last year.</p>
<p>A year later, in 1994, the band released their second studio album, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No%20Need%20to%20Argue">No Need to Argue</ref></hi>, which featured the song <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zombie%20(song)">Zombie</ref></hi>,  a song about bombings related to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Northern_Ireland">Northern Ireland</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Zombie</hi> topped the singles charts in various countries. In the same year, O'Riordan married Don Burton, sometime manager of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duran%20Duran">Duran Duran</ref> band. Their third album, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/To%20the%20Faithful%20Departed">To the Faithful Departed</ref></hi>, was released in 1996. The album did not receive the acclamation of the first two.</p>
<p>In 2003, the band split, and it was reunited in 2009. During those six years, O'Riordan released two solo albums — <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Are%20You%20Listening%3F%20(Dolores%20O'Riordan%20album)">Are You Listening?</ref></hi> in 2007 and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No%20Baggage">No Baggage</ref></hi> in 2009. 2012's <hi rend="italic">Roses</hi> was the first album The Cranberries released after reunification.</p>
<p>Last year, O'Riordan revealed through London's <hi rend="italic">Metro</hi> newspaper she had been diagnosed with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bipolar_disorder">bipolar disorder</ref>. She also spoke of suffering from depression to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Irish%20News">The Irish News</ref></hi>. In 2014, the singer was involved in assaulting a flight attendant and three police officials on a flight from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> to Ireland. She was fined <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/€">€</ref>6000 (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US$">US$</ref>6600) after she pleaded guilty; medical reports said she suffered from mental illness during that incident. Last year, the band's tour to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_America">North America</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Europe">Europe</ref> for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Something%20Else">Something Else</ref></hi> was cancelled partway through as O'Riordan suffered from a back problem.</p>
<p>After announcement of O'Riordan's death, Irish prime minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Leo_Varadkar">Leo Varadkar</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">tweeted</ref>, "For anyone who grew up in Ireland in the 1990s, Dolores O'Riordan was the voice of a generation. As the female lead singer of a hugely successful rock band, she blazed a trail and might just have been <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Limerick">Limerick</ref>'s greatest ever rock star. RIP."</p>
<p>The official twitter handle of The Cranberries posted a tweet saying, "We are devastated on the passing of our friend Dolores. She was an extraordinary talent and we feel very privileged to have been part of her life from 1989 when we started the Cranberries. The world has lost a true artist today."</p>
<p>Born on September 6, 1971 in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ballybricken">Ballybricken</ref>, a town in southeastern Ireland, O'Riordan had six older siblings. She wrote songs since the age of twelve. James Walton, a priest from her home area, said, "The plan is for her to be buried here at home. When that will be will depend on when her body is released."</p>
<p>Dolores O'Riordan is survived by three children and ex-husband Don Burton.</p>
</text>
