<text id="autogum_news_doc738" title="Expected U.S. Senate special election taking shape in Massachusetts" shortTile="expected-us-senate" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-29" dateModified="2017-09-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Expected_U.S._Senate_special_election_taking_shape_in_Massachusetts" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Expected U.S. Senate special election taking shape in Massachusetts</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 31, 2012</hi></p>
<p>With <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democratic</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Senate">Senator</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Kerry">John Kerry</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Massachusetts">Massachusetts</ref>'s nomination and likely approval as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States">President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>'s choice to replace the retiring <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Secretary%20of%20State">Secretary of State</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hillary_Clinton">Hillary Clinton</ref>, Kerry's Senate seat is expected soon to be vacated, making necessary a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/special%20election">special election</ref> to choose a new Senator. That potential race is now taking shape with two candidates having emerged as the frontrunners for their respective parties' nominations: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(US)">Republican</ref> Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott%20Brown">Scott Brown</ref> and Democratic <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_House_of_Representatives">Representative</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ed_Markey">Ed Markey</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>Republican Senator Scott BrownImage: United States Congress.</caption></figure>
<p>Massachusetts law adopted in 2004 requires a vacated seat to be filled permanently through special election held 145 to 160 days following vacation. This law was passed purportedly to prevent then-Governor <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</ref>, a Republican, from naming a replacement for Kerry, who was at the time, the Democratic presidential nominee.  No such election occurred until long-time Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ted%20Kennedy">Ted Kennedy</ref> died in office, vacating his seat in 2009. At the time, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor%20of%20Massachusetts">Massachusetts governor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deval%20Patrick">Deval Patrick</ref> named Democrat <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul%20G.%20Kirk">Paul G. Kirk</ref> as a temporary replacement. Kirk chose not to run for the seat, and instead the Democrats nominated Massachusetts Attorney General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martha%20Coakley">Martha Coakley</ref>, who lost to Brown. Now, Patrick reportedly wishes to again name a temporary replacement who will not run in the special election. Candidates for this position include: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victoria%20Reggie%20Kennedy">Victoria Reggie Kennedy</ref>, the widow of Ted Kennedy; former governor and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20presidential%20election,%201988">1988 Democratic presidential nominee</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Dukakis">Michael Dukakis</ref>; and the retiring Congressman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barney%20Frank">Barney Frank</ref>.</p>
<p>Amid the Senate's consideration of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Affordable%20Health%20Care%20for%20America%20Act">Affordable Health Care for America Act</ref>, Brown's 2010 election broke the Democrats' filibuster-proof super-majority in the chamber.  As the first Massachusetts Republican elected since <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward%20Brooke">Edward Brooke</ref> in 1972, Brown gained a reputation in the Senate as a political moderate, stressing bipartisanship. However, in the most expensive Senate race in the nation's history in 2012, he lost the seat to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liberalism%20in%20the%20United%20States">liberal</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvard%20Law%20school">Harvard Law</ref> professor <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Elizabeth_Warren">Elizabeth Warren</ref>, who tied him to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conservatism%20in%20the%20United%20States">conservative</ref> Senate Republicans. After the defeat, Republican Senators <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dan%20Coats">Dan Coats</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Indiana">Indiana</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_McCain">John McCain</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Arizona">Arizona</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olympia%20Snowe">Olympia Snowe</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Maine">Maine</ref> each asked Brown to run for Senate again. He alluded to a potential return during his farewell address earlier in December, noting, "As I’ve said many times before, victory and defeat is temporary ... Depending on what happens, and where we go, all of us, we may obviously meet again." Though former Governor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20Weld">William Weld</ref> is also considered a potential Republican primary candidate, Brown leads him in opinion polls by a wide margin.  Additionally, a December 17–18 poll conducted by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WBUR">WBUR</ref> shows Brown with a 58 percent favorability rate in his state and ahead of potential Democratic nominees Markey, former Congressman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marty%20Meehan">Marty Meehan</ref>, and Congressmen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike%20Capuano">Mike Capuano</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen%20Lynch%20(politician)">Stephen Lynch</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>Democratic Representative Ed MarkeyImage: United States Congress.</caption></figure>
<p>Patrick, Kennedy, Coakley, and Meehan have all denied interest in the seat as have other Democrats speculated to jump in including actor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ben%20Affleck">Ben Affleck</ref> and attorney <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward%20M.%20Kennedy,%20Jr.">Edward M. Kennedy, Jr.</ref>, Ted Kennedy's son. Though Lynch and Capuano have expressed interest in the seat, Markey is thus far the only announced candidate. In a statement to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Boston%20Globe">The Boston Globe</ref></hi>, Markey affirmed "this fight is too important" not to run and "there is so much at stake" in the election.  He added that an official announcement would come in January. Markey, who has served in Congress since 1976, previously ran for the Senate seat in 1984 but withdrew before the primary; Kerry went on to win the primary and seat that year. Markey intends to focus his campaign on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Global_warming">global warming</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gun_control">gun control</ref>, protection of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social%20Security">Social Security</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medicare">Medicare</ref>, and government spending for jobs. He has secured endorsements from both Kerry and Victoria Kennedy, and with a war chest of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">$</ref>3.1 million from his congressional campaigns, has significantly more funds than any of his potential primary opponents. According to political scientist Peter Ubertaccio of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stonehill%20College">Stonehill College</ref>, that may discourage prominent Democrats thinking about entering the race. Nevertheless, State Senator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benjamin%20Downing">Benjamin Downing</ref> has announced he is exploring a potential bid.</p>
<p>Though Markey has more money than Brown's $464,000 left from his 2012 campaign, Ubertaccio, in his analysis of the race, notes Brown has more recent campaign experience than Markey, who has not had a competitive campaign lately. Moreover, he finds Markey "very much a creature of Washington, which can be problematic in a tough statewide race." He sees the rush to support Markey as unusual, and as a way to discourage Democratic challengers to Markey. Jon Keller of Boston's <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CBS">CBS</ref> affiliate notes the rush was likely to allow Markey to begin attacks on Brown rather than Democrats, but he concludes the lack of choice for Democrats may give Brown an advantage as an outsider running against the insiders' hand-picked successor.</p>
</text>
