<text id="autogum_news_doc667" title="&apos;42-year detour&apos; ends: Garrison Keillor homeward bound" shortTile="year-detour-ends" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-06-27" dateModified="2019-08-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/%2742-year_detour%27_ends%3A_Garrison_Keillor_homeward_bound" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>'42-year detour' ends: Garrison Keillor homeward bound</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 2, 2016</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garrison%20Keillor">Garrison Keillor</ref>, the humorist and longtime host of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A%20Prairie%20Home%20Companion">A Prairie Home Companion</ref></hi> on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> public radio network <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NPR">NPR</ref>, hung up his microphone this week. The final episode of <hi rend="italic">Companion</hi> to be hosted by Keillor was recorded yesterday at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hollywood%20Bowl">Hollywood Bowl</ref> with 18,000 people in attendance. It was broadcast today.</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garrison%20Keillor">Garrison Keillor</ref>. Image: Andrew Harrer / Bloomberg News / Landov.</caption></figure>
<p>Musician <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris%20Thile">Chris Thile</ref> takes over as host in October. Thile is expected to keep the program's basic format intact while updating its content.</p>
<p>Keillor, 73, created <hi rend="italic">A Prairie Home Companion</hi> in 1974, and it turned into a "42-year detour". He had gone to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nashville,%20Tennessee">Nashville</ref>, he said, "to write about the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand%20Ole%20Opry">Grand Ole Opry</ref> for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20New%20Yorker">The New Yorker</ref></hi>." Keillor found Nashville "so unbuttoned. All of these wonderful performers — <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porter%20Wagoner">Porter Wagoner</ref> was there, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minnie%20Pearl">Minnie Pearl</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roy%20Acuff">Roy Acuff</ref>. They were all children of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great%20Depression">Depression</ref>, and they felt so lucky to have whatever they had. And it was really a happy place. So I got seduced by that into trying to start my own show."</p>
<p>On Friday, Keillor said he kept going for the friendship. "[I]t was to get to meet people if you had no social skills. And people would walk up to you and say, 'I heard you on the radio.' This was the beginning of a conversation that would lead in all sorts of interesting directions." The final episode changed direction very little; Keillor added duets with five of his favorite singers, then closed the show with a medley he performed alone.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Companion</hi> highlighted the sensibilities of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Midwestern%20United%20States">Midwest</ref> of Keillor's youth. His on-air persona was a throwback; a "radio bard" telling amusing stories spun from the fictional town of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lake%20Wobegon">Lake Wobegon</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Minnesota">Minnesota</ref>. Now, he says, that version of the Midwest "is receding in the rear-view mirror at high speed."</p>
<p>Garrison Keillor was one of six children raised in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fundamentalism">fundamentalist</ref> family in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anoka,%20Minnesota">Anoka, Minnesota</ref>. Television was forbidden in the home, but their large <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zenith">Zenith</ref> radio allowed him to listen to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/rhythm%20and%20blues">rhythm and blues</ref> music and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serial%20(radio%20and%20television)">serials</ref> like <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lassie#Radio">Lassie</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>Keillor began writing after deciding he wanted to play <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/American_football">football</ref>, only to learn that he had a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/mitral%20valve%20prolapse">heart defect</ref>. "So instead of playing football, I wrote about football. No better thing for a kid, than to write about actual things that are happening before your eyes. [...] I was very, very lucky." His broadcasting career started after a speech coach suggested he could overcome his fear of performing in front of other people by taking off his glasses. "And when you learn that you don't have to be afraid of people you can't see, you've taken a step towards broadcasting, you see?"</p>
<p>42 years later, Keillor says he plans to resume writing. A memoir and a screenplay are in the works.</p>
</text>
