<text id="autogum_news_doc795" title="New denunciations of political corruption create severe political crisis in Brazil" shortTile="new-denunciations" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-06-06" dateModified="2019-07-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_denunciations_of_political_corruption_create_severe_political_crisis_in_Brazil" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>New denunciations of political corruption create severe political crisis in Brazil</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 6, 2005</hi></p><p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref> —
The Brazilian Deputy <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roberto%20Jefferson">Roberto Jefferson</ref> told the Brazilian newspaper <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Folha%20de%20São%20Paulo">Folha de São Paulo</ref> that the ruling <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Workers'%20Party">Workers' Party</ref> (PT) has paid Brazilian deputies 30 thousand Brazilian Reals (US 12 thousand) each, every month. Deputy Jefferson is the President of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brazilian%20Labour%20Party">Brazilian Labour Party</ref> (PTB) and he is accused of directing a corrupt scheme that involves the Brazilian postal service. The PTB is an ally of the government.</p>
<p>Jefferson's allegations increase the severe  political crisis regarding the government of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luiz%20Inácio%20Lula%20da%20Silva">Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva</ref>.  Lula has convened a special meeting to discuss the crisis in the government. Because of the recent scandal Brazilian stock markets went down and the U.S. Dollar increased its value in relation to the Brazilian Real.</p>
<p>The Brazilian Senate and the Chamber of Deputies are discussing the installation of a special congressional commission to investigate the allegations. The first attempt of the Brazilian government to prevent the creation of the Congress' special commission (convincing some deputies not to endorse the commission's creation) has failed.  Now the government is trying to stop the creation of the commission in the Senate and is lobbying against it in the Congress, trying to influence both senators and deputies.</p>
<p>The opposition party, PSDB, criticized recently the efforts of the Brazilian government to stop the special commission of investigation, using the influence of the Minister of the Economy Antonio Palocci.</p>
<p>The Workers’ Party published in its webpage a note denying Jefferson’s allegations and saying that it supports investigations by Brazilian authorities. The Brazilian Minister Waldir Pires has said in an interview with Agencia Brasil that the denunciations of corruption are appearing more because the government is fighting against them. He also blamed previous governments by the corruption.</p>
<p>In a note in the Workers’ Party website, the party accuses the former-President Fernando Henrique Cardoso government of corruption.</p>
<p>On April 2005, the Mayor of Rio de Janeiro, Cesar Maia, denounced the Workers’ Party payment to deputies.</p>
<p>The allegations of Jefferson marks the beginnings of a severe crisis in Brazilian government. This is the most severe crisis since the impeachment of the former President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fernando%20Collor%20de%20Mello">Fernando Collor de Mello</ref> in 1992.</p>
<p>Politicians from the opposition said that they don't want the impeachment of Lula, however they demand the investigation of all denunciations and that the guilty be punished.</p>
<head id="Audio">Audio</head>
<p>Some excerpts of the interview of Roberto Jefferson:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item> "<ref target="http://www1.folha.uol.com.br/folha/multimidia/audio/20050606-entrevista_com_roberto_jefferson.wma">Contei a Lula do "mensalão", diz deputado</ref>" —<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Folha%20de%20São%20Paulo">Folha de São Paulo</ref></hi>, June 6, 2005 (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portuguese%20language">Portuguese</ref>)</item></list>
 The text of this article has been released into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/public%20domain">public domain</ref>. In the event that this is not legally possible, this article may be used for any purpose, without any condition, unless such conditions are required by law. This applies worldwide. Copyright terms on images, however, may vary, so please check individual image pages prior to duplication.
Please note that this only applies to Wikinews content created prior to September 25, 2005.  All content created after that date is released under a Creative Commons license which is mentioned at the bottom of each article. This is currently the Creative Commons Attribution 2.5 License.
</text>
