<text id="autogum_news_doc721" title="Wheelchair Rugby Tri-Nations Series begins in Sydney" shortTile="wheelchair-rugby" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-09-18" dateModified="2014-03-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wheelchair_Rugby_Tri-Nations_Series_begins_in_Sydney" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wheelchair Rugby Tri-Nations Series begins in Sydney</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 20, 2013</hi></p>
<p>Cathedral Square, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sydney">Sydney</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref> —
<hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> attended the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wheelchair_rugby">Wheelchair Rugby</ref> Tri-Nations Series in Cathedral Square, Sydney, ongoing from Wednesday. This is the first time an international wheelchair rugby event has been held outdoors, and in this arena. Three nations are competing: the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>, Australia, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Zealand">New Zealand</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>America's Josh Wheeler Image: Jeff Crow <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australian_Paralympic_Committee">Australian Paralympic Committee</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Left to right: Chuck Aoki (US), Andrew Harrison (Aus), Cameron Carr (Aus), Jeremy Brown (US), Ryan Scott (Aus), Derrick Helton (US) Image: Jeff Crow <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australian_Paralympic_Committee">Australian Paralympic Committee</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Wheelchair Rugby in Cathedral Square, Sydney. Hyde Park and the Centrepoint Tower can be seen in the background.  Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Hawkeye7">Hawkeye7</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>United States National Wheelchair Rugby team Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Hawkeye7">Hawkeye7</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Justice Crew performs Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Hawkeye7">Hawkeye7</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Premier of New South Wales <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barry%20O'Farrell">Barry O'Farrell</ref> and CEO of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australian_Paralympic_Committee">Australian Paralympic Committee</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jason%20Hellwig">Jason Hellwig</ref> Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:Hawkeye7">Hawkeye7</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The venue is Cathedral Square, Sydney, which is adjacent to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyde%20Park,%20Sydney">Hyde Park</ref>. The Sydney Central Business district is on the other side of the park. An outdoor stadium has been constructed specifically for the tournament, which is believed to be the first time an international wheelchair rugby tournament has been held outdoors. This choice was validated by the fine and warm weather. Free sunscreen was given to the crowd.</p>
<p>The Opening Ceremony was officiated by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australian_Paralympic_Committee">Australian Paralympic Committee</ref> Chief Executive Officer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jason%20Hellwig">Jason Hellwig</ref>. In attendance were the Premier of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_South_Wales">New South Wales</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barry%20O'Farrell">Barry O'Farrell</ref>, the Deputy Lord Mayor of Sydney, Robyn Kemmis, and Paralympic swimmer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew%20Cowdrey">Matthew Cowdrey</ref>. A large crowd, mostly consisting of school groups, was entertained by boy band <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justice%20Crew">Justice Crew</ref> singing their hit <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Best%20Night">Best Night</ref></hi>. </p>
<p>Each team is to play the others two twice, on Wednesday September 18 and Thursday September 19. Finals are to be held on Friday.
All three teams are highly ranked internationally. The United States team is ranked number one in the world. It won bronze at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2004%20Summer%20Paralympics">2004 Summer Paralympics</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Athens">Athens</ref>, gold at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2008_Summer_Paralympics">2008 Summer Paralympics</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Beijing">Beijing</ref>, and bronze at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2012_Summer_Paralympics">2012 Summer Paralympics</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, and is the current world champion. This is its first visit to Australia since the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2000%20Summer%20Paralympics">2000 Summer Paralympics</ref>. </p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australia%20national%20wheelchair%20rugby%20team">Australian team</ref>, known as the Steelers, is ranked second in the world. It  won silver in Beijing and gold in London. The team is almost unchanged from the one that won in London. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greg%20Smith%20(Paralympian)">Greg Smith</ref> has become the assistant coach.</p>
<p>The first game, held immediately after the Opening Ceremony, was between the United States and Australia. The United States proved the better team, forcing errors and turnovers. Three turnovers in the first quarter were especially costly for the Steelers, who lost 56–43.</p>
<p>The second game was held at 17:30 under lights. The crowd was small, but there were a number of New Zealand fans in the crowd, including a few <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maori">Maori</ref>. Two of the New Zealand players are also Maori. The well-disciplined United States team proved too good for the Wheel Blacks as well, who lost 58–40 in an entertaining contest.</p>
<p>The third game was at 19:30, between Australia and New Zealand. The Australians led the whole game, which was nonetheless entertaining to the last. In the dying seconds of the game, Australia's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ryley%20Batt">Ryley Batt</ref> shunted a stalling New Zealand player across the line to force him to score, then threw the ball to team mate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris%20Bond%20(wheelchair%20rugby)">Chris Bond</ref>, who raced for the line at high speed but was beaten by the buzzer. Australia won 61–48.</p>
<p>The New Zealand team, known as the Wheel Blacks, is ranked tenth in the world. It won gold in Athens.</p>
<p>Highlights of the tournament are scheduled to be shown on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foxtel">Foxtel</ref> Sports  in Australia on September 28 and 29. </p>
</text>
