<text id="autogum_news_doc630" title="United States: Dr. Larry Nassar sentenced in sexual abuse case" shortTile="united-states-dr" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-01-24" dateModified="2018-02-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States%3A_Dr._Larry_Nassar_sentenced_in_sexual_abuse_case" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>United States: Dr. Larry Nassar sentenced in sexual abuse case</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 27, 2018</hi></p>
<p>Former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/USA%20Gymnastics">USA Gymnastics</ref> team doctor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larry%20Nassar">Larry Nassar</ref> was sentenced to prison on Wednesday for 40 to 175 years in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ingham%20County,%20Michigan">Ingham County</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Michigan">Michigan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>. Nassar pleaded guilty in November to seven charges of sexual assault in Ingham County, however, he is alleged to have victimized over a hundred girls over several years. Nassar is currently serving a 60-year sentence for federal <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Child_pornography">child pornography</ref> charges. </p>
<p>Judge <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rosemarie%20Aquilina">Rosemarie Aquilina</ref>, presiding over the Ingham County Circuit Court in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lansing,%20Michigan">Lansing</ref>, Michigan, handed down the sentence, stating: "I've just signed your death warrant." </p>
<figure><caption>Former US President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> with members of the 2012 Olympic gymnastics team.Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/White_House">White House</ref>. (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Barack_Obama_with_members_of_the_2012_U.S._Olympic_gymnastics_teams.jpg">Reuseterms</ref>.)</caption></figure>
<p>Rachael Denhollander first accused Nassar, filing a criminal complaint in 2016. Nassar was charged in Ingham County with seven counts of sexual abuse and pleaded guilty in November of 2017. The true number of victims is alleged to exceed one hundred. During the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Criminal%20sentencing%20in%20the%20United%20States">sentencing hearings</ref> in court over 150 women testified Nassar abused them. Alleged victims include famous Olympic gymnasts, such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simone%20Biles">Simone Biles</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aly%20Raisman">Aly Raisman</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabby%20Douglas">Gabby Douglas</ref>, although Nassar was not specifically charged with abusing them.</p>
<p>Judge Aquilina read out parts of a statement Nassar submitted to the court. In the statement, Nassar wrote, "I was a good doctor, because my treatments worked and those patients that are now speaking out are the same ones that kept coming back over and over". He also criticized an earlier judge for going "ballistic". Aquilina declined to read the entirety, citing concern for the victims; "I don't want them re-victimized by the words in the letter", she said.</p>
<p>Nassar served as the team physician for USA Gymnastics for years, spanning four <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Olympic_Games">Olympic Games</ref>. Simultaneously, he served with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michigan%20State%20University">Michigan State University</ref>. He abused his victims under pretense of treating them as a doctor.</p>
<p>Nassar's case has led to allegations of lack of oversight by Michigan State University, USA Gymnastics, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Olympic%20Committee">United States Olympic Committee</ref> (USOC). At USA Gymnastics, prior to the sentencing three board members resigned over the case on Monday, as well as its president last year. Corporate sponsors of the organization also pulled out.</p>
<p>The current president of USA Gymnastics, Kerry Perry, who was appointed in December, released a statement after the sentencing: "During the last seven days, more than 150 courageous women have shared their deeply personal experiences and how Larry Nassar’s despicable crimes impacted their lives. [...] USA Gymnastics applauds Judge Rosemarie Aquilina for handing Nassar the maximum sentence of up to 175 years[...] As stated on my first day on Dec. 1, 2017, I will not waver on my commitment to focus each and every day on our organization’s highest priority — the safety, health and well-being of our athletes."</p>
<p>USOC head Scott Blackmun also released a statement in which he apologized: "The purpose of this message is to tell all of Nassar’s victims and survivors, directly, how incredibly sorry we are. We have said it in other contexts, but we have not been direct enough with you. We are sorry for the pain caused by this terrible man, and sorry that you weren’t afforded a safe opportunity to pursue your sports dreams. The Olympic family is among those that have failed you."</p>
<p>Both <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Reuters">Reuters</ref> and the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Los_Angeles_Times">Los Angeles Times</ref></hi> noted applause in the courtroom when Nassar was escorted out. Judge Aquilina said, "There has to be a massive investigation as to why there was inaction, why there was silence."</p>
</text>
