<text id="autogum_news_doc222" title="Latest &apos;CableGate&apos; disclosures hint at US diplomatic tactics in Spain and beyond" shortTile="latest-cablegate" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-11-30" dateModified="2016-03-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Latest_%27CableGate%27_disclosures_hint_at_US_diplomatic_tactics_in_Spain_and_beyond" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Latest 'CableGate' disclosures hint at US diplomatic tactics in Spain and beyond</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 1, 2010</hi></p>
<figure><caption>The logo of whistleblowing website, <hi rend="italic">Wikileaks</hi></caption></figure>
<p>Yesterday's release of more <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> diplomatic cables by <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikileaks">Wikileaks</ref></hi> covered pressure on governments, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>'s judiciary, and buying foreign assistance with detentions at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Guantanamo_Bay">Guantanamo Bay</ref>. <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El%20Pais">El Pais</ref></hi>, one of five mainstream papers partnering with Wikileaks' release of documents, examined key output from Madrid's US embassy.</p>
<p>The latest cables focus on US–Spain relations, particularly during the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref> presidency, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eduardo%20Aguirre">Eduardo Aguirre</ref> serving as ambassador in Madrid. He is cited as having "personally exerted" pressure on Spain's government and judiciary; this leading to at least three investigations being dropped.</p>
<p>Of concern to the press is the death of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/José%20Couso">José Couso</ref> in 2003. The Spanish cameraman was killed during the battle for Baghdad; the Spanish judiciary intended to prosecute three US servicemen over the fatality.</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of Eduardo Aguirre Jr, United States ambassador to Spain.</caption></figure>
<p>American use of Spanish air bases for '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/extraordinary%20rendition">extraordinary rendition</ref>' was a second concern the US embassy in Madrid pressured the government on. Spanish prosecutors had been keen to pursue 13 CIA officers over the illegal flights.</p>
<p>Repeatedly, concern over Spain's independent judiciary invoking 'universal jurisdiction' appears in leaked cables. Reports at the time showed magistrates considered actions at Guantanamo Bay torture, and seemed keen to pursue ex-US government officials on grounds of "criminal responsibility".</p>
<p>Cable 06MADRID1914 highlights the cases of Hamed Abderrahaman Ahmed and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Morocco">Moroccan</ref> Lahcen Ikassrien; respectively transferred from Guantanamo Bay, to Spanish custody, in February 2004 and July 2005.</p>
<p>Describing conditions at the Cuban detention centre as "impossible to explain, much less justify", Hamed — better known as the "Spanish Taliban" — saw a July 2006 ruling by the country's Supreme Court annul his six-year prison sentence, granting him an immediate release. The ruling cast doubt on the reliability of evidence against Lahcen, who was released on bail.</p>
<p>Hamed and his family, at the time, announced their intent to sue the US government over his suffering in Guantanamo Bay.</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of Baltazar Garzón, former Spanish High Court judge.</caption></figure>
<p>Later cables illustrate how concerned the Bush administration were over possible prosecution by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baltasar%20Garzón">Baltasar Garzón</ref>. Citing an op-ed he penned for a Spanish paper in March 2007, and this subsequently being picked up by Socialist Party secretary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/José%20Blanco%20Lopéz">José Blanco Lopéz</ref>. Pronouncements by the two, and others, on "criminal responsibility" were met with a diplomatically stern response; cable 07MADRID546 states that the government of Spain was "cautioned that continued statements on this issue by senior Spanish figures would be viewed negatively."</p>
<p>Garzón, best-known for indicting former dictator <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusto_Pinochet">Augusto Pinochet</ref>, seemed to still trouble US diplomats when planning high-level defence talks in March 2007. Mention is made to a possible investigation, and indictment of, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Rumsfeld">Donald Rumsfeld</ref>. Spain had informed the US embassy in Madrid the judge in the case was working to dismiss it.</p>
<p>As recently as March last year, Garzón sought to prosecute officials from the Bush administration.</p>
<hi rend="bold">[...]continued statements on this issue by senior Spanish figures would be viewed negatively.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—US embassy 'caution' to Spanish government.</p>
<p>Named as potential defendants in a <hi rend="italic">Reuters</hi> report, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Ashcroft">John Ashcroft</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_Yoo">John Yoo</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20J.%20Haynes,%20II">William Haynes II</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jay%20Bybee">Jay Bybee</ref>, and, aide to Vice-President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dick_Cheney">Dick Cheney</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Addington">David Addington</ref> were all being investigated by Garzón.</p>
<p>Come April this year, Garzón himself faced prosecution. A probe into Franco-era war crimes saw him suspended, possibly to be tried for acting contrary to an amnesty extended to Franco supporters. It is alleged he "acted without jurisdiction".</p>
<p>At present, the former Spanish Supreme Court judge is working at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Criminal_Court">International Criminal Court</ref>. Reports based on <hi rend="italic">El Pais'</hi> investigation around the leaked cables suggest the country's judiciary has been politicised to suit American interests.</p>
<p>With a price of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>85,000 cited for each former Guantanamo Bay detainee that Spain was to take, recent reports assert other countries have been offered financial incentives to help empty the camp.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Belgium">Belgium</ref>, alongside Spain, was supposedly offered more influence within the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Union">European Union</ref> in exchange for cooperating with US plans.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kuwait">Kuwait</ref>'s interior minister is said to have refused to take any of their citizens from the camp. Describing inmates as "rotten", <hi rend="italic">DPA</hi> alleges he told the US to "get rid of" detainees in an Afghan war zone.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Yemen">Yemen</ref>, in exchange for agreeing to take Guantanamo detainees, is said to have asked for US$11 million for the construction of a centre to rehabilitate Muslim extremists.</p>
<p>So far, only a tiny fraction of the documents in Wikileaks possession have been made public.</p>
</text>
