<text id="autogum_news_doc789" title="Brazilian Vote Buying parliamentary commission present first joint preliminary report" shortTile="brazilian-vote-buying" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-09-04" dateModified="2010-10-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brazilian_Vote_Buying_parliamentary_commission_present_first_joint_preliminary_report" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Brazilian Vote Buying parliamentary commission present first joint preliminary report</head>
<figure rend="Cpis122514.jpeg"></figure>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 5, 2005</hi><p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref> —
The Post Office and Vote Buying  parliamentary commissions of investigation  unanimously approved on Thursday (1) their first  joint preliminary    report of   activities. The text was prepared by their redactors, Osmar Serraglio (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki//Party%20of%20the%20Brazilian%20Democratic%20Movement">PMDB</ref>) and Ibrahim Abi-Ackel (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressive%20Party%20(Brazil)">PP</ref>), from Post Office and Vote Buying commissions respectively.</p>
<p>The deputies cited in the report are: Carlos Rodrigues (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liberal%20Party%20(Brazil)">PL</ref>-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rio%20de%20Janeiro%20(state)">RJ</ref>), José Janene (PP-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paraná">PR</ref>), Pedro Correia (PP-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pernambuco">PE</ref>), Pedro Henry (PP-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mato%20Grosso%20do%20Sul">MS</ref>), Sandro Mabel (PL-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goiás">GO</ref>), João Magno (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Workers'%20Party%20(Brazil)">PT</ref>-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minas%20Gerais">MG</ref>), João Paulo Cunha (PT-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/São%20Paulo">SP</ref>), José Borba (PMDB-PR), Josias Gomes da Silva (PT-<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bahia">BA</ref>), Paulo Rocha (PT-BA), Professor Luizinho (PT-SP), Romeu Queiroz (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brazilian%20Labour%20Party">PTB</ref>-MG), Vadão Gomes (PP-SP), Vanderval Santos (PL-SP), José Mentor (PT-SP), Roberto Brant (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Party%20of%20the%20Liberal%20Front%20(Brazil)">PFL</ref>-MG), José Dirceu (PT-SP) and Roberto Jefferson (PTB-RJ).</p>
<p>The report indicts 18 Brazilian deputies and the former deputy Valdemar Costa Neto [who resigned on  August 1].  They are accused of illegal campaign finance activities, of placing cronies in strategic positions in government enterprises and getting kickbacks from them, and of receiving cash payments in exchange for voting in line with the government in the Brazilian Congress.</p>
<p>The redactors called the allegation made by some parliamentarians that the resources  were used to settle debts with electoral campaigns a "lame excuse".  According to them it is  "perfectly plausible"  that the loans taken by the businessman Marcos Valerio at the Banco Rural and the BMG for the ruling <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Workers'%20Party%20(Brazil)">Workers' Party</ref> (PT) were false and created to make the illegal funds seem legal.  </p>
<p>In regards to the denunciations done by deputy <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roberto%20Jefferson">Roberto Jefferson</ref> (PTB) the report says:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Everything which he said that could be investigated showed to be true, including confessions against himself .</item>
<item>Everything that must be compared to other testimonies showed a great degree of truth. As a matter of fact, all of who, hurriedly, questioned him, saw their defenses collapse, before the successive discoveries.</item></list>
<p>According to the report, the businessman Marcos Valério  is a not reliable person because of  his contraditory testmonies.</p>
<p>The report says that several documents were identified and reviewed proving that large sums of money were withdrawn from agencies of the Rural Bank,  in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brasilia">Brasilia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belo%20Horizonte">Belo Horizonte</ref>, as well as from bank accounts of the enterprises SMPB and DNA Propaganda.  According to the documents the  beneficiaries  were federal deputies who received the money in person or through relatives, advisers, or  persons nominated by Marcos Valério.</p>
<p>The report affirms that it is possible that some payments were made on a monthly basis, and others more or less frequently. Nevertheless, according to the report  the periodicity of the payments is the less important fact.</p>
<head id="External_page">External page</head>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="http://www.cpmidoscorreios.org.br/1relatorio.htm">Post Office and Vote Buying parliamentary commissions of investigation  first joint preliminary report (in Portuguese)</ref></item></list>
</text>
