<text id="autogum_news_doc627" title="Poet, lyricist, and digital activist John Perry Barlow dies, aged 70" shortTile="poet-lyricist-digital" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-02-08" dateModified="2019-09-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Poet%2C_lyricist%2C_and_digital_activist_John_Perry_Barlow_dies%2C_aged_70" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Poet, lyricist, and digital activist John Perry Barlow dies, aged 70</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 9, 2018</hi></p>
<p>On Wednesday morning, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> poet, lyricist, and digital rights activist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Perry%20Barlow">John Perry Barlow</ref> died in his sleep at his <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/San_Francisco">San Francisco</ref> home. The announcement of his death specified no cause, but reportedly Barlow had recently experienced debilitating health problems. The co-founder of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/digital%20rights">digital rights</ref> legal defense non-profit <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Electronic_Frontier_Foundation">Electronic Frontier Foundation</ref> (EFF) and former lyricist of rock band <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Grateful_Dead">Grateful Dead</ref> was 70.  The EFF announced his death.</p>
<figure><caption>John Perry Barlow, 2009.Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Joi">Joi</ref>. (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:John_Perry_Barlow_cropped.jpg">Reuseterms</ref>.)</caption></figure>
<p>Barlow composed lyrics for the Grateful Dead, several songs for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/psychedelic%20rock">psychedelic rock</ref> band over almost 25years. In the 1990s, he shifted his focus to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Internet">Internet</ref>, composing essays on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet%20culture">Internet culture</ref> and working with the EFF to protect <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/digital%20rights">digital rights</ref>.</p>
<p>Born to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(US)">Republican</ref> state legislator Norman Barlow and his wife Miriam, Barlow was raised on the Bar Cross Ranch in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pinedale,%20Wyoming">Pinedale</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wyoming">Wyoming</ref>. Barlow became friends with future Grateful Dead <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/guitar">guitarist</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Weir">Bob Weir</ref> in high school before attending <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wesleyan%20University">Wesleyan University</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middleton,%20Connecticut">Middleton, Connecticut</ref>, where he studied <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/comparative%20religion">comparative religion</ref>. During his studies, Barlow began visiting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LSD">LSD</ref> (lysergic acid diethylamide) drug advocate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timothy%20Leary">Timothy Leary</ref>.</p>
<p>After graduation in 1969, he opted to travel the world and returned to his family's ranch in 1971.  With his father ill from a stroke, the younger Barlow began ranching before Weir contacted him to finish songs for the latter's solo album <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ace%20(Bob%20Weir%20album)">Ace</ref></hi>. The collaboration continued with the Grateful Dead and their individual members, with Barlow contributing occasional lyrics until the band's 1995 dissolution. In 1977, he married Elaine Parker. He sold the family ranch in 1988 due to financial strain.</p>
<p>Barlow became interested in the online world in the 1980s, including becoming a leader at on-line forum <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/the%20WELL">the WELL</ref>. In 1990, Barlow was interrogated by an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/FBI">Federal Bureau of Investigation</ref> agent about possible connections to underground <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/computer%20hacking">hackers</ref>. He posted his experience to the WELL and discovered that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitch%20Kapor">Mitch Kapor</ref> had had a similar encounter. The duo decided to join together to help provide legal defense for the hackers and formally incorporated the EFF, adding to the EFF board <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stewart%20Brand">Stewart Brand</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Gilmore%20(activist)">John Gilmore</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Apple_Inc.">Apple Inc.</ref> co-founder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve%20Wozniak">Steve Wozniak</ref>. He served on the board of the EFF until his death. He and Elaine divorced in 1995. He met Cynthia Horner in 1993 and was briefly engaged to her before her unexpected death from an undiagnosed health condition at the age of 29.</p>
<p>In addition to digital activism, Barlow was an early commentator on Internet culture, writing several pieces for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wired%20(magazine)">Wired</ref></hi> in its early years and penning essays such as "A Declaration of the Independence of Cyberspace" (1996) that helped define <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/digital%20citizenship">digital citizenship</ref>. In 1998 he became a fellow of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvard%20University">Harvard University</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berkman%20Klein%20Center%20for%20Internet%20&amp;%20Society">Berkman Klein Center for Internet and Society</ref> and in 2013 he was inducted into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet%20Hall%20of%20Fame">Internet Hall of Fame</ref>. Barlow stayed active in issues related to civil liberties and rights, helping to create the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freedom%20of%20the%20Press%20Foundation">Freedom of the Press Foundation</ref> in 2012. Although he had mostly retired from songwriting, he contributed to several songs by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/jam%20band">jam band</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20String%20Cheese%20Incident">The String Cheese Incident</ref>.</p>
<p>Barlow suffered a major <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/heart%20attack">heart attack</ref> in 2015. By late 2016, he faced several serious health conditions, leading several musicians to hold a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/benefit%20concert">benefit concert</ref> for him to raise funds for his medical bills. He recently completed his memoir <hi rend="italic">Mother American Night</hi>, slated for release on June 5.</p>
<p>Barlow is survived by his ex-wife Elaine Parker Barlow; the couple's three daughters Leah Justine, Anna Winter, and Amelia Rose; and a granddaughter.</p>
</text>
