<text id="autogum_news_doc684" title="US to reduce nuclear weapons arsenal" shortTile="reduce-nuclear-weapons" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-03-01" dateModified="2015-03-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_to_reduce_nuclear_weapons_arsenal" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>US to reduce nuclear weapons arsenal</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 2, 2010</hi></p>
<p>According to senior officials in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Obama administration</ref>, the U.S. is to significantly and permanently reduce its stockpile of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/nuclear%20weapons">nuclear weapons</ref> by thousands of weapons as part of a major rethinking of American nuclear policy.</p>
<p>The move is coming as part of a major policy review intended to stop the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuclear%20proliferation">proliferation</ref> of nuclear weapons around the world. According to an unnamed official, the review "will point to dramatic reductions in the stockpile, while maintaining a strong and reliable deterrent." </p>
<p>As part of the new policy, conventional weapons will have a greater role in the future. According to officials, there are thousands of weapons that could be retired, largely by eliminating those currently stored. The move comes as a significant step towards Obama's stated goal of reducing and eventually ending the spread of nuclear weapons worldwide.</p>
<p>The policy changes come as part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuclear%20Posture%20Review">Nuclear Posture Review</ref>, a document which is undertaken by all presidents. In addition to the reduction of nuclear weapons, Obama's review  will also adjust the United States' defense towards non-nuclear options, including missile defense, largely within striking distance of the Persian Gulf to reduce the threat posed by countries such as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref>.  </p>
<p>A centerpiece of the new policy is a new plan called the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prompt%20Global%20Strike">Prompt Global Strike</ref>," which involves a new type of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/conventional%20weapon">conventional weapon</ref> that could be fired from the U.S. and reach anywhere in the world within an hour, providing an effective option for attacks worldwide, such as against a missile launch from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_Korea">North Korea</ref> or a strike against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al-Qaeda">Al-Qaeda</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pakistan">Pakistan</ref>. The new weapons would achieve the same effects as nuclear weapons, without the threat of conventional war escalating into nuclear war.</p>
<p>The changes reflect a new focus on nonproliferation and arms control by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obama%20administration">Obama administration</ref>, policies that were largely dismissed by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bush%20administration">Bush administration</ref>. In conjunction with new domestic policies, the Obama administration is trying to win passage of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comprehensive%20Test%20Ban%20Treaty">Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty</ref>, which would ban all nuclear explosions for any purposes. </p>
<p>The treaty was defeated in the 1990s, during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clinton%20presidency">Clinton presidency</ref>, and still faces strong resistance in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Senate">U.S. Senate</ref>. The Obama administration is also trying to revise the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuclear%20Nonproliferation%20Treaty">Nuclear Nonproliferation Treaty</ref> to close loopholes that have been exploited by North Korea and Iran.</p>
<p>The administration has also been pressured to redefine the role of America's nuclear arsenal. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic%20Party%20(United%20States)">Democrats</ref> have been pressuring the administration to formally declare that the role of America's nuclear weapons is solely to deter nuclear attack on the United States. </p>
<p>American military officials, as well as some officials within the White House, however, have urged the administration to retain more ambiguous wording from the Bush era, which says that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/nuclear%20deterrence">nuclear deterrence</ref> is only the primary role of American nuclear weapons, which would leave open the option of using nuclear weapons against enemies that threaten the US with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/chemical%20weapons">chemical</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/biological%20weapons">biological weapons</ref>.</p>
</text>
