<text id="autogum_news_doc810" title="South American Community of Nations announced at Third South American Summit" shortTile="south-american-community" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2004-12-10" dateModified="2019-07-26" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_American_Community_of_Nations_announced_at_Third_South_American_Summit" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>South American Community of Nations announced at Third South American Summit</head><figure></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">December 2004</hi></p>
<p>South American nations began the creation of an international economic and legislative bloc by a declaration made at the Third South American Summit on 8 December. Named the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South%20American%20Community%20of%20Nations">South American Community of Nations</ref>, the organization is a step toward greater coordination among South American states.</p>
<p>Two existing South American trade blocs, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andean%20Community">Andean Community</ref> (Comunidad Andina) and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mercosur">Southern Common Market</ref> (Mercado Común del Sur, or Mercosur), have been combined and three previously uninvolved states included to create the community. </p>
<p>The summit, held between 7-9 December at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cuzco">Cusco</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayacucho">Ayacucho</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Peru">Peru</ref>, was attended by heads of state from Bolivia, Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Guyana, Peru, Suriname, and Venezuela. Foreign ministers attended for Argentina, Ecuador, Paraguay, and Uruguay. The summit was convened principally to sign the two-page Preamble to the Foundation Act of the South American Union on the second day of the summit. Although the Bolivian and Colombian presidents attended the summit, they did not attend the signing ceremony, this instead being done by representatives. Central American states <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panama">Panama</ref> attended the ceremony as observers.</p>
<p>The locations for the summit were chosen for their historical significance and their association with events that reflect well on South America. Cusco was the ancient capital of the advanced civilization of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inca%20Empire">Incas</ref>. Ayachucho was the site of an 1824 decisive victory against Spanish troops by the South American independence movement headed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simón%20Bolívar">Simón Bolívar</ref>. The First and Second South American Summits were held at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brasília">Brasília</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref> in September 2000 and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guayaquil">Guayaquil</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecuador">Ecuador</ref> in July 2002.</p>
<p>The community will include every state in South America with the exception of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French%20Guiana">French Guiana</ref>, itself a territory of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France">France</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolivia">Bolivia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colombia">Colombia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecuador">Ecuador</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peru">Peru</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venezuela">Venezuela</ref> join SACN from the Andean Community, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/trade%20bloc">trade bloc</ref> established in 1969. From  the more recent (1991) Mercosur comes <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Argentina">Argentina</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paraguay">Paraguay</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uruguay">Uruguay</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guyana">Guyana</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suriname">Suriname</ref>, two small northeastern countries which had previously not participated in a South American trade bloc, will not immediately join the community. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chile">Chile</ref> will additionally join; it has, however, been cautious.</p>
<p>SACN is a more ambitious union than the previous Andean Community and Mercosur. It has been established to be more than a trade union. The "ultimate goal, which can hopefully be reached, in time, is the United States of South America," explains Secretary General of the Andean Community Wagner. A common currency, tariff-free common market, and regional parliament are all proposed in the Cusco declaration.</p>
<p>Many disputes exist between South American nations that may be issues in advancing SACN.</p>
<p>The principal force behind SACN has been Brazil. The First South American Summit was held in Brazil through the efforts of Brazilian President Fernando Henrique Cardoso.</p>
<p>Chile has been an associate member of Mercosur since 1996. It was a member of the Andean Community from its inception in 1969, but withdrew six years later when ruled by General Augusto Pinochet. With 70% of its GDP attributed to foreign trade, Chile has traditionally favored relations with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States">United States</ref> or the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/APEC">Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation</ref> forum over South American agreements. </p>
<p>SACN's short-term political and economic effects may be limited. The elimination of all trade tariffs has long been a goal of both the Andean Community and Mercosur, but has had little success.</p>
<p>However, 32 construction projects were approved at the summit. Worth US$4.3bn over five years, the projects focus on improving regional infrastructure. The largest is a US$700m road highway that will link Brazil and Peru across the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andes">Andes mountains</ref>. "These are anchor projects that will be carried out over five years," said Wagner. "They were chosen because they do not serve merely as corridors between countries and zones, but also as a means of promoting development in border regions, which have traditionally been the poorest and most marginalised in our countries." Wagner identifies 350 potential infrastructure projects of a combined cost of US$200bn.</p>
<p>Details of the South American Community of Nations are expected to be planned further at the first First SACN Summit in March or April of 2005 in Brazil. Work on a constitution is expected to begin in 2005. A Second SACN Summit of unspecified date is to be held in Bolivia.</p>
</text>
