<text id="autogum_news_doc115" title="Ghanaians elect new President" shortTile="ghanaians-elect-new" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-12-28" dateModified="2012-08-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ghanaians_elect_new_President" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Ghanaians elect new President</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 3, 2009</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Ghana">University of Ghana</ref> law professor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Atta%20Mills">John Atta Mills</ref>, age 64, was confirmed on Saturday as the winner of the runoff presidential election, the fifth in Ghana since the return to multi-party democracy in 1992. </p>
<p>According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Election%20Commission%20of%20Ghana">Electoral Commission</ref> Chair, Kwadwo Afari-Gyan, Atta Mills obtained 50.23 percent of ballots cast on December 28, or 4,521,032 votes, while Nana Akufo-Addo got 49.77 percent or 4,480,446 votes. Despite the ruling party's call to boycott, the Tain local election officer also announced that Atta-Mills obtained 19,566 votes in Friday's special election there, while Nana Akufo-Addo had only 2,053 ballots.</p>
<p>In the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghanaian%20parliamentary%20election,%202008">parliamentary elections</ref>, Atta Mills’s NDC won 114 seats to the NPP’s 107. Minor parties and independent candidates won seven seats while two are still being contested.</p>
<p>President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Kufuor">John Kufuor</ref> appealed for sobriety and urged the candidates to accept the official result.</p>
<p>A presidential election was held in Ghana on 7 December 2008, at the same time as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghanaian%20parliamentary%20election,%202008">parliamentary election</ref>. Eight candidates contested the first round of voting.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ghana">Ghana</ref>'s electoral commission announced on December 10 that a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/two-round%20system">run-off election</ref> must be held on 28 December, 2008 for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List%20of%20heads%20of%20state%20of%20Ghana">Ghanaian presidency</ref>. The commission said that the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Patriotic%20Party">New Patriotic Party</ref> (NPP) candidate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nana%20Addo%20Dankwa%20Akufo-Addo">Nana Addo Dankwa Akufo-Addo</ref> won 49.13% of the vote, slightly more than the other main candidate, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Atta%20Mills">John Atta Mills</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Democratic%20Congress%20(Ghana)">National Democratic Congress</ref> (NDC), who obtained 47.92%. However, neither candidate reached the 50% mark needed to declare an outright winner to succeed President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20Kufuor">John Kufuor</ref>, who will step down after two terms.</p>
<p>Turnout on election day was very high. Out of some 8.6 million votes cast, more than 200,000, or 2.4% of the full total, were rejected. Overall voter turnout in the election was 69.52%.</p>
<p>The second round was to be rerun on 2 January 2009 in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tain%20District">Tain District</ref> due to ballot papers irregularities. As the number of voters in Tain, which has a constituency of about 53,000 eligible voters, exceeded Atta Mills' margin of victory without the results, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Election%20Commission%20of%20Ghana">Election Commission</ref> stated it would not announce Atta Mills as the winner until after the election rerun in Tain. </p>
<p>The NPP sought to delay voting in Tain as it claimed that "the atmosphere in the rural district was not conducive to a free and fair election", but the court said it would only hear the case on January 5, denying the NPP an injunction. The NPP then proceeded to call for a voting boycott, for which it was criticized by civil groups.</p>
<p>On December 21, 2006, former Vice-President John Atta-Mills, who unsuccessfully ran as the National Democratic Congress (NDC) presidential candidate in 2000 and 2004, was overwhelmingly elected by NDC as its candidate for the 2008 presidential election.</p>
<p>Former Foreign Minister Nana Addo Dankwa Akufo-Addo was elected as the 2008 presidential candidate of the governing New Patriotic Party (NPP) at a party congress on December 23, 2007. Although he fell short of the required 50%, the second-place candidate, John Alan Kyeremanten, conceded defeat and backed Akufo-Addo.</p>
</text>
