<text id="autogum_news_doc166" title="Obama commutes whistleblower&apos;s sentence: Chelsea Manning to walk free in 120 days" shortTile="obama-commutes-whistleblowers" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-01-18" dateModified="2017-01-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Obama_commutes_whistleblower%27s_sentence%3A_Chelsea_Manning_to_walk_free_in_120_days" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Obama commutes whistleblower's sentence: Chelsea Manning to walk free in 120 days</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 18, 2017</hi></p>
<p>Yesterday, mere days before he is to leave office, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">U.S.</ref> President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> commuted the sentence of Army intelligence officer <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chelsea_Manning">Chelsea Manning</ref> from 35 years to time served. Manning, who in 2010 released thousands of classified documents to the public through <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/WikiLeaks">WikiLeaks</ref> detailing abuses of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/second%20Iraq%20war">Iraq</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afghan%20war">Afghanistan</ref> wars, has already served almost seven years in prison and is now scheduled for release on May 17 of this year</p>
<figure><caption>Artist's rendition of Manning as she views herself.Image: Alicia Neal.</caption></figure>
<p>The information Manning released to the public through WikiLeaks and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Guardian">The Guardian</ref></hi> in 2010 included diplomatic accounts, videos, military incident logs, and battle plans, including footage of an American Apache helicopter firing on suspected Iraqi insurgents, reports of prisoners held in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Guantanamo_Bay">Guantanamo Bay</ref> without trial, and records of detainees abused by the Iraqi military. Many in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Congress">Congress</ref> have denounced Manning as a traitor, stating the breach endangered U.S. national security. Manning was convicted in 2013 of 22 charges, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/espionage">espionage</ref>, but acquitted of aiding the enemy.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Republican_Party">Republican</ref> senator <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/John_McCain">John McCain</ref>, who ran for president against Obama in 2008, said "It is a sad, yet perhaps fitting commentary on President Obama's failed national security policies that he would commute the sentence of an individual that endangered the lives of American troops, diplomats, and intelligence sources by leaking hundreds of thousands of sensitive government documents to WikiLeaks, a virulently anti-American organization that was a tool of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russian%20interference%20in%20the%202016%20U.S.%20presidential%20election">Russia's recent interference in our elections</ref>."</p>
<p>Not everyone has considered Manning's actions to be wrong. "Chelsea Manning exposed serious abuses," says Margaret Huang, executive director of the U.S. branch of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Amnesty_International">Amnesty International</ref>, "and as a result her own human rights have been violated." Huang went on to call Obama's order for Manning's release "long overdue." Despite being a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Transgender">trans woman</ref>, Manning was housed in a men's prison, the U.S. Disciplinary Barracks at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort%20Leavenworth,%20Kansas">Fort Leavenworth, Kansas</ref>. She spent a long period in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/solitary%20confinement">solitary confinement</ref> and attempted suicide twice in 2016.</p>
<p>Obama's staff told the press WikiLeaks founder <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Julian_Assange">Julian Assange</ref>'s promise to agree to U.S. extradition if Manning was granted clemency had nothing to do with the decision. Assange is currently living in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ecuador">Ecuadorian</ref> embassy in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>, where he is claiming asylum. He faces <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rape">rape</ref> accusations from two <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Swedish</ref> women.</p>
<p>The Obama administration has seen what <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_New_York_Times">The New York Times</ref></hi> calls an "unprecedented crackdown on leaks of government secrets." Manning is among more than 1,500 individuals whom President Obama has granted clemency during his tenure. White House Press Secretary Josh Ernest was asked if <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/National_Security_Agency">NSA</ref> whistleblower <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edward_Snowden">Edward Snowden</ref> would also be pardoned. Ernest said no, saying the information Snowden released was more dangerous to the U.S. public and pointed out that while Manning had gone through a formal trial and acknowledged wrongdoing, "Mr. Snowden fled into the arms of an adversary and has sought refuge in a country that most recently made a concerted effort to undermine confidence in our democracy."</p>
<p>This week, Obama also commuted the sentences of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oscar%20Lopez%20Rivera">Oscar Lopez Rivera</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Puerto_Rico">Puerto Rican</ref> nationalist linked to bombings in the 1970s and 1980s, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20E.%20Cartwright">James E. Cartwright</ref>, a former Marine general and White House Chief of Staff convicted of lying to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/FBI">FBI</ref>, and over two hundred other individuals, mostly drug offenders. He also pardoned 63 people outright.</p>
</text>
