<text id="autogum_news_doc724" title="Wikinews interviews peace activist Cindy Sheehan, 2014 California gubernatorial candidate" shortTile="wikinews-interviews" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-08-08" dateModified="2019-08-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_peace_activist_Cindy_Sheehan%2C_2014_California_gubernatorial_candidate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews peace activist Cindy Sheehan, 2014 California gubernatorial candidate</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 8, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Cindy Sheehan in 2007.Image: dbking.</caption></figure>
<p>Peace activist <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cindy_Sheehan">Cindy Sheehan</ref>, who recently announced her intention to run as the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Peace_and_Freedom_Party">Peace and Freedom Party</ref>'s nominee for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Governor%20of%20California">governor</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California%20gubernatorial%20election,%202014">2014</ref>, took some time to answer five questions from <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter William S. Saturn. </p>
<p>Sheehan is best known for her active opposition to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/War_in_Iraq">War in Iraq</ref> following the loss of her son Casey there in 2004. In protest of the war, she set up camp outside President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref>'s ranch in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crawford,%20Texas">Crawford</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Texas">Texas</ref>, demanding a pullout of U.S. troops and prosecution of Bush administration officials for war crimes. According to her website, Sheehan also advocates <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/revolutionary%20socialism">revolutionary socialism</ref>, believing it to be key to loosening the "Imperialist/Capitalist two-party stranglehold" on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> and world politics.</p>
<p>This campaign is not Sheehan's first foray into electoral politics. In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20House%20of%20Representatives%20elections,%202008">2008</ref>, she challenged then-<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_House_of_Representatives">House</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Speaker%20of%20the%20United%20States%20House%20of%20Representatives">Speaker</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nancy_Pelosi">Nancy Pelosi</ref> for Congress, finishing second in a field of seven candidates. During the campaign, she championed the reduction of U.S. troops abroad, and endorsed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/economic%20democracy">economic democracy</ref>, bank <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/nationalization">nationalization</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/single-payer%20health%20care">single-payer health care</ref>, education subsidies, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decriminalization%20of%20non-medical%20cannabis%20in%20the%20United%20States">marijuana decriminalization</ref>, alternative fuels, and electoral reform. In <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_election,_2012">2012</ref>, she ran as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/vice%20presidential">vice presidential</ref> nominee of the Peace and Freedom Party on a similar platform. The party promotes socialism, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Feminism">feminism</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/environmentalism">environmentalism</ref>.</p>
<p>Other gubernatorial candidates include Governor <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jerry_Brown">Jerry Brown</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democratic Party</ref>, former <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lieutenant%20Governor%20of%20California">Lieutenant Governor</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abel%20Maldonado">Abel Maldonado</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican Party</ref>, and 2012 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Justice_Party_(United_States)">Justice Party</ref> vice presidential nominee <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luis%20J.%20Rodriguez">Luis J. Rodriguez</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Green_Party_of_the_United_States">Green Party</ref>.</p>
<p>With <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi>, Sheehan discusses <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third%20party%20(United%20States)">third party politics</ref> and her campaign and governing strategy, and assesses past <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List%20of%20Governors%20of%20California">governors of California</ref>, including Brown.</p>
<head id="Interview">Interview</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">William S. Saturn</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> : Understanding that third party candidates do not often win, what do you hope to achieve by running for governor of California? </p>
<hi rend="bold">Cindy Sheehan</hi>: First of all, unfortunately third party candidates NEVER win for high level state or federal offices, and now since <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California%20Proposition%2014%20(2010)">Prop 14</ref> passed, it is even harder. Having said that, in 2008, I ran as an independent against Nancy Pelosi and I came in second. In California, I think I may have a good chance to advance to the general election and hopefully force the other candidate, (Brown, ?) to debate me and bring up the issues and solutions to more people.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> How do you plan to spread your message throughout the state? </p>
<hi rend="bold">Sheehan</hi>: We already have many Californians who have volunteered to host the campaign with fundraisers and town hall meetings. I am going to ride my bike as much as possible to highlight the need to drastically cut our dependence on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fossil%20fuels">fossil fuels</ref> and to transition to clean, renewable, and sustainable forms of energy — also to highlight the need for cheap and comprehensive public transportation and infrastructure improvement.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> How would you rate Jerry Brown's performance as governor? What would you do differently than him? </p>
<hi rend="bold">Sheehan</hi>: Well, since I am challenging him, I would rate his performance as poor. He is in the pockets of so many special interests, like oil and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/private%20prison">privatized prisons</ref>, that he is not looking out for the interests of everyone in this state. I would hold dozens of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/town%20hall%20meeting">town hall meetings</ref> to talk to the people of this state about their struggles and community-based solutions and work with the people to put their needs first and foremost. Instead of destroying education, I would put a revival of our public school system as one of the most urgent things we need to do.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> If elected, how would you work with a legislature hostile to your agenda?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Sheehan</hi>: By getting the people involved in the process. It’s the only way we can do it.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WSS</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi> Which past California governor do you most admire? </p>
<hi rend="bold">Sheehan</hi>: I majored in US History at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UCLA">UCLA</ref> and was focusing on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History%20of%20California">California history</ref>, so I admire someone who ran for governor, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Upton%20Sinclair">Upton Sinclair</ref>, more than anyone who actually was elected. Our <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/End%20Poverty%20in%20California%20movement">EPIC</ref> campaign is modeled off of his. But if I had to pick one that was actually governor, I would say, populist-progressive <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hiram%20Johnson">Hiram Johnson</ref>. May I also say that it’s way past time that California elected a female?
</text>
