<text id="autogum_news_doc110" title="Egyptian treasures found in ancient tomb" shortTile="egyptian-treasures" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-12" dateModified="2014-04-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egyptian_treasures_found_in_ancient_tomb" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Egyptian treasures found in ancient tomb</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 13, 2009</hi></p>
<p>A team of archaeologists excavating an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ancient%20Egypt">Ancient Egyptian</ref> tomb have discovered golden jewelry in a recently-discovered lower chamber at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valley%20of%20the%20Kings">Valley of the Kings</ref> burial site in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luxor">Luxor</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egypt">Egypt</ref>.</p>
<p>Two golden rings and five golden earrings were found in the tomb of Djehuty, an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eighteenth%20dynasty%20of%20Egypt">18th-dynasty</ref> official of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hatshepsut">Queen Hatshepsut</ref>, and were probably the property of Djehuty or his family. </p>
<p>The discovery was announced by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Farouk%20Hosni">Farouk Hosni</ref>, Egypt's current Minister of Culture.</p>
<figure><caption>The Valley of the Kings</caption></figure><p>Djehuty was overseer of the treasury and overseer of works for the Queen.  Hatshepsut reigned approximately 1479–1458 BCE.  Djehuty was responsible for managing the huge amounts of precious goods brought in from Egypt's military expedition to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Land%20of%20Punt">Punt</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Horn%20of%20Africa">Horn of Africa</ref> and the vast building projects of Hatshepsut which have made the female pharaoh one of the most-remembered of any from ancient Egypt.</p>
<p>Djehuty died after Hatshepsut did, sometime during the reign of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thutmosis%20III">Thutmosis III</ref>.  Both Hatshepsut's and Thutmosis's names are recorded on the tomb.  In a fashion typical of ancient Egyptian rivalries, Hatshepsut's name was partly obscured on the monument over the tomb sometime after the queen's death.</p>
<p>The team, led by José Manuel Galán of the National Research Center (Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas, CSIC), in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madrid">Madrid</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>, had been excavating the tomb, designated TT11 and located in the necropolis of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dra'%20Abu%20el-Naga'">Dra' Abu el-Naga'</ref>, since 2002. While much of Djehuty's funerary equipment was lost to fire in antiquity, the lower chamber of his tomb was concealed at the end of a three-meter shaft and discovered at the end of 2008. </p>
<p>A superficial description of the tomb itself was recorded almost two hundred years ago by 19th-century French Egyptologist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean-François%20Champollion">Jean-François Champollion</ref>, rubble blocking the entrance hindered excavation until the 21st century. In that time, emphasis in Egyptology has changed from the cataloging of treasures to the investigation of ancient culture, life and religion.</p>
<p>Since excavation began, Djehuty's tomb has yielded a number of surprises.  It was discovered that the tomb was re-used repeatedly up to and during the Greco-Roman period.  There is an unusual face-on depiction of pharaoh Thutmosis III hunting ducks, and the mummy of a young, bejewelled, as-yet unidentified woman. </p>
<figure><caption>Djehuty was an official of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hatshepsut">Hatshepsut</ref></caption></figure><p>In 2007, 44 preserved bunches of flowers thought to be from Djehuty's funeral were found in the site. In their 8th season of excavation, which ended on February 22, 2009, the team also found considerable evidence that below Djehuty's tomb is a network of burial sites from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eleventh%20dynasty%20of%20Egypt">11th dynasty</ref>, four thousand years old.</p>
<p>The lower chamber also displays passages from the Egyptian funerary text the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Book%20of%20the%20Dead">Book of the Dead</ref> on its walls and a colorful mural of the goddess <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nut%20(goddess)">Nut</ref>, an embodiment of the heavens, on the ceiling. The names of Djehuty and his parents were also intact in the second chamber; the names were defaced in the previously-known first chamber of the tomb, which had also been looted.</p>
<p>According to a press release from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zahi%20Hawass">Dr. Zahi Hawass</ref>, Secretary General of Egypt’s Supreme Council of Antiquities, Djehuty's tomb is only the fifth known decorated burial chamber of the 18th dynasty. An additional unusual feature of the tomb is that its upper chamber is decorated in relief, rather than simply paint.  When the excavation is completed, Dr Galán's team plans to open the site to the public as the carved stoneworks will not be destroyed by tourists' activities as paint would.</p>
<p>The identification of Djehuty is a complicated one, as a number of officials of the 18th dynasty bore the name, including a general and several governors. The name itself is an alternate transliteration of the name of the Egyptian god usually written in English as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thoth">Thoth</ref>.</p>
</text>
