<text id="autogum_news_doc483" title="England: Multi-storey carpark in Liverpool gutted by fire, 1,300 vehicles destroyed" shortTile="england-multistorey" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-01-03" dateModified="2018-01-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England%3A_Multi-storey_carpark_in_Liverpool_gutted_by_fire%2C_1%2C300_vehicles_destroyed" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>England: Multi-storey carpark in Liverpool gutted by fire, 1,300 vehicles destroyed</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 4, 2018</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Merseyside Fire and Rescue Service vehicle.Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Irate">John Bradley</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>A fire on Sunday night in the seven-storey carpark for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Echo%20Arena%20Liverpool">Echo Arena</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Liverpool">Liverpool</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref> destroyed almost all the vehicles parked inside and led to cancellation of the final evening of the Liverpool International Horse Show and evacuation of nearby blocks of flats. The blaze reportedly started with a parked <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Land%20Rover%20Discovery">Range Rover Discovery</ref>.</p>
Location of Liverpool within the <ref target="/wiki/United_Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref>
<p>Investigators with the fire brigade stated that they believe the fire began with an accidental engine fire in the Range Rover at about 4.30 pm. The first call was made at 4.42 and firefighters arrived eight minutes after that. Ultimately twelve engines and 85 firefighters were involved in combatting the blaze. Aerial appliances were used and also three high-volume pumps. Fed by the fuel in vehicles parked inside, the temperature of the fire in the carpark is believed to have reached as high as 1,000<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Celsius">°C</ref>. It was too hot to be extinguished with water from hydrants, so a high-volume pump was used to draw water from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/River%20Mersey">River Mersey</ref>, and two more were brought from other fire brigades in the region.</p>
<p>The carpark has seven storeys and a capacity of 1,600 vehicles, and approximately 1,300  were parked in it when the fire broke out. According to Dan Stephens, chief fire officer for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merseyside%20Fire%20and%20Rescue%20Service">Merseyside Fire and Rescue Service</ref>, almost all of them were destroyed, with the exception of a few parked on the top level and at corners. "With these very high temperatures, you were never going to put the fire out without the whole building taking hold. The speed at which the fire spreads means you simply aren’t going to put it out," said Stephens.</p>
<p>The carpark itself was severely damaged; according to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe%20Anderson%20(politician)">Joe Anderson</ref>, the mayor of Liverpool. It is not in danger of collapsing but will have to be demolished, which will be difficult with the many burned-out cars still inside it, Anderson told the BBC.</p>
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arena_and_Convention_Centre_Liverpool">Arena and Convention Centre Liverpool</ref> (rectangle) to the burned car park (point).
<p>According to Stephens, there were no serious injuries: one woman injured her hand, and two people were treated for smoke inhalation. A spokesman for the Echo Arena also stated that all animals were safe. All horses were successfully evacuated from the carpark and then removed from the stables after smoke spread to them. Six dogs were also rescued unharmed, two on a lower level in the early stages of the fire and four that had been left in a car on the top level, freed by firefighters on Monday after the fire was put out.</p>
<p>The final evening of the four-day Liverpool International Horse Show had been scheduled to begin at 7.30, and had to be cancelled. Many attendees were stranded in the city on New Year's Eve night. Merseyside police directed people to the Pullman Hotel, where <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Red_Cross">Red Cross</ref> assistance was available, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liverpool%20City%20Council">Liverpool City Council</ref> set up an assistance centre at the Lifestyles Gym. A spokesman for the Association of British Insurers has said that insurance companies will "move very quickly" to reimburse owners whose vehicles were destroyed.</p>
<p>Nearby blocks of flats were evacuated because of the smoke. Eyewitnesses reported hearing what they at first thought were firecrackers, then "multiple explosions", "bangs and popping", "the bangs of car windows exploding". People reported leaving everything in their cars, including their cellphones, and running for their lives.</p>
<p>Mayor Anderson tweeted that cuts to fire services over the last two years made it significantly harder to fight the fire and might have caused it not to be controllable. He also suggested that fire safety in multi-storey carparks had not been sufficiently considered and that installing sprinklers in them might help stop future fires before they become unmanageable, in a letter to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nick%20Hurd">Nick Hurd</ref>, a member of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Parliament_of_the_United_Kingdom">Parliament</ref>.</p>
</text>
