<text id="autogum_news_doc712" title="SpaceX successfully test fires Falcon 9 rocket in Texas" shortTile="spacex-successfully" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-11-24" dateModified="2015-01-18" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/SpaceX_successfully_test_fires_Falcon_9_rocket_in_Texas" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>SpaceX successfully test fires Falcon 9 rocket in Texas</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 24, 2008</hi></p>
<figure rend="SpaceX_Merlin_engine.gif"></figure> <figure rend="Falcon-9.jpg"></figure>At 10:30pm on November 23, 2008, near the airport in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/McGregor,%20Texas">McGregor</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Texas">Texas</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/SpaceX">Space Exploration Technologies Corporation</ref> (SpaceX) tested their new <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Falcon_9">Falcon 9</ref> rocket at full thrust for nearly 3 minutes (160 seconds). The engineers then shut down two of the nine engines — in order to limit potential damage to the launch pad — and continued the test for 18 more seconds before finally shutting the rocket down. "We ran the engines just like they would run during flight, but instead of being up in the air, they were held down. They weren’t moving," said Lauren Dreyer, SpaceX's manager for business development. This was the Falcon 9's first major test firing, and it marks a milestone for the company in its plans to capture a section of the commercial launch market.
<p>The test reportedly shook the windows of houses 5 miles away, causing agitation among residents who felt that they had not received adequate warning. "I appreciate the fact that the company notified [the City of] McGregor, but did they not think the test would affect the surrounding communities?" asked commenter Lorena Resident on the website for the Waco Tribune-Herald. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Waco,_Texas">Waco</ref> lies just east of McGregor.</p>
<p>The Falcon 9 rocket, and its smaller sibling the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Falcon_1">Falcon 1</ref>, are the first rockets capable of entering <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Low%20Earth%20Orbit">Low Earth Orbit</ref> (LEO) to have their design be privately funded in its entirety. According to SpaceX the Falcon 9 can generate 4 times the maximum thrust of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boeing%20747">Boeing 747</ref> while firing in a vacuum, and will eventually be able to perform interplanetary missions in addition to its initial role as an orbital launch vehicle. SpaceX is also designing a crew and cargo capsule for the Falcon 9, which it has named the "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SpaceX%20Dragon">Dragon</ref>".</p>
 HAVE YOUR SAY
 What do you think the future holds for SpaceX and commercial spaceflight in general?
<ref target="//en.wikinews.org/w/index.php?title=Comments:Main_Page&amp;action=edit&amp;preload=Wikinews:Commentary_pages_on_news_events/body&amp;editintro=Template:Editintro_comments&amp;summary=create">Add or view comments</ref>
<p>SpaceX is a contender for future commercial contracts from various government run space agencies, with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref> expressing particular interest. NASA will be retiring their fleet of Columbia Class <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Space%20Shuttle">Space Shuttles</ref> in 2010, but will not have the Shuttles' replacements (the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ares%20I">Ares I</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ares%20V">Ares V</ref> rockets) ready until at least 2014. NASA hopes to fill some of this gap using commercial launches from companies such as SpaceX. SpaceX has already reached an agreement with NASA to conduct three test flights of the Dragon capsule in conjunction with the Falcon 9. The first of these flights is expected in 2009.</p>
<p>Elon Musk, CEO and CTO of SpaceX, said, "The full mission-length test firing clears the highest hurdle for the Falcon 9 first stage before launch. In the next few months, we will have the first Falcon 9 flight vehicle on its launch pad at Cape Canaveral, preparing for lift-off in 2009."</p>
Science and Technology
More articles on Science and Technology
<list type="unordered">
<item>25 October 2019: <ref target="/wiki/Wash_your_hands_or_else_spread_superbug_E._coli,_say_scientists">Wash your hands or else spread superbug E. coli, say scientists</ref></item>
<item>12 October 2019: <ref target="/wiki/Scientists_describe_how_%27upside-down_rivers%27_of_warm_water_break_Antarctica%27s_ice_shelf">Scientists describe how 'upside-down rivers' of warm water break Antarctica's ice shelf</ref></item>
<item>10 October 2019: <ref target="/wiki/Swedish_academy_announces_2019_Nobel_Prize_winners_in_physics">Swedish academy announces 2019 Nobel Prize winners in physics</ref></item>
<item>5 October 2019: <ref target="/wiki/Voracious_fish_defend_coral_reefs_against_warming,_say_scientists">Voracious fish defend coral reefs against warming, say scientists</ref></item>
<item>14 September 2019: <ref target="/wiki/Astronomers_find_water_vapour_in_atmosphere_of_exoplanet_K2-18b">Astronomers find water vapour in atmosphere of exoplanet K2-18b</ref></item></list>
...<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Portal:Science_and_technology">More articles here</ref>
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Portal:Science_and_technology">To write, edit, start or view other articles on topics related to Science and Technology, see the Science and Technology Portal</ref>
Space
More articles on Space
<list type="unordered">
<item><ref target="/wiki/Cosmonaut_Alexei_Leonov_dies_at_age_85">Cosmonaut Alexei Leonov dies at age 85</ref></item>
<item><ref target="/wiki/Swedish_academy_announces_2019_Nobel_Prize_winners_in_physics">Swedish academy announces 2019 Nobel Prize winners in physics</ref></item>
<item><ref target="/wiki/Astronomers_find_water_vapour_in_atmosphere_of_exoplanet_K2-18b">Astronomers find water vapour in atmosphere of exoplanet K2-18b</ref></item>
<item><ref target="/wiki/SpaceX_Crew_Dragon_capsule_docks_with_International_Space_Station">SpaceX Crew Dragon capsule docks with International Space Station</ref></item>
<item><ref target="/wiki/Simple_animals_could_live_in_Martian_brines:_Wikinews_interviews_planetary_scientist_Vlada_Stamenkovi%C4%87">Simple animals could live in Martian brines: Wikinews interviews planetary scientist Vlada Stamenković</ref></item></list>
...<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Portal:Space">More articles here</ref>
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Portal:Space">To write, edit, start or view other articles on Space related topics, see the Space Portal</ref>
</text>
