<text id="autogum_news_doc229" title="CNN journalist fired for controversial Twitter message" shortTile="cnn-journalist-fired" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-07-08" dateModified="2016-10-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CNN_journalist_fired_for_controversial_Twitter_message" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>CNN journalist fired for controversial Twitter message</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 9, 2010</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Octavia Nasr in a publicity photo</caption></figure>
<p>Atlanta-based <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CNN">CNN</ref> journalist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Octavia%20Nasr">Octavia Nasr</ref>, 20-year veteran of the network and senior editor for Middle East affairs, was reprimanded for a Twitter comment published on Sunday in which she expressed sadness at the death of Iraqi-born <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lebanon">Lebanese</ref> Grand Ayatollah <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohammad%20Hussein%20Fadlallah">Mohammad Hussein Fadlallah</ref>. In the post, the journalist stated that she was "<hi rend="italic">Sad to hear of the passing of Sayyed Mohammad Hussein Fadlallah.. One of Hezbollah's giants I respect a lot..</hi>".</p>
<p>According to a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York_Times">New York Times</ref></hi> blog, after Parisa Khosravi, the CNN senior vice president, "had a conversation" with Ms. Nasr she was formally asked to step down. She left the network on Wednesday. </p>
<p>Brian Stelter of the <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> reports that the issue was originally brought to the public's attention by online supporters of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israel</ref>, who republished the comment widely. They criticised her for being a "<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hezbollah">Hezbollah</ref> sympathizer" for a man who was "committed to the destruction of Israel." Critics point to comments Fadlallah has made in the past about the Holocaust, in which he questions the veracity of the agreed-upon figures of Jewish deaths in concentration camps.</p>
<p>"Is this the sort of extremist figure that CNN's Senior Editor of Mideast Affairs should be professing her respect for?" asked <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HonestReporting">HonestReporting</ref>, the media watchdog group which purports to defend Israel "against prejudice in the media." </p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salon%20(website)">Salon</ref></hi> reporter <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glenn%20Greenwald">Glenn Greenwald</ref> has responded to these allegations of "prejudice" by pointing to similar cases in which no controversy arose: "<hi rend="italic">The Washington Post</hi> lavished editorial praise on the brutal, right-wing tyrant <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Augusto_Pinochet">Augusto Pinochet</ref>, and that caused no controversy...Benjamin Netanyahu formally celebrates the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King%20David%20Hotel%20bombing">Terrorist bombing of the King David Hotel</ref> that killed...78 civilians and nobody is stigmatized for supporting him.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erick%20Erickson">Erick Erickson</ref> sent around the most rancid and arguably racist tweets, only to thereafter be hired as a CNN contributor."</p>
<p>Lebanese author and academic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/As'ad%20AbuKhalil">Dr. As'ad Abu-Khalil</ref> has also argued that commentators have not properly placed Fadlallah in context, and pointed to the schools and orphanages he founded in Beirut and southern Lebanon. Amira Al Hussaini of Global Voices quotes Abu-Khalil's post, saying "His [Fadlallah's] relationship with Hizbullah is always misunderstood...he broke from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guardianship%20of%20the%20Islamic%20Jurists">Wilayat Al-Faqih</ref>...and developed a new liberal thinking especially on issues of personal status laws." He also "urged for a closer relationship between science and religion", which drew the ire of both <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref> and Hizbullah. </p>
<p>Nasr herself clarified her comment the day before her dismissal on a post to her CNN blog, saying that she used the words "respect" and "sad" because "to me as a Middle Eastern woman, Fadlallah took a contrarian and pioneering stand among <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shia">Shia</ref> clerics on woman's rights. He called for the abolition of the tribal system of '<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Honor_killing">honor killing</ref>.' He called the practice primitive and non-productive. He warned Muslim men that abuse of women was against Islam."</p>
<p>The cleric has been a controversial figure in the West and has been blacklisted by the United States as a terrorist for several years, along with Hizbullah's leader, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hassan%20Nasrallah">Hassan Nasrallah</ref>. He is thought to have been the target of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1985%20Beirut%20car%20bombing">a 1985 car bombing in Beirut</ref>, which killed 80 people but not the Ayatollah himself. The BBC reports it may have been "the work of the CIA, possibly in conjunction with regional intelligence agencies friendly to the US", while David Kenner of <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foreign%20Policy">Foreign Policy</ref></hi> writes that the plot was all but confirmed by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Woodward">Bob Woodward</ref> through interviews with then-CIA Director <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20Casey">William Casey</ref>.</p>
</text>
