<text id="autogum_news_doc706" title="Wikimedian activist Adrianne Wadewitz dies" shortTile="wikimedian-activist" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-04-10" dateModified="2014-04-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedian_activist_Adrianne_Wadewitz_dies" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikimedian activist Adrianne Wadewitz dies</head>
 This article mentions the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia Foundation</ref>, one of its projects, or people related to it. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> is a project of the Wikimedia Foundation.
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 10, 2014</hi></p>
<figure><caption>A video from 2012 where Wadewitz discusses the impact of Wikipedia Image: Vgrigas.</caption></figure>
<p>News broke early this morning on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Facebook">Facebook</ref> that <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikipedia">Wikipedian</ref> Adrianne Wadewitz died while rock climbing recently. Wadewitz was well known in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Foundation">Wikimedia</ref> community for her activism drawing attention to the lack of female contributors on Wikipedia. She was also very involved in the <ref target="https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Wiki%20Education%20Foundation">Wiki Education Foundation</ref>, serving as a member of its board of directors.</p>
<p>Wadewitz was one of the most visible women in the media on the under-representation of women amongst contributors to Wikipedia, talking to media organizations like the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BBC">BBC</ref>, the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huffington%20Post">Huffington Post</ref></hi> and non-English publications like <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LIFO%20(magazine)">Greek-language magazine <hi rend="italic">LIFO</hi></ref>. Some estimates put female participation rates at around 10% of contributors and there is a body of academic work talking about systemic bias against topics featuring women on Wikipedia. </p>
<p>She was involved in organizing several <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/edit-a-thon">edit-a-thons</ref> aimed at encouraging greater female participation and improving content about women, including Wikipedia Takes America: Los Angeles, FemTech Edit-a-thon, Wikipedia Loves Eagle Rock, Wikipedia Loves WeHo, and Feminists Engage Wikipedia. Wadewitz's own work to address systemic bias as an article contributor included improving English Wikipedia articles relating to women, including:</p>
<hi rend="bold">Adrianne embodied brilliance, determination, and enthusiasm in everything she did</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Tribute by a fellow Wikimedian</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary%20Wollstonecraft">Mary Wollstonecraft</ref></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thoughts%20on%20the%20Education%20of%20Daughters">Thoughts on the Education of Daughters</ref></hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary:%20A%20Fiction">Mary: A Fiction</ref></hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A%20Vindication%20of%20the%20Rights%20of%20Woman">A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</ref></hi></item>
<item><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria:%20or,%20The%20Wrongs%20of%20Woman">Maria: or, The Wrongs of Woman</ref></hi></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timeline%20of%20Mary%20Wollstonecraft">Timeline of Mary Wollstonecraft</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fanny%20Imlay">Fanny Imlay</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary%20Shelley">Mary Shelley</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna%20Laetitia%20Barbauld">Anna Laetitia Barbauld</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarah%20Trimmer">Sarah Trimmer</ref></item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary%20Martha%20Sherwood">Mary Martha Sherwood</ref></item></list>
<figure><caption>The funerary arrangement picture decorating the top of Wadewitz's Wikipedia talk page.Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Moeng">Mogens Engelund</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>She started contributing to English Wikipedia in July 2004.  She had taught two classes on collaborative work on the project, and was involved with FemTechNet Wikistorming, an academic effort to encourage more women involved in academia to contribute to Wikipedia.  In the past month, she had written several blog entries on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HASTAC">HASTAC</ref>, an online collaborative platform dedicated to changing the way people learn, about how to write about academics on Wikipedia.</p>
<p>Fellow activist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarah%20Stierch">Sarah Stierch</ref> said in a public post on Facebook, "My heart hurts. Adrianne was a leading voice - and her legacy still is - in the work we have been doing to get more women and more diverse peoples contributing to Wikipedia. Two days ago she was quoted in the BBC, for godsake." Stierch went on to say, "A sarcastic, feminist, smart, brilliant, to the point delivery type of academic genius who held an honest love life for all to see and a life in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Los_Angeles,_California">LA</ref> that was becoming one she owned."</p>
<p>At the time of her death, she was a Mellon Digital Scholarship Fellow at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Occidental%20College">Occidental College</ref>. In 2011, she earned her PhD from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indiana%20University">Indiana University</ref>.</p>
<p>Wikimedians are memorializing her on her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_Talk:Wadewitz">Wikipedia talk page</ref>, which is adorned with a picture of a funerary arrangement of flowers. A notice at the top of the page invites condolences, which have been arriving in their dozens. "This is a crushing loss, for the Wikipedia community and the world. There was no one else like her." wrote one contributor. Another noted "Adrianne embodied brilliance, determination, and enthusiasm in everything she did."</p>
</text>
