<text id="autogum_news_doc058" title="Drought stricken Somalia nears famine" shortTile="drought-stricken" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-07-13" dateModified="2015-11-17" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Drought_stricken_Somalia_nears_famine" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Drought stricken Somalia nears famine</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 15, 2011</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Drought Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/user:Dl91m">Dl91m</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/African_Union">African Union</ref> made a plea on Tuesday for the international community to come to the aid of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Somalia">Somalia</ref>. This is a country where one in three, (ten million people) is suffering from a severe  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/drought">drought</ref>, a situation complicated by warring rebel factions. In 2009, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UNICEF">UNICEF</ref> discontinued air deliveries to areas controlled by the Islamic insurgent group <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al-Shabaab_(Somalia)">al-Shabab</ref> due to militant threats. </p>
<p>Last week al-Shabab said it would welcome the presence of humanitarian groups, provided aid groups did not have a "hidden agenda".</p>
<p>On Wednesday, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations">United Nations</ref> airlifted supplies to a part of the country controlled by al-Shabab, flying five metric tons of medicines, food and water supplies to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baidoa">Baidoa</ref>, a rebel-held  town, 155 miles south of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mogadishu">Mogadishu</ref>. Maulid Warfa,  UNICEF emergency officer, in an interview with state-run <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radio%20Mogadishu">Radio Mogadishu</ref>, said a very critical humanitarian crisis exists in rural communities where people have lost their livestock and farms after the worst drought in six decades. The aid is to help them and their children who are extremely malnourished.</p>
<hi rend="bold"> [Somalia's crisis is] the most severe humanitarian emergency in the world.  </hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UNICEF">UNICEF</ref></p>
<p>When Warfa, was asked  about the arrest of two aid workers by al Shabaab, one with UNICEF, Warfa did not confirm or deny it. Instead he emphasized the desperate need of  Somalians for assistance.</p>
<p>Although some feared a new Kenyan camp would result in more Somalis fleeing to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kenya">Kenya</ref>, Kenya has announced in will open a new refuge camp near the Somalian border within ten days which will hold 80,000. Kenyan Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Raila_Odinga">Raila Odinga</ref> said, "Although we consider our own security, we can't turn away the refugees."</p>
<hi rend="bold">We are no longer talking about a humanitarian crisis or a humanitarian emergency. We are seeing this as a humanitarian catastrophe.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Jens Oppermann, the country director of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Action%20Against%20Hunger">Action Against Hunger</ref></p>
<p>In a nearby refugee camp in Kenya where 370,000 people are squeezed into a space set up for 90,000 people, conditions are desperate aid workers said.</p>
<p>Somalia's Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abdiweli%20Mohamed%20Ali">Abdiweli Mohamed Ali</ref> in an interview with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BBC">BBC</ref> said  a refugee camp has opened  in Mogadishu, but that the government had "meagre" resources to help drought victims. "We are appealing to the international community to take the matter seriously and to act quickly to save as many lives as we can," he told the BBC.</p>
<p>On Thursday, UNICEF said Somalia's drought and refugee crisis is "the most severe humanitarian emergency in the world."</p>
<p>On Friday, Jens Oppermann, the country director of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Action%20Against%20Hunger">Action Against Hunger</ref> (Action Contre La Faim, ACF), told <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Agence_France-Presse">AFP</ref>: "We are no longer talking about a humanitarian crisis or a humanitarian emergency. We are seeing this as a humanitarian catastrophe."</p>
<p>This is the second consecutive year the summer rains have not come, and according to the BBC,  the current drought threatens the lives of at least four million in Somalia. </p>
</text>
