<text id="autogum_news_doc277" title="Bush says US troop build-up in Iraq has brought &apos;hope&apos;" shortTile="bush-troop-buildup" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-12" dateModified="2013-09-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bush_says_US_troop_build-up_in_Iraq_has_brought_%27hope%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bush says US troop build-up in Iraq has brought 'hope'</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 12, 2008</hi> </p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">US</ref> President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref> says the so-called "surge" strategy in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref> is working. </p>
<p>The President was speaking in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kuwait">Kuwait</ref> during one of several stops on a tour of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Middle_East">Middle East</ref> to build support for his administration's efforts to stabilize Iraq and to contain <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref>'s growing influence in the region.</p>
<p>President Bush said the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>' change of strategy in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref> has sharply reduced violence there and should allow the military to withdraw 20,000 troops on schedule by July this year.</p>
<p>After meeting with his top military commander in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref>, General David Petraeus, and U.S. Ambassador to Iraq Ryan Crocker, Mr.Bush told reporters that hope is returning to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baghdad">Baghdad</ref>.</p>
<p>The president said he has made no decision on withdrawing more troops from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref>. He said that will depend on recommendations by General Petraeus, who is due to report to Congress on that issue in March. A day earlier, the president told the NBC television network that U.S. troops could remain in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref> for at least a decade.</p>
<p>Mr. Bush also called on Syria to cut what he called "the flow of terrorists" into <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref>. He accused <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref> of supporting militias and extremist groups in Iraq, and urged it to stop.</p>
<p>Later, the president addressed a crowd of some 1,500 <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/America">American</ref> troops at a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> military base in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kuwait">Kuwait</ref>.</p>
<p>"The history will say, it was when you were called upon, you served, and the service you rendered was absolutely necessary to defeat an enemy overseas so we do not have to face them here at home," he said.</p>
<p>Mr.Bush said the troops were part of what he called "an ideological struggle" against "cold-blooded murderers" with a "hateful vision of a future."</p>
<p>In his speech Bush said "Iraq is now a different place from one year ago," and that "we [Americans] must do all we can to ensure that 2008 will bring even greater progress"</p>
<p>He said the best way to defeat an ideology of hate is with an ideology of hope, based on liberty.</p>
<p>"There is no doubt in my mind that we will succeed," he said. "There is no doubt in my mind when history was written, the final page will say: Victory was achieved by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/USA">United States of America</ref> for the good of the world; that by doing the hard work now, we can look back and say, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/USA">United States of America</ref> is more secure, and generations of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/America">Americans</ref> will be able to live in peace."</p>
<p>Kuwait is the most pro-<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> country in the Arab world, but even so there is deep anxiety there about some U.S. policies in the Middle East. With a large Shi'ite population and a large U.S. troop presence, Kuwait is worried about the possibility of a U.S. military strike on Iran. The emirate has said it will not allow its territory to be used in such an attack. It is also concerned about a spillover of violence from neighboring Iraq.</p>
<p>After Kuwait, the president continues on to Bahrain, headquarters of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> Navy's Fifth Fleet. He will later visit the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Arab_Emirates">United Arab Emirates</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Saudi_Arabia">Saudi Arabia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egypt">Egypt</ref> before returning to Washington next week. </p>
</text>
