<text id="autogum_news_doc197" title="CBS News correspondent Mike Wallace dies at 93" shortTile="cbs-news-correspondent" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-04-08" dateModified="2016-04-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CBS_News_correspondent_Mike_Wallace_dies_at_93" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>CBS News correspondent Mike Wallace dies at 93</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 10, 2012</hi></p>
<p>Retired <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CBS_News">CBS News</ref> television correspondent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mike%20Wallace%20(journalist)">Mike Wallace</ref>, known for his tough interviewing style, died April 7, at Waveny Care Center in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Canaan,%20Connecticut">New Canaan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Connecticut">Connecticut</ref>, surrounded by his family. He was 93 years old.</p>
<figure><caption>Mike Wallace Interviews 1957 Image: Publicity photo, <hi rend="italic">Mike Wallace Interviews</hi>.</caption></figure>
<p>"It is with tremendous sadness that we mark the passing of Mike Wallace. His extraordinary contribution as a broadcaster is immeasurable and he has been a force within the television industry throughout its existence. His loss will be felt by all of us at CBS. All of us at CBS News and particularly at '<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/60_Minutes">60 Minutes</ref>' owe so much to Mike. Without him and his iconic style, there probably wouldn't be a '60 Minutes," said CEO and president of CBS <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leslie%20Moonves">Leslie Moonves</ref>. CBS plans a tribute broadcast in remembrance of Wallace, scheduled to air on April 15.</p>
<hi rend="bold">It is with tremendous sadness that we mark the passing of Mike Wallace</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Leslie Moonves</p>
<p>Wallace interviewed many famous people including former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> president <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20F.%20Kennedy">John F. Kennedy</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin%20Luther%20King%20Jr.">Martin Luther King Jr.</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malcolm%20X">Malcolm X</ref>, former first lady <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nancy%20Reagan">Nancy</ref> and former president <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ronald_Reagan">Ronald Reagan</ref>. He worked for the CBS News magazine show <hi rend="italic">60 Minutes</hi> for almost 40 years and announced he would step down in 2006, and subsequently interviewed for the program sparingly. His last sit down interview which occurred on January 6, 2007 was with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Major_League_Baseball">baseball</ref> star <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger%20Clemens">Roger Clemens</ref>.</p>
<p>Wallace won his 21st <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emmy%20Award">Emmy Award</ref> for his 2006 interview with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iranian</ref> President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mahmoud_Ahmadinejad">Mahmoud Ahmadinejad</ref>; Wallace was 89 years old at the time. Wallace said that interview stuck out to him the most, as well as his interview with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russian</ref>-American classical piano virtuoso <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vladimir%20Horowitz">Vladimir Horowitz</ref>, which he later said was his favorite interview.</p>
<p>Wallace said the interview that most affected him was his documentary on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vietnam%20War">Vietnam War</ref> in 1982. In the report, Wallace said General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20Westmoreland">William Westmoreland</ref> exaggerated enemy casualty figures so Americans would keep supporting the war. Westmoreland sued CBS (<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Westmoreland%20v.%20CBS">Westmoreland v. CBS</ref></hi>) and Wallace for $120 million, and later dropped the lawsuit. The trial pushed Wallace into clinical depression and he admitted in a 2006 <hi rend="italic">60 Minutes</hi> tribute to himself, that he attempted suicide by overdosing. Wallace eventually became a spokesperson for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brain%20&amp;%20Behavior%20Research%20Foundation">Brain &amp; Behavior Research Foundation</ref>, formerly known as the National Alliance for Research on Schizophrenia and Depression. He appeared in a 1998 documentary about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/depression">depression</ref> called "Dead Blue."</p>
<p>Wallace attended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Michigan">University of Michigan</ref>, where he delved into the broadcasting world. He graduated in 1939 and became a communication officer in the U.S. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Navy">Navy</ref> for three years during <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_War_II">World War II</ref>. In the 1940’s and 1950’s Wallace appeared on many television and radio shows doing both news and entertainment broadcasts. </p>
<p>He married a woman he meet at college, Norma Kaphan and they had two boys, Peter and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris%20Wallace%20(journalist)">Christopher</ref>. The couple divorced in 1948. Wallace then married actress <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buff%20Cobb">Buff Cobb</ref> which ended in divorce. He married twice more to Lorraine Perigord for 28 years and then Mary Yates, his current wife, turned widow.</p>
<p>He is survived by his two sons, wife, stepdaughter Pauline Dora and stepson Eames Yates including several grandchildren.</p>
</text>
