<text id="autogum_news_doc673" title="IndyCar driver Justin Wilson dies aged 37" shortTile="indycar-driver-justin" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-08-24" dateModified="2015-08-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/IndyCar_driver_Justin_Wilson_dies_aged_37" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>IndyCar driver Justin Wilson dies aged 37</head>
<figure><caption>Wilson in Toronto in 2007. Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Midgrid">Midgrid</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 25, 2015</hi></p>
<p>Yesterday, 37-year old <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IndyCar%20Series">IndyCar Series</ref> driver <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justin%20Wilson%20(racing%20driver)">Justin Wilson</ref> died of injuries sustained on Sunday during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ABC%20Supply%20500">ABC Supply 500</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pocono%20Raceway">Pocono Raceway</ref>.</p>
<p>With about twenty laps remaining in the race, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sage%20Karam">Sage Karam</ref>, who had been leading the event, crashed into the turn 1 wall. As Wilson approached the site of the crash, reportedly the nose cone from Karam's car that had been airborne struck Wilson in the helmet; Wilson's car steered to the left and collided with the inside <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SAFER%20barrier">SAFER barrier</ref>. The event was placed under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Racing%20flags#Yellow_flag">caution flag</ref> as safety workers extracted Wilson from his car. Wilson was airlifted to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lehigh%20Valley%20Hospital">Lehigh Valley Hospital</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allentown,%20Pennsylvania">Allentown, Pennsylvania</ref>. At 9 P.M. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern%20Standard%20Time%20Zone">EST</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/INDYCAR">INDYCAR</ref> released a statement, announcing that Wilson had suffered a severe head injury, was in critical condition and had fallen into a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/coma">coma</ref>. The following day, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indianapolis%20Motor%20Speedway">Indianapolis Motor Speedway</ref> president Doug Boles and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hulman%20&amp;%20Company">Hulman &amp; Company</ref> Mark Miles officially announced Wilson's death.</p>
<p>Karam was able to walk away from the accident, and was evaluated for a right foot injury; he was released from the hospital the same day. Wilson's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andretti%20Autosport">Andretti Autosport</ref> teammate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ryan%20Hunter-Reay">Ryan Hunter-Reay</ref> won the race, though he did not celebrate upon finding out about Wilson's accident. In Victory Lane, he stated, "My first thoughts are with Justin, for sure[...] He's a friend, a teammate, and it's a bit hard not knowing anything."</p>
<p>Wilson, a former <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Formula_One">Formula One</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Champ%20Car">Champ Car</ref> driver, did not have a ride entering the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2015%20IndyCar%20Series%20season">2015 season</ref>, and joined Andretti on a seven-race deal. The contract had previously been for two races, but after acquiring sponsorship, the deal was increased by five events; earlier in August, Wilson recorded a best finish of second at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mid-Ohio%20Sports%20Car%20Course">Mid-Ohio Sports Car Course</ref>.</p>
<p>The accident led to discussions regarding the safety of the cars. A suggestion had been the addition of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vehicle%20canopy">canopy</ref> over the car's cockpit. The topic had been controversial: while some supported it for safety reasons, others opposed it because of history, possibly affecting the aerodynamics of the car, limiting one's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/peripheral%20vision">peripheral vision</ref> and movement inside the car, and worry about escaping an upside-down or burning car. Another had been to tether the nose cone to the car; Hunter-Reay mentioned renderings developed of a boomerang-like debris-deflector positioned in front of the driver. A further question raised had been regarding Wilson's height: at 6 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/foot%20(unit)">feet</ref>, 3.5 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/inch">inches</ref> (1.92 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/metre">m</ref>) tall, Wilson was the tallest IndyCar Series driver; however, driver <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josef%20Newgarden">Josef Newgarden</ref> refuted the statement, saying, "They make a regulation for how tall you can be inside the car sitting compared to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/roll%20cage">roll hoop</ref> [...] It's safe for any height for any driver that gets in the car."</p>
</text>
