<text id="autogum_news_doc357" title="AirAsia jet vanishes over Indonesia, 162 missing" shortTile="airasia-jet-vanishes" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-12-28" dateModified="2016-12-25" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/AirAsia_jet_vanishes_over_Indonesia%2C_162_missing" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>AirAsia jet vanishes over Indonesia, 162 missing</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, December 28, 2014</hi></p>
<p>An <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indonesia%20AirAsia">Indonesia AirAsia</ref> jet vanished over the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kumai">Kumai</ref> region today. The flight carried 162 people.</p>
<figure><caption>The missing aircraft, photographed in April.Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Sabung.hamster">Oka Sudiatmika</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Among the 155 passengers and seven crew  flying from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Surabaya">Surabaya</ref> to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Singapore">Singapore</ref> are three <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Korea">Koreans</ref>, one <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Malaysia">Malaysian</ref>, and one person variously reported as a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">French</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">UK</ref> national. The rest are Indonesians. There are sixteen children and an infant. The plane was diverting around weather formations over the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Java_Sea">Java Sea</ref> when contact with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/air%20traffic%20control">air traffic control</ref> (ATC) in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jakarta">Jakarta</ref> was lost.</p>
<p>Local <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/search%20and%20rescue">search and rescue</ref> have been told the flight last spoke to controllers at 6:12 local time seeking to climb from 32,000<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/foot%20(unit)">ft</ref> to 38,000ft. The flight vanished from radar at 6:17. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/transponder">transponder</ref> ceased to be received a minute later. ATC issued a series of escalating alerts in response. It was due to enter Singaporean airspace at 6:52 and land by around 8:30.</p>
<p>The Indonesian Navy, police forces, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/National_Search_and_Rescue_Agency">National Search and Rescue Agency</ref> are focusing on an area 20 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/nautical%20miles">nautical miles</ref> from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East%20Belitung">East Belitung</ref>. The plane went missing in the vicinity of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pulau%20Belitung%20Island">Pulau Belitung Island</ref>. A rescue boat with a crew of 22 has been dispatched, with water police providing an additional vessel. The Indonesian Civil Aviation Authority is overseeing the efforts. Searches are presently suspended until morning.</p>
<figure><caption>The flight path of the missing flight.Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:AHeneen">Andrew Heneen</ref>/Natural Earth.</caption></figure>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil%20Aviation%20Authority%20of%20Singapore">Civil Aviation Authority of Singapore</ref> is "ready to provide any assistance to support the search and rescue effort" according to a statement. The Singaporean military has sent two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C-130">C-130</ref> aircraft to assist. The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">Indian</ref> Navy has reportedly placed three ships and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boeing%20P8-1">Boeing P8-1</ref> on standby to help.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref> has also offered assistance. Australian Foreign Minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Julie_Bishop">Julie Bishop</ref> telephoned her Indonesian equivalent, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Retno%20Marsudi">Retno Marsudi</ref>, to offer support. Bishop has also offered Australian assistance to South Korea, Singapore, and Malaysia. Australian Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tony_Abbott">Tony Abbott</ref> contacted Indonesian President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joko%20Widodo">Joko Widodo</ref> to offer sympathies and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P3%20Orion">P3 Orion</ref> plane.</p>
<p>Areas for families and friends have been set up at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Changi_Airport">Changi Airport</ref> where the flight was headed and at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Juanda_International_Airport">Juanda International Airport</ref> where it departed. The airline said in a statement they would "keep all parties informed as more information becomes available" about "the status of the passengers and crew members on board". </p>
<p>"I hope I can get information soon on the whereabouts of our family members," one weeping woman at Juanda told <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antara%20(news%20agency)">Antara</ref></hi>. She said she has four relatives on board and heard about the disappearance from news reports.</p>
<p>The area where the plane vanished around 40 minutes into its trip was experiencing thunderstorms. Some clouds were as high as 50,000ft. The aircraft, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Airbus%20A320-200">Airbus A320-200</ref> registration PK-AXC and serial number 3648, was six years old. It was undertaking flight designation QZ8501 and last underwent maintenance in November. Management company <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doric">Doric</ref> own and lease the aircraft.</p>
<hi rend="bold">I hope I can get information soon on the whereabouts of our family members</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Woman awaiting news at Juanda Airport</p>
<p>Pilot Iriyanto  and co-pilot Remi Emmanuel Plesel have over 8,000 hours experience between them. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Airbus">Airbus</ref> released a statement saying the plane had accumulated 23,000 flying hours on 13,600 flights. The French-based airframer said it would assist investigators. The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bureau_d'Enquêtes_et_d'Analyses">BEA</ref>, which investigates aviation mishaps in France, is liaising with their Indonesian counterparts at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/National_Transportation_Safety_Committee">National Transportation Safety Committee</ref> to provide assistance.</p>
<p>The engines were built by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CFM%20International">CFM International</ref>, a joint enterprise between <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> firm <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/General_Electric">General Electric</ref> and French engineering company <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safran">Safran</ref>. The US connection means the US <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/National_Transportation_Safety_Board">National Transportation Safety Board</ref> (NTSB) can also join the probe.The NTSB says it is ready and willing to assist if required.</p>
<hi rend="bold">Our priority is looking after all the next-of-kin for my staff and passengers</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—AirAsia owner Tony Fernandes</p>
<p>A screenshot apparently leaked from an ATC radar screen shows the flight ascending through 36,000ft with a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ground%20speed">ground speed</ref> of 353<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/knot%20(unit)">knts</ref>. The aircraft would normally be travelling faster, with an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emirates%20(airline)">Emirates</ref> jet also on the screen showing a ground speed of 503knts at 36,000ft.</p>
<p>"My only thought are with the passengers and my crew" said AirAsia boss Tony Fernandes. He said he is heading to Surabaya and thanked Malaysian, Singaporean, and Indonesian authorities for emergency efforts. Fernandes bought AirAsia for a symbolic price from the Malaysian government in 2002. By 2010 it had expanded from two aircraft to 86.</p>
<p>"I am touched by the massive show of support especially from my fellow airlines" said Fernandes. "This is my worst nightmare." He urged staff to "Pray hard. [...] Our priority is looking after all the next-of-kin for my staff and passengers."</p>
<p>Djoko Murjatmodjo, acting head of transportation in Indonesia, said "We don't dare to presume what has happened except that it has lost contact." Singaporean Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lee_Hsien_Loong">Lee Hsien Loong</ref> said he is "saddened" and his "thoughts are with the passengers and their families". <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pope_Francis">Pope Francis</ref> used today's address in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St.%20Peter's%20Square">St. Peter's Square</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Vatican">the Vatican</ref> to say he was praying for the missing. Malaysian Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Najib_Razak">Najib Razak</ref> called the news "Very sad to hear[...] My thoughts are with the families. Malaysia stands ready to help."</p>
<p>The British Embassy in Jakarta has acknowledged reports a UK citizen may be missing. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> has also been briefed. Initial reports claim AirAsia did not include British when listing the nationalities missing, but the UK <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Foreign_and_Commonwealth_Office">Foreign and Commonwealth Office</ref> say a UK victim's next of kin have been informed.</p>
<p>The present version of AirAsia's statement lists a UK passenger and a French crewmember. <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/France24">France24</ref></hi> identifies co-pilot Plesel as French.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/AirAsia">AirAsia</ref> is based in Malaysia. 2014 has been a year of air disasters for the country; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malaysia%20Airlines%20flight%20370">Malaysia Airlines flight 370</ref> has been missing since March with 239 on board and in July <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malaysia%20Airlines%20Flight%2017">Malaysia Airlines Flight 17</ref> was shot down in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukraine</ref> with 298 casualties. Both involved <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boeing%20777">Boeing 777</ref> aircraft.</p>
<p>AirAsia has a good record with no previous major crashes.</p>
AirAsia Emergency Contact Number: +622129850801Juanda Airport: [031] 8690945
This story has updates
See <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/AirAsia_disaster:_Bodies,_wreckage_found">AirAsia disaster: Bodies, wreckage found</ref>, December 30, 2014
</text>
