<text id="autogum_news_doc283" title="Bush pledges support for Turkey after meeting with PM" shortTile="bush-pledges-support" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-11-05" dateModified="2012-11-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bush_pledges_support_for_Turkey_after_meeting_with_PM" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Bush pledges support for Turkey after meeting with PM</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 6, 2007</hi></p>
<p>On Monday, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prime%20Minister%20of%20Turkey">Prime Minister</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Turkey">Turkey</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Recep_Tayyip_Erdoğan">Recep Tayyip Erdoğan</ref> paid an official <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/state%20visit">state visit</ref> to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>. During his visit, he met with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President%20of%20the%20United%20States">President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">George W. Bush</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White%20House">White House</ref> for talks that centered on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkey-PKK%20conflict">Turkey-PKK conflict</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq_War">Iraq War</ref>.</p>
<p>Turkey is concerned about attacks by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurdistan%20Workers%20Party">Kurdistan Workers Party</ref> (PKK) that originate from within the borders of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref>. There have been <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fall%202007%20clashes%20in%20Hakkari">cross-border clashes</ref> between Turkey and the PKK. Turkey has threatened a major incursion, something the US seeks to avoid, as it could upset the relative calm in northern Iraq. The PKK has been listed as a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terrorism">terrorist</ref> organization by a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List%20of%20countries%20and%20organizations%20that%20list%20the%20PKK%20as%20a%20terrorist%20group">number of countries and organizations</ref>. The PKK's goal has been to create an independent <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialism">socialist</ref> Kurdish state in a territory which it claims as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kurdistan">Kurdistan</ref>, an area that comprises parts of south-eastern Turkey, north-eastern Iraq, north-eastern <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syria</ref> and north-western <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref>.</p>
<p>After the meeting, Bush said of the PKK that "they are an enemy of Turkey, they are an enemy of Iraq, and they are an enemy of the United States." He pledged additional <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military%20intelligence">intelligence</ref> to help Turkey, an offer that was also made by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Secretary%20of%20State">Secretary of State</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Condoleezza_Rice">Condoleezza Rice</ref> last week, during her <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Middle_East">Middle East</ref> tour.</p>
“
We talked about the need to have better intelligence-sharing. In order to chase down people who murder people you need good intelligence. And we talked about the need for our military to stay in constant contact. To this end, the Prime Minister and I have set up a tripartite arrangement, for his number two man in the military to stay in touch with our number man and General Petraeus.
”
— George W. Bush
<p>Bush further offered mutual military assistance with both Turkey and Iraq to fight the PKK. "We want to work in a close way to deal with this problem," he said.</p>
<p>Erdogan mentioned during the post-meeting news conference that the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand%20National%20Assembly%20of%20Turkey">Grand National Assembly of Turkey</ref> has already authorized military action in Iraq. He did not, however, say whether such action would be imminent.</p>
“
There is a lot of difficulty in the region in general. And I believe that it falls to us, it's a responsibility for us as strategic partners to work to ensure that we overcome these difficulties and solve them. I have also seen that the President and I agree on these points, and I'm very happy to see that.
”
— Recep Tayyip Erdoğan
<p>Neither leader indicated to what level, if any, that direct military cooperation would exist.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ali%20Babacan">Ali Babacan</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foreign%20minister">Minister of Foreign Affairs</ref> for Turkey, was last week not so impressed by Rice's offers. "We are at the point where words have been exhausted and where there is need for action," he said on Friday.</p>
<p>"The Bush administration would like to just kick this can down the road," said Bulent Aliriza, a political observer for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Center%20for%20Strategic%20and%20International%20Studies">Center for Strategic and International Studies</ref>. "The problem is, the can has been kicked down the road to the point where now it can't be kicked anymore."</p>
</text>
