<text id="autogum_news_doc423" title="India and China to develop friendly relations" shortTile="india-china-develop" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-01-17" dateModified="2015-05-11" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India_and_China_to_develop_friendly_relations" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>India and China to develop friendly relations</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 18, 2012</hi></p>
<figure><caption>India and China. Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Yug">Yug</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">India</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref> planned to resolve boundary disputes peacefully and develop friendly relations with each other in the 15th round of boundary talks begun Monday. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shivshankar%20Menon">Shivshankar Menon</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Security%20Advisor%20(India)">National Security Advisor</ref>, represented India while <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dai%20Bingguo">Dai Bingguo</ref> represented China.</p>
<p>To control the Sino-Indian border effectively, Liu Zhenmin, China's Assistant Foreign Minister, and S. Jaishankar, India's ambassador to China, signed an agreement titled "Working Mechanism for Consultation and Coordination on India-China Border Affairs". The text of the agreement, as released by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ministry%20of%20External%20Affairs%20(India)">Indian Ministry of External Affairs</ref>, states, "[The mechanism will] undertake other tasks that are mutually agreed upon by the two sides but will not discuss resolution of the Boundary Question or affect the Special Representatives Mechanism."</p>
<p>The agreement allows live contact between the countries' foreign offices for problems along the Sino-Indian border, officially called the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Line%20of%20Actual%20Control">Line of Actual Control</ref> (LOAC). Also, meetings are to be held in each of the two countries alternately, once or twice annually. The two sides see the agreement as an important step in gaining trust and strengthening each other.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sino-Indian%20relations">Relations between the two countries</ref> have not been good since the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sino-Indian%20War">Sino-Indian War</ref> of 1962. The relations lapsed in 2011 due to visa rows and exploration of oil in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_China_Sea">South China Sea</ref>. Further, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Dalai_Lama">Dalai Lama</ref>'s refuge in India has caused friction with China. China also claims 90,000 square kilometers of land governed by India in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tibet">Tibetan</ref> region and India claims 38,000 square kilometers of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kashmir">Kashmir</ref> held by China.</p>
<p>Analysts say China is facing both economic problems, and difficulties with neighbouring countries. Its major allies <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_Korea">North Korea</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pakistan">Pakistan</ref> have their own troubles. China maintains unfavorable relations with other neighbours like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vietnam">Vietnam</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref>.</p>
<p>The 'return to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Asia">Asia</ref>' strategy of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> focuses on China, and India figures in it as an important ally.</p>
<p>Dai wrote in a newspaper column, "What we face is a golden period to grow China-India relations. The world has enough space for China and India to achieve common development, as there are so many areas for us to work together". He further added during the session, "While working hard to develop itself, China is fully committed to developing long-term friendship and cooperation with India."</p>
<p>Dai claimed trade between the two countries has increased by a factor of 20 in the last ten years. He summarized, "As neighbors and two big countries with a combined population of 2.5 billion, China and India can join hands, seize the historic opportunity, and work together to further advance our friendship and cooperation".</p>
<p>The boundary talks were to be held in November, but were postponed over Chinese disapproval of India allowing the Dalai Lama into a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Buddhism">Buddhist</ref> meet in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Delhi">New Delhi</ref>.</p>
</text>
