<text id="autogum_news_doc644" title="Canada to legalise marijuana to &apos;make it more difficult for kids to access&apos;" shortTile="canada-legalise-marijuana" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-04-14" dateModified="2019-08-07" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada_to_legalise_marijuana_to_%27make_it_more_difficult_for_kids_to_access%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Canada to legalise marijuana to 'make it more difficult for kids to access'</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, April 16, 2017</hi></p>
<p>In order to put the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cannabis">cannabis</ref> drug (marijuana) out of reach of minors, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canadian</ref> federal government announced a bill to legalise cannabis for the age group of eighteen and above, on Thursday. The bill would allow adults to possess cannabis publicly, previously a criminal offence.</p>
<p>Canada's health minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jane%20Philpott">Jane Philpott</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">tweeted</ref>, "Today we tabled new legislation to legalise, strictly regulate, and restrict access to cannabis. Our goal: keep it out of the hands of youth, and profits out of the hands of criminals." ((fr))French language: ‍Ajd nous avons déposé un nouveau projet de loi pour légaliser le cannabis, le réglementer de manière stricte et en restreindre l'accès. Notre objectif: garder le cannabis hors de la portée des jeunes, &amp; les profits hors des mains des criminels. The Canadian government, via their official website, explained cannabis is available illegally, and their measures to stop it did not work. Criminal organisations are making money selling cannabis. Under-aged people can obtain the drug easily; they said, "it is easier for our kids to buy cannabis than cigarettes."</p>
<p>The bill allows provinces and territories to set the age limit above eighteen. In order to prevent criminal gangs from making a profit, selling the drug needs a license permitting its sale. Adults can purchase the drug online from a licensed producer if a retail shop is not available in the province.</p>
<p>Adults can carry up to 30<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/gram">g</ref> (slightly over an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ounce">ounce</ref>) of cannabis and grow at most four cannabis plants at home, for personal use. The plants should be no taller than a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/metre">metre</ref>, the bill proposed. Selling cannabis to minors would be a specific criminal offence.</p>
<p>The legislation requires parliamentary approval and royal assent. If passed, the bill would be under effect by July 2018, the government said. Health and safety experts and law enforcement were consulted before proposing the legislation. Except for medical purposes, possession of the drug remains illegal until the bill is passed. Regardless of the status of the bill, import and export of the drug would be illegal. </p>
<p>Previously when the government increased the taxes on cigarettes to discourage citizens from smoking, a black market for cigarettes developed.</p>
<p>Along with legalising cannabis, the bill would also permit the police officials to use tools like oral fluid drug screeners to detect if drivers are under the influence of the drug. Zero tolerance against drivers under influence of drugs is proposed. The government would also implement a public awareness campaign on the perils of driving under the influence of drugs.</p>
<p>The government still working on the restrictions. Lawmaker and former police chief Bill Blair said, "We do accept that more important work remains to be done." If the bill is passed, Canada would be the second country to legalise cannabis completely. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Uruguay">Uruguay</ref> is the first. Some countries, such as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref>, allow medical use of cannabis, but recreational use is prohibited.</p>
</text>
