<text id="autogum_news_doc582" title="Scottish politician David McLetchie dies at age 61" shortTile="scottish-politician" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-08-12" dateModified="2013-08-31" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scottish_politician_David_McLetchie_dies_at_age_61" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Scottish politician David McLetchie dies at age 61</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 12, 2013</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20McLetchie">David McLetchie</ref>, a former leader of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scotland">Scottish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scottish_Conservative_Party">Conservatives</ref>, died today in a hospice in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref> whilst suffering cancer. He was 61.</p>
<figure><caption>Official parliamentary portrait of David McLetchie, from 2011. Image: Scottish Parliament.</caption></figure>
<p>In 1997, a general election produced no Conservative Members of Parliament from within Scotland for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">UK</ref>'s joint parliament in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref>. McLetchie took over the Scottish Conservatives the following year and in 1999 eighteen Conservatives were <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish%20Parliament%20general%20election,%201999">elected</ref> to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History%20of%20Scottish%20devolution">newly-formed</ref> devolved <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scottish_Parliament">Scottish Parliament</ref>.</p>
<p>UK <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Prime_Minister_of_the_United_Kingdom">Prime Minister</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/David_Cameron">David Cameron</ref> said today "when devolution came, [McLetchie] picked up the reins and made sure that the Scottish Conservatives had a strong voice". Cameron also called McLetchie "one of Scottish politics' most formidable intellects and finest debaters. All he did was carried out with dedication and conviction, and his passing leaves a gap in the lives of all who knew him." The Prime Minister said he is "deeply saddened" by the news.</p>
<p>McLetchie lead the party in Scotland for seven years before quitting in 2005 amidst a row regarding expenses claims. He continued to serve as an MSP for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lothian">Lothian</ref> area until his death. Born in Edinburgh in 1952, he remained there for his school and university education and became a solicitor specialising in inheritance tax before turning to politics, first running for office in 1979.</p>
<p>Current Scottish Conservative leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruth%20Davidson">Ruth Davidson</ref> said "First and foremost my deepest condolences go to his wife Sheila and their family. David had so much left to give and it is difficult to describe just what his loss at such a relatively young age means to all who knew him." She said he "had friends in every political party and he was often the fulcrum of some of the most unusual alliances in order to improve, force or block a piece of legislation."</p>
<p>Outside of the Conservative party, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scottish_Labour_Party">Scottish Labour</ref> leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann%20Lamont">Johann Lamont</ref> spoke of McLetchie's "passion, drive and determination", noting his ongoing parliamentary work despite ill health. She called his death "a huge loss to the Scottish Parliament". <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scottish_Liberal_Democrats">Scottish Liberal Democrat</ref> leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Willie%20Rennie">Willie Rennie</ref> spoke of a "towering figure in this new Scottish parliamentary age... who made a difference" and "commanded immediate respect and trust from friend and foe alike."</p>
<p>Scottish First Minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Alex_Salmond">Alex Salmond</ref> called the late politician "an extremely effective leader of the Conservative group in the first Parliament, allowing it to punch politically well above its actual numbers".</p>
<p>McLetchie played golf and followed football and rugby, supporting <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heart%20of%20Midlothian%20F.C.">Hearts</ref>. He has a son from a previous marriage, two stepchildren, and four grandchildren. He put his switch from law to politics down to "a combination of a mid-life career change and a mid-life crisis...  I wanted the challenge of representing the Conservative Party in a parliament which was an ambition I had harboured since my teens, but which I had not been able to put into effect in the preceding 20 years because of career and family commitments." </p>
</text>
