<text id="autogum_news_doc454" title="English court jails policeman over insurance fraud" shortTile="english-court-jails" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-06-30" dateModified="2019-01-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/English_court_jails_policeman_over_insurance_fraud" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>English court jails policeman over insurance fraud</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 1, 2010</hi></p>
<p>A court in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">UK</ref> has jailed a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/police">policeman</ref> for ten months after he was convicted of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fraud">defrauding</ref> his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/car%20insurance">car insurance</ref> company. </p>
<p>Police Constable Simon Hood, 43, arranged for a friend who dealt in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scrap_metal">scrap metal</ref> to dispose of his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Audi%20TT">Audi TT</ref>, then claimed it had been stolen.</p>
<p>Hood had been disappointed with the car's value when he tried to sell it two years after its purchase in 2008. He arranged for friend Peter Marsh, 41, to drive the vehicle to his scrapyard in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great%20Yarmouth">Great Yarmouth</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Norfolk">Norfolk</ref>. Marsh then dismantled the vehicle with the intent of disposing of it, but parts were later found wrapped in bubblewrap at Ace Tyre and Exhaust Centre.</p>
<figure><caption>Audi TT Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/user:IFCAR">IFCAR</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Marsh picked up the TT from outside nearby <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gorleston">Gorleston</ref> police station. Records show <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/mobile%20phone">mobile phone</ref> conversations between the conspirators that day in March, both before and after the vehicle was reported stolen. The pair denied wrongdoing but were convicted of conspiring to commit insurance fraud after trial.</p>
<p>The fraud was uncovered after Hood told former girlfriend Suzanne Coates of the scheme. It was alleged before Norwich Crown Court that he had confessed to her in an effort to resume their relationship. Coates said that after the pseudotheft, Hood told her "he didn't want to look for it. He said it would be like looking for a needle in a haystack, which I thought was a bit strange." </p>
<hi rend="bold">You knew throughout your career that policemen that get involved in serious dishonesty get sent to prison</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Judge Alasdair Darroch</p>
<p>Shortly afterwards Hood suggested they should become a couple once more, she said; she challenged his version of events regarding the car: "He said he did it but I couldn't tell anyone. He said he did it with Peter. Peter had a key and took the car away and it was going to be taken to bits and got rid of so it was never found."</p>
<p>Hood was defended by Michael Clare and Marsh by Richard Potts. Both lawyers told the court that their clients had already suffered as a result of the action in mitigation before sentencing. Clare said Hood had resigned from the police after fifteen years of otherwise good service and risked losing his pension. "It is not a case where his position as a police officer was used in order to facilitate the fraud," he pointed out. "His career is in ruins." Hood is now pursuing a career in plumbing.</p>
<p>Potts defended Marsh by saying that he, too, had already suffered from his actions. His own insurers are refusing to renew their contract with him when it expires and his bank withdrew its overdraft facility. His business employs 21 people and Potts cited Marsh's sponsorship of Great Yarmouth In Bloom as amongst evidence he supported his local community. </p>
<p>Judge Alasdair Darroch told Marsh that he did accept the man was attempting to help his friend. He sentenced Marsh to six months imprisonment, suspended for two years and ordered to carry out 250 hours of community service. He was more critical of Hood:</p>
<p>"As a police officer you know the highest possible standards are demanded by the public. You have let down the force. You knew throughout your career that policemen that get involved in serious dishonesty get sent to prison."</p>
</text>
