<text id="autogum_news_doc165" title="Yemen requests reevaluation of U.S. ground operations on its soil following raid" shortTile="yemen-requests-reevaluation" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-02-08" dateModified="2017-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Yemen_requests_reevaluation_of_U.S._ground_operations_on_its_soil_following_raid" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Yemen requests reevaluation of U.S. ground operations on its soil following raid</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 11, 2017</hi></p>
<p>The official government of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Yemen">Yemen</ref> issued a statement on Wednesday requesting a reevaluation the role of the United States in antiterrorism ground operations on its soil, in response to a January 29 raid by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SEAL%20Team%20Six">SEAL Team Six</ref> that killed several Yemeni citizens.</p>
<p>An earlier report alleged Yemeni officials told the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Executive%20Office%20of%20the%20President%20of%20the%20United%20States">White House</ref> their government had withdrawn its permission for U.S. ground ops, but later Yemeni statements have asked for a "reassessment" of the role of the U.S. in local antiterrorist activities. "We have not withdrawn our permission for the United States to carry out special operations ground missions. However, we made clear our reservations about the last operation," one Yemeni official told <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Reuters">Reuters</ref></hi> of a meeting between the U.S. ambassador and Yemeni President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abd%20Rabbu%20Mansour%20Hadi">Abd Rabbu Mansour Hadi</ref>.</p>
<p>The Yemeni government's remarks stressed consultation before operations. Wednesday's official government statement from the Yemeni embassy in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington,_D.C.">Washington, D.C.</ref> read: "The government of Yemen reiterates its firm position that any counter-terrorism operations carried out in Yemen should continue to be in consultation with Yemeni Authorities and have precautionary measures to prevent civilian casualties. Yemen believes that terrorism is a global menace that has no borders, religion or nationality; one that only a collective and well-coordinated response can address."</p>
<p>"Currently, we have not been ordered to stop conducting any operations nor have been directed to halt any operational planning," said Major Josh Jaques, a spokesperson for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Central%20Command">U.S. Central Command</ref> responsible for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Middle_East">Middle East</ref>.</p>
<p>Although there have been many U.S. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/unmanned%20combat%20aerial%20vehicle">drone</ref> strikes in Yemen in the past few years, the U.S. has publicly acknowledged only one previous ground raid. Last month's operation was approved by U.S. President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref> after planning under his predecessor <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">President Obama</ref>. According to CBS, the SEAL team approached an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al-Qaeda">Al-Qaeda</ref> compound in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al%20Bayda%20Governorate">Bayda province</ref> but became pinned down and called in an <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/air%20strike">air strike</ref> for assistance.  Fatalities included U.S. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Navy%20SEAL">Navy SEAL</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William%20Owens%20(Navy%20SEAL)">William Owens</ref>. According to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Pentagon">Pentagon</ref>, the raid killed more than a dozen members of Al-Qaeda, and, according to medics on the scene, several civilians. These included amongst others, accordingly to various reports, a three-month-old baby, a pregnant woman, and an eight-year-old girl whose U.S.-born <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Anwar_al-Awlaki">father</ref> was a religious leader killed in 2011 after allegedly organizing attacks against the U.S. A <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US$">US$</ref>72 million <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/medevac">medevac</ref> (medical evacuation) aircraft was also destroyed. One U.S. military official remarked, "almost everything went wrong."</p>
<p>"It was highly successful. It achieved the purpose it was going to get, [save] the loss of life that we suffered and the injuries that occurred," announced White House Press Secretary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sean%20Spicer">Sean Spicer</ref>.</p>
<p>US officials said the goal of the raid was to gather intelligence — reportedly, laptops and other electronics that might contain useful intelligence about Al-Qaeda.  One U.S. military official said the raid also targeted Al-Qaeda leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qasim%20al-Raymi">Qassim al-Rimi</ref>.</p>
<p>Yemen is in the second year of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yemeni%20Civil%20War%20(2015–present)">civil war</ref> between <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Houthis">Houthi</ref> rebels and its internationally recognized government, which made the statement on Wednesday.  Extremist groups have used the war to establish Yemeni strongholds.  Yemen is also one of the seven <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Muslim">Muslim</ref>-majority nations named in President Trump's January 27 executive order forbidding travel to the United States.</p>
<p>In another political complication, the raid killed an Al-Qaeda commander <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abdulraoof%20al-Dhahab">Abdulraoof al-Dhahab</ref>, a Yemeni government ally against the Houthi.  "It was wrong to kill him and the children [...] he fought the Houthis and did not have any thought of launching attacks abroad. If the government allowed this to happen, it was a mistake," said one al-Bayda tribal leader.</p>
</text>
