<text id="autogum_news_doc800" title="Peruvians sue Newmont Mining Company over mercury poisoning" shortTile="peruvians-sue-newmont" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2005-03-08" dateModified="2019-10-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Peruvians_sue_Newmont_Mining_Company_over_mercury_poisoning" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Peruvians sue Newmont Mining Company over mercury poisoning</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 8, 2005</hi></p>
<p>Peruvians living near the site of a release of mercury are preparing to sue a U.S. mining company, announcing last Saturday that they will bring their case before a Denver judge.</p>
<p>On <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/June%202">June 2</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2000">2000</ref>, a serious accident in the province of Cajamarca, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peru">Peru</ref>, poisoned many residents with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/mercury%20(element)">mercury</ref>, a highly toxic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/heavy%20metals">heavy metal</ref>. A truck from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newmont%20Mining">Newmont Mining Company</ref> dumped two metal canisters of mercury along an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andean">Andean</ref> highway, in the communities of San Juan, Choropampa, and Magdalena. Curious townspeople (mostly children) picked up the silvery droplets, and some even drank some of it. Many residents became sick from severe mercury poisoning. Some of those who came in contact with the mercury suffered <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/blindness">blindness</ref>, and one even had a purplish <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/rash">rash</ref> on her body.</p>
<p>Over 300 people directly suffered the effects of mercury poisoning.</p>
<p>As the owners of the Yanacocha mine which produced the mercury, Newmont Mining offered up to US$6 thousand to more than 700 local residents, but over 1,100 others are still engaged in a legal battle with Newmont over the case.</p>
<p>In today's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/globalization">global economy</ref>, many international businesses have looked overseas to maintain their profits, but environmental law professor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20Otto">James Otto</ref> is asking about the cost to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/environmentalism">environment</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/public%20health">public health</ref>. "Any company that wants to mine internationally now must not only have the legal right to mine but also a 'social license' to operate," he said. "Peru has been a wake-up call."</p>
<p>As the Peruvian residents gear up for their lawsuit against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denver">Denver</ref>-based Newmont Mining, the world's largest gold mining firm, some of these important questions may finally be answered. After the breakdown of mediation talks with Newmont on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/January%2020">January 20</ref>, the residents and their lawyer decided to stop negotiating behind closed doors and take their case to the public. Last Saturday, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/March%205">March 5</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2005">2005</ref>, they announced that they are bringing their suit before Denver District Judge <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Judge%20Robert%20Hyatt">Robert Hyatt</ref>. "If successful," states <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ken%20Krowder">Ken Krowder</ref> who represents the plaintiffs, "[this] would mark the first time an American firm is held accountable for environmental damages overseas."</p>
<p>This is not the first time Newmont Mining has had trouble with an emerging <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Third%20World">Third World</ref> environmental movement. Recently, in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/August%202004">August 2004</ref>, a US$543 million lawsuit was filed against Newmont Mining by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indonesia">Indonesian</ref> Environmental Ministry and local villagers. They claim that pollution caused by the company’s mining activities has caused serious illnesses and other health problems, including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/skin%20disease">skin disease</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/tumor">tumors</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/birth%20defect">birth defects</ref>, and a decline in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/fish">fish</ref> stocks, a staple food. One particular mining practice used frequently by Newmont Mining in Indonesia is submarine tailings disposal, a waste disposal method for mercury and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/arsenic">arsenic</ref> that is outlawed in the United States.</p>
<p>At least six Newmont Mining managers, including an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American">American</ref> and an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australian">Australian</ref>, face up to 15 years in a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jakarta">Jakarta</ref> prison for environmental and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/corporate%20crime">corporate crime</ref> in that case.</p>
<p>The local Peruvian residents are continuing their fight for safer mining practices and compensation for existing damage and injuries. Thousands of local townspeople protested against the Yanacocha mine last fall, demanding protection for the local water supply.</p>
<p>Newmont Mining officials have blamed the June 2000 mercury spill on a contractor, and have lost the battle to keep the case out of the American court system.</p>
</text>
