<text id="autogum_news_doc475" title="Football: Manchester United defeat AC Milan in Champions League" shortTile="football-manchester" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-04-24" dateModified="2019-08-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Football%3A_Manchester_United_defeat_AC_Milan_in_Champions_League" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Football: Manchester United defeat AC Milan in Champions League</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 24, 2007</hi></p>
<p>A stoppage time goal by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wayne_Rooney">Wayne Rooney</ref> lifted <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Manchester_United">Manchester United</ref> to a 3-2 win over <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/AC_Milan">AC Milan</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old%20Trafford">Old Trafford</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Manchester">Manchester</ref>.  United have never defeated Milan over two legs, having lost twice to them in semi-finals, and once in the round of sixteen previously.  With injuries mounting for United, they were forced to play an extremely altered back line, with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%20O'Shea">John O'Shea</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabriel%20Heinze">Gabriel Heinze</ref> in the centre of defense.  Milan had a boost before the match as keeper <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nelson%20Dida">Nelson Dida</ref> proved fit enough to play.  United opted for only one striker in Wayne Rooney, while Milan did the same fielding <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alberto%20Gilardino">Alberto Gilardino</ref>.  The game also featured two of the best young midfielders in the world currently, with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cristiano_Ronaldo">Cristiano Ronaldo</ref> for United and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ricardo%20Kaka">Kaka</ref> for AC Milan.</p>
<p>Manchester had a dream start to the match when Ronaldo opened the scoring after only five minutes.  Dida was caught out of net as Ronaldo headed towards goal, and after slapping twice at the ball, it eventually found its way into the net.  United, and Ronaldo in particular, continued to threaten the Milan goal, but the next chance fell to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael%20Carrick">Michael Carrick</ref> whos stinging shot was saved well by Dida.  Milan then equalized through a high qualty goal from Kaka. Kaka as he received a through ball from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clarence%20Seedorf">Seedorf</ref>, and the Brazilian sprinted past the defense and slid the ball past <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edwin%20van%20der%20Sar">Van Der Sar</ref>.  United continued to threaten, but nothing came of chances for both <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ryan%20Giggs">Giggs</ref> and Rooney.  A curling shot by Ronaldo almost fooled Dida, but he managed to palm it away.  Kaka then had a solo effort to lift Milan into the lead, as he managed to beat out three defenders, two of which collided with each other, and curl the ball past Van Der Sar.  Milan continued to pressure and Kaka nearly had a hat-trick off a 30-yard drive, but Van Der Sar saved well.  </p>
<p>United started brightly in the second half, clearly not wanting a home loss in the Champions League, and Carrick should have done better as he volleyed wide off a corner from Giggs.  Kaka continued to threaten for Milan, but could not get his attempts on target.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul%20Scholes">Paul Scholes</ref> then played a cheeky scooped ball into Rooney within the box, and after controlling it on his chest, the Englishman slid the ball under Dida to tie the match.  United pushed for the winning goal, and they eventually earned it in stoppage time as a through ball by Giggs found Rooney, and his first time strike flew past an out of position Dida to earn Rooney the brace, and give United the advantage for the second leg.</p>
<p>Milans next match comes this Saturday against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torino%20F.C.">Torino</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Serie_A">Seria A</ref> as they try to clinch a Champions League berth for next season, while United take on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Everton_F.C.">Everton</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goodison%20Park">Goodison Park</ref>, as they are in a tight race with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chelsea_F.C.">Chelsea</ref> for the Premier League title.  The second leg between the two will take place on May 2 at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stadio%20Giuseppe%20Meazza">Stadio Giuseppe Meazza</ref> in Milan.</p>
</text>
