<text id="autogum_news_doc235" title="Waves of arrests in Turkey on suspicion of involvement in &apos;Ergenekon&apos; organization" shortTile="waves-arrests-turkey" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-01-11" dateModified="2016-03-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Waves_of_arrests_in_Turkey_on_suspicion_of_involvement_in_%27Ergenekon%27_organization" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Waves of arrests in Turkey on suspicion of involvement in 'Ergenekon' organization</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, January 11, 2009</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Turkey">Turkish</ref> police arrested two colonels and two lieutenants Saturday as part of a wide-reaching probe into a suspected coup plot. The arrests are the latest related to an alleged clandestine neonationalist organization referred to as "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ergenekon%20(organization)">Ergenekon</ref>". The Ergenekon case has had adverse effects on financial markets in Turkey, a candidate for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Union">European Union</ref>.</p>
<p>Turkey's state-run news service, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anadolu%20Agency">Anatolian News</ref>, reported that the four Turkish army officers were arrested in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Istanbul">Istanbul</ref> for alleged ties to a right-wing group suspected of conspiring to overthrow the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Justice%20and%20Development%20Party%20(Turkey)">AK Party government</ref>. 40 people were detained on Wednesday, including three retired army generals. </p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recep%20Tayyip%20Erdoğan">Recep Tayyip Erdoğan</ref> Image: <ref target="http://www.flickr.com/photos/15237218@N00/345600353/">World Economic Forum</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recep%20Tayyip%20Erdoğan">Recep Tayyip Erdoğan</ref> and General <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ilker%20Basbug">Ilker Basbug</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief%20of%20the%20General%20Staff%20(Turkey)">Chief of the General Staff</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkish%20Armed%20Forces">Turkish Armed Forces</ref>, held crisis talks on Thursday to discuss the recent waves of arrests. General Basbug met with the prime minister after a six-hour meeting with military commanders, including members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gendarmerie%20(Turkey)">Gendarmerie</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkish%20Air%20Force">Turkish Air Force</ref>, and Army. After his meeting with the prime minister, General Basbug met with President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abdullah%20Gul">Abdullah Gul</ref>. President Abdullah Gul met with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Besir%20Atalay">Besir Atalay</ref>, Turkey's interior minister.</p>
<p>The talks between Erdogan and Basbug prompted a spate of selling on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Istanbul%20Stock%20Exchange">Istanbul Stock Exchange</ref>, which fell by six percent on Thursday. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkish%20Industrialists'%20and%20Businessmen's%20Association">TUSIAD</ref>, the main business association in Turkey, voiced its hope that investigators respect the legal rights of the suspects.</p>
<p>Turkish media also reported Saturday that law enforcement officials found ammunition and grenades buried near <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gölbaşı%20lake,%20Adıyaman">Golbasi lake</ref> outside <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ankara">Ankara</ref>, supposedly related to the Ergenekon organization. According to the Turkish media reports, police found a drawing in the home of former police chief Ibrahim Sahin, which led them to the site. Ibrahim Sahin was among the 40 individuals arrested Wednesday.</p>
<hi rend="bold">This is a regime change, like in the Khomeini and Hitler eras.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deniz%20Baykal">Deniz Baykal</ref>, leader of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20People's%20Party%20(Turkey)">Republican People's Party</ref></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deniz%20Baykal">Deniz Baykal</ref>, who heads Turkey's secular chief opposition party the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican%20People's%20Party%20(Turkey)">Republican People's Party</ref>, was critical of the arrests made by police under the AK Party government. "We are witnessing a confrontation against the Republic's core values. This is a regime change, like in the Khomeini and Hitler eras," said Baykal at a news conference held Wednesday. According to Baykal, the Ergenekon investigation is an attempt by the government to silence opposition. Other members of the opposition have also criticized the investigation as being politically motivated.</p>
<p>In a statement published in the Turkish newspaper <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hürriyet">Hürriyet</ref></hi>, Justice Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mehmet%20Ali%20Şahin">Mehmet Ali Şahin</ref> asserted that the Ergenekon investigation is judicial and appropriate. "The investigation has no political aspects. Detentions are purely juridical. I follow developments from the press," said Şahin.</p>
<hi rend="bold">I am terrified here - anytime the wind is not in favor of the ruling party a new wave of this crap happens.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Resident of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Turkey">Turkey</ref>, college graduate</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> interviewed a college graduate and resident of Turkey who wished not to be named, and this individual shared thoughts on the effects of the Ergenekon investigation on local citizens. "It affected everyone in the country. Everyone wonders if they are next," said the source. "I am terrified here - anytime the wind is not in favor of the ruling party a new wave of this crap happens."</p>
<p>Members of the Turkish state bureaucracy, military, and judicial system make up the country's secularist establishment. According to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reuters">Reuters</ref></hi>, this secularist establishment states that the arrests carried out by the AK Party are retaliatory, in response to a 2008 court case. The court case attempted to ban the AK Party, which has roots in political Islam, for anti-secular activities. The AK Party has denied these claims.</p>
<hi rend="bold">The risk of a reaction by the military is growing as the Ergenekon probe is turning into a test of strength between the AKP and secularist circles.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Wolfango Piccoli, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurasia%20Group">Eurasia Group</ref></p>
<p>"The risk of a reaction by the military is growing as the Ergenekon probe is turning into a test of strength between the AKP and secularist circles," said analyst Wolfango Piccoli of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurasia%20Group">Eurasia Group</ref> in a statement published in the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Financial%20Times">Financial Times</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>The investigation by the government began in June 2007, when officials discovered a cache of arms in Istanbul in the home of a retired military officer. According to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Guardian">The Guardian</ref></hi>, in total approximately 200 people have been arrested in relation to the investigation. 86 individuals have been indicted since the investigation started, including many officials from the military and two retired four-star generals. In addition to military officials, the investigation has focused on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Journalism">journalists</ref>, writers, politicians and leaders of gangs. The murder of journalist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hrant%20Dink">Hrant Dink</ref> is sometimes cited as possibly linked to the Ergenekon case.</p>
<p>The indictments allege involvement in plans to increase instability in the country through political assassinations. <hi rend="italic">Hürriyet</hi> reported that the Ergenekon investigation has faced criticism in the past for detaining suspects for extended periods of time in prison without charges, and for its reliance on insubstantial evidence. In the past 50 years, the country's military has intervened to topple four governments in Turkey.</p>
</text>
