<text id="autogum_news_doc440" title="Chinese political dissident Hu Jia freed as Chinese Premier Wen visits Britain" shortTile="chinese-political" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-06-27" dateModified="2015-09-09" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chinese_political_dissident_Hu_Jia_freed_as_Chinese_Premier_Wen_visits_Britain" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Chinese political dissident Hu Jia freed as Chinese Premier Wen visits Britain</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 28, 2011</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Hu Jia Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Stevenliuyi">Stevenliuyi</ref>.<hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Hu_Jia_12apr10_300.jpg">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=File%3AHu+Jia+12apr10+300.jpg">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/People's_Republic_of_China">Chinese government</ref> released human rights activist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hu%20Jia%20(activist)">Hu Jia</ref> from prison on Sunday after he had served over three years for subversion. His release, which had been scheduled in advance, occurred just days after controversial artist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ai%20Weiwei">Ai Weiwei</ref> was unexpectedly released on bail after three months of detention. </p>
<p>Hu was released on the same day that Chinese Premier <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wen%20Jiabao">Wen Jiabao</ref>  began his visit to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">Britain</ref>, the first country  on his three-nation Europe trade tour.</p>
<p>Described by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irish%20Times">Irish Times</ref> as a "mild-mannered, slight figure who suffers from liver ailments", the 37-year-old Hu is  a prominent Chinese dissident who had  spent years campaigning for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese%20democracy%20movement">civil liberties</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/environmentalism">environmentalism</ref>, and on behalf of suffers of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HIV/AIDS%20in%20the%20People's%20Republic%20of%20China">HIV/AIDS</ref> before his imprisonment. He was imprisoned in April 2008 for "inciting to subvert state power" by writing articles about human rights in the period before the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2008_Summer_Olympics">2008 Olympic Games</ref>. He had also given many interviews to foreign news media and government embassies. He was first  detained in December 2007 and his arrest came after he had spent more than 200 days under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/house%20arrest">house arrest</ref>. In 2008 while in prison, he won the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sakharov%20Prize">Sakharov Prize</ref> for freedom of thought,  awarded by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Parliament">European Parliament</ref>. </p>
<p>Hu's wife Zeng Jinyuan  said via <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Twitter</ref> that her husband lost his political rights upon his release and cannot speak to the media for a period of one year.  </p>
<hi rend="bold">(My parents) have told me to just be a normal citizen and don't confront the system because this system is very cruel, using the country's absolute power to violate people's dignity without restraint. But I can only tell my parents I will be careful.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Hu Jia, human rights activist</p>
<p>Hu was briefly interviewed on Sunday via telephone by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cable%20TV%20Hong%20Kong">Hong Kong's Cable TV</ref>, and indicated that despite the danger, he would not give up his work. "(My parents) have told me to just be a normal citizen and don't confront the system because this system is very cruel, using the country's absolute power to violate people's dignity without restraint. But I can only tell my parents I will be careful", he said.</p>
<p>Although  recent releases of high-profile dissidents such as Hu and Ai may seem to some that China is loosening its repressive policies against dissidents, activists and academics said yesterday that the determination of the Chinese government to silence dissent has not lessened and those speaking up continue to be rounded up and detained. </p>
<p>Huang Qi, a dissident released this month from prison and  interviewed by telephone, said, "We closely follow dozens of rights' defense cases, and I've found that that at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/grassroots">grassroots</ref> and lowest levels of society in China, the rights defense environment has not seen any fundamental improvements." He warned, "One cannot count how many ordinary people are being locked up or taken away every day."</p>
<p>However, Wan Yanhau who is a  Chinese activist living in the US said  there might be a short term diminishing of the crackdowns on human rights activists. He suggested  the government could be realizing that the harsh treatment of dissidents has not stopped recent episodes of unrest. The riots by migrant workers in the  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Guangdong">Guangdong</ref> province and protests by ethnic <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mongolians">Mongolians</ref> are recent examples. Further, China is receiving harsh criticism from European countries with which it wants to increase trade.</p>
<p>But illegal detentions are increasing, according to  Nicholas Bequelin of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Human_Rights_Watch">Human Rights Watch</ref>, and are signs that China is not moving toward compliance with international norms. </p>
<head id="Related_articles">Related articles</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>"<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chinese_premier_Wen_Jiabao_visits_Shakespeare's_birthplace">Chinese premier Wen Jiabao visits Shakespeare's birthplace</ref>" — <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Main_Page">Wikinews</ref></hi>, June 27, 2011</item></list>
</text>
