<text id="autogum_news_doc368" title="Wheelchair curling enters third day at 2014 Winter Paralympics" shortTile="wheelchair-curling" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-03-10" dateModified="2015-01-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wheelchair_curling_enters_third_day_at_2014_Winter_Paralympics" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wheelchair curling enters third day at 2014 Winter Paralympics</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 10, 2014</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wheelchair_curling">Wheelchair curling</ref> continued today at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ice%20Cube%20Curling%20Center">Ice Cube Curling Center</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2014_Winter_Paralympics">2014 Winter Paralympics</ref> on difficult playing conditions as a result of the warm temperature outside.  In the morning session, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/South_Korea">South Korea</ref> lost to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref> in the eighth end by a score of 5–7, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> lost to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref> 2–7 in seven ends, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Norway">Norway</ref> edged out <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Finland">Finland</ref> 6–8 in extra ends, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref> defeated <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref> 8–4 in seven ends.  </p>
<p>At the conclusion of the morning session, round robin standing had Canada in first with 4 wins; <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Slovakia">Slovakia</ref> in second with 3 wins; Russia in third with 3 wins and 1 loss; <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">Great Britain</ref> in fourth with 2 wins and 1 loss; China and Norway in fifth with 2 wins and 2 losses; South Korea, Sweden, and the United States in seventh place with 1 win and 3 losses; and Finland last with 4 losses.</p>
<p>Finland and Norway were evenly matched, going point for point in the first pair of ends, trading 2 points each in the next pair of ends, then Norway scored 2 points and 1 point in the next ends with Finland answering back.  Tied after eight ends, they went to extra ends which Norway won with 2 points.</p>
<p>Outpacing other curlers on the ice, United States looked like they might be able to come back to tie things after their second end against Canada, and then only being down one after the fourth end, but Canada went on to score points in the next three ends.</p>
<p>While Sweden won three of the seven ends they played against China, they were unable to beat the Chinese team who scored 2 points in two ends and 3 points in another end.  In the fourth end, the 3 points came after a precision takeout by the Chinese <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/skip%20(curling)">skip</ref> Wang Haitao that cleared two Swedish stones off the sheet.</p>
<p>With the crowd behind them the entire match, Russia came from behind after the first end and third end to tie things up in the fifth end and take the lead.  They allowed the South Koreans to score two points in the seventh end to force an eighth end.  Russian skip Andrei Smirnov cleared a South Korean stone sitting in front of three Russian stones off the sheet that gave the Russians a two point lead.</p>
<p>The United States has not medaled at the past two Paraympic Games, with their best finish a fourth at the 2010 Games. Of the United States's curling team, two are returning wheelchair curling Paralympic veterans.  James Joseph, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/second%20(curling)">second</ref>, competed at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2006%20Winter%20Paralympics">2006 Winter Paralympics</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2010_Winter_Paralympics">2010 Winter Paralympics</ref>.  The skip and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Madison">Madison</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wisconsin">Wisconsin</ref> native, Patrick McDonald, competed at the 2010 Games.  Penny Greely, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/lead%20(curling)">lead</ref>, competed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/sitting%20volleyball">sitting volleyball</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2004%20Summer%20Paralympics">2004 Summer Paralympics</ref> where she won a bronze medal. David Palmer, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/third%20(curling)">third</ref>, is competing at his first games after having a fourth place finish at the 2013 World Championships in Russia and a fifth place finish at the 2012 World Championships in South Korea.  Alternate and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape%20Cod">Cape Cod</ref> native Meghan Lino is also at her first Paralympic Games after taking up the sport in 2009.</p>
<p>Sweden's team has three team members who competed at the 2010 Games in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vancouver">Vancouver</ref>, Canada: Jalle Jungnell, Glenn Ikonen, and Patrik Kallin. 60 year old Jungnell has the team's most Paralympic experience, having competed at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1988%20Summer%20Paralympics">1988</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1992%20Summer%20Paralympics">1992</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1996%20Summer%20Paralympics">1996 Summer Paralympics</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wheelchair_basketball">wheelchair basketball</ref>, as well as competing at the 2006 and 2010 Winter Paralympics in wheelchair curling.  Finnish born Ikonen had been suspended for six months following the Vancouver Games following a positive doping test. He claimed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/metroprolol">metroprolol</ref> was a drug he had been using for 4 or 5 years, and was unhappy that his doctor prescribed the blood pressure reducing drug because he would not have intentionally taken a banned substance.  </p>
<p>The 2014 Games are the first Paralympics for Russia's wheelchair curling team.  Alternate Oksana Slesarenko from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yekaterinburg">Yekaterinburg</ref> and skip Andrei Smirnov also from Yekaterinburg have the most experience on the team, both having taken up the sport in 2003, and competing at the 2004, 2005, 2007, 2008, 2011, 2012, and 2013 World Championships.</p>
<p>Team Canada includes all five members of their 2013 World Championship winning team, including 63-year-old skip Jim Armstrong, 51-year-old Dennis John Thiessen, 52-year-old Ina Forrest, 47-year-old Sonja Gaudet, and 37-year-old Mark Ideson.  Gaudet is the only wheelchair curling Paralympian with two gold medals, having won them in 2006 and 2010.  Teammates Armstrong and Thiessen were part of the 2010 gold medal winning team. Gaudet also has gold medals from the 2009, 2011, and 2013 World Championships.  While Armstrong was inducted into the Canadian Curling Hall of Fame in 1990 for his accomplishments in able bodied curling, Gaudet was the first wheelchair-only curler to be inducted when she was part of the 2013 class.</p>
<p>South Korea has two returning 2010 Games silver medalists, Kang Mi-Suk and Kim Myung-Jin.  Both originally played other sports before taking up curling.  Kang played <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Table_tennis">table tennis</ref> and Kim played wheelchair basketball.</p>
<p>On Saturday, Russia beat China 5–4, South Korea lost to Norway 0–10, Canada beat Great Britain 6–3, and Slovakia defeated the United States 6–4 in the morning session. Sweden beat Finland 7–6, Canada beat Russia 5–4, the United States lost to South Korea 5–9, and Norway lost to China 3–7.  In the morning session yesterday, the United States defeated Norway 8–5, Sweden lost to Great Britain by a score of 4–6, China lost to Slovakia 3–8, and Finland lost to Russia 4–7. In the afternoon session yesterday, Canada defeated Sweden 7–4, Finland lost to Slovakia 6–9, and Great Britain beat South Korea by a score of 8–4.</p>
<p>Unlike able-bodied <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Curling">curling</ref>, players release the stone from a stationary position and there is no <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/curling#Sweeping">sweeping</ref>. Another curler often sits behind the stone thrower to hold their chair in place while they execute their throw. Unlike a number of other Paralympic sports, there is only one classification in wheelchair curling and a variety of lower body disabilities compete in the sport.  South Koreans Kim Myung-Jin and Kim Jong-Pan, Swede Kristina Ulander, Team USA's Meghan Lino, Patrick McDonald, and David Palmer, and Russians Alexander Shevchenko, Svetlana Pakhomova, Oksana Slesarenko, Andrei Smirnov, and Marat Romanov have spinal cord injuries.  Canadian Jim Armstrong has injured knees.  Canadian Ina Forrest lost her leg in a farming accident. Team USA's James Joseph has a limb deficiency.</p>
<p> Team USA confers on a shot  Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Laura_Hale">Laura Hale</ref>.</p>
<p>  The Russian team confers on a shot Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Laura_Hale">Laura Hale</ref>.</p>
   Finland and Norway congratulate eachother following the conclusion of their game Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Laura_Hale">Laura Hale</ref>.
  Team USA fans watching the matches  Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Laura_Hale">Laura Hale</ref>.
   Bagpipers playing before the start of wheelchair curling Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Laura_Hale">Laura Hale</ref>.
</text>
