<text id="autogum_news_doc588" title="Wikinews interviews Spanish Paralympic track and field athlete Elena Congost Mohedano" shortTile="wikinews-interviews" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-07-17" dateModified="2013-08-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_interviews_Spanish_Paralympic_track_and_field_athlete_Elena_Congost_Mohedano" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews interviews Spanish Paralympic track and field athlete Elena Congost Mohedano</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 18, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:LauraHale">Laura Hale</ref> interviews Elena Congost Mohedano for Wikinews</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Elena Congost Mohedano at the airport in Madrid before departing for France Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/User:LauraHale">Laura Hale</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>With the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/IPC_Athletics_World_Championships">IPC Athletics World Championships</ref> scheduled to start this Friday, Wikinews interviewed <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spanish</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T12%20(classification)">T12 classified</ref> long distance runner <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elena%20Congost%20Mohedano">Elena Congost Mohedano</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Madrid–Barajas_Airport">Madrid–Barajas Airport</ref> Monday before he departed for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lyon">Lyon</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref>. Congost is scheduled to compete in  the T12 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1500%20meters">1500 meters</ref>.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">Wikinews</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Hello, I'm interviewing Elena Congost Mohedano who is a Spanish Paralympic athlete who won a silver in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2012_Summer_Paralympics">London</ref> and is going to Lyon to compete in the 2013 IPC Athletics World Championships. Having won a medal in London are you going to get another one in this one?</p>
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elena%20Congost%20Mohedano">Elena Congost Mohedano</ref></hi>: Yes! I train all year to go to win a medal.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Which medal?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>:  Gold! (laughs)
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   Which event?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>:  In 1500m.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   So you're a long distance runner. And you don't train/run with a guide because you're, what, T-13?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>: I'm <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T12%20(classification)">T-12</ref>.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Ah. So you have a degenerative eye disease, so your vision is getting worse?  ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿Tu visión empeora?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>:  Yes.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>    Do you expect it to get much worse over your continued history competing?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>: Now it's stalled, but next year it's possible.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you plan to stick since you've been competing since 2002, right...?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>: Yes, [Unintelligible].
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you plan to continue running until 2020 if Madrid gets the Games?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>: I don't know. (laughs) First <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2016_Summer_Paralympics">2016 in Rio</ref>, and then... I don't know.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  There's so few women competing for Spain. Is that an additional challenge as an athlete in this country?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>: No... In this country there are more girls in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/100m">100m</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/200m">200m</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/long%20jump">long jump</ref>. More people. In middle distance no. Two, three, four girls only.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Why do you think there's so few women on the Spanish team? It's like 27 total Spanish competing, and there's like [three] women?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>:  I don't know... The level is high internationally, but in Spain... no more level.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Someone with a visual impairement, there's a lot of sports you could do?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>:  The people now are very lazy. (laughs) No one runs. (laughs)
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   With so many sporting opportunities for people with vision impairments in Spain, why did you choose track and field?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>:  When I was young, my dream was to become an athlete. I saw them in tv, in races, and I told my parents "my wish is to win a gold medal in the Olympics!"
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Is there any particular athlete you remember from when you were young being particularly inspiring?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>:  No.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Spain has these really distinctive uniforms. The colors... Do people ever comment to you about them? Because in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> they were like, "your uniforms look like <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/McDonald's">McDonald's</ref>!" ((es))Spanish language: ‍¿Hay alguien que ha dicho algo de lo que es el color y tal, porque por lo visto en EE.UU dicen que son como McDonalds.</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>: (laughs) In London, everyone said they were not good... They said we looked like clowns. But this one now is...redder. Better.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   As somebody who's been competing for more than ten years, has there been a big change in the Paralympic movement from your perspective?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>: Yes! Every year the level is higher. In the Paralympics, every four years I increase my performance level.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>  Do you think that the increased competition has made you a better athlete?</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>:  Yes! Yes.
<p><hi rend="bold">((</hi><hi rend="bold">WN</hi><hi rend="bold">))</hi>   Thank you very much!</p>
<hi rend="bold">Elena Congost Mohedano</hi>:  Okay!
</text>
