<text id="autogum_news_doc743" title="Sandra Fluke gives keynote speech at Nebraska women&apos;s health event" shortTile="sandra-fluke-gives" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-12-05" dateModified="2017-09-30" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sandra_Fluke_gives_keynote_speech_at_Nebraska_women%27s_health_event" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sandra Fluke gives keynote speech at Nebraska women's health event</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 6, 2012</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Women's_rights">Women's rights</ref> advocate and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgetown%20University%20Law%20Center">Georgetown University Law Center</ref> graduate <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sandra_Fluke">Sandra Fluke</ref> was the keynote speaker at a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/women's%20health">women's health</ref> event Tuesday night in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nebraska">Nebraska</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sandra_Fluke">Sandra Fluke</ref> (2012) Image: <ref target="http://www.flickr.com/people/81711099@N04">nmogburn</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Fluke was the headliner in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lincoln,%20Nebraska">Lincoln</ref>, Nebraska at the Rococo Theatre for the annual fundraiser of Planned Parenthood of the Heartland, titled: "The Big Event: Courage — No Matter What". She currently resides in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Los_Angeles,_California">Los Angeles</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref> with her fiancé and "Mr. President", their pet dog. After graduating <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cum%20laude">cum laude</ref></hi> with her <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J.D.">J.D.</ref> degree this past May, Fluke successfully took and passed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/bar%20exam">bar exam</ref> in July and is now an attorney.</p>
<hi rend="bold">It’s uplifting and heartening to see how many people really care about the issues I’m talking about.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—<ref target="https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Author:Sandra%20Kay%20Fluke">Sandra Fluke</ref></p>
<p>In an interview with the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lincoln%20Journal%20Star">Lincoln Journal Star</ref></hi>, Fluke reflected on her role as a public figure and her ability to contribute to the contribute to the discourse about women's rights, "It's uplifting and heartening to see how many people really care about the issues I’m talking about." Fluke observed, "I think it's also allowed me to give a voice and shine a light on the work that a lot of people are doing." </p>
<p>Fluke's speech centered on women's rights, women's healthcare, and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Patient_Protection_and_Affordable_Care_Act">Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act</ref>. She stressed the importance of women's issues in the recent election for U.S. President: "This year, something changed in our national conversation about women’s health.... Before my time, women's healthcare has never decided a presidential election. We really did make a difference this election." She spurred on attendees of the event to become more active in supporting women's rights: "It’s time for young women in this country to join the fight, because it’s our rights and our health that are at stake."</p>
<hi rend="bold">She's a voice of reason. I think she has raised the bar for rational conversation about a serious issue.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Tari Hendrickson</p>
<p>Planned Parenthood regional development and planned gifts director Tari Hendrickson told the <hi rend="italic">Lincoln Journal Star</hi> Sandra Fluke was her top choice for keynote speaker at the event: "Sandra was No. 1 on my list; I never had a No. 2. She's a voice of reason. I think she has raised the bar for rational conversation about a serious issue."</p>
<hi rend="bold">She is a wonderfully outspoken person on the affordable care act, women's health and women's rights.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Susan Allen</p>
<p>Planned Parenthood of the Heartland Planned Nebraska communications manager Susan Allen told the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daily%20Nebraskan">Daily Nebraskan</ref></hi> Sandra Fluke was the ideal person to serve as keynote speaker: "She is a wonderfully outspoken person on the affordable care act, women's health and women's rights. We decided she would be the perfect person to speak to Planned Parenthood supporters." </p>
<p>Planned Parenthood intern and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Nebraska-Lincoln">University of Nebraska-Lincoln</ref> student Emily Schiltz commented on landing Fluke as the keynote speaker, "She is definitely the biggest person we've had in a long time."</p>
<p>"I feel like she walks the walk rather than talk the talk," said Planned Parenthood intern and journalism student Audrey Nance.</p>
<p>Fluke indicated her intention was to persevere in speaking about issues she thinks important: "I think my ultimate goal is giving a voice to people who don't always have one."</p>
<p>She has been named as a candidate by <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Time_(magazine)">Time</ref></hi> magazine in a November 26 announcement, for their <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Time_Person_of_the_Year">Person of the Year</ref></hi>. <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> concluded Fluke helped give U.S. President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> an edge in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2012_United_States_presidential_election">his presidential re-election campaign</ref>.</p>
<p>Fluke was a featured speaker on September 5 at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012%20Democratic%20National%20Convention">2012 Democratic National Convention</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlotte,%20North%20Carolina">Charlotte</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_Carolina">North Carolina</ref>. Fluke spoke to attendees at the convention about the consequences for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Women">women</ref> of electing <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</ref> candidate for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States">U.S. President</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</ref>, over incumbent President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>. Fluke has campaigned with President Obama in his bid for re-election.</p>
<p>She was recognized April 22 with the <hi rend="italic">Stand Up for Choice Award</hi>. Fluke was given the <hi rend="italic">Stand Up for Choice Award</hi> at the "Third Annual Multi-Generational Brunch" of the organization <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NARAL%20Pro-Choice%20America">NARAL Pro-Choice America</ref> which was held in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York_City">New York City</ref> (NYC), <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>. </p>
<p>Fluke received a nomination in March as a candidate for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Time_(magazine)">Time</ref></hi> magazine's 100 most influential people in the world. The list is released annually as a special edition of <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> magazine, titled <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time%20100">Time 100</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>She gave testimony to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Congress">US Congress</ref> on February 23 before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House%20Democratic%20Steering%20and%20Policy%20Committee">House Democratic Steering and Policy Committee</ref> at a hearing about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/women's%20health">women's health</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/contraception">contraception</ref>. She also worked for Sanctuary for Families in NYC which worked to crack down on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Human_trafficking">human trafficking</ref> and domestic violence. </p>
</text>
