<text id="autogum_news_doc607" title="SpaceX Crew Dragon capsule docks with International Space Station" shortTile="spacex-crew-dragon" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-02-28" dateModified="2019-04-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/SpaceX_Crew_Dragon_capsule_docks_with_International_Space_Station" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>SpaceX Crew Dragon capsule docks with International Space Station</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 5, 2019</hi></p>
<p>On Sunday, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/SpaceX">SpaceX</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crew%20Dragon">Crew Dragon</ref> capsule successfully docked with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/International_Space_Station">International Space Station</ref> in orbit around the Earth.  Although the Crew Dragon was carrying only cargo and a mannequin equipped with sensors, this was the first time since the retirement of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/space%20shuttle">space shuttles</ref> in 2011 a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> spacecraft capable of carrying humans has made it to the station.</p>
<figure><caption>Artist's rendition of the Crew Dragon en route.Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/SpaceX">SpaceX</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Most of the docking process was automatic by the capsule, though the crew of the ISS were able to send the capsule commands to perform simple movements.  Previous SpaceX pods have relied on the station's own robotic arm apparatus to take hold of them.</p>
<p>At 2:49 a.m. local time (7:49 a.m. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTC">UTC</ref>) on Saturday morning, the Crew Dragon was launched via a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Falcon%209%20rocket">Falcon 9 rocket</ref> from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kennedy%20Space%20Center">Kennedy Space Center</ref> at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cape%20Canaveral">Cape Canaveral</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Florida">Florida</ref> in the southeastern <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>.</p>
<p>Crew Dragon has enough room for seven people but on this occasion carried only a mannequin, nicknamed "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ellen%20Ripley">Ripley</ref>" for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sigourney%20Weaver">Sigourney Weaver</ref>'s character in the film <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alien%20(film)"><hi rend="italic">Alien</hi></ref>.  The Crew Dragon is scheduled to remain at the station during the week and return to Earth on Friday.</p>
<p>Bill Gerstenmaier of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NASA">NASA</ref> spoke of the collaboration between his agency and SpaceX: "It's fun working with a new partner that approaches the problem in a slightly different way. They don't carry the same background that we did in NASA, and they don't approach the design exactly the same way we do. [...] And that's cool. I mean, that's really neat."</p>
<p>"To be frank I'm a little emotionally exhausted because that was super stressful. But it worked — so far," SpaceX founder <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Elon_Musk">Elon Musk</ref> told the press after the launch. "We have to dock to the station, and we have to come back, but so far it's worked. [...] We've passed some of the riskiest items." </p>
<p>The short-term goal of NASA's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commercial%20Crew%20Program">Commercial Crew Program</ref> is to restore NASA's ability to send humans into orbit, which it has been unable to do since retiring the space shuttles in 2011.  Longer term, according to NASA administrator <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim%20Bridenstine">Jim Bridenstine</ref>, the goal is to render space accessible to many customers and, through commercial competition, do so at a lower cost than the space shuttle missions, which ran about <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US$">US$</ref>1.5 billion apiece. Currently, NASA pays for Russian spacecraft to carry living people, at roughly US$80 million per astronaut.</p>
<p>NASA has selected two astronauts, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doug%20Hurley">Doug Hurley</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bob%20Behnken">Bob Behnken</ref>, for Crew Dragon's first manned mission, which NASA said might take place this summer.</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Boeing">Boeing</ref> airframe company is also collaborating with NASA on human-crewable spacecraft and its <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Starliner">Starliner</ref> craft is scheduled to undergo flight test this spring.  NASA's contract with Boeing is currently valued at US$4.2 billion.  The contract with SpaceX is valued at US$2.6 billion.</p>
<p>Last year, SpaceX tested its <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Falcon%20Heavy">Falcon Heavy</ref> rocket by launching company founder Elon Musk's personal <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tesla%20(car)">Tesla convertible</ref> into space.</p>
</text>
