<text id="autogum_news_doc289" title="Rare Middle East cyclone batters Oman" shortTile="rare-middle-east" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2007-06-07" dateModified="2018-04-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rare_Middle_East_cyclone_batters_Oman" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Rare Middle East cyclone batters Oman</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 7, 2007</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tropical%20Cyclone%20Gonu">Tropical Storm Gonu</ref> headed toward <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref> today, after lashing <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Oman">Oman</ref> for two days with high winds and torrential rains, and causing at least 23 deaths and the evacuation of more than 20,000 people to emergency shelters. Concern was high for the oil industry, as rough seas kept tankers from leaving their ports.</p>
<p>Such storms are rare in the Middle East. Early today, Gonu was weakening and was downgraded to a tropical storm. The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joint%20Typhoon%20Warning%20Center">Joint Typhoon Warning Center</ref> projected the storm to continue weakening as it made landfall on Iran's southeastern coast. Offshore Iranian oil installations were expected to be spared, officials said.</p>
<head id="Oman_lashed">Oman lashed</head>
<p>In the Omani capital, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muscat">Muscat</ref> yesterday, there were torrential rains and howling winds, a rarity in the quiet coastal city. Streets were flooded and emergency vehicles were useless. Flights were canceled at Oman's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seeb%20International%20Airport">Seeb International Airport</ref>.</p>
<p>Twenty-three deaths were reported by Omani authorities today. Electricity and phone lines were out and roads flooded. Police said a body washed ashore in Sur. There were also reports of people trapped in homes in low-lying areas of the capital.</p>
<p>Authorities used mobile-phone text messages to warn people away from dangerous areas. Residents were warned to stay at home, or seek shelter in buildings that could withstand the harsh weather.</p>
<p>Shareefa bint Khalfan, Omani minister of social development, said more than 20,000 people were evacuated to government shelters. </p>
<p>At Oman's weather center, where records have been kept since 1890, metorologists said Gonu was likely the strongest storm to hit Oman since 1977. Milder tropical storms are common mid-May to late June.</p>
<head id="Iran_prepares">Iran prepares</head>
<p>In Iran, hundreds of residents of Chabahr, a port on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gulf%20of%20Oman">Gulf of Oman</ref>, were evacuated.</p>
<p>"University and school students were moved to higher ground in the area to avoid the cyclone effects," Hojjat Ali Shayanfar, head of emergency services in Sistan Baluchistan province, was quoted as saying by the Associated Press.</p>
<p>Some major roads were flooded in southeastern Iran. In the port city of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bandar%20Abbas">Bandar Abbas</ref>, winds shattered windows and knocked down billboards &amp; trees.</p>
<head id="Impact_on_oil_industry">Impact on oil industry</head>
<p>Oman has relatively small oil fields, and there was little damage to them. But oil exports were cut off, as the raging seas kept tankers battened down in port for a third day today. To the north, at the world's third-largest shipping fuel center in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fujairah">Fujairah</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Arab_Emirates">United Arab Emirates</ref>, all refueling and supply operations were suspended, and ships were kept in their berths. At the entrance to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persian%20Gulf">Persian Gulf</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strait%20of%20Hormuz">Strait of Hormuz</ref>, ships passed through, despite four- to six-foot swells and strong winds. About one-fifth of the world's oil passes through this narrow chokepoint.</p>
<p>Iran, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OPEC">OPEC's</ref> No. 2 oil exporter, said the storm would not disrupt supplies because its main terminals were inside the Gulf waterway. Analysts were mixed on how the storm will affect prices at the gas pump.</p>
<p>"About 17-21 million barrels a day of oil are coming out of the Persian Gulf. Even if only some of the tankers are delayed, that could reduce the supply of oil and increase prices," Manouchehr Takin, at the Center for Global Energy Studies in London, was quoted as saying by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Associated%20Press">Associated Press</ref>.</p>
<p>But Tim Evans, an analyst at Citigroup Global Markets, said while the storm may delay oil tankers, they will eventually get to their destinations, so prices shouldn't be affected too drastically.</p>
<p>Oil prices rose US$0.25 to $65.86 a barrel in midday trading on the New York Mercantile Exchange.</p>
<head id="Strongest_cyclone">Strongest cyclone</head>
<p>At its peak, Tropical Cyclone Gonu, named for a bag of palm leaves in the language of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Maldives">Maldives</ref>, reached sustained winds of 240 kilometers an hour (149 miles per hour)	. By early today, winds were around 83 km/h, and it was expect to keep weakening.</p>
<p>The storm is believed to be the strongest cyclone to hit the Arabian Peninsula since record-keeping started in 1945, and was tied for the strongest tropical cyclone in the northern <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian%20Ocean">Indian Ocean</ref>, according to the Joint Typhoon Warning Center.</p>
</text>
