<text id="autogum_news_doc550" title="Scientists analyse effects of global warming, atmospheric ozone on crops" shortTile="scientists-analyse" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-07-28" dateModified="2015-06-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Scientists_analyse_effects_of_global_warming%2C_atmospheric_ozone_on_crops" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Scientists analyse effects of global warming, atmospheric ozone on crops</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 28, 2014</hi></p>
<p>A research team from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Massachusetts_Institute_of_Technology">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Colorado_State_University">Colorado State University</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">US</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/University_of_Sheffield">University of Sheffield</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">UK</ref> has analysed effects of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Global_warming">global warming</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ozone#Ozone_air_pollution">ozone pollution</ref> over 2000–2050 on the worldwide production of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/wheat">wheat</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/rice">rice</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/maize">maize</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/soybean">soybean</ref>. The study was published in journal <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nature%20Climate%20Change">Nature Climate Change</ref></hi> yesterday.</p>
<p>The scientists found reduction of crop yields by 2050 exceeded 10% of 2000 levels, substantially decreasing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/food%20security">food security</ref>, in all cases examined. Several scenarios were considered because of uncertainty of future levels of ozone pollution.
They estimated by 2050, increasing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/population%20growth">population</ref> and changing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/diet%20(nutrition)">diet</ref> would increase world food needs by 50 percent.
As coauthor Colette Heald told <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Huffington%20Post">The Huffington Post</ref>, "The climate projections are quite consistent [...] the future of ozone pollution is very different [...] leading to either offsetting or reinforcing effects [of climate change] on crops".
By 2050, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/undernourishment">undernourishment</ref> would increase by either 49 percent or by 27 percent, depending on the scenario.</p>
<p>The study focuses on ozone–temperature <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/covariation">covariation</ref>: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ground-level%20ozone">ground-level ozone</ref> increases with temperatures.
Heald said although temperature and ozone are separately known to impact crop yields, "nobody has looked at these together".
Depending on region and crops, the yields may be primarily sensitive to ozone —in the case of wheat— or heat —in the case of maize— alone, providing a local estimation of relative benefits of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/climate%20change%20adaptation">climate change adaptation</ref> versus <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ozone#Safety_regulations">ozone regulation</ref>.</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Department%20of%20Agriculture">U.S. Department of Agriculture</ref> notes, "Ground-level ozone causes more damage to plants than all other air pollutants combined", highlighting the importance of air quality for agriculture. Results of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Crop%20Loss%20Assessment%20Network">NCLAN</ref> studies, published in a paper by AS Heagle in 1989, show <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/dicot">dicot</ref> species, such as soybean, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cotton">cotton</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/peanut">peanut</ref>, lose more yield from ozone than do <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/monocot">monocot</ref> species such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/sorghum">sorghum</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/field%20corn">field corn</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/winter%20wheat">winter wheat</ref>.
The researchers found that ozone pollution caused 46 percent of previously heat-attributed damage to soybean crops.</p>
<p>The model does not include the effect of rising <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carbon%20dioxide%20in%20Earth's%20atmosphere">carbon dioxide concentration</ref>, which has complex and potentially offsetting impacts on global food supply.
The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Environmental%20Protection%20Agency">U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</ref> says some crops may have higher yields with increased levels of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/carbon%20dioxide">carbon dioxide</ref>.
However, global warming also increases probability of extreme crops-damaging weather events such as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Flood">floods</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/drought">droughts</ref>, and extreme temperatures. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Climate_change">Climate change</ref> affects distribution of weeds, pests, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Disease">diseases</ref>.
Heald noted the findings show <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pollution">pollution</ref> reduction is also important. "An air-quality cleanup would improve crop yields [...] Ozone is something that we understand the causes of, and the steps that need to be taken to improve air quality."</p>
<p>As Heald told <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Huffington%20Post">The Huffington Post</ref>, US surface ozone has dropped partly due to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clean%20Air%20Act%20(United%20States)">Clean Air Act</ref>. "Despite an increase in vehicle miles driven and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Energy">energy</ref> consumption, surface ozone has declined by 25 percent on average across the U.S. from 1980 to 2012 [...] However, the future of ozone <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/air%20quality">air quality</ref> in the U.S. and around the world will depend on local emissions, the use of pollution control technology, regulations, and air quality policy."</p>
<p>The study was supported by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Croucher%20Foundation">Croucher Foundation</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_National_Science_Foundation">US National Science Foundation</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US%20National%20Park%20Service">US National Park Service</ref>.</p>
</text>
