<text id="autogum_news_doc280" title="President Bush urges progress on Palestinian state" shortTile="president-bush-urges" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-01-05" dateModified="2015-03-05" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_Bush_urges_progress_on_Palestinian_state" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>President Bush urges progress on Palestinian state</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 5, 2008</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/George_W._Bush">President Bush</ref> will go to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Middle_East">Middle East</ref> next week where he is hoping to encourage <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israeli</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Palestine">Palestinian</ref> talks towards an independent Palestinian state. </p>
<p>President Bush says his job is to keep Israeli Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ehud%20Olmert">Ehud Olmert</ref> and Palestinian President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahmoud%20Abbas">Mahmoud Abbas</ref> focused on the big picture, despite what he says are considerable roadblocks toward an independent Palestinian state.</p>
<p>"It's to give them confidence and encourage them to come up with what a state will look like, to define that state so that people there in the region can have hope that this long-time conflict will finally come to an end, and the first step is the definition of a state," he said.</p>
<p>Mr. Bush spoke Friday in an interview with <hi rend="italic">al-Hurra</hi>, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">U.S.</ref> government's Arabic-language satellite television network.</p>
<p>His trip follows-up November's conference in Annapolis, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Maryland">Maryland</ref> where Prime Minister Olmert and President Abbas agreed to begin regular talks on a Palestinian state.</p>
<p>The president leaves Tuesday for Israel and the West Bank where he will hold separate talks with the Israeli and Palestinian leaders before continuing on to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kuwait">Kuwait</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bahrain">Bahrain</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Arab_Emirates">United Arab Emirates</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dubai">Dubai</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Saudi_Arabia">Saudi Arabia</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egypt">Egypt</ref>.</p>
<p>Mr. Bush says he hopes to convince friends and allies in the region that there must be strong support for both Palestinians and Israelis in order to make the two-state solution work.</p>
<p>The president has set the goal of having the outlines of a Palestinian state in place before he leaves office one year from now. While he admits there is a lot of work to be done, Mr. Bush says he still believes that is possible.</p>
<p>"Palestinian security forces have to be reformed, which we are helping with, by the way," he said. "The entrepreneurial class of people has to be encouraged with new capital. The institutions of government need to be strengthened."</p>
<p>During the trip, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White%20House">White House</ref> officials say the president will meet with U.S. civilian and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/military">military</ref> commanders from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref> for an update on the fighting there. He will also press for another round of sanctions against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref>, which Mr. Bush says is crucial to force <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tehran">Tehran</ref> to stop enriching <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/uranium">uranium</ref>.</p>
<p>The president says he will meet with regional leaders to discuss the situation in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lebanon">Lebanon</ref>, where he says <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syrian</ref> President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bashar%20al-Assad">Bashar al-Assad</ref> is the main obstacle to Lebanon's selection of a new president.</p>
<p>"President Assad must understand that if he wants better relations with the United States, and frankly better relations in the region, the first thing he has got to do is stop interfering in the Lebanese presidential process," he said.</p>
<p>During the trip, President Bush is scheduled to meet with U.S. troops, speak with leaders of women's groups in Kuwait, and visit a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holocaust">Holocaust</ref> museum in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerusalem">Jerusalem</ref>.</p>
</text>
