<text id="autogum_news_doc111" title="Guantanamo captive returned to the United Kingdom" shortTile="guantanamo-captive" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-02-23" dateModified="2015-08-22" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Guantanamo_captive_returned_to_the_United_Kingdom" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Guantanamo captive returned to the United Kingdom</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 23, 2009</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guantanamo%20Bay%20detention%20camp">Guantanamo captive</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benyam%20Mohammed">Benyam Mohammed</ref> was returned to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref> on February 23, 2009 after years of negotiation. Benyam Mohammed's case stirred controversy for years.  He was a legal resident of the United Kingdom who had come to the UK as a refugee from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethiopia">Ethiopia</ref> when he was a child.  He explained that he had traveled to Afghanistan in an attempt to quit a drug habit he acquired in the UK.  </p>
<p>He claimed that all the very serious allegations that he reportedly confessed to were extracted while he was being tortured.  He had claimed that he wasn't held in military custody when he was first captured, stating instead that the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CIA">CIA</ref> had temporarily transferred him to a brutal prison in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Morocco">Morocco</ref> where the interrogation techniques included mutilating his genitals.  He later spent time in the CIA's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/black%20site">network of secret interrogation centres</ref> including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Dark%20Prison">"The Dark Prison"</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>A Camp Delta recreation and exercise area at Guantanamo Bay, Cuba. The detention block is shown with sunshades drawn on December 3, 2002. Image: <ref target="http://www.defenselink.mil/photos/newsphoto.aspx?newsphotoid=4217">DoD photo by Staff Sgt. Stephen Lewald, U.S. Army</ref></caption></figure>
<p>The Bush administration eventually stopped denying that he had spent considerable time in CIA custody prior to his transfer to Guantanamo.  They continued to deny he had been tortured. He faced the allegation that he had plotted with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/José%20Padilla%20(prisoner)">José Padilla</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Majid%20Khan%20(Guantanamo%20captive%2010020)">Majid Khan</ref> to explode a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/dirty%20bomb">dirty bomb</ref> — a radiological weapon — in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>.  </p>
<p>He was one of the two dozen Guantanamo captives to face charges before a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guantanamo%20military%20commission">Guantanamo military commission</ref>.  He was charged twice in late 2005 before a presidentially authorized commission.  Two years after the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supreme%20Court%20of%20the%20United%20States">Supreme Court of the United States</ref> overturned the original presidentially authorized military commissions he was charged again before a military commission authorized by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military%20Commissions%20Act">Military Commissions Act</ref>.  </p>
<p>His lawyers initiated legal proceedings through the United Kingdom's justice system to compel the UK government to release to them its role in his detention.  The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office%20of%20Military%20Commissions">Office of Military Commissions</ref> dropped the charges against him in October 2008. Benyam Mohammed was reported to have engaged in a hunger strike as a protest during the last months of his detention. His lawyers claimed his weight had dropped to a level where he was just "skin and bones", fainted during their meetings with him, and that his health was at serious risk.</p>
<p>All of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British%20captives%20in%20Guantanamo">British citizens held in Guantanamo</ref> were repatriated by 2005. Seven long term British residents were not returned to the UK.  Initially it was the British position that they had no responsibility for individuals who weren't citizens. When British resident <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bisher%20Amin%20Khalil%20al-Rawi">Bisher al-Rawi</ref>'s story that he had been an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MI5">MI5</ref> informant started to be confirmed, there was public pressure for his return.</p>
<p>In 2006, a frustrated member of the team negotiating Al Rawi's return leaked that the process had become stalled because the Americans were insisting that they would only release Al Rawi if the United Kingdom was prepared to accept all the former British residents and keep them under round the clock surveillance. After his repatriation to the United Kingdom Mohammed spent a few hours being debriefed by British security officials before he was set free. Three former British residents remain in detention in Guantanamo: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shaker%20Aamer">Shaker Aamer</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ahmed%20Beltacha">Ahmed Beltacha</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Farhi%20Saeed%20bin%20Mohammed">Farhi Saeed bin Mohammed</ref>.</p>
</text>
