<text id="autogum_news_doc108" title="US supports UN gay rights declaration" shortTile="supports-un-gay-rights" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2009-03-19" dateModified="2013-12-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_supports_UN_gay_rights_declaration" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>US supports UN gay rights declaration</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 19, 2009</hi></p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Obama administration</ref> announced on March 18, 2009 that the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>, in a reversal of position, would support the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UN%20declaration%20on%20sexual%20orientation%20and%20gender%20identity">UN declaration on sexual orientation and gender identity</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>67 UN member states (green) have signed or say they will sign the Declaration on Sexual Orientation and Gender Identity. 57 UN member states (red) have signed an opposing declaration.</caption></figure><p> The United States will become the 67th signatory to the non-binding document, which was proposed by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Netherlands">the Netherlands</ref> and "condemn[s] the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Human%20rights">human rights</ref> violations based on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sexual%20orientation">sexual orientation</ref> or <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gender%20identity">gender identity</ref> wherever they occur, in particular the use of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capital%20punishment">death penalty</ref> on this ground, extrajudicial, summary or arbitrary executions, the practice of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torture">torture</ref> and other cruel, inhuman and degrading treatment or punishment, arbitrary arrest or detention and deprivation of economic, social and cultural rights, including the right to health".</p>
<figure><caption>US State Department Spokesman Robert A. Wood</caption></figure><p>Accepting the proposal, which according to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Department%20of%20State">US State Department</ref> spokesman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20Wood">Robert Wood</ref> "commits us to no legal obligations", would nonetheless be a reversal from the Bush administration's refusal to sign. According to Mark Bromley of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Council%20for%20Global%20Equality">Council for Global Equality</ref>, "the administration's leadership on this issue will be a powerful rebuke of an earlier Bush administration position that sought to deny the universal application of human rights protections to lesbian, gay, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bisexuality">bisexual</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transgender">transgender</ref> individuals".</p>
<p>57 UN member nations, however, including many but not all members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Organization%20of%20the%20Islamic%20Conference">Organization of the Islamic Conference</ref>, have signed a counter-declaration introduced by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syria</ref> saying that normalization of LGBT rights would lead to "the social normalization, and possibly the legitimization, of many deplorable acts including <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pedophilia">pedophilia</ref>." <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vatican_City">Vatican City</ref> also opposes the resolution but on its introduction made a statement condemning legal discrimination against LGBT persons.</p>
<p>Homosexuality or homosexual behavior is illegal in some 70 UN member nations and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capital%20punishment">punishable by death</ref> in seven.</p>
<p>The United States' adoption of the document comes as the Obama administration faces continued criticism from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LGBT%20social%20movements">gay rights advocates</ref> on the subject of homosexual individuals serving in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armed%20Forces%20of%20the%20United%20States">United States military</ref>. While Obama has stated he would repeal <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bill_Clinton">Bill Clinton</ref>'s 1993 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don't%20ask,%20don't%20tell">"don't ask, don't tell"</ref> compromise and end restrictions on gays, bisexuals and lesbians serving in the military, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secretary%20of%20Defense%20of%20the%20United%20States">US Defense Secretary</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert%20Gates">Robert Gates</ref> says that he has had "one brief conversation with the president" on the subject; meanwhile, a US House bill to end the ban is losing its primary sponsor, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ellen%20Tauscher">Ellen Tauscher</ref>, to the State Department and no complementary piece of legislation has been introduced to the Senate.</p>
<p>France's proposal of the document is one of several instances in the course of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nicolas_Sarkozy">Sarkozy</ref> administration where France and the Vatican have been at odds on issues of sexuality. France's foreign ministry, in response to comments by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Benedict_XVI">Pope Benedict</ref> rejecting the distribution of condoms in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Africa">Africa</ref> to prevent <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/AIDS">AIDS</ref>, led <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Union">EU</ref> member nations in rejecting the Pope's position. In September 2008, France openly affronted the Vatican by appointing an openly gay man, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denis%20Tillinac">Denis Tillinac</ref>, as its ambassador to the Holy See; the Vatican rejected the appointment.</p>
</text>
