<text id="autogum_news_doc136" title="Pedestrian, three others killed in helicopter crash in British Columbia" shortTile="pedestrian-three" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-05-21" dateModified="2008-05-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pedestrian%2C_three_others_killed_in_helicopter_crash_in_British_Columbia" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Pedestrian, three others killed in helicopter crash in British Columbia</head><p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 21, 2008</hi></p>
<p>A 23-year-old <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kenya">Kenyan</ref> man was crushed and killed and three others died after a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/helicopter">helicopter</ref> crashed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cranbrook,%20British%20Columbia">Cranbrook</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/British_Columbia">British Columbia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref> on May 13. All on board the helicopter, two passengers and the pilot of the helicopter, were also killed. </p>
<p>Considered a freak accident, the attention was not centered around the crash or those killed in it, but whether or not the volume on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/iPod">iPod</ref> the 23-year-old pedestrian was allegedly listening to was too loud.</p>
<p>Isaiah Otieno, a student at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/College%20of%20the%20Rockies">College of the Rockies</ref> arrived in Canada two years ago and was the son of Dalmas Otieno, Kenya's Minister of State for Public Service. He was walking down the street to retrieve his mail when the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bell%20206">Bell 206</ref> helicopter crashed on top of him, crushed him, then dragged his body along the pavement, with the helicopter bursting into flames. The helicopter pilot was unable to maintain altitude when it crashed, killing Otieno and those inside the helicopter, instantly. The cause of the crash is not known and is still being investigated, but media outlets such as <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Globe%20and%20Mail">The Globe and Mail</ref></hi> criticized the boy for wearing headphones and having the volume turned up too high, which allegedly caused him not to hear the aircraft falling from the sky.</p>
<p>"He was a brilliant student, very considerate, very aggressive at times. He had strong leadership qualities. Everybody here is just shattered," stated Dalmas.</p>
<p>Despite the reports that Otieno was listening to his iPod, there has been no independent confirmation of those reports. <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikinews">Wikinews</ref></hi> e-mailed the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal%20Canadian%20Mounted%20Police">Royal Canadian Mounted Police</ref> to confirm or deny the iPod reports, but has not yet received a response. </p>
<p>Other deaths have been blamed on media players like the iPod. In 2007, a boy was killed after a train struck him in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grimsby,%20Ontario">Grimsby, Ontario</ref>. The boy, who had headphones on at the time, was unable to hear the sounds of the train's horn as it approached, which subsequently struck and killed him.</p>
<p>The helicopter was owned by Bighorn Helicopters and was rented to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BC%20Hydro">BC Hydro</ref>, the Province's power and water authority. The Pilot has been identified as Edward William Kyle Heeb, 57. The other two individuals killed were employees for BC Hydro and have been identified as Dirk Bentley Rozenboom, 45 and Robert William Lehmann, 37. They were checking power lines along 14th street in Cranbrook, when according to witnesses, the engine stopped and the helicopter crashed in the intersection of 14th and 10th.</p>
<p>Despite the reports, a Canadian music consultant states that the accident involving the helicopter cannot be blamed on the use of Otieno's iPod.</p>
<p>"The average downtown street registers at around 60 decibels. A jet plane flying overhead is generally quoted at 120 to 130 decibels. If you are playing your music loud enough to cut out that level of noise, then you have it cranked to a degree that is damaging your hearing," said Geordon Hoag.</p>
</text>
