<text id="autogum_news_doc133" title="World Health Organization calls for ban on tobacco ads" shortTile="world-health-organization" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-06-01" dateModified="2013-07-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_Health_Organization_calls_for_ban_on_tobacco_ads" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>World Health Organization calls for ban on tobacco ads</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, June 1, 2008</hi></p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations">United Nations</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Health">health</ref> agency the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20Health%20Organization">World Health Organization</ref> (WHO) has called for a ban on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tobacco">tobacco</ref> advertising and promotion in order to protect the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World">world</ref>'s children. The news release from the WHO came on Friday, one day before the annual <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20No%20Tobacco%20Day">World No Tobacco Day</ref> held each year on May 31.</p>
<p>This year's World No Tobacco Day focuses on highlighting the practices of tobacco companies in their efforts to promote their products to young people. According to a WHO press release, studies show that young people are more likely to start smoking if exposed to tobacco advertising. The WHO notes that only five percent of the world population "is covered by comprehensive bans on tobacco advertising, promotion and sponsorship". </p>
<p>"The WHO appeals to member states and policy-makers to require by law a comprehensive ban on all forms of advertising, promotion, and sponsorship of tobacco products," said WHO Regional Director for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Africa">Africa</ref> Luis Sambo, in a statement released Saturday in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kampala">Kampala</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Uganda">Uganda</ref>.</p>
<hi rend="bold">A ban on all tobacco advertising, promotion and sponsorship is a powerful tool we can use to protect the world’s youth.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—WHO Director-General Dr. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret%20Chan">Margaret Chan</ref></p>
<p>"In order to survive, the tobacco industry needs to replace those who quit or die with new young consumers," said WHO Director-General Dr. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margaret%20Chan">Margaret Chan</ref>. "A ban on all tobacco advertising, promotion and sponsorship is a powerful tool we can use to protect the world’s youth."</p>
<p>The WHO said that tobacco companies are specifically targeting the half billion youth in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asia%20Pacific">Asia Pacific</ref> region by tying smoking to the idea of a flashy lifestyle. The agency said the tobacco industry attempts to take advantage of children's susceptibility to advertising and marketing.</p>
<p>According to the WHO most people take up smoking before they reach age 18, and almost twenty-five percent of smokers worldwide are under the age of 10. The agency said that a survey of 13 to 15 year-olds found that fifty-five percent had seen <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cigarette">cigarette</ref> ads on billboards in the prior month, and twenty-percent owned something with a cigarette company's logo.</p>
<p>According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC%20News">BBC News</ref>, in the last ten years female and adolescent smoking in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref> has tripled. Russia does not have many anti-smoking laws. <hi rend="italic">BBC News</hi> compared this to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref>, where smoking levels are at their lowest in 40 years and the country has very restrictive laws on smoking advertising.</p>
<hi rend="bold">The tobacco industry employs predatory marketing strategies to get young people hooked to their addictive drug.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Dr. Douglas Bettcher, Director of WHO's Tobacco Free Initiative</p>
<p>"The tobacco industry employs predatory marketing strategies to get young people hooked to their addictive drug. But comprehensive advertising bans do work, reducing tobacco consumption by up to 16% in countries that have already taken this legislative step," said Dr. Douglas Bettcher, Director of WHO's Tobacco Free Initiative. </p>
<p>A report by the WHO on tobacco use stated that approximately two thirds of the planet's smokers reside in 10 countries including <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">India</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Indonesia">Indonesia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bangladesh">Bangladesh</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Turkey">Turkey</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reuters">Reuters</ref> reported that companies <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip%20Morris">Philip Morris</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperial%20Tobacco">Imperial Tobacco</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/British%20American%20Tobacco">British American Tobacco</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japan%20Tobacco">Japan Tobacco</ref> are among the world's largest producers of cigarettes.</p>
</text>
