<text id="autogum_news_doc662" title="Actress and singer Debbie Reynolds dies, one day after daughter&apos;s death" shortTile="actress-singer-debbie" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2016-12-29" dateModified="2019-10-08" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Actress_and_singer_Debbie_Reynolds_dies%2C_one_day_after_daughter%27s_death" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Actress and singer Debbie Reynolds dies, one day after daughter's death</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 29, 2016</hi></p>
<p>Acclaimed actor and singer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debbie%20Reynolds">Debbie Reynolds</ref> died at the age of 84 yesterday at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cedars-Sinai%20Hospital">Cedars-Sinai Hospital</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Los_Angeles,_California">Los Angeles</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref>.  Her son, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Todd%20Fisher">Todd Fisher</ref>, said around noon yesterday she suffered a stroke brought on by the stress of the death of her daughter, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carrie%20Fisher">Carrie Fisher</ref>.</p>
<p>Reynolds' credits include lead roles in films <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Singin'%20in%20the%20Rain">Singin' in the Rain</ref></hi>, <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bundle%20of%20Joy">Bundle of Joy</ref></hi>, and <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Unsinkable%20Molly%20Brown%20(film)">The Unsinkable Molly Brown</ref></hi>, the last of which earned her an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy%20Award">Academy Award</ref> nomination.  She worked to preserve <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hollywood">Hollywood</ref> history and memorabilia for posterity and, like Carrie Fisher, as an advocate for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mental_health">mental health</ref> awareness.</p>
<figure><caption>Debbie Reynolds at home in 1987. Image: Allan Warren.</caption></figure>
<p>Born Mary Francis Reynolds in 1932, she was given the stage name "Debbie" by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Warner%20Brothers">Warner Brothers</ref> director Jack Warner, which she would later say was done without her permission.  She would go on to spend twenty years with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MGM%20studios">MGM studios</ref>.  Reynolds received a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony%20Award">Tony Award</ref> nomination for her acting in the 1973 revival of <hi rend="italic">Irene</hi>. Reynolds' business interests included owning various private museums of film memorabilia as part of her personal Hollywood history preservation project.  She would often purchase and hold items such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marilyn%20Monroe">Marilyn Monroe</ref>'s dress from <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Seven%20Year%20Itch">The Seven Year Itch</ref></hi> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth%20Taylor">Elizabeth Taylor</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cleopatra">Cleopatra</ref> headdress until they could be displayed to the public. More recently, she was nominated for an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emmy%20Award">Emmy Award</ref> in 2000 for a <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Will%20&amp;%20Grace">Will &amp; Grace</ref></hi> recurring role and appeared as the main character's mother in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HBO">HBO</ref>'s <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Behind%20the%20Candelabra">Behind the Candelabra</ref></hi>.  She worked as a voice actress on animated productions such as the children's show <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kim%20Possible">Kim Possible</ref></hi> and the more adult <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Family%20Guy">Family Guy</ref></hi>.  She was honored with the 2016 Academy Awards <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean%20Hersholt%20Humanitarian%20Award">Jean Hersholt Humanitarian Award</ref> and a Lifetime Achievement Award from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Screen%20Actors%20Guild">Screen Actors Guild</ref> in 2015.</p>
<p>In Reynolds' personal life, her first husband and father of her two children, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eddie%20Fisher">Eddie Fisher</ref>, very publicly left her for her friend Elizabeth Taylor.  She declared bankruptcy in 1997 after a failed casino project.</p>
<p>Carrie Fisher was an actor, author, and mental health advocate best known for acting in the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Star_Wars">Star Wars</ref></hi> film series and for her novel <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Postcards%20from%20the%20Edge">Postcards from the Edge</ref></hi>, which had a character inspired by her mother, Reynolds. Fisher was taken ill while flying from London to Los Angeles and died on Tuesday.  Fisher and Reynolds did not speak for several years, though this rift was long over by the time of Fisher's death.  According to Todd Fisher, he and his mother had been discussing his sister's funeral at his home shortly before the stroke; Reynolds said to him, "I miss her so much, I want to be with Carrie."</p>
<p>Reynolds is survived by son Todd Fisher and granddaughter Billie Lourd.</p>
</text>
