<text id="autogum_news_doc384" title="Kiribati acquires international funding for solar power" shortTile="kiribati-acquires" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-03-26" dateModified="2019-09-12" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kiribati_acquires_international_funding_for_solar_power" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kiribati acquires international funding for solar power</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 26, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Solar panel installation in the United States Image: U.S. Department of Agriculture.</caption></figure>
<p>Last Tuesday, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AusAID">AusAID</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_Bank">World Bank</ref>'s Global Environment Fund (GEF) reached an agreement to give the government of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kiribati">Kiribati</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">US$</ref>5 million (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Australian%20dollar">AU$</ref>4,779,000, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Zealand%20dollar">NZ$</ref>5,985,000, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Euro">€</ref>3,885,000) to install <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solar%20panels">solar panels</ref> around the country capital, located on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarawa">Tarawa</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/atoll">atoll</ref>.  According to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Brunei_Times#Business_Desk">Business Desk</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/the%20Brunei%20Times">the Brunei Times</ref>, AusAID promised AU$3.2 million in funding, while GEF promised US$1 million.  The country was the first in the Pacific to make a deal with the World Bank.</p>
<p>The funding was part of a US$530 million (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New%20Zealand%20dollar">NZ$</ref>635 million) package announced at yesterday's Pacific Energy Summit in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auckland">Auckland</ref> involving <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_Zealand">New Zealand</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Union">European Union</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Australia">Australia</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asian%20Development%20Bank">Asian Development Bank</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European%20Investment%20Bank">European Investment Bank</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japan%20International%20Cooperation%20Agency">Japan International Cooperation Agency</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20Bank%20Group">World Bank Group</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Arab_Emirates">United Arab Emirates</ref>.  Also at the summit yesterday, New Zealand's Foreign Affairs Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Murray%20McCully">Murray McCully</ref> had announced a national commitment of USD$54,262,000 (AU$51,861,000 NZ$65 million, €42,178,000) to Pacific region energy solutions, of which US$8,348,000 (AU$8 million, NZ$10 million, €6,483,000) would be specifically earmarked for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Renewable_energy">renewable energy</ref> and improved energy efficiency in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cook_Islands">Cook Islands</ref>, Kiribati, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Papua_New_Guinea">Papua New Guinea</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Samoa">Samoa</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tonga">Tonga</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tuvalu">Tuvalu</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>A small school maneaba (equivalent to a school hall) in Nabeina, North Tarawa, Kiribati<hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Koririnteuea_maneaba_in_Nabeina,_North_Tarawa,_Kiribati.jpg">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=File%3AKoririnteuea+maneaba+in+Nabeina%2C+North+Tarawa%2C+Kiribati.jpg">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure><p>Kiribati is heavily dependent on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/diesel%20fuel">diesel fuel</ref> for most of the energy available on the national power grid, which supplies power to half Kiribati's population of 110,000. In addition, a third of the country's population lacks access to electricity. Once installation of the solar panels is complete, they are estimated to reduce diesel consumption by 230,000 liters (60,760 gallons) a year and give access to the electricity to some parts of the population that currently have no electricity.  The European Union already has committed €100 million to sustainable energy in the region, with €10 million of that coming as a result of an announcement made last week.</p>
<p>In a press release about the news, Kiribati President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anote%20Tong">Anote Tong</ref> was quoted as saying, "Kiribati faces big challenges it is remote, it is at risk from the effects of climate change, and it is vulnerable to economic shocks. [...] Shifting Kiribati's focus to reliable solar energy will provide a more secure, more sustainable power source for the country's people." <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radio%20New%20Zealand%20International">Radio New Zealand International</ref></hi> quoted Tong as saying, "It's the first time we are doing this. We're excited at the prospect of even substituting fossil fuel to a small extent at this stage. What the system being envisaged will only produce around 500 kilowatts, but this is the beginning of what I hope will be a pattern, the trend in the future."</p>
<p>The European Union's <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Fiji">Fiji</ref>-based head of operations for the Pacific region, Renato Mele, supported alternative energy solutions like solar power for the region, but said that solar power had limitations because climate and environmental conditions sometimes meant batteries required to power the panels had a life of only 12 months, compared to other climates where batteries normally last five years.  This created the potential to drive up standard operating costs. Mele has also noted these additional costs though are still lower than the cost of diesel power.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/One%20News%20(New%20Zealand)">One News</ref></hi> Pacific Correspondent Barbara Dreaver noted, "Governments will be able to put the money they (currently) spend on diesel into things like education and health."</p>
</text>
