<text id="autogum_news_doc064" title="France, Italy, UK sending military advisers to Libya; photojournalists killed in Misrata" shortTile="france-italy-uk-sending" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-04-20" dateModified="2019-01-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France%2C_Italy%2C_UK_sending_military_advisers_to_Libya%3B_photojournalists_killed_in_Misrata" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>France, Italy, UK sending military advisers to Libya; photojournalists killed in Misrata</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 21, 2011</hi></p>
<figure><caption>La Russa in 2007. Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:G.dallorto">G.dallorto</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Italy">Italy</ref> have announced along with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Kingdom">United Kingdom</ref> that they will be sending military advisers to help <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libya">Libyan</ref> rebels in their fight against the forces of Libyan leader <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Muammar_Gaddafi">Muammar Gaddafi</ref>.</p>
<p>Italian Minister for Defence <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ignazio%20La%20Russa">Ignazio La Russa</ref> said Wednesday that his country will send ten instructors. French officials said they would send fewer than ten. The British Foreign Secretary, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/William_Hague">William Hague</ref>, said they would send a team that could possibly contain up to twenty advisers.</p>
<p>La Russa said in a news conference that the advisers' roles had yet to be determined, "They won't be on the battlefield. They'll be mentors, they won't accompany them. Training is one thing, participation another." </p>
<p>He further said of the rebels, "They're rich in enthusiasm, they want to fight for liberty, but naturally they are poor in experience and arms." However, La Russa believes that not all the arms the rebels have were taken from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libyan%20Army">Libyan Army</ref> stockpiles, stating, "I don't think they only have arms from the Gaddafi army. Some help arrived." He did not elaborate on the final statement.      </p>
<p>Meanwhile, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">U.S.</ref> officials say President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>'s administration plans to give the Libyan opposition <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/USD">$</ref>25 million in non-lethal assistance. The officials say the assistance could include items such as vehicles, fuel trucks, protective vests and non-secure radios.</p>
<figure><caption>Libyan rebels on the outskirts of Brega on March 10, 2011. Image: VOA - Phil Ittner.<hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Libya_Brega_rebel_fighters_10_March_2011_-_VOA_Ittner.jpg">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=File%3ALibya+Brega+rebel+fighters+10+March+2011+-+VOA+Ittner.jpg">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure>
<p>Libya's foreign minister, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abdul%20Ati%20al-Obeidi">Abdul Ati al-Obeidi</ref>, criticized the dispatch of foreign military advisers, saying it will harm chances for peace in the  country.  In an interview with the BBC, Obeidi called for a ceasefire  followed by a six month period to prepare for an election. "We think any military presence is a step backwards, and we are sure that if this bombing stopped and there is a real ceasefire we could have a dialogue among all Libyans about what they  want — democracy, political reform, constitution, election. This could not be done with what is going on now," said Obeidi.</p>
<p>The move comes as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_Nations">UN</ref> officials condemn the use of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/cluster%20bombs">cluster bombs</ref> that are in use by pro-Gaddaffi forces, a tactic banned under the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convention%20on%20Cluster%20Munitions">Convention on Cluster Munitions</ref>, of which Libya is not a signatory. </p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UN%20High%20Commissioner%20for%20Human%20Rights">UN High Commissioner for Human Rights</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Navi%20Pillay">Navi Pillay</ref> stated, amidst reports of snipers attacking civilians in many towns, that use of such munitions would "inevitably lead to civilian casualties", whilst also calling for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NATO">NATO</ref> forces to "exercise the utmost caution and vigilance so as not to kill civilians by mistake". Pillay praised the Libyan government for allowing on Monday a U.N. humanitarian base in the capital city of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tripoli">Tripoli</ref>.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, fighting has continued between rebel and pro-government forces this Wednesday in the besieged western port city of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Misrata">Misrata</ref>, where residents are pleading for international intervention. </p>
<p>British photojournalist <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim%20Hetherington">Tim Hetherington</ref>, who co-directed the documentary film <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Restrepo">Restrepo</ref></hi>, which was nominated for an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academy%20Award%20for%20Best%20Documentary%20Feature">Academy Award for Best Documentary Feature</ref> this year, died from wounds he suffered in an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rocket-propelled%20grenade">RPG</ref> attack in the city. </p>
<hi rend="bold">In besieged Libyan city of Misrata. Indiscriminate shelling by Qaddafi forces. No sign of NATO.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—Tim Hetherington's last tweet</p>
<p>His colleagues, photographers <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris%20Hondros">Chris Hondros</ref> and Guy Martin were also severely wounded. Hondros suffered a severe brain injury leaving him in a critical condition and eventually succumbed to his injury at a triage center and Martin, a British citizen, was injured by shrapnel, and is now receiving <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/vascular">vascular</ref> surgery. Another with the group, Michael Christopher Brown also received shrapnel wounds which were not life-threatening. </p>
<p>Hetherington last updated his <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Twitter</ref> account on Tuesday, which read, "In besieged Libyan city of Misrata. Indiscriminate shelling by Qaddafi forces. No sign of NATO."</p>
<p>Leaders in the rebel-held city called  for the urgent intervention of foreign ground troops to protect the  500,000 civilians there, the first  such request by anyone among Libya's  opposition forces. The rebels' civilian leadership, the Transitional National Council, has however rejected the presence of foreign troops on Libyan soil to help  their cause.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, across the country, NATO airstrikes again struck government installations in several cities. </p>
</text>
