<text id="autogum_news_doc500" title="U.S. Attorney General Jeff Sessions bows out of Russia investigation over contact with ambassador" shortTile="us-attorney-general" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-03-03" dateModified="2018-02-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._Attorney_General_Jeff_Sessions_bows_out_of_Russia_investigation_over_contact_with_ambassador" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>U.S. Attorney General Jeff Sessions bows out of Russia investigation over contact with ambassador</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, March 5, 2017</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S.">U.S.</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US%20Attorney%20General">Attorney General</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jeff_Sessions">Jeff Sessions</ref> on Thursday recused himself from any investigation of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russian_interference_in_the_2016_United_States_elections">alleged interference</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2016_U.S._presidential_race">2016 U.S. presidential race</ref> but reserved the right to make decisions "on a case-by-case basis" about other issues involving Russian hacking.</p>
<hi rend="bold">I have decided to recuse myself from any existing or future investigations of any matters related in any way to the campaigns for President of the United States</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—U.S. Attorney General Jeff Sessions</p>
<p>"I have decided," Sessions told the press, "to recuse myself from any existing or future investigations of any matters related in any way to the campaigns for President of the United States."</p>
<p>During his confirmation hearing on January 10, Sessions was asked about contact between the Russian government and now-President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref>'s campaign.  He responded, "I did not have communications with the Russians."  However, he met twice with Russian ambassador <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sergey%20Kislyak">Sergey Kislyak</ref>, whom the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20Department%20of%20Justice">U.S. Justice Department</ref> considers a spy.  A spokesperson for Sessions said those meetings, like meetings he had with other ambassadors, were in his capacity as a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Senate">Senator</ref> and member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Armed%20Services%20Committee">Armed Services Committee</ref> and not as a member of the Trump campaign, which is why he feels his answer was not truly misleading.</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_House_of_Representatives">House</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House%20Minority%20Leader">Minority Leader</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nancy_Pelosi">Nancy Pelosi</ref> has called for Sessions to resign entirely. Democrats want a special prosecutor to investigate the Russians' role in the election, but there are not enough of them in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Congress">Congress</ref> to force this. Sessions' statement delegated his duties to his acting deputy, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dana%20Boente">Dana Boente</ref>. </p>
<p>"Jeff Sessions is an honest man. He did not say anything wrong. He could have stated his response more accurately, but it was clearly not intentional [...]" said <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">President Trump</ref> in an official statement defending Sessions. "[The Democrats] lost the election and now, they have lost their grip on reality. The real story is all of the illegal leaks of classified and other information. It is a total witch hunt!"</p>
<figure><caption>File photo of Jeff Sessions, 2016.  Image: US Customs and Border Protection (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/flickr">flickr</ref>).</caption></figure>
<hi rend="bold">Jeff Sessions is an honest man. He did not say anything wrong. He could have stated his response more accurately, but it was clearly not intentional</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—President Donald J. Trump</p>
<p>Although Sessions has recused himself from any such investigation, it was not disclosed to the public whether the Justice Department is, in fact, conducting one. The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._Federal_Bureau_of_Investigation">U.S. Federal Bureau of Investigation</ref> has done some exploration and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House%20Intelligence%20Committee">House Intelligence Committee</ref> has commissioned an inquiry, but Sessions' statement reads "This announcement should not be interpreted as confirmation of the existence of any investigation or suggestive of the scope of any such investigation."</p>
<p>Earlier this year, National Security Advisor <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Michael_Flynn">Michael Flynn</ref> resigned, also over concerns of impropriety related to contact with the Russian ambassador.</p>
</text>
