<text id="autogum_news_doc307" title="FIFA World Cup 2018 quarterfinals: France, Belgium beat Uruguay, Brazil" shortTile="fifa-world-cup--quarterfinals" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-07-06" dateModified="2018-10-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/FIFA_World_Cup_2018_quarterfinals%3A_France%2C_Belgium_beat_Uruguay%2C_Brazil" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>FIFA World Cup 2018 quarterfinals: France, Belgium beat Uruguay, Brazil</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 9, 2018</hi></p>
<p>On Friday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref> defeated <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Uruguay">Uruguay</ref> 2–0 in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/FIFA">FIFA</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Soccer">football</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2018_FIFA_World_Cup">World Cup</ref> quarter-finals and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref> lost 1–2 against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Belgium">Belgium</ref>. With this defeat only countries from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UEFA">UEFA</ref> Confederation are now remaining in the tournament.</p>
<head id="France_vs_Uruguay">France vs Uruguay</head>
<p>France faced Uruguay at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nizhny%20Novgorod%20Stadium">Nizhny Novgorod Stadium</ref>. The French side had better ball possession. Uruguayan striker <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edinson_Cavani">Edinson Cavani</ref> was rested for the match and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Luis_Suárez">Luis Suárez</ref> faced his <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/FC_Barcelona">FC Barcelona</ref> teammate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel%20Umtiti">Samuel Umtiti</ref> in the quarter-final clash. Both the sides had early attempts to open the scoring. Uruguay blocked <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/N'Golo%20Kanté">N'Golo Kanté</ref>'s 12th-minute attempt for a goal. Three minutes later, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kylian%20Mbappé">Kylian Mbappé</ref> missed a chance from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Olivier_Giroud">Olivier Giroud</ref>'s pass to put France in the lead. In the 19th minute, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paul_Pogba">Paul Pogba</ref> also had an attempt for goal but went wide. France opened the scoring in the 40th minute when <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Raphaël_Varane">Raphaël Varane</ref> scored a header from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Antoine_Griezmann">Antoine Griezmann</ref>'s assist. Minutes before the half-time, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugo%20Lloris">Hugo Lloris</ref> saved a shot preventing Uruguay from equalising, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diego%20Godín">Diego Godín</ref> missed a close-range shot. The first half ended with France having a one-goal lead.</p>
<p>In the second half, just after the one-hour mark, Griezmann doubled the lead for France, scoring a goal from outside the penalty area from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corentin%20Tolisso">Corentin Tolisso</ref>'s assist. In the final ten minutes of the 90-minute play, French side made two substitutions, as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steven%20N'Zonzi">Steven N'Zonzi</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ousmane%20Dembélé">Ousmane Dembélé</ref> replaced Tolisso and Mbappé. The match ended 2–0.</p>
<p>After the match, France's coach <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Didier%20Deschamps">Didier Deschamps</ref> said, "We had done something big against Argentina and today we have again raised our level. I have a good team that still has plenty of room for improvement. You can see our lack of experience sometimes, but we have so many qualities too."</p>
<p>Uruguayan coach <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Óscar%20Tabárez">Óscar Tabárez</ref> said, "The boys really gave everything, but France were able to control the match very well. After the second goal, there was a huge gap between the teams."</p>
<p>With this victory, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UEFA_Euro_2016">UEFA Euro 2016</ref>-finalists France reached the semi-finals of the FIFA World Cup for the sixth time.</p>
<head id="Brazil_vs_Belgium">Brazil vs Belgium</head>
<p>Brazil faced Belgium at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kazan%20Arena">Kazan Arena</ref>. After Uruguay's defeat against France, Brazil was the only South American nation left in the tournament. The South Americans had better ball possession. In the 8th minute, Brazilian captain <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thiago%20Silva">Thiago Silva</ref> missed a chance to open the scoring as his header rebounded from the goalpost. Belgian defender <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vincent%20Kompany">Vincent Kompany</ref> missed a header in the 13th minute from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nacer%20Chadli">Nacer Chadli</ref> assist, but Fernandinho scored an own goal, giving Belgium an early lead. A couple of minutes later, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabriel%20Jesus">Gabriel Jesus</ref> had an attempt to equalise, from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Neymar">Neymar</ref>'s assist, but the shot was blocked. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Marcelo_Vieira">Marcelo</ref> also attempted for a goal in the 26th minute but was saved.</p>
<p>In the 31st minute, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kevin%20De%20Bruyne">Kevin De Bruyne</ref> scored from outside the penalty area, doubling the lead for Belgium, assisted by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Romelu_Lukaku">Romelu Lukaku</ref>. Six minutes later, Belgian goalkeeper <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Thibaut_Courtois">Thibaut Courtois</ref> saved a long-range shot by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Philippe_Coutinho">Philippe Coutinho</ref>. The first half ended and Belgium had a two-goal advantage.</p>
<p>At the start of the second half, Brazil made a substitution as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roberto%20Firmino">Roberto Firmino</ref> replaced <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Willian%20Borges">Willian</ref>. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/José%20Paulo%20Bezerra%20Maciel%20Júnior">Paulinho</ref> had an attempt in the 55th minute. Paulinho was substituted off in the 73rd minute for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renato%20Augusto">Renato Augusto</ref> and just three minutes after coming on, Augusto scored the first goal for Brazil in the 76th minute. Chadli was subbed off in the 83rd minute due to injury and was replaced by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas%20Vermaelen">Thomas Vermaelen</ref>. Brazil tried to score an equaliser, but the match ended 2–1 as Belgium advanced to the semi-final.</p>
<p>After the match, Belgium's coach <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roberto%20Martinez">Roberto Martinez</ref> said, "Brazil have so much finesse and you know that they can cut you open. But I didn't think for one second that the players would give up. They've done something special and I hope everyone in Belgium is very, very proud. It has created a nice memory and we should treasure it. But now we need more energy for our next game to try to make sure we're just as good in the semi-finals."</p>
<p>Brazil's coach <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adenor%20Bacchi">Tite</ref> said, ""I thought it was a great match and we had a lot of it, with plenty of possession and a lot of opportunities. But Belgium were more effective in converting their opportunities. They have a lot of top players and finished well. Thibaut Courtois also made a real difference. For all the pain I feel right now, if you like football, you have to watch this game. It's going to give you pleasure."</p>
<p>Belgium is now scheduled to face France in the semi-finals.</p>
July 6, 2018 1700 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow%20Time">MSK</ref> (UTC+0300)
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Uruguay">Uruguay</ref></hi>
<hi rend="bold">0–2</hi>
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref></hi>
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nizhny%20Novgorod%20Stadium">Nizhny Novgorod Stadium</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nizhny%20Novgorod">Nizhny Novgorod</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref> Attendance: 43,319 Referee:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Néstor%20Pitana">Néstor Pitana</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asociación%20del%20Fútbol%20Argentino">Argentina</ref>)
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rodrigo%20Bentancur">Rodrigo Bentancur</ref>  38'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cristian%20Rodríguez">Cristian Rodríguez</ref>  69'
0–1 (HT)
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Raphaël_Varane">Raphaël Varane</ref>  40'<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Antoine_Griezmann">Antoine Griezmann</ref>  61'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucas%20Hernández">Lucas Hernández</ref>  33'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kylian%20Mbappé">Kylian Mbappé</ref>  69'
July 6, 2018 2100 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moscow%20Time">MSK</ref> (UTC+0300)
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref></hi>
<hi rend="bold">1–2</hi>
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Belgium">Belgium</ref></hi>
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kazan%20Arena">Kazan Arena</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kazan">Kazan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref> Attendance: 42,873 Referee:  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milorad%20Mažić">Milorad Mažić</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fudbalski%20savez%20Srbije">Serbia</ref>)
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renato%20Augusto">Renato Augusto</ref>  76'Fernandinho  85'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fagner%20Conserva%20Lemos">Fangar</ref>  90'
0–2 (HT)
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fernando%20Luiz%20Roza">Fernandinho</ref>  13'(o.g.)<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kevin%20De%20Bruyne">Kevin De Bruyne</ref>  31'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Toby%20Alderweireld">Toby Alderweireld</ref>  47'<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Thomas_Meunier">Thomas Meunier</ref>  71'
</text>
