<text id="autogum_news_doc455" title="Arrest made as mayor of Gdańsk, Poland stabbed on stage" shortTile="arrest-made-mayor" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2019-01-13" dateModified="2019-02-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Arrest_made_as_mayor_of_Gda%C5%84sk%2C_Poland_stabbed_on_stage" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Arrest made as mayor of Gdańsk, Poland stabbed on stage</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 14, 2019</hi></p>
<p>An individual has been arrested after <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paweł_Adamowicz">Paweł Adamowicz</ref>, mayor of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Poland">Polish</ref> city of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gdańsk">Gdańsk</ref>, was stabbed last night whilst on stage at a fundraising event. He died today.</p>
<hi rend="bold">We couldn’t win</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Łukasz Szumowski on the failed efforts to save the mayor's life</p>
<p>Reports on the implement used vary between a knife and a "sharp tool". The attacker is reported to have jumped on stage during the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great%20Orchestra%20of%20Christmas%20Charity">Great Orchestra of Christmas Charity</ref> and claimed he was wrongfully imprisoned under Adamowicz's former party <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civic%20Platform">Civic Platform</ref>'s time in government. Adamowicz was an early supporter of democracy, and has been mayor since 1998.</p>
<p>Ex-Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Tusk">Donald Tusk</ref>, the current President of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European%20Council">European Council</ref>, wrote "Let's all pray for Mayor Adamowicz. Paweł, we are with you." Tusk, a founding Civic Platform member, is from Gdańsk. Interior Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joachim%20Brudziński">Joachim Brudziński</ref> called the stabbing "an act of inexplicable barbarity." He said "I can’t find the words, an explanation, for this kind of act. Especially since the finale of the Great Orchestra of Christmas Charity has for the last 27 years always been associated with good, with something joyful, positive." </p>
<p>The fundraiser was intending this year to obtain money for children's hospitals to buy equipment. It raises money annually to assist the nation's medical services.</p>
<p>Brudziński said Adamowicz required resuscitation, and was in a "serious" condition; <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TVN24">TVN24</ref> reported he received surgery. Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mateusz%20Morawiecki">Mateusz Morawiecki</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">tweeted</ref> "We are with Mayor Adamowicz in our <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/thoughts%20and%20prayers">thoughts and prayers</ref>." President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Andrzej_Duda">Andrzej Duda</ref> remarked, "Today I am unconditionally with him and his loved ones, just as I hope all of us compatriots are. I pray for his return to health and full strength."</p>
<figure><caption>Adamowicz from file, last year.Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:1rhb">Rudolf H. Boettcher</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Duda told local media Adamowicz's heart was restarted by doctors "and there is hope, but his condition is very difficult." Police spokesman Mariusz Ciarka said a press badge was used by the assailant, reported by <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Guardian">The Guardian</ref></hi> as convicted of assaults and by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Associated_Press">Associated Press</ref> of bank robberies, to gain entry. The detained suspect's identity is restricted to 'Stefan W' owing to Polish privacy legislation.</p>
<p>Adamowicz was taken to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medical%20University%20of%20Gdańsk">Medical University of Gdańsk</ref>, where Dr. Tomasz Stefaniak was met with applause early today upon announcing to journalists Adamowicz remained alive. "The next hours will decide everything," Stefaniak said. Politicians and the Archbishop of Gdańsk, Sławoj Leszek Głódź, were reported by local media to have visited the hospital while Adamowicz received emergency surgery.</p>
<p>Adamowicz subsequently was announced to have died. Health Minister Łukasz Szumowski said "We couldn’t win," and the city flag is at half-mast. Gdańsk residents donated blood by the hundreds today in a bid to assist. Vigils nationwide this evening were attended by thousands.</p>
<p>Adamowicz, 53, has supported <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/LGBT">LGBT</ref> rights and and the inclusion of minority groups. He recently condemned <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/anti-semitism">anti-semitism</ref> after vandalism against a synagogue in the city. Adamowicz was at the event after collecting money for the organisation in Gdańsk's streets alongside volunteers nationwide.</p>
<p>A potential charge of murder against Stefan W carries a possible life sentence. Prosecutor Krzysztof Sierak told reporters today psychiatric assessments will be carried out to confirm if Stefan W is fit for trial.</p>
</text>
