<text id="autogum_news_doc159" title="&apos;Save the Children&apos; organisation suspends all activities in Afghanistan after ISIL attack" shortTile="save-children-organisation" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2018-01-24" dateModified="2018-02-03" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/%27Save_the_Children%27_organisation_suspends_all_activities_in_Afghanistan_after_ISIL_attack" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>'Save the Children' organisation suspends all activities in Afghanistan after ISIL attack</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, January 26, 2018</hi></p>
<p>Wednesday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">UK</ref>-based non-governmental charity organisation <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Save%20the%20Children">Save the Children</ref> announced in an official statement on their website the temporary suspension of all their activities in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Afghanistan">Afghanistan</ref>. The reason for this is an <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islamic_State_of_Iraq_and_the_Levant">ISIL</ref>-claimed attack on a Save the Children office in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jalalabad">Jalalabad</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nangarhar%20Province">Nangarhar</ref>, which cost the lives of three staff members of the charity. </p>
<p>A group of militants attacked Save the Children's office after a suicide car explosion Wednesday morning just after 9 AM, local time. Staff member Zabiullah told <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Guardian">The Guardian</ref></hi> he heard "a very big explosion", after which he and his friends "rushed the basement". According to the latest reports, the attackers killed six people in total and injured more than two dozen people. One eyewitness said the attackers used <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/rocket-propelled%20grenade">rocket-propelled grenades</ref> to blast the compound gates, according to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BBC">BBC</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>Location of Nangarhar within Afghanistan Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/user:TUBS">TUBS</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>A spokesperson for Nangarhar's governor said in a statement, six militants were involved in the attack. Later, in an updated statement, he said there were only five and all of them were killed. Afghan security personnel said the attackers killed two soldiers, two guards and two civilians. Sohrab Qaderi, a government member of Nangarhar province, said about four dozen people were rescued from the basement of the building, most of whom were Save the Children employees. They managed to escape through a back exit, one of them told the BBC afterwards. It took about ten hours to stop the attack, Qaderi added.</p>
<p>"We have temporarily suspended our operations across the country following today's events, however we remain fully committed to helping the most deprived children of Afghanistan", stated Save the Children in an official statement published Wednesday. They added, "We remain committed to resuming our operations and lifesaving work as quickly as possible, as soon as we can be assured that it is safe to do so." Furthermore, the organisation confirmed in the statement the death of three of its own staff members, one of whom was one of the two killed civilians. They also said four other staff members, who were injured, were receiving medical aid. </p>
<p>Via <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amaq%20news%20agency">Amaq news agency</ref>, militant group <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islamic_State_of_Iraq_and_the_Levant">Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant</ref> (ISIL) has claimed the responsibility of the attack, calling British and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Swedish</ref> foundations, as well as institutes of the Afghan government, the targets of the attack.</p>
<p>Save the Children established operations in Afghanistan in 1976. As of 2018, it was present in sixteen Afghan provinces. In recent years, several attacks on rescue organisations have taken place northern Afghanistan. In February 2017, six people working for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Red_Cross">Red Cross</ref> were killed in Dasth-e-Leili, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jowzjan%20Province">Jowzjan Province</ref> while delivering humanitarian aid. Nine members of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Czech_Republic">Czech</ref>-based organisation <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/People%20in%20Need%20(Czech%20Republic)">People in Need</ref> were killed in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balkh">Balkh</ref> in 2015; and in 2013, six staff members of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agency%20for%20Technical%20Cooperation%20and%20Development">ACTED</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">French</ref> charity, were shot dead in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Faryab">Faryab</ref>.</p>
</text>
