<text id="autogum_news_doc147" title="UN Secretary-General expresses concern about crises in Chad, Kenya, Sudan" shortTile="un-secretarygeneral" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-02-07" dateModified="2011-08-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UN_Secretary-General_expresses_concern_about_crises_in_Chad%2C_Kenya%2C_Sudan" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>UN Secretary-General expresses concern about crises in Chad, Kenya, Sudan</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 7, 2008</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20Nations%20Secretary-General">United Nations Secretary-General</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ban%20Ki-moon">Ban Ki-moon</ref> has expressed concern about crises in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chad">Chad</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kenya">Kenya</ref>, and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sudan">Sudan</ref>. The U.N. chief is recently back from Africa where he attended the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African%20Union">African Union</ref> summit in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethiopia">Ethiopia</ref> and met with leaders in Kenya.</p>
<p>On rebel efforts to overthrow the government in Chad in recent days, the secretary-general welcomed an African Union initiative to have the leaders of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Libya">Libya</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic%20Republic%20of%20Congo">Democratic Republic of Congo</ref> mediate the crisis. He says the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20Nations">United Nations</ref> will do its utmost to help resolve the crisis, urging the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Security%20Council">Security Council</ref> to act swiftly to help bring an end to the violence.</p>
<p>"It has devastating consequences not only for the people of Chad and Darfurian refugees seeking shelter there, but also for Darfur itself," said Ban.</p>
<p>Mr. Ban told reporters the situation in the neighboring <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darfur">Darfur</ref> region of Sudan is no less troubling. He says the deployment of the AU-U.N. peacekeeping force, known as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UNAMID">UNAMID</ref>, must be sped up and urged member states to properly equip the troops.</p>
<p>"UNAMID still lacks required aviation and ground transportation - chiefly helicopters. Additional troops will not make up for this shortfall," said Ban. "Those countries that called for intervention in Darfur are under special obligation to deliver on their promises."</p>
<p>While at the AU summit, Mr. Ban says he discussed some of the outstanding issues affecting the deployment with Sudanese President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Omar%20al-Bashir">Omar al-Bashir</ref>, and he expects the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Status%20of%20Forces%20Agreement">Status of Forces Agreement</ref> (SOFA) to be signed this week. But Mr. Ban remained vague on whether some of the agreement's sticking points - such as night flights, land agreements, and advance notice of U.N. movements - had been settled.</p>
<p>On Kenya, Mr. Ban says he has been deeply engaged in the post-election crisis and told political leaders during his visit there that they bear particular responsibility for the future of Kenya.</p>
<p>"I stressed to all the Kenyan leaders the need to stop the unacceptable violence and killings, and to resolve their differences through dialogue and democratic process. I also appealed to all the political leaders to think beyond their individual interests or party lines and to look to the future of Kenya as one country," he said.</p>
<p>Mr. Ban also met in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nairobi">Nairobi</ref> with his U.N. predecessor, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kofi%20Annan">Kofi Annan</ref>, who is leading the panel of eminent Africans trying to mediate the crisis, and said they discussed his roadmap for the talks.</p>
<p>Security of U.N. personnel in Africa and elsewhere has been high on the secretary-general's agenda, especially in the wake of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/December%2011,%202007%20Algiers%20bombings">December bombing</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algeria">Algeria</ref> that killed 17 staff members. Mr. Ban announced that he is naming diplomat <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lakhdar%20Brahimi">Lakhdar Brahimi</ref> to chair an independent panel on safety and security of U.N. personnel and premises. Brahimi is an Algerian, but Mr. Ban says he has no concerns about his fairness or objectivity in heading up the panel.</p>
</text>
