<text id="autogum_news_doc755" title="Four aftershocks hit central Chile; no damages reported" shortTile="four-aftershocks" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-11-28" dateModified="2014-04-14" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Four_aftershocks_hit_central_Chile%3B_no_damages_reported" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Four aftershocks hit central Chile; no damages reported</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, November 28, 2010</hi></p>
<figure><caption>"It catched my mother in Pichilemu. She got dressed in case of she having to flee to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La%20Cruz%20Hill">[La Cruz] Hill</ref>," Bárbara Ponce said. In the picture, people staying in the La Cruz Hill after the March 11 earthquake. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>USGS' location map for the 08:19 UTC aftershock. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Geological_Survey">United States Geological Survey</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>Four strong aftershocks have occurred on today's early morning in Chile. The fourth and strongest quake had a 5.6 magnitude in the Richter scale. No damage was reported.</p>
<p>The first shaking took place at 00:37 local time (03:37 UTC), which according to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Chile">University of Chile Seismological Service</ref> had a 4.7 magnitude in the Richter scale. It occurred 64 kilometers west of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Navidad,%20Chile">Navidad</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/O'Higgins_Region">O'Higgins Region</ref> at a depth of 31 kilometers, University of Chile reported. It was felt in cities such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melipilla">Melipilla</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Santiago_Metropolitan_Region">Santiago Metropolitan Region</ref>), <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pichilemu">Pichilemu</ref> (O'Higgins Region) and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rancagua">Rancagua</ref> (O'Higgins Region).</p>
<p>The second tremor took place at 02:21 local time (05:21 UTC), 18 kilometers southwest of Rancagua, O'Higgins Region at a depth of 90.8 kilometers. It had a magnitude of 4.1.</p>
<p>At 04:31 local time (07:31 UTC), the third movement occurred. With a magnitude of 4.3, it occurred 34 kilometers northwest of Talca, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maule%20Region">Maule Region</ref>, near <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lolol">Lolol</ref> at a depth of 65.1 kilometers.</p>
<p>The fourth shake took place at 05:19 local time (08:19 UTC). According to the University of Chile, it had a magnitude of 5.6, and occurred 32 kilometers south of Pichilemu, O'Higgins Region at a depth of 41.9 kilometers. According to ONEMI, there were no casualties nor damage provoked by the aftershock. This movement was felt across the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Valparaíso_Region">Valparaíso</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Santiago_Metropolitan_Region">Santiago Metropolitan</ref>, O'Higgins, Maule, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bío%20Bío%20Region">Bío Bío</ref> Regions, in cities such as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Valparaíso">Valparaíso</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viña%20del%20Mar">Viña del Mar</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santiago%20(commune)">Santiago Centro</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/San%20Fernando,%20Chile">San Fernando</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curicó">Curicó</ref>, Talca, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitución,%20Chile">Constitución</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talcahuano">Talcahuano</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cauquenes">Cauquenes</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concepción,%20Chile">Concepción</ref>. Chile's National System of Tsunami Alerts ruled out the possibility of a tsunami, according to <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radio%20Cooperativa">Radio Cooperativa</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>"In Rancagua, it all was really shake-y," said Daniela Banda Sandoval, a Facebook user who commented on Pichilemu's Facebook page. "[It was felt] very strong[ly] here in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Santa_Cruz,_Chile">Santa Cruz</ref>, in addition of being noisy, it was as strong as the [February] earthquake!," Agustín Toro Reyes said. "At least we are sure now the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ONEMI">ONEMI</ref>'s guy was awake! Jinx <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ricardo%20Arjona">Arjona</ref>... drift away from Chile!," Ro Fernandez said on Pichilemu's page, referring to ONEMI's late response after the February 27 earthquake and Ricardo Arjona's announcement to visit Chile. Arjona was one of the last artists to perform on the 2010 Viña del Mar International Festival before the February earthquake.</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Geological_Survey">United States Geological Survey</ref>, however, reported that the earthquake had a magnitude of 5.4, and that it occurred at a depth of 35 kilometers, 60 kilometers northwest of Curicó, Maule Region.</p>
<p>A further aftershock occurred at 06:57 local time (09:57 UTC), which was of a lesser magnitude.</p>
</text>
