<text id="autogum_news_doc503" title="Putin calls US troops in Poland &apos;a threat&apos;" shortTile="putin-calls-troops" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-01-13" dateModified="2017-01-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Putin_calls_US_troops_in_Poland_%27a_threat%27" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Putin calls US troops in Poland 'a threat'</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, January 13, 2017</hi></p>
<p>Reports yesterday indicated <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russian</ref> President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Vladimir_Putin">Vladimir Putin</ref> views the arrival of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> troops in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Poland">Poland</ref> as "a threat".</p>
<figure><caption>US troops and tanks in Poland in 2015, as part of an earlier deployment under <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation%20Atlantic%20Resolve">Operation Atlantic Resolve</ref>.Image: Sgt. Christina Dion (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/US%20Army">US Army</ref>).</caption></figure>
<p>Earlier this week around a quarter of 4,000 troops earmarked for Poland crossed into Poland from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref>. Also included were trucks, tanks, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humvee">Humvee</ref>s. Many are set to be based in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Żagań">Żagań</ref>, where Polish Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Beata_Szydło">Beata Szydło</ref> and Defence Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antoni%20Macierewicz">Antoni Macierewicz</ref> are scheduled to ceremonially welcome them tomorrow.</p>
<p>Part of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation%20Atlantic%20Resolve">Operation Atlantic Resolve</ref>, the deployment is set to include <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M1%20Abrams">Abrams</ref> tanks, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bradley%20Fighting%20Vehicle">Bradley Fighting Vehicle</ref>s, and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M109%20howitzer">Paladin artillery</ref>. It is the largest deployment of US troops to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Europe">Europe</ref> since the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cold%20War">Cold War</ref> ended. The presence of US assets "threatens our interests and our security," according to Putin. "It's a third country that is building up its military presence on our borders in Europe," he told the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BBC">BBC</ref>. "It isn't even a European country."</p>
<p>Outgoing US President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> authorised the move in response to Russian intervention in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ukraine">Ukraine</ref> in 2014, in which <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Crimea">Crimea</ref> was annexed. It was agreed at a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/NATO">NATO</ref> summit in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Warsaw">Warsaw</ref> last year. Tomasz Szatkowski, Polish Undersecretary of State for Defence, noted "large exercises" by Russia near the Polish border as another reason the troops were needed.</p>
<p>Szatkowski also mentioned Russian action in Ukraine, which he called "aggressive actions in our vicinity". Russian Deputy Foreign Minister Alexei Mechkov, however, said the incoming troops and vehicles were a "factor destabilising European security". Russian Presidential spokesperson Dmitry Peskov echoed Putin, saying the troops are "a threat. These actions threaten our interests, our security. Especially as it concerns a third party building up its military presence near our borders. It's [the US], not even a European state."</p>
<p>Ties between Russia and the US are strained. Last month the US expelled 35 Russian diplomats accused of espionage, and sanctioned Russian intelligence agencies. This was in response to a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Central_Intelligence_Agency">CIA</ref> report issued two weeks earlier that concluded the Russian government hacked servers belonging to the U.S. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Republican_Party">Republican</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Democratic_Party">Democratic</ref> parties. The CIA report said this was to turn the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2016_U.S._presidential_election">2016 presidential election</ref> toward president-elect <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref>.</p>
<p>Since Szydło took office in 2015, Poland has also suffered a decline in relations with Russia. Within a week of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Law_and_Justice_Party">Law and Justice Party</ref> coming to power in Poland, it removed web pages featuring the results of an investigation into the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2010%20Polish%20Air%20Force%20Tu-154%20crash">Smolensk air disaster</ref> in Russia in 2010. The cause of the crash, which killed dignitaries including Polish President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lech%20Kaczynski">Lech Kaczynski</ref>, is disputed. </p>
<p>A Polish probe concluded the Polish pilots put safety second in their determination to get their passengers through dense fog. It also placed blame on Russian controllers for failing to divert the aircraft. Russian investigators blamed the pilots alone. The flight was carrying high-profile political figures to attend a ceremony commemorating the 70th anniversary of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Katyn%20massacre">Katyn massacre</ref>, when thousands of Polish prisoners of war and civilians were killed by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Soviet_Union">Soviets</ref>.</p>
<p>Russia has refused to return wreckage, encouraging conspiracy theories about the crash. In 2015 Szydło said in response to the vanishing investigatory findings "the website has been closed and will simply remain closed." </p>
<p>In recent months tension has mounted further as Russia deployed missiles to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalingrad">Kalingrad</ref>. The enclave, Russian territory lying between Poland and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lithuania">Lithuania</ref>, now has <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nuclear_weapons">nuclear</ref>-capable <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/9K720%20Iskander">Iskanders</ref> and anti-ship <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K-300P%20Bastion-P">Bastion equipment</ref>. NATO considered these deployments a response to its own.</p>
<p>The US troops are set to rotate around the Balkans every nine months. Other planned host nations are <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Estonia">Estonia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Latvia">Latvia</ref>, Lithuania, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Romania">Romania</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bulgaria">Bulgaria</ref>, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hungary">Hungary</ref>. The rotation is due to a treaty with Russia preventing permanent deployment to any particular territory. </p>
<p>Russia-US relations face a potential thaw, as President-Elect <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref> moves towards office on January 20. Trump has made clear he intends to seek a closer relationship with Russia. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rex%20Tillerson">Rex Tillerson</ref>, proposed Secretary of State for the Trump administration, implied the troops would be staying put. He said Russia had claimed Crimea "as an act of force" requiring the US to offer "a proportional show of force".</p>
<p>Trump's proposed Secretary of Defense, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James%20Mattis">James Mattis</ref>, backed NATO before the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Senate">US Senate</ref> yesterday. He said Putin aimed to weaken the NATO alliance. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Witold%20Waszczykowski">Witold Waszczykowski</ref>, Polish foreign minister, earlier this week remarked any improvement in US-Russia relations should avoid harming Polish interests.</p>
</text>
