<text id="autogum_news_doc531" title="Reflections, Lichtenstein, two new exhibitions at Edinburgh&apos;s Modern One" shortTile="reflections-lichtenstein" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-03-14" dateModified="2015-10-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Reflections%2C_Lichtenstein%2C_two_new_exhibitions_at_Edinburgh%27s_Modern_One" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Reflections, Lichtenstein, two new exhibitions at Edinburgh's Modern One</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 14, 2015</hi></p>
<p>This weekend saw the opening of two new exhibitions at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish%20National%20Gallery%20of%20Modern%20Art">National Gallery of Modern Art</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> attended Thursday's press preview for the event where a full contingent of the capital's press turned out to see the striking collection of paintings, photographs, and other works. Presented below are a selection of images captured at the preview.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">REFLECTIONS: A Series of Changing Displays of Contemporary Art</hi>, billed as a showcase of a "diverse range of internationally-renowned contemporary and modern artists" is to display major works from the Gallery's permanent collection, alongside important loans. Alongside this broad range of works, a three-room display of pieces on-loan from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roy%20Lichtenstein">Roy Lichtenstein</ref> Foundation — with a dramatic painted steel relief, 'borrowed' from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tate%20Britain">Tate</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/London">London</ref> — runs from March 14 through to January 10 next year.</p>
<p>Admission to both exhibitions is free; being located in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dean%20Village">Dean</ref>, to the north-west of Edinburgh's city centre, a free Gallery bus service is available.</p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref>'s press pack at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roy%20Lichtenstein">Roy Lichtenstein</ref> exhibition preview. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>The exterior of the <hi rend="italic">Modern One</hi> building of Edinburgh's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish%20National%20Gallery%20of%20Modern%20Art">Scottish National Gallery of Modern Art</ref>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>A film crew sets up with one of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roy%20Lichtenstein's">Roy Lichtenstein's</ref> works as a backdrop, and the steel roundel on-loan from the Tate Gallery in London dramatically displayed on the wall of the main Artists' Room. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>The exterior of the <hi rend="italic">Modern One</hi> building of Edinburgh's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish%20National%20Gallery%20of%20Modern%20Art">Scottish National Gallery of Modern Art</ref>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>A rather unusual installation; part of the <hi rend="italic">REFLECTIONS</hi> exhibition at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish%20National%20Gallery%20of%20Modern%20Art">Scottish National Gallery of Modern Art</ref>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Dorothy Lichtenstein, at the press preview for an exhibition of her late husband's works. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>A pair of Lichtenstein's paintings, hanging in the main gallery of the Artists' Rooms. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>The exterior of the <hi rend="italic">Modern One</hi> building of Edinburgh's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish%20National%20Gallery%20of%20Modern%20Art">Scottish National Gallery of Modern Art</ref>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>A selection of prints and postcards, available for sale in the Gallery's shop. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>The 'scrum' of photographers capturing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roy%20Lichtenstein">Roy Lichtenstein</ref>'s widow, Dorothy, in front of one of her late husband's paintings. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Dorothy Lichtenstein, being lit as she poses for the cameras at the press preview of her late husband's work. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Another pair of Lichtenstein's paintings, with the doorway through to another part of the Gallery. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>A corridor in the Gallery makes an effective space to display a range of the works from the <hi rend="italic">REFLECTIONS</hi> exhibit. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>The main Artists Room of the Gallery, displaying some of Lichtenstein's dramatic works. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>A different take on the corridor display part of the <hi rend="italic">REFLECTIONS</hi> exhibit, with mirror at end of corridor. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>A display of photographs from the <hi rend="italic">REFLECTIONS</hi> exhibit. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Member of the press admiring one of Lichtenstein's works at new exhibition in the <hi rend="italic">Modern One</hi> building of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish%20National%20Gallery%20of%20Modern%20Art">Scottish National Gallery of Modern Art</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>One of the display galleries hosting part of the <hi rend="italic">REFLECTIONS</hi> exhibit. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Wall of artworks making up part of the <hi rend="italic">REFLECTIONS</hi> exhibit, with mirror at end of corridor. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Press film crew sets up and tests lighting levels in front of one of Lichtenstein's most-famous works. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>The licensed cafe on the lower level of the Scottish National Gallery of Modern Art. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>The kitchen garden to the rear of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish%20National%20Gallery%20of%20Modern%20Art">Scottish National Gallery of Modern Art</ref>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>The licensed cafe on the lower level of the Scottish National Gallery of Modern Art. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Rear of the <hi rend="italic">Modern One</hi> building of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish%20National%20Gallery%20of%20Modern%20Art">Scottish National Gallery of Modern Art</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Edinburgh">Edinburgh</ref>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Display of cakes and biscuits in cafe of the <hi rend="italic">Modern One</hi> building of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish%20National%20Gallery%20of%20Modern%20Art">Scottish National Gallery of Modern Art</ref>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Douglas Gordon's dramatic <hi rend="italic">List of Names</hi> which adorns the wall of the stairwell in the <hi rend="italic">Modern One</hi> building. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
</text>
