<text id="autogum_news_doc173" title="Kurdish forces advance as international opposition to Islamic State grows" shortTile="kurdish-forces-advance" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-08-17" dateModified="2017-10-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kurdish_forces_advance_as_international_opposition_to_Islamic_State_grows" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Kurdish forces advance as international opposition to Islamic State grows</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 18, 2014</hi></p>
<p>Yesterday the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peshmerga">Peshmerga</ref>, military of the autonomous region of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kurdistan">Kurdistan</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref>, gained control of parts of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mosul%20Dam">Mosul Dam</ref>, as part of their advance against insurgents of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islamic_State_of_Iraq_and_the_Levant">Islamic State</ref>. International opposition to the Islamic militant group has grown this week.</p>
<figure><caption>Mosul Dam Image: <ref target="http://www.defendamerica.mil/articles/sep2005/a090905ms3.html">United States Army Corps of Engineers</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The Peshmerga were supported this weekend by <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> airstrikes in their attempt to push back the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sunni">Sunni</ref> insurgents, and Kurdish officials reported "good progress" in the face of "fierce resistance". <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Reuters">Reuters</ref></hi> reported eyewitness accounts of Kurdish forces successfully retaking Batmaiya and Telasqaf, mostly <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Christianity">Christian</ref> towns as close to Mosul — about 18 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/mile">miles</ref> (30 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/kilometre">km</ref>) — as they have come since June when government forces were forced out.</p>
<p>Mosul Dam, Iraq's largest <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/hydroelectric%20dam">hydroelectric dam</ref>, is vital to the region's irrigation, as well as water and power supplies. It was seized by the insurgents of the Islamic State, also known as ISIS or ISIL, on August 7, as part of their advance across Northern Iraq.</p>
<head id="International_response">International response</head>
<p>The advance of the Islamic State has prompted responses from many parts of the international community. On Friday the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UN_Security_Council">UN Security Council</ref> unanimously adopted a resolution targeting the extremist group's finances and leaders. Six individuals were named and now face travel bans, asset freezes, and arms embargoes. The resolution also warned of the possibility of other sanctions against anyone found to be trading with the Islamic State, in a move aimed at stopping their supply of weapons and economic gain from sale of oil being produced by the oil fields under their control.</p>
<figure><caption>UN security council chamber Image: Bernd Untiedt.</caption></figure>
<p>On the same day as the Security Council's resolution, foreign ministers of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Union">European Union</ref>'s member states issued a joint statement welcoming the efforts of those European states supporting Kurdish forces. This support includes the supply of military supplies from France, and humanitarian aid from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">UK</ref>, with Eastern European countries providing military materials also being transported by the UK. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">Germany</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref> were also reportedly considering the possibility of supplying aid where needed.</p>
<p>The US began launching airstrikes on August 8, and have continued to do so in support of the Kurdish forces and civilians stranded on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mount%20Sinjar">Mount Sinjar</ref>.</p>
<p>The responses from the international community follow reports of brutality against religious minorities in Northern Iraq — such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yazidi">Yazidis</ref> and Christians — accompanying the Islamic State advance across the region.</p>
<head id="Local_response">Local response</head>
<p><hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rudaw">Rudaw</ref></hi> reported from within Kurdistan that the local political parties have put aside their differences and are recruiting volunteers to send to the front. Many of these parties can trace their beginnings back to the 1960s–1990s struggle against the Iraqi army, many of whom continue to maintain militias which are now being deployed to reinforce the Kurdish army in the region. These are reported to have been joined by groups of ethnic Kurds from Iran.</p>
<p>Reports say hundreds of Yazidi volunteers are also being trained inside Kurdistan to help fight the Islamic State's advance. </p>
</text>
