<text id="autogum_news_doc492" title="Borussia Dortmund announces former Ajax coach Peter Bosz as team&apos;s new boss" shortTile="borussia-dortmund" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-06-08" dateModified="2017-12-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Borussia_Dortmund_announces_former_Ajax_coach_Peter_Bosz_as_team%27s_new_boss" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Borussia Dortmund announces former Ajax coach Peter Bosz as team's new boss</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 9, 2017</hi></p>
<p>On Tuesday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Germany">German</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Soccer">football</ref> club <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Borussia_Dortmund">Borussia Dortmund</ref> (BVB) announced <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter%20Bosz">Peter Bosz</ref> as their new head coach. Bosz, who spent one season with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Netherlands">Dutch</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eredivisie">Eredivisie</ref> runners-up <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/AFC_Ajax">Ajax</ref>, was to sign a two-year deal with the DFB Pokal winners BVB which runs through June 2019. Ajax's assistant coach Hendrie Krüzen also was to leave the Dutch side for Dortmund.</p>
<p>The 53-year-old Dutch manager led the the Dutch capital club to a second place finish in the Dutch league Eredivisie, finishing just one point below <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feyenoord%20Rotterdam">Feyenoord Rotterdam</ref> and won a silver medal in the UEFA Europa League, losing 2–0 against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Manchester_United">Manchester United</ref>.</p>
<p>Bosz's predecessor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas%20Tuchel">Thomas Tuchel</ref> led Dortmund to the DFB Pokal victory, third place finish in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bundesliga">Bundesliga</ref> the last season and a qualification to next season's <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UEFA_Champions_League">Champions League</ref> group stage. Two years ago, Tuchel succeded <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jürgen_Klopp">Jürgen Klopp</ref> and his side remained unbeaten in the home games. On May 30, days after winning his first trophy with Borussia Dortmund, the club announced Tuchel was sacked with immediate effect via their official website. "'Unfortunately we couldn't see a basis for continued work together built on trust with a successful outlook in the current personnel constellation.", the CEO said.</p>
<p>Edwin van der Sar, Ajax's General Manager said, "I have mixed feelings about this transfer. When we brought Peter in to Ajax last summer, it wasn't our intention that our partnership would end after just one season. Especially in the Europa League, we've had an amazing season. For our players, and our coach, that has attracted extra attention from clubs in top European competitions. But we couldn't go so far as to bind him to his contract, and we worked out a good deal with Dortmund. It's now up to us, prior to the start of the pre-season, to sign on a good successor." ((nl))Dutch language: ‍Ik heb gemengde gevoelens bij deze overgang. Toen we Peter vorige zomer naar Ajax haalden was het niet de bedoeling dat na één jaar alweer een einde zou komen aan de samenwerking. We hebben, met name in de Europa League, een geweldig seizoen neergezet. Net als bij onze spelers trekt dat ook voor de trainer de aandacht van clubs uit de Europese topcompetities. Het ging ons te ver om hem aan zijn contract te houden en we zijn er met Dortmund goed uitgekomen. Het is nu aan ons om, voordat de voorbereiding begint, een goede opvolger te contracteren.</p>
<p>Under former coach Thomas Tuchel, Borussia Dortmund's key players <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/İlkay%20Gündoğan">İlkay Gündoğan</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henrikh%20Mkhitaryan">Henrikh Mkhitaryan</ref> and Dortmund then-captain <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mats_Hummels">Mats Hummels</ref> left <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signal%20Iduna%20Park">Signal Iduna Park</ref> last season, but signed <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ousmane%20Dembélé">Ousmane Dembélé</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/André%20Schürrle">André Schürrle</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marc%20Bartra">Marc Bartra</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mario%20Götze">Mario Götze</ref>.</p>
<p>This season, Dortmund signed Ömer Toprak, Mahmoud Dahoud, Dan-Axel Zagadou and Maximilian Philipp.</p>
</text>
