<text id="autogum_news_doc263" title="Lebanon forms unity government with Hezbollah-led opposition" shortTile="lebanon-forms-unity" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2008-07-11" dateModified="2013-09-16" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lebanon_forms_unity_government_with_Hezbollah-led_opposition" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Lebanon forms unity government with Hezbollah-led opposition</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 11, 2008</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lebanon">Lebanese</ref> political leaders have agreed to the formation of a 30-member national unity government, in which paramilitary group <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hezbollah">Hezbollah</ref> and its political allies hold effective <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/veto">veto</ref> power in the new cabinet. The announcement came seven weeks after the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doha%20Agreement">Doha Agreement</ref>, which ended an 18-month-long <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2006–2008%20Lebanese%20political%20protests">political crisis</ref> in Lebanon.</p>
<p>A decree announcing the cabinet was signed by Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fouad%20Siniora">Fouad Siniora</ref> and President <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michel%20Suleiman">Michel Suleiman</ref>. Of the 30 member cabinet, 11 seats were given to the pro-Syria, Hezbollah-led opposition, fulfilling a promise of at least one third of the cabinet and giving them the power to veto legislation. The ruling coalition appointed 16 cabinet members, and President Suleiman chose the remaining three.</p>
<p>Only one of the 11 opposition ministers, Labor Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohammad%20Fneish">Mohammad Fneish</ref>, is from Hezbollah. The rest are from the organization's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shi'a">Shi'a</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Druze">Druze</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian">Christian</ref> allies. The opposition also secured the coveted posts of Foreign Minister, Telecommunications Minister, and Deputy Premier. </p>
<hi rend="bold">Our differences will not be resolved overnight, but we have decided to resolve them through institutions and dialogue rather than in the streets.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Prime Minister Fouad Siniora</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elias%20Murr">Elias Murr</ref> kept his post as Defense Minister, and the position of Finance Minister was given to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mohammed%20Shatah">Mohammed Shatah</ref>, who served as Siniori's senior adviser in the previous cabinet. Education Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bahia%20Hariri">Bahia Hariri</ref>, sister of slain Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rafik%20Hariri">Rafik Hariri</ref>, is the only woman in the new cabinet.</p>
<p>"Our differences will not be resolved overnight," Prime Minister Siniori said, "but we have decided to resolve them through institutions and dialogue rather than in the streets." He says the two main tasks of the new government will be "regaining confidence in the Lebanese political system" and "securing the holding of a transparent parliamentary election". </p>
<p>Under the Doha Agreement signed on May 21, Michel Suleiman became president, and the opposition and the parliamentary majority agreed to form a unity government. However, the formation of the new government was hampered by political squabbles. Parliamentary majority leader <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saad%20Hariri">Saad Hariri</ref> said the final breakthrough came when Siniora conceded to the opposition by accepting into the cabinet <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ali%20Kanso">Ali Kanso</ref>, former head of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrian%20Social%20Nationalist%20Party">Syrian Social Nationalist Party</ref>.</p>
<p>The two factions arrived at the Doha Agreement after a long series of Hezbollah-led protests against Siniora's government led to fears of a new civil war. In May, 65 people were killed in sectarian clashes initiated by Hezbollah following a government attempt to outlaw their telecommunications systems. The forces of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syrian</ref>-backed Hezbollah were largely unopposed by the Lebanese military while taking over Sunni neighborhoods in Beirut but encountered heavy losses attacking Druze controlled areas. </p>
<p>One of the issues expected to be discussed among the new government is the fate of Hezbollah's weapons, which the group claims it needs for defense against a possible <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israeli</ref> attack. Hezbollah has yet to disarm and even boasted on enhancing it's weaponry status despite it's signing of U.N. resolution 1701, calling for it's disarmament.</p>
</text>
