<text id="autogum_news_doc084" title="Wikinews Shorts: August 4, 2010" shortTile="wikinews-shorts-august" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-08-04" dateModified="2019-02-27" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wikinews_Shorts%3A_August_4%2C_2010" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Wikinews Shorts: August 4, 2010</head>Correction — August 13, 2010
This article incorrectly describes BP as 'British Petroleum'. In fact, such a company has not existed for many years as BP dropped this name when becoming a multinational company. The initials no longer stand for anything.
<p>A compilation of brief news reports for<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 4, 2010</hi>.
</p>
<head id='BP_starts_"static_kill"_to_permanently_stop_oil_spill'>BP starts "static kill" to permanently stop oil spill</head>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/BP">BP (British Petroleum)</ref> engineers began injecting drilling mud into the capped <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Deepwater_Horizon_oil_spill"><hi rend="italic">Deepwater Horizon</hi> oil well</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Gulf_of_Mexico">Gulf of Mexico</ref> as the first part of a "static kill" procedure intended to permanently stop the flow of oil into the Gulf coast. Earlier in the day, the multi-national energy company ran  "injectivity tests" to find out if the well, which had been leaking for months, could withstand the pressure of the procedure, which is meant to plug up the oil that isn't flowing because the well has been capped. The procedure, unlike the "top kill" attempted in May, is designed to proceed slowly. </p>
<p>After a day-long delay, BP declared that the procedure could safely begin and that company's senior vice president, Kent Wells, said that the afternoon pressure test "went exactly as planned". </p>
<p>The company also said that the "static kill" was only half the solution, with the other half being two relief wells that are planned to plug the well from the bottom.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sources</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Lauren Frayer. "<ref target="http://www.aolnews.com/gulf-oil-spill/article/as-bp-tests-for-top-kill-site-named-worlds-worst-ever-accidental-oil-spill/19578603?icid=main">Crews in Gulf of Mexico Begin 'Static Kill' Procedure</ref>" —<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AOL%20News">AOL News</ref></hi>, August 3 2010</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Dan Vergano. "<ref target="http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2010-08-04-spill04_ST_N.htm">BP starts 'static kill' to snuff oil well slowly, surely</ref>" —<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/USA_Today">USA Today</ref></hi>, August 3 2010</item></list>
<head id="Drunk_illegal_immigrant_kills_nun,_injures_two">Drunk illegal immigrant kills nun, injures two</head>
<p>An illegal immigrant accused of driving drunk has been charged with killing Sister Denise Mosier, a nun, and severely injuring two other nuns. Carlos Martinelly Montano, 23, has been charged with driving under the influence of alcohol (DUI) and involuntary manslaughter, following a car crash which occurred at 8:30 AM EDT on Sunday  (0030 Monday, UTC). The man has also been charged with felony driving under a revoked drivers license. The car accident occurred in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Virginia">Virginia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">USA's</ref> Prince William County. Police also said that Montano is an illegal immigrant awaiting deportation and has also repeatedly been charged with drunk driving. </p>
<p>The US <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Department%20of%20Homeland%20Security">Department of Homeland Security</ref> stated that Montano had been released in 2008, with immigration judge's review of his case pending. Homeland Security Secretary <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janet%20Napolitano">Janet Napolitano</ref> called the accident "a horrible thing" and saying, "this is a horrible case. Why is it that this individual was still out driving? He was in removal proceedings. Why were the removal proceedings taking so long?"</p>
<p>All three nuns were driving to a retreat at the Benedictine Monastery in Bristow, Va when Montano crashed into their car. Montano has been treated for injuries.</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sources</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Kathleen Miller, Associated Press. "<ref target="http://www.aolnews.com/crime/article/police-illegal-immigrant-carlos-martinelly-montano-kills-sister-denise-mosier-in-drunken-driving-crash/19580015">Police: Illegal Immigrant Driving Drunk Kills Nun</ref>" —<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AOL%20News">AOL News</ref></hi>, August 3 2010</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item>Stephen Dinan. "<ref target="http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2010/aug/2/illegal-immigrant-killed-nun-released-by-feds/?clear_cache_true">Illegal immigrant who killed nun in accident was released by feds</ref>" —<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%20Washington%20Times">The Washington Times</ref></hi>, August 2 2010</item></list>
<head id="Kenyans_to_vote_on_new_constitution">Kenyans to vote on new constitution</head>
<p>On Wednesday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Kenya">Kenyans</ref> will vote on a new constitution that intends to fix many of the country's political problems like widespread corruption and heightened ethnic divisions. Wednesday has been declared a public holiday so more people can vote. </p>
<p>Billie O’Kadameri of Radio France International described opposition that arose from an alliance of churches and political leaders.  Warnings of disruption in opposition areas have marred what the government initially hoped would be a united vote in support of the proposal.</p>
<p>However, Salim Lone, senior adviser to Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Raila_Odinga">Raila Odinga</ref>, said that "[Kenyans] are united as we have never been since independence more than 45 years ago," and, "Virtually all Kenyans, from across the political and ethnic divides, want this constitution". </p>
<p>The new constitution would restrict the president's power, gives the people a bill of rights, gives more power to local governments and encourages land reform. However, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalenjin">Kalenjin</ref> tribe claims that the new land reform would lead to the taxation and even seizure of their lands.</p>
<p>The last time a major vote was held (the Kenyan presidential election in 2007), violence left almost 1,500 people dead and over half a million displaced. </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sources</hi></p>
<list type="unordered"><item>Jeffrey Gettleman. "<ref target="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/04/world/africa/04kenya.html?_r=1&amp;ref=world">Kenya Stakes Reinvention on Constitution Vote</ref>" —<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_New_York_Times">The New York Times</ref></hi>, August 3 2010</item></list>
<list type="unordered"><item> "<ref target="http://www.english.rfi.fr/africa/20100803-calls-calm-ahead-kenya-constitutional-vote">Calls for calm ahead of Kenya constitution vote</ref>" —<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radio%20France%20Internationale">Radio France Internationale</ref></hi>, August 3 2010</item></list>
</text>
