<text id="autogum_news_doc233" title="6.0 magnitude earthquake rocks eastern Turkey" shortTile="-magnitude-earthquake" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2010-03-08" dateModified="2016-09-10" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/6.0_magnitude_earthquake_rocks_eastern_Turkey" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>6.0 magnitude earthquake rocks eastern Turkey</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 9, 2010</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Location of Elazig province in Turkey</caption></figure>
<p>A 6.0-magnitude earthquake struck Basyurt, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elazığ">Elazig</ref> province or eastern <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Turkey">Turkey</ref> at 04:32 AM (02:32 GMT) on Monday. According to local Kandilli observatory, the quake struck at a depth of five kilometres; the epicenter was near Karakocan town in the same province.</p>
<p>The pre-dawn earthquake killed at least 40 people and almost 100 were injured. The village of Okcular was worst hit, claimed the press secretary for the provincial governor, Ozcan Yalcin. According to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._Geological_Survey">U.S. Geological Survey</ref>, nearly five hours later, a magnitude-5.5 aftershock hit the province. 40 other aftershocks followed shortly, the highest of them being 4.4 magnitude, according to sources.</p>
<p>While no deaths were immediately reported, the government's crisis management center soon put the toll at seventeen with another 60 injured according to the officials at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Ankara">Ankara</ref>, the capital. It was soon confirmed that at least 39 were dead; the toll is expected to rise. At least four of the victims were children.</p>
<p>Muammer Erol, the provincial governor of Elazig, stated Okcular, Yukari Kanatli and Kayali accounted for majority of the dead. He told CNN Turk that "villages consisting mainly of mud-brick houses have been damaged, but we have minimal damage such as cracks in buildings made of cement or stone".</p>
<p>Okcular, the largest of the affected villages, accounted for at least seventeen of the dead. The village has a population of 800, and the majority of the dwellers live in mud-brick homes built on hillsides. About 25 to 30 houses were demolished in this village. "The village is totally flattened," Hasan Demirdag, local administrator, told NTV.</p>
<p>Yadin Apaydin, the administrator of Yukari Kanatli, said his village had been severely affected. "Everything has been knocked down - there is not a stone in place," he told <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/CNN">CNN</ref>'s Turkey sister network, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CNN%20Türk">CNN Türk</ref>.</p>
<p>"Many houses have collapsed. Search and rescue teams have been sent to the area," said the prime minister's office in a statement. Injured people are being rushed to local hospitals according to sources. At least 100 people have been taken to hospital. Some who panicked after the first quake jumped from balconies or windows were injured. </p>
<p>Rescue workers, consisting of policemen as well as civilians dug with shovels to rescue people from the debris. The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Turkish_Red_Crescent">Turkish Red Crescent</ref> is also sending tents and blankets to be distributed. Neighboring districts are providing ambulances to assist the victims. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cemil%20Cicek">Cemil Cicek</ref>, deputy Prime Minister of Turkey has left for the disaster area. Health Minister Recep Akdag, Housing Minister Mustafa Demir and State Minister Cevdet Yilmaz are accompanying him.</p>
<p>According to CNN Türk, the tremor of the earthquake was felt in the adjacent provinces of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bitlis">Bitlis</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diyarbakir">Diyarbakir</ref>, causing residents to panic. </p>
<p>Turkey lies on highly active fault lines and earthquakes often hit the nation. A 7.4-magnitude earthquake in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Istanbul">Istanbul</ref> killed 20,000 people in August 1999. Most of the earthquakes that hit Turkey are usually minor.</p>
</text>
