<text id="autogum_news_doc647" title="Travel ban 2.0 exempts Iraqis, U.S. permanent residents" shortTile="travel-ban--exempts" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-03-06" dateModified="2019-11-01" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Travel_ban_2.0_exempts_Iraqis%2C_U.S._permanent_residents" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Travel ban 2.0 exempts Iraqis, U.S. permanent residents</head>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 9, 2017</hi></p>
<p>On Monday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_of_America">U.S.</ref> president <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Donald_Trump">Donald Trump</ref> signed in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oval%20Office">Oval Office</ref> a revised version of his executive order barring entry to the United States by refugees and individuals from certain Muslim-majority countries.  While the previous ban, which caused chaos at airports and drew considerable criticism from within and outside of the U.S. government, covered seven countries, this one names only six and specifically exempts legal permanent residents and anyone who already has a visa to enter the country, or a visa revoked by the earlier executive order.</p>
<p>Residents of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syria</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iran">Iran</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libya">Libya</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Somalia">Somalia</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sudan">Sudan</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Yemen">Yemen</ref> must now wait 90 days for visas.  <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq">Iraq</ref> was removed following concerns that people who had helped the United States military and Iraqi government during and after the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iraq_War">Iraq War</ref> might be left in danger. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20Secretary%20of%20State">Secretary of State</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rex%20Tillerson">Rex Tillerson</ref> said this was because the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20State%20Department">U.S. State Department</ref> and Iraqi government improved the vetting process, though he did not say what exactly changed.  The Iraqi government also lobbied heavily. Prime Minister <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haider%20al-Abadi">Haider al-Abadi</ref> spoke with President Trump by phone and Vice President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mike_Pence">Pence</ref> in person. A senior official with the Trump administration also told reporters the Iraqi government had promised "timely repatriation" for Iraqi nationals whom the U.S. has decided to deport.</p>
<p>There is still a 120-day moratorium on accepting refugees into the U.S., though the ban on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syrian</ref> refugees is no longer indefinite. The new order omits language that gave priority to religious minorities, which critics such as <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/National_Public_Radio">National Public Radio</ref>'s Domenico Montanaro read as "<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Christianity">Christians</ref>." Claims of religious discrimination against Muslims contributed to the first order's overturn by the judiciary.</p>
<p>Under the previous travel ban, permanent residents in possession of a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/green%20card">green card</ref> were concerned that if they were to visit their home countries they might be barred from returning to the United States.  The new executive order exempts them.</p>
<p>Representative <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Adam_Schiff">Adam Schiff</ref>, a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._Democratic_Party">Democrat</ref> on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House%20Intelligence%20Committee">House Intelligence Committee</ref>, said both orders have "the same fundamental flaws."  Representative <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andre%20Carson">Andre Carson</ref> of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Indiana">Indiana</ref>, who is Muslim, referred to this as "Muslim ban 2.0" on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Twitter</ref>. Senator <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chuck_Schumer">Chuck Schumer</ref>, a Democrat from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref>, called for the order's repeal, saying, "A watered-down ban is still a ban."</p>
<p>Not all of the response has been negative. "I have always shared President Trump's desire to protect our homeland," said Senator <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Lindsey_Graham">Lindsey Graham</ref>, a Republican and a critic of the first executive order. "This Executive Order will achieve the goal of protecting our homeland and will, in my view, pass legal muster."</p>
<p>The order is set to go into effect on March 16.  The White House continues to affirm that the original travel ban was legal and the issue may still be heard before the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/U.S._Supreme_Court">U.S. Supreme Court</ref>.</p>
</text>
