<text id="autogum_news_doc494" title="Manchester United bests Ajax to win Europa league" shortTile="manchester-united" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-05-25" dateModified="2018-12-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Manchester_United_bests_Ajax_to_win_Europa_league" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Manchester United bests Ajax to win Europa league</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 26, 2017</hi></p>
<p>On Wednesday, in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UEFA%20Europa%20League">UEFA Europa League</ref> final, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Manchester_United">Manchester United</ref> defeated <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Netherlands">Dutch</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Amsterdam">capital</ref>-club <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ajax%20AFC">Ajax AFC</ref> 0–2 to win the Europa League title and qualify for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UEFA_Champions_League">UEFA Champions League</ref> group stage despite finishing sixth in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Premier%20League">Premier League</ref> this season.  A deflected goal from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paul_Pogba">Paul Pogba</ref>'s left-footed shot in the first half and a flick goal by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henrikh%20Mkhitaryan">Henrikh Mkhitaryan</ref> in the second half ensured that <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/José_Mourinho">José Mourinho</ref>'s side lifts its third trophy in this season, previously winning <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Community%20Shield">Community Shield</ref> and the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EFL%20Cup">EFL Cup</ref>.</p>
<p>Before the kick-off, a one-minute silence was observed at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friends%20Arena">Friends Arena</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Stockholm">Stockholm</ref>, for the victims of a suicide attack in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manchester%20Arena">Manchester Arena</ref> on Monday. The English side had just 33% ball possession in the entire match, completing 192 passes out of 276. A comparatively young Ajax team, with the average age of the starting lineup no more than 23 years, had 88% passing accuracy, with 565 successful passes. Manchester United had better numbers for defense, recovering 64 balls – 22 more than Ajax, and had almost twice as many ball clearances as the Dutch counterpart. A total of 32 fouls were committed in the match, and the official booked six players – three players of each side received a yellow card.</p>
<p>At the age of 17 years and 285 days, Ajax's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthijs%20de%20Ligt">Matthijs de Ligt</ref> became the youngest player to play in the Europa League final, while <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcus%20Rashford">Marcus Rashford</ref> became the youngest winner of the tournament at the age of 19 years and 205 days.</p>
<p>A deflection off <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Davinson%20Sánchez">Davinson Sánchez</ref> from Paul Pogba's left-footed shot gave United an early lead. Ajax's shot-stopper saved <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonio%20Valencia">Antonio Valencia</ref>'s close-range strike. Another attempt in the first half by Ajax's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bertrand%20Traoré">Bertrand Traoré</ref> was saved by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sergio%20Romero">Sergio Romero</ref>. The half time ended 0–1. Minutes into the second half, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Armenia">Armenian</ref> midfielder Mkhitaryan scored a goal just in front of Ajax's net, which doubled Manchester's lead. Five players were booked in the second half. Ajax's attempts in the final minutes of the game were stopped by Romero, not giving them a chance to reduce the difference. </p>
<p>Last season, Premier League club <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Liverpool_FC">Liverpool FC</ref> lost the Europa finals against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spanish</ref> side <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sevilla%20FC">Sevilla FC</ref>. United is the first English club to win the Europa since 2013. This season's Premier League winners <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chelsea_FC">Chelsea</ref> won the tournament four years ago against <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/S.L.%20Benfica">Benfica</ref> at Ajax's ground, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amsterdam%20ArenA">Amsterdam ArenA</ref>. Since then, Sevilla has added three Europa titles to their collection.</p>
<p>After the match, Ajax's coach <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter%20Bosz">Peter Bosz</ref> said, "We're obviously disappointed. I didn't see the Ajax team I'm used to, pressing and competing for first balls. We weren't good enough. Often, to win finals you must first lose them. It's all new for all my team. They will learn a lot from it and if we keep the squad together they will be stronger for it." Bosz's first season as Ajax's coach ended trophy-less.</p>
<p>Manchester United's boss José Mourinho said, "We are in the Champions League in the right way and for me the right way is winning the Premier League or winning the Europa League. We were not strong enough to win the Premier League but we were strong enough to win the Europa League and we are back in the Champions League. The club now has every trophy in world football. We fought hard for this since the beginning. We totally deserved the win. I am so happy to see all the players, including the boys with the crutches, with the trophy." The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Portugal">Portuguese</ref> has won two Champions League titles – one each with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/FC_Porto">FC Porto</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/FC_Internazionale_Milano">Inter</ref>, and two Europa titles – the first one with Porto.</p>
<p>United became the fifth team after <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bayern_Munich">Bayern Munich</ref>, Chelsea, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Juventus">Juventus</ref>, and Ajax to win all three major UEFA trophies – European Cup Winners' Cup, the European Cup (rebranded as Champions League) and UEFA Cup (rebranded as Europa League). They are to face the winner of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Real_Madrid">Real Madrid</ref> and Juventus in the Champions League final in the UEFA Super Cup scheduled on August 8 at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip%20II%20Arena">Philip II Arena</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skopje">Skopje</ref>.</p>
<p>José Mourinho, Manchester United manager‍:"We are in the Champions League in the right way and for me the right way is winning the Premier League or winning the Europa League."</p>
May 24, 2017
<hi rend="bold">Ajax AFC</hi>
<hi rend="bold">0–2</hi>
<hi rend="bold">Manchester United</hi>
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friends%20Arena">Friends Arena</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Stockholm">Stockholm</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref> Referee: Damir Skomina
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joël%20Veltman">Joël Veltman</ref>  58'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amin%20Younes">Amin Younes</ref>  64'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jairo%20Riedewald">Jairo Riedewald</ref>  78'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kasper%20Dolberg">Kasper Dolberg</ref>  62'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%20Neres">David Neres</ref>  62'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lasse%20Schöne">Lasse Schöne</ref>  70'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donny%20van%20de%20Beek">Donny van de Beek</ref>  70'Jairo Riedewald  82'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frenkie%20de%20Jong">Frenkie de Jong</ref>  82'
0–1 (HT)
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Paul_Pogba">Paul Pogba</ref>  18'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henrikh%20Mkhitaryan">Henrikh Mkhitaryan</ref>  48'Henrikh Mkhitaryan  31'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marouane%20Fellaini">Marouane Fellaini</ref>  52'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Juan%20Mata">Juan Mata</ref>  78'Henrikh Mkhitaryan  74'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesse%20Lingard">Jesse Lingard</ref>  74'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcus%20Rashford">Marcus Rashford</ref>  84'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anthony%20Martial">Anthony Martial</ref>  84'Juan Mata  90'<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Wayne_Rooney">Wayne Rooney</ref>  90'
<head id="External_link">External link</head>
<list type="unordered"><item>Ajax AFC. "<ref target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K8qHiI0wLfQ">Highlights Ajax - Manchester United (Europa League Finale)</ref>" —<hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/YouTube">YouTube</ref></hi>, May 25, 2017
</item></list>
</text>
