<text id="autogum_news_doc437" title="French parliament approves bill on Armenian Genocide denial" shortTile="french-parliament" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2006-10-12" dateModified="2013-08-15" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/French_parliament_approves_bill_on_Armenian_Genocide_denial" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>French parliament approves bill on Armenian Genocide denial</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 12, 2006</hi></p>
<p>Today, the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">French</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/French_National_Assembly">National Assembly</ref> passed a bill that would penalise what the bill calls <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Historical%20revisionism%20(negationism)">negationism</ref> of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Armenian%20Genocide">Armenian Genocide</ref>. The French government however opposes the bill; Catherine Colonna, Minister charged with European Affairs, reacted that "It's the task, first and foremost, of historians and not of lawmakers to clarify history."</p>
<p>The label "<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/genocide">genocide</ref>" is disputed by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Turkey">Turkish</ref> government, who has called the vote a "serious blow" to diplomatic relations.  Turkey has been known to prosecute Turkish intellectuals who discuss the Armenian genocide, including recent Nobel Prize winner <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orhan%20Pamuk">Orhan Pamuk</ref>. Under the Turkish Penal Code, "prosecution for anti-national plots" faces those who call "for the recognition of the Armenian genocide".</p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List%20of%20Prime%20Ministers%20of%20Turkey">Turkey's Prime Minister</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Recep_Tayyip_Erdoğan">Erdoğan</ref> had warned France to look into its own colonial past in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Africa">Africa</ref> instead of demanding Turkish recognition of the events. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ali%20Babacan">Ali Babacan</ref>, the Turkish Minister of Economy, in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brussels">Brussels</ref> for talks on Turkey's <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Union">E.U.</ref>-membership, said he could not exclude that people would start boycotting French products in Turkey. In a recent visit to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Armenia">Armenia</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President%20of%20the%20French%20Republic">French President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jacques_Chirac">Jacques Chirac</ref> launched the idea that recognition as a "genocide" would be necessary for Turkey to enter the E.U., causing the media to label it as the "Chirac criterion". The European Commission, which has confirmed that such a criterion would not be instituted, deplored the initiative of the French parliament, because it could damage contacts with the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/European_Union">European Union</ref>.</p>
<p>Most historians view the events comprising the Armenian genocide as a state-sponsored plan of mass extermination.  Their reasons include various eye witness reports, Turkey's recruitment of violent criminals to posts within the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special%20Organization%20(Ottoman%20Empire)">"Special Organization"</ref>, and the sheer number of dead, estimates of which remain as high as 1.5 million. Some politically influential countries like the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">U.S.</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canada">Canada</ref>, and France have driven efforts to interpret these events as an attempt to eradicate an ethnic group. The Turkish government, as well as a few historians, estimate the number of casualties much lower, and attribute them to inter-ethnic strife, disease and famine during <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_War_I">World War I</ref>.</p>
<p>Armenia has congratulated France over its "natural response" to an "aggressive" policy of "denial" by the Turkish government.  Armenians often argue that Turkey's recognition will help prevent similar events in the future. These assertions include claims that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludwig%20Maximilian%20Erwin%20von%20Scheubner-Richter">Scheubner-Richter's</ref> observations of the Armenian genocide had a formative influence upon <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hitler">Hitler's</ref> plans for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jews">Jews</ref>.</p>
<p>The French bill provides for a 1-year prison sentence and a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Euro">€</ref> 45,000 fine, the same as for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Holocaust%20denial">Holocaust denial</ref>. It must still be approved by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French%20Senate">Senate</ref> and the President, and due to the parliamentary calendar, news sources think it is unlikely that it will be discussed before the end of the legislation period in February 2007.</p>
</text>
