<text id="autogum_news_doc747" title="Roberto Córdova wins Concertación primary elections in Pichilemu, Chile" shortTile="roberto-cordova-wins" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2012-04-01" dateModified="2014-04-21" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Roberto_C%C3%B3rdova_wins_Concertaci%C3%B3n_primary_elections_in_Pichilemu%2C_Chile" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Roberto Córdova wins Concertación primary elections in Pichilemu, Chile</head><figure><caption>Roberto Córdova won the primary elections. Pictured during an interview in November 2010. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, April 1, 2012</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Pichilemu">Pichilemu</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Chile">Chile</ref> – Incumbent mayor of the Chilean commune of Pichilemu, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Roberto_Córdova">Roberto Córdova Carreño</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialist%20Party%20of%20Chile">Socialist Party</ref>) won the primary elections —qualified as "historic" by local newspaper <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expreso%20de%20la%20Costa">Expreso de la Costa</ref></hi>— to choose a unique candidate for mayor representing the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concertación%20de%20Partidos%20por%20la%20Democracia">Concertación de Partidos por la Democracia</ref></hi> (Concert of Parties for Democracy) coalition of left-winged parties in the next municipal elections of October 28. The elections were held in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digna%20Camilo%20Aguilar%20School">Digna Camilo Aguilar School</ref>. Córdova ran against incumbent councillor <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea%20Aranda">Andrea Aranda</ref> (<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Party%20for%20Democracy">Party for Democracy</ref>).</p>
<p>Anyone inscribed in the poll registry before November 30, 2011 and without membership in non-Concertación parties can participate in the election. Simultaneously, similar elections are were held in thirteen other communes of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/O'Higgins_Region">O'Higgins Region</ref>, including regional capital <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rancagua">Rancagua</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Santa_Cruz,_Chile">Santa Cruz</ref>.</p>
<p>Both Aranda and Córdova participated on Saturday night in a televised debate hosted by municipal worker Fabricio Cáceres Jorquera in his program <hi rend="italic">Cóctel de Sábado</hi>, broadcasted by <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canal%203%20Pichilemu">Canal 3 Pichilemu</ref></hi>.</p>
<head id="The_candidates">The candidates</head>
Roberto Córdova
<p>Roberto del Carmen Córdova Carreño is the current mayor of the commune of Pichilemu. He was elected during a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pichilemu%20City%20Council">city council</ref> meeting in September 2009, after Mayor Marcelo Cabrera Martínez was forced to leave office permanently. Córdova is a Performance Engineer in Public Management.</p>
<p>Amongst other things, Córdova had to face the emergency triggered by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2010_Chile_earthquake">2010 Chile earthquake</ref> and the subsequent <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2010_Pichilemu_earthquake">Pichilemu earthquake</ref>. He also inaugurated the renovated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agustín%20Ross%20Cultural%20Centre">Agustín Ross Cultural Centre</ref> with then-President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Michelle_Bachelet">Michelle Bachelet</ref>.</p>
<p>During his primary campaign, he reportedly visited rural areas such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rodeíllo">Rodeíllo</ref> with a small group of people. His slogan is "Pichilemu, better every day." ("Pichilemu, cada día mejor.")</p>
<p>As reported by <hi rend="italic">El Expreso de la Costa</hi>, he is supported by the regional president of the Party for Democracy (Aranda's party) Leandro Sánchez, and senator Juan Pablo Letelier.</p>
<p>"In this voluntary but necessary election, I invite everyone [to vote] for Pichilemu to be better every day," Córdova said to <hi rend="italic">El Expreso</hi>.</p>
<figure><caption>Aranda in August 2011, during the <hi rend="italic">Marcha por la Educación Gratuita</hi> in Pichilemu. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.</caption></figure>
Andrea Aranda
<p>Andrea Natalia Aranda Escudero currently is one of the five councillors of Pichilemu, elected in 2008. She is married to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jorge_Vargas">Jorge Vargas</ref>, former Mayor of Pichilemu, with whom she has three daughters: Camila, Alicia, and Emilia. She is, by profession, a midwife.</p>
<p>She has been criticized by local media as following in the footsteps of her husband, Jorge Vargas, currently prohibited from active politics following his arrest for bribery.</p>
<p>Additionally, an anonymous editor of <hi rend="italic">El Expreso de la Costa</hi> nicknamed Bellaco wrote: "[Aranda] assures her contender is campaigning with municipal funds, somebody asked, does she forget her husband made the same thing years before when he was elected for three terms?"</p>
<p>During her campaign, she visited places such as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardonal%20de%20Panilonco">Cardonal de Panilonco</ref>, and organized several meetings with local leaders. Her slogan is "With woman's strength." ("Con fuerza de mujer.")</p>
<p>Aranda wrote in an open letter published in <hi rend="italic">El Expreso de la Costa</hi>: "As a woman, I'm sensitive to human necessity, and brave to defend the cause of family. My commitment is to work, providing all my capacities, for concrete works and materialization of dreams with you."</p>
<head id="Results">Results</head>
<figure><caption>The primary elections were held at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digna%20Camilo%20Aguilar%20School">Digna Camilo Aguilar School</ref>. Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Diego_Grez">Diego Grez</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>At 19:12 local time (22:12 UTC), regional newspaper <hi rend="italic">El Pulso</hi> reported Córdova won the election, on Twitter.</p>
<p>The final results, as published by local TV channel <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canal%203%20Pichilemu">Canal 3 Pichilemu</ref></hi> on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">Twitter</ref>, are the following:</p>
<list type="unordered"><item><hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Roberto_Córdova">Roberto Córdova</ref></hi> - 1,903 (73.1%)</item>
<item><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea%20Aranda">Andrea Aranda</ref> - 699 (23.9%)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Total votes</hi> - 2,602 (100%)</item></list>
<p>Andrea Aranda said she "will continue to work for the people" and accused she was "the victim of a campaign of terror" against her. She later personally congratulated Roberto Córdova, who said "the election leaves several morals to local democracy," and announced he would make an appeareance in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los%20Navegantes">Los Navegantes</ref> "to thank those who voted for him and those who did not."</p>
</text>
