<text id="autogum_news_doc709" title="Sandra Fluke declares candidacy for California State Senate" shortTile="sandra-fluke-declares" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-02-06" dateModified="2015-10-29" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sandra_Fluke_declares_candidacy_for_California_State_Senate" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Sandra Fluke declares candidacy for California State Senate</head><p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 6, 2014</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Women's_rights">Women's rights</ref> advocate and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georgetown%20University%20Law%20Center">Georgetown University Law Center</ref> graduate <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sandra_Fluke">Sandra Fluke</ref> announced her candidacy yesterday to run for the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California%20State%20Senate">California State Senate</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sandra_Fluke">Sandra Fluke</ref> (2012) Image: <ref target="http://www.flickr.com/people/81711099@N04">nmogburn</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Democratic_Party_(United_States)">Democrat</ref> previously stated she would run for a seat in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_Congress">United States Congress</ref> being vacated by retiring Congressman <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry%20Waxman">Henry Waxman</ref>. She informed the <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Los_Angeles_Times">Los Angeles Times</ref></hi> that she decided to run for the California State Senate instead of the U.S. Congress because she felt she would be able to accomplish more for the people of California as a state Senator.</p>
<p>She will attempt to gain election to the seat currently occupied by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ted%20Lieu">Ted Lieu</ref>, a Democrat from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torrance,%20California">Torrance</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref>. Lieu is currently in the beginning of his own campaign for Congressman Waxman's seat representing <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California's%2033rd%20congressional%20district">California's 33rd congressional district</ref>.</p>
<hi rend="bold">My entire career has been devoted to the public interest, whether representing victims of human trafficking or advocating for working families.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller;line-height:1em;text-align: right">—<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sandra_Fluke">Sandra Fluke</ref></p>
<p>In a release to the press, Fluke said: "I am extremely moved by the outpouring of local and national support I have received since I announced that I was considering running for office. My entire career has been devoted to the public interest, whether representing victims of human trafficking or advocating for working families."</p>
<p>She described her intentions for the California legislature: "I am committed to continuing that fight in Sacramento, working to protect our environment, ensure our access to health care, and create the jobs that are desperately needed. While I strongly considered offering my candidacy for Congress, I feel there is a better way for me to advance the causes that are important to our community."</p>
<hi rend="bold">I am eager to get to work fighting for the causes that matter most to our future as a community, state and nation.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—Sandra Fluke</p>
<p>Fluke characterized herself as a new voice for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/progressivism">progressivism</ref>: "I believe that the families and communities of this district — from West Hollywood to West L.A. and from Santa Monica to Torrance and beyond — deserve to have a fresh perspective from a new generation of progressive leadership in Sacramento, and I am eager to get to work fighting for the causes that matter most to our future as a community, state and nation."</p>
<p>After graduating from law school, Fluke moved to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Los_Angeles">Los Angeles</ref> where she used her skills as a lawyer to help improve conditions for individuals related to improving the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/living%20wage">living wage</ref> and advocating for better <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/foster%20care">foster care</ref> for children.</p>
<p>Fluke was nominated as a candidate by <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Time_(magazine)">Time</ref></hi> magazine for their <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Time_Person_of_the_Year">Person of the Year</ref></hi> of 2012. <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> concluded Fluke helped give U.S. President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> an edge in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2012_United_States_presidential_election">his 2012 presidential re-election campaign</ref>.</p>
<p>Fluke was a featured speaker on September 5, 2012 at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012%20Democratic%20National%20Convention">2012 Democratic National Convention</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlotte,%20North%20Carolina">Charlotte</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_Carolina">North Carolina</ref>. Fluke spoke to attendees at the convention about the consequences for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Women">women</ref> of electing <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</ref> candidate for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States">U.S. President</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</ref> over incumbent President <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>. Fluke campaigned with President Obama in his bid for re-election.</p>
<p>She was recognized April 22, 2012 with the <hi rend="italic">Stand Up for Choice Award</hi>. Fluke was given the <hi rend="italic">Stand Up for Choice Award</hi> at the "Third Annual Multi-Generational Brunch" of the organization <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NARAL%20Pro-Choice%20America">NARAL Pro-Choice America</ref> which was held in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York_City">New York City</ref> (NYC), <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/New_York">New York</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref>. </p>
<p>Fluke received a nomination in March 2012 as a candidate for <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Time_(magazine)">Time</ref></hi> magazine's 100 most influential people in the world. The list is released annually as a special edition of <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> magazine, titled <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Time%20100">Time 100</ref></hi>.</p>
<p>She gave testimony to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_Congress">US Congress</ref> on February 23, 2012 before the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/House%20Democratic%20Steering%20and%20Policy%20Committee">House Democratic Steering and Policy Committee</ref> at a hearing about <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/women's%20health">women's health</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/contraception">contraception</ref>. She also worked for Sanctuary for Families in NYC which worked to crack down on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Human_trafficking">human trafficking</ref> and domestic violence. </p>
</text>
