<text id="autogum_news_doc487" title="Football: Robben retires from international football after Netherlands fails to qualify for World Cup" shortTile="football-robben-retires" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2017-10-10" dateModified="2018-06-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Football%3A_Robben_retires_from_international_football_after_Netherlands_fails_to_qualify_for_World_Cup" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Football: Robben retires from international football after Netherlands fails to qualify for World Cup</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 13, 2017</hi></p>
<p>On Tuesday, Dutch <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Soccer">football</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/winger%20(association%20football)">winger</ref> and captain <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arjen%20Robben">Arjen Robben</ref> announced retirement from international play after <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref> failed to qualify for next year's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FIFA%20World%20Cup">World Cup</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Russia">Russia</ref>. <hi rend="italic">Oranje</hi> defeated <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref> 2–1 at home, but failed to qualify for a second consecutive major tournament, after <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UEFA_Euro_2016">last year's UEFA Euro</ref> tournament.</p>
<p>Robben, playing his 96th international match on Tuesday, made his international debut in April 2003. Netherlands played <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref> at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amsterdam%20ArenA">Amsterdam ArenA</ref> in the Dutch <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Amsterdam">capital</ref>, and were awarded a penalty kick in the sixteenth minute after a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/foul%20(association%20football)">handball</ref> from Swedish defender <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victor%20Lindelöf">Victor Lindelöf</ref> in the penalty area. Robben scored from the spot, netting his 36th international goal from a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panenka%20kick">Panenka kick</ref>. In the 40th minute, Robben scored his second of the night, from outside the box. The scoreline remained 2–0 at the end of full time. </p>
<p>Netherlands dominated in ball possession having 69%. The win gave the <hi rend="italic">Oranjes</hi> three points, tying with Sweden with nineteen points from all the group stage matches. However, Sweden finished second in the Group A table above Netherlands, leading in goals scored. In order to play the play-offs for the World Cup, Netherlands needed to defeat Sweden by a seven-goal margin.</p>
<p>Robben's second goal brings his tally of international goals to 37, and is fourth in the list of top scorers for Netherlands, tied with <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denis%20Bergkamp">Denis Bergkamp</ref>. Robben has featured in the FIFA World Cup tournaments of 2006, 2010 and 2014. He has won a silver medal at the 2010 World Cup, losing to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref> in extra time, and a bronze medal finishing third in 2014's World Cup in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brazil">Brazil</ref>.
After the match, Robben said, "I've been thinking about this for a long time. I've thought about stopping, but I've continued. I'm 33 years old, I'm playing in a top club in Europe, so you have to make choices. I'm going to concentrate completely on my club now. This is a good time to leave it to someone else." ((nl))Dutch language: ‍Ik heb hier lang over nagedacht. Een hele tijd terug heb ik al overwogen te stoppen, maar toen ben ik toch doorgegaan. Ik ben nu 33 jaar, ik speel bij een topclub in Europa, dan moet je keuzes maken. Ik ga me nu vol concentreren op mijn club. Dit is een goed moment om het stokje over te geven.</p>
<p>His <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bayern_Munich">Bayern Munich</ref> teammate <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Robert_Lewandowski">Robert Lewandowski</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Poland">Poland</ref> qualified for the World Cup on Sunday. Lewandowski scored a goal against <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Montenegro">Montenegro</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Warsaw">Warsaw</ref>, which was his sixteenth in the qualification stage becoming the first <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Europe">European</ref> player to net sixteen in one FIFA World Cup qualifying tournament. On the same day, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egypt">Egypt</ref> defeated <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Congo">Congo</ref> 2–1 with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mohamed_Salah">Mohamed Salah</ref> scoring both goals including the match winning last minute penalty kick for Egypt. Egypt previously featured in the World Cup 28 years ago in 1990, which was their second ever World Cup tournament.</p>
<p>On Monday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iceland">Iceland</ref> secured a place for their maiden World Cup. Iceland became the smallest nation to to qualify for the FIFA tournament, in country population. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/France">France</ref> defeated <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Belarus">Belarus</ref> 2–1 at home, and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Portugal">Portugal</ref> defeated <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Switzerland">Switzerland</ref> two goals to none, qualifying for the World Cup as well.</p>
October 10, 2017 20:45 (UTC+2)
<hi rend="bold"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Netherlands">Netherlands</ref> </hi>
<hi rend="bold">2–0</hi>
<hi rend="bold"> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Sweden">Sweden</ref></hi>
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amsterdam%20ArenA">Amsterdam ArenA</ref> Referee: Sergei Karasev
<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arjen%20Robben">Arjen Robben</ref>  16'(pen.)Arjen Robben  40'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daley%20Blind">Daley Blind</ref>  44'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vincent%20Janssen">Vincent Janssen</ref>  46'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bas%20Dost">Bas Dost</ref>  46'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kenny%20Tete">Kenny Tete</ref>  71'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daryl%20Janmaat">Daryl Janmaat</ref>  71'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georginio%20Wijnaldum">Georginio Wijnaldum</ref>  71'<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Davy%20Klaassen">Davy Klaassen</ref>  71'
2–0 (HT)
 55' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mikael%20Lustig">Mikael Lustig</ref> 68' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viktor%20Claesson">Viktor Claesson</ref> 68' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gustav%20Svensson">Gustav Svensson</ref> 76' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ola%20Toivonen">Ola Toivonen</ref> 76' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isaac%20Kiese%20Thelin">Isaac Kiese Thelin</ref> 82' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seb%20Larsson">Seb Larsson</ref> 82' <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin%20Olsson">Martin Olsson</ref>
</text>
