<text id="autogum_news_doc699" title="Thousands attend skateboarder Jay Adams funeral over Labor Day weekend" shortTile="thousands-attend" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-09-01" dateModified="2019-09-06" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Thousands_attend_skateboarder_Jay_Adams_funeral_over_Labor_Day_weekend" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Thousands attend skateboarder Jay Adams funeral over Labor Day weekend</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 5, 2014</hi></p>
<p>An estimated two thousand people from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/skateboarding">skateboarding</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Surfing">surfing</ref> communities, and a <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporter, attended the funeral service and memorial paddle-out and skateboarding session this past <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Labor%20Day">Labor Day</ref> weekend in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/California">California</ref> for skateboarding pioneer <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jay%20Adams">Jay Adams</ref>, who died on August 15 while on a surfing trip with his wife Tracy in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Puero%20Escondido,%20Mexico">Puerto Escondido</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Mexico">Mexico</ref>.  Within days after his death several smaller <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hawaii">Hawaiian</ref>-style paddle-out tributes were also held in his honor from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Santa%20Cruz,%20California">Santa Cruz</ref>, California to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Jacksonville,_Florida">Jacksonville</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Florida">Florida</ref>.</p>
<figure><caption>Photo of the memorial paddle-out next to the Venice Beach Pier on Saturday. Image: SIX12 MEDIA.</caption></figure>
<p>Broadcast live on the web from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calvary%20Chapel%20Costa%20Mesa">Calvary Chapel Costa Mesa</ref> on Friday, pastor Raul Ries delivered the eulogy along with Skateboarder <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christian%20Hosoi">Christian Hosoi</ref>.  Both spoke about Adams character and influence on the skateboarding and surfing communities.  Adams' own church pastor and one of his closest friends Trip shared personal stories from letters Adams had written him concerning his faith and his desire to be known for being a man of God.  Adams' step-father Kent Sherwood who taught Adams how to surf when he was just three years old, also shared personal stories about Adams when he was just starting to surf and skateboard as a young child.</p>
<p>With clear skies and warm sunny weather on Saturday, hundreds of surfers, amongst them long time friends of Adam's from the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Z-Boys">Z-Boys</ref>, held a large memorial paddle-out tribute mid-day on the north side of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venice%20Beach">Venice Beach</ref> Pier.  Chants of "Jay Jay Jay" could be heard from the pier as onlookers watched water being splashed about into the air by the hundreds of people perched on their surfboards.  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los%20Angeles%20County">Los Angeles County</ref> fire department boats and lifeguards were on hand to add to the paddle-out by spraying their water cannons high into the air and blowing their horns, while monitoring everyone's safety.  Later in the afternoon nearby a skateboarding session was held at the Venice beach skate park also in Adams' honor.</p>
<p>Adams became an influential figure in skateboarding and its culture during the mid-seventies when he was a teenager, skateboarding with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Z-Boys">Zephyr team</ref> in Southern California.  He has been acknowledged as someone who helped transform the novelty of skateboarding into a global phenomenon.  His story was featured in the films <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dogtown%20and%20Z-Boys">Dogtown and Z-Boys</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lords%20of%20Dogtown">Lords of Dogtown</ref> and he was inducted into the skateboarding hall of fame in 2012.</p>
<p>Later in life Adams became a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Christian">Christian</ref> and found a purpose in helping the next generation of skaters and surfers by speaking to the public with positive messages about making good choices in life, along with other notable skateboarder Dennis Martinez.
Adams is the second member of the Z-Boys to die this year, Shogo Kubo died while surfing in Hawaii in June.</p>
<p>He is survived by his wife Tracy, his son Seven and his daughter Venice.</p>
</text>
