<text id="autogum_news_doc063" title="Obama supports Middle East protesters in speech" shortTile="obama-supports-middle" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2011-05-19" dateModified="2015-10-02" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Obama_supports_Middle_East_protesters_in_speech" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Obama supports Middle East protesters in speech</head><p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 20, 2011</hi></p>
<figure><caption>File photograph of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref>.</caption></figure>
<hi rend="bold">Strategies of repression and diversion won’t work anymore.</hi>
<p style="font-size:smaller; line-height:1em; text-align:right">—<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">U.S.</ref> president <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">Barack Obama</ref> has put the support of his <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Administration%20of%20Barack%20Obama">administration</ref> behind <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2010–2011%20Middle%20East%20and%20North%20Africa%20protests">protesters demanding democracy</ref> in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Middle_East">Middle East</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North%20Africa">North Africa</ref>, demanded <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syrian</ref> president <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bashar_al-Assad">Bashar al-Assad</ref> embrace reforms or resign, and warned a failure to address the uprisings in the region could lead to deep division between the U.S. and Muslim nations.</p>
<p>In a speech in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Washington,_D.C.">Washington, D.C.</ref>, Obama said it was a "historic opportunity" for his government to "promote reform, and to support transitions to democracy" in the region. Warning of "a deepening spiral of division between the United States and Muslim communities," he pledged to invest in a democratic future for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Tunisia">Tunisia</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Egypt">Egypt</ref>, where protesters have overthrown dictators in the past few months. "Strategies of repression and diversion won’t work anymore," he said, announcing a "new chapter" in Washington diplomacy.</p>
<p>He also criticized the government of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bahrain">Bahrain</ref> for attacking peaceful protesters and conducting mass arrests. A crackdown on protesters, he said, "will not make legitimate calls for reform go away." Obama defended his decision to launch military action in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Libya">Libya</ref>, saying "thousands would have been killed," and accused <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Muammar_Gaddafi">Muammar Gaddafi</ref> of launching "a war against his people, promising to hunt them down like rats." Gaddafi, he said, will "inevitably" leave or be forced from power.</p>
<p>After imposing sanctions on Syria this week as military forces in the country clamp down on demonstrators in the capital, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Damascus">Damascus</ref>, Obama again condemned violence against peaceful protesters. He demanded the administration of president Assad stop shooting protesters and allow peaceful demonstrations, release <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/political%20prisoners">political prisoners</ref>, and pass democratic reforms. "The Syrian people have shown their courage in demanding a transition to democracy," he said. Assad, he added, could either lead the transition or "get out of the way."</p>
<p>Speaking at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/U.S.%20State%20Department">U.S. State Department</ref>, Obama said he would react to the uprising in the region "in a way that advances our values and strengthens our security." He pledged to broaden the approach of his government beyond <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/counterterrorism">counterterrorism</ref> and ceasing the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Nuclear_proliferation">spread of nuclear weapons</ref>, to crack down on oppressive dictatorships which would harm U.S. interests. Unveiling a series of new economic initiatives intended to force out dictators, Obama pledged aid for Tunisia and Egypt to help them transform into democratic states.</p>
<p>The speech is being seen by analysts as an attempt by Obama to reach out to <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Islam">Muslim</ref> communities abroad amid U.S. unpopularity. The president is also trying to convince his U.S. audience that the outcome of the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Arab_Spring">Arab Spring</ref> will have an impact on the future of the U.S. and is worth spending money on during tumultuous economic times in Washington.
<ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Special:FilePath/Syria_Damascus_Douma_Protests_2011_-_22.jpg">File:Syria Damascus Douma Protests 2011 - 22.jpg</ref></p><figure><caption>Protesters in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Damascus">Damascus</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Syria">Syria</ref>, demanding democratic reform. Image: syriana2011.<hi rend="italic">(Image <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Template:Missing_image/message">missing</ref> from commons: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/File:Syria_Damascus_Douma_Protests_2011_-_22.jpg">image</ref>; <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Log?page=File%3ASyria+Damascus+Douma+Protests+2011+-+22.jpg">log</ref>)</hi></caption></figure>
<p>The push for democracy began in January, as protesters in Tunisia overthrew president <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zine%20al-Abidine%20Ben%20Ali">Zine al-Abidine Ben Ali</ref> in January. A month later, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Hosni_Mubarak">Hosni Mubarak</ref> was forced to resign from the Egyptian presidency. In Libya, demonstrators continue to try to topple Gaddafi, but have faced heavy bombardment from government forces.</p>
<p>Obama also signaled that <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Al-Qaeda">al-Qaeda</ref> is "losing its struggle for relevance" amid the uprising in the region, and said <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Osama_bin_Laden">Osama bin Laden</ref> was rapidly losing followers before his death earlier this month. As the uprising spread, the agenda of the terrorist organization responsible for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/September_11_attacks">attacks of September 11, 2001</ref>, was at a "dead end," he said. "Through the moral force of nonviolence, the people of the region have achieved more change in six months than terrorists have accomplished in decades."</p>
<p>He called on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Israel">Israel</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Palestine">Palestine</ref> to begin talks based on the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1967%20borders">1967 borders</ref> as the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israeli–Palestinian%20conflict">conflict</ref> stalls. "No peace can be imposed upon them, nor can endless delay make the problem go away," Obama said. "A lasting peace will involve two states for two peoples." But Israeli prime minister <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Benjamin_Netanyahu">Benjamin Netanyahu</ref> tonight rejected the suggestion because it would endanger Israeli security.</p>
</text>
