<text id="autogum_news_doc370" title="Japan government panel urges reinterpretation of pacifist constitution" shortTile="japan-government" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-02-07" dateModified="2019-02-28" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan_government_panel_urges_reinterpretation_of_pacifist_constitution" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Japan government panel urges reinterpretation of pacifist constitution</head><p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 8, 2014</hi></p>
<figure><caption>File photo of Shinzo Abe in 2010.  Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:多摩に暇人">多摩に暇人</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>A <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref> government panel met last Tuesday and is drafting a report aimed to urge Japan to loosen restrictions on participation in military combat — restriction of military to self-defense — imposed in its <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitution%20of%20Japan">constitution</ref> since the end of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_War_II">World War II</ref>. They expected to finalize the report after April. <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_Korea">North Korea</ref> reacted by calling the Prime Minister of Japan, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Shinzo_Abe">Shinzo Abe</ref>, an "Asian <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Adolf_Hitler">Hitler</ref>" on Wednesday.</p>
<p>The government panel — fourteen members headed by Shunji Yanai, former ambassador to the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US">US</ref> — sought ways to reinterpret the constitution on the grounds there was not enough public support for revising, or rewriting, the constitution itself.</p>
<p>Shinzo Abe said he was motivated to help keep international peace — by protecting other nations' troops, which was beyond the scope currently allowed under the constitution. He interpreted it as a country's right, commenting, "it's about whether we can exercise this right that every country has".</p>
<p>During the Tuesday meeting, Abe also expressed a concern that the country's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/national%20security">national security</ref> was not ready for potential regional conflicts: "Japan's preparation for national security threats in the region is not sufficient. We must cover all the bases to protect the people's lives and safety in any possible scenario". Yousuke Isozaki, a security policy adviser to Mr Abe, said a revised military policy would strengthen Japan's ties with allies, the US in particular.</p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Korean_Central_News_Agency">Korean Central News Agency</ref>, the official news agency of the North Korean government, commented in an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/editorial">editorial</ref>, saying Abe was trying to conjure up fears of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/North_Korea">North Korea</ref> using missiles or nuclear weapons to help justify expanding <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref>'s military. The Korean Central News Agency were likening Abe to Hitler. The editorial followed a comment by <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rodong%20Sinmun">Rodong Sinmun</ref>, the ruling party — <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Workers'%20Party%20of%20Korea">Workers' Party of Korea</ref> — newspaper, which described Abe as a "militarist maniac" last month. The reaction was also inspired by Abe's visit to <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yasukuni%20Shrine">Yasukuni Shrine</ref> in December.</p>
<p>Under <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Japan">Japan</ref>'s pacifist constitution, the country has not been able to engage in militaristic combat since the end of <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_War_II">World War II</ref>.</p>
<p> CHAPTER II. RENUNCIATION OF WAR</p>
Article 9
<list type="ordered"><item>Aspiring sincerely to an international peace based on justice and order, the Japanese people forever renounce war as a sovereign right of the nation and the threat or use of force as means of settling international disputes.</item>
<item>In order to accomplish the aim of the preceding paragraph, land, sea, and air forces, as well as other war potential, will never be maintained. The right of belligerency of the state will not be recognized.</item></list>
<p style="text-align: right;"> – Constitution of Japan</p>
<p>Commenters related the move to escalated tensions with <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/China">China</ref>, who had set up an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air%20Defense%20Identification%20Zone">Air Defense Identification Zone</ref> over a part of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/East%20China%20Sea">East China Sea</ref>, including Japan's <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Senkaku%20Islands">Senkaku Islands</ref>, in November last year.
</p>
</text>
