<text id="autogum_news_doc025" title="Medal-seeking Spanish men arrive at 2014 Goalball World Championships" shortTile="medalseeking-spanish" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-06-28" dateModified="2014-07-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Medal-seeking_Spanish_men_arrive_at_2014_Goalball_World_Championships" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Medal-seeking Spanish men arrive at 2014 Goalball World Championships</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, June 29, 2014</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Spain">Spain</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spain%20men's%20national%20goalball%20team">men's national goalball team</ref> arrived in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Espoo">Espoo</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Finland">Finland</ref> Friday for the start of the 2014 IBSA <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Goalball">Goalball</ref> World Championships.  The team comes into the tournament with the goal of securing a medal, which would qualify them for the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2016_Summer_Paralympics">2016 Summer Paralympics</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Rio_de_Janeiro">Rio de Janeiro</ref>.  The team missed the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/2012_Summer_Paralympics">2012 Summer Paralympics</ref>.</p>
<p>Head coach Francisco Monreal said, "The objective is to reach the medal round, and qualify directly for the 2016 Games, but we need to be realistic and not think game by game, we can get a surprise. [...] The competition will be decided in one game, head or tails, where it doesn't matter what happened before. ((es))Spanish language: ‍el objetivo previsto es alcanzar las medallas y clasificarnos directamente para los Juegos de 2016, pero hay que ser realistas y como no vayamos pensando partido a partido, nos podemos llevar una sorpresa. [...] La competición se decidirá en un partido a cara o cruz, como son los cruces de cuartos, y donde no sirve de nada lo realizado en la primera fase"</p>
<p>Coming into the competition, the team was ranked eleventh in the world based on the IBSA Unofficial rankings published late last month, down one spot from the April rankings. The team is scheduled to play their first game against the ninth ranked <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20States%20men's%20national%20goalball%20team">United States</ref> men's team on Monday morning, before playing twenty-first ranked <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Germany%20men's%20national%20goalball%20team">Germany</ref> later in the afternoon.  Their other scheduled competitors in pool play are top ranked <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iran%20men's%20national%20goalball%20team">Iran</ref>, third ranked <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algeria%20men's%20national%20goalball%20team">Algeria</ref>, seventh ranked <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finland%20men's%20national%20goalball%20team">Finland</ref>, twelfth ranked <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Czech%20Republic%20men's%20national%20goalball%20team">Czech Republic</ref> and twentieth ranked <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ukraine%20men's%20national%20goalball%20team">Ukraine</ref>.  The team needs to finish in the top four in their group to advance to the second round.</p>
<p>The team's roster includes Jose Daniel Fernández, Cristian Santamaria, Félix Vargas, Roman Martínez, Jesús Santana, and Javier Serrato.  They are led by head coach Monreal, with assistant coach Carles Estrany and physiotherapist José Bravo.  The team is drawn from around the country, with Santana playing for a club in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Canary_Islands">Canary Islands</ref>, Serrato playing for Valencia, Fernández  for <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Madrid">Madrid</ref> area <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chamartín">Chamartín</ref>, Santamaría for <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cantabria">Cantabria</ref>, Vargas coming from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Barcelona">Barcelona</ref> and Martínez from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aragón">Aragón</ref>.</p>
<p>Absent from the 2012 Summer Paralympics, the last major international competition the team competed in was the 2010 Goalball World Championships in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheffield">Sheffield</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/England">England</ref> where the team finished fifth.  In last year's IBSA European Goalball Championships in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Turkey">Turkey</ref>, the team finished second, behind World Championship hosts and Paralympic gold medalists Finland.</p>
<p>Goalball was created in 1946, exclusively for people with a visual disability and designed to help with the rehabilitation of veterans returning from <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/World_War_II">World War II</ref>. Play in the Paralympics consists of two twelve-minute periods, with a three minute break between halves. Players are blindfolded to ensure all are equally visually handicapped on-court, and the game can be stopped to ensure goggles are properly fitted. Standing in front of a long goal, they throw the ball at the opposition team's net who in turn try to block it by listening to the ball, which contains a bell, and using their bodies to prevent the ball from going in. The audience is asked to remain silent during play.</p>
</text>
