<text id="autogum_news_doc524" title="Formula One driver Jules Bianchi dies aged 25" shortTile="formula-one-driver" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2015-07-18" dateModified="2015-08-24" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Formula_One_driver_Jules_Bianchi_dies_aged_25" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Formula One driver Jules Bianchi dies aged 25</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, July 19, 2015</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Bianchi at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nürburgring">Nürburgring</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World%20Series%20by%20Renault">World Series by Renault</ref> race in 2012. Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Henry%20Mineur">Henry Mineur</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>French <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Formula_One">Formula One</ref> (F1) driver <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jules%20Bianchi">Jules Bianchi</ref> died on Friday night at age 25, nine months after his serious accident at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2014%20Japanese%20Grand%20Prix">2014 Japanese Grand Prix</ref>. News of his death was announced by his family the following morning:</p>
It is with deep sadness that the parents of Jules Bianchi, Philippe and Christine, his brother Tom and sister Mélanie, wish to make it known that Jules passed away last night at the Centre Hospitalier Universitaire (CHU) in Nice, (France) where he was admitted following the accident of 5th October 2014 at Suzuka Circuit during the Japanese Formula 1 Grand Prix.
<p>This is the first F1 race-related driver death since the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1994%20San%20Marino%20Grand%20Prix">1994 San Marino Grand Prix</ref>, when <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayrton%20Senna">Ayrton Senna</ref> was killed.</p>
<p>On October 5, 2014, at the late portion of the Japanese Grand Prix at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suzuka%20Circuit">Suzuka Circuit</ref>, Bianchi collided with a tractor crane that had been attending to the crashed car of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian%20Sutil">Adrian Sutil</ref>. Bianchi's helmet became wedged underneath the tractor, causing a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/diffuse%20axonal%20injury">diffuse axonal injury</ref>, and he fell into a coma. After being treated at a Japanese medical centre, he was moved about two months after the accident to a hospital in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nice">Nice</ref>. Placed in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/intensive%20care%20unit">intensive care unit</ref>, in December he began rehabilitation therapy. Bianchi's father, Philippe, described his non-progress as a "daily torture".</p>
<p>Bianchi, the 2007 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Championnat%20de%20France%20Formula%20Renault%202.0">French Formula Renault</ref> and 2009 <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Formula%203%20Euro%20Series">Formula 3 Euro Series</ref> champion, was the inaugural member of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ferrari%20Driver%20Academy">Ferrari Driver Academy</ref>. He joined F1 team <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Force%20India">Force India</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012%20Formula%20One%20season">2012</ref>. In <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2013%20Formula%20One%20season">2013</ref>, he joined <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marussia%20F1">Marussia F1</ref>; the following year, at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2014%20Monaco%20Grand%20Prix">2014 Monaco Grand Prix</ref>, he scored his and Marussia's first points with a ninth-place finish.</p>
<p>After the accident, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fédération%20Internationale%20de%20l'Automobile">FIA</ref>, which sanctions Formula One racing, formed a panel to investigate the crash. Afterwards, the group revealed its findings: as Bianchi entered the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/run-off%20area">run-off area</ref> of the track, he disabled the failsafe mechanism by "[applying] both throttle and brake together, using both feet", while his front wheels were locked; the panel also stated he did not slow down enough to control his car. Eventually, F1 mandated the use of the "virtual <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/safety%20car">safety car</ref>", which requires drivers to enter the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/pit%20stop">pit lane</ref> at slower speeds instead of proceeding around the track.</p>
<p>This is the Bianchi family's second driver death. <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucien%20Bianchi">Lucien Bianchi</ref>, the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1968%2024%20Hours%20of%20Le%20Mans">1968 24 Hours of Le Mans</ref> winner and Jules's great uncle, was killed in 1969 during testing at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circuit%20de%20la%20Sarthe">Circuit de la Sarthe</ref>, where the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/24%20Hours%20of%20Le%20Mans">24 Hours of Le Mans</ref> race is held.</p>
<p>Upon the news of his death, many drivers sent their condolences through social media. Bianchi's Marussia team mate <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Max%20Chilton">Max Chilton</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Twitter">tweeted</ref>, "No words can describe what his family and the sport have lost. All I can say [is] it was a pleasure knowing and racing you."</p>
</text>
