<text id="autogum_news_doc380" title="Buddhist UNESCO World Heritage site in India suffers terrorist attack" shortTile="buddhist-unesco-world" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2013-07-08" dateModified="2017-06-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Buddhist_UNESCO_World_Heritage_site_in_India_suffers_terrorist_attack" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Buddhist UNESCO World Heritage site in India suffers terrorist attack</head><p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 8, 2013</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Mahabodhi Temple in December, 2006. Image: <ref target="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Cacahuate">Cacahuate</ref>. </caption></figure>
<p>A '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/terrorism">terrorist</ref> attack' took place yesterday in the form of reportedly at least four explosions at the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahabodhi%20Temple">Mahabodhi Temple</ref> in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodh%20Gaya">Bodh Gaya</ref>, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/India">India</ref>. Four other explosions took place in the vicinity, including one near an eighty-foot tall statue of Buddha and three at Tergar <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monastery">Monastery</ref>. Three other <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/bombs">bombs</ref> were discovered and all were diffused. Early reports claim little damage was done to the temple. Two <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buddhist%20monks">Buddhist monks</ref> were injured. Police commented that Sundays are quiet days at the temple, or more could have been injured. One suspect has been arrested based on closed circuit television that recorded two men placing bombs at the temple. </p>
<p>Mahabodhi Temple is considered one of the holiest sites in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Buddhism">Buddhism</ref> and in India. Totaling twelve acres, it is a designated <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UNESCO%20World%20Heritage%20Site">UNESCO World Heritage Site</ref>. The temple is located next to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodhi%20tree">Bodhi tree</ref>, where Buddhists believe that <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buddha">Buddha</ref> achieved <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/enlightenment">enlightenment</ref>. The bombs were described as "low-intensity but not crude," according to police. The bombs used comprised of a small container with gas, a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/detonator">detonator</ref>, and an <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/analog%20clock">analog clock</ref>. The bombs were timed to explode at 5:45 AM local time, when Buddhists start praying in the morning. The bombs actually went off starting at 5:25 AM and ending at 5:58 AM local time. Early reports state that while the temple suffered little damage, the staircase near the Bodhi tree suffered damage and windows were broken. The Bodhi tree suffered no damage. 200 monks live at the monastery, where daily classes take place during the times when the explosions happened. However, no classes were being held the morning of the attack. </p>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ministry%20of%20Home%20Affairs">Ministry of Home Affairs</ref> has declared the explosions an act of terrorism. In October members of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian%20Mujahideen">Indian Mujahideen</ref> claimed to have visited Mahabodhi Temple to plan a terrorist attack. That led to the arrests of four suspects involved in the Indian Mujahideen, who were believed to have been involved in the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2012%20Pune%20bombings">2012 Pune bombings</ref>. The four suspects named other members of the terrorist group and claimed that they planned to attack Mahabodhi Temple. The police in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Delhi">Delhi</ref> claim to have told the police in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bihar">Bihar</ref> about the potential of a terrorist attack. Political conflict has risen in the wake of the attacks between the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Bharatiya_Janata_Party">Bharatiya Janata Party</ref> (BJP) and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Indian_National_Congress">Indian National Congress</ref>. BJP is accusing the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United%20Progressive%20Alliance">United Progressive Alliance</ref>, which is under the umbrella of the Indian National Congress, of ignoring the Indian Mujahideen's threats about attacking the temple. </p>
<p>The Ministry also believes that it could be tied to conflicts in <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Myanmar">Myanmar</ref> between Buddhists and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Muslim">Muslims</ref>, despite the rarity of violence against Buddhists in India. Additional security has been placed at Buddhist temples and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tibetan">Tibetan</ref> communities in India after the explosions. One suspect, Vinod Mistri, was arrested on Monday morning in <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patna">Patna</ref>. </p>
</text>
