<text id="autogum_news_doc555" title="Glasgow cannabis enthusiasts celebrate &apos;green&apos; on city green" shortTile="glasgow-cannabis" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-04-22" dateModified="2015-08-20" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Glasgow_cannabis_enthusiasts_celebrate_%27green%27_on_city_green" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>Glasgow cannabis enthusiasts celebrate 'green' on city green</head><p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 22, 2014</hi></p>
<p>Coinciding with Easter Sunday, <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Glasgow">Glasgow</ref> Cannabis Social Club's annual <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/420%20(cannabis%20culture)">420</ref> event was held on <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glasgow%20Green">Glasgow Green</ref>, under sunny blue skies, and overlooking the river <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/River_Clyde">Clyde</ref>. Despite <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glasgow%20City%20Council">the city's council</ref> attempting to revoke permission for the gathering at the last minute, police were happy for it to go-ahead with approximately a dozen officers attending in high-visibility vests.</p>
<figure><caption>Setting up the stalls, with the river Clyde and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adelphi%20Whisky">Adelphi distillery</ref> as a backdrop Image: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
<figure><caption>Good weather, albeit tempered with a cool breeze, saw higher numbers than the prior year's eventImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glasgow%20Green">Glasgow Green</ref>, in the East End is the city's oldest parkImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>A speaker from <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law%20Enforcement%20Against%20Prohibition">Law Enforcement Against Prohibition</ref> (LEAP) explained his organisation's position on cannabisImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Brian_McNeil">Brian McNeil</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Police were in-attendance from early-on, with Monday's issue of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daily%20Record">Daily Record</ref> reporting five arrests, but no troubleImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>A section of the crowd, with the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/People's%20Palace">People's Palace</ref> in the backgroundImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>One of the bands setting up to entertain the crowdImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>A neon-bright sign for the Glasgow branch of the UK Cannabis Social ClubImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Small stall, with obvious pro-cannabis signageImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Home-made sign for the Legalise Cannabis Campaign ScotlandImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>View of stage from partway up the hillImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>People buying refreshments from the stallImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Several attendees wore clothing with slogans openly advocating cannabisImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>A view of the tents over the stage and stalls from across the ClydeImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Attendees watch the stage entertainment while police look onImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Small groups of attendees regularly walked away from watchful police once it was made clear people would be arrested and cautioned for smokingImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>View of the stage area from opposite bank of the ClydeImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Trumpet player in one of the Reggae bands that performedImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>A small stand offered hydroponic suppliesImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Clear view of the hemp products stallImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
 <figure><caption>Close-up of some hemp-based products on saleImage: <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Iain_Macdonald">Iain Macdonald</ref>.</caption></figure>
<p>The <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daily%20Record%20(Scotland)"><hi rend="italic">Daily Record</hi></ref> reported five arrests were made for minor offences, likely smoking and possession of small quantities of cannabis. Taking a less-sensational —  and more accurate — line of reporting, the Monday edition of Glasgow's <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evening%20News">Evening News</ref></hi> stated five were referred to the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Procurator%20Fiscal">Procurator Fiscal</ref> who is responsible for deciding if charges should be brought.</p>
<p>Official figures provided by the police were that 150 attended. With people coming and going, <hi rend="italic">Wikinews</hi> reporters estimated upwards of 200 attended, compared to nearly 700 who had signed up for the event on <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Facebook">Facebook</ref>. Hemp goods were advertised and on sale at the event, and some attendees were seen drinking cannabis-themed  <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/energy%20drink">energy drinks</ref>.</p>
<p>"I was searched and charged under the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Misuse_of_Drugs_Act_1971">Misuse of Drugs Act</ref> (which is a lot of bollocks)" one attendee noted online, adding "not fair to happen on a brilliant day like it was, other than that I had a great day!" A second said they were openly smoking and ignored by police, who "were only really focusing on people who looked particularly young".</p>
<p>Cannabis seeds were openly and legally sold at the event and a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/hydroponics">hydroponics</ref> supplier brought a motortrike  towing an advertising trailer. Actually growing cannabis is, however, illegal in the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/UK">UK</ref>.</p>
<p>With the event openly advocating the legalisation of cannabis, speakers put their arguments for this to a receptive crowd. Retired police officer James Duffy, of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law%20Enforcement%20Against%20Prohibition">Law Enforcement Against Prohibition</ref>, spoke of the failed <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States">United States</ref> alcohol prohibition policy; stressing such policies needlessly bring people into contact with criminal elements. Highlighting other countries where legalisation has been implemented, he pointed out such led to lower crime, and lower drug use overall.</p>
<p>One speaker, who produced a bottle of cannabis oil he had received through the post, asserted this cured his prostate cancer. Others highlighted the current use of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nabiximols">Sativex</ref> by the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National%20Health%20Service">National Health Service</ref>, with a cost in-excess of £150 for a single bottle of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GW%20Pharmaceuticals">GW Pharmaceuticals</ref> patented spray — as-compared to the oil shown to the crowd, with a manufacturing cost of approximately £10.</p>
<p>Similar '<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/420%20(cannabis%20culture)">420</ref>' pro-cannabis events were held globally.
</p>
</text>
