<text id="autogum_news_doc701" title="US scientists create prototype of autonomous origami-inspired robot" shortTile="scientists-create" type="news" dateCollected="2019-11-05" dateCreated="2014-08-08" dateModified="2019-09-13" sourceURL="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/US_scientists_create_prototype_of_autonomous_origami-inspired_robot" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head>US scientists create prototype of autonomous origami-inspired robot</head><p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, August 10, 2014</hi></p>
<figure><caption>Self-folding crawling robot in three stages. Image: Seth Kroll, Wyss Institute.</caption></figure>
<p>A research team from the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Massachusetts_Institute_of_Technology">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</ref> (MIT) and <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvard%20University">Harvard University</ref>'s <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wyss%20Institute%20for%20Biologically%20Inspired%20Engineering">Wyss Institute for Biologically Inspired Engineering</ref>
has developed a <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/robot">robot</ref> that assembles itself within four minutes from a flat sheet into a 3D (three-dimensional) moving structure. Unlike previous self-folding machines, the robot can function <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/autonomous">autonomously</ref>. <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Science%20(journal)">Science</ref></hi> published the study this Friday.</p>
<p>Also on Friday, <hi rend="italic">Science</hi> published a report of a <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cornell_University">Cornell University</ref>-led research team on applications of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/origami">origami</ref> in design of programmable <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/metamaterial">metamaterials</ref>.</p>
<p>As <hi rend="italic"><ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/The_Guardian">The Guardian</ref></hi> reported, MIT–Harvard team lead author Sam Felton, a Harvard University <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PhD">Ph.D. candidate</ref>, priced the manufacturing equipment for the robot at <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/United_States_dollar">$</ref>3,000, which could then make each individual unit — a 13<ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/centimeter">cm</ref>-long, <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transformers%20(franchise)">Transformer</ref>-like robot — for about $100.</p>
<p>As described by MIT researchers, the initially flat sheet consists of five layers: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/copper">copper</ref> wires in the middle, then two layers of paper (above and below), and two outer layers of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/shape%20memory">shape memory</ref> <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/polymer">polymer</ref>.
The embedded heating circuits activate the robot's self-folding by heating shape memory polymers at the hinges.
The parameters defining the fold pattern which determines the final 3D shape are placement of the self-folding hinges, and the order of their triggering.
Felton told about creation of the pattern: "Cyclic folds are used by a software program called 'Origamizer' as building blocks to create any <ref target="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/polyhedron">polyhedron</ref>. We've discovered that we can [...] create a wide variety of structures and machines."</p>
<p>Once the battery is attached to the design, the robot folds itself into the pre-determined shape and walks away, with motion of the four-legged robot controlled by the included <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/microprocessor">microprocessor</ref> and two small motors synchronised by it.
Each of the four legs has eight "linkages" which convert the force applied by a motor into motion.
"It lets you transfer just one degree of freedom into a whole complicated motion, all through the mechanics of the structure," says coauthor Erik Demaine, MIT professor of <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/computer%20science">computer science</ref> and <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Engineering">engineering</ref>.</p>
<p>The robot moved during testing at about 5.4 centimeters per second, over a pre-determined route, not just a straight line — without any outside assistance.
Marc Lavine, a senior <hi rend="italic">Science</hi> editor, suggested such robots might be put in place "through a confined passageway, such as a collapsed building, after which they would assemble into their final form autonomously".</p>
<p>The folding pattern studied by the <ref target="https://en.wikinews.org/wiki/Cornell_University">Cornell</ref>-led research team is well-known in origami as <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miura-ori">Miura-ori</ref>, whose unusual engineering properties caught the attention of team member Chris Santangelo of the <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University%20of%20Massachusetts%20Amherst">University of Massachusetts Amherst</ref>.</p>
<p>Cornell University lead author Jesse Silverberg commented on potential of origami-based engineering: "When incorporated into more complex devices, these materials will enable on-the-fly transformation of mechanical function. We envision combining these origami-inspired materials with computer-controlled actuators to build more complex machines, such as hardening shells, locked-in joints and deployable barriers; and ultimately, this transformer technology will revolutionize the way we think about materials, moving them beyond their current static form, and revealing more functionality than what originally meets the eye".</p>
</text>
