<text id="autogum_academic_doc187" title="An Identity Authentication Method Combining Liveness Detection and Face Recognition" shortTile="identity-authentication" author="Shuhua Liu, Yu Song, Mengyu Zhang, Jianwei Zhao, Shihao Yang, Kun Hou" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4733/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Related Works</head>
<p>
Face recognition has gradually become an important encryption and decryption method because of its rapidity, effectiveness, and user friendliness. However, the security issues of face recognition technology are becoming increasingly prominent. Therefore, liveness detection has become an important part for reliable authentication systems. With the development of the Internet, criminals collect user face images from the Internet and produce fake faces to attack an authentication system. Ref. passed the authentication of six commercial face recognition systems, namely, Face Unlock, Facelock Pro, Visidon, Veriface, Luxand Blink, and FastAccess, by using photos of valid users. Common spoof faces include photos (print), videos (replay), masks, and synthetic 3D face models. Among them, photos and videos are 2D fake faces that are less expensive for spoof attacks and are the two most popular forms of deception. Therefore, it is urgent to introduce liveness detection into identity authentication systems to improve the practicality and safety of face recognition. Liveness detection methods can obtain different classification systems depending on different classification criteria. According to their application forms, current mainstream liveness detection methods are divided into interactive and noninteractive categories. Interactive detection methods use action instructions to interact with users and require users to cooperate to complete certain actions. The noninteractive method does not need user interactions and automatically completes the detection task. According to the extraction methods of face features, these methods can be divided into two categories: manual feature extraction and automatic feature extraction using a deep learning network. </p>

<p>Common liveness detection methods are mainly based on texture, life information, different sensors, and deep features. Live faces have complex 3D structures, while photo and video attacks are 2D planar structures. Different light reflections of surfaces from the 3D and 2D structures will exhibit differences in bright and dark areas of facial colors. Texture-based methods mainly use these differences as clues to classify live and fake faces. The detection method based on texture is implemented using Local Binary Pattern(LBP) and improved LBP algorithms. This method has a low computational complexity and is easy to implement, but it is greatly influenced by hardware conditions. The accuracy of the algorithm decreases when the image quality is low. The method based on life features uses vital signs, such as heartbeat, blood flow, blinking, and involuntary micromotion of facial muscles, to classify live and fake faces. Under the constraint conditions, this method has a high detection accuracy if life features can be extracted stably; however, this method requires face video as the input and needs a large amount of computation. Even more unfortunately, the simulated micromotion of fake faces can also attack this method. The method based on different sensors adopts different image acquisition systems, such as a multispectral camera, an infrared camera, a deep camera, and a light field camera, to capture corresponding types of human face images for liveness detection. The overall recognition accuracy of this method is high, but this method needs to add new hardware and, thus, increases the system cost. The methods based on deep features involve training of the initial CNN to extract depth features followed by classification. These methods use pretrained ResNet-50, VGG, and other models to extract features and 3D convolution to extract spatiotemporal deep features. </p>

<p>Given that deep learning can extract high-level abstract features of human faces autonomously, noninteractive liveness detection using deep learning is a future development trend. With the gradual popularization of face recognition systems and the decrease in the price of hardware, it is necessary and worthy by adding image acquisition equipment into some important face authentication systems to improve the security and reliability of them. Liveness detection of faces using real depth information is not commonly used in biometrics technology and the literature. All publicly available datasets such as CASIA, NUAA, and PRINT-ATTACK DB are designed for 2D spoofing prevention, and no depth data are included in these datasets. Therefore, we adopted a Kinect camera acquiring real infrared radiation (IR) images for liveness detection. </p>
</text>
