<text id="autogum_academic_doc363" title="Investigation of Gas-Sensitive Properties of Thin-Film Thermovoltaic Sensor Elements Based on Zinc Oxide" shortTile="investigation-gassensitive" author="Igor Pronin, Nadejda Yakushova, Igor Averin, Andrey Karmanov, Vyacheslav Moshnikov, Dimitre Dimitrov" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-6412/9/11/693/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Conclusions</head>
<p>
Thus, a systematic study of novel potentiometric gas sensor elements based on the thermovoltaic effect arising in the ZnO/ZnO–Me samples was carried out for the first time. An analysis of the obtained results showed the prospects of using the thermovoltaic effect in sensor elements for detection of various gas-analyzers. <figure>Figure 1</figure> and <figure>Figure 2</figure> show that ethanol exposure with a concentration of 1000 ppm led to an increase in the electromotive force arising in homojunctions by 1.5–2 mV over the entire temperature range. Moreover, the thickness of the upper layer doped by metal cations significantly affected the sensitization result. For all samples, the upper layer of which was formed by two immersions (as well as for the ZnO–ZnO(Fe) sample, the upper layer of which was formed by three immersions), the dependence curves of the EMF on the temperature in air and ethanol vapor behaved symbatically.  </p>

<p>However, for the ZnO–ZnO(Cu) sample, the upper layer of which was formed by three immersions in sol, the EMF dependence on temperature in ethanol vapors was an increasing function, and it was a decreasing one in air vapors. In addition, there was a change in the polarity of the EMF. This opens up additional possibilities for controlling the magnitude of the sensor response and the operating temperatures of sensor elements. An analysis of dependences of the EMF arising in the samples on the concentration of ethanol vapors was well described by the logarithmic function for all series of samples. At the same time, the ZnO–ZnO(Cu) samples, the upper layer of which was formed by three immersions in sol, had the maximum sensitivity to ethanol with a concentration of 2500 ppm. A minimum sensitivity was observed for ZnO–ZnO(Fe) samples, the upper layer of which was formed by three immersions (only 50% for 2500 ppm). Moreover, over the entire temperature range, the ZnO–ZnO(Cu) samples showed larger sensory responses (a maximum value of 1100% was observed at a temperature of about 280 °С for the ZnO–ZnO(Cu)-3 samples at an ethanol vapor concentration of 1000 ppm). </p>

<p>It is also worth noting the revealed correlation between the surface fractal dimension of the upper layer modified by metal cations and the sensory responses of the samples: A decrease in sensory response with increasing fractality was observed for all series. Moreover, fractal dimension values were in the range 2.33–2.37 for all samples, which indirectly indicates their developed surface.
 </p>
</text>
