<text id="autogum_academic_doc476" title="Artificial Intelligence in Lung Cancer Pathology Image Analysis" shortTile="artificial-intelligence" author="Shidan Wang, Donghan  M. Yang, Ruichen Rong, Xiaowei Zhan, Junya Fujimoto, Hongyu Liu, John Minna, Ignacio  Ivan Wistuba, Yang Xie, Guanghua Xiao" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6694/11/11/1673/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Advantages of Deep Learning Methods</head>
<p>
To overcome the aforementioned challenges, various image processing and machine learning methods have been proposed and have so far achieved great progress. However, it is important to note the advantages of deep learning methods over non-deep-learning methods (also called shallow-learning methods). </p>

<p>Currently, convolutional neural networks (CNNs) are the most frequently used deep learning model for image data classification, including tumor detection in pathology images of breast cancer, renal cell carcinoma, prostate cancer, and head and neck cancer. Several forms of neural network have been derived from CNNs for image segmentation, including fully convolutional networks (FCNs) and mask-regional convolutional neural networks (mask-RCNNs). Recurrent neural networks (RNNs), which are well known for modeling dynamic sequence behavior such as speech recognition, have also been explored in multi-label image classification and image segmentation. In additional to the aforementioned supervised deep learning models, autoencoder, an unsupervised deep learning model, has shown ability in analyzing pathology images through pre-training models, cell detection, and image feature extraction. The taxonomy of the common neural networks used in image analysis is summarized in <figure>Figure 2</figure>. </p>

<head> 3.1. Inherent Characteristics and Advantages of Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs)</head>
<p>
Inspired by the working mechanisms of the brain, deep neural networks, also called “deep learning”, have one or more “hidden” layers between the input and output layers. In each layer, there are many neurons, also called kernels. Each kernel (usually a function in mathematics) takes inputs and computes an output. In a CNN model, a convolution kernel computes a feature at a specific location, called a “receptive field”, in the input space. The term “convolutional” denotes the operation of sliding the receptive fields through the input layer to generate the “feature map” from the convolution layer as the outputs. In essence, this operation was inspired by the functional mechanism of the visual cortex, and it makes CNN a great solution for many image analysis tasks. </p>

<p>A deep learning model has two important characteristics: (1) it allows for the construction and extraction of flexible representational features from input data, and (2) it contains multiple layers and many kernels that enable it to approximate basically any complex functions using the extracted features. In all, deep neural networks are capable of automatically extracting features and solving highly complex prediction problems. In contrast, traditional machine learning methods have two major steps: (1) defining the features, and (2) constructing models using these handcrafted features. Compared with traditional methods, deep learning models have the following advantages: </p>

<p>First, deep learning models greatly simplify or remove the task of manually defining features. Manual feature extraction is very challenging and time consuming, especially in the following two scenarios: (1) the prediction problem is complex, and/or (2) there is limited prior knowledge about the relationship between input data and the outcomes to be predicted. Both scenarios are true of pathology image analysis, as the prediction problems (such as using pathology images to predict patient outcomes or recognizing various tissue structures and cells from H&amp;E-stained images) are very complex, and despite the accumulated knowledge from pathologists, little is known about which quantitative image features predict the outcomes. As a result, the advance of pathology image analysis had been slow and limited until the recent development of deep learning. </p>

<p>Second, the computation of deep learning algorithms can be highly parallel. As a result, deep learning can largely leverage the parallel computing power from the recent developments in GPU (graphics processing unit) hardware. With GPU-aided computation, processing (classifying or segmenting) a 1000 × 1000 pixels image usually takes less than one second for a deep learning model, much faster than traditional feature extraction steps and non-deep-learning-based image segmentation methods. Furthermore, since deep learning does not require handcrafted features, it can handle much more complex prediction problems and is able to recognize multiple objects simultaneously. For example, CNNs have shown great power in distinguishing as many as 1000 object categories. </p>

<p>Other advantages of deep learning methods include the following: (1) deep learning models fully utilize image data, as every pixel can be utilized in prediction model; (2) CNN models are insensitive to object position on the image, an inherent property of convolution operation; and (3) as discussed in the next section, by using extensive data augmentations in the model training process, CNN models are robust to different staining conditions in pathology image analysis. </p>
</text>
