<text id="autogum_academic_doc321" title="Determination of Optimum Frequency for Electromagnetic-Assisted Nanofluid Core Flooding" shortTile="determination-optimum" author="Fatai  A. Wahaab, Noorhana Yahya, Afza Shafie, Hassan Soleimani, Amir Rostami, Menaka Ganeson" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4608/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The electromagnetic (EM) assisted enhanced oil recovery (EOR) method has gained significant attention for the recovery of residual oil. The transfer of EM energy to reservoir materials depends on the molecular composition, such as the dipolar and magnetic molecules having free or bound charges like electrons or ions. Therefore, EM waves behave differently at different interfaces within the reservoir. The propagating EM wave exerts forces on the molecules, which then align in a direction parallel to the external EM field. Application of electromagnetic (EM) waves of certain frequency ranges has been used in nanofluid core flooding experiments for stimulating the recovery of residual oil after water flooding. The potential efficiency of this method has been demonstrated by several experimental and numerical studies. Different recovery mechanisms other than the common EM heating method have been reported recently. For instance, the application of a magnetic field gradient for the polarization of ferromagnetic nanofluid during nanoflooding experiments has been demonstrated. A considerable recovery factor attributed to interfacial tension (IFT) reduction and hyperthermia phenomena has also been reported with the application of EM waves (frequency range 500–1000 MHz). There have also been similar reports on the use of EM waves for wettability alteration, implying an improvement in reservoir oil production rate. Currently, few research articles have been generated on transmitter design considerations for EM-assisted oil recovery processes. For instance, numerical studies on EM-assisted oil recovery using a shaped dipole antenna was conducted by, likewise, a cylindrical antenna model using the wavelets analysis method has also been reported. Similarly, dimensional constraints have been considered in simulating three types of antennae at different operating frequencies, 915 MHz, 2.45 GHz and 5.8 GHz. </p>

<p>Despite the amount of reported studies, the effect of reservoir EM properties at varying formation fluid contents on the efficiency of the EM transmitter, and its propagation pattern have not been considered. Most of the reported studies irradiate the reservoir with EM waves of an arbitrary frequency (sometimes based on dimensional constraints) without considering the medium’s EM response, and its effect on the antenna operating frequency. Thus, this area requires further investigation. This is crucial because the operating frequency, penetration depth and radiation pattern of a transmitter depend on reservoir EM properties. These properties include the electrical conductivity σ, dielectric permittivity ε and magnetic permeability µ, all of which vary with fluid content, and are frequency dependent in varying degrees. Consequently, it is vital to factor reservoir EM properties into the determination of antenna dimensions and operating frequency to achieve the desired uniform far-field pattern, homogenous EM energy dissipation and to avoid hot spots on the antenna surface. Furthermore, the three-dimensional far-field pattern of a plane wave can be obtained from Equation (1), expressed in terms of the complex permittivity, permeability and conductivity of the medium.

(1)

where <hi rend="italic">μr</hi> is the relative permeability, <hi rend="italic"><b>E</b></hi> is the electric field vector, <hi rend="italic">k</hi>0 is the wavenumber in free space, <hi rend="italic">εr</hi> is the relative permittivity, <hi rend="italic">ω</hi> is the angular frequency, <hi rend="italic"><b>σ</b></hi> is conductivity and <hi rend="italic">ε0</hi> is the permittivity of free space. Thus, the phasor is represented as , where <hi rend="italic">r</hi> is the propagation distance, γ (m−1) is the propagation constant, which is a complex quantity of the form , where the real part α (Np/m) is the attenuation factor and the imaginary part β (rad/m) is the phase constant. Generally, oil reservoirs are a low-loss medium, that is . Hence, the irradiated EM waves are absorbed and attenuated as they propagate and spread within the medium. Therefore, the attenuation factor α and phase constant β becomes:

(2)

(3)

</p>

<p>The skin depth/penetration depth δ in low-loss media is , which is the inverse of the attenuation constant indicating the distance travelled by the wave in the medium before its amplitude reduces to 1/e of its initial value on the surface of the transmitter. </p>

<p>The half-wave dipole antenna was used in this study due to its extensive application in the EM enhanced oil recovery method, because of its radiation pattern. This type of transmitter focuses the EM energy in the center of the dipole and exhibits an omnidirectional radiation pattern. The relationship between the length of a half-wave dipole and its operating wavelength has been established by. The conventional method is to design an antenna with a calculated length based on a predetermined frequency of propagation. However, considering the constraint and practical feasibility of transmitter placement in a reservoir well, it is reasonable to fix the antenna dimension based on reservoir geometry. Thereafter calculating its operating frequency over a range of possible values of reservoir EM properties (ε, μ and σ) for optimal EM radiation. Hence, this research investigates the impact of reservoir effective EM properties at different fluid saturations on the operating efficiency of a half-wave dipole antenna. The ensuing EM propagation pattern of the antenna in a cylindrical oil reservoir model and its operating frequencies were analyzed. </p>
</text>
