<text id="autogum_academic_doc670" title="The Impact of Older Age on Functional Recovery and Quality of Life Outcomes after Surgical Decompression for Degenerative Cervical Myelopathy: Results from an Ambispective, Propensity-Matched Analysis from the CSM-NA and CSM-I International, Multi-Center Studies" shortTile="impact-older-age" author="Jamie  R. F. Wilson, Jetan  H. Badhiwala, Fan Jiang, Jefferson  R. Wilson, Branko Kopjar, Alexander  R. Vaccaro, Michael  G. Fehlings" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/10/1708/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
Renewed focus on functional and quality of life outcomes after surgery for DCM in adults has come from rigorous scrutiny of the results of several large-scale studies in the last decade. The traditional doctrine of the use of surgery to ‘arrest clinical progression’ has been replaced with a more modern approach with decompressive surgery used as a means to provide both functional and quality of life improvement. The assessment of quality of life metrics has become particularly important in the examination of patients with mild functional impairment (or asymptomatic cord compression), and is the focus of a number of studies. Careful evaluation has discovered a number of predictors of clinical outcomes from surgery for DCM, including baseline severity of impairment, duration of symptoms, presence of systemic or psychological co-morbidities, obesity, and of course age. With simple univariate analysis of outcome measures, many studies have reported worse functional and QOL outcomes with increasing age after surgery for DCM. However, elderly patients often present with increased duration and worse severity of symptoms, with an increased incidence of co-morbidities. Many elderly patients also present a high, sometimes unacceptable, surgical risk profile that makes decisions regarding surgical management less appropriate. DCM is a disease that can cause a significant amount of potentially reversible or preventable neurological disability in the elderly population, and therefore concerted efforts should be made to improve decision-making strategies for this patient group. </p>

<p>The results of the current study demonstrate a number of important conclusions, some of which have not been described in previous literature. Firstly, even when matched for co-morbidities, duration of symptoms, sex, smoking status and severity of functional impairment, younger adults report significantly worse effects on their baseline physical and mental quality of life scores compared to the older aged cohort. This could be explained through 2 potential mechanisms. Firstly, as the younger cohort were of working age, the psychological impact of DCM may be greater if employment security is perceived to be threatened. Secondly, the elderly patients demonstrate psychological resilience or adaptations/support that mean the symptoms of DCM have a less pronounced effect on their quality of life. This is an interesting concept, and is an important consideration for clinicians managing elderly DCM patients. </p>

<p>All patients showed improved functional impairment scores after 2 years (see Table 2). Taking the older cohort in isolation, this is good evidence that surgery is an effective modality to produce functional improvements in elderly DCM patients. This is an important stand-alone conclusion from this study. When the change from baseline scores at 2 years is calculated, it becomes evident that the functional improvement seen after surgery is of a greater magnitude in younger patients compared to the older cohort. This conclusion is similar to those described from previous univariate analyses in prior studies. Suggested mechanisms for this discrepancy include the fact that elderly patients often present with increased duration of symptoms at diagnosis, often have difficulty accessing specialist assessment and imaging, and also have less neurological plasticity or reserve compared to younger adults. The level of disability as measured by the NDI was improved significantly by surgery for all patients, but the order of magnitude was similar for both age groups (<hi rend="italic">p</hi> = 0.094). </p>

<p>All patients demonstrated improved SF-36 PCS and MCS from baseline at the 2-year interval, with the exception of the MCS scores in the elderly group. Both PCS and MCS metrics echoed the functional improvement in that the younger cohort had a significantly greater degree of improvement from baseline compared to the older cohort (<hi rend="italic">p</hi> &lt; 0.001, <hi rend="italic">p</hi> = 0.007). This provides good evidence that surgery leads to increased physical and mental perception of quality of life outcomes in all patients undergoing surgery for DCM. It appears that older patients’ mental perception of quality of life remains stable throughout the treatment period, despite having a worse functional improvement, and less magnitude of quality of life improvement overall. This study is the first to report this difference in quality of life measures between younger and older aged cohorts and has potentially large implications on pre-surgical assessment and counselling in older patients with DCM. However, age-related effects on health perception have been found to influence the SF-36 score, and the contribution from the perception of physical effects often misses a number of important determinants of overall quality of life in older persons. For these reasons, it has been suggested that the focus of quality of life determinants in the elderly should be weighted toward mental components rather than the physical. This also raises certain questions about the efficacy of functional assessment measures for DCM in the elderly, but this was beyond the scope of the current study. </p>
</text>
