<text id="autogum_academic_doc196" title="Computer-Aided Chemotaxonomy and Bioprospecting Study of Diterpenes of the Lamiaceae Family" shortTile="computeraided-chemotaxonomy" author="Andreza Barbosa Silva Cavalcanti, Renata  Priscila Costa Barros, Vicente  Carlos de Oliveira Costa, Marcelo Sobral da Silva, Josean Fechine Tavares, Luciana Scotti, Marcus  Tullius Scotti" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1420-3049/24/21/3908/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Historically, natural products have been used as sources to treat, cure and prevent diseases. The greatest contribution of these natural products occurs through plants, which can be classified according to their chemical constitution, and this classification is defined as chemotaxonomy. A wide variety of studies include the chemotaxonomic classification of secondary metabolites; among the most investigated compounds are phenolics, alkaloids, terpenoids and nonprotein amino acids. </p>

<p>Lamiaceae is one of the largest families of Angiosperms, the largest family of Lamiales, an order comprising 26 families and more than 20,000 species. This family is classified into 12 subfamilies, which are composed of 295 genera and 7775 species. Their species are usually represented by herbs and shrubs that are distributed throughout the world in tropical and temperate regions. </p>

<p>This family accumulates substances with very diverse structures and many of them are reported as chemotaxonomic markers at all levels: subfamily, genus and species. The main secondary metabolites isolated from Lamiaceae species are monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, diterpenes, triterpenes, pyrones, iridoids, phenolic compounds and flavonoids. Among these, diterpenes are more prominent as chemotaxonomic markers because they are easily found in most species of this family. </p>

<p>Several botanical studies have demonstrated the classification of Lamiaceae in the level of subfamilies. In the work of Harley et al., it was observed that 236 genera are distributed in seven subfamilies: Ajugoideae, Lamioideae, Nepetoideae, Prostantheroideae, Scutellarioideae, Symphorematoideae and Viticoideae, although 10 genera were left unassigned at the subfamily level. </p>

<p>Recently, Li et al. presented a review containing several findings that strengthen arguments for a new classification of the family Lamiaceae, reporting for each subfamily its phylogenetics and morphology. They observed through DNA analysis the presence of three new subfamilies, making up a total of 10 subfamilies (<figure>Figure 1</figure>). Of the ten genera that were unclassified in the study by Harley et al., the only two that were not allocated to a subfamily were <hi rend="italic">Callicarpa</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tectona</hi>. However, these two genera are inserted between the subfamilies in positions that corroborate with the phylogeny (<figure>Figure 1</figure>). </p>

<p>In the study by Li et al., the presence of two new subfamilies, Callicarpoideae and Tectonoideae, was determined, which in the previous study had not been classified. Therefore, the current Lamiaceae classification is composed of 12 subfamilies arranged in four clades, thus facilitating the organization of genera and species. </p>

<p>The biological and physicochemical properties of the molecules can be predicted through molecular descriptors, which are the result of the conversion of the symbolic representation of a chemical structure into a useful number, and there are several software packages to generate molecular descriptors, such as Dragon 7.0. The descriptor can be used to obtain chemical patterns that, to be visualized, need the creation of computational models that can be obtained using several algorithms such as the use of artificial neural networks (ANNs). </p>

<p>ANNs are defined as a mathematical model inspired by the neural structure of intelligent organisms, in which several nodes, called neurons, are interconnected in a network-like structure. In the process of identifying and classifying patterns, the commonly used ANNs’ unsupervised architecture is the self-organizing map (SOM). This is an unsupervised method capable of providing multivariate data maps in a two-dimensional (2-D) grid. It results in the clustering of similar patterns next to each other and has been used successfully in different studies that use database chemistry, including chemotaxonomic studies. </p>

<p>In the search for secondary metabolite banks already isolated from the Lamiaceae family, we can use databases that provide information about the compounds, such as biological, biogeographical and taxonomic data. Some of these tools are commercially available or freely available, such as the Bioassay Nucleus, Biosynthesis and Ecophysiology of Natural Products (NuBBE), Dictionary of Natural Products (DNP), NAPRALERT and Marinlit for natural marine products. </p>

<p>SistematX has a different relationship to the other databases available on the web, in that it is possible to use a browser to directly add and manage the data useful to the academic community about the secondary metabolites, such as research by chemical structure, SMILES code, compound names as well as information-specific species for taxonomic classification (from family to species) and the geographic location of the species from which the compounds were isolated. </p>

<p>Thus, the aim of this work is to construct a database of diterpenes from the Lamiaceae family and extract information for chemotaxonomic analysis among the subfamilies, using the molecular descriptors and SOMs, and comparing the results with the phylogenetic classification proposed by Li et al.. This will test if it is possible to predict the botanical occurrence in its corresponding subfamily. </p>
</text>
