<text id="autogum_academic_doc207" title="A Survey of Collaborative UAV–WSN Systems for Efficient Monitoring" shortTile="survey-collaborative" author="Dan Popescu, Florin Stoican, Grigore Stamatescu, Oana Chenaru, Loretta Ichim" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4690/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Applications</head>
<p>When addressing specific applications, most authors use a UAV as a mobile sink in either small or large scale WSN. Papers addressing specific applications usually do not detail data gathering or advanced path planning algorithms, but rather how such architectures respond to specific challenges and how a specific implementation achieved application objectives in a certain use-case. The implemented functions depend on each of the application’s objectives. The main applications of integrated UAV–WSN systems are synthesized in Table 5. More detailed characteristics of applications in agriculture, environment and disaster management are provided in the following subsections. </p>

<head> 6.1. Agriculture</head>
<p>Traditional WSN topologies are not suitable for monitoring small, strictly delimited, dispersed and isolated parcels, which are commonly found in agriculture applications. WSN nodes might also become unreachable as the vegetation becomes denser and performance is affected by the variable node elevation. </p>

<p>Hovering UAVs were used in real conditions for collecting data from cluster nodes in such applications and in reliability at different flight heights is evaluated. Di Gennaroa et al. and Primicerio proposed the use of micro UAVs equipped with multispectral cameras along with WSN meteorological data to evaluate the correlation between grapes quality and measured values. </p>

<p>In the specific domain of spraying pesticides applications, the following challenges were identified: </p>

<list>
<item>- Some areas might not have the proper amount of chemicals, while other might have a higher level;</item>
<item>- The efficiency of the process is highly influenced by weather conditions;</item>
<item>- The chemicals must be spread only inside a predefined boundary.</item>
</list>

<p>The authors in developed methods for these operations, which use sensor measurement values to change the UAV route. The sensors are deployed in a matrix to be able to apply the proposed algorithm. A chemicals concentration map is designed using the available sensor data. </p>

<p>An UAV–WSN–IoT systems in data-driven agriculture is described in. The UAV flight planning is done in conjunction to ground level data depending on the specific parameters to be collected. Duty cycling is applied as well as a scheme that leverages wind speed and orientation to optimize UAV flight time across the fields. UAV video feeds are compared against measured sensor values for improving inference of specific agriculture events. A prediction model is evaluated for inference of precision parameter maps and compared against nearest neighbor (NN) and inverse distance-based interpolation schemes. </p>

<p>A relevant application in agriculture is described by. A 1.9 m wingspan fixed wing Skywalker UAV is used to remotely collect ground sensor reading from commercial Xbee nodes deployed in the field. The parameters include temperature and humidity from a Rotronic HygtoClip HC2-S sensor. The UAV can be equipped with either a normal camera or an infrared camera and the on-board embedded control platform of choice is a Raspberry Pi. Field trial run results illustrate the autopilot enabled operation of the UAV over the target crop while analyzing communication and data collection performance from the Xbee node. A salient feature of the integrated system is that the UAV includes a small on-board tank for deploying directly fertilizers, herbicides or insecticides based on the output of the decision algorithms allowing for fast response to critical conditions with a maximum payload of 2 kg. </p>

<head> 6.2. Environment</head>
<p>In the environmental domain the integration of WSN with UAV devices led to the development of new applications, rather than increasing efficiency in existing ones, like in agriculture or disaster management. They cover various topics for air pollution, underwater or animal monitoring. </p>

<p>In marine applications, the challenges are given by the difficult access to sensor nodes dispersed over extremely large areas. Thus, proposes an application where several buoys are deployed in a marine environment, with no fixed positions. They collect environmental data like temperature, wind speed, pressure and humidity using the LoRa communication protocol. Subsequently, a UAV is used as a mobile sink to collect data from these nodes. Tests showed that a transmission range of 4 km could be achieved with a data rate of 5.4 kbps. </p>

<p>An advantage of integrating WSNs and UAVs in air pollution is the capability of obtaining a tridimensional sampling of physical phenomena, allowing further analysis and prediction of weather impact and/or pollutant propagation over large geographical areas. Orestis et al. have proposed the architecture for such an application and used a cube map area to model each pollutant. </p>

<p>In the case of wild animals monitoring, the algorithms chosen for path planning must take into consideration their movement over the monitored area. Authors in use the metric of value of information (VoI) to characterize sections of a grid where animal movement was identified as an area where intensive data collection is required. This way, the UAV can be directed with priority towards the areas where animals are detected and afterwards cover the rest of the network. Monitored information includes the picture, sound and odor. </p>
</text>
