<text id="autogum_academic_doc070" title="Zinc and Iron Agronomic Biofortification of Brassicaceae Microgreens" shortTile="zinc-iron-agronomic" author="Francesco Di Gioia, Spyridon  A. Petropoulos, Monica Ozores-Hampton, Kelly Morgan, Erin  N. Rosskopf" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4395/9/11/677/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Conclusions</head>
<p>
Addressing malnutrition issues such as Fe and Zn deficiency afflicting a large portion of the world population is a big challenge that deserves great attention and dedication in order to enhance the health and life quality of billions of people around the world. While there are no simple solutions to such a complex public health issue, the agronomic biofortification of staple crops and vegetables aimed at artificially enriching their content of essential nutrients has the potential to complement other strategies and contribute to address dietary Fe and Zn deficiency providing a relatively quick short-term solution that may be applied to face nutrition security emergencies. The potential success of this strategy relies on the adequate selection of target crops and the optimization and potential standardization of the biofortification process in order to assure the sustainability of the production process and the obtainment of a biofortified product that is of high quality, safe to eat, effective in delivering adequate levels of micronutrients in order to meet the RDA of the specific element, and easy to introduce as a crop or as a food source to the diet of communities affected by malnutrition and often resident in poor regions of the world. In this study, we propose microgreens as a target crop category for Fe and Zn biofortification. The possibility to self-produce nutrient-dense biofortified microgreens domestically, in a very short time (7–21 days), using only very simple soilless systems with the potential of exploiting a wide variety of species, could contribute to enrich and diversify the diet of malnourished communities in marginal areas of both industrialized and developing countries. By using three Brassicaceae species as test crops, it is demonstrated here that microgreens are a good candidate crop category for Fe and Zn agronomic biofortification. While genotype specific responses were observed for both Fe and Zn enrichment, this study allowed for: (i) identification of levels of Fe and Zn supply through the nutrient solution above which it is possible to observe phytotoxicity and accumulation of Fe and Zn at toxic levels not safe for human consumption; (ii) establishing levels of Fe and Zn supply that may allow for adequate accumulation levels for both micronutrients without decreasing yield and quality of the microgreens; (iii) identification of species that respond better to both Fe and Zn biofortification. Using a simple NFT (nutrient film technique) soilless growing system, supplementing a standard half-strength Hoagland nutrient solution with 5–10 mg L−1 of Zn (ZnSO4) allowed an increase in the concentration in microgreen tissue from a minimum of 75% to a maximum of 281%, the level observed in microgreens grown with a standard nutrient solution without any yield or quality reduction. Similarly, supplementing the standard nutrient solution with 10–20 mg L−1 of Fe allowed an increase in Fe concentration in the microgreens shoots ranging from 64% to 278%, the level observed in the untreated control, with no or only small negative impacts on fresh yield. It is concluded that Brassicaceae microgreens grown in a NFT soilless system are a good candidate crop for Zn and Fe agronomic biofortification through the simple regulation of Fe and Zn concentration in the nutrient solution. Further investigations should be conducted to optimize the biofortification method and (i) explore the suitability of Fe and Zn biofortification of other microgreens species and cultivars; (ii) assess the potential presence of antinutritional (phytates, nitrates, accumulation of toxic metals) or pro-absorption factors (ascorbic acid, β-carotene) in Zn and Fe biofortified microgreens; and (iii) assess the bioavailability and bioaccessibility of both Fe and Zn biofortified microgreens.
 </p>
</text>
