<text id="autogum_academic_doc555" title="Archaeological Prospection with Motorised Multichannel Ground-Penetrating Radar Arrays on Snow-Covered Areas in Norway" shortTile="archaeological-prospection" author="Manuel Gabler, Immo Trinks, Erich Nau, Alois Hinterleitner, Knut Paasche, Lars Gustavsen, Monica Kristiansen, Christer Tonning, Petra Schneidhofer, Matthias Kucera, Wolfgang Neubauer" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/21/2485/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion</head>
<p>The results show that archaeological prospection with a motorised multi-channel GPR system can be successful even in areas covered with a substantial layer of snow. However, the GPR measurements on frozen ground with a thin snow cover of only 5–10 cm thickness resulted in the data images with highest signal-to-noise ratio regarding the archaeological target structures, better even than measurements conducted on bare ground at temperatures above freezing. <figure>Figure 10</figure> illustrates the four different situations encountered in this study: </p>

<p>
<list>
<item>(a) Normal survey on ground without snow cover at temperatures above freezing.</item>
<item>(b) Survey on frozen ground covered with a thin layer of dry snow, as the situation encountered at Borre in winter time.</item>
<item>(c) Survey on a thick layer of dry snow. Due to the insulating character of the snow layer the ground possibly has not been as deeply frozen as in case (b). This is assumed to have been the situation encountered at Odberg. The situation encountered at Stange is assumed to have been between situations (b) and (c).</item>
<item>(d) Survey on medium thick layer of wet snow above frozen ground. The snow contains wet water due to thawing and rainfall, causing a liquid water accumulation at the snow-ground surface. This is assumed to have been the situation encountered at Sem.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>The differences in obtained data quality in regard to the imaging of buried archaeological remains is understood to have been mainly caused by the variable GPR pulse absorption rates due to the different properties of the snow cover and the underlying topsoil. Table 2 lists GPR pulse propagation parameters relevant for media encountered in this study, derived for a 400 MHz pulse (<ref target="http://gpr-parameters.ch">http://gpr-parameters.ch</ref>). The GPR pulse attenuation  is computed as a function of the relative dielectric constant  and the electrical conductivity

(1)</p>

<p>We see that a layer of dry snow hardly attenuates the GPR pulse at all. Its thickness may however have a detrimental effect on the image resolution due to geometrical spreading of the GPR pulse, as discussed below. In general, the air/ground interface can have a dramatic effect on all GPR measurements in which the antenna is not placed closely on the ground surface. Too great a distance from the ground will cause the reflection of a large part of the transmitted electromagnetic energy of the GPR pulse, preventing it from reaching further below for subsurface imaging. Critical distances of the GPR antenna from the ground surface are those greater than one quarter to a half of the wavelength of the transmitted pulse. </p>

<p>When the air temperature is above zero and the top soil is not frozen, the amount of liquid water in the soil has a great effect on GPR pulse propagation and attenuation. “<hi rend="italic">Water is the single biggest factor which determines the bulk electrical properties of materials in most Earth settings</hi>” stated Davis and Annan in 1989. The topsoil, which in agriculturally used fields corresponds to the plough layer, is rich in organic material and pore space between the solid particles, comprising the soil water. In media where liquid water is present, dramatic changes of the GPR velocity can occur, complicating the imaging of buried structures, as described by Urban et al.. The electrical properties of water change dramatically when freezing, resulting in frozen soil to behave very differently than soil that is not frozen. According to the values listed in Table 2, frozen soil has a signal attenuation of 0.138 dB/m, which is considerably less than the values for loamy or clayey soils. Only dry sand has a lower attenuation among the soils. Snow has a very low attenuation factor of 0.003 dB/m. While no attenuation value is given for wet snow, in comparison it can be assumed that it is similar to the much increased attenuation observed in wet sand. </p>
</text>
