<text id="autogum_academic_doc046" title="Structural Characterization of Full-Length Human Dehydrodolichyl Diphosphate Synthase Using an Integrative Computational and Experimental Approach" shortTile="structural-characterization" author="Michal Lisnyansky Bar-El, Su  Youn Lee, Ah  Young Ki, Noa Kapelushnik, Anat Loewenstein, Ka  Young Chung, Dina Schneidman-Duhovny, Moshe Giladi, Hadas Newman, Yoni Haitin" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2218-273X/9/11/660/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Protein N-glycosylation is a critical post-translational modification, in which an oligosaccharide moiety is transferred from the glycosyl carrier dolichol-phosphate (Dol-P) and covalently attaches to a polypeptide chain via an asparagine residue. Following protein conjugation, the oligosaccharide is further modified, increasing the functional and structural diversity of the proteome. Indeed, this modification is crucial for proper protein folding, oligomerization, quality control, sorting, and transport. Accordingly, even slight variations in protein glycosylation can markedly affect proteins structure and function and, thus, glycosylation disorders result in a wide range of clinical syndromes affecting practically every organ system. </p>

<p>Dehydrodolichyl diphosphate synthase (DHDDS) together with Nogo-B receptor (NgBR) form the human <hi rend="italic">cis</hi>-prenyltransferase complex. This complex catalyzes the formation of dehydrodolichyl diphosphate (DHDD), a long-chain polyprenyl serving as a precursor for Dol-P. DHDD is synthesized by chain elongation of farnesyl diphosphate (FPP) via multiple condensations with isopentenyl diphosphate (IPP) (<figure>Figure 1</figure>A). Importantly, while previous studies revealed that DHDDS is required and sufficient for this catalytic activity, NgBR induces an increase in the expression and activity of the complex but exhibits no catalytic activity. In line with the important role of DHDDS in protein glycosylation, mutations in DHDDS were recently shown to cause autosomal recessive retinitis pigmentosa, a fatal glycosylation disorder, and developmental epileptic encephalopathies. </p>

<p>Despite the clinical importance of DHDDS, it was not structurally and functionally characterized to date. Conserved domains search analysis reveals that the <hi rend="italic">cis</hi>-prenyltransferase catalytic domain of DHDDS (residues 24–248) is homologous to undecaprenyl pyrophosphate synthase (UPPS), a well characterized bacterial <hi rend="italic">cis</hi>-prenyltransferase. Consisting of seven α-helices and six β-strands, this domain forms dimers, with a hydrophobic catalytic tunnel surrounded by two α-helices and four β−strands within each monomer. In contrast with the N-terminal <hi rend="italic">cis</hi>-prenyltransferase homology domain, the C-terminus of human DHDDS does not converge with any known conserved domains. Intriguingly, despite the low level of conservation, a C-terminal domain is common to long-chain <hi rend="italic">cis</hi>-prenyltransferases and is absent in short- and medium-chain <hi rend="italic">cis</hi>-prenyltransferases (<figure>Figure 1</figure>B). Nevertheless, its structure and functional role remains elusive. </p>

<p>Recently, we have devised an efficient procedure for overexpression and purification of human DHDDS in <hi rend="italic">Escherichia coli</hi>. Similar to the bacterial homolog UPPS, we showed that human DHDDS forms active homodimers. However, the molecular details of the interaction interface and the overall architecture of the enzyme remained obscure. Here, we determine a structural model for the full-length human DHDDS homodimer using an integrative approach that combines multiple sources of information, including a radioligand-based enzyme kinetics assay, size-exclusion chromatography multi-angle light scattering (SEC-MALS), small-angle X-ray scattering (SAXS), and hydrogen–deuterium exchange mass-spectrometry (HDX-MS). </p>
</text>
