<text id="autogum_academic_doc017" title="Characterization of Extracellular Vesicles from Cilia and Epithelial Cells of Ductuli Efferentes in a Turtle (Pelodiscus sinensis)" shortTile="characterization" author="Imran Tarique, Yifei Liu, Xuebing Bai, Abdul Haseeb, Ping Yang, Yufei Huang, Wenjia Qu, Ruizhi Wu, Waseem  Ali Vistro, Quisheng Chen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2615/9/11/888/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Results</head><head> 3.1. CD63 Immunohistochemistry of Ductuli Efferentes in Chinese Soft-Shelled Turtle</head>
<p>
Light microscopic observation of DE in Chinese soft-shelled turtle (<figure>Figure 1</figure> shows sections through DE), and sperm were exhibited in the DE lumens (<figure>Figure 1</figure>A). The detailed observation indicates that DE had distinct populations of ciliated cells (CC) and non-ciliated cells (NCC). The nuclei of CC and NCC are located apically and basally, respectively. Numbers of cilias originating from the CC into the lumen of DE, forming a network that had spermatozoa (<figure>Figure 1</figure>B,C). The CD63 immunohistochemistry results indicated moderate to strong immunosignals, mainly observed within the apical cytoplasm of CC. More precisely, the strong CD63 immunopositivity was observed within the apical region where cilia protrude out to the lumen of the DE. Between CC and NCC, the CD63 immunolabeling was moderate to strong. Whereas, the cytoplasm of NCC showed weak to moderate localization of CD63 (<figure>Figure 1</figure>D,E). </p>

<head> 3.2. Ultrastructure of Ductuli Efferentes and Distribution of Early Endosomes and Multivesicular Bodies</head>
<p>
The morphology of DE consists of the CC and NCC as described earlier by our research group. The nuclei of CC were ovoid, and mitochondria were predominantly observed in the perinuclear cytoplasm. Coated pits and junctional complexes were frequently observed at apical borders of CC and vesicles were evenly distributed throughout the cytoplasm in the CC and NCC. The nuclei of NCC were euchromatic and mitochondria were mainly observed in the perinuclear and supranuclear cytoplasm. The lumen of ductuli efferentes showed various microvilli and few cilia. (<figure>Figure 1</figure>A,B). </p>

<p>Careful observation of the basal region of DE showed that lipid droplets and mitochondria exist near interdigitations and cytoplasmic spaces of CC and NCC. Fascinatingly, early endosomes (EE) were also clearly observed with heterogeneity of few or more intraluminal vesicles (ILVs) (<figure>Figure 2</figure>C,D). In the DE middle region, the EE and multivesicular bodies (MVBs) were observed within the peripheral cytoplasm of NCC and near the interdigitations (<figure>Figure 3</figure>A–E). EE, MVBs with varied numbers of ILVs (Intra-Luminal Vesicles), and numerous small vesicles were observed at the basal body of cilia from the CC (<figure>Figure 3</figure>F,G). </p>

<head> 3.3. Extracellular Vesicles and Their Interaction with Spermatozoa in the Lumen of Ductuli Efferentes</head>
<p>
The lumen of DE showed microvilli, apical blebs, and cilia. Microvilli and cilia can easily be distinguished due to their thickness and morphological appearance. Apical blebs were observed over the microvilli from the NCC (<figure>Figure 4</figure>A). However, cilia showed blebs containing numerous vesicles that became more numerous with the size of blebs, for that reason, we suggest using the name ciliary blebs (<figure>Figure 4</figure>A,B). Many extracellular vesicles (EVs) appeared in the lumen and between the distinct lateral boundary of CC and NCC. Collectively, the DE epithelia possessed a well-developed exocytic pathway and showed numerous EVs that might be secreted by the shedding of apical blebs or ciliary blebs. Hence, EVs in DE originate in a different way. In addition, at the ultrastructural level, these EVs are associated with the principal piece of the spermatozoa (<figure>Figure 5</figure>E).  </p>
</text>
