<text id="autogum_academic_doc245" title="The Construction of the Past: Towards a Theory for Knowing the Past" shortTile="construction-past" author="Kenneth Thibodeau" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2078-2489/10/11/332/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Towards Testing, Verification and Quantification</head>
<p>
The presentation of CPT in Part 3 is highly abstract and requires the addition of more specific classes and properties, with greater precision, to be applicable in practice; however, between articulation and application, the critical issue that needs to be addressed is whether CPT can support empirical testing and verification. To enable the reformulation of archival science as an engineering discipline, verification should be against quantitative parameters. Reformulating qualitative concepts in quantitative terms has the further benefit of creating the opportunity to apply a variety of powerful and supple mathematical tools in the construction of the past. </p>

<p>In the development of CPT, the issue of verifiability has been addressed from the bottom-up, starting with Construction Materials and focusing on Archival Assets. An Item Vestige that is a member of an instance of Archival Assets may be called an Archival Vestige. A record, as defined in archival science, is a subclass of Archival Vestige. Archival Assets that comprise records include files, series and archival fonds, progressively higher levels of aggregation of records in accordance with a filing system or records classification system. The systematic arrangement of records in such systems typically has a tree structure. A tree is a type of graph, suggesting the possibility of adopting a graph theoretical approach in archival engineering. </p>

<p>This possibility becomes compelling in light of the fundamental concept of archival science. “At the core of archival science is the concept of the archival bond, that is, the network of relationships that each record has with the records belonging in the same aggregation. The archival bond first arises when a record is set aside and thereby connected to another in the course of action, but is incremental, because, as the connective tissue that joins a record to those surrounding it, it is in continuing formation and growth until the aggregation in which the record belongs is no longer subject to expansion, that is, until the activity producing such aggregation is completed”. There are several problems with the way this concept has been articulated. Obviously it deviates from Cencetti’s original formulation where the archival bond arises from the use of documents by the same Human Agent in the same Activity, thus prior to and independently of being set aside as a record. Moreover, neither the quoted description nor Cencetti’s formulation distinguish between the network as a whole and the specific relationships between pairs or among groups of records. Additionally, the application of the concept of archival bond has assumed that all the relationships that arise in use are embodied in the filing system in which the records are kept. Except in very simple cases, a filing system is a partial way of expressing relationships among records; partial in both senses of incomplete and biased. By locating a record in a single position in a hierarchical classification, filing systems constrain the expression of the relationships of a document to other records and to the action or actions in which it was used. </p>

<p>These confusions and other difficulties can be eliminated by introducing the concept of an archival graph. An archival graph is a graph whose nodes are the Archival Units used in an activity and whose edges are the Relationships that arise from that use. Strictly speaking, in conformance with graph theory, an Archival Unit is itself a graph whose nodes are an Item Vestige and the Relationships it has with other Item Vestiges used in the same Activity. It is a directed graph where each edge goes from an Item Vestige to a Relationship with a “has a” label. This construct eliminates the confusion entailed by the fact that the same document, or information item of any kind can be a different record in different contexts. For example, an invoice identifies an account receivable in the records of a supplier, but an account payable as a record of the customer. </p>

<p>The definition of an archival graph encompasses a domain that is larger than that of the archival bond when there is more than one independent Human Agent participating in an activity. That is because ‘record’ is defined with respect to a single Individual Person, Group of Persons or Organization acting as a records creator. If several independent Human Agents participate in an Activity, each may keep its own records. While some information objects will likely be duplicated in the different aggregates, just as likely there will be records unique to each. Furthermore, the Archival Units used in many activities may include some that are not kept as records by any Participant; for example, Human Agents may have frequent recourse to data available on the Internet and not downloaded to any local store. </p>
</text>
