<text id="autogum_academic_doc013" title="An Analysis of Irrigation Organizations in Colombia through the Prism of Collective Action" shortTile="analysis-irrigation" author="Juan  Patricio Molina-Ochoa, Rosa Gallardo-Cobos, Pedro Sánchez-Zamora" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0472/9/11/235/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions</head>
<p>
In short, the complexity of rural life is overwhelming, and its crossroads are also expressed in organizations. The analysis of this reality highlights the need to complement technical solutions with human variables. Hence, it is important that the State and the organizations themselves become aware of the challenges of associating under these circumstances. </p>

<p>To understand the complexity, the methodology used was based on the construction of some categories of analysis to identify the factors that influence collective action. These categories were developed based on the results of the research and a theoretical framework in which the concepts of common good, collective action, social capital, and human capital were valuable inputs to achieve a systemic vision. The information obtained was organized according to the economic, social, and institutional characteristics of the producers, together with the characteristics of their collective work. These constituted the categories of the results achieved after analysis. </p>

<p>The results achieved allow us to answer the research question about the factors that limit collective action, validate the theoretical elements used, and highlight the need to deepen the categories of analysis and the factors examined. With the use of the mixed research method, a complement between qualitative and quantitative information was achieved, which enriched the analysis and contributed to a better approach to complexity based on the voices of the producers and their interpretation. </p>

<p>The investigation allows us to conclude that collective action in smallholder irrigation organizations is negatively affected by the following factors. </p>

<p>An incipient awareness of water as a common good, marked by a tradition of individual management without prior associative experience and without being subject to strict regulations. This lack of awareness represents a starting point of influence due to its role in determining the course. Because members of the organizations use water as a productive resource but not from a more integral perspective, a resource of common use and the interests of the group or of the beneficiary community and their management agreements do not acquire the relevance they deserve with respect to individual interests. This suggests that achieving a collective irrigation culture is not an immediate effect of belonging to a user organization but requires time and training over a long period. </p>

<p>An instrumental vision of organizations perceived exclusively as a means of accessing State funding resources and having an irrigation infrastructure. This is expressed in the motivations of the associates in which, although there is a discourse on collective and far-reaching purposes, the immediate and short-term private interests take precedence in practice. The lack of coherence between motivations that praise collective work and actions that prioritize personal interests restricts the scope of collective action. </p>

<p>A structuring of the organizations are limited to state and legal requirements, but without being concerned about establishing agreements that transcend the construction of the works. Therefore, they interpret the conditions and interests of their members. From this perspective, the organization acquires a strictly formal meaning. It seems that the central concern of the members is to comply with the legal requirements, by neglecting the organization itself in terms of its collective performance, its future projection, and its background scope, which are also not visualized. It is one thing to adapt to a format and another to use it to give it its own content with a strategic sense. This problem is aggravated by the absence of initiatives on the part of the State to support or accompany these more far-reaching purposes. </p>

<p>An internal division of organizations expressed in conflicts between directors and the members, caused mainly by mutual distrust. All the organizations have directors focused on performance, but who do not always enjoy sufficient credibility from usually indifferent, passive, or uninformed bases. This shows weaknesses in, and even absence of, leadership and participation. Then leadership and participation lose their cohesive power and become the opposite: a source of conflict. Overcoming this problem requires organizations to move toward community leadership, which is characterized by inclusivity. This requires replacing leadership that concentrates on the interests and power of managers.  </p>

<p>The adverse conditions of the organizational context and the marginality of the associates reinforce the occurrence of the factors mentioned above, which generates a snowball effect. Individualism becomes a strategy of subsistence and risk minimization, while collective work is assumed as a requirement of public policy that, in theory, would serve the common purposes, but which, in practice, conflicts with prevention toward associativity and, in general, with the incipient formation of values and indispensable capacities for enduring collective dynamics. </p>

<p>The substantive contribution of this research lies in the identification and analysis of this set of factors relevant to collective action. It is hoped that they can be taken into account in other investigations, in which their importance will most likely vary according to the case studied. Likewise, this research highlights the importance of studying these factors in light of the categories of analysis used, so that a systemic approach that aids a better understanding of complexity is advanced. </p>
</text>
