<text id="autogum_academic_doc441" title="Channel Selection and Pricing Decisions Considering Three Charging Modes of Production Capacity Sharing Platform: A Sustainable Operations Perspective" shortTile="channel-selection" author="Daozhi Zhao, Yang Xue, Cejun Cao, Hongshuai Han" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5913/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Numerical Examples</head>
<p>
The numerical examples were constructed to illustrate the effects of interaction among the capacity supplier, the traditional supplier, the manufacturer, the platform, and sustainably conscious consumers on the profit of each participant from the perspective of sustainable operations. Furthermore, the changes in the platform’s charging mode selection in different stages of sustainable development were analyzed. In addition, the impacts of charging modes on consumer surplus and social welfare were discussed. </p>

<head> 6.1. Relationship Between Access Requirements and Commission Rates for Sustainable Operations</head>
<p>
Scenario  where all parameters were used was adopted to investigate the impacts of interaction between  and commission rates on the profit of each stakeholder, which is depicted in <figure>Figure 3</figure>a–h. In order to make the results more obvious, parameter values were set as:  in <figure>Figure 3</figure>a–h;  in <figure>Figure 3</figure>e–h;  in <figure>Figure 3</figure>a–d;  in <figure>Figure 3</figure>a,  in <figure>Figure 3</figure>b,e,  in <figure>Figure 3</figure>c,f,  in <figure>Figure 3</figure>g, and  in <figure>Figure 3</figure>d,h. </p>

<p>Comparing (b) and (e), or (c) and (f), or (d) and (h), the commission rates charged to the capacity supplier had stronger effects than the equal commission rates charged to the manufacturer on the profit of each participant. Specifically, take the profit of the platform as an example:  with  and  with  in <figure>Figure 3</figure>b;  with  and  with  in <figure>Figure 3</figure>e. When  was fixed,  with  and  was larger than  with  and . Furthermore, the difference between  with  and  with  in <figure>Figure 3</figure>b was larger than that between  with  and  with  in <figure>Figure 3</figure>e. In addition, the profits of the manufacturer and the capacity supplier were decreasing in commission rates. Traditional supplier benefits from an increase in commission rates. The results of numerical examples were consistent with actual situations where some sharing platforms that choose bilateral charging set the commission rates charged to the demand side higher than that charged to the suppliers in order to give each participant a more profitable space for sustainable operations. </p>

<p>According to Theorem 6, based on the relationship between the access requirements and the commission rate, the impacts of the commission rates on platform’s profits lead to three situations. Firstly, low capacity management costs, which reflect a low level of access requirements for the capacity supplier, set by the platform can result in that the platform benefits from an increase in commission rates such as <figure>Figure 3</figure>a,e. There were  in <figure>Figure 3</figure>a and  in <figure>Figure 3</figure>e because the commission rate  had stronger effects than the equal commission rate  on the profit of each participant and that there was a mutual relationship between  and commission rates with a given , which was found in Theorem 5. Secondly, with moderate capacity management costs, the profit of platform first increased and then decreased as the commission rates increase, which is shown in <figure>Figure 3</figure>b,c,f,g. Thirdly, a high level of access requirements set by the platform caused a decrease in profit of the platform as commission rates to increase such as <figure>Figure 3</figure>d,h. The results provided a reference for platform operators to balance access requirements and commission rates for sustainable operations when the manufacturer faces sustainably conscious consumers in a given market. </p>

<head> 6.2. Relationship Between Access Requirements and Charging Modes for Sustainable Operations</head>
<p>
<figure>Figure 4</figure> integrates twelve curves about profits of the platform with different parameter values under three charging modes. As described in Section 5, the commission rates set by sharing platforms typically ranges from 10 to 30 percent. Thus, parameter values were set as: (1) , , , and  or ; (2) , , , and  or  to examine the platform’s charging mode selection for optimal profits considering the level of . Among the three charging modes: when  was low, the platform obtained the most profits by charging the capacity supplier; when  was moderate, the platform can collected the most profits by charging both sides; when  was high, the platform obtained the most profits by charging the manufacturer. Additionally, combined with Corollary 2, the platform could obtain the most profits when it charges the capacity supplier and sets the access requirements that cause the capacity supplier to undertake the cost  to manage the surplus production capacity. </p>
</text>
