<text id="autogum_academic_doc677" title="Causes and Mitigation Strategies of Delay in Power Construction Projects: Gaps between Owners and Contractors in Successful and Unsuccessful Projects" shortTile="causes-mitigation" author="Edwin  Thomas Banobi, Wooyong Jung" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5973/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Literature Review</head><head> 2.1. Causes of Construction Project Delays</head>
<p>
Previous studies have largely identified causes of construction project delays based on literature reviews and expert interviews, and the delay factors were classified into various groups depending upon each paper’s authors, as follows. Chan and Kumaraswamy classified causes of delay into eight groups; project-, client-, design team-, and contractor-related, material, labor, equipment, and external factors. Odeh and Battaineh studied causes of schedule delays in construction projects with traditional types of contracts and identified eight major groups of causes: client-, contractor-, consultant-, material-, labor and equipment-, contract-, and external-related factors. Aziz and Abdel-Hakam used various categories to classify delay factors; project-, owner-, and contractor-related, financing, contract, design, site, labor, material, equipment, rules and regulations, scheduling and controlling, external, and contractual relationships. Alsuliman investigated causes of delay according to stages in a public construction project, including before, during, and after the award, as well as general factors. Risk factors, which cause schedule delays in a construction project, can be categorized into various standards depending on the purpose of establishing the categorization. This study reviews the literature related to causes of delay in power construction projects from five perspectives related to the: owner, contractor, design, infrastructure and social, and external factors. </p>

<head> 2.1.1. Owner-Related Causes of Delay</head>
<p>
The owner’s insufficient project management capability affects delays significantly. Majid and McCaffer suggested that inadequate fund allocation, insufficient communication among participants, and damaged materials and equipment are owner-related causes of delay, while Ogunlana et al. suggested change orders and slow decision making. Long et al. conducted a case study in Vietnam to identify common and general problems in large construction projects in developing countries. They suggested ten owner-related problems that cause delays, including lack of strategic management, construction requirements, improper project feasibility study, lack of a clear bidding process, excessive change orders, unclear responsibility, lack of capable representatives, owner’s financial difficulties, poor contract management, and slow decision making. In addition, they specified delays attributable to participants’ communication and coordination into seven factors. According to Frimpong et al.’s study, participants, material procurement, and frequent breakdowns in the construction plant and equipment contributed to projects’ schedule delays. Koushki et al. studied the causes of time delays associated with the construction of private residential projects, particularly from the owner’s and developer’s perspectives. Their analysis of 450 questionnaires suggested three main causes of delays from the owner’s perspective: change orders, financial constraints, and owner’s lack of experience. Aziz and Abdel-Hakam also identified a total of twenty highly frequent causes of delay in their literature review. Among them, owner-related causes were the owner’s slow decisions, shop drawings and samples’ slow preparation and approval, the owner’s change orders during construction, owner’s financial problems for the project, and owner’s delay in contractors’ progress payment. As owner-related causes of delay, Khatib et al. suggested their financial problems and difficulties, change orders, delays and shortages of materials, poor site management and supervision, poor communication and coordination among construction parties, lowest bid awards, slow decisions, the contract type, delays in performing inspections and tests, and lack of clarity of the project’s scope. Alsuliman used a questionnaire to investigate the causes of delay according to stages of a public construction project. The results showed that the most significant group of causes of the delay was the factors associated with awarding tenders. In particular, the bid and award process, financial problems, approval delay, and owner’s poor management capability were ranked among the top 20 causes of delays. Marques and Berg, showed that the lowest tender award system frequently fosters contractors to assume optimistic design and price estimation for winning awards. This opportunism induces the changes in scope for increasing project contract price. Marques and Berg, also explained that the budget reduction by government frequently invokes the project delay.  </p>

<p>Based on the factors reviewed above, this study selected seven owner-related causes of project delays: change in scope; owner’s poor supervision; poor communication and coordination; approval delay; delay in procuring items, lowest bid tender award; owner’s inadequate fund or budget allocation, and materials/equipment damaged during construction. </p>
</text>
