<text id="autogum_academic_doc735" title="Investigation of Energy Efficient Retrofit HVAC Systems for a University: Case Study" shortTile="investigation-energy" author="Jayraj Ligade, Ali Razban" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5593/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Building Overview, Current HVAC system</head>
<p>
The building under study is mostly office spaces. Building construction was completed in 1976. The current HVAC system was commissioned that same year. The building has six floors with a basement. Windows are very limited with only two small windows per floor and at the front entrance. The area distribution of the seven floors is given in Table 1. </p>

<p>The current HVAC system is a DFDD with electric heating and has multiple maintenance issues. A DFDD has two supply ducts running to each conditioned space. One duct supplies cold air and the other supplies warm air. Air from both ducts is blended in a mixing box to provide air at a desired temperature to the conditioned space. A generic diagram of a DFDD system is shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>. The building has thermostats, which are not programmable. The orientation of the building entrance is south. The building has an addition on the east side, which has a new HVAC system. For modeling purposes, however, only the original building with DFDD is considered. The zones of the old building and the addition are separate. </p>

<p>Dual-duct systems, in general, require more ductwork and dampers, and therefore occupy more space. One of the most problematic issues with dual-duct systems is that a volume of air much larger than that required by the building, must be cooled, heated, and circulated. DFDD systems tend to be noisier since the noise and vibration associated with the air passing over the mixing dampers are directly above the conditioned space. In addition, the dampers in dual-duct mixing boxes frequently leak, even when they are supposed to be fully closed. During cooling operation, the leakage of the warm duct increases the required energy for conditioning the space. The leakage is a function of construction quality and of the duct static pressure. Leakage ratios vary between roughly 3 percent and 20 percent, which is higher than single-duct systems. </p>

<p>Because health professionals are present around the clock, the building is set to be always occupied in all design considerations. To have a comparative study of this building with similar buildings across the US, the electric energy utilization index (EUI) for the building was calculated using ENERGY STAR Portfolio Manager. The ENERGY STAR score of the building was found to be 39. The site electric EUI was found to be 133.4 kBtu/ft2, while the US average with similar office occupancy and conditions is 44.4 kBtu/ft2. Thus, the energy consumption of the building was very high, indicating a need to lower the energy consumption. Table 2 shows the average local area utility prices used for analysis. </p>
</text>
