<text id="autogum_academic_doc268" title="Construction Hazard Investigation Leveraging Object Anatomization on an Augmented Photoreality Platform" shortTile="construction-hazard" author="Hai  Chien Pham, Nhu-Ngoc Dao, Sungrae Cho, Phong  Thanh Nguyen, Anh-Tuan Pham-Hang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4477/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Related Work</head><head> 2.1. Bloom’s Taxonomy for Construction Hazard Education</head>
<p>
Bloom’s cognitive taxonomy was an attempt to improve educational objectives regarding assessment and testing of teaching materials. It provided an organizational structure including six categories, namely knowledge, comprehension, application, analysis, synthesis and evaluation, which are arranged from the simplest to the most complex. Subsequently, many theorists have developed improvements in the domains of human learning such as effective domain and psychomotor domain. In 2001, Anderson and Krathwohl proposed a revised Bloom’s taxonomy which improved from uni-dimension to two-dimension. In the knowledge dimension, the authors classified four types: factual, conceptual, procedural, and metacognitive knowledge. In the cognitive process dimension, six levels were changed into verb format: 1-remembering, 2-understanding, 3-applying, 4-analyzing, 5-evaluating, and 6-creating. With the combination of two dimensions, educators could change from passive views of learning towards active engagement in meaningful learning. Bloom’s taxonomy and its revised version became the standard for designing educational curricula. For example, Thambyah et al. recommended twenty four learning outcomes based on the revised Bloom’s taxonomy for the final year project of undergraduate engineering. In addition, it provided for teachers a common language to compare and discuss between two different subject areas, understand how these subjects overlap, and deliver the conceptual and practical knowledge concurrently. Thus, Bloom’s taxonomy could widely influence the educational systems as a whole, through teacher preparing programs, assessment programs, and educational research. A survey of the education literature also revealed that several studies attempted to apply and implement the taxonomy in many domains of education including computing, medical and nursing, music, and engineering. </p>

<p>In the construction hazard domain, there is a potential to apply Bloom’s taxonomy for educational enhancement. The recent assessment methods reveal a gap in evaluating the implementation level of safety knowledge and skills in practice. To overcome these gaps, appropriate approaches and solutions based on cognitive and awareness processes should be proposed to achieve the learning outcomes and maximize the collective amount of knowledge for each objective. Using Bloom’s taxonomy, Kaskutas et al. identified the gap between fall prevention training and the favorite learning methods of apprentices, and then designed new curricula. Endroyoa et al. built an occupational safety and health model to achieve learning outcomes according to Bloom’s taxonomy. Pedro et al. proposed a context-based assessment system to improve visualization in teaching safety knowledge. Moreover, there is a growing tendency to apply modern technologies to construction hazard education. Building anatomy modelling and social virtual reality integrated into construction safety system are some examples. Although most studies have their own evaluation system, the application of Bloom’s taxonomy could be beneficial in helping educational programs better meet their learning objectives. </p>

<head> 2.2. Virtual Reality in Construction Hazard Investigation</head>
<p>
Virtual Reality (VR) has been applied widely in the context of hazard education and training in recent years. Several VR applications have been developed for hazard identification for targeted users such as designers, site workers, construction students, safety managers, among others. For example, these research efforts include Design-for-Safety-Process (DFSP) systems, Cave Automatic Virtual Environments (CAVEs), System for Augmented Virtuality Environments (SAVEs), Visualized Safety Management System (VSMS), Multiuser Virtual Safety Training System (MVSTS), among others. Le et al. developed a learning framework based on an online social VR system, which includes role-playing, dialogic learning, and social interaction for construction safety and health education. Following this, researches have proved the advantages of VR in providing interactive and experiential learning environments, which are very important to motivate and engage learners in obtaining hazard knowledge and skills. In an effort to develop VR systems that can provide close-to-reality visibility, recent studies have adopted the 360VP technology, which captures 360 panorama images of real construction sites. The 360VP enhances the real-world learning environment by presenting the dynamic nature of construction sites in reality to improve the hazard investigation knowledge skills of construction students and professionals. Furthermore, 360VP has demonstrated improvements in not only hazard education and training, but also energy-efficiency. Since VR or 360VP have their own limitations, researches have tried to integrate some VR technologies in order to enhance the advantages of these VR technologies so that hazard education and training can be improved. </p>
</text>
