<text id="autogum_academic_doc058" title="IL-33 Promotes CD11b/CD18-Mediated Adhesion of Eosinophils to Cancer Cells and Synapse-Polarized Degranulation Leading to Tumor Cell Killing" shortTile="il-promotes-cdbcdmediated" author="Sara Andreone, Francesca Spadaro, Carla Buccione, Jacopo Mancini, Antonella Tinari, Paola Sestili, Adriana  Rosa Gambardella, Valeria Lucarini, Giovanna Ziccheddu, Isabella Parolini, Cristiana Zanetti, Maria  Teresa D’Urso, Adele De Ninno, Luca Businaro, Claudia Afferni, Fabrizio Mattei, Giovanna Schiavoni" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6694/11/11/1664/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Eosinophils are a subset of granulocytes mostly known for their capacity to stimulate allergic reactions and to fight parasites. Under normal conditions, these cells are relatively rare representing 1–3% of total white blood cells. During certain inflammatory conditions (i.e., allergies, parasitic infections, autoimmune diseases) eosinophils can rapidly increase, due to both de novo generation from bone marrow precursors and proliferation of tissue-resident cells, infiltrating inflamed tissues, including tumors. Tumor-associated tissue eosinophilia has been described in various solid tumors although its prognostic value in clinical oncology remains controversial. In vivo, eosinophils were shown to exert a protective role inhibiting tumor growth in mouse models of melanoma, colorectal cancer, hepatocellular carcinoma, and inducible fibrosarcoma. Furthermore, eosinophils infiltration in the lung can prevent the formation of experimental pulmonary metastasis. </p>

<p>Eosinophils are equipped with granules carrying a plethora of cytotoxic mediators, such as the cationic proteins major basic protein (MBP), eosinophil cationic protein (ECP), eosinophil peroxidase (EPX), and granzymes (granzyme-A in human cells, granzyme-B in murine cells) that can destroy target cells or tissues. Indeed, eosinophils were shown to directly kill human colon carcinoma cells via release of granzyme-A in a mechanism dependent on the integrin CD11a/CD18 and on the cytokine IL-18. In addition, eosinophils activated by cross-linking of the receptor 2B4/CD244 exhibited tumoricidal activities against human B lymphoma cells. It appears that the process of adhesion through integrins is important for eosinophil activation during inflammation. However, it is unclear whether cell adhesion and degranulation are sequential or independent events. In addition, the mechanisms of granule protein secretion (i.e., degranulation) in eosinophils leading to tumor cytotoxicity remain to be defined. </p>

<p>IL-33 is an epithelial-derived “alarmin” playing multiple functions in Th2-related immunopathologies and recently implied in cancer immunity, exerting pro- or anti-tumoral activities, depending on the tumor type and microenvironmental factors. Tumor over-expression or exogenous administration of IL-33 promotes anti-tumor immune responses in vivo in models of melanoma, acute myeloid leukemia, lung and colorectal cancer. IL-33 drives substantial recruitment of eosinophils to inflamed sites, such as the lung, likely by promoting eosinophilopoiesis in the bone marrow. In addition, IL-33 can induce eosinophil superoxide anion production and promote the survival of eosinophils. We initially reported that IL-33 inhibits tumor growth and pulmonary metastasis in vivo in an eosinophil-dependent manner. Subsequent studies confirmed eosinophil-mediated anti-tumoral effects of IL-33 in pre-clinical models of metastatic peritoneal cancer, hepatocellular, and prostatic cancer. Our study suggested that eosinophils recruited by IL-33 might either function as accessory cells attracting CD8 T cells or play a direct antitumor role. Here, we further investigated the anti-tumoral mechanisms operated by eosinophils following activation with IL-33. By using a panel of tumor cell lines, we show that IL-33 promotes tumoricidal functions of eosinophils in vitro and in vivo in a cell adhesion-dependent manner, through the integrin CD11b/CD18 and by inducing lytic granule convergence to the immune synapse. Our data provide mechanistic insights into eosinophil anti-tumor activities stimulated by IL-33 that involve cell contact and directional secretion of granules toward target tumor cells enhancing killing efficiency. </p>
</text>
