<text id="autogum_academic_doc071" title="Genomic Perspective on Mouse Liver Cancer Models" shortTile="genomic-perspective" author="Sun  Young Yim, Ju-Seog Lee" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6694/11/11/1648/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Conventional Mouse Models for Liver Cancer</head>
<p>
A relatively large number of mouse models are presently available for the study of hepatocarcinogenesis. The common ones are chemically induced models, genetically engineered mouse (GEM) models, implantation models, and viral models. Our aim here is not to review all mouse models for liver cancer but rather to provide examples of the representative ones, mostly chemically induced or genetically engineered models (GEMs) that have been integrated to genomics of human HCCs (<figure>Figure 1</figure>).  </p>

<head> 2.1. Chemically Induced Models </head>
<p>
Chemically induced hepatocarcinogenesis is caused by an irreversible process of structural DNA changes. The most widely used chemical to induce liver cancer in mice is diethylnitrosamine (DEN) (Table 1). DEN is a DNA alkylating agent and when injected into juvenile mice, it forms mutagenic DNA adducts, which are generated rapidly in centrilobular hepatocytes. DEN is metabolic activated in hepatocytes by enzymes of the cytochrome P450 family and acts as a complete carcinogen if injected into young mice younger than two weeks old with actively proliferating hepatocytes resulting in dysplastic nodules, which progress to carcinoma. If given to an older mouse, additional stimulation is required for instance, phenobarbital (PB), carbon tetrachloride, or high-fat diet feeding. In addition, oxidative stress induced by reactive oxygen species (ROS) during DEN metabolization is known to contribute to hepatocarcinogenesis as they cause DNA, protein, and lipid damage.  </p>

<p>The mutational landscape of a DEN-induced tumor was described in a recent study using the whole exome sequencing technique. A high burden of somatic mutation was observed and almost all of the DNA changes in the DEN-induced tumors were single-base substitutions. Four recurrently mutated genes that are putative oncogenic drivers of DEN-induced tumors were <hi rend="italic">Hras</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Braf</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Egfr</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Apc</hi>. The incidence of <hi rend="italic">Hras</hi> was the highest reaching approximately 80% suggesting selective advantage during hepatocarcinogenesis. <hi rend="italic">Hras</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Braf</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Egfr</hi> mutations were present in every DEN-induced HCC with mutual exclusivity and may replace each other in terms of oncogenic drivers. Activation of the <hi rend="italic">Ras/Raf/MEK/ERK</hi> signal transduction pathway was the hallmark feature in the DEN-induced mouse model which is rare in human HCC. Of note, <hi rend="italic">TP53</hi> and <hi rend="italic">CTNNB1</hi>, the most frequently altered genes in human were never found in DEN-induced tumors. Although <hi rend="italic">ctnnb1</hi> mutation is not observed in DEN-induced model, its mutation is known to be observed in a two-stage model, the DEN-initiated and PB-promoted protocol. In addition, loss of <hi rend="italic">Apc</hi> function, mutation and aberrant nuclear expression of β-catenin may disrupt the canonical Wnt/β-catenin pathway.  </p>

<p>The Stelic Animal Model (STAM) demonstrates non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH) progression resembling the disease in humans. Since NASH is evolving as a major cause of non-viral HCC and may account for a large proportion of HCC in developed countries in recent years, HCC arising from NASH is important. The STAM model is created by combination of chemical (a single subcutaneous injection of 200 μg of streptozotocin at two days after birth) and dietary intervention (high-fat diet ad libitum four weeks after injection) in C57BL/6 mice. STAM mice manifest NASH at eight weeks, which progresses to fibrosis at 12 weeks, and eventually develops into HCC at a rate of nearly 100% in males. The STAM model had pathway mutation rates comparable to those in humans for most pathways with more alterations in receptor tyrosine kinase (RTK) signaling and chromatin-modification genes. This model also showed low mutation rate of <hi rend="italic">TP53</hi> but the cell-cycle pathway alteration rate was similar to human tumors. The limitation of this model is that the model does not show obesity or insulin resistance, which is the common characteristics of patients with NASH. </p>

<head> 2.2. Genetically Engineered Mouse Models</head>
<p>
Genetically engineered mouse (GEM) models recapitulate the multistep process of hepatocarcinogenesis with multiple genetic and epigenetic changes occurring along each stage of progression toward cancer formation. They are highly useful for assessing the impacts of a driver oncogene alone or in combination with other driver oncogenes or tumor suppressors. Recently, the Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) characterized the genomic landscape of HCC using large-scale multi-platform analysis of HCC, including evaluation of somatic mutations and copy number alterations. Commonly altered pathways such as cell cycle pathway, RTK/RAS/PI3K, and WNT pathways were also identified and therefore, data generated from GEMs would be useful in developing novel therapies and be tested in the preclinical setting if they recapitulate human HCCs. </p>
</text>
