<text id="autogum_academic_doc697" title="Increasing Landscape Appreciation through the Landscape Services Approach. A Case Study from Switzerland" shortTile="increasing-landscape" author="Roger Keller, Mélanie Clivaz, Emmanuel Reynard, Norman Backhaus" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5826/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion: Recommendations for Stakeholders</head>
<p>
At first glance, the results of this study seem comparable to similar landscape management projects, supporting the idea that landscape cannot be addressed only by a specific landscape-oriented policy; rather, its management must take several sectoral policies (i.e., forest, water, agriculture—see) into account. </p>

<p>However, the concept of landscape services can be used at the operational level as a coordination tool between stakeholders in charge of the management and planning of landscapes. By naming and describing the relevant LS (see Table 1) it is possible to establish a shared understanding of the relevant issues and the ways that different stakeholders can relate to them. Talking about “identification and sense of place” or “recreation and health” in specific areas can reveal more concrete needs than abstract discussions about goals of visitor guidance. For example within one of the study sites, the research team was able to connect different stakeholders based on their similar requirements to the landscape. They have now formed a project team that develops different awareness-raising projects, and a completely new visitor guidance for the study site. </p>

<p>On a more analytical level, using the LS approach can help find co-operative solutions in cases where conflicts arise between resource-based and non-utility conceptions of landscapes, as discussed by Gerber and Knoepfel. In particular, the LS “aesthetic pleasure” and “identification and sense of place” are clearly associated with non-utility conceptions of landscape. These two LS could bridge more resource-oriented conceptions represented by the “recreation and health” and “attractiveness of location” LS. The LS concept and typology have therefore demonstrated to be useful analytical tools for landscape research. </p>

<p>We furthermore consider that LS are powerful communication tools for improving awareness of the qualities of the landscape amongst the public, the visitors and the inhabitants. By formalizing the types of relationships (cf.) these stakeholders have with the landscape—whether a relation of exploitation of resources, aesthetic appreciation, or symbolic identification—LS can increase people’s awareness of the importance of landscapes and ultimately their willingness to protect them and/or develop them sustainably.  </p>

<p>How can landscape services help to increase landscape appreciation? An important factor is the interdisciplinary and cross-sectoral engagement with landscape services. LS provides three types of opportunities: (1) Communication, information, and dialogue: to communicate about the special characteristics and services of landscapes, and to encourage the population to engage with landscapes. (2) Cooperation between landscape actors: to constructively handle conflicting areas and options for further development, exchanging views on common objectives. (3) Support from public authorities: to develop suggestions for dealing with LS at strategic and operational levels, develop a set of best practice examples, and (co)finance dialogue processes on landscape services.  </p>

<p>Assigning responsibilities within the fields of action outlined above is challenging because there is often a lack of resources and expertise for a proactive approach to LS. It is much more common to react when problems arise, e.g., when the pressure on land use in an area has become too great. For this reason it was decided to support the interested actors from the five pilot regions directly in their work on LS in a next step: Specifically, various smaller pilot projects will be carried out in 2019, in which, for example, school classes will tackle the special landscape characteristics in their residential communities, or landscape events will be offered to the interested public in partnership with authorities, agricultural organizations, and nature conservation organizations. All these projects will be documented, and the lessons learnt will be prepared and generalized in such a way that best practices can be transposed to other regions. </p>

<p>The research questions examined in this project deal with a highly relevant but narrowly defined subject area by focusing on landscapes of national importance in Switzerland. They thus encompass a specific political and institutional context as well as certain landscape qualities. Consequently, the following questions arise: How can the findings be transferred to other areas, e.g., to non-protected landscapes? What services do densely populated or intensively used landscapes offer, for example? </p>

<p>The application of LS analysis on everyday landscapes should help answer these questions. With our focus on BLN sites, we already established that it does not make much sense to assess every kind of landscape with the same tool. Rather, we found that the specific landscape traits and services that different stakeholders see in a certain landscape should be the starting point from which a landscape service assessment can be developed. This is where the LS approach is helpful: it enables stakeholders to express the benefits and the needs that they see in regards to a specific landscape. Subsequently, a growing collection of best-practice examples can be used to inform the analyses of different kinds of landscapes. We therefore believe that not only special, such as protected, landscapes will receive better appreciation with such an assessment but also every-day landscapes. This, consequently, should lead to a more sustainable development of landscapes.
 </p>
</text>
