<text id="autogum_academic_doc110" title="Temporal-Spatial Differentiation and Optimization Analysis of Cultivated Land Green Utilization Efficiency in China" shortTile="temporalspatial-differentiation" author="Qianru Chen, Hualin Xie" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-445X/8/11/158/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Analysis of the Factors Influencing the GUECL</head>
<p>
The GUECL measured by the super-efficiency SBM-VRS model was a truncated variable with a value range greater than 0. For such limited dependent variables, if the OLS (ordinary least squares) method is used to estimate the model, the parameters obtained would then be inconsistent and biased, but the inconsistency and bias could be avoided by adopting the Tobit model. The Tobit regression model is an econometric model first put forward by economist James Tobin (1958) to study durable goods; it was then continuously developed and improved by many economists. The Tobit model can be used to analyze factors influencing efficiency and to determine directions and ways to improve efficiency. In regard to panel data, it is usually difficult to obtain consistent and unbiased estimators by adopting the fixed-effect Tobit model, so the random-effect panel Tobit model was adopted in this paper. The model is as follows:

(3)

</p>

<p>In the above formula,  represents the GUECL, <hi rend="italic">i</hi> and <hi rend="italic">t</hi> represent the <hi rend="italic">i</hi>-th province and the <hi rend="italic">t</hi>-th year, α represents the intercept term,  represents the estimated coefficient of the <hi rend="italic">j</hi>-th influencing factor,  represents the influencing factor,  represents the individual effect, and  represents the stochastic error term, which obeys normal distribution. </p>

<head> 5.1. Indicators</head>
<p>
Based on the existing research results and by considering data availability, agricultural human capital, farmer occupational differentiation, the extent of farmers’ dependence on cultivated land, agricultural added value, agricultural machinery density, agricultural scale level and agricultural disaster rate were selected as the variables to study the factors influencing the GUECL in this paper (Table 2). </p>

<p>In the above influencing factors, ① is an important condition that affects the GUECL—agricultural human capital, which is represented by the proportion of population above a high school education level in the rural population aged six and above in this paper. Generally, farmers with more education have a stronger learning ability for the GUECL and a deeper understanding of the concept of green environmental protection. Therefore, it was assumed that agricultural human capital has a positive effect on the GUECL. ② The main characteristic of farmer differentiation is the occupational differences. Considering data availability, the proportion of agricultural employment in total rural employment was adopted in this paper to represent the degree of farmer occupational differentiation. The higher the proportion of agricultural employment in total rural employment is, the lower the degree of farmer occupational differentiation is. Farmer occupational differentiation results in differences in farmers’ income levels and structures, so the influence of farmer occupational differentiation on the GUECL is undefined. ③ The higher the proportion of rural household per capita net farmland income in rural household per capita net income, the greater farmers’ dependence on cultivated land income. On the one hand, they are motivated to apply more chemical fertilizers to ensure crop yield and maintain agricultural income; on the other hand, they are also motivated to protect soil fertility to obtain a long-term and stable farmland income. Therefore, the influence of farmers’ dependence on cultivated land on the GUECL remains unknown. ④ According to the environmental Kuznets curve, agricultural added value may have different effects on the GUECL at different stages. Therefore, the influence remains undefined. ⑤ Agricultural machinery density reflects the level of agricultural mechanization. On the one hand, it is conducive for the efficient use of input factors and pollution reduction; on the other hand, it may lead to an increase of non-expected output such as carbon emissions. Therefore, the influence of agricultural machinery density on the GUECL is unknown. ⑥ The scale effect brought by agricultural scale operation helps reduce the cost of fertilizer application, leading to the over application of fertilizers, but it helps improve cultivated land use efficiency. Therefore, the influence of agricultural scale degree was undefined in this paper. ⑦ The higher the agricultural disaster rate is, the greater the factor input loss. Theoretically, the agricultural disaster rate has a negative effect on the GUECL. </p>

<head> 5.2. Analysis of Empirical Results</head>
<p>
In this paper, the software Stata 13.0 was used to conduct a random-effect panel Tobit regression analysis on the factors influencing the GUECL in the 30 provinces (autonomous regions or municipalities directly under the central government) of China during 2001–2016. The <hi rend="italic">p</hi> value of the model (Prob &gt; chi2 = 0.000) indicated that the model has passed the 1% significance level test. The log likelihood ratio (Log likelihood = 156.08984) indicated that the overall goodness of fit of the model was good with statistical significance. </p>
</text>
