<text id="autogum_academic_doc522" title="Influence of Potato Crisps Processing Parameters on Acrylamide Formation and Bioaccesibility" shortTile="influence-potato" author="Emmanuel Martinez, Jose  A. Rodriguez, Alicia  C. Mondragon, Jose  Manuel Lorenzo, Eva  M. Santos" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1420-3049/24/21/3827/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Acrylamide, a thermal processing contaminant with a low molecular weight, which is soluble in water, is formed when carbohydrate-rich foods are subjected to temperatures above 120 °C in low-moisture conditions, such as frying, roasting or baking. Several studies consider Maillard reactions to be the main pathway for acrylamide, 5 hydroxymethylfurfural, methylglyoxal–lysine dimers, Nε–carboxymethyl–lysine and pyrraline formation in processed foods, particularly reactions between the carbonyl group of reducing sugars and amino acids. Initial reports showed relatively high concentrations of acrylamide in high-carbohydrate foodstuffs, such as crispy bread, breakfast cereals, pastries, coffee, French fries and crisps. In general, potato products present higher acrylamide contents (250–4000 µg kg−1) compared to other food products, because of the higher concentration of asparagine in potato tubers.  </p>

<p>Acrylamide has been classified by the Agency for Research on Cancer as “probably carcinogenic to humans” (Group 2A) and, in the latest report from the European Food Safety Authority Expert Panel on Contaminants in the Food Chain (CONTAM, 2015), the margins of exposure for acrylamide lead to concerns regarding their neoplastic effects, based on animal evidence. Therefore, the European Commission recently established “indicative” levels for the presence of acrylamide in food, suggesting a limit of 750 µg kg−1 for crisps. Previously, the European Union and FDA had encouraged food industries to reduce the presence of this contaminant. </p>

<p>In response to this, the food industry has been forced to apply different strategies to reduce acrylamide formation, applying processing modifications according to recommendations published by the European Food and Drink Federation in the document “Acrylamide Toolbox”, which includes the following variables: temperature and time during frying, blanching treatment, and thickness of potato slices. However, the main challenge for the food industries is in producing potato chips with low acrylamide levels without affecting their sensory properties. </p>

<p>Although it is important to evaluate the effect of pre-treatments on the frying process on acrylamide mitigation, it is also necessary to determine their influence on its bioavailability. Potato chips are an important part of the snack food market in many countries, and few studies have been published about the bioavailability of acrylamide after crisps have been through the digestion process. Acrylamide intake in humans occurs mainly via food ingestion, where the total amount of this compound does not necessarily reflect the available amount to the body. There are chemical changes in the food when it enters the digestive tract, because of pH variations, and the action of several enzymes in every stage of the digestion process. In this sense, bioaccessibility is used to evaluate the amount of a chemical compound available for absorption after it is released from the food matrix into the gastrointestinal tract. Several methodologies can be used to assess the bioaccessibility of contaminants or nutrients: 1) in vitro, 2) ex vivo, 3) in situ and 4) in vivo models. Among the techniques mentioned before, in vitro models are more commonly used than in vivo models, because of their simplicity, lower cost, lack of ethical issues and good reproducibility under controlled conditions. </p>

<p>The present work evaluated some acrylamide mitigation strategies, employing a fractional factorial design experiment, and their influence on textural properties and bioaccesibility, by an in vitro simulated digestion assay. </p>
</text>
