<text id="autogum_academic_doc238" title="A Review of Automatic Phenotyping Approaches using Electronic Health Records" shortTile="review-automatic" author="Hadeel Alzoubi, Raid Alzubi, Naeem Ramzan, Daune West, Tawfik Al-Hadhrami, Mamoun Alazab" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-9292/8/11/1235/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Feature Extraction</head>
<p>
Feature extraction is one of the main steps in analysing clinical data and a primary key to success in any rule-based or machine learning phenotyping approach. Feature extraction can be defined as identifying a vector set that represents efficiently the content of information for a cohort while reducing the dimensionality space. Phenotyping systems extract discriminating features to distinguish individuals with a specific condition (disease). Feature extraction can be simple and straightforward, such as when using code frequency as a feature. Additional features can be extracted by applying some rules on the structured data fields, such as abnormal laboratory lipid levels or the number of visits. However, in case the previous techniques fail to increase the accuracy of the prediction systems, NLP is usually applied to extract more features from narrative text. A summary of feature extraction methods is presented at the end of this section. </p>

<head> 4.1. Structured Feature Extraction</head>
<p>
Many EHR structured fields are stored in coded format. These fields vary across different institutions’ datasets. ‘Diagnoses’, ‘medication’, and ‘procedure’ fields are the most common types of data represented in code. To represent diagnoses, the International Classification of Diseases Ninth Revision (ICD-9) is usually used. In representing procedures, the Current Procedural Terminology (CPT) is mainly used while RxNorm is utilized to code medication. Feature extraction using coded data is available and easy to access and is usually conducted by selecting the code that most likely identifies a cohort with a particular disease. However, since coding in EHRs is usually for billing purposes, it is not always sufficient to support clinical research. </p>

<p>The accuracy of code extraction within an EHR depends on whether the code reflects the physician’ opinion and whether the physician was able to make a diagnosis correctly. In both cases, often the code fields cannot be fully trusted. Recently, extracting features from coded fields alone is rarely used, and some additional rules on other structured fields are needed. Additional features can be extracted by setting a logical constraint on the structured field data to derive informative features describing phenotype status. These features may take different datatypes such as real numbers, true/false or enumerated categories. For example, the number of clinical visits, the number of prescriptions and frequency of ICD-9 code can be counted and stored as real numbers. The existence of some values, such as medication code, prescription code and hospital admission, can be stored as Boolean values (0, 1). The enumerated categories data field can be divided into different subcategories such as (low, median, and high) for laboratory results, (normal, and abnormal) for blood pressure, or classify patients into certain groups based on age. However, in some cases, using structured data alone results in poor predictability in capturing disease cases, making it necessary to look for more features in unstructured fields. </p>

<head> 4.2. Unstructured Feature Extraction</head>
<p>
While structured data are available and easy to access, there are limitations in using these data to describe patients’ phenotypes. Not all diagnoses and symptoms are coded and, therefore, they may offer a weak clue to the patient’s status. Unstructured, or free text EHRs, contain valuable information such as patient history and clinical opinion of this history. An analysis of these clinical notes could offer better information and description of the patient’s status; however, the manual review of these notes for large-scale projects is costly and highly time-consuming. To unlock and extract the hidden information from the narrative text efficiently and accurately, NLP techniques are usually applied. NLP is a field of computer-based methods allowing computers to understand and process human (natural) language. The ability to extract critical components from these data and convert them into a structured format could provide great value for clinical research. Narrative text has been utilized to supplement structured data in recognizing particular phenotypes of patients. </p>

<p>Recent developments in NLP techniques have shown an increasing promise in recognizing and extracting meaningful pieces of information from clinical narrative text. NLP techniques automate the processes required to access the large amount of embedded information in EHRs and consolidate the processes into a coherent structure. From an Information Extraction (IE) perspective, it is essential to pre-process the clinical text by some NLP techniques, such as tokenization, sentence detection, word sense disambiguation, part of speech tagging (POS) and parsing. Higher-level NLP techniques, such as negation, temporality, and entity relations, are crucial for the precise interpretation of the extracted information. Adoption of the previously mentioned techniques varies between reviewed systems and some of these components can be or are omitted. For the task of EHR phenotyping, NLP is commonly applied in three different manners: bag of words, keywords search and concept extraction. Further details on these techniques are given in the following sections. </p>
</text>
