<text id="autogum_academic_doc105" title="Ethical Financing in Europe—Non-Parametric Assessment of Efficiency" shortTile="ethical-financing" author="Teodora  Cristina Barbu, Iustina  Alina Boitan" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5922/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Conclusions</head>
<p>
The efficiency assessment in this paper focused on ethical banks as they represent a successful example of business strategy that reconciles financial profitability with social and economic returns. Their financial intermediation mission is always subordinated to triggering social and environmental impact. Their activity has received the highest recognition in the last years, as institutional bodies such as the European Commission or the UN are more and more focused on smart and sustainable economic development and growth. This new orientation of policies and strategies also incorporates ethical banks, as reliable pillars and tools for implementing this ambitious mission by channeling financing to small and medium-sized enterprises—SMEs, start-ups and entrepreneurs. </p>

<p>The study relied upon the most representative European ethical banks and aimed at investigating whether this special segment of the European banking sector performs its banking intermediation function efficiently, given the increased role it is going to play in the near future. Their efficiency scores were computed successively for a time window of four years, in order to get a comparative view both across banks in the sample and across different time frames. This dynamic picture shows that one bank (Credit Cooperatif) is the only fully efficient ethical bank, as it always reached a score of 1 which placed it on the best-practices, efficiency frontier in each of the four years considered. At the opposite end are two ethical banks from Norway and Denmark which persistently exhibited the lowest efficiency levels. Interestingly, we obtained evidence of another ethical bank (Alternative Bank from Switzerland) which constantly improved its efficiency scores, from 71% in 2014 to a level of 95.4% in 2017. Consequently, two business models emerge as being successful in terms of achieved efficiency, namely the ones of Credit Cooperatif and Alternative Bank. </p>

<p>Further research should explore the risk management issues arising from environmental and climate change considerations. The robustness of the risk mitigation framework has to be assessed for both the ethical and traditional banks as in the future they will have to turn towards a more responsible financial conduct, from a societal and environmental viewpoint. As argues, the different time horizons of risk exposure have to be appropriately managed and screened: Most financial risks exhibit a short-to medium-term horizon, as opposed to long-term environmental risks. </p>

<p>In a recent communication, the European Parliament warned that the inaccurate assessment or misleading presentation of climate and other environmental risks associated to financial products provided by banks can constitute a risk to market stability and asked the European Commission to design and adopt a new regulatory strategy aimed at measuring sustainability risks and to promote the inclusion of sustainability risks in the Basel IV framework to ensure that banks highly exposed to sustainability risks hold sufficient capital reserves for withstanding sudden losses.
 </p>
</text>
