<text id="autogum_academic_doc049" title="Comparison of Mitochondrial Superoxide Detection Ex Vivo/In Vivo by mitoSOX HPLC Method with Classical Assays in Three Different Animal Models of Oxidative Stress" shortTile="comparison-mitochondrial" author="Sanela Kalinovic, Matthias Oelze, Swenja Kröller-Schön, Sebastian Steven, Ksenija Vujacic-Mirski, Miroslava Kvandová, Isabella Schmal, Ahmad Al Zuabi, Thomas Münzel, Andreas Daiber" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3921/8/11/514/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Oxidative stress was identified as a hallmark of almost all cardiovascular and neurodegenerative diseases. The term oxidative stress describes a condition that is either characterized by increased generation of reactive oxygen and nitrogen species (RONS) and/or dysregulated cellular antioxidant defense mechanisms (e.g., decreased expression of central antioxidant enzymes). This will ultimately cause that tissue, plasma or intercellular fluid run out of low molecular weight antioxidant compounds leading to detrimental alterations of cellular redox state. The most abundant biological RONS include superoxide radical, hydrogen peroxide, hydroxyl radical, carbon-centered peroxides and peroxyl radicals, nitric oxide radical (NO∙), nitrogen dioxide radial, peroxynitrite, and hypochlorite. Some of these species were reported to act as cellular messengers and participate in redox signaling mechanisms. Nitric oxide (NO∙) for instance acts as an important vasodilator and inhibitor of platelet activation via formation of nitrosyl-iron enzyme complexes but also provides the basis for wide-spread signaling mechanisms by S-nitros(yl)ation of protein thiol groups as exemplified by suppression of apoptosis by S-nitros(yl)ation of caspases. The superoxide radical anion (O2∙−) can be formed from different sources such as xanthine oxidase, NADPH (nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate) oxidases, uncoupled NO synthases and the mitochondrial respiratory chain, and represent in many ways a direct antagonist of nitric oxide as shown by the famous experiment by Gryglewski et al.. The existence of superoxide dismutases (mitochondrial MnSOD and cytosolic/extracellular Cu, Zn-SOD) implies that superoxide may be harmful for the cell, which is supported by the fact that deficiency in MnSOD is lethal and deficiency in Cu, Zn-SOD renders mice susceptible to cardiovascular and neuronal complications. </p>

<p>Since the transition between oxidative stress and redox signaling is a thin line, the exact knowledge of the identity of formed species, the cellular and subcellular localization of their formation, as well as their time duration and concentration, are of high clinical and pharmacological importance. With our previous work, we have stressed that the traditional or old RONS assays are not necessarily inferior as compared to up-to-date or even cutting-edge assays and at least have their specific features and application spectra. With the present studies, we evaluated the specific probe for mitochondrial superoxide formation, mitochondria-targeted, triphenylphosphonium-linked hydroethidium (mitoSOX), for its usefulness in the detection of mitochondrial superoxide formation ex vivo/in vivo and compared this high-performance/pressure liquid chromatography (HPLC)-based assay with two alternative/traditional methods. For this purpose, we used three different animal models with well established oxidative stress burden, namely diabetic, hypertensive and nitrate tolerant rats. Given the recent report by Xiao &amp; Meierhofer raising doubts about the reliable use of hydroethidium-based probes for superoxide detection in cell culture, we think that our present data are of interest for all researchers using hydroethidium-based probes, but especially mitoSOX, in cell culture, isolated mitochondria and tissue samples. </p>
</text>
