<text id="autogum_academic_doc303" title="Forest Canopy Height and Gaps from Multiangular BRDF, Assessed with Airborne LiDAR Data (Short Title: Vegetation Structure from LiDAR and Multiangular Data)" shortTile="forest-canopy-height" author="Qiang Wang, Wenge Ni-Meister" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/21/2566/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Conclusions</head>
<p>
This was an exploratory study to investigate how a single anisotropic index calculated from multiangular measurements is related to the LiDAR-derived vertical structure parameters of vegetation. Based on the result, the physics of the relationships between the multiangular signal and forest canopy structure parameters were studied and assessed using airborne LiDAR data, and multiangular remote sensing data were used to map the forest parameters at larger regions with more complete geographic coverage. We found better relationships between the LiDAR-derived tree height, gap fraction, and NDMM index at the near-infrared band for sparse conifer forests in Howland. The difference between maximum and minimum reflectance from different angles includes the main three-dimensional structural information of a forest canopy. This paper presented a new and potential NDMM index to retrieve the tree heights and gap fractions from multiangular data.  </p>

<p>However, for the relationships between the NDMM index and LiDAR-derived tree height, the gap also varies according to tree species, stand density, and wavelength. As the Pearson correlation coefficient between the NDMM index and tree height, the gap fraction shows that the NDMM index for conifer forests is better than those of deciduous and mixed forests. For the relationship between the NDMM index and LiDAR-derived tree height, gap fraction also varies with stand density, and the conifer forest is superior to the dense forest. The results show that the NDMM index at the near-infrared band is better than three other visible bands. Gao, et al. also showed that an evergreen needle leaf forest has a more constant geometric effect than that of deciduous and mixed forests, and the relationship at blue and red wavelengths is weak, which is consistent with the results of previous studies by Kimes, et al., which show that the relationship at the near infrared wavelength is better.  </p>

<p>The BRDF vegetation structure retrieval works better in conifer forests, which indicates that forest biomass retrieval based on the NDMM index can be used to understand how to take advantage of the implied information between multiangular data and forest canopies. In this respect, the feasibility of retrieving the structural properties of a tree canopy from different satellite observations is a challenge. This challenge will provide scientific evidence for more rigorous models. Further studies using GORT models are needed to better understand the physics of the relationships between the NDMM index and the forest canopy’s structural information observed in real airborne LiDAR and AirMISR data. Starting with this paper, better anisotropic factors will be developed to link LiDAR-derived vegetation-structure parameters and multiangular remote sensing data to map vegetation structure parameters at larger regions for carbon cycle studies.
 </p>
</text>
