<text id="autogum_academic_doc010" title="Cloning, Characterization and Functional Analysis of the LtuPTOX Gene, a Homologue of Arabidopsis thaliana IMMUTANS Derived from Liriodendron tulipifera" shortTile="cloning-characterization" author="Ziyuan Hao, Yaxian Zong, Huanhuan Liu, Zhonghua Tu, Huogen Li" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4425/10/11/878/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Flower colour is an important trait for ornamental species, as brightly coloured flowers are attractive to people. Additionally, colour patterns and colour spots play an essential role in attracting pollinators to insect-pollinated flowers, helping to improve the fitness of seeds and gene flow within species. The response of pollinators to flower color is closely related to plant development and vigour. Pigments in the petals have been extensively studied in many species, whereas the most important pigments in flowers are flavonoids, carotenoids and alkaloids. </p>

<p>In recent decades, many studies have focused on the formation of petal colour in plants. In particular, the synthesis and degradation of anthocyanins have been illustrated, yet the genetic mechanism of carotenoid metabolism remains unclear. One of the reasons for this ambiguity is that carotenoids are a subgroup of isoprenoid compounds that contain over 1158 isoforms. Moreover, the genetic regulatory and metabolic pathways of carotenoids are not unique to C40 and other carotenoid categories. Nevertheless, the precursor for the synthesis of almost all carotenoids is isopentenyl diphosphate, an organic substance containing five carbon atoms. Multistage precursors involve a set of catalytic enzymes (including geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate (GGPP) synthase, phytoene synthase, phytoene desaturase (PDS), zeta-carotene desaturase (ZDS) and carotenoid isomerase (CRTISO), among others; see <figure>Figure 1</figure>), that are ultimately converted to carotene. In addition, some co-factors such as phytochromes, electron mediators and transcription factors also participate in the synthesis of carotenoids. </p>

<p>Plastid terminal oxidase (PTOX) is a terminal oxidase involved in chlororespiration. The discovery of this gene took more than half a century. Diner and Mauzerall first revealed the positive feedback of oxygen in the photooxidation system almost fifty years ago. Interestingly, this discovery indicated that there is a novel oxygen-dependent electron transport chain (ETC) in chloroplasts. Subsequently, in the 1980s, Bennoun proved that a photorespiration chain, which was similar to the respiratory ETC in mitochondria, also existed in the chloroplasts in plants. In 1999, the <hi rend="italic">immutans</hi> mutant of <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</hi> brought attention to the PTOX gene. Green and white stripes on the leaves of <hi rend="italic">immutans</hi> confused researchers because they were not caused by the loss of enzymes in the chlorophyll synthesis pathway; the white sectors contained few carotenoids but accumulated phytoene. The same pattern was also observed in the <hi rend="italic">ghost</hi> mutant of tomato, with faded fruits, and further studies revealed that this abnormal phenotype was caused by the loss of PTOX gene function. In contrast to other enzymes in the carotenoid metabolic pathway, PTOX did not directly accelerate the conversion of intermediate products but accepted the electrons from PDS and ZDS and then delivered them as soon as possible (<figure>Figure 1</figure>). Importantly, the absence of PTOX combined with the <hi rend="italic">IMMUTANS</hi> and <hi rend="italic">GHOST</hi> mutations almost impeded carotenoid accumulation. Hence, PTOX is considered an indispensable cofactor in the synthesis of carotenoids. </p>

<p>As a cyanide-sensitive oxidase, PTOX was frequently used to compare with another ubiquinol oxidase AOX (alternative oxidase). PTOX and AOX sequences are fairly similar and also regarded as homologues in many other studies. One of the reasons is that they are both SHAM (Salicylhydroxamic acid) sensitive. Besides, the two subfamilies share the same domain of AOX (PF01786) in the C-terminus including two “ExxH” iron-binding motifs and a E(x)6Y motif as described by Carol and Kuntz. Although they are similar in sequence and domains, nevertheless, gene structure analysis would give us a viewpoint to distinguish these two proteins. Additionally, PTOXs mainly exist in plastids, especially in chloroplast, while AOXs are merely found in the inner membrane of mitochondria in accordance with current reports. </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">L. tulipifera</hi> is well known as an ornamental tree species due to its brightly colored flowers, odd leaf shape and graceful tree form. The tulip-like color and shape of the flowers give <hi rend="italic">L. tulipifera</hi> another name: “tulip tree”. As a result, <hi rend="italic">Liriodendron</hi> is often used for courtyard greening and street embellishment. In recent years, the disadvantages of other ornamental trees are increasingly exposed, i.e., clouds of poplar and planetree catkins; hence, the tulip tree has become incredibly popular in China. <hi rend="italic">L. tulipifera</hi> originated in North America and was introduced to China decades ago to improve the adaptability and wood yield of <hi rend="italic">Liriodendron chinense</hi>, a related species native to southern China. Studies of <hi rend="italic">L. tulipifera</hi> have focused on its origin and evolution, the development of its flowers and nectaries and its interspecific breeding, among other topics in the past years. Accordingly, attracted to the color and color patterns on the petals, specifically the orange band lying in the nectary area, Demuth also demonstrated that the main pigments of this area of <hi rend="italic">L. tulipifera</hi> were carotenoids. Even though the orange band is essential for aesthetic purposes and facilitating pollination, the genetic mechanism underlying the formation of this band remains unclear. </p>
</text>
