<text id="autogum_academic_doc679" title="The Flow Network of Chinese Scientists and Its Driving Mechanisms Based on the Spatial Development Path of CAS and CAE Academicians" shortTile="flow-network-chinese" author="Wentian Shi, Debin Du, Wenlong Yang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5938/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
A new round of technological and industrial revolution is reshaping the global innovation landscape, and the competition for the first-class scientific and technological talents to seize the advantage of scientific and technological innovation has already become a key support for increasing comprehensive national strength. In recent years, the flow of scientific and technological talents’ spatial migration has been scaling up. For example, talents have gravitated to developed regions with first-class research resources and good career prospects for study and employment. In addition, emerging areas, with rapid economic development, improvement of social conditions and a proactive talent strategy, have begun to attract talents back. Scientists’ clusters depend on the use of rich human resources to produce a scale effect that effectively promotes knowledge innovation, technological innovation, and scientific and technological progress in regions with talent agglomeration. For example, groups of multinational scientists have built important technological innovation networks in Silicon Valley, Hsinchu, and Shanghai, which has promoted the growth of technology centers in mainland China and Taiwan, China. In the 1980s and 1990s, Taiwan pioneered semiconductor and personal computer manufacturing centers worldwide. The key to that was the flow and spillover of knowledge produced by a batch of US scientists shuttling between Silicon Valley and Taiwan. </p>

<p>As outstanding representatives of China’s top innovative talents and scientists, academicians of the Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS) and Chinese Academy of Engineering (CAE) embody China’s highest level of science and technology, so agglomeration areas of CAS and CAE academicians are bound to be dominant in the competition for technological innovation. As one of the main carriers of knowledge flow and communication, the spatial migration of CAS and CAE academicians at different development stages accelerates the agglomeration and diffusion of knowledge, to some degree, and promotes the formation and development of knowledge and technology centers. Against the backdrop of the acceleration of globalization and the implementation of China’s innovation-driven development strategy, China has stepped up efforts to make itself an innovative country with strong innovative capacity and global competitiveness. The task of cultivating and introducing scientists, as well as allowing them to realize their full potential, is one of China’s priorities. Thus, it is of great practical significance to reveal the spatial distribution and the characteristics of Chinese scientists’ space migration, so as to better attract and agglomerate global high-end technological talents, and promote the regional agglomeration and flow. </p>

<p>The purpose of this paper is to reveal the flow network of Chinese scientists and to analyze the driving mechanisms behind their space migration. The following three questions will be studied: (1) What are the characteristics of the spatial distribution of Chinese scientists at different development stages? (2) What is the structure of their flow network? (3) What factors drive the flow of Chinese scientists? Based on data sourced from the academicians of the Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS) and the Chinese Academy of Engineering (CAE) at different development stages, this paper uses spatial statistics, social network approaches and visualization software to study the issues above. </p>

<p>The three main contributions of the study are as follows. First, the characteristics of the spatial distribution of Chinese scientists at different development stages at an urban scale are systematically revealed. Second, topological structures and core-periphery structures of the flow network of Chinese scientists are depicted and the role of cities as network nodes is identified by curriculum vitae analysis. Third, driving mechanisms behind Chinese scientists’ flow patterns are revealed through the application of relevant talent flow theories.  </p>

<p>The structure of this paper is as follows. Section 2 provides a literature review. Section 3 describes the data and methods. Section 4 and Section 5 present the results of analysis, and the final section contains the conclusions and discussion. </p>
</text>
