<text id="autogum_academic_doc426" title="Measuring Health Vulnerability: An Interdisciplinary Indicator Applied to Mainland Portugal" shortTile="measuring-health" author="Gisela  M. Oliveira, Diogo  Guedes Vidal, Maria  Pia Ferraz, José  Manuel Cabeda, Manuela Pontes, Rui  Leandro Maia, José  Manuel Calheiros, Esmeralda Barreira" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4121/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>Equity in health was defined by Margaret Whitehead in 1991, and is an utmost issue related to an unfair and uneven distribution of healthcare. In the scope of the United Nations 2030 Agenda for sustainable development goals (SDGs), health promotion—SDG 3—is a multidimensional target directly related to other goals, such as inequality reduction—SDG 10—which emphasizes its complexity. It is widely recognized that health outcomes have a strong association with socioeconomic position, becoming more evident in unequal societies and in dense urban areas. Individual health condition is no longer considered only as a consequence of biological causes as previous studies indicate that it is also influenced by social, environmental, cultural, political, and economic factors. These factors include housing quality, access to healthcare and education, work conditions, environmental quality, sanitation availability, and safety. </p>

<p>Welfare states, namely in Europe, play an important role in the development of policies and strategies aiming to reduce health vulnerabilities and inequalities through social transfers and provision of services. The biggest public health policy challenge is to promote universal health services, which results in healthier communities. This promotion should be supported through education and health literacy that ensure healthy lifestyles. European Health 2020 policy focuses on the reduction of health gaps that are directly associated with social determinants. The objective is to reduce health differences and disparities within and across groups. The worst and most visible outcome of health disparities is death by avoidable causes, resulting from absent, delayed, or inadequate healthcare services. </p>

<p>The concept of “fundamental causes” of death was developed stating that socioeconomic status is the main cause of inequality in mortality. Within this concept, socioeconomic status embodies an availability of resources, such as money, knowledge, prestige, power, and beneficial social connections that may provide relevant mechanisms, at any given time, that facilitate access to specialized medical services. The World Health Organization analyzed health determinants at a multiscale level, deriving the following key findings: </p>

<p>
<list>
<item>▪ Social factors determine populations health;</item>
<item>▪ Social determinants of health produce inequalities;</item>
<item>▪ Disadvantaged groups are more vulnerable to disease, die younger and experience worse health conditions;</item>
<item>▪ Plans and actions to fight against health inequalities imply a multidisciplinary approach due to its complexity;</item>
<item>▪ Development of instruments to measure social determinants in health are useful to provide knowledge to design tailored public health policies;</item>
<item>▪ Monitoring is very important; thus, health inequalities diagnosis should not be the goal but the starting point of health plans and policies;</item>
<item>▪ Health policies’ effects should be understood as a way to evaluate effectiveness in reducing inequalities.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>The Portuguese National Health Service (NHS) was founded with the purpose to assure universal access to healthcare, independently of one’s socio and economic condition, including foreigners, stateless, and political refugees. Despite the gains of the NHS public health policies intervention in Portugal, recent studies reveal a mismatch between services offered and populations needs. This gap is aggravated in rural and isolated areas where aged, poorly educated, and unemployed groups are predominant.  </p>

<p>This paper addresses the vulnerability in health aligned within the scope of the UN Sustainable Development Goals: “no one is left behind”. For decades, investments in healthcare infrastructures and professionals of NHS have been focused on densely populated urban centers to cover growing population needs, neglecting isolated and rural areas. However, the systematic phenomenon of depopulation, observed for decades, is worsening in rural areas. Response to acute medical emergencies is rather difficult in areas far from densely urban centers where specialized healthcare services are located, therefore specifically affecting the underprivileged communities of rural areas. Recent international studies have highlighted that the human right to health must consider, among other factors, that the universal health “coverage should be on the basis of need, with extra weight given to the needs of the underprivileged”. </p>

<p>Further research on national health vulnerabilities and recommendations for policies to cope with this issue remains a challenge due to the scarcity of data. Furthermore, the difficulty of accessing periodic data needed to design longitudinal studies is another limitation. Alongside these difficulties, Portugal health’s inequalities are dispersed across the country, justifying a local-scale approach to study this subject. </p>

<p>In this context, the present work proposes a composite index—socioeconomic health vulnerability index (<hi rend="italic">SEHVI</hi>)—built with several indicators related to health determinants and health outcomes. <hi rend="italic">SEHVI</hi> was applied on three different years over a nine-year period to assess the evolution of the Portuguese reality: 2009 is the onset of a financial and economic crisis; in 2015, the United Nations declared the 2030 Agenda of Sustainable Development; and 2017/2018 correspond to the last data available on the national databases. </p>
</text>
