<text id="autogum_academic_doc051" title="Efficacy of In Ovo Delivered Prebiotics on Growth Performance, Meat Quality and Gut Health of Kuroiler Chickens in the Face of a Natural Coccidiosis Challenge" shortTile="efficacy-ovo-delivered" author="Harriet Angwech, Siria Tavaniello, Acaye Ongwech, Archileo  N. Kaaya, Giuseppe Maiorano" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2615/9/11/876/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Poultry production forms an integral part of the economy with many socio-economic and cultural values attached to the birds in most developing countries including Uganda. However, one of the major challenges to improved poultry production is the prevalence of poultry diseases that threaten the intensification of production. Among these are gastrointestinal parasitic diseases notably, coccidiosis. Coccidiosis is a disease caused by parasites of the genus <hi rend="italic">Eimeria</hi> and phylum Apicomplexa with a complex life cycle, affecting mainly the intestinal tract of many species of birds. It is of great economic significance in farm animals, especially chickens. The economic significance of coccidiosis is attributed to decreased animal production in terms of poor feed conversion, growth depression and increased mortality; and the costs involved in treatment and prevention. Pathogenesis entails <hi rend="italic">Eimeria</hi> invading the intestinal cells as part of the life cycle. The resulting intestinal damage impairs nutrients digestion and absorption, gut barrier function, and ultimately leads to bacterial infections particularly necrotic enteritis. The global annual costs inflicted by coccidiosis to commercial poultry have been estimated at 2 billion €. </p>

<p>For the past 5 decades, the use of anti-coccidial feed additives has played a major role in the growth of the poultry industry facilitating increased availability of quality and affordable poultry products to the consumers. However, some degree of resistance to all anticoccidial drugs, including ionophores which are now the mainstay of coccidiosis control has been reported. Concerns over the development of resistant <hi rend="italic">Eimeria</hi> species to existing anticoccidial drugs and restrictive use of antibiotics to control secondary bacterial infections further stresses the urgent need to explore alternative strategies for maintaining intestinal functionality in chickens. In addition, serious public health and food safety concerns regarding drug residues in animal products highlight the need for researchers to develop alternative strategies for the control of parasitic problems. Vaccines for coccidiosis have been reported as an effective tool for disease control and to ameliorate anticoccidial drug resistance in poultry. However, their efficacy depends greatly on the management strategies in a farm. </p>

<p>The digestive tract of animals harbors a great number of living and metabolizing microorganisms (microbiota), that not only influence physiological functions of the host, but are also considered fundamental for a proper development of several vital traits, including immune system. Thus, the past decades, have seen much effort going into optimizing the gut microbiota of chickens using dietary interventions. Although use of antibiotics at subtherapeutic levels has been the most popular and perhaps the most effective strategy to enhance feed efficiency and to keep animals healthy, the approach is no longer a feasible tool for poultry production performance enhancement due to its ban by the EU in 2006. Incorporation of immunobiotics, particularly lactic acid bacteria is thought to be useful as immunomodulators to stimulate the gut-associated immune system in neonatal chicks, and thereby protect them from disease without decreasing growth performance as a possible substitution of antibiotics. Prebiotics, which are defined as non-digestible oligosaccharides, are also potent modulators of the intestinal microflora. For instance, addition of prebiotic mannanoligosaccharides (MOS) to the diet of broilers reduced the severity of the infection due to either <hi rend="italic">E. tenella</hi> alone or a mixture of <hi rend="italic">E. acervulina</hi>, <hi rend="italic">E. maxima</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">E. tenella</hi>. However, for the bioactives to be effective, these compounds have to be administered to the animals under fully controlled conditions and as early as possible. An innovative method for introducing bioactive substances into chickens is the in ovo injection into eggs intended for hatching. This is a technique that is based on the introduction on the appropriate day of embryonic development of bioactive substances into the air chamber of the egg or directly into the developing embryo. This method allows for a precise and uniform delivery of the bioactive substance to all embryos at an early stage of development, which unifies the effects of prebiotics across the flock and ensures proper development of gut microflora in all chicks. </p>

<p>Studies conducted in the temperate climatic condition have already revealed that in ovo injection of prebiotics and probiotics into the air cell during embryogenesis improves egg hatchability and modulate the optimal composition of the chicken’s microbiota, fully developed at hatching. These effects are reportedly stable throughout the chicken’s lifespan, influencing metabolic and immune responses of the host, resulting in improvement in performance and meat quality. </p>

<p>However, the efficacy of in ovo delivered prebiotics has been evaluated mainly under fully controlled disease-free experimental conditions in the temperate using meat type chickens. In this study, it was hypothesized that prebiotics perform differently under field conditions in the tropics where management and environmental factors predispose birds to enteric diseases. Thus, the efficacy of in ovo delivered prebiotics, antibiotic-chick formula, and a combination of the two on growth performance, carcass traits, meat quality, and gut health in the face of a natural coccidiosis infection was assessed in Kuroiler chickens reared under field conditions in Uganda. </p>
</text>
