<text id="autogum_academic_doc091" title="Nonmarketization Bargaining and Actual Compensation Level for Land Requisition: A Qualitative Comparative Analysis of China’s Land Requisition Conflict Events" shortTile="nonmarketization" author="Li Huang, Shougeng Hu, Shixiang Li, Zhenqi Fu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6084/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Conclusions and Avenues for Future Research</head>
<p>
This paper analyzes in detail 70 land requisition conflict events occurring from 2002–2017 by means of qualitative comparative analysis and thus discusses the causal relationship between land-losing farmers’ nonmarketization bargaining behavior and the actual compensation level for land requisition. The basic research conclusions prove that local governments’ unilateral pricing of the compensation level for land requisition is equivalent to depriving farmers of the opportunity to participate in the distribution of land increment revenue and induces a sizeable difference between the true market value of rural lands and the official compensation level for land requisition. Dissatisfied with the current distribution pattern of land increment revenue, land-losing farmers have successfully bargained with local governments through various behavioral methods of nonmarketization bargaining and loosened the rigidity of the official compensation level to a certain degree. If land-losing farmers have a relatively strong bargaining ability, forego radical bargaining strategies, and use relatively gentle bargaining strategies instead, they are able to effectively force local governments to make concessions and compromises in terms of the compensation level for land requisition. Accompanying nonmarketization bargaining behaviors are frequently occurring group incidents and relatively high operation costs, so an important direction for the reform of the land requisition system to take in future is to promote marketization negotiation and bargaining between local governments and land-losing farmers. </p>

<p>More concrete research conclusions include the following: (1) if bargaining ability is used to measure the ability of land-losing farmers to bargain with local governments, then broader mobilization networks, higher levels of organization, forming alliances with village cadres, and the intervention of grassroots leaders or clan power could all force local governments to make concessions and compromises in terms of the level of compensation granted for land requisition. </p>

<p>(2) If bargaining strategy is used to measure how land-losing farmers use their own bargaining ability, then if land-losing farmers adopt bargaining strategies that constitute serious opposition and conflict with local governments, it will be very difficult for them to succeed in bargaining. Instead, adopting relatively gentle resistance strategies within the scope allowed by law will increase their probability of successful resistance. (3) If land-losing farmers’ bargaining ability and bargaining strategy are reasonably combined, then the combination of a relatively strong bargaining ability with a relatively gentle bargaining strategy could effectively increase the probability of success in bargaining with local governments. (4) If external intervention (including media support and higher-level government intervention) could create appropriate combination conditions with bargaining ability and bargaining strategy, it would be possible to increase the possibility of successful bargaining to a certain degree. But if land-losing farmers only depend on external intervention, it will be very difficult for them to change the existing land increment revenue distribution pattern. </p>

<p>Although this paper has many limitations, they offer several possibilities for future research. First, this paper describes in-depth the nonmarketization bargaining behaviors of land-losing farmers, but due to a lack of research materials, it was unable to describe and analyze local governments. In order to analyze the land requisition benefit between land-losing farmers and local governments, the authors of this paper strive to take relevant explanatory conditions into the expanded analysis framework in the future like local government administrative officials, budgets, governance ability, etc. Second, when selecting the samples, this paper emphasizes the integrity of the sample materials and excludes numerous research samples on the basis of insufficient data, so this paper does not achieve a random sampling. This inevitably leads to errors of bias in the sample selection, so in future, the authors of this paper will further expand the source base from which this paper gather the research samples in order to strengthen the representativeness of the research conclusions. Another limitation of this study is the time span of the research. The samples cover 2002–2017 and during this period China’s land requisition system did not change much, but new trends did arise, like the official compensation level for land requisition consistently increasing; the scope of land requisition began to decrease; the procedures for negotiation on land requisition were fixed in the form of a formal system in some regions, etc. Restricted by the research methods employed, our research design does not contain the time dimension of each explanatory condition, so it is impossible to deeply excavate the dynamic mechanism between explanatory conditions and result variables. In future research, it will be feasible to use larger sample data to carry out time measurements and analysis and then execute mutual corroboration with the results obtained from the case comparison. Finally, the description of the external intervention dimension in this paper is relatively superficial. Distinguishing between the support of traditional state media and that of emerging Internet-based media and distinguishing between the methods and channels of the intervention behaviors adopted by all levels of government could help us to understand Chinese stories of conflict governance more profoundly.
 </p>
</text>
