<text id="autogum_academic_doc355" title="Comparison of Meteorological- and Agriculture-Related Drought Indicators across Ethiopia" shortTile="comparison-meteorological" author="Dawit Teweldebirhan Tsige, Venkatesh Uddameri, Farhang. Forghanparast, Elma  Annette. Hernandez, Stephen. Ekwaro-Osire" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4441/11/11/2218/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Methodology</head>
<p>
The proposed agricultural and meteorological drought comparison framework begins with the selection of appropriate indicators to quantify agricultural and meteorological droughts. Time series of these indicators over a common time period are then used to make comparisons. Drought indicators provide numerical values whose magnitude indicates the (moisture) state the system is in. This continuous drought indicator time series can be used directly to understand correlations between agricultural and meteorological droughts, as well as to perform confirmatory hypothesis tests to establish their relationships under various lags. For most indicators, negative values below a prespecified threshold indicate drought. Therefore, indicator time series can be transformed into a binary (drought/non-drought) time series using the appropriate thresholds. These binary time series have traditionally been used to calculate drought duration, severity, and intensity. Binary time series can also be compared to determine the level of agreement between various drought indices, and can be used to construct contingency tables and perform a wide array of statistical analyses to compare meteorological- and agriculture-related droughts. The proposed framework provides a suite of exploratory and confirmatory tests that can be used to evaluate continuous and discrete (binary) meteorological and agricultural drought time series, which are illustrated using Ethiopia as a case-study. </p>

<head> 2.1. Selection of Meteorological and Agricultural Drought Indicators</head>
<p>
As stated, the first step in the evaluation framework is to select appropriate meteorological and agricultural drought indicators. While there are many such indicators, the Lincoln declaration recommended the adoption of the Standardized Precipitation Index (SPI) as a universal indicator of meteorological droughts. Several studies have adopted this indicator to study meteorological droughts in Ethiopia, and as such, it has been adopted here. </p>

<p>While the quantification of meteorological droughts using SPI has become standard practice worldwide, no universally-accepted indicator for characterizing agricultural droughts exists today. It is widely recognized that agricultural droughts are best defined using soil moisture as the master variable. However, soil moisture has not been extensively monitored in most parts of the world (Ethiopia included), as doing so has proven to be challenging due to the high level of spatio-temporal variability of this parameter and lack of reliable methods for upscaling point level measurements to larger spatial scales. While agricultural drought indices based on model-derived soil moisture estimates have been proposed, calculating them is usually unfeasible for large-scale (regional and national) studies spanning multiple watersheds. Crop stress and vegetative health indices (e.g., the normalized difference vegetation index, or NDVI) have also been used to assess agricultural droughts. However, these methods do not yield standardized measures that can be consistently compared in space and time, and are also affected by the limited length of the records, as they rely on satellite-derived data, and as such, are not suitable for evaluating long-term droughts to capture natural climatic and hydrologic variability that manifest over multi-decadal scales due to limited data availability. Gridded soil moisture datasets have also been developed in recent times, either using simple water budgets or energy budgets from remotely-sensed data. These derived datasets can be directly used to study agricultural droughts, especially when their adequacy can be ascertained using ground-based soil moisture data. Efforts have also been made to archive in situ soil moisture measurements collected worldwide. </p>

<p>In areas where soil moisture data are unavailable to validate model- or remote-sensed-based soil moisture products, drought indices that utilize temperature-based potential evapotranspiration, in addition to rainfall, to indirectly capture the effects of soil moisture deficits have been proposed, and are often used to characterize agricultural droughts. The standardized precipitation evapotranspiration index (SPEI) uses the standardized measure of precipitation (P) minus evapotranspiration (PET) to characterize droughts. While SPEI is a meteorological drought indicator, and does not explicitly model soil moisture dynamics, it is known to correlate well with agricultural droughts, as the atmospheric water budget (P-PET) affects surface soil dryness. Therefore, SPEI computed over short accumulation periods (typically 1–6 months) has been widely used as an indicator of agricultural droughts. Therefore, SPEI can be viewed as an agriculture-related drought indicator. In this regard, Vicente-Serrano et al. indicated that the method used to estimate PET has little bearing on the computation of SPEI, and recommended using the Thornthwaite model which allows the use of the SPEI drought index with minimal data requirements. </p>
</text>
