<text id="autogum_academic_doc460" title="Food Safety through Natural Antimicrobials" shortTile="food-safety-through" author="Emiliano  J. Quinto, Irma Caro, Luz  H. Villalobos-Delgado, Javier Mateo, Beatriz De-Mateo-Silleras, María  P. Redondo-Del-Río" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-6382/8/4/208/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Natural Antimicrobials from Bacteria and Viruses: Biopreservation</head>
<p>
Biopreservation is defined as “the use of microorganisms (including bacteriophages), their metabolic products, or both to preserve foods that are not generally considered fermented”. </p>

<head> 4.1. Controlled Acidification</head>
<p>
The production of acid by lactic acid bacteria (LAB) under controlled acidification conditions is a preservation form very important in food production; the pH of the food, the characteristics of the targeted microorganism, the fermented carbohydrate that is going to be used by the biopreservatives, the LAB growth kinetics, the temperature (refrigeration or abuse), and the targeted pathogens are factors to be taken into account. The use of LAB for biopreservation comes back to the 1950s for preventing the production of botulinum toxin; <hi rend="italic">Clostridium botulinum</hi> is unable to grow at pH &lt; 4.6, so LAB is added to the food for acid production after the use of a fermentable carbohydrate also added to it and, consequently, the pH decreases. Hutton and Chehak described the “Wisconsin process” (lactic acid starter culture combined with sucrose) as a similar method to be applied in bacon with a reduced content of nitrite. These authors also found a similar effect with the combination of <hi rend="italic">Pediococcus acidilactici</hi> plus dextrose in chicken salad; it was interesting to report that conditions of abuse temperature were the most effective for the production of acid by <hi rend="italic">P. acidilactici</hi> after the use of dextrose. </p>

<head> 4.2. Bacteriocins</head>
<p>
Some lactic acid bacteria produce ribosomally synthesized peptides, called bacteriocins, with antimicrobial capacity that are not lethal to the host; these proteins inhibit both pathogenic and spoilage bacteria without changing the physicochemical characteristics of the food, that is, the inhibition is not exerted by acidification, protein denaturation, or other processes. The interest in LAB-produced bacteriocins has grown dramatically because of their antimicrobial capacities and the use of LAB as starter cultures. The use of bacteriocins or bacteriocinogenic LAB or both is important to the food industry because of the demand for natural products by consumers that are also increasing concern about foodborne pathogens. </p>

<p>Gram-positive bacteria are inhibited by most bacteriocins. Gram-negative bacteria can be increasingly sensitive to bacteriocins after the use of chelating agents or hydrostatic pressure; these techniques can also be synergic enhancing the action of bacteriocins against Gram-positive bacteria, or even with the use of nanoparticles or nanovesicles. </p>

<p>Bacteriocins can be used in different ways in foods: (i) They can be directly added to foods inhibiting the growth of both pathogenic and spoilage bacteria; nisin is the only bacteriocin commercially available. Nisin is added to milk, cheese, canned foods, mayonnaise, and other foods. It is considered as a Generally Recognized as Safe (GRAS) food preservative, and once it is absorbed onto surfaces it inhibits the growth of <hi rend="italic">Listeria</hi> spp. and prevents the formation of biofilms. Pediocins also inhibit the growth of <hi rend="italic">L. monocytogenes</hi> and they are used in salads and salad dressings, cream, cheese and meats. Reuterin is secreted by <hi rend="italic">Lactobacillus reuteri</hi> and possess activity against Gram-positive and -negative pathogenic bacteria. (ii) To add bacteriocin-producing bacteria to non-fermented foods or use them as starter cultures for the improvement of food safety. For a fine description see Montville and Chikindas. Natamycin is produced by fermentation using <hi rend="italic">Streptomyces</hi> spp. acting against foodborne moulds and yeasts; however, it is inactive against bacteria and viruses. (iii) A third way is to use bacteriocin-producing bacteria as starter cultures to direct the fermentation. The benefits of defined starter cultures depend on their capacity to predominate over the indigenous microbiota. </p>
</text>
