<text id="autogum_academic_doc011" title="The Roles of MicroRNAs (miRNAs) in Avian Response to Viral Infection and Pathogenesis of Avian Immunosuppressive Diseases" shortTile="roles-micrornas-mirnas" author="Linyi Zhou, Shijun  J. Zheng" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5454/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are a class of non-coding single-stranded RNA molecules encoded by endogenous genes of approximately 20 to 24 nucleotide (nt) in length. Since miRNAs were first discovered in <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi>, more and more miRNAs have been identified in humans, animals, plants and viruses. With the advance in miRNA research, the way miRNAs are produced and function is well clarified. The maturity of miRNA includes the following stages: First, the non-coding region of DNA is transcribed by RNA polymerase I to form a precursor transcript (primary miRNA, pri-miRNA) with a hat structure (7MGpppG) and a poly(A) tail. The pri-miRNA is then subjected to cleavage by RNase III nuclease Drosha and cofactor Pasha to generate a miRNA precursor (pre-miRNA) with a hairpin structure of approximately 70–90 nt. Pre-miRNA is exported to the cytoplasm by RanGTP-dependent exportin 5. Subsequently, the pre-miRNA is hydrolyzed and digested into a double-stranded miRNA of 20 to 24 nt in length, which consists of a guide strand miRNA and an incompletely complementary passenger strand miRNA*. The duplex is unwounded by helicase and miRNA guide strand then combined with the RNA-induced silencing complex (RISC) to recognize the target gene. The passenger strand miRNA* is usually rapidly degraded in the cytoplasm. The mature miRNA recognizes the target gene through the 3′UTR of the target gene mRNA. When the mature miRNA is fully complementary to the target mRNA, the target mRNA will be degraded. However, if their sequences are not fully paired, the translation of the target mRNA will be inhibited and the integrity of the mRNA will not be affected. miRNAs have the broadest range of gene regulation and regulate a variety of biological processes, including early embryo development, cell proliferation and differentiation, apoptosis and death, viral infection and tumorigenesis. </p>

<p>Avian immunosuppressive disease refers to a series of infectious diseases that result in damage or loss of function to the immune system of the poultry after infection. Viruses that cause immunosuppression in chickens include Marek’s disease virus (MDV), reticuloendotheliosis virus (REV), avian leukosis virus (ALV), infectious bursal disease virus (IBDV), chicken infectious anemia virus (CIAV) and avian reovirus (ARV). The infection of chickens with these viruses not only causes death, but also increases susceptibility to other microbial infections and the risk of failure in subsequent vaccination against other diseases, leading to serious economic losses. It has been reported that miRNAs are involved in a number of regulatory activities in the response of chickens with avian immunosuppressive diseases, including tumorigenesis, immunosuppression, cell proliferation and viral replication. In this review, the roles of miRNAs in the pathogenesis and control of different avian immunosuppressive diseases will be discussed, which may provide some clues to further understandings of pathogenesis of avian immunosuppressive diseases. </p>
</text>
