<text id="autogum_academic_doc643" title="Gut DNA Virome Diversity and Its Association with Host Bacteria Regulate Inflammatory Phenotype and Neuronal Immunotoxicity in Experimental Gulf War Illness" shortTile="gut-dna-virome-diversity" author="Ratanesh  K. Seth, Rabia Maqsood, Ayan Mondal, Dipro Bose, Diana Kimono, LaRinda  A. Holland, Patricia Janulewicz Lloyd, Nancy Klimas, Ronnie  D. Horner, Kimberly Sullivan, Efrem  S. Lim, Saurabh Chatterjee" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4915/11/10/968/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
The well-characterized GWI symptoms are GI inflammatory disease, chronic fatigue, neuroinflammation, and cognitive impairment. The current study investigates a mechanistic analysis of the gut virome-bacteriome mediated GI and neuroinflammation. To our knowledge, this is the first study that examined GW chemical-induced virome dysbiosis and bacteriome-virome interactions in GWI. In our previous study, we have shown that GW chemical exposure causes bacterial dysbiosis and that led to the loss of healthy gut bacteria such as Lactobacillus and Bifidobacterium. Gut dysbiosis induced leaky gut symptoms and systemic inflammation in GWI. In a recent review, it has been reported that gut virome is the missing link between bacterial dysbiosis and host immunity. The same study also described the role of virome in TLR signaling and GI diseases and hence concluding that virome analysis may lead to a novel therapeutic strategy for GI complications. The above study prompted us to explore the role of enteric viruses in GWI pathology and as a probable therapeutic target. In the present study, we found that the GW chemical exposure led to an increase in virome richness and relative abundance of dsDNA bacteriophages <hi rend="italic">Myoviridae</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Siphoviridae</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Caudovirales</hi> and decreased relative abundance of ssDNA bacteriophages <hi rend="italic">Microviridae</hi>. We used a broad-spectrum antiviral compound Ribavirin to test the hypothesis that (a) inhibition of gut viruses in the host may prove the role of gut virome in GWI and (b) antiviral treatment may help to reconstruct and restore the virome signature in GWI. Ribavirin has been extensively used as a therapeutic drug in several viral infections including Paramyxovirus, Adenovirus, and RSV infections. Our results showed that Ribavirin reverses GWI-induced alterations of the enteric viral community. The enteric bacteriophage-bacteria (parasite-host) interaction is an essential phenomenon to regulate both bacterial and viral community in the gut and play as a key role in gut health. Here, we found an independent or cumulative effect of both virome and bacteriome dysbiosis in weakening of GI tight junctions (increased Claudin-2 and decreased ZO1 and Occludin), GI inflammation (increased MCP1 and IL6), systemic inflammation (increased serum IFNγ and IL6) and neuroinflammation (increased microglia activation and brain IL6). The present study also showed that Ribavirin treatment improved GI tight junction assembly and subsequently decreasing GI and neuroinflammation. Interestingly, inducing gut sterility by using antibiotics also improves such GI and neurological complications. Results reported here are also strongly supported by previous such studies where Ribavirin or antibiotics were applied as therapeutics in other GI complications and neurological illnesses. However, nonavailability of germ-free and gnotobiotic mice or mice completely devoid of gut viruses prove to be a serious handicap in establishing the exact role of viruses in GWI or any other disease pathology though use of antiviral cocktails similar to our approach have been shown to serve the purpose.  </p>

<p>Gut microbiome is a collection of trillions of microorganisms that modulated host pathology and physiology through different mechanisms. Previous reports have suggested that the intestinal microbiota had a strong influence on the mucosal immune system and vice versa. A balanced pathogen and commensal microbiome composition maintain the microbiome-host immune homeostasis. However, any alteration in the microbiome may activate innate and adaptive immune responses and may progress to an inflammatory phenotype. In the present study we have shown that the GW chemical-induced virome richness and dysbiosis showed a strong association with activated Toll-like receptor-7 (TLR7) and TLR9 mediated proinflammatory pathways. We also found that the expression and activation of downstream signaling molecules including TLR7-MyD88 (binding of TLR7 with adaptor molecule myosin D88), TLR9-MyD88, or TLR4-Flottilin (localization of TLR4 in lipid raft) complex formation, TRAF6, IKK-α, and p65 (NFκB activation) have been increased upon gut virome and microbiome dysbiosis. The dysbiosis was also accompanied by increased inflammation while use of Ribavirin or antibiotics independently downregulated these pathways and subsequently inflammation. The above results prompted us to study whether virome diversity had a direct connection to a sustained systemic inflammatory response via increased serum IL6 or vice versa. We found that IL6 and virome diversity had a positive correlation in GWI. Studies have shown that the enteric viruses can activate TLR3 signaling pathway to induce anti-inflammatory response via IFNβ production. However, it has always been a conflict whether viral-induced TLR3 activation leads to pro- or anti-inflammatory response in viral pathogenesis. In our study, we observed that increased TLR3 might switch to pro-inflammatory response via IL6 or fail to produce significant IFNβ in order to support its anti-inflammatory role in GWI though such mechanisms in the host remain inconclusive at this time.  </p>
</text>
