<text id="autogum_academic_doc308" title="On the Use of MOFs and ALD Layers as Nanomembranes for the Enhancement of Gas Sensors Selectivity" shortTile="use-mofs-ald-layers" author="Matthieu Weber, Octavio Graniel, Sebastien Balme, Philippe Miele, Mikhael Bechelany" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-4991/9/11/1552/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Nanomembrane Layers Prepared by Atomic Layer Deposition (ALD)</head><head> 4.1. Introduction to ALD</head>
<p>
A key strategy for the direct growth of thin films with controllable dimensions at the nanometer scale is atomic layer deposition (ALD). ALD is based on sequential and self-limiting chemical reactions, allowing the preparation of inorganic nanomaterials such as oxides, nitrides and metals, with a (sub)nanometer thickness control. Typically, during an ALD cycle, alternate pulses of precursors and co-reactant gas molecules are injected in a vacuum reactor, separated by purge/pumping steps. The advantages of the ALD technique are thickness control at the atomic-level, the excellent uniformity and the conformality over the substrate surface. This route is therefore an excellent technique to coat complex 3D substrates such as nanowires and other nanostructures. These key benefits allowed this technology to become a key route for the deposition of thin films for a wide range of applications, especially microelectronics, but the technique is also used for catalysis, membranes, photovoltaics and sensing.  </p>

<head> 4.2. ALD Layers for the Enhancement of Gas Sensors</head>
<p>
Semiconductor metal oxide materials are used as gas sensors because of their chemoresistant behavior. The incorporation of the gas sensitive material in a sensor as a thin film is very advantageous, as it makes the sensor production compatible with semiconductor manufacturing processes, allows for miniaturization and relatively low costs. Furthermore, a thin sensing layer results typically in high sensitivity, fast response, and minimal power consumption. Therefore, ALD has been used for the fabrication of various gas sensing materials. For example, Du and George synthesized SnO2 films for CO sensing, and Aronniemi et al. applied ALD for the production of iron oxide films applied to CO and O2 sensing. Other gas sensing semiconductor compounds have been fabricated by ALD such as TiO2, ZnO, or In2O3 for examples. Recently, our group reported a novel route for the preparation of gas sensors with enhanced hydrogen selectivity, by using ultrathin BN layers prepared by ALD. The sensors presented in this study were based on ZnO nanowires coated with a 5 nm BN film prepared by ALD decorated with Pd NPs. <figure>Figure 12</figure> shows TEM images of these nanowires. </p>

<p>Due to the difference in work function between ZnO and the BN monolayer, electrons from Schottky barriers are formed on the interfaces which expand the electron depletion layer, when compared to pristine ZnO NWs. Upon exposure of the gas sensor to dihydrogen gas and release of electrons to ZnO NWs surface, the barrier height is decreased, leading to a higher modulation of the resistance and thus a higher sensor response. Furthermore, as Pd can efficiently adsorb and dissociate H2 molecules upon exposure to dihydrogen gas, the metallic Pd may be partially converted to PdHx. Due to the difference in the resistance of Pd and PdHx, this conversion is also expected to increase the gas sensor sensitivity. Finally, due to the BN structure which is somewhat similar to graphene, the ultrathin film can act as an efficient nanomembrane and let hydrogen atoms reach the surface of the ZnO NWs forming the transducer of the sensor. Due to their very small size, hydrogen atoms could pass the BN layer, whereas the other molecules tested such as C6H6, C7H8, C2H6O and C3H6O could not cross this layer. This phenomenon enabled to considerably improve the sensor selectivity towards hydrogen.  </p>

<p>Similarly, Mirzaei et al. prepared ZnO layers by ALD to cap Fe2O3 nanorods based gas sensors. The sensing characteristics of the core/shell nanorods for ethanol were studied. The increased response of the Fe2O3–ZnO nanorods sensor are linked to the modulation of the width of the conduction channel and the potential barrier height at the level of the interface, as well as to a nanomembrane effect of the ZnO coating. In fact, crystallographic defects are formed at the Fe2O3–ZnO interface resulting from the lattice mismatch between the two nanomaterials, providing preferential adsorption sites and paths for small molecules such as oxygen and ethanol, also contributing to the increased ethanol sensing properties of the core-shell structured nanorod sensor. </p>

<p>Although this is not typically desired and strongly depends on the process used, ALD films can present a residual porosity. Using ellipsometric porosimetry, Perrotta et al. extensively studied the residual nanoporosity (0.3–2 nm) in alumina and SiO2 layers fabricated by (plasma-assisted) ALD and its role in controlling the oxygen and moisture barrier performance. A correlation between the nanoporosity of the films and their intrinsic barrier properties has been observed, regardless of the film chemistry. In fact, pores presenting diameters higher than 1 nm with a relative content above 1% have been found responsible for the low barrier performances obtained. </p>

<p>When taking into account this residual nanoporosity, thin films prepared by ALD can advantageously be employed as selective nanomembranes to coat functional materials, for different purposes such as catalysis and gas sensing. Thus, ALD nanolayers can also be used to enhance the selectivity using the molecular sieving effect. </p>
</text>
