<text id="autogum_academic_doc200" title="Use of Superelastic Nitinol and Highly-Stretchable Latex to Develop a Tongue Prosthetic Assist Device and Facilitate Swallowing for Dysphagia Patients" shortTile="use-superelastic" author="Mahdis Shayan, Neil Gildener-Leapman, Moataz Elsisy, Jack  T. Hastings, Shinjae Kwon, Woon-Hong Yeo, Jee-Hong Kim, Puneeth Shridhar, Gabrielle Salazar, Youngjae Chun" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1944/12/21/3555/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
The tongue plays a significant role in swallowing, through preparing the bolus of food and pushing it posteriorly in order to transfer it from the oral to the pharyngeal phase of swallowing. Therefore, abnormal tongue performance can disturb swallowing whether at the oral preparatory or oral phase of swallowing. The aim of the development of the TPAD was to augment the function of the impaired tongue by additional force on the food bolus to elevate it towards the palate and direct it posteriorly from the mouth to the pharynx. Our prototype uniquely demonstrated the concept of a simplistic prosthetic tongue through in vitro laboratory and cadaver testing. While these qualitative movements and exerted pressures were encouraging, our data did not prove clinical utility. The movements of the native tongue and pharynx are complex and coordinated, so the simplistic elevation movement of our device was only a partial mimic. To develop a device with potential clinical utility, several criteria were used in the design process.  </p>

<p>First, the biting force of normal people was analyzed in order to design a “biting force” based mechanical prosthetic tongue device. People typically move their jaw in multiple directions while eating. Mastication is complicated and thus the exerted biting force is not constant; biting force is an indicator of the masticatory system and is dependent on the gender, age, craniofacial morphology, type of the food, and the measurement techniques. The human temporomandibular joint (TMJ) and muscles of mastication are capable of moving the mandible in anterior to posterior, lateral, and vertical displacement. The lateral and anterior–posterior chewing movements are more difficult to transfer into wire deformation. For this reason, only the vertical biting force was used to design TPAD. The exerted biting force in vertical direction must overcome the resistance force of the tongue prototypes. Gay et al. reported the maximum biting force in ten different subjects are between 25 to 400 N, which are significantly greater force values than the maximum resistance force (i.e., ~2 N) that was measured in our prosthetic tongue devices. Therefore, the force that is exerted through chewing process is sufficient to operate the TPAD by overcoming the resistance force of the tongue prototypes.  </p>

<p>Secondly, the pressure levels produced by TPAD were evaluated. IOPI medical device results show that the average strength of tongue (i.e., pushing force by tongue) for different ages is in the range between 50 and 75 kPa. The tongue strengths of our prototype shown in this study ranged from 6 to 12 kPa depending on the design of prototype, such as the angle and geometry of guiding tubes, as well as the type of measurement systems (i.e., IOPI and MOST). The use of thick nitinol strips in more locations increased the mechanical tongue strength showing the maximum mechanical tongue pressure exerted by the TPAD. While the pressure exerted by the prosthetic device is an important design factor to be considered, the device should have a low-profile design that has a sufficient spring-back force to recover the nitinol strips original geometry when the biting force is removed. In addition, the value of the exerted pressures was further reduced in the cadaver compared to the in vitro pressure measurement test of the same prototype (<figure>Figure 7</figure>). The first reason was that the cadaver model was not sufficiently soft and easy to manipulate to apply for the vertical direction biting force to the device mimicking human jaw motion. The second reason was that the central area of the prototype (i.e., bulging region) was difficult to align with the placed pressure sensors during the measurement. The cadaver model was especially useful to demonstrate device fit in the human mouth. We qualitatively assessed the proper fit using in vitro X-ray visualization technique with the cadaver model. The patient specific TPAD was placed on the bottom teeth and moved well with the biting motion of the cadaver. The device successfully transferred the vertical direction force to the central area that created an upward bulge mimicking typical tongue motion during swallowing. While the device worked properly with cadavers, additional ceramic materials were added to stabilize the device on the mandible in these specimens, since the teeth were irregular, and some were missing. The device could have equally been used as a type of dynamic palatal augmentation prosthesis, affixed to the maxillary dentition.  </p>
</text>
