<text id="autogum_academic_doc159" title="Functionalized Electrospun Nanofibers as Colorimetric Sensory Probe for Mercury Detection: A Review" shortTile="functionalized-electrospun" author="Brabu Balusamy, Anitha Senthamizhan, Tamer Uyar" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4763/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Functionalized, Electrospun Nanofibers for Colorimetric Mercury Ion Detection</head><head> 2.1. Direct Incorporation</head>
<p>
To date, there has been tremendous progress made in the design and fabrication of nanofibers through the blending of inorganic/organic functional materials with polymeric materials followed by electrospinning to enhance the functional properties for specific applications. The resultant nanofibers possess advantageous features, including being stable, flexible, lightweight, and mechanically strong from the organic polymers, while the incorporation of functional nanomaterials achieves the functionality. Such electrospun nanofibers have shown tremendous applicability in the energy, filter, sensor, and biomedicine sectors. Therefore, this approach can also be extended to fabricate the electrospun nanofibers through blending functional materials that are capable of detecting Hg2+ ions with a polymeric matrix, which is believed to preserve the functional characteristics. To date, several functional materials have been incorporated in electrospun nanofibers for the sake of detecting mercury ions. In this context, Kacmaz et al. have demonstrated the fabrication of ethyl cellulose (EC)-based electrospun nanofibers for the sub nanomolar optical detection of the ionic mercury by using azomethine ionophore. Briefly, the electrospinning precursor solution was optimized through varying concentrations of EC polymer, plasticizer (dioctyl phthalate), room temperature ionic liquid (RTIL, 1-ethyl-3-methylimidazolium tetrafluoroborate (EMIMBF4)), and (4-(dimethylamino) benzaldehyde2-[[4-cyanophenyl]methylene]hydrazine (DC-AZM) dye. Furthermore, the precursor solution mixture was electrospun to obtain the composite nanofibrous membrane and was applied for the detection of mercury ions. Owing to the high ionic conductivity, non-volatile nature, low toxicity, and chemical and thermal stability, the EMIMBF4 was selected as a polymer electrolyte. Additionally, a thin film with a similar composition to the electrospun nanofibrous membrane was fabricated for a comparison of detection performance. The DC-AZM dye turned the Hg(II) ions into selective probes after the doping of anionic additive potassium tetrakis-(4-chlorophenyl) borate in EC matrices. The anionic additive plays a critical role in the extraction of Hg(II) ions into the polymer phase; meanwhile, potassium ions diffuse into the aqueous phase from the nanofibrous membrane thanks to the ion-exchange phenomenon, owing to electroneutrality. The comparative response of the thin film and EC-based nanofibers to various concentrations of Hg (II) ions are illustrated in <figure>Figure 2</figure>. The Hg (II) ions are responsible for the DC-AZM dye fluorescence intensity changes noted at 572 nm due to the collision and complex formation. The nanofiber-based sensor has shown an enhanced response to Hg (II) ions compared to the thin film prepared using a similar composition, and the limit of detection was found to be 0.07 nM. The high sensitivity observed may be associated with the higher surface area and the diffusion of mercury ions to the ionophores. The response of nanofiber-based sensor has proven it an alternative technique to the cold-vapor atomic absorption spectrometry (CV-AAS), inductively coupled plasma-mass spectrometry (ICP-MS), and flame emission methods. </p>
</text>
