<text id="autogum_academic_doc403" title="Association of Typical Toxic Heavy Metals with Schizophrenia" shortTile="association-typical" author="Jiahui Ma, Lailai Yan, Tongjun Guo, Siyu Yang, Chen Guo, Yaqiong Liu, Qing Xie, Jingyu Wang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4200/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Schizophrenia is a severe mental illness that affects about one percent of the world’s population. The patients with schizophrenia are characterized with cognitive impairment, confusion, hallucinations and deterioration of social function. It is noted that schizophrenia leads to a heavy burden on the patients, their families and society. Substantial efforts have been devoted to elucidating the pathophysiology of schizophrenia development from genetic and environmental perspectives, as well as gene-environment interactions. Epidemiological studies have suggested that urban environments could increase the risk of schizophrenia, which may be due to the exposure to the toxic heavy metals (THMs) in the environment. </p>

<p>Chronic exposure to THMs impairs numerous biological functions and results in a series of health problems, such as aberrant immunological responses and neuropathological conditions. Moreover, it has been reported that THMs could cause oxidative stress and subsequently DNA damage, lipid peroxidation and protein modification, which play a role in the pathogenesis of numerous diseases, including cancer, diabetes, neurological disorders and chronic inflammation. THMs are suggested as an important risk factor for mental diseases since they cause neurobehavioral alterations and disrupt dopamine receptors. For example, arsenic (As) -induced neurotoxicity has been reported to cause compositional changes and hyperphosphorylation on the cytoskeletal protein, leading to the disintegration of the cytoskeletal framework and causing neurodegenerative diseases. An animal study showed lead (Pb) as an environmental toxin, which contributed to the pathogenesis of schizophrenia in Disrupted-in-Schizophrenia 1 (Disc1)-mutant mice. Therefore, investigating the association of environmental THM exposure with the risk of schizophrenia via a reliable epidemiological study is worthwhile.  </p>

<p>The serum concentration of THMs has been suggested to act as an internal indicator of their intake levels, reflecting exposure to environmental THMs. Changes in THM concentrations have been observed in peripheral tissues to be correlated with the risk of schizophrenia. Although multiple studies have investigated the association between THMs and schizophrenia, the results remain inconsistent. For example, despite supporting evidence both in vitro and in vivo for the association between Pb and schizophrenia, a cross-sectional study among a Chinese population showed no significant difference in the concentration of Pb between patients with schizophrenia and healthy controls. However, another study applying a very similar study design towards the same sampling region resulted in a significant association. The reason for the divergence may be related to the choice of the population, such as whether the schizophrenic patients have received antipsychotics drug during the time of study. A previous study has compared serum cadmium (Cd) concentration between healthy controls and schizophrenia patients with or without treatment. The serum concentration of Cd in patients after treatment was significantly higher than that of the healthy controls but no significant change was observed from the pre-treatment patients. The concentration of antimony and uranium were also found significantly different between pre-treatment patients and post-treatment patients of schizophrenia.  </p>

<p>Although several studies have investigated the association between THMs and schizophrenia, the potential mechanisms which could link THMs and schizophrenia have not been elucidated. Recent studies have suggested metabolic syndrome as a risk factor of schizophrenia, attributed to poor dietary habits, unhealthy lifestyle and physical inactivity of the patients and side-effects of the second generation-antipsychotics. On the other hand, THMs such as As and Pb were found to be associated with metabolic diseases, suggesting a role of abnormal metabolisms in linking THMs and schizophrenia. </p>

<p>Therefore, we performed a case-control study with first-episode and drug-naïve schizophrenia patients and healthy controls to identify the association between serum concentrations of the 4 THMs (i.e., Cr, Cd, Pb and As, selected as commonly surveyed heavy metals in schizophrenia studies) and the risk of schizophrenia. The correlations between the 4 THMs and multiple metabolic biomarkers were also tested to explore the potential metabolisms associated between these THMs and schizophrenia. Furthermore, meta-analysis was conducted to comprehensively summarize the association between the 4 individual THMs and the risk of schizophrenia.  </p>
</text>
