<text id="autogum_academic_doc508" title="Quercetin Synergistically Inhibit EBV-Associated Gastric Carcinoma with Ganoderma lucidum Extracts" shortTile="quercetin-synergistically" author="Sora Huh, Seulki Lee, Su  Jin Choi, Zhexue Wu, Jae-Han Cho, Lina Kim, Yu  Su Shin, Byung  Woog Kang, Jong  Gwang Kim, Kwanghyeon Liu, Hyosun Cho, Hyojeung Kang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1420-3049/24/21/3834/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Discussion</head>
<p>
This study showed that the cotreatment of <hi rend="italic">G. lucidum</hi> extracts (GLE) and quercetin (QCT) exerted synergistic antitumor and antiviral activities against SNU719 EBVaGC cells. Low concentrations of the cotreatment resulted in both the synergistic activation of cytotoxicity in SNU719 cells and the suppression of tumor development in MKN1-EBV xenograft mice. The addition of a low concentration GLE to QCT reinforced QCT-mediated cytotoxicity and QCT-mediated apoptosis in SNU719 cells. Furthermore, the addition also activated the EBV lytic gene promoter and upregulated EBV genes. Interestingly, ganoderic acid A (GAA), an effective molecule of GLE also showed similar bioactive features with QCT like GLE. The low concentrations of the GAA and QCT cotreatment reinforced QCT-mediated cytotoxicity and QCT-mediated apoptosis in SNU719 cells. Furthermore, the cotreatment activated the EBV lytic gene promoter and upregulated EBV genes, like GLE.  </p>

<p>QCT has been shown to exhibit potential anticancer properties owing to its antiproliferative, growth factor suppressive and antioxidant effects. In addition, QCT can induce apoptosis, where it has been shown to reduce the growth of tumors and inhibit the spread of malignant cells. Moreover, it inhibited chemical carcinogen-induced cell transformation, which was evident as cell viability decreased, ROS generation and microRNA-21 elevation occurred in cancer cells. Besides its antitumor effects, QCT has been shown to have antiviral activity through its anti-infective and anti-replicative abilities. The replication of herpes viruses, including EBV, was found to be affected by QCT. EBVaGC exhibits mixed characteristics of both gastric carcinoma and EBV. Apoptosis and EBV lytic reactivation can control the fate of EBVaGC cells, where antitumor agents can induce apoptosis and antiviral agents can stimulate EBV lytic reactivation to further aggravate cell lysis. QCT exhibits both antitumor and antiviral activities against EBVaGC. This dual function of QCT is likely to be synergistic. GLE, containing polysaccharides and triterpenes, is known to suppress the proliferation and metastatic potential of breast cancer cells by inhibiting Akt, AP-1 and NF-κB. Moreover, GLE modulated the estrogen receptor signaling and inhibited oxidative stress-induced invasiveness of breast cancer cells. Consistent with the results of previous studies on breast cancer, our study showed that GLE enhanced both QCT-mediated apoptosis and EBV-lytic reactivation. The effects of GLE were evident at low concentrations of QCT. Furthermore, QCT also enhanced the GLE-mediated upregulation of the EBV gene expression. Similarly, the effects of QCT were evident at low concentrations of GLE. Therefore, these results suggested that GLE enhanced QCT-mediated apoptosis, whereas QCT increased GLE-mediated EBV lytic reactivation.  </p>

<p>Mycotherapy has several benefits, where it improves the overall response rate during cancer treatment, enhances immunity owing to the stimulation of T cell proliferation and reduces some chemotherapy-associated adverse events, such as nausea and insomnia. Medicinal mushrooms have mainly been used in Asian countries for hundreds of years for the treatment of infectious diseases. More recently, they have been used for cancer treatment as adjuncts. Importantly, they have an extensive clinical history of safe use as single agents or in combination with chemotherapy. GLE has been intensively combined with mycotherapy for the treatment of broad-spectrum cancers. GLE has shown antitumor activities against breast cancer, bladder cancer, prostate cancer, colorectal cancer and others. These tumor inhibitory effects of GLE were attributed to the disruption of the proliferation and metastasis of cancer cells. However, the fact that EBV is the initiator of gastric carcinoma should be considered in the treatment of EBVaGC. EBV should be eliminated to reduce the risk of EBVaGC relapse. In this study, QCT strongly induced EBV lytic reactivation. The synergistic effects of the GLE and QCT cotreatment might enhance QCT-mediated apoptosis and GLE-mediated EBV lytic reactivation. Therefore, QCT-supplemented GLE might be used as a medicinal food with a dual function as an antitumor and antiviral agent for EBVaGC treatment.  </p>

<p>To the author’s knowledge, this is the first study to report that QCT-supplemented GLE might be effective in treating EBVaGC. The synergistic antitumor and antiviral effects were supported by both in vivo and in vitro studies. Hence, the combined use of GLE and QCT could be beneficial in cancer treatment by alleviating the toxicity of conventional chemotherapy and improving the immune function. However, more studies are still needed to further elucidate the molecular mechanisms of the direct antitumor and antiviral effects of QCT-supplemented GLE.  </p>
</text>
