<text id="autogum_academic_doc340" title="An Integrated Approach to 3D Web Visualization of Cultural Heritage Heterogeneous Datasets" shortTile="integrated-approach" author="Argyro-Maria Boutsi, Charalabos Ioannidis, Sofia Soile" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/21/2508/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Methodology</head>
<p>
A detailed overview of the methodology followed with the core underlying components of the implementation is described in this section. After clarifying the problem formulation and the difficulties to be resolved in the current work, insights into the technological means are provided, comprising the multiresolution schema of Nexus.js library, the programming tools and the 3D visualization pipeline. The case study is presented with emphasis to data acquisition and processing workflow and finally, the architecture of the platform and its data structure are defined and analyzed. </p>

<head> 3.1. Problem Definition</head>
<p>
The main problem in managing heterogeneous datasets of the Cultural Heritage lies in their size, especially when remote access and use over the Internet is entailed. Loading time, lossless transmission, network load and hardware limitations are consequent issues that dictate 3D visualization quality, website’s overall performance and eventually, user’s engagement and retention. The amount of 3D and 2D data largely determines their transmission speed to the client browser. This overall time is bound by the network bandwidth, namely, the maximum data rate which is specified by the Internet Service Provider (ISP). Exceeding the bandwidth limit creates congestion points and bottlenecks on the data transmission line. Congestion occurs once the router is running out of available buffer, an overflow which is likely to happen when large amounts of contents are transferred online. Therefore, the huge 3D models size leads to increased latency, packets loss and poor performance and the site ceases to be functional. In order to compensate for the transmission delay and network load, the total amount of the 3D models is often reduced. Depending on the editing software, the compression method and the development platform, the consequences may be loss of geo-referencing as most software impose their own coordinate systems and quality degradation related to geometry and texture. The perceived visual quality is inevitably equated with the visual fidelity of the original models. Its degradation does not justify their high-cost and time-consuming generation processes and is not consistent with their role as geospatial and geometrically accurate data. The end users take the visualized cultural assets at face value as the rendered appearance is not appealing and doesn’t correspond to a detailed and realistic representation. In addition, precise measurement tools cannot be implemented in the context of scientific and professional use. </p>

<p>At the same time, the platform’s development must conform to the practices and the thematic design of an online 3D Cultural Heritage repository in order to fulfill its purposes. Besides the aforementioned visualization efficiency, basic practices encompass interactivity, data interoperability and information systems. Their objectives are user’s familiarization with the cultural resources via easy-to-use interaction components and accessible archiving, multidisciplinary knowledge transfer and obviously digital preservation of its prominent content. Common services comprise manipulation of the 3D scene (move, rotate and zoom) using the trackball, highlighted and clickable points of interest with aside relative information and textual labeling. The freely navigation is appropriate for artifacts, small-scale assets and flat surfaces but rather inadequate for large-scale monuments and complex geometries. Polymorphic and heterogeneous data are usually displayed on independent webpages accordingly to their visualization format or the type of information they educe. In the case of image and text incorporation to the 3D visualization page, they undertake a static role with a specific position outside the border of the 3D viewer. Such platforms are insufficient to spatially relate 3D and 2D information, failing to generate a two-way access and provide an exploratory examination of the data. In terms of programming technique, user interaction requires the design of a coordinated events’ system to avoid glitches and delays in response. The hierarchical model of the interface and the WebGL 3D specifications restrict some content and structure adjustments. Exceeding the canvas element and executing queries asynchronously, imitating multi-threading process without runtime errors would attain high-performance and advanced interaction. </p>
</text>
