<text id="autogum_academic_doc066" title="Wnt Glycation Inhibits Canonical Signaling" shortTile="wnt-glycation-inhibits" author="Zhennan Ye, Sonnhild Mittag, Martin Schmidt, Andreas Simm, Rüdiger Horstkorte, Otmar Huber" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4409/8/11/1320/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Aging-associated disabilities are generated by an accumulation of randomly occurring molecular damages during life time, which affect the organism at multiple levels such as metabolism, immune response, repair, and regeneration as well as altered inter- and intracellular communication. Typical alterations detectable in aged tissues are increased concentrations of reactive oxygen species (ROS) and concomitant increased DNA-damage, lipid and protein oxidation. Often this is accompanied by accumulation of insoluble protein aggregates (lipofuscin) at least partially as a consequence of impaired proteasome function. In addition, glycation was reported to contribute to limited degradation and function of proteins. Glycation represents an important posttranslational modification that significantly increases during aging and results in the formation of advanced glycation end products (AGEs). </p>

<p>AGEs are generated by an initial non-enzymatic reaction of amino groups with reactive carbonyl groups of monosaccharides known as the Maillard reaction, thereby forming Schiff-base adducts. These adducts are subsequently rearranged to so-called Amadori products which undergo further oxidation and dehydration reactions leading to a large group of heterogeneous products. Up to the stage of the Amadori products, adducts are basically reversible. Preferentially lysine residues, but also other amino acids including arginine, histidine, tryptophan, or cysteine, are modified by glycation. The most prominent and well-known AGEs identified in cells and tissues are carboxymethyllysine (CML), carboxyethyllysine (CEL), pentosidine, and desoxyglucosone. Physiologically, these AGEs are formed in response to so-called “dicarbonyl stress” as given under conditions of hyperglycemia or in the presence of highly reactive α-dicarbonyls (α-DCs) such as glyoxal (GO), methylglyoxal (MGO) or 3-deoxyglucosone. These α-DCs are inevitable byproducts of anaerobic glycolysis and lipid peroxidation and in consequence, induce the formation of highly stable AGEs which crosslink proteins and lead to protease-resistant protein aggregates. In this context, glycation-induced modifications of extracellular matrix proteins resulting in intermolecular crosslinks lead to increased stiffness of tissues and vessels and affect cell migration. Furthermore, there is clear evidence that glycation and AGEs lead to mitochondrial dysfunction and impaired immune responses. Glycation of growth factors such as platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF) and insulin, as well as receptors such as nerve growth factor (NGF)-receptor, were reported to affect signaling functions.  </p>

<p>In addition, AGE modification itself can induce signaling mainly through the receptor for advanced glycation end products (RAGE), a multi-ligand transmembrane receptor containing immunoglobulin domains. RAGE-induced signaling contributes to aging-related inflammation and metabolic diseases by modulation of multiple pathways including phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K), Erk1/2 and Wnt signaling. However, the outcome of AGEs and RAGE signaling appears to be a double-edged sword with degenerative and protective effects. This also appears to be true in respect to the role of Wnt signaling in aging. </p>

<p>The canonical Wnt/β-catenin signaling cascade acts as a pivotal regulator of developmental and pathogenesis pathways including cell stemness maintenance/differentiation, carcinogenesis, and aging-related phenotypes. Moreover, there is clear evidence for a role of the Wnt pathway in mitochondrial respiratory capacity and metabolic homeostasis, especially of glucose metabolism. Within the canonical Wnt signaling pathway, β-catenin is the central player. Normally, excess β-catenin is rapidly degraded by the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway. Activation of the pathway leads to the stabilization of β-catenin and its accumulation within the cytosol and the nucleus, where it interacts with T-cell factor/lymphoid enhancer-binding factor (TCF/LEF) transcription factors and thereby regulates transcription of multiple target genes. During recent years, a multitude of other crosstalks and co-operations affecting the pathway have been identified. Interestingly, variants of the TCF-4 (TCF7L2) gene have been associated with increased risk of type 2 diabetes. </p>

<p>Based on that knowledge, we hypothesized that Wnt ligands as secreted, cysteine-rich proteins are susceptible to α-DC-mediated modifications and that glycation might modulate their signaling activities. For this study, we decided to use Wnt3a as a proof of principle to study effects of GO-treatment on Wnt3a conditioned medium (Wnt3a CM). We observed that the ratio of phospho-β-catenin to total β-catenin increased. As a further consequence, Wnt3a-induced activation of the β-catenin/TCF transcription complex was reduced as shown by reporter gene assays and by decreased expression of endogenous Wnt target genes. </p>
</text>
