<text id="autogum_academic_doc160" title="The Thermal Swelling Properties of Plant Chemical Alcohol Waste Liquid" shortTile="thermal-swelling" author="Dawei Wang, Chuanming Du, Dongdong Feng, Yuting Li, Yu Zhang, Yijun Zhao, Guangbo Zhao" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4184/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Results and Discussion</head>
<p>
During the reaction, the waste liquids were dropped on the metal spoon and placed in a vertical tube furnace. The effects of droplet quality, heating temperature, atmosphere, and other conditions on the expansion characteristics and expansion time were investigated. The volume expansion of the waste liquid droplets after heating in the vertical tube furnace is shown in <figure>Figure 5</figure>. As the droplet length increased with an increase in the heating time, the volume first increased and then became smaller, and the maximum volume appeared in the middle. </p>

<p><figure>Figure 6</figure> shows the expansion index under a nitrogen atmosphere. <figure>Figure 6</figure>a shows the effect of furnace temperature on the expansion index, and <figure>Figure 6</figure>b is the effect of droplet mass on the expansion index. Tests showed that the overall expansion index of the droplets increased with increasing temperature, while the index of droplet expansion varied little with mass. The expansion process of the droplets at high temperatures was accompanied by the evaporation of water, the precipitation of volatiles, and multiphase chemical reactions. The surface temperature of the droplet rose very quickly. The surface of the droplets was volatilized to analyze the volume expansion during this process to form hollow microspheres, which increased the heat and mass transfer efficiency of the surface. The residual carbon on the surface of the droplet reacted with the internal moisture by self-gasification (C + H2O → CO + H2). The higher the furnace temperature, the more obvious was the reaction. This significantly changed the pore structure of the droplets, which was beneficial to the volume expansion of the droplets. At 600 °C, the droplets were mainly precipitated by moisture and some volatiles. The reaction process was slow, and it remained difficult to form porous solid particles; the expansion index was also relatively small. </p>

<p><figure>Figure 7</figure> shows the distribution index of waste liquid expansion under an air atmosphere. The droplet expansion index decreased first and then increased with an increase in furnace temperature and decreased slightly with an increase in the droplet quality, but the amplitude was small. When the droplets were heated in an air atmosphere, the expansion characteristics of the waste liquid became complicated due to the participation of O2 in the air, especially at high temperatures. Chemical reactions, including C/CO2, C/O2, and C/Na, were also considered. During the test, no fire was observed when the furnace temperature was 600 °C. When the temperature was above 700 °C, an obvious flare was observed, indicating that the expansion process of the waste liquid at a high temperature was accompanied by a violent combustion reaction. When the furnace temperature was less than 600 °C, the expansion process of the droplets was mainly due to the evaporation of water and pyrolysis of the waste liquid, which caused the droplet volume to increase sharply. However, when the droplet size increased, the specific surface area decreased, the heat transfer and mass transfer became slower, and the oxidation of the air formed a dense shell on the surface of the droplet, which hindered the volume expansion of the droplet. When the furnace temperature was 700–1000 °C, the droplet evaporation and small molecule evaporation analysis time was very short—that is, by entering the macromolecular pyrolysis stage, a large amount of gas was released and accompanied by combustion, and the droplet expansion index reached the maximum value. When the mass of the droplet increased, the precipitation inside the droplet was weaker than the combustion reaction on the surface, and the droplet expansion index became smaller. However, as the sodium salt melt began to react with the char, the expansion index of the large mass droplets increased. </p>

<p>As shown in <figure>Figure 7</figure> and <figure>Figure 8</figure>, the variation index of the expansion index of the liquid droplets under an inert atmosphere and oxidizing atmosphere was completely different. The volume expansion of the droplets under an inert atmosphere was mainly the effect of moisture evaporation and volatilization analysis. The higher the temperature, the faster the volatile analysis and the larger the SVI index. Under an oxidizing atmosphere, the expansion of droplets was related to the analysis of moisture and volatilization as well as the participation of oxygen around the droplets. The influencing factors increased, and the regularity of SVI was not affected by temperature. </p>

<p><figure>Figure 8</figure> shows the maximum swelling volume index (SVImax) as a function of temperature and mass under nitrogen and air atmospheres. <figure>Figure 8</figure>a considers the effect of temperature on SVImax, while <figure>Figure 8</figure>b considers the effect of mass on SVImax. As can be seen from the figure, the maximum expansion index under a nitrogen atmosphere was substantially larger than that of the air atmosphere except at a lower temperature and a lower mass. This shows that, due to the presence of air, the surface of the droplet reacted with oxygen, destroying the porous structure of the droplet and reducing the maximum expansion index. </p>
</text>
