<text id="autogum_academic_doc053" title="Characterization of Endophytic Streptomyces griseorubens MPT42 and Assessment of Antimicrobial Synergistic Interactions of Its Extract and Essential Oil from Host Plant Litsea cubeba" shortTile="characterization" author="Quang  Huy Nguyen, Hai  Van Nguyen, Thi  Hanh-Nguyen Vu, Son Chu-Ky, Thu  Trang Vu, Ha Hoang, Ngoc  Tung Quach, Thi  Lien Bui, Hoang  Ha Chu, Thi  Nhan Khieu, Samira Sarter, Wen-Jun Li, Quyet-Tien Phi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-6382/8/4/197/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Discussion</head>
<p>
So far, <hi rend="italic">S. griseorubens</hi> species has mainly been found in soils and was previously demonstrated as a strong antagonistic species conveying broad antifungal activities. The present research revealed for the first time the activity of the endophytic actinomycete <hi rend="italic">S. griseorubens</hi> MPT42 isolated from the stem of <hi rend="italic">L. cubeba.</hi> Its CEAE extract exhibited a broad-spectrum antimicrobial activity toward various microbial types including drug-sensitive and multidrug-resistant pathogens. It showed moderate—strong inhibitory effects with MICs values between 80–600 µg/mL on 10 different microbes. Since many novel antibiotics exhibiting strong effects against multiple-drug resistant bacteria have been isolated from medicinal plant-associated endophytic <hi rend="italic">Streptomyces</hi> spp. in the last decades, endophytic <hi rend="italic">S. griseorubens</hi> MP42 could be a potential candidate for the production of valuable bioactive substances. </p>

<p>In agreement with previous reports, the present study demonstrated the potential growth inhibiting effect of <hi rend="italic">L. cubeba</hi> EO (MICs of 0.70–5.5 mg/mL) toward a broad array of microbial species, compared with EOs derived from other medicinal plants. For instance, <hi rend="italic">Ocimum gratissimum</hi> EO inhibited both Gram-positive bacteria (<hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Bacillus</hi> spp.) at the concentration of 93.7–150 mg/mL and Gram-negative bacteria (<hi rend="italic">E. coli, P. aeruginosa, S</hi>. Typhimurium, <hi rend="italic">Klebsiella pneumoniae, Proteus mirabilis</hi>) at the concentration of 107–750 mg/mL. Another study showed that <hi rend="italic">Cinnamomum</hi> EO (Lauraceae family) possessed low MIC values ranging from 1.2 to 12.5 mg/mL against <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi>, <hi rend="italic">C. jejuni</hi>, <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">S. enteritidis, S.</hi> Typhimurium, <hi rend="italic">L. innocua,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">L. monocytogenes</hi>. Thus, different chemical constituents in the EO of medicinal plant species affect their potential antimicrobial activity. Using <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> as a model for exploring the mechanism of action of <hi rend="italic">L. cubeba</hi> fruit EO, we demonstrated that EO-treated cells were rapidly killed after 2 h of treatment at the EO concentrations ≥ 2 MIC. It is worth noting that the cells showed extraordinary deformation and elongation. Our study found citral, carveol, and limonene as the main constituents, accounting together for 86.1% of total <hi rend="italic">L. cubeba</hi> fruit EO, concordant with previous studies. Since the effect of each substance on microbes was examined separately in these studies, therefore, the present study aimed at investigating the antimicrobial inhibitory effects possessed by the total EO. This combination showed broad-spectrum inhibitory effects against various microbial species tested. In fact, citral, carveol, and limonene are phenolic substances with polarity characteristics that might act on the bacterial cell membrane, inactivate cell adhesions, and/or interact with the outer and inner membrane proteins. Consequently, the EO treatment might result in the weakening of cell structure and inhibition of cell growth by creating holes on the cell wall and increasing the cell permeability.  </p>
</text>
