<text id="autogum_academic_doc096" title="Regioselective Acylation of Levoglucosan Catalyzed by Candida Antarctica (CaLB) Lipase Immobilized on Epoxy Resin" shortTile="regioselective-acylation" author="Marcelo Avelar do Nascimento, Larissa Ester Gotardo, Eduardo Miguez Bastos, Fabio C. L. Almeida, Raquel A. C. Leão, Rodrigo O. M. A. de Souza, Robert Wojcieszak, Ivaldo Itabaiana" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6044/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Biotechnology has focused its attention on the development of sustainable processes. The Twelve Principles of Green Chemistry reflect the need for actions in the development of bioprocesses both at universities and in industries. In this context, the availability of cheap raw materials and renewable energy is the basis for global sustainability, where strategies for the development of clean technologies for chemical processes has aimed to balance economic and environmental aspects. In this trend, the application of enzymes as biocatalysts and the reuse of agroindustry waste are key-procedures in the current initiatives that are aimed at the development of sustainable chemical synthesis. </p>

<p>Every year, a substantial amount of residual lignocellulosic biomass is generated and only 10% is in fact reused. Therefore, the development of new strategies is important to add value to these commodities. The sugarcane sector has high use of lignocellulosic biomass to obtain biofuels, such as first-generation ethanol, as well as small reuse of bagasse to obtain second- and third-generation ethanol. Its composition ranges from 40% to 50% cellulose, 20% to 30% hemicellulose, 20% to 25% lignin, and 1.5% to 3% ash. </p>

<p>Thus, new biomass valorization methods can be applied, such as pyrolysis—a process that can generate various organic compounds in short intervals of time. Among the products of rapid pyrolysis is bio-oil, a viscous mixture resulting from the oxidation of biomass polymers, of which their main component is levoglucosan (<figure>Figure 1</figure>), an anhydrous sugar that can be hydrolyzed to glucose, and is used in fermentative processes to obtain various products. However, this molecule offers other chemical possibilities as it has a hydrophobic moiety and free hydroxyls. Levoglucosan can be transformed into derived esters with a hydrophobic/hydrophilic balance that is of great value as surfactants, emulsifiers, or even lubricants, showing great potential of application in the most diverse industrial sectors, as our research group has observed with other esters that are produced by enzymatic routes. </p>

<p>Amphiphilic esters are currently produced from alkaline glycerolizes of natural oils and fats at elevated temperatures and pressure. In addition to high energy consumption, the conditions that are used result in low productivity and the formation of polymerization byproducts, resulting in dark staining and poor product quality, which requires expensive later purification steps. In this way, the use of enzymatic processes can overcome these issues and lead to a greener approach. Among the several enzymes that are currently applied in biocatalysis, lipases (triacylglycerol ester hydrolases E.C. 3.1.1.3) have been outstanding for their great industrial application in the production of high added value esters due to, among other advantages, their ability to show activity both of hydrolysis and esterification, the non-requirement of cofactors, and their ability to be able to perform reactions with high regio-, enantio-, and chemo-selectivity. Lipase-catalyzed transformations play an important role in organic synthesis to fulfill the rapidly growing demand for enantiomerically pure compounds such as pharmaceuticals, agrochemicals, and natural products, mainly due to no requirement for cofactors and also the capacity of catalyzing different reactions such as asymmetric esterification, asymmetric transesterification, and asymmetric hydrolysis. </p>

<p>Lipase immobilization is an effective method to improve the performance of free enzymes. Compared with free enzymes, the immobilized enzymes with long-term operational stability can be easily recovered and reutilized, thus reducing the costs of catalytic processes. The activity of the immobilized lipases depends on some parameters such as enzyme and support types and the protocols of immobilization. Immobilization of lipases on different supports or different protocols in the same support allows the development of systems with different stabilities and specificities, depending on the support used, the intensity of the enzyme–support interaction, and the orientation of the enzyme molecule on the support surface. The immobilization of an enzyme may produce different adverse effects on the enzyme activity because the enzyme molecule may become distorted, mainly when some multi-interactions between the enzyme and the support occur. Also, the active center may become blocked by the immobilization itself. Finally, immobilization may promote diffusion problems of the substrate. These problems may have a different impact on the activity of the enzyme depending on the different immobilization strategies. Many functional groups of carriers, such as epoxy, amide, and aldehyde, have been extensively used for covalent binding of lipases. Supports containing epoxy groups are characterized as having short spacer arms and being very stable at a neutral pH. They have been reported to immobilize enzymes through multipoint covalent attachment at their amino, phenolic, and thiol groups at an alkaline pH or at their carboxylic groups at a moderately acidic pH. </p>

<p>In this work, we performed both the esterification and transesterification of levoglucosan with different acyl donors catalyzed by the lipases Novozym 435®, PSIM®, and the home-made lipase CaLB_epoxy, aiming to evaluate conversion and selectivity for the obtained mono- and diesters in the batch processes. </p>
</text>
