<text id="autogum_academic_doc725" title="Parametric Modeling for Form-Based Planning in Dense Urban Environments" shortTile="parametric-modeling" author="Yingyi Zhang, Chang Liu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5678/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Parametric instruments have been applied in the architecture and construction industry for some decades. They enable architectural design cooperation, multi-scenario testing, and three-dimensional modeling. Some scholars argue that parametric architecture has come to its second phase of evolution, called “parametricism 2.0”, showing promise in solving intricate socio-environmental issues. A series of parametric urban-scale practices have been adopted by architectural institutes and studios such as Zaha Hadid Architects. Most of these projects focus on parametric representation or design simulation rather than on enhancing planning processes. This paper is not about the performance of a single building or a small group of buildings but large-scale urban planning. Parametric planning does not focus on surface patterns, dynamic facades, or flowing space. It focuses more on controlling parameters of land scale, density, floor area ratio, street width, building heights, etc. It may be appropriate to say that parametric planning and parametric architecture are two separate research fields. Parametric techniques have rarely been applied to urban-scale planning; especially the form-based planning projects. This paper thus assesses parametric techniques for facilitating form-based planning in an urban socio-environment. The research questions whether a parametric technique can improve the form-based planning processes and generate feasible layouts in a complex urban socio-environment.  </p>

<p>As its name implies, form-based planning shapes the urban form rather than zoning land uses. Existing form-based planning methods regard an urban environment as a collection of various transects. These transects are mainly described with hand-drawings and manual models. Mapping transect zones depends on existing urban development conditions and the planners’ experience. A transect matrix of form-based planning defines a hierarchical development scale from sparse suburban to dense urban cores. It includes forms from rural to city, including natural, rural, suburban, general urban, urban center, and urban core zones. These transects are aligned as an array from natural to artificial. The natural side of the transect matrix represents areas in which human intervention is comparatively weak and the natural preservation strong. The artificial side indicates where human intervention is relatively strong and natural retention weaker. Duany describes the transect matrix as an approach whereby:</p>
<blockquote>
<hi rend="italic">“… it arranges in useful order the elements of urbanism by classifying them from rural to urban. Every urban element finds a place within its continuum. For example, a street is more urban than a road, a curb more urban than a swale, a brick wall more urban than a wooden one, and an alley of trees more urban than a cluster. Even the character of streetlights can be assigned in the transect according to the fabrication from cast iron (most urban), extruded pipe, or wood post (most rural)”</hi>.[9]</blockquote>

<p>The theoretical foundation of form-based planning can be traced back to the 19th century when contemporaneous understandings of the natural environment influenced perceptions of the urban environment. Accordingly, researchers applied ecological methods to elaborate on the typology of urban sites. In 1826, Von Thunen created the concentric development ring (CDR) model to describe how natural lands and agricultural costs affected urban-periphery environment development. The CDR model described city area as located at the center of a series of circles. Between city and grazing were horticulture and dairying, forestry, crop rotation, enclosed fields, and three-field land areas from inside to edge. According to the sectional system of CDR, scholars argued that inhabitants’ activities, living density, even social development were also sections following natural resource distribution. Patrick Geddes’ Valley Section (1909) concluded that natural conditions guided human activities from mining to fishing and this concept shaped the subsequent analysis of both eco- and urban systems. Some naturalists use sections to describe land composition: Land within a specific range is expressed in sectional transformations, including ocean, beach, primary dune, trough, secondary dune, and base dune. This method of dividing the land using section transformations appears in urban environmental analysis. Duany adopted the concept for human settlements and, from about 2000, this idea has permeated the thinking of New Urbanists and form-based planning. Like the sectional transformations of an ecological environment, transects in an urban environment describe the characteristics of the physical surroundings with related human behaviors. Social activities depend on the division of transects and so will correspond to a specific zone. For example, in an urban core zone, people tend to shop, gather, or engage in other public activities. In a suburban zone, people lean toward more private or casual activities, such as home or community life. When people move from a community living area to a public activity area, their routes cross different transect zones. Overlapping moving routes helps to describe the range and activity trends of multiple transect zones. </p>
</text>
