<text id="autogum_academic_doc659" title="Adherence to the Mediterranean Diet and Bone Fracture Risk in Middle-Aged Women: A Case Control Study" shortTile="adherence-mediterranean" author="Anna Palomeras-Vilches, Eva Viñals-Mayolas, Concepció Bou-Mias, MªÀngels Jordà-Castro, MªÀngels Agüero-Martínez, Montserrat Busquets-Barceló, Georgina Pujol-Busquets, Carme Carrion, Marina Bosque-Prous, Lluís Serra-Majem, Anna Bach-Faig" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/10/2508/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The Mediterranean diet (MD) has been recognized as a model of healthy eating because of its contribution to a healthy lifestyle and a better quality of life. The MD is much more than a dietary pattern. The word diet comes from the Greek <hi rend="italic">diaita</hi> and means ‘way of life’ and the MD holds true to this meaning as MD covers not only what to eat but how to eat and live (active lifestyle, prioritizing culinary activities, etc.). And it should be preserved in the Mediterranean basin where, in the past decades, dietary trends are departing from traditional dietary patterns. The principles underlying the MD—widely documented elsewhere—can be summarized as follows: high consumption of fruits, vegetables, cereals (especially whole seeds), legumes, and nuts; relatively high fat consumption (up to 40% of total energy intake), mainly monounsaturated fatty acids (MUFAs) from extra-virgin olive oil, the main fat used for seasoning and cooking; moderate to high consumption of fish; moderate dairy product consumption, usually in the form of yogurt and cheese; low red meat and meat product consumption; moderate alcohol consumption, mainly in the form of red wine during meals; low consumption of simple sugars (pastries, soft drinks, etc.); and high consumption of herbs and spices—an important source of micronutrients, including calcium (Ca)—used to flavor dishes. This traditional diet, however, has been affected by the onslaught of dietary trends of recent decades. </p>

<p>Osteoporosis (OP) is among the diseases with the highest incidence in advanced age, i.e., coronary heart diseases, cancer, respiratory system diseases, depression, and neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer’s disease. Associated with OP, especially prevalent among older women, is bone fracture risk. This growing global health problem suggests that the prevention of OP and its complications and the maintenance of bone mass are public health concerns. </p>

<p>OP is a systemic disease characterized by a low bone mass index and destruction of the microarchitecture of bone mass—i.e., bone mineral density (BMD)—posing a major risk of fractures. There are no symptoms indicating a reduction in bone mass, and fractures are the only clinical consequences of OP; therefore, despite being the most common bone disease, the incidence is difficult to establish, and the prevalence is often based on estimates using indirect indicators such as fractures. In Spain, prevalence, as determined by densitometry, is about 30% in women aged 50 years old, increasing to 50% in women older than 70 years old. About 40% of Caucasian women will suffer at least one bone fracture after their 50s. </p>

<p>Strategies to minimize the prevalence of the disease and its complications would be to enhance bone mass and reduce loss at advanced ages. There is convincing scientific evidence supporting the MD’s role in the reduction of overall risk for diabetes, cardiovascular, and neurodegenerative diseases. Regarding site-specific cancers and inflammatory and metabolic conditions, the evidence is suggestive or weak and is unconvincing regarding low-density lipid reduction. The MD has been shown to modestly reduce the risk of fracture and is associated with higher BMD. Thus, the overall evidence points toward the role of the MD in maintaining bone health, especially in postmenopausal women. </p>

<p>Residual confounding factors in observational studies has become a major concern, with many international studies analyzing the relationship between diet and fracture risk. For instance, bias should be taken into account when considering meta-analysis results on prospective cohort studies beyond the Mediterranean region. This is due to the paucity of data and the lack of consensus on the definition of the MD. Furthermore, physical activity has been demonstrated to be a robust indicator of a lower risk of bone fractures. Since a healthier diet is related to higher physical activity levels, the latter needs also to be taken into account. </p>

<p>The observed inverse association between dietary quality and bone fracture risk should be interpreted with caution because the case-control design of most studies’ findings cannot indicate causality. There is a lack of research into the relationship between the MD and bone fracture risk that clarifies causation or confounding factors. </p>
</text>
