<text id="autogum_academic_doc172" title="Two-Dimensional Carbon: A Review of Synthesis Methods, and Electronic, Optical, and Vibrational Properties of Single-Layer Graphene" shortTile="twodimensional-carbon" author="Angelo Armano, Simonpietro Agnello" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2311-5629/5/4/67/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 7. Synthesis Methods</head>
<p>Since the first isolation carried out by Novoselov and Geim in 2004, a plethora of methods have been developed to produce graphene, by exploiting a wide variety of physical or chemical phenomena. Currently, the various methods show different and complementary characteristics, but none of them can comply all the possible requirements, for example large extension, large production, defect-free structure, functionalization, cleanliness from impurities, low costs. Therefore, case by case the choice between them is driven by the evaluation of which method is better suitable for the specific application in which graphene must be implemented. In general, the methods developed until now can be grouped in two categories depending on the direction of the manufacturing process: <hi rend="italic">bottom up</hi> methods, which start from molecular precursor in that assembled together to build up objects of higher hierarchical level, and <hi rend="italic">top down</hi> methods, in which macroscopic materials are reduced to the nano-size element of which are constituted or used as raw material, as in the case of graphite and waste plastic for graphene, respectively. Some of the most common synthesis methods of graphene are described in the following. </p>

<head> 7.1. Top Down</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Mechanical Exfoliation</hi></p>

<p>based on the separation of the single graphene sheets which constitute graphite (<figure>Figure 28</figure>a), and thanks to its simplicity this method was used for the first isolation of graphene. On its favor, it produces the highest quality of graphene because of the high purity of graphite, and moreover it is a relatively easy procedure since the vertical stacking of graphene sheets is assured only by weak van der Waals interactions. For this reason this technique can be extended to other van der Waals heterostructures, such as transition metal dichalcogenide (, , , ). However, this method is limited by two main factors: the small amount of product and in the exiguous extension of graphene flakes, the latter factor bypassable by using of HOPG as raw material. In detail, the direct manipulation of top graphene sheet on graphite can be performed both by scotch tape and by tips originally produced for scanning probe microscopy.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Liquid-phase Exfoliation</hi></p>

<p>in this case the exfoliation procedure is performed in liquid-phase, and the separation of graphene sheets is obtained by sonication (<figure>Figure 28</figure>b). This procedure is preferable to the mechanical exfoliation since in comparison it produces a large quantity of graphene flakes with larger lateral size. By contrast, the most critical issue consists of the damaging of the internal structure of graphene flakes in which some defects can be induced. However, some investigations have shown that this undesired effect can be avoided by putting in solution some specific chemicals, such as surfactants or intercalating molecules, which facilitate the exfoliation, thus requiring weaker sonication.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Electrochemical exfoliation</hi></p>

<p>performed in liquid-phase as the previous method, but based on the use of a graphite source (usually HOPG) as electrodes in an electrolyte solution (<figure>Figure 28</figure>c). In this case </p>
</text>
