<text id="autogum_academic_doc133" title="Sustainability and Resource Equilibrium Evaluation of a Tourism Traffic Network Based on a Tourism Traffic Matching Curve" shortTile="sustainability-resource" author="Huiying Wen, Yuchen Zeng, Zuogan Tang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5769/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Conclusions</head>
<p>The accompanying increased traffic due to the rapid development of tourism at present calls for the better sustainability and equilibrium of tourism and traffic resources in the future. This paper proposed a double-layered coupling system focusing on tourism traffic, which combined optimization of the network structure and adjustment of future resource levels in a systematic way. </p>

<p>In the upper layer of the system, we examined three main tourism traffic factors, i.e., socioeconomic benefits, levelling benefits of tourism and traffic resources, and green benefits, which have been identified as important aspects of the multi-objective model. The socioeconomic benefits mainly consist of the optimization cost of the tourism traffic network and the time cost saved for road users. The levelling benefits of tourism and traffic resources comprise both the investment and income of tourism projects. Last but not least, emission of carbon dioxide is set as a fundamental index of green benefits. This comprehensive benefit-oriented model not only paves the way to utilize the importance degree of nodes to quantify the long-neglected radiation effect of the tourism economy, but also has a more concise format, and the involved factors are more relevant compared with other models. In addition, a genetic algorithm approach with adapted parameters has been developed to solve the established model. Through the adjustment of relevant parameters, Pareto solutions were obtained at a high-iteration speed. </p>

<p>In the lower layer, we introduced the idea of the tourism traffic matching curve, which provided a direct and efficient evaluation method for the equilibrium of the tourism traffic network. On the curve, the abscissa and the vertical axis stand for the importance degree of the tourism node and the cumulative percentage of the network scale respectively. It is notable that the slope change of the curve could evaluate the equilibrium of allocations of the network, and that the boundaries of two indicators, i.e.,  and , are calculated in terms of the results of the upper layer and are used as evaluation criteria. Thus, the corresponding indicators of the current network could be determined and compared with standards, which results in an effective evaluation of the tourism traffic network. </p>

<p>The practical case study in this paper provided proof of the feasibility and effectiveness of the proposed system, based on graphs and concise results. Genetic algorithm parameters are adjusted to make the iteration process more efficient, including a population of 100, a crossover probability of 0.80 and a deviation value of the fitness function of 1e-100. In addition, the upper and lower boundaries of  are 7.34 and 4.13, respectively, in this case, while those of  are calculated as 3.40 and 2.61, respectively. Relative to the current indicators, a certain range was successfully identified wherein jump phenomena could possibly occur. More importantly, the calculation results agreed with the tourism matching curve. Certain nodes with imbalanced resources of tourism and traffic are identified, and detailed suggestions on sustainability and resource equilibrium are provided for these nodes. </p>

<p>Compared to traditional network optimization, the proposed method has the following advantages:
<list>
<item>Result visualization via the tourism matching curve makes it possible to identify nodes that have imbalanced tourism and traffic resources, and provides direct information about the node importance and corresponding scale, which can help decision makers determine whether adjustment of the node is urgently required and how large the project can be. The traditional model is very likely to lack any comparison with the current network, and can hardly generate a timetable for the necessity and sequence of network reconstruction measures.</item>
<item>The method tends to be very flexible because the parameters in the proposed model can be modified and adapted to different regions on the basis of specific definitions. Through exact classification of the different benefits, decision makers could supplement or eliminate factors and allow these factors to be adapted to different regions. In contrast, the traditional approach lacks adjustment considerations due to a combination of different factors, so that the range of application is limited.</item>
<item>The tourism traffic factors that were analyzed in this paper have been systematically determined. Guidance for decision makers to evaluate the network was given in a general way. Traditional equilibrium evaluations tend to not focus on tourism traffic, and neglect certain important aspects, such as radiation effects and green benefits.</item>
<item>The proposed optimization and evaluation system can help to guarantee a high efficiency, safety, and availability of tourism road networks, with which policy makers can evaluate the sustainability of their policies in planning from different aspects, i.e. socioeconomic benefits, levelling benefits of tourism and traffic resources, and green benefits.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>In summary, the proposed system opens the door to sustainability and evaluation research on tourism and traffic resource levelling. Future research will focus on modification of the proposed  and  in this paper. The main extensions could be adapted to regional limitations and road type influences under multimodal transport and mixed-traffic conditions. </p>
</text>
