<text id="autogum_academic_doc175" title="Medically Useful Plant Terpenoids: Biosynthesis, Occurrence, and Mechanism of Action" shortTile="medically-useful" author="Matthew  E. Bergman, Benjamin Davis, Michael  A. Phillips" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1420-3049/24/21/3961/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Medicinal Sesquiterpenes</head>
<p>
Sesquiterpene biosynthesis normally begins in the cytosol via the C15 prenyl diphosphate FDP, which itself is derived from mevalonic acid and the MVA pathway. Sesquiterpene synthases act on FDP to yield hundreds of sesquiterpene hydrocarbons and alcohols based on dozens of carbon skeletons. They are frequently responsible for familiar scents and flavors, for instance ginger (gingerol), clove, cannabis, rosemary (β-caryophyllene), patchouli (patchoulol), sandalwood (α-santalene), and rain (geosmin, a bacterial sesquiterpene). They are the heaviest of the volatile terpenes under standard conditions (diterpene hydrocarbons ordinarily require heating to form gases). Plant families known to be principal producers of sesquiterpene volatiles include the Lamiaceae, Geraniaceae, Rutaceae, Myrtaceae, Cannabaceae, and Gingeraceae. The use of these essential oils in traditional herbal medicine such as aromatherapy and Ayurvedic medicine is well documented. There is currently little evidence their use confers actual medical benefits, yet their use remains widespread due to their aesthetic, historical, and cultural significance. On the other hand, a number of highly functionalized, non-volatile sesquiterpenes of plant origin have demonstrated highly specific biological activity and have therefore been investigated for their clinical potential. A selection of these medically useful plant sesquiterpenoids follows. </p>

<head> 4.1. Artemisinin</head>
<p>
Wormwood (<hi rend="italic">Artemisia annua</hi> L., or qinghaosu, Asteraceae) is native to China and is the source of the sesquiterpene endoperoxide artemisinin, shown to be highly effective at treating malaria. In the early 1970s, phytochemists such as Youyou Tu investigated plants used in traditional Chinese herbal medicine and identified the usefulness of the traditional remedy qinghaosu in eradicating <hi rend="italic">Plasmodium spp</hi>. infections, the causative agent of malaria, for which she received a Nobel Prize in Medicine in 2015. It is more effective against a broader range of life cycle stages of the apicomplexan parasite than traditional anti-malarials such as quinine. </p>

<p>Artemisinin is a sesquiterpene lactone with an unusual endoperoxide ring which imparts its anti-malarial properties (<figure>Figure 6</figure>). The mechanism of action is still unclear, and several possibilities have been proposed. Most involve the degradation of the endoperoxide bridge in a heme-dependent process to form carbon centered radicals which then alkylate multiple targets including heme and proteins. The involvement of heme is consistent with the specificity of artemisinin towards <hi rend="italic">Plasmodium spp</hi>.. The direct cause of toxicity to the parasite is unclear but may involve interference with the conversion of heme to hemozoin, although this hypothesis has been disputed (and reviewed in reference). </p>

<p>The early stages of artemisinin biosynthesis in glandular trichomes of <hi rend="italic">A. annua</hi> are now understood at the biochemical and molecular levels, although the exact mechanism of the later stages remains unclear. Current efforts now focus on the regulation of this pathway in an effort to improve artemisinin production directly in plants. The pathway begins with the conversion of FDP to amorpha-4,11-diene by amorpha-4,11-diene synthase (<figure>Figure 6</figure>). Biochemical characterization and metabolite profiling of plant tissue indicated the presence of this olefin as well as its oxygenated derivatives artemisinic alcohol and aldehyde, dihydroartemisinic alcohol and aldehyde, and dihydroartemisinic acid. Following the cloning and expression of CYP71AV1, which converts amorpha-4,11-diene to artemisinic alcohol and aldehyde, Zhang et al. characterized the artemisinic aldehyde Δ11(13) reductase (Double bond reductase 2, Dbr2), which preferentially reduces artemisinic aldehyde to dihydroartemisinic aldehyde. This substrate is then converted to dihydroartemisinic acid by aldehyde dehydrogenase 1 (Aldh1). From dihydroartemisinic acid, the remaining steps involve the photooxidative formation of the endoperoxide ring. However, the details of this process, such as the potential involvement of additional enzyme activities, are currently unclear. </p>
</text>
