<text id="autogum_academic_doc063" title="Chemical Patterns of Proteasome Inhibitors: Lessons Learned from Two Decades of Drug Design" shortTile="chemical-patterns" author="Romina  A. Guedes, Natália Aniceto, Marina  A. P. Andrade, Jorge  A. R. Salvador, Rita  C. Guedes" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5326/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Results and Discussion</head>
<p>
During the drug design process, to assess the potential druggability of a compound as a new starting point, some initial rules like drug-likeness (as defined by Lipinski and colleagues in 1997), lead-likeness (as defined by Oprea) and known drug space, are usually applied. In general, the rules to characterise/filter compound collections are based upon physicochemical parameters, e.g., logP, logS, MW, TPSA, MR, RotN, HBA and HBD, among others. As a result, it would be interesting to assess how proteasome inhibitors are positioned with respect to the typically expected “drug-like” chemical space. </p>

<p>To do so, we performed a comprehensive analysis of the 680 small-molecules proteasome inhibitors dataset spanning a large range of activity (0.08 nM &lt; IC50 ≤ 150,000 nM). This entailed looking at chemical space distribution, scaffold similarity and the extraction of chemical rules with machine learning, using either direct structural information (scaffolds and Morgan fingerprints) or being based on 21 general molecular (QuaSAR) descriptors. This set of analyses was ultimately employed to produce meaningful chemical patterns that are correlated with proteasome inhibitory activity. The dataset comprises only human proteasome activity data for the CT-L catalytic site, as this is the only site with the largest number of compounds, and is divided into four classes. Full data are available in Table S1. </p>

<p>Analysis of chemical space distribution and the scaffold similarity of proteasome inhibitors. First, we analyzed human proteasome inhibitors’ chemical space distribution. To address this analysis, chemical space was defined by the t-SNE calculation applied to the 21 calculated molecular descriptors listed in the Supplementary Information (Table S1). The proximity in a t-SNE plot is relative in nature, and the distance between points simply represents relative proximity (i.e., it is not a direct scaling from real distances in the 21 dimensional space). </p>

<p>In <figure>Figure 4</figure> (left) the difference of distribution of the four activity classes is easily perceptible, with the most active compounds (class A, purple) having close to half of its compounds (~47%) in the top-right quadrant of the plot, while the least active compounds (class D, orange) are mainly concentrated in the bottom-left quadrant (~58% of class D compounds), as quantified in <figure>Figure 4</figure> (right). Classes B (blue) and C (green) have a more disperse distribution, but show some higher density areas close to the bottom-left corner. This indicates that class D, for example, is fundamentally different to the remaining classes from a structural and physicochemical level, and therefore supports the existence of a SAR in the proteasome inhibitors developed in the last 20 years. Additionally, no particular cluster was formed with a single class, which means there is no particular location in chemical space (at least one that is defined by the descriptors that we considered) which is reserved to one single class. This observation indicates that carrying out compound selection biased for physicochemical similarity to known inhibitors might be a good initial filter to enrich the set of compound candidates with active hits. </p>

<p>Next, we wanted to investigate what characteristics are responsible for the differences between classes in the chemical space distribution. Upon applying the Tc to characterize the similarity between Murcko scaffolds within each class, we observed a high diversity in the dataset, not just within each class, but also between the different classes, with most pairs of compounds showing a Tc below 0.5 that represents a considerable dissimilarity (<figure>Figure 5</figure>). Nonetheless a clear trend of correlation between activity and similarity is observed. </p>

<p>The scaffolds of class B differ negligibly from class A, however, class C shows a two-peak distribution which suggests it contains scaffolds similar to both classes A/B, as well as with lower activity compounds (class D). This is probably a result of the practical strategies applied in medicinal chemistry where inactive structures are modified/derivatized to meet or better resemble substructures seen among actives, thus creating this transition from A to D. As concluded from the chemical space observation, this also shows that functionalizing scaffolds from more potent compounds (class A/B) might be a feasible initial strategy to find new actives. However, selected scaffolds should also be sufficiently dissimilar to the lower activity scaffolds, effectively avoiding the right-end tail of the class D (i.e., the most similar scaffolds to A, which are still largely inactive). </p>
</text>
