<text id="autogum_academic_doc477" title="Extracellular Vesicles as Natural, Safe and Efficient Drug Delivery Systems" shortTile="extracellular-vesicles" author="Federico Villa, Rodolfo Quarto, Roberta Tasso" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4923/11/11/557/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Extracellular vesicles (EVs) are cell-derived membrane vesicles that represent an endogenous mechanism for intercellular communication. EVs can be classified in exosomes, nano-sized vesicles (with a diameter in the range of 30 to 120 nm), that originate from the cell endocytic compartment through the formation of multivesicular bodies (MVB), microvesicles, with a diameter up to 1 μm released by cell membrane budding, and apoptotic bodies, with a dimension similar to platelets, derived from blebbing of dying cells. Despite the distinct sizes and biogenesis, the absence of standardized isolation methods and the numerous similarities existing between these two subclasses make it particularly challenging to distinguish among them. In this review, we will use the generic term EVs to indicate both exosomes and microvesicles. </p>

<p>EVs have been shown to carry functionally active biological materials including proteins, mRNAs and miRNAs, which makes them capable of transmitting signals to target cells in the surrounding environment as well as to distant organs, via blood and lymphatic vessels. </p>

<p>The scientific community has recently turned its interest toward the evaluation of EVs as drug delivery vehicles. In this context, EVs offer significant advantages over current drug delivery systems, such as liposomes and polymeric nanoparticles. Since EVs can be obtained with an autologous procedure from the patient’s cells or blood, they do not solicit the immune system as usual synthetic formulations do. In addition, given their phospholipid bilayer, EVs can directly fuse with the targeted plasma membrane, thus allowing a more efficient internalization of the encapsulated drug. Their hydrophilic shell, together with the presence of anti-phagocytosis surface markers (i.e., CD47), enables them to evade phagocytosis by monocytes and macrophages of the reticulo-endothelial system, hence weakening their clearance. Moreover, the limited size allows them to efficiently extravasate through the inter-endothelial junctions and fenestrations of both existing and neo-synthesized vessels. Thanks to these peculiar characteristics, they can spread and accumulate in the parenchyma of solid tumors. EV biological properties derive from their sophisticated membrane structure, characterized by the presence of several proteins for active targeting, adhesion, cell fusion, and intracellular release of their content; this functional complexity is not easily reproduced by de novo synthesized nanoparticles. Among the several types of nano-based drug delivery systems, liposomes are probably the most used, due to their non-toxicity and capacity to accommodate high amounts of compounds. However, a still inadequate in vivo targeting efficiency together with a potential immunogenicity associated to liposomal formulations has limited their broad applicability in therapeutics. </p>

<p>Therefore, the greater specificity combined with the consequent limited induction of systemic side effects make EVs ideal vehicles for drug delivery. Although this research field is in its infancy, in the last decade, the use of bio-engineered EVs for the delivery of cytotoxic molecules in preclinical models has produced encouraging results. These experimental evidences, in addition to preliminary clinical data, indicate that EV formulations may not only enhance the safety and biodistribution of commonly used drugs, but also increase their efficacy. For example, it has been demonstrated that the administration of EV-encapsulating chemotherapy drugs leads to a significant reduction of drug accumulation in off-target organs, thus preventing important side effects during standard clinical protocols. An astonishing number of newly published papers perfectly depict the scientific community’s authentic interest in this flourishing research field. </p>

<p>Nevertheless, the first aim of this review is to disclose an overview of the latest applications of EVs as drug delivery vehicles, focusing on the sources employed, the molecules selected, and the final intended targets. In the second part of the review, we will take a step back and bring attention to the basics of one of the main pitfalls concerning EVs: the urgent need for highly pure vesicle preparation. </p>
</text>
