<text id="autogum_academic_doc613" title="Deciphering the Structural Basis of High Thermostability of Dehalogenase from Psychrophilic Bacterium Marinobacter sp. ELB17" shortTile="deciphering-structural" author="Lukas Chrast, Katsiaryna Tratsiak, Joan Planas-Iglesias, Lukas Daniel, Tatyana Prudnikova, Jan Brezovsky, David Bednar, Ivana Kuta Smatanova, Radka Chaloupkova, Jiri Damborsky" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2607/7/11/498/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
The biochemical and structural analyses of a new haloalkane dehalogenase DmxA from Antarctic bacterium <hi rend="italic">Marinobacter</hi> sp. ELB17 revealed the paradoxical stability of the enzyme. Despite its psychrophilic origin, DmxA wt exhibited the highest apparent melting temperature (<hi rend="italic">T</hi>m,app = 65.9 ± 0.1 °C) of all biochemically characterized HLD-II members, and the second highest of all thus far characterized wild-type HLDs. The only HLD exhibiting higher apparent melting temperature than DmxA was DhmeA from halophilic archaea <hi rend="italic">Haloferax mediterranei</hi> ATCC 33500, which belongs to the subfamily HLD-III. The enzyme DhmeA from subfamily HLD-III is a multimeric protein with <hi rend="italic">T</hi>m,app = 70.6 °C. The tertiary structure of DhmeA is not available at this moment, preventing its direct comparison with DmxA. Several thermostable enzymes from psychrophiles and mesophiles have been reported in the literature; however, their unexpected thermostability remains poorly understood. Only two studies focused on such paradoxically thermostable enzymes from psychrophilic and mesophilic origin have attempted so far to explain the structural basis of their stability, suggesting that either the flexibility of a global structure or the presence of extra disulfide and salt bridges are responsible for the unusual thermal stability of these enzymes. </p>

<p>In this study, several structural features of DmxA wt were analyzed in detail to explain its extraordinary stability. DmxA wt was found to form a dimer via a cysteine bridge, which may be formed only after heterologous expression in <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> and purification, while is less likely to occur in the cytoplasm of the original host organism. This is the first observation ever of HLD oligomerization mediated by the covalent bond. Thus far, the reported dimers of DbjA and DbeA were formed through the hydrophobic interactions of C-terminal α-helices. Although cysteines in protein structures often serve as stabilizing elements, the S-S bridge between DmxA wt units in its dimeric form did not have any effect on the stability or the activity of the enzyme. Furthermore, our experiments revealed that the presence or absence of such cysteine bridge neither influenced any of the catalytic properties nor the storage stability of the enzyme. It is also worth mentioning that the DmxA wt oligomer equilibrium varies in solution, and only a small part of the enzyme (up to 30%) is present as a dimer. Therefore, the disulfide bridge does not contribute to the overall stability of the enzyme. </p>

<p>A unique composition of the catalytic pentad was observed both in DmxA wt sequence and crystal structure, containing a glutamine instead of the typical asparagine present in other members of the subfamily HLD-II. Another HLD with an unusual halide-stabilizing residue (DatA containing tyrosine instead of tryptophan) was described earlier. In this case, the unique halide stabilizing residue decreased enzyme stability (by 3.5 °C) and only moderately affected enzyme specificity. The position of the Q40 side chain in DmxA wt structure disables its functioning as a halide-stabilizing residue. When replacing the glutamine with asparagine, the melting temperature of the enzyme decreased by 2 °C (<hi rend="italic">T</hi>m,app = 63.9 ± 0.2 °C) confirming a small stabilizing effect of glutamine interactions in the protein core. Moreover, an interesting shift in substrate specificity from SSG-I to SSG-IV was observed on the variant DmxA Q/N. Such changes in the substrate specificity in HLDs are normally only be achieved after a sophisticated protein engineering. In our case, a single mutation was sufficient to shift the enzyme substrate specificity group. </p>

<p>A deeper analysis of DmxA wt structure revealed an unusually small hydrophobic pocket containing the enzyme active site connected with the surrounding solvent by very narrow and closed tunnels. The presence of phenylalanine and methionine as bottleneck residues was not overly surprising since they often provide stabilization of protein structures via hydrophobic interactions. Replacement of bulky residues with alanines in the main tunnel opened the tunnel and suppressed stabilization of the tunnel structure via interactions provided by the bottleneck residues. This led to the destabilization of the protein core represented by 9 °C decrease of the enzyme apparent melting temperature. Engineering of the tunnels connecting buried enzyme active site with the surrounding solvent has previously been described as a powerful strategy for enzyme stabilization. In this study, we proved that narrow tunnels play a crucial role in the paradoxical stability of DmxA due to multiple van der Waals and hydrophobic interactions, although they are not the only factor responsible for the unique properties of the enzyme. </p>

<p>To decipher the high stability of the new haloalkane dehalogenase DmxA wt, we investigated three unique features of the enzyme, corresponding to three possible sources of its stabilization. Both replacements of glutamine with asparagine and opening of the main tunnel brought desired outcomes in terms of decreased stability and improved activity. More importantly, introducing only two mutations, we managed to turn the thermostable enzyme into a mesophilic-like counterpart, with a melting temperature comparable to that of other related HLDs and a significantly improved catalytic performance. If we combined the effects of mutations in DmxA Q/N and DmxA MF/AA variants, the consequent enzyme would result in a highly active catalyst.
 </p>
</text>
