<text id="autogum_academic_doc645" title="Low Temperature (15 °C) Reduces Bacterial Diversity and Prolongs the Preservation Time of Volvariella volvacea" shortTile="low-temperature-" author="Xiuling Wang, Shunjie Liu, Mingjie Chen, Changxia Yu, Yan Zhao, Huanling Yang, Lei Zha, Zhengpeng Li" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2607/7/10/475/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Straw mushroom (<hi rend="italic">Volvariella volvacea</hi>), also known as Guangdong mushroom and Chinese mushroom, is one of the largest cultivated edible fungi in the world and one of the main exported mushrooms in China. China began cultivating straw mushroom 300 years ago and was the first country to do so. </p>

<p>Straw mushroom is a kind of high-temperature mushroom that is not only delicious but also has a high nutritional value. Its antioxidant, low-fat and high-protein properties make straw mushroom a typically healthy food in the public mind. <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi> grows in hot and rainy environments in tropical and subtropical areas, and the optimum growth temperature of this mushroom is 30–32 °C, which is similar to the average summer temperature of its main production area. However, the high temperature is not conducive to the storage of the fruit body of <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi>. During transport, straw mushroom is placed in paper boxes at 5 kg per box. Due to the respiration of the picked <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi>, the temperature at the center of each package can be as high as 50 °C, which is extremely unfavorable for the preservation of <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi>. To date, there has been much advancement in <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi> cultivation, resulting in the ready availability of this mushroom, while the preservation of <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi> remains a serious problem. <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi> is unable to withstand low temperatures: when it is stored at 4 °C, the mycelium disintegrates and dies, and the fruit body softens and undergoes autolysis, which complicates the preservation of <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi>. At the same time, researchers found that the storage time of <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi> was significantly extended when the temperature was approximately 15 °C. While it is expensive to maintain <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi> at the ideal storage temperature (15 °C), it is also difficult to control the temperature at the center of the box at 15 °C. </p>

<p>Numerous studies have shown that bacteria are an important reason for food spoilage and degradation. To prolong the shelf life of the <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi> fruit bodies, this study focused on the bacterial community succession process on the surfaces of postharvest fruit bodies of <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi> and aimed to find a solution for <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi> fruit body preservation. </p>

<p>The bacterial community structures differ greatly among different stages of food spoilage, so investigation of the succession of the bacterial communities could help the identification of decay-causing bacteria. To explore the succession of bacteria on the surfaces of <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi> fruit bodies during the process of spoilage, a high-throughput sequencing of the V4 16S rRNA gene was performed to identify bacterial species. The purpose of this research was to identify the bacterial community that played a key role in the process of <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi> fruit body decay, thus providing a reference for the preservation of <hi rend="italic">V. volvacea</hi> fruit bodies. </p>
</text>
