<text id="autogum_academic_doc015" title="Artificial Grass as an Alternative Laneway Surface for Dairy Cows Walking to Pasture" shortTile="artificial-grass" author="Stephanie Buijs, Gillian Scoley, Deborah McConnell" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2615/9/11/891/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Dairy cows’ gait characteristics are affected by their claw health as well as the surface on which they are walking. Claw problems cause lameness, which is one of the most important dairy cow welfare issues and is associated with a decrease in walking speed and stride length. For instance, mildly and moderately lame cows have been shown to walk slower than sound ones (5% and 11% slower, respectively), and moderately lame cows use shorter strides than sound and mildly lame ones (10% and 8% shorter, respectively). Lameness is commonly associated with painful claws (in 67% of the cases). Specific painful claw conditions have also been shown to decrease walking speed and stride length (e.g., cows with sole ulcers walked 19% slower using 7% shorter strides). Painful claws can also occur on sound limbs, although this is less common (23% of the cases) and the pain is less severe. Floor type also affects walking speed and stride length, which is at least partially due to alleviation of discomfort by softer (i.e., more compressible), less abrasive floor types. Cows have been estimated to walk 4–6% faster on rubber than on concrete (although in one study, a higher walking speed was only noted when both floor types were slatted). Stride length has been estimated to be 3–5% longer on rubber than on concrete. In line with the suggestion that softer floor types alleviate some of the pain associated with lameness, cows with more severe signs of lameness showed the greatest increase in stride length when walking on rubber instead of concrete, and cows’ mobility score is improved when walking on rubber. It has been suggested that cows reduce their speed when walking on concrete floors to reduce the impact on the hooves when these hit the floor.  </p>

<p>Although increased walking speed and stride length often coincide, this is not necessarily the case. For instance, studies comparing solid rubber to solid concrete reported that stride length was greater on rubber, but speed was higher on concrete, or that stride length increased significantly, whereas only a numerical increase occurred for walking speed. In some cases, discrepancies between walking speed and stride length may occur because the tested floor types differ not only in softness and abrasiveness, but also in other characteristics. Slipperiness also affects gait characteristics, which is likely because cows adjust their gait to reduce the chance of slipping and falling. Slipperiness is itself affected by the softness and abrasiveness of the floor. Softer floors that claws can sink into have been suggested to be the most effective in reducing slipperiness, and also reduce discomfort due to pressure on the claws. Thus, both characteristics would be expected to influence walking speed and stride length in the same direction. However, slipperiness can also be reduced by making a floor more abrasive, which may make claw–surface contact more aversive. When bauxite aggregates were added to an epoxy resin floor, making it both less slippery and more abrasive, stride length was 5% greater, but walking speed was 5% lower. The increased stride length was interpreted as an attempt to minimise contact with the floor. The friction and abrasiveness of a floor is reported to be more strongly correlated to stride length than to walking speed. </p>

<p>As the relationship between gait characteristics and how a cow experiences a walking surface is complex, assessing cows’ preferences for different floor types can provide important additional information, allowing a more correct interpretation of changes in gait. Dairy cows are likely to avoid less comfortable surfaces, and are known to prefer rubber over concrete flooring, both when standing and walking. Although this preference would be expected to be stronger in cows with painful claws, the opposite was found when cows’ preferences were evaluated in a group setting. This may have been due to competition between sound cows and lame ones, during which the sound cows would be more successful in claiming a space on the preferred floor type, as lameness reduces dominance rank. Cows showed no significant preference for epoxy resin floors with and without added aggregates (which decreased slipperiness but increased abrasiveness). This may indicate that although cows will adapt their walking pattern to such floors, they can do so in a satisfactory way and therefore feel no need to avoid these. </p>
</text>
