<text id="autogum_academic_doc531" title="Special Issue “Advanced Signal Processing in Intelligent Systems for Health Monitoring”" shortTile="special-issue-advanced" author="Maysam Abbod, Jiann-Shing Shieh" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4727/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Health monitoring is a diverse subject since it covers biological systems as well as physical systems. Biological systems are usually associated with the monitoring of human health, whether it is related to diagnosis of diseases, monitoring of daily activities, or vital signs. On the other hand, physical systems health monitoring is associated with checking physical systems, such as structures and rotary or linear displacement machines. Structural health is related to checking vibration, cracks, or fatigues of materials in buildings, aircrafts, or pipes. </p>

<p>Due to the development of handheld-device technologies, processing power, and sensory accuracy, the penetration into the biomedical field has received intense interest, which has led to the development of new sensors and signal processing algorithms in the field. However, there is still a need to integrate different systems and technologies such that real-time detection and diagnosis can be made available to all people to meet the demand and requisites of the world health monitoring systems. </p>

<p>On the other hand, advances in technology, such as high-resolution cameras, optical sensors, drones, and robotics, have evolved the generation of intelligent monitoring systems for physical system health monitoring. Infrastructure health monitoring systems can monitor vibration in buildings, displacement, rotation, stress/strain, cracks/spalling, and defects either directly or remotely. Structural health traditionally is monitored using conventional sensors with data acquisition, transmission, and information processing to assess the structure’s health check. Recently, smart sensors with embedded microprocessors and wireless communication are being used, in addition to fibre optic sensor technology and automated low-cost photogrammetry for flexible structure monitoring. Furthermore, non-destructive testing equipment, such as eddy current equipment in pipes and aircraft bodies, have also evolved to become more accurate and reliable due to the developments of intelligent signal processing systems. </p>

<p>On-line monitoring systems have also been used to monitor rotary and displacement machines. The utilisation of vibration-based sensors in addition to image and wireless communication of smart devices, and the use of programmable and web connected applications are the base for the next-generation measurement technology of structural health monitoring. The abundance of handheld smartphones with an easily programmable framework has helped in modifying the relevant software to acquire data using embedded sensors. And in addition, noncontact sensors, such as unmanned aerial vehicles (drones) and mobile sensors, to acquire structural data. The state-of-the-art methods have been presented in a detailed literature review of the recent applications of smartphones, unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs), cameras, and robotic sensors used for structural condition monitoring and maintenance. </p>

<p>The acquired data needs to be filtered, processed, and classified using the latest developments in Artificial Intelligence (AI), such as deep learning and signal processing algorithms like Wavelets transforms (WL) and Empirical Mode Decomposition (EMD). Such algorithms are computationally intensive and require high speed computing. This has caused no major hurdle as the developments and advances in computing has fulfilled this requirement, such as the use of GPUs, computer clusters, edge computing, and cloud applications. Many systems now reside on the cloud, which only requires access via the internet, providing sophisticated algorithm and high-speed processing power. </p>
</text>
