<text id="autogum_academic_doc445" title="Seed Germination and Early Seedling Growth of Barley at Negative Water Potentials" shortTile="seed-germination" author="Tim  L. Springer, Dolores  W. Mornhinweg" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4395/9/11/671/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Droughts commonly occur on the landscape and are among the costliest natural hazards in the USA with an estimated annual loss of $9 billion from the loss of crops, water supplies, recreation and tourism, ecosystem services, and human health. Future climate projections predict an increase in winter and spring precipitation over much of North America and a decrease in summer precipitation over central and southern North America. Surface temperatures are projected to increase, especially in the winter, at high latitudes, and in the summer throughout southwestern North America. The increase in surface temperature and associated evapotranspiration is expected to have a major impact on the frequency and duration of drought. Many communities have turned to advanced planning to reduce the effects of drought. </p>

<p>Although rainfall occasionally occurs during drought periods, it is effectively impossible for seeds to germinate, become established, and survive. Genetic variation can be used to develop plant materials with superior seed germination and establishment characteristics. For example, Springer after two cycles of phenotypic recurrent selection nearly doubled the seven-day laboratory seed germination of sand bluestem (<hi rend="italic">Andropogon hallii</hi>) in water of potential −0.8 MPa. The seed germination of the sand bluestem base populations (cycle 0, C0) averaged 21.5% after seven days in water of potential −0.8 MPa compared with 38.4% for seeds of the cycle 2 (C2) populations. Field establishment of C2 sand bluestem populations was 8.6% greater than that of the C0 populations under field conditions. As a result of the research, ‘Centennial’ sand bluestem was released. Centennial has greater seed germination in water of potential −0.8 MPa and greater seedling establishment under field conditions when compared with ‘Chet’ sand bluestem (the C0 population). In addition, Springer has used the genetic variation found in little bluestem (<hi rend="italic">Schizachyrium scoparium</hi>) to develop breeding lines with superior seed quality. </p>

<p>In an unrelated crop, Russian dandelion (<hi rend="italic">Taraxacum kok-saghyz</hi>), Hodgson-Kratky et al. reported that, after three cycles of recurrent selection for increased seed germination at a negative water potential, the percentage seed germination of breeding lines was increased 34.5% and 42.5%, and the germination time was reduced by three and five days, respectively. They concluded it was possible to increase the laboratory seed germination of Russian dandelion using phenotypic recurrent selection and that this increase had the potential to improve field establishment. Hodgson-Kratky reported average gains per selection cycle for laboratory seed germination of Russian dandelion were greater for family selection compared to phenotypic selection due to greater selection intensity in the families. </p>

<p>As has been demonstrated, phenotypic recurrent selection is extremely effective for developing cross-pollinated species with superior seed germination characteristics under simulated water deficits. Recurrent selection in self-pollinated species, however, may be constrained by the number of hand emasculations and pollinations that need to be made in order to have enough plant materials for selection to be effective. There is evidence that indicates that seed germination is a quantitative trait. When large numbers of genes are segregating for a trait, the frequency of obtaining a specific genotype in a population is low. Palmer suggested a breeding approach to improve self-pollinated crops that is comparable to phenotypic recurrent selection. This approach involves crossing superior lines for the desired trait that were isolated from the same cross thereby increasing the frequency of the desired genotype. Recurrent selection has been used to increase grain yield in barley. </p>

<p>Studying seed germination under moisture stress is the first step for developing an effected selection pressure for identifying plant materials with rapid seed germination. Thus, the objectives of this study were to determine the effect of moisture stress on seed germination and seedling growth of six winter barley genotypes and discuss how the data are used to select plant materials for rapid germination. </p>
</text>
