<text id="autogum_academic_doc349" title="An Efficient Encryption Algorithm for the Security of Sensitive Private Information in Cyber-Physical Systems" shortTile="efficient-encryption" author="Xiaogang Zhu, Gautam Srivastava, Reza M. Parizi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-9292/8/11/1220/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Related Work</head>
<p>
Recently, encryption of personal information has been studied in depth as an effective way to solve the issues with <tt>SPI</tt>. It has drawn the attention of experts and scholars in many fields, and has resulted in several strong methods. </p>

<p>In, Zhang et al. proposed a dual encryption reversible concealment algorithm for real-time network information based on chaotic sequences. The two kinds of scrambling methods are used to double encrypt the network information. For the first time, the chaotic sequence encryption algorithm is used to globally scramble the network information location. The second time, based on another set of chaotic sequences, the 0 bit and 1 bit of the target pixel value are again scrambled to ensure that the selected explicit (dense) attack can be defended. In this domain, the pseudo pixel is constructed by using the information to be embedded to replace the target pixel, thereby realizing rapid embedding of information. The embedded information is directly extracted from the ciphertext information according to the key calculation. After the receiver decrypts the information, each bit data of the target pixel is extracted to recover the original network information, thereby realizing reversible information hiding under double encryption. The experimental results show that the algorithm has the advantages of fast and efficient information embedding and large capacity. However, since the problem that some information can be shared is not considered, the algorithm has the problems of low security information recognition rate and high information query time delay. </p>

<p>In, Solomon et al., aiming at the problem that the current algorithm’s anti-deciphering ability is not high, proposed a network privacy protection digital information encryption technology based on homomorphic symbol frequency detection. First, the digital information encryption key structure of the network privacy protection object is constructed. Then, the encoding design of encryption and decryption is carried out, which uses the homomorphic symbol frequency detection to perform key optimization of digital encryption to improve the anti-deciphering level. Finally, a simulation experiment was conducted. The delay results show that the digital information encryption technology makes the encryption depth higher, and the deciphering rate of the encrypted data is effectively controlled. However, there is a problem that the information query time is high. </p>

<p>Zhang et al. proposed an anti-peep network security authentication information encryption method. The anti-peep network data attributes are selected according to the professional knowledge and the overall structure of the data, and the selection results are pre-processed. According to the attribute processing result, a variable window is introduced to realize the determination and clearing of redundant data. First, the method sets the minimum, maximum, and minimum thresholds of the variable window and initializes the window. After that, the data to be matched is set, and the segmentation of the string is realized by the 3-gram method. After calculating the similarity between the data to be matched and the window data record, the calculation result is stored in a two-dimensional array. In addition, the data record similarity in the case of missing fields is calculated, thereby realizing the redundancy of each type of data in the network, and then the redundant data in the determination result is cleared. The method treats the plaintext as a continuous bitstream transmitted in the privacy network and inputs its link number into the data encryption. The seed is used to complete the initialization of the key sequence generator and generator, and the random encryption function is called to generate a random encryption number. The encrypted bitstream is then encrypted using the encrypted number. Experiments show that the information anti-attack coefficient is larger after encryption. However, this method has a problem of low resource utilization and cannot effectively meet the needs of users. </p>

<p>Qian et al. proposed a scheme they refer to as Privacy-Preserving Selective Aggregation (<tt>PPSA</tt>). <tt>PPSA</tt> can be described as a method which encrypts users’ <tt>SPI</tt> to prevent privacy disclosure from outside analysts and service providers alike. <tt>PPSA</tt> fully supports selective aggregate functions that are used for online user-based behavior analysis while also being able to guarantee differential privacy. The authors provided experimental results that show that their model can effectively support both aggregate queries (overall and selective) with acceptable levels of communication and computation overhead. However, due to the fact that some information can be shared, the algorithm has the well-known issues of slow data acquisition speeds. </p>

<p>Zhang et al. proposed a user privacy protection method based on dynamic hiding of sensitive itemsets (<tt>SIDH</tt>), which senses the positive and negative boundaries of sensitive rules corresponding to the itemsets space and incrementally expands the original snapshot to query anonymous set data. This methodology hides and purifies sensitive association rules dynamically and finally realizes user privacy protection. The experimental results showed that the <tt>SIDH</tt> method is hidden. The speed of hiding sensitive itemsets is high, but the recognition rate of data is low. </p>
</text>
