<text id="autogum_academic_doc102" title="Economic Dispatch Optimization of Multi-Water Resources: A Case Study of an Island in South Korea" shortTile="economic-dispatch" author="Kapil Gnawali, Kuk  Heon Han, Zong  Woo Geem, Kyung  Soo Jun, Kyung  Taek Yum" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5964/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Water scarcity has become the main problem the world is facing in the 21st century. In recent years, due to global population growth and climate change, the global demand for water has increased. Worldwide, water security issues have been rising and adding challenges and complexity to water authorities and water utilities for the continuous supply of water, and Korea is no exception. The country’s population has grown, industrialization has increased, and the uncertainties due to climate change have put increased pressures on limited available water resources, creating water use conflicts between stakeholders in Korea. It is essential to ensure the water security of islands like Yeongjong, where the water supply is highly dependent on external factors. Sudden loss of function in the existing water supply system can cause enormous social costs. </p>

<p>Currently, somewhat limited water resources, such as reclaimed waste water, harvested rain water, desalinated sea water, and imported water have been widely introduced in Korea to meet the challenge of water security. Accordingly, water resources managers need to determine the optimal water withdrawal rates from multiple sources to satisfy multiple water demands, while meeting the water quality constraints, at the lowest possible overall economic and environmental cost, and enhancing sustainability. Because of the complexity of multi-source combined water supply systems, their optimization presents significant challenges in practice. Multi-objective algorithms are the main tool for determining the optimal allocation of water resources and can effectively reduce the conflicts between competing water user sectors. </p>

<p>In the literature, several optimization methodologies have been proposed to deal with the multi-water resource management problem. Zhang et al. developed a multi-water source joint scheduling model using a refined water supply network and proposed the concept of a water treatment and distribution station (water station). They generalized the water supply system into three modules: the water supply source, the water station, and the water user. Wei et al. established an urban water supply system (UWSS), optimization framework for alternative water resources configuration, considering the trade-offs among total cost, life-cycle greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions, and an extended water ecosystem objective by integrating a multi-objective optimization model based on a non-dominated sorting genetic algorithm (NSGA II) with life-cycle assessment and a water distribution system simulation model. Liu et al. studied a “two-stage multi-water sources allocation model in regional water resources management under uncertainty” to solve for optimized water allocation among multiple sectors and water sources and made recommendations for the future of sustainable utilization of regional water resources. </p>

<p>Verdaguer et al. developed a methodological approach for optimal freshwater blending to improve the resilience of water supply systems, based on a virtual case study. They also simulated the decision-making process of selecting the most suitable mixture of fresh water from eight different sources, including surface water, groundwater, brackish groundwater, potable waste reuse water, and desalinated sea water. The procedure achieves an optimal water blend at the lowest overall cost and improves the resilience and sustainability of urban water supplies. Byeon et al. proposed a new water balance assessment system as part of a smart water grid project in Korea and suggested a smart water management system to counter potential risks to the water distribution system for Yeongjong Island. Park et al. developed a decision support system for blending multiple water resources and system diagnoses in water treatment plants and tested it in the demo plant of the city of Incheon. Puleo et al. studied the optimal control of a multi-source water supply system (desalination/surface water/groundwater, etc.), while reducing the source cost and energy cost (pumping) in addition to maintaining satisfactory water quality. Avni et al. developed and tested an optimization (Q and C domain) model to provide recommendations for a water distribution system (WDS) quality control in terms of meeting optimal water quality requirements; they carried out computational experiments based on an actual regional WDS.  </p>

<p>For many years the optimization concept of economic dispatch (ED) for optimally matching multiple power sources to multiple demands has been popular in the energy system field, and has been solved by various optimization techniques including genetic algorithm (GA), evolutionary programming (EP), honey bee mating optimization (HBMO), tabu search (TS), particle swarm optimization (PSO), harmony search (HS), and firefly algorithm (FA). For the first time we adopt that ED concept from the power supply field into the water supply field for optimally matching multiple water sources to multiple demands in this study. </p>

<p>Considering this background, the main objective of this study is to propose a methodological approach that provides the optimal withdrawal of water from multiple sources with different qualities, while minimizing the total costs and complying with the source constraints of varying supply capacities, marginal water quality, and different types of water demands. In other words, we propose a decision support system to improve the resilience of contributing water systems to ensure a continuous supply of water at a given location. This developed approach is applied to Yeongjong Island, where currently the only water source is piped from Seoul, under the sea. This underwater pipeline is vulnerable to failure due to damage at any time. </p>
</text>
