<text id="autogum_academic_doc711" title="Global Capital, Local Conservation, and Ecological Civilization: The Tiejia Ecology Temple and the Chinese Daoist Association’s Green Agenda" shortTile="global-capital-local" author="Jennifer Lemche, James Miller" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-1444/10/10/580/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Ecology and Globalization </head>
<p>
Two key themes stand out in this history of the Chinese Daoist Association’s pursuit of a green agenda. The first is the role of international agencies such as ARC and the Valley Management Foundation in helping to work with and promote the CDA’s efforts in producing a green agenda. The second is the increasing important of ecological juridifcation, the creation of environmental laws as a means to assert central authority over local practice.  </p>

<head> 3.1. The Role of International Agencies</head>
<p>
The Alliance for Religion and Conservation (ARC) led by Martin Palmer, was founded by Prince Philip in 1995 when he convened a meeting of leading conservation groups and nine world religions at Windsor Castle in England, the aim of which was “to link the secular worlds of conservation and ecology with the faith worlds of the major religions.” (ARC n.d.). Ten years prior to this, Prince Philip, as head of the World Wild Life Fund for Nature (WWF) had organized a meeting between leaders of the world’s largest religions and several environmental organizations to discuss the role that faith could play in address growing ecological problems. The organizers of the Assisi conference stressed the value of cultural diversity with a special invitation to all participants to “Come, proud of your own tradition but humble enough to learn from others” (ARC n.d.). With funding largely from the World Bank, ARC sought to bring a global environmental agenda to the world’s major faith traditions, including the Chinese Daoist Association, a particular interest of Palmer. The development of a green agenda by the CDA can be seen as the fruitful engagement between a local religious tradition, one not widely known or understood even in China, let alone abroad, with a global environmental NGO. Indeed, the ARC website, though now defunct, was a major regular source of English-language information about the ongoing activities of the Chinese Daoist Association, and of course served to highlight the CDA’s ecological activities.  </p>

<p>The CDA’s green agenda, however, would have been unlikely to achieve concrete results without the inspiration and financing of Allerd Stikker and the Valley Management Foundation, who played an instrumental role in the concrete realization of the goal of producing a model “ecology temple” within the Heihe National Park. The ecology temple stands as the first practical example of what the CDA’s green agenda might actually look like and gave a real impetus to the production of laws, guidelines and statements over the next decade. That the first Daoist ecology temple in China was realized principally through a Chinese-UK-Dutch partnership stands as testament to the role played by global actors and global capital in the practical development of the Chinese Daoist Association’s environmental agenda.  </p>

<p>The CDA’s green agenda thus relied in part on the expertise and financing of global instructions and actors. At the same time, analysis of the CDA’s documents reveals a gradual shift away from the formulation of unique Daoist values and concepts regarding environmental and ecological issues, towards a focus on more practical and more globally recognizable concerns such as environmental education, energy conservation, and biodiversity preservation. A question that arises from this is whether this shift is partly the result of the CDA’s engagement with global environmental actors, or whether this reflects changes within the domestic environmental policy situation in China. That is to say, is the CDA’s focus on more generic and less uniquely Daoist formulations of environmental policy the result of its engagement with ARC (or other global agencies)?  </p>

<p>As Miller (2017) has noted, environmental communication in China has tended to adopt a global scientific discourse of environmental concepts and principles, rather than favoring their reworking or reformulation in traditional Chinese terms. Indeed, as Yeh (2013) has amply demonstrated, the disjunction of global environmental goals and local traditions has produced miscommunication and even failure of environmental projects.  </p>

<head> 3.2. Environment and Juridification</head>
<p>
The second point to be made about the involvement of ARC and the CDA thus draws on the issue of juridification. The environmental agenda pursued by the CDA took the form of a top-down initiative designed to be applied more or less uniformly across temples in China. The ecological declarations and statements of the CDA make repeated references to overarching policies such as restrictions on incense burning, banning endangered species from being used in Traditional Chinese Medicine practices and injunctions to make all temples ecological temples. Together, we can theorize that the environmental agenda developed in partnership with ARC contributed to the development of a religious policy discourse focused principally on the good governance and management of temples.  </p>
</text>
