<text id="autogum_academic_doc482" title="Novel Approaches for the Delivery of Anti-HIV Drugs—What Is New?" shortTile="novel-approaches" author="José das Neves" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4923/11/11/554/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>HIV/AIDS continues to be one of the most challenging individual and public health concerns of our days. According to the latest UNAIDS data, in 2018, roughly 37.9 million individuals were infected with HIV globally, while around 770,000 people died of AIDS-related illness. During that same year, an estimated 1.7 million new infections occurred, mainly due to unprotected sexual intercourse. Investment in the field has been considerable, but a cure to the infection remains elusive. Nonetheless, tremendous advances have been made over the last 36 years since HIV-1 was identified, namely in prevention, diagnostics, and treatment. The development of antiretroviral drugs and the introduction of highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) in the mid-1990s—currently referred to as combination antiretroviral therapy (cART)—led to a dramatic shift of AIDS from a fatal disease into a chronic and often stable medical condition. In fact, cART contributed decisively to a steady decrease in the number of HIV-related deaths since the first years of the new millennium. Antiretroviral drugs have also been found useful in the prevention field, particularly in post-exposure prophylaxis or mother-to-child transmission. Treatment as prevention and pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) have further contributed to the reduction of sexually transmitted HIV infections. Long-lasting injectable products and antiretroviral-based microbicides that are currently in late stages of clinical development or regulatory approval may soon provide new options for prevention. Gene therapy and the use of broadly neutralizing antibodies are also attracting a great deal of interest as possible approaches to HIV/AIDS management. </p>

<p>Still, different challenges remain in anti-HIV drug therapy/prophylaxis, and these include the following, among others: (i) the onset of severe adverse effects leading to the discontinuation or interruption of therapy or even prophylaxis; (ii) sub-optimal biodistribution and pharmacokinetics, particularly in reservoir sites or mucosae involved in sexual transmission; (iii) the occurrence of viral resistance; (iv) troublesome regimens and/or drug delivery routes that lead to poor adherence by patients/users; (v) low stability and reduced shelf-life of active molecules, which may be particularly challenging in tropical climates and low-resource regions lacking adequate refrigerated distribution channels and storage; (vi) lack of suitable dosage forms for particular populations (e.g., children and women); (vii) costly drug products that are often inaccessible to populations in need of therapy/prophylaxis; and (viii) social and legal constraints resulting in poor access to and the discontinuation of anti-HIV therapy/prophylaxis. The response from the scientific community could not be more affirmative, and novel ideas and concepts have been emerging throughout the last decade or so. More important, innovative products are now under development, holding great promise for mitigating many of the challenges identified above. </p>

<p>This Special Issue presents an exciting series of reviews and original research articles from eminent scientists in academia and different nonprofit organizations involved in the development of antiretroviral drug products, focusing mainly on novel strategies for the formulation and delivery of anti-HIV compounds. Innovative approaches towards improved gene therapy and immunotherapy are also addressed. The presented reports provide not only interesting overviews and opinion on recent developments in the broad field of antiretroviral therapy/prophylaxis and drug delivery, but also describe the development of new products that are currently tracked for clinical testing. </p>

<p>The Special Issue starts with an interesting review by Tsukamoto at Kindai University, Japan, on strategies explored for curing HIV infection using a combination of gene therapy and host immunization. In particular, the author emphasizes the possible role of anti-HIV intracellular immunization using gene silencing, among other approaches, in the protection of bone marrow hematopoietic stem/progenitor cells. Still in the same field, Düzgüneş and Konopka at the University of the Pacific, USA, contributed a stimulating review on a potential strategy for the eradication of cellular reservoirs of HIV. This thought-provoking piece explores how such an objective could be achieved by using suicide gene therapy for killing HIV-infected cells, excision of chromosome-integrated viral DNA, and cytotoxic liposomes targeted to latency-reversed HIV-infected cells. </p>
</text>
