<text id="autogum_academic_doc286" title="Cellulases Production by a Trichoderma sp. Using Food Manufacturing Wastes" shortTile="cellulases-production" author="Felipe Gordillo-Fuenzalida, Alex Echeverria-Vega, Sara Cuadros-Orellana, Claudia Faundez, Thilo Kähne, Rodrigo Morales-Vera" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/20/4419/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The production of food manufacturing wastes (FMWs) is potentially damaging to the environment; these materials, if not properly disposed of, can lead to the release of greenhouse gases or contaminate soil and water as they decay. Biotechnological approaches may be one solution to utilize these materials before they cause damage to the environment. </p>

<p>In Chile, three important waste materials generated from the food manufacturing industry are olive-mill solid waste (OMSW), tomato pomace (TP), and grape pomace (GP). OMSW is a sub-product of olive oil production by two-phase centrifugation. It is composed of a liquid fraction also known as “alpechin” and a semisolid residue known as “alperujo”. The chemical characterization of “alperujo” reveals a high moisture content, slightly acidic pH, and high content of organic matter, mainly consisting of lignin, hemicellulose, and cellulose. Furthermore, “alperujo” contains lipids and water-soluble polyphenols. TP is a sub-product of tomato processing which mainly consists of peels and seeds and is composed of lignocellulosic material, proteins, minerals, and lipids. GP is a sub-product of grape processing, mainly composed of lignocellulosic residues, glucan, alcohol, phenols, and flavonoids. </p>

<p>One of the simplest strategies for disposal of these FMWs is biodegradation through enzymatic attack. FMWs are mainly composed of lignocellulose, of which cellulose is the major component (20–50% <hi rend="italic">w/w</hi>). In nature, a wide range of microorganisms can use cellulose as a carbon and energy source. To accomplish this, fungi and bacteria secrete extracellular enzymes able to degrade this complex polymer. Cellulose is hydrolyzed by three different classes of enzymes: endo-β-1,4-D-glucanases (EC 3.2.1.4), which hydrolyze internal β-1,4-glucosidic linkages, 1,4-β-D-glucan cellobiohydrolases (EC 3.2.1.91), which cleave off cellulose fragments from the cellulose chain ends, generating the cellobiose disaccharide and β-D-glucosidases (EC 3.2.1.21), which use cellobiose hydrolysis to generate glucose. </p>

<p>Cellulases have been applied in many different industries, such as food, textiles, pulp, paper and wastewater treatment of residue effluents. However, one of the most significant current applications is in bioethanol production from lignocellulosic materials. Bioethanol is considered a fuel alternative for reducing the dependence on crude oil. The majority of bioethanol produced globally is made from biomass containing starch (from corn) or sucrose (from molasses or cane juice). However, bioethanol can also be made from non-edible lignocellulosic biomass like wood or agricultural residues. </p>

<p>Generally, the production of bioethanol from lignocellulosic biomass requires several steps: pretreatment, enzymatic hydrolysis to monomers (also called saccharification), fermentation, distillation, and dehydration. The pretreatment phase can be performed using several different processes, such as concentrated acid hydrolysis, dilute acid hydrolysis, alkali treatment, sodium sulfite treatment, and steam explosion, among others. The objective of the pretreatment is to remove lignin and improve the access of the enzymes to the cell wall carbohydrates (mainly cellulose) to obtain fermentable sugars. The next step is saccharification, in which cellulases, typically from <hi rend="italic">Trichoderma</hi> spp., are applied to produce fermentable monomer sugars from polysaccharides, primarily cellulose. After saccharification, sugar monomers can be fermented to ethanol, typically with <hi rend="italic">Saccharomyces</hi> spp., resulting in concentrations of 40–50 g/L. </p>

<p>Almost all commercially available lignocellulolytic enzymes needed for the hydrolysis step are produced by fermentation with the ascomycete <hi rend="italic">Trichoderma reesei</hi>. However, the purchase of this enzymes can make up 20–40% of the operating costs in a lignocellulosic biomass-based biorefinery. Accordingly, enzyme cost is a major determinant of the viability of commercial-scale production of bioethanol. Onsite production of enzymes using low-value substrates could be an option to make a bioethanol facility more economical. In addition, using FMWs materials as a substrate for fungal cellulases production would make the biorefinery more environmentally sustainable. </p>

<p>In order to improve enzyme performance, extensive research has been carried out on the cellulolytic system of <hi rend="italic">T. reesei</hi> to elucidate the enzymes and gene regulation involved in the utilization of lignocellulosic materials. Despite this, enzyme production from <hi rend="italic">T. reesei</hi> still faces two major bottlenecks. The first one is because some of the produced enzymes have low catalytic activity under industrial conditions, due to the presence of high concentrations of inhibitory compounds generated from the degradation of carbohydrates and lignin during the pretreatment of lignocellulosic biomass. The second one is because certain key enzymes are present in limited amounts. Most research to date has focused on overcoming these bottlenecks by improving the performance of <hi rend="italic">T. reesei</hi> secretion systems and investigating other <hi rend="italic">Trichoderma</hi> spp. with higher secretion potential. Few studies have centered on evaluating enzyme production using less expensive lignocellulosic raw materials. Consequently, the main objective of this research was to study the use of FMWs for cellulases production using an isolated fungal strain from olive stones. Production of cellulases from low-cost residues such as FMWS, could support future on-site production of cellulase enzymes from locally available waste materials for bioethanol production. </p>
</text>
