<text id="autogum_academic_doc465" title="Successful Targeting of the Warburg Effect in Prostate Cancer by Glucose-Conjugated 1,4-Naphthoquinones" shortTile="successful-targeting" author="Sergey  A. Dyshlovoy, Dmitry  N. Pelageev, Jessica Hauschild, Ksenia  L. Borisova, Moritz Kaune, Christoph Krisp, Simone Venz, Yurii  E. Sabutskii, Ekaterina  A. Khmelevskaya, Tobias Busenbender, Vladimir  A. Denisenko, Natalia  D. Pokhilo, Lyubov  N. Atopkina, Markus Graefen, Hartmut Schlüter, Valentin  A. Stonik, Carsten Bokemeyer, Victor  Ph. Anufriev, Gunhild von Amsberg" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6694/11/11/1690/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Discussion</head>
<p>
Increased selectivity and efficacy can be achieved by linking cytotoxic anticancer drugs to specific target/carrier molecules. Successful examples of this treatment strategy are antibody-drug conjugates, which target cancer cells due to increased expression of specific proteins, and folate conjugates, which utilize a commonly high expression of the folate receptor (FR) on the surface of different human cancer cells. </p>

<p>Warburg effect targeting is another promising strategy for the design and synthesis of new cytotoxic anticancer drugs. Here, the conjugation of sugar residues to cytotoxic drugs shall increase selectivity to cancerous tissues and reduce side effects in patients due to a higher sugar uptake by the cancer cells. To date one sugar-conjugated molecule glufosfamide is in clinical development for the treatment of lung, ovary, pancreatic, brain and CNS cancer as well as soft tissue sarcoma. In addition, different sugar-conjugated molecules are currently evaluated preclinically. In prostate cancer Warburg effect was observed specifically in metastatic tumors which makes glucose-derived chemotherapeutics promising in the treatment of metastatic CRPC. In our research, we found the derivatives of natural 1,4-naphtoquinone compounds to be active in drug-resistant prostate cancer cells. Preliminary data, however, have shown that these substances are also rather cytotoxic for non-cancerous cells, suggesting undesired side effects <hi rend="italic">in vivo</hi>. Therefore, we utilized the Warburg effect in order to increase the selectivity of the compounds towards tumor cells. We synthesized hybrid molecules, which contain selected natural 1,4-naphtoquinone moieties conjugated with glucose residues via non-glycoside bond at C6 position. The non-glycoside nature of the conjugates was chosen in order to provide the highest affinity to glucose transporters located in the cellular membrane. It is known that the presence of free unsubstituted glycoside hydroxyl (at C1 position) is important for the stabilization of hydrogen bonding interactions with GLUT-1 and therefore is required for the successful cellular uptake of the sugar-conjugated molecules. In contrast, the hydroxyl at C6 position of glucose molecule is not relevant for the hydrogen bond interactions and therefore it’s substitution may be more tolerable. In fact, the affinity of glucose with substituted C6-OH to GLUT-1 was reported to be almost equal to its unsubstituted analogues. Therefore, instead of a conventional glycosylation reaction (results in C1-substituted glucose) we applied a new reaction of alkylation of 2-hydroxy-1,4-naphthoquinones with 6-deoxy-6-iodo-1,2:3,5-di-O- isopropylidene-α-D-glucofuranose (results in a C6-substituted glucose). This reaction was more efficient in comparison with transesterification reaction of 2-methoxy-1,4-naphthoquinones, which was recently discovered by us. Thus, we synthesized a series of 6-(1,4-naphtoquinonyl)-D-glucose conjugates containing diprotected, monoprotected, or unprotected glucose residues. </p>

<p>In line with our hypotheses the glucose-conjugated compounds revealed higher selectivity towards five human prostate cancer cell lines compared with five non-cancerous lines. The successful targeting of the Warburg effect by the newly synthesized glucose derivatives is strongly suggested by the following findings: (a) correlation of cytotoxicity and selectivity of the synthesized conjugates with higher expression of GLUT-1 in human prostate cancer cells; (b) inhibition of cytotoxicity of the conjugates by addition of glucose to the media; c) ability of the compounds to inhibit a glucose uptake by cancer cells. In general, the binding of the quinone core with the glucose moiety lead to an increased water solubility and selectivity. However, at the same time it resulted in an absolute cytotoxicity decrease when compared to methoxy derivatives, most probably due to the increased polarity of the molecule. It should also be noted that normal prostate cells are known to have an active glycolysis and also consume significant amount of glucose (reviewed in). Thus, these cells may also be affected by the Warburg effect targeting therapeutics in vivo. However, frequently patients with advanced prostate cancer have had local treatment for their primary tumors leaving no vital tissue behind. In the patients cytoreduction of the remaining prostate tissue maybe a pleasant side effect in order to avoid local complications. </p>
</text>
