<text id="autogum_academic_doc064" title="Similar Impacts of Alien and Native Tree Species on Understory Light Availability in a Temperate Forest" shortTile="similar-impacts-alien" author="Marcin  K. Dyderski, Andrzej  M. Jagodziński" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4907/10/11/951/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head><head> 4.1. Drivers of Light Interception by Canopy</head>
<p>
Light interception by forest canopies is driven by different features describing foliage: its vertical distribution, biomass quantity, and allocation, as well as leaf traits. Leaf distribution across strata in tree stands is determined by canopy dominant light transmittance. The most frequent tree species in the study area—<hi rend="italic">P. sylvestris</hi>—has loose crowns, allowing higher light availability beneath its crowns than the other species. Similarly, a small LAI to BA ratio for <hi rend="italic">P. sylvestris</hi> in mature tree stands was reported by Bauer. For that reason its stands are usually occupied by dense shrub layers, including invasive species. For species with higher light interception, e.g., <hi rend="italic">Q. rubra</hi> and <hi rend="italic">F. sylvatica</hi>, presence of shrub layers is least developed. Different proportions of tree species in the main (highest) canopy layer determine overall light availability at lower forest strata. For that reason forests with dominance of light-transmitting species in the overstory have more developed shrub layers, which also determines lower light availability at the forest floor. However, in stands with well-developed both canopy and shrub layers, increasing LAI does not decrease DIFN, because light availability is vertically stratified—more than one layer of leaves covers open sky. </p>

<p>Quantity of foliage biomass depends on tree dimensions, according to metabolic scaling theory. However, the exponent of this relationship is size-dependent, as more biomass is allocated to stems in larger trees. Despite decreasing allocation, foliage biomass increases with stand age. In older stands, due to self-thinning and years of light competition, more gaps provide more light into the lower strata. Lower trees and shrubs have lower total biomass, and therefore higher biomass allocation to foliage. For that reason we found the highest LAI to BA ratios in shrubs and the lowest in trees. </p>

<p>Leaf area in the canopy layer also depends on leaf architecture and functioning. The wide range of SLA shows that for trees similar leaf mass might differ in area up to one order of magnitude. This trait reflects plant strategy of facing limited resources and life span, as well as investment in foliage development. Although SLA varies with climate, light availability, and growing season, interspecific variation is higher than intraspecific. Therefore, each tree species LAI to BA ratio is also dependent on leaf morphology, compromising species-specific evolutionary legacies. </p>

<head> 4.2. Impacts of Alien Species</head>
<p>
We found the highest LAI to BA ratio in <hi rend="italic">C. lucidus</hi>, a species coming from Central Asia. This species is known as a naturalized, potentially invasive species in Poland, a casual neophyte in Czechia, and as naturalized in Armenia, Canada, Finland, Latvia, Norway, Russia, Sweden, the United Kingdom, and the United States. This species is known for creating dense stands which decrease the richness and abundance of native species. The cited authors suggested that the mechanism of negative impacts might be limiting of light availability, however, they did not provide a quantitative assessment. In the study area <hi rend="italic">C. lucidus</hi> had limited distribution—we found it only in one of the study blocks, but with high abundances. Due to its ability to be bird-dispersed, a risk assessment is highly needed for this species, which might cause more severe impacts than the currently most frequent invasive species. </p>

<p>Our study showed different impacts of four main invasive tree species. <hi rend="italic">P. serotina</hi> revealed the highest LAI to BA ratio. This species, which in Europe usually has the form of a shrub or small tree, is able to dominate lower strata of forest ecosystems. Similar to our results, a twice higher leaf area index of <hi rend="italic">P. serotina</hi> than <hi rend="italic">P. sylvestris</hi> was also reported from forests in Belgium. This influence gives <hi rend="italic">P. serotina</hi> an impact, especially high in cases of changing species composition of understory vegetation. As young regeneration of <hi rend="italic">P. serotina</hi> requires light to grow, decrease of light availability would stop further invasion of <hi rend="italic">P. serotina</hi> beneath already invaded canopies. However, due to vegetative regeneration, as well as high number of seedlings able to survive in less-suitable conditions for a few years, it is able to develop a persistent sapling bank. Although impact of <hi rend="italic">P. serotina</hi> on LAI is lower than impact of native shrubs, this species is able to reach higher BA, making its quantity the most important driver of light availability modification. </p>

<p>Another invasive species with relatively high LAI to BA ratio is <hi rend="italic">A. negundo</hi>. This species has high SLA, which is helpful in invading pioneer vegetation of riparian forests. This species is mid-successional, which allows it to take advantage of release opportunities from forest disturbance in riparian ecosystems. However, it was not frequent in the ecosystem studied here, as riparian forests were not frequent. </p>
</text>
