<text id="autogum_academic_doc040" title="Pan-European Study on the Prevalence of the Feline Leukaemia Virus Infection – Reported by the European Advisory Board on Cat Diseases (ABCD Europe)" shortTile="paneuropean-study" author="Nadine Studer, Hans Lutz, Claude Saegerman, Enikö Gönczi, Marina  L. Meli, Gianluca Boo, Katrin Hartmann, Margaret  J. Hosie, Karin Moestl, Séverine Tasker, Sándor Belák, Albert Lloret, Corine Boucraut-Baralon, Herman  F. Egberink, Maria-Grazia Pennisi, Uwe Truyen, Tadeusz Frymus, Etienne Thiry, Fulvio Marsilio, Diane Addie, Manfred Hochleithner, Filip Tkalec, Zsuzsanna Vizi, Anna Brunetti, Boyko Georgiev, Louisa  F. Ludwig-Begall, Flurin Tschuor, Carmel  T. Mooney, Catarina Eliasson, Janne Orro, Helle Johansen, Kirsi Juuti, Igor Krampl, Kaspars Kovalenko, Jakov Šengaut, Cristina Sobral, Petra Borska, Simona Kovaříková, Regina Hofmann-Lehmann" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4915/11/11/993/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Feline leukaemia virus (FeLV) is a gammaretrovirus that infects domestic cats and closely related wild felids worldwide. Since the first description of the virus in 1964 in feline lymphoma tissue, increasing knowledge has been gained concerning the pathogenesis, diagnosis, and treatment of the infection. FeLV infection can lead to fatal diseases in cats with progressive infection. Testing and eradication programs and the introduction of effective vaccines led to a decrease in FeLV prevalence in many countries in the last 30 years. However, more recently, the decrease of the FeLV prevalence has stagnated. In other countries, such as Denmark, FeLV is rarely detected nowadays. For the USA, Canada, and Australia, large prevalence studies have been published. There have also been some recent studies on the prevalence of FeLV in single European countries. However, there has been no pan-European study determining the current FeLV prevalence in domestic cats. FeLV prevalence can vary considerably depending on the composition of the investigated cat population; feral or stray cats versus privately owned cats, cats in shelters or from breeders, clinically healthy cats or sick cats. In addition, preselection of the samples has an influence; e.g., if samples are obtained only from cats suspected of being infected with FeLV. A recent meta-analysis suggested an indirect relation between FeLV prevalence and the yearly gross domestic product (GDP) per capita using purchasing power parity (PPP), i.e., the total value of all the goods and services produced by a country in a particular year, divided by the number of people living there and corrected for purchasing power using a “basket of goods”. However, no FeLV prevalence data were available for many European countries, or the data were obtained several years ago. </p>

<p>The aim of the present study was to determine the current prevalence of FeLV viraemia in cats that visit a veterinary facility. The study protocol included cats from 32 European countries in the survey. In order to avoid any preselection of the cats (apart from visiting a veterinary facility), 10 animals arriving consecutively at each facility were tested independently of the reason for the veterinary appointment. Risk and protective factors for FeLV infection were determined using the demographic, husbandry, clinical as well as FeLV vaccination history data from each cat. Furthermore, using our data, we tested the recently postulated hypothesis of a correlation between the FeLV prevalence and the GDP in European countries, and extended the analysis to test also for a potential correlation with FeLV vaccination rates. For minimally invasive sample collection and to avoid bias by requesting blood collection, saliva swabs were collected and analysed by RT-qPCR; the detection of viral RNA by RT-qPCR in saliva was shown to be an excellent measure of FeLV viraemia. </p>
</text>
