<text id="autogum_academic_doc493" title="Excessive Fructose Intake Impairs Baroreflex Sensitivity and Led to Elevated Blood Pressure in Rats" shortTile="excessive-fructose" author="Hsin-Hung Chen, Chih-Hsun Chu, Shu-Wei Wen, Chi-Cheng Lai, Pei-Wen Cheng, Ching-Jiunn Tseng" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/11/2581/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
Here, we describe a link between fructose and NO levels in the NTS, as well as its association with baroreflex sensitivity and activation of the CNS. Our findings showed that excessive fructose consumption increased BP and renal SNA, decreased NO bioavailability, and impaired baroreflex response. Excessive fructose intake increased serum triglycerides levels and induced BP elevation by stimulating SNA; however, alleviation of hypertriglyceridemia did not attenuate sympathetic activation and only slightly lowered BP. It was suggested that, mechanistically, SNA played a role in modulating changes in BP due to increased fructose consumption through another unknown pathway.  </p>

<p>Epidemiological studies have hinted at a link between fructose consumption and elevated blood pressure. Jalal et al. reported that excess dietary fructose (≥74 g/day) in the form of added sugar was associated with higher BP values in adults in the United States who did not have a history of hypertension. Similarly, a study of 4867 adolescents found that SBP rose by 2 mmHg following the intake of sugar-sweetened beverages from the lowest to the highest category. In a prospective study involving adults in the United States, Chen et al. found that intake of one less sugar-sweetened beverage per day was associated with a 1.8 mmHg reduction in SBP and a 1.1 mmHg reduction in DBP over 18 months. Some animal studies showed that a high-fructose diet was associated with hypertriglyceridemia, hyperinsulinemia, impaired glucose tolerance, insulin resistance, and increased BP and body weight. However, these adverse effects were not indicated with equivalent calories of glucose. In this study, increased fructose intake for 0 to 2 days evoked increases in BP levels, and the high BP levels were maintained until day 7 (<figure>Figure 2</figure>).  </p>

<p>The great increase in fructose consumption in the last decades leads to the rapid accumulation of triglyceride in the Occidental population. Tran et al. reported that serum norepinephrine and triglyceride levels are significantly increased in fructose-fed hypertensive rats, as reflected by high SNA. According to Tran et al., hypertension can develop in rats owing to excessive fructose consumption, and the developed hypertension can be treated using a sympatholytic agent called prazosin, which blocks the α1-adrenoreceptors. Hypertension inhibition by prazosin did not reduce the level of triglyceride in serum. Consistent with this previous result, our data showed that the use of a DGAT1 inhibitor for inhibiting serum triglyceride level led to a slight decrease in BP but did not affect SNA (<figure>Figure 3</figure>).  </p>

<p>The baroreflex system is an important mechanism in the regulation of heart rate, sympathetic tone, and consequently BP. Impairment of baroreflex sensitivity is involved in the sympathoexcitatory and sympathoinhibitory effects of metabolic syndromes. A previous study showed that hypertriglyceridemia may be the main contributory factor associated with impaired baroreflex sensitivity during a metabolic syndrome. Soncrant et al. reported that elevated BP was increased by sympathoexcitation in 20% fructose-induced, salt-sensitive, hypertensive rats. It has been shown that the ingestion of fructose altered the secretion of hormones that regulate energy balance associated with increased SNA. However, in the current study, although a DGAT1 inhibitor was administered orally to block triglycerides production, sympathoexcitation was not inhibited in fructose-fed rats. Dos Santos et al indicated that fructose consumption similarly reduced both baroreflex sensitivity and activity. Our research further indicated that fructose intake may reduce NO levels in the NTS and cause baroreflex dysfunction, which further stimulates SNA and induces the development of high BP (<figure>Figure 4</figure> and <figure>Figure 5</figure>).  </p>

<p>Generally, anesthetics affect the basal levels of sympathetic nerve activity to regulate blood pressure, which plays an important role in controlling cardiovascular function. Sun et al. indicated that anesthesia attenuated the excitatory response of RSNA and HR to anaphylactic hypotension, while these excitatory responses were attenuated by anesthetics in the order ketamine-xylazine &gt; urethane = pentobarbital. Bencze et al. found that pentobarbital anesthesia had a modest influence on the BP level and its maintenance by the above vasoactive systems. In addition, anesthetics may inhibit the primary area in the baroreceptor reflex pathway of the central nervous system, resulting in attenuation of the baroreceptor reflex. Therefore, sympathetic nerve activity and cardiovascular function may be affected by the anesthetic. However, there were some limitations to our study. First, we measured BP during consciousness, whereas RSNA and baroreflex sensitivity measurements were performed under the anesthetic. Second, our sample size was relatively small and the study used nonparametric methods for analysis. Third, the fructose group was used as the control group only on day 0. </p>
</text>
