<text id="autogum_academic_doc029" title="Dynamics of Plant Metabolism during Cold Acclimation" shortTile="dynamics-plant-metabolism" author="Lisa Fürtauer, Jakob Weiszmann, Wolfram Weckwerth, Thomas Nägele" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5411/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Carbohydrate Dynamics of Plant Cold Acclimation</head>
<p>
Carbohydrates are the primary products of photosynthesis, and they play a central role in energy metabolism, developmental processes, stress signalling and temperature acclimation. Reprogramming of primary metabolism during cold acclimation typically results in the accumulation of soluble sugars, sugar alcohols, organic acids, amino acids, polyamines and substrates for secondary metabolites. This accumulation eventually allows plants to withstand lower temperatures when compared to non-acclimated plants. Sugars play diverse roles which are, e.g., stabilization of membranes, osmo-protection, and protection of proteins from desiccation. Further, sugar accumulation might also result from reduced sink activity because growth retardation at low temperatures is stronger than the reduction of photosynthetic activity. In general, reactions in primary metabolism are tightly regulated and closely linked to the circadian clock to ensure continuous carbohydrate availability. Clock components are significantly influenced by low temperature and sugars are also known to be important for entrainment of the clock. Besides the clock components, light itself is deemed to be essential for cold acclimation. </p>

<p>It has been suggested that carbohydrates directly influence cell membrane stability by interacting with the membrane interface and therefore support the maintenance of membrane integrity under freezing conditions. For example, sucrose can interact with the phosphate in lipid headgroups, thereby decreasing membrane permeability. Carbohydrates have been found to stabilize in vitro liposomes against leakage of aqueous content, which suggests a cryoprotective role in vivo. Fructans have been found to move via vesicle transport from vacuoles to the apoplast where they can assist in stabilizing the plasma membrane. Further, sugar transport proteins are believed to play a role in vacuolar fructan export. Raffinose family oligosaccharides (RFOs) are known to protect membranes under cold stress and contribute to higher freezing resistance. Raffinose is synthesised within the cytosol and transported into plastids to protect thylakoid membranes, contributing to PSII integrity and acting as a potential ROS scavenger. Furthermore, hydrogen bonds between sugars and proteins are discussed to inhibit dehydration-induced protein unfolding. </p>

<p>Starch is a direct product of photosynthesis and a storage compound for carbon. Starch biosynthesis and breakdown are tightly regulated during abiotic stress. Many enzymes involved in starch metabolism are redox regulated. During cold stress, starch metabolism in <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis</hi> has great flexibility in the way it reacts to differences in growth conditions and it is a determinant of plant fitness under abiotic stress. Starch degradation is an initial response as starch metabolism has the potential to relieve product inhibition effects on Calvin cycle-associated enzymes and might allow the release of Pi in chloroplasts under cold. Increased activity of beta-amylases supplements maltose accumulation during cold exposure. Further, mobilisation of starch seems to differ between different natural accessions of <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis</hi> and might influence their cold acclimation capacities. Interestingly, impairment of plastidial α-glucan phosphorylase resulted in no significant changes in the starch content of <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis</hi> leaves, but reduced survival under stress. This highlights that the dynamics of synthesis and breakdown pathways rather than the absolute amount of starch might be responsible for metabolic reprogramming and survival under abiotic stress. Starch has several roles in both source and sink tissues and starch degradation into sugars has a pivotal role for plant cold stress responses via offering osmo-protective sugars and rapid energy supplies. </p>

<p>Maltose, a product of starch degradation, might serve as a direct osmo-protectant in chloroplasts by protecting stromal proteins from dehydration. Maltose supplies biosynthesis of other carbohydrates like hexoses and raffinose, but also proline to fuel and maintain carbon metabolism. A direct correlation between freezing tolerance in <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis</hi> accessions and the degree of accumulation of raffinose and proline has been observed. Proline is well-known to accumulate during stress response, affecting signaling events, cryoprotection and redox balance in several plant species. In a protein-protein interaction network, delta 1-pyrroline-5-carboxylate synthase 2 (P5CS2), which is a central enzyme in proline biosynthesis, indicated a linkage to heat-shock proteins and to the interface of primary and secondary metabolism. In general, gene expression related to secondary metabolism is well correlated with freezing tolerance. In <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis</hi>, biosynthesis of secondary metabolites, e.g., flavonoids, is induced during cold exposure. The substance class of flavonoids is estimated to comprise more than 8000 metabolites and flavonoid metabolism may comprise 20% of the total carbon flux in a plant cell. Flavonoids frequently contain sugars like rhamnose, arabinose, glucose, galactose, which directly shows the necessity of a regulatory and metabolic interaction between plant carbohydrates and secondary metabolism during cold acclimation. Several flavonoid biosynthesis mutants with reduced flavonoid content showed impaired freezing tolerance, and the contribution of flavonoids to freezing tolerance was shown to be genotype-dependent. Flavonoid metabolism was found to be regulated via post-transcriptional mechanisms as the corresponding transcripts and metabolites correlated poorly in response to cold. </p>
</text>
