<text id="autogum_academic_doc603" title="Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorder: What does Public Awareness Tell Us about Prevention Programming?" shortTile="fetal-alcohol-spectrum" author="Peter Choate, Dorothy Badry, Bruce MacLaurin, Kehinde Ariyo, Dorsa Sobhani" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4229/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorder (FASD) results from alcohol use during pregnancy creating lifelong functional and cognitive impairments that fall across a spectrum. The actual prevalence of FASD is unknown, but recent estimates suggest a rate of 1.4%–4.4% of the population in Alberta with 4% identified as the best estimate in Canada. It is thought that the vast majority of people affected are not diagnosed with the disorder either because their health problems are diagnosed under other categories or the individual does not come to the attention of diagnosticians. In essence, FASD often goes unrecognized. </p>

<p>Prevention efforts have been ongoing for over two decades with a focus on broad messaging about the importance of avoiding alcohol use during pregnancy, but these efforts, while creating awareness, have not necessarily changed alcohol use behavior. Despite prevention and education efforts, the rates of FASD are thought to be much higher than previously considered, raising concerns that prevention has not been successful in reducing incidence. Hoyme, Kalberg, Elliot et al. indicate that the “soaring prevalence and burden of FASD in children recently led the American Academy of Pediatrics to stress the following: no amount of alcohol intake during pregnancy can be considered safe; there is no safe trimester to drink alcohol; all forms of alcohol pose a similar risk; and binge drinking poses a dose-related risk to the fetus” (p. 2) and, as noted above, many cases of FASD simply go unrecognized by health and helping professionals. We are cautious with this data, as, given that screening and diagnostic criteria and methods are changing, this may confound the prevalence data. </p>

<p>FASD is a clearly established priority for the province of Alberta, Canada, which is where the research reported here was conducted. In 2008, the Government of Alberta implemented an FASD 10-Year Strategic Plan. The first two pillars of that plan focus upon public awareness and education strategies and prevention, while the other pillars look at assessment and diagnosis, support for caregivers, and the presence of an FASD learning organization. This research looks at public awareness, which is part of the first pillar. It uses a secondary data analysis of the 2011 and 2017 datasets to examine characteristics and changes in public awareness of FASD in Alberta.  </p>

<p>The present project looks to understand the degree of awareness of FASD, which can assist in understanding whether the messaging is at least impacting at that level. </p>
</text>
