<text id="autogum_academic_doc436" title="Are the Innovative Electronic Labels for Extra Virgin Olive Oil Sustainable, Traceable, and Accepted by Consumers?" shortTile="innovative-electronic" author="Simona Violino, Federico Pallottino, Giulio Sperandio, Simone Figorilli, Francesca Antonucci, Vanessa Ioannoni, Daniele Fappiano, Corrado Costa" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2304-8158/8/11/529/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Conclusions</head>
<p>
This study contributes to the EVOO production panorama providing concrete tools for improving the internal logistics of the company on the one hand and promoting infotracing and safeguarding consumers on the other. Even if the technologies have been present on the market for some years, now they are almost new to the olive oil production food chain. </p>

<p>EVOO represents the one of the excellences of Italian products; it is a basic ingredient of the Mediterranean diet; for this reason, it must be protected from fraud and sophistication that could damage “made in Italy” and have repercussions both for producers and consumers. This study showed some interesting and surprising outcomes. Following the questionnaire results, the high level of the respondent education could mainly due to the media (a specialized online tool) adopted to spread the questionnaire. First of all, the unexpectedly high willingness to pay (+17.8%) by Italian consumers for the implementation of traceability information on EVOO mediated by smart technologies. This interesting result is not affected by the high level of education of the respondents (63% graduated) even if it may have influenced the considerable percentage (93.9%) of those interviewed. However, the education level and technological knowledge may not be properly on par. Furthermore, according with the survey results, the age composition revealed different spending behavior patterns. Respondents less than 35 years old (19.9% of the respondents) were less available to pay additional costs for the implementation of information regarding traceability. A future study could try to improve the effectiveness of the present work crossing data related to technological knowledge along with those already asked. </p>

<p>Although blockchains are not yet very widespread in EVOO traceability, their use may be an excellent solution to ensure reliability, transparency, and security, especially for those commodities susceptible to fraud such as EVOO. Among the three proposed technologies for traceability, consumers greatly prefer the QR-B system, despite the different advantages linkable to the other systems. The success of the QR-B could be ascribable to different aspects: the indubitable cutting-edge fashion trend of blockchain in the food sector, the use of incentives (financial rewards mechanism), the easy-to-use QR-code, and the gamification strategy. Another interesting result regards the economic analysis which reports a sustainable implementation of the three technologies proposed starting from a mid-production EVOO level. However, it must be said that further studies should investigate the deeper costs that farms/industries etc., would have to pay in relation to the business planning, prior the technological system adoption. </p>

<p>On the basis of the obtained results, it is possible to predict an evolution of the proposed traceability systems merging the benefits of each technology into a syncretic one, aiming to preserve the bottle content (DAB), the easy-to-use properties (NFC and QR-code) with the QR-B aforementioned qualities, and integrating other information, such as the preservation status from bottling to consumers adopting functional inks.
 </p>
</text>
