<text id="autogum_academic_doc185" title="Synthesis and Characterization of New Layered Double Hydroxide-Polyolefin Film Nanocomposites with Special Optical Properties" shortTile="synthesis-characterization" author="Fuensanta Monzó, Ana Vanessa Caparrós, Diego Pérez-Pérez, Alejandro Arribas, Ramón Pamies" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1944/12/21/3580/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
One of the most common types of degradation of polymers is induced by Ultraviolet (UV) light radiation which produces highly reactive free radicals. The so-called aging process is a result of photodegradation and color fading of polymers. A wide range of additives are included in thermoplastic films to avoid UV light aging. These UV blocking compounds are classified based on the blocking mechanism: shielding by inorganic additives and UV light absorption by organic species. The thermal performance of the final product is one of the most important aspects to be taken into consideration since the processing of thermoplastic films occurs at high temperatures. In this case, inorganic additives usually are more stable at high temperatures than the organic additives. Besides, the UV energy absorbed can be dissipated as heat promoting a thermal aging of the thermoplastic matrix causing a loss of the mechanical properties. In addition, organic UV absorbers migrate to the surface of the plastic due to their volatility and different polarity, so the plastic matrix loses its UV protection over time. However, there are several strategies to reduce these negative effects. For example, the usage of layered double hydroxides (LDH) as host matrix of organic compounds results into a hybrid absorber which can block the UV light, increasing the thermal and photostability of the nanocomposite. </p>

<p>Layered double hydroxides (LDH) are anionic clays represented by the general formula of [M2+1−xM3+x(OH)2]x+(An−)x/n·mH2O, where M2+ and M3+ are divalent and trivalent metallic cations and An− depicts the anions which can be present in the hydrated interlayer galleries of the clay. The value of x is in the range of 0.20–0.33. Therefore, positively-charged metal hydroxide layers are intercalated with anions in order to keep the materials electroneutrality. The cations fill octahedral sites having hydroxide ions in the vertices. These anions are weakly bound to the structure and ion exchange reactions are suitable for the modification of LDHs. LDHs composed of Mg and Al hydroxyl sheets with carbonate ions as counter anions and M2+:M3+ = 3:1 are called hydrotalcite, and quintinite when the ratio M2+:M3+ = 2:1. LDHs have attracted the attention of the scientific community due to their unique properties such as anion exchange ability, thermal stability and easy production and the promising applications in different fields of adsorption, sensors, biomedicine, polymer additives, among others. LDH host layers promote the thermal and optical stabilization of the exchanged anions. Many thermoplastic materials such as polyethylene (PE) do not contain polar groups in their backbone. Therefore, a homogenous dispersion of clay platelets at a nonmetric level is a challenging aim in this technology. The addition of compatibilizers has been proven to favor the exfoliation of hydrotalcite particles. In this work, we have evaluated the effect on the viscoelastic, mechanical and optical properties of the addition of a polar whitening agent to low density polyethylene. A modified LDH hosting the anionic whitening agent has been prepared. The research compares the effect on the polymeric matrix to the addition of the whitening agent, the modified LDH, and also the addition of a commercial surfactant. A characterization of the LDHs has been performed by means of XRD, TGA and FT–IR. The viscoelastic behavior at different temperatures of the resulting nanocomposite has been performed to evaluate the impact on processing conditions. The mechanical and optical properties have been also determined. </p>
</text>
