<text id="autogum_academic_doc518" title="Inhibitory Effect of Oat Bran Ethanol Extract on Survival and Gemcitabine Resistance of Pancreatic Cancer Cells" shortTile="inhibitory-effect" author="Myoungjae Kim, Jeong-Geon Mun, Hyun  Jin Lee, So-Ri Son, Mi-Ja Lee, Ji-Ye Kee" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1420-3049/24/21/3829/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Pancreatic cancer (PC) is the one of the most aggressive and therapeutically ineffective malignant cancers. Mortality due to PC is fourth among the various cancer types worldwide. In 2018, 458,918 new cases and 432,242 deaths by PC were recorded worldwide. One of the primary reasons for the high mortality is the difficulty in early diagnosis of the disease because pancreas is behind the stomach and the patient shows general symptoms such as digestive problems, abdominal pain, and weight loss before metastasis. More than 80% of PC patients show metastasis at the time of diagnosis. Despite various therapeutic methods, the 5-year survival rate of PC is only 8% and PC is projected to be the second leading cause of cancer deaths by 2030. </p>

<p>Gemcitabine (Gem) is approved as a first-line chemotherapeutic drug for PC treatment. However, the response rate of Gem in PC patients is only 12% and most patients are resistant to Gem within a few weeks. Less than 25% of PC patients benefit from Gem treatment and the median overall survival is only 6 months. In order to overcome these limitations of Gem, combinatorial regimens such as folinic acid, 5-fluorouracil, irinotecan and oxaliplatin (FOLFIRINOX) have been widely used to treat PC patients. FOLFIRINOX presents higher response rates and its median overall survival is nearly 12 months. However, this regimen shows considerable adverse effects such as lower blood counts, fever, infection, diarrhea, and weight loss. Therefore, development of new chemotherapeutic drugs that can overcome chemoresistance and have less adverse effects on patients is needed. </p>

<p>Oat (<hi rend="italic">Avena sativa</hi> L.) is an important cereal crop of the family of Poaceae grown worldwide. Oats have various advantages; they require less nutrients to grow than the wheat or the corn. Additionally, as people become more aware of their health, more people are consuming oats in the form of oatmeal, granola bars, cookies, and beverages. Recent studies have revealed that oats possess beneficial health effects on aging, oxidant, cancer, liver injury, hypercholesterolemia, and gastrointestinal problems. </p>

<p>In this study, the effects of ethanol extract from the oat bran (OBE) on PC were investigated in vitro. To confirm the anti-cancer effect of OBE on PC cell viability, colony formation, cell cycle distribution, apoptosis, and proteins were evaluated. Moreover, the combination effects of Gem and OBE on PC cells with acquired resistance to Gem was investigated to test if combination therapy could overcome drug resistance developed during cancer treatment. </p>
</text>
