<text id="autogum_academic_doc485" title="Road Traffic Noise Exposure and Depression/Anxiety: An Updated Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis" shortTile="road-traffic-noise" author="Angel  M. Dzhambov, Peter Lercher" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4134/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Recent World Health Organization (WHO) evidence reviews, published in the International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, have revealed sufficient evidence that sources of transportation noise lead to serious annoyance, sleep disturbance, and cardio-metabolic disorders. Less convincing evidence and no exposure-response information was provided for mental health. Mental health is a perquisite for well-being and participation in social and economic life, with the burden already amounting to about 4% of the gross domestic product across European Union countries. Unlike other chronic diseases, mental disorders such as anxiety and depression show an early-life onset, ranging from mild and time-limited to chronic and severe impairments. This feature makes the illness difficult to identify, and therefore, it is often poorly treated and overlooked. The 12-month point prevalence of anxiety and depressive disorders in Western countries sums up to 10%–14% on average now, and it has become a public health priority issue around the World in the case of adults and children. Although the treatment of both conditions is increasing, undertreatment is still prevalent and treatment effectiveness is modest. Moreover, the pathway to mental disorders is a complex and interactive process, and over-reliance on individual treatment at the expense of broader “structural prevention” approaches has further hindered the successful reduction of disease prevalence. </p>

<p>It was unfortunate that the WHO evidence review on mental health was hampered mainly by the broad outcome selection, which embraced different levels of severity, from health-related quality of life to clinical outcomes like depression or anxiety disorders. The small number of studies in the sub-section outcomes and the diverse measurement instruments used in the available studies (symptom questionnaires, clinical diagnoses, psychotropic medication) prevented the authors from conducting full meta-analyses. Clark and Paunovic concluded that there were too few studies of clinically significant mental health outcomes, and studies of large samples were needed. However, quantitative evidence is a necessary requirement for burden of disease estimation and setting exposure guidelines. </p>

<p>In the meantime (the mental health review included papers up to October 2015), a sufficient number of new studies on more severe mental health outcomes, such as depression and other mental health disorders, were published. A few studies were of longitudinal design and improved the quality aspect of the evidence base. With that in mind, we aimed to supplement the WHO review by providing a formal meta-analysis with these additional studies. By restricting to more confined clinical outcomes, such as depression and anxiety, and the exposure to residential road traffic noise (as the most prevalent type of traffic noise exposure) too many analysis subsets can be avoided. The updated meta-analysis should add to the growing collection of up-to-date systematic reviews on health effects of traffic noise (e.g., birth outcomes, cardiovascular and metabolic disease, and behavioral/emotional disorders in youth). </p>
</text>
