<text id="autogum_academic_doc164" title="Preparation of Chitosan/Poly(Vinyl Alcohol) Nanocomposite Films Incorporated with Oxidized Carbon Nano-Onions (Multi-Layer Fullerenes) for Tissue-Engineering Applications" shortTile="preparation-chitosanpolyvinyl" author="Carlos  David Grande Tovar, Jorge  Iván Castro, Carlos  Humberto Valencia, Diana  Paola Navia Porras, José  Herminsul Mina Hernandez, Mayra  Eliana Valencia, José  Daniel Velásquez, Manuel  N. Chaur" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2218-273X/9/11/684/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Designed scaffolds should be biocompatible and biodegradable, capable of producing an extracellular matrix (ECM) by supporting the cell’s adhesion and proliferation. They should also have porosity to promote nutrient transportation, and their mechanical properties should be similar to native tissue. To meet these requirements, a high surface area and an interconnected three-dimensional (3D) porous structure with sizes ranging between 200 and 600 μm are essential, while also providing nutrient transfer, waste disposal, cellular infiltration, neovascularization, and cell proliferation. </p>

<p>Natural polymers are preferred materials for producing scaffolds, due to their better overall interactions with various cell types, and their lack of toxicity. However, synthetic polymers are cheaper and allow chemical functionalization to assist cell adhesion despite the immune response. The preferred synthetic polymers used for scaffold synthesis include poly(l-lactic acid) (PLLA), poly(glycolic acid) (PGA), poly(caprolactone) (PCL), and poly(lactic-<hi rend="italic">co</hi>-glycolic) acid (PLGA). Composites with natural polymers are also available with better hydrophilicity, cell attachment, and biodegradability. The most used biopolymers are chitosan, alginate (Alg), collagen (Col), gelatin (Gn), silk fibroin (SF), and glycosaminoglycans (GAGs). </p>

<p>Chitosan (CS), a natural polymer obtained from the partial deacetylation of chitin, is one of the most common biopolymers on earth. It is present in the shells of crustaceans such as crab and shrimp. CS has many desirable properties for tissue engineering such as biocompatibility, non-toxicity, and biodegradability. CS was used in several tissue-engineering applications involving bone, cartilage, liver, tendons, ligaments and nerves, wound healing, separation membranes, blood anticoagulants, contact lenses, controlled release of drugs, fat-sequestering agent, hydrogel preparations, and food packaging material. CS was evaluated for bone tissue engineering (BTE) with good cell adhesion and proliferation observed. CS composites with different materials such as ceramics, nanofillers, and polymers were evaluated for BTE with excellent biocompatibility and cell proliferation results. It was recognized that amine and hydroxyl groups facilitate the addition of side groups for cell incorporation and recognition in BTE. However, like many other polysaccharides, it presents some disadvantages such as poor mechanical properties, poor solubility in conventional solvents, and poor stability in physiological media due to the high amount of hydrogen bonding. </p>

<p>Many studies addressed the physicochemical attributes of nanocomposite polymers thanks to their effectiveness in overcoming the disadvantages of naturally occurring polymers. Our group investigated the use of nanocomposites based on graphene oxide and chitosan for applications in tissue engineering. Even with the nanofillers, there is still a need to achieve better mechanical and thermal stability combined with higher biocompatibility in nanocomposites of chitosan and carbon nanomaterials. </p>

<p>Carbon nano-onions (CNOs) are multi-shell fullerenes of 5 to 10 nm, discovered by Ugarte in 1992 upon impacting carbon nanostructures with an electron beam through a TEM experiment. For the chemical derivatization of CNOs, various synthetic routes were applied, introducing new functional groups that increase their application possibilities. Some potential uses include optical applications, catalysis, and gas storage. CNOs are also useful in photovoltaic and fuel cell applications. They demonstrated a superior lubrication ability compared to conventional lubricants.  </p>

<p>However, there are few reports of CS and CNO composites in the literature. The electrochemical properties of composites consisting of CNOs and poly(diallyl dimethylammonium chloride) (PDDA) or chitosan (CS) were reported. The lack of literature regarding nanocomposites of CS and oxidized (ox-)CNOs for biomedical applications is evident. Very few studies were carried out to determine the cytotoxicity of CNOs. They were even used for the treatment of cancer; however, many more studies are still required to show whether they are toxic or if, on the contrary, they promote cell adhesion and proliferation, while facilitating the recognition and permanence of scaffolds in animal tissues without immune responses. There is a lack of information on their characterization including the physical, chemical, and mechanical evaluation of nanocomposite films based on CS/poly(vinyl alcohol) (PVA)/ox-CNO, together with biological tests in vitro and in vivo. The results of this investigation will allow collecting toxicological information for these nanocomposites, as well as evaluating their possible application in tissue engineering. Therefore, this research investigates nanocomposite films of PVA/CS reinforced with ox-CNOs for biocompatibility studies at 90 days of subdermal implantation in biomodel skin.  </p>
</text>
