<text id="autogum_academic_doc464" title="Differential Cell Lysis Among Periodontal Strains of JP2 and Non-JP2 Genotype of Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans Serotype B Is Not Reflected in Dissimilar Expression and Production of Leukotoxin" shortTile="differential-cell" author="Anne  Birkeholm Jensen, Marianne Lund, Niels Nørskov-Lauritsen, Anders Johansson, Rolf Claesson, Jesper Reinholdt, Dorte Haubek" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-0817/8/4/211/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans</hi> is a Gram-negative member of the human oral microbiota and is involved in human infections and diseases. One of these diseases is periodontitis, characterized by destruction of tooth-supporting periodontal tissues due to an inflammatory response. <hi rend="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</hi> possesses several virulence factors, of which the production of the RTX (repeats-in-toxin) leukotoxin (LtxA) has received much attention. LtxA induces cell lysis, degranulation and an inflammatory response in human leukocytes by interaction with the β2-integrins in the cell membrane of human immune cells. A 530-bp deletion in the promoter region of the LtxA gene operon was identified in the original JP2 strain, cultured from a young individual diagnosed with juvenile periodontitis. This discovery marked the beginning of an era, where the detection of the 530-bp deletion categorized highly leukotoxic <hi rend="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</hi> strains as a member of the JP2 clone of <hi rend="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</hi>, possessing enhanced virulence. Based on in vitro studies, it was reported that the JP2 genotype of <hi rend="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</hi> has a 10–20 fold higher lytic activity than the non-JP2 genotypes of <hi rend="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</hi>. Furthermore, longitudinal clinical studies reported a clear correlation between being carrier of the JP2 genotype of <hi rend="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</hi> and having an increased risk of developing periodontitis at a young age. </p>

<p>Often the leukotoxic potential of <hi rend="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</hi> is characterized by the leukotoxicity in in vitro studies. This leukotoxicity is determined by use of cell lysis assays, where human immune cells are exposed either to the bacteria or to purified LtxA, and most often the leukotoxicity is correlated with the JP2 or non-JP2 genotype of the <hi rend="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</hi> strain. Therefore, it has been the common believe that the leukotoxicity of an <hi rend="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</hi> strain could be explained by the 530-bp deletion, an explanation supported by recent results presented by Sampathkumar and co-workers. However, <hi rend="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</hi> strains without the 530-bp deletion with high leukotoxicity according to results obtained by cell lysis assay have been reported on. Furthermore, the leukotoxic potential of <hi rend="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</hi> strains has been explained by different mechanisms. A higher expression of the mRNA, encoding the <hi rend="italic">ltxA,</hi> has been reported to correspond with a higher leukotoxic potential, but also a variation in the activity of LtxA in some <hi rend="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</hi> has been reported. Only a few studies have compared the leukotoxicity of <hi rend="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</hi> with the LtxA expression and production defined as a quantification of the LtxA, e.g., by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA), or mRNA coding for LtxA, but it seems reasonable to assume that the two factors are related. </p>

<p>In the present study, we aimed to investigate if the leukotoxicity of a collection of Ghanaian <hi rend="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</hi>, serotype b, is related to the LtxA production of the strains determined by Western blotting and ELISA, and LtxA expression as determined in a mRNA expression assay. Furthermore, we wanted to compare the results obtained by ELISA and mRNA expression assay to elucidate the relationship between the two quantification methods used to determine leukotoxic potential as the LtxA production and expression of <hi rend="italic">A. actinomycetemcomitans</hi>, respectively. </p>
</text>
