<text id="autogum_academic_doc684" title="Sequential Disaster Forensics: A Case Study on Direct and Socio-Economic Impacts" shortTile="sequential-disaster" author="Marina  T. Mendoza, Reimund Schwarze" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5898/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Materials and Methods</head>
<p>
This research follows the case study concept of disaster forensics methodology, i.e., a combination of methods and findings from different disciplines with the aim of describing and reconstructing disasters and their relevant drivers as comprehensively as possible. The approach considers the complexity of loss events and the risk of natural catastrophes with multiple interactions and triggers in natural and socio-economic systems.  </p>

<p>Concerning the data for performing a disaster forensic investigation, this case study makes use of many different data categories. These include data on the risk factors, damage data, data on prevention measures, data on the response, and data on recovery processes. Data on the risk factors include data on the hazard (e.g., flood characteristics), the exposure (elements inside the flood-prone area), and the vulnerability of the exposed objects. Damage data comprise data on different damages and impacts associated with the flood event. Data on prevention measures include all the data related to the measures taken during the prevention phase to mitigate flood risk. Data on the response process concerns data on the activities performed during the emergency period, such as the emergency measures taken at the household level. Data on the recovery process refers to data on the recovery and reconstruction phase, for instance on damage compensation and reconstruction time. </p>

<p>We are recurring to a large variety of sources of evidence. They include documents of different kinds, archival records, interviews from past projects, satellite imagery and maps. Consulted documents include peer-reviewed papers, reports, master theses, urban plans and newspaper articles. The collected archival records regard data on the population from the municipal registry of residents of Grimma. Flood damage and other related data of the residential sector from the 2002 and 2013 flood events were provided by the University of Potsdam, the German Research Centre for Geosciences, and Deutsche Rückversicherung. These data were collected through computer-aided interviews (CATI) among households in the flooded area in the aftermaths of both the 2002 and the 2013 floods as explained by Thieken et al.. The questionnaires contained around 180 question, addressing multiple topics including flood characteristics, flood warning, emergency measures, damage to building, compensation, and prevention measures. </p>

<p>Regarding data analysis, the starting point is the disaster forensics methods previously mentioned. Specifically, the requirement of a holistic disaster forensic methodology that makes use of disaster damage data collected ex-post. In the case of floods, this means that the data under consideration are collected after the flood event, through damage assessments done at the end of the emergency, and/or in the recovery period. For example, Menoni et al. developed a post-flood damage assessment model that supports a more integrated interpretation of flood events for a variety of purposes, including forensic investigation. </p>

<p>Table 1 presents an overview of the existing approaches in Disaster Forensics, as mentioned in Section 1. CEDIM proposes a forensic analysis of disasters in “near real-time,” delivering results hours to days after the disaster event. This approach makes use of different kinds of data that are available almost in real-time, from the very first moments when the disaster unfolds and the emergency phase (e.g., data from social media, GPS and sensors data, meteorological data, etc.) Our work instead is developed long after the occurrence of the disaster, using mostly data collected ex-post. </p>

<p>The forensic framework and tool proposed by the DKKV rests on expert interviews and on synthesizing and combining them with previous analyses to create a comprehensive overview of the disaster. The tool, therefore, does not directly employ post-event damage data.  </p>

<p>FORIN suggests the “comparative case analysis” as a forensic research approach: a limited amount of detailed studies of “comparative” disasters. These disasters can either have similar characteristics in terms of the hazard and different locations, or the same location, involving the same or other kind of hazard. This last type of comparative analysis is “in-situ” and is particularly suitable for the forensic investigation of Grimma’s repeated floods.  </p>

<p>The PERC methodology has been applied mostly to study flood events. The analysis is based on data gathered from a desk review and on informal and semi-structured interviews from fieldwork, and it is organized around the disaster risk reduction and management cycle. The final product of the PERC process is a structured report, which also acts as guidance to conduct the investigation.  </p>

<p>The approach for the forensic investigation in this research is inspired by FORIN’s comparative case analysis “in situ” and by PERC. Specifically, the approach consists of a detailed study of repeated hazard events in the same location, while the PERC report was followed as guidance for determining the different aspects and factors that required investigation.  </p>
</text>
