<text id="autogum_academic_doc001" title="Gas Separation Silica Membranes Prepared by Chemical Vapor Deposition of Methyl-Substituted Silanes" shortTile="gas-separation-silica" author="Harumi Kato, Sean-Thomas  B. Lundin, So-Jin Ahn, Atsushi Takagaki, Ryuji Kikuchi, S.  Ted Oyama" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0375/9/11/144/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Silica membranes are an attractive emerging gas separation technology because of advantages over palladium membranes such as chemical resistance, stability, and low cost. Additionally, silica membranes exhibit high perm-selectivity at high temperature and a tunable morphology that can be modified for a variety of gas separations such as CO2/CH4. Silica and silica-containing membranes were studied for use in membrane reactors and are beginning to be applied industrially in gas separation systems. A drawback of silica membranes is their poor hydrothermal stability, which is detrimental in industrial applications with steam, such as pervaporation of aqueous mixtures and hydrogen production by steam reforming. </p>

<p>To improve the hydrothermal stability of silica membranes, various silicon compounds with different functional groups were studied such as silanes containing organic functional groups (methyl, propyl, hexyl, phenyl, and vinyl) attached directly to a single silicon atom, and alkoxy siloxanes bridged with ≡Si–R–Si≡ structures (e.g., bis(triethoxysilyl)ethane). However, there were few reports focused on the number of the functional groups in a silicon compound. </p>

<p>One functional group that was studied is the addition of phenyl groups, such as dimethoxydiphenylsilane. Ohta et al. and Zhang et al., for example, developed silica membranes deposited with silicon compounds containing zero, one, two, or three phenyl groups. Notably, the increasing number of phenyl groups was correlated with an increase in the estimated pore size in the membrane, increasing from ca. 0.3 nm for the tetraethyl orthosilicate-derived membrane to ca. 0.49 nm for the membrane derived from methoxy(triphenyl)silane. This increase in pore size has the potential to increase H2 permeance while maintaining high selectivity toward larger organic species such as methylcyclohexane (kinetic diameter: 0.60 nm) and toluene (0.59 nm). </p>

<p>Nomura et al. studied methyl groups in silicon compounds and developed silica membranes deposited with five kinds of silica precursors including tetramethyl orthosilicate (TMOS), methyltrimethoxysilane (MTMOS), dimethyldimethoxysilane (DMDMOS), and trimethylmethoxy-silane (TMMOS) using the chemical vapor deposition (CVD) method, in which oxygen was added to the synthesis mixture. In that work, with increasing number of methyl groups in the silica precursor, the H2 permeance reached a maximum of 9.0 × 10−7 mol∙m−2∙s−1∙Pa−1 at 600 °C using DMDMOS, but then declined for TMMOS. The activation energies calculated from Arrhenius plots were 10 kJ∙mol−1 for TMOS, 9.3 kJ∙mol−1 for MTMOS, 7.9 kJ∙mol−1 for DMDMOS, and 3.9 kJ∙mol−1 for TMMOS. The authors claimed that the deposition mechanism of TMMOS appeared to be different from that of TMOS or DMDMOS. Finally, they concluded that the TMOS-derived membrane was the best among the five membranes because of the smooth membrane surface, the dense silica, and the lowest activation energy for H2 permeation. </p>

<p>The main objective of this study is to determine the effect of the number of methyl groups in a silica precursor on the synthesized membrane properties. The work here builds upon the previous research of Nomura et al. by conducting CVD under different conditions than those used previously, and uses additional characterization techniques, such as Fourier-transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR), to probe deeper into the microstructure of these silica membranes. In this study, membrane features such as the surface morphology, the presence of surface functional groups, and the silica matrix structure were studied. Furthermore, the gas permeation properties were investigated for various gas species not tested by Nomura et al., and all results were fitted to known gas diffusion mechanisms in an effort to gain insight into the mechanism of transport across a wide array of gas species. Before comparison between the silica precursors, adjustments in the deposition conditions were carried out in order to develop defect-free membranes. </p>
</text>
