<text id="autogum_academic_doc641" title="Small Bowel—Key Player in Health and Disease" shortTile="small-bowelkey-player" author="Wojciech Marlicz, Anastasios Koulaouzidis" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/10/1748/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>
Over the last two decades, remarkable progress has been made in understanding the etiology and pathophysiology of diseases. New discoveries emphasize the importance of the small bowel (SB) ‘ecosystem’ in the pathogenesis of acute and chronic illness alike. Emerging factors, such as microbiome, stem and progenitor cells, innate intestinal immunity, and the enteric nervous system, along with mucosal and endothelial barriers, play a key role in the development of gastrointestinal (GI) and extra-GI diseases. The results of other studies point also towards a link between the digestive tract and common non-communicable diseases, such as obesity and cancer. These discoveries unravel novel dimensions of uncertainty in the area of clinical decision-making motivating researchers to search for novel diagnostic and therapeutic solutions.  </p>

<p>Recent studies unravel the role of the poorly-understood complexity of the SB. Insights into its critical physiologic and pathophysiologic role in metabolic homeostasis and its potential role as a driver of obesity, insulin resistance, and subsequent type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) have been revealed. For example, bypassing the proximal small intestine by means of bariatric surgery results in a significant metabolic benefit to an individual undergoing such a procedure. Moreover, endoscopic procedures aimed at placing devices separating luminal contents from the duodenal mucosa result in modest weight loss and improvement in glucose homeostasis.  </p>

<p>Another endoscopic treatment which aims at resurfacing duodenal mucosa (DMR, duodenal mucosal resurfacing), leads to improvement in glycemia and insulin resistance in patients with T2DM. It is not surprising when we recall that SB endocrine cells secrete glycemia-regulating incretin hormones (e.g., glucagon-like peptide, GLP-1), and this process is dependent on food content in the intestinal lumen. Moreover, bile acids with various targets in the liver and small intestine (e.g., farnesoid receptor, FXR) together with a plethora of other small signaling molecules act in concert in regulating metabolic and digestive GI function. </p>

<p>The human digestive tract and enteric nervous system (ENS) communicate with the central nervous system (CNS) through the gut-brain axis (GBA). This bidirectional communication involves diverse neural networks through the X cranial vagal nerve—dorsal roots of the sympathetic/ parasympathetic nervous system. Important roles in the regulation of the gut-brain axis are played by: (i) the hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal axis (HPA), (ii) the stress hormones (cortisol), (iii) the short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs), and (iv) the gut microbiota. The intestinal barrier, another important part of GBA, is composed of: (i) goblet cells derived mucus, (ii) microbiota, (iii) epithelial cells, (iv) endothelial cells, (v) lymphatic vessels, and v) enterocytes’ tight cellular junctions. Of interest, the structure and function of the intestinal barrier resemble that of the blood-brain barrier (BBB). The gut-brain communication is mediated via blood, portal/hepatic circulation, and the bone marrow.  </p>

<p>Recently, it has been described that the alterations of the intestinal barrier play a crucial role in the pathology of several human inflammatory and autoimmune diseases. Mohanan et al. documented the crucial role of the C1orf106 inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) susceptibility gene in stabilizing intestinal barrier function and intestinal inflammation. Manfredo Vieira et al. evidenced the role of pathobionts in the process of intestinal barrier alterations, which were followed by their translocation to lymph nodes and the hepatic portal system, triggering systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE). Thaiss et al. reported that hyperglycemia leads to disruption of the intestinal barrier followed by intestinal inflammation and systemic infection. Spadoni et al. recently documented that the presence of the gut-vascular barrier (GVB) in the small intestine controls the dissemination of bacteria into the bloodstream. The authors reported a decrease of the wnt/beta catenin-inducible gene Axin2 (a marker of stem cell renewal) in gut endothelium under the presence of <hi rend="italic">Salmonella typhimirum</hi> in the SB. The GVB was modified in patients with coeliac disease (CD) with altered serum transaminases, which suggests that GVB deterioration may be responsible for liver damage in CD patients. It has been shown that disruption of epithelial and vascular barriers in the intestine were early events in non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH), and GVB leakage marker could be identified in colonic biopsies in patients with NASH. Of importance, SB epithelial and vascular barriers are FXR-controlled, which opens avenues to clinical trials aimed at investigation of novel FXR-agonists as future therapeutics. Of interest, intestinal barriers could be monitored in vivo with the aid of confocal laser endomicroscopy (CLE).  </p>

<p>Therefore, the SB is considered a key player in metabolic disease development, including diabetes mellitus and NASH, and other diet-related disorders such as coeliac and non-coeliac enteropathies. Another major field is drug metabolism and its interaction with small bowel microbiome. Moreover, the emergence of gut-brain, gut-liver, and gut-blood barriers point towards the important role of the SB in the pathogenesis of previously unthought and GI-unrelated conditions such as neurodegenerative and cardiovascular disease. The SB remains an organ that is difficult to fully access and assess and accurate diagnosis often poses a clinical challenge. Undoubtedly, the therapeutic potential remains untapped. Therefore, it is now time to direct more of our interest towards the SB and unravel the interplay between the SB and other GI and non-GI related diseases.  </p>
</text>
