<text id="autogum_academic_doc462" title="Deconvolution of the Genomic and Epigenomic Interaction Landscape of Triple-Negative Breast Cancer" shortTile="deconvolution-genomic" author="Jiande Wu, Tarun  Karthik Kumar Mamidi, Lu Zhang, Chindo Hicks" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6694/11/11/1692/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC) is a heterogeneous disease, characterized by aggressive clinical behavior, poor prognosis, a significantly increased risk of relapse, and shorter survival rates than patients affected by other molecular subtypes of breast cancer. TNBC is clinically defined as tumors that lack expression of the estrogen receptor (ER), progesterone receptor (PR), and HER2 amplification. It affects primarily younger premenopausal women and tends to have higher incidences in African American women, although recent studies reported no differences in clinical outcomes between Caucasian and African American women after adjusting for socioeconomic factors. Currently, there are no effective targeted therapies. Cytotoxic chemotherapy remains the only effective therapeutic modality for this aggressive and often lethal type of breast cancer. Therefore, there is an urgent need for the discovery of molecular markers and targets for the development of novel targeted therapeutics.  </p>

<p>Our understanding of the molecular basis of TNBC and development of effective targeted therapies has been hampered by the complexity and multifactorial etiology of the disease. Genes play a major role in the pathogenesis of TNBC. The majority of TNBC patients carry mutations in the highly penetrant cancer susceptibility genes BRCA1 and BRCA2. In unselected TNBC cases, the prevalence of pathogenic germline <hi rend="italic">BRCA1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">BRCA2</hi> mutations is approximately twice as high as in breast cancer overall. Apart from <hi rend="italic">BRCA1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">BRCA2</hi>, the rarely mutated breast cancer predisposition genes <hi rend="italic">PALB2</hi> and <hi rend="italic">FANCM</hi> have been associated with TNBC. Multigene panel testing has also identified genes with high and moderate penetrance associated with an increased risk of developing TNBC. However, although genes may play a strong role, molecular epidemiology studies suggest that TNBC risk is largely determined by interactions between genes and environment. Increased attention has focused on epigenetic variation such as DNA methylation and TNBC because enduring epigenetic landmarks define the tumor microenvironment. Moreover, because DNA methylation regulates gene expression, aberrant methylated genes could serve as complementary diagnostic tools, prognostic markers and predictors of response to treatment. Thus, a critical knowledge gap, and an unmet medical need, is understanding the interplay between genetic (both germline and somatic) variation and epigenomic variation in TNBC. </p>

<p>Advances in microarray technology have enabled molecular classification of subtypes of TNBC. At least, several clinically validated prognostic assays including the Prosigna PAM50, MammaPrint and Oncotype DX, have been developed using transcription profiling. However, although these primary analyses have been successful in identifying prognostic markers, they have been unsuccessful in establishing the causal association between gene expression and the disease. High-throughput genotyping using genome-wide association studies (GWAS) has enabled discovery of genetic variants associated with an increased risk of developing TNBC. The recent surge of next generation sequencing of tumor genomes by large multicenter projects, such as The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) and the International Cancer Genome Consortium (ICGC), have generated comprehensive catalogues of somatic mutations associated with TNBC. The clonal and mutational spectrum of primary TNBCs have also been characterized. We recently reported oncogenic interactions between genes containing germline and somatic mutations in TNBC. </p>

<p>However, to date, information on germline, somatic and gene expression variation has not been leveraged and integrated with DNA methylation data to map the interplay between genetic and epigenetic variation in TNBC. This limited progress must be balanced against the recognition that genomic and epigenomic alterations have long been considered as two separate molecular mechanisms participating in TNBC pathogenesis. The objective of this investigation is to deconvolute the genomic and epigenomic interaction landscape, and to discover and characterize the molecular networks and signaling pathways perturbed by these interactions in TNBC. Our working hypothesis was that TNBC originates from a complex interplay between genomic (both germline and somatic) variation and epigenomic variations. We further hypothesized that these complex arrays of interacting genomic and epigenomic factors affect entire molecular networks and signaling pathways which, in turn, drive TNBC. We addressed these hypotheses by integrating information on germline variation from GWAS with information on somatic and epigenomic variation from TCGA using gene expression as the intermediated phenotype. </p>
</text>
