<text id="autogum_academic_doc619" title="Serum Level and Activity of Butylcholinesterase: A Biomarker for Post-Stroke Dementia" shortTile="serum-level-activity" author="Yi-Chun Chen, Wen-Hai Chou, Chiu-Ping Fang, Tung-Hsia Liu, Hsiao-Hui Tsou, Yun Wang, Yu-Li Liu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/11/1778/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Stroke is a major cause of dementia, especially in the elderly. Specifically, the one-year post-stroke dementia (PSD) rates after first-ever and recurrent stroke are approximately 10% and 30%, respectively. Neuropathological studies into Alzheimer’s disease (AD) have shown that AD pathology is often concomitant with ischemic lesions in the elderly. For instance, evidence from the Nun Study showed that lacunes increase the risk of clinical expression of cognitive impairment more than 20 times during early Braak stages that were yet sufficient to produce dementia symptoms. It follows that vascular insults enhance the clinical expression of AD pathology. Vascular dementia is more prevalent in men and in populations affected by cerebral small-vessel disease, including Asians, Hispanics, and Africans. </p>

<p>The cholinergic system is distributed throughout the central nervous system, playing a role in neurotransmission and possibly mediating various neuroprotective functions. Furthermore, cholinergic neurotransmission regulates the immune response during inflammation, in a pathway that involves nicotinic acetylcholine receptors (nAChRs) and inhibits peripheral cytokine release. In particular, the efferent vagus nerve may release acetylcholine (Ach), which subsequently binds with macrophage receptors and therefore may inhibit the release of inflammatory factors after stroke. In addition to inflammation, excitotoxicity and energy failure following cerebral ischemia may also initiate intracellular death pathways and oxidative stress (OS). The structural and functional changes caused by OS led to cholinergic and other cellular damage. Cholinergic deficit further caused brain atrophy and finally resulted in cognitive impairment. Anticholinergic agents have been shown to regulate OS and alleviate apoptosis. Therefore, a key role in the pathogenesis of stroke and dementia may be attributed to OS. </p>

<p>Cholinergic dysfunction is related to vascular dementia. Specifically, Ach levels in the cerebrospinal fluid are up to 49% lower in patients with small-vessel vascular dementia than in control patients, suggesting that cholinergic agents or cholinesterase inhibitors, both of which increase the Ach level, could be used to treat such patients. One pilot study showed that acetylcholinesterase (AChE) inhibitor promoted functional recovery in elderly patients with cognitive impairment who had suffered stroke. In a rat model of chronic ischemic, AChE activity was slightly decreased in the frontal cortex, but muscarinic acetylcholine receptor M1 was gradually depleted in cerebral cortex, striatum and hippocampus that are involved in cognitive function. In addition, in stroke patients, reduced AChE activity was correlated with lower survival rate. Taken together, these results suggest that AChE dysfunction is a result of stroke rather than a cause for further neurodegeneration. Moreover, AChE inhibitors exert no effect on stroke risk in dementia patients. These observations suggest that Ach and AChE function may predict post-stroke neuronal damage. To date, only a few blood biomarkers for predicting PSD have been examined (e.g., D-amino acid oxidase, β-secretase, and inflammation markers), and few studies have focused on changes in blood cholinesterase (ChE) levels and activity in patients with PSD. Since plasma Ach is metabolized by AChE and butylcholinesterase (BChE), the present study examined the functional activities of these two enzymes in a population of patients with chronic ischemic stroke (IS). </p>
</text>
