<text id="autogum_academic_doc003" title="Coupled Response of Membrane Hydration with Oscillating Metabolism in Live Cells: An Alternative Way to Modulate Structural Aspects of Biological Membranes?" shortTile="coupled-response" author="Luis  A. Bagatolli, Roberto  P. Stock, Lars  F. Olsen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2218-273X/9/11/687/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Background</head>
<p>
In the last five years, we have studied distinct physicochemical aspects of a well-known biological oscillator, namely, oscillating glycolysis, in the yeast <hi rend="italic">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</hi>. When these cells are starved and respiration is blocked, they will use externally added glucose in such a way that the chemical activity of essential central metabolites such as reduced Nicotinamide Adenine dinucleotide (NADH) and Adenosine Triphosphate (ATP) will follow a well-established temporal waveform. This remarkable oscillatory behavior was discovered over 60 years ago and has been studied intensely in both intact cells and cell extracts. While the circumstances under which glycolytic oscillations take place are documented and the enzymes and participating biochemical reactions have been characterized, an adequate explanatory framework remains unspecified: why glycolytic oscillations arise and what they reveal about the complex relationship between the various levels of the description of life processes are questions still awaiting definite answers. </p>

<p>The classical approach to comprehend why glycolysis oscillates envisages the pathway largely in isolation from the rest of the cell. Particularly, it considers the intracellular environment as an isotropic aqueous solution where enzymes and metabolites react and diffuse according to principles of mass action kinetics and dilute solution theory (van’t Hoff). Although this interpretation exerts a robust influence on the way we currently grasp and think about biological systems, it has been repeatedly challenged when consideration is given to well-accepted (although largely ignored) features of the cellular milieu such as molecular crowding and spatial confinement that are likely to strongly influence the way that the cellular machinery operates. In this respect, it is important to underscore the strong influence of these environmental features on the most abundant component of biological systems (i.e., water). Due to the high concentration of macromolecules, estimated to be around 200–350 mg/mL, the cell interior is a very crowded environment. Therefore, it is unlikely that it will share properties of dilute solutions where enzymes are generally characterized; in fact, it is becoming increasingly evident that intracellular water is affected by such a high concentration of solutes and that its behavior significantly deviates from tractable ideality. Furthermore, water in the cell is not just a passive medium where reactions occur, but an active participant (e.g., many cellular reactions are condensations that produce water, or hydrolytic ones that consume it). Water also participates as a key thermodynamically active structural component of lipid membranes, playing an important role in their topology and function. However, <hi rend="italic">the role of water as an active component</hi> is seldom acknowledged in the current models describing the cell and, as a consequence, in those defining biological membranes. Finally, it is important to remark that there is still an unresolved debate about the state of water in intact cells. While some suggest that most intracellular water is in a state akin to dilute solutions, others claim that it exists in a H-bonded polymer-based gel-like state. </p>

<p>In a series of papers, we reported a number of key observations that challenge some basic tenets of the established view of cellular systems. Particularly, we observed that during glycolytic oscillations, the extent of dipolar relaxation in the cellular interior, which is governed mainly by the rotational dynamics of intracellular water, is coupled to the behavior of the pathway (intervening metabolites such as ATP and NADH) in that it oscillates synchronously. We showed that this coupling is obliterated by inhibiting ATP production and that it depends on a functional actin network. We also found that intracellular water relaxation is a crucial parameter for the manifestation of glycolytic oscillations (e.g., oscillations occur only within a defined range of relaxation values), and this parameter emerges as an intensive property of the system (i.e., it is scale independent). These observations call into question the idea that intracellular water acts as a mere passive biological solvent, as implicitly understood in the standard membrane-based model of the cell. In a subsequent study, we observed that cell volume, heat flux, and temperature also oscillated synchronously with glycolytic oscillations, showing a strong coupling of these physical properties with the biochemical pathway. These results were consistent with a recently proposed thermodynamic formalism where isentropic thermodynamic systems can display coupled oscillations in all extensive and intensive variables, reminiscent of adiabatic waves. This approximation suggests that glycolytic oscillations may arise as a consequence of a living cell’s requirement for a near constant low-entropy state while remaining metabolically active, in contrast to the prevailing notion that metabolic processes have to be understood as essentially dissipative (i.e., in terms of steady state energetics).  </p>
</text>
