<text id="autogum_academic_doc016" title="Understanding the Interactions between Biomass, Grain Production and Grain Protein Content in High and Low Protein Wheat Genotypes under Controlled Environments" shortTile="understanding-interactions" author="Vahid Rahimi Eichi, Mamoru Okamato, Stephan  M. Haefele, Nathaniel Jewell, Chris Brien, Trevor Garnett, Peter Langridge" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4395/9/11/706/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head><head> 4.1. Biomass Can Indicate the Impact of Nitrogen on Grain Weight</head>
<p>
As noted in previous studies, the strong correlation between above-ground biomass and grain weight (<figure>Figure 5</figure>A) showed that biomass can be used as an indicator of grain weight responses to N in the six wheat genotypes evaluated in this experiment. The relationship between above-ground biomass and grain weight is likely to be due to the positive correlation between leaf surface area and total photosynthesis per unit ground area. Previous studies using destructive methods also showed a strong relationship between biomass and grain weight in both hard and soft wheat genotypes. </p>

<p>The high positive correlation between above-ground biomass and grain weight (<figure>Figure 5</figure>A) is counteracted by the negative correlation between biomass and grain N% (<figure>Figure 5</figure>B,C). Consequently, increasing grain weight appears to result in a grain N% penalty, particularly at low N. The reduction in grain N% with increasing grain weight may reflect the high priority placed on elevating grain weight by wheat breeders rather than grain N% accumulation under low N conditions. The results suggest that once the maximum level of grain weight has been achieved, the additional N is invested in increasing grain N%, particularly, for high GPC genotypes. The relatively low grain N% seen for all varieties in this study (<figure>Figure 4</figure>A–C) may be due to the favourable growth conditions in the greenhouse and, consequent, increase in biomass. It appears that the high N requirements of plants seen in this experiment, meant that the applied N at low and medium N was mostly used for grain weight production rather than to increase grain N%. </p>

<head> 4.2. Differences in Nitrogen Responsiveness between High and Low GPC Genotypes</head>
<p>
Spitfire and Mace produced less biomass at low N than the other genotypes and were more responsive at high N compared with the low grain N% genotypes (<figure>Figure 1</figure>A and <figure>Figure 4</figure>G–I). Related studies on wheat and oilseed spring rape indicate that genotypes, which show reduced yield at low N may show greater responses to higher N levels compared to other genotypes. It is shown that high compared to low GPC wheat genotypes require higher N rates to show favourable yield responses. </p>

<p>In accordance with previous studies, reducing N supply diminished the total biomass and growth rate. However, by reducing N inputs, biomass and growth rate declined more in high than in low grain N concentration genotypes. In fact, the biomass of genotypes that were selected for high GPC was more vulnerable to low N in comparison with the biomass of low GPC genotypes (<figure>Figure 1</figure>A, <figure>Figure 2</figure>, and <figure>Figure 4</figure>G–I). The high reduction of biomass growth in high GPC genotypes at low N was previously observed in wheat. In high GPC genotypes, biomass growth under limited N may be reduced in favour of root growth to support N uptake after anthesis. </p>

<p>This study showed that shortening t-maxAGR was the key limiting factor for PSA production for high grain N genotypes (<figure>Figure 6</figure>A). In other words, high N genotypes appear to reach the peak of growth and terminate the vegetative stage earlier in low N than high N-treated plants (<figure>Figure 1</figure>B, <figure>Figure 3</figure> and Table 1). Compressing phenology at low N, which decreases N requirement, has been previously observed in different species. However, the low impact of N shortage on the t-maxAGR and biomass growth of Gazelle and QAL2000 was a new finding in this study. </p>

<p>Our results indicated that the rate of t-maxAGR reduction from high to low N was related to the grain N concentration (Table 1 and <figure>Figure 6</figure>A–C). Spitfire and Mace had higher grain N than Gazelle and QAL2000, and appeared to demand more N to grow their biomass. It might be that high grain N% genotypes sense the low N status early in development and shorten their vegetative growth phase to maintain sufficient N for grain development and filling. Hence, Spitfire responded to low N by reducing growth rate, possibly to conserve N for grains (<figure>Figure 1</figure>B and Table 1). In this context, the grain N% of Spitfire and Mace were not influenced by t-maxAGR at different N treatments (<figure>Figure 7</figure>A,B). Therefore, high grain N% genotypes in this study were able to prevent grain N loss at low N conditions regardless of the variations in the time to maximum absolute growth rate. </p>

<p>Accelerating the life cycle is a typical response of plants to low N. N translocation corresponds with senescence since senescing leaf and stem tissues are an important N source for grains. Therefore, the increase of shoot biomass and carbon assimilation after flowering can compete with grain demand for N. In Gazelle and QAL2000, which are genotypes used for low GPC purposes, low N supply did not trigger accelerated development and a decrease in the time to maxAGR (<figure>Figure 6</figure>C). This suggests that Gazelle and QAL2000 use the available N primarily for biomass production and do not show the conservative strategy used by Spitfire and Mace. </p>
</text>
