<text id="autogum_academic_doc687" title="The Effects of Electricity Production on Industrial Development and Sustainable Economic Growth: A VAR Analysis for BRICS Countries" shortTile="effects-electricity" author="Zhongdong Yu, Wei Liu, Liming Chen, Serkan Eti, Hasan Dinçer, Serhat Yüksel" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5895/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion and Conclusion</head>
<p>
In this study, the effect of electricity production on sustainable economic growth and industrial production is analyzed. In this context, BRICS countries are included in the scope of the review. They are the countries with the highest increase in electricity production in the period of 2000–2018. In the analysis process of this study, three different models were established by using the VAR method. For this purpose, annual data of these variables in the period of 1991–2018 are taken into consideration. </p>

<p>According to the results of the analysis, the increase in electricity production will contribute to the sustainable economic growth in the following period. On the other hand, it is also identified that higher electricity production will have a positive effect on industrial production in the following period. In summary, it is concluded that electricity production has a significant impact on both sustainable economic growth and industrial production for BRICS countries. </p>

<p>As can be seen from the results of this study, electricity generation is vital for both industrial production and sustainable economic growth. Therefore, electricity production needs to be increased especially for BRICS countries. The main reason for this is that they have the status of developing countries. The most important objective for them is to reach the level of developed countries, since economic development, among other factors, can improve population health status. Hence, electricity generation is thought to serve this purpose seriously. Within this framework, it is thought that the most significant duty belongs to the governments in these countries. For example, it would be appropriate to give the necessary incentives for the construction of the dam. For this purpose, it is important to encourage investors with tax advantages, location orientation and financing. By increasing the number of the dams, it can be possible to increase electricity production, which has a positive contribution to sustainable growth. </p>

<p>In addition to these issues, it is also important that these countries turn to alternative energy sources in order to increase electricity production. For instance, renewable energy sources such as solar, wind and geothermal energy have gained importance especially in recent years. These energy alternatives have an inexhaustible structure because they take their resources from nature. On the other hand, these alternative energy sources have no negative impact on the environment. Because of these issues, BRICS countries should turn to renewable energy investments. For this purpose, it is important to provide financial support to investors, such as tax advantage and providing loans. Thus, it will be possible to achieve sustainable electricity production and sustainable economic growth by using renewable energy sources. </p>

<p>It is also recommended that countries should give importance to electricity production. Another important point is that a detailed plan should be designed by the authorities with the aim of using this electricity effectively. This situation is essential especially for developing countries. Because they aim to improve their economies in order to reach the status of a developed economy, they should mainly focus on electricity production and use it effectively. In this study, BRICS countries are selected because they have the highest ratio in electricity production. The most important limitation of this study is the scope because of the data availability problem. However, in future studies, if all necessary data can be provided, different countries or country groups can be considered, such as G7, E7 or European Union.
 </p>
</text>
