<text id="autogum_academic_doc073" title="Kinetics of Whey Protein Glycation Using Dextran and the Dry-Heating Method" shortTile="kinetics-whey-protein" author="Na Li, Abhiram Arunkumar, Mark  R. Etzel" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2304-8158/8/11/528/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Glycation of proteins by the Maillard reaction is a promising food-grade method to modify food proteins. Glycated proteins have improved functional properties in foods such as superior solubility, heat stability, emulsification, foaming, and gelation properties. Glycation of proteins may help people who suffer from food protein allergies by lowering IgE-binding capacity. Glycation uses the first step in the Maillard reaction to create a reversible Schiff-base linkage between the free amino moiety in the protein and the carbonyl moiety in the polysaccharide. The Schiff-base linkage can be created via the dry-heating method or the wet-heating method. In the dry-heating method, an aqueous mixture of the protein and polysaccharide is first dried and then heated for a certain time (2 h to 9 days) at a fixed temperature (60 to 130 °C) and relative humidity (60 to 80%). In the wet-heating method, the aqueous solution is heated for a specific time (2 h to 2 days) at a fixed temperature (60 to 95 °C). </p>

<p>Schiff base formation is a reversible condensation reaction that generates water as a by-product. By Le Chatelier’s principle, the presence of water in the reaction mixture drives the reaction in reverse, lowering yield. For example, the yield of glycation using the wet method is low (&lt;5%). Subsequently yield was increased to 18% using a reaction time of 24 h at 60 °C. The dry-heating method uses a desiccator to remove water generated by the condensation reaction, shifting the chemical equilibrium towards product formation, which increases yield. For example, whey protein-maltodextrin powders heated for 2 h at 80 °C in a desiccator at 79% relative humidity formed substantial amounts of glycates with little un-glycated protein remaining in the reaction mixture. </p>

<p>The purpose of the present study was to measure the time course and equilibrium yield of the glycation reaction between dextran and whey protein isolate (WPI) or glycomacropeptide (GMP) using the dry-heating method. The reaction between polysaccharides and proteins via the Maillard reaction is different from the reaction between simple sugars and proteins. In either case, the Maillard reaction pathway starts with the formation of a Schiff base between the free amino moiety in the protein and the carbonyl moiety in the carbohydrate. For simple sugars the Schiff base undergoes spontaneous rearrangement to either an Amadori or Heyn’s compound. Protein-polysaccharide glycation products are not subject to post-Amadori–Maillard reaction steps. The Maillard reaction stops at Schiff base formation. The protein-polysaccharide product is colorless and has no odor. It was not the purpose of the present work to explore the sequence of elementary chemical reactions that make up the Maillard reaction pathway by using the tools of chemical kinetics. Rather, the present work was aimed at measuring the time course and equilibrium yield of the glycate formation reaction and extracting apparent rate constants using a simple mathematical model and a fitting procedure. </p>

<p>In order to determine the time course and equilibrium yield, a quantitative method was required to measure the concentration of reactants (un-glycated protein and dextran) and products (glycated protein) versus time. We used a new method for the chromatographic analysis of whey protein-dextran glycation products and a complementary fluorescence laser densitometry method for this purpose. The present work is important because producing glycates quickly and in high yield is essential for delivering on the potential benefits of this new food-grade method for protein modification. </p>
</text>
