<text id="autogum_academic_doc629" title="Influence of Immunogenetic Biomarkers in the Clinical Outcome of HTLV-1 Infected Persons" shortTile="influence-immunogenetic" author="Antonio  Carlos Rosário Vallinoto, Izaura Cayres-Vallinoto, Maria  Alice Freitas Queiroz, Marluísa  de Oliveira Guimarães Ishak, Ricardo Ishak" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4915/11/11/974/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Human T-lymphotropic virus 1 (HTLV-1) is a <hi rend="italic">Deltaretrovirus</hi>, endemic in Japan, Caribbean, South America, Sub-Saharan Africa, and Melanesia. </p>

<p>HTLV-1 is associated with several different types of diseases. Adult T-cell leukemia/lymphoma (ATLL) develops in up to 5% of infected people, and sometimes a chronic neurodegenerative inflammatory disease called HTLV-1-associated myelopathy (HAM) develops. Although a high percentage of people remain asymptomatic during their lifetime, a great number of infected people develop a large range of neurological diseases. Other opportunistic-like infections, such as Strongyloidiasis, Norwegian scabies, infective dermatitis, as well as autoimmune syndromes, including rheumatoid arthritis and Sjögren’s syndrome, have also been described among HTLV-1 carriers. In these patients, the clinical conditions appear to be the result of the interaction between the virus and the host susceptibility, leading to the abnormal functioning of immuno-modulatory mechanisms, cell proliferation, and inflammation. </p>

<p>HAM is a chronic progressive demyelinating disease that affects the spinal cord and the white matter of the brain, leading to a severe clinical syndrome due to the motor limitations that affect the lower limbs associated with the autonomic dysfunction. The clinical picture begins and evolves insidiously, being difficult to establish when the first symptoms appeared. The main signs and symptoms of HAM may include gait disturbance, weakness, and stiffness of the lower limbs. The first manifestations of the disease occur in the fourth decade of life and there is a 2:1 woman/man ratio. The incubation period differs from patient to patient and seems to be shorter in the cases where the virus was acquired through blood transfusion. </p>

<p>Two important aspects of HAM development have been reported, including the efficiency of the cellular immune response and the rate of spontaneous expression of the viral antigen, due to the numerous immunological alterations, mediated mainly by the expression of Tax (regulatory protein of the virus) in the peripheral blood and in the cerebrospinal fluid of patients with HAM. </p>

<p>In order to control HTLV-1 replication and the proliferation of infected cells, CD8+ T lymphocytes mediate the main defense strategy of the host immune system. HTLV-1 infects mainly CD4+ T cells, which are the central regulators of the acquired immune response, deregulating the host immune system. To establish persistent infection, HTLV-1 deregulates CD4+ T cells, sometimes leading to ATLL or to chronic inflammatory diseases, such as HAM and uveitis. </p>

<p>The absence of symptoms in most of the infected people raises the question of the multiple etiological roles of the virus-associated diseases and some of the interesting questions still unanswered includes: does the immunogenic characteristics of the host contribute to the upsurge of symptoms associated with HTLV-1 infection? The present manuscript presents the most relevant published results from several laboratories, including ours over the years regarding the associations between the genetic variations of the host related to the immune response and HTLV-1 infection, particularly those showing the close relationship between HTLV-1 infection and single nucleotide polymorphisms in genes of the immune system. </p>
</text>
