<text id="autogum_academic_doc467" title="Candida albicans Biofilm Heterogeneity and Tolerance of Clinical Isolates: Implications for Secondary Endodontic Infections" shortTile="candida-albicans" author="Om  Alkhir Alshanta, Suror Shaban, Christopher  J Nile, William McLean, Gordon Ramage" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-6382/8/4/204/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Fungal infections are generally perceived as being relatively uncommon, yet are reported to affect more than a billion people. This is exacerbated when we consider the alarming global burden of antifungal resistance that we now experience. Many infections we believe to be of bacterial origin are in fact fungal. Indeed, the yeast <hi rend="italic">Candida albicans</hi> is a ubiquitous human commensal, but with opportunistic tendencies. Its capacity to morphologically transition from yeast to hyphal cells enables it to react dynamically, both in evasion of host immunity and in its ability to readily form biofilm structures that impact increased antifungal resistance. <hi rend="italic">C. albicans</hi> frequently resides in the oral cavity as a biofilm forming microorganism, interacting with other oral microbiota and the host. When we consider root canal infections, pathogenic yeasts have also been isolated from teeth associated with primary apical periodontitis and post-treatment disease. </p>

<p>Dental pulp is generally a sterile tissue containing nerves and vascular tissues that are connected to the surrounding periradicular tissues, though recent studies appear to suggest the presence of bacterial DNA in the pulp of pristine healthy teeth. The pulp is protected from the oral microbiome by layers of mineralised tissues (dentin, enamel and cementum). Breach to these tissues, as a result of dental caries, tooth fractures or cracks, can expose the dentin and provide routes for oral microbiota to ingress towards the pulp. Another route of pulp infection is the direct invasion of microorganisms to the pulp during root canal treatment during substandard clinical procedures. <hi rend="italic">C. albicans</hi> is the most frequently isolated species in endodontic infections. The prevalence of yeast in persistent infections is higher than that in primary infections. However, two recent systematic reviews found that <hi rend="italic">C. albicans</hi> prevalence does vary significantly between primary and secondary endodontic infections. In this environment <hi rend="italic">C. albicans</hi> can colonise dentinal walls and penetrate into dentinal tubules. The route of fungal invasion to the root canals is likely to be through cracks or via leaking restoration, though the diameter of hyphae, which is 1.9–2.6 µm, cannot exclude the possibility of dentinal tubules invasion especially in deep caries lesions. Here, candida yeasts are capable of coalescing with one another in the form of biofilm, which is a multicellular community of yeast and hyphal forms encased in polymeric glue. The biofilm lifestyle enhances the ability of the cells to withstand host and antifungal factors, ultimately contributing to its persistence within the root canal. This phenotype, along with the complexity of root canal system, particularly in the apical third of root canals, are thought to be the major causes of treatment-resistant apical periodontitis. </p>

<p>Root canal treatment (RCT) is the treatment of choice for these endodontic infections. RCT aims to: (1) eliminate microorganisms from the root canal system to a level that promotes the healing of periradicular tissues, and (2) provide a three-dimensional hermetic seal to prevent reinfection. Different hand and rotary instruments are used during RCT in order to mechanically debride the biofilm on the root canal walls. Nevertheless, the cross-sectional root canal configuration can pose a challenge to adequate debridement, as these instruments tend to leave untouched recesses in oval canals. This instrumentation can however create a smear layer that covers the root canal walls, which consists of organic (pulp tissue remnants) and inorganic (dentin chips) tissues. This layer might act as a protective barrier to encase biofilms formed on root canal walls and might also encourage the adherence of microorganisms, such as <hi rend="italic">C. albicans</hi>. Furthermore, it may compromise the quality of root canal sealing. Therefore, the use of chemical irrigating solutions to maximise root canal debridement and removal of the smear layer is vital for successful RCT, which includes ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA), though not universally. EDTA acts mainly as an adjunct irrigant to remove smear layer, though an alternative effect is the inhibition of filamentation through chelation of necessary divalent cations in the pathogenic yeast <hi rend="italic">C. albicans</hi>, a structural element strongly associated with robust biofilm formation. </p>

<p>Recent work from our group has highlighted the clinical relevance of biofilm heterogeneity between isolates of <hi rend="italic">C. albicans</hi> from the oral cavity and other clinical sites. The overriding message from this review is that with respect to particular groups of microorganisms, they cannot all be considered as a single entity and “one size does not fit all” when it comes to treatment regimens. We have shown that the greater capacity to form biofilm is linked to enhanced virulence and increased resistance to antifungals. Further studies of this yeast, alongside the emerging yeast pathogen <hi rend="italic">C. auris</hi>, have demonstrated that biofilm-mediated patterns of resistance also exist for both antiseptics and disinfectants, including sodium hypochlorite. Given that sodium hypochlorite (NaOCl) and EDTA are principal components of the management of endodontic infections, we hypothesised that root canal treatment failure involving <hi rend="italic">C. albicans</hi> may be driven by biofilm heterogeneity resulting in an enhanced ability to withstand treatment and regrow within root canals. We therefore aimed to assess how different biofilm phenotypes responded in vitro to NaOCl and EDTA treatments. </p>
</text>
