<text id="autogum_academic_doc074" title="A Multiscale Review of Behavioral Variation in Collective Foraging Behavior in Honey Bees" shortTile="multiscale-review" author="Natalie  J. Lemanski, Chelsea  N. Cook, Brian  H. Smith, Noa Pinter-Wollman" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-4450/10/11/370/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Fitness Consequences of Collective Behavior</head>
<p>
Collecting food for the entire colony is a major challenge for honey bees. Honey bees from the same colony forage across areas spanning up to several hundred square kilometers, and at linear distances as far as 9 km from the hive. To increase efficiency, foraging labor is divided into different task groups. Foragers specialize in the type of food they collect, as well as whether they scout for new resources or are recruited to known resources. Variation in learning among individuals in the colony is important for this division of labor because learning influences which of the foraging tasks individuals are most likely to perform, as detailed above. </p>

<p>The collective decisions that result from differences in behavior at the individual level have an important impact on a colony’s foraging success, and therefore on its fitness. Both the range of behavioral variation and the frequency of each behavioral type in the colony can impact collective outcomes. A wider range of behavioral types can increase the likelihood that complementary behavioral types, such as scouts and recruits, will be represented in the colony. For instance, Mattila and Seeley found that greater genetic diversity increases the likelihood that the rare scout-like genotypes are present in a colony, thus increasing a colony’s ability to discover new resource patches. </p>

<p>Collective dynamics can also be determined by the frequency of each behavioral type. When foraging, colonies face a trade-off between exploiting known resources and exploring for new ones. This trade-off can be resolved by allocating the task of scouting only to a sufficient number of individuals to allow locating new resources without losing too many foragers to the costs of exploration. There is an optimal ratio of scouts to recruits, or explorers to exploiters, which maximizes collective foraging. However, this balance may change as a function of the structure of the landscape in which the colony forages. For example, theoretical models have established that when resources are concentrated into a small number of highly rewarding patches, colonies perform best with few scouts and many recruits. In contrast, when resource patches are small, evenly distributed, and easy to locate, successful colonies invest more in scouting than in recruitment. Furthermore, having many recruits is beneficial when patches are highly variable in quality, because recruitment drives foragers to the highest quality patches. Empirical tests have provided support for the prediction that high investment in recruitment is most beneficial when resources are distributed in few large patches and are variable in quality. </p>

<p>The behavioral composition of the colony has consequences for collective pollen foraging, which can have major impacts on worker health and larval development. For instance, genetic differences in the sucrose response thresholds of individual foragers scale up to influence the total amount of pollen that the colony collects. Because pollen is often variable in nutritional quality, having fewer pollen scouts and more recruits allows colonies to focus efforts on the highest quality pollen resources. </p>
</text>
