<text id="autogum_academic_doc570" title="Determination of Liberation Degree of Mechanically Processed Waste Printed Circuit Boards by Using the Digital Microscope and SEM-EDS Analysis" shortTile="determination-liberation" author="Pedro Pereira Gonçalves, Akira Otsuki" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-9292/8/10/1202/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Waste electrical and electronic equipment (WEEE) is one of the fastest growing waste categories in the EU, with the growth rate of 3–5% per year, as a result of massive production of the EEE and its market expansion based on technological progress. The printed circuit boards (PCBs) present in almost every single piece of electronic equipment, and account for roughly 5 wt% of the entire e-waste currently produced. Nevertheless, they carry the most important share of the valuable and also toxic metals. This creates an urgent need for recovering/recycling valuable materials from PCBs. On the other hand, their complex and heterogeneous structures (e.g., mixture of number of different metals, plastics, and ceramics in different sizes) and their diversion with time raise the issues associated with their effective pre-concentration process development as well as environmental concerns. One of the major limitations in the recycling of PCBs is a lack of a proper characterization method to quantitatively evaluate the distribution and liberation of each metal without destroying the heterogeneous particle status at each separation/beneficiation unit operation. </p>

<p>The degree of liberation, indicating how much the target component is liberated from the non-valuable components, is a key factor when establishing the liberation performance of the comminution to determine the success of subsequent process for valuable material recovery. The study of the degree of liberation was initially introduced in the mineral processing field, where the main objective was to achieve selective liberation of the valuable minerals of interest aiming for the coarsest particle size possible, saving energy on the grinding process and reducing the amount of non-desirable fine fractions produced.  </p>

<p>One of the methods for the degree of liberation for mineral grains is the analysis of images (and elemental maps) obtained by optical microscopy or scanning electron microscopy. For instance, there was a report on liberation within complex assemblages, such as in a Galena-Sphalerite ore. In the mineral industry, the image analysis has shifted towards an automatic procedure lately, using automated analyzers coupled with the electron microscopes, such as MLA and QEMSCAN. However, the applicability of the automated image analyzers algorithms to electronic wastes, mostly for such complex assemblage resulting from the waste PCBs can be challenging. The heterogeneous nature of the samples, in terms of diverse materials used (i.e., metals, glass, ceramics), the irregular shape of the particles due to the different physical properties of the materials (e.g., round ball-like shaped, elongated rod-like shapes, cubic-like) and associated software developed for mineral analysis are some of the issues that could face by automated analysis. Hence, particle counting method is preferred for the conditions and heterogeneous samples of our study in order to evaluate and understand the liberation degree of the metals of interest, by applying a non-destructive characterization. The importance of using non-destructive characterization methods and how it can be helpful to understand the association and deportment of metals/plastics in the different size fractions was alerted in our previous studies e.g.,. </p>

<p>Comparing with the primary ore beneficiations, in a waste PCB assemblage, a specific size fraction for the liberation of valuable metals from non-metallic fractions is still not clearly understood. Some previous studies investigated the effect of the particles size and shape on the liberation characteristics, and high liberation degree was reported with the particle sizes below &lt; 100 μm or from 100 μm up to 3 mm. Such discrepancies are likely related to the differences in the PCB material compositions and the grinding mechanisms used in the comminution processes.  </p>

<p>Our previous work reported the selective metal enrichment and agglomeration of metallic components (e.g., Cu, Al) through the application of a hammer milling for PCBs comminution. Based on our results and abovementioned research gaps, the objective of the present study is to assess the degree of liberation of metals within the products of hammer milling process via the combination of image acquisition and analysis, in order to evaluate their selective liberation. The particles produced under different milling conditions (i.e., feed mass, milling time) for different metals (i.e., Cu, Al) were compared as a function of particle size fractions. The results obtained for the liberation degree using digital optical microscopic images were compared with the analysis of backscattered electron (BSE) images and elemental maps obtained by scanning electron microscope coupled with an energy dispersive spectroscopy (SEM-EDS). The advantages and disadvantages of the above two methods for investigating the liberation degree of mechanically processed PCB particles will be discussed in the paper, in addition to their methodological developments. </p>
</text>
