<text id="autogum_academic_doc263" title="Development of Scalable On-Line Anomaly Detection System for Autonomous and Adaptive Manufacturing Processes" shortTile="development-scalable" author="Seunghyun Choi, Sekyoung Youm, Yong-Shin Kang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4502/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions and Future Work</head>
<p>
This paper proposed the architecture of the Scalable On-line Anomaly Detection System (SOADS), which can be used to detect anomalies of the manufacturing flow by considering the manufacturing process of an autonomous and adaptive smart factory. The goodness of the system was verified via implementation and experimentation. The first advantage of the SOADS is that it satisfies the large-scale system requirement, which is the ability to analyze the flow of objects that are generated in large volumes in an autonomous and adaptive smart factory. This advantage is attributable to the use of Spark streaming and Hbase as subsystems, which are distributed processing technologies. The second advantage is that the method employed for subsequence pattern derivation using the <hi rend="italic">RELATIONAL DEPENCENCY TABLE</hi> of the SOADS is efficient in terms of the pattern search time relative to the existing PrefixSpan algorithm, which searches from the length-1 pattern. </p>

<p>Most studies related to smart factories in academic and industrial circles are abstract studies from a high-level perspective, such as from the viewpoint of architecture, reference models, and future prospects, or they address current problems such as automation, failure diagnosis, and quality prediction for unit processes. The main contribution of this study is that it proposed, implemented, and proved a priori a system that can solve problems that may occur in future autonomous and adaptive smart factories for all processes by merging manufacturing (domain), information and communication technology (ICT), and engineering analysis (methodology) unlike previous studies. Furthermore, theories that have been used for data mining and gene sequence analysis were applied to the smart factory (new territory) using distributed computing technology (new computer environment), thus demonstrating that Big Data technology, which is a next-generation technology, can further evolve existing theories, which can be applied to various fields.  </p>

<p>The anomaly detection perspective in this study is centered on control flow, and anomaly detection studies from more diverse perspectives are required. Therefore, in the future, we would need to expand this study to more intensively investigate process anomaly detection by considering multiple perspectives including the time perspective, such as processing time and movement time, the data perspective by considering the properties, types, and cost of objects, and the contextual perspective such as temperature and humidity changes in the manufacturing flow. Furthermore, the simulation data used in this study did not consider the noise, which is inevitably generated when barcodes, RFID, and sensors are used in the actual manufacturing process. Therefore, research on the derivation of subsequence pattern and anomaly scoring after refinement of noise of event logs by smoothing, noise filtering, etc. using a method like Bayesian network will be needed. </p>

<p>In the future, this research could be extended to not only deriving material flow patterns in smart factories, but also deriving worker movement and patterns in factories using techniques such as crowd sensing. In addition, this research could be integrated with numerous Smart X studies, including smart logistics, smart cities and smart streets, beyond smart factory fields.
 </p>
</text>
