<text id="autogum_academic_doc357" title="Hour-Ahead Solar Irradiance Forecasting Using Multivariate Gated Recurrent Units" shortTile="hourahead-solar-irradiance" author="Jessica Wojtkiewicz, Matin Hosseini, Raju Gottumukkala, Terrence  Lynn Chambers" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4055/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Conclusions</head>
<p>
In this paper, we propose the application of a relatively new and robust RNN to forecast hourly solar irradiance. We applied univariate and multivariate GRU models using historical solar irradiance, exogenous meteorological variables, and cloud cover data to forecast solar irradiance in Phoenix, Arizona. The proposed is compared with LSTM, another popular deep learning model. We further analyze the performance of models to forecast multiple time steps into future, how the models perform with cloud cover variable, and how the performance of different models vary across a given day, over the year, and days with high variability in irradiance. Our primary motivation for this work is to be able to find a model that can continuously produce real-time forecasts based on publicly available weather data. Therefore, we also study the computational performance of various models. Overall, multivariate deep learning methods perform better than univariate models. There is significant performance improvement with including cloud cover in the multivariate models. We observe from Phoenix dataset that multivariate LSTM has slightly less error compared to multivariate GRU, but multivariate GRU has less training and prediction time compared to multivariate LSTM. There is not much difference between per month MAPE and RMSE between multivariate GRU and multivariate LSTM. </p>

<p>In our future work, we would like to improve irradiance forecasting performance that would further help grid operators to manage uncertainty associated with solar power. This includes using better quality cloud cover data in the model, techniques to further improve the performance of the model, and finally, evaluating the utility of these models to help grid operators manage the variability of irradiance under different conditions. The proposed deep learning methods could be further improved by incorporating more detailed cloud cover related features as well as higher resolution GHI data. The data used in our experiments includes hourly GHI data which is freely available from NREL, but many solar installations collect one-minute resolution data that could be used to potentially improve the model performance. On days where there is no cloud cover, both models performed exceptionally; however, on days with cloud cover, both models fail to accurately predict future solar irradiance. Rather than having one static model to predict non-cloudy and cloudy days, we could potentially use ensemble methods or concept drift methods to reduce over-fitting on days where there is high variability in cloud cover. Moreover, more research is needed in not only reducing the forecast error, but also maximizing the utility of irradiance forecasts. The use of variables, namely back-of-module temperature and DNI, could be used to predict solar power plant production. Being able to predict solar power plant production using DNI and back-of-module temperature would allow power grid operators to calculate future production directly, further reducing the margin of error.
 </p>
</text>
