<text id="autogum_academic_doc307" title="The Performance Assessment of a Precast, Panel-Segmented Arch Bridge with Outriggers" shortTile="performance-assessment" author="Seok  Hyeon Jeon, Kwang-Il Cho, Jungwon Huh, Jin-Hee Ahn" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4646/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions</head>
<p>
This paper proposes a precast, panel-segmented arch bridge with outriggers that form the cross-section and shape of the arch, in which the precast panel members and outriggers resist the bending moment generated during construction and the compressive force generated during use. In this study, the stability of the arch bridge was evaluated with respect to the construction step and rise ratio during construction; the performances of the target arch bridges were determined by conducting a 3D, non-linear, finite element analysis. The conclusions are as follows: </p>

<p>(1) The proposed precast, panel-segmented arch bridge with outriggers consists of precast panel members subject to compressive force and continuous rib-type outriggers connected to the precast panels that resist the tensile force. In this bridge type, the compressive and tensile forces applied to the arch bridge, with respect to the construction step, were efficiently transmitted through the concrete panels and continuous rib-type outriggers. </p>

<p>(2) Based on 3D structural analysis results of the proposed arch bridge, the stresses in the precast panels and outriggers were in accordance with the thrust line and deformation characteristics based on the behavior of the arch bridge. The outriggers’ tensile and compressive stresses were caused by the horizontal displacement of the arch support and the vertical displacement of the crown in the self-weight state. Furthermore, the compressive stress of the precast panel and the tensile and compressive stress of the outrigger at the final construction step exhibited structurally stable stress distributions, because of the decreased difference in all of the members. </p>

<p>(3) Based on the results, in the self-weight state, there was a relatively large displacement near the support of the bridge and arch crown, causing the thrust line to be located outside the precast panels in the arch crown and the support. With an increase in load with respect to the construction step, the thrust line was found to act inside the precast panels at the final construction step. </p>

<p>(4) There was a relatively large horizontal displacement in the precast panels near the lower support in the self-weight state, and there was a vertical displacement in the upper crown precast panels. However, the horizontal displacement in the arch bridge was reduced because of the backfill soil and soil mass load during construction, in addition to the vertical displacement in the arch crown. The proposed arch bridge exhibited different behaviors with respect to changes in the rise ratio. However, given that the deformation and member forces were very small, the proposed arch bridge was considered to have a stable structural behavior after increasing the construction step number and applying the upper soil mass load. </p>

<p>In the proposed arch bridge, the applied span and structural behavior can be varied with the precast panel installation method. In future work, the efficiency and applicability of the proposed arch bridge should be examined through a detailed review of the characteristics of the precast panel connections and members. Moreover, various analyses and empirical experiments should be conducted to determine the structural behavior.
 </p>
</text>
