<text id="autogum_academic_doc158" title="An Integrated Multi-Sensor Approach for the Remote Monitoring of Parkinson’s Disease" shortTile="integrated-multisensor" author="Giovanni Albani, Claudia Ferraris, Roberto Nerino, Antonio Chimienti, Giuseppe Pettiti, Federico Parisi, Gianluigi Ferrari, Nicola Cau, Veronica Cimolin, Corrado Azzaro, Lorenzo Priano, Alessandro Mauro" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4764/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
In 2030, in Western Europe and in the ten most populous nations of the world, the estimated number of individuals with Parkinson’s disease (PD) will be over 8 million. One of the main challenges to be faced will be the development of technological and cost-effective solutions to improve the healthcare of these patients. Remote medical communications, for example in the form of telemedicine and decentralized care pathways, will inevitably become part of the clinical management of such disease. </p>

<p>Among the tougher hurdles to overcome, there is the accurate, low-cost and objective quantification of the typical motor symptoms, which is a key issue for obtaining a complete indication of the patient’s state of impairment. Since 1967, when the motor effects of Levodopa (LD) on bradykinesia have been shown for the first time in a video, the way has been traced towards the quantification of movement disorders and their therapeutic response. This pathway passes through semi-quantitative rating scales, such as the Hoehn and Yahr stage and unified Parkinson’s disease rating scale (UPDRS), which is still the gold standard scale for assessing symptoms in PD. Evaluation through the UPDRS score is a subjective process that comes after a global clinical judgment for the diagnosis in which the experience of the specialist in movement disorders is crucial. This process is, in fact, characterized by an intrinsic inter-rater variability due to the different experience of the examiners, influencing the final judgment on the impairment severity. A percentage of incorrect diagnosis of 25% has also been reported, especially when symptoms such as essential tremor, vascular parkinsonism and atypical parkinsonian syndromes manifest.  </p>

<p>Another difficulty to overcome, shared by all clinical assessment scales, is the mandatory presence of the specialist: this strongly influences the clinical management of the patient, as all the therapeutic decisions are restricted at the time of the single medical examination. However, during the time interval between two consecutive examinations, the patient’s motor status may change significantly, out of the examiner’s sight. The chance of monitoring any change of the impairment in PD subjects over time, possibly daily and in a domestic environment, could have a strong impact on the clinical management of the patients and, consequently, on the long-term costs for the healthcare system. </p>

<p>In an attempt to address these challenges and quantify motor symptoms, motion analysis studies have played a growing role in managing subjects with PD, exploring kinematic variables on gait; tremor; bradykinesia and rigidity. Motion capture systems are the reference standard for motion analysis, but they are expensive and non-portable, so their use is limited to laboratory environments and scientific research rather than to a routine clinical use.  </p>

<p>Therefore, in order to overcome these hurdles, it is urgent to find automatic and cost-effective solutions, capable of providing accurate and objective kinematic measures of motor performance and automatic scores that are well correlated to the standard clinical ones. </p>

<p>Recently, various technological approaches have been proposed for the analysis of movement in PD, including wearable sensor networks based on the use of inertial measurement units (IMUs), smartphones and active vision systems based on new low-cost RGB-Depth optical devices such as Microsoft Kinect® (Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, WA, USA) and Intel RealSense® SR300 (Intel Corporation, Santa Clara, CA, USA)[26]. </p>

<p>On the basis of these considerations, we propose the integration of two different sensor-based subsystems as a single solution for the objective, accurate and automated assessment of some standard tasks for the upper and lower limbs, as defined in the motor examination section (Section 3) of UPDRS. The first component is an active vision system dedicated to the analysis of the motor tasks related to upper limbs; the second applies a body sensor network (BSN) approach with wireless wearable sensors for the analysis of the lower limb tasks. The technical details of both and the validation of their accuracy as UPDRS automatic scoring systems have been already presented in previous works and will be briefly summarized in the Materials and Methods section.  </p>

<p>A gesture-based human machine interface has been developed as part of the solution, to simplify the interaction and the self-management of the system by people with impairment, in view of a possible use at home. </p>

<p>The system is able to analyze and automatically score the patient movements during the performance of UPDRS tasks. In addition, it archives in the Cloud the kinematic data, the score and the video of each motor performance, guaranteeing the remote supervision by clinicians and overcoming the mandatory presence of the specialist during the execution of the motor activities. Finally, in view of a decentralized approach to the clinical management of the patient, the issue of acceptability and usability of the integrated system has been evaluated through a standard questionnaire. </p>

<p>The integrated system here presented is aimed at a more comprehensive evaluation of the neuro-motor status of PD subjects by a decentralized approach, and could represent a new example of an accurate, feasible and cost-effective strategy for the clinical management of PD. </p>
</text>
