<text id="autogum_academic_doc165" title="Improved Accumulation Capabilities of Phosphorus and Potassium in Green Manures and Its Relationship with Soil Properties and Enzymatic Activities" shortTile="improved-accumulation" author="Farheen Solangi, Jinshun Bai, Songjuan Gao, Lu Yang, Guopeng Zhou, Weidong Cao" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4395/9/11/708/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Phosphorus (P) and potassium (K) are the most significant macronutrients in the soil ecosystem after nitrogen (N), which involves various processes, i.e., energy formation, nucleic acid synthesis, photosynthesis, glycolysis, respiration, enzymes activation and redox reactions. Nutrient management is important for sustainable crop production. P- and K-efficient cultivars are important options in an agro-ecosystem. Uptake efficiencies of nutrients such as P and K are related to the abilities of plants to produce high yields in low-nutrient conditions. Deficiency in P is mainly attributed to its immobilization in soil. Low K content is highly dependent on soil composition, especially on its fixation to clay particles, leading to deficiency in plant uptake. Immobilized P can be re-mobilized, and non-exchangeable K can also become available in soil solution under biochemical processes. However, they could be strongly dependent on soil chemistry Exploitation of legumes is an essential approach for sustainable agriculture as it can increase nutrient cycling and promote soil fertility This approach can also potentially improve P and K availability in the soil, which is beneficial for plant uptake and soil microorganisms. Root growth and root morphological mechanisms of leguminous plants are the principal factors that usually require greater P and K levels in the soil, which is also related to plant P and K uptake. Several green manure crops such as white lupin (<hi rend="italic">Lupines albas</hi> L.), chickpea (<hi rend="italic">Cicer arietinum</hi> L.), field pea (<hi rend="italic">Pisum sativum</hi> L), and faba bean (<hi rend="italic">Vicia faba</hi>), are able to mobilize soil P through a variety of root mechanisms. </p>

<p>Recent studies have shown that legumes can regulate soil enzymatic activities more than mineral fertilizers. According to other researchers, legumes such as chickpeas and cowpeas increase phosphatase enzyme activities more than non-legumes. Soil enzymes play important roles in catalyzing reactions and are associated, directly or indirectly, with nutrient availability and organic matter decomposition. The specific activity of an enzyme is not considered useful in the complete nutrient cycle of soil because it has a particular substrate. Some hydrolytic enzymes (e.g., β-glucosidase, N-acetyl-glucosaminidase, Leucine-aminopeptidase, and phosphatase), which are related to C, N, and P cycles, are more responsible for the soil properties (pH and soil organic matter) than other variables. Such enzymes could be valuable as early indicators of biological soil modification.  </p>

<p>Leguminous plants, especially broad bean (<hi rend="italic">V. faba</hi>), Chinese milk vetch (<hi rend="italic">Astragalus sinicus</hi> L.), clover (<hi rend="italic">Trifolium repens</hi> L.), and hairy vetch (<hi rend="italic">V. villosa</hi> L.), have been used in crop rotation systems worldwide. Although, P and K uptake efficiencies have been reported to be different in various legumes crops, and the relative knowledge and profound information about leguminous green manures in South China are still unclear. Moreover, less information exists in the literature about the changes in enzymatic activities in response to cultivation of different legume species in the field. Green manuring has become a popular practice in South China to improve soil fertility and rice yields at present. The most popular winter green manure is milk vetch, which has traditionally been used for several thousands of years, and most attention has focused on N utilization.  </p>

<p>The main objectives of this study were to (1) evaluate P and K uptake capabilities in various winter leguminous green manure species in South China and (2) investigate their ability to affect soil enzyme activity by interacting with soil properties. </p>
</text>
