<text id="autogum_academic_doc132" title="The Role of Experiments and Demonstration Projects in Efforts of Upscaling: An Analysis of Two Projects Attempting to Reconfigure Production and Consumption in Energy and Mobility" shortTile="role-experiments" author="Marianne Ryghaug, Michael Ornetzeder, Tomas Moe Skjølsvold, William Throndsen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5771/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Methods </head>
<p>
For this study, we mobilized a comparative, qualitative case study design. A multiple case study design increases generalizability, as it allows comparison of analytic conclusions across a range of contexts. From the nine cases studied within the ERA-Net project mentioned above, two experiments were selected for in depth analysis herein. This was a decision based on a measure of comparability, as the cases—the Austrian VLOTTE and the Norwegian ASKO—both were smart grid experiments with certain similar features which made them interesting for comparison. Both cases were company driven projects with a focus on the development of solutions to convert vehicle fleets to renewable energy sources. In both cases, the activities were in-house developments aiming first at the companies’ own needs. However, at the same time, both activities can be characterized as mission-oriented innovation, as they aimed to contribute to a decarbonized transport sector in general. In the VLOTTE project, a regional Austrian ESCO together with an associated DSO developed a smart e-car park as part of their own e-vehicle fleet. In the ASKO case, a large grocery wholesaler from Norway established a hydrogen infrastructure for a hydrogen-powered fleet of heavy-duty delivery trucks and fork lifts. In addition to a similar thematic mission of the projects, there is another interesting common feature: In both cases, we are dealing with companies that have transformed their relation to and participation in the transport system as an outcome of the project. </p>

<p>Our analysis of the case studies provided a comprehensive description of the activities, framework conditions and outcomes. The empirical surveys therefore focused on the historical development of the projects, the local and regional contexts, and the roles and strategies of various actors. In addition, the solutions developed in the projects were described as socio-technical configurations. Further on, SNM concepts were used to direct the analysis: comparing data to concepts introduced in the theory section. This created an idea of what features and aspects to look for when analysing upscaling dynamics, in line with the transformation category proposed by Naber et al.. </p>

<p>Data collection took place between November 2016 and May 2017. Data about the experiments was collected through semi-structured interviews with project partners and analysis of project documents (e.g., evaluation reports project plans, project presentations, and factsheets). Overall, 31 interviews have been conducted altogether in Austria, with a total of 11 interviews related to the VLOTTE case, studied here. In Norway, the total number on interviews was 38, of which 6 were expert interviews conducted with middle and upper management at ASKO. These interviews lasted between one and two hours. All interviews were transcribed verbatim. For each case an individual case description and analysis was written. After the individual reports, the cases were compared with each other and cross-case patterns were identified in an iterative process. Before moving to the analyses of the two cases, in the subsection below we will briefly describe the national context in which the demos are established and embedded. </p>

<head> More Detailed Case Descriptions: ASKO and VLOTTE</head>
<p>
The Norwegian case is represented by ASKO midt-Norge, a large grocery wholesaler, and focuses on their endeavour to be self-supplied with energy. At the time of the study, they had installed a 300-m2 solar PV rig on the roof of their warehouse (storage) complex, the surplus energy of which is going to power a hydrogen production facility. During the next year, they increased the acreage of this PV park to 12,000 m2. A hydrogen production was planned to fuel delivery trucks that operate in the middle and low north regions of Norway. Most of the solar power, however, was to be used to power the company storage facility to keep goods cold. Because of this, and contrary to most other use scenarios that include solar power, ASKO has a demand curve that follows the production curve of the PV system quite well as the demand for keeping goods cold correlates with the supply of solar energy. </p>

<p>The Austrian case—called VLOTTE—is located in Vorarlberg, the most western region of Austria and focuses on e-mobility, distributed generation and load management. VLOTTE started as a demo project funded by a national e-mobility model region program in 2008. Today, Vorarlberg is one of the leading e-mobility regions in Europe. Led by the local state-owned energy and utility company Illwerke vkw, the VLOTTE project still is the main promoter of e-mobility in the region. After the publicly funded project phase, Illwerke vkw turned VLOTTE into a business model offering several services. One example is consulting on setting up electric vehicle fleets. In our case, a local construction company approached Illwerke vkw with the request to integrate a public charging infrastructure with the company’s parking space, which is also the parking space of a shopping centre. In accommodation of this request Illwerke vkw installed a fast charging infrastructure that is owned by them and can be used by customers that own a vkw membership card, but it is also connected to the company’s premises and therefore easily accessible by its employees. </p>
</text>
