<text id="autogum_academic_doc092" title="Individual Condensation Trails in Aircraft Trajectory Optimization" shortTile="individual-condensation" author="Judith Rosenow, Hartmut Fricke" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6082/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The term condensation trail (contrail) summarizes a type of human-induced cloud, developed behind aircraft due to condensation of water vapor emissions and ambient humidity around exhausted soot particles and atmospheric condensation nuclei in a cold ambient atmosphere, satisfying the Schmidt–Appleman criterion. In an ice supersaturated environment, these artificial ice clouds form into long-living cirrus clouds called “Cirrus homogenitus” as defined by the World Meteorological Organization. </p>

<p>In the Earth–atmosphere energy budget, contrails act like a barrier. They scatter incoming shortwave solar radiation back to the sky (resulting in a cooling effect) and they absorb and emit the outgoing longwave terrestrial radiation back to the Earth’s surface (yielding a warming effect in the lower layer of the atmosphere). The dominating effect may be defined as radiative forcing , as the change in net downward radiative flux at the tropopause (considering the instantaneous response of the stratosphere). The contribution of contrails to global warming cannot yet be determined with high precision and depends on flight performance, weather conditions, and time. Latest combinations of several approaches to model a global impact of contrails on global warming summarize a warming net effect of  W m with accuracy to within  and  W m for 2010. Single studies result in a precision of the environmental impact of contrails including negative (cooling) net effects (e.g.,  W m for 2005). Using global climate models and historic air traffic data, reliable estimations of the global contrail radiative forcing for the year 2000 of  W m have been improved for 2010 to  W m considering an increased traffic distance by 22% between 2005 and 2010. For 2002, Burkhardt and Kärcher estimated  W m of contrails and contrail cirrus clouds within a global climate model. </p>

<p>Compared to the summed effect of one year’s aviation-emitted carbon dioxide  and nitrogen oxides  which is  W m, the impact of contrails on global warming is no longer negligible, as it might exceed those effects of  and , even though contrails are only formed during  of the flights, on a global average. Thus, the need for contrails to be considered in trajectory optimization becomes indisputable. </p>

<p>The impact of single condensation trails on trajectory optimization has been analyzed by Gounou et al. and Forster et al., focusing on the importance of large solar zenith angles during sunset and sunrise. In an application of a Monte Carlo code for photon transport, Forster et al. already considered effects like multiple scattering, but in a coarse spatial grid and ignoring the impact of flight performance on the optical properties of the contrail. Detailed studies on all significant impact factors have been elaborated by Rosenow. In the current study, the results have been simplified and harnessed for trajectory optimization. All other research interests known to the authors concentrated on the effect of contrails on a global scale. </p>
</text>
