<text id="autogum_academic_doc596" title="Positive Orientation and Strategies for Coping with Stress as Predictors of Professional Burnout among Polish Nurses" shortTile="positive-orientation" author="Ewa Kupcewicz, Marcin Jóźwik" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4264/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
In the course of performing work-related tasks, nurses are exposed to many harmful, cumbersome, and dangerous factors, including emotional and interpersonal stressors. As early as the 1950s, M.S. Schwartz and G.T. Will described the case of a nurse working in a psychiatric ward who began to lose energy and motivation to work. The nurse felt mental and physical fatigue, exhaustion, helplessness, skepticism, and lack of joy in performing nursing tasks as a result of intense tension at work caused by various stressors. In subsequent studies, it has been shown that the observed symptoms were evidence of burnout. </p>

<p>In Europe, Danish researchers from Copenhagen lead by T.S. Kristensen identified three components of burnout: personal burnout, work-related burnout, and burnout in contacts with patients. Personal burnout was defined as “physical and psychological fatigue and exhaustion experienced by a given person”, work-related burnout by the researchers referred to “physical and mental fatigue or exhaustion experienced by a person while performing work”, whereas burnout in contacts with patients was defined as “a physical and mental fatigue or exhaustion experienced by a person when dealing with patients”. </p>

<p>An overview of the available literature clearly highlights the variety of factors associated with burnout syndrome. Most often, they can be classified into three groups: organizational factors, socio-demographic and lifestyle factors, and personality variables and coping strategies. Worth noting is the study by Manzano-García and Ayala with a group of 40 experts from 6 countries. The study identified potentially important factors in explaining burnout in nursing that have been insufficiently studied or ignored. Among the many analyzed factors, the authors emphasized the importance of personal factors and personal resources in the process of professional burnout. Other studies show that personal (psychological) resources, often considered to be stress moderators, such as optimism, high self-esteem, effectiveness, and the ability to build relationships with other people, can facilitate an individual to cope better with stressors. This effect takes place even if the encountered events are evaluated in the categories of stress, but an individual does not experience the negative effects or experiences less of the negative effects in the process. The authors of this paper argue that there is a need to continue research into the theory of positive orientation, as positive orientation refers to the components of mental well-being in everyday life and may play a significant role in the professional burnout of nurses. </p>

<p>Gian Vittorio Caprara, one of the most eminent Italian psychologists, formulated the concept of positive orientation, which fits into the positive psychology of the last quarter century. Positive orientation is defined by Caprara as “a fundamental tendency to notice and to attach importance to the positive aspects of life, experience and self”. The results of the Italian and Canadian studies confirmed that positive orientation is a latent (hidden) higher order variable that combines three components: self-esteem, optimism, and satisfaction from life. In the literature, it is emphasized that positive orientation is largely responsible for adaptive functioning and is motivational in the actions of individuals. It signifies “natural inclinations towards positive self-esteem, high satisfaction in life, and a high evaluation of the chances of achieving goals, which translates into commitment to life’s aspirations and a high quality of life”. Alessandri et al. investigated the relationship between positive orientation and behavior in organizations. As it turned out, positive orientation was significantly associated with selected organizational behaviors that brought immediate benefits to the organization as a whole, and altruistic behaviors aimed at benefiting individuals. The results of Polish research have shown that positive orientation and self-efficacy are significantly connected but distinct variables. In studies conducted by Miciuk et al., 200 students showed moderate correlations between positive orientation and a generalized sense of effectiveness, positive affect, sense of meaning, and purpose in life. In other studies, there was a positive relationship between gratitude, self-esteem, and positive orientation. The above empirical data draw a picture of potential relationships between positive orientation and functioning. </p>
</text>
