<text id="autogum_academic_doc407" title="A Hybrid Method with TOPSIS and Machine Learning Techniques for Sustainable Development of Green Hotels Considering Online Reviews" shortTile="hybrid-method-topsis" author="Mehrbakhsh Nilashi, Abbas Mardani, Huchang Liao, Hossein Ahmadi, Azizah  Abdul Manaf, Wafa Almukadi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6013/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Conclusions</head>
<p>
This paper investigated customer satisfaction in green hotels through travellers’ online review analysis. We used machine learning techniques to analyze the online text-based reviews and numerical data analysis. SOM was used for travelers’ segmentation in both green spa and non-spa hotels. LDA was used for the identification of the main satisfaction dimensions (topics) from the text-based reviews. We also used TOPSIS to rank the main criteria for green hotel selection from numerical reviews. The neuro-fuzzy system was then used to reveal the relative importance of the hotel features on the customers’ satisfaction and find the importance role of spa services and its impact on the customers’ satisfaction. We investigated the role of spa services on the travellers’ overall satisfaction in four main travelling groups, Travelled with Friends, Solo Travelers, Travelled with Family and Travelled as a Couple. The data were collected from Malaysian green spa and non-spa hotels in the TripAdvisor platform. The results showed that, in general, the travellers’ satisfaction was relatively higher than in green spa hotels in relation to the green non-spa hotels. This result was proved in four travelling groups, Travelled with Friends, Solo Travelers, Travelled with Family and Travelled as a Couple. In our experimental analysis, we observed that travellers are relatively more satisfied in green spa hotels and accordingly provide a higher degree of overall ratings to the hotels with spa services. </p>

<p>This research has some limitations. First, this study has considered only the data from TripAdvisor to investigate the role of spa services on customers’ satisfaction. The data from other social networking sites such as trivago.com, booking.com, and trip.com can further confirm the results of this study. Second, this study only considered the Malaysian green spa and non-spa hotels to validate the proposed hypothesis. The data from hotels registered in TripAdvisor for other developed and developing countries may better reveal the significance of spa services on customers’ satisfaction. Third, although our method was implemented to assess the travellers’ satisfaction in green hotels, the proposed method can also be implemented for other types of hotels (e.g., non-green hotels with spa services) and then comparisons are made for the travellers’ satisfaction levels in different hotels (i.e., comparisons for travellers’ satisfaction levels in green hotels with spa services and non-green hotels with spa services). Fourth, four travelling groups have been considered for hypothesis evaluation. Future studies can investigate the role of spa services on other travelling groups such as business travellers. Fifth, this study does not investigate the role of spa services on the travelers’ satisfaction from the gender perspective. This can be an interesting investigation for future studies in the tourism context. Sixth, our method was based on non-incremental learning techniques. The use of deep learning approaches, Random Forest (RF) and incremental learning or the development of our method with incremental updates, especially in LDA and neuro-fuzzy learning techniques, can be effective in online reviews analysis. This limitation could be a rich avenue for future research. Besides the TOPSIS method, we can also consider group decision-making (GDM) and other multiple criteria decision-making methods such as the double normalization-based multiple aggregation (DNMA) method and the gained and lost dominance score (GLDS) method, to solve such problems. Finally, multicollinearity phenomenon may occur due to the high correlations among the features of dataset which should be solved through appropriate learning techniques.
 </p>
</text>
