<text id="autogum_academic_doc600" title="‘Having a Quiet Word’: Yarning with Aboriginal Women in the Pilbara Region of Western Australia about Mental Health and Mental Health Screening during the Perinatal Period" shortTile="having-quiet-word" author="Emma Carlin, David Atkinson, Julia  V Marley" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4253/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Results</head><head> 3.1. Theme One: A lived Experience </head>
<p>Seven of the fifteen women spoke about their or a close family member’s experience with perinatal depression and/or anxiety. A further six women identified extreme and multiple stressors during their own perinatal period (violence, homelessness, drug and alcohol use, child protection intervention, traumatic birth outcomes, primary health problems) but did not talk about depression or anxiety. They talked about things being ‘hard’ or ‘stressful’.</p>

<p><quote><hi rend="italic">‘I was on my own for my pregnancy, I was excited but scared too you know. Her dad [</hi>baby’s dad<hi rend="italic">] was in jail for drink driving. I stopped drinking for her but it was still hard, my dad and I don’t talk and my mother passed. I was sometimes stressing out’.</hi>(Participant 002)</quote></p>

<p>The idea of not knowing how to talk or having the ‘right’ words was a common theme raised during the yarns. Participants spoke about being unfamiliar with the language of depression and anxiety.</p>

<p><quote><hi rend="italic">‘I never heard anyone say they are depressed, I hear them say they are ‘stressing out’, ‘going mad’. Sometimes we might use language words, but those are the ones mostly. We find it hard to talk about pain, I don’t know why, I think as Aboriginal people we like to laugh and talk for the good times but now everyone has a story of pain and we don’t know how to talk [</hi>about it<hi rend="italic">]’.</hi>(Participant 010)</quote></p>

<p>Participants spoke about the multiple stressors that many Pilbara Aboriginal women are negotiating while pregnant or having a small child. Violence, alcohol and drugs, homelessness, caring responsibilities, financial instability and not having family support were frequently mentioned as directly impacting on a woman’s wellbeing. Mothers leaving their babies with family members for extended periods of time or mothers who were not responsive to their baby’s needs (feeding, changing nappies, etc.) were identified by participants as suffering from ‘something serious’, although it was not always understood as perinatal depression and/or anxiety. </p>

<head> 3.2. Theme Two: Connectedness and Support</head>
<p>Participants spoke about clinics and family both having a significant role in supporting women during the perinatal period. Five participants spoke about the support they received from intimate and/or family relationships and the ‘strength’ this gave them.</p>

<p><quote><hi rend="italic">‘Since my sister went through this [</hi>perinatal depression<hi rend="italic">] we are all a lot more aware. We don’t, like, bang on about it, but I see they [</hi>partner and mother<hi rend="italic">] ask me things in a way we never talked about before…. I feel supported, I think whatever happens I will be ok’.</hi>(Participant 008)</quote></p>

<p>Several participants suggested that family do not always have the capacity to ‘help take the load off’, particularly families that are struggling with the effects of intergenerational trauma and/or intergenerational alcohol misuse. Six women talked about the importance of their relationship with their midwife. Home visiting, feeling cared about, ‘worried for’, and the continuity of care during pregnancy were the commonly identified elements of value in the relationship. Four of the six women who spoke about the importance of the relationship with their midwife had inaccessible or weak family support.</p>

<p><quote><hi rend="italic">‘My midwife is in</hi> [name of Pilbara town] <hi rend="italic">but she is gone now. She was really good to me. I still call her. She made me feel it is ok to talk even when I didn’t know what I was going to say’.</hi>(Participant 001)</quote></p>

<p>Religion was noted by a third of the participants (five women) as a strong protective factor for mental wellbeing. Religion was spoken about as a catalyst for a positive life change (e.g., finding religion and giving up drinking) or religion was discussed as an a priori protective factor (e.g., because I am a Christian my family don’t drink at my house). All five respondents who talked about religion stated that their religion gave them someone to talk too. </p>
</text>
