<text id="autogum_academic_doc384" title="Low Back Pain and Its Associated Factors among Nurses in Public Hospitals of Penang, Malaysia" shortTile="low-back-pain-associated" author="Mohd  Ismail Ibrahim, Izani  Uzair Zubair, Najib  Majdi Yaacob, Mohd  Izmi Ahmad, Mohd  Nazri Shafei" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4254/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
Nurses play a major role in managing patients, and the nature of their work exposes them to back pain. In the present study, the one-year prevalence of LBP among the nurses working in public hospitals was 74.8%. The finding is almost similar to the study among the nurses in Switzerland, which ranged from 73% to 76%. It is also in line with the studies in Kuwait, Tunisia, and Nepal. However, the prevalence was lower in developed countries such as Canada, Ireland, and Japan. The prevalence of LBP among nurses may differ between developed and developing countries, within countries, and across the region. The differences of the findings could be due to the difference in the research methodology, questionnaire used, history of back pain among nurses, and self-report of the disease having a pattern of recurrence and reduction. On top of that, the application of back hygiene policy and workplace interventions also play a major role in the differences. Despite the modernization of the health care system, the studies in Taiwan and South Africa reported that the lifetime prevalence of LBP among nurses working in hospitals was 82% and 84%, respectively. It indicates that regardless of the modernization status of the country, pain could occur if there were no preventive measures taken while working. </p>

<p>The present study shows that working hours play a significant role in the development of LBP. It was found that those who work more than seven hours a day were at risk of LBP as compared to others. It can be due to the repetitive exposure to excessive work, such as lifting a heavy object, which leads to injury to the lower back region. Furthermore, sometimes they need to work a few hours more covering for their colleagues on emergency leave or when there is lack of manpower. This is in line with a study in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia, which describes that nurses who worked more than 10 hours a day had an increased risk of LBP compared to those who did not. In addition, Shieh et al. described that the risk of LBP increases by 35% for every additional daily working hour. As a result, it was suggested that the work schedule of nurses needs to be relooked into, as it plays a significant role in the development of back pain. </p>

<p>Nurses usually worked longer than their normal schedule because of the shortage of registered nurses. With a big ratio between nurses and patients, the risks of making errors were significantly increased. Fatigue is one of the symptoms that arises because of work exhaustion, which can contribute to accidents and injuries at the workplace. On top of that, it was reported that the incidence of LBP is increased with an increase in working hours. In addition, a study found that prolonged working hours exposed nurses to repeated manual handling and, thus, sustained the accumulation of wears and tears of the back muscles. </p>

<p>Another important factor in the development of LBP is manual handling performed by nurses. Many nurses in Malaysia are still required to manually lift patients from one place or one position to another. All nurses in Malaysia are required to use small aids like sliding sheets to move patients in the hospitals. However, the present study found a significant association between manual handling and LBP. The repetitive work exposes them to injuries, especially in the lumbar area. It is caused by the kinetic imbalance and pressure exerted on this area. The repeated load application by lifting a patient may result in cumulative fatigue and reduction in the stress-bearing capacity of nurses.  </p>

<p>Apart from lifting patients, nurses often conduct patient handling by bending their waists and maintaining an uncomfortable posture toward the opposite side of the bed or chair. This position increases the risk of back pain. This is supported by a study in the Netherlands and Iran, which found that the bending position increases the risk of back pain. However, in the present study, the bending position was not significantly associated with the development of LBP. This difference could be due to the recall bias of the respondents. </p>

<p>Nurses frequently need to twist their bodies while handling patients. In the present study, this has a significant association with LBP. This is in line with the studies in India and Brazil, which found that twisting of the body was associated with LBP. On top of that, back muscle fatigue is found to be strongly associated with decreased postural stability especially in standing position. The present study revealed that there was a significant association between fatigue and LBP. This can be explained by the negative influence of fatigue on the muscle receptors and thereby on proprioception.  </p>
</text>
