<text id="autogum_academic_doc717" title="What Does In-Work Poverty Mean for Women: Comparing the Gender Employment Segregation in Belgium and China" shortTile="work-poverty-mean" author="Jinghong Liu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5725/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Belgium and China: Two Distinct Forms of Female Working Poor in a Pluralistic Modernity</head><head> 2.1. Two Distinct Forms According to a Country’s Level of Economic Development</head>
<p>
In the research, we look at two different forms of gendered in-work poverty: (1) Female working poor in a highly industrialized society—Belgium. As one of the earliest countries to be industrialized on the continent of Europe, Belgium is a classical case, which went through the Industrial Revolution in the 1830s. Nowadays, Belgium is a developed country with an advanced high-income economy and relatively well-integrated social security system. In this Western European society, workers have experienced significant structural changes in the economic framework, e.g., the progressive process of agricultural decline and a knowledge-based service sector development. These features contribute to promote women’s participation in employment, but many women have low-quality jobs and face work-family conflicts. With this background, the gendered in-work poverty mirrors a series of industrial (or postindustrial) problems in a highly developed economy. (2) Female working poor in a developing country under social transition and rapid economic development—China. The Western mainstream discourse has accumulated rich materials for exploring the in-work poverty issue and has provided a reference for further research in this field. However, this conceptualization does not include female in-work poverty in the Chinese specific context. Different from Western society, China is a big developing oriental nation based on a long history of self-sufficient peasant economy; furthermore, with thousands of years of civilization history, China has cultivated its own strong system of compound culture and formed its atypical Eastern culture. In a developing country with the transition from an agricultural to an industrial society, many social problems are overlapping with ambiguous boundaries. In this context, the issue of female working poverty seems both more complicated and more challenging. It thus shows a specific profile of this kind of in-work poverty with its over-represented rural features; it reflects the issues socioeconomically related to both agricultural and industrial stages. </p>

<head> 2.2. Two Distinct Types According to a Society’s Level of Pluralistic Modernity</head>
<p>
The selection in Belgium and China is also a reflection of two spatial logics in the spread of poverty (and even misery) placed at the same time. One is the female in-work poverty in full urbanization. After having experienced rapid industrialization and urbanization, by 1870, most Belgians lived in cities and depended directly on industry or trade. Belgium has ancient industrial traditions with a large number of developed professional guilds and with social mutual assistance (or solidarity) as the core of a social spirit, which constitutes the foundation of Belgium’s well-developed social security in which people achieve quite high standards of living, life quality, and healthcare. On this basis, female working poverty reveals the severity of increasing social differentiation in the labor market and social welfare; this is our first form of in-work poverty. The other is the rural female poverty type in a “contradictory compressed modernization” in which both agricultural and industrial societies coexist. Indeed, despite the dramatic economic growth, the socioeconomic transformation is still in the process. China is an ancient agricultural country with a long history of land development and utilization. Land remains the core to understand the nature of Chinese social structure, and the Chinese social relationships based on this continue to shape the specificity of this type of female in-work poverty. </p>
</text>
