<text id="autogum_academic_doc117" title="Private Transfer Payments, Inequality, and Poverty: From the Perspective of Households" shortTile="private-transfer" author="Zengzeng Fan, Wei Zou" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5872/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 7. Conclusions</head>
<p>
This paper took IPTP as the research object and used CHFS data to analyze the impact of IPTP on income inequality and social poverty. Statistical analysis shows that the proportion of private transfer income in the total household income of rural families is lower than that of urban families. Family income inequality analysis showed that the income inequality of rural households is more serious than that of urban areas. Because the living standards and consumption levels in urban areas are far higher than those in rural areas, only when household income reaches a certain level can they live in cities. That is to say, there is a threshold of household income, which is the floor level to meet the basic life needs in cities, and the urban household incomes are mostly above the threshold value. Moreover, the middle-income group in urban areas accounts for the vast majority. However, in rural areas, the income of poor families is very low, and the income of rich families may be very high, resulting in greater inequality than in urban areas. If IPTP is exogenous, it can reduce the inequality of both rural families and urban families, and the improvement in rural areas is greater than that of urban areas. This is because in rural areas, the lower family income, the more motivation to work in cities, so as to increase the income of poor families. Considering the possible endogeneity of IPTP, counterfactual analysis shows that IPTP increases family income inequality. From the perspective of the human network, every family has its own private transfer payment network. Private transfer payment has a strong correlation with the family income level in the network. According to the hierarchical distribution of family income levels, the hierarchical distribution of private transfer payment can be obtained. Private transfer payments can create more wealth in high-income family networks, while in low-income family networks, private transfer payments are also at a low level, which plays a very limited role. One result of this is that the rich get richer, while the poor are still at a low-income level, thus widening the gap between the rich and the poor and aggravating inequality. </p>

<p>From the analysis of income, consumption, and household poverty, we found that the IPTP not only directly subsidizes the total household income but also indirectly promotes the increase of household income. At the same time, IPTPs also stimulate household consumption and increase household consumption expenditure. Although IPTPs increases household income and consumption expenditure, they have no significant impact on the poverty level of Chinese households. On the whole, the objective existence of IPTPs still have a positive significance. Firstly, IPTPs improve people’s living standards from two aspects: Increasing the total family income and rising household consumption expenditure. Secondly, although the IPTP may deepen the inequality of household income, it makes the rich richer by promoting the income growth of high-income families, thus widening the income gap. For low-income families, although there is no significant improvement, it does not make the poor poorer. </p>

<p>Based on the findings of this study, we can draw the following policy implications about improving income inequality and reducing social poverty. First, people should try their best to maintain the "exogeneity" of IPTP and reduce its substitution for household income. The study finds that if the IPTP is exogenous, it can reduce the income inequality of both urban and rural households. Therefore, urban and rural residents should be encouraged not to reduce their production and work time even if they have IPTP, so that IPTP is independent of family income expectations. Second, be good at making use of IPTP to invest or reproduce. At present, IPTPs have not significantly alleviated the poverty levels of families. The main reason is that for most families, the IPTP has directly transformed into household consumption expenditure and has not played a greater role. Third, the government should encourage urban and rural residents to strive to develop stable sources of income and become rich through hard work. IPTP is often an “unexpected gift.” To get rid of poverty and become rich, people should rely on their own efforts to increase family income, instead of expecting other people’s private gifts. Just as Chinese President Xi Jinping said, “Happiness comes from struggle.” </p>

<p>In future research, we can focus on more details, such as who remits, and how much, if the data permits it. Remittances are always related to migration closely. In this paper, we did not differentiate the remittances according to their sources. We can also research remittances together with population migration in a further study. Different migration routes lead to different remittances styles. We could also conduct research on how different styles of migration and remittances affect income distribution and poverty.
 </p>
</text>
