<text id="autogum_academic_doc658" title="Left Ventricular Assist Devices 101: Shared Care for General Cardiologists and Primary Care" shortTile="left-ventricular" author="Aditi Singhvi, Barry Trachtenberg" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/10/1720/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 8. Complications of LVADs</head>
<p>
While survival has improved with CF-LVADS, the adverse event profile remains high. At 1 month post-implant, nearly 30% and at 1 year, almost 80% of patients, require readmission. The common LVAD-related complications, outside of the immediate post-operative period, are outlined in Table 4. Providers in the community may be the first medical contact for patients with LVADs experiencing a complication. Though management of these complications should be in concert with LVAD specialists, an awareness and understanding of the common complications can help with timely diagnosis and therapeutic intervention.  </p>

<head> 8.1. LVAD Infections</head>
<p>
Due to the presence of a percutaneous driveline exiting the skin, infections remain the Achilles heel of LVADs. Recent implantation of the first-in-man totally implantable LVAD aims to minimize this risk. ISHLT classifies infections in LVAD patients as VAD-specific (involving the pump, cannula, pocket, or percutaneous driveline), VAD-related (infective endocarditis, blood stream infections including central venous catheter associated, mediastinitis) and non-VAD infections such as pneumonia.  </p>

<p>Different techniques, largely limited to single-center experiences, have been shown to reduce infection rates and there is no universal protocol. Risk factors for driveline infection include trauma to the driveline exit site, younger age, higher body mass index and exposed driveline velour. Meticulous exit site and driveline care and driveline immobilization are advised to reduce the risk of infection.  </p>

<p>Driveline drainage culture and blood cultures should be obtained, and imaging may be needed as well. It is important to note that driveline site assessment and obtaining specimens of the drainage should only be performed by members of the LVAD team (or designated shared care centers) in order to limit the number of times and the number of people to whom the driveline is exposed. Culture of any drainage is recommended. Abnormal swelling of the region surrounding the driveline site should be assessed by imaging studies (i.e., ultrasound, CT scan or PET scan) to assess the presence, extent, and appearance of any fluid collections. Blood cultures are important to evaluate for occult bloodstream infections, because LVAD patients may not present with typical signs and symptoms. Typical pathogens are skin flora like coagulase-negative Staphylococci and <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus.</hi> Gram-negative organisms like <hi rend="italic">Pseudomonas</hi> spp. and Enterobacteriaceae, and fungal infections can also occur. Surgical evaluation for debridement of the driveline exit site may be needed depending on the extent of the infection, and should be performed by a surgical team with LVAD experience. Infectious diseases consultation may be needed, particularly in the case of polymicrobial infections or multidrug-resistant organisms. If bacteremia or sepsis are present, a chest and abdomen CT, transthoracic and even transesophageal echocardiogram should be obtained to evaluate for the source of the infection (especially in patients with pacemaker or defibrillator leads). There is an emerging role for PET imaging with F-18 labeled fluoro-2-deoxyglucose. VAD infections are biofilm-based and difficult to eradicate. Treatment strategies for VAD infections include intravenous antibiotics followed by oral suppression in tandem with surgical debridement. Infections tend to be recurrent despite debridement, with Pseudomonas infection in particular, showing a lower success rate. The role of pump exchange is not clearly defined. One study noted a particularly poor prognosis with candidemia and concomitant presence of a cardiac-implanted electronic device, and failure to remove the device during pump exchange was associated with poor outcomes in 65% of patients.  </p>

<p>Some studies have shown that LVAD infections adversely affect survival after adjusting for age and comorbidities. One prospective study showed a 22% overall infection rate of LVADs and a 5.6-times greater 1-year mortality in patients with infections. Besides mortality, LVAD infections are associated with a greater risk of pump thrombosis, bleeding complications, prolonged hospitalization, need for pump exchange, and failure to achieve transplantation. Bloodstream infections, in particular, are associated with stroke and increased mortality. Despite these risks, the presence of an LVAD infection has not been shown to have a negative impact on post-transplant outcomes.  </p>

<head> 8.2. Gastrointestinal (GI) Bleed</head>
<p>
GI bleed is one of the most frequent complications after LVAD implant and the most common reason for hospital readmission. It is triggered by the use of antiplatelet and anticoagulant therapy. Additionally, CF-LVADs can cause acquired von Willebrand factor deficiency due to the high shear stress imposed by the LVAD motor, resulting in breakdown of large von Willebrand factor multimers. Also, continuous flow physiology and dysregulation of angiogenic factors have been shown to lead to development of arteriovenous malformations (AVMs) in the gastrointestinal tract, nasopharynx, brain, and other tissues.  </p>
</text>
