<text id="autogum_academic_doc193" title="Appraisal of Comparative Therapeutic Potential of Undoped and Nitrogen-Doped Titanium Dioxide Nanoparticles" shortTile="appraisal-comparative" author="Muhammad  Arslan Ahmad, Yang Yuesuo, Qiang Ao, Muhammad Adeel, Zhang  Yan Hui, Rabia Javed" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1420-3049/24/21/3916/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Biomedical applications of metallic oxide nanoparticles are recently considered an interesting avenue of research regarding nano-biotechnology. Nanoparticles possess unique physio-chemical, optical and electro-magnetic properties that make them appropriate tools for various applications in the field of materials science and pharmacy. Co-precipitation is the most adaptive method for preparation of metallic oxide nanoparticles because of its reproducibility and cheapness. Titanium dioxide (TiO2) nanoparticles have been vastly synthesized by different chemical routes. Doping prevents aggregation between nanoparticles ultimately leading to their stability, longevity as well as intensified reactivity. Hence, TiO2 nanoparticles have been doped with Ni, Cu, Fe, Mo, N and other metals using hydrolysis, precipitation, sol-gel and other methods for fabrication in the past. Metal-doped TiO2 nanoparticles serve many environmental remediation purposes like removal of organic dyes and wastes/pollutants owing to their tremendous photocatalytic activity. In context of their role in biomedicine, antibacterial activity of Mn-doped TiO2 and Nd-doped TiO2 nanoparticles has been documented. TiO2 nanoparticles have been proven important skin protecting agents against UV radiation and used in sunscreens/cosmetics as reported by Viana et al.. Cytotoxicity of TiO2 nanoparticles doped with Ag, Cu, Fe has been validated against human cancer cell lines and hence these nanoparticles have been successfully declared anti-cancerous materials. </p>

<p>Regarding bioremediation studies, the photocatalytic property of N-doped TiO2 nanoparticles for air and water purification was exclusively described. Talking about biomedical properties, Zane et al. reported the biocompatibility and antibacterial activity of N-doped TiO2 nanoparticles and its applications in dental resin formulations. Moreover, the assessment of orthodontic brackets coated with N-doped TiO2 nanoparticles against <hi rend="italic">Streptococcus mutans</hi> was illuminated by Salehi et al.. Atchudan et al. explained the applications of N-doped TiO2 nanoparticles in cell imaging due to their good biocompatibility. Li et al. studied the photokilling effect of N-doped TiO2 nanoparticles on cancer cells. </p>

<p>The purpose of the present study was to complement the vacuum in literature regarding exploration of comprehensive biological potential of N-doped and undoped TiO2 nanoparticles. According to our knowledge, this is the first report covering multifunctional role of bare TiO2 nanoparticles and N-doped TiO2 nanoparticles in biomedicine. Antibacterial, antifungal, antioxidant, antidiabetic, protein kinase inhibition and cytotoxicity assays have been carried out under in vitro conditions. Comparative assessment of undoped and N-doped TiO2 nanoparticles has been performed to exploit the effectivity of these nanoparticles to be used as drug-loading agents or carriers in nanomedicine for the cure of countless fatal diseases disrupting human health. </p>
</text>
