<text id="autogum_academic_doc021" title="Dasatinib Inhibits Procoagulant and Clot Retracting Activities of Human Platelets" shortTile="dasatinib-inhibits" author="Ildikó Beke Debreceni, Gabriella Mezei, Péter Batár, Árpád Illés, János Kappelmayer" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5430/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs) are widely used drugs as a targeted strategy for cancer treatment with the aim of prolonging progression-free survival. Deregulated tyrosine kinase activity of the BCR-ABL oncoprotein is the biochemical hallmark of Philadelphia chromosome-positive (Ph+) hematological malignancies. Currently, several generations of BCR-ABL TKIs are in clinical use for treatment of these malignancies. Introduction of the second-generation TKIs, nilotinib and dasatinib as first-line treatment resulted in rapid and deep reduction of BCR/ABL1 allele transcripts, and this provided a possibility for long-term survival in CML. In addition to CML, several other patient populations were identified that undoubtedly benefited from TKI treatment. Patients with Ph+ adult acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) may also benefit from an alternate TKI therapy. In the treatment of pediatric patients with Ph+ ALL the addition of TKIs to conventional chemotherapy has improved outcomes of patients. It has long been known that second-generation TKIs may have side effects as nilotinib can potentiate a prothrombotic state while dasatinib is known to cause platelet dysfunction e.g. impaired collagen-induced platelet adhesion and aggregation. Although both drugs bind to the ATP binding site of the kinase domain of the BCR/ABL protein they have different off target inhibitory effect on several other tyrosine kinases. Dasatinib is a potent multikinase inhibitor, including c-KIT, EPHA2, platelet-derived growth factor receptor-β, and SFKs. Nilotinib is also a second generation TKI with a broad inhibitory spectrum of various tyrosine kinases (PDGFR, c-KIT, ARG, EPHB4), but it does not inhibit SFKs. Previous in vitro and ex vivo studies with dasatinib have demonstrated a faulty platelet aggregation. On the contrary nilotinib has no effect on platelet aggregation, at all. Therefore, we used nilotinib as a negative control in our experiments. </p>

<p>Sarcoma family kinases (SFKs) are critical regulators of platelet signaling and activation. These kinases play a central role in mediating rapid response of platelets to vascular injury. They transmit activation signals from several various platelet receptors. There are numerous members of this group and among the SFKs Lyn, Fyn, and Src have been implicated in activation of the GPVI receptor and the integrin receptor signaling and are frequently studied proteins as they are present in both human and mouse platelets. TKIs have a different off-target multikinase inhibitory effect. Comprehensive drug-protein interaction profiles were described to predict the potential side effects of BCR-ABL TKIs. It was found that the most prominent dasatinib-targeted SFKs are Lyn, Fyn, and Src, kinases and their negative regulator C-terminal Src kinase (Csk), but nilotinib does not bind to these kinases. During vascular injury it is primarily the subendothelial collagen that activates platelets and result in subsequent platelet aggregation. A population of the collagen-adhered platelets responds by surface exposure of the procoagulant phosphatidylserine (PS). This surface expressed PS facilitates the binding of coagulation factors and by this promotes thrombin generation. In addition, platelets participate in fibrin formation and regulate the process of clot retraction. </p>

<p>We intended to investigate whether dasatinib also affects the platelet procoagulant activity and thereby coagulation. For this reason, we examined the in vitro and ex vivo effects of dasatinib on platelet procoagulant response in dasatinib treated platelets of healthy volunteers and in samples derived from CML patients on dasatinib therapy. We found that at therapeutic concentration dasatainib, but not nilotinib, has a strong inhibitory effect on platelet procoagulant activity and on clot retraction both in non activated as well as in convulxin activated platelets. </p>
</text>
