<text id="autogum_academic_doc704" title="Theorizing Conscious Black Asexuality through Claire Kann’s Let’s Talk about Love" shortTile="theorizing-conscious" author="Brittney Miles" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-0787/8/4/165/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Defining Asexuality in Academic Literature</head>
<p>
Asexuality is often defined as some degree of being void of sexual attraction to others, sexual interest, or desire. Historically, asexuality has been framed as either pathological or non-pathological in different contexts. Asexuality was originally defined as non-pathological when it was considered a lack of sexual interest towards other people with the potential to engage in sexual activities. This is differentiated from the more frequent, medically pathologized people who have a lifelong disinterest in any sexual activity (Chasin 2013; Cerankowski and Milks 2010). The framing of asexuality as an indication of an inherent biological problem comes from the belief that humans are naturally sexual. However, this fails to recognize the role of dynamic sexual politics, which challenge the notion of asexuality as unnatural. </p>

<p>Furthermore, a confusion about asexuality persists where asexuality is conflated with celibacy. While (not) performing sex because of celibacy or asexuality is a choice, asexuality is a sexual politic that is present regardless of one’s choice to engage in sex or not. Asexuality as an orientation is social, biological, agentic, and not simply situated in whether or not a person has sex; celibacy is more simply a choice to abstain (Hanson 2014). Confusion about the definition and boundaries of asexuality is tied to its erasure and exclusion from mainstream queer narratives. Asexuality as a queer identity is often left out of general queer knowledges that stops short of understanding what LGBT means. While asexualities rest in the margins of unfamiliarity when considered against other queer identities such as lesbian, gay, bisexual, and trans identity categories, expectedly, within asexual identities, there are hierarchies of privilege. These stratified relations prioritize cisgendered, hetero- or aromantic, white, middle-class people (Chu 2014). These identities are more legible than asexuality in their hegemonic navigation of power structures in society. As a result of this illegibility, asexualities are made invisible, including the ways which they differently challenge norms and cultural expectations of eroticism. </p>

<p>Asexuality has been included in recent calls for greater inclusivity and representation in sexuality literature (Cerankowski and Milks 2010). As part of a call for critical sexuality studies, asexuality was situated as a necessary topic of further exploration to adequately explore power and privilege as they intersect with sexuality (Fahs and McClelland 2016). Additionally, a recent study of asexual women of color found that the identity construction processes tied to self-definition and acceptance are strongly shaped by the inseparability of race, gender, and asexuality (Foster et al. 2019). These more recent academic calls to more broadly interrogate asexuality in theoretical explorations and clinical practice aim to improve general knowledge of asexuality and the interpersonal experiences of asexual folks (Foster and Scherrer 2014). These studies indicate a shift towards and need for more radical conceptions of asexuality beyond the meanings we currently use. </p>
</text>
