<text id="autogum_academic_doc008" title="Research on the Vertical Vibration Characteristics of Hydraulic Screw Down System of Rolling Mill under Nonlinear Friction" shortTile="research-vertical" author="Yongshun Zhang, Wanlu Jiang, Yong Zhu, Zhenbao Li" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2227-9717/7/11/792/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Numerical Simulation</head><head> 4.1. The Parameters Selection of Simulation Model</head>
<p>
The MATLAB is adopted for system modeling and simulation, and ode45 algorithm is employed. Considering that the pressure pulsation caused by the oil pump is 12%, the speed of plunger pump is 990 rpm, the number of plungers is seven, so the pulsation frequency is 116 Hz. The nominal parameters of the hydraulic screw down system of the rolling mill used in the simulation are shown in Table 1. </p>

<head> 4.2. Simulation Results and Analysis</head><head> 4.2.1. Influence of Different Equivalent Damping Coefficients on Nonlinear Dynamic Behavior</head>
<p>
It is found that different equivalent damping coefficients have a great influence on the nonlinear system. At the initial value , the system damping coefficients are respectively defined as , , and . The time–domain diagrams of the vibration displacement of the cylinder are displayed in <figure>Figure 4</figure>a,b. The phase diagrams of the vibration displacement–velocity are shown in <figure>Figure 4</figure>c. An improved frequency–domain integral method based on low-frequency filtering of vibration intensity is adopted to obtain the vibration intensity of the system under different damping coefficients. The curve is shown in <figure>Figure 5</figure>. </p>

<p><figure>Figure 4</figure> shows the vibration simulations that result from the hydraulic cylinder of the rolling mill with different equivalent damping coefficients under the same conditions. Through the vibration displacement curve, it can be clearly found that the vibration amplitude of vibration displacement significantly increases with the damping coefficient decreasing. Through the phase diagram, it can be found that the system moves from a stable state to a periodic vibration state and becomes unstable with the damping coefficient decreasing. From the perspective of vibration intensity, as shown in <figure>Figure 5</figure>, it can clearly be found that the vibration intensity of the system can be effectively suppressed by increasing the damping. </p>

<head> 4.2.2. Influence of Different Leakage Coefficients on Nonlinear Dynamic Behavior</head>
<p>
The hydraulic system is sealed with a rubber ring. Due to the influence of oil temperature and oil cleanliness, the seal of the hydraulic cylinder will deteriorate with time, resulting in different levels of oil leakage. By studying the influence of different internal leakage coefficients on the system, the vibration mechanism of the hydraulic cylinder caused by the leakage can be analyzed. </p>

<p>The leak coefficients of the hydraulic cylinder are defined as , , and . If you take the initial value , the time–domain diagram of the vibration displacement of the cylinder and the phase diagram of the vibration displacement–speed are shown in <figure>Figure 6</figure>. The vibration intensities of the system under different leakage coefficients are displayed in <figure>Figure 7</figure>. </p>

<p><figure>Figure 6</figure> shows the simulation results of the different leakage coefficients of the hydraulic cylinder under the same other conditions. It can be seen from <figure>Figure 6</figure> that the vibration displacement of the hydraulic cylinder is small when the leakage coefficient is small. And from the phase diagram, it can be observed that the system is convergence. By increasing the leakage coefficient of the hydraulic cylinder, the amplitude of the vibration displacement increases. From the phase diagram, it is difficult to stabilize from the convergence to the stage of multi-period vibration. From the variation of vibration intensity in <figure>Figure 7</figure>, it can be found that the vibration intensity increases with the increase of the leakage coefficient. Therefore, the increase of system leakage will increase the intensity of vertical vibration. </p>

<head> 4.2.3. The Influences of Proportional Parameter of Vibration Controller on Nonlinear Dynamic Behavior</head>
<p>
The proportional parameters of the controller affect the control effect of vibration suppression. As certain process parameters or structural parameters of the system are changed, fixed parameters  are bound to have adverse effects. When other parameters are the same, the proportional coefficients of the controller are set as , , and . Integral coefficient , and differential coefficient . The initial value is set as . The time–domain diagram and the vibration displacement–speed phase diagram of the cylinder are shown in <figure>Figure 8</figure>. With the proportional coefficient increasing, the vibration intensity of the cylinder is reveled in <figure>Figure 9</figure>. </p>

<p>The PID control algorithm, with the characteristics of simple structure and convenient implementation, can be well applied to practical engineering. In the PID control algorithm, the proportion coefficient determines the speed of system response, and the appropriate integral coefficient can effectively eliminate the system error. Therefore, increasing the proportional coefficient can improve the response speed of the system, but a big proportional coefficient may cause the system instability. </p>
</text>
