<text id="autogum_academic_doc019" title="Density Functional Theory Analysis of the Adsorption Interactions of Carbon Impurities in Coal-associated Kaolinite" shortTile="density-functional" author="Fangqin Lu, Lingyun Liu, Fanfei Min, Jun Chen, Mingxu Zhang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2227-9717/7/11/782/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Coal-associated kaolinite is one of the major clay minerals in coal-water slurries. It is fine-grained with high surface electronegativity, and strong hydration films readily form on the particle surfaces. The surface hydration films strengthen the hydration repulsion as well as steric hindrance effects among the particles in the coal slurries. These effects, combined with the electrostatic repulsion caused by the large number of negative charges on the particle surfaces, help maintain the stability of fine kaolinites in coal slurries, which makes it difficult for the kaolinite to aggregate and settle, and thus, seriously affects the sedimentation and clarification of coal-water slurries. Meanwhile, the hydration film can also increase the viscosity of kaolinite particle–fluid suspensions, thus further reducing the efficiency of subsequent coal-slurry dewatering. </p>

<p>Through experiments and theoretical calculations, Cui et al. found that an important premise for the separation of fine kaolinite is to regulate the structural properties of its interface. The main method of regulation is to add surfactants, such as cationic amine salts or quaternary ammonium salts, which regulate the hydrophobicity of the kaolinite surfaces. To more deeply understand the functional mechanism, the interactions of the reagent at the kaolinite interface must be explored from a microscopic viewpoint at the molecular/atomic level. Density functional theory (DFT) and DFT-based first-principles calculation methods are widely applied as effective theoretical tools for the calculation of mineral structures and their surface interactions. For example, Wang et al. applied DFT to find that 2,4-dinitrotoluene adsorbs on fine kaolinite surfaces mainly through the formation of hydrogen bonds. Also using DFT methods, Chen et al. simulated the adsorption of amine/ammonium cations on kaolinite (001) and (001) surfaces, and found that adsorption was the joint result of electrostatic attraction and the formation of hydrogen bonds, with the former as the major driving force. </p>

<p>Currently, researchers who have applied DFT to study surface adsorption in kaolinite have established simulations based on a perfect bulk kaolinite lattice, with few studies accounting for the occurrence of impurities in the kaolinite. Carbon impurities are a common contaminant type in coal-associated kaolinite. In the present study, scanning electron microscopy/energy dispersive spectrometry (SEM-EDS) and X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS) analyses were performed to determine the major elemental constituents of the carbon impurities and the structure and relative contents of the C and O elements. Subsequently, two typical structural models were constructed for the carbon impurities, and DFT was applied to simulate the adsorption mechanism of each unit on the kaolinite (001) and (001) surfaces so as to determine the adsorption configuration. The results of the present study can provide a theoretical basis for the further understanding of actual adsorption on the surface of kaolinite in coal slurries. </p>
</text>
