<text id="autogum_academic_doc480" title="Repeated Vaginal Exposures to the Common Cosmetic and Household Preservative Methylisothiazolinone Induce Persistent, Mast Cell-Dependent Genital Pain in ND4 Mice" shortTile="repeated-vaginal" author="Erica Arriaga-Gomez, Jaclyn Kline, Elizabeth Emanuel, Nefeli Neamonitaki, Tenzin Yangdon, Hayley Zacheis, Dogukan Pasha, Jinyoung Lim, Susan Bush, Beebie Boo, Hanna Mengistu, Ruby Kinnamon, Robin Shields-Cutler, Elizabeth Wattenberg, Devavani Chatterjea" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5361/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Debilitating, unexplained provoked localized vulvar pain or vulvodynia affects a significant proportion (~8%) of women and is epidemiologically linked to a history of both seasonal and contact allergies. Vulvar biopsies from diagnosed patients show increases in mast cells and nerves. To recapitulate and dissect the pathobiology of allergy-driven tactile sensitivity and to inform novel therapies, we established mouse models of allergy-driven genital pain. We have shown that contact hypersensitivity to the commonly used laboratory haptens oxazolone (Ox) on the labiar skin or dinitrofluorobenzene (DNFB) on the labiar skin or vaginal canal induces persistent tactile genital pain and increased accumulation of mast cells in the labiar tissues of outbred, female ND4 mice well beyond the resolution of visible inflammation. Chemical depletion of labiar mast cells reduced Ox-driven painful responses and therapeutic topical administration of Δ-9-tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) in the vaginal canal alleviated DNFB-induced pain and reduced numbers of accumulated mast cells in the affected tissue. Here, we examined the potential of a common household chemical, 2-methyl-4-isothiazolin-3-one/methylisothiazolinone (MI), to induce contact hypersensitivity reactions and consequent allergy-driven genital pain in ND4 female outbred mice. MI is a biocide preservative present in soaps, shampoos, vaginal washes, household cleaners, and paints. Recent evidence suggests that a significant portion of people exposed to MI developed the capacity for an allergic response, showed exacerbated inflammatory responses, and experienced tissue injury in the skin or lungs after exposure. Allergic responses to MI have also been linked to vulvar dermatitis, but no connections between such dermatoses and the later development of vulvar pain have been made in the published clinical literature. Recently, Reed and colleagues identified exposures to household and workplace chemicals as a possible risk factor for the development of vulvodynia. Our previously published mouse models demonstrated the biological plausibility of the epidemiological link between chemical exposures and the development of genital pain. However, a specific link between vulvodynia and a known environmental chemical does not yet exist. We suggest that MI is a plausible candidate for an environmental irritant/allergen, and that exposure to MI might drive allergy-provoked pain. Here, we repeatedly applied MI dissolved in saline (a surrogate for water-based cleansers that typically contain MI as a preservative) topically within the vaginal canals of mice and characterized consequent allergic inflammation, accumulation of mast cells, and ano-genital sensitivity to pressure. We also assessed the effects of therapeutic and preventive administration of topical THC treatments in the vaginal canal on mast cell abundance and painful sensitivity. </p>
</text>
