<text id="autogum_academic_doc271" title="Integrated Battery Charger for Electric Vehicles Based on a Dual-Inverter Drive and a Three-Phase Current Rectifier" shortTile="integrated-battery" author="Vitor  Fernão Pires, Joaquim Monteiro, Armando Cordeiro, José  Fernando Silva" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-9292/8/10/1199/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The importance of electrical vehicles (EV) has been hugely increased, year after year. Certainly, their role is critical to answering the problem of the greenhouse effect. Indeed, in accordance with the International Energy Agency, in 2018 the global stock of electric passenger cars exceeded 5 million, which has increased 63%, taking into consideration the previous year. On the other hand, several governments have passed legislation in order to encourage the transition from fuel fossil vehicles to EVs. In this context, the technology solutions and research associated with these vehicles have become increasingly important. One of the fundamental areas of the EV is the charging of the EVs batteries. </p>

<p>There are several aspects that should be considered for EV chargers connected to the grid. It should be considered whether they will be used for slow or fast charging, as well as their impact on the grid. Regarding this last issue, the charger must be designed in order to minimize the impact on the grid power quality. In this way, it should be designed to ensure that the charger is a load with high power factor. Many high power factor rectifiers have been proposed and studied. Their topologies have been classified as Boost, Buck-Boost, and Buck, in accordance with their capability to generate an output voltage that is higher or lower than the maximum input voltage. </p>

<p>Usually, EV chargers are classified as off-board or on-board. The off-board chargers are normally developed for high power DC fast charging. Several rectifier types have been proposed and investigated as surveyed in. The on-board chargers are for reduced powers and are integrated into the EVs. This solution gives high flexibility to the drivers since it usually allows the EV to charge through an electric power outlet. However, the integration of the charger in the EV will increase total weight, volume, and cost. Thus, to minimize this drawback, the chargers should be designed, in order to use as much as possible, the same available hardware used for the traction of the EV. To implement this type of solution, it must be considered that the charging and propulsion of the EV do not occur simultaneously. Indeed, the vehicle has the electric motor stopped when the vehicle is connected to the electric grid for the charging process. So, when the EV is in charging mode, the motor(s) windings will be used as filter inductors, storage elements, or isolated transformers. </p>

<p>Several configurations have been proposed for the integrated battery charger of EVs. These proposals have also taken into consideration the motor type. For the case of the three-phase motors, solutions using a Boost rectifier were considered, being the motor used as a filter inductor. These solutions require having access to the motor, namely to the terminals of the motors windings, or neutral point of the windings or use a contactor to reconfigure the connection of the motor windings. An EV isolated charger for a lift truck was also proposed in. Another approach was through the use of current rectifiers with Buck-Boost characteristics. An integrated charger with this type of converter and three-phase connection is presented in. Due to the converter type, in charging mode, the motor is used as a coupled DC inductor. Integrated chargers have also been proposed for multiphase motors. These chargers have the advantage of avoiding the problem of torque generation in the propulsion motor that exists in systems that use three-phase motors and Boost rectifiers. So, solutions for five, six, and nine machine phases have been proposed. However, for many EVs, the dominant motor is the three-phase and chargers for multiphase motors cannot be applied. A good possibility is the use of multilevel inverters for the drive of the three-phase AC motor. Very few works have addressed the multilevel configuration for the EVs. A charger was presented for an EV drive with two, two-level voltage source inverters (dual inverter), in. However, the proposed charger was developed for connection to DC power outlets only. </p>
</text>
