<text id="autogum_academic_doc714" title="Sustainable Construction Project Management (SCPM) Evaluation—A Case Study of the Guangzhou Metro Line-7, PR China" shortTile="sustainable-construction" author="Na Dong, Yanting Fu, Feng Xiong, Lujie Li, Yibin Ao, Igor Martek" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5731/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Methodology</head>
<p>
In view of the above literature review, this paper aims at establishing a set of sustainable performance evaluation indexes considering social well-being, environmental protection, and financial earnings, along with a set of feasible evaluation methods to ensure that reasonable performance evaluation can be realized within a project. Firstly, the comprehensive evaluation index system of SCPM is constructed. In the index system, the greenization and informatization are not considered in isolation, but their impact on traditional project management performance measures, such as finances and safety, is also reflected. Secondly, the ratings for the evaluation index that is modeled by the iG1, are given in linguistic terms. Given different kinds of professional knowledge and work experience, the evaluators’ understanding of the evaluation index and the enterprises may be different. Thus, in aggregating linguistic ratings, the amount of calculation is small so as to reduce errors. Thirdly, the feasibility and practical application of the proposed approach is verified using a case study of the Guangzhou Metro Line 7 (GML7). It also provides a valuable reference for the implementation of the evaluation of SCPM for other construction enterprises. </p>

<head> 3.1. Index System of SCPM Performance</head><head> 3.1.1. The Dimension of the Index System</head>
<p>
An important step in establishing a comprehensive performance evaluation system for SCPM is to identify key aspects. It is impossible to analyze all aspects of SCPM. Such an attempt might not only confuse the experts of interactive information but also lead to an inefficient evaluation process. The indicators of this research are mainly established through three channels: Literature review, enterprise database analysis, and the future development trend analysis of the construction industry. The framework of the performance evaluation index system establishment is shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>. The first step is the selection of the dimension of the evaluation index system. The traditional dimension of management performance includes financial, safety, schedule, and quality. Others, the frontier dimension includes two aspects, which are informatization and greenization. The second step is classification and filtering the secondary indicator based on literature review and construction enterprise management database.  </p>

<p>The “knowledge area” proposed by PMI has been used in traditional CPM performance research studies. Various studies have focused on reducing the integration management, construction cost, and schedule control. Demirkesen and Ozorhon contributed to the project management body of knowledge in that it develops a conceptual framework consisting of specific components for integration CPM, whereas the dimensions of project management performance are time, cost, quality, safety, and client satisfaction. Tan and Xiong sorted out 50 domestic theses related to performance evaluation in China and finally listed the high-frequency performance indicators which were divided into different hierarchical structures. In their review, the most frequent indicators focus on financial, quality and time management. The performance evaluation indicators of large-scale engineering projects were divided into five categories: Human, material, machine, method, and environment. In this study, we chose the four most representative dimensions, which are finance, safety, schedule, quality, as the dimensions of the performance index system for SCPM. </p>

<p>In addition to the four dimensions of project management mentioned above, the SCPM performance should take the sustainable development of enterprises into account and encourage the application of cutting-edge technologies to adapt to the future development of the industry. Therefore, based on the traditional view and the perspective of future development, the final sustainable performance index system should consist of the six dimensions: Finance, safety, schedule, quality, informatization, and greenization management. </p>

<head> 3.1.2. The Secondary Indicators of the Index System</head>
<p>
The database established by this enterprise includes two parts: historical projects and actual needs of the Sichuan Huashi construction enterprise group (Huashi Group), which contains 18 sub-construction companies at home and abroad. The Huashi Group ranks 18th among China’s top 60 contractors in ENR, with annual revenue from its main business exceeds 12.7 billion yuan, and stands for the overall development level of the construction industry. </p>

<p>The secondary indicators are filtered and classificated from the Huashi Group management database and literature review. This research looks for the 39 secondary indicators of the six dimensions, <figure>Figure 2</figure> shows the final index system for the comprehensive performance evaluation of the SCPM, and then, the secondary indicators are described in the next chapter. </p>

<head> Indicators for Financial Management</head>
<p>
A company attaches much significance to financial management, which determines how much benefit the construction enterprise can get from a project. According to the enterprise database, the financial management contains three aspects, which are overall financial position, construction costs and financial management plans of the project. The overall financial situation of the project is measured by FM1 (project profit ratio), FM2 (unit profit) and FM3 (per capita profit). FM4 (project cost-saving), FM5 (success of project claims) and FM6 (project payment default) during the project construction stage are used to measure the funds and cost management ability. Beyond that, FM7 (the financial management plan) is crucial to the success of the project.  </p>
</text>
