<text id="autogum_academic_doc359" title="Flow Process for Ketone Reduction Using a Superabsorber-Immobilized Alcohol Dehydrogenase from Lactobacillus brevis in a Packed-Bed Reactor" shortTile="flow-process-ketone" author="Niklas Adebar, Harald Gröger" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2306-5354/6/4/99/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The development of flow processes has gained tremendous interest in recent years in organic chemistry due to numerous advantages of such types of processes over classic batch approaches. In addition to higher efficiency and safety advantages, the ability to ensure constant product quality has turned out to be a major driving force for the development of flow processes. In particular, for active pharmaceutical ingredients (APIs), this aspect is important, as the FDA along with the EPA, as the respective institutions in United States and Europe for approval of medicines, added aspects of continuous manufacturing to their guidelines, whereas for a long time the focus of flow processes was on “classic” chemical processes with, for example, hazardous and thermally labile substances and chemocatalytic reactions. Recently, biocatalysis in flow processes has become an emerging field with an increasing number of examples. An enzymatic reaction of particular interest for an application in flow mode due to its matured technology level is asymmetric ketone reduction, having a proven track record underlined by many successful examples demonstrated in the past for the batch mode. Recently, significant process in the biocatalytic reductive synthesis of alcohols starting from ketones, as well as syntheses by non-enzymatic means, have been reported. In recent years, an increasing number of examples of biocatalysis in flow processes have been reported. Although only being studied to a minor extent, some examples of ketone reductions with an alcohol dehydrogenase (ADH) in flow processes have been described. For example, Wandrey’s and Liese’s groups studied in detail the application of enzyme membrane reactors for enzymatic ketone reduction in a continuously running mode, and packed bed reactor setups were described by further groups using carrier-bound ADH from <hi rend="italic">Lactobacillus brevis</hi> (LB-ADH) in combination with a mobile aqueous phase, or magnetic nanoparticle-bound ADH. In addition, Buehler et al. investigated intensively the use of ADH in aqueous/organic segmented flow systems. It was shown that emulsion formation could be eliminated, and enzymatic mass transfer-limited reactions can be enhanced. Furthermore, different means of stabilization of this reaction system were investigated. Very recently, our group published an improved downstream process by means of such a segmented flow process, illustrated using two different ADHs and substrates. </p>

<p>In continuous processes using packed bed reactors (PBR), catalyst immobilization is a prerequisite. Also, downstream processes benefit from immobilization, as separation of the reaction mixture from the catalyst is easier, and the catalyst reusability is improved. Moreover, both, operational, as well as storage stability of the catalyst can potentially be significantly increased. However, often a significant loss of enzymatic activity during the immobilization process represents a drawback, and the reproducible production of immobilized catalyst may be a further challenge. Numerous techniques have been developed over the past years, which can be classified in the following three major methods: (a) binding to a solid support (carrier), (b) entrapment (encapsulation) in polymer networks, or (c) cross-linking in the form of cross-linked enzyme aggregates (CLEAs) or cross-linked enzyme crystals (CLECs). Recently, much progress in the field of enzyme immobilization has been made.  </p>

<p>In this work, the option of entrapment of enzymes in polymer networks has been chosen. Often for this purpose, organic polymers containing cavities, sol-gel-processed particles, or membranes are used. A special case is the use of superabsorbent polymers to immobilize the entire aqueous phase.. In this case, the enzyme is immobilized in its native aqueous environment, whereby undesired interactions of protein moieties with the support can be prevented. Recently, Gröger et al. applied a method of immobilizing ADHs with superabsorber efficiently for the synthesis of diols in enantiomerically pure form. In this example, the immobilized ADH from <hi rend="italic">Rhodococcus</hi> sp. was used in organic solvents without a major loss in activity. Advantages of this method is the low cost, the very fast immobilization procedure (&lt;30 min), and the excellent catalyst reusability. Challenging, in particular with respect to an application in a fixed bed reactor, might be the gel-like consistency of the hydrogel and mass transfer limitations through phase interfaces in general.  </p>

<p>The absorbent polymer consists of cross-linked polyacrylic acid, which was partially neutralized. Proteins can be embedded in this polymer matrix and can be bound, for example, by ionic interactions of its acid moieties to ionic amino acid residues of the protein (see <figure>Figure 1</figure>A). Also, hydrogen bridges from non-ionic protein residues with superabsorber functionalities (<figure>Figure 1</figure>B) or entrapment of enzyme in superabsorber-bound water residues (<figure>Figure 1</figure>C) can be a possible mode of interaction. </p>

<p>An (<hi rend="italic">R</hi>)-enantioselective ADH from <hi rend="italic">Lactobacillus brevis</hi> (LB-ADH) has been shown to be a versatile catalyst for the reduction of a variety of ketones, ranging from aliphatic ketones to benzylic or propargylic ketones. It can be used as an isolated enzyme or as a whole-cell catalyst. In particular, its tolerance towards organic solvents is outstanding. The stability depends on several factors, such as the nature of the buffer or solvent additives. </p>

<p>In this contribution, the application of a superabsorber-immobilized ADH from <hi rend="italic">L. brevis</hi> for an enzymatic reduction of acetophenone (<b>1</b>) in a flow process is described.  </p>
</text>
