<text id="autogum_academic_doc226" title="Analysis of Tourism Hotspot Behaviour Based on Geolocated Travel Blog Data: The Case of Qyer" shortTile="analysis-tourism" author="Michael Kaufmann, Patrick Siegfried, Lukas Huck, Jürg Stettler" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2220-9964/8/11/493/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Conclusions</head>
<p>
We contribute a system design for detecting tourism hotspots and for segmenting tourists based on their interests in these hotspots, in the case of the geolocated social medium Qyer.com. We theorize our solution towards a generalized formal methodology that can be applied to other geolocated travel blogs. We demonstrate the potential of our system and method through pilot application, analysing Chinese tourism in Switzerland. The following methodological and practical knowledge can be concluded from our research. From an information systems perspective, firstly, our system design and formal methodology for hotspot detection from geolocated social media resulted in plausible geographical distributions of tourism hotspots, as validated by cross-references. This study confirmed the known geographical long-tail distribution of interest, including the hotspot areas of Lucerne, Zurich, Interlaken and Geneva, validating the plausibility of the data and its analysis. Secondly, in the case study, by application of our proposed method we discovered a highly significant stochastic dependence, thus providing evidence for the value or our proposed methodology for segmentation. From a tourism management perspective, thirdly, we can conclude that Chinese independent travellers, which are the main target group of Qyer, are mainly interested in discovering travel hotspots in the same way as packaged tourists are; in addition, they show interest in other, less popular places. Fourthly, we found that social media activity, as measured by the number of followers and the number of distinct commented locations, is a very selective criteria to segment the observed users regarding their interest in travel hotspots versus alternative destinations. Users who are more active, who comment on different places and who have followers are a minority. However, these more active users are significantly more interested in alternative destinations outside the hotspot axis. This information can be applied to define a target group for online marketing to promote alternative travel destinations with the goal to reduce overtourism in travel hotspots. </p>

<p>Nevertheless, this study is not without its limitations. First, there are uncertainties in terms of the user base of Qyer and its representativeness. Even though Qyer is known to be a platform where independent Chinese travellers share their experiences, the possibility that packaged travellers are also active on Qyer cannot be eliminated. Furthermore, it is unknown whether the sample is biased towards other subgroups of Chinese outbound travellers, such as budget travellers. In fact, research has shown that different social media platforms target different user groups. Overall, there are various uncertainties in terms of the representativeness of the entire visitor population as there is a lack of data covering the behaviour and characteristics of the visiting population, which would be necessary to validate the sample. Second, the fact that a user has commented on a place or POI does not necessarily mean that this user has visited the place or POI to which the comment refers, even if this indicates interest. Third, even though Qyer does provide a timestamp for every comment, we found that users tend to upload their comments on various places and POIs at the same time. It is likely that they upload their posts upon return to their accommodations, where Internet access is available to them. As a result, it is impossible to retrace visitor flows and evaluate the length of stay. Finally, it was not possible to separate Chinese residents of Switzerland from the Chinese tourists in Switzerland. Residents could be those visiting less popular areas. </p>

<p>Regarding future research directions, the hotspots detected in this paper do not necessarily imply that the respective destinations experience effects of overtourism. There are various factors, e.,g. population size, history of a tourism destination, distribution of the value added, that leverage the symptoms of overtourism. Thus, the detected hotspots in this paper should be critically evaluated based on additional criteria. In fact, there are major issues associated with social media and blog data. The information gained from these sources may be always biased, which is an issue often associated with generalizations. So, in future studies, we plan to put even more efforts on validating/evaluating the data we used. </p>
</text>
