<text id="autogum_academic_doc400" title="An Intellectual Capital Approach to Citizens’ Quality of Life in Sustainable Cities: A Focus on Europe" shortTile="intellectual-capital" author="Víctor-Raúl López-Ruiz, José-Luis Alfaro-Navarro, Domingo Nevado-Peña" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6025/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Materials and Methods</head>
<p>
The fact that there is no generally-accepted methodology for defining either sustainability or quality of life indicators led us to use the methodology developed in a study by Alfaro et al. (2017). These authors proposed a TBL sustainability indicator for 158 European cities that includes three dimensions related to the types of capital considered in the measurement of intellectual capital. In this regard, environmental structural capital was used to measure the environmental dimension (ED), gross domestic product (GDP) and the labor market situation were used to measure the economic dimension (EcD), and social human capital was used to measure the social dimension (SD). A principal component analysis was used to construct these indices, as was done in a study López et al. (2014), where the good performance of this technique for index construction was demonstrated. This method allows the variable information with available data to be aggregated into a number of synthetic indicators without any loss of information, with weights assigned objectively.  </p>

<p>To prevent any loss of relevance, since it is not possible to aggregate information on variables of different types, they were rescaled by assigning them a maximum value of 100 and a minimum value of 0. These variables were transformed into principal components (PCs) by means of Equation (1):

(1)

where ui is the characteristic vector of each PC and xi is the variable used to build the capitals for the total of k variables considered. Finally, on the basis of these PCs, a value for each of the proposed indicators can be determined by a weighted geometric mean, whereby weightings are assigned according to the percentage of variance retained by each component in the principal component analysis. </p>

<p>According to Alfaro et al. (2017), the environmental dimension (ED) includes four components: pollution, water consumption, waste management, and land uses. Each of these components is measured by a set of indicators. The economic dimension (EcD) is measured using gross domestic product (GDP) and labor market indicators such as unemployment rate, active population, and types of jobs (self-employed, salaried, part-time, and full time). Finally, the social dimension (SD) is disaggregated into four components: health, safety, education, and cultural conditions. Again, each of these is measured by a set of indicators. The cities and indicators used were selected on the basis of the literature review carried out, depending on the data available in the Urban Audit database from Eurostat. Specifically, 17 environmental indicators, 8 economic indicators and 15 social indicators were used to measure the consequences of a sustainable governance for cities within a macroeconomic framework of intellectual capital. Subsequently, these three dimensions were aggregated into a sustainability index using the same procedure.  </p>

<p>Regarding quality of life, we again took a multidimensional approach and drew on the information published by Eurostat in the Flash Eurobarometer 419 to produce a measurement of European citizens’ subjective quality of life based on four dimensions: life satisfaction, mobility, culture and sports, social integration, and public services. In this case, the framework was microeconomic, based on citizens’ subjective perceptions. Table 3 presents the variables used to measure each of these dimensions, along with the definition and the acronym. Values correspond to the percentage of people who, in the abovementioned survey developed in 2015, declared themselves very satisfied with each of the aspects considered. Finally, the indicators obtained for each of the dimensions could be merged to obtain an overall quality of life index for each city, which we refer to as the quality of life (QOL) index. </p>

<p>The available data, taking into account both indices and their component dimensions, yielded complete information for 52 European cities from 24 countries. The results showed that the cities of Hamburg, Kobenhavn and Bratislava occupy the top three positions in terms of sustainability, while Zurich, Kobenhavn and Stockholm stand out in terms of their citizens’ assessment of quality of life. At the other end of the spectrum, the cities with the worst sustainability index score are Napoli, Bucharest and Oviedo, and the worst in terms of quality of life are Roma, Palermo and Lisbon. According to the rankings of the general indices, we observed that the less populated cities offer better positions in terms of citizen’s quality of life, with notable differences with respect to their sustainable development strategy (see Table A1 in Appendix A).  </p>
</text>
