<text id="autogum_academic_doc611" title="Effect of Ambient Oxygen Content, Safety Shoe Type, and Lifting Frequency on Subject’s MAWL and Physiological Responses" shortTile="effect-ambient-oxygen" author="Atef  M. Ghaleb, Mohamed  Z. Ramadan, Ahmed Badwelan, Khalid Saad Aljaloud" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4172/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Over the years, there is an increase in the studies concerning the manual material handling task. Mirta resonates that this is because of the increased documentation of work-related musculoskeletal disorders (WMSDs). Similarly, Mavor and Graham have demonstrated growing episodes of workplace injuries across all occupations, gender, and age. Generally, manual task handling and lifting occur frequently in both occupation and non-occupational jobs, as per its specific requirement, significantly contributing to the increased lower back pain. The occurrence of lower back pain and related musculoskeletal disorders triggered by work rank as second common reasons for referral to physicians following cardiovascular diseases. </p>

<p>A recent study by Shojaei et al. illustrated that work-related musculoskeletal disorder impacts the quality of the industrial workers, and affects the overall production capacity of the company, globally. Vos et al. concluded that lower back pain has accounted for worker’s disability across 139 countries from a total of 188 countries. Not only this, but low back pain (LBP) also adds to the economic and medical burden of the nation, due to lost time, and decreased productivity. It was found in the Workplace Safety and Insurance Board (WSIB) statistical report that a total of 7.7 days of work are lost in a month due to a workplace injury, which accounted for an average of 14.1 working days within three months. Most studies have emphasized on understanding the critical mechanistic and environmental factors that add to the global prevalence and development of LBP. </p>

<p>Evidence from the literature has drawn attention to several parameters (frequency, work postures, load, vertical and horizontal distance, etc.) that impact the occupational workers. Such as, an earlier study of Ciriello and Snook assessed the influence of frequency, distance, height, and size of the box on the worker concerning his lifting, pulling, and pushing tasks by measuring oxygen consumption and heart rate(HR). The study concluded that frequency, distance, height, and size important variables should be considered when determining maximum acceptable weights (MAW). Similar results are indicated by the recent research of Abadi et al. on Iranian workers, which reported that variables such as lifting frequency and the box size affected worker’s maximum acceptable weight of lift (MAWL) and heart rate. </p>

<p>Analysis of experimental studies has shown that generally, the focus of the lifting tasks for the previous researches has been centered on a single parameter rather than all. Moreover, those studies, which have included all parameters, were restricted to the Western work population such as America, Australia, Britain, and more. In order to expand the research area further, the study evaluates the materials handling activities in Saudi Arabia constituting, all parameters of lifting tasks as an integrated group. Many researchers had investigated a person’s capacity to do manual handling activities in a normal environment or a hot environment. Despite it, the influence of different hypoxia levels on manual handling activities is found to be an untested area. The lack of literature concerning the safety guidelines regarding worker’s lifting capabilities while wearing safety shoes also encourages the researcher to carry out this study on the Saudi population.  </p>

<p>Moreover, Ayoub provided three methods to control the lifting risk, which can be used separately or together. These include; (a) hazard control through training in safe lifting, (b) control of employee exposure through pre-employment strength testing, and (c) control of job demands through the adoption of workloads acceptable for the industrial worker. Snook et al. studied 191 cases of lower back (LB) injuries to define the effectiveness of prophylactic methods utilized in industrial establishments. They have noticed that the popular selection approaches were not an effective control for injuries of LB, as well as training on procedures of safe lifting. The authors noted that the worker who performed extensive manual handling tasks is three times more likely to experience back pain. </p>

<p>Similarly, Maiti proposed a technique to define the mean steady pause time from fluctuating working heart rate and frequency of lifting. This kind of load-handling task presented a higher relative heart rate and lower work efficiency. Abadi et al. supply that this pain increases the absenteeism of the worker, impacting the overall functionality of the nation. </p>
</text>
