<text id="autogum_academic_doc587" title="Sea Ice Extent Detection in the Bohai Sea Using Sentinel-3 OLCI Data" shortTile="sea-ice-extent-detection" author="Hua Su, Bowen Ji, Yunpeng Wang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/20/2436/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions</head>
<p>
Two sea ice information indexes have been developed to quickly and accurately extract the extent of sea ice from OLCI remote-sensing data. Comparison of the extraction results with higher-resolution Sentinel-2 MSI imagery verifies that these indexes enable sea ice mapping with OLCI data in the Bohai Sea. The Normalized Difference Sea Ice Information Index (), which is the normalized ratio of Band 20 to Band 21 in OLCI TOA reflectance images, and the Enhanced Normalized Difference Sea Ice Information Index (), which is a modification of  in which Bands 12 and 16 are also incorporated, can effectively detect sea ice information in the Bohai Sea and suppress most background information, such as coverage by land, cloud, and snow. Comparison between the results from our indexes, famous NDSI, and SVM methods indicates that sediment-laden water can interfere with sea ice extraction with the  and NDSI but that the  and SVM suffer from less such interference. However, these four methods have poorer performance in detecting thin sea ice in the western Bohai Sea than they do in detecting thick sea ice. The accuracy evaluation suggests that our  index can rapidly and accurately detect and map the sea ice extent in the Bohai Sea during winter. The results also show our approach can extract most of the sea ice (including nilas ice, gray ice, and gray-white ice) in OLCI images, but the new ice which is small and thin is hard to interpret and detect from the medium-resolution OLCI images due to the limitation of the spatial resolution. Moreover, it would be better to reset the threshold values when employing our indexes to detect sea ice extent in other years because the ice conditions vary with the years. </p>

<p>The spatiotemporal evolution of the Bohai Sea ice in the winter of 2017–2018 was monitored by applying the  to OLCI images. Two major increases were detected in the sea ice extent in mid-January and early February. The largest extent of the sea ice was 13,060 km2 on January 28. After reaching its peak in late January 2018, sea ice coverage remained high until early February, and the sea ice then gradually melted from south to north in mid-February. The whole period when there was ice coverage lasted for about four months, within which there was a significant expansion in mid-January and a final fading away in early March. Overall, our proposed method provides a convenient and effective technique for sea ice detection and evolution study in the Bohai Sea, which can help monitor the recent impacts of global warming.
 </p>
</text>
