<text id="autogum_academic_doc530" title="A Coupled 1D–3D Numerical Method for Buoyancy-Driven Heat Transfer in a Generic Engine Bay" shortTile="coupled-dd-numerical" author="Blago Minovski, Lennart Löfdahl, Jelena Andrić, Peter Gullberg" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4156/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Numerical Procedure</head><head> 4.1. Computational Domain</head>
<p>
The computational domain illustrated in <figure>Figure 2</figure> is an exact replica of the experimental setup, comprising the solid subdomain parts (the engine, the exhaust manifolds, and the enclosure), and the fluid subdomain (the volume under the enclosure, as well as the surrounding containment area), making it possible to employ the most suitable models for the fluid and solid parts, respectively, and to establish a direct coupling between these models. In this manner, the physics of the system can be capured with sufficient accuracy at lower computational costs. </p>

<head> 4.2. 1D Model of Transient Heat Transfer in Engine Solids</head>
<p>
The 1D thermal model of heat transfer in the engine solids is used where the simplified engine and the exhaust manifolds are represented by lumped thermal masses. The concept of lumped thermal masses is based on the assumption that temperature variations within a solid, participating in heat transfer with a surrounding medium, can be neglected as compared to the temperature difference between the solid and the fluid. Previous experimental and numerical results have shown that this approach is valid for the exhaust manifolds and for all engine surfaces except the right and left engine walls, see Merati et al. and Chen et al. for more details. A good example of solids which can be accurately modeled using a single lumped thermal mass are the exhaust manifolds, for which experimental observations confirmed negligible internal temperature differences and uniform temperature distribution on their surfaces. The surfaces of the left and right engine walls, on the other hand, exhibit significant temperature gradients due to high radiative heat flux from the adjacent exhaust manifolds. Therefore, each of the engine side walls is represented by a network of 55 interfaced lumped thermal masses to provide sufficient spatial discretization to accurately capture the temperature distribution. The specific topography and dimensions of the thermal masses comprising this network are chosen so that their centers coincide with the locations of the thermocouples from the experiment, as illustrated in <figure>Figure 3</figure>. The actual materials used to build the parts of the experimental setup and their exact masses are used to model the lumped thermal masses. The variations of thermal conductivity and specific heat with temperature are accounted for. All relevant details are provided in Table 2 and Table 3, respectively. It should be noted that each row of interfaced thermal masses in the network representing the engine side wall corresponds to one row of adjacent sectors of the physical wall from top to bottom. </p>

<head> 4.3. 3D CFD Numerical Solver for the Fluid Flow and Heat Transfer</head>
<p>
The governing equations of the fluid flow are numerically solved in STAR-CCM+ and a polyhedral computational mesh with a total cell count of 25 million is generated from the CAD model of the enclosure and the containment area. The average spatial discretization varies within the limits of 2 and 120 mm depending on the location. Denser mesh is used in the vicinity of the exhaust manifolds and in the upper part of the enclosure to more accurately resolve the temperature gradients and the buoyancy-driven flow field. The maximum cell size is 3 mm for all the surfaces located above the exhaust manifolds. The thickness of the first prismatic layer on the surfaces is approximately 0.3 mm, which results in maximum  values of close to unity. <figure>Figure 4</figure> illustrates the computational grid at the central section plane through the fluid domain. The boundary conditions for the 3D CFD model are the temperatures of the exhaust manifolds, the engine walls and the containment walls as obtained from stable measurement readings in the experiment. A no-slip boundary condition is applied on all walls. An initially quiescent flow field with a uniform temperature of 30 C is considered. A second-order spatial discretization scheme is used with a coupled implicit solver to compute the flow and temperature fields. </p>
</text>
