<text id="autogum_academic_doc027" title="Improved Astaxanthin Production with Corynebacterium glutamicum by Application of a Membrane Fusion Protein" shortTile="improved-astaxanthin" author="Nadja  A. Henke, Volker  F. Wendisch" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-3397/17/11/621/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The demand for naturally produced astaxanthin is estimated to witness an exponential growth of 25% (CAGR) by 2025. This fact is in accordance with a worldwide trend: consumers seek for natural products that are produced in an environmentally friendly way. Moreover, the feed industry, which is the main purchaser of astaxanthin, is growing as well in order to satisfy the demand for animal-based food products such as meat, fish and eggs. As the astaxanthin market is dominated by synthetic astaxanthin that is made from petro chemistry, new production capacities are needed to meet the increasing demand for naturally produced astaxanthin. Fermentations with <hi rend="italic">Corynebacterium glutamicum</hi> dominate food and feed biotechnology since decades for the production of amino acids e.g. l-glutamate and l-lysine. This microorganism naturally synthesizes carotenoids as pigments and yet investigations concerning this output are limited. The carotenoid/terpenoid precursors dimethylallyl pyrophosphate (DMAPP) and isopentenyl pyrophosphate (IPP) are derived from the MEP-pathway in this organism. Carotenoid biosynthesis of the natural C50 carotenoid decaprenoxanthin is based on the accumulation of the C40 intermediate lycopene. The genome of <hi rend="italic">C. glutamicum</hi> contains a major carotenoid operon and the regulatory mechanism involving a MarR-type transcriptional regulator CrtR was identified. Interestingly, this regulation is working in a metabolite dependent manner in which the carotenoid precursor molecule geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate (GGPP) is acting as an effector of the repressor CrtR. Thus, as the genetic background was analyzed in more detail, the production of industrially relevant carotenoids of the C40 family was conducted over the last years (<figure>Figure 1</figure>). Indeed, metabolic engineering studies showed that <hi rend="italic">C. glutamicum</hi> is a suitable host for production of various C40 and C50 carotenoids with astaxanthin as prominant example. The previously published strain ASTA1 possesses a good volumetric productivity, but for industrial scale production further improvement is needed in order to meet economically feasible production titers.  </p>

<p>The construction of fusion proteins and the application of membrane anchors was shown to be an efficient strategy to increase membrane integrity and protein stability. It was shown that linkage of CrtW and CrtZ with the GlpF protein from <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> increased astaxanthin production by approximately 2-fold. Moreover, the fusion of a geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate synthase with a phytoene synthase improved carotenoid production in plant cells. Recently, it was shown that fusion of the terminal carotenoid enzymes increased astaxanthin production in <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi>. </p>

<p>In this study, a fusion protein strategy was conducted (<figure>Figure 2</figure>) that resulted in an approximately five-fold improved astaxanthin production under high glucose concentration in <hi rend="italic">C. glutamicum</hi>. Moreover, it turned out that the co-utilization of glucose and potassium acetate significantly improved astaxanthin production in small-scale fermentations. Thus, not only classical metabolic engineering strategies, but also the construction of fusion proteins and the optimization of cultivation media are powerful strategies to exploit the potential of valuable compound formation.  </p>
</text>
