<text id="autogum_academic_doc410" title="Comparison of Clay Ceramsite and Biodegradable Polymers as Carriers in Pack-bed Biofilm Reactor for Nitrate Removal" shortTile="comparison-clay-ceramsite" author="Qian Zhang, Xue Chen, Heng Wu, Wandong Luo, Xiangyang Liu, Li Feng, Tiantao Zhao" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4184/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Secondary effluent, which is produced from wastewater treatment plants (WWTPs) has to be further treated, due to increasing emission standards and water scarcity. Considering the feature of low turbidity and oligotrophic secondary effluent, biofiltration processes such as ceramsite grains, granular activated carbon and quartz sand were widely employed in the advanced treatment. Due to limited organic carbon source in secondary effluent, denitrification of secondary effluent is usually achieved by extra organic carbon addition (e.g., acetic acid, sodium acetate, glucose, ethanol, etc.). However, the disadvantages of this treatment process are the necessity of a closed, sophisticated, and costly control process, the risk of overdosing, and the need for in-depth knowledge about the operation of this biological system. Biodegradable polymers (BDPs), which act as both an energy source and biofilm carrier, have sparked great interest in the scientific community. In contrast to conventional treatment units, denitrification with biodegradable polymers facilitates operation. Solid-phase denitrification can effectively avoid process risk resulted from carbon addition (i.e., excess or insufficient) since denitrification of solid organic matter is only realized via enzymatic attack.  </p>

<p>Previous studies mainly focused on materials selection and the determination of specific nitrogen removal efficiencies of different BDPs. However, comprehensive solid-phase denitrification processes are lacking and the results vary with the type, structure and molecular weight of BDPs. Rodrigues et al. found that the same type of BDPs showed different performance on volumetric nitrate removal rate when comparing with the previous literature since the BDPs employed in the different works have different physical-chemical properties. Thus, a direct results comparison between solid-phase denitrification and conventional denitrification processes for the different denitrification performances between the two processes during the start-up period and under adverse running conditions (i.e., low carbon to nitrogen (C/N) ratio, short hydraulic retention time (HRT) and continuous shock nitrate loadings) is essential. </p>

<p>In the preliminary experiment, the effects of the type, structure and molecular weight of BDPs on nitrogen removal efficiency was studied. BDPs (PCL) were chosen in this work attributing to the quantities of clear pores on its irregular and rough surface that can provide growth space for the biofilms and protect the attachment of biofilms. This led to the best denitrification performances. The objective of the present study was to investigate the nitrogen removal efficiency of solid-phase denitrification process compared to the conventional denitrification process. The denitrification performances of the two processes during the start-up period were studied and the effect of operation conditions (i.e., HRT, C/N ratio and shock nitrate loading) on denitrification was investigated. The present paper would be useful for researchers and engineers in the field of nitrogen removal from water and wastewater. </p>
</text>
