<text id="autogum_academic_doc028" title="Variability in Water Use Efficiency of Grapevine Tempranillo Clones and Stability over Years at Field Conditions" shortTile="variability-water" author="Ignacio Tortosa, Cyril Douthe, Alicia Pou, Pedro Balda, Esther Hernandez-Montes, Guillermo Toro, José  M. Escalona, Hipólito Medrano" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4395/9/11/701/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Agriculture is one of the largest water consumers on the planet. In many semi-arid areas, dryland viticulture is becoming increasingly more challenging and sometimes is reconverted into irrigated crops, thus there is concern about the water scarcity increase linked to climatic change. Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) predicts an increase of average temperatures and the frequency of extreme drought and/or warm events. So, for most viticulture areas, improving the water use efficiency (WUE) of the grape is becoming more and more important to secure the sustainability of vineyards. There are different ways to improve grape WUE, and the most immediate way is to adjust irrigation dosage and schedule. However, to explore the genetic variation inside grapevine varieties and clones, and to identify the genetic material characterised by a better WUE, is also a promising way to improve the vineyard WUE. </p>

<p>The WUE can be measured at different spatial and temporal scales. From an agronomic approach, the crop WUE (WUEcrop) refers to the final yield and total water consumed. At the leaf level, intrinsic WUE (WUEi) reflects the balance between carbon gain (An) and stomatal conductance (gs). Several studies on grapevines have intended to link the different scales and results are sometimes contradictory, showing good or bad correspondences. Fortunately, for the wine industry the main concern is not only to reach a high productivity, but rather a higher quality of grapes. Grape quality components are largely dependent on an efficient water deficit, which can be achieved by adjusting irrigation but also the plant density or pruning management,. </p>

<p>In either case, to classify genotypes’ WUE, the measurements of leaf gas exchange have been recognised as a useful tool because it is feasible to screen a large quantity of genotypes grown under field conditions and to characterize their behaviour under different water statuses. This allows the revealing of a genetic variability of drought tolerance and WUEi between several vine cultivars. In the same way, some progress has also been made by using other techniques such as the δ13C. </p>

<p>In our research group, after having identified differences in WUEi at the cultivar scale, and considering the narrow rules of wine regions to introduce new varieties, the next step has consisted of an intra-cultivar variability evaluation. First, our study showed such variability in a Tempranillo clonal collection. With respect to a wide cultivar collection, the intra-cultivar variability was at least 80% of the shown variability among cultivars. In more recent work, it has been shown that an intra-cultivar genetic variability of WUEi exists among several clones of the Tempranillo cultivar. </p>

<p>It is important to note that there are several ways to estimate the WUE of a given genotype under realistic field conditions. Most of the studies showed average gas exchange values under different water conditions. As mentioned above, the WUEi, or photosynthetic water use efficiency, is obtained from the quotient between net photosynthesis and stomatal conductance, (AN/gs) and is largely used to qualify drought resistance or water scarcity responses in plants. However, there is a strong mathematical influence of gs upon WUEi, because the soil water depletion is followed by a progressive reduction in gs thus WUE is largely dependent on the soil water availability for the plant. This implies that the comparison of the WUEi should be done under a similar range of gs. To overcome this dependency and compare under the whole range of gs samples, we have used a method proposed by Tortosa et al.. This consists of establishing a general WUEi-gs relationship (log transformed for linearity) based on the data of all genotypes that, in general, presents a high correlation coefficient. Then, an average of the residuals of each genotype (observed-predicted value) is calculated (and expressed in percentage), to rank the given genotype among the rest. </p>

<p>As part of a wide program to identify Tempranillo clones with enhanced WUE, the main objective of the present study was to evaluate whether, under realistic field conditions, the previously observed clonal differences in WUEi within Tempranillo cultivars were affected by environmental complex variations such as the “year effect,” commonly reported for grapevine harvest and quality. </p>
</text>
