<text id="autogum_academic_doc566" title="AD/RANS Simulations of Wind Turbine Wake Flow Employing the RSM Turbulence Model: Impact of Isotropic and Anisotropic Inflow Conditions" shortTile="adrans-simulations" author="Linlin Tian, Yilei Song, Ning Zhao, Wenzhong Shen, Tongguang Wang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4026/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Computational Settings</head><head> 3.1. Computational Domain and Boundary Conditions</head>
<p>
The computational domain is constructed according to the Architectural Institute of Japan (AIJ) guidelines, as illustrated in <figure>Figure 1</figure>a with its main boundary conditions, and this domain is used for all the test cases. Moreover, the corresponding computational settings are summarized in Table 1. For the ground layer, the grids are refined to gain y+ values between 30 and 300 (it is in the accepted range for the wall function approach used in the computations), getting nearly 50 nodes below hub height for all the test cases. In order to resolve the strong gradients around the turbine rotor, a high concentration of grid points is distributed in the vicinity of the rotor, with the generated mesh shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>b. Finally, the total number of grid points used for the computations is around 3.8 million. Similar grid resolutions have been employed in previous studies that used the actuator-type models, and they have been proven sufficient to capture the wake characteristics behind a single turbine. </p>

<head> 3.2. Isotropic and Anisotropic Inflow Conditions</head>
<p>
For every CFD analysis, accurate inflow conditions are paramount to the fidelity of the outcome. It was observed that on one hand, wind turbine wake problems are very sensitive to inflow conditions; on the other hand, different expressions of the inlet profile exist in the literature when using the RSM. Therefore, a sensitive analysis of the influence of incoming wind profiles on the downstream wake flow was performed. The adopted inflow profiles (which are classified into isotropic and anisotropic inflow profiles) are listed in Table 2, in which the velocity profile <hi rend="italic">u</hi>(<hi rend="italic">z</hi>) is characterized by the power law, which is widely used in wind engineering applications due to its simplicity and practicality. As regarding the turbulence quantities <hi rend="italic">k</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ε</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">ω</hi>, they are fundamental for the RSM but difficult to be estimated directly; instead, it is an effective way to relate them to easily obtained parameters such as the wind speed <hi rend="italic">u</hi> and turbulence intensity <hi rend="italic">TI</hi>. Therefore, the mostly used relation typically resorted to is to derive <hi rend="italic">k</hi> using Equation (6). Accordingly, the values of <hi rend="italic">ε</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ω</hi> are estimated with the assumption of a local equilibrium, as given by Equations (7) and (8). </p>

<p>It should be noted that the RSM in ANSYS FLUENT requires boundary conditions for each of the Reynolds stresses . If their values are not specified explicitly at the inlet, then the turbulence is assumed to be isotropic (as described by Equation (9)); if the anisotropic property of the atmospheric boundary layer (ABL) turbulence is considered, the normal and shear Reynolds stress profiles have the form as given in Equation (10). Note that for these two types of inflow conditions, the profiles of <hi rend="italic">u</hi>, <hi rend="italic">TI</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ε</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">ω</hi> are identical, in which the variables <hi rend="italic">uhub</hi> and <hi rend="italic">TIhub</hi> are defined at a reference height, i.e., hub height, and <hi rend="italic">α</hi> is the power-law exponent that can be determined according to the surface roughness categorization upwind of the site. Note that the value of <hi rend="italic">α</hi> is set to be 0.15 for all the following test cases. On the other hand, the difference between two sets of profiles reflects in three aspects: (1) calculation of the turbulence kinetic energy <hi rend="italic">k</hi>; (2) the expression of each Reynolds stress; (3) the value of the RSM constant <hi rend="italic">Cμ</hi>. </p>
</text>
