<text id="autogum_academic_doc635" title="Oral–Gut Microbiota and Arthritis: Is There an Evidence-Based Axis?" shortTile="oralgut-microbiota" author="Drago Lorenzo, Zuccotti GianVincenzo, Romanò Carlo Luca, Goswami Karan, Jorge Hugo Villafañe, Mattina Roberto, Parvizi Javad" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/10/1753/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Gut Microbiota in RA and OA</head>
<p>
The hypothesis that not only oral but also intestinal microbiota can be associated with the development of RA is supported by many data. Zhang et al. published a case-control metagenome-wide association study (MGWAS) of the fecal, dental and salivary microbiomes of a cohort of treatment-naive and treated RA patients. They found that the RA-associated microbiome deviated significantly from healthy controls in all sites. In this study, <hi rend="italic">Haemophilus</hi> spp. was depleted in individuals with RA at the fecal and oral levels, whereas <hi rend="italic">Lactobacillus salivarius</hi> was over-represented in individuals with RA at both microbiota sites. </p>

<p>Older patients often manifest more severe diseases, and this appears connected to age-related gut dysbiosis. Alterations in the microbiota provide plausible candidate mechanisms for driving both inflammation and altering the immune response and host metabolism, which in turn may modulate the development of musculoskeletal problems (see the <hi rend="italic">Prevotella copri</hi> case below). The microbiome is thus a highly plausible target for the modulation of diseases of aging owing to its close relationship with innate and adaptive immune systems. Components of intestinal microbiota can indeed direct key aspects of host immunity, in particular effector T-cell differentiation, which may impact susceptibility to autoimmune diseases and RA in particular. </p>

<p>Different studies investigating the etiology of RA have established the involvement of regulatory T (T-reg) cells, which are defective at suppressing IFN-γ and TNF-α production by conventional T cells in the peripheral blood of active RA patients. It has been well established that the gut microbiota–immune interaction and homeostasis, via balancing pro- and anti-inflammatory mechanisms, can regulate the differentiation of various T cell types, especially T-reg cells. A clear example is the potential therapeutic effect of SCFAs (short chain fatty acids), which are microbial fermentation products found in the bowel, that have demonstrated a profound influence on T-reg cell differentiation in a variety of experimental models of autoimmunity or inflammatory T-cell-mediated diseases.  </p>

<p>An elegant collagen-induced arthritis mouse model published by Hui et al. demonstrated that butyrate (a functional SCFA) administration inhibited arthritis by suppressing the expression of inflammatory cytokines. The authors suggested that modulation was likely mediated by the differentiation of CD4 T cells towards T-reg cells, which produce anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10, and thus influenced the function of Th17 cells. </p>

<p>As mentioned, an altered microbiota profile has also been associated with juvenile idiopathic arthritis (JIA). Current evidence indeed suggests that the perturbation of gut microbiota may contribute to the development of JIA. </p>

<p>It remains difficult, however, to establish a definitive microbial marker or specific enterotypes that are associated with RA. It has been hypothesized that the alteration of single bacterial genus could have direct impact on driving inflammation, as suggested for <hi rend="italic">Bacteroides</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Akkermansia</hi> or the anti-inflammatory <hi rend="italic">Faecalobacterium prausnitzii</hi>, which has been noted to be depleted in RA patients, while <hi rend="italic">Prevotella</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ruminococcus</hi> were more prevalent. Increasing <hi rend="italic">Prevotella copri</hi> and decreasing <hi rend="italic">Bacteroides</hi> concentrations in the stool have both been associated with new onset, untreated RA in humans.  </p>

<p>The above studies, although not always homogenous, have directly or indirectly demonstrated that genetic risk may be modulated by alterations in the microbiome and that the presence of particular microbial markers can be predictive of disease. As mentioned, intestinal microbiota are also known to change with age. Many of the clinical issues, including OA, are related to the inflammatory change—either specific to disease or associated with age. OA is indeed considered a degeneration of joint cartilage and the underlying bone which commonly occurs from middle age onward. The precise etiology of OA remains unknown thus far, even if various risk factors have been associated with presence of the disease, including age, sex, obesity, and diet, and local joint injury. </p>

<p>Most of these factors are associated with drastic changes in the intestinal microbiota. Age, in fact, shifts the intestinal microbiota with significant differences between younger adults and older people, showing a lower diversity of gut microbiota, a greater proportion of <hi rend="italic">Bacteroides</hi> spp., and a distinct abundance pattern of <hi rend="italic">Clostridium</hi> groups. In addition, obesity is associated with phylum-level changes in the microbiota (i.e., ratio of Firmicutes/Bacteroidetes), reduced bacterial diversity, and an altered representation of bacterial genes and metabolic pathways. Finally, diet can shape gut microbiota and consequently change the composition and metabolism of intestinal microbiota as well as impact host immune responses.  </p>

<p>For these reasons, OA is now considered an induced inflammatory condition in which the role of the microbiome has emerging as one of the most important factors. Several publications have reported a clear demonstration of the link between osteoarthritis and gut microbiota. For instance, animals with a low-grade chronic systemic inflammation due to a high-fat diet have developed osteoarthritis, and others with an increased body weight due to diet have shown an increased progression of osteoarthritis. Metcalfe et al. proposed that metabolic endotoxemia (raised LPS blood and synovial concentrations) caused by impaired gastric mucosa and low-grade chronic inflammation, may contribute to the onset and progression of OA in obese patients.  </p>
</text>
