<text id="autogum_academic_doc361" title="Greedy Mechanism Based Particle Swarm Optimization for Path Planning Problem of an Unmanned Surface Vehicle" shortTile="greedy-mechanism" author="Junfeng Xin, Jiabao Zhong, Shixin Li, Jinlu Sheng, Ying Cui" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4620/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Unmanned Surface vehicles (USVs), also known as autonomous surface crafts, have attracted worldwide attention in commercial, scientific and military fields recently. USVs have the advantages of low operation and maintenance costs, reduced casualty risk, and good maneuverability and deployability for different operating conditions. With the aid of effective and reliable navigation equipment, such as global positioning systems (GPS), wireless communication units, and various types of sensors, USVs can be employed cost-efficiently for a variety of applications, including underwater surveying, pollutant tracking, acoustic navigation, marine rescue, and obstacle detection. Although rapid progress of corresponding techniques for USV systems have been achieved in recent times, it is still challenging in promoting the level of USV autonomy when faced with complex or hazardous environments. Key issues, including hull hydrodynamics, communication techniques, and navigation, guidance and control (NGC) strategies, require further developments. </p>

<p>As a vital component of USV guidance systems, path planning is of critical importance in designing and updating feasible and optimal trajectories for the control system on basis of navigation information, mission demands, and environmental conditions. Its effectiveness not only determines the autonomy of unmanned vehicles, but also affects the reliability and efficiency of mission execution. From the literature, plenty of intelligent techniques have been employed in the USV path planner. Meanwhile, it is a research hot pot to propose an algorithm having fast convergence speed, admirable robustness, low computation consumption, and satisfactory route planning. </p>

<p>The USV path planning problem is normally formulated as a travelling salesman problem (TSP), which is a typical combinatorial optimization problem. The specific description is to find a shortest loop that passes through all target cities without repetition. However, when a USV performs multi-objective tasks in a complex marine environment, the number of possible paths increases exponentially with the increase of target points’ number, resulting in the so-called “exponential explosion”. In this circumstance, traditional algorithms, such as the exhaustive method and branch-and-bound algorithm, are unable to find the optimal solution within reasonable time cost. Hence, it is vital to develop efficient and feasible heuristic algorithms instead of traditional methods to solve this kind of problem, although the optimality, accuracy, and completeness becomes sacrificed for running speed to some degree. Commonly used heuristic algorithms include elephant search algorithm (ESA), genetic algorithm (GA), particle swam optimization (PSO), firefly algorithm (FA), grey wolf optimizer (GWO), and so on. </p>

<p>However, the conventional type of each method has its inherent limitation. For instance, it is known that the ESA provides a random and improper replacement for an elephant with the worst fitness, which is likely to result in the deterioration of search space. The conventional GA has inherent issues of slow convergence speed, poor capability of local search and easy occurrence of premature convergence. In other words, the loss of population diversity is likely to appear during the implementation of GA, making individual genes tend to be same and terminating the search at local optimum. Additionally, the use of a real-number code also generates repetitive genes during crossover operations, which affects convergence speed greatly. For the PSO, the lack of a balanced mechanism would lead to the loss of population diversity and finally being trapped into the local optimum. In addition, the FA only considers the distance and maximum attractive force between two fireflies, and has intrinsic shortcomings of poor search capability during early iterations and severe oscillations around the optimal solution during later iterations. In terms of the GWO, the search mechanism of judging distance from prey would lead to a slow convergence speed for later iterations. Nowadays, it has become a tendency to combine two or more algorithms, making full use of their respective advantages to enhance the algorithm effectiveness.  </p>

<p>Inspired by the combination strategy, this work optimizes the conventional PSO method by introducing a greedy mechanism to generate partial particles and 2-opt operation to eliminate path-crossing phenomena. Comparative study with some state-of-the-art algorithms is conducted to verify the effectiveness and reliability of the improved method in terms of solution quality, algorithm robustness, and computing efficiency. Then the improved algorithm is adopted to generate a feasible closed trajectory for a self-developed USV to follow in real marine environments. </p>

<p>It is worth noting that this work has certain connections and essential differences with our two recently published works. In the first work, we optimized GA by multi-domain inversion for the purpose of increasing the number of offsprings. The inspiration comes from the biological theory foundation, where the number of offsprings needs to be larger than the number of parents so as to prevent species extinction and maintain species diversity in the process of biological evolution. In the other work, we optimized PSO by iteratively adjusting the control parameters of the PSO algorithm, such as inertia weight and acceleration coefficients, and introducing merit-based selection and uncertain mutation. The optimization is from the point of view of global searching. However, in this work, we start form the inspiration of the combination strategy of several intelligent algorithms and introduce the greedy mechanism and 2-opt operation in order to optimize the local search of PSO. </p>
</text>
