<text id="autogum_academic_doc188" title="Automatic Visual Acuity Estimation by Means of Computational Vascularity Biomarkers Using Oct Angiographies" shortTile="automatic-visual" author="Macarena Díaz, Marta Díez-Sotelo, Francisco Gómez-Ulla, Jorge Novo, Manuel  Francisco G. Penedo, Marcos Ortega" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4732/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
In many clinical specialties, there exists a high variety of image modalities that clinicians typically use to analyze the patient’s condition and aid in the diagnostic process. Given the importance of technology at present, namely, its inclusion in different areas to improve an expert’s work, many computational systems have been implemented to facilitate this clinical processes. This automatization of different clinical manual tasks provide solutions and improvements that are characterized by desirable properties that the expert cannot offer such as determinism, repeatability or objectivity. Regarding image analysis, over the years, many computational proposals have been presented based on computer vision techniques that are exploited to analyze relevant areas of the images of interest, measure relevant parameters and monitor their evolution and potential variations, which is the typical procedure that is used in many Computer Aided Diagnostic (CAD) systems. </p>

<p>In ophthalmology, different image modalities have increased in popularity over the last years. The color fundus retinography is the most traditional and widely extended ophthalmic image modality, that allows the direct visualization of the eye fundus and their possible pathological visible structures. Being an invasive capture technique, the Fluorescein Angiography (FA) provides an enhanced visualization of the retinal vascular structure by injecting a dye contrast into the patient. With the Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT), we can visualize and analyze volumetric scans of the inner retinal layers, non-invasively and in real time. Based on the OCT and the FA characteristics, a new image modality appeared, combining both the OCT benefits and the FA visualization: the Optical Coherence Tomography by Angiography (OCTA). OCTA imaging constitutes the new ophthalmic image modality, and it is the first that allows an exhaustive and non-invasive vascular analysis of the retina. OCTA accurately represents the vascularity of the foveal region within the retinal layers. This representation is extracted based on the blood movement in the eye microvasculature. Given that numerous systematic and eye diseases are related with the microvascular circulation, OCTA constitutes a relevant new ophthalmic image modality that better aids the diagnosis and monitoring processes of these pathologies. As reference, diseases such as diabetes can generate a Diabetic Retinopathy (DR), which provokes microvascular problems in advanced stages of the disease, eventually producing total blindness in the worst case scenario. Also, the Retinal Vein Occlusion (RVO) produces a problematic loss of vascularity and a progressive vision loss. </p>

<p>With these representative examples among many others, it is clear that the retinal vascular integrity is related with the Visual Acuity (VA) of the patients. Commonly, to estimate the VA of a given patient, it is necessary to perform different rudimentary tests. In particular, these tests are normally related with the analysis of the ability of the patient to observe characteristic objects of different sizes and at different distances. Consequently, the final VA estimation is subjective whereas its process is tedious and slow. In that context, any technological contribution that avoids or facilitates this revision process is extremely desired in the ophthalmic field. </p>

<p>Given the potential of the OCTA image modality, over recent years, several clinical studies were published demonstrating its utility in the analysis of different vascular diseases. Hence, Balaratnasingam et al. demonstrated in their study that the VA is correlated with the Foveal Avascular Zone (FAZ) in patients with DR and RVO diseases. Other clinical studies related different manual biomarkers extracted from the OCTA images with the VA of the patient. Wei et al. demonstrated the adequate repeatability of the vascular density as representative biomarker in healthy subjects in both macular and optic disk regions. Posteriorly, Vivien at al., demonstrated the influence of the glaucoma disease over the vessel tree characteristics, obtaining as conclusions the absence of retinal vascularity in the pathological cases over a control group. Given its novelty, there exists a limited number of computational proposals to aid the diagnosis and monitoring of pathologies with this image modality. In fact, the existing works are mainly based on the extraction of characteristic biomarkers in the OCTA images or improving the image quality to facilitate its posterior analysis. As reference, Díaz et al. briefly introduced a method to automatically extract and measure generally the Vascular Density (VD). Also, the authors proposed a method to extract and measure the FAZ in healthy and DR OCTA images and they performed a FAZ circularity study in healthy and pathological images. Alam et al. proposed different features extracted from the OCTA images, namely, the vessel tortuosity, the mean diameter of the blood vessels, the semi-automatic FAZ area, the FAZ irregularity and the density of the parafoveal avascular region using fractal dimensions. Guo et al. segmented and quantified avascular ischemic zones with map probabilities that were extracted by a deep convolutional neural network. Wang et al. proposed a method to produce mosaics using different overlapping OCTA images, increasing the wide field of vision for the posterior clinical analysis. Wei et al. improved the quality of the OCTA scans in their work whereas Camino et al. identified existing shadow artifacts that typically appear in the OCTA images to improve the visualization and facilitate their inspection. </p>
</text>
