<text id="autogum_academic_doc625" title="Association of Working Hours and Patient Safety Competencies with Adverse Nurse Outcomes: A Cross-Sectional Study" shortTile="association-working" author="Youn-Jung Son, Eun  Kyoung Lee, Yukyung Ko" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4083/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
Positive nursing performance and outcomes are highly important as they are directly linked to PS. We investigated nurses’ working hours, PS competencies, and adverse nurse outcomes and aimed to identify the factors correlated with adverse nurse outcomes, ultimately seeking to determine ways to improve PS and boost the quality of nurses’ work. We found that long working hours were strongly associated with adverse nurse outcomes. </p>

<p>First, we examined nurses’ general characteristics related to their working hours. We found that working hours significantly differed across work units. Ko and Park investigated overtime hours in diverse medical departments in South Korea, revealing that nurses working daytime shifts in internal medicine wards worked more overtime than did those in specialized units. Weekly overtime was the highest in ear-nose-and-throat wards and the lowest in psychiatric wards. Similarly, in our study, the number of nurses working more than 50 h/week was lower in the intensive care unit than in internal medicine or surgery wards, presumably because its ratio of patients to nurses is relatively smaller, and working overtime is usually not necessary. Bae and Champion found that working hours significantly differed by working environment—a significantly higher number of nurse practitioners working in hospitals and long-term care settings worked for more than 40 h/week. Long working hours are known to have detrimental effects on workers’ health and outcomes. Based on our findings, it is imperative that hospital nurse managers and health professionals perceive the impact of long working hours. Furthermore, if longer working hours are necessary because of the nature of the department or unit, it is desirable to adjust them to appropriate levels through various approaches, such as hiring more personnel or altering the nursing delivery system. </p>

<p>In the present study, the scores for PS competencies decreased with increasing working hours. This result is in line with previous findings that confidence in or perceptions about PS decline as working hours increase. There is substantial evidence to suggest the possibility of the association of fatigue and shorter sleep with long working hours, which can lead to loss of concentration and perceived quality of care and PS. A recent study on the effect of hospital nurses’ shift lengths on the perceived quality and PS reported that longer working hours were negatively associated with care quality and safety. More prospective studies are needed to identify the mechanism linking long working hours and perceived or actual PS activities. Furthermore, the perceptions of adverse nurse outcomes by nurses working more than 50 h were significantly higher than those of nurses working less than 40 h. This suggests that working long hours exposes nurses to adverse outcomes, potentially having detrimental effects on PS. Olds and Clarke conducted a similar study and found that all variables of adverse nurse outcomes were significantly correlated with errors in the group of nurses who worked more than 40 h/week. Moreover, medication error and needle stick injuries were associated with voluntary overtime and working hours. Based on these findings, they called for regulations specifying mandatory working hours. Direct comparisons between this study and previous research must be attempted with caution because of differing circumstances and contexts across countries. Nevertheless, it is of great significance that the results of this study can be used as a basis for establishing overtime rules in South Korea. </p>

<p>Having filed more than three PS accident reports in the past year, working more than 40 h/week, and having high PS competencies were significantly associated with adverse nurse outcomes. Of these, working more than 40 h had the most significant association. Long working hours are the most prominent issue in hospital organizations because they affect the safety of both patients and healthcare personnel. Nevertheless, South Korea lacks regulations concerning limiting nurses’ overtime work. Some studies have suggested that long working hours undermine intelligibility while increasing fatigue. Further, working overtime has been reported to induce fatigue and stress and facilitate burnout among nurses, while mandatory overtime was found to be related to lower organizational commitment. In a study analyzing the relevance of depression to the working hours of public sector workers in South Korea, those working more than 10 h/day reported 1.63 times higher levels of depression than those working fewer than 10 h. In addition, they reported 2.2 times higher levels of depression when working nights. As such, it will also be necessary to confirm the relevance of overtime and mental health problems through further research. Hospital administrators must formulate policies to reduce overtime based on its link with mental health problems. Hence, our findings provide grounds for nurse leaders and policymakers to develop regulations on appropriate nurse staffing and mandatory overtime. Mostly, South Korean nurses employed at medium to large hospitals work in three daily shifts—eight hours each in the day, evening, and night. Thus, implementing various work schedules, such as night or day-only shifts and 12 h shifts, could be useful. In addition, various in-hospital efforts are needed to establish protocols regarding transition time in order to reduce overtime. </p>
</text>
