<text id="autogum_academic_doc138" title="The Impact of Rural Labor Migration on Elderly Health from the Perspective of Gender Structure: A Case Study in Western China" shortTile="impact-rural-labor" author="Sha Cao, Dingde Xu, Yi Liu, Shaoquan Liu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5763/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Aging and migration of agricultural labor, especially of young and middle-aged people, have become two of the most prominent demographic characteristics in developing countries. Moreover, there is growing attention given to the impact of labor migration on the health of elderly. As a result of the lack of a pension system, family support remains the main pension model in developing countries such as China, especially in rural areas, by means of the intergenerational support of family members for the security of the elderly. The research suggests that labor migration not only exacerbates rural population aging, but also changes the traditional family intergenerational support structure, and thus affects the health of left-behind elderly. </p>

<p>Intergenerational support mainly includes three parts, economic, instrumental, and emotional support. Current studies generally address the effects of change caused by labor migration on the elderly health via two paths. The first is through economic support. On the one hand, some scholars believe that labor migration can improve the overall ability of the family to provide economic support, and thus improve the living standard of family members, including the medical service level of the elderly, which has a positive impact on the health of the elderly. On the other hand, some studies argue that labor migration in rural families weakens economic support for the elderly and increases their workload, thus, harming the elderly’s health, because migrant labor may pay more attention to their own development, and may not necessarily provide economic support to the elderly left behind. Moreover, even if the migrant labor remits to the elderly left behind, little is known about the extent to which remittances are directed to the elderly; especially when the migrants have children left at home, the elderly often have to raise grandchildren in exchange for economic support from their children, which further aggravates the labor burden of the elderly. The second path is through instrumental and emotional support. Most scholars who focus on this path believe that labor migration reduces the accessibility of instrumental and emotional support that the elderly receive and has a negative impact on the elderly’s health. Furthermore, in China, most studies show that elderly with only one child and living alone are most affected. In summary, existing studies have shown that labor migration creates disruptions in family care systems and affects the health of left-behind elderly, however, the existing conclusions are not consistent, and there are still some important limitations that may affect the comprehensive understanding of the correlation between labor migration and elderly health. </p>

<p>First, not much research has been undertaken to analyze the impact of labor migration on the health of the elderly from the perspective of gender structure. In the traditional Chinese rural family division of labor, men tend to seek work through migration as the main breadwinners, whereas women are more likely to act as caregivers, and intergenerational support, especially economic support, should be provided mainly by sons. Nevertheless, currently, rural female labor is increasingly inclined to seek work through migration for higher income and the gender differences in economic support for the elderly by sons and daughters have been narrowing. Moreover, although son preference is still highly prevalent in rural China, daughters tend to offer a greater benefit to parents who have reached old age, being associated with greater filial piety, better relationships, and satisfactory care. Furthermore, while married sons usually assume social responsibility for supporting the family’s elderly, their spouses (daughters-in-law) are, in fact, the main contributors to daily care. In other words, daughters and daughters-in-law often play a more important role than sons do in daily instrumental and emotional support for the elderly. Therefore, it can be assumed that the migration of male labor, which is a traditional source of economic support, can improve the economic support for the elderly, but might not have a significant negative impact on the elderly with respect to instrumental support and emotional support. Although the migration of female labor can also increase economic support for the elderly, it may remove a source of caregiving and companionship for the elderly who are left behind, which will weaken the family’s daily instrumental and emotional support for the elderly. Thus, differences due to migrant gender of the impact of labor migration on the health of the elderly need further quantitative analysis. </p>

<p>Secondly, only a few earlier studies have considered the differences in the effects of labor migration on different aspects of the elderly’s health, however, health is a multidimensional concept, and the effects of labor migration on the physical and mental health of the elderly differ. For example, Adhikari et al. found that the migration of adult children has a significant negative effect on the mental health of the elderly but no significant effect on physical health. Furthermore, most research to date has focused mainly on the elderly’s physical health, neglecting the interactions between physical and mental health, however, if the elderly feel isolated when left behind, their physical health might also deteriorate. Therefore, the comprehensive health statue of the elderly other than physical health should also be taken into account. </p>
</text>
