<text id="autogum_academic_doc054" title="Synthetic Peptides Elicit Strong Cellular Immunity in Visceral Leishmaniasis Natural Reservoir and Contribute to Long-Lasting Polyfunctional T-Cells in BALB/c Mice" shortTile="synthetic-peptides" author="Rory  Cristiane Fortes De Brito, Jamille  Mirelle de Oliveira Cardoso, Levi  Eduardo Soares Reis, Fernando  Augusto Siqueira Mathias, Rodrigo  Dian de Oliveira Aguiar-Soares, Andréa Teixeira-Carvalho, Bruno  Mendes Roatt, Rodrigo Corrêa-Oliveira, Jeronimo  Conceição Ruiz, Daniela  de Melo Resende, Alexandre  Barbosa Reis" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-393X/7/4/162/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
It is believed that an ideal vaccine against <hi rend="italic">Leishmania spp</hi>. should have epitopes that will be recognized by APCs and will be able to trigger a T- lymphocyte effector response and maintain a long-lasting immune memory, which would be critical for protection against the parasite. Therefore, the high-throughput search for epitopes with this potential has become one of the greatest current challenges for the rational design of vaccines. Thus, reverse vaccinology started to be used for this purpose, and one of the strategies used is the search for immunogenic epitopes in whole <hi rend="italic">Leishmania</hi> proteomes. </p>

<p>Epitope mapping in proteomes of parasites is much more complex than the mapping of epitopes in proteins already described as immunogenic. In this way, the use of the integrative approach to immunoinformatics proposed by Brito, Guimaraes, Velloso, Correa-Oliveira, Ruiz, Reis and Resende was important to achieve potential epitopes in this study. After employing the immunoinformatics methodologies, we identified MHC class I and class II ligand epitopes comprising mouse and human alleles, due to the absence of predictors comprising dog alleles. However, based on some studies, we can verify that there are high levels of identity between MHC alleles of dogs and those of humans and mice. For example, some loci of the MHC region II of dogs have an identity with those of humans and mice around 85% and 79%, respectively. </p>

<p>Regarding the in vivo screening of the immunoinformatics-selected peptides in the canine model, we selected asymptomatic dogs naturally infected by <hi rend="italic">L. infantum</hi> (natural reservoir). Several studies have shown that dogs and humans with asymptomatic clinical forms have better reactivity with intra-dermal reaction than symptomatic individuals. Similarly, Reis, et al. have already shown that asymptomatic dogs have a profile of circulating lymphocytes in the peripheral blood capable of conferring a degree of resistance to the disease. When we performed the in vitro screening, the purpose was to identify potential epitopes in a huge number of peptides. For this, we focused on the main biomarkers of protection, namely: lymphocyte proliferation after stimulation with <hi rend="italic">L. infantum</hi> and IFN-γ production by subpopulations of T-lymphocytes (CD4+ and CD8+). Currently, some markers related to protection have been studied, such as proinflammatory cytokines, production of immunoglobulins of IgG1 and IgG2 subtypes, and responsive CD4+ and CD8+ T-cells. The biomarkers that we chose are essential to determine resistance or susceptibility to visceral leishmaniasis and they are widely demonstrated in the literature. Our data support that some peptides were able to induce lymphoproliferation and the production of IFN-γ by T-cells in vitro. In this regard, in many studies reporting the use of murine model and PBMC from patients with leishmaniasis, the main biomarker analyzed was IFN-γ produced after stimuli with different peptides. </p>

<p>After the in vitro screening, the reverse antigen screening (RAS) was used, a robust methodology that allows the selection of promising targets for the development of vaccines intended to trigger a strong cellular response. Our findings demonstrate that an immunoinformatic approach increases the chance of finding peptides molecules (epitopes) which can trigger a cellular response in a naturally and asymptomatic infected model. The fact that an antigen generates a cellular response classified as type IV or late hypersensitivity implies that this antigen may be able to generate immune memory and trigger a response characterized by important cytokines, such as IFN-γ and TNF-α. When we analyzed the epitope conservancy of these peptides among the proteome of other <hi rend="italic">Leishmania</hi> species, it was observed that peptide PEP17 demonstrated to be the most conserved epitope among various viscerotropic and dermatotropic <hi rend="italic">Leishmania</hi> species. Immunogenic peptides that show a high degree of conservancy with other parasites may be related to a better protection when compared to those not conserved. In this way, peptides 17, 30, 33, and 34 may be considered promising epitopes for the design of vaccines against VL. </p>
</text>
