<text id="autogum_academic_doc608" title="Authentic Leadership and Employees’ Innovative Behaviour: A Multilevel Investigation in Three Countries" shortTile="authentic-leadership" author="Mariola Laguna, Karolina Walachowska, Marjan  J. Gorgievski-Duijvesteijn, Juan  A. Moriano" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4201/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
In the present era, the implementation of innovative ideas in organizations is crucial, both for the long-term survival of a firm and for the development of new solutions that protect the environment and the well-being of societies. Studies on innovations in general and on ecological innovations specifically tend to focus on external influences (such as policy making and market opportunities), but usually ignore the processes within the company—the mechanisms operating at the micro-level which stimulate innovative behaviour. The innovative behaviour of employees, i.e., creation and implementation of new solutions in the workplace as manifested in everyday activities, is an important micro foundation of the innovativeness of the whole firm. This especially prominent in small firms, which provide the majority of private employment and do not have special innovation departments, and thus the innovative behaviour of their employees is major driver of the organization’s innovation. In addition, the entrepreneurial owner who operates the firm is usually also the manager and supervisor of his or her employees. Thus, his or her leadership behaviours are of vital importance for creating a working environment that fosters employees’ innovative behaviour. Taking into account that entrepreneurs in small firms perform multiple roles and are usually direct managers of their employees, we treat them as leaders of these organizations, as proposed in other research. </p>

<p>Leadership may cover a variety of conducts, and the influence of leader’s characteristics on employee behaviour has become an emerging research area. This study builds on the theory of authentic leadership. Today, as the disreputable conduct of some company managers has been unveiled, it is significant to direct attention to the leaders’ behaviours in terms of displaying sincerity and authenticity in work relationships rather than manipulation or work towards hidden purposes. Authentic leadership theory defines the authentic leader as being characterized by high self-awareness, balanced processing of information, relational transparency and internalized moral perspective, and acting in accordance with their inner thoughts and feelings. Research has explored the influence of authentic leadership on a variety of work attitudes. However, leadership scholars have identified a lack of research addressing underlying mechanisms that explain how leaders influence important processes in organizations, including stimulation of innovativeness. Leadership scholars have also noted that more studies are needed that investigate the effects of leadership behaviours at different levels of analysis, such as linking leaders’ characteristics to the attitudes and behaviours of their employees within teams or organisations. </p>

<p>Filling these gaps in the literature, the present study investigates underlying psychological mechanisms linking entrepreneurial owners’ authentic leadership and employee innovative behaviour. We propose and test a multilevel model which postulates that the more authentic the leader is perceived to be, the more innovative behaviour his or her followers show. The evidence posits that authentic leadership enhances employees’ feelings of involvement and commitment. This suggests that personal motivational variables related to involvement and engagement may play a role in transferring leader’s attitudes into employees’ behaviours. Based on this, we postulate that the relationship between the authentic leadership displayed by the entrepreneurial owner and his or her employees’ innovative behaviour is mediated by employees’ work engagement and their personal initiative. If the leader exhibits authenticity, his or her followers are inspired by their supervisor, they are likely to become more engaged with their assignments, and are more willing to go beyond their job description. High work engagement and personal initiative are expected to result in increased innovative behaviour, as they equip employees with energy and motivation, and enable them to introduce novel practices in the workplace. </p>

<p>Our study contributes to the innovation and leadership literature in several ways. Firstly, applying a multilevel study design allows us to analyse the relations between the leadership style of entrepreneurial firm owners (representing a higher level of analysis—Level 2) and their employees’ work behaviour (representing a lower level, i.e., individual-level—Level 1). Secondly, this study is among the first to test the explanatory mechanisms linking employee innovation and authentic leadership attitudes and behaviours through individual-level, psychological variables. Thirdly, we will analyse data of employees from three European countries. Hence, the study provides preliminary evidence for the extent to which results generalize across different cultures as well as possible cross-country differences. </p>

<head> 1.1. Authentic Leadership and the Innovative Behaviour of Employees</head>
<p>
Innovation is the creation of valuable and useful new products, services or production processes in the organizational context. It has been proven that both large corporations and small companies develop and prosper in the long term due to the innovative potential of employees. In small organizations, the business owner usually also manages the company. Therefore, his or her attitudes and leadership behaviours are especially influential. The importance of managers’ support for employees’ innovative behaviour has been confirmed in earlier studies. In a meta-analysis concerning predictors of the innovation of organizational members, Hammond and colleagues revealed that immediate supervisors are able to spur innovation in subordinates. </p>
</text>
