<text id="autogum_academic_doc367" title="Orange Snow—A Saharan Dust Intrusion over Romania During Winter Conditions" shortTile="orange-snow-saharan" author="Luminiţa Mărmureanu, Cristina  Antonia Marin, Simona Andrei, Bogdan Antonescu, Dragoş Ene, Mihai Boldeanu, Jeni Vasilescu, Cătălin Viţelaru, Oana Cadar, Erika Levei" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/21/2466/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Every year, approximately 1.2–1.8 Gt yr of dust is released into the atmosphere reaching the medium and upper troposphere. Of this, approximately 50.7% is transported from the Sahara to Europe. The most affected European countries by the Saharan dust transport are those from the Mediterranean basin. This dust transport can have a direct and indirect effect on the radiative budget, human health and terrestrial and aquatic ecosystems. Dust intrusions were observed up to 6 km altitude, and their transport directly influenced the Alps, the Apennines, the Pyrenees, and the Carpathian Mountains. Di Mauro et al. showed that dust deposition changes the snow melt-out dates, altering the hydrological cycle in the Alps. Also, dust is influencing the severity of respiratory conditions (e.g., asthma) especially when significant quantities of particulate matter (PM) including dust are present in the air (i.e., an increase of more than 10 g m in PM,). Saharan dust particles can also carry bacteria over long distances (e.g., the Alps) despite the low temperatures and UV radiation at which the are exposed during transport. Dust deposition can also have beneficial effects, for example, the high Fe content of dust can act as a soil nutrient. </p>

<p>The transport of Saharan dust over Europe has been extensively analyzed during the last decades. This was facilitated by the developments of remote sensing techniques and networks using ground-based measurements e.g.,, in-situ measurements e.g.,, satellite-based measurements e.g.,, and numerical modelling e.g.,. To understand the seasonality of dust intrusions over Europe, Marinou et al. performed a 9-year study of Saharan dust transport based on satellite data from Cloud-Aerosol Lidar and Infrared Pathfinder Satellite Observation (CALIPSO) and lidar ground-based measurements from the European Aerosol Research Lidar Network (EARLINET). The study showed, that during the spring, dust aerosols are transported from Sahara to Europe, with the highest incidence of dust intrusion over the Mediterranean region. Similar results concerning the seasonal variation of dust over Europe were obtained by Mandija et al. using a modelling approach. </p>

<p>Not only the countries bordering the Mediterranean Sea ([16,24] for Greece) but also those located in central and southeastern Europe (e.g., for Romania, for Hungary) are affected by Saharan dust transport which can negatively impact the daily activities. Thus, under certain meteorological conditions the dust can reach high altitudes later being detected at the ground due to the dry and wet depositions (e.g.,). Over southeastern Europe, Saharan dust is reported more frequently during the spring (March–May) compared with other periods of the year. </p>

<p>One example, is the event that occurred on 22–23 March 2018 when Saharan dust was deposited at the ground over southeastern Romania. A particularity of this event is that the dust was deposited together with snow. Previous studies on Saharan dust deposited onto snow surfaces focused on events that occurred at high altitudes over central Europe (e.g., for the Alps). There are very few studies on Saharan dust deposition by rainfalls (e.g.,) over southeastern Europe, and no studies, to the authors knowledge, analyzing the dust deposition by snowfall. </p>

<p>The purpose of this article is to analyze for the first time the characteristics of a long-range Saharan dust transport event accompanied by snowfall that occurred over southeastern Europe between 22–23 March 2018. The analysis is based on the continuous measurements performed at the Romanian Atmospheric 3D Observatory (RADO) situated near Bucharest which allowed the analysis of the type of mineral particles transported, the chemical composition of the refractory or non-refractory aerosols and their physical properties. This article is structured as follows. Section 2 describes the sampling site, the data and the methodology, including discussions on its main limitations. Section 3 provides the synoptic context of the dust transport and the local environment before the dust event. The dust particle morphology, their chemical composition and their optical properties are also described in Section 3. Finally, Section 4 summarizes the results of this paper. </p>
</text>
