<text id="autogum_academic_doc521" title="Fungal Diversity in Intertidal Mudflats and Abandoned Solar Salterns as a Source for Biological Resources" shortTile="fungal-diversity" author="Young  Mok Heo, Hanbyul Lee, Kyeongwon Kim, Sun  Lul Kwon, Min  Young Park, Ji  Eun Kang, Gyu-Hyeok Kim, Beom  Seok Kim, Jae-Jin Kim" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-3397/17/11/601/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Conclusions</head>
<p>
The results of the fungal community analysis showed that only the abandoned saltern in Yongyudo was significantly different from the other abandoned salterns or mudflats. The fungal communities in the abandoned salterns in Yubudo and Gopado had been restored to a similar status as those in the mudflats, but that was not the case of the saltern in Yongyudo, which was abandoned less than a year ago. The results also implied that it takes more than 35 years to restore abandoned salterns to mudflats via natural restoration. The α-diversity of the fungal community in the NS was significantly lower than that of the RSs and mudflats. The diversity indices were high in general, which implies that these unique environments are valuable for bioprospecting. </p>

<p>Through various statistical analyses, the lineages of Gigasporales sp. and <hi rend="italic">Umbelopsis</hi> sp. were selected as indicator taxa of mudflats in the Yellow Sea in South Korea. We demonstrate that the ecological recovery of the abandoned salterns can be assessed by using the two indicator taxa to indicate not only the recovery state but also the recovery direction, i.e., whether the recovery process is moving in the right direction. In this study, several analytical methods were applied to investigate indicator taxa. However, the results were not identical, even though we only used methods that use the absolute abundance data rather than processed data such as ecological distances that could lead to statistical misinterpretation. Therefore, indicator taxa must be selected by carefully comparing the results of various types of analysis. We also proved that the fungal community is highly suitable for use in ecosystem assessment, as it has a sufficient level of identification with good resolution. The limitation was that the number of samples, especially for the NS and RS environments, was insufficient. A larger sample size is recommended for more accurate statistical analysis with high fidelity. </p>

<p>To evaluate the fungal diversity and compare it with the results from the metagenome analysis, the culturable fungi were isolated from the sediment samples. A total of 53 fungal strains was isolated, and the number of fungal isolates differed by sampling location rather than by environment type. Based on the phylogenetic analysis, <hi rend="italic">Talaromyces</hi> was the most diverse genus, consisting of seven different species. The genera <hi rend="italic">Talaromyces</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Trichoderma</hi> were mostly isolated from the mudflat sediments, and most <hi rend="italic">Penicillium</hi> spp. were found in the NS. The diversity and the number of isolates in the NS were higher than those in the other salterns, which is inconsistent with the results of metagenomics, and every isolate except <hi rend="italic">P. chrysosporium</hi> belongs to the Ascomycota. This result showed that metagenomics must be applied when examining the microbial diversity within an actual environment, as has been suggested over the past decades. Interestingly, a total of 18 fungal isolates was identified as candidate novel species. </p>

<p>To evaluate the potential value of the intertidal environments for bioprospecting, a variety of biological activities of the fungal extracts were investigated. Regardless of the actual diversity, the isolates from both intertidal environments exhibited a variety of biological activities. Over half of the culturable fungal isolates (29 strains) exhibited biological activities, and <hi rend="italic">Penicillium</hi> spp. exhibited the most varied activities. The antioxidant compound of <hi rend="italic">Phoma</hi> sp. KUC21426, the tyrosinase inhibitors of <hi rend="italic">C. sphaerospermum</hi> KUC21388, the antifungal compounds of <hi rend="italic">Penicillium</hi> sp. 1 KUC21389 and <hi rend="italic">P. bakeri</hi> KUC21422, and the quorum-sensing inhibitor of <hi rend="italic">A. urmiensis</hi> KUC21392 will be separated and identified in the near future. Since bioactive compounds with these activities have never been reported from these species, the likelihood of discovering novel compounds is high. </p>

<p>In this study, we presented the fungal community and diversity of the abandoned solar salterns and the intertidal mudflats on three different islands located in the Yellow Sea of South Korea, and we identified indicator taxa for the assessment of the restoration of abandoned salterns to mudflats. Additionally, we provided reliable DNA information for the 53 fungal isolates from the intertidal sediments and their exploitable biological activities. We demonstrated that these unique environments are highly valuable in bioprospecting not only for novel microorganisms but also for novel bioactive compounds. Restoring the reduced biodiversity of abandoned salterns is important in terms of environmental protection and conservation. However, many novel fungal species were found from the abandoned salterns, and interestingly, all fungal strains selected for high bioactivity were isolated from NS or RS. Therefore, active measures to recover abandoned salterns to mudflats should be carefully determined and planned, taking into account their value as a source of biological resources.
 </p>
</text>
