<text id="autogum_academic_doc399" title="An Analysis of Large-Scale Forced Migration in Africa" shortTile="analysis-largescale" author="Murat Bayar, Mustafa  M. Aral" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4210/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Literature Review: Human Security and Forced Migration</head>
<p>
Developed by the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP), the concept of human security stresses economic, environmental, health, food, personal/community and political aspects of people’s wellbeing. Accordingly, the human development index introduced by UNDP has expanded the study of development from mere economic terms to 13 different dimensions. </p>

<p>Supported by the UN, the Commission on Human Security (CHC) has defined human security as <hi rend="italic">“… creating political, social, environmental, economic, military and cultural systems that together give people the building blocks of survival, livelihood and dignity</hi>” (p. 4). Human security and national security are not mutually exclusive, since a failed state would largely be incapable of providing essential provisions for its citizens. Yet, these two concepts are not fully compatible, because undemocratic states can protect their national borders while ripping their citizens of their personal and community resources. To note, human security has also been questioned for the tangibility of its contributions to the development debate, especially from an environmental perspective. </p>

<p>The study of forced migration requires that we clarify the differences between various migrant categories. The International Organization for Migration (IOM) has defined “migrant” as, “<hi rend="italic">any person who is moving or has moved across an international border or within a State away from his/her habitual place of residence, regardless of (1) the person’s legal status; (2) whether the movement is voluntary or involuntary; (3) what the causes for the movement are; or (4) what the length of the stay is</hi>”. </p>

<p>The IOM has defined forced migration as, “<hi rend="italic">A migratory movement in which an element of coercion exists, including threats to life and livelihood, whether arising from natural or man-made causes (e.g., movements of refugees and internally displaced persons as well as people displaced by natural or environmental disasters, chemical or nuclear disasters, famine, or development projects)</hi>”. In parallel, “refugee” is someone “who has been forced to flee his or her country because of persecution, war or violence”, and “asylum seeker” is someone “whose request for sanctuary has yet to be processed”. Although the IOM’s definition of “migrant” comprises “refugee” and “asylum seeker”, the legal framework of different countries can actually make a vital distinction for these categories. While refugees can be provided with some socioeconomic rights and a path to full citizenship, asylum seekers are not granted these options. </p>

<p>Noting the legal and conceptual differences between various migrant categories, we pool all refugees, asylum-seekers and other types of internally and externally displaced persons (but not voluntary migrants, as measured by the UN High Commissioner for Refugees—UNHCR) together for each country-year in this study. As discussed in the methodology section, our underlying assumption is that total number of forced migrants amounting to at least 5 percent of a country’s population constitutes a special case for origin countries, although these people may be classified differently in destination countries. For instance, Turkey considers forced migrants coming from Europe as refugees, whereas it considers those coming from “East” (including Africa) as asylum seekers (p. 21). We assume that these legal differences have no theoretical implications for the purposes of this study, because we are investigating the relationship between our variables for each origin country, not for destination or transit countries. </p>

<p>The literature highlights international wage differentials, policies of origin and destination states, poverty and violent conflict among the drivers of human migration. Simply put, repressive (e.g., against ethnic/religious minorities) home governments push, and welcoming (e.g., through multicultural policies) destination countries attract migrants. Not surprisingly, migrants flow from poor and/or conflict-ridden countries to relatively developed and stable states. Moreover, adverse environmental factors, such as drought, flood and inundation, increase the likelihood of conflict and migration. For example, Gleick has attributed the mass uprising and the subsequent civil war in Syria during the so-called Arab Spring to a prior collapse in food output due to several years of drought. </p>

<p>Given that several African economies rely heavily on agricultural production, their exposure to extreme weather conditions (whether causing drought, heavy rainfall or other extreme events) makes an adverse effect on the livelihoods of millions of people. Sea level rise poses another threat on both populations and commercial activities of coastal cities. Taken together with “poverty traps” that have strangled the continent for decades, these challenges are among the potential causes of large-scale human migration in Africa. Below we review various aspects of human security, as well as foreign aid as a potential remedy for these challenges. </p>
</text>
