<text id="autogum_academic_doc742" title="Platform Growth Model: The Four Stages of Growth Model" shortTile="platform-growth-model" author="Junic Kim, Jaewook Yoo" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5562/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Data Analysis</head>
<p>
A conceptual framework based on a logic model is useful for research related to evaluation. A conceptual framework is a heuristic frame for assessing cause-and-effect relationships, which describes the logical relationship of concepts used and identifies the conditions, objects and the idea itself. It creates a complicated connection of cases that tend to repeat the pattern “cause–result–cause–result” and can cause variables that are dependent on the initial phase to become independent in the next stage. Using a conceptual framework as an analytical method means that observed cases can be matched based on experience with theoretically predictable cases. A conceptual framework might, therefore, be seen as a kind of pattern-matching technique. However, since it is related to consecutive phases, it is possible to proceed with a more accurate analysis when using a conceptual framework than with simple pattern-matching. </p>

<p>This study used a conceptual framework (<figure>Figure 2</figure>) based on the literature review to analyse whether the logical propositions were consistent with the patterns in the data and to derive the results. It examined explicitly whether consecutive cases with the same cause–result–effect were connected and repeatable, as well as whether they applied in other cases. The strategy is increasingly dynamic, and there are many different strategic issues for each growth stage. Therefore, adequate core elements and strategies for each stage are crucial in today’s business world. According to a “cyclical model of technological change” by Anderson and Tushman and a “stages of growth model” by Gibson and Nolan, growth models can be divided into four stages: entry, growth, expansion and stage. Depending on the nature of the platform, each stage consists of economics and business theories, two-sided markets, network effects and business ecosystems, which are the main theories relating to platform businesses. Each stage has a different set of tasks, and each task has a different set of decision items and influence factors to be considered.</p>
<list>
<item>Entry stage: Internal and external analysis for selecting the platform business;</item>
<item>Growth stage: Solutions to the chicken-or-the-egg problem endemic to constructing a two-sided market;</item>
<item>Expansion stage: Way to reach critical mass for accelerating the network effect;</item>
<item>Maturity stage: Platform quality management and revenue structure construction measure for establishing the business ecosystem.</item>
</list>

<p>
The dynamic model of platform business presented herein is based on the four-stage conceptual framework. The propositions were deduced through matching and comparing the encoded contents with the conceptual framework. The results of the second-step case study were classified into four chronological stages, and then, they were summarised and presented for each stage. The strategic questions and core elements of each chronological stage are shown in <figure>Figure 2</figure>. </p>
</text>
