<text id="autogum_academic_doc383" title="Critical Factors Influencing the Adoption of Smart Home Energy Technology in China: A Guangdong Province Case Study" shortTile="critical-factors" author="WeiYu Ji, Edwin  H. W. Chan" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4180/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Globally, the residential sector is responsible for 20% of the total energy consumption, and this is expected to increase by 10% until 2040 due to the growth of population, economic development and improvement of living standards. Many technologies have been developed and engaged to solve the energy efficiency problem of residential buildings. In recent years, with the rapid development of information and communication technology (ICT) and smart grids, smart home technology (SHT) has become a promising measure to benefit home occupant’s living environment and improve living quality. One important category of SHT is smart home energy technology (SHET), particularly aiming to provide energy management services or energy reduction measures to residents. SHET includes integrated systems or isolated components to manage the demand side of a smart grid by monitoring and arranging the home electricity consumption and various smart home appliances. SHET achieves its energy management goals in two ways: (1) providing residents with their energy consumption information, to help residents cultivate energy saving behaviors; and (2) providing residents the ability to control the domestic appliances which can be scheduled or optimized via smart devices, so that they can utilize some electricity tariff policies to cut their energy bills. </p>

<p>Under the pressure of reducing the energy consumption of residential sector, several country governments have proposed various policies or strategies to promote the use of smart technology in home energy saving, such as the European Commission’s “Create technologies and services for smart homes that provide smart solutions to energy consumers” and the Smart Hong Kong plan “Promote and support households to utilize smart home mobile apps to monitor household energy consumption and set targets”. In Singapore, some households were selected to install a home energy management system (HEMS) in a collaboration between the government and Panasonic. </p>

<p>Lots of previous research has focused on the technical issues of smart home energy technology. Karlin categorized the current SHET into three groups: user interfaces, including energy portal, in-home display, load monitor; and smart hardware, including smart appliance, smart light, smart thermostat, smart plug/switch as well as software platforms, such as smart home/web service platform. The energy-saving capacity of each category of SHET have been demonstrated by many studies. Louis et al. focused their attention on the environmental impacts of home energy systems during their lifecycle, and pointed out the energy payback time would be 1.6 years. </p>

<p>Additionally, several researchers have worked on topics related to the adoption and diffusion of smart home energy technology. Balta-Ozkan organized expert interviews and questionnaire surveys in European countries, and investigated social barriers to smart home technology diffusion, including fitting to lifestyles, public administration, interoperability, reliability, privacy, trust, and cost; he also pointed out energy cost savings, improving quality of life, environment, and information transparency as the four main drivers of smart home market development. In Singapore, Bhati analyzed the perceptions of households about the usage of smart energy technology, concluding that residents have high awareness of the energy efficiency and indoor comfort, but are also concerned about the problem of security and privacy. Some articles have examined the factors determining the adoption intention of specific home energy technology such as energy efficient household appliances or home energy management systems in several different countries, including Korea, Malaysia, China and Pakistan. </p>

<p>However, the influential factors of adoption intention are highly affected by the regional culture or demographic situation. When talking about China, it has a huge population of 1.4 billion, and the residential sector accounts for 30.6% of the total primary energy consumption. Currently, the penetration rate of smart home energy technology in China is only 1.4%, lower than the global average level of 1.67%. What is more, the literature studying the adoption of SHET by Chinese urban residents is not adequate. More endeavor will be needed to investigate residents’ perceptions towards SHET and the factors affecting resident’s adoption intention. Bridging this research gap could provide support to policy decisions or market strategies to promote the adoption and diffusion of SHET in China. </p>
</text>
