<text id="autogum_academic_doc048" title="Toward a New Generation of Two-Fluid Flow Models Based on the Thermodynamically-Constrained Averaging Theory" shortTile="toward-new-generation" author="Kelsey Bruning, Cass  T. Miller" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4441/11/11/2260/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Thermodynamically Constrained Averaging Theory</head>
<p>
A wide range of length scales exist and the terminology used to describe these length scales varies in the literature. For our purposes, three discrete length scales are of concern to support the discussion that follows. The microscale is a length scale that is long compared to the mean distance between molecular collisions or the vibrational scale for a solid. At the microscale a point represents an averaging region that is related to the lower bound on the length scale needed for the laws of continuum mechanics to apply. Another characteristic of the microscale is that a point exists entirely within an individual phase, even in a system that includes multiphase phases (fluids, solids). Porous medium systems are systems that contain multiple phases by definition. At the microscale, the morphology and topology of the phase distributions are resolved in time. For porous medium systems, the microscale is oftentimes referred to as the pore scale. </p>

<p>The second scale of concern herein is the macroscale. The macroscale is a scale where phase distributions are resolved only in an averaged sense; a point is the centroid of an averaging region which extends over all phases, interfaces, common curves, and common points that exist in a system. Macroscale extent measures involve concepts such as volume fractions, fluid saturations, specific interfacial areas, and specific common curve lengths. The boundaries of the phases are not resolved at the macroscale, only the averaged extent measures are resolved. Macroscale representations are necessary to make many systems of interest tractable, including engineered systems such as filters and reactors and natural systems such as subsurface porous medium systems, including petroleum reservoirs. This is so because even for cases in which microscale details of phase distribution are accessible, computational limitations of even the world’s fastest computers precludes the detailed simulations of systems at the scale of applications of concern, say the unsaturated zone above an aquifer. Macroscale representations are also used as a simplification when microscale details are unnecessary for the problem of interest. </p>

<p>The third scale of interest is termed the megascale, and it is the overall length scale of the system of concern, which might vary greatly in size between a model laboratory system, an engineered system, and a natural system. What is common at the megascale however is that the details of the spatial distribution of quantities within the system are not resolved. Instead, inputs and outputs from the system are considered only on the boundaries of the system. Oftentimes systems may be considered megascale in one or two dimensions and say macroscale in the remaining dimensions. An example of such an instance is the treatment of a subsurface region in a vertically averaged fashion; only spatial variations in the horizontal plane are resolved. </p>

<p>The typical situation is that macroscale models are phenomenological in nature—meaning conservation equations are written following an assumed form usually based upon a presumed extension of microscale principles, which are better understood. Then the macroscale models are typically closed using empirical relations intended to represent small-scale behavior in a simplified, yet meaningful and tractable manner. The literature is replete with such examples, and flow and transport phenomena in porous medium systems is a prime class of example. The phenomenological approach can lead to solvable systems that enable solutions, but the general procedure is fraught with problems, many of which are not well understood because the general approach is deeply ingrained in text books and practice, and generally accepted. </p>

<p>The phenomenological approach of model formulation suffers from several problems. First, fundamental microscale physics may not be naturally and explicitly present in posited macroscale models. Second, certain microscale principles, such as thermodynamics, are often completely ignored. Third, quantities that appear in macroscale models may not be precisely defined in terms of microscale quantities, precluding a rigorous connection between microscale systems and macroscale systems. Fourth, macroscale closure relations are often constructs of convenience intended to produce solvable systems but not deduced from fundamentals or constrained to obey thermodynamic principles, such as the second law of thermodynamics. Fifth, phenomenological models are typically evaluated and validated by comparing to the overall system of concern, and when they fail to provide an adequate description a new model must be formulated without a rigorous, well-defined procedure to do so. TCAT has been developed to resolve these issues associated with standard phenomenological approaches. </p>
</text>
