<text id="autogum_academic_doc434" title="Advances and Challenges of Using the Sterile Insect Technique for the Management of Pest Lepidoptera" shortTile="advances-challenges" author="František Marec, Marc  J. B. Vreysen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-4450/10/11/371/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 7. Challenges</head>
<p>
As can be seen from this review, over the last 20 years, considerable progress has been made in the research on the applicability and improvement of SIT/IS for the control of lepidopteran pests, including the successful implementation of SIT programs against several major agricultural pests. However, there are still some challenges to further improve the applicability of SIT/IS. </p>

<p>Current programs using SIT/IS against lepidopteran pests rely on bisexual releases, but there are reasons to believe that male-only releases would bring significant economic benefits by decreasing operational costs and increasing the efficiency of the sterile males. This has been well demonstrated in the SIT programs against the Mediterranean fruit fly (medfly), <hi rend="italic">Ceratitis capitata</hi> (Wiedemann), using a genetic sexing strain that allowed the mass production and release of males only. On the contrary, the results of field-cage experiments with several lepidopteran pests, such as the cactus moth, suggest that sterile females might have a positive impact on population suppression, thus casting doubts on the need for genetic sexing strains. However, experience with the Mediterranean fruit fly shows that a clear conclusion cannot be reached without large-scale field tests that would compare the efficiency of male-only versus bisexual releases for the control of lepidopteran pests. </p>

<p>In Lepidoptera, a pure genetic sexing system has been developed in only two species: the silkworm <hi rend="italic">B. mori</hi> and the flour moth <hi rend="italic">E. kuehniella</hi>. This sexing system is based on the construction of a balanced lethal strain generating transheterozygous males for two sex-linked recessive lethal mutations. When the males are mated to wild-type females, the F1 generation consists almost exclusively of male progeny. However, this system is impractical for SIT/IS programs. It requires (i) the mass rearing of two colonies, (ii) the manual separation of sexes in both colonies before crosses producing male-only progeny, and (iii) the regular checking of the genetic structure of the balanced lethal strain to prevent its breakdown. </p>

<p>New opportunities for genetic sexing emerged along with advances in genetic technologies, especially in transgenesis and gene editing. In Lepidoptera, the first germline transformations were performed in the pink bollworm and in the silkworm using a <hi rend="italic">piggyBac</hi> transposable element. Based on this success, it has been proposed to construct genetic sexing strains using a transgenic approach so that the females carry a transgene with a dominant conditional lethal mutation in their W chromosome that would be expressed in embryogenesis. Such strains, if their eggs are kept at restrictive conditions, would produce non-transgenic male-only progeny that could be irradiated and released (<figure>Figure 9</figure>a,b). The development of such strains was initiated in the codling moth, but this work was later discontinued due to the low efficiency of transgenesis in this species. That this approach is feasible has recently been demonstrated in the silkworm by the successful insertion of a transgene carrying the EGFP (enhanced green fluorescent protein) reporter into the W chromosome. Furthermore, new transgenic strains providing a conditional sex-specific lethality were constructed in the silkworm and in two pest species: the diamondback moth and the pink bollworm. In these strains, conditional female lethality is controlled by the tetracycline-repressible transactivator (tTAV) protein, which is expressed only in females due to the female-specific spliced region of the pink bollworm <hi rend="italic">doublesex</hi> gene, <hi rend="italic">Pgdsx</hi>. Methods of gene editing appear to be even more promising for the development of genetic sexing strains than transgenesis, because they allow targeted mutagenesis. Although these methods have not yet been used for genetic sexing in Lepidoptera, particularly the CRISPR/Cas9 (clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats/CRISPR-associated protein 9) technique has already been successfully established in several species and used to study gene functions. </p>

<p>A detailed knowledge of the sex-determining pathway could greatly facilitate the development of genetic sexing strains that are suitable for the mass rearing of lepidopteran pests. However, little is known about the mechanism of sex determination in Lepidoptera except for the silkworm <hi rend="italic">B. mori</hi>. In this model species, a homologue of the <hi rend="italic">Drosophila doublesex</hi> (<hi rend="italic">dsx</hi>) gene, <hi rend="italic">Bmdsx</hi>, was found to be sex-specifically spliced and confirmed to control sexual differentiation, as does the <hi rend="italic">Drosophila dsx</hi> gene. This bottom gene of the sex-determining cascade in <hi rend="italic">Drosophila</hi> seems to be the only conserved gene of this cascade in Lepidoptera. In the silkworm, sex determination depends on the presence or absence of the W chromosome, which carries a dominant female-determining factor (<hi rend="italic">Fem</hi>) that promotes femaleness, irrespective of the number of Z chromosomes present in the genome. Recently, a surprising discovery has been made that <hi rend="italic">Fem</hi> is not a protein-coding gene, as originally assumed, but rather a W-encoded small RNA named <hi rend="italic">Fem</hi> piRNA. The <hi rend="italic">Fem</hi> piRNA downregulates the expression of a Z-linked gene, <hi rend="italic">Masculinizer</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Masc</hi>), which promotes male development through male-specific splicing of the <hi rend="italic">Bmdsx</hi> gene in the absence of the W chromosome. </p>
</text>
