<text id="autogum_academic_doc377" title="Potential Analysis of Hybrid Renewable Energy Systems for Self-Sufficient Residential Use in Germany and the Czech Republic" shortTile="potential-analysis" author="Luis Ramirez Camargo, Felix Nitsch, Katharina Gruber, Javier Valdes, Jane Wuth, Wolfgang Dorner" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4185/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Conclusions</head>
<p>
In the presented study, the economically optimal configurations of PV-wind-battery systems are calculated with the help of a MILP model based on datasets of weather variables and population density as well as detailed technical specifications on the generation technologies. In the investigated low-populated regions of Germany and the Czech Republic, clusters of 10 and 50 Electricity Self-Sufficient Single Family Houses are modelled. The results show that including wind power in such self-sufficient systems decreases the comparatively high installed capacities of PV necessary at higher geographic latitudes due to lower solar irradiation while reducing total installation costs compared to PV-battery systems only. In areas of intermediate and high wind resources, storage capacities can be significantly reduced. The results remain stable, even if limited PV production due to snow coverage is considered in the model.  </p>

<p>Regarding particular areas, maps revealing the total costs for a hybrid renewable electricity system show most profitable locations in the south of Germany, as well as challenging locations mainly in the western part of the Czech Republic and in the eastern parts of Germany. There are important differences depending on weather conditions. In the majority of Bavaria in south Germany, as well as large areas in the western Czech Republic, small-scale wind power plants are not considered in a cost-minimized solution due to low wind resources and a lack of complementarity between wind and solar power. Total costs of the hybrid systems for the 50 households’ clusters, aiming for full electricity self-sufficiency and without considering financing costs, range between EUR 1.8 million and EUR 5 million. These costs divided by the number of households and the amount of electricity that these would require in a 20 years’ horizon are at least 2.3 (best locations in Germany) and up to 10.5 (worst locations in the Czech Republic) times larger than the current costs of obtaining electricity from the grid. </p>

<p>The results are not only relevant for groups of homeowners who consider installing a hybrid stand-alone renewable electricity system as a community, but also for investors or policy makers, as they present a guideline on how to size such systems and where in Germany and the Czech Republic, they are the most attractive regarding installation costs. Further research should focus on simulations with differing load profiles and under different policy and cost scenarios. Several cases of homeowners who reflect different levels of risk aversion with regards to levels of self-sufficiency, respectively the probability of loss of power supply and grid-dependency could further provide valuable insights. Such results may allow defining how technology improvements and cost reductions can impact the overall systems’ profitability under regionally more explicit consumer behaviour scenarios. Finally, in order to assess full energy self-sufficiency, the study conducted here has to be extended to include the energy demand for heating/cooling of the households and alternative hybrid system configurations to supply it.
 </p>
</text>
