<text id="autogum_academic_doc050" title="Bystander Effects of Nitric Oxide in Cellular Models of Anti-Tumor Photodynamic Therapy" shortTile="bystander-effects" author="Jerzy Bazak, Witold Korytowski, Albert  W. Girotti" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6694/11/11/1674/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Clinically relevant photodynamic therapy (PDT) was introduced about 45 years ago as a novel means for selectively eradicating a variety of solid tumors via cytotoxic photochemistry. As an anti-tumor modality, PDT is unique in requiring three components: a photosensitizing agent (PS), PS-exciting light in the far-visible-to-near-infrared range, and molecular oxygen. PS photoexcitation during PDT gives rise to cytotoxic reactive oxygen species (ROS) such as singlet oxygen (1O2). The first PS to receive FDA approval for PDT applications was Photofrin®, an oligomeric form of hematoporphyrin that continues to be used for a variety of malignancies. Unlike more conventional chemotherapy or radiotherapy, PDT has few (if any) light-independent side effects and is non-invasive and site-specific, i.e., limited to the tumor upon which light is directed, typically via fiber optic networks. Moreover, PDT can often overcome the innate or acquired resistance to other therapies that many tumors exhibit. In addition to pre-existing administered sensitizers such as Photofrin®, pro-sensitizers have been developed, one common example being 5-aminolevulinic acid (ALA). Upon entering cancer cells via an amino acid transporter, ALA is metabolized to protoporphyrin IX (PpIX), the active PS, via the heme biosynthetic pathway, PpIX accumulating initially in mitochondria. For rapid proliferative needs, tumor cells are more active in heme synthesis than normal counterparts. In addition to acting as a PDT sensitizer, ALA-induced PpIX, like that induced by more lipophilic ALA esters, e.g., Hexvix, can serve as a highly effective fluorophore for image-guided tumor resection. Many cancer cells exhibit an intrinsic or acquired resistance to radiotherapy or chemotherapy, and resistance to PDT has also been demonstrated. For ALA-PDT, one notable resistance mechanism involves efflux of newly synthesized PpIX via the plasma membrane transporter ABCG2. Another important mechanism involves nitric oxide (NO) generated by constitutive and/or PDT stress-upregulated inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS/NOS2). </p>

<p>NO is a bioactive free radical molecule (1–2 sec lifetime in water) that diffuses freely on its own and, similar to oxygen (O2), tends to partition into hydrophobic regions of cells, e.g., cell membranes. At relatively low steady state levels (e.g., 50–300 nM range), NO is known to play a key signaling role in survival, migration, and drug resistance of many different cancer cells. This contrasts with the cytotoxic effects of NO produced at much higher levels (≥1 µM) by activated macrophages during an inflammatory response, e.g., to infection. In previous work, we discovered that various cancer cell lines significantly upregulate cytoprotective iNOS and NO after a moderate photodynamic challenge sensitized by ALA-induced PpIX. The iNOS/NO induction in PDT-surviving (still attached) cells was relatively rapid after irradiation (2–3 h) and prolonged (at least 24 h). Importantly, these cells exhibited a more aggressive growth, migratory, and invasive phenotype than non-photostressed controls, and this was suppressed by inhibition of iNOS or by NO scavenging. We postulated that induced diffusible NO from PDT-targeted cells might elicit a pro-growth/migratory response in non- or minimally-targeted bystander cells. In an actual tumor, such targeting diversity might result from uneven PS distribution due to irregularities in the tumor microvasculature. Using photosensitized prostate cancer PC3 cells, we recently observed NO-mediated hyper-aggressive bystander effects for the first time in the context of PDT. In the present study, we compared the ability of four PDT-treated cancer lines (melanoma BLM, glioblastoma U87, breast MDA-MB-231, and prostate PC3) to stimulate NO-dependent aggressiveness in bystander cells of the same type. </p>
</text>
