<text id="autogum_academic_doc069" title="Method for Estimating Sediment Mass Movement from Delta Recutting: A Case Study Using Single Beam Sonar in Deer Creek Reservoir" shortTile="method-estimating" author="Gustavious  Paul Williams, Ashley  Childers Walton" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4441/11/11/2222/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion</head><head> 5.1. General Issues</head>
<p>
The data showed sediment movement within the channels over time. The survey lines showed both deposition and erosion at different locations on various lines. In some cases, the changes did not appear to be from the result of physical processes, but were either the results of data collection errors, such as not surveying the identical location, or issues relating to the analysis. </p>

<p>The following sections describe trends within the channels for each survey line. In these discussions we explain the observed trends or changes and attempt to associate these trends with physical processes or attribute the changes to other issues; however, these explanations may not accurately represent what is actually happening due to the limited amount of data. While enough data were collected to determine if this approach is feasible, there were not sufficient data collected to adequately characterize all the various processes occurring in the channels, which was not an objective of this study. </p>

<p>The sonar data matched our expectations and what we know of the physical delta recutting that occurs at DCR. <figure>Figure 6</figure> shows two channels in the exposed DCR sediment delta taken when the reservoir was significantly drawn down for dam repair. The left panel of <figure>Figure 6</figure> shows sharp slopes resembles sonar geometry in the results from Lines 4 to 7 which show channels with sharp side slopes that are almost vertical (sonar results are shown later in <figure>Figure 7</figure>, <figure>Figure 8</figure>, <figure>Figure 9</figure> and <figure>Figure 10</figure>). These results closely matched channel shapes in the exposed delta area shown in the left panel of <figure>Figure 6</figure>. The right panel of <figure>Figure 6</figure>, from the same time period, shows a more rounded channel, similar sonar-delimited channels that appear in Lines 1 to 4 (sonar results are shown later in <figure>Figure 7</figure> and <figure>Figure 8</figure>). </p>

<p>The data for all the lines showed that as the distance along the survey line increases, there is more apparent change in the sediment. That is, it appears that there is more sediment movement occurring at the end of the line than near the beginning. This occurs even in areas between the channels where we expected no, or little, change. Both the nature of these differences, increasing with increasing distance along the line, and changes occurring in regions we expect to have no or little change indicate that these changes were a result of a problem with our measurement or processing methods. These changes were not large, but were noticeable. </p>

<p>We determined that the most likely cause of these anomalies was the processing step where we converted the latitude and longitude readings (<hi rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y</hi> data), to one-dimensional data representing distance along a line. In our method we used the starting coordinate of the survey line as the initial point and we computed distance along the line as the distance from this point. However, during field data collections, it was extremely rare (i.e., never) for the survey line to be perfectly straight during collection, as the boat occasionally moved slightly off the heading and was brought back on line. Thus the distance from the line origin to a sample point was not necessarily the distance along the line. </p>

<p>One potential way to address this issue would be to not to compute the distance between the line origin and a measured point, but to create a rotated coordinate system for each line with one ordinal direction matched to the line direction. Then the converted data would show distance from the starting point along the line (on-track distance) and the perpendicular distance of the point (off-track distance) from the line. This would have the added benefit of easier identification of measured points significantly off the survey line. This was an error in our method. </p>

<head> 5.2. Discussion Survey Lines 1, 2, and 3</head>
<p>
Lines 1, 2, and 3 (<figure>Figure 7</figure>), were only surveyed two times on 2 July and 16 July and because of reservoir drawdown this area was too shallow to access on the other trips. The data for these lines showed little change over this two-week period, but the data indicated several potential survey problems and small changes would not be evident. As these were to first two surveys, it is likely that there may have been problems with the sonar setup, as the sonar requires accurate off-set and other information that may have been entered incorrectly. Because we could not access these lines in subsequent surveys, we could not determine the cause or causes of the anomalies present in the data. </p>
</text>
