<text id="autogum_academic_doc537" title="Underwater Acoustic Impulsive Noise Monitoring in Port Facilities: Case Study of the Port of Cartagena†" shortTile="underwater-acoustic" author="Ivan  Felis Enguix, Marta Sánchez Egea, Antonio Guerrero González, David  Arenas Serrano" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4672/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Conclusions</head>
<p>Through this study it has been proven that
<list>
<item>After analyzing the background and continuous sound levels in the Port of Cartagena, it was found that impulsive sound must have a level above approximately 70 dB re 1 µPa to be detected, depending on the frequency (between 80 and 45 dB re 1 µPa in the frequency range from 10 to 100 kHz, respectively). Only one impulsive sound source was detected, and this was due to container loading operations on the east side of the port. Although this source is not usually indicated in the search for impulsive sources, these operations can be considered as a potentially impulsive noise generating activity, according to the requirements of the Marine Strategy Framework Directive.</item>
<item>The analysis of the bathymetric survey of the study area was fundamental in the application of acoustic propagation models, as the type of seabed influenced the intensity of the sound, due to the reflections of the waves. Also, having reliable bathymetric information contributed to the construction of a consistent acoustic propagation model, as the accuracy of the data will also affect the accuracy of the model.</item>
<item>The application of the acoustic propagation model implemented in this study, despite being approximate, provided information on the potential impact produced by the generation of impulsive noise in the vicinity of the Port of Cartagena.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>
In addition, this study has provided
<list>
<item>Measurements of impulsive sound, in accordance with the requirements of the Marine Strategy Framework Directive, which will serve to form part of the port’s underwater sound record.</item>
<item>Updated and accurate data on the bathymetry of the port that can be used in subsequent studies and projects.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>The results of this study can serve as a starting point for a larger scale strategy against the potential impact of underwater noise (both impulsive and continuous) in the Port of Cartagena. </p>

<p>To continue advancing in this regard, the following recommendations are proposed:
<list>
<item>Continuous monitoring of the levels of underwater sound in the Port of Cartagena, especially during activities that could potentially generate underwater noise during the periods of high sensitivity of any marine species that could be affected.</item>
<item>Collection of information on marine biodiversity present in the area where activities are carried out and their surroundings. Identifying species with special sensitivity to the potential impact of submarine noise in the vicinity of the Port of Cartagena.</item>
<item>Incorporating location systems for sensitive species in the port area, through, for example, passive acoustic systems.</item>
<item>Adopting a set of preventive and corrective measures for activities potentially generating submarine noise, firstly related to the selection and exclusion of areas to carry out activities according to their potential impact and to minimize their environmental impact. Secondly, to control activities in seasons of special sensitivity (migrations, breeding, etc.), including the regulation of activities (navigation, works, etc.) to minimize their possible adverse effects.</item>
</list>
</p>
</text>
