<text id="autogum_academic_doc002" title="The Impact of Oxidative Stress on Ribosomes: From Injury to Regulation" shortTile="impact-oxidative" author="Natalia Shcherbik, Dimitri  G. Pestov" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4409/8/11/1379/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Oxidative Modification of rRNA</head>
<p>
rRNA constitutes the structural and functional core of the ribosome. ROS can affect RNA in a multitude of ways, including chemical modification of the base and sugar moieties, generation of abasic sites, and strand breaks. Guanine is the most easily oxidized nucleobase and best studied in this respect. An oxidized form of guanine, 8-oxo-7,8-dihydroguanine (8-hydroxyguanine; 8-oxo-G), is a ubiquitous oxidative lesion, readily detectable in cellular nucleic acids. When present in mRNA, 8-oxo-G interferes with decoding, possibly through the formation of a Hoogsteen pair with adenine when the base rotates around the N-glycosidic bond. The altered base-pairing capacity of 8-oxo-G can also perturb RNA folding. A recent study revealed a variety of outcomes when 8-oxo-G was incorporated into model RNA substrates, from stabilization of existing structural motifs to their destabilization and rearrangements into new structures. Since ribosome activities in translation depend on many precisely tuned conformational changes and movements within its rRNA framework, oxidation of the bases that are critical for maintaining the correct rRNA structure may impair ribosome functions. It seems therefore likely that the need to withstand a certain degree of oxidation was one of the forces in shaping the evolution of the ribosome. A striking disappearance of many guanines from mitochondrial rRNA and reduced overall RNA content may be two such evolutionary adaptations that “hardened” mitoribosomes against damage from the abundant ROS generated inside mitochondria. </p>

<p>The extent of cellular RNA oxidation was reported to exceed that of DNA when cells were directly treated with H2O2 or subjected to conditions that induce secondary oxidative damage, such as UVA irradiation and ammonia overload. In one study, exposure of <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> cells to H2O2 was shown to induce a dosage-dependent increase of 8-oxo-G in all tested RNA types, including rRNA. By comparing 8-oxo-G levels after in vitro H2O2 treatment of RNAs in their native and denatured forms, the same study concluded that folding of rRNA did not protect it against oxidative damage. Similar conclusions were made by Willi and colleagues, who used an 8-oxo-G antibody to immunoprecipitate oxidized RNA from H2O2-treated <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> cells. </p>

<p>A large body of observations points to the association of oxidized RNA with disease. High 8-oxo-G content in cytoplasmic and nucleolar RNA was found in vulnerable neurons in Alzheimer′s disease (AD), Parkinson’s disease, and neurons of the hippocampal region and temporal neocortex in patients with Lewy body dementia. Elevated levels of 8-oxo-G in RNA were also detected in neuropsychiatric disorders, including schizophrenia, depressive, and bipolar disorders. Furthermore, RNA extracted from atherosclerotic plaques was heavily modified with 8-oxo-G. Although links between 8-oxo-G and human pathologies have been based largely on the analysis of total RNA, rRNA is the most abundant cellular RNA type, which typically accounts for about 80% of the total RNA, from which one can reasonably assume that oxidative damage to ribosomes in all these pathological conditions must be widespread. Studies that focused specifically on rRNA confirmed it to be a major target of the 8-oxo-G modification in patients with AD and mild cognitive impairment, a condition that often precedes AD. </p>
</text>
