<text id="autogum_academic_doc055" title="Discrimination of DNA Methylation Signal from Background Variation for Clinical Diagnostics" shortTile="discrimination-dna" author="Robersy Sanchez, Xiaodong Yang, Thomas Maher, Sally  A. Mackenzie" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5343/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Cytosine DNA methylation (5-methylcytosine; 5mC, CDM) is one of the most well-studied epigenomic marks and mechanistically understood epigenetic modifications to date. It plays important roles in various biological processes, including X-chromosome inactivation, genomic imprinting, transposon suppression and transcriptional regulation. Technological improvements and dramatic cost reductions for whole-genome sodium bisulfite sequencing (WGBS) of DNA have opened the door to the quantitative measurement of DNA methylation at a single base resolution, with datasets now available from numerous species. </p>

<p>In humans, significant methylation differences are observed in the white blood cells of matched monozygotic and dizygotic twins, and significant intra- and inter-population differential methylation has been identified in a study of three human populations (Caucasian-American, African-American and Chinese-American). Likewise, DNA methylation levels vary considerably in samples experiencing changes during development or in response to environmental change. </p>

<p>Translation of the advances in DNA methylation to clinical and personalized medical contexts has been proposed. Evidence of epigenetic alterations induced by disease emphasizes the significant potential value of high-resolution methylation pattern analysis. However, proper translation of this knowledge for diagnostics depends upon the development of genome-wide techniques for the rapid and robust identification of specific epigenetic alterations associated with the disease. </p>

<p>Currently, there are numerous available bioinformatics tools to estimate the methylation status of nearly every cytosine position within a whole-genome bisulfite sequencing dataset. These tools are generally supported by an application of robust statistical approaches; DSS, BiSeq, and methylKit, among others, are ones that apply generalized linear regression (beta-regression) in the estimation of differentially methylated positions (DMPs). In addition, methylKit provides the option to apply Fisher’s exact test. Alternatively, methylpy bases its estimation on the implementation of the root-mean-square test (RMST). Most of these approaches do not incorporate the influence of natural stochasticity (randomness) to their models, limiting their resolution predominantly to genomic regions with the highest probability of having undergone a methylation change. As a consequence, these approaches do not have the ability to distinguish the DMP signal associated with a specific treatment (or disease) from DMPs deriving from natural variation within control (or heathy) individuals, and are thus not suitable for clinical diagnostics. We suggest that methylation variation in diagnostics is essentially a signal detection problem, equivalent to a binary classification problem for discriminating healthy versus diseased individuals. Signal detection theory provides the methodological framework to address this type of detection problem, evidenced in its common application to clinical diagnostic tests, machine-learning (ML) approaches, and human communication technologies. </p>

<p>The probability of extreme methylation changes occurring spontaneously in a control group of samples by the stochastic fluctuations inherent to biochemical processes and DNA maintenance, requires the discrimination of this background variation from a biological treatment signal. Regardless of environmental constancy, statistically significant methylation changes are found in control populations with probability greater than zero. These system fluctuations, inherent in biological stochastic processes, comprise natural background variation detected in human methylomes. By simulation, it is feasible to demonstrate that DMPs spontaneously arise in control populations, and that regulatory methylation signals also occur naturally in the control group. </p>

<p>Stochastic fluctuation of the methylation process is expected, since methylation regulatory machinery participates, not only in organismal adaptation to micro- and macro-environmental fluctuations, but also in transitions across different stages of organismal ontogenetic development. This variation must be factored into the construction of a methylation pipeline to be used in clinical diagnostics. </p>

<p>The need for the application of signal detection-based approaches in diagnostics was pointed out decades ago, and is standard practice in current implementations of clinical diagnostic tests. Detection approaches are, by default, included in machine/statistical learning implementations for classification tasks, since the evaluation of classifier performance is basically a detection problem. Thus, the determination of the optimal cutoff (threshold) value at which signal can be discriminated from noise at an acceptable signal-to-noise ratio (i.e., maximum accuracy and sensitivity, lowest false discovery rate (FDR)) is equivalent to a classification problem, a direct corollary to diagnostic detection. </p>

<p>The natural spontaneous variation of DNA methylation in human populations complicates the discrimination of the methylation signal from background variation. We address this issue by determining whether a given DMP detected in the treatment/patient population occurs within the control population as well, and the probability of observing it. Therefore, the focus is not on the identification of DMPs, but on whether these statistically significant changes occur with high probability (under the fixed experimental conditions) in only the treatment group. Here we address this problem in the context of signal detection theory and ML frameworks. </p>

<p>To illustrate the feasibility of our proposed approach in clinical diagnostics, results from simulation studies and tests of two available methylome datasets from leukemia and autism patients are presented and discussed. This approach is implemented in the R package Methyl-IT, available at GitHub: <ref target="https://github.com/genomaths/MethylIT">https://github.com/genomaths/MethylIT</ref>. The R scripts to reproduce these analyses are available at the PSU GitLab: <ref target="https://git.psu.edu/genomath/MethylIT_examples">https://git.psu.edu/genomath/MethylIT_examples</ref>. </p>
</text>
