<text id="autogum_academic_doc020" title="The Role of Plasticity and Adaptation in the Incipient Speciation of a Fire Salamander Population" shortTile="role-plasticity-adaptation" author="Joana Sabino-Pinto, Daniel  J. Goedbloed, Eugenia Sanchez, Till Czypionka, Arne  W. Nolte, Sebastian Steinfartz" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4425/10/11/875/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Phenotypic plasticity and local adaptation are two major mechanisms of response to dynamic environmental conditions. These mechanisms appear under different population parameters and selection regimes. In changing environments, phenotypic plasticity allows organisms to conserve their genotypes and still produce alternative phenotypes, in contrast to local adaptations that incorporate changes at the genetic level producing long-lasting phenotypes and resulting in higher fitness in home habitats. In theory, locally adapted traits are established via strong natural selection—even under conditions of high gene flow between locally and non-locally adapted populations. In this situation, natural selection should also favour prezygotic isolation mechanisms to prevent mating between the populations, in doing so, this process can result in adaptive speciation (sensu Dieckman et al.), which has been demonstrated for various groups of organisms. </p>

<p>Traditionally, phenotypic plasticity has been considered a force counteracting speciation because it buffers the effect of natural selection on plastic traits. However, modern research demonstrates that—by reinforcing the survival of organisms under varying environmental conditions—phenotypic plasticity exposes other traits to natural selection that are related but not directly involved in a given plastic response (plastic acclimatization). This way, plastic acclimatization serves as a key initial step towards the evolutionary divergence of other traits and characters. Furthermore, some plastic responses are heritable, and if subject to selection can evolve via genetic adaptation (i.e., genetic accommodation). </p>

<p>Amphibians constitute particularly good models to study the role of plasticity in evolution. They offer numerous examples of plasticity, and are known for their variability with regards to behavior, morphology, physiology, and life history. The aquatic larvae of amphibians are of particular interest because many of the easily measurable morphological traits (such as size, weight, and gill length) are plastic and related to metamorphosis and fitness. A well-established natural system for evolutionary-ecological research is the European fire salamander (<hi rend="italic">Salamandra salamandra</hi>); larvae of this species are capable of living in a variety of environments (streams, ponds, and underground springs) by changing their behavior and growth rate to the environmental conditions. In Central Europe, <hi rend="italic">S. salamandra</hi> larvae typically develop in small primary streams until metamorphosis, but females of some populations are known to deposit their larva in ephemeral water bodies, such as small ponds or ditches, and sometimes even in underground springs. Both habitat types are ecologically different in many biotic and abiotic aspects, including water dynamics, temperature regime, food availability, and intraspecific competition; for instance, ponds tend to have lower oxygen content and higher temperatures than streams. One area where this kind of differential habitat use has been intensively studied is the range of the Ville forest in the West of Germany, with a special focus on the Kottenforst near Bonn. The Kottenforst represents a continuous old broad-leaf forest with streams and rain-filled bomb craters, in which adult salamanders can move freely and females deposit their larvae into small water bodies (streams or ponds), in which the latter develop until metamorphosis is completed. The adaptation to different larval habitat conditions has promoted the adaptive divergence of the ancestral local population into two genetically differentiated subpopulations, thus potentially representing a case of early stage ecological speciation.  </p>

<p>In order to better study acclimatization and adaptation, a <hi rend="italic">S. salamandra</hi> specific microarray chip was designed to estimate gene expression in different ecological contexts. A previous study integrating results from gene expression in Kottenforst larvae under common environmental conditions revealed that the differential gene expression observed is mainly driven by transcriptional plasticity rather than local adaptation. However, this was a laboratory-based study that focused on the effect of temperature and did not inform about the degree of plasticity in nature; it remains necessary to determine whether the patterns observed explain the variance observed in nature, or if other ecological parameters besides thermal adaptation drive the observed patterns.  </p>

<p>In this study, we performed a reciprocal transfer experiment of larvae between stream and pond habitats in the Kottenforst to estimate individual performance in the contrasting environments. Reciprocal transfer experiments—also known as transplant experiments—are experiments in which individuals are translocated from their native or original habitat to a new or ecologically different habitat, which allows the testing of heritability and fixation of traits in the natural environment. The aim of our transplant experiment was to test how far larvae can compensate for ecological differences between the two habitats. The performance of larvae was monitored using morphological variables and gene expression. Our results identify candidate genes underlying differential habitat adaptation in the fire salamander system, and illuminate their degree of plasticity and local adaptation. </p>
</text>
