<text id="autogum_academic_doc702" title="The Impact of Environmental Administrative Penalties on the Disclosure of Environmental Information" shortTile="impact-environmental" author="Xiangan Ding, Ying Qu, Mohsin Shahzad" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5820/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Environmental administrative penalties directly affect companies’ revenues by disrupting their production process, but they also generate negative externalities. Companies that are subject to environmental penalties are ultimately responsible for the punishment, and have to bear the related costs. As profit-seeking entities, most organizations would be expected to react by undertaking strategies to reduce the negative effects that may flow from unexpected penalties. </p>

<p>Previous research suggests that environmental disclosures in annual reports can be integrated as an environmental strategy or used as a self-serving tool to alleviate the crisis of legitimacy to gain legitimacy from stakeholders. Based on the theory of legitimacy, some researchers found that companies will increase environmental disclosures under the circumstances of being prosecuted by the Environmental Protection Agency, being subject to regulatory fines, or facing environmental crises or accidents. Managers can also rely on impression management strategies to obfuscate the company’s actual performance and pursue their interests. The researchers argued that if managers want to conceal negative aspects of the company, they will obfuscate negative outcomes by increasing reading difficulty in their annual reports or providing less complete information, and so on. Then, under the environmental administrative penalty, how might environmental information disclosure (EID) be affected? The extant literature does not provide an answer. Revealing the effect of the environmental administrative penalty on environmental disclosure is the key to understanding the disclosure strategy of penalized companies. </p>

<p>In China, the Ministry of Environmental Protection encourages listed companies to disclose environmental information. However, companies in heavily polluting industries are required to disclose some specific environmental information according to relevant policies. Hence, mandatory EID is only a disclosure requirement for heavily polluting industries. Environmental events such as environmental penalties may affect voluntary EID or mandatory EID, but few studies have incorporated the voluntary disclosure and mandatory disclosure together to addresses the effects of environmental penalties on EID. </p>

<p>Content analysis is a general method to measure EID, but the method does not take into account the characteristics of information quality in measuring the quality of environmental information disclosure. Among the quality characteristics of environmental information (relevance, reliability, comprehensibility, comparability, balance, and integrality), which aspects of characteristics are affected by the environmental penalty? The extant literature also does not provide an answer. </p>

<p>To fill these research gaps and help stakeholders understand the corporate EID under the environmental administrative penalty, the objective of the research is to reveal how environmental penalties affect the level and quality of EID. We seek to answer the question of how environmental penalties affect EID from the aspects of voluntary disclosure, mandatory disclosure, and quality characteristics of environmental information. We combine legitimacy theory with impression management theory to explain the environmental information disclosure of penalized companies, and try to examine the impact of environmental penalties on EID from two aspects of level and quality to find out which aspects of quality characteristics of environmental information have been affected by environmental penalties. </p>

<p>This structure of the article is as follows. The following section presents the theoretical background and hypotheses development, followed by research design and methods. The subsequent section presents the empirical results. The final section summarizes the main findings of the study with a discussion of its practical implications. </p>
</text>
