<text id="autogum_academic_doc470" title="Substantial Overview on Mesenchymal Stem Cell Biological and Physical Properties as an Opportunity in Translational Medicine" shortTile="substantial-overview" author="Heba Abdelrazik, Emanuele Giordano, Giovanni Barbanti Brodano, Cristiana Griffoni, Elena De Falco, Alessandra Pelagalli" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5386/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Challenges in MSC Translation into Clinical Practice: The Bone Disease Framework</head>
<p>
Other interesting aspects and new perspectives in the field of tissue regeneration and applicative use of MSC are strictly related to their potential to tackle the increase in bone diseases related with the extended life expectancy. Indeed, in many countries bone diseases are becoming a relevant cause of disability, even if they are acute, such as fractures, or chronic, such as osteoporosis and tumours. In any case these pathologies require treatments to enhance the healing and regenerative capacity of bone tissue. The common therapeutic strategies based on bone grafting (autografts or allografts) show some disadvantages. Autografts are limited by the bone volume that can be harvested from the iliac crest and present surgical risks such as bleeding, inflammation, infection, chronic pain, damage at the donor site and morbidity. Allografts also have some limitations, such as the lack of donors, high costs, the need for sterilization and the risk of infectious agent transmission or immune mediated tissue rejection. </p>

<p>These limitations and disadvantages associated with auto- and allograft approaches indicate a clinical need for alternative therapeutic strategies aimed at bone healing and regeneration. Thus, new biomaterials and scaffolds, in association with MSC and growth factors, having requirements of biocompatibility, osteoinductive and osteoconductive properties, are investigated to improve bone repair. The use of MSC is attractive since they can be harvested from the host with minimal morbidity, they can be modified to secrete osteoinductive factors and implanted on an osteoconductive scaffold, to obtain the three key components leading to osteogenesis. </p>

<p>hMSC have been found in several adult tissues, including the synovial membrane, the adipose tissue, the dental pulp tissue, or in perinatal tissues (umbilical cord blood and umbilical cord tissue). All these cells are suited to therapeutic applications for bone regeneration, by means of two different ways of autologous cells transplantation: (1) cell therapies without expansion in culture (one-step procedure) and (2) cell therapies with ex vivo expansion. In the first case, cells are harvested during surgery. In 2010, Jagër et al., successfully treated more than 100 patients with local bone healing disorders using a biomaterial composite in association with BM aspiration concentrate. They observed that the use of BM concentrate reduced the harvest of autogenous bone by 50% without negative effects on bone healing. The second clinical application of MSC includes the autologous cell transplantation after ex-vivo expansion. In 2007, Nöth et al., used a cell population from BM aspirate cultured over 12 days under GMP conditions and transplanted them autologously with a tricalcium phosphate biomaterial for the treatment of femoral head necrosis. The main limitations for clinical application are the sterility technique, long culture time, high cost, and the mixture of human cell culture medium with fetal bovine serum. Thus, recently, orthopedic researchers focused their attention on the clinical use of BM aspirate (BMA) and BM concentrate (BMC) for musculoskeletal regeneration with a “one-step” procedure, avoiding the need of additional laboratory stages and GMP facility, thus reducing costs and risks. </p>

<p>Bone marrow contains MSC, hematopoietic stem cells, endothelial progenitor cells, other progenitor cells and growth factors, including bone morphogenetic proteins (BMP), platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF), transforming growth factor-β (TGF-β), vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), interleukin-8 (IL-8), and IL-1 receptor antagonist. It has been identified as an excellent source of cells and growth factors and it has been used with success for bone, cartilage and soft tissue healing. </p>

<p>We focused our attention on the use of BM-derived MSC in spinal fusion surgical procedures, which is the most definitive treatment performed to restore the structural stability of the spinal column in degenerative and oncological spine diseases. Currently, the gold standard stimulus to achieve spinal fusion is autologous bone (autograft), which is commonly harvested from the iliac crest or obtained from the surgical site (local bone). As autologous bone possesses osteogenic, osteoinductive and osteoconductive abilities; the success rate of spinal fusion with autograft is high (up to 95%). However, autograft material is limited in quantity and its quality varies depending on the patient. Moreover, significant morbidity is associated with bone harvesting, as previously described. Between many alternatives proposed to achieve spinal fusion, MSC are interesting because they can provide osteogenic properties allowing bone regeneration. </p>

<p>We recently published a descriptive systematic literature review in order to understand if the use of MSC may represent a valid strategy to facilitate and accelerate bone regeneration and fusion during spine surgery. In this review we selected and analyzed 50 relevant papers, stratified according to preclinical studies and clinical trials. Preclinical published data showed that MSC have the potential to achieve, facilitate and accelerate spinal fusion. However, preclinical studies on animal models indicated that some barriers remain prior to this therapy translation into the clinical application. </p>

<p>So far, few published clinical studies employ stem cells for spinal fusion. Most of them used concentrated autologous BM as primary source of stem cells and they showed fusion results ranging from 87% to 92.3% in a total of 297 patients. </p>
</text>
