<text id="autogum_academic_doc386" title="Technology-Driven Transition in Urban Food Production Practices: A Case Study of Shanghai" shortTile="technologydriven" author="Mohsen Hosseinifarhangi, Margherita  E. Turvani, Arnold van der Valk, Gerrit  J. Carsjens" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6070/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion</head>
<p>
The objectives of this paper were to study the transition toward high-tech urban agriculture and its adoption in urban planning practices in Shanghai. A combination of multi-level perspective (MLP) and actor–network Theory (ANT) was used to identify institutional barriers and driving forces in this transition. The main findings are synthesized below. </p>

<head> 5.1. Empirical Findings </head>
<p>
The development of agricultural technology and the application in urban food production practices in Shanghai were led by the Chinese Academy of Agricultural Science (CAAS) and the Agricultural Science and Technology Innovation Program (ASTIP). The transition pathway in Shanghai was organized by the state government through top-down R&amp;D activities. Agricultural technologies were imported by CAAS from other countries, in particular the Netherlands. The state government allowed the involvement of foreign businesses in the transition through open-door policies, such as the establishment of the Special Economic Zone in Shanghai. The imported technologies were adopted by incumbent industries, such as lighting and home appliance manufacturers, and adapted to create new equipment and products for HTUA practices. These products and equipment were brought into national and international markets by Chinese agricultural technology firms. The niche developers in this transition pathway (i.e., SOCs) collaborated with agricultural technology firms to adopt agricultural technologies in new urban food production practices, such as the Sunqiao modern agriculture zone. To ensure that the interested actors became involved in the transition process and part of the actor network of transition, CAAS developed the key laboratories and demonstration zone for urban agriculture. The result of the collective actions of the actor-network of transition was the identification of plant factories as immutable mobiles; in other words, they were introduced as the promising solution for the challenges of the agricultural sector in China. To mobilize the actor network, the vegetable basket program was promoted by the local government, MoA, and CAAS to connect the urban food production and consumption practices. Additionally, spokespersons were appointed to represent the actor network of transition and to mobilize the involved actors. The director of CAAS as the main spokesperson had the responsibility of introducing plant factories and their positive contribution to the economy and society.  </p>

<p>The research shows that political and economic interests were the main driving forces behind the transition process in Shanghai. These findings are in line with Miller, who concluded that the rise of HTUA practices is a result of the adaptation of technologies by “dominant political and economic interests” for providing food security (p. 11). Hallock describes HTUA as a capitalist form of urban agriculture with the “ability to standardize the food cultivation process, and to incorporate it into factory like production systems” (p. 7). This clearly applies to Shanghai, where the top-down approach of CAAS and the involved SOCs was effective for the development of large-scale practices. Large-scale plant factories with a focus on high yields were supported and subsidized, driven by the central government’s aims of increasing the local production capacity and becoming less dependent on the import of agricultural products. Therefore, the HTUA have become oriented toward large-scale commercial vegetable production practices. CAAS also persuaded local planning organizations to remove any regulatory barriers. It shows that the government continues to play a dominant role in the development of urban agriculture in Shanghai. However, this dominant role also made it such that private enterprises involved in niche developments could not compete with the SOCs, and therefore, many of these private companies went bankrupt. This may have reduced the role of talented pioneers in the development of novelties. The focus on large-scale food production may also have resulted in the loss of its potential for improving urban lifestyles and integration into urban residents’ lives. </p>

<p>Furthermore, the results show that strategies for representing material entities (technologies) were crucial in the integration of agricultural technologies in urban practices. The representation of technologies by visualizations was an effective tool for making investors and the public interested in HTUA in Shanghai. The developers of the Sunqiao modern agriculture zone hired architectural companies to create visualizations of their projects. The architects created futuristic designs that were not based on in-depth knowledge of HTUA technologies. Although the visualizations were highly effective in attracting investors and public attention, they also raised concerns about the feasibility of HTUA practices among agricultural experts and decision-makers. Consequently, the decision-makers consulted agricultural experts to validate the feasibility of the proposed practices. These results show that visualizations can only play an effective role as an intermediary between niche developers and decision-makers if technology experts are involved in the design process. These findings are in line with Billger, Thuvander, and Wästberg who argue that visualization is an effective tool for communication among stakeholders in planning processes, but also involves a risk of “potential misuse, misinterpretation and misempowerment” (p. 12). To plan for technology-driven transitions, the identity of material entities (technologies) and their characteristics must be understood by planners. Bridges between knowledge institutes, architecture, and planning organizations are therefore essential for providing clear and representative visualizations.  </p>
</text>
