<text id="autogum_academic_doc559" title="Performance of a Simple Energetic-Converting Reaction Model Using Linear Irreversible Thermodynamics" shortTile="performance-simple" author="J. C. Chimal-Eguia, R. Paez-Hernandez, Delfino Ladino-Luna, Juan Manuel Velázquez-Arcos" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1099-4300/21/11/1030/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
A very interesting problem in non-equilibrium thermodynamics and in the theory of thermodynamics in general, is to determine the efficiency with which energy is exchanged. In fact, in many biological systems, the transfer of energy is of decisive importance. It is well known that all intracellular processes can be studied as chemical reactions of some kind, and that many of the biochemical reactions in living organisms have been seen to be catalyzed by enzymes; there are some good examples where the energetic properties studied are really relevant. </p>

<p>Considering the classical ideas of thermodynamics when one wants to analyze biological systems, it is typical to take the free energy of the biological system and convert it into work. For instance, to carry out a transport process or a chemical reaction, it is usual for this type of study to focus on analyzing the energetic properties of such systems. Note, however, that the subject is hard to study from the classical perspective of thermodynamics, since the temperature in many biological systems is homogeneous). </p>

<p>An additional step to analyze the energetic properties of a simple energy converter was given by Curzon and Ahlborn in 1975, who proposed a model which operates between two heat sources with high and low temperatures,  and , respectively. They found an expression for the efficiency at maximum power output given by  , a result that in principle is independent of the model parameters and only depends on the temperatures of the heat reservoirs; analogously this is what happens with the efficiency for a reversible Carnot cycle . </p>

<p>Considering the Curzon and Alhbor article, many authors began to introduce different objective functions, among others, such as the ecological function, the omega function, the efficient power function, etc. All of them trying to obtain efficiency and power values mainly for real power plants, but also heat pumps and refrigerators. </p>

<p>Moreover, it was reported that thermal engines show some universality regarding the behavior of the efficiency when it works at the maximum power regime, although the analyzed models are different in nature and scale. Recently, some thermal engines with kinetic and mesoscopic descriptions were published as examples of devices which convert non-thermal energy (mainly chemical energy) into useful work. The importance of these models is that the energy production processes seen in the molecular biological level obey similar principles as those observed in the classical thermal engines. </p>

<p>On the other hand, Kedem et al. published in 1965 the first step of a non-equilibrium theory towards a description of linear converters of energy (which would be called Linear Irreversible Thermodynamics, LIT). Since then, many authors have agreed in considering this theory as a basis for the analysis of non-equilibrium systems, (particularly, in biological systems remarkably close to the equilibrium). One of the relevant questions tackled by Kedem et al. at that time was to answer which was the maximal efficiency of the oxidative phosphorylation in an isolated mitochondrion. Kandem et al. obtained some qualitative predictions confirmed by experimental data. </p>

<p>For biological process, for instance, several authors have studied different optimal regimes like Prigogine with his minimum entropy production theorem. Odun and Pinkerton who analyzed the maximum power output regime for various biological systems, Stucki who introduced some optimal criteria to study the optimum oxidative phosphorylation regime, among others who have studied many biological energy conversion processes by means of the LIT where some optimum performance regimes have been analyzed. </p>

<p>In this context, we have decided to study the thermodynamical properties of an energetic converting biological process, using for this purpose a simple model for an enzymatic reaction that couples one exothermic and one endothermic reaction in the same fashion described by Diaz-Hernandez et al., but now using the Linear Irreversible Thermodynamics (LIT) for three different operating regimes,;namely, Maximum Power Output (MPO), Maximum Ecological Function (MEF) and Maximum Efficient Power Function (MEPF), respectively. </p>

<p>The paper is organized as follows: Section 2 introduces a model and the phenomenological flow equations of a remarkably simple system enzymatic reaction coupled with ATP hydrolysis. Section 3 presents the analysis of the optimal operation regimes in the context of the Linear Irreversible Thermodynamics. Finally, Section 4 gives some concluding remarks. </p>
</text>
