<text id="autogum_academic_doc397" title="An Efficient Representation Using Harmony Search for Solving the Virtual Machine Consolidation" shortTile="efficient-representation" author="MinJun Kim, JuneSeok Hong, Wooju Kim" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6030/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Proposed Grouping Harmony Search for Virtual Machine Consolidation</head>
<p>
This section described the detailed procedures of harmony search (HS) and grouping harmony search (GHS), one of the metaheuristic techniques used to solve VMC, and the contents of the operators designed to efficiently solve VMC problems. </p>

<head> 4.1. Overview of Harmony Search</head>
<p>
HS is an optimization algorithm that was created based on the observation that better chords are produced by repeated practice in improvisation of jazz. This refers to a series of processes that the most beautiful chords (global optimum) can be made through repetitive practice (iteration) when played by a variety of instruments. </p>

<p>In the case of GA, inspired by population genetics inspired by population genetics, generates new genes from two genes, but HS generates new solution from multiple solution, which has a high probability of searching for global optimal. Compared to SA and TS, which are typical single solution based metaheuristics, population based HS has a high global search capability. In the case of SA and TS, it is possible to drive a good quality through a mechanism that probabilistically adopts a bad solution. When HS generates a new solution, it adopts a quality solution within the population and searches for an optimal solution. </p>

<p>HS consists of three operators in total: memory considering, pitch adjusting, and random playing. Each operator determines the frequency of operation based on predefined parameter values. The pseudo code of HS is shown in Table 1. </p>

<p>HS generates one solution (HM, harmony memory) per iteration (line 5–17). New Harmony x’ is generated through memory considering, pitch adjusting, and random playing operators by increasing the index (line 6). The operator of HS generates the first random number (line 7) to determine whether to calculate the memory considering (line 8). If the first random number is smaller than the predefined harmony memory considering rate (HMCR), memory considering is executed. If the first random number is larger than HMCR, random playing is executed (line 13). Random playing is a method of adopting the value of one of the feasible solution groups. Memory considering adopts the value of one of several solutions of harmony memory size (HMS). When the solution is generated through memory considering, the operation for pitch adjusting is determined by generating a second random number. If the second random number is smaller than the predefined pitch adjusting rate (PAR), pitch adjusting is executed (line 10). Pitch adjusting means the neighboring value of the solution generated by memory considering. The target value is calculated once x’ is generated, and if it has a better value than the target value of the worst HM in the HMS, the solution is replaced with new harmony (line 16–17). HS repeats the above process until the end condition is met. </p>

<head> 4.2. Grouping Representation for Virtual Machine Consolidation</head>
<p>
Harmony search is population-based metaheuristics that generate new HMs by combining multiple HMs and has the advantage of having a high degree of diversification; however, as a result of controlling a large number of HMs, there is a disadvantage that computation times increase compared to single solution metaheuristics. As the size of the node grows, the HMS also needs to grow to increase the efficiency of searching for a solution, so the problem occurs when handling a large-scale problem. To solve this problem, we adopted grouping representation in this study for the efficient design of algorithms. </p>

<p>VMC belongs to grouping problems, and the ordering of objects within a group is meaningless. In other words, the combination of VMs located in the PM is important, not the order in the group. Since it also deals with virtualization environments, the number of PMs is basically smaller than the number of VMs. Since there are multiple VMs in one PM, if the problem size is adjusted, the increase in VM is higher than the increase in PM. If the solution is encoded in the permutation form of the VM, the length of the solution also increases as the number of VMs increases. This method is inefficient when searching for a solution as the solution space is increased with many duplicate solution representations. Therefore, PM-oriented representation is more efficient than VM-oriented solution representation. Falkenauer proposed a one-gene-for-one-group method for one solution grouping problem. With this in mind, this study represented PM and VM information based on groups as shown in <figure>Figure 3</figure>. The index of each array indicates the index of PM, and the value of each array indicates the index of VM located in the corresponding PM, which is controlled in the form of a list. </p>

<head> 4.3. Pitch Adjustments for Virtual Machine Consolidation</head>
<p>
HS consists of three operators—memory considering, pitch adjustment, and randomization. Among them, the operator that directly changes the new HM is pitch adjustment. VMC has to decide the source PM selection, VM selection, and destination PM selection as a problem of migrating VM located in one PM to another PM. The pitch adjustment operator changes the solution by determining the above three factors. The criteria for determining each problem are as follows. </p>
</text>
