<text id="autogum_academic_doc129" title="Exploring the Severity of Factors Influencing Sustainable Affordable Housing Choice: Evidence from Abuja, Nigeria" shortTile="exploring-severity" author="Ikenna  Stephen Ezennia, Sebnem  Onal Hoskara" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5792/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Housing is required to provide comfort, safety, satisfaction, experience, and convenience for its occupants. Hence, it is one of the essential social conditions which define the living standard of a country’s citizens. If the housing quality is adequate and available, the citizens and government will spend less on health care, crime prevention, recreation, and pollution; leading to increased productivity and prosperity. However, due to rapid rates of urbanization reported worldwide, housing supply has always failed to satisfy demand. Therefore, exploring the reasons why households pay or choose what they pay for housing, would help to sustain housing delivery, which can eliminate or reduce artificial restrictions and prevent housing abandonment. A clear understanding of the households’ choice will offer new insight towards addressing the challenges of housing shortages and poor distribution. According to Olanrewaju &amp; woon,, the most likely problem triggering the imbalance between the demand and supply of affordable housing, is the inability to reconcile households choice and supply.  </p>

<p>Several factors are responsible for the poor delivery of affordable housing, but studies have demonstrated that unsold properties and abandoned houses are due to choice. Households apply choice factors to define their housing demand. Housing choice is a topic of interest amongst researchers of diverse disciplines and has been studied from different theoretical perspectives. For instance, economists focus primarily on housing prices and how housing costs determine the choice between owning and renting. Sociologists and geographers study the housing choices individual households make and examining housing distribution in a given population. They focus on socioeconomic and demographic aspects, dwelling, and the neighborhood features that influence housing choice. </p>

<p>Demand for affordable housing has been essentially evaluated in financial terms, but affordable housing concerns have progressed beyond mere economic concepts, to wider issues of social wellbeing and sustainability. However, it is uncommon to address affordable housing demand concerns within the ambit of sustainability. Regarding this, Sirgy, et al. recommended that further studies on housing choice determinants should be improved by incorporating wide-ranging criteria like socio-psychological factors, amongst others. Several studies have examined housing choice from other perspectives, like uncertainties and lifestyles, but none has discussed housing choice within the sustainability framework. However, integrating sustainability into the concept of housing choice allows for the introduction of wide-ranging and broader variables such as environmental factors, which are routinely neglected in housing choice literature. For instance, ÆRØ explored why residents chose a particular dwelling type in Denmark by referring to lifestyle variables and personal tradition. Jansen found that lifestyle variables exact strong influence on housing choices of medium and high-income Dutch households. It is given that individual lifestyle variables influence their choice of housing, but this influence is little when compared with those of their socio-demographic characteristics. </p>

<p>In Nigeria, affordable housing choice has never been studied, nor investigated in academic literature. Therefore this study aims to fill this gap in housing choice literature by identifying within the framework of sustainability the determinants of sustainable affordable housing choice in Abuja, Nigeria. The study investigates sustainable affordable housing from the perspective of housing choice and identifies a set of factors that strongly influence it. The purpose is to establish the severity of the identified factors and rank them based on the respondent’s opinion. This study is concerned with the change of residence in a national context and the process through which urban residents find and choose a particular dwelling to live-in in an urban setting. The research objectives are (1) To discuss the relationship between the identified factors. (2) To study the agreement levels in the opinions of the three respondent groups, that is; To determine if the general opinion of the three groups agrees with the opinion of each group. Specifically, if there is an agreement between affordable housing applicants’ opinionand the overall opinion of all the parties. If also there is an agreement between affordable housing estate residents’ opinion and the overall opinion of all the groups, and if there is an agreement between the opinion of residents of shanty towns’ and the overall opinion of all the groups? (4) Lastly, to develop a framework for achieving SAHC in the study area.  </p>

<p>Based on the main research question, what are the factors that determine urban residents’ choice of affordable housing? From this, the following two sub-questions emerge: (1) What is the extent of the relationship and interplay between the identified factors? (2) Is there an agreement between affordable housing applicants’ opinion and the overall opinion of all the groups, affordable housing estate residents’ opinion, and overall opinion of all the groups and residents of shanty towns’ opinion and the overall opinion of all the groups? This research is guided by the postulation that Null Hypothesis (Ho): There is no agreement between the opinions of the three respondent groups. </p>
</text>
