<text id="autogum_academic_doc660" title="Past, Present, and Future of Groundwater Remediation Research: A Scientometric Analysis" shortTile="past-present-future" author="Qibin Chen, Guilian Fan, Wei Na, Jiming Liu, Jianguo Cui, Hongyan Li" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/20/3975/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Data Acquisition and Methods</head><head> 2.1. Data Acquisition</head>
<p>
It is essential for researchers to quickly and accurately locate publications, using the search strategy and screen methods. The article retrieval source for analysis was the SCI-E databases, which are frequently used in scientific research. Several topic terms, including “groundwater restoration”, “groundwater reclamation”, and “groundwater remediation”, were used to retrieve publications that contained these words in publications’ titles, keyword lists, and abstracts. These terms helped to locate the majority of groundwater-remediation-related publications. Though there may be other groundwater-remediation-related terminology, they account for a small percentage of publications and may have marginal relation to groundwater remediation research. The search results have been refined or filtered by web of science categories, research areas, and document types. To do this, several categories needed to be excluded, such as (i) unrelated categories—physiology, pharmacology pharmacy, genetics heredity—(ii) document types—book chapter, data paper, proceedings abstract—and (iii) research areas—imaging science photographic technology, business economics. The search resulted in 2867 publications dated from January 1950 to September 2018. The entire records, including the titles, abstracts, keywords, and references, were then exported for subsequent analyses. Based on the frequency of groundwater remediation research over the past seven decades, we reviewed numerous studies published between 1950 and 2018 (see the Supplementary Materials). </p>

<head> 2.2. Scientometric Analytical Methods</head>
<p>
Scientometrics, created by Tibor Braun, has been defined as the “quantitative study of science and technology”. As a branch of informatics, scientometrics is used to analyze patterns in scientific literature quantitatively, to understand the knowledge structure of emerging trends in a research field. As a scientometric approach, CiteSpace is used to clarify multidisciplinary relationships, assess research status, map knowledge domains, reveal research frontiers, and predict emerging trends, by analyzing the bibliographic records of associated publications. In the net knowledge maps generated by CiteSpace, a node represents one item (e.g., country, author, subject, term, journal, or reference), and links describe co-citations or co-occurrences between these nodes. Furthermore, each node is described as a series of tree rings of different colours, with blue representing the oldest and orange the most recent. A purple ring around an item indicates good centrality. </p>

<p>To date, CiteSpace has been employed in studies of, for example, nonpoint source pollution, information sciences, psychological science, and global green innovation. In this study, we produced and analyzed co-occurrence networks of subject categories and countries, and co-citation networks of journals, authors, and references using CiteSpace. </p>
</text>
