<text id="autogum_academic_doc616" title="Knowledge and Expectations on Antibiotic Use among Older Adults in Malaysia: A Cross-Sectional Survey" shortTile="knowledge-expectations" author="Lai  San Kong, Farida Islahudin, Leelavathi Muthupalaniappen, Wei  Wen Chong" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2308-3417/4/4/61/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The devastating threat of antimicrobial resistance (AMR) to global human health is unquestionable. Antimicrobials are losing their effectiveness in treating infections, due to the rapid emergence of AMR and the drying up of antimicrobial pipelines. The difficult-to-treat AMR infections require longer hospital stays and more costly treatment, increase morbidity and mortality, and reduce productivity; therefore, increasing the economic burden of the countries. In recent years, this global health crisis has been gaining much attention in Malaysia, and Malaysia has been striving hard to combat it via different approaches. The major contributing factors of AMR are known to be overuse and misuse of antimicrobials. </p>

<p>Antibiotic consumption by the elderly population was found to be between 11% to 45%, with a significant rise over the past decade. As much as 18% of the total antibiotic prescriptions in older adults was unnecessary, with 54% of them prescribed for acute respiratory conditions. Healthcare providers face challenges in adequately diagnosing and managing infections in this vulnerable population because of the altered drug metabolism in this particular group, the common occurrence of drug–drug interactions due to polypharmacy and lower medication adherence. Nursing homes or long term care facilities in the United States and Australia were found to be a reservoir for AMR pathogens due to excessive, inappropriate and prolonged broad-spectrum antimicrobial use, inadequate infection control and increased risk of pathogen colonization. The prevalence of antimicrobial consumption in nursing homes was reported to be 11% in the United States, where only 66% of it was documented for therapeutic use. </p>

<p>The reported incidence of infections was higher in the older adult population because of the presence of chronic comorbidities, deteriorating organ functions and reduced host defence system. Older adults also have poorer outcomes as a consequence of infections, including higher mortality, compared to adults of other age groups. Atypical clinical presentations of infections, undertreatment or overtreatment, high risk of multidrug-resistant organism acquisition, rapid disease progression and prolonged recovery all contribute to poorer outcomes in the elderly. Moreover, older adults who were living alone have lower health literacy and hence lower self-management abilities, contributing to poorer health. </p>

<p>A lack of knowledge on antibiotic use in the general public has been reported, with more than half of them who thought that antibiotics are useful in treating viral infections, and about one half of them would stop taking antibiotics when they felt better. Those who were aware of antibiotic resistance were unaware that misuse of antibiotics could lead to this global crisis. Those who had poor knowledge of antibiotic use were associated with a higher probability of antibiotic self-medication and practices of using leftover antibiotics, sharing antibiotics, keeping antibiotics for future use and stopping antibiotics when symptoms disappear. Inappropriate practices related to antibiotics, including self-medication, were reported to be common among older adults. In one study, a considerable proportion of older adults (77.8%) who had antibiotic use within the past six months were found to have experience of receiving antibiotics without prescriptions. However, only a few studies reported the lack of knowledge and poor attitude on antibiotic use and resistance among older adults. </p>

<p>Patients who were unaware of the consequences of antibiotic overuse to the community were found to expect antibiotics from their prescriber. Studies have found that those who incorrectly believed that antibiotics will work for viral infections were more likely to expect antibiotics from prescribers. Patients’ expectations of antibiotics are found to be an important predictor of antibiotic prescribing. Expectations for antibiotics for common cold were found among older adults when they felt sick enough to visit a physician, although most of them disagreed that antibiotics could speed the recovery.  </p>

<p>To our knowledge, many studies have been done to assess the knowledge of antibiotic use and resistance; however, there has been limited research targeting vulnerable population groups, including older adults. Due to the paucity of information in this area, we conducted a study among the older adult population in Malaysia to assess their knowledge on antibiotic use and resistance and their expectations towards the need for antibiotics. This study also aimed to assess the relationship between knowledge, expectations and practices related to antibiotic use among older adults. </p>
</text>
