<text id="autogum_academic_doc505" title="Genomic-Destabilization-Associated Mutagenesis and Clonal Evolution of Cells with Mutations in Tumor-Suppressor Genes" shortTile="genomicdestabilizationassociated" author="Ken-ichi Yoshioka, Yusuke Matsuno, Mai Hyodo, Haruka Fujimori" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6694/11/11/1643/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Mutations Induced along with Genomic Destabilization</head><head> 2.1. Mutation Rate and Its Association with Cancer Risk</head>
<p>
In normal human cells, DNA is usually replicated by high-fidelity polymerases δ and ε. Errors caused by those polymerases are primarily repaired by their proofreading system (Table 1), and the remaining errors are targeted by the mismatch repair (MMR) system.  </p>

<p>Consequently, mutation is largely suppressed during normal replication. Deficiencies in MMR and proofreading performed by polymerase ε are associated with hypermutation and cancer predisposition; thus, the mutation rate is strongly associated with cancer risk. However, this association between mutation rate and cancer risk may be unrelated to cell division frequency and resultant changes in cell number, as aptly pointed out by Peto’s paradox: cancer incidence does not appear to correlate with the number of cells in an organism at the species level. </p>

<p>Mutations in cancer cells are not induced randomly. Based on whole-genome and exome analyses, chromatin loci with higher mutation levels can be characterized as (I) gene loci that are not highly expressed, (II) chromosome regions replicating in late S phase, (III) heterochromatic loci, and (IV) loci with closed chromatin that is not sensitive to DNase I. Mutation rates differ by severalfold between high- and low-mutation loci. Although the source of these differences remains unclear, the phenomenon might be associated with genomic instability, as heterochromatic loci are often subjected to replication stress and chromosomal rearrangements. Consistent with this, a recent study reported that hypermutation is associated with genomic destabilization. </p>

<head> 2.2. Mutation Induction when Replication-Stress-Associated DSBs Accumulate</head>
<p>
Among the many mutations induced in cancer cells, somatically-induced replicative mutations are the most prominent. Based on a recent study, such replicative mutations can be separated into two types: those induced as random errors during canonical replication, and those induced in association with replication-stress-associated DSBs that accumulate in association with genomic destabilization. Unexpectedly, the former type is relatively rare even in MMR-deficient cells that cannot correct errors during replication. By contrast, in the latter, hypermutation occurs in association with DSBs and genomic destabilization in barely replicating cells (<figure>Figure 1</figure>). </p>

<p>Importantly, cancer-driver mutations arise during the latter; the induced mutations include base substitutions, small insertions and deletions, and large deletions of entire genes (<figure>Figure 1</figure>). The mechanisms responsible for mutations in this context are not clear, probably because of the presence of repair systems and other related polymerases (Table 1). Indeed, these DSBs are generally a target of homologous recombination (HR), which does not involve high-fidelity polymerases (pols) δ and ε. Instead, low-fidelity translesion synthesis (TLS) polymerases δ, κ, and θ, which synthesize DNA over lesioned templates, are highly expressed. Thus, the higher mutation rates are probably due to DNA synthesis performed by these polymerases, which lack proofreading activity, and the errors probably occur during translesion synthesis. Thus, while mutations are strongly suppressed during normal cell division, they increase after replication-stress-associated DSB accumulation and genomic destabilization. Given that most cancers ultimately develop genomic instability, these mutations are most likely the ones that contribute to cancer progression. </p>

<head> 2.3. Senescence-Associated Increase in the Risk of Genomic Destabilization</head>
<p>
Most cancer cells develop one of two forms of genomic instability: chromosomal instability (CIN) or microsatellite instability (MSI). CIN is the most frequent, but MSI usually arises in MMR-deficient cancers (Table 1). The induction of both CIN and MSI is triggered by replication-stress-associated DSBs (<figure>Figure 2</figure>).  </p>

<p>CIN often occurs when such DSBs are not effectively repaired by HR, that is, when DSBs arising during replication are carried over into the following G1 phase at a time when HR is not functional. Consequently, the DSBs are often erroneously ligated by non-homologous end joining (NHEJ) with topologically incorrect broken ends, resulting in a background that causes CIN-associated chromosomal alterations such as chromosomal translocations, deletions, and rearrangements. By contrast, MSI arises when those DSBs are effectively but erroneously repaired by microhomology-mediated end joining (MMEJ; also known as alternative end joining) (<figure>Figure 3</figure>), during which CIN is suppressed because of the resultant DSB repair (<figure>Figure 2</figure>). Thus, both CIN and MSI are triggered by replication-stress-associated DSBs and arise due to abnormalities in the repair of these lesions. </p>

<p>Most cancers develop genomic instability due to abnormalities in DSB repair; paradoxically, however, most lack background mutations in DNA repair systems. This raises the question of how genomic destabilization occurs even in normal cells, that is, genetically normal cells with functional DNA repair systems. This phenomenon is probably associated with age, which is associated with an elevated cancer risk. Indeed, irreparable DSBs accumulate widely in association with age in vivo and passage in vitro. Consistent with this, cells often undergo senescence as a consequence of DSB accumulation. Although the reasons for DSB accumulation are not clear, they are likely to include a reduction in histone H2AX, which mediates repair-factor recruitment and is required for genome stability.  </p>
</text>
