<text id="autogum_academic_doc456" title="Classification of WHO Essential Oral Medicines for Children Applying a Provisional Pediatric Biopharmaceutics Classification System" shortTile="classification-essential" author="Jose-Manuel delMoral-Sanchez, Isabel Gonzalez-Alvarez, Marta Gonzalez-Alvarez, Andres Navarro, Marival Bermejo" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4923/11/11/567/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The objective of this paper was using the Essential Medicines List for children by the World Health Organization (WHO) to create a provisional pediatric biopharmaceutics classification system (pBCS) for oral drugs and to compare our results with the BCS for adults (aBCS). </p>

<p>Since 2007, the WHO has provided the WHO Model List of Essential Medicines for Children; a core drug list for a basic health-care system. This resource list considers the safest, efficacious and cost-effective drugs for priority pathologies in pediatrics up to 12 years old. All immediate release oral drugs from the sixth edition of this list were selected for this work. </p>

<p>The need for and importance of developing appropriate, safe and effective medicines for pediatrics have now been recognized. Pediatrics have long been considered as a therapeutically disregarded group. This fact lies in the therapeutic gap that originates from formulation development (mainly focused on adults), low availability of commercial pediatric drugs for pediatric use and physiological and anatomical differences relative to the adult population. </p>

<p>In younger pediatrics, neonates and infants, the therapeutic-risk benefits associated with drug treatment may be different from those in adults. Developmental physiological differences (as the composition of gastrointestinal fluids and the presence or activity of intestinal drug metabolizing enzymes and efflux transporters) can markedly alter the bioavailability of drugs. Age-related changes in the characteristics of luminal fluids such as pH may lead to changes in drug solubility and, therefore, in absorption since only the dissolved drug would be available for absorption. Since fluctuations in pH may influence ionizable drugs and the relative amount of unionized available drug, there could be changes in absorption during maturation. The gastric pH of the newborn is approximately neutral, and within the first 48 h of life, the gastrointestinal pH decreases to adult values and then for the first month increases back to values close to neutrality. After the first month, gastric pH decreases progressively to reach similar values as in adults by two years of age. </p>

<p>On the other hand, another determinant of bioavailability is ontogenic changes in the expression of drug metabolizing enzymes and transporters, which would mark the first pass effect and consequently would change the oral absorbed fraction. For example, the CYP3A4 isoenzyme increases expression and activity with age. CYP3A4 is practically undetectable in neonates, and its expression increases with age, reaching a maximum level at two years of age. Likewise, in these age groups, there is immature intestinal activity of alkaline phosphatase, glucuronidation enzymes and carboxylesterase-2. Conversely, there are no differences in p-glycoprotein expression, the most studied intestinal efflux transporter from the earliest stages of life to adults. </p>

<p>Many drugs are formulated as pharmaceutical forms that are often not appropriate for pediatrics, such as tablets or capsules. Children need different oral dosage formulations from adults mainly due to their developmental capabilities in swallowing ability, palatability and dosage requirements. Especially in pediatrics, palatability is closely related to acceptance and adherence. Consequently, bitterness, trigeminal irritation and perceptible malodors must be minimized. </p>

<p>The increasing need for age-related medicines in pediatrics could be met by extemporaneous formulations. The compounding of an extemporaneous formula is not allowed if an authorized commercial pharmaceutical product (adequate for a particular age group) exists, but the reality in the clinical setting is that for some age groups, that is not the case, while extemporaneous formulation is still used as the only alternative to the therapeutic need. Although solid products have higher stability than liquid formulations, this practice can solve the problem of swallowing capability and dose adjustments, but these manufactured preparations can be a risk to safety, efficacy and quality, because there is little or no information for compatibility between the original medicine and additional excipients or their effect in children. The excipients used in formulations designed for children should be appropriate for each age group because, as is known, these are not inert substances and cannot be supposed to have the same effects in pediatrics as in adults. The most common example is early stage children who are not able to metabolize or eliminate them as adults. The ideal situation in the development of pediatric formulations is the minimal use of added excipients, both in number and quantity. </p>
</text>
