<text id="autogum_academic_doc404" title="How to Improve Water Resources Allocation Efficiency: A Two-Stage Performance-Based Allocation Mechanism" shortTile="improve-water-resources" author="Hui Zhang, Qiyu Ren, Jiaying Li" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6021/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion and Conclusion </head><head> 4.1. Discussion</head>
<p>
There are three main extensions for future investigation. </p>

<p>First, we can naturally extend this fixed amount of water resources to a variable. In other words, the overall disposable water resources could be more or less in the following step. In case of more disposable water resources, if the hydropower is included, water quantity and water quality will not be reduced. If hydropower is considered, the two water users will also need to consider the secondary distribution of water resources, which makes for another incentive mechanism from the water user j’s point of view. The participants need to balance between making the cake bigger and getting a larger slice of it in the future at the same time, as illustrated by Huck et al.. Under this situation, the three participating parties have a common goal at first, that is, getting more disposable water resources. Then, all the parties try to maximize their own interests. In case of less disposable water resources, due to extreme drought weather, like what happened in Meikong River Basins in 2011, the overall supply water will be less than normal year. Under this situation, the governor will need another incentive mechanism or an emergency mechanism, which will be another interesting research direction. </p>

<p>The second extension is the multi-principal and multi-agent model, including many governors and many water users, existing in transboundary river basins, such as Lancang River, Nu River, Yalu River. There are also competitions between governors whose aims may not be the same. The conflicts of water users involve various agricultural users and industrial users, which will be another complicated model. As this paper only presents a one-principal and two-agent model, we can naturally extend this model to multi-principal or multi-agent (more than two agents). In fact, in addition to the water user j’s allocation, the players could get water resources from various channels, such as water reuse, buying from other players, and so on.  </p>

<p>There are also uncertainties of the water allocation process, such as flood or extreme droughts, which affect water allocation substantially. Risk management mechanisms need to address this issue. In fact, the uncertainty of all participants’ behaviors is based on the definition of risk of the water allocation process. It is worth research in the future. </p>

<p>What is left for future research also includes the distribution plan and incentive mechanism under these conditions, and the fact that these water users may have private information, risk-preference, or risk-aversion, which would be left for future research. </p>

<head> 4.2. Conclusions </head>
<p>
The current paper, based on cross-subsidy mechanism, explores the issue of efficient water resources allocation management between the governor and two competing water users under the AS. The two-stage performance-based allocation mechanism presented in the paper has four novel aspects. First, from the governor’s perspective, we focus on allocation rules covering two stages, including production and environment aspects, which is consistent with sustainability. Even though this two-stage allocation is just a small part of the long-term allocation cycle, it could reflect the real allocation process and reflect the requirement of water resources sustainability under the current social–environmental–economic development. Second, the performance-based incentive mechanism will induce competition between the two users based on the penalty–incentive system to motivate them to act in accordance with the governor’s goals. Users’ payoff depends on their own performances and their relative performances, covering production and environment aspects. Therefore, this mechanism involves not only the interactions between the government and users, but the interactions between two users, which could help the governor balance the economic and environment developments, and balance the short-term development and long-term development. This paper also covers the internalization of the external costs, another innovative aspect in this paper. The internalization of the external costs could help the governor transfer the costs to the users, which could further motivate the two users to act according to the governor’s interests rather than their own interests. At last, these perspectives could also provide a new insight for agricultural water resources allocation management and relative decision support for the governor, such as the sustainable development of water resources, the interactions between the governor and users, competition between users, penalty–reward mechanism, multi-stage multi-agent and multi-objective decision-making, and so on.
 </p>
</text>
