<text id="autogum_academic_doc022" title="Neutral Sphingomyelinase Modulation in the Protective/Preventive Role of rMnSOD from Radiation-Induced Damage in the Brain" shortTile="neutral-sphingomyelinase" author="Samuela Cataldi, Antonella Borrelli, Maria  Rachele Ceccarini, Irina Nakashidze, Michela Codini, Oleg Belov, Alexander Ivanov, Eugene Krasavin, Ivana Ferri, Carmela Conte, Federica  Filomena Patria, Giovanna Traina, Tommaso Beccari, Aldo Mancini, Francesco Curcio, Francesco  Saverio Ambesi-Impiombato, Elisabetta Albi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5431/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Discussion</head>
<p>
The aim of this study was to elucidate the rMnSOD-dependent nSMase changes and their role in the protective-preventive effect from ionizing radiation in the brain. Mice were exposed to a set of minor γ radiation and neutrons and a spectrum of neutrons, simulating the radiation levels to which cosmonauts will be exposed during deep-space, long-term missions. At the moment we do not know whether γ radiation only was unable to induce nSMase activation. We show that rMnSOD particles are capable to cross the blood-brain barrier and localize in the midbrain. Here, rMnSOD has the ability to limit radiation-induced damage, such as the loss of neuron number and the alteration of neurofilaments. The effect of radiation on brain damage has previously been reported by other authors. Although many studies elucidated the radioprotective role of rMnSOD through antioxidant mechanisms in mitochondria, no data exist about its effect on nSMase. We show that rMnSOD stimulates nSMase gene and protein expression and enzymatic activity. The study was articulated with the aim of analyzing the response of nSMase in samples in which rMnSOD has a protective effect (non-pretreated samples) and in samples in which rMnSOD has a preventive effect (pretreated samples). In samples for protective effect study, rMnSOD increases strongly nSMase gene and protein expression in irradiated samples in a dose-dependent manner. Small variations of nSMase enzyme activities are obtained only with high radiation doses. This observation is relevant, as nSMase plays a crucial role in the regulation of ROS generation and in the maintenance of homeostasis between proapoptotic and prosurvival signals. In line with this, we show that highest radiation levels induce significant nSMase responses only in the presence of rMnSOD. Although the present results indicate that nSMase may be required for the action of rMnSOD, we cannot prove the direct action of rMnSOD on this enzyme. To our knowledge, this is the first study indicating SMase as a potential effector of rMnSOD during its protection action. In samples for preventive effect study, nSMase gene and protein expression is reduced in comparison with the samples in which the protective effect of rMnSOD is studied but the enzyme activity is much higher. At this moment we can only speculate why nSMase levels are reduced with pretreatment, a possible explanation being that an extended treatment time could stimulate different metabolic patterns, leading to inhibition of nSMase gene expression. Merging already published data with our findings, it is possible to suggest that in brain tissues exposed to radiation, significant amounts of ROS are generated, stimulating nSMase production to significantly increase MnSOD levels. This may in turn stimulate nSMase. At this point, ROS levels may be reduced, with the end result of limiting the damage. In the above described series of events, nSMase may play predominant roles. </p>
</text>
