<text id="autogum_academic_doc500" title="Variation in Dysphagia Assessment and Management in Acute Stroke: An Interview Study" shortTile="variation-dysphagia" author="Sabrina  A. Eltringham, Craig  J. Smith, Sue Pownall, Karen Sage, Ben Bray" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2308-3417/4/4/60/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Stroke-associated pneumonia (SAP) is defined as a spectrum of lower respiratory infections within the first 7 days of stroke onset. It is one of the most frequent post-stroke infections affecting 14% of patients and is associated with a three-fold increase in hospital mortality, prolonged hospital stay and poor functional outcomes. The pathophysiology of SAP is multifactorial. Stroke induced immunosuppression, aspiration of oropharyngeal secretions and stomach contents, related to impaired consciousness and dysphagia increase vulnerability to SAP in the acute phase. </p>

<p>Dysphagia occurs in 37–78% of stroke patients and increases risk of pneumonia 11-fold in patients with confirmed aspiration. In the United Kingdom (UK), national guidelines recommend people with acute stroke have their swallow screened within 4 h of hospital admission by a specifically trained healthcare professional and, if dysphagia is suspected, the person should have a specialist swallow assessment by a speech and language therapist (SLT) within 72 h of admission (Supplementary Table S1: Summary of Royal College of Physicians (RCP) Clinical Guideline for Stroke). There is increasing evidence that early dysphagia screening is associated with reduced odds of SAP and that delays in SLT assessment increase pneumonia incidence by 1% per day of delay. </p>

<p>The type of dysphagia screening protocol (DSP) used varies widely and there is limited information about the components of the specialist swallow assessment. Screening protocols can vary from informal screens to validated protocols that assess with water only and stepwise screens that provide separate evaluations for non-fluids and fluids. The RCP Clinical Guideline for Stroke state that there is good evidence that a multi-item DSP that includes at least a water test of 10 teaspoons and a lingual motor test is more accurate than screening protocols with a single item, but do not recommend a standardised screen. Typically, a swallow assessment by a SLT comprises a cranial nerve examination, trials of different fluids and diet textures and compensatory strategies. Those suspected of risk of aspiration should be assessed for instrumental examination using techniques such as videofluoroscopic swallowing examination (VFSE) or fibreoptic endoscopic evaluation of swallowing (FEES). These assessments provide direct imaging for assessment of the swallowing physiology and help to predict outcomes and treatment planning. </p>

<p>A range of medical interventions and clinical processes may also be associated with the risk of SAP in patients with dysphagia. There is emerging evidence for the use of preventative measures such as screening for stroke-induced immunosuppression and dysphagia, for identifying patients at high risk for SAP. Further studies are needed to test this and screening for oral aerobic Gram-negative bacteria as well as the need to evaluate if treatment with proton pump inhibitors and nasogastric tubes (NGT) are associated with SAP in patients with dysphagia. </p>

<p>This study forms part of an over-arching series of studies aiming to explore whether variation in assessment and management of dysphagia in acute stroke affects the development of SAP. Interviews with staff responsible for dysphagia screening, assessment and or clinical management of stroke patients were undertaken as part of a mixed methods research design to inform the development of a national survey of hospitals registered in the Sentinel Stroke National Audit Programme (SSNAP) database. Statistical analysis of the survey responses with the database will highlight barriers and facilitators for reducing SAP. The aim of the interview study was to explore beyond the 4-h and 72-h audit criteria for screening and assessing patients for dysphagia to give a more rounded picture of care beyond the SSNAP performance indicators. </p>
</text>
