<text id="autogum_academic_doc126" title="Towards Systems-Oriented Energy Solutions: A Multilevel Analysis of a Low-Income Energy Efficiency Program in Brazil" shortTile="towards-systemsoriented" author="Jairo  da Costa Junior, Jan  Carel Diehl, Fernando Secomandi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5799/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Discussion of Findings from the Multilevel Analysis</head><head> 6.1. Towards Systems-Oriented Energy Solutions</head>
<p>
Drawing on a multilevel perspective, this paper analyzes Brazilian electricity distribution by focusing on energy solutions for low-income households. The insights from this analysis have been synthesized in a multilevel analysis at three aggregation levels: macro level, which described the relevant energy policies, regulatory frameworks, and the intended societal transformation required to achieve the national energy goals; meso level, which focused on product–service arrangements, stakeholders’ relationships, infrastructural development, and organizational changes taking place in the electricity distributions sector; and micro level, which looked at product technology intervention and behavioral change at household level. The study identified several aspects that contribute to the hindering of energy solutions that could increase the ability of low-income energy efficiency programs to reduce environmental impacts and increase the socioeconomic benefits of electricity distribution in low-income contexts. Results show that adopting a multilevel perspective allows new insights and identification of relevant constraints and opportunities across different system levels. </p>

<p>Notably, because there is high top-down interaction between levels, elements at the micro level have difficulty breaking out from the lower level and making contributions at higher levels. It is clear that the adoption of regulatory and economic tools is a success determinant for problem-solvers tackling energy challenges in low-income energy markets. In contrast, there is a missed opportunity for the collection of insights from emerging energy solutions and DSM business models for low-income contexts to support policymakers in future national energy planning. The study shows that promoting the long-term transition to sustainable energy systems in low-income energy markets does not only involve the adoption of energy policies and regulatory frameworks, but also depends largely on changes to infrastructure, stakeholders’ networks, technology, user practices, and culture. Therefore, policymakers and problem-solvers have to work towards increasing the alignment between components at lower and higher system levels, in other words to create new opportunities for the improvement of energy solutions for low-income households in Brazil. </p>

<head> 6.2. Recommendations for the Improvement of PEE Energy Solutions</head>
<p>
The study has highlighted that in the PEE’s low-income category, mostly incremental improvements can be achieved with current project guidelines for energy solutions. Although the activities in PEE projects are not limited to demand-side management (DSM), the focus group discussion revealed that energy utilities are reluctant to approve new projects that differ from more established methodologies. PEE programs have rigid methodologies for their implementation, and opportunities for developing solutions capable to produce radical improvements in energy systems are limited to the typology “pilot project”. In contrast, projects in the “low-income” typology face many challenges to develop and implement solutions that go beyond incremental improvements. </p>

<p>It is worth noting that projects need to be contracted through public calls that must respect specific laws and procedures regarding the bidding for products and services. Therefore, new products and services that do not follow previously established methodologies, although they may be implemented as a pilot project, need to be evaluated and approved by ANEEL. Moreover, it is time-consuming and bureaucratic for energy utilities to purchase products and services that can only be designed by one specific company (e.g., due to exclusive rights over certain technologies or methodologies), which can discourage energy service companies (ESCOs) from participating in such programs through energy performance contracts. </p>

<p>Another major barrier, which affects the promotion of radical improvements, was the need to develop context-specific measurement and verification tools. The adoption of alternative measurement and verification tools and metrics could be an option to increase the feasibility and viability of new projects that aim to create radical improvements in low-income energy markets. The measurement and verification methodology adopted in the PEE programs is the International Protocol for Measurement and Verification of Performance by Efficiency Validation Organization (EVO). Energy utilities are required to comply with targets and protocols that reinforce the assessment of impact by predominately quantitative performance measures. For instance, the impact of energy efficiency programs is primarily assessed based on the expected cost–benefit relationship (CBR). Therefore, outcomes that cannot be objectively measured and quantified, but which are relevant to low-income markets, such as increased wellbeing, long-term effects, and indirect effects of behavioral change, are often overlooked. In particular, for the low-income category, PEE could use a mixture of measurement and verification methodologies that consider the social and technical analysis of the low-income context prior to and post implementation of the energy program. </p>
</text>
