<text id="autogum_academic_doc435" title="Dynamic Duty-Cycle MAC Protocol for IoT Environments and Wireless Sensor Networks" shortTile="dynamic-dutycycle" author="Gayoung Kim, Jin-Gu Kang, Minjoong Rim" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4069/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Recently, due to the rapid increase in sensor devices, a large amount of reliable data transmission has required the use of limited energy. Thus, it is urgent to develop a protocol that efficiently processes data with a high amount of devices and energy in the Internet of Things (IoT) environment. IoT devices are mostly occupied by sensor networks that require minimum energy consumption and low transfer delay. These devices should be able to transmit data as efficiently as possible. In wireless sensor networks (WSNs), heavy traffic occurs, or data rapidly change, for a short period, and it is also frequently lost. Therefore, research efforts to reduce transmission delay by minimizing energy consumption for devices in WSNs or IoT environments. Typical techniques used in the research are duty-cycling. </p>

<p>Duty-cycling technology supports periodic switching to listen and sleep modes to reduce energy consumption when events occur for IoT devices. Listen mode consumes less power than other protocols that consume power for communication but do not consume energy in sleep mode. In a WSN, the duty-cycle MAC protocol is divided into a sleep interval and a listening interval, which can monitor and collect data with less energy when events occur. It is possible to detect events and collect data in various environments by sending information on electricity, water, or gas to users. Reliable data collection and detection is crucial for data transmission with minimum energy and delay because data must be transmitted without delay in the event of fire in areas where it is difficult to replace batteries. </p>

<p>However, the periodic switching mode changes to the listen mode for communication even when there is no event. This results in an unnecessary wastage of energy. Data transmission in an environment with traffic congestion causes problems of transmission delay, and the entire service life of the application is shortened due to the collision. Thus, the use of the existing duty-cycle (DC) MAC protocol is not suitable. Therefore, it is necessary to develop a protocol for effective event detection and data collection considering various traffic conditions. For example, if the total number of wake-ups to listen to an application is determined, the existing duty-cycle MAC occurs irrespective of the congestion occurring at the time of the traffic. This reduces data collisions and transmission delays if the receiver wakes up frequently only at times in heavy traffic. </p>

<p>The proposed algorithm increases the number of wake-up times by reducing the sleep time of the receiver at the peak traffic time and reduces the number of wake-up in the opposite case. This demonstrates reduced energy consumption. This paper proposes a new duty-cycle based MAC protocol suitable for congested WSNs and IoT. According to the degree of network traffic congestion, the duty-cycle ratio of the receiver and the contention window size information of the senders are broadcast through E-ACK (Early Acknowledgment), which reduces the transmission latency and waste of energy. </p>

<p>The composition of the paper is described in detail in Section 1, followed by a summary of related work in Section 2. Section 3 proposes the operation procedure of the MAC layer. In Section 4, mathematical modeling is performed to predict the proposed algorithm and performance. In Section 5, we compare the performance of the proposed algorithm with the energy consumption and average service latency. Finally, Section 6 presents conclusions and future research topics. </p>
</text>
