<text id="autogum_academic_doc644" title="Water Extract of Curcuma longa L. Ameliorates Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease" shortTile="water-extract-curcuma" author="Jeongeun Mun, Shintae Kim, Ho-Geun Yoon, Yanghee You, Ok-Kyung Kim, Kyung-Chul Choi, Yoo-Hyun Lee, Jeongmin Lee, Jeongjin Park, Woojin Jun" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/10/2536/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The liver is the central organ of lipid metabolism. Dietary fatty acids are transported to the liver and oxidized to produce as much energy as the hepatocyte needs. The excess fatty acids are converted to triglycerides (TG) and stored in the hepatocyte. When the amount of TG accounts for more than 5% of the liver weight, the organ function is impaired, and this condition is known as fatty liver disease. Chronic alcohol intake has long been considered the major cause of alcoholic fatty liver, while non-alcoholic fatty liver has been shown to be unrelated to alcohol intake. The causes of non-alcoholic fatty liver are lifestyle habits, which include excessive dietary intake and lack of energy consumption. Therefore, it is often accompanied by lifestyle diseases such as obesity, diabetes, and metabolic syndrome. In recent times, with the growing incidence of these diseases, the attention paid to non-alcoholic fatty liver is gradually increasing. Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) shows various stages. Simple hepatic steatosis is characterized by lipid accumulation in hepatocytes. Non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH) can be further developed into cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma. Although many factors such as obesity, diabetes, and inflammation have been implicated in relation to NAFLD in humans, the underlying mechanism of the development and progression of NAFLD remains unclear. </p>

<p>When free fatty acid (FFA) is overloaded in the body, FFA uptake factors such as cluster of differentiation 36 (CD36) and fatty acid transport proteins (FATPs) are significantly up-regulated, and then excessive FFA is accepted into the liver, gradually accumulating. According to previous studies, palmitic acid and high-fat (HF) diet markedly increased CD36 expression, which is closely associated with the development of NAFLD. Furthermore, several studies have indicated that fatty acid overflow by activated CD36 subsequently produced a higher level of reactive oxygen species (ROS), which could be linked to oxidative stress. </p>

<p>Oxidative stress is the imbalance between the production of ROS and the activation of antioxidants in the body and results in several metabolic disorders. It particularly produces a disturbance in lipid metabolism, eventually leading to lipid accumulation in hepatocytes. Of the several existing pathogenic mechanisms of NAFLD, oxidative stress is considered a major contributor. According to a previous study, uric acid-induced oxidative stress in hepatocytes significantly elevated the expression of lipogenesis factors such as acetyl-coenzyme A carboxylase (ACC), fatty acid synthase (FAS), and sterol regulatory element-binding protein-1c (SREBP-1c). Another study has shown that an HF diet destroyed the antioxidant defense system by decreasing superoxide dismutase (SOD) and catalase (CAT) activities, and markedly increased the production of ROS. To prevent metabolic disorders due to oxidative stress, antioxidative capability that suppresses or eliminates ROS production plays an important role in the body. Plants contain a variety of phytochemicals that have antioxidant ability to effectively remove ROS. </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Curcuma longa</hi> L. is a flowering plant of the ginger family (Zingiberaceae). As <hi rend="italic">C. longa</hi> possesses natural antioxidants, which leads to free radical scavenging potential, it has been widely used to prevent many diseases, including liver injury.  </p>

<p>The aim of our study was to investigate in vitro and in vivo protective effects of hot water extract (CLW) from <hi rend="italic">C. longa</hi> on the development of fatty liver. Furthermore, the mode of action against lipid accumulation and oxidative stress in non-alcoholic liver damage was determined. </p>
</text>
