<text id="autogum_academic_doc043" title="Comparative Study on A Novel Pathogen of European Seabass. Diversity of Aeromonas veronii in the Aegean Sea" shortTile="comparative-study" author="Maria Smyrli, Adriana Triga, Nancy Dourala, Panos Varvarigos, Michael Pavlidis, Viet  Ha Quoc, Pantelis Katharios" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2607/7/11/504/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Aeromonas veronii</hi> was isolated from diseased European seabass farmed in seven localities in both West and East Aegean Sea. The species was the most prevalent in all incidents of <hi rend="italic">Aeromonas</hi>-suspected infections with key clinical signs lethargy, icteric appearance and petechial hemorrhages externally, splenomegaly and nodules on spleen and kidney internally, as initially described. To our knowledge this is the first study after the description of the disease that directly correlates this pathology of seabass with <hi rend="italic">A. veronii</hi> in a large geographic area. The study aimed to record and describe the variability of the pathogen in the affected areas and set the basis for the disease’s management in the future. Comparative analysis was conducted on different features of the pathogen. </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Aeromonas veronii</hi> was the most prevalent species in all incidents of <hi rend="italic">Aeromonas</hi> infections in seabass in both sides of the Aegean Sea (West/East). In the case of fish farm 1 (West) where the disease was initially described we can now talk for an established problem as long as <hi rend="italic">A. veronii</hi> was isolated from diseased fish almost all year round (March–December) excluding the winter months (temperature &lt;18 °C), over the past ten years. Regarding the West Aegean Sea, while initially the disease was reported to affect only two neighboring fish farms in Argolikos Bay, it has now affected one more farm in the same area but more importantly it has geographically expanded to the neighboring Saronikos Bay where aquaculture activity is very intensive. </p>

<p>In the East Aegean Sea, the situation appeared less persistent. Reports for aeromonad outbreaks were not constant in time. Outbreaks also occurred during the summer months. Fish exhibiting the typical clinical signs of <hi rend="italic">A. veronii</hi> disease are still present in the field in summer months (personal communications with fish farmers) but are not considered a threat for the moment because impacts are much lower than those recorded in the West Aegean Sea. Nevertheless, a recent outbreak in Bodrum (sampling 24) and the similarities of strain T04-D with the rest of eastern isolates should be considered when discussing the disease’s occurrence in East Aegean Sea. In any case, the ability to cause hemolysis in seabass blood agar was observed in all tested isolates, an attribute related to the hepatic jaundice and the icteric appearance of the diseased fish in the field but also to the in vivo hemolysis observed in seabass challenged with strains NS and PDB. Pathogenicity tests in zebrafish showed similar virulence ability for all the strains. However, it should be noted that virulence in seabass is much higher following intraperitoneal injection with doses as low as 104 cfu per fish resulting in 100% mortality within 48 h. This together with the fact that other fish species cultured in adjacent cages are not affected during disease outbreaks suggests either an adaptation of the pathogen to this host, or an increase sensitivity of seabass to <hi rend="italic">A. veronii</hi>. This should be further investigated in future studies. </p>

<p>The same species (<hi rend="italic">A. veronii</hi> bv. <hi rend="italic">sobria</hi>) has been reported in diseased seabass and seabream in Italy, and from diseased seabass in one more case in the Black Sea. In the latter, the bacterium was reported as the most prevalent species in diseased seabass, isolated alone, or in mixed-infections with <hi rend="italic">Ph. damselae</hi> subsp. <hi rend="italic">damselae</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Vibrio</hi> spp. The sampling was conducted during summer and autumn in water temperature between 20–26 °C, in the same range with the outbreaks in the Aegean Sea. <hi rend="italic">A. veronii</hi> has also been reported in diseased rainbow trout farmed in the Black Sea and in the Aegean Sea. Fish transfers between farms located in the Black Sea and the Aegean regions could explain the establishment of the pathogen in the latter, however this should be confirmed in a future study using molecular epidemiological methods. </p>
</text>
