<text id="autogum_academic_doc060" title="Weathering the Cold: Modifying Membrane and Storage Fatty Acid Composition of Seeds to Improve Cold Germination Ability in Upland Cotton (Gossypium hirsutum L.)" shortTile="weathering-cold-modifying" author="Jacobo Sanchez, Puneet  Kaur Mangat, Rosalyn  B. Angeles-Shim" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4395/9/11/684/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Membrane and Storage Lipids Share Similar Biochemical Reactions and Intermediaries</head>
<p>
Lipids are fundamental to the very existence of plant life. They serve as structural components of biological membranes, as energy stores in developing seeds, and as signaling molecules that are necessary for plant growth and development, abiotic stress response, and pathogen defense. </p>

<p>As major components of plant membranes, lipids create hydrophobic barriers that separate cells from their environment and prevent diffusion of organelle contents in and out of a cell. Lipids are composed of a hydrophilic, polar head attached to a glycerol backbone and a hydrophobic tail composed of two fatty acids. Membrane lipids in plants are synthesized via two distinct pathways, i.e., the prokaryotic and the eukaryotic pathways. The prokaryotic pathway occurs in the chloroplasts and produces the major plastidic lipids such as monogalactosyldiacylglycerol (MGDG), digalactosyldiacylglycerol (DGDG), trigalactosyldiacylglycerol (TGDG), and sulfoquinovosyldiacylglycerol (SQDG), otherwise known as sulfolipids. In contrast, the eukaryotic pathway occurs in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and synthesizes phospholipids including phosphatidic acid (PA), phosphatidylcholine (PC), phosphatidylethanolamine (PE), phosphatidylglycerol (PG), phosphatidylinositol (PI), and phosphatidylserine (PS). In both the prokaryotic and eukaryotic pathways, membrane lipid biosynthesis is initiated by the formation of PAs, which are then utilized to produce plastidic lipids or phospholipids, depending on the site of biosynthesis. PAs produced in the chloroplasts can also be converted to diacylglycerol (DAG) which then serves as a precursor for plastidic lipid synthesis. During the life cycle of plants, an active lipid exchange between the chloroplast and ER occurs via the import of the DAG moiety of PCs from the ER to the chloroplast envelope where it contributes to the DAG pool used to synthesize plastidic lipids. Besides their function in membrane lipid synthesis, PAs and PCs also serve as intermediaries in storage lipid metabolism. </p>

<p>The biosynthesis of fatty acids that make up storage lipids follows the same pathway as those that comprise membrane lipids using many similar precursors. They are packaged in the seeds primarily as triacylglycerols (TAGs) which are composed of a glycerol backbone esterified with three fatty acids in saturated and/or unsaturated forms. A general overview of the membrane and lipid biosynthesis is illustrated in <figure>Figure 1</figure>. </p>

<p>Fatty acids are the major components of both membrane and storage lipids. They are made up of carboxylic acids with highly reduced hydrocarbon chains. The saturated fatty acids contain carbon molecules linked by single bonds, whereas the unsaturated fatty acids consist of carbon chains that are linked by one or multiple cis double bonds. The most common fatty acids in both membrane and storage lipids contain 16 or 18 carbons that are either saturated or unsaturated. All unsaturated fatty acid species are derived by the sequential unsaturation of the fully saturated species i.e., palmitic acid (C16:0) and stearic acid (C18:0) (the values preceding the colon represent the number of carbons in the fatty acid, whereas the numbers following it are the number of double bonds) (Table 1). This chemical reaction is catalyzed by the activity of various fatty acid desaturase enzymes. Desaturases convert single bonds at specific positions in the fatty acyl chains to double bonds by the removal of two hydrogen atoms. </p>

<p>In the subsequent sections, the role of membrane and storage lipid composition in the normal biological function of seeds, particularly during the early stages of germination, i.e., imbibition and lipid reserve metabolism, is discussed. </p>
</text>
