<text id="autogum_academic_doc454" title="The SGLT2 Inhibitor Empagliflozin Ameliorates the Inflammatory Profile in Type 2 Diabetic Patients and Promotes an Antioxidant Response in Leukocytes" shortTile="sglt-inhibitor-empagliflozin" author="Francesca Iannantuoni, Aranzazu M. de Marañon, Noelia Diaz-Morales, Rosa Falcon, Celia Bañuls, Zaida Abad-Jimenez, Victor  M. Victor, Antonio Hernandez-Mijares, Susana Rovira-Llopis" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/11/1814/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
iSGLT2s are a new class of oral hypoglycaemic drugs that block glucose reabsorption at the renal level, thus promoting urine glucose and sodium excretion and reducing plasma glucose levels. In the present study, we have focused on the effects of empagliflozin on oxidative stress in the leukocytes of T2D subjects, and on inflammatory parameters. In addition to a reduction in body weight and an improved metabolic profile—characterized by reduced plasma glucose and HbA1c levels—we observed a reduction in mitochondrial superoxide production in diabetic patients after treatment with the iSGLT2 empagliflozin, together with increased antioxidant defenses. Moreover, reduced proinflammatory markers and increased anti-inflammatory parameters were maintained after 24 weeks of treatment with empagliflozin. Besides their glucose-lowering effect, iSGLT2s produce changes in the lipid profile that should also be highlighted. Empagliflozin treatment is correlated with increased total cholesterol due to slight increases in HDL-c and LDL-c, as we have observed, and reported in other studies. However, there is a well-documented cardiovascular protection exerted by iSGLT2s, which endows these drugs with clinical potential. This has been reflected by several studies, such as the EMPA-REG OUTCOME study in which a reduction of 38% in cardiovascular mortality was evident in the empagliflozin vs. placebo group. However, neither the reduction in HbA1c observed in the study (0.60% over 12 weeks) nor the reduction in SBP (up to 5 mmHg) are sufficient to explain the reported protection against cardiovascular mortality. </p>

<p>Interestingly, as little as 24 weeks of treatment with iSGLT2 is sufficient to witness their beneficial effects on HbA1c, body weight, blood pressure and, most importantly, on the cardiovascular system. As an example, the reduction in hospitalization rates for heart failure in the group treated with empagliflozin in the EMPA-REG OUTCOME study was already significant at this time point. A recent study demonstrated an improved arterial stiffness after 6 weeks of treatment with empagliflozin in T2D patients, and hs-CRP was shown to be one of the main significant determinants for this improvement. Nevertheless, despite the available evidence, the molecular mechanisms underlying the cardiovascular protection attributable to iSGLT2 treatment are still unknown, though amelioration of oxidative stress has been hypothesized to be a potential contributor. Because cardiac tissue possesses low antioxidant defenses, increasing the expression or activity of antioxidant enzymes could be a mechanism of cardiac protection under high risk situations such as T2D. </p>

<p>Oxidative stress occurs when the production of pro-oxidant species overcomes the intrinsic antioxidant defense system of the cell, thus triggering damage to lipids, proteins and DNA, and eventually compromising cellular and tissue function. Exploring the role of SGLT2 inhibition in the prevention or reduction of oxidative stress conditions has been the subject of several studies over the last decade. However, to date, most of the studies evaluating the effect of iSGLT2 on oxidative stress have been performed in animal models. </p>

<p>Our data demonstrate that T2D patients receiving iSGLT2 treatment undergo a reduction in mitochondrial superoxide production in parallel to an increase in glutathione content, and markedly so after 24 weeks of treatment. This is accompanied by increased expression of the antioxidant enzymes GSR and CAT. However, no changes in plasma protein carbonyl content were observed with empagliflozin treatment at these time-points. Whether this could be due to the small sample size or would require long-term empagliflozin treatment needs to be addressed in future research. Our findings are in accordance with previous studies in rat models of T2D, in which increased antioxidant enzyme content and activity in renal tissues has been reported. Furthermore, iSGLT2 treatment in diabetic mice has been shown to induce antioxidant gene expression (manganese-dependent superoxide dismutase and CAT) in adipose tissue and muscle. </p>
</text>
