<text id="autogum_academic_doc324" title="Co-Seismic Deformation and Fault Slip Model of the 2017 Mw 7.3 Darbandikhan, Iran–Iraq Earthquake Inferred from D-InSAR Measurements" shortTile="coseismic-deformation" author="Zicheng Huang, Guohong Zhang, Xinjian Shan, Wenyu Gong, Yingfeng Zhang, Yanchuan Li" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/21/2521/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Determination of the Three-Dimensional (3D) Coseismic Displacement Field</head><head> 3.1. Methodology</head>
<p>
The ground deformation field, limited to the single direction (LOS), can be decomposed into three mutually perpendicular components (east–west, north–south, and up–down). Theoretically, we can obtain the three-dimensional deformation field utilizing multiple InSAR measurement results acquired by different SAR satellites. However, this method is not applicable in the Darbandikhan earthquake because of three reasons. First, most current SAR satellites fly in near-polar orbits, so the acquired SAR data is not quite sensitive to the north–south deformation. Second, the interferograms of different satellites are right-looking. Third, the source mechanism of different organization (Table 1) indicate that this earthquake had a strike-slip movement close to the north–south direction accompanied by large deformations. The along-track deformation field, extracted from each interferometric pair, can overcome the limitations of LOS deformation and acquire reliable results. Therefore, combining the LOS and along-track measurements, we can get the complete 3D displacement. </p>

<p>In this study, we mapped the complete 3D co-seismic surface of the earthquake by integrating the ascending (track 72) and descending orbits (track 6) LOS measurements derived from D-InSAR and the along-track measurements derived from offset-tracking (<figure>Figure 3</figure>). The offset-tracking method searches the corresponding point on the amplitude images by the cross-correlation technique and calculates the selected points′ azimuth offsets. Then, the robust azimuth offset of the surface deformation can be got by subtracting the components of the topographic relief and orbit trend separation. Given four independent components (LOS and along-track directions) (<figure>Figure 3</figure>a–c), we can directly obtain the 3D surface deformation. </p>

<head> 3.2. Analysis on the 3D Co-Seismic Deformation Field</head>
<p>
The full 3D co-seismic surface deformation of the Darbandikhan earthquake are shown in <figure>Figure 3</figure>e–g. There are significant deformation in the region around the epicenter in all the three directions, especially in the east–west and up–down direction. In the east–west direction, the solution area is characterized by westward movement and the maximum displacement can is −0.65 m. In the north–south direction, there is no horizontal displacement toward the north and the maximum deformation is −0.73 m. Therefore, the horizontal displacement is toward southwest, which suggests that the region with co-seismic deformation mainly concentrates in the northeast part of the seismogenic fault. This conclusion is similar to the focal mechanism solution from USGS. In the vertical direction, there are two significant lobes in the main rupture region. The maximum uplift is −0.81 m and the maximum subsidence is −0.28 m. The huge value difference between the uplift and the subsidence lobes on the two sides of the fault confirms the thrust movement. Moreover, the field geological survey shows that there is no surface rupture related to the seismogenic fault. Therefore, this earthquake might be caused by a blind thrust fault close to north–south with the deformation field concentrating on the northwest side of the fault. </p>
</text>
