<text id="autogum_academic_doc292" title="Deep Learning Object-Impulse Detection for Enhancing Leakage Detection of a Boiler Tube Using Acoustic Emission Signal" shortTile="deep-learning-objectimpulse" author="Bach  Phi Duong, Jaeyoung Kim, Cheol-Hong Kim, Jong-Myon Kim" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/20/4368/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Impulse Detection Methodology Using Deep Learning Flexible Boundary Regression</head>
<p>
Since the time lengths of the AE impulse signal excited by the fuel stream are variable, the proposed method must adapt to predict boundaries of different sizes. This research introduces the DLFBR impulse detection model, which considers an impulse as an object to be analyzed and recognized. This model improves the 1D-CNN to adapt for hit detection in the AE signal. The research reframes hit detection as a straightforward regression issue, directly from the AE signal vector to the boundary box coordinates. The proposed method takes an AE signal as the input, feeds it through a neural network structure that looks similar to a 1D-CNN to integrate the boundary regression layer, and receives a vector of box coordinates around the impulse position in the output. The basic idea of the detection algorithm includes two steps: preprocessing the signal to extract the shape signal and a flexible boundary detector. </p>

<head> 3.1. Preprocessing to Extract the Shape Signal</head>
<p>
The preprocessing step works to extract the global shape of the impulse at the macro-level, corresponding to the length of the sampled signal. Normally, the concept of object detection is used in an image processing technique where the object is smooth, continuous, and mostly homogenous inside the point area of the object. With this condition, the convolution neural network considers the boundary of an object to be composed of an edge and blob patterns, which have a sudden change between their different colors. However, the AE signal collected from the leak detection testbed always includes environmental noise and contains many small troughs and peaks. If these troughs and peaks are smaller than the grid size generated by the deep learning detector, the object detection algorithm cannot give a satisfying result. To mitigate the undesired variations and unexpected instantaneous frequency values produced by the remaining amount of small noise, the preprocessing step helps obtain the overall shape of the signal with little random noise. <figure>Figure 3</figure> presents the preprocessing step of the algorithm. </p>

<p>In the first step, the AE signal sample is segmented into non-overlapping frames and rectified to obtain the positive part. Then, in each window, the root means square (RMS) is calculated to form the lower rate RMS signal. Next, the lower rate signal is expanded to its original size by scaling the time axis using cubic interpolation and antialiasing. The cubic interpolation method performs piecewise cubic Hermite interpolation based on the values at neighboring grid points. It seeks to match only the first-order derivatives at the data points with those in the intervals before and after. For a set of data points , , the cubic Hermite interpolant at any point , with , takes the form:

(1)

where

</p>

<p>An instance based on piecewise cubic Hermite interpolation is shape-preserving piecewise cubic, which preserves the shape of the data since the resulting interpolated function has a continuous derivative. Shape-preserving piecewise cubic interpolation has a similar formula to that of piecewise cubic Hermite interpolation, but it differs in the component of the first-order derivatives . The output vector value is a weighted average of points taken from at least the nearest four neighborhoods; this interpolation ensures that the value of the interpolant is located within a range of local points. </p>

<head> 3.2. Impulse Detection with the Deep Learning Flexible Boundary Regression Detector</head>
<p>
In contrast to general CNNs, the proposed method employs a one-dimensional time-domain signal as the input data instead of two-dimensional pixels. The one-dimensional AE signal is fed into the first convolution layer. To detect an object, the detector takes the feature for that object and assesses it at various locations and scales in the sample signal. DLFBR observes the entire signal during the training and testing process to implicitly encode contextual information about the type of object as well as its position. The component object detector is only unified into an end-to-end single neural network, which utilizes features from the entire signal to estimate the position for each boundary box. To reason globally about the full sample signal and all of the objects inside the signal, DLFBR divides the input signal into a grid with a grid size . If the center of an object drops into a cell in the grid, that cell responds to detecting that object. From the generated grid, each grid cell regresses the  encircled box and the confidence score for each box. These confidence scores represent how confident the network is that the box contains an object, as well as how accurate the network thinks the predicted box is. The confidence is specified as

(2)

</p>
</text>
