<text id="autogum_academic_doc179" title="A Modified k – ε Turbulence Model for a Wave Breaking Simulation" shortTile="modified-k--e-turbulence" author="Giovanni Cannata, Federica Palleschi, Benedetta Iele, Francesco Gallerano" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4441/11/11/2282/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Results</head>
<p>
In this section the numerical results obtained by the Gallerano et al. numerical model are compared with the experimental measurements by Ting and Kirby. The test conducted by Ting and Kirby consisted of realizing a spilling breaking wave on a sloping beach. It is possible to examine the wave energy dissipation in the surf zone due to the turbulence by means of the turbulence model. The experimental wave tank was  long,  wide, and  deep and consisted of a beach with a constant slope equal to  connected to a region with a constant depth equal to  the wavemaker was placed at the left end of the wave tank. In this paper, in order to save computational time, we numerically reproduced only the final eighteen meters of the experimental arrangement shown in <figure>Figure 2</figure>, and the abscissa  indicates the toe of the slope where the still water depth is equal to .  </p>

<p>The computational grid adopted for all the numerical simulations consisted of  grid cells in the horizontal direction in which  spanned from  to  and the grid spacing was . In the vertical direction,  grid cells were used. As shown in <figure>Figure 3</figure>, the mesh was refined at the top and bottom boundaries. For this test, cnoidal waves with period  and wave height  were imposed as input boundary conditions. In the swash region, a wetting–drying treatment was used. </p>

<head> 4.1. Spilling Breaking Test without Turbulence Model</head>
<p>
In this subsection we present briefly the numerical results obtained without the turbulence model. </p>

<p><figure>Figure 4</figure> shows the distribution of the wave crest and wave trough in the cross-shore direction, together with the mean water level, obtained by the Gallerano et al. numerical model in which the turbulence model was switched off. The mean water level and the wave crest and trough, shown in <figure>Figure 4</figure>, were computed by performing, respectively, a time-average and a phase-average, over five wave periods of the date extracted from the numerical simulation, once the simulation reached a quasi-stationary state. In the same figure, the experimental results by Ting and Kirby and the numerical results by Ma are also shown. In the shoaling zone () the numerical results obtained by the Gallerano et al. numerical model fit quite well with the experimental results, while after the initial wave breaking point () the numerical results overestimated the experimental ones. As shown in <figure>Figure 4</figure>, similar numerical results were obtained by Ma et al.. </p>

<head> 4.2. Spilling Breaking Test with Turbulence Model</head>
<p>
<figure>Figure 5</figure> shows the distribution of the wave crest and wave trough in the cross-shore direction, together with the mean water level, obtained by the Gallerano et al. numerical model in which the turbulence model is the standard  proposed by Rodi. From this figure, it is possible to notice that for this test case the standard  turbulence model produces an excessive non-physical decrease in the wave height with respect to the experimental results. </p>

<p><figure>Figure 6</figure> shows a snapshot of the instantaneous spatial distribution of the turbulent kinetic energy (a,b) and the turbulent eddy viscosity (c,d), in two different time steps, obtained by the Gallerano et al. numerical model in which the turbulence model is the standard proposed by Rodi. From this figure, it can be noticed that the turbulent kinetic energy is generated in correspondence with the wave fronts in all the surf zone, also before , where the initial wave breaking point is located according to the experimental measurements. <figure>Figure 6</figure> also shows that, by using the standard  turbulence model, the simulated wave fronts are very smooth, due to an excess of the turbulent eddy viscosity produced by the modelled turbulent kinetic energy. </p>

<p>From <figure>Figure 5</figure> and <figure>Figure 6</figure> it can be deduced that, for this test case, the standard  turbulence model produces an excess of turbulent kinetic energy and turbulent eddy viscosity, which entails very small simulated wave heights and very smooth wave fronts in the whole surf zone. </p>

<p><figure>Figure 7</figure> shows the distribution of the wave crest and wave trough in the cross-shore direction, together with the mean water level, obtained by the Gallerano et al. numerical model in which the turbulence model is the modified  turbulence proposed in this paper. In the same figure, the above numerical results are compared with the experimental results by Ting and Kirby and the numerical results obtained by the Gallerano et al. numerical model in which the turbulence model is switched off. From this figure, it is possible to notice that the initial wave breaking point is correctly predicted by the modified  turbulence model; the modified  turbulence model adequately represents the distribution of the wave crest and wave trough before and after the initial wave breaking point. </p>
</text>
