<text id="autogum_academic_doc631" title="Effects of Freeway Rerouting and Boulevard Replacement on Air Pollution Exposure and Neighborhood Attributes" shortTile="effects-freeway-rerouting" author="Regan  F. Patterson, Robert  A. Harley" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4072/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Conclusions</head>
<p>
West Oakland residents saw rerouting of the Cypress Freeway and replacement with a street-level boulevard as an opportunity to mitigate the air pollution burden that freeway construction had caused in their neighborhood and increase access to urban green space. Our air pollution maps and distance–decay curves reveal that rerouting the Cypress Freeway resulted in substantial reductions in annual average NOx and BC concentrations in the middle of West Oakland when compared to the Cypress Freeway rebuild-in-place scenario. These air quality benefits highlight the importance of roadway types planned through residential neighborhoods, such as freeways and designated truck routes. We observe that the new freeway route still impacts air pollutant levels in the Mandela Parkway corridor, so it is critical to select an alternative route that does not have segments in close proximity to residential areas. Limitations may be present in port communities and communities impacted by goods-movement activities.  </p>

<p>Environmental justice activism sometimes has unintended paradoxical consequences, where efforts to improve a neighborhood make existing residents vulnerable to displacement. This displacement is facilitated through economic revitalization efforts that do not prioritize the needs of existing residents. While the urban freeway was thought of as a tool for urban revitalization by mid-century transportation planners, the removal and rerouting of the urban freeway are viewed as opportunities for redevelopment. An investigation of West Oakland indicates that freeway rerouting and construction of a street-level boulevard result in some environmental gentrification, with property value increases and the displacement of long-time Black residents, similar to freeway removal and tunneling. To ensure existing residents benefit from the air pollution reductions caused by freeway rerouting, affordable housing and other anti-displacement strategies, such as inclusionary zoning and renter protections, should be instituted. </p>

<p>There are some limitations in our analysis methods. Traffic counts on the Mandela Parkway were based on a short-duration traffic survey. These counts were extrapolated to annual counts, using temporal allocation factors from McDonald et al. that were derived from freeway traffic count data. Although traffic activity profiles can vary by roadway type, data on arterial traffic patterns were not available. More extensive traffic count data on local arterials is needed to improve estimates of the air quality impacts of freeway rerouting. Additionally, our analysis of neighborhood change was conducted at the tract level. Using an area-weighting method to estimate demographic and socioeconomic variables along the Mandela Parkway introduces error. As freeway removal and replacement with a street-level boulevard receives increased attention as a contemporary urban transportation policy, due to aging freeway infrastructure, it is critical to accurately determine who benefits from such urban green space projects.
 </p>
</text>
