<text id="autogum_academic_doc707" title="The Impact of Strategic Human Resource Management Practices on Competitive Advantage Sustainability: The Mediation of Human Capital Development and Employee Commitment" shortTile="impact-strategic" author="Halbast  Hussein Hamadamin, Tarik Atan" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5782/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
In the dynamic and competitive business world of today, where the exchange of ideas is proficient, a “sustainable competitive advantage” (SCA) is no longer deep-rooted in the organization’s physical resources but in the organization’s nonphysical human resources. In view of these findings, the attention of scholars has been on the factors that could be instrumental to the achievement of SCA. O’Reily and Pfeffer opined that the world we are in today is the one wherein “knowledge and intellectual capital” is required instead of “physical capital”. Thus, the study believes it is becoming significant in the business world where people can be effective and efficient in developing innovative goods and services. It is on this note that other scholars have attempted to understand the particular factors that could enable an organization to achieve SCA. Barney investigated the relationship between SCA and organizational resources and found that every organization operates with a tacit knowledge and has the potential to improve, SCA. </p>

<p>Meanwhile, in the efforts of scholars to examine the nexus in strategic human resources management practices, a behavioral approach has been commonly used. Behavioral approaches, which identify divergent role behaviors as significant to the kind of strategy that is being pursued by an organization, are found in the literature to be the most often used theory to explain the nexus in strategic human resources management (HRM) practices. Much emphasis is placed on individual employee behavior as a mediator between organization strategy and the result by this approach or as a mediator between strategic HRM and SCA. The behavioral school of thought is of the view that divergent behavior roles are important in determining the kinds of strategies that an organization engages in. It has been established in the literature that an employee stands out as one of the major sources of achieving SCA in an organization. Thus, the integrative model for strategic HRM, which combines rational and progressive approaches and is ingrained in some theories—for instance resource-based view (RBV), social exchange theory (SET), and behavioral-based view—are found as an appropriate approach to strategic HRM and SCA. This research utilized the perception of HRM practices to explain in detail from the angle of human capital development and the commitment of employees to their organization. Therefore, this study will examine the relationship between the strategies deployed by the universities in Iraq and the sustainability of their competitive advantages by also evaluating the mediation role of human capital development and employee commitment. In accordance with the theories highlighted above, this study aims at determining the impact of “strategic HRM practices” on the SCA within academic institutions through the evaluation of the mediating function of human capital development and “employee commitment”. The remainder of the paper is structured as follows: Section 2 discusses the theoretical background to the study and development of the hypotheses for the study. This is followed in the subsequent section with research methodology. In this section, the instrument and procedure for data collection are discussed. In Section 4, data analysis techniques employed for the study are discussed; the psychometric properties of the constructs and structural model testing results are also presented. The last section contains a discussion of the results in which the theoretical and managerial implications are discussed, and the study limitations and suggestions for further study are wrapped up the section. </p>
</text>
