<text id="autogum_academic_doc525" title="Development of an Improved Model to Predict Building Thermal Energy Consumption by Utilizing Feature Selection" shortTile="development-improved" author="Jihoon Jang, Joosang Lee, Eunjo Son, Kyungyong Park, Gahee Kim, Jee  Hang Lee, Seung-Bok Leigh" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4187/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head><head> 1.1. Background</head>
<p>
The emission of greenhouse gas (GHG) has steeply increased by approximately 82.5% since 1979, which has been a major contributor to climate change globally. This gives rise to considerable global efforts to reduce its emissions. As a part of it, South Korea announced a target of reducing GHG emissions by 37% compared to Business As Usual (BAU) by 2030 in the Paris Agreement of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) in 2016. </p>

<p>Humans, who are mostly responsible for GHG emissions, spend approximately 90% of the daytime in buildings. The estimated GHG emissions from buildings are as high as 20% of the total emissions. Therefore, many studies have been conducted to reduce energy consumption in buildings in an effort to reduce GHG emissions from buildings. </p>

<p>The application of renewable energy to buildings has increased recently in an effort to reduce the energy consumption of buildings. To properly distribute the supply of renewable energy sources, it is necessary to accurately predict the energy consumption of each building. In particular, from a building life-cycle perspective, the energy consumed in the operation stage of a building amounts to approximately 70–90% of the total energy. Therefore, it is essential to accurately predict the energy consumption of buildings for their efficient operation. </p>

<head> 1.2. Literature Review (Analysis of Previous Studies)</head>
<p>
In this section, previous studies were reviewed to introduce (i) the necessity of predicting building energy consumption, (ii) a comparative analysis of energy prediction methods, and (iii) the advantages of feature selection. Based on these, the optimal modeling strategy for predicting building energy consumption was developed. </p>

<p>Linda et al. showed that energy distribution systems can be planned by predicting heat and electricity demand. They created regression analysis models for buildings using the heat and electricity consumptions measured every hour and predicted the heat and electricity loads as well as the annual energy demand in a specific area. As a result, they optimized a system for energy distribution to buildings. Yudong Ma et al. conducted research on energy reduction in buildings using an energy demand prediction. They constructed a system optimized for storing the heat source generated from a cooling system and a prediction control system for preventing the overproduction of heat sources. The simulation results showed that an energy-saving effect of up to 24.5% can be achieved. The district heating system efficiently provides heat sources using a centralized supply of cold and hot water used in local facilities. Therefore, it is possible to determine an optimal operation plan before using chillers and boilers if their loads can be accurately predicted. M. Sakawa et al. predicted the load using an artificial neural network (ANN) for efficient district cooling and heating operation. Kody M. Powell et al. conducted research on the energy reduction of heating, ventilation and air conditioning (HVAC) using a building energy consumption prediction model. They presented an efficient method of coping with the peak load by controlling the thermal storage system. Samuel et al. conducted a study to predict the heating load in a district heating system by applying four types of machine learning. They used district heating data collected from 10 residential and commercial buildings located in Skellefteå, Sweden, and using machine learning techniques, namely, support vector machine (SVM), forward backpropagation neural network (FFNN), multilinear regression (MLR), regression. Prediction of energy consumption shows that it is a key step towards the realization of optimized energy production, distribution, and consumption. To improve present and future energy supplies, predicting energy demands is an essential stage. However, the lack of accurate and comprehensive data sets to predict future demand is one of the big problems in developing economies. Therefore, Sasan et al. proposed an ensemble hybrid forecasting model as a solution for predicting energy consumption while dealing with the shortage of data sets. These studies controlled the production and operation of heat sources by predicting the building energy consumption and the induced energy reduction. They also prevented the overproduction of heat sources through the energy consumption prediction. </p>
</text>
