<text id="autogum_academic_doc474" title="SL-BioDP: Multi-Cancer Interactive Tool for Prediction of Synthetic Lethality and Response to Cancer Treatment" shortTile="slbiodp-multicancer" author="Xiang Deng, Shaoli Das, Kristin Valdez, Kevin Camphausen, Uma Shankavaram" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6694/11/11/1682/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Discussion</head>
<p>
Synthetic lethality has immense potential in cancer therapeutics. Where the driver genes or oncogenes cannot be targeted, synthetic lethal interactors can potentially serve as drug targets in the presence of mutations in the driver genes, as the mutant tumor cells are dependent upon the synthetic lethal interactors for their survival. Recent advances in RNAi and CRISPR technologies have enabled large-scale synthetic lethality screens for individual genes to be performed in human cell lines. The genetic dependency map (DepMap) project is dedicated towards finding genetic dependencies from the published shRNA/CRISPR or drug screening data in cancer cell lines. While identifying genetic dependencies or essentiality in the context of specific genetic alterations is important for screening potential targets for cancer therapy, identification of clinically relevant synthetic lethal pairs in cancers has been a challenge. A recent work tried to address this limitation with an in silico analysis of clinical relevance of the SL interactions identified from in vitro SL screens and reported that only a fraction of these SL interactions hold up to be clinically significant when tested on TCGA tumor data. Also, these in vitro screens are costly and finding synthetic lethal interactors for many cancer genes remain challenging. SL-BioDP addresses such problems by using a computational method that leverages the available cancer genetic data resources to predict synthetic lethal partners of all cancer susceptibility genes and assesses the clinical relevance from matched clinical data. The computational predictions of SL interactions were subjected to extensive in silico validation using either published literature or shRNA and drug screening data from cancer cell lines. SL-BioDP is a comprehensive resource for the query and visualization of cancer-specific synthetic lethality and potential drug targets based on the concept of synthetic lethality. The utility of this web tool is that it enables multilevel querying based on cancer genes, tissues, or drugs of interest. In contrast to the other database resources on synthetic lethality, SL-BioDP enables assessment of the clinical relevance of targeting the SL interactor gene in the presence of mutation in the primary gene. The prediction of drug response depending on the presence of mutations in the primary genes is another important feature added in SL-BioDP. Our analysis of published drug screening data and gene mutation data from matched cancer cell lines identified known synthetic lethality-based drug targets like sensitivity of the drug, olaparib (PARP inhibitor) in the presence of mutation in the <hi rend="italic">BRCA1</hi> gene, and in general the homologous recombination repair pathway. In addition, the analysis offers to look into new potentially effective gene mutation-based drug therapies. We extended our analysis to infer potential synergy between drugs targeting the predicted SL interactors. We reasoned that if the presence of a mutation (or loss of function) in a primary gene makes cancer cells sensitive to certain drugs targeting an SL interactor, then it is highly likely that the drugs targeting the primary gene will also make the cancer cells sensitive to those drugs targeting the SL interactor. These inferred drug synergies can be searched in SL-BioDP for each of the 18 tumor histologies included in SL-BioDP. In support of our predictions of synergistic drugs in cancers, we collected literature references and reports of ongoing clinical trials, which is included in Supplementary Table S3. Combined together, SL-BioDP can serve as a comprehensive tool, for exploring potentially actionable mutation-based targeted therapies based on the concept of synthetic lethality, that shows possible clinical relevance. </p>
</text>
