<text id="autogum_academic_doc544" title="Gibbs Free Energy and Reaction Rate Acceleration in and on Microdroplets" shortTile="gibbs-free-energy" author="Adrian  F Tuck" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1099-4300/21/11/1044/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Methods</head>
<p>
In viewing a microdroplet reactor, the most obvious effect is that of the restricted volume available to the reactants, leading to the classical but vaguely defined concept of ‘crowding’. Considering a 1 micrometer (10−6 m) radius droplet, it will be capable of holding thousands of small molecules, typically of nanometer (10−9 m) radius. The encasing layer or film will be of different composition to the interior, depending upon the detailed characteristics of the molecules involved; the solvent involved is commonly but not always water. For the law of mass action to be applicable, all reactant molecules must have random access to the entire volume in the time scale concerned. Restriction to less than three dimensions will accelerate reactions. It has been shown in the case of stratospheric ozone that this is a relevant consideration. For scale invariance to be diagnosed and applied to the estimation of entropy and <hi rend="italic">G</hi>, there must be three orders of magnitude in scale, a condition met with nanometric resolution in the observations. This scaling range will be defined by the three orders of magnitude between the inner scale of a few mean free paths and the outer scale defined by the microdroplet’s circumference, much as a great circle defines the outer scale for the atmosphere. </p>

<p>Applying the principle that attractive forces produce organization in the form of reaction, these forces will be more effective in microdroplets than in bulk because they will be acting over closer ranges. The entropic price is paid by repulsive forces effecting dissipation and will also be constrained by the microdroplet, which has a smaller volume than that in bulk. Thus, both these effects result in a favorable effect on Δ<hi rend="italic">G</hi>. ‘Organization’ can be, for example, the production of oligomers or polymers from monomers, with the reaction products at the bottom of their potential well representing dilution of energy density. It should be emphasized that the interior of a microdroplet is unlikely to be of the same uniform molar composition as bulk liquid, because the effects of interaction with the encasing layer will propagate into the interior, with the result that composition will have a dynamical gradient along a radius from the center to the exterior. The transfer will be fluid mechanical rather than diffusive in the Einstein–Smolukowski sense. </p>

<p>In a homogeneous droplet, the Gibbs energy of the confining layer is regarded as the surface tension of the bulk liquid. In a heterogeneous microdroplet, the situation is more complicated. Even for small polar molecules in aqueous solution, the outer layer will not be the same composition as the interior. Where amphiphiles and surfactants are concerned, they may form films, which can be two-dimensional gases, liquids or solids, depending upon surface pressure, with significant chemical consequences. In the case of a microdroplet with a liquid or solid exterior film, it can provide a radically different reaction medium from either the interior or the bulk. Particularly important in this context is the ability to form an anhydrous environment of the condensation reactions that eliminate water to produce biopolymers, including peptides, nucleotides and phosphorylation reactions. </p>

<p>The scale of microdroplets is such that they fall into the category of systems ranging from mesoscopic to macroscopic, thus being capable of non-equilibrium statistical thermodynamic analysis, both experimentally and theoretically. Scale invariant determination of <hi rend="italic">G</hi> is viable in principle, therefore turbulent flow, necessarily scale invariant, is possible both in the interior and two-dimensionally in the exterior layer. </p>

<p>It has been argued recently that <hi rend="italic">G</hi> is computable from observations in a scale invariant medium, and shown to work:

(1)

where <hi rend="italic">K</hi>(<hi rend="italic">q</hi>)/<hi rend="italic">q</hi> is a scaling quantity related to partition function <hi rend="italic">f</hi>, Boltzmann constant <hi rend="italic">k</hi> and temperature <hi rend="italic">T</hi> by:

(2)

(3)

</p>

<p>The relationship of <hi rend="italic">Kq</hi> to the Hurst exponent <hi rend="italic">H</hi> is given in as

(4)

where

(5)

and <hi rend="italic">ζ</hi>(<hi rend="italic">q</hi>) is the linear slope of a log–log plot of the first order structure function of the fluctuations of the observed variable versus a lag parameter covering the range of the variable. By applying scale invariance to the bulk medium, and separately to the microdroplet, the Δ<hi rend="italic">G</hi> between the two may be obtained by difference. Application of high-resolution experimental and imaging techniques would then enable a comparison with the values obtained by quantum statistical methods applied to the reactant molecules. It is noted for example that the Hurst exponent <hi rend="italic">H</hi> has been obtained for essential genes in bacteria. </p>
</text>
