<text id="autogum_academic_doc153" title="Fatigue Life of 7475-T7351 Aluminum After Local Severe Plastic Deformation Caused by Machining" shortTile="fatigue-life-t-aluminum" author="Petra Ohnistova, Miroslav Piska, Martin Petrenec, Jiri Dluhos, Jana Hornikova, Pavel Sandera" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1944/12/21/3605/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
The observations from the experimental machining, surface analyses, and fatigue testing confirm similar results as those of Ojolo et al. and Novovic et al.. </p>

<p>Surface topography analysis confirmed that the roughness parameters increase with the increase of the feed speed (feed per tooth). The increase of the cutting speed caused a decrease of the surface roughness parameters. This result partially confirms the observation of Ojolo et al.. </p>

<p>The increase of the feed speed increases surface topography parameters such as average height of the selected area (<hi rend="italic">Sa</hi>), root-mean-square height of the selected area (<hi rend="italic">Sq</hi>), or maximum valley depth of the selected area (<hi rend="italic">Sv</hi>). The roughness parameters were found to be similar for both strategies (perpendicular and inclined by 1°); however, a greater increase of roughness parameters was observed while using higher feed speeds for samples machined with the tool inclined by 1°. The average height of the selected area (<hi rend="italic">Sa</hi>) showed higher values for samples machined with the tool inclined by 1°. This parameter was not adequate, considering that maximum valley depth of the selected area (<hi rend="italic">Sv</hi>) was higher for samples machined by a tool positioned perpendicularly to the machined surface. </p>

<p>The trends of specific cutting force and shear deformation confirm a reduction of plastic deformation with increasing cutting speed, but more intensive deformation with reduction of feed per tooth. In other words, the intensity of plastic deformation is higher for shallow cuts and higher cutting speeds. </p>

<p>The highest fatigue resistance was observed at samples machined with the highest cutting speed (<hi rend="italic">vc</hi> =200 m.min−1) and lowest feed per tooth (<hi rend="italic">fz</hi> = 0.05 mm). A decrease of the fatigue life of specimens machined with higher feed rates while keeping the same cutting speed was observed (increase from feed per tooth <hi rend="italic">fz</hi> = 0.05 mm to <hi rend="italic">fz</hi> = 0.90 mm). This decrease of the fatigue life may be caused by the severe plastic deformation achieved in the smallest chip cross sections and machined at the highest cutting speeds (<hi rend="italic">vc</hi> = 200 m.min−1). </p>

<p>Slight inclination of the cutting tool (1°) resulted in reduction of the total cycles for specimens machined with cutting speed <hi rend="italic">vc</hi> = 90 m.min−1 and different feed speeds. This reduction may be caused by plastic deformation caused by teeth not engaged in the cut, as in the case of face milling perpendicular to the machined surface. This plastic deformation may impose beneficial compressive residual stresses into the machined surface and thus increase the fatigue life. </p>

<p>Therefore, the cutting conditions can affect the material removal rate, but a more serious impact can be seen in terms of the surface quality and the resistance to mechanical loading. The effect of inclusions is very serious, and materials used for dynamic loading should be carefully analyzed not only in view the surface integrity, but also considering the occurrence of the phases, which confirms the results of Piska et al.. The effect of material hardening and thermal softening when cutting should be studied further in terms of the density and arrangement of dislocations, stacking fault energy, and other atomic hardening or softening mechanisms. </p>
</text>
