<text id="autogum_academic_doc675" title="Institutional Investors and Corporate Performance: Insights from China" shortTile="institutional-investors" author="Shu-Ling Lin, Jun Lu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6010/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions</head>
<p>
This study used annual data to investigate the impact of institutional ownership on stock return volatility, idiosyncratic risks, and corporate governance in China. In order to identify this effect, We employed the panel regression model by using the ordinary least squares (OLS) to first explore the relationship between institutional ownership and stock return volatility. Then, this study used the CAPM one-factor model and the Fama–French three-factor model to analyze the relationship between institutional ownership and idiosyncratic risks and the binary logic panel model to estimate the relationship between institutional ownership and corporate governance. Furthermore, this study compared the empirical results during the pre-crisis, during crisis, and post-crisis periods. We were interested in whether institutional investors have a different effect on the volatility of stock returns, idiosyncratic risks, and corporate governance in the Chinese market. We tried to determine what type of institutional investors help stabilize the individual market effectively. Moreover, this study was interested in which type of institutional ownership has the role of stewardship. </p>

<p>The empirical results show that independent institutions and domestic institutions reduce stock return volatility. The results are consistent with hypothesis 1a and 2a. However, grey institutions and foreign institutions have no significant effects on stock return volatility, so hypotheses 1b and 2b could not be confirmed. </p>

<p>For the effect on the idiosyncratic risks of stock, the empirical results of the CAPM one factor and the Fama–French three-factors models show that independent institutions reduce the idiosyncratic risks of stocks in the periods during the crisis. However, grey institutions and foreign institutions have no significant effect on the idiosyncratic risk in all three periods. </p>

<p>The empirical results of the effects on corporate governance show different effects on the top 10 shareholders, senior shareholders, and the personnel change of the first shareholder and CEO. For the top 10 shareholders, all institutional ownerships have a significantly positive effect, but for senior shareholders, this effect is reversed, and independent and domestic institutional ownerships have a significantly negative effect. The effects on the personnel change of first shareholder and CEO are not significant. </p>

<p>With this research, we have a clearer understanding of the behavior of institutional investors in the Chinese market. Independent institutional investors have exercised their supervisory responsibilities as active ownership, and this kind of stewardship behavior of independent institutional investors was more obvious during post-crisis. On the other hand, in the regression of the CAPM one-factor models, domestic institutional investors effectively reduce the idiosyncratic risks before the financial crisis. As for foreign institutions, the performance of their supervision in the periods of pre-crisis, during crisis, and post-crisis is not obvious. On the other hand, for corporate governance, institutional ownership, as a form of large professional ownership, improves the quality of corporate governance. Institutional investors are one of the company’s most important shareholders, suppressing the equity of senior shareholders after the financial crisis, while maintaining the neutrality of supervision. </p>

<p>We sought to explore the sustainability of institutional investors and stable economic growth in developing countries from a holistic perspective. Continuing the previous research, from the perspective of sustainable development, Lin et al. studied the behavior of institutional investors from the external market environment. This study explores the contribution of institutional investors in the market environment. Both parts of this study have effectively proven that, in independent institutions, the role of stewardship in both the external market environments supports national policies and the internal market environment for financial stability and corporate governance. </p>

<p>However, foreign institutional investors who are active in both institutions have no obvious effect on the role of housekeepers in China, which is inconsistent with previous scholars’ research. This study believes that the reason for this result is related to the degree of China’s openness to foreign investment. Although the amount of investment in foreign institutions has increased significantly during the study period (2005–2016), its proportion among the total institutional investors is still small (1.68%). Therefore, in order for foreign institutional investors to play the role of stewards, it will be necessary for developing countries to be open to foreign investment institutions. The continued clarity of national policies is also an indispensable factor for attracting foreign institutional investors. The increase in active institutional investors will have a sustainable effect on national policy and market stability, as well as investor profitability.
 </p>
</text>
