<text id="autogum_academic_doc503" title="Sex Differences in the Relationship between Student School Burnout and Problematic Internet Use among Adolescents" shortTile="sex-differences-relationship" author="Katarzyna Tomaszek, Agnieszka Muchacka-Cymerman" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4107/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
Many studies show the problem of burnout and its negative impact on some forms of addiction. We found that if a lack of resources appear, an individual becomes burned out, and thus, the risk of addiction increases. Our assumption is consistent with other studies in which burnout may cause many behavioral addictions, such as Internet Addiction, substance abuse or alcohol dependence. Additionally, similar to our results, many studies have revealed that the risk factors of IA stem from feelings of a lack of social resources, and is manifested by poor social relationships, loneliness, lack of social skills, and lack of social support. Following the Job Demands Resources Model chronic stress, which is sparked by excessive demands and lacking resources may—via burnout—cause negative outcomes such as poor performance and health. What is more, by increasing resources, such as social support, we reduce the risk of burnout syndrome and health problems. One of these health problems are addictive behaviours, such as problematic Internet use. Academic burnout heightened the potential risk of addiction among adolescents. The authors suggested that symptoms of school burnout, frustration, and a sense of disappointment in people cause maladaptive behaviours such as isolation adaptations, and addiction to alcohol and drugs. These are one of possible ways to escape from the present difficult situation and reduce the tensions. </p>

<p>The main objective of this research was to test for gender differences in school-related predictors of Internet addiction. Our study supplemented the existing literature by examining the association between school burnout and Internet addiction for adolescent girls and boys separately. According to the results, it was discovered that a higher level of school burnout is related to higher Internet addiction indicators. However, in the female adolescent group these relationships were weaker (we noted a smaller number of significant Pearson’s correlations, all significant correlations were low). In the male adolescent group, we found a larger number of significant correlation coefficients and with higher effect size (low to moderate). In other words, young burnout boys are at a higher risk of suffering from Internet addiction than girls. This result is consistent with the statement that gender-related differences exist in most addictive behaviors. Other research showed differentiated effects on Internet addiction by gender in such prevalence of IA like: school grades, parental education, alcohol drinking, smoking consumption, and substance use. Many previous studies showed that Internet addiction affects boys more often. One possible explanation is that they try to cope with negative school pressure and stress, and negative feelings and thoughts connected with burnout syndrome, by indulging themselves on the Internet, which is rather an avoidance and ineffective strategy of problem solving. </p>

<p>Secondly, gender significantly predicted Internet addiction, and moderated the link between school burnout and Internet addiction. Hierarchical multiple regression analyses confirmed different predictors of Internet addiction for female and male students. </p>

<p>Our findings suggest that school burnout and school-related characteristics have greater prediction power of Internet addiction in a male group than in a female group. As the results show, burnout due to parents appeared to be a significant predictor of IA for both male and female high school students. However, in the female group also, burnout due to study and loss of interest were significant predictors of PUI; in the male group only, burnout due to homework was significantly associated with PUI. What is more, in the female adolescent group, quality of teacher-student relationships had a significant connection to Internet addiction; in the male adolescent group it was quality of classmates’ relationship. It is well confirmed that parental pressure on school achievements lead to stress and anxiety in students. Other studies prove that male students are pressurized by parents more than female students, however, female students’ levels of stress and anxiety were higher. What is more, recent research has confirmed different family related factors of IA such as family support, family conflict, family functionality and approaches. Perceived parental psychological control explained 18% of the IA level among students aged 14–18. In addition, peer pressure and perceived teacher support also were found to be a significantly related to IA. There is an agreement between researchers and findings about the crucial role of deficits in social resources in the developing of IA. Lack of “face to face” interactions with others may lead young people to look for them on the Internet. Numerous studies have demonstrated the link between loneliness and IA. The results of studies conducted among 300 high school students (M = 16.49) confirmed that perceived social support from significant others, loneliness, cognitive avoidance, and problem solving were among coping strategies which significantly predicted IA.  </p>
</text>
