<text id="autogum_academic_doc488" title="Oral Health and Its Associated Factors Among Older Institutionalized Residents—A Systematic Review" shortTile="oral-health-associated" author="Florence  M. F. Wong, Yannies  T. Y. Ng, W.  Keung Leung" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4132/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>Twenty-two of the included studies used a cross-sectional design, whereas three adopted a case-control design. The methodological quality of most of the studies ranged from moderate to strong (Table 1 and Table 2). The reasons for these studies not achieving a higher quality standard were often because of the following:
<list>
<item>The time for the research objects was not well defined;</item>
<item>Convenience sampling or a lack of sampling strategy/randomization was used;</item>
<item>No proper sample size estimation was calculated, particularly in reference to the nature of the dependent variable and number of independent variables to be analyzed and the subsequent regression analyses, including the control protocol for the confounders.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>The methodological quality of these studies may also affect the quality of this review. Because these studies were cross-sectional and examined the outcome measures at one point in time, the lack of a longitudinal design, randomization, and/or comparison methods may affect the validity and consistency of the results on oral health problems and the factors associated with oral health among institutionalized residents. </p>

<p>In general, the included 25 studies/series exhibited no standardized reporting style and some did not include clear a summary of the primary data or essential background information of the surveyed residents. As a result, only a small proportion of studies reported the dependency level, malnutrition risks, MCI/dementia proportion or systemic conditions. Concerning oral health and OHRQoL data, the situation appeared slightly better; however, the varied recording protocol and disease categorization criteria also limited the generalizability of the observations across different reports. </p>

<p>This review investigated the relationship between the aspects of oral health and the associated factors on oral health problems and the OHRQoL among the institutionalized elderly population. The results confirm that this population comprises vulnerable people who have poor oral health because they are relatively weak and dependent. The identified non-modifiable and modifiable factors associated with vulnerable oral health among this underprivileged group could be categorized as individual or environmental factors. </p>

<p>Individual factors are most likely due to limited physical functioning and/or cognitive impairment, leading to a limited self-care ability. Although the limited data could be extracted and therefore reported in this review, non-communicable diseases are common in elderly, institutionalized or not. The current report suggests the non-communicable diseases likely to increase physical inability and self-care dependence. Based on the evidence-based findings of the relevant included studies over the past decade, the institutionalized elderly population is at increased odds to have poor oral health with various degrees of dental, periodontal, oral mucosal and TMJ problems and poor functions due to missing teeth, inadequate replacement or poor dentures. Oral problems cause oral distress, poor function and a deprived OHRQoL. Chronic oral distress and poor chewing function could affect general health, such as through the increased risk of malnourishment. The outcomes of this review are comparable to those of the previous findings. Notably, maintaining oral hygiene is a decisive factor in good oral and general health. </p>

<p>The oral examinations were performed by dentists, dental hygienists, dental/hygienist students, trained ward nurses or calibrated examiners using varied protocols, with some not accounted for in detail. With that, the outcomes of the oral health evaluations were diverse and, oftentimes, non-generalizable and hard to compare. Nevertheless, this review found that poor oral hygiene in residents was probably due to inadequate teeth/denture brushing or cleaning, which increases the prevalence of dental problems and periodontal diseases or other severe complications. In addition, in this special group, the related predisposing factors were considered to be MCI/dementia, high care dependency and lack of access (except in a few North American institutions) to dental and oral care. The most common dental problems included large amounts of plaque, debris and calculus and moderate to advanced periodontitis. Periodontitis is a common oral problem in middle age or elderly populations, particularly in institutional residents. All residents were found to have plaque and more than 70% of residents had plaque covering one index tooth. Poor oral hygiene indicates a higher possibility of gingivitis, periodontitis, periodontal attachment loss and tooth loss. In the elderly population suffering from hyposalivation due to ageing or concurrent medications, caries of crown and roots, tooth loss and so on are common. Dental problems also increase the risk of oral health complications and general health problems. </p>
</text>
