<text id="autogum_academic_doc389" title="Groundwater Vulnerability and Risk Assessment in A Karst Aquifer of Greece Using EPIK Method" shortTile="groundwater-vulnerability" author="Anastasia Vogelbacher, Nerantzis Kazakis, Konstantinos Voudouris, Steffen Bold" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3298/6/11/116/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Methodology</head>
<p>In order to perform pollution risk assessment, vulnerability as well as hazard assessment have to be performed in advance. The whole procedure is displayed in the flowchart in <figure>Figure 4</figure>. Firstly, the four parameters have to be determined to apply the Epikarst, Protective Cover, Infiltration Conditions and Degree of Karstic Network Development (EPIK) method.  </p>

<p>Therefore, each parameter is assigned with category values, ranging from 1–3 or 1–4. For the evaluation of the four parameters of the EPIK method, various tools can be used besides. </p>

<p>In this case study, geomorphological maps were used in order to determine the Epikarst parameter (E). Remote sensing and aerial photography can be used for further investigation, as well as field investigation. Additionally, hydrogeophysical methods are useful and essential for the Epikarst determination and karst aquifer structure. For the definition of the P factor, the present soil, as well as geological formations covering the karst aquifer, are taken into account. Due to its practicability, only the thickness of the protective cover is considered.  </p>

<p>Therefore, geological maps in combination with satellite pictures were used, based on existing data. The I and K parameters were determined with the help of ArcGIS, more precise, digital elevation and slope models were used, based on the data available from the study of Voudouris et al. and Nikolaou. The determination of the K parameter is usually based on direct identification through the presence of caves or swallow holes. In this case study, further indirect methods, based on flow hydrograph analysis, tracer tests, as well as water quality examination, had to be used.  </p>

<p>Subsequently, ArcGIS Software was utilized for the preparation of single parameter maps (<figure>Figure 5</figure>). Accordingly, to its protective function, the parameters are weighted, and last of all, added up obtaining the values for the four parameters.  </p>

<p>The following Equation (1) describes the process for calculating the protection index F:

(1)

</p>

<p>The indices, α = 3, β = 1, γ = 3 and δ = 2 are determined by Doerfliger and Zwahlen and represent the weighting coefficients for each parameter. The indices Ei, Pj, Ik, and Ki represent the ratings of each parameter. The vulnerability values range from 9–34 and are ranked in four classes.  </p>

<p>Low values of the protection index F signify a higher vulnerability of the karst aquifer. Following Equation (1), and by using raster calculator in GIS, the vulnerability map was created (<figure>Figure 6</figure>). Additionally, a single parameter sensitivity analysis was implemented. The sensitivity analysis is a dynamic tool that helps the analyst to judge the significance of subjectivity components and provides essential information on the influence of the weights of each parameter. The sensitivity analysis performed according to Equation 2 using raster calculator within the toolbox of ArcGIS, is as follows:

<hi rend="italic">W</hi> = [(<hi rend="italic">Pr</hi> × <hi rend="italic">Pw</hi>)/<hi rend="italic">V</hi>] × 100

(2)

where:<list>
<item><hi rend="italic">W</hi> = the effective weight of each parameter (%)</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Pr</hi> = the parameter’s rating</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">Pw</hi> = the parameter’s weight</item>
<item><hi rend="italic">V</hi> = the aggregated value of the applied index.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>Subsequent to the validation of the parameters and the creation of the final vulnerability map, the hazard map was prepared. The hazard map in this context describes the potential threat of pollution and was produced with ArcGIS by taking Corine land use data and possible pollution sources into account. More detailed, the hazard map was adapted in ArcGIS, according to the present pollution sources mentioned in Table 1.  </p>

<p>The pollution risk map depicts the areas in which it is most likely that groundwater will be polluted, caused by human activities. The risk is very high, where high vulnerable zones and dangerous hazards come together. For this case study, the risk map was evaluated by overlaying the vulnerability and hazard map, following Equation (3).

(3)</p>
</text>
