<text id="autogum_academic_doc507" title="Efficacy, Safety, and Tolerability of Approved Combination BRAF and MEK Inhibitor Regimens for BRAF-Mutant Melanoma" shortTile="efficacy-safety-tolerability" author="Omid Hamid, C.  Lance Cowey, Michelle Offner, Mark Faries, Richard  D. Carvajal" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6694/11/11/1642/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Materials and Methods</head>
<p>
A search was performed of regulatory and scientific literature to identify sources of clinical data to be used to compare the efficacy and safety of BRAFi/MEKi combination therapies for the treatment of <hi rend="italic">BRAF</hi>-mutant metastatic melanoma. The full details of the literature search are outlined in Table S4. Four phase III studies were identified: coBRIM, a phase III trial of cobimetinib plus vemurafenib versus vemurafenib monotherapy in previously untreated patients with advanced <hi rend="italic">BRAF</hi>-mutant melanoma; COMBI-d, a phase III trial of dabrafenib and trametinib versus dabrafenib monotherapy in previously untreated patients with unresectable stage IIIC or stage IV melanoma with a <hi rend="italic">BRAF</hi> V600E or V600K mutation; COMBI-v, a phase III trial of dabrafenib plus trametinib versus vemurafenib monotherapy in previously untreated patients with unresectable stage IIIC or IV melanoma with <hi rend="italic">BRAF</hi> mutation; and COLUMBUS Part 1, a phase III trial of encorafenib plus binimetinib versus vemurafenib or encorafenib monotherapy in patients with <hi rend="italic">BRAF</hi>-mutant melanoma. Three of the identified studies (coBRIM, COMBI-v, and COLUMBUS Part 1), had vemurafenib 960 mg twice daily (BID) as a control arm, and were the chief sources of data for the comparisons presented here. Although the COMBI-d was identified as part of the initial literature search, it was not included in the efficacy comparison of the cross-trial comparison due to the lack of a vemurafenib control arm. It should be noted, however, that the outcomes in COMBI-d were substantially similar to those in COMBI-v. The key design features of the three included phase III trials are summarized in Table 5. To assist with the completeness of the cross-trial comparison, medical information requests were made to the registered sponsor of cobimetinib, vemurafenib, dabrafenib, trametinib, encorafenib, or binimetinib if any missing data were identified. </p>

<p>The data sources for the coBRIM and COMBI-v trials included primary and secondary publications of data, European public assessment reports (EPAR), U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) medical review documents, and the current U.S. prescribing information (see Table S5, which illustrates the data sources and cutoff dates for COMBI-v, coBRIM, and COLUMBUS trials). The data sources for the COLUMBUS trial include a primary publication, U.S. prescribing information, and Array BioPharma data on file. </p>

<p>The efficacy outcomes presented are PFS, objective response rate (ORR), duration of response (DOR) per investigator assessment, and OS. The assessments of the tumor response across the studies were performed using Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) version 1.1. </p>

<p>The safety comparisons were made using the adverse event (any untoward medical occurrence regardless of causal relationship) and adverse drug reaction (noxious and unintended responses with at least a reasonable possibility of a causal relationship) data.The adverse event data included the overall summaries (comprising all-grade, serious, and grade 3/4 AEs, and AEs leading to death, dose interruption/modification, and discontinuation) and the incidence of specific all-grade and grade 3/4 AEs by individual preferred terms per the MedDRA dictionary. All studies utilized the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) to assess severity. The coBRIM and COMBI-v trials used version 4.0, whereas the COLUMBUS trial used version 4.03. The primary source of data on adverse drug reactions was the available U.S. prescribing information. The additional adverse event data for the dabrafenib plus trametinib combination was derived from the COMBI-d trial. For the cobimetinib plus vemurafenib combination, the coBRIM trial was utilized. The COLUMBUS study was utilized as a source of additional information for adverse events for the encorafenib plus binimetinib combination. </p>
</text>
