<text id="autogum_academic_doc721" title="Subjective Immediate Experiences during Large-Scale Cultural Events in Cities: A Geotagging Experiment" shortTile="subjective-immediate" author="Gamze Dane, Aloys Borgers, Tao Feng" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5698/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion and Conclusions</head>
<p>
Research that analyzes the subjective immediate experience at large-scale cultural events and its relation with physical urban environment is still limited. Therefore, one of the contribution of this study was that its attempt to capture and measure subjective immediate experiences at a large-scale cultural event while taking into account the relation with physical urban environment (objective variables). Moreover, existing empirical studies on the subjective immediate experiences took place in restricted and small environments for a limited time frame of several hours. Therefore, another contribution of this study was that it demonstrates a large-scale data collection from 234 respondents by means of GPS devices and surveys. In addition to this, this study combined the collected data with secondary data sources for physical urban environment characteristics and weather. Since, with the approach used in this current study, it was possible to capture where the subjective immediate experiences took place. This enabled us to extract more data about the surroundings that could help to improve the organization of events and to develop policy on urban environments. In addition, as the subjective momentary experiences at cultural events are a relatively new subject, this study provided experiences that might support data collection in future research. </p>

<p>We concluded that geotagging with GPS devices was useful to collect immediate experiences, especially in outdoor environments. For indoor environments, other devices (i.e., Wi-Fi and Bluetooth) might be more accurate. Although using GPS loggers and paper surveys was proved to be useful, it is also demanding both for researchers and the respondents. Therefore, a practical tool such as a smartphone app that will enable respondents to geotag their experiences and to respond prompt surveys about the characteristics of experiences and underlying reasons can be more useful for the implementation of this study. </p>

<p>The idea of collecting geotagged data and combining this with other databases (i.e., weather, land use and surveys) appears to be successful, especially in the context of the Dutch Design Week in Eindhoven as this event provides a nice test case because the locational attributes of the exhibitions differ considerably. In a future study, more secondary data on the physical environment such as bike facilities, public restrooms, parking lots, etc. could be added to the analysis to see their influence on immediate experiences. Integrating more other data sources to analysis such as geotagged social network data would enable further investigations of affective states of experiences, and improve this study further. Finally, in the future, the routes that are taken by visitors should be derived from the GPS logs and integrated into the study for more insights. Especially, temporal mapping can reveal the experience hotspots in time and space. </p>

<p>According to the findings of this empirical study, visitors give more value to the positive immediate experiences than negative ones but the values attached to an experience increase or decrease depending on the temporality, physical environment and the weather of the experience. Especially visitors appear to be sensitive to number of exhibitions, distance to café/bars and distance to railways. These findings make it clear that physical environment characteristics should be investigated further in future studies. Moreover, the findings can help to shape the experiences at different locations. At large-scale events, usually prominent public spaces are chosen for exhibitions. The infrastructure and nearby facilities support the suitability of the public spaces to accommodate such exhibitions. However, the prominent public spaces will be known by a large public and after a few years these public spaces will not become better known. The prominent public spaces might even face problems of congestion, dirt and noise during events, which is not desired for the city, its residents and visitors. By using different locations in the city, cities would benefit from a more equal distribution of exhibitions in the city. Less prominent public spaces that have potentially suitable location attributes might be improved or prepared to host events. This will attract visitors to different parts of the city, which will become better known and reduce the spatial inequality in cities. To select such potentially suitable locations, based on findings, we advise to look for locations located at some distance from railways and close to cafes and restaurants or otherwise by adding temporary drink and food facilities. Thus large events can promote and encourage future visitation of less prominent public spaces. Providing memorable experiences in different locations will optimize the placemaking opportunities for cities and also reduce the negative impacts of events on cities and citizens. Besides, with this approach, negatively experienced places can be observed and turned into positively experienced places by implementing necessary interventions. </p>
</text>
