<text id="autogum_academic_doc336" title="Photovoltaic Roof Tiles: The Influence of Heat Recovery on Overall Performance" shortTile="photovoltaic-roof" author="Jan Wajs, Aleksandra Golabek, Roksana Bochniak" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4097/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. The Experimental Approach</head><head> 2.1. The Photovoltaic Roof Tile</head>
<p>
The subject of the research was a commercial PV roof tile, which consisted of nine monocrystalline silicon solar cells. Table 1 shows the basic data concerning its construction, while Table 2 shows the electrical data of the tested unit. </p>

<p>Cooling of the PV roof tile, which was heated by the influence of incident light, was made possible by placing it in a specially designed wooden casing. It was decided to use wood to reproduce the conditions prevailing on a roof (PV roof tiles, similarly to traditional ones, are attached to a wooden frame). This casing, together with the inlet and outlet, formed a channel through which the air flowed, cooling the back wall of the PV roof tile. To intensify the heat transfer and to direct the air flow, there were special fins mounted on the bottom. The PV roof tile was pressed from the top, preventing its shifting relative to the entire casing. <figure>Figure 1</figure> presents a 3D model of the designed casing together with the PV roof tile: this construction only reproduces a small part of the roofing. </p>

<p>As presented above, the PV roof tile, in accordance with the producer’s data, could be mounted on a roof in the way shown in <figure>Figure 2</figure>. The PV roof tiles were hung on metal hooks attached to the roof battens, and a steel cable reinforced the fixing. </p>

<head> 2.2. The Solar Light Simulator</head>
<p>
Since the research was carried out in the laboratory, without access to natural solar radiation, it was necessary to use a halogen light simulator (<figure>Figure 3</figure>), which imitated the conditions prevailing in the natural environment at an acceptable level. For this purpose, lamps with a total power of 10 kW were used. A supporting structure of the simulator (the spherical shape with a large radius) ensured that the rays focused on the examined PV roof tile surface. In addition, the use of many radiation sources (in this case, 20 lamps) was more advantageous than the case with a single source. Additionally, by adjusting the lamps supply voltage, it was possible to control the light beam of the radiation source precisely: this allowed for performing tests in a wide range of solar irradiance. The PV roof tile was 1.5 m away from the presented solar light simulator, which was in a configuration reflecting the position of the sun at the zenith: the light rays were the shortest, and the air mass coefficient (AM) was <hi rend="italic">AM</hi> = 1. </p>

<head> 2.3. The Experimental Setup</head>
<p>
The dedicated experimental setup was located in the Department of Energy and Industrial Apparatus of the Gdansk University of Technology (Gdańsk, Poland). It consisted of the above-described PV roof tile together with the casing, which formed a flow channel of cooling air with a height of 51 mm. This set was placed on a tripod perpendicular to the ground. <figure>Figure 4</figure> shows a view of the PV roof tile with the casing and the solarimeter. </p>
</text>
