<text id="autogum_academic_doc374" title="The Customer Orientation of Salesperson for Performance in Korean Market Case: A Relationship between Customer Orientation and Adaptive Selling" shortTile="customer-orientation" author="Chankoo Yeo, Chung Hur, Seonggoo Ji" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6115/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
As the current market environment among companies tends to shift from product-oriented to service- and customer-oriented, the importance of customer management through creating positive customer value is further emphasized. Effective salespeople play key roles in creating positive customer value by fostering sustainable relationships between customers and firms. These behaviors contribute to the sustainable benefits of their companies as well as positive relationships with customers. </p>

<p>A salesperson plays an important role in representing his or her company in the liberal market economy. Their role is even more critical in representing their firm when the company’s products are not particularly superior. A salesperson is also a key factor in delivering corporate images to customers. The salesperson is the contact point for customers to quickly identify changes in their needs, acquire and utilize customer information, and provide services and products that meet the customers’ expectations, except when there exists a purchase facilitator such as a digital signage and a different shopping characteristics. The salesperson not only increases customer satisfaction but also superior sales performance in a sustainable way. </p>

<p>Previous studies have been conducted since the 1960s to improve the salesperson’s performance and to explore what is needed for effective sales. As a result, many studies have shown that it is possible to improve the performance of salespeople through monetary rewards, such as incentive and salary increases, and welfare provisions and non-monetary rewards, such as education, training, and communication. However, there are other studies that suggest that if a salesperson is not able to provide good customer services, he will feel exhausted and emotionally unstable. As such, monetary or non-monetary rewards alone cannot improve the performance of the salesperson. Thus, more recent studies focus on customer orientation and adaptive selling as resources of effective and sustainable sales. </p>

<p>According to previous research, sustainable behaviors have been defined as a set of actions to protect natural, social, and human resources. In marketing strategy and sales domains, marketing orientation or customer orientation is a philosophy and an action plan that focuses on long-term business relationships. Companies conducting a coherent set of behaviors which focuses on their B2B partners find that a solid business entry barrier can be created by their satisfied clients. Furthermore, in the B2C market, brand loyalty can be strengthened by meeting the market needs, and all these efforts ensure sustainability when managing core business activities. </p>

<p>In the marketing field, as relationship marketing was highlighted, one began to pay attention to how to maintain and promote long-term relationships with existing customers rather than short-term sales-oriented relationships with new customers. The term, relationship marketing, was first mentioned in the literature of Berry, and since then, much has been discussed about relationship marketing in the service marketing literature. This relationship marketing has been more effective in the service industry when there is a high orientation towards customers and salespeople interact closely with customers in order to benefit from short-term exchanges. </p>

<p>Definitions of relationship marketing may vary, but the concept of relationship marketing is the same as pursuing mutual benefits that seek long-term relationships between customers and companies. Morgan and Hunt defined relationship marketing as the first line of marketing activities carried out to form, develop, and maintain successful relationship exchanges, while Treacy and Wiersema emphasized a company's sustainable competitive advantage and customer value. For this, they argued that customer intimacy, product leadership, and differentiation were necessary. Several studies directly investigate this influence of relationship marketing on business sustainability. In sum, the main purpose of relationship marketing is to maximize mutual benefits between customers and companies by having a long-term and sustainable relationship with customers. </p>

<p>Customer orientation is one of the major concerns to maintain a long-term relationship with customers. Salespeople focus on customers’ needs and desires and deliver relevant services. They acquire customer information and knowledge, deliver services to satisfy their customers’ needs and desires, and develop products and company knowledge. Several previous studies found that customer orientation affected performance of salespeople in a significant way. It also had an effect on salespeople’s behaviors in relational sales environments. </p>

<p>Adaptive selling is the ability of a salesperson to change his sales behavior while interacting with customers, or based on perceived information about the nature of sales situations such as correcting communication styles, content, and sales behaviors. In other words, adaptive selling modifies sales behaviors to meet the individual needs of customers, which strengthens the relationship between the customer and the salesperson, resulting in a significant impact on the sales performance. </p>

<p>This study of customer orientation and adaptive selling argues that these sales behaviors are formed by the characteristics of organizations and the psychological characteristics of the individual salesperson and directly affect the sales performance. However, research on the difference between customer orientation and adaptive selling for the salesperson is insufficient, and the two concepts tend to be considered as identical. </p>
</text>
