<text id="autogum_academic_doc579" title="Fault Ride-Through Enhancement of Grid Supporting Inverter-Based Microgrid Using Delayed Signal Cancellation Algorithm Secondary Control" shortTile="fault-ridethrough" author="Elutunji Buraimoh, Innocent  E. Davidson, Fernando Martinez-Rodrigo" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/20/3994/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Power Flow and Switched Reactor</head><head> 4.1. Voltage Source Inverter and Grid Interactive Power Flow</head>
<p>
In inverter grid supporting mode, there is power interaction with host grid which involves power exchange. The equivalent power flow diagram between the inverter-based microgrid and the host grid is shown in <figure>Figure 6</figure>, where <hi rend="italic">vi</hi> signifies the VSI voltage and <hi rend="italic">vg</hi> represents the grid voltage. Similarly, the inherent impedances of the inverter and its filter circuit are lumped together as <hi rend="italic">Zi</hi> while the grid impedance is represented as <hi rend="italic">Zg</hi>. The load current and impedance are signified by <hi rend="italic">IL</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ZL</hi>. These aforementioned impedances are typically inductive owing to the significant output inductance of the VSI. Nevertheless, this inverter impedance can be greatly influenced by the type of control strategy employed, and grid impedance is highly resistive in low-voltage distribution feeder lines. Similarly, the impedance (resistance and inductive reactance) of the grid is significantly present and taken into consideration in microgrids located at a long distance away far from the host grid. Consequently, this work put into consideration the line impedance of the grid. In line with the stipulation of the grid codes, only reactive current is injected all through the period of voltage sag. Consequently, the resulting compensating voltage is relatively in phase with the grid voltage. </p>

<head> 4.2. Switched Inductance: Sizing and Switching</head>
<p>
A microgrid is to ensure required uninterrupted supply of quality power to the local sensitive loads besides fulfilling FRT requirement of reactive power support in the event of disturbance on the main grid. In this work, this is ensured by ascertaining that all the sections in the microgrid are supplied with a constant voltage at a regular frequency. The proposed scheme in <figure>Figure 5</figure> shows the implementation of this requirement through an additional reactive power injection. The VSI injects a significantly high amount of reactive power in supporting the utility grid and sustain microgrid load voltages since the grid impedance is usually low. However, the aforementioned secondary control based LVRT schemes are significantly limited in voltage sag compensation. To tackle this problem, a PCC voltage moderation scheme based on PI control using the DSC positive and negative is introduced. Furthermore, under a strong (stiff) main grid connection, independent control of the point of common coupling voltage and by extension microgrid voltage is not sufficient for good power quality since the host grid imposes the voltage. Thus, control strategies may not be able to effectively restore the network voltage especially at the PCC. Hence, a switched inductance is inserted in series at the PCC to the main network during a voltage disturbance to increase the network impedance to independently regulate the microgrid voltage irrespective of the host grid condition. Thus, sustaining the PCC voltage at the rated magnitude. </p>

<p>The appropriate sizing and switching of this inductance ensure sustained microgrid voltage irrespective of a host grid disturbance. The inductance size is estimated in relation to the voltage sag in the worst-case scenario which must be compensated at PCC. It also depends on the expected current flow through the inductance under voltage sag. The balance between microgrid generated power (active and reactive) and the local load consumption determines the current flow (magnitude and phase angle) through the inductance during grid disturbance. In the proposed strategy of this work, during the grid fault, the total microgrid generated active power is commensurate with the rated local load capacity to limit the amplitude of the current flow into the main grid. However, excess active power may still be supplied to the main grid due to varying load demand and this affects the inductance size. To estimate required value for the series inductance, the load demand is assumed to be zero and the rated load power is assumed generated and supplied to the host grid. The phasor diagram of this estimation is presented in <figure>Figure 7</figure>, where <hi rend="italic">Vg</hi> represents the phase voltage of the host grid, <hi rend="italic">Vmg</hi> represents phase voltage within the microgrid. Similarly, <hi rend="italic">Xn</hi> signifies needed switched inductive reactance while <hi rend="italic">In</hi> signifies current flow across <hi rend="italic">Xn</hi>. The inverter voltage is therefore given by

(19)

</p>

<p>Consequently, the value of the series inductance is determined by solving the quadratic equation generated by making the <hi rend="italic">Xn</hi> the subject of the formula in Equation (18). It is therefore given as

(20)

</p>

<p>The inverter current <hi rend="italic">Ii</hi> is in phase with the current flowing through the switched inductance <hi rend="italic">Xn</hi>, hence angle <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> is calculated from

(21)

</p>
</text>
