<text id="autogum_academic_doc006" title="Small RNA Sequencing Reveals Regulatory Roles of MicroRNAs in the Development of Meloidogyne incognita" shortTile="small-rna-sequencing" author="Huawei Liu, Robert  L. Nichols, Li Qiu, Runrun Sun, Baohong Zhang, Xiaoping Pan" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5466/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Parasitic nematodes are pests affecting crop yields and quality in many important crops such as cotton (<hi rend="italic">Gossypium hirsutum</hi> L.), the most economically significant fiber crop. The most damaging nematode parasites in the U.S. cotton crop are root-knot (<hi rend="italic">Meloidogyne incognita</hi>), reniform (<hi rend="italic">Rotylenchulus reniformis</hi>), and sting (<hi rend="italic">Belonolaimus longicaudatus</hi>) nematodes. The southern root-knot nematode (RKN) <hi rend="italic">M. incognita</hi> is considered the most damaging in part because it occurs widely from California to North Carolina. Infection of <hi rend="italic">M. incognita</hi> to plant roots is intimately involved in its life-cycle. The infective second-stage juvenile (J2) enters plant roots and migrates to the vascular tissues, where it transforms certain vascular cells into multinucleate and hypertrophied so-termed “giant cells”, which become the nematodes’ feeding and reproduction sites. To transform and maintain the giant cells, the nematodes secrete effector proteins into the plants via the stylet in their mouth parts. The nematode will then become sedentary, use the giant cells as feeding sites, go through J3 and J4 molts, and develop into a reproductive female which will lay thousands of eggs. The infected roots will become gnarled; the feeding sites are colloquially called “knots”. Some genes coding for the effector proteins that facilitate parasitism have been identified; however, the regulation of such gene expression remains unclear.  </p>

<p>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are an extensive class of small (~21 nt) noncoding endogenous RNA molecules. miRNA-mediated gene silencing is a fundamental regulatory mechanism of gene expression. miRNAs inhibit gene expression by binding to specific sites located at the 3′ untranslated region (UTR) of the target mRNAs and degrade or inhibit its translation. More than 30% of protein-coding genes may be regulated by miRNAs. Thus, miRNAs play a significant role in the regulation of almost all critical biological processes in plant and animals; they act as regulatory switches, controlling reproduction and developmental timing, signal transduction, cell fate, apoptosis, and response to environmental stressors. Knowledge of individual miRNA regulation in nematodes has been primarily obtained from model, free-living species such as <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi> and some animal parasites. For example, the miRNAs <hi rend="italic">lin-4</hi> and <hi rend="italic">let-7</hi> function as key regulators of developmental timing in <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Lin 4</hi> controls early stage development in <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi>, while miRNA <hi rend="italic">let-7</hi> mediates transition of <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> larvae to adults. Aberrant expression of either of these miRNAs causes aberrant development and growth of <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi>. miRNAs function by targeting protein-coding genes. For example, miRNA <hi rend="italic">lin-4</hi> targets <hi rend="italic">lin-14</hi>, which regulates the timing of cell division during postembryonic development. The miRNA <hi rend="italic">let-7</hi> targets <hi rend="italic">hbl-1</hi>, which regulates developmental timing and affects locomotion and egg-laying. However, much work on the role of miRNAs in the major agricultural pest nematode, <hi rend="italic">M. incognita</hi> has not been accomplished. With the draft genome of <hi rend="italic">M. incognita</hi> available, it may be possible to identify miRNAs in <hi rend="italic">M. incognita</hi> and further study their functions in regulating reproduction, development, metabolism, and parasitism. Our previous work and that of others have identified <hi rend="italic">M. incognita</hi> miRNAs isolated from pepper roots (<hi rend="italic">Capsicum annuum</hi> L.) and identified certain miRNAs that were conserved in other parasitic nematodes. It is known that expression of miRNAs corresponds with developmental stages and can be induced by biotic and abiotic stresses. To date, there has been no study of the miRNA expression profile of <hi rend="italic">M. incognita</hi> concurrent with its infection of cotton. Additionally, there is no study reporting the temporal miRNA expression changes at different developmental stages of <hi rend="italic">M. incognita</hi>.  </p>

<p>Several reports indicate the benefits and efficiency of using RNAi-related strategies for controlling critical gene functions in nematodes, highlighting the importance of better understanding the process of small RNA regulation of gene expression in RKN. Our results have potential to be used in integrated pest management programs and together with biopesticides and basic substances. </p>
</text>
