<text id="autogum_academic_doc329" title="Secondary Flow and Endwall Optimization of a Transonic Turbine" shortTile="secondary-flow-endwall" author="Abdul Rehman, Bo Liu, Muhammad  Afzaal Asghar" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4103/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Optimization Framework</head>
<p>
Before starting the optimization cycle, the fillets of the vane and the blade were removed, as this study was dedicated to understanding the effect of a non-axisymmetrical endwall on secondary flows. All steps of the flow diagram are shown in <figure>Figure 4</figure>. </p>

<p>The first task of parameterization in the “Preparation” box is elucidated in the following section. The parametric geometry, the control points, and the performance parameters defined for the optimization objective were fed to the environment of FINE/Design3D. The parametric geometry was screened for performance evaluation with respect to the original geometry and considered appropriate for the optimization cycle because it was a perfect replica of the original geometry. </p>

<p>The foundation of the optimization framework is the database with the results of all RANS computations performed during the design process. Before the optimization cycle begins, it is always necessary to have a sufficient number of samples to initialize the optimization process. In this study, the initial database was comprised of a combination of the samples generated through the Latin Hypercube Sampling (LHS) method and random sampling method. The number of initial samples was more than 10 times the number of control points of the stator hub and the rotor hub, and these were fed into the approximation model. Steady RANS were solved for each of the samples and converged solutions were stored in the database. To reduce the computational cost, the connection between the optimization target (objective function) and the initial database samples was established through some approximation model that replaced numerical simulations before the optimization cycle. BPNN was used as an approximation model because of the excellent capability of non-linear mappings which led to the best reproduction of initial samples contained in the database. BPNN consists of two hidden layers in between the first layer containing the information of perturbed endwall geometry and the last layer containing the information of performance parameters. Using small random values, the weight and bias factors are initialized, and the information is passed to the next layer through a sigmoidal transfer function. Usually, the output vector provided by the network corresponds to the desired output vector in the forward training phase of BPNN iteration. The error between the real and desired value is back-propagated to the network input to adjust connecting weights and minimize the error. This process of updating weights is repeated for each training set until the weights converged in the backward process. This is why it is called a back-propagating neural network. BPNN in conjunction with the genetic algorithm was successfully used by Demeulenaere et al. for the formulation of single objective functions. </p>

<p>Therefore, BPNN predicted the approximate relationship between the design control variables and performance. The optimum solutions were found based on this relationship by using the optimization technique formed in NSGA-II, which was developed by Deb et al.. The result of every design iteration was determined by solving three-dimensional steady RANS. The result of each iteration was inspected and anticipated to be in accordance with the criterion of the minimization of the objective function. NSGA-II is a multi-objective evolutionary algorithm and searches for a set of optimum solutions called a “Pareto set”. An individual dominates another individual if and only if the objectives of the former are better than the objective of the latter. The solutions that were not dominated by other solutions form the “Pareto front set”, and the best solution was selected from among these. </p>
</text>
