<text id="autogum_academic_doc484" title="Icariin Promotes the Osteogenic Action of BMP2 by Activating the cAMP Signaling Pathway" shortTile="icariin-promotes" author="Meng Chen, Yazhou Cui, Hui Li, Jing Luan, Xiaoyan Zhou, Jinxiang Han" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1420-3049/24/21/3875/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Bone disorders, especially osteoporosis, are becoming increasingly prevalent as the aging population grows, and bone fractures also occur frequently. Osteoporosis contributes significantly to global healthcare costs, and the treatment of osteoporosis remains a great challenge. Thus, new bone anabolic drugs need to be developed for the prevention and treatment of osteoporosis. </p>

<p>Bone morphogenetic protein 2 (BMP2) is one of the most important growth factors that induce osteoblast differentiation and stimulate bone or cartilage formation. BMP2 has been widely used in the clinic to promote bone formation. However, the therapeutic dose of BMP2 is very expensive, and there are some life-threatening side effects that can occur with larger doses. Hence, it is necessary to find additional agents or methods for the improvement of BMP2 itself to intensify the osteogenic effects of BMP2. The combination of BMP2 and these small molecules can promote BMP2-mediated osteoblast differentiation and reduces the risk of its side effects in the treatment of bone diseases. From a clinical perspective, these small molecules that regulate BMP2 activity provide powerful tools for the treatment of osteoporosis and fracture repair. </p>

<p>Icariin (ICA) (the chemical structure is shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>) is the main active flavonoid glucoside from herbs of the genus <hi rend="italic">Epimedium</hi>; these herbs are used in traditional Chinese medicine and have long been prescribed for the treatment of bone fractures and osteoporosis as a bone-protecting agent. In addition to promoting bone regeneration and repair, ICA also has many beneficial pharmacological and biological activities, including neuroprotective effects; protective effects against atherosclerosis; antitumor effects; anti-inflammatory and antioxidant effects; and improved sexual function effects. Several animal and cell studies have shown that treatment with ICA can increase osteogenic differentiation and reduce bone loss in vivo and in vitro. The extremely low cost of ICA and its strong bone regenerative effects indicate its potential in clinical applications. </p>

<p>The cAMP/PKA/CREB axis is a vital pathway that regulates osteogenic differentiation and mineralization. Several previous studies have reported that PTH affects osteoblastic cells by activating the cAMP/PKA/CREB axis. Several studies have reported that pretreatment of human mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) with cAMP analogs, adenylate cyclase activators or phosphodiesterase inhibitors can enhance bone formation.  </p>

<p>In the present study, we combined ICA and BMP2 to promote osteogenesis for the first time. We aimed to determine whether ICA could enhance the osteogenic induction of BMP2 in C2C12 cells. We concluded that the combination of ICA and BMP2 could promote BMP2-mediated osteoblast differentiation in a dose-dependent manner. We also found that ICA stimulates BMP2-mediated osteogenesis by activating the cAMP/PKA/CREB signaling pathway. Therefore, ICA is a promising candidate as an alternative for BMP2 or as a promoter for enhancing the therapeutic effects of BMP2. This combination will reduce the risk of side effects from BMP2 in the treatment of bone diseases such as osteoporosis. </p>
</text>
