<text id="autogum_academic_doc044" title="Browning Effects of a Chronic Pterostilbene Supplementation in Mice Fed a High-Fat Diet" shortTile="browning-effects" author="Martina La Spina, Eva Galletta, Michele Azzolini, Saioa Gomez Zorita, Sofia Parrasia, Marika Salvalaio, Andrea Salmaso, Lucia Biasutto" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5377/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Obesity and related disorders are widely perceived by both the public and the scientific community as a major and growing threat to global human health; more than 2 billion people worldwide are currently overweight or obese, and obesity is associated with an increased hazard for a range of ailments, including type-2 diabetes, cardiovascular diseases and hypertension, multiple cancer types, chronic inflammatory diseases, dementia, and neurodegenerative diseases. All these complications lead to a shortened life expectancy and have a high economic impact on healthcare systems. </p>

<p>Lifestyle changes (such as diet modification, physical activity, and behavioral interventions) are the cornerstones of obesity treatment but maintaining a healthy lifestyle is often perceived as challenging. Alternatively, pharmacotherapy and bariatric surgery represent more “aggressive” interventions, and are applicable only if the problem is severe. Current pharmacotherapy for obesity relies on a few drugs that are approved only for patients with BMI &gt; 30. With the only exception of orlistat (which decreases fat absorption by inhibiting lipases), most of these drugs act through the central nervous system to reduce food intake (via reduction of appetite or enhancement of satiety). However, the use of these treatments may lead to severe adverse effects and a long-term prescription is usually not recommended. </p>

<p>A nutraceutical approach could be a useful supporting tool to treat overweight people, since the use of natural compounds offers clear advantages over drug treatments in terms of adverse side effects, suitability for chronic treatments, marketability, and safety. Here we focus our attention on pterostilbene (Pt; 3,5-dimethylresveratrol), an analogue of resveratrol that differs from the latter for the presence of two methyl groups. Its increased lipophilicity accounts for its ability to reach higher tissue levels in comparison to resveratrol’s. Moreover, there is no concern about its safety. Pterostilbene has already been shown to have positive effects in combating obesity and related disorders. In rat models of obesity, Pt reduces fat accumulation and ameliorates liver steatosis modulating lipolysis, lipogenesis, fatty acid oxidation, improves glycemic control by modulating glycolysis, gluconeogenesis, and glucose uptake, increases thermogenic markers in brown adipose tissue, and induces changes in the gut microbiota towards a healthier composition. Furthermore, Pt exerts its beneficial effects combating adipose tissue inflammation. </p>

<p>An interesting therapeutic target for treating obesity and metabolic syndrome is represented by beige (or brite, i.e., brown-in-white) adipocytes. These cells are an inducible form of thermogenic adipocytes residing in subcutaneous white adipose tissue (WAT) and are also found in human adults. Beige adipocytes can derive from white adipocyte trans differentiation and from the differentiation of adipogenic progenitor cells. They express a set of beige-specific genes, such as <hi rend="italic">Cited1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tbx1</hi>, but also have similarities with brown adipocytes, including abundant mitochondria, multilocular lipid droplets and expression of brown-specific genes such as <hi rend="italic">uncoupling protein 1</hi> (<hi rend="italic">UCP1</hi>) and <hi rend="italic">Cidea</hi>; similar to brown adipocytes, they are able to dissipate energy as heat. Induction of beige adipocytes (i.e., WAT browning) can be induced by environmental or physiological stimuli (such as cold exposure, physical activity, or thyroid hormones), but also pharmacologically (for example, with PPAR agonists), and could prevent or combat obesity by increasing energy consumption through non-shivering thermogenesis. </p>

<p>Various phytochemicals have been reported to promote fat browning. The aim of this study was to investigate the ability of Pt to do it in WAT. Its effects were first assayed on cultured 3T3-L1 adipocytes, and then in a mouse model of diet-induced obesity. To take into account possible gender-specific differences, both females and males were included in our experimental groups; a 30 week-long treatment was performed, to highlight long-term effects of a chronic Pt supplementation. We found that Pt diminished body weight gain induced by a high-fat diet regimen; also, glucose homeostasis was partially preserved, at least up to week 18. Interestingly, Pt was able to induce WAT browning, leading to an increase in the transcription of beige- and brown-related genes and of UCP1 protein levels, which, however, did not achieve significance. </p>
</text>
