<text id="autogum_academic_doc061" title="Effects of Sphaeropsis Blight on Rhizosphere Soil Bacterial Community Structure and Soil Physicochemical Properties of Pinus sylvestris var. mongolica in Zhanggutai, China" shortTile="effects-sphaeropsis" author="Saiyaremu Halifu, Xun Deng, Xiaoshuang Song, Yuning An, Ruiqing Song" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4907/10/11/954/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
Soil microorganisms, one of the most active components in the forest-soil ecosystem, play a critical role in plant functioning, improving plant health, the cycling of nutrient elements (C, N, P, and S), the maintenance of ecological balance, soil purification, and bioremediation. Beneficial rhizospheric microorganisms, which secrete phytohormones such as auxin, gibberellin, and cytokinin, enhance plant growth, root length, and leaf surface area, xylem function, photosynthesis, and stress resistance. In addition, beneficial rhizospheric microorganisms occupy space and trophic niches by competing with other counterparts and improve nutrient uptake, plant health, and growth by establishing interactions with the plant rhizosphere. In the present study, NMDS showed that there is no difference between CK and SS soil bacterial community structure, but other sampling showed differences during May and other months. At the phylum level, Proteobacteria, Actinobacteria, and Acidobacteria were common dominant species in CK and SS soil in three seasons (the relative abundance &gt; 10%). The abundance of Proteobacteria in coniferous forests was recorded to be about 29.5%, while it was only 25% in the previous report. The relative abundance of Actinobacteria and Acidobacteria in <hi rend="italic">P. thunbergii Parl</hi> soil has been reported to range from 24% to 32% and from 14% to 51%, respectively, which is similar to our findings. At the phylum level, no significant difference was reported in this study. However, of the 19 significantly different bacterial genera, six were classified as beneficial rhizospheric microorganisms, which could be attributed to the stability of soil bacterial community structure and the property of <hi rend="italic">P. sylvestris</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">mongolica</hi> sphaeropsis blight, which is host-dependent. A number of studies (national as well as international) have explored certain important measures for the prevention and control of this disease, such as the selection of trees suitable for the environment, young growth tending, tending felling, pruning and disposal of blighted needles, twigs, and cones, cleaning stands, planting mixed stands, and so on. Moreover, the growth and health of <hi rend="italic">P. sylvestris</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">mongolica</hi> can be enhanced by filtering the beneficial rhizospheric microorganisms and using them as biological fertilizers. At the same time, these also help to reduce the use of chemical pesticides and the problems associated with these, including widespread disease, polluted soil, weakening of plants, etc.. <hi rend="italic">Bacillus</hi>, with excellent tolerance to leanness, heat, and cold and the ability to produce phytohormone (auxin) could improve plant stress resistance and plant growth. An earlier study proved that <hi rend="italic">Burkholderia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Rhodococcus</hi> enhance the growth and health of <hi rend="italic">P. sylvestris</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">mongolica</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Bacillus cereus HB12</hi> and <hi rend="italic">HB59</hi> were found to be beneficial for pine growth and disease resistance. <hi rend="italic">Acidothermus</hi>, with its acid resistance, helps in the degradation of cellulose, hemicellulose, and lignin. In addition, <hi rend="italic">A. cellulolyticus</hi> degraded soluble soils and improved plant growth and biomass by secreting endo- and exoglucanase. By virtue of interactions with plant rhizosphere, <hi rend="italic">Rhizomicrobium</hi> produced auxin and enhanced plant growth, simultaneously promoting plant production of β-glucanase and protease, thereby improved anticoagulant resistance and plant health. Soil nutrient and enzymatic activity were enhanced after <hi rend="italic">Rhizobium</hi> sp. was inoculated into <hi rend="italic">Cicer arietinum</hi> Linn, which subsequently improved plant health and biomass. In a separate study, <hi rend="italic">Bradyrhizobium japonicum</hi> also improved plant and root growth after being inoculated into <hi rend="italic">Glycine max</hi>. Several studies have reported the successful isolation of mycorrhizal fungi, <hi rend="italic">Trichoderma</hi>, dark septate endophytes, and bacteria in the Zhanggutai area. In the present study, we successfully isolated mycorrhizal fungi, bacteria, and <hi rend="italic">Trichoderma</hi>, which had antagonistic effect on Sphaeropsis blight and wilt disease in the in vitro condition; afterward, the inoculation experiment was tested with annual and perennial seedlings of <hi rend="italic">P. sylvestris</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">mongolica</hi>. </p>
</text>
