<text id="autogum_academic_doc504" title="Prokaryotic Aquaporins" shortTile="prokaryotic-aquaporins" author="Huichun Tong, Qingqing Hu, Lin Zhu, Xiuzhu Dong" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4409/8/11/1316/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. The Conserved Amino Acid Motifs and Topological Characteristics of Prokaryotic Aquaporins</head>
<p>
The <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> water channel <hi rend="italic">aqpZ</hi> and glycerol facilitator <hi rend="italic">glpF</hi> are the most intensively studied prokaryotic aquaporins, and they encode 231 and 281-amino acid polypeptides, respectively. Resembling their eukaryotic counterparts, both AqpZ and GlpF are proteins comprised of six transmembrane domains (H1–H6), three extracellular loops (A, C, and E), and two cytoplasmic loops (B and D). Loops B and E are highly hydrophobic and insert into the lipid bilayer from opposite directions (<figure>Figure 3</figure>A). The two NPA motifs, located at loops B and E respectively, meet in the middle of the lipid bilayer and form a substrate-permeable channel (<figure>Figure 3</figure>B). </p>

<p>Sequence alignment of AqpZ, GlpF, and their homologues, including 94 AQPs and 103 GLPs, which are used for phylogenetic analysis, was performed using the Clustal Omega, and the sequence alignment of 15 AQPs and 14 GLPs, which are the most representative of the overall characterization of prokaryotic aquaporins, are shown in <figure>Figure 4</figure>. The two characteristic NPA motifs are highly conserved among bacterial aquaporins. Non-conserved NPAs are found in a <hi rend="italic">Segniliparus rotundus</hi> AQP, in which the N-terminal NPA motif is replaced by TPV, and the <hi rend="italic">Flavisolibacter tropicus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Segniliparus rotundus</hi> AQPs, in which the C-terminal NPA motifs are substituted by NPI and VPA, respectively. Residue-substituted NPAs were also observed in some bacterial GLPs, such as the N-terminal NPS in <hi rend="italic">Bartonella apis</hi>, NPI in <hi rend="italic">Burkholderia mallei</hi>, and NPV in <hi rend="italic">Janthinobacterium svalbardensis</hi>; and the C-terminal NAA in <hi rend="italic">Bartonella apis</hi>; SPA in <hi rend="italic">Burkholderia mallei</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Janthinobacterium svalbardensis</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Chromobacterium violaceum</hi>; NLA in <hi rend="italic">Leuconostoc carnosum</hi>; and NPV in <hi rend="italic">Corynebacterium aurimucosum</hi>. </p>

<p>Consistent with the divergent phylogenetic clustering and different facilitated substrates, AqpZ and GlpF possess four distinct conserved amino acid residues that comprise the ar/R region, which is also named the selective filter (SF) (<figure>Figure 3</figure>B). The ar/R region of the AqpZ homologues in bacteria is mostly composed of a Phe at the second transmembrane helix (H2); a His or Ile at the fifth transmembrane helix (H5); a Cys, Thr, Ala, Leu, Gly, or Val at loop E (LE1), which provides a backbone carbonyl oxygen; and an Arg residue in most species, but that is substituted by Val in six species, at loop E (LE2), which provides donor hydrogen bonds for water molecules. Based on the hydrophilic characteristics of the amino acid residues in the SF region, these AQPs are predicted as water facilitators. However, IAGV constitutes the SF region of an AQP in <hi rend="italic">Singulisphaera acidiphila</hi> belonging to phylum Planctomycetes, and <hi rend="italic">Isosphaera pallid</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Methylacidiphilun infernorum</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Opitutus terrae</hi> of phylum Verrucomicrobia; AIGV is in the <hi rend="italic">Neisseriaceae bacterium</hi> AQP. Because only glycine is hydrophilic in this IAGV/AIGV region, whether these AQPs function as water facilitators remains unclear. The SF of GlpF and its bacterial homologues is mostly composed of a Trp at H2; a Gly in most species, but that is substituted by Ile in five species, at H5; a Phe, Tyr, Ala, or Ser at position LE1; and an Arg residue at LE2. Overall, the SF amino acid residues of the GLPs are more hydrophobic than those of the AQPs, in accordance with the characteristics of the facilitated substrates. </p>

<p>Similar to eukaryotic aquaporins, both the N and C-terminal amino acid residues of AqpZ and GlpF are localized in the cytoplasm. However, the lengths of the AqpZ cytoplasmic domains are significantly shorter than its eukaryotic counterpart aquaporin-1 (<figure>Figure 3</figure>A), implying that the AqpZ protein is more hydrophobic. This could explain why the <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> AqpZ tetramers, unlike the eukaryotic aquaporins, resist dissociation on an SDS-PAGE gel. </p>

<p>The SF region of the archaeal AQPs is similar to its bacterial counterparts, but for GLPs, except for an Arg at LE2, the other three conserved amino acids are different from those of bacteria (<figure>Figure 4</figure>). For example, a Phe at H2, a medium-sized and hydrophobic Ile or Val at H5, and a Ser or Ala at LE1 are found in Euryarchaeota GLPs. However, in the GLPs of <hi rend="italic">Sulfolobus</hi> spp. of Crenarchaeota, a Trp at H2, a Lys at H5, and a Gly at LE1 are observed, and the N and C-terminal NPA motifs are replaced by NPN and NEA, respectively. Thus, it appears that the archaeal GLPs merge the characteristics of narrow SF and channel in the obligate water-type aquaporins with the more hydrophobic but less polar SF of the aquaglyceroporins. A consensus SF sequence to that of the archaeal GLPs occurs in some bacterial GLPs, such as those from <hi rend="italic">Geobacter lovleyi</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Desulfomonile tiedjei</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Kyrpidia spormanii</hi>. AqpM, an archaeal GLP in <hi rend="italic">Methanothermobacter marburgensis</hi>, has been experimentally verified to weakly facilitate water permeation, but not glycerol. Thus, archaeal GLPs could represent primitive non-specialized aquaporins, a possible ancestor of specialized aquaporins. </p>
</text>
