<text id="autogum_academic_doc586" title="Research on a Temperature Control Device for Seawater Hydraulic Systems Based on a Natural Gas Hydrate Core Sample Pressure-Retaining and Transfer Device" shortTile="research-temperature" author="Peihao Zhang, Jiawang Chen, Qiaoling Gao, Bo Xiao, Xueqiao Geng, Peng Zhou" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/20/3990/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
At present, a large amount of natural gas hydrate (NGH) resources have been explored all over the world. The carbon content of NGH is twice that of other fossil energy, making NGH an important potential energy source. NGH is a kind of white crystalline solid in porous media that usually forms and remains stable under the favorable conditions of low temperature and high pressure, that is, 2–4 °C and about 20 MPa. When the temperature increases or the pressure decreases to a certain extent, the hydrate will decompose. In the process of pressure drop, NGH in sediments begins to decompose rapidly. The gas production rate of NGH increases with the decrease in decomposition pressure. Previous tests have shown that gas production rate also increases with the increase of test temperature. Because of the metastable behavior of NGH, it is still a challenge to describe the in situ occurrence of NGH via core samples. To enable modeling of gas hydrate-bearing sediment layers as a natural gas reservoir, and to realize the large-scale exploitation, it is necessary to fully understand its geological structure characteristics under the condition of gas hydrate bearing sediments in situ. At present, because there is no feasible solution to detect and analyze the gas hydrate in the seabed under the in situ conditions, it is still necessary to investigate the gas hydrate morphology and formation mechanism via x-ray micro-computed tomography in 3D. In addition, it is still necessary to collect long-column high-pressure gas hydrate cores from the seabed, cut them into small sections, and transfer them under the conditions in which the pressure and temperature are maintained, thus obtaining the analyses of various physical and chemical characteristics in the laboratory. </p>

<p>The NGH exploration mainly contains subsea pressure and temperature core sampling, shipboard core sample pressure-retaining and transferring, and laboratory analysis of core samples. So far, the pressure and temperature sampling technology of core samples has been developed well. After the core samples are drilled from seabed and transferred to shipboard, the pressure-retaining and transfer system is used to perform some subsequent processing on the core sample. There are two mainstream devices that can realize these functions. The pressure core analysis and transfer system (PCATS), developed by Geotek Ltd. (Daventry, UK) in the HYACINTH program, can realize the following operations at in situ pressure: 1) nondestructively testing the core, 2) cutting the core into sections, 3) transferring the core sections into and out of storage chambers, 4) controlling the core motion for third-party analysis. The pressure core characterization tools (PCCTs) developed by the Georgia Institute of Technology, based on original sample detection system instrument pressure test chamber (IPTC), have more test chambers, such as a direct shear chamber (DSC), bio-reactor chambers (BIO), and a controlled depressurization chamber (CDC), having similar functions to PCAT. Both PCATS and PCCTs can maintain the NGH core sample at low temperature and in situ pressure; however, these devices depend on a rather passive method that must set the ambient temperature of the operation room to affect the temperature of samples. The method described above not only fails to react quickly and effectively to temperature fluctuations, but also keeps the operating room at a temperature close to 4 °C, making the environment too adverse for the operator to work with for long hours. In addition, there are few papers focusing on temperature control issues in core samples during transfer and analysis. </p>

<p>The first-generation core sample pressure-retaining and transfer device developed by Zhejiang University in 2016 can realize the functions as PCATS. Based on previous development, this paper considers the PMTCD, a part of new generation NGH core sample pressure-retaining and transfer devices, and analyzes the causes of temperature increase during the pressure maintenance of the sample. By designing a chiller and a thermoelectrical refrigeration device, the seawater flowing into the sample cylinder is cooled separately before and after being pressurized, and the temperature control effect is explored, effectively preventing the decomposition and deterioration of the NGH sample due to temperature increase during the transfer process. </p>
</text>
