<text id="autogum_academic_doc304" title="Facilitating the Energy Transition—The Governance Role of Local Renewable Energy Cooperatives" shortTile="facilitating-energy" author="Donné Wagemans, Christian Scholl, Véronique Vasseur" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4171/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 7. Conclusions and Discussion</head>
<p>
This paper set out to inquire in which ways LRECs contribute to the renewable energy transition from a governance perspective. A conceptual framework is developed for analysing the governance roles that cooperatives play in the renewable energy transition. The framework is built around three key interactions shaping these governance roles, between (1) LRECs and their (potential) members, (2) LRECs and the government and (3) LRECs with other LRECs. Based on the survey and in-depth, semi-structured interviews in the province of Limburg, the Netherlands, five different roles for LRECs for facilitating the energy transition could be distilled. These indicated roles are: (1) mobilizing the public; (2) brokering between government and citizens; (3) providing context specific knowledge and expertise; (4) initiating accepted change; and (5) proffering the integration of sustainability. These five roles are a new addition to academic literature as the literature review did not reveal any peer-reviewed articles that attempted to identify the governance roles that LRECs fulfil in the energy transition. </p>

<p>Mobilizing the public is the first role, where cooperatives play a role in actively involving citizens for the energy transition. The second role is brokering between government and citizens, here cooperatives play a role in translating government policy to the citizen level for implementation. Simultaneously the cooperative acts as a representative of its members, voicing the citizens’ opinions to the government. Third, providing context specific knowledge and expertise, here local energy cooperatives leverage their local embeddedness and personal approach towards facilitating the energy transition to provide context specific solutions. Fourth, initiating accepted change, here the energy cooperatives fulfil a role initiating projects within their communities. As the projects are initiated from the community and community members can have a say in how the project develops, there is a bigger chance that the project is accepted. This prevents any protest from within the community and builds support for a sustainable energy transition. And the last (fifth) role is proffering the integration of sustainability, here cooperatives take an active role is advocating for a more integrated sustainability approach towards the energy transition by focusing on factors beyond just energy generation. </p>

<p>Based on our empirical analysis, we distilled key factors for success for local energy cooperatives. First, they need to be locally embedded and try to be part of the community they are trying to serve. This provides the cooperative with unique knowledge, connections, as well as the goodwill of local citizens preventing potential NIMBY-effects. A second success factor is that the cooperatives often have regular and direct communications with municipal or regional governments, this allows them to provide their insights and push for change at controlling government levels, this is especially important if the cooperatives manage to collaborate with the government to conduct sustainability projects. While regular collaboration with a municipality enables local small scale energy projects such as improvements of home insulations or small arrays of solar panels, collaboration with regional governments have the potential for larger projects such as wind-turbines or solar farms. The third success factor is honesty and transparency where the openness and honest trustworthy advice that the cooperatives try to provide earns them respect and trust from local citizens. The final success factor is related to this as it is non-commercial interests, whereas many other energy initiatives have a direct incentive to sell a certain product, the cooperatives try to steer away from these biases, leading to more citizen acceptance. While many cooperatives are focusing on small-scale projects, a small number of cooperatives such as <hi rend="italic">Leudal Energie</hi> are working on major projects such as a wind farm, indicating the potential of cooperatives for contributing significantly to the energy transition. This success will be largely dependent on the cooperative’s ability to mobilize citizens, government actors and resources resulting from these success factors and handling the following barriers. </p>
</text>
