<text id="autogum_academic_doc224" title="Tailoring Celluclast® Cocktail’s Performance towards the Production of Prebiotic Cello-Oligosaccharides from Waste Forest Biomass" shortTile="tailoring-celluclastr" author="Anthi Karnaouri, Leonidas Matsakas, Saskja Bühler, Madhu  Nair Muraleedharan, Paul Christakopoulos, Ulrika Rova" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4344/9/11/897/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Discussion</head>
<p>
Lignocellulosic biomass residues constitute an abundant, renewable source of energy-rich polysaccharides that, when subjected to enzymatic hydrolysis, are transformed into oligomeric and monomeric sugars. The latter can either be processed through chemical and/or biological treatment towards a repertoire of high added-value products or, depending on their structural properties, to be used as animal feed or human dietary supplements with prebiotic properties. Many tons of forest materials are annually made available by the forest industry and these residual streams are usually under-valorized. Biomass from birch trees consists of approximately 43.9% w/w cellulose, while this percentage reaches 42% w/w for spruce trees, underlining the great potential of these residues towards the production of COS. It has been already reported in the literature that COS produced by enzymatic hydrolysis of wheat straw, comprised of 84% of cellobiose, showed a substantial improvement of the microbial consortium of weaned pigs. However, limited studies on production of COS from forest biomass have yet been reported. Production of non-digestible COS from forest residual biomass includes a complete process starting from physicochemical pretreatment and fractionation in order to obtain a cellulose-rich solid pulp, followed by controlled enzymatic hydrolysis in order to increase the ratio of oligomers over monomers, product recovery and purification and, eventually, evaluation of prebiotic activity. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to report the optimization of parameters for tuning the performance of the commercial cocktail Celluclast® towards the production of oligosaccharides and, moreover, this is one of the first reports that describes the whole procedure covering from the pretreatment/fractionation to the in vitro evaluation of COS prebiotic potential on <hi rend="italic">Lactobacilli</hi> strains.  </p>

<p>Lignocellulose degradation is a challenging process due a number of factors linked with the recalcitrance and complex nature of this material. The saccharification of the lignocellulosic biomass is hence limited due to these factors. Particularly, the hemicellulose and lignin removal, the decrease of the degree of polymerization of the cellulose chain and the decrease of the cellulose crystallinity index, which is also accompanied by the decrease of the particle size and thus the increase of the accessible surface area, are considered as major requirements for a hydrolysis process to be efficient. Therefore, to boost the hydrolysis of lignocellulose towards the production of prebiotic oligosaccharides, there is a necessity to overcome the difficulty and complexity of the depolymerization of this substrate. Applying an efficient pretreatment/fractionation method, such as organosolv process, has proven a promising solution, particularly by employing food-grade aqueous ethanol solutions. Combining an efficient fractionation process with controlled enzymatic hydrolysis can boost the release of oligomers over monomers. Synthesis of cellobiose and other oligosaccharides with higher DP is also possible through enzyme-mediated condensation reaction of monosaccharides, catalyzed by β-glucosidases. However, the reaction rate is quite slow, leading to very low oligosaccharide yields and thus, making the process not economically viable. Compared to synthesis, hydrolysis of cellulose-containing substrates, including lignocellulosic residues, is an attractive alternative. The main bottleneck of the process is the end-product inhibition, which is more severe in case of cellobiohydrolases but can also affect many enzymatic activities that are present in a cellulase mixture. Additionally, the remaining hemicellulose-derived products on the substrate, like xylan, also impact the hydrolysis rates of cellulases. Even though generally the inhibition is more apparent at high-solid concentrations it is also significant at low-solid concentrations and therefore can occur under the conditions of the present study. </p>

<p>To eliminate the adverse effects of the end-product inhibition, we studied the effect of buffer exchange on the increase of cellobiose yields. A similar strategy described as a multistage degradation process of cellulose towards the production of cellobiose has been also reported in the literature. This process is expected not only to alleviate the inhibitory reactions from present cellobiose and glucose, but also to enable the removal of unbound β-glucosidase in the washing fraction, while other cellulases containing a carbohydrate binding module (CBM) remain attached onto the substrate and continue the hydrolysis process. Moreover, we studied the addition of the β-glucosidase inhibitor conduritol-B-epoxide at different concentrations, which led to a substantial increase of the final cellobiose produced. Finally, modifying the reaction conditions and performing the hydrolysis at pH 7.0 resulted in a high ratio of CB:Glu. This is in accordance with data reported in the literature describing that activity of Celluclast® against pNP-glucopyranoside (indicative of β-glucosidase activity) is observed only in a narrow pH range between 4.0–5.5. By combining buffer exchange with addition of conduritol and changing the pH of the reaction, we achieved a CB:Glu ratio of 21.8, which is the highest among those reported. Ultrafiltration in order to remove the enzymes and possibly re-use them, combined with nanofiltration in order to remove glucose, conduritol and other low-molecular-weight compounds was also employed for the scale-up reactions. </p>
</text>
