<text id="autogum_academic_doc569" title="Improving Field-Scale Wheat LAI Retrieval Based on UAV Remote-Sensing Observations and Optimized VI-LUTs" shortTile="improving-fieldscale" author="Wanxue Zhu, Zhigang Sun, Yaohuan Huang, Jianbin Lai, Jing Li, Junqiang Zhang, Bin Yang, Binbin Li, Shiji Li, Kangying Zhu, Yang Li, Xiaohan Liao" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/20/2456/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Crop growth varies between/within fields owing to differences in environmental conditions (e.g., climate, soil, and water), management (e.g., fertilization, irrigation, and pest/disease control), and crop genotypes. Mapping the spatial variation of crop canopy traits and the factors affecting them is important for agriculture since these field-scale maps are helpful for precise agronomic management. The precise management is essential to improve crop production and light-utilization efficiency. Satellite remote sensing has been widely applied in crop monitoring. However, its coarse spatial resolutions (e.g., moderate-resolution imaging spectroradiometer (MODIS) (1 km), Sentinel 1A (10 m), Landsat (30 m)) fail to fulfill the requirement of precise mapping at the field scale (~cm level). In contrast to satellite platforms, ground platforms are able to map at the centimeter scale, but they fail to be applied in relatively large areas. However, unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) are able to solve these issues. UAVs are easy to use, have a low cost, and are able to capture data with a high spatial resolution (~cm); they provide a promising platform for monitoring the crop growth status and evaluating the results of field management. Multispectral cameras onboard UAVs capture the spectral reflectance of the vegetation canopy at specific bands. These remote-sensing observations can be used to obtain the leaf area index (LAI) which is a crucial biophysical parameter related to crop growth. LAI data can be used to quantify crop variability, monitor crop growth, predict the crop yield, estimate the amount of aboveground biomass, and evaluate the effects of field management. However, LAI retrieval methods based on UAV remotely sensed data must be robust and easy use so that the crop LAI will be estimated with similar accuracy to fulfill the requirement of practical application. </p>

<p>The PROSAIL, a radiative transfer model, which is run in a forward mode with appropriate parameter combinations (e.g., LAI, chlorophyll content, and leaf structure parameters) to simulate the spectral reflectance of vegetation canopy, is widely employed to retrieve LAI. The PROSAIL inputs (parameter combinations) and outputs (spectral reflectance) are used to generate look-up tables (LUTs). Thus, LAI, one of the PROSAIL inputs, can be retrieved by searching for the corresponding spectral reflectance in a given LUT using cost functions. The cost function is developed by simulated reflectance and measure reflectance. This LUT inversion method can reduce computational loads, lower the risk of converging to local minima, and help to avoid the ill-posed problems caused by uncertainties of the measurements and models. </p>

<p>The reflectance-LUT strategy, searching for the optimal simulated LAI by simulated reflectance and measured reflectance, is widely employed, particularly for traditional satellite remote sensing (Table 1). For UAV/airborne remote sensing, reflectance-LUTs are generated via multispectral or hyperspectral imaging. LAI retrieval based on UAV/airborne hyperspectral reflectance-LUTs can achieve high accuracy. However, the multispectral cameras onboard UAVs typically have only three to six channels. Spectral information for crops captured by multispectral cameras may be deficient owing to the limited bands. Therefore, the direct use of multispectral reflectance for LAI retrieval may be inaccurate. Generally, for multispectral UAV/airborne data, LAI estimation requires auxiliary methods, such as multi-angle observations for more vegetation information and combinations with other algorithms (e.g., Bayesian networks, artificial neural networks, and random forests). Multi-angle observations cost extra time and labor; machine learning requires ground sampling for the development of models. Therefore, these auxiliary methods may increase the difficulty of UAV multispectral remote sensing in practical application.  </p>
</text>
