<text id="autogum_academic_doc425" title="Laboratory Experiments of Drainage, Imbibition and Infiltration under Artificial Rainfall Characterized by Image Analysis Method and Numerical Simulations" shortTile="laboratory-experiments" author="Benjamin Belfort, Sylvain Weill, Marwan Fahs, François Lehmann" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4441/11/11/2232/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Conclusions</head>
<p>
The purpose of the present study was to test the methodology proposed by Belfort et al. (2017) in a more complex flow situation and a much larger experimental tank. Indeed, the internal dimensions of the flow chamber are 120 cm × 180 cm × 4 cm (L × W × D), which corresponds to a viewing area 90 times larger than for the validation experiment. As for the experimental conditions, in addition to the drainage and imbibition steps, a rain simulation was carried out on the central upper part of the tank, introducing true 2D flows. </p>

<p>First, we demonstrated the interest of the different steps of our methodology; mainly, normalization and then filtering according to a chosen radius. The calibration line was constructed according to a well-established protocol based on different drainage and imbibition levels. The confidence interval and error bars have been depicted to show the quality of the calibration. For the first experiment, the absolute and relative cumulative errors are very good, with global amplitude that does not exceed 8%. The monitoring of the cumulative mass of water leaving (or entering the interior of) the flow chamber also shows a good match between measurements and results from the photometric method. For the vertical line located in the middle of the tank, the representation of simulated water content profiles and those obtained from the photos are very close together. In the second experiment carried out, which included a step of constant rainfall simulation, the cumulative mass was depicted to validate the numerical simulation compared to the measurement. The constant intensity of rain was clearly observed with a steady state occurring in the tank for both the experiment and the simulation. Then, water content maps obtained from image analysis methods and numerical models were depicted. It appears that the photometric method did not lead to regular maps compared to those resulting from simulations, and that instabilities were present. Nevertheless, the trend of the infiltration front, even during typical 2D flow related to rain infiltration, and the values of the water content in the main zones of the domain show great similitudes. Finally, the photometric method gave satisfactory results even in more complex conditions, and this article confirmed the potential of our previously published methodology. Again, we underline the interest of applying the methodology directly during the experiment because of the specific structure of the porous medium and environmental conditions. </p>

<p>Our previous study concluded by expressing our desire to develop a form of benchmark problem for unsaturated flow inspired by Vauclin’s experiment. With these two experiments, we can say that this objective has been achieved, since we have a wide range of water content and pressure measurements, as well as complete water content maps. Now, all this data could serve to develop and test parameter estimation methodologies directly in 2D without having to limit themselves to spot measurements. Ongoing work would also consider heterogeneous domain and/or more complex geometries.
 </p>
</text>
