<text id="autogum_academic_doc202" title="Microstructure and Mechanical Properties of Gas Tungsten Arc Welded High Manganese Steel Sheet" shortTile="microstructure-mechanical" author="Geon-Woo Park, Haeju Jo, Minha Park, Sunmi Shin, Won-Seok Ko, Nokeun Park, Byung-Jun Kim, Yong-Sik Ahn, Jong  Bae Jeon" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-4701/9/11/1167/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Due to global environmental issues, the demand for cryogenic industries relating to clean liquefied natural gas (LNG) has been increasing. Materials with excellent mechanical properties at cryogenic temperatures are thus required for stable transportation and storage of LNG. Traditionally, cryogenic steel pipes are made of 300-grade stainless steels such as STS304 and STS316 and 9%-Ni steel, but due to their high cost, industries are requiring new cryogenic steel grades. In this regard, high manganese steel has been recently attracting attention as a new cryogenic steel grade. </p>

<p>For decades, high manganese steel has been studied for the application of automotive frame due to its excellent strength–ductility combination from the early stage of development. Recently high manganese steel was tried to be applied for slurry pipes due to its excellent wear resistance. In addition, as LNG ships and carriers have been in the spotlight recently, high manganese steel is receiving attention as a material for cryogenic steel pipes. From this point of view, studies on the processing technology such as forming, welding and heat treatment have been conducted in recent years.  </p>

<p>One of the issues that must be resolved for high manganese steel to be used in LNG applications is weldability evaluation for pipe manufacturing. In this regard, several welding processes on high manganese steel have been investigated, such as RSW (Resistance Spot Welding), GTAW (Gas Tungsten Arc Welding), CLBW (Continuous Laser Beam Welding), PLBW (Pulsed Laser Beam Welding) and FCAW (Flux Cored Arc Welding). Common issues aroused are (1) manganese evaporation may occur during welding due to the high vapor pressure of manganese, (2) manganese segregation and deficiency may occur due to high manganese content. M3C carbides can be formed in the segregated region while the epsilon phase can be formed in the deficient region, which degrades the mechanical properties of weld zone. (3) Mechanical properties may show anisotropy owing to the difference in grain size in heat affected zone (HAZ) and weld zone, and (4) residual stresses may also lead to property degradation. </p>

<p>If the manganese content in the weld zone changes during welding due to the evaporation of manganese, initial phase and deformation mechanism may alter depending on stacking fault energy, which may cause inhomogeneous microstructure and local stress concentration during deformation. Therefore, it is necessary to minimize the evaporation of manganese or to use filler metals of higher manganese content for compensating the evaporated amount. Also, the M3C carbide in the weld zone may cause deterioration of the mechanical properties, so solid-solutionizing may be necessary before deformation processes such as forming, drawing and bending. </p>

<p>Even though a few studies have been reported on weld properties of high manganese steels, fundamental research on welding properties of high manganese steel is highly required due to the recently arising industrial demand for manufacturing high manganese steel pipes. In this study, GTAW—one of the industrially applicable welding techniques—was thus applied to a high manganese steel sheet. This work focused on the welding microstructure and mechanical properties of a 24Mn high manganese steel sheet jointed by GTAW. The microstructural changes before and after the GTAW were analyzed and the resultant effect on mechanical properties were discussed. </p>
</text>
