<text id="autogum_academic_doc288" title="Experimental Study on Dynamics of Wooden House Wall Panels with Different Thermal Isolation" shortTile="experimental-study" author="Marcin Szczepański, Wojciech Migda, Robert Jankowski" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/20/4387/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The seismic resistance of civil engineering structures, especially buildings, is an important aspect related to structural safety in the event of an earthquake. Damages to building structures are the most common cause of fatalities due to seismic excitation. This applies to structures erected with different technologies. </p>

<p>Buildings of major importance, such as hospitals, facilities of fire brigades or crisis management centres are designed in accordance with the applicable standards. Methods of strengthening these structures, mainly constructed of reinforced concrete or steel frame (for example using the fiber-reinforced cementitious composite), are subjected to many tests, including experimental and numerical ones. There are many methods of retrofitting masonry structures, including methods for strengthening cracked walls using high-strength composite materials and a rigid adhesive with low deformability. The concept of increasing the effectiveness of secondary structural elements in the overall seismic behaviour of buildings has also been investigated; for example, the application of special mechanical connectors interposed at the interface between a multi-storey building and the glazing facade. The results of the study indicate that, once the input parameters of the connecting devices are properly designed, the glazing facade may work as an effective passive control system for the primary structure. </p>

<p>An increasing number of newly constructed wooden frame buildings has also been recently observed. The technology is popular both in rich and poor countries. Properly designed wooden structures are inherently well resistant to dynamic loads, such as extreme earthquakes. The current research concerning wooden buildings is focused, among others, on forecasting the occurrence of damage and monitoring the critical structural elements during seismic shocks. The research work includes both experimental investigations, including the shaking table tests (see), as well as numerical analyses. A number of studies have been focused on structural connectors, anchor connections and special flat bars and angles, the use of which results in stiffening of the whole structure and increasing its seismic resistance. The role of connections, with the lateral deformation of the light walls and with q-factor, has also been investigated (for example, see). </p>

<p>In addition, the low construction cost is one of the most popular and well-known advantages of wooden buildings. This is due to the relatively good availability of building material in many parts of the world and ease of assembly related to technical aspects (heavy equipment is not required), as well as assembly time and good usability parameters (aesthetics, easy repairs and modifications, good climate, etc.). However, one of the most important technological elements in a wooden frame is the application and proper arrangement of thermal insulation. Thermal insulation affects the lifespan and durability of the building, and defines the energy class. Unlike other elements of a wooden frame building, the results of research focused on thermal insulation are relatively limited. One of a few examples concerns a study on the seismic efficiency of structural insulated panels. The behaviour of wood-composite laminated frames under the dynamic loads has also been investigated. </p>

<p>There are some numerical analyses available, which indicate that thermal insulation of the wooden frame building can substantially affect the dynamic resistance of the whole structure (for example, see). The results of these analyses show that using polyurethane foam instead of mineral wool for the in-wall insulation of a wood-frame building leads to an increase in the rigidity of the whole structure. This effect is obtained mainly due to full connection between the polyurethane foam and the surrounding wooden elements, and a lack of such connection in the case of mineral wool. It has been found that the increase in the rigidity of the building insulated with the polyurethane foam leads to the substantial reduction in the structural response under different seismic excitations. It should be added that, in construction, polyurethane foam is known only as an insulation material. It turns out that this insulation material can also effectively stiffen the whole structure and improve its dynamic resistance substantially. However, the results of the numerical analyses described in have to be verified experimentally. </p>

<p>Therefore, the aim of the present study is to show the results of experimental tests focused on the dynamic response of wall panels of a wooden frame building with thermal isolation made of traditional mineral wool and polyurethane foam. Firstly, the static and the dynamic mechanical analysis (DMA) tests were conducted so as to determine the basic thermomechanical properties of the analyzed isolation materials. Then, the elements of exterior walls with two types of thermal insulation were tested under harmonic excitation for different amplitudes of displacement. </p>
</text>
