<text id="autogum_academic_doc693" title="Exploring the Benefits of Productization in the Utilities Sector" shortTile="exploring-benefits" author="Valerio Elia, Maria  Grazia Gnoni, Fabiana Tornese" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5864/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion</head>
<p>
Although the concept of productization has not been deeply investigated in the PSS scientific literature, which is more focused on the opposite phenomenon of servitization, this transformation in the service sector has several recent examples in utilities companies. The analysis conducted revealed a variety of PSS offerings, which can combine both the strategies identified (service standardization and addition of a tangible product) at different levels. This combination can result in different shades of productization, that we clustered in three different PSS integration levels. A summary is shown in Table 3. </p>

<p>The first is represented by pure standardized services. Considering the examples presented in Section 4, the proposal of insurance or maintenance services for the home electric and heating systems fall into this category, as well as the standard packages offered to customers in the mobile communication sector, the inclusion of media contents in such contracts, or the PAYT service in the waste collection sector.  </p>

<p>The second level is represented by an integrated PSS, providing both a standardized service and a product component. Some examples are the installation of photovoltaic systems, efficient boilers and air conditioners, and water purifiers, all of which come with an integrated service of maintenance included in the contract. Similarly, the remote control devices and smart thermostats, that allow a smart control of the heating and electric systems, as well as comfort and security sensors, are usually sold with a service package including installation and maintenance. In the communication sector, the inclusion of smartphones, laptops and tablets, or modem, web cubes and TV boxes, are typical examples of product and service integration, since they include access to the communication service and, more often, to specific media contents. The sensors for bin filling in the waste collection sector are another example of integrated PSSs, since their installation is necessary to implement a dynamic collection service. Finally, the integration of electric cars and charging stations with the electric service is also included in this category. </p>

<p>On the third level, we find PSSs that are prominently product-based. Typical examples are the sale of kits with energy-saving led bulbs, smart home kits, air purifiers and domestic composters. These products are not usually provided with a strong service component, but aim at widening the offer for the customer. </p>

<p>Another interesting discussion point is represented by the possible impacts of productization in the utilities sector on the three main dimensions of sustainability. While the impacts on sustainability of PSSs in general, dematerialization, and servitization have been often analyzed in literature, discussing benefits and criticalities, a similar analysis on productization is still missing. The main objective of productization is identified in the possibility to improve the value offered to customers, but other possible environmental, social, and economic outcomes are not clear yet. For this reason, we propose a first analysis of the main impacts that the strategies presented for the utilities sector can have on sustainability, summarized in <figure>Figure 3</figure>. </p>

<head> 5.1. Social Sustainability</head>
<p>
Considering a social sustainability point of view, the adoption of productization in the public service can enable the use of more “innovative” products and updated technologies for people who did not have access to them before, due to their high purchase costs. In fact, most PSSs including a physical product often offer the possibility to choose flexible payment plans that facilitate the access to customers. Typical examples are boilers, air conditioners, photovoltaic systems, but also smaller devices such as smartphones and tablets. The proposal of new business models based on leasing plans or the possibility for the user to pay in instalments, including the cost of the product in the monthly fees paid for the service, can extend the market to users with lower income. This can foster the diffusion of more reliable, safe, and energy-efficient technologies, improving the health and safety dimension in domestic environments. This can also be improved by PSSs based on sensors for comfort and security, aimed at improving the domestic quality of life. </p>

<p>Another social impact related to the more diversified offer of the company is the enhancement of its brand value, that can improve significantly thanks to the increase of the service level provided. </p>
</text>
