<text id="autogum_academic_doc373" title="Integrating UAV Technology in an Ecological Monitoring System for Community Wildlife Management Areas in Tanzania" shortTile="integrating-uav-technology" author="Lazaro  J. Mangewa, Patrick  A. Ndakidemi, Linus  K. Munishi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6116/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Relevance of UAV Technology in Ecological Monitoring of Small Community Wildlife Management Areas</head>
<p>
Sustainable conservation and management of wildlife inside and outside core protected areas, such as the WMAs in Tanzania, is largely anchored on reliable ecological monitoring data. In Kenya, inadequate ecological management of the conservation areas has been linked with deficiencies in ecological information, ultimately leading to loss of wildlife. The researchers call for serious ecological monitoring of multi-species and their habitat variables. This has an implication for the application of a technologically effective and efficient ecological monitoring system. The UAV technology, as the newly emerged remote sensing aerial platform, has significant potentials for sustainable conservation of wildlife in the community wildlife management areas. </p>

<p>The WMAs are a new protected area category in Tanzania formed on village land whereby neighboring villages contribute part of their land to form a jointly managed WMA. The establishment strives to ensure conservation and management of wildlife, biodiversity, and habitats on community lands. The WMA’s concept is a strategy for wildlife conservation outside core protected areas while supporting the National Strategy for Growth and Reduction of Poverty of 2005. This is also in line with the Communal Areas Management Programme for Indigenous Resources (CAMPFIRE) program in Zimbabwe designed to tackle environmental problems and help rural communities to manage their resources for their development. The approach was based on the rationale that many wildlife and biodiversity found outside core protected areas face many threats, including illegal harvest and habitats loss, particularly buffer zones, dispersal areas, and migratory corridors. The WMAs, thus, serve as strategic buffers, dispersal areas, and/or migratory corridors for the wildlife. These areas are jointly managed through the establishment of a Community Based Organization that will later be upgraded to Authorized Association (AA) status by the Ministry of Natural Resources and Tourism once they have accomplished all the requirements stipulated by the Wildlife Management Area Regulations of 2012. </p>

<p>Despite all the aforementioned conservation policy efforts to establish community conservation areas, problems and challenges still persist on their ecological monitoring for appropriate actions to address them. Ecological monitoring in the WMAs is especially challenging due to the lack of a quick, effective, and technologically user-friendly monitoring system that can be applied by both researchers and locally-based monitoring teams to generate useful real-time data as an alternative to the traditional biodiversity and habitats assessment techniques. These ecological monitoring gaps form the basis for this review to ascertain how much ecologists, researchers, and local communities can rely on the UAV technology for ecological monitoring of wildlife and habitats in the community conservation areas. Inadequately monitored wildlife corridors and dispersal areas, including those embedded in the community WMAs, result in the decline of wildlife populations. </p>

<p>Effective monitoring of animals and their habitats detect changes that are taking place and the quality of biodiversity, informing decision-makers to address the possible causes of the changes. Monitoring is the information system that deals with the observation, estimation, and forecast of changes in the environment, created to allocate the anthropogenic component of these changes on the background of natural processes. It is the “process of repeated observations (for specific purposes) of one or more elements of the environment according to pre-arranged schedules in space and time”. Monitoring data can indicate any need for correction of the management strategies towards achieving the intended objectives. Ultimately, such data is useful in improving conservation and management practices and the performance evaluations of the community WMAs. </p>
</text>
