<text id="autogum_academic_doc072" title="Integrated Solutions for the Water-Energy-Land Nexus: Are Global Models Rising to the Challenge?" shortTile="integrated-solutions" author="Nils Johnson, Peter Burek, Edward Byers, Giacomo Falchetta, Martina Flörke, Shinichiro Fujimori, Petr Havlik, Mohamad Hejazi, Julian Hunt, Volker Krey, Simon Langan, Nebojsa Nakicenovic, Amanda Palazzo, Alexander Popp, Keywan Riahi, Michiel van Dijk, Michelle  T.H. van Vliet, Detlef  P. van Vuuren, Yoshihide Wada, David Wiberg, Barbara Willaarts, Caroline Zimm, Simon Parkinson" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4441/11/11/2223/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Assessing Solutions for Mitigating and Adapting to Global Change</head>
<p>
The second group of models includes sectoral or multi-sectoral global economic models that are designed to investigate possible strategies for responding to future socioeconomic and climatic change. Outputs from GHMs and GGCs previously discussed are sometimes aggregated and soft-linked to economic models, used as inputs to provide physical resource constraints and supply and demand curves. However, the economic models add the important capability of evaluating economic trade-offs and synergies among multiple strategies for both mitigating environmental degradation and ensuring the provision of adequate and affordable food, energy, and water to meet future anthropogenic demands. Consequently, these models provide insights into possible regional and global solutions to nexus challenges and thus are useful for informing long-term policy and planning decisions. The inclusion of environmental objectives is particularly relevant to the identification of synergistic strategies for meeting multiple SDGs. The SDG targets seek not only to eradicate human poverty and hunger but also a range of other objectives, including the mitigation of climate change and biodiversity loss. </p>

<p>Both partial equilibrium (PE) and computable general equilibrium (CGE) models have been developed at the global-scale for exploring the response of supply systems to socioeconomic and climatic changes. PE models include: (1) <hi rend="italic">agro-economic, models</hi> which are designed to identify land use, management, and demand responses in the agricultural and forestry sectors; (2) <hi rend="italic">energy-economic models,</hi> which evaluate transformations of the energy sector; and (3) <hi rend="italic">hydro-economic models,</hi> which evaluate management and demand responses in the water sector. Integrated nexus frameworks have also been developed for evaluating interactions among water, energy, and land management, either through the linkage of PE models or the extension of CGE models, which endogenously capture interactions among global economic sectors. </p>

<head> 3.1. Agro-Economic Models</head>
<p>
Agro-economic models are useful for exploring the interactions between water and land management as they quantify how future food, fiber, and bioenergy demands can be met under water, land, and climate constraints and economic impacts. The main response strategies that are evaluated by these models are spatial re-allocation of crops and livestock production to locations with higher productivity (including inter-regional trade), expansion of managed land, agricultural intensification, and demand response. Many agro-economic models are linked to global gridded crop models, which provide the potential yields, suitable areas, and fertilizer and irrigation water requirements for particular crops as inputs.  </p>

<p>Global agro-economic models incorporating water constraints on agricultural production include GLOBIOM (GLObal BIOsphere Management model; linked to EPIC and LPJmL), MAgPIE (Model of Agricultural Production and its Impact on the Environment; linked to LPJmL), GCAM (Global Change Assessment Model, IMAGE (Integrated Model to Assess the Global Environment; linked to MAGNET and LPJmL), and IMPACT-WATER (International Model for Policy Analysis of Agricultural Commodities and Trade). Crop yields and irrigation are constrained by water availability within each agricultural production unit, which can be represented on a grid as small as 30-arcminutes. GLOBIOM and MAgPIE do not include explicitly a representation of water allocation between up and downstream spatial units. However, it should be noted that although MAgPIE, GLOBIOM and IMAGE make production decisions at high resolution, commodity demands, prices, and trade are calculated within coarser economic regions (up to 57 regions in GLOBIOM, 10 regions in MAgPIE, and 26 regions in IMAGE) (<figure>Figure 1</figure>). The fact that demands need only to be met by the aggregated regional production tends to concentrate agricultural expansion in the most profitable and productive areas, regardless of their proximity to demands. Notable exceptions occur when internal transportation cost is used for the distance to internal markets such as in regional GLOBIOM implementations. This assumption may be appropriate in developed regions with sophisticated food distribution infrastructure, but may misrepresent cropland expansion and overestimate the potential for adaptation in developing regions with poor infrastructure and a reliance on subsistence farming. </p>

<p>In terms of land use conversion, most global agro-economic models project a 20–25% increase of cropland by 2050 relative to 2005 when climate change is not considered. Most of the expansion occurs in South America and sub-Saharan Africa. However, the results across models are quite diverse as a result of differences in the potential for endogenous productivity responses, availability of cropland, and the ease of land conversion and trade (see and for descriptions of model differences). Further research is needed to resolve some of the underlying uncertainties that drive these model differences. Furthermore, developments are needed to improve the representation of localized water constraints, governance, and the heterogeneity of both agricultural producers and consumers in order to better account for financial and institutional constraints on adaptation. Finally, most global agro-economic models do not track the energy requirements associated with agricultural production, which will be necessary for examining the land-energy nexus including the response of farmers to varying energy prices. </p>
</text>
