<text id="autogum_academic_doc005" title="Novel Small-molecule Antibacterials against Gram-positive Pathogens of Staphylococcus and Enterococcus Species" shortTile="novel-smallmolecule" author="Marius Seethaler, Tobias Hertlein, Björn Wecklein, Alba Ymeraj, Knut Ohlsen, Michael Lalk, Andreas Hilgeroth" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-6382/8/4/210/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The increasing resistances of pathogenic bacteria are one great problem for worldwide health policy, because it means a threat of humanity. Pathogenic bacteria can be found in human surroundings, and drinking water may be contaminated with bacteria in developing countries. In the last century sufficient antibacterials were available to effectively treat infections with those various bacteria. Beside the standard antibacterials like penicillin, reserve antibiotics have been discovered from natural sources and were resynthesized by industrial companies. However, an abuse and overuse of those antibiotics is one of the reasons for the present crisis with resistant bacteria. In the case of viral infections, antibiotics are often prescribed. In the case of existing sensitivities of bacteria towards standard antibiotics, novel reserve antibiotics have been used in clinics. Therefore, bacteria with contact to those antibiotics like <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</hi> on human surfaces like skin developed early resistances. A misuse of antibiotics is also present in the mast of poultry. Those antibiotics contaminate the environment by animal excretions. Finally, industrial waste of antibiotic production is pumped into rivers in producing countries like India. Moreover, bacteria develop resistance mechanisms that allow the spread of resistance genes via plasmids, and also between different species. One other problem that contributes to the present antibiotic crisis is the fact that pharmaceutical companies recently announced that they would no longer invest in the development of novel antibiotics. The financial outcome of the development of life style drugs is much better than that of antibiotics. Antibiotics have to be cheap for a use in low-income or developing countries. Innovative but vague approaches to find novel antibiotics have been an influencing of the bacterial gene expression to modify the bacterial metabolism. Such a modified metabolism might lead to novel metabolic products which have to be identified and tested for their antibacterial properties. Methods to alter gene expression may be varied growth conditions or a microbial co-culturing of various bacteria or of fungi and bacteria. Other sources for the identification of novel antibiotics have been plants, marine invertebrates and insects or amphibia. Isolated antimicrobial peptides from such sources have long been favored. However, they still hamper with various problems like proteolytic instability, short in vivo half-lives, insufficient solubility and a poor bioavailability. </p>

<p>Alternative small-molecule antibacterials are rare. They own promising properties for an oral use, and are not expected to show problems reported for those antimicrobial peptides. Presently, such small-molecule antibacterials that result from synthetic chemistry are unknown to emerge as a novel antibacterial compound class. </p>

<p>We gained access to two novel structurally-related classes of small-molecule antibacterials by the reaction of substituted indoles and thiophene dicarbaldehyde. Therefore, various composed hybrid molecules were yielded from those indoles and benzothiophene. Hybrid molecules of antimicrobial active antibiotics, or antifungal drugs have recently been reviewed. They mostly consist either of two different antibiotics or antifungals that are connected by a linker like a simple carbon chain. So fluoroquinolone-oxazolidinone hybrids reached clinical trials and novel 1, 2, 3-triazole antifungal hybrids with 8-aminoquinoline or dioxolane have recently been reported. </p>

<p>Our novel compound classes were tested against prominent Gram-positive bacteria that are associated with severe hospital infections by <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Enterococcus</hi> strains. We identified first lead compounds with promising activities and confirmed the in vitro results first in the in vivo studies for selected derivatives. </p>
</text>
