<text id="autogum_academic_doc578" title="Quasi-Entropies and Non-Markovianity" shortTile="quasientropies-nonmarkovianity" author="Fabio Benatti, Luigi Brancati" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1099-4300/21/10/1020/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Physicality Quantifiers</head>
<p>The fact that, unlike CP-divisibility, P-divisibility is not stable under double tensorisation represents a puzzle within another approach to non-Markovianity that identifies it with an information back-flow from the environment <hi rend="italic">E</hi> into the open quantum system <hi rend="italic">S</hi>. In order to discuss this issue, we shall use a recent approach that has been developed as a unifying framework for all measures, called Physicality Quantifiers, of information flows. Indeed, whether the latter goes into the system <hi rend="italic">S</hi> from the environment <hi rend="italic">E</hi> or vice versa from <hi rend="italic">S</hi> into <hi rend="italic">E</hi> can be witnessed by suitable bounded functionals from all possible statistical ensembles of states of <hi rend="italic">S</hi> into the positive reals, that monotonically decrease under the action of Completely Positive maps. A statistical ensemble of states of <hi rend="italic">S</hi> is any set  of density matrices  and statistical weights , .<b>Definition</b> <b>2.</b></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Let  denote the set of all statistical ensembles  comprising n states and weights and let  correspond to the set of all possible statistical ensembles. A Physicality Quantifier, , is any Positive, bounded functional on  decreasing under the action of Completely Positive trace-preserving maps</hi> Λ <hi rend="italic">on the state space of the system S, in the following sense</hi>

(39) </p>

<p>The most used among such Physicality Quantifiers are the trace-distance (see (35))

(40)

and the extended trace distance

(41)

Both these Physicality Quantifiers involve two density matrices and thus act on  the first one being characterised by fixed weights . Both these quantities decrease under Positive (and thus a fortiori under Completely Positive) maps because, as already observed, Positive trace-preserving maps are contractive with respect to the trace-norm.<b>Remark</b> <b>2.</b></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Another quantity with the same monotonic behaviour relative to statistical ensembles consisting of two density matrices  is the relative entropy</hi>

(42)

<hi rend="italic">This expression vanishes only when  and it has been much used in describing entropy production in quantum thermodynamics. Recently, it has been shown that Positivity of  is sufficient to ensure that</hi>

(43)

<hi rend="italic">Though the relative entropy, being unbounded on , is not a Physicality Quantifier as in Definition 2, we will nevertheless consider it as such by virtue of its monotonic behaviour.</hi> </p>

<p>All the three previous functionals on  measure the degree of distinguishability of two density matrices and can thus be related to how the information about the system <hi rend="italic">S</hi> behaves in time: the argument goes as follows. In the case of unitary time-evolutions, both the maps  and their inverse maps  are of the Kraus-Stinespring form (4) and thus Completely Positive. Therefore, any Physicality Quantifier dos not change in time under their action:

(44)

Given a monotonically decreasing functional  on , one may distinguish between an internal information content relative to the systems <hi rend="italic">S</hi>, only; namely,

(45)

and a global one concerning the entire closed compound system  together with its statistical ensembles of the form , the environment state  being the equilibrium state from which, together with , one derives the reduced dynamics  of the open system <hi rend="italic">S</hi>. By subtracting from the global information content the internal one, one gets a measure of the information external to <hi rend="italic">S</hi>:

(46)

Since the dynamics of  is unitary,  is constant in time; then,

(47)

Therefore, if  decreases, the information content of the environment increases; this is an effect that can be interpreted as a flow of information from the system <hi rend="italic">S</hi> to the environment <hi rend="italic">E</hi>. Vice versa, if  decreases, the increase of the internal information is interpreted as an information back-flow from the environment to the system. This argument is at the basis of the definition of non-Markovianity proposed in, respectively, and based on the trace-distance (40), respectively generalised trace-distance (41). Both these approaches to non-Markovianity can be accommodated within the framework of Physicality Quantifiers in where one can introduce various degrees of Markovianity.<b>Definition</b> <b>3.</b></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">A physical map  is said to be -Markovian if  is monotonically decreasing in time for any given statistical ensemble ,</hi>

(48)

<hi rend="italic"> is said to be n-Markovian if all Physicality Quantifiers  on  are monotonically decreasing and S-Markovian if it is n-Markovian for all n.</hi> </p>

<p>The idea behind this classification is clear: CP-divisible dynamics cannot break the monotonic decrease of Physicality Quantifiers, by the very definition of these latter quantities. However, lack of Markovianity is not identified with lack of CP-divisibility; indeed, as we have seen, the trace-distances and the relative entropy behave monotonically also under the action of P-divisible, but not necessarily CP-divisible maps. Rather, lack of Markovianity is identified with back-flow of information as witnessed by the lack of monotonicity of some Physicality Quantifier of a certain degree that might be higher than that of the trace-distance or of the generalised trace-distance and might thus require statistical ensembles comprising more than two density matrices. </p>
</text>
