<text id="autogum_academic_doc732" title="A New Methodology for the Development of Appropriate Technology: A Case Study for the Development of a Wood Solar Dryer" shortTile="new-methodology-development" author="Luis  Bernardo López-Sosa, José Núñez-González, Alberto Beltrán, Mario Morales-Máximo, Mario Morales-Sánchez, Montserrat Serrano-Medrano, Carlos  A. García" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5620/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Summary and Conclusions</head>
<p>
A new methodology is proposed for the development of appropriate technology that allows satisfying energy needs in rural communities. Thus, the novelty of this work consisted in the integration of the technical, environmental and social aspects to obtain a device, which not only met the engineering required features but also takes into account the user opinions and needs in the whole process. The integration of all these characteristics is crucial because it contributes to a successful functionality and operability of the proposed appropriate technology. The introduced methodology included several stages grouped in a process that consists of two parts: (a) Identification of energy consumption or natural resources, and (b) development of appropriate technology. </p>

<p>The methodology is implemented in a case study for the development of a solar wood-dryer in the artisan community of the indigenous population of Pichátaro, in the Mexican state of Michoacán. The key results and findings from this investigation are as follows:</p>
<list>
<item>Three geometries of a solar wood-dryer prototype were proposed and analyzed with the computer software Open FOAM. All proposed geometries showed better interior heat transfer than the traditional wood-brick dryer.</item>
<item>A Life-Cycle Analysis (LCA) of the proposed solar wood-dryer was carried out as part of the methodology. The results showed that the new solar wood-dryer prototype has environmental impacts in all analyzed categories that are 5% or smaller than those of the traditional dryer. Particularly, global warming potential figures decreased by about 98% with the use of the proposed solar wood-dryer. Due to the aim of this study was to compare our proposed solar wood-dryer with the traditional dryer it was immediately displacing, we omitted comparisons with other devices in the market.</item>
<item>Based on the designed geometries, the LCA, and the considerations proposed by the artisans of the community, a solar wood-dryer was developed which has 20% efficiency. The design, construction, and energy evaluation of this device, incorporated the technical and operational requirements requested by the artisans in the community.</item>
<item>The functionality of the solar wood-dryer was checked to meet an identified need based on a diagnosis of consumption of timber resources. The dryer met the purpose for which it was designed, and it will be delivered to artisans for frequent use.</item>
<item>It was identified that the accompaniment of artisans during all stages of the methodology was essential to facilitate the construction and functionality evaluation. The information that they provided at each stage represented an exercise in co-design and technology development that covered their needs and motivated its possible adoption. Therefore, it should be noted that accompaniment is a key factor since we believe that technology should always suits the user and not vice versa. Finally, it is envisioned that the systematic way of developing appropriate technology should be energy efficient, socially acceptable, and economic and environmentally viable as suggested in this methodology.</item>
</list>

<p>
It is well known that the way to check the impact of the appropriate technology is through monitoring that evaluates the transfer and adoption of it. Therefore, the monitoring process will be discussed in a follow-up work.
 </p>
</text>
