<text id="autogum_academic_doc090" title="Mechanical Properties of Recycled Polymer Composites Made from Side-Stream Materials from Different Industries" shortTile="mechanical-properties" author="Anna Keskisaari, Timo Kärki, Tommi Vuorinen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6054/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Awareness of the reduction of non-renewable sources increased, and there is a desire for a more sustainable environment. Due to the tightening legislation in the European Union (EU), more resource-efficient and sustainable waste management is required. Polymer composites are one alternative for recycling materials or utilizing side-streams which otherwise would be discarded. A wide range of materials were used for this purpose, such as rice straw, deinked newspaper, and chicken feather fibers. One way to classify fillers in polymers is to divide them into two classes: organic and inorganic. Several incentives guided the utilization of these waste materials. Mineral fillers were used to decrease the price of plastic, and natural fibers as fillers in plastic enhance material properties and give a more environmentally friendly characteristic to the material. Mineral fillers increase the stiffness and the flame retardancy of plastic, for example. Using recycled materials instead of virgin ones makes the use of the filler even more meaningful, from the environmental point of view. </p>

<p>The study of using different waste fractions as fillers for polymers increased in recent years. Different materials from various fields were tested. One of the most often studied areas is natural fiber polymer composites. Various types of fibers from different parts of a plant can be used as a filler. Several studies were conducted, for example, on paper mill sludge that was utilized as a filler in a polymer. Primary sludge can also be utilized as a material for energy production. Recycled cellulose was also a topic of research. </p>

<p>One group of materials utilized in this study is side-streams from the insulation industry. Mineral-based materials as fillers in polymer composites are not studied as much as natural fiber products. Usually, mineral wool is used as a recycled material, not a virgin one as in this case. For high-quality raw material, mineral wool has to be separated properly from other construction and demolition (C&amp;D) waste. Väntsi and Kärki used recycled mineral wood as a filler in a wood–plastic composite. Rock wool waste was used in the manufacturing of a cement-based composite. The last material used in this study was waste from a powder coating factory. This type of material is quite a new area of research, but Souza et al. studied composite manufacturing using ink waste as an adhesive. With these materials, it was possible to manufacture more environmentally friendly products, without using virgin materials as much.  </p>

<p>In this study, six different composites were manufactured by using fillers from industrial side-streams. The purpose of the study was to investigate how the selected filler materials change the mechanical properties of polymer composites. Materials selected for this study are underutilized; thus, this research has the potential to bring new application fields for materials that are not effectively used at this moment. Side-streams from different industries create a steady material flow with uniform quality that has the potential to be utilized as a filler in polymer composites.  </p>
</text>
