<text id="autogum_academic_doc723" title="Assisting Sustainable Entrepreneurial Activities Through the Analysis of Mobile IT Services’ Success and Failure Factors" shortTile="assisting-sustainable" author="Chang  Hee Yoon, Francis  Joseph Costello, Cheong Kim" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5694/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Research Methodology</head><head> 3.1. Research Model</head>
<p>
On the basis of previous research, we now discuss the definitions of success and failure and how to measure them. The number and variety of recent IT services provide many cases where success and failure can be clearly determined, whereas it is difficult to make individual assessments uniformly. Therefore, when determining the success or failure of IT services through participants using a questionnaire, the constructs were measured considering the mean and using t-tests to determine any significant difference between the groups investigated within this study. Three subjective evaluation factors (i.e., interests established by the research hypothesis, ecosystem establishment, and technology completeness) for merchant and two-sided models, which are separated from service and platform businesses, were applied to success and failure analyses via logistic regression of four objective evaluation factors (i.e., scale of companies examined separately, PC interworking, consumer billing, and introduction of new technologies). Our research model is presented in <figure>Figure 4</figure>. </p>

<head> 3.2. IT Service Case Selection</head>
<p>
For this study, a total of 98 cases of ICT convergence were obtained from 65 ICT experts from 17 February to 18 February, 2018. Of these 98 cases, 46 were cases of success, and 52 were cases of failure. These ICT convergence cases were re-classified as global and regional releases and were selected as original Korean IT services. The final 22 IT service cases, as Table 1 shows, were selected by removing services that were too old to be independently verified and whereby system units were difficult to evaluate individually for success and failure factors (see Appendix A and Appendix D for detailed information of the 22 IT service cases). </p>

<p>Furthermore, although some of the services within the sample were well known in the market via advertising and media coverage, in some cases, the services were unfamiliar due to the fact they had originated from start-ups. Additionally, in attempting to choose appropriate cases for analysis, the final selection of services was not performed on a purely market recognition basis. Instead, the services were chosen on the basis of the fact they were established through an application, with some in the process of expanding their service functionality through PC-based platforms. </p>

<head> 3.3. Survey to IT Entrepreneurs</head>
<p>
A survey was submitted to entrepreneurs who had experience in similar fields of this study and who showed an interest in creating their own IT start-up. To assist participants who were lacking awareness of IT services, the survey introduced each service and their assessments of success and failure. By displaying these descriptions of the IT services, we were able to increase the understanding by introducing a detailed overview of the business models and operating methods for each service selected. In addition, we introduced detailed cases, demos, and competitive services to participants when they were unfamiliar with the presented service. Individual surveys conducted simultaneously led to a seven-point evaluation of a total of three categories: establishing interests selected as factors for success and failure of mobile IT services for this study; establishing ecosystems; and completing technologies. A pre-arranged questionnaire containing survey items separated into each service was distributed to the participants. The survey participants’ successes and failures were subsequently judged, and, with the survey items, the participants were asked to list factors of success and failure for the services they chose. When introducing each service, the results of separate judgments about success and failure were not considered, so that the actual operational results would not be reflected in the survey results of the participants. </p>
</text>
