<text id="autogum_academic_doc031" title="Do EEG and Startle Reflex Modulation Vary with Self-Reported Aggression in Response to Violent Images?" shortTile="eeg-startle-reflex" author="Sajeev Kunaharan, Sean Halpin, Thiagarajan Sitharthan, Peter Walla" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3425/9/11/298/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
The present study aimed to determine whether a particular sub-section of the general population, characterised only by their self-reported aggressive tendencies, differed in their conscious evaluation of emotional stimuli compared to objectively measured neurophysiological reaction to the same stimuli. By utilising a triangulation approach incorporating explicit rating measures (which require conscious, evaluative reasoning and responding via cortical brain processing), SRM (which is a measure of raw, affective information processing and is sensitive to sub-cortical brain processes), and EEG (which measures cortical graded potential changes of pyramidal cells), we were able to demonstrate that our participants differed in their subjective rating and their objectively measured neural responses to affective stimuli. </p>

<p>Event-related potential analysis showed significant group effects related to differences between the ‘pleasant’ and ‘violent’ emotion conditions across both hemispheres between both groups. Upon visual inspection of the curves in the frontal areas of the brain, the ERPs of the ‘pleasant’ and ‘violent’ emotion categories appear to follow a similar trajectory in the high aggression group which then separates in the left hemisphere approximately 800 ms post-stimulus onset. In the low aggression group, both curves (‘pleasant’ and ‘violent’) appear to follow a similar trajectory across both hemispheres but remain separate throughout the 1000 ms epoch studied. Much like the results obtained in the present study, Gagnon et al. showed a similar response among aggressive individuals who responded with a larger N400 than their non-aggressive controls when both groups were presented with a critical word which violated a hostile expectation. The increased negative attenuation of the ERP amplitudes, noted in later time periods of the high aggression group to images portraying violence, may be due to increased attention payed to the image. Since individuals who are low aggressors are perhaps less likely to view violent images, the larger amplitude of their ERP is perhaps indicative of an increased motivational relevance due to the perception of threatening stimuli. Though not statistically significant, visual inspection of the curves obtained also showed that the high aggression group showed a decreased frontal response to the ‘violent’ images. These results can be compared with a study performed by Lu et al. who demonstrated that highly aggressive individuals in their study reacted to threat-based stimuli (fearful faces) with a decreased fronto-central response compared with individuals with low aggression. The authors stated that this immediate reaction to threat-based stimuli was due to a fearful face representing a threat-based stimulus which requires a quick response. Heading more posteriorly to central and parietal sites, similar trends between the ‘pleasant’ and ‘violent’ emotion conditions can be seen. The ERP of the ‘violent’ emotion category appears to be more attenuated in the high aggressive group and so follows a similar trajectory to the ERP curve of the ‘pleasant’ condition, whereas the ERP curves of the ‘violent’ and ‘pleasant’ conditions remain separate in the low aggressive group. Although interesting, these findings are difficult to compare with previous studies on aggression. The vast majority of studies previously performed focused largely on the P300 component. They overwhelmingly show that highly aggressive individuals tend to show a more inhibited (smaller amplitude) P300 response than low aggressive individuals. These studies posit the idea that the smaller P300 component may be due to cognitive deficits or be associated with increases of aggression. Wang et al. stated that this effect may imply a reduction in brain activity which has been known to reflect activation of the averse motivational system which can be linked to aggressive behaviour. Present findings found statistically meaningful differences at the P300 component. Furthermore, rather prolonged statistically meaningful results were found post 300 ms. An explanation of the observed findings may be that, changes were seen in later time periods due to variations in meaningfulness of the displayed emotion images between the groups. Alternatively, as a consequence of life experience, high aggressors may be somewhat less responsive to violent stimuli, due to desensitisation effects. This may prevent them in engaging cognitively with the stimulus, resulting in the observed attenuated ERP amplitudes. </p>
</text>
