<text id="autogum_academic_doc255" title="Numerical Simulation of a Scanning Illumination System for Deep Tissue Fluorescence Imaging" shortTile="numerical-simulation" author="Qimei Zhang, Anna  M. Grabowska, Philip  A. Clarke, Stephen  P. Morgan" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2313-433X/5/11/83/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussions</head>
<p>
Much attention has been focused on developing novel probes emitting light in the NIR spectral window, because tissue has minimal absorbance in the wavelength range between 650 nm and 1000 nm, allowing for deep penetration depth and higher sensitivity. The findings in this paper suggest that imaging at near-infrared wavelength can indeed obtain higher levels of surface radiance compared with visible light at the same depth, and near-infrared light has better penetration depth. However, fluorophores at the near-infrared window can degrade spatial resolution mainly due to lower absorption. This is because the lower absorption means that photons that have propagated on longer paths are not heavily attenuated. For example, for transmission mode imaging of full-field illumination system at z =  mm, the FWHM is  mm instead of  mm if using fluorescent probes with 1000 nm emission wavelength rather than 620 nm emission wavelength. Therefore, there is a compromise between the penetration depth and the spatial resolution. Only absorption due to blood components which are the dominant factors is considered in the simulation. The effect of the other absorbers such as water, fat and melanosome is to increase slightly the absorption coefficient depending on the specific tissue. Different tissues have different absorbing chromophores and concentration therefore have different . However, a range of  and  are simulated, and the effect of the other absorbers is only a shift of the simulated  to other values, which will not affect the overall conclusions of this work. </p>

<p>Improvement of spatial resolution can be obtained by using a scanning system, which has a much better spatial resolution than the full-field illumination system. For example, for the case when the targets are located in the middle of the phantom, the FWHM obtained by the full-field illumination system is 8 mm, whereas that obtained by the scanning system is 6 mm which is 25% lower. The spatial probability distribution of photons entering tissue at a source location, scattering through the tissue, and being emitted at a particular detector location, defines the spatial sensitivity profile for that source-detector pair. A typical sensitivity profile can be found in Ref.. The sensitivity profile can be used to indicate spatial resolution—targets located at narrower position of the profile can be better distinguished. The excitation light of the full-field illumination system has a large field ( 20 mm radius), therefore the closer the targets are to the detector, the narrower the profile and the better the spatial resolution, as shown in <figure>Figure 7</figure>a,b. For the scanning system, because a point excitation source is used, the sensitivity profile is narrower and the spatial resolution is better. Such capabilities can now be found in current imaging platforms, such as the IVIS Spectrum (Perkin Elmer), but these at present do not include spatial filtering at the detector plane. A similar conclusion that a scanning system provides better spatial resolution than wide field illumination system is found by Fantoni. However, in this study, a line scanning method is used and the wavelength range considered is much smaller. </p>

<p>It was found that for the scanning system, the same spatial resolution is obtained for reflection mode and transmission mode. The emission wavelength of the fluorescent probe also has no effect on the spatial resolution. The spatial resolution is only dependent on the distance between the excitation source and the targets. This is because the  of emission works as a scaling factor and only affects the photon fluence detected; the FWHM remains the same. The increase of  changes the exit position of the emitted photons, but due to an integrated detector (  mm in radius) applied in this case, the spatial resolution stays the same. The spatial resolution depends on the spatial light distribution at the object plane which depends on the optical parameters of excitation rather than emission. </p>

<p>In the simulation, the resolution is estimated as the average value of the FWHMs of the two fluorescent targets with an arbitrary separation of 16 mm. A change of the separation will not influence on the resolution. To demonstrate that this method of estimating resolution is accurate within the Born approximation, the light distribution of the two fluorescent targets are calculated separately and then superimposed, followed by an image of two targets. The fluorescence light distribution of the first target, the second target, the superposition of the two images of the single targets and the fluorescence light distribution of the two targets are shown in <figure>Figure A3</figure> in Appendix A. It can be seen that the cases of the superposition and the two targets are very close to each other. The resolution obtained for the linear superposition case is  mm. Therefore, the coordinates of the targets in the combined image are chosen as  and , respectively. It was found that the FWHMs of the light distribution of the two points are  mm and  mm, respectively, and the overlapping position of the two points are at their FWHMs. This suggests that the resolution of the image is indeed close to  mm. </p>
</text>
