<text id="autogum_academic_doc490" title="A Data-Independent Methodology for the Structural Characterization of Microcystins and Anabaenopeptins Leading to the Identification of Four New Congeners" shortTile="dataindependent-methodology" author="Audrey Roy-Lachapelle, Morgan Solliec, Sébastien Sauvé, Christian Gagnon" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6651/11/11/619/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Eutrophication of natural water sources is closely linked to the distinctive appearance of massive and episodic proliferations of cyanobacteria. These prokaryotic organisms do not systematically carry the expressed genes for toxin production, yet about 40 of the 150 cyanobacteria genera do possess these genes. For more than two decades, microcystins (MCs) have been the main family of cyanopeptides extensively studied. This dominance has been triggered by tragic incidents, such as in a Brazilian hospital in 1996, where 52 patients undergoing dialysis succumbed to liver failure caused by contaminated water with MCs. Following this, the World Health Organization (WHO) has suggested regulation levels for MC-LR in drinking water (1 µg L−1) which was extended by the US EPA to MC-LR equivalents to include more congeners and other cyanotoxins. However, several families of cyanopeptides have long been identified along with MCs isolated from common cyanobacteria, i.e., <hi rend="italic">Microcystis</hi> sp. Amongst them, cyanopeptolins, anabaenopeptins (APs), aerucyclamides, aeruginosines, and microginins are to mention when specifying the dominant families. Still, the high diversity of produced congeners from each family and the little information known about factors and mechanisms linked to their production greatly complicates their study. </p>

<p>Potential cyanopeptides toxicity critically depends on the variants structure, but is still misunderstood and poorly documented. MCs are hepatotoxic and readily accumulated in the liver from the specific binding to protein phosphatases 1 and 2A. The latter causes disruption of cellular homeostasis, and, in most acute cases, leads to liver necrosis, as well as colorectal and liver cancer. Thus far, bioactive APs are considered non-toxic. Nevertheless, a few studies suggest that some APs congeners, such as AP-A, may demonstrate the potential to inhibit protease and protein phosphatases. Moreover, AP-B and -F induce cyanobacteria lysis, ultimately affecting the bioavailability of other cell-bound cyanotoxins. Accordingly, much still needs to be done on the unambiguous identification of these cyanopeptides and the assessment of their potential toxicity. </p>

<p>Cyanopeptide’s structures are characterized by cyclic or linear non-ribosomal peptides, each family possessing a characteristic substructure and some variable amino acids and peptides. These variations in the core structure of each cyanopeptide multiply the number of combinations which is the cause of the large variety of potential congeners; to date, more than 500 cyanopeptides, including 240 MCs and 96 APs have been identified. More specifically, MCs are cyclic heptapeptides (<figure>Figure 1</figure>) with a characteristic β-amino acid moiety named Adda (3-amino-9-methoxy-2,6,8-trimethyl-10-phenyldeca-4,6-dienoic acid), and two distinctive positions with the highest variation of monomers (X and Z). APs are cyclic peptides bound through a characteristic ureido-linkage (<figure>Figure 1</figure>); their structure is characterized as the following: AA1-CO-[Lys-AA3-AA4-MeAA5-AA6] with AA representing a variable amino acid residues and brackets, including the cyclic structure. Based on the various amino acid combinations identified for these two families, an extensive list of potential amino acids per variable sites can be proposed to enumerate all possible theoretical combinations of cyanopeptides identifiable to date. Based on the proposed combinations, one could theoretically propose a significantly higher number of congeners, although most of the variants may not occur naturally in practice, due to the low frequency of some amino acids in the possible combinations. </p>

<p>High-resolution mass spectrometry (HRMS) can use exact mass measurement coupled to database and software packages to become an increasingly more effective tool regarding the accurate identification of the suspect and unknown compounds without the use of certified standards, where target analysis is unfeasible. Suspect and non-target screening are the two main strategies used for the exhaustive search of the known and unknown compound where almost no reference material is available. In recent years, the use of these screening techniques in the environmental field has greatly increased, particularly for the non-target analysis of pharmaceuticals, pesticides, hormones in surface and treated water. Reversewise, the presence of cyanotoxins in surface water has only been investigated by few authors using this type of analysis. Isobaric interferences and co-eluting substances can represent major challenges in the identification process of a compound even when using HRMS. Moreover, a sole analysis, based on the accurate mass, is insufficient to confirm a structural identification, e.g., determining the degradation by-products or metabolites related to a compound of interest. A non-target screening method should include various confirmatory elements, such as the accurate mass (<hi rend="italic">m/z</hi>), mass defect, isotopic pattern, charge states, adducts and fragmentation pattern that increase the confidence of identification. Suspect screening includes the benefit and disadvantage to depend on suspect lists. It is mainly based on some of the information mentioned above for the identification, but a major drawback comes from a lack of data in online libraries for some small molecule families, i.e., cyanotoxins, which allow a formal identification. Nonetheless, considering the possibility to build specific in-house databases for the unambiguous identification of the known and unknown cyanopeptides is promising for the study and identification of less known congeners.  </p>
</text>
