<text id="autogum_academic_doc491" title="Treatment of Metformin-Containing Wastewater by a Hybrid Vertical Anaerobic Biofilm-Reactor (HyVAB)" shortTile="treatment-metformincontaining" author="Eshetu Janka, Diego Carvajal, Shuai Wang, Rune Bakke, Carlos Dinamarca" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4125/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The rapid development of large-scale pharmaceutical manufacturing has contributed to increased concentrations of contaminants present in wastewater and surface waters. Pharmaceutical wastewaters are produced during the drug manufacturing processes (i.e., fermentation, extraction, chemical synthesis, formulation, packaging and washing of solid cake and equipment). Hence, the main pollution source of these pharmaceutical compounds in the environment is through industrial process water discharge. Several studies have shown that pharmaceutical drugs (and their derived metabolites) are found in effluents of wastewater treatment plants (WWTPs) and their removal is very inefficient. Wastewater originating during the manufacturing of antidiabetic drugs is also an important environmental challenge due to the high production volume. Several research papers have reported the occurrence, degradability, and environmental impact of antidiabetic drugs in wastewater, and substantial efforts to achieve environmental improvements in line with regulations and legislation have been implemented. </p>

<p>Metformin (C4H11N5) is one of the most prescribed and widely used antidiabetic drugs worldwide, since a significant portion of the population suffers from diabetes. Recent reports have indicated that there are also high concentrations of metformin in domestic wastewater treatment plants’ influent. This is because it is excreted un-metabolized from the human body in urine and ends up in wastewater and aquatic environments. Metformin is the pharmaceutical compound with the highest concentration in domestic wastewater (i.e., 64–98 µg/L). This study is therefore relevant for wastewater treatment in general, even though it is focused on metformin-containing industrial wastewater. Pharmaceutical wastewater has traditionally been treated using conventional physico-chemical and biological process methods. Metformin can be aerobically degraded to guanylurea (C2H6N4O)—a metabolite that is stable against further biodegradation in wastewater treatment plants. However, it appears to be a novel idea to integrate anaerobic and aerobic processes for the efficient removal of metformin and other pharmaceutical constituents.  </p>

<p>The basic hypothesis of this study is that anaerobic granular sludge and aerobic biofilms supported by a hybrid vertical anaerobic biofilm (HyVAB®) reactor design (<figure>Figure 1</figure>) are the most robust combined niches for microorganisms to treat inhibitory substances, since microbial aggregates protect the microorganisms against such substances as they are delivered slowly by diffusion from the liquid phase. The more sensitive organisms are in the deeper layers protected by layers of organisms embedded in an extracellular polymeric matrix. Adaptation to toxic chemicals can be slow and can go through the stages of survival, tolerance, capture, and—if at all biodegradable—the final adaptation stage is degradation. The process can even remove non-biodegradable constituents by integration in the extracellular matrix to build more aggregates.  </p>

<p>HyVAB® is a compact reactor that integrates both anaerobic and aerobic processes. Wastewater is introduced at the bottom anaerobic digestion (AD) stage, where organic matter is degraded and converted into methane. The remaining unconsumed organics flow up for further treatment in the aerobic biofilm stage designed as a Continuous Flow Intermittent Cleaning (CFIC®). Plastic bio-carriers serve as a biofilm substratum in the aerobic biofilm stage, protecting the biofilm from shear force. Excess aerobic sludge is washed off during the intermittent washing process (i.e., CFIC®). Part of the detached aerobic biofilm settles down by gravity to the AD stage in the HyVAB®, where it is degraded simultaneously with the feed substrates. In this study, two types of wastewater—wastewater I (WWI) and wastewater II (WWII)—were fed to the reactor, and performance was evaluated on the basis of metformin reduction, chemical oxygen demand (COD) removal efficiency, and biogas production.  </p>
</text>
