<text id="autogum_academic_doc437" title="Sustainable Academic Motivation" shortTile="sustainable-academic" author="Martina Blašková, Justyna Majchrzak-Lepczyk, Dominika Hriníková, Rudolf Blaško" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5934/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Definition of Sustainable Academic Motivation and Discussion</head>
<p>The main inspiration of this article was to contribute to the development of behavioral sciences on the one hand, and to help in the development of higher education on the other. For this reason, the comprehensive and conclusive focus of this article is the experimental definition of the concept of sustainable academic motivation (Section 4.1). The reason is achieving an appropriately high and sustainable level of motivation, i.e., “integrating sustainability within institutions of higher education can have a tremendous impact on students, faculty, and the larger community”. </p>

<head> 4.1. Sustainable Academic Motivation</head>
<p>Sustainable academic motivation can be defined as a conscious, firm, persistent, responsible, and action-capable force, a mixture of reasons, and the commitment of key participants in university activities. It is a proactive interconnection and even penetration of sustainability and academic motivation into one unique behavioral system. When examining the nature of sustainable academic motivation, the topic should be considered from the following perspectives or inner contents: </p>

<p>
<list>
<item>(1) As the most important component of conscious behavior.

<p>- The sustainable motivation of university staff can be characterized as deliberately selected and respected motives and accepted (experientially repeated) patterns of academic behavior. Academic motivation positively influences academic performance and focuses it to complex developmental and prosocial goals. Regarding sustainably motivated behavior, setting goals higher is very important.</p>

<p>- Because the academic motivation of students can most simply be defined as “the variety of all factors and reasons that influence a person to attend school and obtain a degree” (p. 709), awareness, understanding, and application of these elements severely shape both academic and private efforts of students. If students deliberately build and strengthen their academic motivation, it becomes sustainable for a long period of time—the conscious and motivated stay of the student at the university affects not only their behavior during university studies, but also their entire future. </p></item>

<item>(2) As the starting point of a behavior. Because motivation is a function or substructure of personality, personality predetermines and somehow starts all motivated activities of individuals. Building on individuals’ genetic predispositions, initial academic motivation is shaped and built by prior upbringing, education, or career.

<p>- In general, motivation explains and justifies both real and intended behavior of scholars at the beginning of their academic career. If scholars decided to work in higher education, and their motivation for this decision was desirably strong and firm, by entering the academic environment, their former work motivation becomes academic, and triggers/starts their following career ambitions and resolutions. However, it is important to prevent the application of questionable research practices (QRPs).</p>

<p>- Motivation of students during their start at the university is a reflection of their learning motivation created in high school. The beginning of university studies is a breakthrough element of students’ motivation and life, and is often caused by leaving home for campus, getting to know new classmates, the higher difficulty of studies, awareness of own responsibilities, etc.. The effort to handle university studies thus opens up another dimension of their former academic motivation—motivation for sustaining it.</p></item>

<item>(3) As the accelerator of behavior and development.

<p>- The sustainable motivation of students, managers, and teachers strengthens, invigorates, and even vitalizes the sustainable motivation of all professorates. This idea can also be worded in the opposite sense: “If talented and competent staff members are not motivated enough by their supervisors, and if they are not happy with their job, university, and management, then they may leave the university” (p. 731), decrease, or resign from their academic effort. This means that the sustainable motivation of scholars has to accelerate, progress, and excel all scientific, publication, and educational outputs.</p>

<p>- The sustainable motivation of all university teachers, scientists, managers, and clerks dynamizes the motivation of students, and can even transform it to a higher, more self-responsible and self-aware level, i.e., transcendental motivation. Transcendental is “the motivation to do things for others, the motivation to contribute” (p. 204). When consciously and creatively supporting and accelerating such motivation from the side of university staff, it can meet the essential principles of sustainability. This can transform oneself to sustainable transcendental motivation of students and graduates.</p></item>

<item>(4) As a process. “The process of motivate others consists in unifying or establishing of a common goal, thereby showing the distance between the state that currently exists and the state that is to be achieved, while the individual will perceive this distance as a certain tension is to be overcome” (p. 127).

<p>- For the motivating to become a systematic and sustainable process, it must be embedded in the university’s system of management as a crucial internal process. It must impact the motivation of as many lecturers, managers, and students as possible.</p>

<p>- Moreover, motivating from the side of university must be continually complemented by self-motivating processes. That means processes that both the university staff and students evoke and perform inside themselves: “By self-motivating, academic goal-directed activity is instigated and sustained” (p. 283).</p></item>

<item>(5) As a resultative level of all motivational efforts and powers at higher-education institutions.</item>
</list>
</p>
</text>
