<text id="autogum_academic_doc089" title="A Simulation Study on the Potential of Moving Urban Freight by a Cross-City Railway Line" shortTile="simulation-study" author="Praful Potti, Marin Marinov, Edward Sweeney" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6088/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The freight movement through heavy good vehicles (HGVs) is expected to grow by 22% each year until 2050 in the United Kingdom. The increase in HGVs number causes more congestion on the roads and also increases the emission of green-house gases into the atmosphere. However, on the other side, the UK has legally committed to reduce the carbon emissions by 80% by the year 2050 to that of the current number in 2016. The forecasts that are showing an increase in the usage of motor vehicles for freight transport does not seem promising as the transport sector is already being accounted for 17% of the UK’s total domestic GHG emissions. Adapting to movement of urban freight by rail seems to present a greater opportunity to overcome the emission issues as well as the road congestion problem as the region under study possesses a high value and demand for freight movement. Apart from this, providing a greener option to move goods, this method actually has the capacity to match up the trade-off between the utilisation levels and capital costs, as the organisations running the rail services largely invest in spending on the infrastructure. This situation was the motivation to evaluate the utilisation levels of the Cross-City railway line in the West Midlands County in England and come up with cases to accommodate to move urban freight by rail in one of the busiest industrial hubs of the country. </p>

<p>There are three main objectives for this paper: Firstly, to analyse the current Cross-City railway line and evaluate the utilisation levels of the line using the timetable as a reference. This is achieved by replicating the system in the simulation model using SIMUL8 software; secondly, to propose suitable scenarios by identifying gaps in the evaluated system so that it presents with a case to improve the current utilisation levels of the system; finally, to evaluate the proposed scenarios if they are feasible to operate and generate the expected utilisation levels. This also includes studying and analysing the performance of those proposed systems and concluding by suggesting the best fit system among them to replace the currently operating system. </p>

<p>This paper employs a systems approach: Firstly, problem formulation that is achieved by understanding the freight transport scenario in the UK and identifying the need for Urban freight movement by rail in a robust manner; secondly, evaluating the Cross-City railway line to study the utilisation levels by developing a model that replicates the existing railway line accurately using SIMUL8 software; thirdly, devising solutions to propose a replacement to the current system that has the ability to move freight between Lichfield Trent Valley and Birmingham New Street station by rail; finally, evaluating and comparing the proposed models and obtained results and suggest the best suitable scenario. </p>

<p>This paper is organised as follows. Section 2 illustrates the literature review regarding urban logistics freight movement and the trend followed by several countries in the world in using rail to move urban freight. Section 3 holds the discussion for the state of practice of the region under the study and provides an overview of the Cross-City railway line. Section 4 provides description of the proposed system. A brief introduction to the fundamentals and characteristics of SIMUL8 are addressed in Section 5. In Section 6, the simulation layout of the railway line and the computed utilisation levels for different scenarios have been illustrated and the results obtained from the simulation model were analysed and the best suitable scenario was presented. Section 7 concludes and addresses the future scope of research work, followed by references in Section 8. </p>
</text>
