<text id="autogum_academic_doc560" title="Investigating Primary Factors Affecting Electricity Consumption in Non-Residential Buildings Using a Data-Driven Approach" shortTile="investigating-primary" author="Sooyoun Cho, Jeehang Lee, Jumi Baek, Gi-Seok Kim, Seung-Bok Leigh" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4046/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Approach</head>
<p>
The purpose of this study was to identify the power consumption of buildings and determine the variables that contribute to their use. This study confirms that key variables obtained using clustering in machine learning strongly correlate with the energy consumption of buildings. For this purpose, it is important to first identify building energy consumption patterns. This was done based on a total of 16 variables related to building energy usage, in addition to the electricity consumption of the target building. Then, the variables that best define the energy consumption patterns were identified. The major elements affecting consumption are not identified by simulation, or by the analyst’s experience, but through a machine learning process. The structure of the research work is described below and <figure>Figure 2</figure> shows simplify the process of this study from the number one to six. </p>

<p>(1) This study targets 11 office buildings in eight different regions of South Korea. Their heating and cooling systems use electricity. The 11 buildings all have different areas, building designs, and heating and cooling systems, and are used for different purposes. In the data analysis, the physical qualities are referred to as nominal variables. In this study, only the continuous data that change in real time as a result of the actions of the occupants were used for the analysis. Four categories of variables were identified for the analysis, i.e., the amount of electric energy used by the building, external environmental data, building system data, and occupancy schedules. In total, 16 continuous variables were selected; </p>

<p>(2) Before analyzing the large amount of data used in machine learning, preprocessing is a necessary step that prepares data by processing missing values, removing noise, or removing outliers. In data preprocessing, cleaning is a process that fills in or removes missing values, corrects noisy data, identifies outliers, and therefore ensures the consistency of data outcomes; </p>

<p>(3) The data set in this research contains time variables (such as the year, month, day, day of the week, and hour), external environment variables (including temperature, humidity, sunlight, airflow, wind speed, and soil temperature), and energy variables that track the energy consumed during the building operating hours (in 2016, use of electricity consumption hourly data of 11 offices); </p>

<p>(4) To determine the most important variables, unsupervised learning, which does not require a ground truth, was used. This involved using clustering to extract the most important variables that control the building energy usage and cluster similar variables together; </p>

<p>(5) In addition, using the <hi rend="italic">t</hi>-test, we aimed to verify the validity of the variables, derived from machine learning, that affect the building energy consumption; </p>

<p>(6) For each target building, the first 16 variables related to energy consumption, and five variables derived from machine learning, were compared with the same verification logic. </p>

<p>As stated in Section 3, this study aims to use energy data derived from a building and identify important variables that control most of the energy consumption. Two representative clustering methodologies used for this purpose are the Density-Based Spatial Clustering of Applications with Noise (DBSCAN) and K-means. </p>

<head> 3.1. Clustering: DBSCAN and K-Means</head>
<p>
Density-based spatial clustering of applications with noise, one of the most widely used density-based clustering methods, explores core objects that have a high density in a neighborhood. Centroid-based clustering methods of K-means predetermine the K value and the number of clusters, and then assign each datum to one of the K clusters to minimize dispersion. Centroid-based algorithms have the advantages of clustering many data points quickly and easily, and spherical data have a relatively better reliability. </p>

<p>Table 4 shows a sequential list of operations performed through DBSCAN and K-means using the open-source program R 3.6.1. To summarize the clustering process for extracting key variables, first, similar characteristics (density center, distance-based) in the various data were assessed to create the first cluster. Although N clusters were formed, it was impossible to determine which clusters were meaningful. Then, results were extracted only for clusters containing a large amount of data. Based on these results, the data were classified into high-energy-consumption and low-energy-consumption data clusters. Lastly, for the two clusters with large amounts of high-energy-consumption data, box plots were used to confirm which of the 16 variables related to building energy were the most important. </p>
</text>
