<text id="autogum_academic_doc396" title="Supply Chain Partner Communication in a Managed Programme in the UK Water Industry: A Case Study with Social Network Analysis" shortTile="supply-chain-partner" author="Qing Li, Shengqiao Wang, Nicky Shaw, Victor Shi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4211/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Case Study Details</head>
<p>
This case study focuses on one of the UK’s largest water utility companies (UC). Project numbers and their variation in size, technical work content, and value indicate the challenging complexity of the water programme. The projects vary in technical work content since different types of capital infrastructure are dealt with, e.g., pumping stations, reservoirs, and pipeline renewal. Project values range from less than £2 million to £15 million. In addition, complexity stems from the involvement of a sizeable network of organisations, such as major contractors, subcontractors, suppliers, consultants, and regulatory institutions. Because the water programme typically engages with multiple stakeholders and is a long-term endeavour, effective interorganisational relationships between the water company and its major first tier contractors are important for programme performance.  </p>

<p>In delivering its capital programme, UC chose to adopt a partnering approach with its main contractors. The collaborative network studied here comprises the utility company (UC) and its main eight contractors (CTs), with the UC adopting a programme management approach to working with its CTs. UC management looks to design contracts to encourage competition between partners and to stimulate innovation. They change organisational structures frequently, particularly for each AMP cycle, as the regulator rewards companies for introducing managerial innovation as a source of “efficiency saving”.  </p>

<p>UC managers believe the company’s success relies heavily on partnership with its tier 1 contractors. A CT is typically formed by a partnership between a design company and a civil construction company, an arrangement with what could be termed tier 2 suppliers. In successive cycles of asset management programmes, UC has employed a different mix of tier 1 contractors. These changes stem from Ofwat encouraging a “shake up” in each AMP. </p>

<p>Two major changes were instituted at the start of the studied programme: (1) key personnel from all nine organisations were co-located in a newly acquired multistorey office block to form a newly created Asset Delivery Unit (ADU) and (2) project work was organised into five streams containing projects of a similar technical nature, under two higher level “production units”. The project grouping determines the work allocation to stream members and establishes key relationships between employees. Each stream has a UC manager who was also in charge of lower-level work allocations by batch and project. Contractors operate in different numbers of streams, ranging from one to four streams (see <figure>Figure 1</figure>); however, individuals are often restricted to working on one stream or sometimes two. Some contractors have prior relationships with the UC from previous AMPs. Collaboration between contractors is expected across both production units and all five streams as part of the performance criteria established as a response to incentives from the regulatory body. Production Unit 1 comprises streams 2, 3, and 5, while Production Unit 2 is made up of streams 1 and 4. A stream level analysis, amongst others, was applied in the research to investigate the connections among the nine organisations (UC and the eight CTs).  </p>

<p>In <figure>Figure 1</figure>, each contractor is anonymised by using a capital letter (A–H), while each stream is represented using a number (1–5). The combination of eight contractors with five streams of work adds complexity to the analysis of relationships. For instance, contractor G is assigned to streams 1, 2, 4, and 5 while contractors A, B, C, D, and F work for only one stream. Each stream is independent from each other but related in the programme. Furthermore, prior association with UC varies to a large degree. Contractors B and D are new to working with UC on a programme for this cycle, whereas contractors G and E had collaborative relationships with UC for 15 years through three programme cycles of association.  </p>
</text>
