<text id="autogum_academic_doc413" title="Organization Mechanisms and Spatial Characteristics of Urban Collaborative Innovation Networks: A Case Study in Hangzhou, China" shortTile="organization-mechanisms" author="Nina Liu, Jiwu Wang, Yan Song" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5988/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Literature Review</head>
<p>
Innovation is a system, and the cohesion between the various innovation subjects in the system determines the innovation efficiency of the system. According to the theory of innovation, Schumpeter stated that innovation is a reorganization of the elements linked to socio-economic transformation and development, and is different from the development paradigm of the industrial economy. Based on the characteristics of the innovation development paradigm, since the concept of the innovation system was first proposed by Lundvall, different scholars have studied the functional structure and dynamic mechanism of innovation development from a system perspective, and proposed that the innovation model should shift from focusing on the composition of elements to the association of elements. Etzkowitz and Leydesdorff reported that universities, enterprises, and governments are the three major innovation factors, and the three interact to promote the spiral of innovation. The research space created by universities, research institutes, and enterprises transforms the elements of technological innovation into scientific and technological achievements, and enterprises develop applications and extension technologies on the core technologies absorbed. Adner and Kapoor considered the innovation system as the coordination and symbiosis system of the resources of innovation, and stated that the collaboration and integration of the government, industry, and research is indispensable to innovation. The coordination between the various innovation subjects is the basic functioning mechanism and development driving force of the innovation system. </p>

<p>A collaborative innovation network is an effective organizational model for achieving sustainable innovation. With the integration of innovation resources and the cohesion of behavioral actors, the innovation process has experienced a simple linear technology-driven mode, linear market-driven mode, technology–market interaction mode, system integration mode, and collaborative network mode. The innovation model development has become a multi-systematic network process that combines multiple factors. Freeman stated that the contribution of the network to the role of innovation is a relatively new area of research, and the formation and the network emerges in response to organizations’ need for knowledge. Jacobides and Billinger thought that the innovation process no longer only occurs within enterprise boundaries or in a single industry, but is increasingly distributed in complementary network behaviors formed by resource differences. Ritter and Gemunden showed that the companies that have close relationships with customers, suppliers, research institutions, and competitors are more likely to have higher product and process innovation success. Xie et al. considered collaborative innovation networks as an effective framework to enable knowledge transfer between firms, and their findings revealed that the network size, network tie-strength, and network centrality determine the level of knowledge transfer performance. The innovation network emphasizes that the innovation subjects (including enterprises, universities, research institutions, intermediary organizations, and governments) implement the transmission of explicit or tacit knowledge through formal or informal institutional arrangements in the network for collaborative innovation. </p>

<p>Research on innovation networks is more consistently focusing on revealing their characteristics. People have begun to pay attention to how space matters in collaboration innovation on the macro scale. Li et al. examined the topological and spatial features of urban innovation networks in China, and analyzed the evolution of scientific knowledge networks (SKNs) and technological knowledge networks (TKNs) with published papers and applied patents in the biotechnology field from 2000 to 2012. Lifener and Hennemann analyzed the spatial configurations of knowledge networks and their overlap with spatial concentrations, such as urban agglomerations, and proposed a type of spatial concentrations in knowledge networks. Peschl and Thomas proposed that space is important for collaborative innovation networks, enabling a more suitable approach to innovation. Space can be designed so that it enables and facilitates processes of collaborative knowledge creation and innovation. Cohen et al. noted the increasing role of cities as drivers for innovation and entrepreneurship, and framed the innovation space as being cultivated by proactive cities. At the macro scale, research on collaborative innovation networks is gradually being conducted. Taking the Yangze River Delta urban agglomeration as the study object, Zhou et al. analyzed the innovation network structure and measured the innovation network statutes based on cooperative patents. </p>

<p>Most studies characterized collaborative innovation networks with innovative outputs. Hoekman et al. analyzed inter-regional research collaboration as measured by scientific publications and patents with multiple addresses, covering 1316 regions in 29 European countries. To study the structure and evolution of the global technological collaboration network, De Prato and Nepelski used the patent-based data of international co-inventions and applied network analysis. The use of patent data to observe and analyze the organizational mechanism and spatial development characteristics of innovation activities has become a more common research strategy. Patent data reflects effective innovation output, and the reliability of the distribution characteristics and development laws of innovation activities based on patent data has been verified. The research on collaborative innovation networks using cooperative patents has been widely recognized by scholars. </p>
</text>
