<text id="autogum_academic_doc487" title="What Does the History of Research on the Repair of DNA Double-Strand Breaks Tell Us?—A Comprehensive Review of Human Radiosensitivity" shortTile="history-research" author="Elise Berthel, Mélanie  L. Ferlazzo, Clément Devic, Michel Bourguignon, Nicolas Foray" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5339/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. What do the Clinical Data Teach Us?</head>
<p>
As discussed above, the great majority of the radiobiological investigations have been done with very radioresistant and hyper-radiosensitive cells. However, the hyper-radiosensitive and hyper-radioresistant cellular models are not representative of the clinical reality. For example, there is no known human genetic syndromes caused by mutations of Ku or DNA-PKcs proteins, the major NHEJ actors. The only human case of gross defect in NHEJ function to non-viability was caused by mutations of DNA ligase IV (LIG4). The majority of cases of fatal post-radiotherapy events were encountered after whole-body irradiation of children with ataxia telangiectasia (AT) caused by homozygous <hi rend="italic">ATM</hi> mutations during their anti-leukemia or lymphoma treatment. It is important to note that AT frequency is of about 1/100,000. By contrast, about 5%–20% cancer of patients treated by radiotherapy exhibit post-radiotherapy tissue reactions that can be considered as moderate radiosensitivity. Surprisingly, no or very few rodent cells with moderate radiosensitivity have been the subject of a published radiobiological characterization. Interestingly, some of the proteins whose mutations are responsible for these syndromes were cited as components of the different variants of A-NHEJ (see Section 4). In addition, some genetic syndromes, associated or not with cancer proneness, different from the precited ones, also show a moderate radiosensitivity: this is notably the case of neurofibromatosis, Huntington’s chorea, and tuberous sclerosis syndromes. It must be stressed that these syndromes are caused by mutations of cytoplasmic proteins, which may contradict the historical hypothesis that nucleus is the most radiosensitive part of the cell (see the Introduction). Furthermore, it also contradicts the hypothesis that defect of DSB repair is the unique cause of cellular radiosensitivity. The question of how to build a unified model that would describe both hyper-radiosensitivity observed in <hi rend="italic">LIG4</hi>- and <hi rend="italic">ATM</hi>-mutated cells and moderate radiosensitivity caused by impairment of alternative signaling and DSB repair pathways remains. </p>

<p>To date, the ATM protein has been considered as an early actor of the DSB recognition via its phosphorylation of H2AX and the individual radiation response. Surprisingly, ATM has not been integrated in all the DSB repair models discussed above while mutations of RAD51 and RAD52 (for HR) and Ku and DNA-PKcs (for NHEJ) do not cause any viable syndromes in humans (<figure>Figure 1</figure>). Recently, the delay in the radiation-induced nucleo-shuttling of ATM protein (RIANS) was shown to be a reliable parameter for predicting radiosensitivity and to provide a biologically relevant interpretation of the linear-quadratic model, the mathematical basis of the cellular radiation response. In the context of the RIANS model, the following mechanistic hypothesis has been proposed: after irradiation, cytoplasmic trans-auto-phosphorylated dimeric forms of ATM become monomeric and diffuse to the nucleus. In the nucleus, active ATM monomers phosphorylate H2AX molecules at DSB sites, which activates NHEJ. The ATM monomers will re-dimerize during the DSB repair process. Once in nucleus, ATM may also inhibit MRE11 nuclease activity or any other actor responsible for genomic instability. By contrast, in cells with moderate radiosensitivity, over-expressed ATM substrates may delay the RIANS, thereby favoring cancer proneness and aging. This is notably the case for huntingtin, neurofibromin, and tuberin. (<figure>Figure 6</figure>). </p>

<p>Three groups of radiosensitivity have been defined: </p>

<p>Group I (about 75% to 85% whole population) represents the normosensitive (radioresistant) patients with a rapid RIANS after 2 Gy, a low risk of post-radiotherapy tissue reaction and of cancer </p>

<p>Group II (about 5–20% of whole population) represents the patients who elicit a moderate radiosensitivity with a delay in the RIANS due to the sequestration of ATM by mutated and over-expressed substrates. These patients are moderately radiosensitive and may have a high risk of cancer or neurodegeneration. </p>

<p>Group III (&lt;1% whole population) represents the <hi rend="italic">ATM</hi>-mutated patients with no functional ATM kinase or those who show strong DSB repair defects (like the <hi rend="italic">LIG4</hi>-mutated patient described above), hyper-radiosensitivity, and either high cancer proneness or severe accelerated aging. </p>

<p>While it provides relevant explanation of the radiosensitivity of syndromes caused by mutations of cytoplasmic proteins, the RIANS model appears to be compatible with all the alternative models, as ATM is upstream of all the cascades of radiation-induced phosphorylations involved in the individual response to IR. Obviously, further investigations are needed to better understand the direct or indirect role of cytoplasmic ATM forms in the activation or the inhibition of DSB repair pathways. </p>
</text>
