<text id="autogum_academic_doc135" title="Investigating Environmental Transgressions at Corbett Tiger Reserve, India" shortTile="investigating-environmental" author="Tanmay Sharma, Joseph  S. Chen, Wan-Yu Liu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5766/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions and Recommendations</head>
<p>
This study investigates tourists’ environmental transgressions while revealing the attitude and behavior of tourists toward the park under study. Consequently, the following recommendations are rendered to assuage the issue of environmental transgressions. </p>

<p>In response to the turmoil in tourism development, as custodians of national parks and its adjoining areas, the local authorities should not allow any new construction in the ecologically sensitive vicinity of CTR, and action should be taken against illegal, unauthorized activities at holiday resorts. Local authorities should adopt conservationist views, leading to restrictions on tourism development and putting in place harsher restrictions on the number of vehicles that can operate in and around CTR. Heavy penalties should be imposed on businesses that are habitual offenders and do not readily lend themselves to pro-environmental influences. Professional planning and commitment towards tourism infrastructure development on the part of local authorities could go a long way toward reducing environmental transgressions. </p>

<p>About the tourist’s attitudes, priority needs to be given towards transformation of tourists’ attitudes, from ‘individuals’ just seeking thrill and leisure to ‘eco-tourists’ who leave national parks with an appreciation for the environment and iconic species. In this regard, in line with the current literature, this study finds the visitors’ lived experiences can play a significant role in effectively altering visitor knowledge and behavior. Therefore, the park should stage the tourist experience as one that tourists are visiting an iconic tourist destination that is a national treasure; thus, the responsibility of exhibiting environmental compliance falls on them. Similarly, as suggested by Ballantyne, Packer, and Hughes, wildlife tourism management practices that enlist tourists as conservation partners, communicate the reasons behind any constraints imposed, and present a consistent message regarding interactions with wildlife are likely to be successful in reducing environmental transgressions. </p>

<p>Further, evoking an emotional bond (i.e., place attachment) with the park is a viable way to curb a tourist’s environmental transgression. Likely, tourists are not able to establish an emotional bond with the park after spending just two to three hours inside the park. This study finds that returned tourists have developed an attachment to the park by experiencing a sense of awe and appreciation for nature during their multiple visits to the park. Hence, it is vital to strengthen the communicative message about the park’s conservation efforts on the ecosystem to allow tourists to utilize the best of the resources provided by the park, which, consequently, will boost the tourist’s attachment to the park. </p>

<p>In regard to deviant tourist behavior, in agreement with the literature, respondents also confirm that to reduce deviant behaviors, the number of tourists needs to be regulated. However, respondents are also of the opinion that time allowed inside the park should be relaxed to enhance appreciation for nature and place attachment. Historically, the Indian society has been known to have immense respect for nature. Since deviant behavior is generally caused due to ignorance of laws and lack of social pressures, it could be countered by offering guidelines or codes of conduct for tourists through effective communication that informs tourists of the negative health consequences of these actions. Furthermore, the local tourism business community should establish its corporate social responsibility to prevent environmental transgressions effectively. For example, tour guides should play a proactive role in decreasing tourists’ environmental transgressions in the park. Meanwhile, park staffs must strictly prohibit littering in and around CTR by issuing penalties against littering, and they should have more display/message boards and interpretation centers to enhance environmental awareness amongst tourists. </p>

<p>While more overt enforcement could be applied to address behaviors inside national parks, complementary efforts could begin in private hotels and guest houses outside CTR. A practical institutional framework and formulation of comprehensive policy and legislation could ensure local tourism providers’ compliance with prescribed rules and guidelines. Since most local tourism providers seem to be environmental offenders, policymakers need to introduce a new destination development strategy that promotes ethical and ‘uncompromised’ development by bringing the entire CTR region under strict environmental regulations and by enforcing sustained vigilant monitoring. Similarly, legislation for diverting a specific proportion of profits made by businesses into local conservation efforts may also support countering environmental degradation. Further tourism development should be geared toward community-based operations in which the community plays a central role in scrutinizing its progress. </p>

<p>Based on research themes emerging from this study, a framework for strategic transformation towards the reduction of environmental transgression is presented in <figure>Figure 4</figure>. Park authorities, the local municipality, local tourism providers, communities, and tourists have been identified as critical stakeholders that must contribute towards a reduction in environmental transgressions. Based on the findings, as CTR management and village residents share a preference for low-impact tourism, in the long run, it may be useful to examine the possible strategy of tourism being managed by an autonomous agency with the support of community-based institutions, the forest department, and NGOs. Additionally, results also point towards strengthening locally active NGOs to escalate their environmental advocacy efforts towards reducing negative impacts of tourism activities in and around CTR. </p>
</text>
