<text id="autogum_academic_doc669" title="Social Stability Risk Assessment of Land Expropriation: Lessons from the Chinese Case" shortTile="social-stability" author="Chenxi Li, Zenglei Xi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/20/3952/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Conclusions and Policy Implications</head><head> 6.1. Conclusions</head>
<p>
Based on a case study of land expropriation social stability risk assessment in China, this study investigated the social stability risk caused by land expropriation. The current social stability risk assessment system of land expropriation was analyzed. The results showed that: (1) the current land expropriation risk assessment system mostly considers the land administration department to be the main body of responsibility, identifies the risk by means of seminars, letters and visits, and takes the opinion of the masses or experts as the risk assessment result. In the course of practice, there is an unclear appraisal subject, unclear functional orientation, and unscientific assessment process, among other issues. (2) The current land expropriation risk assessment system should be standardized in terms of defining the risk assessment of land expropriation, improving the land expropriation risk assessment system, and optimizing the land expropriation assessment procedures. To ensure that risk assessment is carried out at the time of construction project establishment and that a scientific and objective assessment method is adopted to establish a risk assessment system that includes land expropriation risk assessment, demolition risk assessment, and environmental impact assessment, the main role of local governments in the risk assessment must be clarified and the land expropriation conflict assessment of supporting mechanisms and regulatory mechanisms must be established and improved. </p>

<head> 6.2. Policy Implications</head>
<p>
Based on the above analysis, we think that the reform of the land expropriation procedure should focus on the following aspects:
</p>

<p><dl class="html-order"><dt id="">(1)</dt><dd>
Establishment of a land expropriation pre-announcement system: The county government is responsible for drawing up the land expropriation plan. The preannouncement should be made in the townships (towns) and villages where the land is to be expropriated by means of land use, compensation standards, resettlement channels, and social security measures. As the main body of land expropriation, the government should fully listen to the opinions of the members of the collective rural economic organizations and sign agreements with the vast majority of the members of the collective economic organizations or the farmers. Land expropriation can only be initiated after land expropriation compensation and social security charges are implemented.</dd><dt id="">(2)</dt><dd>
Establishing the system of confirming the results of land expropriation investigation: After the announcement of the proposed expropriation of land is issued, the local administrative organ should, together with the village collective economic organizations, jointly carry out the site investigation of the land expropriation, and conduct field investigation on the title, category, area, title, type, quantity, etc. of the land to be expropriated. Finally, it should be confirmed by the collective economic organizations, farmers, and property owners of the land expropriated rural areas.</dd><dt id="">(3)</dt><dd>
Perfecting the measures of land expropriation and conflict settlement: The government should give full attention to the functions of administrative mediation, administrative reconsideration, administrative litigation, and judicial arbitration to prevent and resolve contradictions and disputes over land expropriation. On the other hand, the government should clarify ways to resolve the differences in land expropriation and compensation agreements within collective rural economic organizations.</dd><dt id="">(4)</dt><dd>
Standardizing the publicity of land expropriation Information: Land expropriation approval documents, scope, compensation, resettlement, and other information should be unified and made public by the county government and should be subject to supervision by the masses and society. In addition to the confidential content, the relevant land expropriation information should be made public.</dd></dl>
</p>
</text>
