<text id="autogum_academic_doc056" title="The Impact of Chemotherapy on the Ovaries: Molecular Aspects and the Prevention of Ovarian Damage" shortTile="impact-chemotherapy" author="Charlotte Sonigo, Isabelle Beau, Nadine Binart, Michaël Grynberg" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5342/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Follicular Ovarian Reserve and Its Regulation</head>
<p>
In mammals, the follicular ovarian reserve, constituted by primordial follicles, is established early on in life then keeps declining regularly throughout the reproductive period. The pool of primordial follicles serves as a source of growing follicles and fertilizable eggs for the entire female reproductive life. Actually, each primordial follicle can remain quiescent for years; be activated and enter the growing process; or undergo atresia directly from the dormant stage. To produce mature oocytes, activated primordial follicles develop through primary and secondary stages before acquiring an antral cavity. At the antral stage, most follicles undergo apoptotic degeneration and only a few of them grow further to reach the preovulatory stage under the cyclic gonadotropin stimulation that occurs after puberty. </p>

<p>The maintenance of female reproductive function implies the presence of a vast majority of quiescent primordial follicles and continuous repression of primordial follicle activation into early growing follicles. This activation, starting during fetal life, is finely controlled though maintaining a balance between inhibitory and stimulatory factors. In vitro experiments and genetically modified mouse or sheep models have enabled the decoding of the molecular mechanisms that control follicular activation. Numerous factors, such as growth factors, hormones, transcription factors, or cytokines, produced by oocytes and/or granulosa cells, can act in an autocrine, paracrine, or endocrine manner. The quiescence of primordial follicles is maintained by several molecules including phosphatase and tensin homolog deleted on chromosome 10 (Pten), tuberous sclerosis complexes 1–2 (Tsc1–Tsc2) complex, Forkhead box protein O3A (Foxo3A), p27, anti-Müllerian hormone (AMH), and Forkhead box L2 (FoxL2). Many studies have highlighted the crucial roles of the phosphatidyl-inositol-3-kinase (PI3K) signaling pathway in oocytes in controlling follicular activation. Indeed, in genetically modified mouse models, it was observed that the PI3K–Akt–mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) signaling pathway is crucial for the control of survival and activation of primordial follicles. For example, Pten and Tsc1–2 are negative regulators of this signaling pathway and, in mice, the deletion of these genes from oocytes leads to primordial follicle activation and subsequent early follicular depletion. In these models, mTOR activity is accelerated within the oocyte, highlighting the critical role of this serine/threonine kinase in primordial follicle activation. The transcription factor FoxO3A, mainly expressed in the oocytes of resting follicles, acts downstream of the PI3K signaling pathway and appears to be the main actor involved in follicular activation. At the same time, the survival of primordial follicles is maintained by other mechanisms involving PDK1 signaling, rpS6. Several studies have suggested the involvement of the autophagy process in the regulation of the ovarian reserve of primordial follicles. For example, autophagy is implicated in maintaining the primordial oocyte pool in murine newborns, and the induction of autophagy at birth seems to be a crucial step to preserve the stock of primordial follicles. </p>

<p>In the same manner, primordial follicle survival or apoptosis results from a balance between the expression of survival (antiapoptotic) and proapoptotic factors. Among these factors, the proteins B-cell lymphoma 2 (Bcl-2) and Bcl-2-associated X protein (BAX) likely play a critical role. </p>

<p>Thus, a synergistic and coordinated suppression of follicular activation, provided by multiple inhibitory and activator molecules, is necessary to preserve the primordial follicular stockpile in association with the process maintaining dormancy. Any disorder in these complex mechanisms can lead to a premature loss of the follicular reserve. </p>
</text>
