<text id="autogum_academic_doc583" title="Optimal Position of the Intermediate Coils in a Magnetic Coupled Resonant Wireless Power Transfer System" shortTile="optimal-position" author="Dongsheng Yang, Jiangwei Tian, Sokhui Won, Bowen Zhou, Zixin Cheng, Bo Hu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/20/3991/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Theoretical Analysis of MCR-WPT System with Intermediate Coils</head><head> 2.1. Equivalent Circuit Model with a Single-Intermediate Coil</head>
<p>
<figure>Figure 1</figure> shows an MCR-WPT system with an intermediate coil, which is the coaxial circular coil. The transmitter circuit is composed of an adjustable rectifier whose input is city alternating current power, a high frequency power inverter, transmitter coil, and the compensation capacitor. Similarly, each intermediate resonator circuit is composed of an intermediate coil and a compensation capacitor. The receiver circuit is composed of the receiver coil, the receiver compensation capacitor, and a load. </p>

<p>The system can be expressed with the equivalent circuit model, and <figure>Figure 2</figure> shows the equivalent circuit of an MCR-WPT system with an intermediate coil. In the transmitter circuit,  is the RMS (Root Mean Square) value of the output voltage of the high-frequency inverter,  is the internal resistance of the source,  is the equivalent resistance of the transmitter coil when it is operated at high frequency,  is the inductance of the transmitter coil, and  is the compensation capacitance of the transmitter. In the intermediate coil circuit,  is the inductance of intermediate coil-1, and  is the compensation capacitance of the intermediate coil-1. In the receiver circuit,  is the equivalent resistance of the intermediate coil-1 when it is operated at high frequency,  is the equivalent resistance of the receiver coil when it is operated at high frequency,  is the inductance of the receiver coil,  is the compensation capacitance of the receiver, and  is the load resistance. ,  and  are the mutual inductances between the transmitter coil and the intermediate coil-1, the intermediate coil-1 and the receiver coil, the transmitter coil and the receiver coil, respectively.  is the angular frequency of the high-frequency inverter output. </p>

<p>Based on the Kirchhoff’s voltage law (KVL), the equivalent circuit model in <figure>Figure 2</figure> is built by

(1)

where

(2)

</p>

<p>The resonant frequency can be expressed by

(3)

</p>

<p>Due to the far distance, the mutual inductance  between the transmitter and the receiver is small. In general,  and  are far greater than the non-adjacent coupling coefficient . Thus, the influence of mutual inductance  on the system can be ignored. This paper assumes . Solving the KVL equation of the equivalent circuit, the current expression of each circuit can be obtained, and all the current solutions given in (4) are valid only at the resonant frequency:

(4)

where

(5)

</p>

<p>Furthermore, the expressions of the powers of the transmitter and the receiver can be derived, respectively:

(6)

</p>

<p>To facilitate the analysis, the distance between the transmitter coil and the intermediate coil-1 is ; the transfer distance between the transmitter and the receiver coil is <hi rend="italic">D</hi>, and the distance coefficient  is defined as the position of the intermediate coil-1:

(7)

</p>

<p>On this topology, to ensure that the intermediate coil-1 is always between the transmitter coil and the receiver coil, the distance coefficient should be in the following constraint condition:

(8)

</p>

<p>The mutual inductances are related to the distances between the coils, and the coupling coefficients are directly derived from the mutual inductances. In addition, the transfer power is related to the coupling coefficients. Thus, the transfer power is also related to the distance coefficient . The mutual inductance between the coils is shown in (9):

(9)

(10)

</p>

<p> and  are the numbers of turns of the two coil’s, and ,  are the radii of the two circular coils.  and  are the complete elliptic integrals of the first type and the second type, respectively, and  is the center distance of the two round coils. The flat circular spiral coil can be considered as the overlay group of several single-turn coaxial rings with different radii on the same plane. Similarly, the mutual inductance between two spiral coils can be considered as the overlay group of several pairs on different planes. </p>

<p>The mutual inductance between the adjacent coils can be expressed as:

(11)

</p>

<p>The mutual inductance between the coils  and  can be further expressed as:

(12)

</p>

<p>The relationship between transfer power and distance coefficient  can be obtained by Equations (6)–(12):

(13)

</p>

<p>By solving the above equation, the position of the intermediate coil-1 can be decided, and then transmission power is maximized. </p>

<head> 2.2. Equivalent Circuit Model of a Two-Intermediate Coil WPT System</head>
<p>
Two intermediate coils have the short circuit topology. The transmission distance is longer owing to using two-intermediate coils with a high quality factor. </p>
</text>
