<text id="autogum_academic_doc004" title="The Fast Potential Evaluation Method of Enhanced Oil Recovery Based on Statistical Analysis" shortTile="fast-potential-evaluation" author="Zhengbo Wang, Qiang Wang, Desheng Ma, Wanchun Zhao, Xiaohan Feng, Zhaoxia Liu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2227-9717/7/11/795/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
All countries in the world actively carry out technical research and the application of enhanced oil recovery according to the characteristics of their own oil national reservoirs. In particular, under the background of the continuous collapse of the international oil price since October 2014, the practical significance of enhancing oil recovery is more obvious. In 2014, the Journal of <hi rend="italic">Oil and Gas</hi> examined enhancing oil recovery projects worldwide, in which tertiary oil recovery contributed 663,000 BBL/d of crude oil to the United States. Thermal oil production and gas-flooding production accounted for a significant proportion of the tertiary oil production contribution. </p>

<p>In 1990, a study on enhancing the oil recovery of the potential evaluation and development strategy of waterflood oilfields in China revealed that polymer flooding is a technology with great potential, and it is feasible both technically and economically for enhanced oil recovery in China, who have used it to solve a series of key problems and make breakthroughs. Limited to the conditions at that time, the initial potential evaluation still has many deficiencies. Since 1996, there has been chemical compound flooding, CO2 miscible flooding, gas injection immiscible flooding, thermal recovery, ect. This was supplemented by the Petroleum Exploration and Development Institute, who compiled the corresponding economic potential evaluation software. The range of the second potential evaluation is wider, the software used is more suitable for the actual situation of our country, and the evaluation result is more reliable, which has more guiding significance for future work. </p>

<p>The following problems exist in the application and promotion of the second national potential evaluation software: (a) The model mechanism is oversimplified, which results in the limitation of the application scope of the model and affects the reliability of the operation results. (b) The increase of polymer flooding potential and chemical compound flooding is lower than that of numerical simulation, and the enhancing oil recovery of most blocks is less than 2–5%. (c) Heavy oil thermal recovery and steam flooding effect time lag, affecting the technical and economic evaluation results. (d) There are some bugs in the model program, through a series of means, which still cannot be solved. (e) The materialization parameters are too simple to be considered without considering the relationship between them, and so on. Since 1998, the third potential evaluation has been carried out in China. This evaluation is of great significance for the standardization of the third oil recovery and the formulation of medium - and long-term development strategies. </p>

<p>In this paper, a rapid evaluation method of tertiary oil recovery potential based on a statistical analysis is established by investigating the actuality of the tertiary oil recovery application, potential evaluation methods, and system technology of software at home and abroad, summarizing the experience of the field application and technical development trend. The fine quantitative screening method for tertiary oil recovery, and the rapid analogy evaluation method for the tertiary oil recovery potential are two important components of this method. The two parts are mutually inherited and progressively developed. At the same time, the integrated software of the potential evaluation and economic evaluation with a high integration degree, perfect function, and independent intellectual property rights are developed according to this method, which provides good technical support for the work of the tertiary oil recovery potential evaluation. </p>
</text>
