<text id="autogum_academic_doc387" title="Spatial Distribution of Temporalis Pressure Pain Sensitivity in Men with Episodic Cluster Headache" shortTile="spatial-distribution" author="María Palacios-Ceña, Stella Fuensalida-Novo, María  L Cuadrado, Carlos Ordás-Bandera, Pascal Madeleine, César Fernández-de-las-Peñas, Ángel  L. Guerrero" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4239/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
We found bilateral hypersensitivity to pressure pain within the temporalis muscle in men with episodic CH not to be associated with levels of anxiety or depression. Additionally, our mapping revealed a spatial anterior-to-posterior gradient of sensitivity to pressure pain in men with CH but not in headache-free controls. </p>

<p>In line with our hypothesis, there was a bilateral decrease of PPTs in men with CH compared with controls with large effect sizes. Our results agree with those previously reported where bilateral hypersensitivity to pain pressure in the temporalis area in patients with CH was also observed. However, these results differ from those reported by Malo-Urriés et al., who observed that the symptomatic side was more sensitive than the non-symptomatic side in a small sample of patients with CH. The current and previous findings suggest the presence of sensitization of trigeminal pain pathways in CH patients. In addition, the presence of bilateral pressure pain hyperalgesia in patients with unilateral symptoms supports potential sensitization of the central nervous system, as previously suggested, although further studies are needed. Similarly, bilateral hyperalgesia to pressure over the temporalis muscle has previously been found in patients with strictly unilateral migraine, suggesting that bilateral hypersensitivity is present albeit the presence of just unilateral symptoms in individuals with primary headaches. </p>

<p>Our patients were assessed during a long-lasting remission phase. Therefore, pressure pain hyperalgesia in the trigeminal area seems to be present in patients with CH during asymptomatic periods. These findings indicate that there is a baseline state of trigeminal sensitization in CH predisposing to periods of pain. Alternatively, it is also possible that the altered nociceptive processing could be induced by repetitive headache attacks of high intensity and then maintained without the presence of any nociceptive stimuli during the remission phase. Indeed, the occurrence of long-term potentiation induced by nociceptive stimuli has been suggested in other primary headaches. However, we cannot confirm the presence of central sensitization in CH, since PPTs represent a static outcome and dynamic measures of nociception would be needed. </p>

<p>Pressure pain sensitivity mapping based on multi-site recordings has previously been documented as a useful technique for visualizing the spatial topographic distribution of pain sensitivity. This study is the first attempt at assessing topographical pressure pain sensitivity maps in patients with episodic CH. According to our findings, in CH patients, there is an anterior-to-posterior gradient of sensitivity within the temporalis muscle so that the lowest pain thresholds are located in the anterior region of the muscle. This gradient is not present in headache-free controls, where the most sensitive area was located in the mid-muscle belly. The results of this study are similar to those previously described in other primary headaches, such as tension-type headache and unilateral migraine. To determine the mechanisms underlying the anterior-to-posterior gradient is beyond the scope of the current paper. However, two hypotheses can be stated. First, sensitization of trigeminal pathways could generate a pressure pain hyperalgesic pattern with an anterior-to-posterior distribution in primary headaches, regardless of unilateral or bilateral location of the symptoms or the specific type of headache. Secondly, an anterior-to-posterior gradient could be also related to different distribution of muscle nociceptors between the different areas of the temporalis muscle that could predispose to headaches, but this cannot be confirmed until histological studies are conducted. </p>

<p>Additionally, we also found that the levels of anxiety and depression do not seem to have a significant influence on pressure pain hyperalgesia within the trigeminal area in men with episodic CH. It would be interesting to investigate other potential psychological factors related to the observed anterior-to-posterior distribution of sensitivity to pressure pain in primary headaches. In fact, differences in the spatial distribution of sensitivity to pressure pain should be considered in future studies comparing headache populations and headache-free controls, since taking the same point as a reference could be biased. In addition, changes in the spatial distribution of pressure pain within the trigeminal area could be used to monitor the effects of treatment in individuals with CH. </p>

<p>We must recognize some limitations of our study. First, our sample was only comprised of men with episodic CH in a remission phase. Therefore, we cannot draw conclusions concerning women with CH, or men with chronic CH, or with episodic CH in an active phase. Secondly, depressive and anxiety levels of our sample were relatively low, thus, their potential role in spatial distribution of pressure pain sensitivity should be considered with caution at this stage. Thirdly, we used a cross-sectional design, which does not permit to determine a cause and effect relationship between spatial distribution of pressure pain sensitivity and the development or maintenance of CH. However, the fact that headache-free control subjects showed heterogeneous pain maps suggests that the anterior-to-posterior gradient observed in men with CH is related to the presence of pain. Longitudinal studies are needed to clarify this hypothesis. Finally, we only assessed static outcomes of nociception, i.e., PPT. Thus, dynamic outcomes such as temporal summation, wind-up, or conditioned pain modulation should be used in future studies to further characterize the presence of central sensitization in CH. </p>
</text>
