<text id="autogum_academic_doc743" title="Thermal Performance Assessment of Flexible Modular Housing Units for Energy Independence Following Disasters" shortTile="thermal-performance" author="Beungyong Park, Jinkyun Cho, Yongdae Jeong" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5561/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Theoretical Discussion and Case Studies</head>
<p>
According to Smith, industrialized housing has developed based on demand and available construction techniques. During the 16th and 17th centuries, Great Britain colonized much of the world, including India, the Middle East, Africa, Canada, and the United States. As a result, rapid construction was required in these areas. To meet this demand, components (wooden kits) were manufactured in England then transported worldwide via ships. This was first recorded in 1624. Later, on-site methods, where components are assembled at the construction site, and out-site methods, where the components are assembled in a factory before transportation, were developed; this is called the modularization method. Modular structures can be used for commercial and residential applications, which may be temporary or permanent. Modular commercial buildings include temporary structures such as construction site trailers, mobile classrooms, communication pods, and exhibition rooms as well as permanent structures such as dormitories, healthcare facilities, hotels, government buildings, and schools. The overseas modular building market has been led by advanced countries such as those in Europe, Japan, the United States, Canada, and Australia. The United Kingdom has the largest market for modular buildings, which make up 2.1% of the total construction market. In Korea, the market is estimated to be worth between ₩1.34 and ₩4.3 trillion. </p>

<head> 2.1. Literature Review</head>
<p>
In South Korea, studies on disaster relief housing are mostly related to architectural planning, such as planning requirements for temporary housing facilities, construction methodology, and functional demands. Kim et al. examined different types and plans for temporary housing relief as architectural countermeasures for disaster refugees. In particular, they classified and examined time-series-type structures and construction methods and then proposed a relief housing system suitable for open system modular housing. Moon et al. mentioned that temporary housing is affected by climate, structure, material, and duration of use, with structure being the most important factor. They demonstrated that fixed and portable housing can be categorized according to the structural characteristics. The relief housing development by Lim et al. can be seen as a representative study on practical development. They developed relief housing using standard elevation modules. The pilot application was examined using a subway station as a temporary shelter. Wang et al. proposed a horizontal expansion method based on joint development with modular-method-applied temporary housing. Through the design and mock-up module fabrication, they addressed the need for additional techniques to be developed with respect to reinforcing airtightness when joining, horizontal leveling when joining units, and the locking method between units. Similarly, disaster relief housing plans and temporary modular housing have been developed, but they are limited by the development of technical plans, structural aspects, and the joining of modules. In fact, few studies have addressed the thermal insulation and environmental performance aspects of housing development, which is necessary to understand the energy independence performance and the need for new and renewable energy generation and storage systems. </p>

<p>Modular housing for use in disaster areas should be able to provide the energy required by residents by utilizing elemental technologies such as solar panels, even in areas where the supply infrastructure is not available. Many previous studies have been conducted on net zero energy buildings and energy-independent buildings utilizing passive and active designs. Wind energy systems and PV panels are actively used for zero energy buildings and the energy savings achieved using active elements have been compared and analyzed. Aldegheri et al. demonstrated that it is possible to achieve energy production equivalent to 43% of the annual energy consumption of demonstration houses with building-integrated concentrating photovoltaics (BICPVs). It is important for modular housing to be suitable for various climates. Zubair et al. showed that the cooling load could be reduced by 12.3% by installing a PV panel on net present cost(NPC)-based roof, even in hot climates. </p>

<head> 2.2. Domestic and Overseas Modular Housing for Disaster Response</head>
<p>
Table 1 summarizes the existing research for modular disaster relief housing in South Korea and overseas in terms of the climate, shape, and vertical/horizontal expansion. Typical shapes include modules, containers, a combination of containers and tents, assembly type, and box unit type. Each of these is classified as either horizontal or vertical space expansion type due to structural differences based on the shape characteristics. In situations where the structures are not secured to make them stable, horizontal expansion is common; in contrast, modular and container-type buildings have a steel structure that facilitates vertical expansion. Features such as the finish and design of the exterior material are selected according to the local climate. </p>
</text>
