<text id="autogum_academic_doc204" title="From Newspaper Substrate to Nanotubes—Analysis of Carbonized Soot Grown on Kaolin Sized Newsprint" shortTile="newspaper-substrate" author="Bruce  E. Brinson, Varun  Shenoy Gangoli, Anjli Kumar, Robert  H. Hauge, W.  Wade Adams, Andrew  R. Barron" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2311-5629/5/4/66/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Despite the potential application of both single-walled carbon nanotubes (SWCNTs) and multi-walled carbon nanotubes (MWCNTs) for a broad range of research and commercial fields extending from electronics to medicine, their purity is of paramount importance with many of the end-uses. As a result, we have, among other things, concentrated much of our research efforts in developing purification methods to remove amorphous carbon, catalyst residue and defects. Conversely, one of the most commonly raised value enhancements of materials by CNTs is the modification of elastomer properties, where purity can actually be detrimental in some cases. This has led towards the use of larger MWCNTs that are inherently more defective, and hence easier to functionalize; however, there are limits on the number of concentric CNT tube walls before MWCNT embrittlement becomes an issue. For polymer matrices, mixtures of graphitic carbon, CNTs, and carbon black (CB) are of interest and have been shown to improve/preferentially modify CNT dispersion, electrical conductivity, mechanical reinforcement, and surface properties. A further consideration is that rubber compound reinforcing materials are considered as commodity products, and thus production cost is a critical consideration. A continuous flow method by which inexpensive heterogeneous CNT/CB products can be mass-produced and applied to rubber compounding, especially one that does not require industrial retooling, would hence be quite advantageous. </p>

<p>CNT synthesis has been a subject of interest in research labs around the world for multiple decades, and much has been learned, especially when it comes to chemical vapor deposition (CVD). CVD synthesis of CNTs began with directed growth on substrates but has since evolved to include floating-catalyst growth that is substrate-free, especially as it comes to more commercial-scale production utilizing a larger reaction volume. In addition, to process control and cost considerations, there is also a need to adopt greener and environment friendly synthesis methods utilizing natural, renewable, cheaper waste materials. In this regard, the synthesis of graphene, CNTs and carbon dots has been reported using several natural hydrocarbon precursors, as well food waste, vegetation waste, animal/bird/insect waste, and agro-waste for the synthesis of graphene and CNTs. A second component, the growth catalyst, has also been investigated using natural materials; however, there are limited studies on alternative substrates. </p>

<p>One of the challenges here is that large scale CVD growth of carbon nanotubes from fixed substrates is hampered by the cost of substrate preparation in addition to limitations of single surface batch processing as it comes to scaling up the process. A continuous flow system, that dramatically reduces both substrate and post synthesis process cost, needs to be devised. Common substrate preparation methods combine FexOy catalyst particles with silica, silicon and alumina films. Fixed bed CVD, the method used in this study, typically utilizes a single surface substrate. This clearly limits scalability relative to 3D or continuously formed substrates. As part of our exploration of potential stackable (3D), currently mass-produced, large-area and inexpensive substrates to produce a CNT containing soot product compatible with current industrial tooling, we investigated the use of newsprint as a substrate. Paper has been previously employed as a flexible substrate for CNT growth; however, this was limited to relatively small areas and varying degrees of success. Herein we report that hybridized graphitic-SWCNT-carbon black soot is rapidly grown on stacks of kaolin (china clay) sized newspaper stock, which makes it suitable as part of a method capable of using a multi-surface continuous feed process. </p>
</text>
