<text id="autogum_academic_doc075" title="Effect of Lipid-Encapsulated Acacia Tannin Extract on Feed Intake, Nutrient Digestibility and Methane Emission in Sheep" shortTile="effect-lipidencapsulated" author="Festus  Adeyemi Adejoro, Abubeker Hassen, Abiodun  Mayowa Akanmu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2615/9/11/863/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The use of plant secondary metabolites as natural alternatives to antibiotic growth promoters has continued to elicit great interest globally. Furthermore, supplementation with plant secondary metabolites is capable of improving livestock productivity while also reducing the impact of livestock production on the environment. One type of plant secondary metabolite known for their wide application in animal production are condensed tannins, which are water-soluble polyphenolic compounds of high molecular weight with the ability to modulate rumen fermentation. Past research has revealed that condensed tannins can bind with protein in feed, saliva, tissue, enzymes, and microbes. This results in reduced rumen protein degradability, and reduced urinary nitrogen loss. Other applications of CTs include the control of bloat and intestinal parasites in ruminants, as well as a reduction in enteric methane emissions. Condensed tannins exhibit their anti-methanogenic activity directly by inhibiting the growth of methanogens through the tanning action of their functional proteins, resulting in bacteriostatic and bactericidal effects. </p>

<p>However, moderate to high concentrations of dietary CT, which proved consistently effective in methane reduction, may also significantly depress dry matter intake and nutrient digestibility depending on the concentration and biological activity of the tannin. The astringency of tannins is particularly noted for the negative responses in feed intake observed in ruminants consuming high tannin concentrations. Equally, a compromise on intake and nutrient digestibility, if not carefully balanced, may impose a serious challenge on production performance. Beyond the rumen, free CT may also re-bind to dietary protein, digestive enzymes, or membrane proteins of mucosal cells, thereby reducing nutrient absorption. Recent studies have shown that encapsulation may be used to mask or reduce the negative effects associated with tannins and other bioactive compounds in the food or feed industry, with additional tendency to control the release of the active ingredient at the required site for optimum effectiveness. </p>

<p>Thus, encapsulation of tannin extract has the potential to mask the astringency by restricting the biological activity of tannins in the mouth and provide a sustained release in the rumen, guaranteeing the modulation of microbial fermentation, and, therefore, the tannin effect is limited to the rumen and post-rumen environment. According to Mamvura et al., the productivity of bioactive compounds may be enhanced when they are fully available at the precise location where they are required such as in the rumen. It is hypothesised that encapsulated <hi rend="italic">Acacia</hi> tannin extract (ATE) will confine the effect of tannin to the rumen, resulting in improved anti-methanogenic effect without an associated depression in feed intake. A gradual release of tannin in the rumen may equally ensure the minimal effect of tannin on nutrient absorption in the intestine. </p>

<p>The aim of this study, therefore, was to determine if encapsulating <hi rend="italic">Acacia mearnsii</hi> tannin extract in a lipid matrix will favourably mask the bitter taste of tannin and possibly slow down its release in the rumen without reducing its antimethanogenic potency. By this, the anticipated utilisation of encapsulated CT extract in methane reduction can be achieved without the associated negative effects on dry matter intake, nutrient digestibility and N-balance, using South Africa Mutton Merino wethers as a model animal. </p>
</text>
