<text id="autogum_academic_doc313" title="Hardness and Roughness of Overlaid Wood Composites Exposed to a High-Humidity Environment" shortTile="hardness-roughness" author="Emilia-Adela Salca, Salim Hiziroglu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-6412/9/11/711/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Wood composites are man-made products designed for specific quality or performance requirements. These products can be made in different thicknesses, grades, sizes, and may present different degrees of exposure durability. They can be found in diverse array of applications, from industrial scale to small home projects. </p>

<p>Wood composites such as particleboards and medium density fiberboards (MDF) are major products for furniture manufacturing and interior design of living spaces. Particleboard and MDF are still preferred nowadays to solid wood in cabinetry applications mostly for their low cost and finishing properties in overlaying and coating. To keep a balance between quality and low cost, manufacturers may use panels with either higher density or higher thickness, as well as high-quality resins. </p>

<p>Wood-based composites are hygroscopic materials changing their properties as a function of humidity. During processing and service, such composites are exposed to various changes of temperature and relative humidity which directly affect panel properties, such as thickness, surface smoothness, thermal and mechanical properties as well as formaldehyde emissions. Under such influences the panel balance is disturbed and deviations from its initial flatness may appear affecting the overall performance of the final product. </p>

<p>Laminated and overlaid particleboard and MDF panels are commonly used in the furniture industry because they provide durable and decorative surfaces.  </p>

<p>Resin impregnated decorative papers are used to produce both low-pressure laminates (LPL) and high-pressure laminates (HPL). Heat and pressure activate the resin in the impregnated paper creating a cross-linked bond with the substrate. These light weight papers have a weight between 40 and 150 g/m2 and can be manufactured from cellulosic or polymer-based synthetic papers. A low-pressure melamine (LPM) paper is obtained by impregnation with the thermoset resin, typically melamine which is thermally fused to a substrate, such as particleboard and MDF to form melamine boards, but it does not have any kraft paper core as those found in HPL. </p>

<p>Decorative panels present a low impact resistance as a drawback but have some other key benefits such as low cost, readiness for use, easy maintenance, and availability in a variety of colors and finishes, along with a range of thicknesses to suit residential and commercial applications. It was found that these impregnated papers retard the release of formaldehyde, reduce the absorption of humidity, and have improved abrasion and weathering resistance. </p>

<p>The surface quality of laminated panels is determined by the size of the wood particles or fibers on the surface layer. The so-called telegraphic effect is due to the roughness of the substrate penetrating through the overlay. Low humidity conditions do not affect any properties of these panels, but under exposure to high humidity, the surface roughness of these panels will be deteriorated. A proper control of the temperature and relative humidity (RH) in a house is healthy for both the inhabitants and the furniture within. Therefore, it is important to quantify the effect of changes in RH over a period of time on the properties of laminated panels to have a better understanding of their behavior during their service life and use. </p>

<p>There is a great potential for furniture production in Romania, including that of laminated furniture which is supported by residential construction works. </p>

<p>Therefore, this experimental work aims to evaluate the surface roughness and hardness of laminated wood-based composite panels produced in Romania when they are exposed to 65% and 95% RH levels. The findings of this study can be useful to enhance the manufacturing and service life of these overlaid composite panels. </p>
</text>
