<text id="autogum_academic_doc312" title="Thermoeconomic Optimization with PSO Algorithm of Waste Heat Recovery Systems Based on Organic Rankine Cycle System for a Natural Gas Engine" shortTile="thermoeconomic-optimization" author="Guillermo Valencia Ochoa, Carlos Acevedo Peñaloza, Jorge Duarte Forero" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4165/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The extensive use of industrial generation engines worldwide, the low efficiency (which does not exceed 42%), and the potential of the waste gases generated, makes this thermal machine a central research issue. Several methods have been proposed to improve the efficiency of these engines. One has been the implementation of an organic Rankine cycle (ORC) as a waste heat recovery system from the exhaust gases, where the working fluids play an important role in the optimization study to obtain better performance in the process. </p>

<p>In a power generation system, several thermodynamic cycles were implemented for waste heat recoveries, such as the ORC, the Kalina cycle, and the steam Rankine cycle. The complex structure of the Kalina cycle, the operational requirement of the steam Rankine cycle such as the high operating pressures and high risk of erosion, means the ORC cycle has the advantage given its simplicity, high reliability, and easy maintenance, which uses organic fluids for its operation. In addition, ORC is more suitable for using low and moderate energies (coolant engines and exhaust gases, for example) than the Kalina cycle and the steam Rankine. However, the different waste heat recovery configurations based on ORC cycle should be studied to be optimized under a thermoeconomic point of view for a particular heat source. Lion et al. present a complete thermodynamic study of a Winterthur Gas &amp; Diesel’s marine diesel engine, which is alow-speed 6 MW of power, using Ricardo Wave simulation software (2018.1, Ricardo UK Ltd, United Kingdom). The model was validated by comparing the results with experimental data, an exhaust gas recirculation low-pressure architecture was implemented to measure engine performance within the framework of international maritime organization Tier III regulations, where the data obtained from the simulation were the inputs used in a thermodynamic model implemented in engineering equation solver, capable of quantifying the performance of the ORC, of evaluating the viability of the proposed system. From the results, it is observed that about 5% of annual fuel consumption would be saved for the system without ORC since improving the efficiency would help to maximize the fuel economy. This research is limited to a thermodynamic study of several ORC architectures, but thermoeconomic indicators were not considered in detail. </p>

<p>Additionally, Liu et al. proposed different modifications to the configurations of the ORC cycle and how to evaluate the performance of this cycle, where they presented ORC best practice, and with these proposed modifications a thermal efficiency of 18.57% was achieved, higher than the other models evaluated, thus the study provides to future researchers relevant information to evaluate the cost-benefit of each configuration and determine which direction to take for further improvements, but the optimal practical reported for the ORC systems applied only to diesel engines and the contribution presented in this research is oriented to industrial gas engines. </p>

<p>In order to increase the energy efficiency, different modifications have been proposed to the ORC architecture, several of the proposed improvements aim to optimize the temperature profile, where the organic working fluid follows the external heat source in order to reduce the exergy destroyed in the evaporator and thus increase the general second low efficiency of the system. One of the modifications to the architecture of this system is known as RORC, where research has been carried out to increase the efficiency of the cycle by 9.29%, and from the data obtained from these studies it can also be appreciated that both the RORC and the simple ORC (SORC) work better with drier fluids, where the efficiency of the cycle was also affected by the critical temperature. These studies are limited to compare only the SORC and RORC cycles, and the double-stage ORC (DORC) study is not integrated with exhaust gases from a natural gas engine as a heat source. </p>

<p>In addition to these changes, more than one stage of the evaporation of the working fluid was added, where each stage has a different temperature and working pressure. This modification is considered in the DORC system, for this system was able to increase the efficiency with respect to SORC between 8.97% and 25% depending on the operating conditions described according to Braimakis et al. and Yang et al. investigations. However, this system has not been optimized and integrated to a GE Jenbacher engine type 6 as a bottoming cycle, and in thermoeconomic terms, some indicators of this thermal engine with ORC have not been studied in a real operational context, such as the leveled cost of energy (LCOE), the specific investment cost (SIC), and the payback period (PBP), which allow the technical and economic feasibility of this solution to be determined. </p>
</text>
