<text id="autogum_academic_doc719" title="Road Users’ Behavior at Marked Crosswalks on Channelized Right-Turn Lanes at Intersections in the State of Qatar" shortTile="road-users-behavior" author="Deepti Muley, Mohamed Kharbeche, Lucy Downey, Wafaa Saleh, Mohammed Al-Salem" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5699/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Users’ Behavior at Marked Crosswalks</head>
<p>
<figure>Figure 1</figure> shows the framework for pedestrians’ crossing behavior at marked crosswalks located on a channelized right-turn lane. In many cases, while approaching the marked crosswalk, a pedestrian analyzes the situation and if they do not see any oncoming vehicle/s, they start crossing without waiting at the sidewalk. If they see any oncoming vehicle while crossing, they accelerate or run to complete the crossing. This can be dangerous if the driver does not yield and continues at the same speed. However, if a pedestrian sees a vehicle or a series of oncoming vehicles, they wait at the sidewalk until they can cross safely. If the oncoming vehicle gives the right of way to the pedestrian by yielding, then the pedestrian starts crossing and completes the crossing maneuver safely; this is the safest crossing scenario. If the oncoming vehicle or series of vehicles do not stop, then the pedestrian must wait for a sufficient gap in the traffic stream before they can start crossing. The longer the pedestrian has to wait, the greater the chances that they will take risks when they cross. Drivers yielding and respecting the pedestrians’ right of way are essential for pedestrian’s safety at these crosswalks. </p>

<p>Some special cases, which impact pedestrian safety, are summarized below:</p><list>
<item>Some pedestrians step down from the sidewalk onto the crosswalk and wait for a gap in the traffic stream. This sometimes compels drivers to yield;</item>
<item>Sometimes, the pedestrian makes more than one attempt for initiating crossing. This occurs when drivers do not acknowledge the pedestrian’s right of way;</item>
<item>Some pedestrians start crossing as soon as the approaching vehicle is seen and cross the crosswalk just after a vehicle has passed and before the next one arrives. This is rolling gap acceptance;</item>
<item>Some pedestrians, who arrive running, maintain the same speed when on the crosswalk. This behavior can be risky, as the pedestrian might not have made accurate judgments about the speed or distance of oncoming vehicles; and</item>
<item>Some pedestrians appear distracted when they cross. Examples include talking with companions while crossing in groups, using a mobile phone, carrying luggage, grooming, drinking or eating, reading, looking at the surrounding instead of oncoming traffic, searching their bags, carrying a bicycle or umbrella, holding a child’s hand, or pushing a stroller.</item>
</list>

<p>
From the above observed special cases, only the effect of pedestrians crossing without waiting and distraction were considered in the analysis and pedestrians who waited on the road, rolling gap acceptance, and number of attempts were not considered. </p>
</text>
