<text id="autogum_academic_doc260" title="Secure Transmission for Buffer-Aided Relay Networks in the Internet of Things" shortTile="secure-transmission" author="Chen Wei, Wendong Yang, Yueming Cai" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4506/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Transmission Schemes</head>
<p>
In this section, a conventional non-jamming scheme and two source cooperative jamming schemes are presented for the considered buffer-aided relay IoT networks. </p>

<head> 3.1. NJ Scheme</head>
<p>
The total transmission is divided into two hops. In the first hop, the source sensor <hi rend="italic">S</hi> sends the signal to the relay sensor while intercepted by <hi rend="italic">K</hi> eavesdroppers . Hence, the received SNR at  and  can be, respectively, expressed as

(4)

(5)

where  denotes the transmit power of the source sensor, which obeys the uniform power allocation for ease of analysis.  and  represent the channel gains of link  and ,  is the variance of the additive white Gaussian noise (AWGN). </p>

<p>Similar to the first hop, the received SNR at <hi rend="italic">D</hi> and  can be, respectively, given by

(6)

(7)

where  is the transmit power of the selected relay sensor, and  and  denote the channel gains of link  and , respectively. </p>

<p>Due to the presence of multiple eavesdroppers, we take both NCE and CE scenarios into account. </p>

<p>In the NCE scenario, the eavesdroppers decode information individually without interactions. Hence, the received signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) at the eavesdroppers of the first and second hops can be, respectively, given by

(8)

(9)

</p>

<p>In the CE scenario, all eavesdroppers can exchange the information with each other and adopt the maximal ratio combining (MRC) for enhancing the intercept ability. Thus, the instantaneous SNR of the eavesdroppers’ channels for the first and second hops are expressed as

(10)

(11)

where  denotes the  channel vector between the source sensor and the eavesdroppers. Similarly,  represents the channel vector between the selected relay sensor and the eavesdroppers. </p>

<p>The NJ scheme is a benchmark invoked for the purpose of comparison, which can also be applicable for the practical application scenario due to it lower complexity. </p>

<head> 3.2. SCJ Scheme</head>
<p>
In this case, when the second hop is selected, the source sensor can send jamming signals to the eavesdroppers with the transmit power , which degrades the quality of eavesdroppers’ channels effectively without interfering other nodes. Furthermore, due to the total power constraint, we have , where  denotes the transmit power of the source sensor when transmitting useful information. Similar to the NJ scheme, the power allocation follows the uniform allocation rule, i.e., , . </p>

<p>The first hop of the SCJ scheme is the same as the NJ scheme, hence we have  and . In the second hop, the received signal-to-interference-plus-noise-ratio (SINR) at  is given by

(12)

where  denotes the link of  when <hi rend="italic">S</hi> acts as a jamming node. </p>

<p>Thus, for the NCE scenario, the received SNR and SINR at the eavesdroppers of the first and second hops can be written as

(13)

(14)

</p>

<p>For the CE mode, the received SNR and SINR of the eavesdroppers’ channel for the first and second hops are given by

(15)

(16)

where  represents the  channel vector between the source sensor and the eavesdroppers when the source acts as a jamming node. </p>

<head> 3.3. SCJ-OPA Scheme</head>
<p>
To further enhance the physical layer security for the SCJ scheme, the optimal power allocation operation is employed at the source sensor node under the SCJ-OPA scheme. Similar to the section above, we still assume that . Then, we have . Given  and  where  denotes the power allocation factor. We aim to find the optimal power allocation factor to minimize the secrecy outage probability of the considered system. Therefore, the optimization problem can be written as

(17)

where  represents the overall secrecy outage probability of the system. We derive the expression of the secrecy outage probability and solve the optimization in the following section. Moreover, making an appropriate substitution of the parameters, i.e.,  and , the received SNR or SINR at the corresponding node under the SCJ-OPA scheme can be obtained easily, hence is omitted. </p>

<p>Now, according to the authors of, the achievable secrecy rate of the first and second hops can be, respectively, expressed as

(18)

(19)

where , , , . </p>
</text>
