<text id="autogum_academic_doc068" title="Assessing Forms of Application of Azospirillum brasilense Associated with Silicon Use on Wheat" shortTile="assessing-forms-application" author="Fernando  Shintate Galindo, Willian  Lima Rodrigues, Antônio  Leonardo Campos Biagini, Guilherme  Carlos Fernandes, Eduardo  Bianchi Baratella, Castro  Alves da Silva Junior, Salatiér Buzetti, Marcelo  Carvalho Minhoto Teixeira Filho" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4395/9/11/678/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Among the winter season cereals, wheat (<hi rend="italic">Triticum aestivum</hi>) is considered to have great economic importance, with large productive capacity. Wheat is the third most produced crop, with over 600 million tons produced globally per year. However, despite the technological advances available in plant nutrition, soil management, and machinery, Brazil needs to import about 50% of all wheat consumed in the country. </p>

<p>The use of biological techniques such as plant growth-promoting bacteria (PGPB) can represent a sustainable alternative for cereal growth in tropical areas. Several PGPB genera show associations with different species of agricultural importance, such as <hi rend="italic">Azospirillum</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Arthobacter</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Azobacter</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bacillus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bradyrhizobium</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Burkholderia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Clostridium</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Gluconacetobacter</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Herbaspirillum</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pseudomonas</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Rhizobium</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Streptomyces</hi>. The use of these PGPB is growing, particularly in Latin America, for different crops. <hi rend="italic">Azospirillum</hi> is considered one of the most studied plant growth-promoting genera. An analysis of field trials that were conducted worldwide for over 20 years, where various non-legume crops were inoculated with <hi rend="italic">Azospirillum</hi> spp. under different weather and soil conditions, concluded that crop yield can increase up to 30%. </p>

<p>These bacteria can stimulate plant growth via a series of mechanisms, including the production of phytohormones, such as indole-3-acetic acid (IAA), gibberellins, cytokinins, and salicylic acid, as well as biological nitrogen fixation (BNF), and an increase in nutrient availability and nitric oxide production. In addition, <hi rend="italic">Azospirillum</hi> spp. were reported to reduce biotic and abiotic stresses, increase proline content in shoots and roots, improve water potential and apoplast water content, increase cell wall elasticity and chlorophyll content, increase photoprotection pigments, and improve stomatal conductance. <hi rend="italic">Azospirillum</hi> spp. were related to an increase in plant resistance to pathogens, inhibiting the development of bacterial diseases. The level of inoculation response was described as wide ranging, as determined by plant–inoculant–environment interactions. </p>

<p>Seed inoculation is the most commonly used technique for delivery of PGPB to cropped plants. However, it is possible to achieve the same or greater responses with other inoculation forms, such as groove or leaf inoculation. Also, more technological inputs were introduced in seed treatment, such as fungicides, insecticides, micronutrients, and biostimulants, which may cause harmful effects on soil microbiota, reducing inoculation efficiency. Therefore, studies with inoculation forms in tropical conditions should be performed, since very few field studies were conducted under Brazilian conditions, and new reports can be largely applicable to other important producing countries in South America and Africa. </p>

<p>Another strategy related to improved plant growth is the use of Si-based fertilizers. Some crops (e.g., sugarcane (<hi rend="italic">Saccharum officinarum</hi> L.), rice (<hi rend="italic">Oryza sativa</hi> L.), wheat, and maize (<hi rend="italic">Zea mays</hi> L.) can remove Si quickly and in great quantity. In recent years, the number of studies on Si increased substantially in many crops, especially grasses, due to the beneficial effects of Si application on plant resistance to abiotic and biotic stresses and on crop yields. Silicon application is related to a reduction in insect and pathogen occurrences, salt stress and drought, and the negative effect of heavy rain and winds, common in Savannah conditions. Silicon can also provide several benefits in plant growth and plant architecture, such as erectness and photosynthetic rate; it also results in decreased transpiration rate, as well as improvements in pest and diseases control and water economy. Calcium and magnesium silicate can also increase base saturation and soluble levels of P, Ca, Mg, and Si, thus decreasing the phytotoxic effect of Fe, Mn, Zn, Al, and Cd and correcting soil acidity. </p>

<p>Despite the several benefits of Ca and Mg silicate application as an Si source and inoculation with <hi rend="italic">Azospirillum brasilense</hi>, an increase in wheat grain yield is not always the case. Further research with inoculation forms associated with Si use are needed to determine how to maximize its benefits on growth promotion, wheat development, and yield. In addition, studies are needed to determine if Si utilization has any positive or negative interactions when wheat is inoculated with <hi rend="italic">A. brasilense</hi>. This study was based on the hypothesis of a synergistic effect between <hi rend="italic">A. brasilense</hi> inoculation forms and Si utilization, providing greater wheat development and yield. The objective of this study was to evaluate the effect of <hi rend="italic">A. brasilense</hi> inoculation forms and Ca and Mg silicate application as an Si source on the nutritional and productive properties and wheat grain yield in Savannah conditions. </p>
</text>
