<text id="autogum_academic_doc018" title="Transcriptomic Analysis Reveals Insect Hormone Biosynthesis Pathway Involved in Desynchronized Development Phenomenon in Hybridized Sibling Species of Tea Geometrids (Ectropis grisescens and Ectropis obliqua)" shortTile="transcriptomic-analysis" author="Zhibo Wang, Jiahe Bai, Yongjian Liu, Hong Li, Shuai Zhan, Qiang Xiao" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-4450/10/11/381/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Tea is an important non-alcoholic beverage crop. Hence, improving the yield and quality of tea would provide meaningful economic gain for many countries, particularly China, where tea is cultivated in. China is the largest tea-growing country, in which the tea plantation area reached approximately 3.1 million hectares in 2017 and currently includes 20 provinces and regions. In China, two sibling tea geometrid species, <hi rend="italic">Ectropis grisescens</hi> (Warren) (Lepidoptera: Geometridae, Ennominae) and <hi rend="italic">Ectropis obliqua</hi> (Prout), are the most serious pests chewing leaves of tea. The larvae feed on tea leaves and tender buds, resulting in a severe reduction in tea production and quality in the current and following years. </p>

<p>Though <hi rend="italic">Ectropis grisescens</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ectropis obliqua</hi> were named by Warren and Prout several decades ago, the two sibling tea geometrids were always mistaken as one species because of their extremely similar morphology. Such mistakes also caused a lot of problems in terms of prevention and control for tea-plant management. Afterwards <hi rend="italic">E. obliqua</hi> nucleopolyhedrovirus (<hi rend="italic">Eo</hi>NPV), an effective natural biological agent, has been successfully developed as a bio-insecticide in China for the control of the tea geometrids. Following that, Xi et al. found that some tea geometrid populations revealed diverse sensitivity to the virus but they did not know the reason at that time. Jiang et al. successfully differentiated the tea geometrid species in China as two independent species, i.e., <hi rend="italic">E. grisescens</hi> and <hi rend="italic">E. obliqua</hi>, based on evidence of morphology and molecular biology. Specifically, the 3.7% genetic distance between <hi rend="italic">E. obliqua</hi> and <hi rend="italic">E. grisescens</hi>, based on cytochrome oxidase I (COI) sequences, was found to be a practical distinguishing method that can provide a basis for further research on sibling species of tea geometrids. At the same time, they also found the reason why virus sensitivity showed that, despite differences between the two species, <hi rend="italic">E. obliqua</hi> is more sensitive to <hi rend="italic">Eo</hi>NPV than <hi rend="italic">E. grisescens</hi>. Further research focused on sibling species of tea geometrid after they became easily distinguished. Another bio-control method of sex pheromone trapping the sibling species of tea geometrids was restarted with the different components of sex pheromone reported between them. The main sex pheromone components of <hi rend="italic">E. grisescens</hi> were Z3, Z6, Z9-18:H and Z3, epo6, Z9-18:H, correspondingly Z3, Z6, Z9-18:H, Z3, epo6, Z9-18:H and Z3, epo6, Z9-19:H were sex pheromone components of <hi rend="italic">E. obliqua</hi>. As sibling species, tea geometrids sharing the same effective components of sex pheromone mean that reproductive interference may exist in sympatry. In fact, Zhang et al. verified the hypothesis of asymmetrical reproductive interference existing between two sibling geometrids in the laboratory. Males of both <hi rend="italic">E. grisescens</hi> and <hi rend="italic">E. obliqua</hi> could interfere through the intraspecific mating of the other species, but the impact of the mating interference differed. Such asymmetric mating preference and competitive interaction might be a driving force of reproductive isolation, speciation and evolution. </p>

<p>In order to accurately control to the two-sibling tea geometrids, their distribution was investigated in China and sympatric distribution of two species was found in some areas. Geographical isolation can be a pathway of reproductive isolation. For the two-sibling tea geometrids, it was not clear whether reproductive isolation existed in the condition of incomplete geographical isolation. Furthermore, hybridization experiments were implemented in order to verify this. During the study, transcriptomic analysis was applied for those asynchronously growing hybrid individuals in order to explore the regulating mechanism of desynchronized development phenomenon. More importantly, we think the filial generation is appropriate material for researching on the mechanism of insect development and reproductive isolation. </p>
</text>
