<text id="autogum_academic_doc376" title="GNSS Ionosphere Sounding of Equatorial Plasma Bubbles" shortTile="gnss-ionosphere-sounding" author="Guanyi Ma, Klemens Hocke, Jinghua Li, Qingtao Wan, Weijun Lu, Weizheng Fu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4433/10/11/676/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Manifested as irregular electron density or total electron content (TEC) variations, the equatorial plasma bubbles (EPBs) are a phenomenon related to the collisional Rayleigh-Taylor instability (RTI) mechanisms. Although the onset condition remains unclear, the RTI is believed to occur after sunset at low latitudes near magnetic equator and generates plasma depletions which grow up from the bottom side to the upper F layer. While moving upward, EPBs extend along the magnetic flux tube to higher latitudes and often reach the equatorial ionization anomaly crest. These plasma irregularities disturb radio communication and navigation by causing phase and amplitude scintillations or even signal loss, which is an important issue for space weather. Furthermore, the study of the RTI and EPBs is relevant to progress in understanding and modeling of ionospheric plasma physics. </p>

<p>The study of EPBs has gone a long way since it was first recorded as equatorial spread F (ESF) with ionosonde. The term EPBs was proposed when ground-based incoherent scatter radar detected low-density irregularities rising from the bottom side of F layer to an altitude far beyond the ionospheric peak. These irregularities were directly confirmed by AE-C satellite in-situ measurements to be regions with an abrupt decrease of electron density by two orders of magnitude with tens of kilometers scale. The optical imaging techniques probed a two-dimensional structure of the plasma bubble. Effects of scintillations on radio waves from the stars or satellites have been also used to investigate the behavior of EPBs. TEC fluctuation measured with ground-based Global Navigation Satellite System (GNSS) networks can capture occurrence and evolution of EPBs and reveal their longitudinal occurrence characteristics as well. Spaceborne GNSS radio occultation of Constellation Observing System for Meteorology, Ionosphere, and Climate (COSMIC) complements the ground-based observations of EPBs with its global coverage. Moreover, it is crucial to obtain the vertical structure of the ionosphere. For this reason, basing on GNSS and radio occultation measurements, a three-dimensional morphology of EPBs was deduced and a tomography method was attempted to reconstruct EPBs in a Brazilian sector. </p>

<p>Recent researches on RTI and EPBs have been driven mostly by space weather concerns to identify the key environmental parameters leading to the presence of EPBs. Comprehensive observation can reveal the structure and evolution of EPBs that are connected with their initial conditions. This paper aims to investigate the characteristics of EPBs in space- and ground-based GNSS data. The scintillation index S4 and electron density of the ionosphere, profiled by spaceborne GNSS radio occultation of COSMIC, can provide new information on their vertical structure, occurrence, and evolution process of EPBs. Together with ground-based observation, three-dimensional aspects of EPBs can be inspected. We focus on low latitude regions at longitude ~110° E in south China in March 2014 when EPBs occurred every day of the month, and therefore a common underlying cause to seed the RTI can be examined. We use GNSS radio occultation of COSMIC to derive the vertical structure of EPBs and relate their characteristics with ground-based GNSS measurements in China. Global distribution of irregularities occurrence is also presented. Section 2 introduces data and analysis methods. Our results are described in Section 3, where TEC fluctuation and occurrence from ground-based GNSS observation are displayed in Section 3.1, as well as temporal variations of electron density and EPBs occurrence profiles, global occurrence of scintillations caused by EPBs, and sporadic E (Es) from COSMIC are shown in Section 3.2. Section 4 presents a discussion of a comprehensive view of EPBs by combining both ground-based and space-based observations and referencing previous research findings. The conclusions are drawn in Section 5. </p>
</text>
