<text id="autogum_academic_doc289" title="Deduction in Non-Fregean Propositional Logic SCI" shortTile="deduction-nonfregean" author="Joanna Golińska-Pilarek, Magdalena Welle" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-1680/8/4/115/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>One of the tasks of formal logic is to provide adequate tools for the formal analysis of certain fragments of natural language, as well as for the languages of particular fields of science. It is commonly accepted that the theory of interpretation of a language is semantics. The choice of semantics determines how we think about a given language and what meaning we assign to its components. It is often acknowledged that the first precisely formulated semantic principles—that serves as a foundation for contemporary formal logic and have determined its development—were presented by Frege in his <hi rend="italic">Begriffsschrift</hi>. According to Frege, a correct and adequate formal system of a given language should meet the following conditions: </p>

<p>
<list>
<item><b>F1</b>All names and all sentences have meaning and denotation. Meaning is not the same as denotation.</item>
<item><b>F2</b>A name and a sentence are the proper names of their denotations.</item>
<item><b>F3</b>Only one logical value can be assigned to each sentence: true or false.</item>
<item><b>F4</b>If two expressions have the same denotation, then they are exchangeable in any propositional context of a sentence without changing the logical value of that sentence.</item>
<item><b>F5</b>If two sentences are exchangeable in any propositional context of a sentence without changing its logical value, then they have the same denotation.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>Note that crucial notions for Frege’s account are the following: meaning, denotation, and logical valuation. Frege admits that the meaning of a sentence is not the same as its denotation. Indeed, the same holds for names: ‘Evening Star’ and ‘Morning Star’ denote the same object, but they have different meanings. The meaning of a sentence should be understood as its sense that the sentence expresses. Thus, we should ask what a sentence is referring to. From the formal point of view, the answer to this question requires, in particular, to decide what the denotation of a propositional variable is. </p>

<p>Propositional variables have an unusual character due to the fact that, at the same time, they are formulas. In classical logic, this ambiguity is removed as it identifies denotations of sentences with their truth values. In other words, in classical logic, propositional variables occur only at the metalogical level (they are not treated as real variables) or, as it holds in propositional calculus, variables range over the two element set of logical values. Within such an account, only terms have a meaningful ontological reference. Thus, the advocate of classical logic, if he is also a proponent of the Fregean semantic principles, must accept that all true sentences have one and the same denotation, namely the logical value , and denotation of all false sentences is the logical value . </p>

<p>The consequence of Frege’s semantic principles, according to which denotations of sentences are logical values, is usually called the <hi rend="italic">Fregean principle</hi>, and every logical system that adopts this principle is called a <hi rend="italic">Fregean system</hi>. The Fregean approach can be considered as philosophically justified in the study of mathematical languages, but it is not obvious that such an approach is justified as a foundation of a philosophically adequate semantics. The debatable cases of the applicability of the Fregean account in the formalization of any language are, for instance, theories of meaning or ontology. If we admit that the references of sentences are situations (states of affairs) that these sentences describe (in analogy with the assumption that the semantic references of terms are objects named by these terms), then the Fregean principle is not only a semantic principle, but also an ontological one which imposes a quantitative restriction on the universe of situations: there are at most two situations described by sentences. This is an extremely strong assumption. Note that the Fregean account does not impose an upper limit on the universe of objects. </p>

<p>Roman Suszko in 1968 proposed to change the Fregean paradigm and introduced the so-called <hi rend="italic">non-Fregean logic</hi> (see also). The basic philosophical assumption underlying non-Fregean logic is the thesis in reality to which the language is referring, and there exist semantic correlates of all expressions that are not purely syntactic. Therefore, in the non-Fregean approach, it is assumed that the semantic correlates of names are objects from the universe of objects, the semantic correlates of predicates are appropriate sets, and the semantic correlates of sentences are situations described by these sentences. Furthermore, a universe of situations cannot be quantitatively restricted, except that there are at least two situations. </p>
</text>
