<text id="autogum_academic_doc077" title="Effects of Regulatory T Cell Depletion on NK Cell Responses against Listeria monocytogenes in Feline Immunodeficiency Virus Infected Cats" shortTile="effects-regulatory" author="Rita  D. Simões, Alora LaVoy, Gregg  A. Dean" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4915/11/11/984/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Three key immunological features of lentiviral infection are the lack of an effective immune response against the virus, susceptibility to opportunistic pathogens, and generalized immune activation. The underlying mechanisms that lead to these immunologic alterations are complex and interrelated. Regulatory T cells (Treg) are thought to contribute to the control of excessive immune activation on one hand and suppression of the anti-viral response on the other hand. Such Treg-mediated suppression can render the host immune system unable to clear chronic infections. During chronic human, simian, or feline immunodeficiency virus infection (HIV-1, SIV, and FIV, respectively), Treg cells are capable of suppressing antiviral responses in vitro. Our lab has shown that Treg suppression of antiviral responses is also exerted in vivo during chronic FIV infection and that transient depletion of CD25+ Treg cells improved the antiviral response. Treg cells thus contribute to viral persistence in lentiviral infection by suppressing adaptive immune responses. The role of Treg in the suppression of the innate immune system and susceptibility to opportunistic infections has been much less studied. </p>

<p>We have employed the intracellular opportunistic pathogen <hi rend="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</hi> (Lm) to probe the immune defects associated with FIV. Using this immune challenge model, we found that FIV-infected cats have an impaired innate response that fails to gain initial control of bacterial replication prior to the adaptive immune response. We also showed that locally delivered interleukin 15 (IL-15), a cytokine known to activate and stimulate natural killer (NK) cells, significantly restored innate immune function as measured by Lm clearance. Further investigation revealed that NK cells and NK T cells (NKT) from FIV-infected cats display heightened constitutive levels of proliferation and apoptosis, and a defective response to Lm compared to the NK/NKT cell response in specific-pathogen-free (SPF) control cats. </p>

<p>The early control mechanism of Lm does not rely on T cells; however, a T cell response is required for bacterial clearance, as demonstrated by T cell-deficient mice that are able to control but not clear Lm infection. It seems that NK cell production of interferon gamma after stimulation with IL-12 and IL-18 plays an important role in Lm control. Several studies have shown that NK cell-depleted mice and rats fail to control initial Lm infection, resulting in a higher bacterial burden, whereas in normal animals infected with Lm, NK cells are recruited from the blood to the spleen, liver, and/or lymph nodes, and increased NK cell activity is observed during the first days of Lm infection. </p>

<p>Our objective in the present study was to determine whether Treg contribute to the impaired NK cell function in FIV-infected cats, and reduced capacity to clear Lm. We hypothesized that in vivo Treg cell depletion using anti-feline CD25 monoclonal antibody prior to innate immune challenge with Lm would improve the innate immune response and the clearance of bacteria. </p>
</text>
