<text id="autogum_academic_doc730" title="Sustainable Online Shopping Logistics for Customer Satisfaction and Repeat Purchasing Behavior: Evidence from China" shortTile="sustainable-online" author="Daeheon Choi, Chune  Young Chung, Jason Young" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5626/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions</head><head> 5.1. Research Summary and Conclusion </head>
<p>
This study found that the quality of an online shopping logistics service influences customer satisfaction, which drives repeat purchasing behavior. Five hypotheses were established to represent the relationship between customer satisfaction and each factor of the logistics service; namely, quality of information, quality of order, quality of delivery, price of delivery, customer service, and customer satisfaction. Each subject from a sample of 150 Chinese customers with online shopping experience was sent a questionnaire. The results of the empirical analysis show that the quality of a logistics service has a statistically significant impact on customer satisfaction and that quality of delivery is the main factor of influence. Furthermore, the results show that customer satisfaction has a statistically significant impact on repeat purchasing behavior. The results provide insights into the strategy behind China’s fast-growing online shopping industry, which focuses on maintaining stability through long-term customer relationship management. The factors affecting customer satisfaction in the online shopping industry are quality of order, quality of information, quality of delivery, price of delivery, and customer service. Furthermore, customer satisfaction affects the intention to repurchase. In conclusion, strategic management of the factors that affect customer satisfaction can increase customers’ intentions to repurchase. </p>

<head> 5.2. Research Implications and Future Research Directions </head>
<p>
The results of this research provide various theoretical meanings for online shopping logistics services, which can be considered for empirical analysis. This, in turn, can be used to suggest several policies and solutions to assist online shopping malls in establishing customer-oriented strategies that improve quality management. This study suggests practical semantics to direct the operations and management of online shopping transactions and to effectively pursue customer-oriented strategies. </p>

<p>The implications of this study and future directions for research are as follows. First, the scale of online shopping in China is increasing gradually. Accordingly, the number of Internet users is increasing. China joined the World Trade Organization and signed a free-trade agreement with Korea in early 2016, and, thus, the documented information related to the Chinese online shopping industry is important for businesses attempting to enter the market. </p>

<p>Second, the literature on the logistics services of online shopping is insufficient, therefore warranting further research on leading variables. These determinants of logistics service quality were found to yield similar results to the factors related to online shopping mall success as well as the factors previously related to service quality. However, some limitations to these determinants remain. In the future, various determinant factors should be systematically researched and analyzed, enabling the extraction of factors constituting logistics service quality. </p>

<p>Third, online shopping logistics service is an important factor in competition between online shopping malls. Considering that the cost of return shipping is problematic, it is essential that this topic be studied further.  </p>

<p>To extract and measure the determining factors of logistics service quality in online shopping, a method of measurement that eliminates subjectivity must be developed. An improved measurement index for customer satisfaction should also be created. </p>

<p>Fourth, the prediction by the 2017 information and technology (IT) market is that service platforms will continuously evolve in line with the mobile era. As the Chinese market transforms, many mobile-based online-to-offline (O2O) services are attracting large-scale investment and experiencing rapid growth. </p>

<p>O2O, a buzzword of the 2017 IT market, is a service devised to organically converge online and offline markets. Based on ICT, O2O attracts customers online and then provides them with services offline. In other words, customers purchase products and services online, and the actual services are provided offline. This is also referred to as a bilateral marketing technique. </p>

<p>Many countries around the world, including China and Korea, are utilizing O2O services that serve as the bridge between online payment and offline service. Examples include placing an order for food delivery, reserving a taxi, and searching for lodgings through a mobile application. As O2O services grow in diversity, so will their customer base. Future studies should develop indices and conduct research in this area. </p>

<p>Lastly, due to the small sample size in the empirical analysis, a structural equation model could not be used. This model may be employed as an alternative estimation approach with a large sample in the future.
 </p>
</text>
