<text id="autogum_academic_doc605" title="Do Compactness and Poly-Centricity Mitigate PM10 Emissions? Evidence from Yangtze River Delta Area" shortTile="compactness-polycentricity" author="Jing Tao, Ying Wang, Rong Wang, Chuanmin Mi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4204/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions</head>
<p>
Urban form plays a key role in explaining the concentration of transport-related pollutant emissions. Regarding the rapid urbanization and urban expansion and the consequent long-lasting impacts on accessibility, housing affordability, and air pollutants, knowledge on the issue of how compactness and poly-centricity affect air quality is of crucial importance for China. For the mitigation of pollutant emissions, many studies suggest developing compact urban forms and polycentricism to reduce the level of emissions. However, the effect of compact form on air quality is usually controversial. In addition, knowledge on the effects of poly-centricity and compactness of an urban form in terms of jobs-housing balance on air quality in Chinese cities is scarce.  </p>

<p>The current study takes the first step toward a better understanding of the relationships between compact urban form and poly-centricity and air quality for a sample of 19 YRD cities by using the analysis of the spatial durbin model (SDM). Notwithstanding the limitations of OLS analysis, the SDM provide a unique opportunity to be able to investigate the spatial effect of pollutants and the way to mitigate emissions. The analysis indicates that air pollutants in these cities responds differently to some urban characteristics than was expected from the evidence in the case of the US and EU cities.  </p>

<p>The findings show that compactness in terms of urban density, jobs-housing balance, and urban centralization are important determinants for air pollutants in terms of PM10 emissions. The rapid urbanization and urban expansion have led to clustered development in the outskirts, as yet most of jobs and amenities remained concentrated in the traditional centers. Hence, the large effect of an increase in city size on VMT and congestion, cities with a larger city size tend to emit more PM10. In addition, cities with more vehicle ownerships have a large effect on PM10 emissions, which indicates that more vehicles used are one of the reasons for more PM10 emissions. After controlling these variables, cities with higher urban density have more PM10, while higher degree of jobs-housing balance and urban centralization have less PM10. In addition, poly-centricity in terms of developing too many activity centers has a higher level of PM10 emissions, while enhancing polycentric clusters does not necessarily result in more PM10 emissions. However, for cities with more private car vehicles of &gt;10 million, polycentric clustered development may improve air quality in terms of PM10, but this improvement may be limited. Therefore, our paper indicates that jobs-housing balanced and concentrated compactness can be two effective strategies to reduce air pollution.  </p>

<p>Our findings suggest that strategies aimed to reduce air pollution by compactness and polycentric development may need to be reconsidered in the context of Chinese cities. According to the findings of this empirical study, policy implications for cities in developed countries should be cautiously developed. Some incomparable results of our empirical findings, such as the positive impact of compactness in terms of urban density on air pollutants in the context of YRD cities, might contribute to the longstanding debate and the impact of compact development on air pollution in developed countries. In addition, our empirical results also contribute additional evidence to the literature and provide some policy implications for Chinese cities that aim to mitigate air pollution by polycentric development. To some degree, our findings support the current polycentric development pattern in Chinese cities, as polycentric development enhances a more balanced population distribution between the main center and its sub-centers for those cities with a large number of private car ownerships (&gt;10 million within cities). However, poly-centricity by developing too many centers may also lead to more air pollutant emissions. </p>

<p>However, the data used in this paper have limitations, which need to be further extended. First, following Engelfriet and Koomen and Li et al., we use population centers rather than employment centers to measure poly-centricity. Focusing on employment data will shed more light on the heterogeneity that potentially exists in the relationship between poly-centricity and air pollution, i.e., the impacts may be heterogeneous for cities with different jobs-housing balances, which is not considered in our paper. Second, the data obtained in this paper is limited to the administrative boundary of urban districts from the statistical yearbook of local cities. Future studies can use more a fine-grained level of data, to advance our understanding of compactness and poly-centricity in air pollution emissions.
 </p>
</text>
