<text id="autogum_academic_doc250" title="What is still Limiting the Deployment of Cellulosic Ethanol? Analysis of the Current Status of the Sector" shortTile="still-limiting-deployment" author="Monica Padella, Adrian O’Connell, Matteo Prussi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4523/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Technology Trends and Barriers to Large Scale Deployment</head>
<p>
The trend in development of cellulosic ethanol production has been towards projects seeking to show (and indeed improve) upon the overall production chain; important to demonstrating the viability of this pathway. Overall, the development of both energy and cost effective pretreatment, hydrolysis and fermentation, remain the challenges hindering large-scale deployment of lignocellulosic biomass conversion to ethanol. </p>

<head> 5.1. Pretreatment</head>
<p>
One of the major challenges of lignocellulosic to ethanol is to ensure optimization of biomass conversion into components and by-products. Pretreatment schemes ensuring optimized use of the biomass continue to be developed. Raw material flexibility, minimum inhibitor formation, as well as maximum carbohydrate yields are central targets. Using feedstocks available in quantities large enough to supply a factory (as opposed to tiny amounts upon which a laboratory test could be carried out) brings its own technological challenges: the variability in quality and composition of the feedstock is clearly recognized as a key point, resulting in the need for a robust pretreatments section. Among the various techniques applied in real plants, enzymatic hydrolysis has proven to be efficient, but enzymes cost can account for up to 30–50% of the total cost of ethanol production. In order to overcome this barrier, new types of cellulases are being studied, such as bacterial enzyme complexes. Additionally, the presence of lignin during hydrolysis behaves as an inhibitor when it deposits itself onto cellulose in biomass, making it inaccessible to enzymes, or it can even adsorb the enzymes itself. </p>

<head> 5.2. Fermentation</head>
<p>
Simultaneous utilization of pentose sugars by highly effective industrial yeast strains is still a challenge in developing continuous fermentation, which is expected to increase the yield and reduce the cost of the final product. The tolerance of ethanol producing bacteria for high substrate, inhibitor, and product concentration still needs to be improved; its progress on developments of co-fermenting microbes have been slower than projected. Review on “present technical issues” hindering cellulosic ethanol production indicated microbial species had been engineered to ferment both C5 and C6 sugars, but ethanol yields were low, and the microbes had low tolerance to high ethanol contents compared to C5 fermenting microbes. Liu et al. further reported that there has been considerable work trying to improve co-fermenting bacteria for at least four decades to date, but still today, it’s possible to recognize familiar difficulties amongst various projects.  </p>

<p>Other ethanol producing organisms such as yeasts, Escherichia coli, Klebsiella oxytoca, Lactobacillus sp., Clostridium sp., and others are developed for the simultaneous utilization of pentose and hexose sugars but their practical application has still to be proven. Alcohol producing strains with the ability to hydrolyze polymeric substrates have been in development for some time; although high end product concentration and selectivity (toward greater production of the desired alcohol), and insensitivity to inherent and generated inhibitors and process conditions remain major goals.  </p>

<p>High dry matter concentration in a fermentation batch is also desirable as this will give high product concentration and help product recovery from fermentation broth. This could be achieved by developing novel process layouts involving systems aiming at immobilization of the fermenting organisms by the advanced use of non-fouling membrane systems, encapsulation of the organisms in polymer beads, etc. Efficient product separation is another advantage of advanced fermentation set-ups. This could be a critical step in the direction of a transfer from the current batch-wise into continuous fermentation processes, which would represent a more effective conversion. </p>

<head> 5.3. Downstream</head>
<p>
Downstream processing of products requires advances in membrane or adsorbent technology. One challenge is effective separation of alcohols from water. There is a need for membranes with high removal capacity of product, e.g., for pervaporation or suitable absorbents. Separation and rectification technology is the most demanding and needs further research on materials (membranes and adsorbents). The need to add water to the fermentation mixture to keep viscosity low and to limit bacteria inhibition creates another issue as the water will need to be driven-off during distillation. Thus, work to improve this need for water addition would likely improve the overall plant energy balance. </p>

<head> 5.4. By-Products</head>
<p>
The fate of lignin and hemicelluloses are one of the important challenges to be overcome. Processing has to avoid unfavorable conditions for sugar re-formation (back-reaction), chemical derivatization (pentoses to furfural, lignin to sulfo-lignin, and formation of lignin-carbohydrate complexes), and physical change. Separated raw material constituents (i.e., lignin and extractives) can be further converted into value-added products, for which a lot of research has been done. Fermentation broth as well as solid residues (including bacterial/yeast cell mass) are nutrient rich and can be recycled into the process, used as feed for animals, or added to biogas plants. However, it should be noted that an effective separation process for the biomass constituents after pretreatment remains a challenge. </p>
</text>
