<text id="autogum_academic_doc085" title="Analysis of the Performance of Transporting Soybeans from Mato Grosso for Export: A Case Study of the Tapajós-Teles Pires Waterway" shortTile="analysis-performance" author="Breno  Tostes de Gomes Garcia, Diana  Mery Messias Lopes, Ilton  Curty Leal Junior, José  Carlos Cesar Amorim, Marcelino  Aurélio Vieira da Silva, Vanessa  de Almeida Guimarães" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6124/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Literature Review</head>
<p>
The concept of sustainability has been attracting increasing attention from the international community due to demands from society for better quality of life and the impacts of climate change caused by human activity, altering the dynamics of ecosystems, as well as economic pressures for improvement in productive processes. </p>

<p>Originally, the concept of sustainability focused on reducing the consumption of resources by productive activities. However, this concept has evolved to include aspects such as economic and social welfare, such as justice, human health, and environmental integrity. </p>

<p>The Brundtland Report defined sustainable development as “development that meets the needs of the present without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own needs.” This idea indicates the need to establish limits on the use of natural resources, considering the current availability of technology and how society (social organization) manages natural resources, while considering the ability of the biosphere to absorb the effects of human activities. </p>

<p>The limited availability of natural resources with increasing demand for consumption means that these resources are becoming scarcer, with a parallel increase in the generation of wastes. According to, if the use of nonrenewable resources continues to expand at the current pace of global population growth, humankind will simply exhaust many natural resources. </p>

<p>Therefore, it is imperative to search for more sustainable economic models, where materials and energy from discarded products do not leave the economic system (closed system), as observed in the circular economy (CE). </p>

<p>The idea of the CE concept assumes that natural resources are finite, in contrast to the currently prevailing paradigm of the economic system. In light of this, CE approaches consider the implementation of closed economic and physical cycles, with regenerative and restorative characteristics, such as maintenance, repair, reuse, refurbishment, remanufacturing, and recycling). Therefore, the CE idea aims to achieve sustainable production and consumption, with conciliation of the economic, social and environmental aspects. </p>

<p>With the adoption of a CE approach, organizations can holistically obtain benefits in the economic, environmental, and social dimensions through sustainable development, such as:<list>
<item>increased recycling and more efficient use of resources and greater reliance of renewable energies, to minimize the negative impacts on the global ecosystem;</item>
<item>increased business competitiveness, generating social gains (job and income creation), through greater remanufacture, refurbishment and reuse of materials, products, and components, along with extension of the useful life of products, through changes in the patterns of consumption, including shared use;</item>
<item>lowering of costs, maximization of value, minimization of risks of shortages of natural resources, and sudden price fluctuations in the supply and demand for raw materials.</item>
</list>

<p>
According to, sustainability should permeate all economic sectors, such as the industrial, commercial, and service sectors. In the last case, this includes the transport service sector, where the concept offers a way to reduce the impacts of the intense flow of goods around the world. </p>

<head> Sustainable Transportation Systems</head>
<p>
The externalities generated in the environmental and social ambits of cargo transport operations have attracted strong interest from the academic community and from public policymakers. Therefore, the management of transport systems should be integrated in sustainable development strategies. </p>

<p>For this to become reality, the transport sector must meet economic needs (commercial relations), be easy for the public to access, and be structured to minimize the consumption of energy and emission of pollutants, along with safety, with the overall goal of improving the quality of current and future generations. According to, a sustainable transport sector should consider the social, environmental, and economic aspects, a position corroborated by. </p>

<p>A sustainable transport system must reduce the consumption of energy, emission of pollutants (CO2 and other GHGs), and maintenance costs of vehicles, besides improving the safety of roadways, railways, and waterways. For this, stated that it is necessary to carry out actions related to:<list>
<item>modal transfer to transport alternatives with greater energy efficiency;</item>
<item>greater use of renewable energy sources;</item>
<item>improvement of existing transport infrastructure along with the use of new vehicle technologies;</item>
<item>management of supply chains with focus on reducing GHG emissions; and</item>
<item>increased reliance on circular economy precepts with the objective of recycling products to obtain raw materials for the production of others.</item>
</list>
 </p>
</text>
