<text id="autogum_academic_doc012" title="Performance and Behavioural Responses of Group Housed Dairy Calves to Two Different Weaning Methods" shortTile="performance-behavioural" author="Gillian Scoley, Alan Gordon, Steven Morrison" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2615/9/11/895/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Weaning is a multifaceted stressor incorporating nutritional, environmental and physiological elements and thus is one of the most challenging periods for both producers and calves (e.g.,). Improper handling of stressors in early calfhood can impact negatively upon future health, welfare and productivity. Abrupt weaning of calves, whereby a previously unchanged milk allowance is removed suddenly over 24 h, has been associated with decreased solid feed consumption in the pre-wean period and a decrease or stall in growth rate in the period following the withdrawal of milk. Practices such as step-down or gradual weaning through reduction in volume of milk over a number of days or reduction in number of milk meals have been suggested as a means of reducing the impact of weaning stress. Sweeney et al. examined the impact of weaning duration on concentrate intake and performance of calves offered high levels of milk. Concentrate intake was increased in calves subject to 10 or 22 day weaning durations when compared to those weaned either abruptly or over 4 days. However, the increased intake was not sufficient to compensate for the reduced intake of milk, leading to lower digestible energy intakes and low live weight gains in the calves weaned over 22 days. Another method of gradual weaning is to increase dilution of milk replacer. This method was used by Overvest et al. in pair housed calves as it was considered that if a volume reduction method had been implemented there could have been greater variation in milk intake between calves. These gradual weaning methods have been shown to encourage solid feed intake at an earlier age which is thought to help prepare calves for a solid feed diet and thus lessen the impact of milk removal (e.g.,). However, these studies also highlight the importance of considering calf age, concentrate intake and milk feeding system when choosing a weaning method so as to ensure calves achieve performance targets. </p>

<p>Calf reaction to stressors such as weaning has traditionally been assessed using behavioural and aural observations (e.g.,). Recently, however, it has been suggested that the use of combined remote sensing technologies could allow measurement of several behavioural and physiological responses, which, when compared with measuring only a single aspect, could provide a more accurate aggregate indicator of animal well-being. The use of automatic milk feeders and pedometers has provided increased opportunities for behaviour monitoring in a remote, non-invasive manner. With regard to long-term measurements, automated feeders allow precise measurement of individual feed intake (e.g.,) and the recording of behavioural traits, deviations in which can be indicative of increased stress as a result of feeding regime. Measurement of calf activity using pedometers or accelerometers has previously been linked with hunger, with De Paula Vieira et al. finding that standing time was increased by 1 hr in limit fed calves when compared with those fed ad libitum. With regard to underlying physiological response to stressors, recent research has highlighted heart rate variability (HRV) as a viable, non-invasive parameter for measuring response to environmental, physiological and psychological stress load. </p>

<p>With an increasing range of on-farm sensing technologies available, the aim of this study was to determine the effect of gradual versus abrupt weaning on group housed calves using non-invasive, automated behavioural and physiological parameters. A further objective was to assess the impact of weaning method on calf performance parameters. </p>
</text>
