<text id="autogum_academic_doc672" title="A System Dynamics Model of Online Stores’ Sales: Positive and Negative E-WOM and Promotion Perspective" shortTile="system-dynamics-model" author="Qiang Yan, Simin Zhou, Xiaoyan Zhang, Ye Li" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6045/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
With the development of the internet, the emergence of electronic commerce has broken the limitations of traditional retail. Today, online transactions occupy a large part of our life. In a fiercely competitive environment, it is quite critical for online stores to improve the sales and profits for sustainable development. In virtual network transactions, we have no access to see the actual goods, so the trust and evaluations of online consumers becomes quite important. Consumers can create much more value for the company, not only economic value, but also intangible value including electronic word of mouth (e-WOM), referees, and feedback, which give an essential reference for other consumers. </p>

<p>In recent years, researchers have paid a lot of attention to the impact of e-WOM on online sales. Consumers can collect information about products or services and share their own opinions, evaluations, or knowledge on the internet. Research shows that e-WOM has a significant impact on consumers’ brand cognition, preference, perceived value, purchase intention, and decision making. Therefore, e-WOM is extraordinarily vital for the operation and development of an enterprise. Positive e-WOM can promote sales of the enterprise, while the spread of negative e-WOM can quickly lead to a crisis. </p>

<p>In addition to the e-WOM towards a product, the product price is also an important factor that contributes to online stores’ sales and profits, while it is the promotion measures taken by the online stores that influence the price fluctuations. Promotions have a specific impact on the perceptions, attitude, and behaviors of the consumers. Research has shown that promotions have a short-term increase effect on the sales of products. Sometimes, promotions can also cause some adverse impacts, such as price fatigue and lower perceived quality. In retrospect, the server congestion and lower quality of service during the Double eleven sales activities of a Tmall shop in China caused great consumer dissatisfaction.  </p>

<p>Nowadays, there is a lot of literature about the impact of positive/negative e-WOM and promotions on consumer decision making and online stores’ operation. However, there is a lack of studies that focus on the interactions of the factors that are relevant to the operation of online stores. There needs to be systematic discussion to discover the relationships between these factors. Meanwhile, the study methods of previous studies were limited. Existing studies mainly used questionnaires to obtain research data, which lacked representativeness compared to real data. </p>

<p>Therefore, in order to fit the research gaps, this paper uses the system dynamic method to structure a model of online stores’ operations and especially consideres the impacts of e-WOM and promotion. The real operation data of an online store was used to help determine the causal relationships between variables and was compared with the simulation results. The following are contributions of this paper: (a) we build a framework for the operation of online stores, which provides a more comprehensive perspective to understand e-commerce, (b) we consider the systematic impact of positive and negative e-WOM on online stores’ operation, which were ignored in previous studies, and the findings update the context of e-WOM to some extent, and (c) the real data used in this study can complement the empirical research methods used in previous research. The research findings provide some reference for the sustainable operation and management of online stores and help them predict sales volume in the future. </p>
</text>
