<text id="autogum_academic_doc099" title="Environmental and Economic Life Cycle Analysis of Primary Construction Materials Sourcing under Geopolitical Uncertainties: A Case Study of Qatar" shortTile="environmental-economic" author="Shaikha Al-Nuaimi, Abdul-Aziz  A. Banawi, Sami  G. Al-Ghamdi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6000/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
In global economics, countries interact with one another in an assortment of ways. Developing countries tend to be active in the areas of exporting and importing to keep pace with developed nations and to provide a better standard of living for their citizens. However, many developmental interruptions may occur. The construction industry in Qatar is dependent on foreign imports, and the country is also surrounded by a gulf and maintains a single land neighbor. As such, on account of geopolitical uncertainty, it is at constant risk of sudden changes within importing supply routes. A disruption in the supply chain of a certain type of commodity may require an immediate change in plans and actions to maintain the country’s growth and stability. Changes in a supply chain can occur on account of geopolitical changes, which can have an impact on the country’s economic and environmental aspects; therefore, these aspects should be considered, and a country should take appropriate action to maintain its development. Sustainable supply chain management (SCM) aims to mitigate environmental and economic risks as well as to enhance the overall ecological efficiency of certain practices within a shared production system. </p>

<p>This study aims to analyze the environmental and economic impacts related to changes in supply chains. This study focused on changes in supply chains caused by the geopolitical uncertainties by taking the State of Qatar as a case study. This provides an opportunity to obtain real-time data to identify and quantify environmental impacts and compare costs before and after exposure to the geopolitical challenges. The study emphasizes the importance of maintaining a resilient supply chain network in the market while considering the associated environmental and economic burdens. The study starts with a literature review on subjects regarding uncertainties and the associated environmental and economic impact, the construction sector worldwide and in the State of Qatar, the assessment methods used in previous studies with similar scope, and the sourcing of primary construction materials in the State of Qatar. Then, the materials and methodology applied in the study are explained, followed by results and discussion, and lastly a conclusion to summarize the main findings.  </p>

<head> 1.1. Uncertainties and the Associated Environmental and Economic Impact</head>
<p>
Geopolitical uncertainties can cause numerous variations to existing supply chains within the construction industry. Such variations result in environmental and economic impacts. Based on a review work by Prajapati et al. (2019) and Govindan and Soleimani (2017), supply chain managers need to consider many issues of supply chain network design, such as facility allocation, product flow, and the trade-off between environmental protection and cost reduction. </p>

<p>Nowadays, it is difficult to assess the sustainability of a supply chain due to its complexity. A supply chain includes many stakeholders such as investors, customers, project managers, member organizations, and policy makers. Uncertainty in supply chains can negatively affect supply chain configuration which may reduce efficiency, and which have an impact on supply chain performance. Therefore, uncertainty is considered an important factor that should be taken into consideration when planning a supply chain. However, most supply chain studies have not considered this factor as a part of their research. This obvious absence of research in the area of supply chain indicates that uncertainty factors are often ignored in supply chain and network-related issues. Several studies have agreed that the absence of uncertainty factors would lead to negative sequences on supply chains (e.g.,). Uncertainty can occur at different nodes within a supply chain network. Transportation is one of the nodes at which uncertainty may occur due to its complexity. </p>

<p>One of the biggest challenges in the region in relation to achieving sustainable cities and maintaining regional development is transportation in a supply chain network. Since the transportation sector is known to be a significant source of Green House Gases (GHG) emissions, which are considered the main cause of global warming. Therefore, studies have been concerned about improving the transportation efficiency within a supply chain in order to minimize uncertainties and reduce GHG emissions. However, studies have shown lack of knowledge regarding the achievement of more efficient transportation methods that can result in the saving of the environment (e.g.,). Within a supply chain, carbon dioxide (CO2) emitted during transport represents 14% of all supply chain emissions at both the global and European Union levels. </p>
</text>
