<text id="autogum_academic_doc101" title="The Role of Small Farm Activities for the Sustainable Management of Agricultural Landscapes: Case Studies from Europe" shortTile="role-small-farm-activities" author="Martina Slámová, Ingrid Belčáková" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5966/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Over several thousand years the landscape has been influenced by agriculture. In Europe, a broad variety of agricultural landscape types have originated as a result of traditional farming activities and landscape diversity maintenance. Such traditional landscapes usually represent the surviving remnants of landscape heritage going back to a remote past. They are characterized by a man-made features with irreplaceable ecological, cultural, and historical value. A broad range of European agricultural landscape types (EALs) represent a specific time-limited pattern of landscapes that express a unique sense or spirit of place. They are also cherished due to their biological or anthropogenic values. </p>

<p>The massive socioeconomic changes of the twentieth century caused serious loss of unique rural ecosystem habitats. Agriculture has become oriented towards maximum profit, requiring strict specialization of agricultural production. Specialized agricultural systems brought higher economic income for farmers. On the other hand, typical EALs with mixed farming structures bearing historically-, culturally-, and regionally-specific characteristics have become rare and, in many regions, have disappeared. In the European Eastern Bloc countries, EALs were influenced by collectivization or land consolidation, mostly for arable and pastoral landscapes. The more marginal ones in the mountains changed less, and traditional land use forms have persisted to date. In Central Europe, traditional farming practices have been significantly influenced by current innovative technologies, intensification of agriculture, industry, transport development, and collectivization. The present-day character of the agricultural landscape in Europe has been significantly influenced by several processes but in a number of places a dominant rural character remains, delivering cultural, recreational, habitat, and supporting services </p>

<p>Despite the above-mentioned exceptional value of the historical rural landscape, its conservation practice is very poor. The unique features of EALs are becoming rare and more valuable. Considering the disappearance and ongoing abandonment of historical rural landscapes in Europe, the preservation of these landscapes is an issue of growing importance.  </p>

<p>Multifunctional and sustainable farming activities emerged as a concept that contributes to the preservation of rural landscape's heritage. Multifunctionality is one of the most important aspects of sustainable rural development. In the scientific literature there is no generally accepted understanding of the essence of multifunctionality. There are essentially two approaches. The first one interprets multifunctionality as a characteristic of an economic activity. The second one refers to the multiple roles assigned to agriculture. Even the most commonly cited definition, the working definition of the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (2001), does not reflect the essence of the phenomenon, but rather its two main characteristics. According to this definition, “the key elements of multifunctionality are the existence of numerous market and non-market results that are jointly produced in agriculture”.  </p>

<p>Rural identity expressed in the knowledge and perception of both local land users and rural entrepreneurs plays a crucial role in historical EAL maintenance and sustainable rural development. Raising awareness on landscape values for farmers and stakeholders should improve the quality of landscape and bring added value to the landscape. The concept of multifunctional and sustainable farming should be disseminated and should become a philosophy for product trademark. The main problem is weak knowledge of people living in a territory with respect to a particular EAL. Residents, including farmers and other inhabitants, usually underestimate cultural, historical, and environmental value. Moreover, they have no idea of how to implement landscape values into their farm business plans.  </p>

<p>Due to the lack of EAL maintenance, preservation status, and farmer awareness of landscape values we aimed to deliver comprehensive research findings on the relationship between multifunctional and/or sustainable farming practices of small farms and EALs particularly embedding traditional features in land use. The FEAL project (FEAL: multifunctional Farming for the sustainability of European Agricultural Landscapes) aimed at the development of online vocational and educational training material (VET) for small, family, and young farmers living in the rural environment. The training material explained how to apply knowledge on landscape values in different landscape types and to implement it into daily farming activities through case studies. Further, it clarified how multifunctional and sustainable farming practices aiming at protecting the heritage of European agricultural landscapes lead to win–win situations. The FEAL research was grounded in material collected from farmers/promoters of good practices through questionnaires. </p>

<p>The article's objective was to evaluate data gathered from case studies of the FEAL project. We evaluated the frequency of farm locations within coordination of information on the environment (CORINE) 2012 Land Cover (CLC) classes with traditional land use forms, nature and landscape protection areas/ecologically important areas, and High Nature Value (HNV) farmland. Attitudes of farmers to the multifunctional and sustainable agriculture mirrored in key words which were selected by the farmers and collected during a questionnaire survey. The presence of key words within CLC 2012 classes with traditional land use forms documented preferences of farmers characterizing a certain land cover class. Results interpreted positive external effects of farms on values of European agricultural landscapes. </p>
</text>
