<text id="autogum_academic_doc624" title="The Application of GSCM in Eliminating Healthcare Waste: Hospital EDC as an Example" shortTile="application-gscm" author="Huan-Cheng Chang, Mei-Chin Wang, Hung-Chang Liao, Ya-huei Wang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4087/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. The Dynamic Taguchi Method and Neural Network for the Optimal Factors Levels Setting</head>
<p>
To obtain the optimal parameters setting, four steps, including dynamic method and neural network, were used to achieve the research objectives. </p>

<head> 5.1. STEP 1. Use the Orthogonal Array of the Taguchi Method to Derive the Simulation Data</head>
<p>
This study used the orthogonal array of the Taguchi method to obtain the simulation data. Ahalt et al. used a discrete-event simulation approach to compare different EDC’s scores in a large academic hospital in North Carolina to provide some strategies to bring better patient care outcomes. Hurwitz et al. created a flexible simulation platform to quantify the EDC’s information, which can be used in the management of EDC. Hoot et al. developed a simulation approach for EDC to forecast the near future situation. The forecasting results showed that the actual outcomes are near to the forecasting results. Using simulation data to solve EDC problems has been used by an increasing number of researchers. However, these simulation scenarios are case by case. Hence, the selected parameters for constructing the simulation scenario must be considered based on the selected hospitals.  </p>

<p>Furthermore, to evaluate robustness and variation in the EMS system, a signal-to-noise (SN) ratio was used in the system. A higher SN value corresponds to better performance and less response variation. </p>

<p>Using the dynamic Taguchi method to resolve the EMS problem, the EMS formed a dynamic multi-response system including two responses, two signal levels, four control factors, and two noise factor levels. Regarding the two responses, the response  was determined by a set of signal settings , a set of control factor vectors , and a set of noise factor settings . The response model of the EMS system could be indicated as , in which  was the error term. Hence, in the formed dynamic EMS system, denoted the <hi rend="italic">i</hi>th response corresponding to the <hi rend="italic">j</hi>th signal factors level. Assuming there was no intercept in the linear ideal function, there came to , where  denoted the <hi rend="italic">j</hi>th signal factors level and  was the slope. To evaluate the performance in the dynamic EMS systems using the Taguchi method, the equation  was applied, in which <hi rend="italic">MSE</hi> was the mean square error of the distance from the measured response to the best-fitted line. </p>

<p>The orthogonal array, , was simulated to obtain the performance data. Thirty-six, 2*2*9 (2 levels for noise factor, 2 levels for signal factors, and control factors for ), combinations of parameter levels were simulated. Each combination was simulated 1000 times. The results showed that based on the performance of , the linear ideal function was , the optimal parameters setting for factors (A, B, C, D) was (Level 1, Level 1, Level 1, Level 1) and the expected result at optimum condition was 11.04 dB (dB is a unit of measurement for SN). In addition, the result showed that based on the performance of , the optimal parameters setting for factors (A, B, C, D) was (Level 3, Level 3, Level 2, Level 2) and the expected result at optimum condition was 1.01 dB. </p>

<head> 5.2. STEP 2. Build the Relationship between Parameters and Performances</head>
<p>
Because the time variables were a probability distribution, this study used the NN to construct a mathematical model to obtain the optimal parameters setting for the EMS. The input nodes for the NN were the signal factor levels, noise factor levels, and control factors levels, and the output nodes for the NN were desirability values  from normalized  and  from normalized . The NN’s procedure is as follows:  </p>

<p>A soft computing algorithm, NN, has been used as a computational model in different research fields, such as medical diagnoses, financial analysis, signal processing, and pattern recognition. Inspired by animals’ central nervous systems, an NN was created to mimic a human biological, neurological network. The network is formed by parallel processing units, that is, neurons or nodes. The nodes are linked together to form a network, in which knowledge is derived through the interconnection or relationship between input and output nodes. The weighted and transformed function is used for the weighted sum of the previous input neuronal layers, except the first layer. Different weighted and transformed functions used in the NN meant that NNs could be used in wide-ranging applications. Therefore, NNs create a black-box mathematical model, with a form of nonlinear mathematical network structure. That is, if an NN’s architecture and parameters can be adequately selected, an NN can effectively address complex nonlinear problems.  </p>
</text>
