<text id="autogum_academic_doc585" title="Coalescence of Kerr Black Holes—Binary Systems from GW150914 to GW170814" shortTile="coalescence-kerr" author="Bogeun Gwak" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1099-4300/21/10/1017/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The coalescence of black holes is one of the most important sources of gravitational waves. A gravitational wave occurs owing to a variation in the gravitational field, such as the motion of massive bodies. Although a gravitational wave can commonly occur owing to a small variation in the gravitational field, the magnitude of the gravitational wave in such a variation is too small to detect at our observable accuracy. Hence, an observable gravitational wave needs a sufficient magnitude so that it can be detected at observatories such as the Laser Interferometer Gravitational-Wave Observatory (LIGO). Since the magnitude of a gravitational wave becomes large along with the mass of its source, the candidate sources of detectable gravitational waves should be massive. Thus, the coalescence of black holes can be a source that releases a gravitational wave that is sufficiently large to be detected at the LIGO. Nowadays, several gravitational waves are detected at observatories. Most of their sources are the binary black hole mergers in GW150914, GW151226, GW170104, GW170608, GW170814. Thus, the coalescence of black holes can be a frequently detectable source of gravitational waves. Further, a system of binary black holes has three angular momenta—two spin angular momenta of the black holes and one orbital angular momentum—and these angular momenta play important roles in the analysis of the system. Note that the angular momenta for a binary black hole merger are described by the primary spin parameter , secondary spin parameter  and orbital angular momentum  in the initial state, and the spin parameter  in the final state. </p>

<p>Black holes have conserved quantities such as mass and angular momentum. Two types of energies are included in the mass of the black hole: a reducible energy and an irreducible mass. The roles of these two energies can be clarified in consideration of particle absorption to vary the black hole. In particle absorption, the variations in the mass and angular momentum of a black hole can be related to a particle’s momenta such as the radial and angular momenta. Here, the black hole’s angular momentum can be reduced by our choice of the particle’s angular momentum; thus, part of the particle’s angular momentum is a reducible energy in the variation of the black hole’s mass. Interestingly, the remaining part cannot be reduced with any choice of the particle’s momenta; therefore, the remaining part is called the irreducible mass of a black hole. This irreducible mass can be understood as the surface energy of the black hole. For example, even if the mass of a black hole decreases during particle absorption, the irreducible mass still increases. Since this behavior of the irreducible mass is very similar to the entropy in thermodynamics, its square—the area of the horizon—is related to the Bekenstein–Hawking entropy. Further, the black hole can emit energy away from its horizon according to a quantum process. Owing to this small portion of the energy, the black hole can be assumed to be a thermal object having the Hawking temperature accounted from the emission. For the variation in the black hole’s mass, the Bekenstein–Hawking entropy and Hawking temperature act as thermodynamic variables in the first law of thermodynamics. In addition, the Bekenstein–Hawking entropy increases in an irreversible process in the second law of thermodynamics according to the behavior of the irreducible mass. Thus, the black hole itself can be considered as a thermal system obeying the laws of thermodynamics. </p>
</text>
