<text id="autogum_academic_doc353" title="Sand Transport and Deposition Behaviour in Subsea Pipelines for Flow Assurance" shortTile="sand-transport-deposition" author="Yan Yang, Haoping Peng, Chuang Wen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4070/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The demand for energy supply is a key issue for the global economy. The petroleum supply plays an important role in primary energy. In the petroleum supply networks, sand transport is generally a severe problem for most oil and gas reservoirs all over the world. It is more important especially for the subsea production systems considering the flow assurance. The deposition of solid sand in the pipe bottom and equipment can cause a series of risks. For instance, the formation of the sand bed in the pipeline decreases the flow area and correspondingly increases the frictional pressure losses. Moreover, sand transport can cause erosion and corrosion problems as a result of the impact on the pipe wall and the microbial attack under the sand bed. In addition, the slurry flow containing sands could lead to equipment failure. Therefore, the deposition and transport of the sand in slurry flows attract much attention, and it is also a very significant issue in the petroleum industry. </p>

<p>A series of computer-controlled experiments were conducted in a thin fluid (like water) and the key parameter distribution was obtained at various flow rates, injected sand concentrations, and fluid viscosities. Doron et al. experimentally studied the transport behaviour of the coarse solids in a horizontal pipeline. Gillies and Shook employed the traversing gamma-ray gauges to measure the sand concentration in a horizontal pipeline with coarse solids nominally from 180 to 2400 μm. Their results indicated that the maximal concentration gradient (0.47 in their studies) was irrelevant to the mean velocity. Gillies et al. experimentally studied the sand transport characteristics in a horizontal pipeline with viscous Newtonian fluids. Their results showed that a pressure gradient of 2 kPa/m was required to transport sand in laminar flow. Kaushal et al. conducted a series of experiments to study the sand transport characteristic in multiphase flow pipelines. The measurement of the pressure drop and concentration was experimentally observed in the liquid-solid slurry flow. Duan et al. investigated experimentally the critical resuspension velocity and the critical deposition velocity for different size sands in slurry flows. It indicated that the critical resuspension velocity was two to three times smaller than the critical deposition velocity. Najmi et al. experimentally studied the critical flow rate of gas and liquid to keep particles moving in a horizontal pipeline in stratified and intermittent flow with a small liquid hold-up of about 0.02. The volume fraction of the solid phase (0.01–0.1%) was experimentally measured in a horizontal pipeline at a very low concentration. Rice et al. utilized two kinds of particles including the glass and plastic solids to understand the sand transport behaviour in the multiphase flow pipeline. </p>

<p>A computational model was developed by Roco and Shook to predict the quasi-uniform slurry flow with the range of sand volume concentration below 40%. Their simulated results of concentration and velocity were compared with experimental data and showed a good agreement. The sand transport process was investigated in a horizontal well by means of numerical simulations. Ebadian et al. developed an algebraic slip mixture model to predict the sand transport behaviour within a horizontal pipeline. Their comparison of the pressure drop between the computational and experimental results showed a good agreement. Danielson considered the slip velocity to develop a two-fluid model for the slurry flows, and a good agreement between the simulation and experiment was obtained in the sand bed height. An analytical near-wall model was developed to describe the liquid-solid two-phase flow, and the numerical result showed a good agreement with the experimental concentration. A two-fluid model was proposed to predict the fully suspended slurry flow, and it was validated by experimental data. In another study, they proposed an improved mathematical model for the slurry flow within a horizontal pipeline. The comparison between the simulation and experiment showed that the new model was more accurate than the previous one. Hadinoto adapted the two-fluid flow model to predict the turbulence modulation characteristic in a vertical pipeline at a low solid volume fraction from 0.5% to 4.0%. The numerical and experimental results showed that the drag correlation significantly affected the accuracy of the computational fluid dynamics (CFD simulation). The Euler-granular model was employed by Kaushal et al. to predict the sand transport behaviour in a horizontal pipeline with fine particles at high concentrations. The concentration distributions of the numerical and experimental results were in good agreement. Soepyan et al. developed a CFD model to predict the fluid velocity of the slurry flow in a horizontal pipeline at a low concentration by volume. Table 1 lists recent studies on sand transport and deposition in multiphase flow pipelines with a focus on low concentration conditions. These studies demonstrated the importance of the effect of sands on the flow process even in low concentrations for multiphase flow pipelines. </p>
</text>
