<text id="autogum_academic_doc382" title="Development of a Teen-Informed Coding Tool to Measure the Power of Food Advertisements" shortTile="development-teeninformed" author="Drew  D. Bowman, Leia  M. Minaker, Bonnie  J. K. Simpson, Jason  A. Gilliland" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/21/4258/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Results</head><head> 3.1. Teen-Directed Marketing Criteria</head>
<p>Ten advertisement features identified by the youth advisory council as key teen-directed marketing techniques that attract teenagers to food establishments are shown below, in order of importance:
<list>
<item>Price</item>
<item>Image of Food/Beverage</item>
<item>Taste Description</item>
<item>Sale/Deal/Special Offer</item>
<item>Slogan/Description</item>
<item>Logo/Company Name</item>
<item>Geographic/Online Location or Directions</item>
<item>Gamification (e.g., contest, game, giveaway)</item>
<item>Loyalty Points/Rewards</item>
<item>Character, Celebrity, or TV/Sports tie-in</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>Both the online survey results as well as the discussions with the youth revealed that these features are perceived by teenagers to be highly influential when it comes to perceptions of their own food purchases (see Table 1). For instance, prices are important to teens, who claim to be “more likely to go for stuff that’s cheaper”. Results also revealed that teens are often attracted to company logos; one teen mentioned that they “wouldn’t go if it didn’t look familiar”. Other elements from the literature that were initially considered by the youth council members include: (1) online/social media connections; (2) health appeal; (3) nutritional composition of items; (4) humour/clever language; (5) portrayal of values; (6) other enticements/amenities (e.g., wifi, parking); and (7) strange shapes or unusual colours. These criteria were discussed by the youth advisory council and were not deemed to be the most important influencers when it comes to their advertising and purchasing perceptions.  </p>

<p>It was found that certain criteria researchers consider to be teen-directed were not actually perceived to be important from a teen perspective. For instance, 13 of 14 youth advisory council members indicated that health appeal is not an important consideration in choosing where to eat out, and thus, it did not make the top ten criteria. Based on discussions with the youth advisory council, teens do not seem to be influenced by the healthfulness of the food items they purchase, as reflected in the comment, “if I’m going to eat out, I want to go all out”. Social media was another criterion that was not perceived by teens to be influential regarding their food purchases; several council members stated that they and their peers “do not use snapchap codes” or other methods of social media outreach. Although food vendors were the focus of this study, the discussions with teens also revealed that other community spaces where teens often congregate, including gaming centres and other settings that house teen-centred attractions, are common places where teens purchase food; for example, a council member said that their peers “like to eat at places like [Place X] because they have other attractions to do” (i.e., games, axe throwing, etc.). In a structured discussion, the youth advisory council determined definitions for the coding criteria, including inclusion/exclusion criteria and examples of these advertisement features. These criteria are outlined in Table 1 above. </p>

<p>Additionally, teens recognized that the appearance or layout of the ads (i.e., size, placement, and colour) plays a key role in the appeal of the food or beverage advertisement, with size being identified as the most important appearance-related feature. This became evident through the online photo analysis survey, with teens commonly indicating that the most attention-grabbing features of ads were often chosen because they are “the biggest part of the ad”, or because they “take up the most space” on the advertisement. Similarly, the least attention-grabbing features of ads were mainly selected due to their small size, often making them “too small in comparison to the rest” of the ad and “hard to read”. This reveals that the power of marketing techniques is not only a function of presence (whether each feature is present on the ad, and its relative importance), but also size.  </p>

<head> 3.2. Teen-Developed Weights</head>
<p>Table 2 shows the teen-developed weights for each item, which represent the mean scores of each item based on the three weighting questions. The “order” refers to the order of importance, with 1 being the most important feature and 10 being the least important. Although point allocation was the weighting method chosen for this tool, teens rated the importance of the criteria similarly and consistently across all three survey questions (see Table 2). There was a high correlation between the three weighting methods (0.872–0.966). This adds to the rigor and reliability of the results and reveals that the three weighting methods are related. </p>

<p>The sizing diagram for the coding tool was originally developed by the research team (<figure>Figure 3</figure>). However, after additional consultations with teens regarding the size of ad features, it was decided the medium and large categories would be combined. The online hot spot activity particularly shed light on the importance of weighting on the basis of sizing, with teens rarely selecting the advertisement features that fell into the small categories as being attention-drawing. Thus, the following weights for sizing were created: small features get multiplied by 0.25, and anything larger (medium and large features) gets multiplied by 1.00. Absent features are coded as N/A (or 0). </p>
</text>
