<text id="autogum_academic_doc181" title="Impact of Aerosol-Cloud Cycling on Aqueous Secondary Organic Aerosol Formation" shortTile="impact-aerosolcloud" author="William  G. Tsui, Joseph  L. Woo, V.  Faye McNeill" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4433/10/11/666/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Aerosols are known to affect human health, air quality, and climate and are ubiquitous in the atmosphere. They can also act as condensation nuclei to form cloud droplets, and evaporation of liquid water from the cloud droplets allows for cycling between cloud droplets and aqueous aerosols. Cycling between these two aqueous regimes can occur on timescales of seconds to minutes, significantly shorter than the typical lifetime of aerosols, which is roughly one week. The uptake of water by aerosols or the evaporation of cloud droplets has the potential to impact atmospheric chemistry by altering the partitioning of semivolatile species, or perturbing equilibrium reactions in the aqueous phase. Although the composition of aqueous aerosols can vary considerably, liquid water and aqueous organic material are a significant portion of atmospheric aerosol mass, and much of the aqueous-phase organic material that comprises aerosols is known to be secondary. The cycling between aqueous aerosols and cloudwater provides two different aqueous environments in which aqueous secondary organic aerosol material (aqSOA) can form. Since both environments are aqueous, the same chemical processes occur in both environments. However, different processes are dominant due to the difference in water content, and therefore dilution of nonvolatile components, with aqueous aerosols having less water content per volume of air than cloudwater where clouds are present. For example, relatively lower water content and generally lower pH are typical of aqueous aerosols, and high concentrations of organic material can limit the availability of oxidants. This results in dark (nonphotochemical) reactions, such as acid-catalyzed accretion reactions and organosulfate formation, being more dominant in aerosol water than in cloudwater. Typical cloudwater pH can range between three and six, as measured at the Whiteface Mountain Field Station summit observatory in Wilmington, NY, USA, whereas aerosol particles tend to be considerably more acidic. </p>

<p>Isoprene is the most abundant nonmethane hydrocarbon gas in the atmosphere and a major source of aqSOA. One of the most significant pathways of aqSOA formation from isoprene is through the gas-phase photooxidation of isoprene to form isoprene epoxydiols (IEPOX). IEPOX secondary organic aerosols (SOA), which in part consists of tetrols and organosulfates, is formed via the acid-catalyzed ring opening of the epoxide followed by nucleophilic addition of water or anions (e.g., HSO4−). In laboratory studies, IEPOX SOA has been found to form most efficiently at low pH as a result of the acid-catalyzed ring-opening step. The low pH and high nucleophile concentrations in aqueous aerosol provide a favorable environment for IEPOX SOA formation. However, a number of scenarios which are believed to be common for aqueous aerosols, such as organic coatings, phase separation, or low-viscosity aerosols, are known to result in mass transfer limitations which inhibit the uptake of IEPOX into aqueous aerosols, limiting subsequent IEPOX SOA formation. Despite this, IEPOX SOA is observed ubiquitously in the environment. Therefore, it is possible that cloudwater may be a greater source of IEPOX SOA than previously believed. Although the lower acidity and sulfate concentrations of cloudwater would make the rate of IEPOX SOA formation in cloudwater lower than in aqueous aerosol, other factors, such as high liquid water content and lack of organic coating or viscosity-based mass transfer limitations, may promote SOA formation. </p>

<p>Currently, some regional and global models cannot accurately predict atmospheric aqueous organic material due to uncertainties in SOA production despite the availability of detailed chemical models representative of atmospheric processes. Such discrepancies between models and observed measurements may be attributed, in part, to the lack of consideration of the cycling between cloudwater and aqueous aerosol in the models. Although several models have shown that SOA formation does occur in cloudwater, the extent to which SOA is produced as compared to formation in aqueous aerosol is unclear since very few models represent both processes. In this work, we aim to compare IEPOX SOA production in both cloudwater and aqueous aerosols while considering the cycling that can occur between the two phases upon evaporation or condensation of water. We used a recently updated version of GAMMA (Gas-Aerosol Model for Mechanism Analysis), a photochemical box model developed by the McNeill group, to quantify IEPOX SOA formation. We previously used GAMMA and a related model, simpleGAMMA, to predict IEPOX SOA in aqueous aerosols, and the results were in good agreement with ambient measurements. The recent update to GAMMA includes uptake of IEPOX and subsequent formation of SOA in cloudwater, allowing for the direct comparison of the efficiency of IEPOX SOA formation in both aqueous environments, and captures the coupled effect of the two modes of processing in a single simulation. </p>
</text>
