<text id="autogum_academic_doc297" title="Existence Conditions and General Solutions of Closed-form Inverse Kinematics for Revolute Serial Robots" shortTile="existence-conditions" author="Wang Shanda, Luo Xiao, Luo Qingsheng, Han Baoling" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/20/4365/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Conclusions</head>
<p>
Based on the DH model, this study proposed a universal algorithm for finding an inverse kinematics closed-form solution. This algorithm divided the inverse kinematics problem related to robots with a closed-form solution into three sub-problems assuming that the algebraic equation had a formula solution. The solvability conditions for the three types of sub-problems were analyzed to derive a formula solution. If a serial robot can be described with these three types of sub-problems, the robot will definitely have a closed-form solution. Meanwhile, the formula solution based on such a problem could quickly solve for all the joint angles. This method was not only applicable to six-DOF robots with a closed-form solution but also to low-DOF robots with the same solution form. In addition, establishing an algorithm based on the DH model provides a concise and efficient tool for selecting sub-problems and a real-time inverse kinematics solution for the motion controller of a serial robot. To verify the correctness and real-time performance of the algorithm, we presented four experimental designs. The first three experiments were conducted on MATLAB with a series of robot to verify the completeness, universality, and continuity of this algorithm. </p>

<p>In the first experiment, the completeness of the algorithm was verified. The experiment used a low-degree-of-freedom robot with closed inverse solutions to prove that the algorithm could solve its closed inverse solution, and the algorithm would be terminated for the robot without closed inverse solutions to avoid infinite loop. This was used to prove the completeness of the algorithm. In the second experiment, two uncommon robots were constructed through using some basic problems, but the closed inverse solution could still be solved. Therefore, it could be known that the closed inverse solution of the series robots constructed by basic problems could be solved. Meanwhile, for these robots whose structure was not changed but the link parameter was changed, the closed inverse solution of them could also be solved correctly, which indicates that the algorithm had certain versatility in solving the closed inverse solution problem. In the third experiment, the common Puma560 robot was used as the experimental object. In the experiment, a spatial curve was planned. The correct joint angle sequence was obtained and the changes of the joint angle curve were continuously without jumping after been inversely solved by the algorithm. Which indicates that the algorithm could guarantee the continuity of its mapping on the inverse solution problem. </p>

<p>The fourth experiment was conducted on a six-DOF robotic platform built using a Beckhoff-C6920 controller and an RGM motor to verify the real-time performance of the algorithm using the above hardware platform. The spatial and joint positions were computed with a close-loop cycle of 2 ms and were transmitted to the motor via CanOpen. The results demonstrated the ability of the algorithm to solve the three sub-problems within a specified cycle and to compute the appropriate joint angles. Moreover, the curve was continuous. This paper used a completely new approach to study the inverse kinematics of serial robots. In this study, the conditions for the existence of the closed-form inverse kinematic solution of a serial robot were completed and the basic theory of robotics was perfected. Based on this method, a general closed-form inverse kinematics algorithm based on the DH model was implemented, which had not been done in previous studies. Importantly, this method is a general-purpose algorithm that can be used in industrial fields in real time. This increases the versatility of the universal serial robot motion controller. </p>

<p>However, the algorithm still has shortcomings. First, the algorithm only targets serial robots and the moving joints are not included in the solution model. This limits the scope of application of the algorithm, due to its inability to solve the cases of SCARA robots or other parallel robots. In addition, the algorithm cannot solve the problem when the robot passes through a singular point; singular points are avoided via restrictions implemented in the software. Moreover, because the algorithm is a purely analytical method, it is difficult to combine with other numerical methods to solve the problem of singular points.
 </p>
</text>
