<text id="autogum_academic_doc700" title="Exploring the Spatial Characteristics of Inbound Tourist Flows in China Using Geotagged Photos" shortTile="exploring-spatial" author="Jing Qin, Ci Song, Mingdi Tang, Youyin Zhang, Jinwei Wang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5822/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Results</head><head> 3.1. Spatial Distribution of Geotagged Photos</head>
<p>
The locations of the geotagged photos were mapped using ArcGIS10.3 software based on their coordinates. Popular destination regions for inbound tourists, which were obtained using kernel density analysis, are shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>. Cities with the highest aggregate number of geotagged photos are distributed within three large regions, which include the Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei Region (where Beijing is the regional central city), the Yangtze River Delta Zone (where Shanghai, Suzhou, and Hangzhou are regional central cities), and the Pearl River Delta Zone (where Guangzhou and Shenzhen are regional central cities). These regions are China’s political and economic centers, and constitute the core of China’s cultural heritage. Secondary concentration regions are primarily centered on the cities of Xi’an and Chengdu. Moreover, small-scale concentrations are also found around Guilin (Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region), Lijiang (Yunnan Province), Lhasa (Tibet Autonomous Region), and Dalian (Liaoning Province). These observations show that inbound tourists seek out China’s unique natural landscapes, cultural heritage, and economic development centers. </p>

<p>To further explore the cities’ popularity, we calculate the number of inbound tourists in each city. The top 20 most visited cities are shown in Table 1. We then classify those cities into three tiers using the Nature Breaks method. Natural Breaks classes are based on natural groupings inherent in the data. Class breaks are identified that best group similar values and that maximize the differences between classes. Beijing and Shanghai are in the first tier since the number of inbound tourists in Beijing and Shanghai is much larger than in any other city. The second tier is constituted of traditional tourist destinations such as Xi’an, Guilin, Guangzhou, Suzhou, and Hangzhou. The third tier consists of newly emerging destination cities, which are generally in the central and western regions of China such as Lijiang, Lhasa, Kunming, Diqing, Dali, and Aba. In this case, the beautiful natural scenery and unique ethnic cultures have attracted growing attention from foreign visitors. In particular, Lijiang and Lhasa are already among the top 10 destination cities. Overall, traditional destination cities are still the most popular among inbound tourists. However, with the development of airports, high-speed railway, and other transportation services, the newly emerging destination cities have gradually become more popular. </p>

<head> 3.2. Spatial Structure of Inbound Tourist Flows</head>
<p>
The various different routes chosen by tourists converge into tourist flows. The convergence of flows ultimately forms a tourist transition network. The major tourist flow connections between tourism nodes constitute the main spatial characteristics of the tourist flows network. In addition, the number of small tourist flow cities connected to the node cities with high tourist flows determine the tourist collecting and distributing ability of cities with high tourist flows. Therefore, when exploring the spatial characteristics of tourist flow, we first calculate the tourist flow connections between cities and describe the spatial framework formed by major inbound flows. Next, we discuss the characteristics of tourist movements between major tourist-node cities. Lastly, we identify urban agglomeration regions with high spatial concentrations of inbound tourists to examine the travel patterns in these regions. </p>
</text>
