<text id="autogum_academic_doc712" title="Individuals’ Demand for Ride-hailing Services: Investigating the Combined Effects of Attitudinal Factors, Land Use, and Travel Attributes on Demand for App-based Taxis in Tehran, Iran" shortTile="individuals-demand" author="Roya Etminani-Ghasrodashti, Shima Hamidi" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5755/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Literature Review</head><head> 2.1. Ride-hailing as an Emerging Mode of Transportation</head>
<p>
Ride-hailing is a transportation service that allows passengers to request a ride in a real-time via smartphone applications that link passengers to nearby drivers. Once a driver accepts the request, the passenger can evaluate the waiting time and decide whether to accept the ride. Both the passenger and the driver can use Global Position System (GPS) navigation during the trip, and the application guides the driver to shortcuts and less-congested roadways. Many terms are used to describe this emerging transportation mode, including ride-sourcing, ride-hailing, TNC’s, e-hailing, and app-based on-demand service. </p>

<p>Literature on the benefits and effectiveness of ride-hailing services is mixed. Research points to several measurable advantages of the services, such as low waiting times and reduced commute-related stress, cost-effectiveness over other modes and congestion mitigation particularly for the shared-ride options. On the other hand, the advanced technology of e-hailing does not guarantee success. This is often due to key challenges, such as determining an appropriate local strategy for an e-hailing platform, and also frequent cancellations by passengers. According to a study by Jin et al., ride-hailing impacts the efficiency, equity, and sustainability of cities. While ride-hailing offers economic efficiency in many cases, there have been issues reported related to discrimination and security among riders and drivers. Also, the environmental impacts of ride-hailing remain to be substantively documented or tracked over time. </p>

<head> 2.2. The Comparison of Ride-hailing and Traditional Taxis</head>
<p>
The literature points to several potential impacts of e-hailing on the traditional taxi industry. Some studies have compared ride-hailing and yellow taxis side-by-side, and investigated the ways in which yellow taxis could compete with ride-hailing services. A recent study in Shenzhen, China, found that taxis could effectively compete with ride-hailing services in peak periods and in dense areas. It found that traditional taxis with experienced and professional drivers tended to operate more efficiently during peak hours and in more congested locations than the often-amateur drivers of ride-hailing services, many of whom rely heavily on GPS rather than personal knowledge. This line of research posits that the emergence of ride-hailing is unlikely to eliminate the demand for traditional taxis, and both services are ultimately required (and desired) in large metropolitan areas. </p>

<p>Another line of research compares the influences of determinant factors on ride-hailing versus traditional taxi services. Studies indicate that weather conditions may affect Uber and Lyft ridership more than yellow taxi ridership, likely due to their flexible pricing structure. According to a study conducted in New York City, the number of Uber and Lyft rides per hour increases dramatically when it rains. Evidence shows that ridership for yellow taxis is less likely to be influenced by rain.  </p>

<p>Another study by Rayle et al. surveyed 380 ride-hailing patrons in San Francisco, and compared them with a control group of taxi riders in the same city. Findings confirmed that frequent ride-hailing users were mostly younger, better educated, and more car-dependent than the control group of frequent taxi riders. Moreover, time efficiency and convenience were found to be the main attractions for ride-hailing services. Their average wait time was reported to be less than 10 minutes, and ride-hailing trips documented in the study were generally shorter than the control group’s taxi trips. Finally, a majority of the ride-hailing trips requested by patrons were for social purposes, indicating a robust pool of choice riders. </p>

<p>Other studies focused on determinants of traditional taxi demand. For instance, Schaller, found that the number of employees using subway, households with no car ownership and the number of airport taxi trips accounted for the increasing number of taxi cabs in the US. Another study, linked taxi demand with land use attributes, socio-demographics, and employment factors from 1972’s Traffic Analysis Zones (TAZs) in Washington DC. Results confirm that land use measures such as residential density, employment density, average block size, and number of transit stations have a significant and positive impact on ridership demand for taxis. At the same time, land use mix negatively correlates with the number of taxi pick-ups in each TAZ. The study concludes by positing that the demand for taxis is higher in zones that host more workplaces than residences, such as central business districts (CBD’ s). Among the sociodemographic factors, income was found to be positively related to taxi demand. </p>
</text>
