<text id="autogum_academic_doc025" title="Npro of Classical Swine Fever Virus Suppresses Type III Interferon Production by Inhibiting IRF1 Expression and Its Nuclear Translocation" shortTile="npro-classical-swine" author="Tong Cao, Xiaoye Li, Yonghao Xu, Shengnan Zhang, Zuohuan Wang, Ying Shan, Jianhe Sun, Weihuan Fang, Xiaoliang Li" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4915/11/11/998/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
Understanding mechanisms of viral strategy to evade from host antiviral responses is critical for elucidation of the pathogenesis of CSFV infection. Type I IFNs represent one of the first lines of defense of the innate immune system and are produced rapidly upon recognition of viral factors by PRRs. CSFV is known to interfere with the generation of type I IFNs by inducing proteasomal degradation of IRF3. Type III IFNs play a critical role in antiviral innate immunity in mucosal epithelial cells. However, little information is available as to whether and how CSFV modulates type III IFN response. The present study demonstrates that the Npro protein of CSFV inhibited IRF1-mediated type III IFNs production by down-regulation of IRF1 expression and blockage of its nuclear translocation. </p>

<p>The Npro-deleted mutant showed similar growth kinetics to its parental strain, indicating that CSFV Npro does not alter the replication in cell culture, which is consistent with the previous study. Some viruses have evolved to encode viral antagonists for evasion of type III IFNs responses. Reid et al showed the induction of type III IFNs in pDCs upon BVDV infection, and type III IFNs contributed to suppression of cellular immune response during BVDV infection. Cai et al shows that CSFV induced the expression of type III IFNs in PK-15 cells, but with a limited level of increase, suggesting that CSFV might have a strategy to suppress expression of type III IFNs. We also found limited up-regulation of type III IFNs transcription upon wtCSFV infection in IPEC-J2 cells, though the transcription level peaked at 24 hpi and decreased thereafter, which is different from the results shown by Cai et al that the mRNA level of IFN-λ1 and IFN-λ3 induced by wtCSFV peaked at 36 and 48 hpi, respectively. We speculate that the difference might be due to different cell types used. Because CSFV causes enteric pathologies, a cell line from the intestines could be a good choice. The IPEC-J2 cell line was from non-transformed cells collected from the jejunum of a neonatal piglet and suitable for infection studies for enteropathogens. IPEC-J2 exhibited robust expression of type III IFNs with a relatively lower type I IFNs response. Thus, the IPEC-J2 cell line was chosen in this study. Cell lines or primary cultures from other intestinal areas or from adult pigs could be approached for further investigation of the interactions between CSFV and type III IFNs. </p>

<p>We found that the ∆Npro mutant induced significantly higher transcription of IFNs in IPEC-J2 cells from 24 to 48 hpi than its parental strain, suggesting that the Npro protein might be antagonistic to expression of type III IFNs. Because CSFV Npro has been found to subvert the type I IFN response, we speculated if Npro might have similar effect on type III IFNs. We showed that wtCSFV strongly inhibited expression of poly(I:C)-induced type III IFNs in IPEC-J2 cells and Npro deletion abolished such an inhibitory effect. We further showed that Npro over-expression led to a marked reduction of mRNA transcripts of type III IFNs. Either infection with wtCSFV or over-expression of Npro also resulted in significant reduction of the IFN-λ3 promoter activity of poly(I:C)-treated IPEC-J2 cells. These results demonstrate that CSFV employs its Npro to inhibit type III IFNs expression probably by targeting the regulatory elements involved in transcription of IFN-λs. </p>

<p>Activation of type III IFNs, as the case with type I IFNs, requires IRF3, IRF7 and NF-κB. However, expression of type III IFNs does not need all components of the enhanceosome. IRF1 is a predominant antiviral molecule against many viruses. It is the first identified member of the IRF family, but it does not induce production of type I IFNs. Odendall et al has shown that IRF1 regulates peroxisome-mediated IFN-λ1 expression. Epithelial cells have preference of producing IFN-λs over IFN-α/β upon viral infection. This may be due to relatively higher expression of peroxisomes in epithelial cells. Peroxisomal MAVS is known to induce type III IFNs, as opposed to induction of type I IFNs via mitochondrial MAVS. To better understand the regulation of type III IFNs by IRF1, we attempted to regulate levels of IRF1 expression by overexpression or RNA interference in IPEC-J2 cells. Overexpression of IRF1 led to a significant increase of transcription of all IFN-λs and IFN-λ3 promoter activity, while gene silencing showed opposite effects, indicating that IRF1 positively regulates expression of type III IFNs. </p>
</text>
