<text id="autogum_academic_doc745" title="Understanding the Sustainable Usage Intention of Mobile Payment Technology in Korea: Cross-Countries Comparison of Chinese and Korean Users" shortTile="understanding-sustainable" author="Xin Lin, RunZe Wu, Yong-Taek Lim, Jieping Han, Shih-Chih Chen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/19/5532/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Background and Literature Review</head><head> 2.1. Mobile Payment</head>
<p>
M-payment has been explained as any payment transaction that is explicitly initiated, conferred, and confirmed by a mobile terminal. A mobile payment transaction is usually conducted remotely via preferential rate SMS, wireless application protocol billing, cellular networks, direct subscriber billing, and direct credit cards. Therefore, m-payments can efficiently handle financial transactions through mobile networks, as well as through several wireless skills, such as near field communication (NFC) and radio frequency identification (RFID). M-payment technology has grown extensively around the world, and its spreading power and cross-border influence are increasing. Digital wallets, also called "electronic wallets", refer to the mobile equipment or online business transaction that supports a consumer when conducting electronic business. Consumers can use a smartphone to purchase something at an off-line store. An individual’s bank account can be connected to the digital wallet, and the vouchers can be wirelessly transmitted to the seller’s terminals through NFC. </p>

<p>In 2018, mobile payment technology accounted for 4.6% of the global GDP, a contribution worth $3.9 trillion USD in economic value. Wang reported that cross-border m-payment had a pivotal role in promoting international trade, showing that systemized m-payment services would encourage the integration of m-payment and settlement in the Asia-Pacific region, and had even enabled the integration and sustainable development of consumer markets in Southeast Asia. </p>

<p>However, not all customers have accepted mobile payment as an important service. Therefore, academics have been focusing on determining the factors influencing usage intention. Chun stated that when arguments arose between customers and companies in electronic businesses, responsibility allocation was crucial to the sustainability of e-commerce. By analyzing the market reactions to Samsung Pay and Apple Pay, Son and Kim revealed that technology administration policies could confirm the sustainability of fast-changing technological progress. Other authors have used various typical structural equation models, including the technology acceptance model (TAM), UTAUT, and the unified theory of acceptance and use of technology 2 (UTAUT2), as the basic structures in their research to identify any factor that can affect m-payment usage willingness.  </p>

<head> 2.2. UTAUT</head>
<p>
Eight main technology acceptance relevant models were unified and incorporated in UTAUT by Venkatesh et al.. UTAUT also posits four core variables that are the factors determining usage willingness in relation to the adoption of technology: Performance expectancy (PE), effort expectancy (EE), social influence (SI), and facilitating conditions (FC). Additionally, it postulates the role of four vital moderating elements.  </p>

<p>UTAUT has been studied from different research perspectives of behavior usage intention and technology adoption. Proposed as an extension to TAM, UTAUT was used to evaluate the importance of increasingly commonplace information system technology in usage intention. According to the UTAUT model, the usage intention is influenced by PE, EE, SI, and FC. UTAUT has been applied to identify and examine variables that affect the usage intention of mobile commerce acceptance, mobile shopping and mobile banking usage adoption. Palau-Saumell reported that the consumer experience has moderating effects on the hypothesis of the independent elements of the task–technology fit, user satisfaction, PE, EE, SI, FC, and m-payment usage intention. A survey on the potential adoption of mobile payments found that user experience is a moderator of their intention to switch mobile platforms, integrating the experience into D&amp;M ISS to investigate what determines the reason why users’ switch mobile platforms. Therefore, to test how strongly the direct variables affect usage intention, we included the users’ experience in the UTAUT model as a moderating variable.  </p>

<p>The flexible universal characteristics of the UTAUT model make it appropriate for the aim of this research, in which we integrated some of the technology acceptance theories and TAM models into a comprehensive model. </p>

<head> 2.3. DeLone and McLean’s ISS</head>
<p>
In this study, the D&amp;M ISS model was applied to recognize the influencing effect of satisfaction and performance expectancy in mobile payment systems on usage intention. D&amp;M ISS was integrated into UTAUT to measure the information system. System quality (SYQ), service quality (SQ), and information quality (IQ) jointly influence user satisfaction and performance expectancy, both of which eventually affect usage intention.  </p>

<p>Since its reinvention, ISS has been broadly applied to evaluate usage willingness in diverse information systems. Mohammadi integrated D&amp;M ISS into TAM for assessing the influential effect of quality facilitators, performance expectancy, and user satisfaction, as well as the usability in e-learning. Sharma exploited D&amp;M to survey and measure mobile payment user intention, and proposed a modified conceptual model by expanding D&amp;M ISS to grasp the actual mobile payment usage intention.  </p>

<p>As these studies have demonstrated, even if D&amp;M ISS has been widely applied to determine customer behavior usage intention, researchers have rarely examined the area of mobile payments among Chinese and Korean customers, which represents advanced payment technology. Hence, the D&amp;M ISS model should be exploited as a conceptual model of mobile payments. </p>
</text>
