<text id="autogum_academic_doc124" title="Embedding Sustainability Competences into Engineering Education. The Case of Informatics Engineering and Industrial Engineering Degree Programs at Spanish Universities" shortTile="embedding-sustainability" author="Rafael Miñano Rubio, Diego Uribe, Ana Moreno-Romero, Susana Yáñez" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5832/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Methodology</head>
<p>The main purpose of this study is to describe how the current degrees of both industrial engineering and informatics engineering are integrating sustainability competences in teaching, paying special attention to whether it is done holistically and systematically throughout the curriculum, and identifying good practices and reference models. </p>

<p>The methodology is based on benchmarking methods, used in the competitive analysis of companies and organizations, that focus on best practices and continuous improvement. An external benchmarking typology has been chosen, comparing the behaviour of different universities that offer similar degrees. This approach has also been used for Sánchez Carracedo et al.—with a lower range of universities—but it is different from other studies aimed at analyzing the performance of just one university in its different degrees (internal benchmarking). Moreover, a functional approach has been adopted, focusing the study on two specific aspects that have been considered critical: the holistic vision of sustainability competencies and its systematic inclusion in the curricula. </p>

<p>The study has been carried out exhaustively in the universities of the Community of Madrid (13 universities, 6 public and 7 private). To complete it, other Spanish universities have been selected that could contribute to the objectives of the study: technical universities, as specialists and referents in the field of engineering, and other universities attending to their involvement in the field of sustainability (such as their participation in the Higher Education Sustainability Initiative). Finally, 27 degrees of computer engineering (hereafter, Informatics) and 28 degrees of industrial engineering (hereafter, Industrial) have been analyzed. </p>

<head> 5.1. Data Collection</head>
<p>For the collection of data, the web pages on each of the selected universities and degrees have been reviewed, with the purpose of analyzing the presence of sustainability competences in the competences and objectives that define the degree, and especially the presence in the courses of the curriculum. To analyze the presence in each course, the information has been obtained from the mentioned <hi rend="italic">Learning Guides</hi>. </p>

<p>A first pilot study was carried out, in which data from three universities were collected, and the possibility of extending the study to some foreign universities was studied, an option that was rejected due to the lack of homogeneity in the sources of information. From this pilot study, a small number of <hi rend="italic">key dimensions</hi> were determined, attending their significance for the goal of the study and the facility to be clearly identified in the sources of information. They were the following:
<list>
<item>Ethics and professional responsibility</item>
<item>Environmental</item>
<item>Social</item>
<item>Legal and regulatory</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>In this election, some competences relevant to ESD—critical reasoning, systemic thinking, multidisciplinary work or the economic dimension—have been ruled out. Every engineering degree in Spain includes mandatory courses on Economy, but the contents are not so much related to the inclusive economy, poverty, inequality, or employment, which would be the most significant topics for ESD; when they appear, they have been considered as social issues. The presence of critical reasoning skills is fundamentally related to technical aspects. The difficulty of distinguishing these nuances from the information provided by the <hi rend="italic">Learning Guides</hi> has been the reason for not considering these competences as <hi rend="italic">key dimensions.</hi> However, when they appear, they have been collected as relevant qualitative aspects. </p>

<p>As an example, Table 4 reflects the identifications made from the competences recommended in the official guidelines. </p>

<p>Specifically, information has been collected on:
<list>
<item>Which <hi rend="italic">key dimensions</hi> are included in the degrees competences.</item>
<item>Which <hi rend="italic">key dimensions</hi> are included in the courses competences.</item>
<item>Which <hi rend="italic">key dimensions</hi>, and how many, are included in the syllabus of the courses.</item>
<item>Methodological aspects that are considered of interest for the development of sustainability competences.</item>
<item>Specific assessment methods for sustainability competences.</item>
<item>Other data of the course: compulsory/elective, year, credits, faculty.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>A thorough revision of the <hi rend="italic">Learning Guides</hi> was carried out to collect all this information, using some keywords for each <hi rend="italic">key dimension,</hi> but also taking advantage of the researchers’ knowledge of the subjects for identifying their presence into the syllabuses and selecting inspiring practices. <figure>Figure 1</figure> outlines the way the information has been collected. </p>
</text>
