<text id="autogum_academic_doc668" title="Furcellaran-Coated Microcapsules as Carriers of Cyprinus carpio Skin-Derived Antioxidant Hydrolysate: An In Vitro and In Vivo Study" shortTile="furcellarancoated" author="Joanna Tkaczewska, Ewelina Jamróz, Ewa Piątkowska, Barbara Borczak, Joanna Kapusta-Duch, Małgorzata Morawska" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/10/2502/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Currently, we expect foods to satisfy hunger while delivering nutrients essential for humans, but their task is also the prevention of diet-related diseases. Functional foods play a significant role in this case. Due to their beneficial physiological effects, including antioxidant, anticancer, and anti-inflammatory properties, nutrients from marine animals, as well as bioactive components have great potential as ingredients in functional foods. </p>

<p>After filleting, fish processing waste comprises 75% of the overall fish weight. Approximately 30% of the waste is in the form of bones and skins. Gelatine can be derived from the processing of fish skins, solving the problem of waste disposal while producing a value-added product. Its fast growth rate, as well as good fodder usage cause carp (<hi rend="italic">Cyprinus carpio</hi>) to be one of the most commonly-bred species in eastern Europe, as well as in Poland. The annual European carp production totals approximately 4,328,083 tons. In our previous research, we demonstrated that protein hydrolysates from carp skin gelatine hydrolysate (CSGH) can be potential bioactive peptide sources. </p>

<p>Bioactive peptides consisting of 2–20 residues of amino acids are inactive within the sequences of parent proteins. They can be released via enzymatic hydrolysis either at the time of digestion or during food processing. Antioxidant peptides are among the most frequently-studied bioactive peptides. In particular, in the health food and pharmaceutical industry, fish protein hydrolysates with antioxidant properties have become a highly interesting and discussed subject. </p>

<p>There can be a reduction in bioactive peptide activity due to susceptibility to proteolytic degradation or undesirable interactions with other compounds. Encapsulation usage is a highly significant factor in the protection of these biomolecules, consequently providing greater therapeutic efficacy. Encapsulation may also permit the development of the delivery system through the improvement of stability, causing an increase in residence time regarding circulation, while at the same time causing a significant decrease in toxicity. </p>

<p>The encapsulation of bioactive ingredients within colloidal particles is an influential means of protecting them from degradation. Different types of colloidal delivery systems have been developed, for example emulsions, nanoemulsions, microemulsions, liposomes, solid lipid nanoparticles, hydrogel beads, and biopolymer nanoparticles, each with its own advantages and disadvantages. Edible coating materials are usually composed of polysaccharides and proteins. These materials could be used not only in the form of capsules, but also as films covering the food. Edible films and coatings often containing bioactive agents or food additives like nutrients are gaining relevance as potential tools to reduce the deleterious effects of the incidence of microorganisms or to improve the nutritional value of a product. In the research by Sapper et al., polysaccharide protein films with the addition of thyme essential oil were obtained, which has a strong in vitro fungicidal effect. However, in vivo studies did not confirm the inhibitory effect on the surface of apples. Furthermore, other data from the literature indicate that the properties of biologically-active compounds tested in vitro are not always confirmed in vivo. </p>

<p>Bioactive peptides differ from other food bioactive compounds like vitamins or polyphenols. There is slight heterogeneity regarding the chemical species in the protein hydrolysates. Most studies on bioactive peptides focus on finding new bioactivity and protein precursors, while limited attention is paid to their biostability or bioavailability. Presently, there is a gap in the literature illustrating the various aspects of encapsulation concerning food-protein-derived bioactive peptides. Moreover, there is a need for in vivo studies applying animal models to confirm the success of encapsulation in bioactivity retention following the oral consumption of these products. </p>

<p>Polysaccharides are generally ideal as delivery agents in microcapsules as they are structurally stable, ample in nature, and inexpensive. Polysaccharides with reactive functional groups (carboxyl (COOH)), hydroxyl (OH), amide (NH2), and sulphate groups (SO4H)) are good candidates as carrier matrices. Furcellaran (FUR) is structurally connected with the algal polysaccharide κ carrageenan; however, there is a major structural difference. Furcellaran, which has units consisting of a fragment of (1–3) β-D-galactopyranose with a sulphate group at C-4 and (1–4) -3, 6-anhydro-α-D-galactopyranose, is used as a gelling and stabilizing agent in the food industry. In addition, furcellaran can form complexes with various proteins, which can be used for encapsulation in food and agriculture applications. The interactions between proteins and polysaccharides can lead to the creation of completely new materials. Negatively-charged furcellaran can act as a film-forming matrix in active, biopolymer films and as a carrier material in the encapsulation process. </p>
</text>
