<text id="autogum_academic_doc197" title="Multiphase Computational Fluid Dynamics Analysis of Hydrodynamic Journal Bearing Under the Combined Influence of Texture and Slip" shortTile="multiphase-computational" author="Mohammad Tauviqirrahman, J. Jamari, Bayu  Siswo Wibowo, Hilmy  Muhammad Fauzan, M. Muchammad" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-4442/7/11/97/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Computational Analysis </head><head> 3.1. Geometric Model</head>
<p>
In the frame of both experimental and theoretical studies, recent technological improvements suggest that in order to enhance the tribological performance concerning the load support and friction properties of the journal bearing, partial texturing must be employed. In the present work, textured bearing with a rectangular dimple is of particular interest. The reason for using the rectangular-shaped dimple is that this shape is able to achieve the best performance compared to other shapes based on the work of Vilhena et al.. Additionally, in practice, it is easier to manufacture it. A schematic diagram of smooth (untextured) and textured journal bearings is shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>. The film thickness is approximated by a cosine profile as follows:

(7)

where <hi rend="italic">c</hi> refers to the radial clearance, <hi rend="italic">ε</hi> denotes the eccentricity ratio, and  expresses the circumferential angle.  </p>

<p>For the textured bearing studied here, a texture cell is defined by its dimple depth, <hi rend="italic">D</hi>, dimple length, <hi rend="italic">W</hi>G, and texture cell length, <hi rend="italic">W</hi>cell, as shown in the inset of <figure>Figure 2</figure>. For all following simulations studied here, the texture density, <hi rend="italic">S</hi>T (the ratio of the dimple length, <hi rend="italic">W</hi>G, over the texture cell, <hi rend="italic">W</hi>cell), is assumed to be constant and equal to 0.5. In the present work, more work has been paid to optimizing the texturing parameters with respect to the improvement of the pressure profile and the load support. The length of the texturing zone and the dimple depth for three eccentricity ratios were studied for two surface characteristics (i.e., with and without slip condition). With respect to the effect of dimple depth, a dimensionless parameter, <hi rend="italic">D</hi>/<hi rend="italic">h</hi>min, is introduced, which is the ratio of the dimple depth, <hi rend="italic">D</hi>, over the minimal film thickness, <hi rend="italic">h</hi>min. The surface texturing employed in the present study is a series of dimples on the bearing (stationary) surface depending on the length of the texturing zone. In terms of the texturing zone, for all following computation, the dimples are introduced from the angular coordinates (i.e., circumferential angle) of , with the reference position measured at the <hi rend="italic">h</hi>max as indicated <figure>Figure 1</figure>. Computations were made by varying the length of the texturing zone, , from 0–30° to 0–180°. It should be noted that for all computations, the dimple length, <hi rend="italic">W</hi>G, is equal to 5°. In this way, for each interval of the texturing zone of 30°, there will be six texture cells covering the specified zone.  </p>

<p>A comparative performance analysis between the textured geometry with or without slip and the corresponding smooth configuration was then conducted. The parameters studied are the hydrodynamic pressure and the load support. The load support, <hi rend="italic">W</hi>, per unit length was obtained from the integration of the hydrodynamic pressure acting on the journal.  </p>

<head> 3.2. Solution Set Up</head>
<p>
To determine the appropriate mesh density for evaluating the lubricant characteristics of the journal bearing accurately, the meshing analysis needs to be performed. In the present study, for the calculation the CFD-based commercial software ANSYS DesignModeler and ANSYS ICEM CFD were employed to produce the computational model and structural mesh, respectively. The computational domain is meshed with the uniform quadrilateral grid, as shown in <figure>Figure 3</figure>. The number of mesh points in the longitudinal (<hi rend="italic">N</hi>x) and transverse (<hi rend="italic">N</hi>z) direction was varied in order to get mesh independence. In addition, more refinement of the mesh system, particularly around the dimple area, was also conducted to capture the presence of the flow recirculation due to the sudden change in texture geometry. Consequently, the mesh number used was around 200,000 to 400,000 nodes across the film depending on the texturing zone, dimple depth, and eccentricity ratio.  </p>

<p>In the present work, as reflected in <figure>Figure 4</figure> the boundary condition of the computational domain was set as follows: One side of the location of the maximum film thickness, <hi rend="italic">h</hi>max, is used as an inlet condition and the other as an outlet. The pressure at the inlet (<hi rend="italic">P</hi>in) and outlet (<hi rend="italic">P</hi>out) boundaries is taken as the ambient pressure, i.e., zero pressure. The top wall of the lubricant film is modelled as a stationary surface, whereas the bottom surface is modelled as a moving surface assuming no-slip condition and a rotational velocity equal to that of the shaft. During the calculation in ANSYS FLUENT® software, the regions of cavitation and the hydrodynamic pressure are computed with the MIXTURE model. </p>

<p>In the present numerical study, the pressure-based solver was employed. The SIMPLEC algorithm was used to treat the pressure–velocity coupling. For the momentum equations, the second order upwind discretization scheme was used, whereas the QUICK discretization scheme was employed for the turbulent kinetic energy as well as for the turbulent dissipation rate and the volume fraction equation. In the present work, a convergence tolerance of 1 × 10−6 was adopted for all residual terms for more accurate computational results.  </p>
</text>
