<text id="autogum_academic_doc737" title="Pedestrians and E-Scooters: An Initial Look at E-Scooter Parking and Perceptions by Riders and Non-Riders" shortTile="pedestrians-escooters" author="Owain James, J I Swiderski, John Hicks, Denis Teoman, Ralph Buehler" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5591/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head><head> 4.1. Perception of Safety</head>
<p>
Our survey showed that respondents generally felt less safe while walking around dockless e-scooters than they were around the different types of bicycles. We found a similar result for driving around e-scooters. Increased discomfort around e-scooters may be explained by e-scooters being a new mode that pedestrians (and drivers) are not yet used to. For drivers, previous research has found that motorists fail to notice motorcycles at a higher rate than automobiles, likely due to drivers not expecting to see motorcycles, making it difficult to notice them. This phenomenon has been used to explain the inverse correlation between the number of bicyclists and pedestrians and the rate of cyclist and pedestrian crashes. Researchers have found that, as cyclists and pedestrian numbers increase, safety increases, known as the ‘safety in numbers effect,’ which could be explained by drivers becoming more acclimated to seeing cyclists on the road. E-scooters, unlike bicycles and motorcycles, are a new mode of transport, and both riders and drivers are not yet used to how they operate in traffic. </p>

<p>The survey also reveals large differences in comfort and perceived safety between those who had used dockless e-scooters before and those who had not. More than three quarters (76%) of non-riders reported feeling “unsafe” or “very unsafe” walking around dockless e-scooters while only one quarter (24%) of riders felt this way. This could be explained by riders having a greater familiarity with the devices than those who had never ridden them before. A similar difference appeared when respondents were asked to report how frequently they encountered a sidewalk blocked by a dockless e-scooter. One-third of non-riders reported “always” encountering blocked sidewalks while only 7% of riders reported “always” encountering them. These results are similar toa Washington, DC survey that found that 80% of respondents who did not approve of the city allowing e-scooters to operate had never tried the service (p.34). </p>

<p>While these differences could indicate that greater familiarity with dockless e-scooters leads people to be less bothered by them and to feel safer around them, causation is hard to determine. It could also be the case that people who do not like dockless e-scooters and feel uncomfortable around them choose not to use them. In our survey, those who had used dockless e-scooters before were, on average, much younger than those who had not (84% of riders were younger than 34 compared to 45% of non-riders). This age difference may matter. An e-scooter on the sidewalk might pose a greater challenge to older individuals who may not be able to move the e-scooter out of the way or walk around it as easily as younger respondents.  </p>

<p>Moreover, our study did not define what a “blocked” sidewalk was, nor did we quantify the frequency terms we offered (e.g. “always”). Thus, our respondents likely had different ideas about what constitutes a blocked sidewalk when responding to our question. Similarly, it is possible that someone who has experience with using the devices or is able to step over or move them out of the way does not notice how often they have to do so; while, conversely, someone who has more trouble with them may notice it more, so that the same number of encounters may seem “frequent” or “infrequent” to different people. We recommend that future studies ask more specifically about the number of instances of blocked sidewalks rather than reporting on the categories we used. </p>

<head> 4.2. Knowledge of Laws</head>
<p>
Respondents, even those who had used dockless e-scooters before, were generally unfamiliar with local e-scooter laws. In Arlington County, e-scooters are not allowed to be ridden on the sidewalk or trails, e-bikes are allowed to be ridden on sidewalks but not trails, and riders of bikes and e-scooters are not required to wear helmets. Of note, 43% of respondents who had used a dockless e-scooter in Rosslyn reported that they did not know what the laws governing dockless vehicles in Arlington County were. This is a much higher percentage than a similar survey of e-scooter riders in Portland, OR found. In that survey, 26% of e-scooter riders said they were unfamiliar with e-scooter laws. Portland e-scooter riders were also better at correctly identifying laws; 59% of Rosslyn e-scooter riders thought that riders were required to wear helmets even though Arlington does not require helmet use. In Portland, which requires riders to wear helmets, 67% of e-scooter riders correctly said that helmet use was required, while 65% of Portland riders correctly said that e-scooters were not allowed to be ridden on the sidewalk compared to only 57% of Rosslyn e-scooter riders. </p>
</text>
