<text id="autogum_academic_doc695" title="Air Quality Trend of PM10. Statistical Models for Assessing the Air Quality Impact of Environmental Policies" shortTile="air-quality-trend" author="Ana  Belen Vicente, Pablo Juan, Sergi Meseguer, Laura Serra, Sergio Trilles" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5857/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Due to rapid industrialization, air quality is recognized to be an issue of primary importance for human health. Scientific studies have suggested links between air pollutants and numerous health problems. Thereby, the neediness of improvement air quality in terms of pollutants concentration reduction is essential. In order to deal with this issue, it is necessary to identify and implement long-term air pollution abatement strategies. In this way, the European Union (EU) Framework supplies useful information on air quality assessment techniques, establishes limit values of the pollutants, and urges to develop Air Quality Plans, in particular through Directive 2008/50/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council on ambient air quality and cleaner air for Europe (amended by 2015/1480/EC). </p>

<p>In order to develop Air Quality Plans is essential to know properly the concentrations of the different several pollutants. The EU normative (Directive 2008/50/EC, amended by 2015/1480/EC) suggests that 90% of the data per year are necessary, and where possible, modelling techniques should be applied to enable point data to be interpreted in terms of geographical distribution of concentration. This could serve as a basis for calculating the collective exposure of the population living in the area. The results of modelling shall be taken into account for the assessment of air quality with respect to the target values. </p>

<p>In this context, a spatio-temporal modelling of PM10 (particles &lt; 10 m) concentration is applied to understand the trend, to know the influence of the variables to exposure risk, to find the missing data to evaluate air quality, and to estimate data for those sites where they are not available. In addition, it is a useful tool to reduce the number of the sampling points or the days of sampling when there is not enough equipment. This assessment is essential to improve air quality policies and warning alert systems. </p>

<p>The lack of information in time series for each of the monitoring stations makes it difficult to analyse and manage statistics. Previously, statistical methods have been used to predict the concentration of PM10 over time. The aim of this study is to fill missing data by using interpolation statistical methods. The study also focuses on testing the goodness of these methods in order to find the one that better approaches the gaps. After comparing the results of the methods employed through the correlation analysis, the best matching method to restore missing data is chosen. </p>
</text>
