<text id="autogum_academic_doc042" title="Phytotoxic Metabolites Produced by Legume-Associated Ascochyta and Its Related Genera in the Dothideomycetes" shortTile="phytotoxic-metabolites" author="Wonyong Kim, Weidong Chen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6651/11/11/627/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Biosynthesis Gene Cluster and Ecological Roles</head><head> 3.1. Solanapyrone Biosynthesis Gene Cluster</head>
<p>
The solanapyrone biosynthesis gene cluster comprises six genes (<hi rend="italic">sol1</hi>–<hi rend="italic">sol6</hi>), and was first identified in <hi rend="italic">Alternaria solani</hi>. Interestingly, the highly conserved gene cluster was also found in <hi rend="italic">A. rabiei</hi>, showing overall 97% similarity at the amino acid sequence level. The polyketide synthase (PKS) encoded by the <hi rend="italic">sol1</hi> is classified as a highly-reducing PKS and is thought to be involved in biosynthesis of the precursor prosolanapyrone, an α-pyrone with an unsaturated alkyl chain. The production of such linear α-pyrones has been reported in <hi rend="italic">Al. solani</hi> and related fungi, but the difference in solanapyrone biosynthesis from other linear α-pyrones is the involvement of a Diels–Alder reaction catalyzed by <hi rend="italic">sol5</hi> to form a decalin ring from the unsaturated alkyl chain of prosolanapyrone. </p>

<p>As mentioned above, solanapyrones have been considered a pathogenicity factor due to their strong phytotoxicity. However, genetic mutants of both <hi rend="italic">A. rabiei</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Al. solani</hi> lacking the Diels–Alderase enzyme lost the production of solanapyrone but remained pathogenic, suggesting that solanapyrones are not required for pathogenicity. The expression patterns of the Diels–Alderase gene in <hi rend="italic">A. rabiei</hi> also supported this observation, as the gene was specifically expressed at the site of sporulation, but not during plant infection. Furthermore, solanapyrones were produced in <hi rend="italic">A. rabiei</hi> growing on chickpea straw, and interestingly, xylan, when used as a sole carbon source, supported the greatest production of solanapyrones, suggesting the saprobic growth stage-specific production. Similarly, brefeldin A was specifically produced during the saprobic growth of <hi rend="italic">P. medicaginis</hi>. Given the observed antimicrobial activities of solanapyrones produced by fungi occupying diverse ecological niches, solanapyrones may play a role in competition with other saprobic microbes. </p>

<head> 3.2. Ascochitine Biosynthesis Gene Cluster</head>
<p>
Ascochitine is structurally similar to the well-known mycotoxin citrinin produced by fungal species in the genera <hi rend="italic">Aspergillus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Monascus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Penicillium</hi>. A putative PKS gene for ascochitine biosynthesis was identified in <hi rend="italic">A. fabae</hi> through a homology-based search with PKS genes responsible for citrinin biosynthesis, and its involvement in ascochitine biosynthesis was confirmed by gene knockout study. Intriguingly, homologs of the ascochitine PKS gene were found in the genome sequences of multiple <hi rend="italic">A. lentis</hi> isolates from which ascochitine was not detected. Many single nucleotide polymorphisms were observed in the homologous PKS genes, which include nonsense mutations, resulting in no ascochitine production in <hi rend="italic">A. lentis</hi> isolates. </p>

<p>The putative ascochitine gene cluster comprises eleven genes including a transcription factor (TF), a transporter, tailoring enzymes and proteins with unknown function. The putative TF in the ascochitine gene cluster belongs to the fungal-specific Zn(II)2Cys6 zinc cluster TF family. However, it lacked a DNA-binding domain that is typically found in the TF family. Interestingly, this unusual type of TF was also found in the solanapyrone gene cluster, and it was reported that the TF encoded by the <hi rend="italic">sol4</hi> positively regulates the whole solanapyrone gene cluster. </p>

<p>Pathogenicity tests with asochitine-minus mutants of <hi rend="italic">A. fabae</hi> lacking the ascochitine PKS gene indicated that ascochitine was not essential for causing disease on faba bean. Unlike in another ascochitine-producing fungus <hi rend="italic">P. clematidina</hi>, there was no positive correlation between the aggressiveness of <hi rend="italic">A. fabae</hi> isolates and their capability in in vitro ascochitine production. Ascochitine accumulated in aged hyphae where sporulation was initiated in <hi rend="italic">A. fabae</hi> and <hi rend="italic">A. viciae-villosae</hi>, suggesting ascochitine may have a role in combatting with microbial competitors in nature. </p>

<head> 3.3. Ascofuranone Biosynthesis Gene Cluster</head>
<p>
The transcriptome-based approach for identifying SM gene clusters was excellently applied to discover ascofuranone/ascochlorin biosynthesis gene cluster in <hi rend="italic">Acremonium egyptiacum</hi>. The ascofuranone/ascochlorin gene clusters were separated at two genomic loci, and the main gene cluster harboring a PKS gene was sufficient for ascochlorin biosynthesis. Combining differential gene expression analyses and the functional prediction of genes by homology, the authors were able to locate the second gene cluster harboring three genes that are required for further modifications of an ascochlorin precursor to biosynthesize ascofuranone. Although the complete biosynthetic pathway and responsible genes for the biosynthesis of ascofuranone/ascochlorin were identified, their ecological roles in the fungal biology remain to be determined. </p>

<head> 3.4. Identification of Other SM Gene Clustesrs in the Legume-Associated Ascochyta Species</head>
<p>
The advancement in bioinformatics tools and growing knowledge on PKS genes allowed the recent identification of ascochitine and ascofuranone/ascochlorin biosynthesis gene clusters. The homology-based search and subsequent phylogenetic analysis of candidate PKS genes with known PKS genes that have been linked to biosynthetic pathways will aid in the future identification of SM gene clusters in the legume-associated <hi rend="italic">Ascochyta</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Phoma</hi> species. </p>
</text>
