<text id="autogum_academic_doc390" title="Morphological Traits, Kernel Composition and Sensory Evaluation of Hazelnut (Corylus avellana L.) Cultivars Grown in Poland" shortTile="morphological-traits" author="Katarzyna Król, Magdalena Gantner, Anna Piotrowska" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4395/9/11/703/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Hazelnut (<hi rend="italic">Corylus avellana</hi> L.) is one of the most important tree nut crops in worldwide production. Poland ranks as the 11th largest producer of hazelnuts in the world, with total production of 4635 tons and harvested area 3740 ha in 2017. Turkey is the main producer and exporter of hazelnuts with 569,162 tons/year, followed by Italy and USA with 108,428 and 33,783 tons/year, respectively. The world market for hazelnuts is divided into two groups: nuts with intact shells for direct consumption (10%) and shelled nuts transferred for further technological purposes (90%). Poland has developed the cultivation of only large-sized, so-called table cultivars, with large, oval nuts, almost all of which are sold as a raw product for fresh consumption. Furthermore, most of hazelnut grown in Poland are originated from <hi rend="italic">C. avellane</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">pontica, Corylus maxima, Corylus lamberti</hi> or are derived from their hybrids.  </p>

<p>Knowledge of nut and kernel physical characteristics (such as volume, sphericity, etc.) are necessary to project the processing lines of hazelnuts because many types of machines are influenced by the size and shape of the food. The size of hazelnuts is used in the separation of foreign materials and separation into size categories. Sphericity is one of the most important quality traits among hazelnut properties because it is mostly spherical nuts that most preferred in the food industry, whereas the surface area is used to estimate the amount of packaging material required and is important in roasting and cooling operations. The rupture force required for the whole nut and kernel is important during the mechanical shelling process because the application of too great a force can cause damage to the hazelnuts and nut losses in production. </p>

<p>In recent years, some studies have been carried out on the physicochemical properties of hazelnuts grown in Poland. However, research on the morphological and physical characteristics of hazelnuts grown in Poland is limited compared to that on nuts from Turkey, Italy Iran, Portugal and Serbia. Furthermore, high-quality hazelnut cultivars to be used for processing purposes have not been identified in Poland and the cultivated kernels often do not meet market standards determined by the confectionery industry. The first objective of this research was to determine the genetic variability between all six hazelnut cultivars in relation to the nut and kernel genetic variability physical characteristics as well as major physio-quality traits. The second objective was to select the most suitable hazelnut cultivar with the highest processing value for confectionery use and table consumption for Poland. </p>
</text>
