<text id="autogum_academic_doc438" title="A Fuzzy Set Qualitative Comparative Analysis (fsQCA) of the Agricultural Cooperatives from South East Region of Romania" shortTile="fuzzy-set-qualitative" author="Andrei-Mirel Florea, Florentin Bercu, Riana  Iren Radu, Silvius Stanciu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5927/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. The Development of Some Competitive Cooperatives</head>
<p>The approach of the theme of the present paper started from “A Guide to Setting up Cooperatives” study issued by the International Labor Office in 1984. The fundamental elements of a cooperative are presented in detail within the guide. By corroborating the provisions of the guide with the specialty literature in an empirical manner, a series of reciprocal relations, which must exist within any agricultural cooperative, was established (<figure>Figure 1</figure>). </p>

<p>According to Iliopoulos, the traditional agricultural cooperatives must be in a continuous development process in order to be able to resist the market and to cope with the challenges and competition. </p>

<p>This process is defined by Cook and Burress as a cyclic struggle, with an evolution on five distinct phases. The first two phases are represented by the economic justification and the organizational design, which are defining the cooperative setting up stage. The following two phases are characteristic of the development stage of the cooperative and its related problems. The last phase is represented by the choice of reorganizing or redesigning the activity, of the management, and of the strategies pursued, or by renouncing cooperation. In the present study, we aim to analyze the first two phases and the impact of their non-fulfillment on the sustainability and competitiveness of the cooperative. </p>

<head> 2.1. Group—Capital Cohesion</head>
<p>It represents the stage in which the members have been co-opted within the cooperative, have understood the operating principles, and brought capital to cover the setting up expenses. This stage reflects the creation of the core. In addition, at this stage, the co-operators must understand that the participation in the cooperative is a medium and long-term investment, and that the initial contribution must be supplemented, together with the maintenance and development of the group cohesion for a harmonious operation of the cooperative. The same opinion is also expressed by Bercu, who draws attention on the strengthening of the farmer’s position in the food chain, in order to combat unfair commercial practices. </p>

<p>As Cook and Burress state, it is necessary for the members to understand both the benefits of the cooperative (economic justification) and its role of common protection of the cooperative members, as compared to the individual risk. Problems and difficulties may arise when these elements are not well clarified. </p>

<p>There is a mutual connection between the trust of the members based on social cohesion and their contribution within the cooperative. The involvement of the participants in the cooperative through the capital, in a regulated proportion, represents, in Ostrom’s opinion, “a collection of both formal and informal forms and standards” that determine the members to work together and to cooperate. The importance of the share capital within the cooperative is compared by Chloupkova et al. with physical and human capital in trading companies. </p>

<p>Thus, the size of the member participation in the capital of the cooperative has an important impact on its development and performance. </p>

<p>The absence of the three elements of the initial stage, which ensures the cohesion of the group, including the trust, capital, and communication between members, discourages their involvement in collective actions. </p>

<p>Given the complexity of the relationships within a cooperative, represented using each member’s own production factors and their desire to exercise control and ownership, the cooperatives cannot be viewed in the same way as other enterprises. </p>

<p>The Copa Cogeca report draws attention to the need for the legislative regulation of cooperative financing in Romania, because they are treated in the same way as commercial companies, without being included in the bank nomenclature. Under these conditions, the main financing sources of agricultural cooperatives during the setup phase are represented by the share capital deposited by the members and by accessing non-reimbursable funds/subsidies. </p>

<p>Based on these aspects, the first proposition of the study was defined.<b>Proposition</b> <b>1.</b></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Members’ contribution, which is limited only to covering the minimum capital regulated by law, impacts the competitiveness of the cooperative.</hi> </p>

<head> 2.2. Central Collection Space</head>
<p>In order to comply with the objective of the agricultural cooperative to obtain better prices than by individual trade or by trade immediately after harvest, the existence of at least one collection/storage space of the harvest is important for the sale at advantageous prices. The policy of the cooperative in what concerns the sales must be well adapted in order to be able to establish the price, the conditions in which they are prepared to sell, and the collection place. </p>

<p>According to the type of product/products traded by the cooperative, the collection space must fulfill certain particularities. We consider the existence of an adequate space for weighting, selling, and packing products necessary. </p>

<p>The International Labor Office, through the Guide on the collection of agricultural production, makes a series of determinations regarding the support of transport costs both by the members and the cooperative, diversified according to product categories, perishability, durability, value, and season.<b>Proposition</b><b>2.</b></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Without an adequate collection space, the cooperatives cannot develop their activity in optimum conditions.</hi> </p>
</text>
