<text id="autogum_academic_doc093" title="Maize Open-Pollinated Populations Physiological Improvement: Validating Tools for Drought Response Participatory Selection" shortTile="maize-openpollinated" author="Susana  T. Leitão, Emanuel Ferreira, M.  Catarina Bicho, Mara  L. Alves, Duarte Pintado, Daniela Santos, Pedro Mendes-Moreira, Susana  S. Araújo, J.  Miguel Costa, Maria  Carlota Vaz Patto" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6081/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Conventional plant breeding has been efficient in increasing the yield of most major crops, especially under favorable environments. For example, in the USA, maize yields increased by more than five-fold since 1930, mainly due to the development of uniform hybrid varieties. However, conventional plant breeding was less successful in traditional low-input or organic farming systems in which more severe stress conditions are experienced. In this context, participatory plant breeding (PPB) programs are arising worldwide as an alternative solution to meet the needs of small-scale farmers normally overlooked by conventional breeding. Participatory breeding differs from conventional breeding mainly on the active participation of other actors besides breeders, such as farmers and/or consumers. </p>

<p>Portugal was one of the first European countries to adopt maize more than five centuries ago, and is characterized by its great diversity of historical maize populations that can still be found under cultivation. In this way, Portuguese maize populations (Open-Pollinated Varieties—OPVs) are still evolving and adapting both to the local environment and human uses, namely, to bread production (‘breadability’).  </p>

<p>To answer the needs of the Portuguese farmers concerning their maize populations (yield, biotic stress resistance, ‘breadability’, intercropping systems), a successful long-term maize PPB program has been running in Portugal since 1984. As part of this program, farmers are encouraged to add simple, low-cost population improvement methodologies to their selection criteria, increasing its efficiency, and allowing them to optimize the use of their own maize populations. Maize populations are subject to stratified mass selection with two parental (male and female) controls at farmers’ fields, in a breeder and farmer partnership, with the farmer establishing the breeding objectives. Selection takes place not only after harvesting, at the storage facilities (considering ear morphological traits) as traditionally applied by the farmer, but also during crop growing before harvest (considering plant architecture ideotype, root and stalk quality traits). Several improved OPVs were generated by this PPB program. The farmer’s motivation and time availability/field dimensions (the bigger the field, the larger amount of time needed for stratified selection) seem to be the two main limitations for the successful implementation of this participatory approach. Reliable, low-cost, fast and easy-to-use selection tools are needed to attract farmers to these participatory breeding approaches. This PPB program was recently extended to other Portuguese maize OPVs production areas and to organic production systems.  </p>

<p>Both Portuguese and foreign farmers are increasingly concerned with climate change impacts. Indeed, the probability of more severe and persistent droughts may increase especially in areas such as the Mediterranean basin. The expected global average annual maize yield loss rate due to drought is about 19%, being the Iberian Peninsula among the areas with the highest maize drought risk.  </p>

<p>Maize is a crop susceptible to drought, and flowering is the most critical period. Irrigation helps to guarantee yield and quality under dry and warm climates, and it has expanded worldwide namely in Portugal, allowing higher yields with for example hybrid varieties. However, irrigation poses increasing pressure on the available water resources in dry regions such as the Mediterranean. Therefore, breeding for higher crop tolerance to drought is imperative for modern agriculture and horticulture in dry and warm areas and for low-input farming systems. </p>

<p>Incorporation of tolerance/resistance to drought is becoming an important selection objective of ongoing PPB programs and implies the existence of sources of tolerance/resistance traits and adequate and feasible phenotyping approaches and related technologies. Lower water requirements of some Portuguese maize landraces are among the major reasons given by Portuguese farmers to keep on producing them instead of hybrid varieties. Therefore, traditional maize landraces can be a potential source of genes to develop maize varieties better adapted to drought. In addition, the Portuguese maize OPVs have considerable high levels of inter and intra molecular genetic diversity which allows agronomical improvement. However, detailed morphological and eco-physiological studies to evaluate their diversity of response to drought are limited and few field studies using this national germplasm have been performed.  </p>

<p>Selecting for drought tolerance/resistance based on yield is a complicated task due to the complex nature of the trait and its low heritability. The task becomes particularly complex for participatory breeding approaches in which selection tools are to be applied directly by farmers.  </p>
</text>
