<text id="autogum_academic_doc691" title="From Single-Use Community Facilities Support to Integrated Sustainable Development: The Aims of Inter-Municipal Cooperation in Poland, 1990–2018" shortTile="singleuse-community" author="Marek Furmankiewicz, Adrian Campbell" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5890/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Conceptual Background</head>
<p>
Regarding economic development strategies, two basic models have been identified: exo- and endogenous development. The first emphasizes top-down management using external technology, capital and human resources, often organised in separate, sectoral agencies under central government control (e.g., agriculture, industry, culture). The second concept, the endogenous (or grass-roots) approach, encourages bottom-up development factors, trusting in the sustainable use of local resources for socio-economic development by cooperating residents. </p>

<p>The exogenous model of sectoral development policies was common in democratic countries in the mid-20th century and dominated in the socialist (or “communist”) countries of Central and Eastern Europe to such an extent that independent local and regional self-government did not exist, in Poland for example, until these were re-introduced in 1990. However, in the Western liberal democracies, in the 1980s, that model of development policy began to be perceived as ineffective and even detrimental, leading to regional disparity, environmental damage and the degradation of nature. As a result, a neo-endogenous approach, based on territorial cross-sectoral cooperation of local stakeholders (i.e., on territorial governance processes) began to gain favour. The model of territorial governance as a horizontal, cross-sectoral regional network has tended to be most pronounced in the Anglo-Saxon countries and has remained popular through much of Western Europe where traditions of co-operative governance are strong, not least because the state is sufficiently powerful to be confident of maintaining the initiative in partnerships. In developing countries the notion of collaborative governance has been widely promoted as a means of legitimising and strengthening the role of civil society in the management of public goods in the absence of sufficient local state capacity or for increasing state accountability. Collaborative territorial governance may be seen as an instrument not only for the production of public goods and management of local, limited resources, but also for changing the nature and logic of state-society relations in a given country. It was disseminated throughout most European post-socialist countries from the early 21st century, mainly after their accession to the European Union. The term “endogenous development” is considered as more or less synonymous with the “grassroots”, “bottom-up” or “participatory” approach to management of local resources and is closely related to “sustainable development” in policy practice. </p>

<p>The advantages attributed to local stakeholders’ territorial cooperation encouraged EU policy makers to promote neo-endogenous and place-based integrated development, in which such governance processes have an important role, and have similar features and are considered more sustainable than the top-down exogenous approach. These models seek to construct a hybrid of top-down and bottom-up development by incorporating top-down support for bottom-up territorial governance in functional areas. According to Ray, neo-endogenous development has a strong emphasis on local resources, capacities, perspectives, needs and knowledge but it also involves hierarchical management of incentives and the replacement of the principle of “administrative territory” by a functional principle, with inter-sectoral co-operation through regional networks and partnerships and increased self-governing responsibilities at regional or local levels. In other words, these models assume the mobilisation of local stakeholders, their knowledge, demands and concerns by instruments and territorial organisational forms determined by central government, for example, via financial grants with territorial partnership creation as conditionality. The approach is seen to further the European Union’s objectives of smart, inclusive and sustainable growth. </p>

<p>The term “place-based development” was popularised initially by the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) report and the Barca report to the European Union as a means of social inclusion and participatory and fair process in development policy. It implied territorially sensitive, multi-sectoral approaches, involving multilevel governance and co-ordination of all relevant levels, policies and stakeholders. The approach informed the creation of area-based development partnerships in functional regions, managed by diverse local stakeholders, for instance EU Local Action Groups in rural and urban areas within the framework of Community-Led Local Development, Integrated Territorial Investment Partnerships in metropolitan areas, “Urban Action Europe” (URBACT) Local Support Groups in cities and others. Place-based development, according to Zaucha and Świątek, is a long-term development strategy aimed at reducing persistent inefficiency (underutilisation of the full potential) and inequality (the share of people below a given standard of well-being and/or extent of interpersonal disparities) in specific places. It can be attained through the production of bundles of integrated, place-tailored public goods and services, designed and implemented by eliciting and aggregating local preferences and knowledge through participatory political institutions, and by establishing linkages with other places. It can be promoted from outside by a system of multilevel governance in which grants, subject to conditionality on both objectives and institutions, are transferred from higher to lower levels of government. Both place-based and neo-endogenous development emphasise the need to take into simultaneous consideration the social, economic and environmental needs of the locality, through a cooperative network of different local and external stakeholders, an approach which is termed as “sustainable” or “integrated”. </p>
</text>
