<text id="autogum_academic_doc201" title="Developing a Data Mining Based Model to Extract Predictor Factors in Energy Systems: Application of Global Natural Gas Demand" shortTile="developing-data-mining" author="Reza Hafezi, Amir  Naser Akhavan, Mazdak Zamani, Saeed Pakseresht, Shahaboddin Shamshirband" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4124/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The world energy demand increased in the two past decades and even predictions implying the growing trends for the next decades. Still, fossil fuels play a critical role in the energy supply chain due to economic feasibility. Refer to International Energy Agency’s (IEA) 2016 report, fossil fuels in the form of liquid fuels, natural gas, and coal contain more than 80% of the world energy consumption. Easiness of utilization, higher performance, compared to traditional energy sources, ease of mobility via land or sea, and affordable extraction cost introduced oil and natural gas (NG) as strategic commodities. However, emergent ecological concerns and rethinking of a more peaceful future (sustainable development goals) attracted attention toward climate change challenges (such as greenhouse gases emissions and global warming). The two non-aligned objectives, on one hand, development and increasing needs for energy supply and on the other hand global environmental concerns, attracted researchers to study energy systems and develop different plausible future perspectives. </p>

<p>World’s economic growth still strongly correlated with the energy and, as a result, the energy price influence potential future trends. The 1970’s energy crisis represented how energy shocks can cause chaotic behavior of economic systems especially in the case of developed countries which mostly play in energy markets as importers. Although new paradigms emerged to address the modern world energy challenges, such as evaluating and improving the energy security level, but policymakers are facing deep uncertainties in this area. Energy markets are known as complex systems, which consist of numerous players with conflict of interests and changing rules. </p>

<p>Despite successful efforts, the main problem is still existing, which is defined as “discovering reliable future trends and probable alternative futures in the field of energy systems and uncover the most influencing driving forces to aid energy management process”. To project a reliable future, it is crucial to investigating almost all informative input features which represent historical behavior of the targeted complex system and extrapolate future trends. Studying different input features means to peruse different aspects, while on the other hand, it means more efforts in term of cost, time, and complicated estimator. A traditional approach to address a complex problem is to simplify and decompose it to its main constituent elements. Feature selection methods are aimed to adjust the unnecessary complexity revealed to refer to the existence of multiple input features. A feature selection method determines the best subset of the initial features set as a representative of the solution space (for more information about feature selection approaches and methods see:). Selected features interpreted as key driving forces which will help to extrapolate future trends. Moreover, pre-processing might also be performed in order to speed up computation. Finally, an estimator is needed to predict future behaviors of the targeted variable. Despite there are many classical methods but artificial intelligence-based methods are extensively used during the last couple of decades that attempt to uncover weak signals and pattern more reliable and accurate. As Kourou et al. noted these methods can discover and identify patterns and relationships between them, from complex datasets, while they are able to effectively predict future outcomes. Technologies as Data Mining, Natural Language Processing, and Machine Learning can provide novel alternatives to explore and exploit potential retrieved knowledge from historical records, and help to decrease prediction errors effectively. </p>

<p>This paper is aimed to develop an intelligent learning-based prediction model which is equipped with data mining (DM) techniques to purify and the setup input vector. The DM step is used to select and organize the best input features that represent patterns of future global NG demand trends. Although many previous studies successfully addressed NG global demand prediction problem, we attempt to uncover the most effective driving forces as input features and analyzing how they will affect the objective function (NG global demand prediction). For example, the proposed model studies time relation between input variables and the target variable. So a less-dimension input set is available to policymakers to simplify and experience reliable decision-making process. </p>

<p>As it is impressed by a series of variables and oscillating time series, the NG forecasting problem is a very challenging. These days, massive efforts have been investigated artificial intelligence (AI) models or integration of several models (hybrid models) for prediction problems to increase the accuracy and the model reliability. </p>
</text>
