<text id="autogum_academic_doc331" title="Assessing the Use of Sentinel-2 Time Series Data for Monitoring Cork Oak Decline in Portugal" shortTile="assessing-use-sentinel" author="Ana Navarro, Joao Catalao, Joao Calvao" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/21/2515/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Conclusions</head>
<p>
A dense Sentinel-2 time series, covering a time period of around 18 months, was used to evaluate the potential of this free and open data for monitoring cork oak vitality. For this purpose, the temporal variability of two samples of healthy and unhealthy trees identified within the two in situ data collection sites considered in this study was analysed using different vegetation indices. </p>

<p>To focus the analysis at the tree level, very high-resolution UAV images were used to develop an algorithm for the automatic detection of individual trees. The algorithm relies first on the binary segmentation and filtering of a SAVI image, followed by an iterative method based on the Euclidean distance of the binary image to detect each tree centre. The algorithm was able to detect trees with an overall accuracy higher than 75%.  </p>

<p>Independently of the vegetation index considered, cork oak status exhibited a positive correlation with increased precipitation for both sets of trees. During the rainy season, the increase in the spectral response of both types of trees in the near infrared region results from the spectral contribution of the understory to cork oak reflectance, particularly for trees with small crowns. However, during the dry season healthy cork oak trees showed higher spectral reflectance responses in the near infrared and red edge bands than unhealthy trees. This might be explained by the higher degree of defoliation exhibited by trees with loss of vitality, implying a reduced photosynthetic activity and consequently a lower spectral response in the near infrared region. </p>

<p>NDVI and CI were the vegetation indices that maximised the discrimination between healthy and unhealthy cork oak trees when using data corresponding to the driest period of 2018, which occurred from the beginning of September until the beginning of October. The ratio between the temporal mean and the temporal standard deviation calculated with data acquired during the dry season seems to be useful for the identification of cork oak trees with less vitality. Healthy cork oak trees showed higher NDVI and CI temporal mean values and lower temporal standard deviation values than unhealthy trees, which is easily explained by the fact that being an evergreen tree, its spectral response in the near infrared region is relatively stable along the year. Alternatively, the NDVI-derived VCI and CI-derived VCI also improved the discrimination between healthy and unhealthy cork oak trees when using a cumulative distribution function (CDF). Both approaches enabled the establishment of three simultaneous conditions for site HMG, which applied to the other test area (site CL) were able to detect around 68% of the unhealthy trees identified on the field. </p>

<p>These preliminary results seem promising, especially when considering VCI that is useful for making relative assessments of changes in the NDVI signal. Relative measurements of the present vegetation condition against a reference condition are critical for understanding and quantifying real vegetation conditions, characterized by historical mean.
 </p>
</text>
