<text id="autogum_academic_doc471" title="mir-101-3p Downregulation Promotes Fibrogenesis by Facilitating Hepatic Stellate Cell Transdifferentiation During Insulin Resistance" shortTile="mirp-downregulation" author="Marica Meroni, Miriam Longo, Veronica Erconi, Luca Valenti, Stefano Gatti, Anna  Ludovica Fracanzani, Paola Dongiovanni" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/11/2597/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) represents the leading cause of progressive liver disorders worldwide, affecting between 20% to 40% of the adult population. NAFLD is defined by increased hepatic fat accumulation not explained by alcohol abuse, and it encompasses a wide spectrum of liver injuries, ranging from simple steatosis (&gt;5% of liver weight) to its inflammatory form nonalcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH). NASH may be complicated by the presence of fibrosis and, eventually, it may progress to cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC). NAFLD has a strong inherited component, and variants in proteins regulating hepatocellular lipid handling, including patatin-like phospholipase domain-containing 3 (PNPLA3), transmembrane 6 superfamily member 2 (TM6SF2), membrane bound O-acyltransferase domain-containing 7 (MBOAT7), predispose to the disease development and progression to NASH and fibrosis. Dietary habits such as excessive caloric intake, fructose consumption, and physical inactivity represent other risk factors for NAFLD development. In addition, its pathogenesis is closely intertwined with excessive adiposity, insulin resistance (IR), and metabolic syndrome. </p>

<p>IR even correlates with the severity of liver fibrosis, the main determinant of NAFLD prognosis. Indeed, fibrosis has been observed in diabetic patients with NAFLD even independently of NASH, and genetic variants that impair insulin receptor (InsR) signaling favor fibrosis development in NAFLD patients. The mechanism whereby IR aggravates fibrosis may be related to reduced extracellular matrix (ECM) degradation and to the induction of proteins involved in collagen crosslinking. </p>

<p>A new perspective of NAFLD pathogenesis and management is provided by epigenetics, which modulate transcriptome in response to environmental cues. In particular, microRNAs (miRNAs) are short non-protein coding, single-strand RNAs of 19–22 nucleotides that regulate gene expression and cell-to-cell communication as it occurs between hepatocytes and hepatic stellate cells (HSCs) during fibrogenesis. Alteration of miRNA expression in response to genetic/epigenetic factors or environmental conditions may contribute to steatosis onset and NAFLD progression to fibrosis and cancer, mirroring the histological features and the molecular events occurring in NAFLD. Thus, they could be exploited as attractive candidate biomarkers for an accurate profiling of the different stages of liver injury, enabling early and non-invasive diagnosis and the clinical monitoring of the disease progression. </p>

<p>Therefore, we aimed to explore the mechanisms through which epigenetics and environmental factors interact to promote progressive NAFLD in the context of IR. To this purpose, we first assessed which miRNAs were deregulated by IR in HSCs whose activation represents the hallmark of liver fibrosis. Secondly, we evaluated whether the miRNAs differentially expressed in insulin resistant HSCs could impact on NAFLD-related fibrosis by using an experimental model of IR-NASH. Thus, to investigate the independent contribution of IR and NASH that is usually intertwined in patients on miRNAs expression, IR was induced in mice by haploinsufficiency for InsR (InsR+/−), which determines an impairment of hepatic insulin signaling recapitulating that has been observed in NAFLD patients. Conversely, to model fibrogenic NASH, we exploited the methionine choline deficient (MCD) diet, which impairs phospholipid metabolism without altering IR. Finally, we tested the expression of the candidate miRNAs in immortalized human hepatoma cells (HepG2) and in HSCs (LX-2) in the presence or absence of miRNA mimics. Here, we showed that miR-101-3p was downregulated in InsR+/− HSCs and hepatocytes, its expression was reduced even in total livers of insulin resistant mice, and it was associated with all stages of liver disease. </p>

<p>Consistently with these results, target prediction analysis revealed that miR-101-3p is involved in insulin signaling, lipid metabolism, cell proliferation, fibrogenesis, and cancer susceptibility, possibly representing a molecular signature in NAFLD during IR. Furthermore, miR-101-3p overexpression in HepG2 and LX-2 reduced proliferation, migration, and invasiveness, regulating pro-fibrotic and pro-carcinogenic markers. </p>
</text>
