<text id="autogum_academic_doc323" title="A LAPS-Based Differential Sensor for Parallelized Metabolism Monitoring of Various Bacteria" shortTile="lapsbased-differential" author="Shahriar Dantism, Désirée Röhlen, Torsten Wagner, Patrick Wagner, Michael  J. Schöning" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4692/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Food digestion within the gastrointestinal tract is a good example for biofermentation processes in our daily life, in which many different types of microorganisms can be involved. Without microbes, large and complex food molecules cannot be broken down into required nutrients for the human body. In the food-research sector, complex microbial interactions have been studied to enhance, for instance, the aroma profile and flavor in soy sauce during the fermentation process. As another example, microorganisms play a major role in coffee fermentation by degrading the mucilage to alcohols, acids, and enzymes. In agricultural biogas plants, various types of bacteria contribute to the conversion of biomass (e.g., maize silage) into a usable energy source (e.g., methane gas). In all applications of bioreactor technology, the on-line monitoring of the metabolic activity of microorganisms should be seriously considered to avoid undesired, time-consuming, and cost-intensive interventions, which can reduce the yield at the end of the production chain. Related fields of application include: cell health monitoring in bioreactors, continuous non-invasive monitoring of cell growth in disposable bioreactors, on-line near-infrared bioreactor monitoring of cell density, online monitoring of cell concentration in high-cell density <hi rend="italic">Escherichia coli</hi> cultivations, sensing metabolites for monitoring the tissue-engineered cellularity in perfusion bioreactors, and micro-biosensors for fed-batch fermentation with integrated online monitoring. In all of those examples, analytical sensors are the enabling element for rapid, sensitive, and cost-effective detection of various parameters (e.g., health, growth, and density of cells in bioreactors). In this context, light-addressable potentiometric sensors (LAPS) can be applied as suitable tools for monitoring the extracellular acidification of cells. A LAPS is a field-effect-based chemical sensor with the ability to monitor concentration changes of biochemical/biological species in a spatially resolved way. It belongs to the family of electrolyte/insulator/semiconductor (EIS)-based capacitive sensors. By addressing defined regions of interest on a sensor chip with modulated light beams such as laser-diode modules, two-dimensional (2D) chemical images of concentration distributions can be recorded. In comparison to other 2D potentiometric chemical imaging sensors applying e.g., arrays of ion-sensitive field-effect transistors (ISFETs) or charge-coupled devices (CCDs), LAPS require no sensor patterns to record chemical images: The LAPS surface does not require pattering, wiring or passivation, which allows bacteria to come directly into contact with the pH-sensitive transducer layer to determine the extracellular acidification. Furthermore, on its planar sensor surface, multi-chamber structures can be attached to perform differential measurements with distinct cell suspensions. The principle of differential measurements allows elimination of unwanted external influences such as sensor signal drift and pH value variations of the measurement solution during experiments. Beside the chemical imaging technique visualizing the pH distribution on the sensor surface, there are a variety of further LAPS sensing techniques such as the scanned light-pulse technique (SLPT) in studies of interface properties (e.g<hi rend="italic">.,</hi> flat-band voltage), or scanning photo-induced impedance microscopy (SPIM) analyzing impedance changes e.g<hi rend="italic">.,</hi> in PAH/PSS polyelectrolyte microcapsules labeled with Au nanoparticles. The equivalent circuit diagram for designing the LAPS set-up consists of three key parts (illumination area, non-illumination area, and an external circuit), which are described in details in. The sensor fabrication steps are described in Section 2.1. Explanations about LAPS operation modes (e.g., constant-bias, constant-current, potential-tracking, and phase-mode) can be found in. </p>

<p>A few examples of on-going research for LAPS-based biosensing are the determination of the extracellular acidification of <hi rend="italic">Escherichia coli</hi>, and differential imaging of the metabolism of bacteria and eukaryotic cells. In this regard, quantitative differential monitoring of the metabolic activity of <hi rend="italic">Corynebacterium glutamicum</hi>, and image detection of yeast <hi rend="italic">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</hi> have been recently discussed. Correspondingly, dual functional extracellular recording for better signal transduction, and monitoring secretion of adrenal chromaffin cells by local extracellular acidification are further applications. </p>

<p>In this work and for the first time, the extracellular acidification of three model microorganisms, namely <hi rend="italic">Escherichia coli</hi> (<hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi>) K12, <hi rend="italic">Corynebacterium glutamicum</hi> (<hi rend="italic">C. glutamicum</hi>) ATCC13032, and <hi rend="italic">Lactobacillus brevis</hi> (<hi rend="italic">L. brevis</hi>) ATCC 14869 is assessed simultaneously by means of a four-chamber differential LAPS set-up by varying the cell number and/or glucose concentration. These model microorganisms were selected, as acid-forming, facultative anaerobe, easy-to-cultivate, and commonly used bacteria in laboratory and industrial applications. Both <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> and <hi rend="italic">C. glutamicum</hi> have been studied in separate LAPS experiments recently, however, the cellular metabolism of <hi rend="italic">L. brevis</hi> has not been analyzed by LAPS so far. In a first experimental step, the extracellular acidification of <hi rend="italic">L. brevis</hi> cells has been evaluated: calibration curves were established, which render the potential-change rate as a function of glucose concentration and cell number. Data were compared with results of already in literature discussed microorganisms such as <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> and <hi rend="italic">C. glutamicum</hi>. Finally, a novel parallelized measurement procedure is introduced, which allows sequentially and simultaneously performed LAPS measurements with all three types of bacteria. </p>
</text>
