<text id="autogum_academic_doc274" title="Sustainable Energy Systems Planning, Integration, and Management" shortTile="sustainable-energy" author="Amjad Anvari-Moghaddam, Behnam Mohammadi-ivatloo, Somayeh Asadi, Kim Guldstrand Larsen, Mohammad Shahidehpour" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/20/4451/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Sustainable Energy Systems Planning, Integration, and Management </head>
<p>
To cover the above-mentioned promising and dynamic areas of research and development, this special issue was launched to allow gathering of contributions in sustainable energy systems planning, integration, and management. In total, 31 papers were submitted to this special issue, out of them 14 were selected for publication which denotes an acceptance rate of 45%. The accepted articles in this special issue cover a variety of topics, ranging from design and planning of small to large-scale energy systems to operation and control of energy networks in different sectors namely electricity 1, heat 9, and transport 13. </p>

<p>Focusing on wave energy harvesting, the paper authored by Eugen Rusu assessed the most relevant patterns of the wave energy propagation in the western side of the Black Sea considering eight different simulating waves nearshore computational domains. Special attention was paid to the high, but not extreme, winter wave energy conditions. The cases considered were focused on the coastal waves generated by distant storms, which means the local wind has not very high values in the targeted areas. From the analysis of the results, it was first noticed that the general patterns regarding the spatial distribution of the wave energy in the basin of the Black Sea do not substantially change. This means that the western side of the sea still remains its most energetic part. Furthermore, a general enhancement of the wave energy is noticed, and it appears that this enhancement is relatively higher in the western side. Moreover, related studies showed that the coastal environment of the Black Sea, and especially its northern and western side, is fully appropriate for the implementation of offshore wind projects. </p>

<p>The work, done by Wang et al. illustrated the role of the multi-criteria decision making in determining the optimal location for solid waste-to-energy plant installation. To this end, the weight of criteria in the multi-criteria decision-making approach was determined using a hybrid fuzzy analysis as well as based on economic factors, technical requirements factors, environment factors, and social factors. In addition, the comprehensive model presented in that research can be used as a guideline to perform the placing mechanism in many countries to determine the optimal location for installing solid waste-to-energy plants.  </p>

<p>The works done by Gebresenbet et al. investigated smart logistics system (SLS) for the management of the pruning biomass supply chain. The major components of SLS including smart box, on-board control unit, information platform, and central control unit were studied. The author extended their work to study the role of smart logistics systems in increasing the efficiency of agricultural subscribers to use pruning biomass for generating renewable energy. The smart logistics systems in the presence of renewable sources was shown to have an undeniable role in decreasing logistics cost, increasing pruning marketing opportunity, and decreasing product loss. Four actors of the presented biomass supply chain include producer, traders, transporter, and consumers. In the proposed model, the initial chain, i.e., producers, were the farmers.  </p>

<p>In order to consider the uncertainty related to the wind speed as well as electrical power produced through wind farms, a new short-term wind speed forecasting method was introduced to achieve a more satisfying performance in forecasting data by Liu et al.. In this research, to overcome the shortcomings of some traditional models and enhance the forecasting ability, Ensemble Empirical Mode Decomposition model was developed. The authors also used six evaluation indexes, Willmott’s Index, Nash–Sutcliffe coefficient, Legates and McCabe Index, mean absolute error, square root of the average of the error square, and the average of absolute percentage error, to assess the effectiveness of the proposed method. </p>

<p>The work done by Peicong Luo elaborated on an efficient approach to dynamically adjust the datacenter load to balance the unstable renewable energy input into the grid. Their experimental results illustrated that the dynamic load management of multiple datacenters could help the smart grid to reduce losses and mitigate stability issues such as bus voltage variations and the overloading of transmission lines and accordingly save operational costs. As a complement to the proposed system, a forecasting method was also designed, based on the concept of neural networks, to predict renewable energy generation in advance so as to adjust the power of the datacenters as soon as possible and reduce the extra losses.  </p>

<p>Authors of studied the effects of the different meteorological variables on the power generation via photovoltaic systems. The investigated meteorological data in this paper included solar radiation, outdoor temperature, wind speed, and daylight time. To obtain a statistical representative model of the generated power by photovoltaic systems, the gradient descent optimization (GDO) was used. It was shown that the presented statistical method has the capability to minimize the introduced structure error using a linear Least Square Regression. Using the presented statistical structure, the estimation results’ error was about 7% compared to the real data.  </p>
</text>
