<text id="autogum_academic_doc731" title="An Assessment of the Environmental Sustainability and Circularity of Future Scenarios of the Copper Life Cycle in the U.S." shortTile="assessment-environmental" author="Miranda  R. Gorman, David  A. Dzombak" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5624/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Copper is among the most important metals in the U.S. due to its widespread use in the economy in large amounts in both commercial and residential sectors. The economic value of the copper metal is driven by its unique properties and wide range of applications. The growth in demand for copper globally, coupled with environmental impacts of extraction and processing, speak to the need for assessment of the life cycle of the material and its circularity, so that reserves may be prolonged and the embedded energy and environmental footprint of copper may be improved. Several research studies have attempted to assess the criticality of future demand for materials generally metals, and even specifically copper, but such assessments typically do not take into account the relevance of circularity and the circular economy, focusing mostly on the front-end of the material life cycle and not assessing end-of-life (EoL) and scrap flows which play a major role in meeting demand and material availability. Previous works differ from this study in that their time frame of forecasts tend to be shorter term, or the scope of the forecast did not include a complete material life cycle, but only a subset of the entire material life. For example, one study, which analyzed 75 years of data to make long-term projections of material stocks focused on the accumulation of all materials in only the use phase in both the U.S. and Japan. In contrast, the present study focused on the complete life cycle of a single material. Another study, by Schandl et al. focused on production and consumption of materials, but in larger regions, which may be problematic in that trends have been shown to vary dramatically even within a region depending on economic development. Existing studies specific to copper include a long-term forecast for the U.S. focused only on the front end of material life cycle, a long-term outlook for intensity of use and in-use stocks that is global in focus with general regional breakdowns, a global outlook of supply and demand, nonspecific to the U.S., as well as a forecast for global and U.S. copper, but only of production. There is a need for regionally high-resolution analyses of complete life cycles of specific materials. </p>

<p>This study investigated prospects for circularity in the future (up to 2030) by forecasting material flows including production, use, and recovery of copper in the U.S. An assessment of the environmental footprint associated with the projected primary and secondary copper production was also performed. Material demand patterns generally have been studied since the 1950s, and socio-economic theories have predicted “dematerialization” or “decoupling” of material consumption from economic growth and development for several decades, though the predicted absolute decrease in material consumption has not been observed at the scale of the national economy. However, starting around the year 2000, copper consumption, both absolute and per capita, and from both primary and secondary copper sources, in the U.S. has declined steadily following steady growth throughout the 20th century. In the development of material flow forecasts, therefore, inclusion of indicators that represent dematerialization or decoupling, which can be represented by material efficiency measurements, was done and potential implications for the copper circular economy into the future were considered. </p>
</text>
