<text id="autogum_academic_doc690" title="Environmental Life Cycle Assessment of Grid-Integrated Hybrid Renewable Energy Systems in Northern Nigeria" shortTile="environmental-life" author="Ismail Abubakar Jumare, Ramchandra Bhandari, Abdellatif Zerga" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5889/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Study Site Description</head>
<p>
Nigeria is a country blessed with abundant fossil fuel resources, specifically oil and natural gas. It is ranked as the leading country in terms of the natural gas reserve, and is second after Libya in oil reserve in the African continent. It must be stated also that abundant renewable energy resources exist in the country namely biomass, wind, solar, and hydro although being site specific. It is unfortunate that the level of utilization of the renewable sources to final energy generation is chronically poor. Instead, overdependence on fossil resources for final energy services particularly electricity as our central focus has been a habitual thing despite their depleting nature and some environmental consequences. In this context as a strong view, integrating the renewable energy resources is very crucial in line with the low carbon development transition target, and most significantly for the environmental concerns. This study focusing on the northern part of the country is driven by the existence of high potential for climate-data related renewable energy resources namely the solar irradiation and wind speed. The other resource of interest namely the biomass in the form of waste is considered to be virtually everywhere and in abundance in the whole country. It is considered a resource in disguise, and needs to be utilized in an efficient manner for environmental benefits. Moving specifically to the study location in the northern part of the country, Zaria, it is a municipal area with Coordinate 11.085° N and 7.72° E. The site is situated on a plateau at an elevation of 670 m above sea level, and has a total area of 563 km2 with a population of about 975,200 during 2015. The site’s climate is tropical wet and dry caused by movement of the inter-tropical discontinuity under two air mass influences, that is tropical continental and tropical maritime. To specify further the tropical wet and dry climate nature, the wet season (i.e., summer) lasts from April to October whereas, the dry season (i.e., winter) lasts from November to March. <figure>Figure 1</figure> and <figure>Figure 2</figure> give the climate-based data, that is solar and wind resources. This is accompanied by the biomass broad classification in <figure>Figure 3</figure>, as well as the specific biogas resources, that is the animal wastes quantification considered for the biogas fuel production applicable to power generations in Table 2. These are fundamental in modelling the power generations useful for analyzing the environmental life cycle impact. </p>
</text>
