<text id="autogum_academic_doc205" title="Peptide–Gold Nanoparticle Conjugates as Artificial Carbonic Anhydrase Mimics" shortTile="peptidegold-nanoparticle" author="Dorian  J. Mikolajczak, Beate Koksch" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4344/9/11/903/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The development of nanostructures that mimic the remarkable functions and catalytic properties of natural enzymes, i.e., to create nanozymes, has been an exciting topic in the field of nanotechnology for the last two decades. Among several approaches used to create nanozymes, the self-assembly of thiolated ligands onto the surface of gold nanoparticles (Au-NPs) to obtain monolayer-protected gold clusters (Au-MPCs) has emerged as a powerful strategy. In particular, the conjugation of peptides on to the surface of gold nanoparticles to yield peptide–gold nanoparticle conjugates (Pep-Au-NPs) expanded the possibilities for the design of artificial enzymes. Peptides are available at low cost by solid-phase peptide synthesis, and their modular design paired with the available repertoire of natural and non-natural amino acids allows for facile diversification of functional groups, and thus the resulting catalytic activities and substrate specificities of the peptide shell. The conjunction of peptides and Au-NPs leads to dense peptide monolayers in which new hydrogen bond and/or charge interactions between individual peptides are established. This enables known enzyme-like effects, such as the perturbation of pKa values of functional groups and cooperativity in substrate binding, and can even lead to new catalytic mechanisms. Altogether, these effects can greatly improve the catalytic performance of a conjugated versus an unconjugated peptide.  </p>

<p>To date, the design and application of Pep-Au-NPs have been limited to organic esterase chemistry, in which catalysis is mediated by a His-imidazole. Considering the fact that zinc metalloenzymes perform numerous other types of reactions in nature, including phosphodiester and amide hydrolysis as well as the (de)hydrogenation of alcohols, it is of great interest to reconstitute such transformations in vitro by developing appropriate robust synthetic systems. For example, carbonic anhydrase (CA) is a naturally occurring zinc metalloenzyme that efficiently and reversibly catalyzes the hydration of CO2 into hydrogen carbonate (HCO3−). Its high activity originates from its zinc (Zn(II)) containing active site, in which three histidine imidazole moieties coordinate a Zn(II)-ion leaving a vacant space for the association of a water molecule. Zn(II) lowers the pKa of the bound water and forms a highly nucleophilic hydroxide species which reacts with CO2, bound in close proximity, to yield HCO3−. CA isoforms have been extensively studied due to their clinical importance as drug targets and artificial lungs, and their great potential as catalysts in carbon capture systems. Especially the latter application drove our interest, as the emission of CO2 and the associated anthropogenic climate change steadily proceeds and new approaches for the absorption of CO2 become increasingly urgent. In order to further increase our understanding of the design of Pep-Au-NPs, and to present a new approach for the absorption CO2, we herein describe the design and synthesis of the first Pep-Au-NP metalloenzyme mimicking carbonic anhydrase activity. </p>
</text>
