<text id="autogum_academic_doc556" title="New “Full-Bridge Buck Inverter–DC Motor” System: Steady-State and Dynamic Analysis and Experimental Validation" shortTile="new-fullbridge-buck" author="Eduardo Hernández-Márquez, Carlos  Alejandro Avila-Rea, José  Rafael García-Sánchez, Ramón Silva-Ortigoza, Magdalena Marciano-Melchor, Mariana Marcelino-Aranda, Alfredo Roldán-Caballero, Celso Márquez-Sánchez" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-9292/8/11/1216/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Electronic power converters as drivers for DC motors have been recently studied. According to the literature on power converters, the Buck, the Boost, and the Buck-Boost topologies are the most used. The Buck topology received the most attention. This is, in part, due to the fact that the mathematical model of the Buck topology is linear and, compared with the Boost and the Buck-Boost topologies, the Buck topology does not have a nonminimum phase output variable. As the present paper focuses on the Buck power converter as a driver for a DC motor, a review of state-of-the-art of this topic is presented below. </p>

<head> 1.1. Related Work</head>
<p>
The literature reviewed has been divided into two approaches: (1) DC/DC Buck converter–DC motor systems and (2) DC/DC Buck converter–inverter–DC motor systems. </p>

<p>Regarding a DC motor when it is fed by a DC/DC Buck converter, the most relevant literature is the following; Lyshevski, in, designed a nonlinear PI control that regulates the velocity of the motor shaft. Ahmad et al., in, presented a performance assessment of the PI, fuzzy PI, and LQR controls for the tracking problem. Bingöl and Paçaci reported, in, a virtual laboratory based on neural networks to control the angular velocity. Sira-Ramírez and Oliver-Salazar used the concepts of active disturbance rejection and differential flatness to design a tracking control for two configurations of a DC/DC Buck converter connected to a DC motor. In, Silva-Ortigoza et al. introduced a two-stage sensorless tracking control based on flatness, whose implementation was executed via a –-modulator. In, Hoyos et al. designed a robust adaptive quasi-sliding mode regulation control, which is generated through the zero average dynamics (ZAD) technique and a fixed point inducting control (FPIC). Later, Silva-Ortigoza et al. proposed a robust hierarchical control approach based on differential flatness in. Wei et al. in reported a robust adaptive controller based on dynamic surface and sliding mode. A two-stage controller based on sliding mode plus PI control and flatness was reported by Silva-Ortigoza et al. in. Hernández-Guzmán et al., in, proposed a simple control scheme by using sliding mode, to regulate the converter current, and three PI controls. These latter to regulate the converter voltage, the motor current, and the angular velocity. Moreover, via sensorless load torque estimation schemes, a passive tracking control based on the exact tracking error dynamics was proposed by Kumar and Thilagar in. Khubalkar et al., in, presented the design and realization of standalone digital fractional order PID control for the Buck converter–DC motor system, where the dynamic particle swarm optimization (dPSO) technique is used to tune the gains and the order of the control. By using the concept of differential flatness and a derivative-free nonlinear Kalman filter, Rigatos et al., in, designed a control to solve the trajectory tracking problem. Another solution was proposed by Nizami et al. in, where a neuroadaptive backstepping tracking control was developed for the system. The dynamic analysis of the Buck converter that uses the combined ZAD-FPIC technique to control the speed of the DC motor, when different reference values are considered, was developed in by Hoyos et al. Khubalkar et al., in, presented for the DC/DC Buck converter driving a DC motor a digital implementation of a fractional order PID control, whose parameters are tuned through the improved inertia weight dPSO technique. A flatness-based tracking control implemented in successive loops was presented by Rigatos et al. in. More recently, the speed regulation problem was addressed by Yang et al. in, by using a robust predictive control via a discrete-time reduced-order GPI observer. Additionally, other important contributions related to the connection of a DC/DC Buck converter and a DC motor have been reported in. </p>

<p>On the other hand, regarding a DC motor when it is fed by a DC/DC Buck converter–inverter, the literature is as follows. In, Silva-Ortigoza et al. developed and experimentally validated a mathematical model associated with the DC/DC Buck converter–inverter–DC motor system. Silva-Ortigoza et al. reported, in, a passive tracking control based on the exact tracking error dynamics. Robust tracking controls were proposed by Hernández-Márquez et al. in. </p>
</text>
