<text id="autogum_academic_doc439" title="Chemical Composition, In Vitro Digestibility and Rumen Fermentation Kinetics of Agro-Industrial By-Products" shortTile="chemical-composition" author="Jairo García-Rodríguez, María  José Ranilla, James France, Héctor Alaiz-Moretón, María  Dolores Carro, Secundino López" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2615/9/11/861/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The world’s human population is in constant growth, and estimated to reach 8.6 billion people by 2030 and 9.8 billion by 2050. Consequently, there is a necessity to increase food production, from both plant and animal origins. Fresh vegetables and fruit production in Spain reached nearly 38,600 hundred tons in 2017 (including olives and grapes), so that Spain is the largest vegetable and fruit producing country in the European Union (EU). Throughout the plant-based food supply chain there is a loss or waste of material generated during the harvesting or processing of food for human consumption. These wastes are known as by-products and their disposal may represent an environmental problem, as they are perishable and potential pollutants. These by-products can have different applications or uses. One valuable possibility in the field of animal nutrition is the recycling of these materials as alternative feedstuffs, in particular for herbivores. Ruminants can digest plant fibre to produce high quality products available to humans such as milk or meat. The potential use of these by-products as ingredients in ruminant diets could reduce the environmental impact of the disposal of these residues, and would favour of the development of a circular economy by recycling the biomass derived from crop production. Also, the use of these by-products as ruminant feedstuffs could reduce competition between ruminants and humans (or other non-ruminant farm animals) for food or land, contributing to moderate the demand for feed resources (cereals or forage) by these species. </p>

<p>The use of agro-industrial by-products as animal feeds has been a matter of interest for the last few decades. However, there is a high variability in their chemical composition associated with multiple factors, such as their botanical or geographical origin, treatments during harvesting and processing, or the climatic conditions during their cultivation, among others. This variability offers a wide range of potential ingredients that could partially or totally substitute for different feeds in ruminant rations. By-products with high energy content could replace the grains in the ration, whereas those with high fibre content might replace the roughage. Also, some by-products rich in nitrogen could be an alternative to protein supplements. Therefore, there is a need for information on the chemical composition and nutritive value of materials and by-products derived from agriculture, horticulture and fruit farming to expand our knowledge on their potential as feedstuffs before making recommendations about their inclusion in ruminant diets. </p>

<p>Chemical composition, in vitro digestibility and in vitro rumen fermentation kinetics are useful tools for feed evaluation. Compared to in vivo experiments, in vitro methods are cheaper and allow for a more precise control of experimental conditions and for the screening of a large number of materials in a relatively short time. The large variability among by-products in chemical composition and nutritive value for ruminants represents an important issue, making it difficult to establish general recommendations on their use as animal feed. This study was designed to determine the chemical composition, in vitro digestibility and fermentation kinetics of a wide range of agro-industrial by-products as an indicator of their potential use as feedstuffs for ruminants. </p>
</text>
