<text id=autogum_academic_doc0> title=A Landscape Connectivity Approach for Determining Minimum Ecological Lake Level: Implications for Lake Restoration subject=bio-life author=Dan Liu, Xuan Wang, Yun-long Zhang, Sheng-jun Yan, Bao-shan Cui, Zhi-feng Yang date=2019-10-26 publisher=Multidisciplinary Digital Publishing Institute sourceURL=https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4441/11/11/2237/htm>
<head> 6. Conclusions</head>
<p>
By taking the water landscape connectivity as a critical ecosystem index, this research proposed a landscape connectivity approach to determine the minimum ecological lake level through identifying the breakpoint of the lake level-connectivity (<hi rend="italic">H</hi>-<hi rend="italic">C</hi>) curve. It was the first to determine the minimum ecological lake level from the perspective of landscape connectivity. Compared with traditional lake morphology approaches, which focused on overall habitat protection, the landscape connectivity approach focused more on the spatial distribution of water resources with respect to internal transfer efficiencies of materials, energy and organisms within lake ecosystems. This study also demonstrated that lake levels that met the requirement of minimum habitat area may not satisfy the minimum connectivity requirement of lake ecosystems. In this case, raising the water level to meet the minimum connectivity requirement only by water diversion would lead to a likely waste of both water and financial resources. Alternatively, landscape connectivity can be enhanced through local reconstruction of landscape patterns. Thus, better connectivity can be achieved at lower water levels. This discovery can provide a new approach for lake restoration through landscape connectivity management at relatively low economic costs. </p>
 
<p>This study developed a landscape connectivity approach based on the relationship between water level and lake connectivity from the perspective of landscape ecology, which can be further improved in future studies. For example, landscape connectivity is limited to reflect the potential connectivity of flows and nutrients, and some functional connectivity indices representing actual process of connectivity should be developed to replace landscape connectivity. Through further discussion of the relationship between lake level and functional connectivity, a more realistic minimum ecological lake level may be obtained. In addition, quantitative spatial differences in connectivity should be investigated to identify areas of weak connectivity, which usually are most sensitive to changes in lake level, thus providing more specific suggestions for managers.
 </p>

</text>