<text id="autogum_academic_doc086" title="A Conceptual Framework for Urban Commoning in Shared Residential Landscapes in the UK" shortTile="conceptual-framework" author="Aimee Felstead, Kevin Thwaites, James Simpson" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6119/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Background and Context: Shared Residential Landscapes and Urban Commons</head>
<p>
In 2017, the UK Government set out plans to build 300,000 new homes a year in England in an attempt to tackle ongoing issues around the affordability and availability of housing (s.5.3). The concern from a social sustainability perspective is how, in the long-term, these new homes will contribute to the everyday social lives of the communities that will live there. In particular, how the spaces between buildings can provide an opportunity for social interaction and engagement.  </p>

<p>Shared residential landscapes are socially valuable spaces that form the backdrop to everyday routines, social encounters and community identity. The characteristics and qualities of these spaces, shaped by their design and maintenance over time, have a significant influence on the social aspects of a neighbourhood. Aligned with this is the understanding that people’s direct interaction with the surrounding environment can provide opportunities for expressing identity, receiving recognition from others and developing a greater sense of belonging. Resident control over shared outdoor spaces also allows potential for residents to shape their common surroundings in a way that is beneficial to them, providing agency over the way they live and increasing opportunities for social interaction.  </p>

<p>A way of encouraging greater potential for communities to have a decision-making role within the make-up of their residential environment can be seen within the community-led housing sector. Even though profession-led top-down approaches remain the predominant model for new housing development in the UK, community-led housing is growing in popularity, something that has been recognised in the UK government’s 2018 announcement of the £163 million Community Housing Fund. Community-led housing challenges some of the limitations within contemporary housing development by generating a new bottom-up approach that shifts residents’ roles from end users to engaged participants in aspects including anything from site acquisition to management.  </p>

<p>Cohousing is a particular model of community-led housing characterised by its combination of individual private dwellings with shared facilities and resident-led decision making during the design, development and occupation phases. Examples of cohousing in the UK are located in both urban and rural contexts and built with a range of densities and layouts. Although cohousing developments are spatially diverse, they are based upon similar design and organisational principles that promote collaborative ways of living. Subsequently, residents have high levels of involvement in the maintenance and management of communal spaces, organisation of social activities and the decision and rule-making process of the community. A review of recent research suggests multiple benefits associated with cohousing, including decreased energy use, affordable living costs, enhanced connection to place, improved self-awareness, strong community relations, mutual support and knowledge sharing. Cohousing, therefore, provides a useful illustration for the potential of collective participation in residential placemaking. </p>

<p>Notable within the increasingly popular community-led housing sector, and resident participation in shared residential landscapes more generally, is the emerging concept of urban commons. While the evolving meaning of the term commons has created a usefully flexible concept applicable to various resources in different contexts and at multiple scales, it remains conceptually challenging in its vagueness. In applying the commons concept within the urban context, the theoretical implications are yet to be fully explored. Furthermore, a polarisation between top-down and bottom-up approaches to urban development in the UK presents additional challenges of integrating commons as a bottom-up approach within the top-down guidelines and practices of urban professions. Therefore, even though the broadening of the commons concept to include shared urban resources has stimulated a reconceptualisation of collective governance in cities generally, challenges remain surrounding clarity in its definition, understanding the spatial implications, and the role of urban professionals in its implementation. These limitations in understanding the urban commons create challenges to appropriately applying the theory in urban residential contexts. </p>

<p>To address these challenges, this paper aims to develop a new conceptual framework for urban commons that strengthens the connection between the emerging concept and spatial theory. This is realised within the following objectives and methodological steps for a literature review of existing commons theory, urban spatial theory and UK cohousing literature (as illustrated in <figure>Figure 1</figure>). Firstly, (1) a review of recognised commons literature is undertaken to highlight the defining components of commons in both traditional and urban settings. Secondly, the contemporary urban commons literature is reviewed to identify the implications arising from the application of the commons idea within urban settings. Thirdly, (3) relevant concepts within urban spatial theory are drawn upon to explain and underpin the implications identified within the urban commons literature. Fourthly, (4) a preliminary conceptual framework is outlined to draw together the key concepts that connect urban commons with urban spatial theory. Finally, (5) the concepts are pre-emptively illustrated within the context of residential landscapes using examples from recent cohousing research in the UK. </p>
</text>
