<text id="autogum_academic_doc098" title="Identification of Schedule-Performance Indicators and Delay-Recovery Strategies for Low-Cost Housing Projects" shortTile="identification-scheduleperformance" author="Elnaz Safapour, Sharareh Kermanshachi, Bahaa Alfasi, Reza Akhavian" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/6005/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Literature Review</head><head> 2.1. Housing</head>
<p>
The United Nations Human Settlements Programme or UN-Habitat stated that housing is a key element in integrated physical and economic development, environmental sustainability, and the creation of wealth; and it impacts the health, social behavior, and general welfare of communities. Housing reflects the cultural, social, and economic values of a society, or in brief, is valuable evidence of civilization in every country. The term housing does not merely refer to the dwelling, but also includes the physical and social components that make up the housing system. </p>

<head> 2.2. Low-Cost Housing (LCH)</head>
<p>
Oxley defined low-income housing as a vehicle for helping households who are unable to support themselves. Similarly, UN-Habitat defined low-income housing as provided housing that meets the needs of low-income individuals/families who are unable to compete in the marketplace for decent housing options.  </p>

<p>The term “low-cost housing” has various meanings in different societies. In underdeveloped countries, low-income individuals/families in urban or rural areas are often unable to access the housing market through mortgage institutions and consequently need low-cost housing. In developed countries, such as the USA, low-income housing is usually affordable if the household can purchase or rent the housing unit for a small portion of its income. Mortgage lenders consider this standard as one of the main criteria in qualifying buyers for mortgage loans.  </p>

<head> 2.3. Schedule Performance </head>
<p>
Failure to finish construction project services on time is a common issue and leads to schedule delays, cost overruns, and in some cases, low-quality products. O’Brien defined schedule delays as the completion of a project beyond the agreed-upon contract deadline and/or beyond the date that the parties agreed on for the delivery of a project. In 2008, described schedule delays as acts or events that extend the time to perform the task beyond the agreed-on contract deadline.  </p>

<p>Project success with respect to a particular project participant was defined by as the degree of achievements of project objectives and expectations of that participant. They also mentioned that schedule, cost, and quality are considered the three factors that most significantly impact a construction projects’ success. In 2009, stated that project success is strongly connected to the project parties’ satisfaction, minimal disputes/conflicts/legal proceedings, safety, and environmental impacts of the project. Additionally, schedule delays commonly have negative impacts on primary and secondary stakeholders such as clients, contractors, and consultants. </p>

<head> 2.4. Schedule-Performance Indicators in Low-Cost Housing (LCH)</head>
<p>
An attribute of LCH projects is their tight schedule and congested critical path. Any delay in the project schedule would result in cost overrun which defeats the purpose of finishing the project with a low cost. As the main purposes of providing LCH is to support low-income individuals/families, delivering the projects on time is critical to preventing cost overruns. Therefore, it is important to identify the critical root causes of delays in these projects. In 2014, conducted a study and identified the main causes of schedule delays in housing projects as ineffective execution policies, unqualified team members, and poor leadership of the project management team. </p>

<p>In 2014, performed a study that found the unavailability of housing loans, high lending costs or interest, short loan repayment terms, and low-quality materials as the most significant delay indicators in housing projects. In 2010, concluded that unsuitable locations of housing projects was one of the main factors of low schedule performance in these projects. In 2008, identified the lack of governmental support as one of the key indicators of schedule delays. </p>
</text>
