<text id="autogum_academic_doc682" title="Mathematical Investigation on the Sustainability of UAV Logistics" shortTile="mathematical-investigation" author="Joonyup Eun, Byung  Duk Song, Sangbok Lee, Dae-Eun Lim" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5932/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Concluding Remarks</head>
<p>
In this study, we investigated how environmentally friendly UAV delivery service is compared to GV delivery service. To perform such a comparison, we first obtained an optimal delivery schedule that minimized the total travelling distance for each service. Since there are different levels of fuel and loadable capacity restrictions for the UAV and GV delivery services, delivery routes for the two services are also different. UAVs need more fuel replenishments and have a lower weight capacity, which causes more hops than GVs. We present a new mathematical model to obtain an optimal delivery schedule for each delivery service under such restrictions. Based on the optimal delivery information obtained, CO2 emissions of the UAV-alone and GV-alone delivery systems are computed. The case study found that the GV-alone delivery generated at least 683 times more CO2 than the UAV-alone delivery in all ranges of the GV speeds tested. </p>

<p>We stress the implications and limitations of this study. The presentations in this study answer the following question: How many UAVs are environmentally friendly if the UAV delivery system is implemented in the logistics industry. Since UAVs, compared to GVs, have different limitations and restrictions for delivering goods, the question must be addressed from the understanding of different characteristics of UAVs and GVs, and their resultant delivery schemes. The two-phase methodology proposed in this study is needed to provide different routes for the two different types of vehicles and to analyze their sustainability in terms of the CO2 emissions of their travels. We believe the methodology and the results of this study provide a guideline to further investigate the true sustainability of UAV logistic services and facilitate the use of UAVs for delivery services. There are, however, two limitations in this study. First, we focused on CO2 emissions only during the vehicle’s travel. It is easy to think that manufacturing and disposal processes of vehicles (including batteries) also cause greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions. Second, this study postulates a specific scenario that uses stationary depots and one type of vehicle (UAVs or GVs) in each delivery system. It is possible and natural to mix the two types of vehicles in one delivery system. Those limitations of this study are expected to be overcome by future research. </p>

<p>We contemplate future research based on the limitations of this research. First, it may be possible to additionally consider greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions during manufacturing and disposal processes of UAVs and GVs. Stolaroff et al. presented the life cycle GHG emissions represented by CO2-equivelent per package delivered by UAVs and GVs. They consider CO2-equivelent emissions during all stages of a vehicle’s life cycle, but do not consider the distance a vehicle should travel for each service. Since the battery life of a UAV is much shorter than the engine life of a GV and the travelling distance of a UAV is longer than that of a GV, the dominance of UAV over GV CO2 emissions can be possibly weakened under the lifecycle assessment (LCA). Second, this sustainability analysis of the UAV delivery service can be applied to various types of logistic services. With respect to vehicle types, there is a UAV-GV combined logistic service. With respect to depot mobility, there exist movable depots that are different from stationary depots postulated in this study. Since various types of logistic systems with UAVs are being developed and tested, we believe that the sustainability analysis of those systems is also required. Even though there is a lack of the sustainable VRP literature so far, this paper may serve as a guideline that triggers research activities on the topic.
 </p>
</text>
