<text id="autogum_academic_doc035" title="FDA- and EMA-Approved Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitors in Advanced EGFR-Mutated Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer: Safety, Tolerability, Plasma Concentration Monitoring, and Management" shortTile="fda-emaapproved-tyrosine" author="Isabelle Solassol, Frédéric Pinguet, Xavier Quantin" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2218-273X/9/11/668/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions and Perspectives </head>
<p>
EGFR-TKIs are currently the standard first-line treatment of patients with advanced NSCLC with activating <hi rend="italic">EGFR</hi> mutations. These targeted therapies are usually well tolerated comparative to conventional chemotherapy. The self-oral administration of the drug positively contributes to improving patient compliance and reducing the use of hospital resources. However, this non-invasive route of administration is also associated with unpredictable bioavailability, increased risk of drug interactions, and concerns about patient safety, surveillance, and follow-up. Chronic EGFR-TKIs underdosage may favor the selection of resistant clones and thus disease progression, and overdosage may increase the risk of dose-related side effects. Self-administration also means that the severity of side effects can be considerably impacted by patient behavior (e.g., dietary habits, self-medicating, smoker status). To date, EGFR-TKIs can be administered in advanced NSCLC for a long period of time, usually until the disease progresses or unacceptable toxicity occurs. As early intervention with supportive care strategies can minimize the intensity of adverse reactions or allow for appropriate dose adjustments without the need to discontinue treatment, acute toxicity follow-up and side effect management is of major interest. </p>

<p>Therefore, medical oncologists should not only understand the AEs associated with these drugs, but also develop the necessary skills to detect and treat them to reduce morbidity and mortality as well as premature discontinuation of treatment. Patient education on these strategies is also of major importance and can improve patient tolerance, quality of life, and overall treatment outcome by initiating supportive care soon after symptoms occur. Within this guidance and preventive strategy, the pharmacist can play a major role. Good knowledge of disease monitoring, response milestones, and the risks versus benefits of the treatment options allows pharmacists to better advise patients or counsel patients more effectively. Nurses and prescribers are qualified to monitor toxicity risks as closely as possible. Unfortunately, they do not necessarily do so at regular intervals. Patients can connect with pharmacists who can provide them additional information or complementary recommendations on AEs without the need for patients to rapidly contact prescribers. When more complex or serious AEs appear, pharmacists who work closely with nurses and prescribers can propose the most appropriate therapeutic strategies. Finally, medical oncologists able to understand AEs along with patient education and collaboration between different medical professional groups for therapeutic drug monitoring systems are needed, but further research on the aforementioned methods of relief for continued TKI use should be also performed in the future. </p>

<p>The importance of proactive patient follow-up must be emphasized rather than relying on self-reporting between clinical visits. A randomized trial showed that patients receiving chemotherapy for advanced cancer, web-based symptom reporting with automated clinician e-mail alerts resulted in better health-related quality of life, fewer emergency room visits, fewer hospitalizations, and superior quality-adjusted survival. </p>

<p>Recently, Cheema et al. assessed the impact of an interprofessional, proactive follow-up algorithm on the incidence of dose interruptions, reductions, and the severity of AEs in patients on afatinib. The authors reported that over half of first AEs and one third of all grade 1-2 and grade ≥3 AEs were detected through proactive follow-up. This multi-disciplinary AE algorithm resulted in a low rate of costly emergency room or urgent clinic visits and a reduced incidence of severe drug-related AEs and discontinuation therapy. </p>

<p>In conclusion, when closely monitoring patients, the ability of clinicians to make rapid therapeutic decisions in the event of medical complications is critical in the diagnosis and management of TKI-related side effects. This is even more decisive in the event of serious or even life-threatening complications. However, good clinician–patient communication, drug patient education, early detection and management of drug side effects, and monitoring of disease response with plasma concentration quantification can also improve patient outcomes. Close cooperation between oncologists, internists, pharmaceutics, and nurses should become the gold standard in the comprehensive clinical care of advanced NSCLC patients receiving TKIs.
 </p>
</text>
