<text id="autogum_academic_doc588" title="A Review of Force Myography Research and Development" shortTile="review-force-myography" author="Zhen  Gang Xiao, Carlo Menon" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/20/4557/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Information about the position or movement of a user’s limb can be used to monitor physical activities or for human-machine-interface applications. Such information can be extracted externally from the user using camera technology or through a wearable approach using sensors worn by the user. Compared to the camera approach, the wearable approach is not constrained to a fixed environment and it offers greater freedom to the user in terms of mobility. Among many wearable approaches, the one that relies on force myography (FMG) has gained ever-increasing traction among researchers over the past 20 years. </p>

<p>FMG is a non-invasive technique to decipher the position or movement of a limb based on changes in the stiffness of the corresponding musculotendinous complex (MC) against a default state. The changes in stiffness of the targeted MC is often monitored by placing a force transducer on the targeted location with a preload force. This preload force corresponds to the default state, which is usually chosen as a state where the limb is in a relaxed position. However, depending on the application, the default state can be arbitrarily chosen. The basic principle of FMG is similar to the palpation technique that a clinician uses for identifying different muscles of a limb. For example, while we are squeezing one of our hands, we can feel some of the extensor muscles become stiffer by placing fingers on the bulk of the forearm. For FMG, we replace the fingers with force transducers. The stiffer the MC is, the higher the pressure the transducers will detect. </p>

<p>The term force myography, a.k.a. FMG, was first introduced in the work of Wininger et al., but such a technique has been exploited as early as the 1950s. Specifically, a device named “French Electric Hand” could be controlled by a pneumatic force transducer located within a transcranial amputee socket. A user could control the opening or closing of the gripper by contracting the residual limb muscles against the transducer. However, such an approach did not gain momentum due to the limitation of the sensor and computer technologies in those days. </p>

<p>Fast forward to the late 1990s, researchers once again reignited the interest of using such an approach for controlling prosthetic devices. For example, Abboudi et al. developed a soft socket that was embedded with three pneumatic pressure transducers for controlling a multi-finger prosthesis. The input signals from the transducers were mapped to different commands based on signal energy. Instead of just opening and closing a gripper, this multi-sensor setup demonstrated the feasibility of controlling complex hand prosthesis through the FMG approach. Subsequently, the same research group was able to increase the number of transducers within the socket to allow more sophisticated control of the prosthetic devices. </p>

<p>Other than using pneumatic pressure sensors to detect the changes in muscle stiffness, researchers also proposed to use the resistive polymer thick film (RPTF) sensor as the main sensing element due to its miniature size and high affordability. For instance, in 2006, Lukowicz’s group demonstrated the potential use of the RPTF sensors to identify different limb movements, including both upper and lower limb actions. The same group also demonstrated the potential use of such a technique to identify different activities of daily living. Many of the early works between the late 1990s and 2000s focused on exploring the potential use of FMG by examining the signal morphology in a few limited scenarios. These works opened many untapped research opportunities in the fields of human-machine-interface and activity monitoring applications. </p>

<p>Starting in the late 2010s, there was an increasing interest in the development of FMG technology, as shown by the number of academic publications depicted in <figure>Figure 1</figure>. A total of 76 papers were found between 1999 and mid-2019 (the list shown in Table A1 of the Appendix A). </p>
</text>
