<text id="autogum_academic_doc128" title="Sustainable Cities: A Reflection on Potentialities and Limits based on Existing Eco-Districts in Europe" shortTile="sustainable-cities" author="Marta Bottero, Caterina Caprioli, Giancarlo Cotella, Marco Santangelo" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5794/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head><head> 4.1. Reflections on Eco-District Models</head>
<p>
Through the analysis of the characteristics of each project, it was possible to develop some empirical insights in relation to sustainability in neighborhoods and its related models. In this sense, for each one of the considered sustainability dimensions, several sub-dimensions have been defined that better specify the contents. It has to be noted that the sub-dimensions were defined based on an inductive method in order to classify and to cluster all the specific actions of each case study in unique identifications. The results of this analysis are represented in radar graphs, where the axes are the sub-dimensions identified, whereas the data points show the number of cases presenting specific actions and interventions under the considered categories (<figure>Figure 2</figure>, <figure>Figure 3</figure>, <figure>Figure 4</figure> and <figure>Figure 5</figure>). A specific code was assigned in order to ease the connection among those categories and the single actions adopted by the case studies reported in Table 2. These values, rather than representing a definitive number, make it possible to understand which characteristics were considered more relevant in developing an eco-district (or sustainable neighborhood). </p>

<p>In the selected experiences, energy aspects have certainly been identified as a priority in developing an eco-district. A transition from non-renewable energies to low environmental impact technologies, such as PV systems, heat pumps or CHP, was widely occurring. It is not surprising that this dimension contains the largest number of indicators (<figure>Figure 2</figure>). An interesting aspect is that the retrofit was not widely proliferated, precisely because many of these projects were in areas with different land-use or that had been under-developed in the past. Instead, the adoption of high-performance insulation systems and the development of the first attempts to develop passive houses and close to zero energy buildings were both more common. Apart from that, strong importance is given to water and waste. Different actions and technologies are applied to their collection, separation and re-use, showing the strong efforts to limit their environmental impact and waste. The actions undertaken not only have a direct effect on the districts, such as the reduction of flooding risks, but also have positive implications at a wider scale, such as the reduction of water consumption and the increasing of municipal waste management. However, less attention has been given to natural resources such as ecosystem and biodiversity protection, due to the stronger prominence in the development of such eco-districts of technological and energetic aspects for acquiring environmental benefits. </p>

<p>If actions related to the energy dimension go in the same direction for all case studies analyzed, something different happens for the socio-economic aspects (<figure>Figure 3</figure>). Some projects, in fact, adopt what is described as a bottom-up approach, others (the majority) a top-down approach. Some case studies were mainly financed by private actors, others through public investment, EU subsidies and mega-events. In general, as already stressed elsewhere, the success of the projects, both bottom-up and top-down, seems to come from a widespread communication, participation and engagement of the population, through the creation of meeting places and the diffusion of community activities, as well as the creation of private–public partnerships and strong stakeholder coordination and engagement (see SE13 in <figure>Figure 2</figure>). Successful projects have also resulted in the creation of local jobs. Instead, the promotion of social mixing, also with previous inhabitants, has still not been widely considered, generating gentrification phenomena. The increasing values of new housing (and of the perceived quality of life) attract inhabitants with higher income levels and cause the displacement of lower-income inhabitants. </p>

<p>As for the energy aspects, also for the mobility ones (<figure>Figure 4</figure>), actions were similar among the different projects. The aim is to discourage the use of private cars through the implementation of public mobility services (in particular new tramway routes). In addition, the disincentive of private cars is encouraged by the proliferation of car-free areas and by a reduction in the number of parking lots, often isolated in the district borders. In many cases, these actions are combined with an increase of streets reserved for pedestrians and bikers. Cars are promoted only when electric or combined with carpooling and car-sharing initiatives. </p>

<p>From the urban design point of view (<figure>Figure 5</figure>), the actions that are most frequently adopted are those regarding the development of different building designs and mixed uses, allowing the combination of different services and facilities (schools, nursery schools, youth facilities, civic meeting places, market places as well as leisure and play areas) with the residential functions. High-density areas are also encouraged, in order to reduce soil consumption and to increase the number of green spaces. Apart from this, the success of these projects also results from the application of different tools to accompany the developments and to gather specific objectives and requirements. The use of specifically selected tools, the definition of plans and the creation of multidisciplinary technical group allow for efficient process management, and to guarantee high-quality standards. All these aspects are considered in <figure>Figure 5</figure> as the project management indicator. </p>
</text>
