<text id="autogum_academic_doc047" title="Proteomic Investigation of S-Nitrosylated Proteins During NO-Induced Adventitious Rooting of Cucumber" shortTile="proteomic-investigation" author="Lijuan Niu, Jihua Yu, Weibiao Liao, Jianming Xie, Jian Yu, Jian Lv, Xuemei Xiao, Linli Hu, Yue Wu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5363/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Free radical nitric oxide (NO) is generated via non-enzymatic and enzymatic pathways in plants. As a multifunctional physiological regulator, NO has been shown to be involved in every aspect of plant growth and every developmental process in plants. Furthermore, an increasing body of evidence has indicated that NO could play an essential role in response to various abiotic stresses. </p>

<p>Previous studies suggested that NO could exert its effects depending on the cyclic guanosine monophosphate (cGMP) signaling pathway. For example, NO could promote the adventitious rooting of marigold through the cGMP-dependent pathway. </p>

<p>Additionally, the emerging picture is that NO also could operate biological functions through protein <hi rend="italic">S</hi>-nitrosylation which is a NO-dependent posttranslational modification (PTM). It has been shown that NO groups could be covalently bound to cysteine (Cys) residues of target proteins, resulting in the formation of <hi rend="italic">S</hi>-nitrosothiols during <hi rend="italic">S</hi>-nitrosylation. At present, increasing evidence demonstrates that <hi rend="italic">S</hi>-nitrosylation might be involved in processes for regulating the growth, development, and stress responses in plants. </p>

<p>In general, proteomics deals with the large-scale determination of gene and cellular function directly at the protein level. Recently, global protein <hi rend="italic">S</hi>-nitrosylation has been identified using the proteomic approach. According to Hu et al., more than 2200 <hi rend="italic">S</hi>-nitrosylated proteins have been identified in mammals and plants. In the present work, several <hi rend="italic">S</hi>-nitrosylated proteins have been identified using proteomic analyses in different plants. For example, Lindermayr et al. identified proteins, which, when treated with NO, were involved in various pathways such as cytoskeleton organization, metabolic processes, redox homeostasis, as well as cellular signaling transduction. Moreover, Morisse et al. identified 492 <hi rend="italic">S</hi>-nitrosylated proteins and 392 sites in <hi rend="italic">chlamydomonas reinhardtii</hi> cells, which were treated with <hi rend="italic">S</hi>-nitrosoglutathione (GSNO). Moreover, 926 proteins that undergo nitrosylation have been identified in <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis</hi>. Certain NO target proteins have been pointed out as important for regulating physiological and pathological cellular processes through proteomic and transcriptomic analyses. Although the identification research on <hi rend="italic">S</hi>-nitrosylation is increasing, the mechanism of <hi rend="italic">S</hi>-nitrosylation during root development remains unclear. The aim of this study was to identify possible candidates for <hi rend="italic">S</hi>-nitrosylation during adventitious rooting to reveal the biological function of NO at the protein level in plants. Therefore, we conducted this experiment to detect and identify the <hi rend="italic">S</hi>-nitrosylated proteins during NO-induced adventitious rooting in cucumber explants. The objective of this study was to decipher the novel role of protein <hi rend="italic">S</hi>-nitrosylation in the process of adventitious root development in order to further improve our understanding of NO signaling transduction in molecular mechanisms. </p>
</text>
