<text id="autogum_academic_doc552" title="Data-Analytics Modeling of Electrical Impedance Measurements for Cell Culture Monitoring" shortTile="dataanalytics-modeling" author="Elvira García, Pablo Pérez, Alberto Olmo, Roberto Díaz, Gloria Huertas, Alberto Yúfera" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4639/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The use of artificial intelligence and data analytic methods to model complex biological processes has proved to be a powerful tool that can provide useful solutions in many different application fields. The electrical cell-substrate impedance sensing technique (ECIS) is a well-established method that allows the real time acquisition of biological parameters (cell growth, motility, activity, or size) of any cell culture and its relationship with the environment through bioimpedance measurements. It can be used in many different studies, such as in toxicity studies, cell growth, cell motility, cancer progression, or stem cell differentiation for regenerative medicine. </p>

<p>ECIS is a non-invasive method (it avoids the death of cells along the timeline, overcoming the limitations of end-point protocols). Furthermore, it is a relatively inexpensive technique, as only one sample or petri plate is required for a performance curve. This petri plate includes different electrodes, and the measured voltage between electrodes can be correlated with different biological parameters. It is currently being used in a wide variety of high-throughput laboratory automation data extraction. </p>

<p>The main drawback of the ECIS technique is the need for managing models to decode the electrical performance of the full system, composed of the electrodes, medium, and cells. Several works have been developed in this field. In, the impedance was deduced from the electric field equation solution at the cell-electrode interface, giving a three-parameter-based model: the cell-electrode distance, the barrier resistance, and the cell radius. In, finite element simulations (FEM) were executed for solving an electrical field considering the whole structure. This method gave one parameter model (Rgap) for describing the gap or cell-electrode interface resistance. In both works, the derived model considered the confluent phase or a fixed area covered by cells. In the model was extended to several cell sizes, allowing one to define the cell-electrode covered area as the main model parameter. A related field to ECIS is electrical impedance tomography (EIT), where the electrical conductivity and permittivity of a part of the body is inferred from surface electrode measurements and used to form a tomographic image of that part. Recent works have shown an interesting improvement on different EIT methods for the decoding of electrical values, with the use of different machine learning methods, such as convolutional neural networks and structure-aware, sparse Bayesian learning. </p>

<p>In, a specific implementation of the ECIS technique was presented based on an oscillation-based-technique (OBT) circuit, wherein oscillation parameters (frequency and amplitude) directly correlate with the cell growth status. Specifically, the oscillation parameters were related with the fill-factor parameter of the cell culture, defined as the ratio of the area covered by the cell culture in the electrodes, from 0 (no cells) to 1 (cells fully covering the electrode area), that being an important biological parameter for the characterization of cell growth. In, an empirical-mathematical approach was proposed for the calibration and fitting of the cell-electrode electrical models in the OBT circuit. First, a calibration procedure by employing the OBT technique and one specific initial cell density was carried out. Then, results were extended to other assays with the same cell type, but with different cells densities. Using the proposed calibration protocol and the OBT technique, a cell-electrode electrical model for the bioimpedance ECIS technique experiments was obtained for specific cell lines. </p>

<p>In the present work, a new approach was followed, using regression techniques to adjust the electrical measurements to analyze and predict the fill-factor parameter in a cell culture, based on the amplitude and frequency of the signal measured in the same OBT circuit. The proposed approach aims to facilitate the interpretation of impedance spectroscopy data, without the need to establish a complex and often difficult-to-implement electrical model. The final aim was to predict the fill-factor parameter of the cell culture using regression techniques, without implementing the electrical model. The methodology can be extended to any cell type and any cell density, which is what makes it of utmost importance in ECIS experiments and high-throughput laboratory data analysis. </p>
</text>
