<text id="autogum_academic_doc366" title="Identification of Bicycling Periods Using the MicroPEM Personal Exposure Monitor" shortTile="identification-bicycling" author="Robert Chew, Jonathan Thornburg, Darby Jack, Cara Smith, Qiang Yang, Steven Chillrud" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4613/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Efficiently mitigating human exposure to air pollution is a top public health objective. According to the most recent global burden of disease/comparative risk assessment, exposure to air pollution causes over 6.8 million premature deaths per year, with roughly equal contributions from ambient and household air pollution. While many countries acknowledge this danger and have enacted air pollution prevention laws, developing specific rules and regulations to implement these laws can be challenging when the relationships between pollutant exposure and health effects are underspecified. Better information on exposure response relationships (how clean is clean enough?) can help regulators more effectively balance the often competing objectives of economic growth and public health. </p>

<p>In air pollution epidemiology, exposure assessment studies are the primary means for understanding links between exposure to chemical and physical agents and adverse health effects. However, exposure assessment studies have traditionally used imperfect proxies based on central site data to assess these relationships, even though ambient concentrations are poor predictors of personal exposure. For measuring personal exposure, ambient concentration readings from stationary sensors have many drawbacks. First, people move through multiple indoor and outdoor micro-environments with fine-scale spatial and temporal heterogeneity in concentrations, resulting in substantial person-to-person variation even among individuals living within the same building or neighborhood. Stationary sensors are unable to capture these differences in daily routines and resulting exposures, potentially biasing health effect estimates. In addition, due to their fixed nature, stationary sensors are unable to decouple the spatiotemporal contributions of individual sources to a person’s exposure. Finally, the actual inhaled dose of a pollutant is a function of respiration rate, and, thus, of physical activity patterns. Since physical activity protects against many pollution-sensitive health outcomes, this may again confound average concentration-based estimates. </p>

<p>To help address concerns with air pollution exposure assessment studies based on fixed, centrally located sensor data, researchers have proposed using wearable monitors to more accurately capture personalized pollutant exposures. Unlike stationary sensors, personal monitors can better capture exposures actually experienced by the wearers and provides the spatial and temporal heterogeneity necessary to design interventions incorporating human behaviors and lifestyle. Furthermore, if personal exposure data is combined with respiration data, it becomes possible to estimate potential inhaled dose, a much higher fidelity measure for mapping the exposure response than using device concentrations alone. However, passively measuring respiratory rates is not always possible without subjects wearing additional devices, increasing the level of study complexity and increasing the risk of protocol non-compliance. </p>

<p>In this study, we focus on classification methods for determining levels of high activity directly from wearable exposure monitor data. This information can be used to develop tiers of respiratory rates for potential inhaled dose calculations, using the same wearable device required for personal exposure monitoring. Specifically, we develop a machine learning model for identifying periods of bicycling activity using passively collected data from the RTI MicroPEM wearable exposure monitor, a lightweight device capable of continuously sampling both particulate matter concentration and the wearer’s acceleration. </p>

<head> 1.1. Motivation</head>
<p>
Our focus on identifying periods of bicycling activity is motivated by the elevated risk of urban cyclists for pollutant exposure when compared to other urban residents. Since urban cyclists undertake strenuous exercise in close proximity to traffic, their potential dose is likely to be higher than many other urban residents, due both to their increased respiration rates and their proximity to traffic sources. For example, Zuurbier et al. estimated cyclists inhale twice as much ultra fine particle (UFP counts) and PM2.5 (mass) per unit time as car and bus occupants because of their much higher minute ventilation, even though the measured UFP and PM concentrations were higher inside the vehicles. A similar study found the average daily dose of cyclists was 1.06–1.30 times higher than non-cyclists. This larger inhaled dose is likely due to the average minute ventilation of cyclists being 4.3 times higher than vehicle passengers. In terms of potential exposures, recent studies in major North American cities have found average exposures along bike routes to be higher than comparable fixed sidewalk stations and significant associations between higher PM2.5 emissions and bicycling volume. Pedestrians and joggers, in addition to cyclists, receive higher potential inhaled doses of traffic related pollutants, but cyclists are the preferred cohort because the exposure and health assessment equipment is less burdensome for cyclists to carry. Lastly, given the growth in ridership and infrastructural support for urban cycling in many U.S. cities, understanding cyclist exposure patterns can help address many practical issues of concern to the public. Does biking to and from work affect cardiovascular health or indicators of future health outcomes? Should one limit exercise and biking to the less polluted days or less polluted areas of the city? Do the health benefits of commuting by bicycle outweigh the costs? </p>
</text>
