<text id="autogum_academic_doc279" title="On One Problems of Spectral Theory for Ordinary Differential Equations of Fractional Order" shortTile="one-problems-spectral" author="Temirkhan Aleroev" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2075-1680/8/4/117/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Results</head>

<p>Reference studied the operator in the spacevwhich was first considered in References, where and is the Green function of the following problem <hi rend="italic">S</hi> (with ):</p>

<p>( , where  is the integer part of ) </p>

<p>In particular, in this paper, we provide very important proof of the completeness of the system of eigenfunctions and associated functions in  of the operator  for  based on fact that the operator of fractional differentiation is sectorial and for  (this fact plays a main role in solving boundary value problems for advection-diffusion equation of fractional order by the method of separation of variables since we can write out both the exact solution in the form of an infinite series by eigenfunctions and the approximate solution replacing the infinite sums by sums of the first <hi rend="italic">n</hi> terms), a proof based on the well-known Livshits theorem (researching of case for  published in this paper firstly):<b>Theorem</b> <b>1</b> (<b>Livshits</b>)<b>.</b></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">If   – is a limited kernel and “real part”  of it is non-negative kernel, then the inequality is hold</hi><hi rend="italic">where —is the characteristic numbers of kernel K. The system of main functions of the kernel K is complete in domain of values of the integral operator  if and only if, when there is an equal sign in inequality above.</hi> </p>

<p>In his paper M. M. Dzhrbashian wrote, that “the question about the completeness of the systems of eigenfunctions of the operator  or a finer question about whether these systems compose a basis in , has a certain interest but its solving is apparently associated with significant analytic difficulties”. The questions of the completeness of the systems of eigenfunctions and associated functions for similar problems were studied by A. V. Agibalova in. Undoubtedly, we shall note the fundamental results of M. M. Malamud and L. L. Oridoroga obtained in this direction. In (see also), using the theorem of Matsaev and Palant, it was established that the system of eigenfunctions of the operator  is complete in . And this fact used by M. Ali, S. Aziz and S.A. Malik in their paper. </p>

<p>As noted above, in this paper, a similar result was obtained using the well-known Livshchits theorem. The following proof of the completeness of the system of eigenfunctions is simpler than the previously presented proofs, which makes the results of this paper very significant. </p>

<p>Next, we need one definition.<b>Definition</b> <b>1.</b></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">If a series of s-numbers of the completely continuous operator is convergent, that is,  then such operator called as trace-class operator.</hi><b>Lemma</b> <b>1.</b></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Let , then the operator  is trace-class and</hi><b>Proof</b> <b>of</b> <b>Lemma</b> <b>1.</b></p>

<p> To find the trace of the operator , let’s rewrite as where

Clearly, for , the operators  and  are trace class. Hence

Moreover, it is clear that  Thus

Since operator  is one-dimensional, it is easy to find a trace. Consider the equation

The Fredhold determinant

where

From above follow that

which proves the Lemma 1. <b>Remark</b> <b>1.</b></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Of course, for , nuclearity of the operator  follows from well-known Dzhrbaschian-Nersisian lemma ([18], p. 142).</hi><b>Lemma</b> <b>2</b> (<b>Dzhrbaschian-Nersisian</b>)<b>.</b></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">1. All zeros of functions  (where ) with largest absolute values, are prime.</hi> </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">2. The following asymptotic formulas are valid</hi><hi rend="italic">and the fact that the value  is an eigenvalue of the operator  if and only if </hi> </p>

<p>Now we give the main result of paper.<b>Theorem</b> <b>2.</b></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">The system of eigenfunctions and associated functions of the operator , where , is complete in .</hi><b>Proof</b> <b>of</b> <b>Theorem</b> <b>2.</b></p>

<p>We denote the kernel of  as . In the authors have proved that this kernel is non-negative by the following way: Let us rewrite  as</p>

<p>Clearly, for , the kernel of  is non-negative. </p>

<p>By the same way, we may show that the kernel  for adjoint operator

is non-negative too. Thus  is non-negative. Let us show that the following expression holds</p>

<p>If  is eigenvalue of the operator , then complex conjugate  is eigenvalue of the operator  too. Thus</p>

<p>So, taking to account lemma 1, we obtain that the system of eigenfunctions and associated functions of the operator  for , is complete in . □<b>Remark</b> <b>2.</b></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">For  the kernel of the operator  is continuous. Therefore, as it was showed by Lalesko, the Fredholm determinant of this kernel is whole function of zero kind. In this case,</hi><hi rend="italic">that is, the equation</hi><hi rend="italic">we can get by the obvious way.</hi><b>Theorem</b> <b>3.</b></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">The system of eigenfunctions and associated functions of the operator , where , is complete in .</hi><b>Proof</b> <b>of</b> <b>Theorem</b> <b>3.</b></p>

<p>For  the kernel of the operator  is not fixed-sign, thus we cannot use the Livshits theorem, used above. To prove the formulated theorem, let us consider the value of the the form . Let us introduce the following designation</p>

<p>So,

where</p>
</text>
