<text id="autogum_academic_doc447" title="Sarcopenia in Older Adults" shortTile="sarcopenia-older" author="David Scott" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/11/1844/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>Sarcopenia was first described in 1988 as the age-related decline of skeletal muscle mass. In the last decade, several international groups have developed operational definitions of sarcopenia which incorporate assessments of muscle function in addition to muscle mass in sarcopenia case-finding guidelines. Nonetheless, recent changes to these recommendations demonstrate that there is significant work to be done in order to achieve an international consensus on the methods to diagnose and treat sarcopenia in clinical settings. Indeed, while sarcopenia is now recognised with its own International Classification of Diseases, 10th Revision, Clinical Modification (ICD-10-CM) code (M62.84), few health care professionals know how to diagnose it, include it as part of their clinical practice, or even recognise it as a disease,. This Special Issue of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Clinical Medicine</hi> was established with a view to increase clinician awareness of the important clinical consequences of sarcopenia and improve understanding of diagnosis and treatment strategies.  </p>

<p>Computed tomography (CT) provides precise estimates of muscle quality and so may be useful for case-finding in sarcopenia, but barriers to this method include high costs, lack of availability and ionising radiation doses. Ultrasound represents a potentially cost-effective, accessible and safe method of measuring muscle quality and Harris-Love and colleagues demonstrate in this special issue that rectus femoris echogenicity assessed by ultrasound is significantly correlated with intra- and inter-muscular adipose tissue estimates from CT, and has similar associations with muscle function and cardiometabolic outcomes. For clinicians without requisite expertise or access to equipment to perform muscle mass assessments, it is possible that questionnaires can be useful in identifying patients at risk of sarcopenia. The SarQoL® (Sarcopenia and Quality of Life), is a validated quality of life (QoL) questionnaire which can discriminate sarcopenic and non-sarcopenic patients and has already been translated into several languages. In this issue, a study on the validation of a Polish version of the SarQoL® is described, highlighting the potential utility of this instrument for identifying individuals at risk of sarcopenia, as well as its impact on QoL, across a number of countries worldwide. Physical function assessments are also simple to perform in clinical settings and may be most appropriate to identify sarcopenia cases in obese older adults who, owing to their larger muscle mass, may generally exceed cut-off points for low muscle mass. Mesinovic and colleagues demonstrate associations between the metabolic syndrome and poorer muscle function despite the generally larger muscle size in overweight and obese older individuals, indicating accelerated loss of muscle quality is common in this population. </p>

<p>Sarcopenia is generally considered a disease of ageing but there is no doubt that risk of developing sarcopenia is increased by numerous medical conditions. Moreover, the presence of sarcopenia appears to consistently impact on prognosis of those with existing comorbidities. Indeed, the review by Han and colleagues demonstrates that sarcopenia is associated with increased progression of chronic disease, postoperative complications, length of hospital stay, all-cause mortality and cognitive impairment. The effects of sarcopenia on cognitive impairment are supported by an original study of community-dwelling older adults residing in rural areas of Korea which reported that physical frailty was significantly associated with poor cognitive function. Liver disease is also associated with weight loss and physical frailty, and a population-based study reported that non-alcoholic fatty liver disease was more common in Korean adults with low muscle mass determined by CT, regardless of their obesity status. Similarly, a study of Japanese patients with chronic liver disease reported that 50% had low muscle mass, either alone or combined with low muscle strength. Interestingly, low serum zinc concentration was an independent predictor of sarcopenia in these patients suggesting zinc supplementation warrants further investigation as a strategy to prevent muscle declines in chronic liver disease.  </p>
</text>
