<text id="autogum_academic_doc648" title="Advances in Understanding the Relationship between Sleep and Attention Deficit-Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)" shortTile="advances-understanding" author="Serena Scarpelli, Maurizio Gorgoni, Aurora D’Atri, Flaminia Reda, Luigi De Gennaro" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/10/1737/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion </head>
<p>
We reviewed for the first time the studies concerning the relation between macrostructural and/or microstructural features of sleep and ADHD, considering the investigations of the last 15 years.  </p>

<head> 4.1. Macrostructural Pattern</head>
<p>
The results concerning the macrostructural parameters are quite conflicting, and drawing a coherent framework is challenging. Almost half of the selected studies did not find differences in the sleep architecture of children with ADHD, compared to those with typical development.  </p>

<p>The investigations revealing significant differences between the ADHD and HC groups demonstrated that the clinical samplea are characterized by poorer sleep than controls. Indeed, the longer SOL, the shorter TST, along with the reduced SE and the indices of faster transition of stages/cycles (e.g., a higher rate of SS and a greater number of sleep cycles) reflect -to some extent- the sleep dysregulation in ADHD. On the one hand, the assumption that children with ADHD have an altered sleep architecture is consistent with the subjective parent reports, mentioning a delayed sleep onset or a sleep fragmentation with several night awakenings. On the other hand, the sleep difficulties reported by parents appear to be significantly higher as compared to objective measures. The gap between subjective and objective measures may be ascribed to other factors that cannot be revealed by the PSG recordings. The subjective reports of increased SOL—confirmed only by some investigations using objective measures (e.g.,)—may be explained by “behavioral” sleep problems occurring <hi rend="italic">before</hi> bedtime. In this regard, the bedtime resistance could depend on multiple factors: (a) inadequate parenting; (b) Inadequate pre-sleep bed routines and/or sleep environment; (c) pharmacotherapy side-effects. This disturbance in ADHD children is often interpreted as oppositional behavior, a significant source of distress for parents. In light of the above, it is fair to assume that subjective reports could overestimate sleep problems in ADHD, reflecting parental concerns. </p>

<p>NREM sleep architecture did not show specific and consistent differences between children with ADHD and HC. We have to underline that a lower SWS has been found in an ADHD sample characterized by a higher rate of comorbidities or when a higher apnea-hypopnea index was detected. In this respect, a strong relationship between SDB and ADHD behavior was found (e.g.,), likely inducing the disruption of sleep homeostasis and less deep sleep. Moreover, as previously mentioned, the exclusion of subjects with externalizing and internalizing problems from the analysis abolished all differences in NREM sleep.  </p>

<p>Although no other differences in SWS were found, it should be underlined that both stage 4 amount and REM sleep density were correlated with the improvement in motor skills performance after sleep in children with ADHD, as assessed by Prehn-Kristensen et al.. This study suggested a possible beneficial role of sleep on tasks measuring procedural memory in ADHD, that –instead- showed compromised performance during the waking state. </p>

<p>REM sleep abnormalities seem to be widespread among children with ADHD, consistently with previous meta-analysis. REM sleep alterations could be related to the dysfunctional reward learning, one of the core deficits of ADHD, due to the dopamine hypofunction. </p>

<p>Specifically, several findings highlighted that REM sleep duration is longer in children with ADHD compared to controls, and only Gruber et al. found a reduced amount of REM sleep in ADHD. It is worth noting that this latter study included patients with PLMS that may induce REM sleep instability, contributing to its shorter duration.  </p>

<p>Interestingly, the higher REM sleep percentage in the ADHD group was found along with a higher number of sleep cycles in two studies. As already suggested, the increased number of sleep cycles may result in a faster transition to REM sleep, contributing to the increased REM sleep amount. Once again, the presence of comorbidities could have affected these results.  </p>

<head> 4.2. Microstructural Pattern</head>
<p>
Concerning the eight studies reporting sleep microstructural features in the ADHD group, the results are not homogenous. </p>

<p>Findings on spindle activity are still scarce and very difficult to interpret. In particular, some methodological differences in the spindle analysis should be taken into account: (a) Saletin et al. did not provide a specific spindle detection, analyzing the whole sigma band; (b) some protocols did not include parietal derivations, where the spindles typically show their maximum. </p>

<p>The most relevant alterations in sleep microstructure of ADHD are related to SWA and theta activity during NREM and REM sleep, respectively.  </p>
</text>
