<text id="autogum_academic_doc516" title="Off-Target Deletion of Conditional Dbc1 Allele in the Foxp3YFP-Cre Mouse Line under Specific Setting" shortTile="target-deletion-conditional" author="Chichu Xie, Fangming Zhu, Julie Wang, Weizhou Zhang, Joseph  A. Bellanti, Bin Li, David Brand, Nancy Olsen, Song  Guo Zheng" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4409/8/11/1309/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Cre–LoxP technology has been utilized extensively for conditional knockouts in yeast, plants, cultured mammalian cells, T cells, neuronal tissue and so forth. Conditional knockout mice using this technology are constructed by breeding a floxed (i.e., flanked by LoxP) gene of interest with mice expressing Cre-recombinase driven by a tissue or cell-type specific promoter. Some examples include the construction of CD4 positive cell knockouts of <hi rend="italic">Irf4</hi> by breeding <hi rend="italic">Cd4</hi>Cre mice with those containing floxed <hi rend="italic">Irf4</hi> sites; breeding dendritic cell driven <hi rend="italic">CD11c</hi>Cre mice with floxed <hi rend="italic">TGFRβ</hi>II and the construction of neuronal tissue knockouts of <hi rend="italic">Rem2</hi> by breeding <hi rend="italic">Rgs9</hi>Cre with <hi rend="italic">Rem2</hi>LoxP/LoxP mice.  </p>

<p>Although the Cre-Lox conditional knockout method is an ideal tool for the study of a gene of interest in a specific cell type, some limitations exist. One limitation is the non-specific expression of the targeted gene resulting in off-target recombination in other cell types. Another limitation is the potential for germline recombination of conditional alleles due to the transient Cre expression in the germline. Thus, a careful characterization of mice generated with this system is an absolute requirement to confirm proper control of conditional recombination.  </p>

<p>Treg cells have been recognized to be crucial in immune tolerance and the prevention of autoimmune responses. <hi rend="italic">Foxp3</hi>YFP-Cre (or <hi rend="italic">Foxp3</hi>Cre) mice were constructed by Rubtsov et al. to study genes related to regulatory T (Treg) cell biology. In the <hi rend="italic">Foxp3</hi>YFP-Cre mouse, the <hi rend="italic">Cre</hi> gene is located after an internal ribosome entry site (IRES) sequence which is inserted just after the normal termination codon of <hi rend="italic">Foxp3</hi>. This mouse was used by several groups to study the function of genes such as <hi rend="italic">Uqcrsf1</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Id2</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Foxp1</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Maf</hi> in Treg cells. However, Rubtsov et al. and Franckaert et al. have reported the off-target recombination in some hematopoietic lineage cells of a <hi rend="italic">Foxp3</hi>YFP-Cre mouse.  </p>

<p>The authors have found that the <hi rend="italic">DBC1</hi> is involved in regulatory T-cell function under conditions of inflammation. To study the specific function of <hi rend="italic">Dbc1</hi> in regulatory T-cells, <hi rend="italic">Foxp3</hi>YFP-Cre mice were crossed with floxed <hi rend="italic">Dbc1</hi> mice to gain the regulatory T-cell knockouts of <hi rend="italic">Dbc1</hi>. During the breeding process, it was unexpectedly found that the floxed <hi rend="italic">Dbc1</hi> allele in some mice was totally deleted and the off-target recombination of floxed <hi rend="italic">Dbc1</hi> allele occurred in tissues other than T cells.  </p>
</text>
