<text id="autogum_academic_doc576" title="Liquid Water Detection under the South Polar Layered Deposits of Mars—A Probabilistic Inversion Approach" shortTile="liquid-water-detection" author="Sebastian  Emanuel Lauro, Francesco Soldovieri, Roberto Orosei, Andrea Cicchetti, Marco Cartacci, Elisabetta Mattei, Barbara Cosciotti, Federico Di Paolo, Raffaella Noschese, Elena Pettinelli" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/11/20/2445/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Electromagnetic Properties of the SPLD Ice-Layer</head>
<p>
The SPLD is predominantly composed by “dirty ice” that is a mixture of water ice with a variable volume fraction of dust. For radar data interpretation, it is suitable to consider the microscopically complex mixture as macroscopically homogeneous and characterized by an effective dielectric permittivity. Several dielectric models have been proposed to estimate the permittivity of mixtures from the known dielectric properties and volume content of the phases. In order to explore different scenarios for the composition of the SPLD, the dielectric permittivity of pure water ice and dirty ice (with different silicate dust volume fractions) is reported below in terms of real part of permittivity ε’ and attenuation factor α, estimated using the following formula: inversion procedure to retrieve the basal permittivity

(10)

where  is the complex relative permittivity. </p>

<head> 4.1. Pure Water Iice</head>
<p>
The dielectric properties of pure water ice have been intensively measured in laboratory over a wide range of temperatures and frequencies; however, the lack of a standard procedure in sample preparation and measuring methodology raises some questions about the reliability of the experimental data. Indeed, the dielectric measurements of pure water ice are affected by cooling procedure, aging, dislocation, cracks and fractures, gas bubbles and inclusions, chemical impurities, vacancies and other lattice imperfections. Since literature data are heterogeneous in terms of temperature intervals and frequency ranges, the complex permittivity of pure water ice is here assumed according to the data provided by Kawada. </p>

<head> 4.2. Dirty Ice</head>
<p>
The real and imaginary part of the dielectric permittivity for dirty ice have been retrieved for four different values of silicate volume fraction (5,10, 15 and 20%) considering the medium as a two-phase mixture (ice/silicate). The Maxwell Garnett mixing rule has been applied to determine the effective dielectric properties of the mixtures: the host medium is considered as pure water ice and the inclusions are Martian meteorite dust . </p>

<p><figure>Figure 2</figure>. reports the attenuation at 4 MHz as a function of temperature for dust, pure water ice and dirty ice, evaluated at four different volume fractions (5, 10, 15 and 20%). The pure water ice shows a typical exponential decay with temperature, whereas no temperature dependence is exhibited by the dust. The behaviour of dirty ice is intermediate between the trends of water ice and dust. </p>

<p>Table 1 reports the values of the real part of the permittivity of the ice layer for the same conditions given in <figure>Figure 2</figure>. It is worth noting that the presence of the dust in the water ice also introduces a small variation in the real part of the dielectric permittivity (ranging from 3.1 to 3.9). These values (permittivity and attenuation) have been used in the inverse model to retrieve the basal material permittivity. </p>
</text>
