<text id="autogum_academic_doc078" title="The Significance of the Intrinsically Disordered Regions for the Functions of the bHLH Transcription Factors" shortTile="significance-intrinsically" author="Aneta Tarczewska, Beata Greb-Markiewicz" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5306/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. The Role of the bHLH Proteins in Transcription</head>
<p>
The regulation of genes expression by multiple transcription factors, cofactors and chromatin regulators establish and maintains a specific state of a cell. Inaccurate regulation of transmitted signals can results in diseases and severe disorders. Therefore, transcription requires balanced orchestration of adjustable complexes of proteins. A key regulator of transcription is Mediator, a multi-subunit Mediator complex which interacts with RNA polymerase II (Pol II), and coordinates the action of numerous co-activators and co-repressors. Function of the Mediator is conserved in all eukaryotes, though, the individual subunits have diverged considerably in some organisms. </p>

<p>Up to date, for some bHLH family representatives, interactions with subunits of the Mediator and/or chromatin remodeling histone acetyltransferases/deacyltransferase, were reported. In plants, the Mediator complex is a core element of transcription regulation important for their immunity. It was shown, that in <hi rend="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</hi> important jasmonate signaling and resistance to fungus <hi rend="italic">Botrytis cinerea</hi>, is dependent on the interaction between MED25 subunit of the Mediator and MYC2, and interaction of MED8 subunit of the Mediator with FAMA belonging to the bHLH family. Sterol regulatory element binding proteins (SREBPs) the class II bHLH TFs (Table 1) are transcription activators critical for regulation of cholesterol and fatty acid homeostasis in animals. It was shown that human SREBPs bind CBP/p300 acetyltransferase and MED15 subunit of the Mediator to activate target genes. Also yeast Ino2 was shown to bind MED15 subunit of the Mediator tail. </p>

<p>The representative of class II TFs TAL1 (Table 1) is required for the specification of the blood lineage and maturation of several hematopoietic cells. TAL1/SCL is considered as a master TF delineating the cell fate and the identity of progenitor and normal hematopoietic stem cells (HSCs). It regulates other hematopoietic TFs thus has a potential for cell reprogramming. TAL1 also binds CBP/p300 acetyltransferase. Similarly MyoD—a myogenic regulatory factor which controls skeletal muscle development binds CBP and recruits histone acetyltransferase to activate myogenic program. Cao et al. showed that of MyoD modify the myoblasts chromatin structure and accessibility. ASCL1 (class II, Table 1) was shown to be a pioneer factor which promotes chromatin accessibility and enables chromatin binding by others TFs. Recently, also AHR (bHLH-PAS, Table 1) was suggested to be a pioneer factor which regulates DNA methylation during embryonic developments in unknown way. In clear cell renal cell carcinoma (ccRCC), the most frequent mutation causes the von Hippel-Lindau (VHL) tumor suppressor inactivation leading to genome-wide enhancer and super-enhancer remodeling. This process is mediated by the interaction of HIF2α and HIF1β (bHLH-PAS, Table 1) with histone acetyltransferase p300. CLOCK, the other bHLH-PAS subfamily member (Table 1) was shown to mediate histone acetylation in a circadian time-specific manner. </p>

<p>Interestingly, the bHLH-O proteins members (class VI, Table 1) HEY proteins can function as transcription repressors as well as transcription activators. They were shown to bind directly DNA and interact with histone deacetylases and other TFs. On the other hand, gene activation by HEY is regulated in an indirect way. Multiple HEY binding sites located downstream and close to the transcriptional start site, resulted in a hypothesis that HEY influence the pausing/elongation switch of Pol II. Interestingly, though most of TFs stimulate transcription initiation, MYC (class III, Table 1) was shown to stimulate transcription elongation by recruitment of the elongation factor. The presented studies indicate that the crucial role of the bHLH proteins in maintaining transcriptional regulation of important developmental (e.g., cell differentiation) and oncogenic pathways is dependent on the multiple interactions with basal transcriptional machinery. </p>
</text>
