<text id="autogum_academic_doc272" title="Deep LSTM with Reinforcement Learning Layer for Financial Trend Prediction in FX High Frequency Trading Systems" shortTile="deep-lstm-reinforcement" author="Francesco Rundo" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/20/4460/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Materials and Methods</head>
<p>
The method proposed in this paper will seek to exploit the correlations between distinct currency crosses in order to predict the medium-term trend of ones of them. To this end, the authors will describe below a pipeline that is based on the use of set of cross-currency exchanges characterizing an arbitrage opportunity in the Forex market. As introduced in the first section, an arbitrage takes advantage of differences in the price of single currency related to short-time misalignments between the traded currency with the related ones. A typical example of arbitrage is the so-called triangular arbitrage referred to three currencies of which one is obtainable from the combination of the prices of the other two crosses. In this article, we will refer to the EUR/USD, GBP/USD, and EUR/GBP crosses. A similar approach can be extended to any other trio of related currencies. The currency on which to execute trading operations is EUR/USD. The price of the EUR/USD cross for arbitrage purposes in the currency market must always be obtainable from the other two pairs EUR/GBP and GBP/USD by the relationship

(1)

</p>

<p>In Equation (1), we have denoted with <b><hi rend="italic">px(tk)</hi></b> the price of the currency. Therefore, in a financially balanced market, so that an investor cannot take advantage of arbitrage conditions and consequently obtain a systematic gain, Equation (1) must always be verified, i.e., there must be a very precise temporal correlation between specific currency crosses. In reality, small short-term misalignments are always found in the Forex markets and these are often excellent trading opportunities for financial robot advisors who automatically execute many operations, taking advantage of these short-time market misalignments. The author is investigating the design and use of specific hand-crafted features (which the author has already used in the medical field) extracted from the chart of currency time-series and which would seem to early indicate the possible misalignments between the cross currency prices from which are extracted. </p>

<p>For the reasons mentioned above, the author has designed a pipeline which, to determine the medium-term trend of a given currency, analyzes the correlations between the related currencies in the context of a triangular arbitrage. In the specific case, without losing generalization, the author will refer to the EUR/USD currency as that on which to execute financial trading operations and to the EUR/GBP and GBP/USD currencies to determine the data set for a possible triangular arbitrage. Similar considerations can be extended to any other set of currencies with the same financial characteristics. </p>

<p>Having established this necessary premise, the author will describe the proposed pipeline below. <figure>Figure 2</figure> below shows the block diagram of the algorithmic pipeline that is intended to be described in this paper: </p>

<p>The following paragraphs will illustrate each of the blocks present in the complete diagram of the proposed pipeline and shown in <figure>Figure 2</figure>. </p>

<head> 2.1. Data Pre-Processing Block</head>
<p>
The objective of this block is to pre-process the data of the incoming financial time-series. Specifically, in this block the data of the incoming time-series will be normalized in the range [0, 1]. <figure>Figure 3</figure> shows an example of normalized financial time-series relating to the three cross currency analyzed in this paper. In this way, whatever the pricing of the cross currency entering our system, the pipeline will always process data in the range [0, 1], greatly improving the stability of the proposed algorithm. </p>

<p>In order to train and validate the proposed pipeline, the author has organized a proper dataset of financial pricing data. Specifically, historical financial data (with 99.9% accuracy) of EUR/USD, GBP/USD, EUR/GBP for the years 2004–2018 have been collected. Again, with reference to the aforementioned time period, for each cross currency the historical data referring to the opening and closing prices, higher and lower in addition to the time of each quotation (CET time) have been collected. This dataset has been properly divided in order to organize a set of data that can be used for the training phase of the proposed system and the remaining for the testing and validation session. Specifically, such training simulations and annual validation have been performed, dividing the dataset as follows: 70% of the mentioned dataset was used to train the pipeline, while the remaining 30% was used to validate and test the proposed method. Both the training set and the validation ones has been analyzed as to understand if the possible trends (LONG, SHORT, NULL) were equally represented in both datasets in order to avoid overfitting issues for the deep learning system.  </p>

<p>The financial data thus organized are therefore presented as input to the pre-processing system described in this section whose output will be further processed by the next deep learning block. </p>
</text>
