<text id="autogum_academic_doc661" title="Burden and Anxiety in Family Caregivers in the Hospital That Debut in Caregiving" shortTile="burden-anxiety-family" author="Margarita Pérez-Cruz, Laura Parra-Anguita, Catalina López-Martínez, Sara Moreno-Cámara, Rafael del-Pino-Casado" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/20/3977/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
In the present study, the level of subjective burden and anxiety was assessed in family caregivers of dependent older adults aged 65 years and over, who had recently started caregiving in the hospital, and the factors associated with anxiety in these caregivers were analysed. </p>

<p>This study on the determinants of anxiety in family caregivers of dependent older adults was conducted in the hospital context. To our knowledge, this is the first study which focuses on those caregivers that debut in caregiving in this setting. </p>

<p>In the present investigation, the characteristics of the caregivers that start caregiving in the hospital are similar to those in a study conducted in Spain by the Institute for the Elderly and Social Services (IMSERSO, acronym of the Spanish name of the Institute), which investigated the care of elderly persons in their homes in Spain in 2005. Their study sample was representative at a national level. Therefore, the sample population in our study could be considered as representative of the caregivers of dependent older adults in Spain. </p>

<head> 4.1. Levels of Burden and Anxiety</head>
<p>
In the present study, the family caregivers presented with a level of burden of 36.1%, with a mean of 5.4 out of 13. Our results demonstrate a higher level of burden than that measured in other studies of hospital caregivers, but similar to studies of family caregivers in the home environment, with sociodemographic characteristics similar to the population sample in our study. </p>

<p>With regards to the level of anxiety, our results are similar to those presented in a systematic review by Sallim et al. on caregivers of patients suffering from Alzheimer disease, and are higher than those in a review by Loh et al. on caregivers of stroke survivors. In the Spanish context, the level of anxiety found in our study is similar to that of studies conducted in the home environment. </p>

<p>Hence, family caregivers that have just started caregiving may have higher levels of burden and anxiety than those that have not recently started. Their level of burden also appears to be similar to those caregiving in the home environment. </p>

<p>Caregivers in the hospital could have theoretically less requirements than at home because several care recipient needs are attended by the healthcare team. However, for the caregiver, providing care in an unknown environment such as a hospital, even though in a lesser grade that at home, and being required to take on this care suddenly without information or previous training, may be more stressful than providing care in the home. This possibly results in the appearance of negative emotional consequences in the caregiver, such as subjective burden or anxiety. </p>

<p>The levels of burden and anxiety found in our study highlight the importance of these problems and the need that debut caregivers in the hospital should be preferentially attended to in order to prevent these consequences. </p>

<head> 4.2. Objective Burden, Burden, and Anxiety</head>
<p>
In terms of the factors related to anxiety, after adjusting for possible confounding factors in the path analysis, we found that the number of basic ADLs attended, the hours of surveillance or supervision by the caregiver, the cognitive impairment of the recipient of care, and the subjective burden of the caregiver were related to higher levels of anxiety; and that the subjective burden mediated the effects of the number of basic ADLs attended, the hours of surveillance or supervision by the caregiver, and the cognitive impairment of the recipient of care on anxiety. Thus, hypotheses (2) and (3) have been demonstrated. Regarding hypothesis (1), only indirect relationships via subjective burden have been demonstrated between objective burden and anxiety. All the primary objective stressors were related with anxiety except functional capacity. </p>

<p>The findings in this study highlight a positive direct effect of subjective burden on anxiety, after adjusting for objective burden, and are consistent with other studies focused on caregivers in the home (both cross-sectional as well as longitudinal) that had valid and reliable measurements that were adjusted for objective burden. Hence, our study increases the available evidence of the possible harmful effect of subjective burden on anxiety, expanding this result to family caregivers in the hospital that newly start to provide care and controlling for stressful life events. </p>
</text>
