<text id="autogum_academic_doc683" title="Advance Management Education for Power-Engineering and Industry of the Future" shortTile="advance-management" author="Lazar Gitelman, Mikhail Kozhevnikov, Olga Ryzhuk" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5930/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Results and Discussion</head>
<head> 5.1. Interdisciplinary Competencies Become Crucial </head>
<p>
In the current period of super-dynamic changes, serious fundamental education is essential. The question arises, however, what fundamental knowledge, what content and depth of study are needed? How to transform this knowledge into the necessary competencies? Should a wide range of knowledge be gained and specific (at least initial) experience and the ability to reflect on your actions be acquired to develop the essential competencies and to successfully operate in the conditions of uncertainty and changeable external environment? Leading universities are actively developing research and managerial training in such areas as systems engineering, future technologies, complex systems’ stability and adaptability, network technologies and distributed architectures, data science, conceptual design, chaos management, self-organization, etc.. </p>

<p>The fundamental principle of modern university education is the application of an interdisciplinary approach that integrates subject knowledge into a new quality (mathematics, physics, biology, engineering and technology, economics and finance, ecology, law, management). Moreover, it is technology in a broad sense, from targeted research and engineering to the introduction of innovation, that interdisciplinary interrelations concentrate on. Therefore, knowledge of the engineering fundamentals of production and scientific and technical trends is an indispensable condition for a manager to successfully fulfill their functions. Hence, in management education, the share and content of scientific, technical, engineering and technological, technical and economic training should be substantially strengthened, as this is what contributes to the development of the relevant competencies. </p>

<p>We should emphasize that interdisciplinarity is not so much a joint consideration of problems by experts from different fields of science and practice, but a synthesis of various knowledge in order to obtain a new solution to a complex problem. It can be assumed that the trend towards interdisciplinarity will become stronger as the flow of new complex tasks, differentiation and integration of knowledge intensify. When training managers, it is important not only to demonstrate the capabilities of an interdisciplinary methodology as a way of organizing teamwork for a comprehensive analysis of the situation and increasing heuristic efficiency, but also to provide them with the tools for interdisciplinary decisions. </p>

<p>The continuously arising new tasks, the need for their understanding, systematization and schematization, taking into account the requirements of numerous stakeholders, frequent restructuring of teams to adjust to the changing requirements, makes relevant the interdisciplinary competencies that are crucial in achieving strategic goals of technological breakthrough: engineering-managerial, engineering-economic competencies and the ability to take anticipatory action (<figure>Figure 2</figure>). The latter becomes a priority and a decisive factor in leadership. However, it cannot be mastered without acquiring engineering-managerial and engineering-economic competencies. </p>

<p>Even with local technological modernization, there is an acute need for the following competencies:</p>
<list>
<item>development of investment projects with rationalized technical and economic standards that characterize its target results;</item>
<item>technical and economic analysis of the applicability of individual models of new machines and equipment, various suppliers and forms of service in the specific context of the enterprise;</item>
<item>a comprehensive assessment of external risks (investment and technical) and ways to minimize them;</item>
<item>implementation of organizational change programs in connection with the technical re-equipment of manufacturing;</item>
<item>selecting innovations that can be obtained from foreign partners and carrying out transactions in the world markets;</item>
<item>analytical work with large amounts of information of various subject content.</item>
</list>

<p>
As the systems become more complex, the contradictions increase between the objectives of research and technological activity (the field of science), users of technology (the field of exploitation) and the interests of business as the main customer of high-tech innovations. As a result, coordinated work of different professionals is required, joining the work at its various stages and performing different functions (<figure>Figure 3</figure>). Under such conditions, it is impossible to predict the consequences of decisions made at early stages that have a significant effect on the efficiency of the development process and on the characteristics of the system being created. It is necessary, on the one hand, to evaluate options taking into account the entire life cycle of the system and the changes in the external environment that can significantly influence it and, on the other hand, to separate the design process of the system as a whole from the detailed work on its individual components and develop iteratively, testing and refining solutions as new information appears. Thus, these clusters of competencies must be mastered by professionals of different profiles, but to a different extent, depending on the tasks they are to deal with. </p>
</text>
