<text id="autogum_academic_doc497" title="Induced Pluripotent Stem Cells as Vasculature Forming Entities" shortTile="induced-pluripotent" author="Antonio Palladino, Isabella Mavaro, Carmela Pizzoleo, Elena De Felice, Carla Lucini, Paolo de Girolamo, Paolo  A. Netti, Chiara Attanasio" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/11/1782/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Protocols to Induce Mature EC Phenotype</head>
<p>
It is well known that for clinical use, it is mandatory to generate cells able to show a high degree of commitment. This requirement fulfills not only functional issues, but also safety ones, in order to prevent teratoma formation after implantation. Thus, a prerequisite to exploit iPSC-ECs in the clinical setting is the development of defined protocols to guide their differentiation into functional endothelial cells. The ideal induction protocol should be reproducible, easy to perform and relatively quick in order to allow yielding an adequate quantity of homogeneous cells. Current induction strategies include embryonic bodies (EB) generation, differentiation on monolayers and co-culture with primary cells (<figure>Figure 4</figure>). </p>

<p>IPSCs tend to self-assemble into three-dimensional (3D) structures (EB) when grown in suspension. From EBs, cell aggregates encompassing all three germ layers develop, and afterwards, within the positive mesodermal, EB cells tend to form vascular structures. This method is affected by low efficiency (1–5%) and slow production rate; however, differentiation can be improved by adding proper growth factors to the culture medium. Another approach involves a co-culture with primary cell lines able to induce iPSC-EC differentiation toward mature ECs. In detail, Choi et al. directed hiPSCs into mature ECs in the presence of OP9, a mouse bone marrow stromal cell line. The authors speculated that these cells regulate iPSC induction via a paracrine signaling. </p>

<p>Monolayer differentiation holds a significantly higher efficiency that depends on external factors, such as medium constituents, showing a final yield that is still too low in the view of clinical applications. To date, the best protocols showing the highest EC yields were developed by culturing a monolayer of hiPSCs on a matrix-coated culture plate and by treating them with different molecules or growth factors in a timed fashion in order to guide the progressive differentiation of hiPSCs toward the EC lineage. In this context, GSK3 inhibitors play an important role among the set of molecules necessary to induce the differentiation of pluripotent cells into mature ECs. In particular, vascular progenitors derive during human development from latero-posterior mesoderm. To specify mesoderm, Wnt signaling, which is activated by GSK3 inhibition, is required. In view of this, several authors have exploited GSK3 inhibitors to differentiate hiPSCs into ECs. Patsch et al. exposed a monolayer of hiPSC to GSK3 inhibitor CHIR-99021 (CHIR) and to mesoderm inducer bone morphogenetic protein 4 (BMP4). The combination of these two molecules led to the production of mature ECs in a relatively short time (six days) with 80% efficiency. </p>

<p>However, mesoderm induction is only the first step of differentiation. The second part starts upon mesodermal commitment by exposing the cells to factors that further induce the mature vascular phenotype. Gu set up a protocol through which, after 4 days of treatment with VEGF and bFGF, he produced mature ECs in only 8 days. These cells, when tested, were molecularly and functionally similar to native ECs. </p>

<p>Paik et al. added VEGF, bFGF and BMP4 to an already established protocol to produce mature ECs from hiPSCs within 12 days. Although this protocol requires more time compared to other ones reported in literature, the aim of this study was different. In fact, these cells were used to draw an RNA signature at different stage of differentiation. </p>

<p>The last step included in the differentiation protocol is the purification of positive cells. This step is essential to fish out a homogenous subset of cells and to ensure the safety needed for the future cell implantation and engraftment. </p>

<p>Cell sorting is usually performed by using magnetic beads on which surface specific antibodies are adsorbed. These antibodies are directed against mature endothelial markers such as CD31 or VE-cadherin (also known as CD144). </p>
</text>
