<text id="autogum_academic_doc671" title="Intertextuality, Christianity and Death: Major Themes in the Poetry of Stevie Smith" shortTile="intertextuality-christianity" author="Judith Woolf" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-0787/8/4/174/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>
On a mid-December morning in 1965, I went beachcombing with Stevie Smith. She had read her poems to the University of Sussex Literary Society the night before, and now she wanted seashells to take home to Avondale Road as proof that she had been to the seaside. It was my task to find the shells, few of which had survived the grinding shingle, but presently, Stevie pounced on a different kind of flotsam. Holding it up by one limp ray, she identified it in her inimitable voice: “A poor dead starfish.” She held it for just long enough to let me wonder if she was going to pop it into her shiny black bag (“and take it home to brew with” added the friend who had breakfasted with us when I told the story later) before dropping it back onto the pebbled shore. </p>

<p>Seamus Heaney famously wrote that Stevie Smith’s “own performance of her verse” prompted him to revise Auden’s definition of poetry as “memorable speech” to “memorable voice”, the “beautifully flawed plainsong” of a performer who was both Gretel and witch,1 while Calvin Bedient perceptively described her as “a fearless and therefore fearful mime”.2 Stevie Smith in performance was a mime artist in words, her sad, expressive eyes and the impeccably unexpected timing of her deadpan delivery reducing audiences to helpless laughter as she felt her way around the bars of the imagined cages, which, one way or another, imprison us all. At the height of her late-flowering fame as a performance artist, to ask Ogden Nash’s question, “Who, or what, is Stevie Smith?”3 in real earnest was to be met with astonishment, as the poet Jonathan Williams discovered:</p>
<blockquote>
I remember once picking up a copy of a faded blue book of poems from the thirties in Bertram Rota’s bookshop in Vigo Street, London. I asked Arthur Uphill, who was tending the store: so who’s Stevie Smith? “Who’s Stevie Smith?” he exclaimed, as though I had failed to recognize Queen Victoria, Dame Edith Sitwell, Gertrude Stein, Mae West, and Bette Davis all walking down Saville Row together.4</blockquote>
<p>Yet fifty years after that morning on Brighton beach, Amy Jenkins, writing in <hi rend="italic">The Guardian</hi>, gives a very different account of her final decade:</p>
<blockquote>
the patriarchy got her in the end. In later years she was overlooked—her poems dismissed as light verse—and she was denied membership of the canon. I can’t help thinking she was sidelined for having become a plain and eccentric spinster.5</blockquote>
<p>Less than six months later, critical acclaim for Will May’s 800 page edition of <hi rend="italic">The Collected Poems &amp; Drawings of Stevie Smith</hi> proved Jenkins wrong in her belief that “nowadays, Smith is only really remembered for her 1957 poem ‘Not Waving But Drowning’”; though David Orr’s description of her, in his review in <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, as “the English poet so odd that even other poets, most of whom are fairly odd themselves, have never been sure what to do with her” suggests that she may still not have found her place in the canon. However, Orr does go on to say, “she is a great poet whether or not she fits into the stories we like to tell about poets and their greatness.”6 </p>

<p>Establishing Smith’s claim to be read as indubitably a major poet, and arguably a modernist one, means moving beyond the aspect of her work represented by her most famous poem. It is all too often supposed that Smith condensed her own autobiography into the twelve short lines of <hi rend="italic">Not Waving but Drowning</hi>,7 but although the quiet desperation of little lives is certainly one of her poetic subjects, she never saw herself as among those doomed to the unenviable fate of having “no fate at all”.8 In <hi rend="italic">Novel on Yellow Paper</hi>, her alter ego Pompey Casmilus remembers the “one dreadful moment” in which Lewis Carroll’s Alice “thought she was going to be Mabel”, and tells us “that is just one thing we don’t have to worry about… There are hazards enough in life and death, but Alice can never be Mabel”,9 while the title character of Smith’s final book of poems answers the imagined question, “Are you Mrs Briggs, dear?” with the emphatic words, “No, I am Scorpion.”10 </p>
</text>
