<text id="autogum_academic_doc463" title="Why Bile Acids Are So Important in Non-Alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease (NAFLD) Progression" shortTile="bile-acids-important" author="Aline Gottlieb, Ali Canbay" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4409/8/11/1358/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Typical Ligands for Bile Acids</head>
<p>
BA targeted therapy is based on their receptors and ligands. The regulation of BAs on other pathways occurs mainly through the activation of nuclear hormone receptors (NHRs) such as the farnesoid X receptor (FXR), pregnane X receptor (PXR), and vitamin D receptor (VDR). For the activation of these receptors, it is necessary that they interact with the retinoid X receptor as a heterodimer (RXR). Afterwards, they act on various regulatory regions by binding to hormone response elements causing several genes to be up or downregulated in their transcription. Most BAs and the secondary BA, and LCA, are binding to FXR and PXR respectively. </p>

<head> 2.1. FXR</head>
<p>
FXR plays an important role in BA, glucose, and lipid metabolism. It is most highly expressed in the liver, ileum, kidneys, and adrenal glands. The strongest activator is CDCA, followed by DCA, CA, and LCA. Despite the fact that LCA is a weak activator of FXR, it is a very strong downregulator of its function and thus could be termed a partial agonist.  </p>

<p>Controlling the synthesis and enterohepatic circulation of BAs, represents the major function of FXR. In the liver, bile flow is prompted through FXR activation. After being activated through BA in the ileum, the expression of fibroblast growth factor 15/19 (FGF15/19) increases, leading to an activation of fibroblast growth factor receptor 4 (FGFR4) in hepatocytes (<figure>Figure 1</figure>). This is of great importance as FGF15/19 is an ileum-derived enterokine that governs BA homeostasis, regulates hepatic glucose metabolism, and stimulates protein synthesis. If administered pharmacologically or expressed transgenically in mice, FGF19 increases hepatic lipid oxidation, reduces lipogenesis and protects from hepatosteatosis. A lack of it causes impaired liver regeneration. A lack of FGF 15 results in increased hepatic steatosis and in the development of endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress in the liver of mice fed a high fat diet. </p>

<p>The activation of FGFR4 together with the activation of small heterodimer partner (SHP) in the liver, inhibits CYP7A1. In order to downregulate <hi rend="italic">CYP7A1,</hi> intestinal-specific FXR is required. On the other hand, the liver-specific FXR plays an important role in the repression of the expression of <hi rend="italic">CYP8B1</hi>.  </p>

<p>One of the mechanisms for BAs to suppress their own synthesis is through FXR.  </p>

<p>FXR influences the hepatic lipid homeostasis via SHP, which reduces the expression of SREBP1. It also regulates the expression of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor PPAR-α, a regulator of triglyceride metabolism, that can induce free fatty acid β-oxidation.  </p>

<head> 2.2. Takeda G-Protein-Coupled Receptor 5 (TGR5)</head>
<p>
TGR5 is a G-protein coupled membrane receptor that BAs activate. LCA is considered to be the strongest activator of TGR5 among the main primary and secondary BAs. It is widely expressed in the body, for example in the gallbladder, ileum, colon, liver (not in hepatocytes though), brown adipose tissue (BAT), nervous system, and muscle. Besides being involved in BA, glucose, and lipid metabolism, interestingly, it also plays a role in increasing the induction of <hi rend="italic">BAT</hi> expression in thermogenesis and energy release via browning of white adipose tissue and. TGR5 knockout leads to a changed BA composition and has anti-inflammatory properties by for example by inhibiting nuclear factor kappa-light-chain-enhancer of activated B cells (NF-κB) or LPS-induced production of inflammatory cytokines in macrophages. In another experiment, TGR5 knockout mice received a sleeve gastrectomy and it was shown how TGR5 is important in order to decrease hepatic steatosis, improve glucose control, and increase the energy expenditure post-surgery.  </p>
</text>
