<text id="autogum_academic_doc143" title="Culture and Tourism in Porto City Centre: Conflicts and (Im)Possible Solutions" shortTile="culture-tourism-porto" author="Inês Gusman, Pedro Chamusca, José Fernandes, Jorge Pinto" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5701/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion: The Risks of Unsustainability and the Conflicts between Culture and Tourism</head>
<p>
The analysis of the recovery strategies of the city centre of Porto and the evolution of its socio-economic dynamics evidence some conflicts that may jeopardize the sustainability of the relation between culture and tourism. This could be especially problematic if we consider the dependency that the city has on its cultural capital. This dependency is notorious, considering the importance that culture had in the process of the physical, functional and symbolic recovery of the city. Among the most important actions are: firstly, efforts made to achieve the distinction of a World Heritage Site by UNESCO in 1996; secondly, the construction of new cultural equipment and the improvements of the infrastructure, carried out through the European Capital of Culture initiative in 2001; and thirdly, using tourism, culture and leisure as development vectors for the revitalization of Porto’s city centre. In fact, according to the SRU-Porto Vivo Masterplan, Porto’s culture, based on the “city’s traditions, history and festivals, represented in their traditional form or with a greater contemporary influence”, has been essential for the renovation project of the city. As a result, together with other already mentioned measures and the strong growth of low-cost travel at the global scale, Porto is now an important urban tourist destination. As a consequence, Porto in general, and its centre in particular, is now heavily influenced by tourism in all areas. </p>

<p>The equilibrium between tourism, culture and urbanism in the city centre of Porto may be in danger because of the overuse of its touristic function and the loss of its residential function. That is precisely what the ICOMOS report of 2018 pointed out: <hi rend="italic">“</hi><hi rend="italic">Local residents and traders are expropriated, and the buildings are replaced by hotels, car parks, shops and luxury apartments, while the World Heritage Committee recommended to deal with the issue of depopulation as soon as the city integrated the World Heritage List. The population of the historic Centre of the city of Porto has decreased by more than 50% since then</hi><hi rend="italic">”</hi> (p. 22). To these warnings, we add all the collected data which show that the transformations experienced by the city of Porto are similar to those verified in many other cities that have a stake in urban recovery based on tourism and culture, and are oriented towards international markets and short-term returns. In fact, Porto’s trajectory is similar to that of Lisbon or Barcelona, for example, although the scale of what happened and the time that it took to happen are especially difficult to absorb. Likewise, in Porto, this process is highly concentrated in the centre of the city, which is the place where the major part of the tourist attractions are located. As a consequence, its residential function is becoming marginal, thus constituting, in the face of processes of speculation, gentrification and touristification, a space of conflict and claim. Consequently, the impacts also seem to be similar to those in these cities. Among the main the main damaging consequences of “over-tourism” (i.e., an overuse of the resources, infrastructure, or facilities of a destination or parts of it) are: the rising costs of living, real-estate speculation and the associated gentrification, congestion of transport infrastructure and a deterioration of the local identity. Furthermore, the evolution of the functions of the city centre, namely, the opening of short-term rentals, the changes in street trade and the expansion of the franchised retailing, seem to indicate that this place is being transformed into a place of visitor consumption. These transformations seem to be in line with what Sequera and Nofre (p. 6) described as being the “new Disneyficated commercial tourist areas”, which today characterize the most central areas of the “tourist city”. </p>

<p>In response to the problems generated by the growing mass tourism, several municipal governments are pushing for specific regulations, legislation and taxes. The most notorious have been made in the regulation of the economic activity of tourist accommodation platforms, which currently in cities such as Amsterdam and Barcelona have limitations on the time and space in which they operate. In the case of Amsterdam, the control of tourist activity has gone further, and it has recently been announced by the municipal authorities that a campaign will be launched to dissuade people from visiting certain parts of the city, having already removed one of the tourist icons of the city, the “Iamsterdam”. Another of the measures most used in several cities, recently adopted in Porto is the application of a tourist tax per person and per night, whose revenue should in principle be used to minimize the consequences of tourism growth. Additionally, in Portugal, the regulations around short-term rentals changed at the end of 2018 and regulatory powers were devolved to municipalities. Nevertheless, the municipality of Porto is being accused by some social movements and political parties of having a passive attitude regarding the problems generated by tourism—especially those which affect housing. </p>
</text>
