<text id="autogum_academic_doc543" title="Critical Dynamics Mediate Learning of New Distributed Memory Representations in Neuronal Networks" shortTile="critical-dynamics" author="Quinton  M. Skilling, Nicolette Ognjanovski, Sara  J. Aton, Michal Zochowski" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1099-4300/21/11/1043/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Phase transitions and critical phenomena are of central importance to statistical physics and there is growing evidence supporting its crucial role in living systems. Here we investigate how near critical network dynamics may recruit neurons and facilitate formation of a new distributed memory in a situation where the incoming input must compete with the already stored (native) memories for neuronal resources.  </p>

<p>It is widely hypothesized that new information is encoded in brain circuits through activity dependent, long-term synaptic structural changes that are a putative substrate for memory formation. While features of memory traces can be localized to specific cell populations (e.g., location information encoded in place cell activity), in general, tracing so-called “engrams” to neural circuits has been an elusive task. Attempts at disrupting well-established memories through brain lesions or, more recently, through optogenetic silencing have shown that they are robust to alterations in communication between individual neurons or brain areas. A parsimonious and longstanding explanation of these phenomena is that a process termed “systems consolidation” leads to diffuse, widespread memory encoding and storage. However, despite more than a century of study, it is not well understood how engrams are initially formed and subsequently stored across vast distances (in terms of numbers of synaptic connections between neurons) in the brain. </p>

<p>A major problem to understanding the mechanisms for systems consolidation is that very little is known about how the formation of new memories (i.e., learning) impacts neural network dynamics. The general, long-accepted assumption is that either strengthening of existing synaptic connections, or the de novo creation of additional synapses (i.e., formation of a discrete structural heterogeneity) leads to the formation of a dynamical attractor. If this is the case, then the dynamical state of the network must support long-range correlations across the network, as the number of neurons actively involved in encoding a specific memory trace is thought to constitute only a small fraction of the total neuronal population. Moreover, individual synapses in regions such as the hippocampus have a surprisingly brief lifetime (approximately 1–2 weeks on average), necessitating rapid dissemination and consolidation of information. These requirements raise two questions: (1) how do permanent and widely-distributed neural engrams form from initial, transient changes to a discrete subset of the network’s synapses during learning, and (2) what mediates transformation of local representations of disparate features to global memory representation? New experimental and computational work shows that theta band oscillatory patterning and/or dynamics associated with sharp wave ripples can mechanistically coordinate neuronal activity recruiting them into the representation.  </p>

<p>In this work, we show computationally that in addition to large scale temporal pattering of neuronal activity, near-critical dynamics in the brain could be an important factor in facilitating memory consolidation. Specifically, we show that storage of new information that is weakly and/or sparsely impinged on the network is mediated through plastic, state-dependent changes in network connectivity and can be successfully consolidated (which is associated with attractor formation) near criticality—a point associated with second order phase transitions. This storage is followed by a subsequent shift from critical to sub-critical dynamics.  </p>

<p>The idea that the brain operates at or near dynamical critically is not new (see References for comprehensive reviews) and it was experimentally observed in in vivo and in vitro preparations. A large body of work also investigated the potential functional benefit of operating in a near-critical regime. Here, we specifically identify very basic, underlying importance for the brain to reside near criticality and demonstrate that near-critical dynamics may be essential for a system-wide consolidation of new memories in a situation when the sensory input is weak and/or sparse in comparison with signals generated by memories native to the network (i.e., those previously stored).  </p>

<p>To substantiate these hypotheses, we analyze in vivo recordings associated with contextual fear memory (CFM) consolidation. Contextual fear conditioning (CFC) is an optimal experimental paradigm in this regard as it allows for rapid formation and consolidation of memory (i.e., after single-trial learning). In this particular case, the CFM consolidation is associated with normal sleep, which has been shown to play a vital role in various types of memory consolidation. Here, we first characterize hippocampal dynamics in mice subjected to CFC and show that: (1) the hippocampus operates in a near critical regime pre- and post-CFC training, and (2) successful, behaviorally-verified consolidation of fear memory leads to an underlying shift in hippocampal dynamics towards a subcritical state, similar to what we predict in our model simulations. </p>

<p>Together, these results indicate that novel learning may occur preferentially near a critical regime and leads to universal widespread stabilization of network activity patterns, which in turn drives the formation of widely-distributed engrams (i.e., systems memory consolidation).  </p>
</text>
