<text id="autogum_academic_doc327" title="Modeling and Assessing of Self-Reconfigurable Cleaning Robot hTetro Based on Energy Consumption" shortTile="modeling-assessing" author="Abdullah  Aamir Hayat, Parasuraman Karthikeyan, Manuel Vega-Heredia, Mohan  Rajesh Elara" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4112/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Floor cleaning in a commercial and domestic environment is usually a monotonous, tedious, and boring task, and thus robots are a viable alternative option to perform such tasks. The floor cleaning problem has attracted many researchers as it extends the focus on the problem of path planning, the design of the robot, executing autonomous motion, and area coverage in an unstructured environment. Many commercially available cleaning robots, like iRoomba, Samsung Powerbot, Bobsweep, Moneual RYDIS, Miele scout, Infinuvo Clean Mate, etc., are available with autonomy and path planning features. However, these fixed morphology robots are generally either equipped with selected modules like wet mopping, dry cleaning, autodocking for recharge and vacuum modules. Apart from this, one major factor for their performance loss is due to fixed morphology design. Their fixed physical morphology act as a constraint on the area covered in the unstructured environment where the shape, size, and location of obstacles like narrow spaces between furniture, room corners, and curved passages are unknown during navigation. </p>

<p>The design philosophy of mechanically transformable shape or self-reconfigurability is beneficial to implement in a cleaning robot to overcome the above-discussed pitfalls. Reconfigurable systems are defined as those that can reversibly attain distinct configurations or states via alternating system form or function to achieve the desired outcome within acceptable reconfiguration time, cost, and energy. The mechanism reconfigurability is classified as intra-reconfigurability and inter-reconfigurability. An intra-reconfigurable robot can be viewed as a collection of components (sensors, actuators, mechanical parts, power sources, controllers, etc.) acting as a single entity while having the ability to change, for instance, its structure, mobility, or principal activity without requiring any external assembly or disassembly. The inter-reconfigurability defines to what extent a robotic system can change its morphology through assembling and disassembling its robotic components. In, the self-reconfigurable mobile robot, called Hinged-Tetro, was conceived for the first time. It was based on the theory of hinged dissection of polyominoes as reported in and was inspired from the tile-matching puzzle video game called “Tetris”, which consists of four identical square blocks that can transform into seven shapes, therefore named as hinged-Tetro. </p>

<p>In the first reported work on hinged-Tetro, the hinged dissection of polyominoes was described in detail. Using theorems on hinged dissection in which using the lemmas it was proved that the hinged Tetromino (hTetro) can be dissected as {LLL, LLR, LRR, LRL, RLL, RLR, RRL, and RRR}. It was proved that only LLL and LLR dissection could attain all the required one-sided transformations or forms named as {I, J, L, O, S, T, Z} on the basis of shape as shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>. The one-sided polyominoes are distinct when none is a translation or rotation of another (geometry cannot be flipped over). Note that the two pairs, i.e., {L, J} and {S, Z}, of tetrominoes look very similar, but we cannot rotate one of them to get the other. In an extension of this work the nested reconfigurability and reported initial tests with hTetro-LLR without the dynamic modeling of the system. </p>

<p>In this paper, we carried out the detailed and systematic measure for the power consumption during the reconfiguration of both the architectures, i.e., hTetro-LLL and hTetro-LLR with its dynamic modeling, simulation, and experimental results. Moreover, with this study, one can understand the current consumption and behavior of hTetro reflected by the movement of each hinge motor during reconfiguration. As hTetro is designed to perform the floor cleaning task, the efficient area coverage of hTetro over the fixed morphology robots was compared. Experimentally, they observed that hTetro covered 95% of the area in a given fixed environment. </p>

<p>Functional modeling is a key step in the product design process, whether using the original or redesigns with the inductive approach. <figure>Figure 2</figure> depicts the advantages of the reconfigurable floor cleaning robot in terms of covering sharp edges, area coverage in an unknown environment. In this work, we have built the hTetro-LLL and hTetro-LLR, as shown in <figure>Figure 2</figure>b,c, respectively, with each of its block designed for higher payload using four omni-wheels. The four omni-wheels in each module will provide mechanical stability to the base along with the higher acceleration over the three omni-wheels. The pavement sweeping robot with reconfigurability and differential wheels were presented in. The matrices for analyzing the performance are, measurement of the covered area using computer vision technique and the distance covered by the cleaning robot which depends on the energy consumption. To evaluate the optimal configuration of the self-reconfigurable robot which will help to improve power management will be extremely useful for energy-efficient performance. </p>
</text>
