<text id="autogum_academic_doc416" title="Research Trends of Hydrological Drought: A Systematic Review" shortTile="research-trends-hydrological" author="Hasrul  Hazman Hasan, Siti  Fatin Mohd Razali, Nur  Shazwani Muhammad, Asmadi Ahmad" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4441/11/11/2252/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Climate change is a natural phenomenon, but the increase in greenhouse gases due to human activities, which alters the climatic system, have become triggers for more rapid changes and influences the occurrence of extreme climatic events. Climate change contributes to increased frequency of extreme weather events, such as drought. The severity of the drought is likely to increase in many parts of the world. Drought, because of its insidious nature, is generally difficult to define and explain. Droughts are recognized as a natural environmental catastrophe and have attracted multidisciplinary attention across all researcher fields. Globally, demand for water and even water scarcity has risen owing to population increase and industrial development. Other factors, such as climate change, have added to the water shortage. </p>

<p>The choice of a suitable drought characteristic for particular drought research depends on the hydro-climatology in the selected region, the type of drought regarded, the vulnerability of nature in that region, the purpose of the research study and the accessible information for the drought evaluation. Limited or lacking adequate quantifiable occurrence, frequency and severity information remains an issue in this respect. Furthermore, there is a lack of sufficient and appropriate methods for evaluating and forecasting drought. To prepare for effective risk and management of drought mitigation, it is vital to assess the conditions of drought. </p>

<p>The classification system for the drought of four types is based on the nature of water deficiency. Meteorological, hydrological and agricultural droughts are considered environmental droughts according to this classification and are defined as periods with insufficient precipitation, river flow or groundwater, and soil moisture, respectively. The fourth type of drought is socio-economic drought, which is associated with water resource systems failing to meet water demands. <figure>Figure 1</figure> presents the classification system for drought was derived from. Droughts are long-term phenomena that affect large regions and cause severe damage to human lives and economic losses.  </p>

<p>This study mainly focuses on hydrological drought. Hydrological drought is usually characterized by water loss over time from both underground and surface supplies. It usually affects water levels from average to low, making it inadequate to meet human and ecosystem requirements. Streamflow is the most crucial water quantity variable. Streamflow is the most crucial variable in quantity of water that expresses the resources of surface water. Therefore, in terms of normal conditions, a hydrological drought occurrence is linked to the streamflow deficit. </p>

<p>The assessment of hydrological drought plays an essential role in water resources management. Hydrological drought assessment is necessary because human activities depend on either surface water or groundwater resources. Data on streamflow is generally used for hydrological drought analysis. Recovery from hydrological drought is usually prolonged, considering the time it takes to recharge streams and lakes. Increased water consumption has also significantly increased the magnitude of hydrological drought by 10–50% and increased the frequency of global drought by 30%. Hydrological drought characteristics, including groundwater and streamflow, will change due to climate change in the 21st century. There will be increased duration and severity of hydrological drought and more significant impacts of events, including on groundwater and streamflow, will be evident. Therefore, there is an urgent need for the management of water resources to design proactive measures to reduce these significant issues. </p>

<p>Assessment approaches for hydrological drought can be separated into two groups. The first group consists of the characteristics of low flow and the second approach to analyse drought is to use the attributes of the deficit analysis. Most hydrological drought evaluation techniques are based on hydrological parameter analysis of the actual time series of streamflow. In comparison, the values from the measured time series are taken below a defined threshold level when determining the deficit characteristics. The drought deficit index is computed from deficit characteristics such as the duration of the deficit period and volumes of the deficit. The vulnerability of the area of interest in the risk of drought can then be assessed based on two defined indices.  </p>
</text>
