<text id="autogum_academic_doc076" title="Detection and Quantification of eDNA-Associated Bacterial Membrane Vesicles by Flow Cytometry" shortTile="detection-quantification" author="Valentina Puca, Eva Ercolino, Christian Celia, Giuseppina Bologna, Luisa Di Marzio, Gabriella Mincione, Marco Marchisio, Sebastiano Miscia, Raffaella Muraro, Paola Lanuti, Rossella Grande" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5307/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Bacterial Membrane Vesicles, which respond to the extracellular vesicles (EVs) definition criteria, are membrane structures, produced by Gram-negative, Gram-positive and Mycobacteria microorganisms during their growth. These elements are spherical in shape, with an average size in the range from 20 to 500 nm and deliver several components, such as proteins, nucleic acids, and phospholipids. It has been reported that EVs are involved in a number of physiological and pathological mechanisms, including biofilm formation, inter-cellular cross-talk, as well as bacteria–host and bacterium–phage interactions. Many studies support the hypothesis that the generation of EVs is a controlled and regulated process, although Turnbull et al. demonstrated that the EVs’ biogenesis is associated with a rearrangement of the bacterial membranes, derived from lysed cells, which incorporate soluble molecules. It is also known that EVs fuse with the outer membrane of Gram-negative cells, while they are not able to interact with Gram-positive bacteria. It was demonstrated that EVs stemming from <hi rend="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</hi> are able to interact with <hi rend="italic">Shigella flexneri</hi> pouring their content into the periplasm of eukaryotic cells; conversely, EVs derived from <hi rend="italic">P. aeruginosa</hi> adhere to the cell wall of <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</hi>. The EVs composition and content are strictly dependent on the environmental conditions where they are generated, as well as on the bacterial species from which they are produced and on their growth phase. For example, iron-limiting conditions increase the EVs production from <hi rend="italic">Helicobacter pylori</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Haemophilus influenzae</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Escherichia coli</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Vibrio cholera</hi>; the oxygen availability affects the generation of EVs and the antibiotic treatment (i.e., polymyxin B or colistin) promotes an increase of EVs production that confers protection to the bacterial cells, thus allowing their survival. A previous study, performed on <hi rend="italic">Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</hi>, demonstrated that the imipenem treatment increases the production of EVs delivering β-lactamases. </p>

<p>Modifications in terms of EVs production and content might also be associated with the growth phase, as well as with the bacterial phenotype (biofilm or planktonic) and the media composition. Park et al. demonstrated that EVs associated to the <hi rend="italic">P. aeruginosa</hi> biofilm phenotype showed a unique proteome profile, with respect to the one carried by EVs stemming from its planktonic counterpart. </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Helicobacter pylori</hi> ATCC 43629 and <hi rend="italic">Lactobacillus reuteri</hi> DSM 17938 are biofilm-producing strains, and both the planktonic and the biofilm phenotypes generate EVs (pEVs and bEVs, respectively) carrying extracellular DNA (eDNA).. In particular, <hi rend="italic">H. pylori</hi>-derived bEVs seemed to “bridge” bacterial cells, thus playing a possible structural role; however, the fact that eDNA are carried by EVs, may protect the eDNA from the enzymatic activity of DNase I in breaking up the biofilm. It cannot be dismissed that EVs produced from the biofilm phenotype may represent a shuttle for eDNA transport. </p>

<p>For all of these reasons, we aimed to optimize a simplified Polychromatic Flow Cytometry (PFC) method for a fast identification, enumeration and characterization of bacterial derived EVs, as well as for the analysis of their eDNA-associated subtypes, produced by the planktonic and the biofilm phenotypes of a Gram-negative (<hi rend="italic">H. pylori</hi> ATCC 43629) and a Gram-positive (<hi rend="italic">L. reuteri</hi> DSM 17938) bacterium. We demonstrated that PFC can be used as a tool to study the modifications of EVs production under different environmental conditions, as well as for the detection and enumeration of bacterial derived EVs, and in particular eDNA-associated EVs, in clinical samples. </p>
</text>
