<text id="autogum_academic_doc033" title="Comparison of the Effect of Perennial Energy Crops and Agricultural Crops on Weed Flora Diversity" shortTile="comparison-effect" author="Beata Feledyn-Szewczyk, Mariusz Matyka, Mariola Staniak" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4395/9/11/695/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Perennial energy crops include plant species cultivated on arable land and processed for biofuels, biocomponents, heat, or electrical power generation. The cultivation of these crops is still a relatively new agricultural practice and so little scientific evidence is available on the effects of these types of crops on the environment, including biodiversity. Areas to be considered regarding the risks and opportunities of energy crop cultivation in relation to biodiversity include: variations in soil management, requirements for fertilization and plant protection, invasiveness, crop diversity, water footprint, climate change mitigation potential, and distortion of species interactions. The influence of these plantations on flora diversity depends on the species cultivated, previous land use, agricultural practices, the age and size of the fields, and their spatial distribution in the landscape. According to Börjesson, the replacement of annual crops by perennial crops affects biodiversity at the genetic, species, and habitat levels. </p>

<p>The most common perennial lignocellulosic species cultivated for energy purposes are willow (<hi rend="italic">Salix viminalis</hi> L.), poplar (<hi rend="italic">Populus</hi> sp.), and false acacia (<hi rend="italic">Robinia pseudoacacia</hi> L.). In addition, there is growing interest in the cultivation of perennial grasses, mainly miscanthus (<hi rend="italic">Miscanthus</hi> sp.), but also other species: prairie cordgrass (<hi rend="italic">Spartina pectinata</hi> Bosc ex Link), reed canary grass (<hi rend="italic">Phalaris arundinacea</hi> L.), big bluestem (<hi rend="italic">Andropogon gerardii</hi> Vitman), and switchgrass (<hi rend="italic">Panicum virgatum</hi> L.). Another group of plants that can be used for energy purposes is the perennial dicotyledons, such as Virginia mallow (<hi rend="italic">Sida hermaphrodita</hi> (L.) Rusby) and Jerusalem artichoke (<hi rend="italic">Helianthus tuberosus</hi> L.). Energy crops differ in terms of their morphological, physiological, and agronomic characteristics, and create adverse habitats for associated flora species. The plantation management system has a significant impact on weed flora diversity, in particular the frequency and timing of energy plants’ harvesting. </p>

<p>The introduction of new perennial plants into agricultural areas for energy purposes creates habitats for various species of flora, including those threatened with extinction, and can be an alternative way of increasing biodiversity. Landscape heterogeneity is maximized by altered harvest rotations, no-till farming, and mixed crop species composition. The positive effect of energy crops on biodiversity is connected with the lower agrochemical input used as compared to the intensive production used in annual crops. </p>

<p>The findings of most research concern willow as a widespread perennial energy crop. Research conducted in Great Britain and Sweden showed that willow cultivation contributed to an increase of flora richness as compared to arable land. According to some authors, miscanthus and other perennial grasses may be a poorer habitat for flora than willow. </p>

<p>However, some authors suggest that the physical structure of the canopy, rapid growth rate, high density, chemical crop protection, and mineral fertilization caused energy crops to be not conducive to weed flora diversity. The intensity of plantation management also has a high impact on biodiversity, which in turn has an effect on plant yields, the diversification of farm crops, rural economies, the role as vegetation filters, water and soil quality, and CO2 emissions. Energy crop plantations have a greater demand for water in comparison to traditional crops, which may cause changes in habitat conditions that affect biodiversity. Biomass crops are likely to increase the biodiversity in regions with low diversity, but they could potentially have adverse effects in landscapes of high conservation value. Some of the most promising biomass crops, e.g., miscanthus, switchgrass, <hi rend="italic">Reynoutria</hi> sp., are not native to Europe and North America and so pose a risk of potential future invasions, so their spread will need to be monitored. Another problem associated with the cultivation of willow on a large scale is the possibility of the hybridization of wild <hi rend="italic">Salix</hi> clones with those introduced during cultivation. </p>

<p>Due to the unknown impact of many plant species used for energy purposes on the environment and biodiversity, there should be wide-ranging and long-term ecological monitoring conducted on these crops. According to Verdade et al., biodiversity monitoring programs are needed to aid the decision-making process concerning the conflict between the expansion of energy crops and the conservation of biodiversity. These programs should take into account comparisons with neighboring agricultural crops. Such a comparison has been done in this current study. </p>

<p>Our hypothesis was that the cultivation of perennial plants for energy purposes would promote weed flora diversity and abundance more than crop production systems on arable land. </p>

<p>Therefore, the aims of this research were: 1) to analyze the changes in the flora community after the introduction of perennial energy crops from different botanical groups onto arable land, and 2) to compare the structure of weed flora communities accompanying perennial energy crops with those in typical agricultural crops grown on arable land under different farming systems (organic, integrated, conventional, monoculture). </p>
</text>
