<text id="autogum_academic_doc617" title="Influence of Transfusion on the Risk of Acute Kidney Injury: ABO-Compatible versus ABO-Incompatible Liver Transplantation" shortTile="influence-transfusion" author="Je  Hyuk Yu, Yongsuk Kwon, Jay Kim, Seong-Mi Yang, Won  Ho Kim, Chul-Woo Jung, Kyung-Suk Suh, Kook  Hyun Lee" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/11/1785/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
The main finding of our study is that the risk of AKI rose proportionally according to the amount of pRBC and FFP transfusions in both ABO-c and ABO-i LT, but this association of pRBC and FFP transfusions with post-transplant AKI was stronger in ABO-i LT than in ABO-c LT. Given that the AKI rates increased in patients with preoperative anemia and that the influence of transfusion on AKI was more pronounced in ABO-i LT patients, any efforts to reduce perioperative transfusions may protect patients with ABO-i LT against AKI. However, as our observations were from a retrospective analysis, prospective trials are required to confirm our hypothesis. </p>

<p>Patient mortality and graft survival after ABO-i LT have been reported to be comparable to ABO-c LT, although there is still concern regarding the high incidence of antibody-mediated rejection, including biliary stricture related to a high isoagglutinin titer. This high isoagglutinin titer may provoke another major organ injury, including AKI, through an immunologic response. As AKI affects graft outcomes and mortality after liver transplantation, it is important to elucidate modifiable risk factors of AKI in ABO-i LT.  </p>

<p>The reason why AKI occurs more frequently in ABO-i LT is not certain, although the high isoagglutinin titer may play a role. A high isoagglutinin titer may lead to major organ damage through possible immunologic injury. In addition, the prevalent baseline metabolic alkalosis, low platelet count, and high incidence of mild arterial hypoxemia prior to transplantation surgery may contribute to the high incidence of intraoperative transfusion and low oxygen delivery to the kidney. Furthermore, patients with ABO-i LT already receive a substantial amount of FFP transfusion for plasma exchange prior to surgery. FFP has been reported to be a risk factor for AKI after surgery, including liver transplantation, and the risk of AKI may increase when patients with ABO-i LT receive intraoperative FFP transfusions. Furthermore, an inflammatory, allergic, and immunologic reaction triggered by FFP transfusion may be exacerbated when patients receive additional intraoperative FFP.  </p>

<p>Red cell transfusion is also a well-known risk factor of AKI after liver transplantation. The negative effect of pRBC transfusion is multifaceted and includes a systemic inflammatory response, which contributes to the development of AKI after surgery. A large amount of transfusion reflects excessive surgical bleeding, which leads to renal hypoperfusion and ischemia, resulting in poor oxygen delivery. There was a dose–response relationship between the amount of pRBC and FFP transfusion and the risk of AKI in our study. However, it is not clear why the patients undergoing ABO-i LT were more susceptible to the deleterious effects of pRBC transfusion. Possible mechanisms include that the adverse effect of pRBC transfusion may be aggravated by a high isoagglutinin titer. Although we accounted for confounding factors through propensity-score-matching and multivariable analysis, we could not adjust the isoagglutinin titer due to a lack of data. In addition, red cell transfusion is closely related to FFP transfusion. Cumulative FFP transfusion after preoperative plasma exchange could be the leading cause, and pRBC transfusion could be a simple association. </p>

<p>To reduce the transfusion amount in ABO-i LT, we could adopt a restrictive transfusion policy by decreasing the transfusion threshold. Although there is no established consensus regarding intraoperative transfusion, the pRBC transfusion threshold in our institution during liver transplantation was around 20% in hematocrit. This threshold could be lowered further depending on the baseline status of recipients or the mixed venous oxygen concentrations. Red cell transfusion during surgery could possibly be reduced by optimizing baseline hematocrit before surgery through the administration of erythropoietin. A previous randomized trial reported that a preoperative single intravenous dose of erythropoietin could reduce the transfusion amount during cardiac surgery, thereby reducing the incidence of postoperative AKI. In addition, to reduce transfusion requirements, the intraoperative use of vasopressin was reported to reduce surgical bleeding through selective splanchnic vasoconstriction and by reducing portal blood flow. </p>

<p>The incidence of AKI in our study was within the range reported in previous literature. The incidence of AKI in ABO-i LT was also similar to a previous study. The risk factors of AKI other than ABO-i LT were mostly consistent with those of the previous literature. The preoperative hemoglobin level was independently associated with post-transplant AKI. The MELD score has been consistently reported to be a predictor of AKI. Ischemic time was not identified as an independent predictor of AKI in our analysis, which could have been due to the relatively short ischemic time of LDLT. </p>
</text>
