<text id="autogum_academic_doc369" title="EMV-Compatible Offline Mobile Payment Protocol with Mutual Authentication" shortTile="emvcompatible-offline" author="Jia-Ning Luo, Ming-Hour Yang" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4611/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Credit cards have become crucial transaction tools. In 2002, the standards for EMV chip credit cards were set by international organizations such as Europay, MasterCard, and Visa. Chip credit cards contain a microprocessor for computing power and a tamper-proof space for storing encryption keys and personal information. Scholars have investigated potential methods of improving the security of EMV protocol. For example, Ruiter and Poll applied the EMV protocol to their standardized modules and used a third-party verification tool to formally analyze and validate the EMV protocol. Chen et al. proposed an improvement to the EMV key generation mechanism. Murdoch and Anderson mentioned that the EMV protocol may come under threat and thus proposed improvements for mitigating threats to the EMV protocol. Moreover, Alhothaily proposed a user-controlled multiple-condition verification method for improving security, solving the problem of a simple card verification method. </p>

<p>Contactless chip credit cards that employ near-field communication (NFC) sensing technology have gradually become mainstream. MasterCard and Visa have created contactless credit cards, namely PayPass and payWave, respectively. Because of the increasing popularity of NFC smartphones, Steffens, Cheng, and Noh et al. proposed the integration of credit cards into mobile phones. Google, Microsoft, and Apple Inc. have also implemented a mobile phone virtual credit card mechanism to replace conventional chip credit cards. Users only need an NFC smartphone with a virtual credit card to make a purchase, not needing to carry a physical chip card. </p>

<p>Numerous scholars have suggested security enhancements, analyzed smartphone NFC-based credit cards, and attempted to implement EMV credit cards on NFC smartphones to achieve convenience and security. Pasquet et al. proposed a security framework for detecting security issues with NFC smartphone credit cards (e.g., transactions may be blocked or forged, privacy protection of secure element’s SIM card owner, protection of essential transaction data, transaction application security, hardware tamper-proof protection mechanism, and protection of personal data), and verified the detection processes using detection tools. Furthermore, Paillès et al. proposed that verification messages be separately sent to both merchant and issuer, with the merchant not told the identity of consumer, but the consumer’s identity is verified by the issuer. Mainetti et al. suggested a peer-to-peer message exchange method when exchanging messages between NFC smartphones and merchants’ points of sale (POSs). Moreover, Urien and Piramuthu proposed that the secure element in an NFC phone be replaced with a cloud-based security element that provides security services to properly implement the EMV credit card protocol. </p>

<p>In addition, scholars have stated that NFC faces the following security threats: (1) NFC is a wireless transfer method in which an electromagnetic wave is received by NFC devices nearby when a message is sent; malicious users can thus eavesdrop and obtain the message. (2) A malicious user can attempt to modify the message content. (3) A malicious user can disturb the NFC-transmitted message and corrupt it, resulting in an inability of the NFC card reader to interpret the message and thus denial of service. Finally, (4) a malicious user can determine the location of a particular NFC device because the identification number of each NFC device is unique. When an EMV transaction is conducted offline (e.g., when on an airplane), the merchant is unable to confirm the validity of a virtual credit card with the issuer in a timely manner as is the case in an online transaction; malicious users can thus commit fraud. The offline risk control mechanism described in the EMV protocol cannot prevent a malicious user from committing fraud if the transaction amount is below a threshold. Some studies have attempted to increase the security of offline transactions; for instance, Blaze et al. proposed risk control mechanisms such as adding a limit to the consumption amount and usage time to users’ certificates obtained from the issuer to reduce the offline payment risk. Rivest and Shamir suggested that users first apply for a certificate that has an expiration date and credit quota from the issuer before making any transactions. A PayWord that does not exceed the credit quota is generated when an offline purchase is made. In research on PayWord, approaches have mainly been suggested that can only be used for single-merchant restrictions, but some have also been proposed for multiple merchant restrictions. </p>

<p>Yang proposed EMV-based Payment with Mutual Authentication and Risk management (EPMAR), which is suitable for both offline and online transactions. EPMAR adds mutual authentication to the original EMV protocol in a compatible manner to solve the problem that anyone can use a POS to read a card; in EPMAR, all messages are encrypted using a shared key so that a malicious user cannot determine the content even if they hack into the transaction message. However, the disadvantage of EPMAR is that the transaction amount exceeds the risk control range allowed by the credit card after multiple offline transactions. </p>
</text>
