<text id="autogum_academic_doc037" title="Virulence Factors of Meningitis-Causing Bacteria: Enabling Brain Entry across the Blood–Brain Barrier" shortTile="virulence-factors" author="Rosanna Herold, Horst Schroten, Christian Schwerk" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5393/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Roles of Bacterial Virulence Factors During Invasion Through the Barriers of the CNS</head>
<p>
To be able to enter the CNS, bacterial pathogens use several virulence factors, which are involved in the different steps of pathogenesis. Of major importance is the capsule of both gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria. The capsular polysaccharide has a protective function in bloodstream survival. However, it was observed to attenuate invasion of the BBB and BCSFB. This could result from electrostatic repulsion or from the masking of bacterial surface structures. The necessity of the capsule for the pathogens survival in the blood but simultaneous hindrance of invasion of the host’s tissues indicates a need for the regulation of capsule expression. </p>

<p>Besides the capsule, a multitude of further virulence factors are used by gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria. These include, among others, adhesins and internalins, pore-forming toxins, and factors involved in intracellular movement as well as cell-to cell spread and are summarized in <figure>Figure 2</figure>. </p>

<p>In this review, we will focus particularly on virulence factors, for which evidence for an involvement during brain entry across the blood–brain barriers has been proposed. A summary of these virulence factors for gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria is given in Table 1 at the end of this section. </p>

<head> 4.1. Gram-Positive Bacteria</head><head> 4.1.1. Listeria Monocytogenes</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</hi> (<hi rend="italic">L. monocytogenes</hi>) is a facultative intracellular gram-positive bacterium. It can traverse several physiological barriers and finally enter the brain via the BBB or BCSFB, especially in immunocompromised individuals. It is ingested through highly contaminated food by the host. Once ingested, <hi rend="italic">L. monocytogenes</hi> traverses the intestinal epithelial barrier into the lamina propria followed by dissemination of the pathogen via the lymph and blood. <hi rend="italic">L. monocytogenes</hi> has multiple target organs, including the liver and spleen, and can enter the CNS across the barriers of the brain. In addition to direct traversal of the BBB and BCSFB via the transcellular route, transportation across the BBB within leukocytes and retrograde migration within axons of cranial nerves have been described. </p>

<p><hi rend="italic">L. monocytogenes</hi> can enter non-phagocytotic cells by hijacking the host’s receptor-mediated endocytosis machinery using the zipper mechanism. The two major invasion proteins of <hi rend="italic">L. monocytogenes</hi> are internalin (InlA) and InlB, which bind to eukaryotic cell membrane members E-cadherin and tyrosine kinase receptor protein Met, respectively. These interactions induce receptor-mediated endocytosis of the pathogen. <hi rend="italic">L. monocytogenes</hi> has been demonstrated to use one or both internalins to mediate invasion of the BBB and BCSFB. A recent study has further demonstrated the importance of the bacterial surface protein InlF, showing that interaction with surface vimentin was required for an optimal colonialization of the brain. </p>

<p>The MAPK signaling cascade is activated during the invasion of <hi rend="italic">L. monocytogenes</hi>. In a model system of the BCSFB consisting of choroid plexus epithelial cells, the requirement of MAPK activation for listerial entry was demonstrated. Both extracellular signal-regulated kinases (ERK) 1 and 2 and p38 inhibition resulted in decreased bacterial invasion into this model system suggesting their involvement in the pathogens traversal of the BCSFB. </p>

<p>It was previously described that ubiquitination of E-cadherin and Met leads to the recruitment of the clathrin-mediated endocytosis machinery. This in turn results in the polymerization of the actin cytoskeleton. During this process, dynamin recruits several factors that result in two waves of actin rearrangements and subsequently result in the entry of the pathogen inside of vacuoles. Accordingly, an in vitro study using a model of the BCSFB based on HIBCPP cells, revealed that <hi rend="italic">L. monocytogenes</hi> invasion is inhibited if dynamin-mediated endocytosis is blocked. </p>

<p>Another essential virulence factor of <hi rend="italic">L. monocytogenes</hi> is the pore-forming cytolysin Listeriolysin O (LLO). Activation of the NF-κB signaling pathway by LLO was reported in the human embryonic kidney HEK-293 cell line, as well as MAPK signaling. It is secreted by <hi rend="italic">L. monocytogenes</hi> and promotes the pathogens intracellular survival. After entering the host cell, lysis of the vacuole is initiated through LLO and the bacterial phospholipases PlcA and PlcB, and followed by intracellular spread in the cytoplasm. </p>

<p>Once <hi rend="italic">L. monocytogenes</hi> has reached the cytoplasm of the host´s cells, it has been demonstrated to move around and enter neighboring cells using actin comet tails and membrane protrusions to facilitate its spread. This F-actin-based intracellular motility is dependent on the expression of another essential listerial virulence factor, ActA. </p>

<p>Activation of the NF-κB signaling pathway is, as previously described, achieved through LLO. Another mechanism involving NF-κB is its activation by InlC, which is secreted intracellularly. It can directly interact with the subunit of the IκB kinase complex, IKKα. By phosphorylating IκB, this complex is critical for the activation of NF-κB, a major regulator of innate immune response. InlC was shown to impair phosphorylation of IκB, thereby scaling down the hosts immune response, and is also involved in cell-to-cell spread.  </p>
</text>
