<text id="autogum_academic_doc726" title="Exploring the Drivers behind Self-Reported and Measured Food Wastage" shortTile="exploring-drivers" author="Efrat Elimelech, Eyal Ert, Ofira Ayalon" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5677/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Food waste reduction efforts are motivated by concerns over resource depletion, food security, economic costs, and greenhouse gas mitigation. Therefore, one of the key elements of the sustainable development goals (SDG) is targeting the food waste challenge. According to SDG 12, by 2030, per capita global food waste among consumers and retailers should be cut in half, while efforts should be put into reducing upstream food losses. Reducing food waste is also a prominent measure of emissions mitigation, as part of SDG 13, which calls to combat climate change. Moreover, cutting food waste will contribute to reducing the adverse environmental impact of waste management within cities as part of SDG 11. However, achieving these ambitious goals requires improving our knowledge on reasons behind food waste, especially among households, which are the main contributors to food wastage. Acquiring a good understanding of what drives food waste will help policy makers, scholars, and practitioners to design and share good prevention practices. However, though essential for designing prevention measures, evidence on why food waste occurs is still very limited. </p>

<p>Current studies present mixed and rather contrasting evidence regarding food waste determinants. They also rarely provide quantitative measures to indicate the effectiveness of different interventions and those that do, report only a 5% to 20% reduction in food waste generation. These rather low performances also question our understanding of what drives households to waste food. Therefore, more evidence-based research is needed. </p>

<p>A major barrier toward a comprehensive understanding of food waste drivers is the fact that most studies rely on self-reports, which are difficult to verify. More specifically, the relationship between different behaviors, attitudes, and food waste quantities has been almost exclusively explored by questionnaires, of which validity has been recently questioned. The underlying assumptions of self-reporting is that respondents (1) are able to recall specific waste events; (2) provide a proper generalization about the total produced amount; and (3) are aware of all food waste generated by other household members. However, some degree of divergence between the behaviors and attitudes of different household members exist, and therefore responses of one person may not fully reflect the household as a whole. Another critique on the use of questionnaires is that they are strongly affected by the ‘social desirability bias’, i.e., participants are prone to report on what they believe is the socially desirable behavior/attitude, which leads to biased waste estimates. Biased assessments might also be affected by a ‘self-serving bias’, the tendency to perceive oneself in a favorable manner, which leads individuals to deny responsibility for negative environmental behaviors. </p>

<p>Another limit of self-reports is that there is no common practice to assess food waste behaviors, hence, cross-study comparisons are practically unfeasible. For example, participants in Stefan et al. and Stancu et al. were asked to assess the relative amount of food waste of the total food purchases, i.e., ‘food waste proportion’, while in other studies ‘discarding frequencies’ were recorded and respondents were asked to indicate how often food is disposed (e.g., daily, weekly, never, most mealtimes). Another common practice is reporting ‘food waste amounts’, expressed by different measures (e.g., weight, cooking units, Likert scale). Other researchers chose to focus on ‘food practices’ (e.g., to what extent prevention measures are taken). </p>

<p>The concern about biased reports has led researchers to call for field work involving objective measurements. However, to the best of our knowledge, so far, only two studies exploring the relation between food waste and its proposed drivers have used an alternative approach that does not rely merely on self-reports.  </p>

<p>In the first study, Grainger et al. analyzed the Waste and Resources Action Program database. This database included statistics regarding objective amount of avoidable household food waste (the terms ‘avoidable food waste’, ‘food waste’, and ‘food wastage’ are being used alternately throughout the paper to describe edible, avoidable food discarded by households) (kg per household; measured through a physical waste survey), sociodemographic factors (gender, household age structure, household size, household composition, home ownership status, type of residence, local authority, presence of children, employment status, and socioeconomic status), and behavioral variables (meal preplanning, pre-shopping cupboard checking, preparing a shopping list, using leftovers, food storage practices, type and frequency of shopping trips, and presence of fussy eaters). Household size, the presence of fussy eaters, employment status, home ownership status, and the local authority were all identified as main drivers of food waste. Grainger et al. found no significant effect of any of the behavioral factors on measured amount of food waste. </p>
</text>
