<text id="autogum_academic_doc103" title="Integrated and Participatory Design of Sustainable Development Strategies on Multiple Governance Levels" shortTile="integrated-participatory" author="Fabian Heitmann, Johannes Halbe, Claudia Pahl-Wostl" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5931/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 6. Discussion</head>
<p>
We identified various interesting results which can inform different stakeholders on the German strategy landscape. These stakeholders are (1) the strategy development teams, (2) actors involved in strategy implementation, (3) experts, and (4) other stakeholders such as the civil society and other practitioners who are influenced by the strategies or its objectives.  </p>

<p>When reviewing the German SDS, it becomes obvious that the central topics, for which specified measures were defined, are linked to the SDGs. We found however, that the SDGs do not represent most of the connecting variables based on the interviews. Our hypothesis is that they have been designed as a guiding framework on a global and national level and are originally not steered towards lower levels such as cities. Whereas the German sustainability agenda may provide helpful guidance to establish and implement a German Agenda 2030, the connection of the national directive to the urban level is still rather unspecific. Various themes could provide a basis for cooperation between state and city actors. For example, innovativeness, which is described as important by our interviewees for promoting new heat sources and for improving the technical potential of solar energy, has the potential to be a guiding topic for cooperation across governance levels. This can be achieved by coordinating the low-level requirements of urban actors with the high-level requirements of governmental actors. The actual political agenda could be designed in a way that it fulfils the needs of urban actors and, at the same time, the strategic requirements on the governance level.  </p>

<p>Although exploratory, we can draw some first insights from our case study.  </p>

<p>Whereas the literature review provided a good starting point for us to understand the situation, and to approach the correct experts for the interviews, the interviews were necessary to get more detailed and “hands-on” knowledge on the specific regional settings in Hamburg and Berlin.  </p>

<p>All in all, we identified a strong dependency of the national strategy on the success of the urban strategies. Especially, the development and implementation of decentralized renewable energy sources such as CHP (combined heat and power) have been done by urban actors, such as municipal utilities, private energy suppliers, or innovative projects such as the NEW 4.0 project in Hamburg. However, financial support for these projects is often provided by the national ministries such as the Federal Ministry of Economics and Energy. Based on individual regional settings, the requirements of the cities are very different. Cities “demand” different functions and policy changes which lead to various implications for the implementation of the respective SDS. </p>

<p>Therefore, our findings strongly support the view that systematic and holistic approaches are important to consider for strategy development and communication across different strategies. Particularly in Germany, the federal governance system implies a multi-level policy system, where coordination across governance levels may be challenging. Participatory modeling can support this process by linking different viewpoints on these levels and building a foundation for learning and understanding different actor objectives. In addition, our methodology can help to report results from the process to the participating actors as well as inform the debate on strategy analysis while considering multiple inherent actor roles. We therefore advise policy makers of cities and on the national level, as well as responsible experts, to focus on shared key-requirements for strategy implementation and to collaboratively design holistic solutions.  </p>

<p>During our interviews, we experienced that, with respect to our research approach, the interest for interactive, easy-to-use and structured participatory methods was very high. We responded to this need by developing and applying an enhanced participatory modeling method which combines elements from causal-loop modeling and requirements engineering. Regarding the study content, participating experts were most interested in our goal to describe multi-level government systems and strategy documents in terms of requirements based upon the individual viewpoints and objectives of actors who have a role in implementing the strategy (actor/user requirements). Thus, we found ourselves in the trade-off of structuring the interviews according to the requirements engineering literature, while not limiting the ability of stakeholders to provide their personal viewpoint in an open way. Therefore, we first introduced all interview partners to our set of different variable types, started the interviews by formulating objectives and measures together with the experts, and then derived requirements, followed by formulation of constraints, actors, objectives, and other variables. Future research might explore if the introduced variable types are sufficient to model the complexity of our type of systems. Although it was helpful to conduct most of the individual interviews face-to-face, it would be less time consuming to use an online platform for data collection. It might be considered to further develop and enhance such tools (i.e., to develop business models such as workshop formats), which also should incorporate helpful methodological guidance for the interviewee and moderators.  </p>
</text>
