<text id="autogum_academic_doc169" title="Crack Propagation and Effect of Mixed Oxides on TGO Growth in Thick La–Gd–YSZ Thermal Barrier Coating" shortTile="crack-propagation" author="Savisha Mahalingam, Salmi Mohd Yunus, Abreeza Manap, Nurfanizan  Mohd Afandi, Rabiatul  A. Zainuddin, Nurul  F. Kadir" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2079-6412/9/11/719/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Thermally sprayed coatings are often used to protect metallic components that suffer breakdown from wear, corrosion or excessive heat load during service in thermally drastic environments. These coatings are widely used as a thermal barrier coating (TBC) applied on gas turbines and also in the aeronautical and automotive industries. Performance of gas turbines is enhanced significantly by reducing the cooling or increasing the gas temperature during service. Hence, a thick protection layer of top-coat (TC) for TBC is able to drop the temperature by up to 170 °C in a gas turbine system. The low-thermal conductivity in TBC causes low heat transfer from TC and achieves effective cooling and reduces the surface temperature. A thickness of above 0.25 mm is considered as thick TC. </p>

<p>However, there is a trade-off between low substrate distress and high TBC distress. Thick TC promotes low substrate temperature on a big scale and prolongs substrate life. At the same time, thicker TC may increase surface temperature during operation and exceeds the ceramic materials limit at elevated temperatures, owing to the excessive growth of thermally grown oxide (TGO) at the interface of the TC/bond coat and leading to detached TC from the bond coat (BC). In addition to that, conventional, partially yttria stabilized zirconia (YSZ) TC has limited phase stability, reducing the high-temperature capability leading to TBC early failure. Therefore, TC and BC are identified as important constituents in developing an effective TBC.  </p>

<p>These shortcomings have initiated plenty of research on alternate ceramics to YSZ. In particular, doping with rare earth zirconates in TC was found to control porosity and improve the microstructure. Lanthanum (La) is a rare earth material which has been introduced as dopant in the TC shows a stable phase up to its melting temperature of 2295 ± 10 °C. Mauer et al. reported that La2O3∙ZrO2 is best processed by atmospheric plasma spraying (APS) at a low power, where it exhibited high durability due to the high fusion enthalpy of ~350 kJ mol−1 of La2O3. Composition of La and gadolinium (Gd) shows great promise for TBC materials with low thermal conductivity, low sintering rate and high thermal stability reaching around the melting point (2300 °C). Besides that, rare earth phosphates such as LaPO4 in TC reported by Zhang et al. are highly resistant to corrosion and possessed only a little detrimental effect on the coating microstructure. </p>

<p>BC is the most vital constituent in TBC as it strengthens the adhesion of the TC to the substrate and acts as an oxidation and corrosion barrier to the superalloy. At elevated temperatures, oxygen diffusion from TC towards BC through micro-cracks inside the TC oxidizes the BC and forms an oxidized scale known as TGO. TGO plays an important role in spallation and the lifetime of TBC. It acts as a diffusion barrier to suppress the growth of other detrimental oxides during further oxidation in service if a continuous scale of Al2O3 is formed on the BC. However, if an inconsistent layer of TGO was grown on the BC, a cluster of oxides such as chromia ((Cr,Al)2O3), spinel (Ni(Cr,Al)2O4) and nickel oxide (NiO) may grow along with it, leading to TBC failure. This is due to the separation of the ceramic TC from the substrate. The deposition method of MCrAlY on the BC is outlined as the main reason behind the TBC failure.  </p>

<p>MCrAlY coatings are typically deposited by electron beam physical vapor deposition, air plasma spray (APS) and high-velocity oxygen fuel (HVOF). Li et al. stated that the durability of TBC can be improved by changing the microstructure in the BC. Greater thickness in TGO of the traditional APS-BC was observed due to the presence of mixed oxides such as chromia, spinel and nickel oxide. The results revealed that these mixed oxides deteriorate the durability of TBCs. They also mentioned that the critical thickness of TGO corresponding to the change of failure mode is around 5–6 µm. Moreover, strength difference (compression and tension) in TBC was studied in the previous literature. The strength difference property was defined as the significant difference between compressions and tensile strengths. They mentioned that TGO thickening generates compressive growth stress and weakens the out-of-plane displacement of the TGO layer. Meanwhile, the tensile stress was distributed at the TC valley and BC peak regions, which is near the interface defects. </p>

<p>However, despite the HVOF technique being costly, it has high adherence and corrosion resistance with a continuous growth of the Al2O3 layer. Thus, HVOF coating is dense, adherent and contains less oxide with fewer voids and considerably reduces the penetration of oxygen into the TBC from the existing micro-cracks at elevated temperatures. That the BC deposition technique has a strong influence in producing an efficient TBC system is speculated.  </p>
</text>
