<text id="autogum_academic_doc461" title="Numerical Investigation on the Effects of Dielectric Barrier on a Nanosecond Pulsed Surface Dielectric Barrier Discharge" shortTile="numerical-investigation" author="Shen Zhang, Zhenli Chen, Binqian Zhang, Yingchun Chen" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1420-3049/24/21/3933/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Effects of Dielectric Barrier</head>
<p>
In practical applications, the dielectric barrier can be changed to optimize the performance of the NS-DBD actuators. The dielectric material, thickness, length, surface roughness, and arrangement of the dielectric barrier vary differently. According to the previous studies, the dielectric material and thickness have strong effects on the discharge characteristics. The main properties of dielectric materials are dielectric constant, thermal conductivity, electric volume resistivity, and specific heat. In the present work, the effects of dielectric materials are studied by changing the dielectric constant, as in the previous studies. As a result, the effects of the dielectric constant () and dielectric barrier thickness () are investigated in the following. </p>

<head> 3.1. Effects of Dielectric Constant</head>
<p>
The effects of dielectric constant on the electric characteristics, the streamer morphology, and discharge energy have been studied experimentally and numerically in the past studies. However, the effects on the electrical characteristics, surface charge, streamer morphology, discharge energy, and gas heating have not been investigated systematically. Here, the effects of  are investigated. </p>

<head> 3.1.1. Plasma Characteristics and Current</head>
<p>
Because the electric strength, electron temperature, and the electron density are the key plasma parameters, the effects of  on , , and  are summarized and shown in <figure>Figure 2</figure>. The values are averaged in time over one pulse, and, in space, over the streamer area, as the ones in the past similar study.  increases with increasing . This is because a higher dielectric constant leads to stronger polarization of the dielectric material; with more charge inside the dielectric barrier, the capacitance also increases, a greater voltage difference between the dielectric and the exposed electrode is obtained. The electric field strength increases. As a result, the electron density and electron temperature also increase with increasing dielectric constant. </p>

<p>The effects of  on the currents are shown in <figure>Figure 3</figure>. The current in the experiment has not been given, Therefore, there is no direct comparison between the results of simulation and the experiment. In the previous studies, the simulated currents were compared with experimental and simulation results in detail for different voltage pulses, which validated the present methods. In the voltage-rise phase, the discharge occurs and extinguishes before the applied voltage reaches its peak. The currents have two spikes, and the two spikes are also observed in previous NS-DBD discharges. The first spike is due to the wave ionization in the streamer propagation and displacement current, which increase with increasing . The second spike is caused by the repeated re-ignition on the plasma area covered previously by the streamer, which is mainly determined by the capacitance of the dielectric barrier, and it also increases with increasing . After the second spike, the current decreases and then increases reversely during the voltage-fall phase due to the ignition of a reverse discharge. The currents in the reverse discharge in the fall phase also increase with increasing  because of the increase of the electric field strength. </p>

<p>According to a past numerical investigation, the electric current increases from 50–100 A/cm to 150–200 A/cm, when  increases from 16 to 80. In another experiment investigation, the current also increases when the dielectric material is changed from glass () to ceramics (). In addition, the average electric field, electron density and electron temperature increase with  increases from 5 to 25 in a similar experimental study on packed bed plasma reactors. Therefore, the effects of  on the plasma parameters and current in the present study are the same to the ones in the past investigations. </p>

<head> 3.1.2. Surface Charge</head>
<p>
First, to investigate the effects of  on the charge on the wall surface, the distributions of the densities of electrons, ions, and the charge in the base case (Case 1) are analyzed. The distributions of , , and  at different times in the rise phase are shown in <figure>Figure 4</figure>a–c, respectively. Due to the ionization in the streamer and the charge accumulation on the dielectric surface, , , and  increase on the dielectric surface (from 10 mm to 15 mm). In the rise phase of the forward discharge, the direction of the horizontal electric field points from the exposed electrode to the dielectric surface. Because  drifts along the electric field, but the electrons and  drift against the electric field,  on the dielectric surface is higher than the one on the surface of the exposed electrode (from 5 mm to 10 mm). However,  and  on the dielectric surface are lower than the ones on the surface of the exposed electrode. Because there is nearly no charge accumulation on surface of the metal electrode, , , and  change little on the surface of the exposed electrode. </p>
</text>
