<text id="autogum_academic_doc007" title="Computer-Aided Strategies for Determining the Amino Acid Composition of Medium for Chinese Hamster Ovary Cell-Based Biomanufacturing Platforms" shortTile="computeraided-strategies" author="Bergthor Traustason, Matthew Cheeks, Duygu Dikicioglu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5464/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Brief Overview of the Established Practice in Determining the Amino Acid Composition of the CHO Cell Medium</head>
<p>
Reports on improving the culture medium composition for CHO cells, specifically in relation to the amino acids, are relatively limited in number. This paucity of reports is strikingly unusual especially considering the widespread use and vast economic importance of CHO cells. </p>

<head> 2.1. Statistical Methods: Utilizing Data-Driven Models in Experimental Design</head>
<p>
Statistical design, also known as design-of-experiments, is arguably the most commonly employed strategy for medium development. Unfortunately most such studies for CHO cells focus on components such as those relevant for the carbon and energy metabolism with only a limited number of studies specifically addressing amino acids. In line with this observation for statistical methodologies, search heuristics such as genetic algorithms commonly employed in medium development and optimization in various organisms have not been utilized for improving CHO cell medium compositions, even the chemically defined cell-free formulations. </p>

<p>Low glutamine and high essential amino acid concentrations led to high mAb production against Botulinum A by CHO cells. An amino acid other than glutamine (analytically uncharacterized) was identified as the limiting component in a study that employed response surface methodology to evaluate medium-associated effects on viable cell density (as a proxy for mAb concentration) during coupled production and growth. </p>

<p>González et al. used the Plackett-Burman design method to optimize the contribution of ten amino acids to the rate of growth and monoclonal antibody production by Chinese hamster ovary cells. These 10 amino acids were specifically identified as per their superior uptake and utilization by the CHO cell metabolism. The analysis was carried out both during exponential phase of growth through monitoring how the specific growth rate and the concentration of the viable cell concentration evolved over time, and during the phase where the cell population reached a very high density, through monitoring of the final monoclonal antibody product concentration and the specific productivity of the cell population. This investigation aimed to determine which among the ten amino acids were critical for supporting health growth of the population and product formation. In return, this information could be utilized for designing an amino acid supplementation regime, through which a superior culture could be achieved through medium improvements. The authors proposed a two-stage strategy for providing the cells with the key amino acids. One stage focused on achieving a healthy cell culture through focusing on growth optimization, and a second stage which optimizes product formation once a large cell population has been achieved. </p>

<p>More recently, Torkashvand et al. used the Plackett-Burman design to screen the effects of amino acids on promoting growth, and then optimized the medium concentrations of a combination of amino acids using response surface methodology to determine the feed composition. </p>

<p>Although statistics were employed in these studies, it would be very difficult to extract learning as to the nature of the potential benefits of employing different design approaches since these investigations focused on the empirical aspects of the study rather than providing an in-depth evaluation of the statistical tools employed. Consequently, they fail to compare and contrast different methods and provide reasoning for the selection of certain models over others, or point towards the utilization of favorable statistical designs, which could prove invaluable to attain systematic medium development strategies. </p>

<head> 2.2. Metabolic Profiling</head>
<p>
Another method widely used in the industry to understand the impact of amino acid composition on mAb production is exo- and endo-metabolic profiling. Such methods are purely empirical and are mainly utilized to improve an established platform process, by suggesting specific nutrients to be added during the course of a cultivation, for example, rather than to conduct a broad de novo exploration. </p>
</text>
