<text id="autogum_academic_doc692" title="Development of Value Creation Drivers for Sustainable Design of Green Buildings in Saudi Arabia" shortTile="development-value" author="Wael Alattyih, Husnain Haider, Halim Boussabaine" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5867/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Modern construction works, such as green buildings, with increasing complexity and immensity involve a wide range of stakeholders, such as consultants, contractors, material suppliers, general public, governmental institutions, etc. Coordinating all of these parties simultaneously in the execution of a construction project is a big challenge. Value management helps to improve communication between the project’s parties, accommodate mutual understanding of the project objectives, provide better quality project definition, build innovation, and eliminate unnecessary cost. Value can be understood in a multitude of dimensions through economic, cultural, and social interpretations. The whole-life-cycle value exchange mechanisms are risky, complex, might have an effect on adding value, and are composed of value exchange and value creation (VC). Therefore, detailed investigations focusing on finding mechanisms for achieving sustainability targets over the entire life cycle of a project is required. </p>

<p>Globally, the construction industry has been showing greater interest in sustainable green buildings since the last few years. Although, the primary benefits that were obtained from sustainable development have been defined in several manners, their financial impacts are alike, including sustainable VC and premium profits. Value management aims to achieve the desired value with lower prices without compromising the quality and function of the building. Experience of several organization revealed that implementing green building initiatives by simply evaluating the existing processes efficiency reduced wastes, improved drives, and saved money. Lützkendorf and Lorenz identified several direct and indirect benefits for investors and other stakeholders, of applying value creation assessment for green buildings, such as: (i) drastic reduction in the operational cost and an increase in marketability, (ii) increase in useful life-spans, (iii) more stable cash flows, (iv) reduced exposure to increasingly stringent environmental legislation, and (v) significantly increased occupant productivity and well-being. Presently, the building sector in Saudi Arabia is also aiming to attain the advantages like the developed countries that have already benefited from the use of green buildings. Therefore, there is a need to set up a framework for improving the creation of value during the building development stage in Saudi Arabia by integrating value with project management. </p>

<p>It has been widely recognized that all of the projects have opportunities for improved VC. The primary aim of value engineering is to deliver quantifiable improvements in the value by reducing the cost, getting better quality, and improving the design features of the building for the customer. It is a systematic process to gather a team of multidisciplinary professionals with experience in the construction industry to perform functional analysis of a system for providing the best value to the owner.  </p>

<p>Improving the VC in a green building development project by improving the function longevity and operation and maintenance costs enhances the performance reliability, quality, safety, life-cycle cost, and brings additional revenue to the building owner. Kelly and Duerk suggested that the client’s value system, comprising of seven elements: time, capital expenditure cost (CAPEX), operating expenditure cost (OPEX), environment, exchange, esteem, and fitness of purpose, should be considered in the construction project. They go on to suggest that measuring and optimising an asset’s performance involves economic performance (to obtain value for money), functional performance (to be fit for purpose such as appropriate in size and form), physical performance (concerns about the efficiency of the asset’s operation and maintenance), and service performance (to achieve a satisfactory working environment for the occupants and satisfaction regarding quality from the client’s perspective). Arena believed that VC drives improving a company’s performance. The nonfinancial performance indicators—which are time (to deliver, to develop, to market), quality, flexibility (respond to change, expansion), productivity, environment and sustainability, plus social responsibility—guide a company in predicting the VC and measure both revenue drivers and cost drivers. Identifying the performance variables in value management is necessary for appraising the client about the project value creation.  </p>

<p>The Construction Industry Council (United Kingdom) has produced design quality indicators to evaluate and measure the design quality and the value obtained, including functionality, build quality, and impact within the project context of finance, time, and environment resources (natural and human). Kelly described the performance variables for a client’s VC system as nine non-correlated performance variables, which are: CAPEX, OPEX, time, esteem, environment, exchange, politics/community, and the use value, which is composed of flexibility and comfort.  </p>

<p>The tangible value of the initiatives is hard to assess in green buildings, but improved productivity is certainly a valuable factor. Even a minor improvement in productivity leading to the corresponding increase in firm value would make more green building initiatives worth the investment. Although several tools have been developed to assess the environmental performance of a green building, disconnect between the design community and the investment community still exists on the tangibility of VC over the short, medium, or long-term. Conducting value analysis can identify project development contextual issues and thus provide opportunities for optimising the design and operation of the green building asset during early stages of the development. </p>
</text>
