<text id="autogum_academic_doc345" title="A Low-Cost, Multi-Sensor System to Monitor Temporary Stream Dynamics in Mountainous Headwater Catchments" shortTile="lowcost-multisensor" author="Rick  S. Assendelft, H.J.  Ilja van Meerveld" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/19/21/4645/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion</head><head> 5.1. Microcontroller Board and Data Logger Shield Combination</head>
<p>
The microcontroller board and data logger shield combination was chosen over the conventional, off-the-shelf data loggers that were used in previous temporary stream monitoring studies. Unlike the conventional loggers, the microcontroller board and data logger shield combination can be custom programmed, which enables a wider range of data logging possibilities. While for this study the microcontroller board and data logger combination was programmed as an interval logger, for future studies it could also be programmed as a state or event logger (the interrupt pins on the microcontroller board can be used for state and event logging). For interval logging, custom programming offers infinite possibilities for the length of the logging interval. Furthermore, the interval can be programmed to be longer or shorter for specified times, (e.g., during base or storm flow) or to increase or decrease in length over time (e.g., during the rising and falling limbs of the hydrograph). For state logging, custom programming offers the possibility to assign custom state change thresholds, rather than having to work with pre-programmed thresholds (which is the case for most conventional loggers). Another advantage of the microcontroller board and data logger shield combination is the memory flexibility of the data logger shield. Conventional loggers often make use of built-in memory to store data, which is difficult to modify. The data logger shield, on the other hand, saves the data on an exchangeable SD-card. This allows the memory size to be adjusted based on the needs of the user. Finally, the microcontroller board and data logger shield combination is cheaper than commercial loggers. Not only is the combined price of a microcontroller board and data logger shield lower, but the microcontroller board also offers more connections for sensors, thus lowering the costs per sensor. The overall reduced costs per monitoring setup allows for higher spatial resolution monitoring. </p>

<p>The interval logging approach used in this study was chosen over a state logging approach as was used in several previous temporary stream monitoring studies. The advantage of interval logging over state logging is that the first enables logging of raw sensor data. The availability of the raw sensor data allowed for data cleaning and defining catchment specific conversion filters prior to converting the data into state data. This improved the quality of the state data. In addition to that, the raw sensor data in combination with the state data helped to better assess the type of errors committed by the sensor. Bhamjee and Lindsay (2011) argued that a state logging approach is preferable to an interval logging approach for temporary stream monitoring because the latter would quickly reduce memory capacity when measuring at short intervals. However, because the data logger shield allows the memory size to be adjusted, this was not an issue.  </p>

<p>The results of the field tests show that the microcontroller board and data logger shield combination was reliable, with close to no data logging failures. The 1.9% failed data logs for the 2016 field season were attributed to a single microcontroller board and data logger shield combination, which for unknown reasons stopped logging data for eight days in the middle of the field season and then continued to work again. There were no failures for the other microcontroller boards and data logger shield combinations. The RTC drift, on the other hand, was considerable. The average RTC drift for both field seasons was more than three times higher than the average clock drift measured for commercial pressure transducers in a study by Rau et al. (2019). Accumulating RTC drift over a relatively long period could be problematic when comparing the sensor data to data from other instruments with significantly smaller clock drifts. During the field tests, the RTCs were reset every month or two. For a period of this order, the amount of RTC drift was less than the logging interval time, which was considered acceptable. If, for a future project, regular resetting of the RTC is not an option, then it could be worth it to invest in a better RTC. </p>

<p>As the data storage setup allowed for years of storage, it was not required to go to the field frequently to collect the sensor data. However, to further simplify data collection and allow the ability to collect real-time data, the next step would be to add a module to the multi-sensor monitoring system that enables wireless data transmission. Such a module was not included in the current setup of the monitoring system because it would have significantly increased the power consumption and costs of the monitoring system. Furthermore, the limited reception in the study catchment would have been an issue for optimal data transfer. However, new developments in wireless technology will improve the power consumption, reception and costs of these modules, making it more practical and cost-effective to include them in future setups. </p>
</text>
