<text id="autogum_academic_doc458" title="Metabolomic Analysis of Influenza A Virus A/WSN/1933 (H1N1) Infected A549 Cells during First Cycle of Viral Replication" shortTile="metabolomic-analysis" author="Xiaodong Tian, Kun Zhang, Jie Min, Can Chen, Ying Cao, Chan Ding, Wenjun Liu, Jing Li" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4915/11/11/1007/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Influenza A virus (IAV), a member of the Orthomyxoviridae family, is a negative-sense, single-stranded, enveloped, segmented RNA virus. IAV usually infects epithelial cells of the upper and lower respiratory tracts, including the nasal mucosa, trachea, and lungs, with no evident symptoms during the early phase of infection. Once an influenza virus invasion occurs, innate immunity is activated, and interferons are secreted by host cells to limit the early viral proliferation. Then, adaptive immunity is activated by other cytokines produced during viral infection. However, in some cases, highly pathogenic influenza viruses induce cytokine storms, a consequence of excessive production of cytokines and interferon, resulting in infections and even death. </p>

<p>To facilitate virus replication in the host cells, IAV has evolved strategies to block the innate and adaptive immune responses of the host cells and seize organelles from host cells to synthesize a large number of metabolites required for viral reproduction, as well as energy for the packaging of the virus. Enveloped, non-enveloped, DNA and RNA viruses share lipid metabolites in their replication cycles to induce the formation of new cytoplasmic membrane structures, which contribute to the replication and packaging of the viral genome. Lipid metabolism also can block the innate immune response of host cells to ensure the large-scale replication of the virus. Therefore, IAV infection is linked closely to metabolism, and the proliferation of the virus also is inseparable from the host metabolism. This changing trend in small molecule metabolites may serve as a characterization of host–pathogen interactions to monitor immune status. </p>

<p>Although significant progress has been made toward an anti-influenza virus drug discovery, including M2 ion channel blockers, neuraminidase inhibitors, and polymerase inhibitors, challenges posed by drug toxicity and viruses with genetic resistance remain a serious problem. Previous research demonstrated the metabolic effects of influenza virus infection in Madin–Darby canine kidney (MDCK) cells, displaying the intra- and extra-cellular metabolite profiling upon IAV infection. Little is known, however, about the systemic metabolic dynamics during the early stage of virus infection. During our study, we analyze changes in metabolism upon influenza virus infection in human cells during the first infectious cycle via metabolomics. Early metabolite analysis will throw new light on the activation of the innate immune metabolism. We believe that the results of this work will elucidate the activation of innate immunity to viral infection from the perspective of the host and provide new control strategies for the development of novel drugs and the treatment and prevention of influenza virus infection. </p>
</text>
