<text id="autogum_academic_doc706" title="A Bibliometric Review of the Knowledge Base for Innovation in Sustainable Development" shortTile="bibliometric-review" author="Ronald Vatananan-Thesenvitz, Amaury-Alexandre Schaller, Randall Shannon" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/20/5783/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Discussion</head>
<p>
In this review we used science mapping to uncover influential authors, articles, and journals on ISD, as well as to reveal the origin of the knowledge base and enhance our understanding of the intellectual structure of the research field. We employed bibliometric analysis and considered 1690 SCOPUS-indexed articles published between 1985 and 2018. The next two sections give an overview of the limitations of the review and propose our understanding of the findings. </p>

<head> 5.1. Interpretation and Implications of the Findings</head>
<p>
Interestingly, the combined term ‘Circular Economy’ did not emerge in the keyword analysis. The similarities and differences between the two terminologies Circular Economy and sustainability are not clear and indefinite. </p>

<p>The knowledge base started to appear in the academic sphere around 1985, but it was not until 2015 that the interest in this topic took off, where a high increase of publications can be noted. The greater interest may be due to the higher mediatization of the general bad development the earth takes and on the recent release of the SDGs by the United Nations. A future growth of this research field can be thus expected, where solutions to diverse development issues will be proposed, i.e., ocean cleaning, combating pollution through e-mobility. </p>

<p>The paucity of works from African countries as well as from the Middle East is on the first sight not explainable with the data at hand and the software package we used. However, an explanation might be given by the fact that they have in relative terms fewer academic institutions than developed societies. The temporal map shows increasing numbers of publications coming from Asia, a trend which is likely to continue. </p>

<p>Furthermore, we can deduct from the analysis that a high interest in the last couple of years around innovation in sustainability emerged and that Anglo-American societies contributed the most to the knowledge base. A high interest in this topic resides in the developed countries, in contrast to the underdeveloped countries, which might be affected most by the outcome of the application of the SDGs, yet thus far, exhibit less attention. </p>

<p>Innovation in general, but also innovation in the context of sustainable development affects many parts of human life and should thus be treated with more concern. The keyword co-occurrence analysis (<figure>Figure 9</figure> and <figure>Figure 10</figure>) covers the three dimensions of sustainable development: Economic, social, and environmental. This also mirrors the SDGs by the United Nations, where goals eight and nine represent the economic dimension, goals four, five, and 16 the social dimension, and goals six, seven, 12, 13, 14, and 15 the environmental dimension. The dimension ‘environmental’ was also recognized as the basis of sustainable development in the keyword co-occurrence network. The topical foci of ISD given by the temporal overlay on the keyword co-occurrence map also reflects the resonance of the report by the United Nations about sustainable development. Therefore, it is safe to say that the keyword analysis also represents the three dimensions of sustainable development. What is striking is that most keywords also occur in the United Nations report ‘<hi rend="italic">Transforming our World: The Agenda for Sustainable Development</hi>’ (e.g., developing countries, world, economic growth, environmental policy, education, renewable energy, technological development, climate change, industrial development, global warming, ecosystem). It seems that the research front is in alignment with the SDGs, and that innovation, especially linked to sustainable development, has great potential to accelerate human progress. According to Sachs, the pressure to take action is on a global as well as on local levels, and that different earth systems such as the carbon, nitrogen, and water cycles are affected. As an example, point 44 of the United Nations report can be reviewed. It states that,</p>
<blockquote> “We acknowledge the importance for international financial institutions to support, in line with their mandates, the policy space of each country, in particular developing countries.”</blockquote>
<p>
This phrase highlights the importance of the collaboration with financial institutions, and thus the potential investments, in order to achieve an improvement in the condition of life for individuals in developing countries. ‘Investment’ and ‘developing countries’ are also identified as keywords (see above) by the temporal overlay keyword co-occurrence map with a recent high interest. In alignment with the keyword ‘planning’ this makes sense and calls for planned and coordinated actions for environmental protection, and more general for sustainable development. </p>

<p>Goal nine needs to be highlighted in the context of innovation. This goal states that the objective by the United Nations is to “promote inclusive and sustainable industrialization and foster innovation” (p. 17). The importance of innovation to reach sustainable development is also recognized by Ashford and Hall, as well as in the keyword co-occurrence map. Therefore, innovation plays a major role for the direction of sustainable development. </p>
</text>
