<text id="autogum_academic_doc065" title="Transcriptional Regulation of Autophagy Genes via Stage-Specific Activation of CEBPB and PPARG during Adipogenesis: A Systematic Study Using Public Gene Expression and Transcription Factor Binding Datasets" shortTile="transcriptional-regulation" author="Mahmoud Ahmed, Trang  Huyen Lai, Jin  Seok Hwang, Sahib Zada, Trang  Minh Pham, Deok  Ryong Kim" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2073-4409/8/11/1321/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Autophagy, a self-eating process, is involved in the development and the differentiation of various cell types including the adipocyte. Autophagy contributes to the adipocyte differentiation by reorganizing the intracellular components, forming the fat droplets and/or providing the energy source for the development of the phenotype. Therefore, the knockdown of essential autophagy genes prevents the adipocyte differentiation and intervenes in the lipid accumulation within adipogenic cells. The adipocyte differentiation is a well-understood process. A well defined transcriptional program is initiated and maintained by specific transcription factors. The 3T3-L1 mouse fibroblast is a key model for studying this process. When the pre-adipocyte is induced with a chemical cocktail containing MDI (1-Methyl-3-isobutylxanthine, Dexamethasone, and Insulin), the cell witnesses morphological and metabolic changes and is finally transformed into mature adipocyte. </p>

<p>Several studies reported functional links between the adipogenic factors and key autophagy genes. For example, the transcription factor CCAAT enhancer-binding protein beta (CEBPB) controls the expression of the autophagy-related 4b cysteine peptidase (<hi rend="italic">Atg4b</hi>). A recent study suggested that peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma (PPARG) regulates autophagy through NEDD4 E3 ubiquitin protein ligase (NEDD4) gene expression in thiazolidinediones-treated HepG2 cells. Forkhead box o1 (FOXO1) regulates autophagy induction and it also negatively regulates Pparg, the master adipogenic factor. Indeed, the inhibition of FOXO1 is thus necessary for the differentiation to proceed. In a previous study from our laboratory, we reported the progressive activation of the <hi rend="italic">Foxo1</hi> gene during the course of differentiation, to reach the highest expression in the mature adipocytes. In addition, we identified a large number of differentially expressed autophagy genes between differentiated and undifferentiated adipocytes. The changes in gene expression were clustered into several groups that corresponded to the known stages of adipocyte differentiation. Therefore, the regulation of autophagy during the course of the differentiation seems to be more dynamic and stage-dependant. Only a few examples of direct and indirect regulation of autophagy genes have been studied. </p>

<p>We hypothesize that the autophagy process may be regulated by the same adipogenic factors either directly or indirectly through specific autophagy transcription factors. To investigate this hypothesis, we modeled the gene expression and transcription factors and co-factors binding at different stages of adipocyte maturation (<figure>Figure 1</figure>). Then, we studied the direct regulatory links between the adipogenic transcription factors and key autophagy genes as well as specific autophagy transcription factors. We were able to quantify the changes in the global expression of autophagy genes as the pre-adipocytes progressed toward the maturation stage. We considered changes at both the individual gene and the gene set levels. Then, we investigated the links between the master adipogenic transcription factors and the observed changes in gene expression. We tested whether the established links hold in the knockdown condition of the adipogenic factors. In addition, the role of transcription co-factors and histone modifications in modulating the function of the transcription factor was discussed. </p>
</text>
