<text id="autogum_academic_doc720" title="Notes on the Nature of Beliefs in Witchcraft: Folklore and Classical Culture in Fifteenth Century Mendicant Traditions" shortTile="notes-nature-beliefs" author="Fabrizio Conti" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-1444/10/10/576/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<p>
Witchcraft is a multifaceted cultural phenomenon with its nature, causes, and outcomes bound to a high degree of variation and fluidity according to the geographical and the chronological boundaries considered.1 The origin and the peculiar cultural substrata shaping witch-beliefs can, however, be reconstructed in detail to shed light on their intellectual formative processes. My aim here is to show how two of the main cultural substrata behind the construction of witch-beliefs, the folkloric and the Classical literary motives, were intertwined in the fifteenth century by Mendicant preachers and inquisitors to produce a coherent and multifaceted picture of witchcraft-related beliefs. By relating some of the most meaningful sources that I have analyzed in my monograph <hi rend="italic">Witchcraft, Superstition, and Observant Franciscan Preachers</hi> (2015) to others that I have not analyzed before, my aim is twofold. I aim to show how this process of amalgamation of various cultural traditions gave shape to the creation and the understanding of the witchcraft phenomenon, and to highlight how the at times contradictory views concerning witch-beliefs pointing either to realistic or to skeptical stances, are associated with specific declensions of those different traditions on the part of the friars. In other words, I shall show how and with what purpose the texts of the friars recall and reuse both folkloric and classical traditions in dealing with witch-beliefs.2 </p>

<p>The myth of witchcraft is not a standalone phenomenon, one disconnected from a wider, and at the same time, specific context. Through their assessment of people’s level of adherence to Christian faith, according to the rules of Scholastic theological models, the Mendicant friars collected and elaborated on elements that would become a constitutive part of beliefs in witchcraft. In this regard, those friars often dealt with witch-beliefs as part of their concerns over superstition—this latter being the domain opposing official Christian religious practices—as well as in the context of pastoral care, as I have shown in the case of fifteenth-century Milanese Franciscan friars3 The teachings of the confessor as well as those of the preacher show how the world of superstition is vast. As the renowned Dominican preacher Girolamo Savonarola (d. 1498) shows in his <hi rend="italic">Eruditorium confessorum</hi>, a handbook for the instruction of confessors, superstition opposes religion, and it includes specific categories of practitioners of witchcraft among those dealing with other classes of magic:</p>
<blockquote>
The sinner has to be interrogated about the superstitious cult, which acts against religion. […] The idolaters, necromancers, evil doers (<hi rend="italic">malefici</hi>), sorceresses (<hi rend="italic">mulieres incantatrices</hi>), and whoever else exhibit cult to the devil, they all sin against that [religion] in a very serious way […]. And similarly [sin] the enchanters, diviners, and those who say to be able to find stolen objects through various superstitions as well as those who wear amulet scrolls hanged on their neck […].4</blockquote>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Malefici</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mulieres incantatrices</hi> certainly belong within the domain of witchcraft. While the term <hi rend="italic">maleficus</hi> can be employed in a general way to indicate the one who conducts evil, in his <hi rend="italic">Libellus</hi> against magicians the Dominican Isidoro Isolani (d. 1528) includes witches (<hi rend="italic">strigae</hi>) as part of the <hi rend="italic">malefici</hi> category.5 The women who practice sorcery (<hi rend="italic">mulieres incantatrices</hi>) offer the category of superstition an even more precise orientation towards witch-beliefs, leading to the construction of the stereotype of the witch practitioner typically being female. Within this context, folklore and classical culture emerged as the two primary domains from which the constitutive elements of beliefs in witchcraft will be taken and assembled.  </p>

<p>In the record of superstitions that is part of the <hi rend="italic">Sermones discipuli de tempore</hi> published in 1418 by the German Dominican preacher Johannes Herolt (d. 1468), known as the <hi rend="italic">Discipulus</hi>, the friar gives an interesting account of beliefs seemingly referring to pre-Christian folkloric traditions. In particular, in his Sermon 41 for the second Sunday of Lent titled “On the twenty-four types of men who falsify faith,” Herolt enlists a number of beliefs and behaviors in opposition to the Christian faith, twenty-one of which are considered to be superstitions.6 Some of these elements concern the domain of divination, such as casting lots, the one of enchantment, such as casting spells, or that of magic, such as putting together love potions. Other elements pertain to superstitious attitudes called <hi rend="italic">vanae observationes</hi> that Herolt, as all the other friars, generally consider with leniency, including observing dreams or observing the course of the moon and the sun. Other beliefs, on the contrary, are of much greater concern for the friar. Above all, the <hi rend="italic">vetulae</hi> or old women who can make a woman sterile or provide advice on how to get rid of a fetus, as well as those women who enchant people and beasts, fall under the suspicion of showing a diabolic attitude endangering life in all its forms. </p>
</text>
