<text id="autogum_academic_doc431" title="Illicit Chinese Small-Scale Mining in Ghana: Beyond Institutional Weakness?" shortTile="illicit-chinese-smallscale" author="James Boafo, Sebastian  Angzoorokuu Paalo, Senyo Dotsey" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5943/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 5. Conclusions </head>
<p>
Contrary to the dominant narratives of the drivers of illegal small-scale mining in Ghana, we have argued that the proliferation of the phenomenon is largely a result of the uncoordinated, and thus functionally parallel, nature of formal institutions (the Minerals Commission and the Ministry of Lands and Natural Resources) and informal institutions (the chieftaincy and customary land institutions) responsible for natural resource management. While the 1992 Constitution, for instance, bequeaths natural resources to the state, the same constitution holds that traditional leaders (mainly chiefs), families, and individuals own land, thus creating parallel and disjointed institutions, and promoting the proliferation of illegal mining activities.  </p>

<p>Because of the hitherto unconstrained access of chiefs and landowners prior to state control of minerals, coupled with some formal bureaucracies, landowners often give out sites for mineral prospection without passing through the requisite state institutions. This is exacerbated by the failure of formal and informal institutions to work in an integrated manner. The condition of institutional disconnection makes it possible for Ghanaians to illegally sublet their licenses to their Chinese counterparts who have the capital and technology. This illegality is not limited to ordinary Ghanaians alone. Chiefs also navigate the system by conniving with Chinese and other locals to perpetuate the illegality supposedly at the blind side of the state, by secretly giving out lands or shielding miners from state surveillance. These findings are in line with Jacobs’ research in Namibia, where Chinese buy licenses of local small-scale miners because the latter often lack the necessary skills and technical know-how, as well as the required funds to purchase the necessary machinery. Further, Gonzalez-Vicente’s work, for instance, highlights the opposite trend in Peru and Ecuador where Chinese companies negotiate directly with the central elites, and thus disregard local authorities in the process. This somewhat contradicts Ghana’s case but still indicates the tension and disconnect between the state and local institutions, suggesting that with the current institutional architecture, illegal small-scale mining will continue, not only in Ghana but also in similar socio-political settings. </p>

<p>While Ghanaians aid their Chinese partners in the illegal mining business, the comparative advantage of the latter tends to provoke local resistance, which spills into the national discourse. Locals have reacted violently to Chinese encroachment and destruction of farms belonging to mining communities, water bodies, and forest reserves. With their superior capital and technology, Chinese miners mostly outcompete their Ghanaian counterparts, thus pushing the latter out of business, forcing them to seek jobs in Chinese mines.  </p>

<p>In essence, the proliferation of illicit mining activities involving Chinese migrants in Ghana is largely a result of the inability of formal and informal rules and actors to coordinate their respective mandates to effectively regularize activities in the sector. This has lent agency to individuals and groups to manipulate the system, conniving with foreigners (Chinese) in the process, for private gains against the state.  </p>

<p>While acknowledging the multiple and interconnected factors contributing to illicit small-scale mining in Ghana, this study offers further in-depth insight into the complex world of the mining industry, thus problematizing the significant role of the formal–informal institutional disconnection in the continual illegality in the small-scale mining industry. The study, therefore, provides the basis for future research on the relations between formal–informal institutions in natural resource governance in Africa and other similar settings across space and time. More importantly, further longitudinal and comparative research on how the relationship between formal and informal institutions shapes extractive resource management would be highly welcome. Such an approach would offer new insights into how these institutions have developed and interacted over time.
 </p>
</text>
