<text id="autogum_academic_doc496" title="Premature Ejaculation: Aetiology and Treatment Strategies" shortTile="premature-ejaculation" author="Nicholas Gillman, Michael Gillman" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3271/7/11/102/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Patient Assessment</head>
<p>Patients with PE may be uncomfortable discussing their ejaculatory disorder and as such may avoid seeking treatment. It is therefore important that clinicians establish sexual health as a routine topic during consultations. One common approach of initiating the conversation about sexual health, and to determine intervention levels for patients, is the PLISSIT Model, first introduced by Annon. This model is a stage-wise approach, and individual patient levels should be identified by the clinician.
<list>
<item>Permission: This is the first stage in which the clinician gives the client permission to feel comfortable about and discuss a particular facet of their sexual health. It is imperative the clinician maintains a professional, non-judgmental attitude during this time in order to facilitate the conversation.</item>
<item>Limited Information: In this stage, the patient is provided with limited information about a topic or issue. It is important in this stage that the clinician learns about specific topics the patient wishes to discuss surrounding their sexual health and provide information for the specific subject.</item>
<item>Specific Suggestion: Here, the clinician provides patients with specific advice on particular topics relating to the patient’s sexual health. This is completed after full patient evaluation surrounding the topic. Information includes suggested behavioural changes as well as treatment options for a specific concern.</item>
<item>Intensive Therapy: This is the last stage in which the patient begins psychological and/or pharmacological therapy to remediate a specific issue the patient is suffering from regarding their sexual health. This may include referral to a specialist for further treatment and management.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>
As previously discussed, confirming a diagnosis of PE requires the presence of all three components. The first relates to ejaculatory latency, with patients having an IELT of one minute or less on all or nearly all sexual encounters, or a reduction in IELT to about three minutes. The second is a lack of control, or inability to delay ejaculation. Finally, there must be negative personal consequences for the patient, which may include psychological or interpersonal issues. </p>

<p>As such, clinicians must primarily explore the patient’s sexual history; however a full medical history, psychological history and a physical exam is often necessary to provide context surrounding the PE and to consider possible underlying causes of acquired PE. The sexual history should involve an estimate of IELT, as well as the onset and duration of PE. Previous sexual functioning and history of sexual relations are also necessary in order to delineate acquired and lifelong PE. Degree of ejaculatory control as well as degree of patient and partner distress should also be ascertained in order to fulfil a diagnosis of PE. A psychological history is also important in order to assess the likelihood of a psychological cause or association with the PE. This includes identifying patient stressors, as well as assessing a history/presence of anxiety or depression. A focused physical examination can point towards an underlying cause of PE and this may include a genitourinary examination and neurological assessment of the lower limbs. </p>

<p>A common diagnostic tool used in the assessment of premature ejaculation is the premature ejaculation diagnostic tool (PEDT) developed by Symonds et al.. The tool asks questions regarding the ISSM criteria of premature ejaculation to cover all three components of the definition. It is important to note however that the tool fails to distinguish between acquired and lifelong PE, and as such, involvement by the clinician is important in the identification of the correct PE subtype. </p>

<p>It is also crucial to manage patient expectations when assessing patients with PE. Waldinger et al. found IELT to vary in a population of men with partners &gt;6 months from 0.55–44.1 min, with a median latency time of 5.4 min. Some patients and/or partners may have preconceived perceptions about IELT that are well in excess of this median latency time and may consequently have unrealistic expectations of what can be achieved with therapy. </p>

<p>By gaining an understanding of patient expectations concerning therapeutic outcomes, initiating suitable treatment, or modifying current treatment, can be appropriately managed. This is best achieved by setting achievable treatment goals with the patient. Examples of treatment goals include increasing IELT, increasing control over ejaculation, increasing satisfaction with sexual intercourse and decreasing personal distress related to PE. </p>
</text>
