<text id="autogum_academic_doc107" title="Are Higher Input Levels to Triticale Growing Technologies Effective in Biofuel Production System?" shortTile="higher-input-levels" author="Stanisław Bielski, Kęstutis Romaneckas, Anastasija Novikova, Egidijus Šarauskis" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/11/21/5915/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Triticale is an increasingly popular cereal species which acreage continues to grow steadily in Poland. Triticale ranks second after wheat in terms of cropped area, and this highly versatile crop has a wide range of end use possibilities. The area sown with triticale in Poland constitutes about 34% of the area of this species in the world. European agriculture has also appreciated this species. In the last decade, the area sown with triticale increased by 30%. This undoubtedly confirms the growing position of this species. </p>

<p>The energy consumption in agriculture has been increasing due to the decreasing arable land, the growing population, the growing machine number, and the pursuit of higher living standards. The Integrated Farming System, the key to which is an attempt at reconciliation of seemingly contradictory economic (assumption of high farming effectiveness), environmental, and social goals, represents one of the concepts of sustainable agriculture development. Sustainable development results from assuming the principle of integrated order seen as consistent and simultaneous perception of the economic, social, and natural order. Agriculture is the sector of the economy in which the most favorable conditions for implementation of the principles of sustainable development exist because, on the one hand, resources of the natural environment are used there, and on the other, farmers, through their activities, shape that environment. In modern farming systems, profitability is closely associated with a reduction in agricultural inputs. One of the methods for evaluating agricultural production relies on the concept of energy consumption. According to Pawlak, growing prices of energy contribute to the effective use of agricultural inputs. There is a growing need for new solutions that would improve energy efficiency in agricultural production, increase the competitive advantage of economies, and contribute to environmental protection. The changes in energy efficiency should be regularly monitored. Previous research showed that the assessment of energy consumption and its efficiency has an influence on improving the efficiency of energy use when receiving similar crop productivity. According to OECD (The Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development), improving energy efficiency in agriculture will reduce GHG (greenhouse gases) emissions nitrous, especially Oxide (N2O) and methane (CH4).  </p>

<p>In agriculture, energy efficiency depends on the type and production intensity, mechanization, and the applied production technology. Agricultural inputs and expenditures can be minimized by selecting the most appropriate means of production and optimizing agricultural technologies.  </p>

<p>Depending on the purpose of the analysis, the energy efficiency of plant production is determined using various methods. No standard methods for calculating the energy balance have been defined yet. Methods found in the literature often differ significantly, especially in terms of energy equivalents. Energy equivalents are not static values and must be adapted to local conditions.. It is necessary to undertake systemic research on the harmonization of contractual conversion factors for energy units of individual agricultural raw materials intended for caloric food products or for biofuels (RES) with a specific heat value. The conversion of agricultural products into conventional cereal units should also be updated. </p>

<p>Currently, the search for alternative energy sources has become an urgent need. Fuels from plant sources are used in huge amounts. Biofuels are considered safe for the environment, improve energy security, and do not negatively affect the food market. The need to acquire energy from other alternative sources arises from the fact that fossil fuels are limited in amount. First generation biofuels (biodiesel, bioethanol) and gas fuels are still the basic sources of renewable energy. They are either obtained from food and fodder raw materials by fermentation or transesterification processes. One of the most important biofuels used in transport is bioethanol, which is recognized as environmentally safe, renewable fuel. </p>

<p>A very important factor shaping the demand for agricultural products is growing purchases from entities operating outside the agri-food sector. Among them, fuel and energy concerns that use agricultural products in the biofuel production process are of particular importance. It is assumed that competition in the use of agricultural raw materials for biofuels negatively affects food prices and therefore contributes to the deepening of world hunger. In recent years, there have also been analyses attributing biofuels a role smaller than before in the negative influence on agricultural market prices. The use of a part of soil resources for biomass production limits the potential of food production, which may result in an increase in its price. Agriculture is expected to continue to increase productivity to meet the food needs of the growing world population. </p>

<p>In recent years, the production of bioethanol grew dynamically, exceeding 8.2 billion liters in the EU (2016), while global production reached 119.7 billion liters. About 6.1% of cereal production in the world (wheat, fodder grains) and 5.0% of harvest in the EU was used for this purpose. In 2005, cereal grains were used much less in the production of bioethanol, 2.7% in the world, and 1.0% in the EU. </p>
</text>
