<text id="autogum_academic_doc637" title="Plasma Kinetics of Choline and Choline Metabolites After A Single Dose of SuperbaBoostTM Krill Oil or Choline Bitartrate in Healthy Volunteers" shortTile="plasma-kinetics-choline" author="Yvonne Mödinger, Christiane Schön, Manfred Wilhelm, Petter-Arnt Hals" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/11/10/2548/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
In the present study, the absorption pattern and pharmacokinetic pattern of free choline from Superba<hi rend="italic">Boost</hi>TM krill oil and choline bitartrate were investigated. In Superba<hi rend="italic">Boost</hi>TM, choline is bound in a lipid-soluble form as phosphatidylcholine, while it is present as a water-soluble salt structure in choline bitartrate. Results show that free choline levels in plasma were comparable between Superba<hi rend="italic">Boost</hi>TM and choline bitartrate, but peak choline concentrations were reached significantly later upon intake of Superba<hi rend="italic">Boost</hi>TM compared to choline bitartrate. Moreover, levels of the choline metabolites betaine and DMG were higher, while levels of TMAO were lower upon intake of Superba<hi rend="italic">Boost</hi>TM compared to choline bitartrate. </p>

<p>The dependency between choline intake and circulating levels of free choline and its metabolites is concealed by homeostatic regulations and rapid tissue uptake. Thus, concentrations of choline and its metabolites are usually within a narrow range. In the literature, endogenous free fasting choline levels under physiological conditions range between 7–12 µmol/L, which could be confirmed in the present study with a mean choline concentration of 9.6 µmol/L before product intake. Moreover, baseline values were highly comparable within all groups and within the two kinetic days. </p>

<p>It is well known that choline levels are influenced by nutrition, and choline sources depend on the diet, In a normal Western diet, choline can be obtained from eggs, liver, soybeans and pork, where choline is present primarily as phosphatidylcholine. It was shown that the consumption of a small breakfast led to 25–30% higher choline levels compared to the fasting condition, and that a high choline-containing diet resulted in an up to two-fold increase in plasma choline. In a recent study by Cho et al., eggs were provided as a choline source, which contained comparable amounts of choline (479 mg) as the herein investigated study products (choline bitartrate: 620 mg; Superba<hi rend="italic">Boost</hi>TM: 572 mg). Cho et al. reported a 1.6-fold increase in free choline after consumption of the egg meal, in comparison to the fruit control meal. Correspondingly, the choline increase in the current study upon supplement intake was comparable (choline bitartrate: 1.35-fold; Superba<hi rend="italic">Boost</hi>TM: 1.48-fold). </p>

<p>To control for confounding factors of food, subjects of the present study adhered to a diet low in choline three days before the study intervention and consumed standardized meals during the kinetic days. In addition, a parallel study arm was included, whose subjects underwent a single kinetic dose after the intake of fish oil as a placebo control that was devoid of choline. Of note, we observed a minor increase in choline levels in the placebo group after the 4 h time point; thus, the standardized lunch served after four hours could have contributed to this elevation. However, no such effect was seen in the study groups receiving choline supplements. In addition, by implementing the control group, we were able to exclude possible circadian rhythm-dependent variations in choline levels, in contrast to Park et al., who observed a slight elevation of free choline levels in the afternoon during a 12 h-lasting observation of endogenous choline levels. </p>

<p>Krill oil is increasingly recognized as a useful source of phosphatidylcholine, in addition to its acknowledged role in providing the omega-3 fatty acids EPA and DHA. In a former study, phosphatidylcholine was shown to raise plasma choline levels more efficiently compared to ingestion of free choline as choline chloride. In the current study we observed a significant increase of choline after single doses of both phosphatidylcholine and the reference product choline bitartrate; however, phosphatidylcholine was not more efficient, since there were no significant differences in the pharmacokinetic endpoints AUC and Cmax. This discrepancy compared to the former study could be due to possible differences in the bioavailability of the chosen choline salts. However, to the best of our knowledge, choline bitartrate and choline chloride bioavailability has not been directly compared to date. Still, the uptake profile of free choline in the current study indicated a slower increase upon phosphatidylcholine (Superba<hi rend="italic">Boost</hi>TM) intake compared to choline bitartrate. This difference in Tmax between the study products could result from the structural differences between the choline forms and from the associated differences in absorption and metabolism. Phosphatidylcholine and/or its isoforms may be absorbed intact and can also be hydrolyzed into phosphatidic acid and free choline by phospholipase D. Due to this conversion step, it supposedly takes longer to obtain free choline from phosphatidylcholine compared to choline bitartrate, where free choline from the salt structure is more rapidly available. Our findings are in agreement with former findings showing that choline levels after choline chloride reached peak levels earlier and were reduced to baseline earlier than after phosphatidylcholine intake, where levels remained elevated for 12 h. </p>
</text>
