<text id="autogum_academic_doc489" title="Non-Invasive Assessment of Metabolic Adaptation in Paediatric Patients Suffering from Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus" shortTile="noninvasive-assessment" author="Phillip Trefz, Sibylle  C. Schmidt, Pritam Sukul, Jochen  K. Schubert, Wolfram Miekisch, Dagmar-Christiane Fischer" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2077-0383/8/11/1797/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Discussion</head>
<p>
Within this study, we used real-time CGM (rtCGM) in combination with a serial analysis of blood and exhaled breath in a highly standardized setting in pediatric T1DM patients and healthy controls over a time course of nine hours. We accumulated more than 4000 measurements of breath VOCs and interstitial glucose and almost 1000 blood samples from 44 participants. Standardization with respect to physical activity, the interval between meals, the type and amount of nutrients, and the restriction to alveolar breath sampling allows the generation of highly comparable diurnal profiles of breath and blood born parameters relative to the metabolic state. For real-time breath analysis, a PTR-ToF-MS was used and we focused on the exhalation of ethanol, acetone, isopropanol, dimethyl sulfide, isoprene, pentanal, and limonene. These compounds have been linked to glucose metabolism and/or to T1DM-related comorbidities including oxidative stress. Thus, we investigated the fade of classical markers via repetitive blood sampling and looked in parallel for the VOCs mentioned above.  </p>

<p>In the case of T1DM, acetone is certainly the most prominent VOC in breath and has previously been investigated under various conditions. Acetone originates from enzymatic or non-enzymatic decarboxylation of acetoacetate via Acetyl-CoA which is derived from pyruvate. Since the latter can originate from both glycolysis and lipolysis, it is impossible to differentiate the amount from either pathway. Regardless of this, we and others noted the significantly elevated exhalation of acetone in T1DM patients compared to controls, as well as the elevated blood levels in T1DM patients. However, although the concentrations of glucose and acetone correlated in T1DM patients, the time and/or the interval between food intake, and breath sampling appears to be an important confounder. In the morning, when ketogenesis is high due to overnight fasting, correlations were low, most probably due to an additive effect of lipolysis and glycolysis on the formation of acetone. Correlation improved markedly after a moderate intake of carbohydrates and insulin-related inhibition of lipolysis. In the afternoon, correlation between acetone and blood glucose remained low. This was most probably due to postprandial hyperglycemia. Thus, a correlation of acetone with blood glucose is difficult even under healthy conditions and the time-resolved calculation of the correlation coefficients in our study strengthen this observation. Furthermore, the impact of hepatic alcohol dehydrogenase, i.e., the reduction of acetone to isopropanol, has to be considered. In fact, T1DM patients exhaled significantly more isopropanol than their healthy peers and both, the diurnal profile as well as the time resolved correlation coefficients, closely resembled that of acetone. Thus, activation of this pathway in T1DM patients may attribute to acetone elimination and indicate metabolic adaptation.  </p>

<p>The shape of the normalized diurnal profiles of glucose, insulin, glucagon, lipids, leptin, and slepR are fairly comparable in T1DM patients and healthy controls, but differ with respect to slope and inter-individual variability, i.e., changes over time are faster in controls while inter-individual variability is much greater in T1DM patients. This might, at least in part, be due to the limited abilities of pharmaceutical insulin preparations to mimic the physiological interplay between insulin-induced cellular uptake of glucose and glucagon secretion. Under physiological conditions, insulin is secreted in response to increasing blood glucose levels and by inducing cellular glucose uptake and inhibition of pancreatic glucagon secretion at the same time it contributes to maintenance of glucose homeostasis. Thus, in healthy individuals, glucagon concentration in blood remains constant as long as the blood glucose concentration stays within the normal range and insulin concentrations peak after meals. In contrast, in T1DM patients glucagon concentrations remain partially elevated even after meals and most likely aggravate postprandial hyperglycemia. The latter, especially in concert with dyslipidemia is considered as a relevant contributor to the overall increased risk for the development of cardiovascular disease.  </p>

<p>On the one hand, poor glycemic control is likely to result in elevated cholesterol and triglyceride levels, on the other hand, peripheral hyperinsulinemia secondary to subcutaneous insulin administration contribute to qualitative abnormalities of lipid metabolism as well and this has recently been shown in young T1DM patients. Albeit no clear correlation between breath ethanol and serum triglycerides exists, the concentration profiles were quite similar, especially in the second half of the examination period, i.e., after challenge with carbohydrates (pasta) at lunch. Endogenous ethanol is supposed to originate from intestinal bacterial activity via fermentation of carbohydrates, i.e., breath ethanol increase is due to the intake with subsequent digestion of carbohydrates and the intestinal microbiota. While the carbohydrate intake at lunch was quite similar in both groups, postprandial hyperglycemia was not and even subtle differences with respect to the intestinal microbiota between T1DM patients and controls have to be considered. Altogether, this may have caused a slightly more pronounced increase of postprandial ethanol with higher peak ethanol concentrations in T1DM patients. Elevated endogenous ethanol was also already previously detected in diabetic patients.  </p>
</text>
