<text id="autogum_academic_doc291" title="Trajectory Tracking of Flexible-Joint Robots Actuated by PMSM via a Novel Smooth Switching Control Strategy" shortTile="trajectory-tracking" author="Yue Wang, Haisheng Yu, Jinpeng Yu, Herong Wu, Xudong Liu" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/20/4382/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 4. Simulation and Comparative Analysis</head>
<p>
In this section, we will verify the control algorithm proposed in Section 3 by simulation. In order to facilitate the simulation, we consider 2DOF flexible manipulator as the controlled object. Firstly, the IHSMC algorithm proposed in this paper is simulated and compared with the traditional HSMC algorithm. The superiority of the control strategy is verified. Then, a PID-IDA-PBC proposed in this paper is simulated and implemented with the IDA-PBC algorithm. In comparison, it is verified that the PID-IDA-PBC algorithm has better steady state performance and disturbance–resistance ability. In the end, we proceed simulations using hybrid control. We use the parameter values of robot manipulator reported in. In this simulation we assume that each joint of the flexible-joint robot is driven by PMSM. The parameters of PMSM are given as . The initial state is set as , we require the expected position vector to be . Lastly, we agree that the counterclockwise direction is the positive direction of the rotation of robot. </p>

<p>For the IHSMC algorithm, the selected controller parameters are ,  The parameter selection of the joint 1 current controller are . The original HSMC control law can be expressed as

(30)

where . According to the results shown in <figure>Figure 2</figure>, joint 1 and joint 2 enter a steady state after a dynamic process of about 0.4 s, but there is still a small chattering in the system at steady state. Compared with the original HSMC algorithm, the IHSMC algorithm has a faster response speed and chattering is effectively suppressed. <figure>Figure 3</figure> shows the simulation curves of  under IHSMC and HSMC method. </p>

<p>The simulation experiment of the PID-IDA-PBC algorithm is divided into two parts. Firstly, the performance difference between the algorithm and the traditional IDA-PBC algorithm is compared without disturbance. Then, a constant value disturbance signal of 2 N·m is added at the System dynamic Equation (2) at 4 s to verify the disturbance–resistance performance of the algorithm. Parameters of PID-PBC-PCH controller: . According to <figure>Figure 4</figure>, it can be concluded that the PID-IDA-PBC has improved dynamic performance and steady-state performance compared to the conventional IDA-PBC control. The PID-IDA-PBC control algorithm can improve the steady-state performance by adjusting <hi rend="italic">v</hi>. <figure>Figure 5</figure> shows the simulation curves of  under IDA-PBC and PID-IDA-PBC method. At the same time, it will reduce the dynamic performance. In order to validate the robustness of the PID-IDA-PBC algorithm, constant-size perturbations of different sizes are added to the drive motors of joint 1 and joint 2 at 4 s. The result is shown in <figure>Figure 6</figure>. The PID-IDA-PBC algorithm has excellent disturbance–resistance performance. </p>

<p>According to the above, it can be concluded that a single control algorithm finds it difficult to balance both dynamic performance and steady state performance. Therefore, this paper proposes a hybrid control strategy that attempts to combine the advantages of the two control algorithms. The simulation experiment of the hybrid control strategy was divided into three parts. First, we compared the control effects of hybrid control and single control algorithms. Then, a disturbance was added at 4 s to verify the immunity of the hybrid control. Finally, a simulation experiment was designed to analyze the effect of switching parameters on the effects of hybrid control. The hybrid controller parameter selection is . </p>

<p>According to the simulation results in <figure>Figure 7</figure>, it can be concluded that the hybrid control strategy combines the advantages of the two control algorithms well, and has good dynamic performance and high tracking accuracy. <figure>Figure 8</figure> shows the simulation curves of  under Hybrid control method. The smoothing function curve in <figure>Figure 9</figure> reflects the proportion of PID-IDA-PBC control during the switching process. <figure>Figure 10</figure> is the trajectory curves when there is a disturbance imposed at the time of . The result shows that even if the system generates small high-frequency chattering due to disturbance, it can eventually eliminate chattering. The simulation results in <figure>Figure 11</figure> show that the control effect of the hybrid control strategy is related to the switching parameter <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. The curve with smooth switching function under different parameters is shown in <figure>Figure 12</figure>. According to the results in <figure>Figure 11</figure> and <figure>Figure 12</figure>, it can be concluded that the effect of the hybrid control is affected by the parameter <hi rend="italic">c</hi> and the switching interval . The larger the <hi rend="italic">c</hi> value, the earlier the position error change ratio is affected by the PID-IDA-PBC algorithm. According to the value of <hi rend="italic">c</hi>, the appropriate switching interval is selected to achieve smooth switching, and the abrupt change of the switching is avoided. </p>
</text>
