<text id="autogum_academic_doc285" title="Towards Safer Primers: A Review" shortTile="towards-safer-primers" author="Stefan Lundgaard, Soon Hock Ng, Damien Cahill, Johan Dahlberg, Dong Ruan, Nerida Cole, Paul R. Stoddart, Saulius Juodkazis" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2227-7080/7/4/75/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
The evolution of energetic material technology is important and is constantly progressing. Energetic materials typically fall into three categories: explosives that are designed to detonate, propellants that generally deflagrate, or pyrolants that can deflagrate or detonate. A detonation is a reaction that propogates faster than the sonic velocity of the material, creating a shock wave at supersonic speeds. Deflagration is the decomposition of a material at velocities much slower than the sonic velocity and is typically thermally propagated. </p>

<p>Explosive materials have proven to be indispensable from the earliest cannons to modern artillery, rockets, airbags, mining and demolition applications. Primers (or detonators more broadly) generally contain small amounts of primary (detonating) explosives that are used to initiate a larger quantity of a high performance, less sensitive material. This combination is important as it is safer than solely using a primary explosive, as these are generally sensitive to stimuli and thus dangerous in large quantities. </p>

<p>Due to the major defence and industrial applications, primer technology has largely evolved outside the public domain, following arcane rules defined by national interests and security concerns. Nonetheless there is a natural progression of high impact technologies towards wider use in commercial applications with higher precision and better efficiency than previous generations of technology. In this regard, the basic principles and materials have to be well understood in order to meet public safety concerns. </p>

<p>There are many factors that contribute to the need for alternatives to commonly used explosives. Manufacturing of energetic materials is a hazardous process, calling for alternative production methods that are safer and more efficient. Lead azide (Pb(N)) is a common primary explosive used in primers and is of concern due to its lead content. Along with other energetic materials used to initiate explosives and pyrotechnics, the toxicity of these materials and their reaction products is apparent. Therefore the concerns for these primer compounds are based on the dangers of handling and manufacturing, their toxicity, and their environmental impact. The stability of these compounds is also critically important: potentially fatal malfunctions of air bags in cars using primary explosives has caused harm, where the chemical stability has been compromised by temperature and humidity. </p>

<p>Research has brought about modern alternatives for primers that are well established in the industry. Replacement compounds have been identified in a number of promising directions. New environmentally friendly “green” explosives that are heavy metal free and non-toxic provide one avenue. Solid-state energetic devices (igniters) to replace the need for explosive primer compounds is another field of great interest. The main purpose of this review is to explore the emerging materials, devices and ignition principles that are underpinning the safer and more controlled use of energetic materials as primers. </p>
</text>
