<text id="autogum_academic_doc547" title="Hazard Analysis for Escalator Emergency Braking System via System Safety Analysis Method Based on STAMP" shortTile="hazard-analysis-escalator" author="Zitong Zhou, Yanyang Zi, Jinglong Chen, Tong An" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-3417/9/21/4530/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 2. Safety Analysis Framework for Complex Electromechanical Equipment System Based on STAMP </head>
<p>
STAMP treats safety as a control problem, and the focus of system safety is changed from preventing failures in implementing safety constraints. It still contains component failures, but it extends the concept of accidental causes to include component interactions. It contains three main concepts: safety constraints, hierarchical control structures, and process models. The most basic concept in STAMP is not an event but a constraint. The main causes of safety issues in the new theory are component failures, system external disturbances, interactions between components, and component behaviors that lead to dangerous system states. </p>

<head> 2.1. Principles of STAMP</head>
<p>
The safety of a complex system is more than component failure or reliability decline. In STAMP, safety is an emergent or system property, rather than a component property. In system theory, complex systems are viewed as a hierarchy of organizational levels. A hierarchical multilevel model of stakeholders is posited in STAMP, like the model of Rasmussen, but more expanded. Another basic concept in STAMP is safety constraints. In system theory, safety can be regarded as an emergent which is originated from interactions between components. The method of controlling the emergent is to impose constraints on the behavior of the components and the interactions between the components. Meanwhile, due to the constraint property of hierarchical structure, the accidents will happen if the higher layers cannot provide enough constraints or the lower layers violate the safety constraints when the high-level constraints control the behavior of the lower layers. With the development of the equipment toward automation and intelligent, the system becomes more and more complex, and the difficulty in identifying and executing safety constraints in design and operation has been increased. <figure>Figure 3</figure> shows a general socio-technical system control structure from STAMP, which does not represent any particular system. Each node in the graph is a human or machine component in a socio-technical system. Connecting lines show control actions used to enforce safety constraints on the system and feedback that provides information to the controlling entity. </p>

<p>Besides constraints and hierarchical models, a third basic concept in STAMP is that of process models. The process model is an important part of the control theory. A typical process model consists of the controller that issued the command and the controlled object that provided the feedback (controlled process), which is shown in <figure>Figure 4</figure>. Usually, the controller contains process model and control algorithm. When the controller sends a command to controlled process, the corresponding feedback which is generated by controlled process will be sent to controller to form a complete controlled process. Component interaction accidents can often be interpreted as process model errors. When the controller’s process model does not match the controlled system or the controller issues an unsafe command, an accident will also happen. </p>

<p>Based on three basic concepts of STAMP, the basic casual factors of a standard control loop under the STAMP framework was concluded in <figure>Figure 5</figure>. </p>

<head> 2.2. Comparison between FTA, FMECA, HAZOP, and STAMP</head>
<p>
Traditional risk analysis theory considers hazards as the result of the action of a series of events. The considered events usually involve several types of component failures or human errors, mainly adopting the forward sequence method (such as failure mode and impact analysis) or the backward sequence method (Such as the fault tree directly describes the linear relationship between the failure and the influencing factors and is suitable for analyzing the hazard caused by the failure of a physical component or a simple system.) Three hazard analysis techniques are suggested in the functional safety standard (ISO26262): fault tree analysis (FTA), failure modes and effects analysis (FMEA), and hazard and operability (HAZOP) analysis. Table 2 summaries and compares three general hazard analysis techniques with STAMP. </p>

<p>FTA, FMECA, and HAZOP are proposed before the 1980s in which industrial automation and intelligence are still not highly dependent. Only giant companies and some research institutes like the nuclear industry, aerospace, and universities have enough human and material resources to carry out relevant technology research. Although some detail can be found by these three methods, the limitation of methods shown in Table 2 is clear. These traditional safety analysis methods based on the event chain model are unable to do as much as they can when dealing with computer-oriented automated control system. However, due to the particularity understanding of safety in STAMP, the connotation of safety has been substantially improved from the introduction of concepts such as hierarchical models, process models, and safety constraints. </p>

<head> 2.3. System-Therotical Process Analysis (STPA)</head>
<p>
STPA is a new hazard analysis technique based on system safety theory. According to the above-mentioned description, an accident is defined as the result of a complex process in which the system behavior goes against the safety constraints. The main steps of STPA can be shown as follows: </p>

<p>Step 1: Identify improper control actions of the system that may cause danger, </p>

<p>Step 2: Determine how potential hazard controls may occur in step 1. </p>
</text>
