<text id="autogum_academic_doc223" title="Review of Detection Methods of Static Eccentricity for Interior Permanent Magnet Synchronous Machine" shortTile="review-detection" author="Anmol Aggarwal, Elias  G. Strangas" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1996-1073/12/21/4105/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Fault Signals for Detection</head>
<p>
This section discuss the signals used for fault detection for the methods proposed. Signals are generated such that the fault detection is more clear. </p>

<head> 3.1. Commanded Voltages Method</head>
<p>
The difference in the voltages between healthy and faulty cases is directly proportional to the difference in the flux linkages of healthy and faulty case. The difference between the flux linkages is significant in certain range of the current. The difference is maximum at the point shown in <figure>Figure 4</figure>. Therefore, for fault detection the machine should be operated as close as possible to point of maximum separation. </p>

<head> 3.2. Calculation of Incremental Inductance</head>
<p>
Incremental inductance is generated by using DC current injection in the d-axis with constant rotation. The current is injected with increasing current levels and the q-axis voltage () is recorded at each level. The value of d-axis flux () is calculated from the q-axis voltage (). Finally, incremental inductance is calculated by taking the derivative of  vs.  curve given by

(29)

</p>

<p>The difference in the two current levels is . Therefore, the above relation reduces to

(30)

where  is the difference in the flux linkages at two different levels of current.  and  are shown in <figure>Figure 5</figure>. </p>

<p>The difference in current levels is chosen such that there is a measurable difference in the q-axis voltages between two levels. The minimum difference in current levels is chosen once measurable difference in the voltages is recorded, because increased difference in current levels decreases peak prominence. </p>

<head> 3.3. Harmonics in Voltage and Current Signals</head>
<p>
The first 15 harmonics present in IAP (Instantaneous Active Power) are used for analysis for fault detection which was extracted using FFT (Fast Fourier Transform). The harmonic that shows the maximum separation between the healthy and faulty cases is used for analysis. The machine is operated at the same operating conditions as it is operated for commanded voltages method. </p>

<head> 3.4. Vibration Signals for Analysis</head>
<p>
The oscillating forces were calculated by using FEA model. First the magnitude of magnetic field density was calculated around the rotor. After that for an angle , as shown in <figure>Figure 6</figure>, radial stress was estimated using Equation (31).

(31)

</p>

<p>Then, the stress is calculated by taking projections in y and x-axis as follows

(32)

(33)

</p>

<p>Net force at a given time can be calculated by integrating the forces over the periphery of the rotor.

(34)

(35)

</p>

<p>Therefore, forces are estimated using flux density at different times. Once, forces are estimated, FFT is performed and results are analyzed. </p>

<p>To analyze the vibration signals the accelerometers were placed on both stator core and rotor bearing in the direction of static eccentricity (y-axis) and 90° apart from the direction of static eccentricity (x-axis). The arrangement of accelerometers on the rotor bearing and stator core is shown in <figure>Figure 7</figure>. </p>
</text>
