<text id="autogum_academic_doc633" title="Adapting Translational Research Methods to Water, Sanitation, and Hygiene" shortTile="adapting-translational" author="Karen Setty, Ryan Cronk, Shannan George, Darcy Anderson, Għanja O’Flaherty, Jamie Bartram" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/16/20/4049/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 1. Introduction</head>
<p>
Water, sanitation, and hygiene (WaSH) services underlie public health and contribute to quality of life, environmental health, social development, and economic growth. The United Nations General Assembly recognized water and sanitation as human rights in 2010 via Resolution 64/292. Since 2015, Sustainable Development Goal (SDG) 6—ensuring availability and sustainable management of water and sanitation for all by 2030—has posed a formidable and time-constrained challenge for policy, programming, and practice. Inadequate WaSH services contribute up to 1.5% of the overall global burden of disease, with an estimated 829,000 deaths per year in low- and middle-income countries. While earlier development policies implicitly dealt with improving access in low- and middle-income countries, the SDGs apply universally to enhancing service levels in all countries. This shift corresponds to growing recognition that WaSH disparities exist even in high-income countries and endemic disease and outbreaks persist. </p>

<p>Service improvements increase convenience, safety, and environmental protection. According to the World Health Organization (WHO) and United Nations Children’s Fund (UNICEF) Joint Monitoring Programme for Water Supply, Sanitation and Hygiene (JMP), water services qualify as “safely managed” when they are improved, accessible on premises, available when needed, and free from contamination. Safely managed sanitation means human excreta is contained in a facility used by a single household and treated prior to safe disposal either onsite or off-site. For a variety of reasons, an estimated 29% of the global population lack water services that meet these criteria, while an estimated 61% lack safely managed sanitation. Although global data on access to hygiene facilities, such as handwashing stations and soap, are not readily available, estimates suggest low coverage in many regions. </p>

<p>The combined need for “software” (i.e., behavior change and demand creation) and “hardware” (i.e., infrastructure or other technology used to deliver services) in WaSH programs often necessitates interdisciplinary collaboration. WaSH professionals come from diverse educational backgrounds, such as engineering, environmental science, public health, medicine, economics, sociology, and political science. Different organizations and actors engage with research in different ways depending on their background knowledge, aims, and dominant local or broader culture. Loevinsohn et al. (2015) suggested disciplinary divisions lead actors to differently understand and evaluate WaSH programming. Geographical proximity, access to learning and training resources, dissemination fora, and competitiveness among groups may further limit knowledge sharing. </p>

<p>A culture of active learning can be achieved where new knowledge (including failure) supports actionable improvement and all actors rapidly integrate it into their policies, planning, and practice. Improving access to WaSH services will require, among other things, service delivery (“supply”) from diverse professional actors as well as health-conscious behaviors (“demand”) among consumers. Effective management of the knowledge-action boundary requires professionals to actively communicate, translate, and mediate. Research and researchers play a critical role in building knowledge for development, for example by identifying problems, comparing potential solutions, and devising strategies for uptake and dissemination of good practices. Research addresses novel problems (e.g., emerging diseases), everyday problems (e.g., increasing efficiency), and persistent problems (e.g., delivering services to hard-to-reach populations). </p>

<p>Regrettably, goals, timing, and lines of communication often misalign among actor groups. Translating novel research into everyday policy and practice can take years, and individual study recommendations may be unhelpful to decision-makers, who must consider competing needs, costs, and the prevailing political landscape. A number of issues have chronically plagued WaSH research and development efforts, such as competition among actors for resources and visibility, bias among both researchers and publishers against publishing null results, weak political support, and inadequate human resources. Recognizing pervasive challenges, some have called for greater attention to applied or “translational” research, which applies scientific techniques to address practical problems. Translational research addresses the science-to-service delivery gap, also referred to as the knowledge-to-action, research-to-practice, bench-to-bedside, or simply “death valley” distance between science and practical action. Others note that pure research (intended to contribute to general knowledge) continues to offer value, and should not be discarded. </p>

<p>Translational research techniques, such as a guiding framework, tool, or compilation of strategies, have not yet become established or standardized within the environmental health or WaSH fields. However, in recent decades, translational research structures and literature have become particularly well developed in the healthcare and mental health fields, demonstrated by active consensus and repetition in the literature. Education, pharmacy, social work, public health, and criminal justice have similarly begun to adopt translational research methods. In this case, we must rely on available examples to begin to guide professionals and harmonize meaning. Reviews aim to consolidate ideas, identify research type gaps, improve consistency, and tailor knowledge to specific fields, such as environmental sciences, biomedical sciences, or healthcare systems. Hering (2018) called for a detailed mapping exercise to understand which aspects of translational science apply to the environmental domain, either directly or in a modified form. </p>
</text>
