<text id="autogum_academic_doc472" title="Investigation of the Possible Pharmacologically Active Forms of the Nicotinic Acetylcholine Receptor Agonist Anabaseine" shortTile="investigation-possible" author="Kristin Andrud, Hong Xing, Bjarne Gabrielsen, Linda Bloom, Vladimir Mahnir, Stephen Lee, Benedict  T. Green, Jon Lindstrom, William Kem" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-3397/17/11/614/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Discussion</head>
<p>
While most nAChR agonists and antagonists binding at ACh orthosteric sites are basic molecules with at least one ionizable N, there are exceptions, including lophotoxin, the neonicotinoids and some recently synthesized pyrimidine agonists. To optimize a molecule to serve as a drug or selective molecular probe of some receptor it is important to identify the form in which it interacts optimally with its target. In the case of anabaseine, our identification of the cyclic iminium form as the most active (and possibly the only) form suggests that structural modifications that enhance the basicity of its tetrahydropyridyl nitrogen will enhance potency and possibly selectivity for the intended receptor target. In fact, a major improvement in stability occurs with addition at the 3-position of the tetrahydropyridyl ring of an electron-conjugated system containing an aromatic ring, as in 3-(4-dimethylaminobenzylidene)-anabaseine or 3-(2,4-dimethoxybenzylidene)-anabaseine, also called GTS-21. These anabaseine derivatives do not undergo ring opening (hydrolysis of the imine bond) under physiological conditions, due to their extended π electron conjugation.  </p>

<p>Previously, it was assumed (but not experimentally tested) that the cyclic iminium form of anabaseine is the one which binds avidly to the ACh binding site in nAChRs. This form was modeled to fit into a muscle type homology model. The crystal structure of the molluscan acetylcholine binding protein binding anabaseine actually was derived from crystals containing both the cyclic iminium and the open-chain monocationic form of anabaseine occupying some of the five identical binding sites. Unlike the cyclic iminium, the ammonium-ketone form ammonium group did not insert into the “aromatic box.” In the preparation of the AChBP-anabaseine crystals very high anabaseine concentrations were used so that most of the five sites would be occupied; therefore the presence of the ammonium-ketone form in the crystal structure does not necessarily indicate that this form of anabaseine would bind to AChBPs and nAChRs at the low concentrations of anabaseine that occur in our in vitro functional and binding studies. </p>

<p>The ability of a variety of 2-(aryl)-1,4,5,6-tetrahydropyrmidines to block neuromuscular nAChRs and produce teratogenic effects in chick embryos was reported long ago. Some of these compounds were reported to be nAChR agonists. The only study of PTHP on neurons was that of Upshall et al. on leech Retzius cells. Our results also indicate that PTHP is a potent agonist at neuronal as well as neuromuscular nAChRs. The 2-aryl compounds reported in the Brimblecombe et al. study did not include PTHP or other compounds having a 2-(3-pyridyl)- substituent, which is known to be essential for the agonist activity of nicotine and of anabaseine. For PTHP to be equipotent with anabaseine, based on the I+ form being the only active form, its EC50 would need to be ~1/3 of the EC50 of anabaseine, since the anabaseine (I+) is ~1/3 of its total concentration. The data for PTHP and anabaseine in <figure>Figure 3</figure> and <figure>Figure 4</figure> and in Table 1, indicate that PTHP has approximately 30% of the potency predicted for the anabaseine cyclic iminium form. One possible explanation for this slightly inferior potency is that the additional N on the tetrahydropyrmidinyl ring must form an H bond with some other atom within the aromatic box of the nAChR orthosteric binding site and this may be energetically unfavorable. </p>

<p>While 2,3′-bipyridyl displayed only a marginal potency at vertebrate receptors that could be predicted from its pKa, it has been found to be quite paralytic to insects and crustaceans. At least some arthropod nAChRs are known to not require a cationic ligand for activation, as shown by many studies with neonicotinoid insecticides such as imidachloprid. These neonicotinoids also display a limited activity at vertebrate nAChRs. It seems likely that 2,3′-bipyridyl affects some arthropod nAChRs through its unionized form.  </p>

<p>One can speculate as to what advantage(s) might accrue to an organism (in this case, a hoplonemertine or ant) to produce and secrete an imine-bond containing toxin like anabaseine. The entire body wall integument as well as the contiguous epithelium of the anterior proboscis of <hi rend="italic">P. peregrina</hi> contains very high concentrations of anabaseine. The proboscis everts and wraps around the prey during its capture allowing extensive contact of this epithelium with its annelid prey. The mineralized stylet of the proboscis can be observed to produce multiple punctures of the prey integument, which should further facilitate envenomation. In addition, potential predators will also be exposed in these ways to anabaseine and related alkaloids. Perhaps a major advantage of possessing an imine bond, besides an enhanced affinity for the nAChR orthosteric site, is its low basicity, which allows the unionized form to reach a relatively high concentration in the neutral pH range of the marine environment and thereby enhance passive diffusion across the integument of the prey or predator. The integument of a marine organism exposed to sea water is likely to have a pH near 8, well above the pH range in which anabaseine is primarily ionized. Thus, the toxin has a much better chance of entering the prey/predator than would anabaseine, the more basic secondary amine analog of anabaseine.  </p>
</text>
