<text id="autogum_academic_doc014" title="Targeting Immune-Related Biological Processes in Solid Tumors: We do Need Biomarkers" shortTile="targeting-immunerelated" author="Fabio Pagni, Elena Guerini-Rocco, Anne  Maria Schultheis, Giulia Grazia, Erika Rijavec, Michele Ghidini, Gianluca Lopez, Konstantinos Venetis, Giorgio  Alberto Croci, Umberto Malapelle, Nicola Fusco" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5452/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Tailoring Immunotherapy in Real-Life Clinical Practice</head>
<p>
After the histology-agnostic approval of pembrolizumab in mismatch repair (MMR)-deficient tumors, the predictive molecular pathology scenario in cancer immunotherapy changed radically. For the first time in the history of medicine, a drug (in this case, an immune-checkpoint inhibitor) was approved based on a specific molecular feature of the neoplasm, irrespective of its anatomical site of origin. A multitude of different tools has been proposed to inform immunotherapy, including morphology, immunohistochemistry (IHC), polymerase chain reaction (PCR)-based techniques and next-generation technology assays, such as next-generation sequencing (NGS) or multiplex barcode technology (e.g., NanoString). However, not all the available tools are validated for patients’ selection in clinical practice, as shown in <figure>Figure 1</figure>. </p>

<p>Among new biomarkers to select patients for immunotherapy, the tumor mutational burden (TMB) has been shown a strong correlation with the response to some compounds. TMB is defined by the total number of somatic nonsynonymous mutations per coding area of the tumor DNA. It has been hypothesized that tumors with a higher TMB are more likely to express neoantigens and to induce a more robust immune response in the presence of immune checkpoint inhibitors. Regrettably, the TMB analysis is considered expensive, time-consuming, and deceptive if the analyses are carried out with an unsuitable NGS panel. Another important facet in TMB analysis is represented by the lack of widely adopted guidelines and recommendations for its assessment and reporting. Initially, TMB was determined using wide approaches (e.g., whole exome sequencing), but more focused gene panels are currently being explored. In addition, there are several indications that TMB is not a universal biomarker, as its value varies not only across tumor types but also across different genomic regions and during the time. This notion highlights the need for disease-specific TMB panels and thresholds. </p>

<p>Likewise, the analysis of the MMR status is troubled by the vastity of the existing diagnostic methods in the substantial absence of companion diagnostic (CD) tests. In general, MMR IHC is mirrored by microsatellite instability (MSI) in endometrial and colorectal cancers. However, not all MMR-deficient tumors show MSI (e.g., breast cancers), questioning the interchangeability of these analyses as pan-cancer predictive tests. Hence, MMR/MSI assays have been originally developed by geneticists to identify Lynch syndrome families and not for choosing the optimal drug to treat acquired tumors. Given the wide heterogeneity in the repertoire of molecular alterations in immune-related genes across different tumor types (<figure>Figure 2</figure>), novel, efficient, reproducible, and reliable techniques coupled with tumor-specific methods and guidelines are needed.  </p>

<p>Another important issue related to the patient’s selection for immunotherapy is represented by the PD-L1 analysis by IHC. In this respect, important harmonization efforts have been made to standardize both the preanalytical and interpretative phases of PD-L1 testing, at least in non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC). The reproducibility of PD-L1 testing in real-life clinical practice evaluated both for “closed” and “open” platforms, showed overlapping results, particularly when the 22C3 antibody clone was used. On the other hand, there are several clues to advise that the same interpretation guidelines should not be translated across different tumor types. For example, the tumor proportion score (TPS) works perfectly for lung cancer but not for head and neck cancer, where the combined positive score (CPS) is more reliable. These two scoring systems are rather different, given that the former considers only the percentage of PD-L1-positive neoplastic cells, while the latter combines all PD-L1-positive cells (i.e., tumor cells, lymphocytes, and macrophages) into the following formula.

</p>

<p>Although the CPS can theoretically exceed the value of 100, the maximum score is defined as 100. Fascinating perspectives are being provided by experimental models addressing the plasticity of the cellular inflammatory response of the host. There are several lines of evidence to suggest that the myeloid-derived cell function is a finely tuned mechanism to control tumor growth. Specifically, both in local and hematopoietic niches, its crosstalk with the tumor cells as well as with exogenous stimuli, is based on the microbiota repertoire. </p>
</text>
