<text id="autogum_academic_doc009" title="Identifying Metabolic Perturbations and Toxic Effects of Rac-Metalaxyl and Metalaxyl-M in Mice Using Integrative NMR and UPLC-MS/MS Based Metabolomics" shortTile="identifying-metabolic" author="Ping Zhang, Sheng Wang, Yuhan He, Yangyang Xu, Dongmei Shi, Furong Yang, Weizhong Yu, Wentao Zhu, Lin He" type="academic" dateCollected="2019-11-03" sourceURL="https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/20/21/5457/htm" speakerList="none" speakerCount="0">
<head> 3. Discussion</head>
<p>
Urine is a vital biofluid in mammals and could be easily collected in a noninvasive manner. Moreover, the metabolites components and concentrations in urine are good indicators of metabolic fluctuations. Comparison of metabolite profiles between the treatment group and the control group could obtain metabolic changes and reveal adverse effects mechanism of stressor. In this study, 1H-NMR and UPLC-MS/MS based metabolomics were employed to investigate the metabolic perturbations after <hi rend="italic">rac</hi>-metalaxyl and metalaxyl-M exposure. The results showed that both <hi rend="italic">rac</hi>-metalaxyl and metalaxyl-M induced systematic metabolic changes in urine and serum. <hi rend="italic">Rac</hi>-metalaxyl and metalaxyl-M induced liver damages and metabolic pathway changes including glycine, serine, and threonine metabolism, citrate cycle (TCA cycle), pyruvate metabolism, glycolysis or gluconeogenesis, glycerophospholipid metabolism, and glyoxylate and dicarboxylate metabolism. These pathways are highly related to energy metabolism, lipid metabolism, amino acids metabolism, microbial metabolism, and tryptophan metabolism. </p>

<head> 3.1. Body Weight Changes and Liver Damage</head>
<p>
Only one mouse was dead in the 60 mg/kg metalaxyl-M treatment group during the whole experiment. After four weeks of exposure, no significant changes in body weight were observed between the control and treatment groups after <hi rend="italic">rac</hi>-metalaxyl and metalaxyl-M exposure. Histopathology examination showed that <hi rend="italic">rac</hi>-metalaxyl and metalaxyl-M can both induce hepatocellular inflammation, necrosis, and vacuolation in mice. Such results suggested <hi rend="italic">rac</hi>-metalaxyl and metalaxyl-M exposure caused liver dysfunction in mice. Moreover, metalaxyl-M induced greater liver damage than <hi rend="italic">rac</hi>-metalaxyl at the same dosage. The liver is a fundamental and essential organ for metabolism and detoxification of xenobiotics with abundant cytochrome P450 enzymes. The damages of the liver may greatly affect the detoxification of mice. </p>

<head> 3.2. Energy Metabolism</head>
<p>
Metabolites involved in energy metabolism were significant changed in mice urine after <hi rend="italic">rac</hi>-metalaxyl and metalaxyl-M exposure, including citrate, succinate, lactate, alanine, pyruvate, and acetate. These metabolites are highly related to energy pathways, including the TCA cycle, pyruvate metabolism, and glycolysis or gluconeogenesis. Citrate and succinate are the main intermediates in the TCA cycle, which is mainly appeared in liver mitochondria. Although other factors cannot be excluded, the increased levels of citrate and succinate in the urine of metalaxyl-M-treated mice indicated that metalaxyl-M affected the activity of mitochondria enzymes involved in the TCA cycle, resulting in the enhancement of energy metabolism in treated mice. In addition, the decreased level of pyruvate and increased levels of lactate and alanine were highly related to pyruvate metabolism. Pyruvate could be converted to acetyl-coenzyme A (COA), which is a vital intermediate in the synthesis of citrate. Lactate and alanine can also be converted to pyruvate. Thus, the increased lactate and alanine could promote the level of acetyl-COA and then up-regulate the energy metabolism. To sum up, these results indicated the enhancement of energy metabolism in mice after <hi rend="italic">rac</hi>-metalaxyl and metalaxyl-M exposure. Furthermore, the perturbation degrees induced by metalaxy-M were higher than <hi rend="italic">rac</hi>-metalaxy in energy metabolism. </p>

<head> 3.3. Lipid Metabolism</head>
<p>
In this study, metalaxyl-M induced two lipid metabolism pathway fluctuations including glycerophospholipid metabolism, glyoxylate, and dicarboxylate metabolism. However, no lipid metabolism pathway was affected by <hi rend="italic">rac</hi>-metalaxyl exposure. According to metabolomics data, metalaxyl-M induced the increased levels of choline and TMAO and decreased levels of PC and GPC. <hi rend="italic">Rac</hi>-metalaxyl only induced the decreased level of GPC. Such metabolites were all related to lipid metabolism and had essential effect on cholesterol level in digestive system. Choline is an important nutrient that is required for lipid transport, methyl-group metabolism, neurotransmitter synthesis, cell membrane structure, and signaling. In addition, choline is a constituent of cell membranes and lipoprotein phospholipids, which play an important role in the integrity of cell membrane and lipid metabolism. Increased choline levels in urine samples suggested the membrane fluidity was disrupted by metalaxyl-M. PC and GPC are known to be important endogenous metabolites related to maintenance of choline homeostasis and bile acids excretion. Moreover, PC, and GPC are not only essential components of cell membranes, but also protect cell from oxidative stress and lipotoxicity. The decreased levels of PC and GPC may be good indicators of oxidative stress and lipotoxicity induced by metalaxyl-M. </p>
</text>
